<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:35:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>NASA topples towers used to test Saturn rockets, space shuttle</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasa-topples-towers-used-to-test-saturn-rockets-space-shuttle/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/news-010826c-lg-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion and Structural Test Facility and Dynamic Test Facility are no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two historic NASA test facilities used in the development of the Saturn V and space shuttle launch vehicles have been demolished after towering over the Marshall Space Flight Center in Alabama since the start of the Space Age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion and Structural Test Facility, which was erected in 1957—the same year the first artificial satellite entered Earth orbit—and the Dynamic Test Facility, which has stood since 1964,were brought down by a coordinated series of implosionson Saturday, January 10. Located in Marshall’s East Test Area on the US Army’s Redstone Arsenal in Huntsville, the two structures were no longer in use and, according to NASA, had a backlog of $25 million in needed repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This work reflects smart stewardship of taxpayer resources,” Jared Isaacman, NASA administrator,said in a statement. “Clearing outdated infrastructure allows NASA to safely modernize, streamline operations and fully leverage the infrastructure investments signed into law by President Trump to keep Marshall positioned at the forefront of aerospace innovation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion and Structural Test Facility, also known as Building 4572 (and 4573, its associated gantry) or the “T-tower” in reference to its shape, was the first stand to support the firing of single-stage rockets with multiple engines. During the 1960s, the 175-foot-tall (53-meter) facility contributed to the development of the F-1 engine and thefirst stage (S-IC) of the Saturn V, the rocket that launched the first astronauts to the moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The facility, which was built by the Army Ballistic Missile Agency, was used to test the Redstone rocket, thefirst stage of the Saturn IBand, after being modified, the solid rocket motor used by the space shuttle program. The site was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 1984 and listed as a National Landmark the next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, NASA considered using the Propulsion and Structural Test Facility to support the Constellation program and its Ares family of rockets, but that program was canceled in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While it is hard to let them go, they’ve earned their retirement,” said Rae Ann Meyer, the acting director of the Marshall Space Flight Center. “Each one of these structures helped NASA make history.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dynamic Test Stand (Building 4550) rises more than twice as high as the Propulsion and Structural Test Facility and for good reason—it was built to fit a fully assembled Saturn V (363 feet or 111 meters tall) for mechanical and vibrational trials. Described once as the tallest building in the state, the stand was later used to form the firstcomplete space shuttle stackwith a winged orbiter (the prototype “Enterprise”), external fuel tank, and solid rocket boosters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dynamic Test Stand is so tall that, according to NASA, its last use in the early 2000s was as a drop tower in support of microgravity testing. It was added to the National Register of Historic Places and deemed a National Landmark in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These structures are not safe,” said Meyer. “Strategic demolition is a necessary step in shaping the future of NASA’s mission to explore, innovate, and inspire. By removing these structures that we have not used in decades, we are saving money on upkeep of facilities we can’t use. We also are making these areas safe to use for future NASA exploration endeavors and investments.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Propulsion and Structural Test Facility and the Dynamic Test Facility were among 19 sites identified for removal at the Marshall Space Flight Center. The count also includes the Neutral Buoyancy Simulator (NBS), a facility that enabled NASA astronauts and researchers to practice for spacewalks and work in microgravity. It comprised a tank that was 75 feet in diameter, 40 feet deep, and designed to hold up to nearly 1.5 million gallons of water (23 by 12 meters by 5.7 million liters).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tests and training conducted in the NBS were pivotal to saving Skylab, the United States’ first space station, from damage it sustained during its 1973 launch. The simulator was also used to prepare for the repair of the Hubble Space Telescope during its first servicing mission in 1993.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NBS opened in 1968 and was succeeded nearly 30 years later by a larger tank in the Neutral Buoyancy Lab at the Sonny Carter Training Facility near NASA’s Johnson Space Center in Houston, Texas. Demolition of the NBS began in mid-December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To preserve the legacy of the NBS, Propulsion and Structural Test Facility, and Dynamic Test Stand, detailed architectural summaries, written histories, and large-format photos were permanently archived in the Library of Congress’ Historic American Engineering Record collection. This ensures the information will be available to the public and researchers for years to come. Additionally, NASA partnered with Auburn University to create digital models of each site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical artifacts from each site were also identified and transferred to theUS Space &amp; Rocket Centerin Huntsville, preserving tangible pieces for educational and inspirational purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As we look to an exciting future, we honor the past, especially thededication of the men and womenwho built these structures and tested hardware that has launched into space, made unprecedented scientific discoveries, and inspired generations of Americans to reach for the stars,” said Meyer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listing image:
    NASA&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasa-topples-towers-used-to-test-saturn-rockets-space-shuttle/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 06:21:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New research shows how shunning ultraprocessed foods helps with aging</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/avoiding-ultraprocessed-foods-supports-healthier-aging/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ultraprocessed-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies have linked ultraprocessed foods to poor health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older adults can dramatically reduce the amount ofultraprocessed foodsthey eat while keeping a familiar, balanced diet—and this shift leads to improvements across several key markers related to how the body regulates appetite and metabolism. That’s the main finding of a new study my colleagues and Ipublished in the journal Clinical Nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultraprocessed foods are made using industrial techniques and ingredients that aren’t typically used in home cooking. They often contain additives such as emulsifiers, flavorings, colors, and preservatives. Common examples include packaged snacks, ready-to-eat meals, and some processed meats. Studies have linked diets high in ultraprocessed foodsto poorer health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team and Ienrolled Americans ages 65 and older in our study, many of whom were overweight or had metabolic risk factors such as insulin resistance or high cholesterol. Participants followed two diets low in ultraprocessed foods for eight weeks each. One included lean red meat (pork); the other was vegetarian with milk and eggs. For two weeks in between, participants returned to their usual diets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A total of 43 people began the dietary intervention, and 36 completed the full study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both diets, ultraprocessed foods made up less than 15 percent of the total calories—a significant reduction fromthe typical American diet, where more than 50 percent of total calories comes from ultraprocessed foods. The diets were designed to be realistic for everyday eating, and participants were not instructed to restrict calories, lose weight, or change their physical activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We prepared, portioned, and provided all meals and snacks for the study. Both diets emphasized minimally processed ingredients and aligned with the2020–2025 Dietary Guidelines for Americans, the US government’s nutrient-based recommendations for healthy eating, while providing similar calories and amounts of key nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2025–2030 Dietary Guidelines for Americans, released on January 7, 2026,explicitly recommend eating less ultraprocessed food, but theprevious versions of the guidelinesdid not specifically address food processing. Our feeding study design allowed us, for the first time, to examine the health effects of reducing ultraprocessed foods while keeping nutrient levels consistent with recommended targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We compared how participants fared while eating their habitual diets with how they responded to the two diets that were low in ultraprocessed foods. During the periods when participants ate fewer ultraprocessed foods, they naturally consumed fewer calories and lost weight, including total and abdominal body fat. Beyond weight loss, they also showed meaningful improvements in insulin sensitivity, healthier cholesterol levels, fewer signs of inflammation, and favorable changes in hormones that help regulate appetite and metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These improvements were similar whether participants followed the meat-based or the vegetarian diet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultraprocessed foodsmake up more than half the caloriesconsumed by most US adults. Although these foods are convenient and widely available, studies that track people’s diets over time increasingly link them withobesity and age-related chronic diseasessuch as Type 2 diabetes and heart disease. With older adults making up a growing share of the global population, strategies that preserve metabolic health could support healthy aging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most previous feeding studies testing how ultraprocessed foods affect people’s healthhaven’t reflected real-world eating, especially among Americans. For example, some studies have compared diets made up almost entirely of ultraprocessed foods with diets that contain little to none at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study aimed to more closely approximate people’s experience while still closely tracking the foods they consumed. It is the first to show that for older adults a realistic reduction in ultraprocessed foods, outside the lab, has measurable health benefits beyond just losing weight.For older adults especially, maintaining metabolic health helps preserve mobility, independence, and quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our study was small, reflecting the complexity of studies in which researchers tightly control what participants eat. It was not designed to show whether the metabolic improvements we observed can prevent or delay diseases such as diabetes or heart disease over time. Larger, longer studies will be needed to answer that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the practical side, it’s still unclear whether people can cut back on ultraprocessed foods in their daily lives without structured support, and what strategies would make it easier to do so. It’s also not fully understood which aspects of processing—for example, additives, emulsifiers, or extrusion—matter more for health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answering these questions could help manufacturers produce foods that are healthier but still convenient—and make it easier for people to choose healthier food options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TheResearch Briefis a short take on interesting academic work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moul Deyis professor of Nutrition Science atSouth Dakota State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is republished fromThe Conversationunder a Creative Commons license. Read theoriginal article.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/avoiding-ultraprocessed-foods-supports-healthier-aging/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 06:55:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Chevrolet Bolt is back… but for how long?</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/the-chevrolet-bolt-is-back-but-for-how-long/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Chevrolet-Bolt-2027-DriverRear-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new LFP battery pack has 262 miles of range and fast-charges at 150 kW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new Chevrolet Equinox EV isa solid entryinto the compact crossover market, and with a (just) sub-$35,000 starting price, it also counts as affordable by the standards of 2026. But if you think that’s too rich for your blood, or that the Equinox is still too large for your needs, take heart—the Chevrolet Bolt is back in dealerships now as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bolt was GM’s first modern electric vehicle, following on from the hand-built, pre-lithium ion EV1 and the compliance car that was the Spark EV. We’re big fans of the Bolt here at Ars Technica. It offered well more than 200 miles of range in a mass-produced EV at a reasonable price well before Tesla’s Model 3 started clogging up our roads, it got more efficient over time, and it managed to be fun to drive in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Motors (which owns Chevrolet) probably feels less well-disposed toward the Bolt. It lost thousands of dollars on each car it sold, even beforethe entire fleet had to be recalledfor a costlybattery replacement. The issue was due toimproperly folded tabson some cells that could cause a battery fire, giving GM (and its battery partner LG) plenty of bad press in the process. That recall alone cost $1.8 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bolt also predated GM’s big investment into the battery platform it used to but no longer calls “Ultium.” As the automaker began to ready a larger portfolio of new EVs (including the aforementioned Equinox EV), it decided the Bolt would have to go to make room for production of other, more profitable vehicles. The announcementwas made in April 2023and helped make the Bolt GM’s bestselling EV by a large margin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcry from Bolt fans was loud and vociferous, and in July 2025, GM CEO Mary Barra announced that it would be coming back, with a new Ultium-based battery pack. But only in the Bolt EUV body style—if you prefer the original hatchback, you’re out of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reengineering the Bolt for a new battery packwasn’t a quick process. The cells, modules, and electronics are all different but had to fit in the same size space with the same mounting points as the original. And GM’s own LFP factory won’t be producing cells until sometime next year. Which means for now, GM is importing LPF cells from CATL in China, paying costly tariffs in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, Chevy released pricing: $28,995 (plus a $1,395 delivery charge) for the Bolt LT, or $32,995 for the Bolt RS. In time—we’re not sure when—there’s supposed to be a stripped-out model that starts at less than $28,000. For the record, thisis more expensive than the Bolt EUV we reviewed in late 2022, particularly once you take trim levels into account. And of course, there’s now no way to cast your Apple or Android phone to the new infotainment system. And the model-year 2027 Bolt makes far less torque than the Bolts we were used to driving, which may well mean a very different on-road experience, given how important that tidal wave of torque is to how an EV feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Chevy has released the all-important info: 262 miles (422 km) of range according to the EPA test, a slight improvement on the 249 miles (398 km) of range from the old Bolt EUV. Better news is that fast charging is almost three times more powerful. Where the old Bolt topped out at 55 kW, often infuriating other EV drivers waiting for them to hurry up at overcrowded charging stations, the new car will reach rates of up to 150 kW, meaning a 10–80 percent charge should take as little as 26 minutes, not close to an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chevy says that the new Bolt is already in dealerships, in both LT and RS trims. But its inventory checker won’t search for MY27 vehicles yet, so we haven’t been able to confirm that. The company has also said that the car is only back “for a limited time only.” Although with no elaboration on what “limited” means in this context, we can’t tell you how many cars the automaker will actually build.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/the-chevrolet-bolt-is-back-but-for-how-long/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 06:59:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UK probes X over Grok CSAM scandal; Elon Musk cries censorship</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/uk-investigating-x-after-grok-undressed-thousands-of-women-and-children/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2246892016-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grok tests if UK can penalize platforms for sexualized deepfakes generated by AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk’s X is currently under investigation in the United Kingdom afterfailing to stopthe platform’s chatbot, Grok, from generatingthousands of sexualized images of women and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, UK media regulator Ofcomconfirmedthat X may have violated the UK’s Online Safety Act, which requires platforms to block illegal content. The proliferation of “undressed images of people” by X users may amount to intimate image abuse, pornography, and child sexual abuse material (CSAM), the regulator said. And X may also have neglected its duty to stop kids from seeing porn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reports of Grok being used to create and share illegal non-consensual intimate images and child sexual abuse material on X have been deeply concerning,” an Ofcom spokesperson said. “Platforms must protect people in the UK from content that’s illegal in the UK, and we won’t hesitate to investigate where we suspect companies are failing in their duties, especially where there’s a risk of harm to children.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X is cooperating with the probe, Ofcom said, noting that X met a “firm” deadline last week to explain what steps it’s taking to comply with the UK law. Ofcom declined Ars’ request to share more details about possible changes X has already made to either limit Grok in the UK or more broadly, since the investigation is “live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grok has already been blocked in Indonesia and Malaysia, as the chatbot remains unchecked. The UK could be next to block Grok if X fails to comply with the Online Safety Act. Additionally, X could face fines of up to 10 percent of its global revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear how long the probe will take to conclude. Ofcom’s spokesperson told Ars that the agency will progress the investigation “as a matter of the highest priority, while ensuring we follow due process.” The probe will end “as soon as reasonably possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X will have an opportunity to respond to Ofcom’s preliminary ruling before any final decision is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars could not reach X to comment on the probe, but Musk has complained that Grok critics are looking for an “excuse for censorship,” the BBCreported. X has previously said that it will report harmful outputs to law enforcement and permanently suspend accounts that are abusing Grok to nudify images that X deems to be illegal content. The platform also startedcharging some users to edit images, instead of blocking outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after Ofcom announced the probe, UK Technology Secretary Liz Kendall said the country would be bringing a new law into force that makes it illegal for companies to supply tools designed to create sexualized images, the BBC reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Kendall’s announcement, it seemed possible for X to escape the investigation unscathed due to “gaps” in the Online Safety Act, according to the chairwomen of the UK Parliament’s technology and media committees, the BBCreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are doubts as to whether the Online Safety Act actually has the power to regulate functionality—that means generative AI’s ability to nudify someone’s image,” Caroline Dinenage, chairwoman of the culture, media, and sport committee, told the BBC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chairwomen suggested that the UK may need to update the law to better explain platforms’ duties to remove or prevent the making and sharing of sexualized deepfakes. In a document defining illegal content, however, Ofcom emphasizes that deepfakes can count as both CSAM and intimate image abuse, suggesting X could face penalties under the Online Safety Act for some of Grok’s outputs, even if Ofcom cannot require changes to Grok’s functionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcomnotedthat in its view, CSAM does include “AI-generated imagery, deepfakes and other manipulated media,” which “would fall under the category of a ‘pseudo-photograph.’” As Ofcom explained, “If the impression conveyed by a pseudo-photograph is that the person shown is a child, then the photo should be treated as showing a child.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, “manipulated images and videos such as deepfakes should be considered within the scope” of intimate image abuse, Ofcom said. “Any photograph or video which appears to depict an intimate situation” that a real person would not want publicly posted should “be treated as a photograph or video actually depicting such a situation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Grok fans think that the chatbot’s outputs that undress people and put them in skimpy bikinis or underwear isn’t abuse. However, the UK law further details that an “intimate situation” could be an image where a person’s “genitals, buttocks, or breasts” are “covered only with underwear” or “covered only by clothing that is wet or otherwise transparent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear how long Ofcom may take to reach its decision, but the regulator acted urgently to intervene. And UK officials who were shocked by the scandal have confirmed that they are quickly moving to protect people in the UK from being targeted by Grok’s worst outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Ofcom does not directly refer to Musk’s comments on censorship, the regulator takes a defensive stance in its announcement—likely preparing to fight X’s argument by pointing out that X would be the one in charge of deciding what is illegal content and what should be removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The legal responsibility is on platforms to decide whether content breaks UK laws, and they can use our Illegal Content Judgements Guidance when making these decisions,” Ofcom noted. “Ofcom is not a censor—we do not tell platforms which specific posts or accounts to take down.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/uk-investigating-x-after-grok-undressed-thousands-of-women-and-children/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 07:32:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is this the beginning of the end for GameStop?</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/is-this-the-beginning-of-the-end-for-gamestop/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/GettyImages-1135950796-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sudden closure of hundreds of storefronts isn’t exactly a great sign…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six and a half years ago—aftera failed corporate sale attempt,massive financial losses, andthe departure/layoffof many key staff—I wrote aboutwhat seemed at the time like the “imminent demise” of GameStop. Now, after five years ofmeme stock maniathathelped prop up the company’s finances a bit, I’ll admit the video gameand Funko Popretailer has lasted much longer as a relevant entity than I anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GameStop’s surprisingly extended run may be coming to an end, though, with Polygon reporting late last week that GameStophas abruptly shut down 400 storesacross the US, with even more closures expected before the end of the month. That comes on top of 590 US stores that were shuttered in fiscal 2024 (which ended in January 2025) and stated plans to close hundreds of remaining international stores across Canada, Australia, and Europe in the coming months,per SEC filings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GameStop still had just over 3,200 stores worldwide as of February 1, 2025, so even hundreds of new and planned store closures don’t literally mean the immediate end of the company as a going concern. But when you consider thatthere were still nearly 6,000 GameStop locations worldwide as of 2019—nearly 4,000 of which were in the US—the long-term trend is clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for that downward trend has been equally clear for years now: downloadable games. We made note back in 2017 whenmore than half ofDestiny 2’s game sales came via download rather than disc, and things have only accelerated from there. Physical game salesnow represent just 3 percent of overall PlayStation revenue, for instance, compared to 20 percent for digital full-game software sales, 17 percent for subscription-based “network services” likePlayStation Plus, and 29 percent for digital “add-on content” like DLC. Some major games areskipping physical releases altogetherthese days, while Nintendo isselling data-free Switch 2 Game Key Cardsthat merely act as a key for a downloadable copy of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just asTower Records couldn’t continue to existin a world where almost all music was being downloaded or streamed, a chain devoted to selling games on physical discs can’t sustain itself in a world where the vast majority of game spending is now online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing the writing on the wall, GameStop has made a number of attempts to rebrand around something other than selling (or re-selling) physical video games. Anyone else remember the chain’sabortive attemptto restructure around “high margin immersive experiential gaming content” like esports? How aboutthe rollout of “GameStop Retro” locationsthat sell games and hardware dating back to the last century? Or themuch-hyped NFT marketplacethat GameStopquietly wound down in 2023?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest attempt at a GameStop corporate pivot seems to be toward collectible trading cards, viain-store partnerships with card-grading agenciesanda “Power Pack” programcombining digital and physical card sales in some novel ways. But a world where GameStop isthe place to trade in a $30,000 Pokémon cardisn’t at all the same as the one where millions of people traded inMadden 09discs for a couple of bucks of GameStop store credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So even though GameStop has lasted longer than I expected, I’m still relatively confident in predicting that the end is coming for the retailer sooner rather than later. Who knows, though, maybe I’ll be writing another article like this in 2033, marveling at how a once-lumbering giant in the world of video game sales is somehow continuing to limp along.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/is-this-the-beginning-of-the-end-for-gamestop/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:08:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple chooses Google’s Gemini over OpenAI’s ChatGPT to power next-gen Siri</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/apple/2026/01/apple-says-its-new-ai-powered-siri-will-use-googles-gemini-language-models/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/apple_google_hero_3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple goes with Google’s tech despite using OpenAI’s ChatGPT elsewhere in iOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “more intelligent” version of Siri that Apple plans to release later this year will be backed by Google’s Gemini language models, the company announced today. CNBCreportsthat the deal is part of a “multi-year partnership” between Apple and Google that will allow Apple to use Google’s AI models in its own software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“After careful evaluation, we determined that Google’s technology provides the most capable foundation for Apple Foundation Models and we’re excited about the innovative new experiences it will unlock for our users,” reads an Apple statement given to CNBC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s announcement confirmsreportingby Bloomberg’s Mark Gurman late last year thatApple and Google were nearing a deal. Apple didn’t disclose terms, but Gurman said that Apple would be paying Google “about $1 billion a year” for access to its AI models “following an extensive evaluation period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bloomberg has also reported that the Gemini model would be run on Apple’s Private Cloud Compute servers, “ensuring that user data remains walled off from Google’s infrastructure,” and that Apple still hopes to improve its own in-house language models to the point that they can eventually be used instead of relying on third-party models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Apple’s iPhones and iOS compete with Google’s Android operating system and the many smartphones that use it, the companies still cooperate in plenty of other areas.Google has paid Apple billions of dollarsto remain the default search engine in Safari on iOS, iPadOS, and macOS (though that deal has faced increased regulatory scrutiny in recent years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’s announcement is a blow to OpenAI and the many versions of its ChatGPT model, which Applehas used elsewhere in iOS and macOS. Bloomberg reports that Apple also tested OpenAI’s ChatGPT and Anthropic’s Claude models before deciding to go with Gemini. ChatGPT came out ahead of Gemini in tests that Ars ranusing earlier versions of the models, but Google’s models have apparently improved enough (and amassed enough users) to worry OpenAI; CEO Sam Altmandeclareda “code red” last month and pushed back several planned ChatGPT features so that the company could better respond to Google’s Gemini 3 release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple originally promised the improved, AI-powered Siri for 2024’s iOS 18 release, but ultimately delayed the feature because itdidn’t work reliably enough. The new version of Siri should arrive in an update to iOS 26, iPadOS 26, and macOS 26 Tahoe later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/apple/2026/01/apple-says-its-new-ai-powered-siri-will-use-googles-gemini-language-models/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:57:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NASA launches new mission to get the most out of the James Webb Space Telescope</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasas-newest-telescope-will-play-an-outsize-role-in-finding-earth-2-0/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Pandora_integrated_blue_BCT-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was not recognized how serious a problem that is until… about 2017 or 2018.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among other things, the James Webb Space Telescope is designed to get us closer to finding habitable worlds around faraway stars. From its perch a million miles from Earth, Webb’s huge gold-coated mirror collects more light than any other telescope put into space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Webb telescope, launched in 2021 at a cost of more than $10 billion, has the sensitivity to peer into distant planetary systems and detect the telltale chemical fingerprints of molecules critical to or indicative of potential life, like water vapor, carbon dioxide, and methane. Webb can do this while also observing the oldest observable galaxies in the Universe and studying planets, moons, and smaller objects within our own Solar System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, astronomers want to get the most out of their big-budget observatory. That’s where NASA’s Pandora mission comes in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pandora satellite rocketed into orbit early Sunday from Vandenberg Space Force Base, California. It hitched a ride with around 40 other small payloads aboard a SpaceX Falcon 9 rocket, launching into a polar Sun-synchronous orbit before deploying at an altitude of roughly 380 miles (613 kilometers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few weeks, ground controllers will put Pandora through a series of commissioning and calibration steps before turning its eyes toward deep space. Pandora is a fraction of the size of Webb. Its primary mirror is about the size of the largest consumer-grade amateur telescopes, less than one-tenth the dimension of Webb’s. NASA capped Pandora’s budget at $20 million. The budget to develop Webb was more than 500 times higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can little Pandora add to Webb’s bleeding-edge science? First, it helps to understand how scientists use Webb to study exoplanets. When a planet passes in front of its parent star, some of the starlight shines through its atmosphere. Webb has the sensitivity to detect the filtered starlight and break it apart into its spectral components, telling astronomers about the composition of clouds and hazes in the planet’s atmosphere. Ultimately, the data is useful in determining whether an exoplanet might be like Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I liken it often to holding a glass of wine in front of a candle, so that we can see really what’s inside,” said Daniel Apai, a member of Pandora’s science team from the University of Arizona. “We can assess, basically, the quality of the wine. In this case, we use the light that filters through the star’s [atmosphere] through the planetary atmosphere to judge what chemicals, gases in particular, may be present. Water vapor is one that we are the most sensitive to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s a catch. Stars shine millions to billions of times brighter than their planetary companions, and starlight isn’t constant. Like the Sun, other stars have spots, flares, and variability over hours, days, or years. Hot spots and cool spots rotate in and out of view. And the star’s own atmospheres can contain some of the same molecules scientists are seeking to find on exoplanets, including water vapor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, a star’s spectral signature easily outshines the signal coming from a nearby planet. Astronomers discovered this signal “contamination” when they started looking for potentially habitable worlds, injecting confounding uncertainties into their findings. Were the promising spectra they were seeing coming from the planet or the star?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the ways that this manifests is by making you think that you’re seeing absorption features like water and potentially methane when there may not be any, or, conversely, you’re not seeing the signatures that are there because they’re masked by the stellar signal,” said Tom Barclay, deputy project scientist and technical lead on the Pandora mission at NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem became apparent in the 2010s as astronomers used more powerful telescopes to see the finer details of exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is something that we always suspected as a community,” Apai told Ars. “We always suspected that stars are not perfect. At some point, it becomes a problem. But it was not recognized how serious a problem that is until, I would say, about 2017 or 2018.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists quickly got to work looking for a solution, and NASA selected the Pandora mission for development in 2021, just months before the launch of Webb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When we’re trying to find water in the atmospheres of these small Earth-like planets, we want to be really sure it’s not coming from the star before we go tell the press and make a big stink about it,” said Elisa Quintana, Pandora’s lead scientist at NASA’s Goddard Space Flight Center. “So we designed the Pandora mission specifically to solve this problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From low-Earth orbit, Pandora will observe exoplanets and their stars simultaneously, allowing astronomers to correct their measurements of the planet’s atmospheric composition and structure based on the ever-changing conditions of the host star itself. Webb could theoretically do this work, but scientists already fill every hour of Webb’s schedule. Pandora will point and stare at 20 preselected exoplanets 10 times during its one-year prime mission, collecting 24 hours of visible and infrared observations with each visit. This will capture short-term and longer-term changes in each star’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX launched Pandora into a so-called “twilight orbit” that follows the boundary between day and night on Earth, allowing the satellite to keep its solar panels illuminated by the Sun while performing its observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can send this small telescope out, sit on a star for a really long time, and sort of map all the star spots, and really disentangle the star and planet signals,” Quintana said in a recent panel discussion at NASA Goddard. “It’s filling a really nice gap in helping us to sort of calibrate all these stars that James Webb is going to look at, so we can be really confident that all of these molecules that we’re detecting in planets are real.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think this is really the most important scientific barrier that we have to break down to fully unlock the potential of Webb and future missions,” Apai said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben Hord, a member of Pandora’s science team at Goddard, singled out one example in a presentation at an American Astronomical Society meeting last year. This planet, named GJ 486 b, is a “super-Earth” discovered in 2021 circling a relatively cool red dwarf star. Hord said astronomers had trouble determining if the planet has a water-rich atmosphere based on Webb’s observations alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want to know if water is in the atmospheres of these exoplanets, and this stellar contamination from the spots on the star can mask or mimic features like water,” Hord said. “Our hope is that Pandora will help James Webb data be even more precise by providing context and understanding for these host stars and these planetary systems.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Planets around small dwarf stars are some of the best candidates for finding a true Earth analog. Because these stars put out a fraction of the heat of the Sun, a potentially habitable planet could lurk very close to its host, completing a year in a handful of days. This allows astronomers to see the planet repeatedly as it passes in front of its star, rapidly building a dataset on its size, structure, and environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists hope they can extend the lessons learned from Pandora’s observations of a sample of 20 exoplanets to other worlds in our galactic neighborhood. As of late last year, astronomers have confirmed detections of more than 6,000 exoplanets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With a well-corrected spectrum, we can say there’s water, there’s nitrogen,” Quintana said. “So with every mission, as we evolve, we’re chipping away and taking bigger and bigger steps toward that question of, ‘OK, we know Earths are out there. We know they’re abundant. We know they have atmospheres. How do we know if they have life on them?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mission like Pandora was not possible until recently, certainly not on the $20 million budget NASA devoted to the project. With Pandora, the agency took advantage of a fast-growing small satellite industry churning out spacecraft at a fraction of what it cost 10 or 15 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pandora spacecraft weighed approximately 716 pounds (325 kilograms) at launch and likely would have required a dedicated rocket to travel to space before SpaceX started offering shared rides on its workhorse Falcon 9 rocket. NASA did not disclose what it paid SpaceX to launch Pandora, but publicly available pricing suggests SpaceX charges a few million dollars to launch a satellite of the same size. Before the rideshare option became available, NASA would have paid tens of millions of dollars for the launch alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pandora mission is part of NASA’s Astrophysics Pioneers program, an initiative set up to solicit ideas for lower-cost astronomy missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s been very, very challenging to try and squeeze this big amount of science into this small cost box, but that’s kind of what makes it fun, right?” Barclay told Ars. “We have to be pretty ruthless in making sure that we only fund the things we need to fund. We accept risk where we need to accept the risk, and at times we need to accept that we may need to give up performance in order to make sure that we hit the schedule and we hit the launch [schedule].”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It helps that Pandora’s 17-inch (45-centimeter) telescope comes from Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California, which had the technology on the shelf from a national security program. Pandora uses a small satellite platform from Blue Canyon Technologies, a Colorado company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no way we could have done Pandora 10 years ago,” Barclay said. “The small launch capabilities that come from companies like Rocket Lab and SpaceX and others meant that now the vendors of spacecraft buses and spacecraft instruments are able to push their costs down because they know that there’s a market for small missions out there. Other parts of the government are investing heavily in small spacecraft, and so that allows us on the science side to make use of that economies of scale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comparison, the European Space Agency launched anexoplanet observatoryabout the same size as Pandora in 2019 at a cost of more than $100 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are companies now looking at how toscale up production of larger satellites, too. Cheaper, heavy satellites could launch on new heavy- and super-heavy rockets like SpaceX’s Starship or Blue Origin’s New Glenn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think it is an amazing capability to have for astrophysicists because science is moving fast,” Apai said. “Exoplanet science is changing. I would say every three or four years, we have breakthroughs. And the product keeps changing. We push the boundaries, and if you ever have to work with 20- or 25-year-long mission lifetimes, that really just limits progress.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasas-newest-telescope-will-play-an-outsize-role-in-finding-earth-2-0/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:25:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apps like Grok are explicitly banned under Google’s rules—why is it still in the Play Store?</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/apps-like-grok-are-explicitly-banned-under-googles-rules-why-is-it-still-in-the-play-store/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/GettyImages-2225386195-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google describes apps exactly like Grok and says they are banned from Google Play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk’s xAI recently weakened content guard rails for image generation in the Grok AI bot. This led to a new spate ofnon-consensual sexual imageryon X, much of it aimed at silencing women on the platform. This, along with the creation of sexualized images of children in the more compliant Grok, has led regulators tobegin investigating xAI. In the meantime, Google has rules in place for exactly this eventuality—it’s just not enforcing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really could not be more clear from Google’s publicly available policies that Grok should have been banned yesterday. And yet, it remains in the Play Store. Not only that—it enjoys a T for Teen rating, one notch below the M-rated X app. Apple also still offers the Grok app on its platform, but its rules actually leave more wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;App content restrictions at Apple and Google have evolved in very different ways. From the start, Apple has been prone to removing apps on a whim, so developers have come to expect that Apple’s guidelines may not mention every possible eventuality. As Google has shifted from a laissez-faire attitude to more hard-nosed control of the Play Store, it has progressively piled on clarifications in the content policy. As a result, Google’s rules are spelled out in no uncertain terms, and Grok runs afoul of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has adedicated support pagethat explains how to interpret its “Inappropriate Content” policy for the Play Store. Like Apple, the rules begin with a ban on apps that contain or promote sexual content including, but not limited to, pornography. That’s where Apple stops, but Google goes on to list more types of content and experiences that it considers against the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t allow apps that contain or promote content associated with sexually predatory behavior,or distribute non-consensual sexual content,” the Play Store policy reads (emphasis ours). So the policy is taking aim at apps like Grok, but this line on its own could be read as focused on apps featuring “real” sexual content. However, Google is very thorough and has helpfully explained that this rule covers AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detailed policy includes examples of content that violate this rule, which include much of what you’d expect—nothing lewd or profane, no escort services, and no illegal sexual themes. After a spate of rudimentary “nudify” apps in 2020 and 2021, Google added language to this page clarifying that “apps that claim to undress people” are not allowed in Google Play. In 2023, as the AI boom got underway, Google added another line to note that it also would remove apps that contained “non-consensual sexual content created via deepfake or similar technology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sound like any apps you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, Google’s description of bannable apps describes Grok’s app to a tee. Google made these additions as new threats became apparent, knowing that developers would try to publish AI-undressing apps in the Play Store. The company did not, apparently, think the world’s richest person would be the one pushing digital humiliation tools on its platform. And Google’s response to this situation so far has been to do nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backlash to xAI’s loosened restrictions prompted the company to limit access to image editing slightly. You can no longer edit images on X without paying for a premium plan. However, the Grok app does not have that limitation. Anyone who downloads Grok can use it to create non-consensual sexual content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the app is cleared for teens, even devices with parental controls enabled will permit 13- to 17-year-olds to download Grok. There is no paywall, and you don’t even have to log in before editing your first image. The app does ask the user to confirm their birth year, but teenagers would never lie about that, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not xAI’s first problem with non-consensual sexual content. Last year, the AI was widely used to createfake Taylor Swift nudes. However, in that case, users were simply prompting the bot with the singer’s name—Grok can create entirely new images of famous people because the training data includes real images of them. Grok’s newer ability to “edit” images of people is a different and more insidious feature because it can turn anyone into an AI plaything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars has reached out to Google to ask why Grok has not been removed and why it has retained a Teen rating. The company has declined to make a statement at this time. So we’re left with a policy that explicitly bans apps like Grok, but Google is taking no action to enforce those policies, allowing impressionable teenagers and unsavory weirdos to use it to sexualize real people.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/apps-like-grok-are-explicitly-banned-under-googles-rules-why-is-it-still-in-the-play-store/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:36:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court takes case that could strip FCC of authority to issue fines</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/supreme-court-takes-case-that-could-strip-fcc-of-authority-to-issue-fines/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/getty-supreme-court-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AT&amp;T and Verizon claim right to a jury trial was violated by FCC fines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court will hear a case that could invalidate the Federal Communications Commission’s authority to issue fines against companies regulated by the FCC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AT&amp;T, Verizon, and T-Mobilechallengedthe FCC’s ability to punish them after the commission fined the carriers for selling customer location data without their users’ consent. AT&amp;T convinced the US Court of Appeals for the 5th Circuit tooverturn its fine, whileVerizonlost in the 2nd Circuit andT-Mobilelost in the District of Columbia Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizonpetitionedthe Supreme Court to reverse its loss, while the FCC and Justice Departmentpetitionedthe court to overturn AT&amp;T’s victory in the 5th Circuit. The Supreme Court granted both petitions to hear the challenges and consolidated the cases in alist of ordersreleased Friday. Oral arguments will be held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, the FCCfined the big three carriersa total of $196 million for location data sales revealed in 2018, saying the companies were punished “for illegally sharing access to customers’ location information without consent and without taking reasonable measures to protect that information against unauthorized disclosure.” Carriers challenged in three appeals courts, arguing that the fines violated their Seventh Amendment right to a jury trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carriers’ cases against the FCC rely on the Supreme Court’s June 2024rulinginSecurities and Exchange Commission v. Jarkesy, which held that a similar but not identical SEC system for issuing fines violated the right to a jury trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conservative-leaning 5th Circuit appeals court decided that the FCC violated AT&amp;T’s rights while “act[ing] as prosecutor, jury, and judge.” But the 2nd Circuit and District of Columbia Circuit courts found that each carrier could have obtained a jury trial if it simply decided not to pay the fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Verizon could have gotten such a trial” if it had “declined to pay the forfeiture and preserved its opportunity for ade novojury trial if the government sought to collect,” the 2nd Circuit judges wrote. Instead, Verizon chose to pay the fine “and seek immediate review in our Court.” That option didn’t exist in theSEC v. Jarkesycase because of differences between US telecom law and securities law, the court said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’s petition to the Supreme Court seeks a ruling on “whether the Communications Act violates the Seventh Amendment and Article III [of the Constitution] by authorizing the FCC to order the payment of monetary penalties for failing to reasonably safeguard customer data, without guaranteeing the defendant carrier a right to a jury trial.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon argued that the option of refusing to pay the fine doesn’t satisfy its right to a jury trial:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a carrier wants to guarantee judicial review, it must pay the penalty and then seek review in a court of appeals, which reviews the agency’s order on the administrative record under the deferential standards of the Administrative Procedure Act. If the carrier wants a jury trial, by contrast, it must defy the FCC’s order and refuse to pay, after which the Department of Justice may, but is not required to, file a lawsuit in district court to collect the unpaid forfeiture. While waiting for that DOJ lawsuit that might never come, the carrier suffers serious practical and reputational harms from the final FCC order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FCC Chairman Brendan Carrvoted againstthe fines last year, arguing that the Biden-era FCC overstepped its authority. But Carr’s argument was about FCC authority to regulate data privacy practices, not the right to a jury trial, and the FCC has continued to defend its legal process since Carr took over as chairman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration petition in the AT&amp;T case said the 5th Circuit ruling “conflicts with this Court’s precedents and with decisions of two other courts of appeals.” The brief said a Supreme Court precedent from1899states that “the Constitution ‘does not prescribe at what stage of an action a trial by jury’ must occur, and that a statute may authorize such a trial ‘for the first time upon appeal’ from an initial decision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A1915Supreme Court ruling upheld a similar scheme “under which an executive agency could issue initial decisions finding regulated parties liable for money damages, subject to review by a jury in an Article III court,” the government told the Supreme Court. The 5th Circuit ruling “identified no basis for distinguishing this case from those precedents,” and “has serious practical consequences, since it deprives the Commission of one of its most important regulatory remedies and severely impairs the agency’s ability to enforce federal communications law,” the government brief said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Supreme Court is only taking up the AT&amp;T and Verizon cases, the T-Mobile case would be affected by whatever ruling the Supreme Court issues. T-Mobile is seeking a rehearing in the District of Columbia Circuit, an effort that could be boosted or rendered moot by whatever the Supreme Court decides.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/supreme-court-takes-case-that-could-strip-fcc-of-authority-to-issue-fines/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:56:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Switching water sources improved hygiene of Pompeii’s public baths</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/switching-water-sources-improved-hygiene-of-pompeiis-public-baths/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/bath1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists analyzed carbonate deposits from baths, aqueduct to learn more about city’s changing water supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eruption of Mount Vesuvius in 79 CE released thermal energy roughly equivalent to 100,000 times the atomic bombs dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki at the end of World War II, spewing molten rock, pumice, and hot ash over Pompeii. Pompeii’s public baths, aqueduct, and water towers were among the preserved structures frozen in time. Anew paperpublished in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences analyzed calcium carbonate deposits from those structures to learn more about the city’s water supply and how it changed over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pompeii was founded in the sixth century BCE. Prior research revealed that, early on, the city relied on rainwater stored in cisterns and wells for its water supply. The public baths used weight-lifting machinery to lift water up well shafts that were as deep as 40 meters. As the city developed, so did the complexity of its water supply system, most notably with the construction of an aqueduct between 27 BCE and 14 CE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of this latest paper were interested in the calcium carbonate deposits left by water in well shafts as well as the baths and aqueduct. The different layers have “different chemical and isotope composition, calcite crystal size, and shape,” which in turn could reveal information about seasonal changes in temperature, as well as changes over time in the chemical composition of the water. Analyzing those properties would enable them to “reconstruct the history of such systems—particularly public baths—revealing aspects of their maintenance and the adaptations made during their period of use,” the authors wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors focused on four distinct time periods: from the second century to 80 BCE; after 80 BCE, when Pompeii became a Roman colony; the reign of Emperor Augustus (31 BCE to 14 CE); and after the earthquake that rocked the city in 62 CE. It was easy enough to collect calcium carbonate samples during field work in 2016 and 2017. The team had to sample present-day groundwater and springs believed to have supplied the aqueduct; however, acknowledging that the properties may have changed significantly, particularly after the 79 CE eruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specific sites studied included the Stabian baths and related structures, which were built after 130 BCE and remained active until the aforementioned eruption; the Republican baths, built around the same period but abandoned around 30 BCE; the Forum baths, built after 80 BCE; and the aqueduct and its 14 water towers, constructed during the Augustan period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were variations in the chemical composition of the deposits, indicating the replacement of boilers for heating water and a renewal of water pipes in the infrastructure of Pompeii, particularly during the time period when modifications were being made to the Republican baths. The results for the Republican baths’ heated pools, for instance, showed clear contamination from human activity, specifically human waste (sweat, sebum, urine, or bathing oil), which suggests the water wasn’t changed regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is consistent with the limitations of supplying water at the time; the water-lifting machines could really only refresh the water about once a day. After the well shaft was enlarged, the carbonate deposits were much thinner, evidence of technological improvements that reduced sloshing as the water was raised. Once the aqueduct had been built, the bathing facilities were expanded with a likely corresponding improvement in hygiene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, the aqueduct was a net good for Pompeii. “The changes in the water supply system of Pompeii revealed by carbonate deposits show an evolution from well-based to aqueduct-based supply with an increase in available water volume and in the scale of the bathing facilities, and likely an increase in hygiene,” the authors concluded. Granted, there was evidence of lead contamination in the water, particularly that supplied by the aqueduct, but carbonate deposits in the lead pipes seem to have reduced those levels over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results may also help resolve a scientific debate about the origins of the aqueduct water: Was it water from the town of Avella that connected to the Aqua Augusta aqueduct or from the wells of Pompeii/springs of Vesuvius? Per the authors, the stable isotope composition of carbonate in the aqueduct is inconsistent with carbonate from volcanic rock sources, thus supporting the Avella source hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PNAS, 2025. DOI:10.1073/pnas.2517276122(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/switching-water-sources-improved-hygiene-of-pompeiis-public-baths/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:00:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge: Trump violated Fifth Amendment by ending energy grants in only blue states</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-trump-violated-fifth-amendment-by-ending-energy-grants-in-only-blue-states/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2254848310-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump’s social media post triggers rare Fifth Amendment ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration violated the Fifth Amendment when canceling billions of dollars in environmental grants for projects in “blue states” that didn’t vote for him in the last election, a judge ruled Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s blatant discrimination came on the same day as the government shut down last fall. In total, 315 grants were terminated in October, ending support for 223 projects worth approximately $7.5 billion, the Department of Energy confirmed. All the awardees, except for one, were based in states where Donald Trump lost the majority vote to Kamala Harris in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only seven awardees sued, defending projects that helped states with “electric vehicle development, updating building energy codes, and addressing methane emissions.” They accused Trump officials of clearly discriminating against Democratic voters by pointing to their social media posts boasting about punishing blue states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On X, the director of the Office of Management and Budget, Russell Vought, bragged that nearly “$8 billion in Green NewScam funding to fuel the Left’s climate agenda is being cancelled,” then listed only states that did not vote for Trump. Meanwhile on Truth Social, Trump confirmed he met with Vought to “determine which of the many Democrat Agencies, most of which are a political SCAM, he recommends to be cut” during the shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, US District Judge Amit Mehta wrote in hisopinionthat the case was “unique” because ordinarily “the mere presence of political considerations in an agency action” does not mean that officials have run “afoul of the Fifth Amendment’s guarantee of equal protection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case, Trump “freely” admitted that he made grant termination decisions “primarily—if not exclusively—based on whether the awardee resided in a state whose citizens voted for President Trump in 2024.” And that classification had “no rational relationship” to the government’s supposed interest in cutting off funding, Mehta found, which was that projects were not “economically viable” or didn’t advance the administration’s energy goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, Mehta noted that similar projects in red states continued to receive funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no reason to believe that terminating an award to a recipient located in a state whose citizens tend to vote for Democratic candidates—and, particularly, voted against President Trump—furthers the agency’s energy priorities any more than terminating a similar grant of a recipient in a state whose citizens tend to vote for Republican candidates or voted for President Trump,” Mehta said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump officials offered “no explanation for how their purposeful segregation of grantees based on their electoral support for President Trump rationally advances their stated government interest,” Mehta said. Instead, “defendants concede that the political identity of a terminated grantee’s state, including the fact that the state supported Vice President Kamala Harris in the 2024 election, played a preponderant role in the October 2025 grant termination decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a total win for plaintiffs, who did not prevail on First Amendment claims, and there are many hundreds of awardees whose grant terminations were so far not impacted by the narrow ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deciding that the government had violated grantees’ rights to equal protection, Mehta only ordered a return to the status quo, reinstating seven grants totaling $27.6 million.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-trump-violated-fifth-amendment-by-ending-energy-grants-in-only-blue-states/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:27:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google removes some AI health summaries after investigation finds “dangerous” flaws</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/google-removes-some-ai-health-summaries-after-investigation-finds-dangerous-flaws/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-1488311999-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Overviews provided false liver test information experts called alarming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Googleremovedsome of itsAI Overviewshealth summaries after a Guardian investigation found people were being put at risk by false and misleading information. The removals came after the newspaper found that Google’s generative AI feature delivered inaccurate health information at the top of search results, potentially leading seriously ill patients to mistakenly conclude they are in good health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google disabled specific queries, such as “what is the normal range for liver blood tests,” after experts contacted by The Guardian flagged the results as dangerous. The report also highlighted a critical error regarding pancreatic cancer: The AI suggested patients avoid high-fat foods, a recommendation that contradicts standard medical guidance to maintain weight and could jeopardize patient health. Despite these findings, Google only deactivated the summaries for the liver test queries, leaving other potentially harmful answers accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation revealed that searching for liver test norms generated raw data tables (listing specific enzymes like ALT, AST, and alkaline phosphatase) that lacked essential context. The AI feature also failed to adjust these figures for patient demographics such as age, sex, and ethnicity. Experts warned that because the AI model’s definition of “normal” often differed from actual medical standards, patients with serious liver conditions might mistakenly believe they are healthy and skip necessary follow-up care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanessa Hebditch, director of communications and policy at the British Liver Trust, told The Guardian that a liver function test is a collection of different blood tests and that understanding the results “is complex and involves a lot more than comparing a set of numbers.” She added that the AI Overviews fail to warn that someone can get normal results for these tests when they have serious liver disease and need further medical care. “This false reassurance could be very harmful,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google declined to comment on the specific removals to The Guardian. A company spokespersontoldThe Verge that Google invests in the quality of AI Overviews, particularly for health topics, and that “the vast majority provide accurate information.” The spokesperson added that the company’s internal team of clinicians reviewed what was shared and “found that in many instances, the information was not inaccurate and was also supported by high-quality websites.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recurring problems with AI Overviews stem from a design flaw in how the system works. As wereportedin May 2024, Google built AI Overviews to show information backed up by top web results from its page ranking system. The company designed the feature this way based on the assumption that highly ranked pages contain accurate information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Google’s page ranking algorithm has long struggled with SEO-gamed content and spam. The system now feeds these unreliable results to its AI model, which then summarizes them with an authoritative tone that can mislead users. Even when the AI draws from accurate sources, the language model can stilldraw incorrect conclusionsfrom the data, producing flawed summaries of otherwise reliable information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology does not inherently provide factual accuracy. Instead, it reflects whatever inaccuracies exist on the websites Google’s algorithm ranks highly, presenting the facts with an authority that makes errors appear trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guardian found that typing slight variations of the original queries into Google, such as “lft reference range” or “lft test reference range,” still prompted AI Overviews. Hebditch said this was a big worry and that the AI Overviews present a list of tests in bold, making it very easy for readers to miss that these numbers might not even be the right ones for their test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Overviews still appear for other examples that The Guardian originally highlighted to Google. When asked why these AI Overviews had not also been removed, Google said they linked to well-known and reputable sources and informed people when it was important to seek out expert advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google said AI Overviews only appear for queries where it has high confidence in the quality of the responses. The company constantly measures and reviews the quality of its summaries across many different categories of information, it added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first controversy for AI Overviews. The feature has previouslytoldpeople to put glue on pizza and eat rocks. It has proven unpopular enough that users havediscoveredthat inserting curse words into search queries disables AI Overviews entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/google-removes-some-ai-health-summaries-after-investigation-finds-dangerous-flaws/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:47:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Verizon to stop automatic unlocking of phones as FCC ends 60-day unlock rule</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/fcc-lets-verizon-lock-phones-for-longer-making-it-harder-to-switch-carriers/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/12/verizon-jerks-locked-phone-1152x648-1765486982.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FCC waives rule that forced Verizon to unlock phones 60 days after activation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Communications Commission is letting Verizon lock phones to its network for longer periods, eliminating a requirement to unlock handsets 60 days after they are activated on its network. The change will make it harder for people to switch from Verizon to other carriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FCC todaygranted Verizon’s petitionfor a waiver of the 60-day unlocking requirement. While the waiver is in effect, Verizon only has to comply with theCTIA trade group’s voluntary unlocking policy. The CTIA policy calls for unlocking prepaid mobile devices one year after activation, while devices on postpaid plans can be unlocked after a contract, device financing plan, or early termination fee is paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlocking a phone allows it to be used on another carrier’s network. While Verizon was previously required to unlock phones automatically after 60 days, the CTIA code says carriers only have to unlock phones “upon request” from consumers. The FCC said the Verizon waiver will remain in effect until the agency “decides on an appropriate industry-wide approach for the unlocking of handsets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FCC rejected arequestto at least limit the locking period to 180 days. The agency’s order said the CTIA code provides “an adequate threshold of ensuring Verizon consumers have competitive options and that granting this waiver will not impede those competitive options. We thus decline to limit today’s waiver to a period of 180 days.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until today’s waiver order, Verizon faced strict unlocking requirements that didn’t apply to other carriers. But that was by choice, as Verizon gained significant benefits in exchange for agreeing to unlocking requirements in 2008 when itpurchased licensesto use 700 MHz spectrum, and again in 2021 when it agreed tomerger conditionsto obtain approval for itspurchase of TracFone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon used to sell phones that were already unlocked, but in 2019 it obtained awaiverthat allowed it to lock phones for 60 days in order to deter fraud. In March 2025, Verizon said the 60-day locking period wasn’t long enough to stop fraud andasked the FCCto waive the requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a press release today, the FCC said the Verizon rule “required one wireless carrier to unlock their handsets well earlier than standard industry practice, thus creating an incentive for bad actors to steal those handsets for purposes of carrying out fraud and other illegal acts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement from FCC Chairman Brendan Carr said, “Sophisticated criminal networks have exploited the FCC’s handset unlocking policies to carry out criminal acts—including transnational handset trafficking schemes and facilitating broader criminal enterprises like drug running and human smuggling. By waiving a regulation that incentivized bad actors to target one particular carrier’s handsets for theft, we now have a uniform industry standard that can help stem the flow of handsets into the black market.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’scurrent policyis for phones to be “remotely unlocked automatically 60 days after paid activation and 60 days of paid active service.” Phones already activated on the Verizon network won’t be affected by the waiver, according to the FCC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The terms of this waiver apply to all handsets that become active on Verizon’s network beginning the day after the release date of this Order,” the FCC ruling said. “The prospective application of this waiver will minimize customer confusion and interference with existing contractual arrangements and service agreements. Upon the release of this waiver, Verizon has stated that it will change its unlocking policies to follow those set out in the CTIA Consumer Code.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently wrote about a Kansas resident, Patrick Roach, whosued Verizonand complained to the FCC after the carrier refused to unlock an iPhone he purchased. Although the FCC took no action on Roach’s complaint, a small claims court ruled in his favor because Verizon tried to retroactively enforce a locking policy implemented in April 2025 on a phone Roach had bought before the policy change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’s April 2025 policy change required “60 days of paid active service” before Verizon would unlock a customer’s phone. Roach alleged that this violated the FCC condition, which required Verizon to unlock phones 60 days after activation and did not say that Verizon may refuse to unlock a phone when a customer has not maintained paid service for 60 days. Going forward, today’s FCC ruling will render that distinction moot and make it easier for Verizon to avoid unlocking phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Verizon petition was opposed in afilingby Public Knowledge, the Benton Foundation, Consumer Reports, the Electronic Frontier Foundation, iFixit, and other groups. The automatic unlocking enforced through the FCC condition was good for consumers and competition, the groups said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Automatic unlocking reduces switching costs, enhances competition, and promotes a more efficient and sustainable device marketplace,” the groups said. “It facilitates the resale and reuse of mobile devices, reduces e-waste, and enables low-cost carriers and MVNOs to compete on a more level playing field. The opposite, which Verizon seeks through its waiver request, merely serves as a way to keep customers locked in one provider.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consumer groups’ filing argued that “Verizon offers no specific evidence that a longer lock period would have prevented the fraudulent acquisition of the devices it identifies,” and said the carrier is capable of detecting and responding to fraud during the 60-day locking period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It can flag suspicious purchases, deny unlocking to devices that show signs of trafficking, and pursue legal or contractual remedies against fraudulent actors,” the groups said. “The Commission has previously found that 60 days is a reasonable and sufficient period to allow providers to identify and act upon fraudulent behavior. Verizon has not shown that these prior determinations were in error or that its current loss mitigation measures are being overwhelmed solely because of the unlocking rule.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FCC rejected these arguments, saying it found that the 60-day period has been insufficient to deter fraud. “Verizon explains that the globalization of 4G LTE and 5G technologies in recent years has created a ready overseas market for fraudulently obtained handsets, and stolen handsets are frequently sold or distributed to a secondary black market in countries that do not participate in GSMA blocking,” the FCC said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency said the waiver will address concerns of law enforcement associations that supported Verizon’s petition. “Law enforcement commenters have convincingly linked our handset unlocking policies and public safety matters on the basis that the current 60-day policy has impacted law enforcement lives and requires that law enforcement entities dedicate significant resources to investigating stolen handsets rather than focus on other public safety matters,” the FCC said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon issued a statement thanking the FCC for the waiver. “The FCC’s action will end bad actors’ ability to exploit the FCC’s unlocking rules to profit from easier access to expensive, heavily subsidized devices in the US that they traffic and sell to other parts of the world,” Verizon said. “Before today’s decision, the FCC’s rules have benefitted these international criminal gangs at the expense of legitimate American consumers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cable lobby group NCTA was not pleased by the FCC decision. Cable companies have increasingly been competing against large mobile carriers by offering wireless service in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mobile phone unlocking delivers clear pro-consumer benefits, saving billions of dollars across the mobile marketplace by expanding choice, competition, and affordability,” the NCTA said. “Today’s decision delays these benefits, underscoring the need for a clear, uniform framework so all wireless providers operate under the same rules.” The NCTA hasurged the FCCto implement a 180-day unlocking requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/fcc-lets-verizon-lock-phones-for-longer-making-it-harder-to-switch-carriers/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:07:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Even Linus Torvalds is trying his hand at vibe coding (but just a little)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/hobby-github-repo-shows-linus-torvalds-vibe-codes-sometimes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/LinuxCon_Europe_Linus_Torvalds_05-1152x648-1768254932.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But then I cut out the middle man—me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux and Git creator Linus Torvalds’ latest project contains code that was “basically written by vibe coding,” but you shouldn’t read that to mean that Torvalds is embracing that approach for anything and everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torvalds sometimes works on a small hobby projects over holiday breaks. Last year, he made guitar pedals. This year, he did some work on AudioNoise, which he calls “another silly guitar-pedal-related repo.” It creates random digital audio effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torvalds revealed that he had used an AI coding tool in the README forthe repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note that the python visualizer tool has been basically written by vibe-coding. I know more about analog filters—and that’s not saying much—than I do about python. It started out as my typical “google and do the monkey-see-monkey-do” kind of programming, but then I cut out the middle-man—me—and just used Google Antigravity to do the audio sample visualizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google’s Antigravity is a fork of the AI-focused IDE Windsurf. He didn’t specify which model he used, but using Antigravity suggests (but does not prove) that it was some version of Google’s Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Torvalds’ past public comments on using large language model-based tools for programming have been more nuanced than many online discussions about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He hastoutedAI primarily as “a tool to help maintain code, including automated patch checking and code review,” citing examples of tools that found problems he had missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, he has also said he is generally “much less interested in AI for writing code,” and has publicly said that he’s not anti-AI in principle, but he’s very much anti-hype around AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on that, you might be surprised that he used self-described vibe coding to build a part of his application, but you probably shouldn’t be. There are a few key things here. First, AudioNoise is entirely a personal hobby project, and it’s pretty much just a toy, not serious infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, Torvalds’ README note makes it clear that he went with this approach in an instance where he previously would have just copied something from a forum thread or StackOverflow anyway, as the visualizer tool component in the project is written in Python, which is not his specialty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers of all stripes are still fiercely debating what use (if any) AI coding tools should have in workflows. Just yesterday, developer Salvatore Sanfilippopublisheda widelycirculatedanddiscussedblog post arguing that such tools have already changed programming forever and aren’t going away, even as he acknowledged the related chaos and problems. He wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do I feel, about all the code I wrote that was ingested by LLMs? I feel great to be part of that, because I see this as a continuation of what I tried to do all my life: democratizing code, systems, knowledge. LLMs are going to help us to write better software, faster, and will allow small teams to have a chance to compete with bigger companies. The same thing open source software did in the 90s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, the debate about this has been spirited. But while people argue in Hacker News comments, Torvalds—normally known to be intensely opinionated himself—is vibe coding audio tools over the holidays.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/hobby-github-repo-shows-linus-torvalds-vibe-codes-sometimes/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:27:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Paramount sues WBD over Netflix deal. WBD says Paramount’s price is still inadequate.</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/paramount-sues-wbd-over-netflix-deal-wbd-says-paramounts-price-is-still-inadequate/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2215193098-1152x648-1768255617.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WBD calls Paramount’s lawsuit “meritless” and its offer deficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount Skydance escalated its hostile takeover bid of Warner Bros. Discovery (WBD) today by filing a lawsuit in Delaware Chancery Court against WBD, declaring its intention to fight Netflix’s acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, WBD agreed tosell its streaming and movie businesses to Netflixfor $82.7 billion. The deal would see WBD’s Global Networks division, comprised of WBD’s legacy cable networks, spun out into a separate company called Discovery Global. But in December,Paramount submitted a hostile takeover bidandamended its bidfor WBD. Subsequently, the company has aggressively tried to convince WBD’s shareholders that its $108.4 billion offer for all of WBD is superior to the Netflix deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Paramount CEO David Ellison wrote a letter to WBD shareholders informing them of Paramount’s lawsuit. The lawsuit requests the court to force WBD to disclose “how it valued the Global Networks stub equity, how it valued the overall Netflix transaction, how the purchase price reduction for debt works in the Netflix transaction, or even what the basis is for its ‘risk adjustment’” of Paramount’s $30 per share all-cash offer. Netflix’s offer equates to $27.72 per share, including $23.25 in cash and shares of Netflix common stock. Paramount hopes the information will encourage more WBD shareholders to tender their shares under Paramount’s offer by the January 21 deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before WBD announced the Netflix deal, Paramountpublicly questionedthe fairness of WBD’s bidding process. Paramount has since argued that its bid wasn’t given fair consideration or negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his letter today, Ellison wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We remain perplexed that WBD never responded to our December 4th offer, never attempted to clarify or negotiate any of the terms in that proposal, nor traded markups of contracts with us. Even as we read WBD’s own narrative of its process, we are struck that there were few actual board meetings in the period leading up to the decision to accept an inferior transaction with Netflix. And we are surprised by the lack of transparency on WBD’s part regarding basic financial matters. It just doesn’t add up – much like the math on how WBD continues to favor taking less than our $30 per share all-cash offer for its shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Paramount plans to nominate board directors for election at WBD’s annual shareholder meeting who will fight against the Netflix deal’s approval. The window for nominations opens in three weeks, Ellison’s letter noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount will also propose that WBD change its bylaws so that WBD’s shareholders have to approve a spinoff of WBD’s cable channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, WBD shared the following statement withDeadline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite six weeks and just as many press releases from Paramount Skydance, it has yet to raise the price or address the numerous and obvious deficiencies of its offer. Instead, Paramount Skydance is seeking to distract with a meritless lawsuit and attacks on a board that has delivered an unprecedented amount of shareholder value. In spite of its multiple opportunities, Paramount Skydance continues to propose a transaction that our board unanimously concluded is not superior to the merger agreement with Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WhenWBD’s board last rejected Paramount’s offeron January 7, it cited Paramount requiring an “extraordinary amount of debt financing,” as well as Paramount having a “junk credit rating” and negative free cash flows compared to Netflix’s “A/A3 crediting rating” and estimated free cash flow of over $12 billion this year. WBD said Paramount’s bid would result in $87 billion in debt and doesn’t cover expensive breakup fees should the Paramount deal fail to close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount has responded to concerns about its finances partially by tapping Ellison’s father, Oracle co-founder and CTO and theworld’s fourth richest man, Larry Ellison, to provide an irrevocable personal guarantee of $40.4 billion of the equity financing for Paramount’s bid. Ellison reaffirmed his familial assets in today’s letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Paramount is committed, my family is committed, and hopefully this helps answer the question of what comes next,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, price remains a top concern for WBD, which has also suggested that it could get more for its cable channels if they were sold separately from its movie studios and HBO Max. A Paramount deal would force WBD to stop working on the spinoff, which could be problematic if the merger fell apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WBD board chairman Samuel Di Piazza Jr. also noted that Paramount has failed to raise the price of its offer across multiple bids. “And so from our perspective, they’ve got to put something on the table that is compelling and is superior,” he said during a January 7 appearance onCNBC’sSquawk Box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statements from WBD shareholders suggest that Paramount still has a chance to woo WBD, whose investors have expressed varied opinions on Paramount’s offer, withsome large shareholdersrecentlystatingthey prefer Paramount’s offer or are open to further negotiation with Ellison’s firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Paramount having been reported to be eyeing a WBD acquisition forat least two years, it’s willing to fight a legal battle, but it’s unclear if it is willing to pay more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either Netflix’s or Paramount’s acquisition would require regulatory approval and could take 12 to 18 months to close. Amid the battle for WBD, Netflix hasstartedworking with regulatory bodies to further its acquisition.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/paramount-sues-wbd-over-netflix-deal-wbd-says-paramounts-price-is-still-inadequate/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:49:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>You can now reserve a hotel room on the Moon for $250,000</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/you-can-now-reserve-a-hotel-room-on-the-moon-for-250000/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/lunar-hotel-1-1152x648-1768258910.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can’t keep everyone living on that first ship that sailed to North America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company called GRU Space publicly announced its intent to construct a series of increasingly sophisticated habitats on the Moon, culminating in a hotel inspired by the Palace of the Fine Arts in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the company invited those interested in a berth toplunk down a depositbetween $250,000 and $1 million, qualifying them for a spot on one of its early lunar surface missions in as little as six years from now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds crazy, doesn’t it? After all, GRU Space had, as of late December when I spoke to founder Skyler Chan, a single full-time employee aside from himself. And Chan, in fact, only recently graduated from the University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this could therefore be dismissed as a lark. But I must say that I am a sucker for these kinds of stories. Chan is perfectly earnest about all of this. And despite all of the talk about lunar resources, my belief is that the surest long-term commercial activity on the Moon will be lunar tourism—it would be an amazing destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I interviewed Chan, I did so with an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many younger people, Chan grew up wanting to become an astronaut. But along the way, in high school and later college, he came to believe that he could lead a more impactful life by enabling everyone to go to space, not just himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I realized I was born in this time where we can actually become interplanetary, and that is probably the singular most impactful thing one person could do with their time,” Chan said. “So I charged towards building the systems necessary and technology to enable that future. That’s actually what led me to go to Berkeley to study electrical engineering and computer science.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had some interesting experiences in college, interning at Tesla to write vehicle software, and building a NASA-funded 3D printer launched into space. Chan also had a stunning realization about the Moon. There were all of these people building cool technology to get humans to the Moon. But he realized that the vast majority of this activity was backed by two pillars: the US government and billionaire-funded companies. Who, he wondered, was the ultimate customer for these services? And were there actually any commercial customers for what was being sold?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I realized we needed to create a third pillar: the space tourism industry,” he said. “We could extend a proven market to the Moon, and build the first hotel there. And then once we build the hotel on the Moon, we can build out our structures, you know, roads, warehouses, and bases. And then we can repeat that on Mars. So that’s what I decided to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He graduated in May 2025, a year early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GRU in the company’s name, by the way, stands for Galactic Resource Utilization. The long-term vision is to derive resources from the Moon, Mars, asteroids, and beyond to fuel human expansion into space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all that sounds audacious and unrealistic, well, it kind of is. But it is not without foundation. GRU Space has already received seed funding from Y Combinator, and it will go through the organization’s three-month program early this year. This will help Chan refine his company’s product and give him more options to raise money. Regarding his vision, you can read GRU Space’swhite paper here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presently, the company plans to fly its initial “mission” in 2029 as a 10-kg payload on a commercial lunar lander, demonstrating an inflatable structure capability and converting lunar regolith into Moon bricks usinggeopolymers. With its second mission, the company plans to launch a larger inflatable structure into a “lunar pit” to test a scaled-up version of its resource development capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first hotel, an inflatable structure, would be launched in 2032 and would be capable of supporting up to four guests at a time. The next iteration beyond this would be the fancier structure, built from Moon bricks, in the style of the Palace of the Fine Arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One question I had was: Why have a hotel at all? Presumably, the company’s customers will be riding to the Moon inside SpaceX’s Starship, which will have plenty of interior room and proven life support equipment by the time tourists are flying aboard it (if they ever do).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“SpaceX is building the FedEx to get us there, right?” Chan said. “But there has to be a destination worthy to stay in. Obviously, there is all kinds of debate around this, and what the future is going to be like. But our conviction is that the fundamental problem we have to solve, to advance humans toward the Moon and Mars, is off-world habitation. We can’t keep everyone living on that first ship that sailed to North America, right? We have to build the roads and structures and offices that we live in today.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/you-can-now-reserve-a-hotel-room-on-the-moon-for-250000/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:04:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Anthropic launches Cowork, a Claude Code-like for general computing</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/anthropic-launches-cowork-a-claude-code-like-for-general-computing/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Claude-Cowork-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can give Claude access to a folder and tell it what to do for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropic’s agentic tool Claude Code has been an enormous hit with some software developers and hobbyists, and now the company is bringing that modality to more general office work with anew feature called Cowork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built on the same foundations as Claude Code and baked into the macOS Claude desktop app, Cowork allows users to give Claude access to a specific folder on their computer and then give plain language instructions for tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropic gave examples like filling out an expense report from a folder full of receipt photos, writing reports based on a big stack of digital notes, or reorganizing a folder (or cleaning up your desktop) based on a prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of this was already possible with Claude Code, but it might not have been clear to all users that it could be used that way, and Claude Code required more technical know-how to set up. Anthropic’s goal with Cowork is to make it something any knowledge worker—from developers to marketers—could get rolling with right away. Anthropic says it started working on Cowork partly because people were already using Claude Code for general knowledge work tasks anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve already been doing things similar to this with the Claude desktop app viaModel Context Protocol (MCP), prompting it to perform tasks like creating notes directly in my Obsidian vault based on files I showed it, but this is clearly a cleaner way to do some of that—and there are Claude Code-like usability perks here, like the ability to make new requests or amendments to the assignment with a new message before the initial task is complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, there are some causes for concern. Generally speaking, you expect a Claude Code-using developer or a hobbyist geeky enough to play around with MCP to understand the risks in what they’re doing. Less technical users might not have that foresight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropic’s announcement about Cowork names a few potential concerns up front. First, you have to be careful with how you word your prompts, as a vague one (or, frankly, just incredibly bad luck) can lead the agent to do destructive things like unexpectedly delete files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s also the very real, seemingly unsolvable risk of prompt injection attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given all of that, Cowork is currently available only as a research preview to Max subscribers. There’s no word about when it might see a wider release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the only effort Anthropic has made to branch out beyond its established footprint among coders this week. Yesterday, the company also announcedClaude for Healthcare, competing with OpenAI’ssimilar announcementof a health management tool for ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/anthropic-launches-cowork-a-claude-code-like-for-general-computing/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:42:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>