<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:33:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>A West Virginia Law Bars One Trans Athlete. Her Case Could Affect the Country.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/supreme-court-transgender-sports.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-scotus-trans-kwmp/12dc-scotus-trans-kwmp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becky Pepper-Jackson was 11 years old and a mediocre runner when she sued the State of West Virginia over a law that barred transgender girls like her from joining girls’ sports teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next four years, Ms. Pepper-Jackson’s status on the school track team was in doubt as judges blocked the law, then unblocked it and then blocked it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now 15, she is an accomplished shot-putter and discus thrower. A decision about whether she can compete for her final two years of high school will now fall to the Supreme Court, which on Tuesday will hear her challenge to the West Virginia law that supporters said was intended to ensure fair competition for female athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, Ms. Pepper-Jackson said she was devastated when the law took effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I want to be able to play on the team with my friends, and that’s all I’ve wanted to do,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pepper-Jackson is the only known athlete in West Virginia who would be subject to the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But her case — and a separate matter from Idaho dealing with college sports that the court is also hearing on Tuesday — has implications far beyond her personal sports saga.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-five other states have enacted similar restrictions since 2020, amid a backlash to transgender students participating in school sports and transgender rights broadly. However the Supreme Court rules this year, the decision could affect all of those states, and the student athletes who seek to play in schools and colleges there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcome may also further influence the national conversation about transgender people in American society. President Trump targeted the community in his last presidential campaign and declared at his inauguration that it would be the “official policy of the United States government that there are only two genders: male and female.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February, surrounded by young female athletes in uniform, Mr. Trump signed an executive order directing agencies to withdraw federal funding from schools that allow transgender athletes in girls’ and women’s sports. The next day, the N.C.A.A., which for years had tried to balance fairness with inclusion in college sports, announced it would bar trans women from competing in women’s sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court has similarly moved against transgender rights and seems likely to reject the trans athletes’ claims based on recent rulings. After protecting transgender people from workplace discrimination in a 2020 decision written by Justice Neil M. Gorsuch, a Trump appointee, the court in June upheld a Tennessee law that prohibits certain medical treatments for transgender adolescents. In a case they heard in October, the justices also seemed poised to strike down a Colorado law that bars mental health professionals from seeking to change a minor’s gender identity through so-called conversion therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for West Virginia and Idaho, the Trump administration and other supporters say the sports laws are needed, claiming transgender girls and women have a competitive edge. Allowing them to compete on girls’ teams, they say, takes away opportunities for female athletes and reverses five decades of progress for women in sports since the passage of Title IX, the civil rights law that bars sex discrimination in schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;West Virginia’s attorney general, John McCuskey, whose office is defending the law, said the restrictions like the one his state adopted in 2021 were not only constitutional but also “common sense” because men are “bigger, faster and stronger.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, Mr. McCuskey, a father of two daughters who play soccer, said, “When you watch your children putting all of this insane and incredible internal effort into being great at something, the idea that their place on one of those teams would be taken by somebody that has a noticeable and obvious unfair advantage does make it personal to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts to bar transgender athletes from women’s sports have seen broad support in polls. A New York Times/Ipsos poll conducted last year found that nearly 80 percent of Americans, including two-thirds of Democrats, opposed allowing transgender women to compete in women’s sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case has attracted the attention of former Olympians, soccer standouts and N.C.A.A. stars, who submitted competing briefs. Some of the athletes urged the court to ensure “a level playing field” for female athletes by limiting participation to people assigned female at birth. Others said the justices should not prevent trans girls and women from experiencing the benefits of being part of a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idaho law was challenged by Lindsay Hecox, a college student who tried out for the women’s track and cross-country teams and played club soccer. Challenges to both states’ laws argue that the restrictions violate the Constitution’s guarantee of equal protection, which requires the government to have valid reasons for treating people differently. Two appeals courts have sided with the students and blocked enforcement of the laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wrinkle in the Idaho case came when Ms. Hecox, now 24 and a senior at Boise State University, moved to withdraw her suit in September, saying she would refrain from playing school-sponsored women’s sports. Ms. Hecox, who receives testosterone suppression and estrogen treatment, cited negative public scrutiny that would distract from her academics and her plans to graduate in May. In response, the justices said they would defer a decision about whether to dismiss her case as moot until after Tuesday’s argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West Virginia, Ms. Pepper-Jackson, who was assigned male at birth, transitioned in third grade. She has legally changed her name, and her birth certificate recognizes her as female. She says that because she takes puberty-blocking medication, she has not gone through typical male puberty and does not have the muscle mass, bone density or hormone levels of boys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, Ms. Pepper-Jackson said she was inspired by her two older brothers to join the middle school cross-country team and was crushed when West Virginia’s governor signed the law a few months before tryouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the help of the American Civil Liberties Union, she and her mother, Heather Jackson, filed a lawsuit, saying the ban violated Title IX protections against sex discrimination in schools and the 14th Amendment’s equal protection guarantee. Among the questions for the justices on Tuesday is whether the word “sex” under Title IX means only biological sex or includes gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pepper-Jackson’s improvement on the field has made her legal case more challenging, as opponents have argued she has taken opportunities from other girls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a lackluster cross-country performance in sixth grade in which, according to her court filings, she regularly finished “near the back of the pack,” Ms. Pepper-Jackson said her coach recommended that she instead try throwing the shot put and discus. Her mother created a practice pit in the backyard, mapping out the precise measurements in the space where an aboveground pool once stood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pepper-Jackson said she stayed late for double practice sessions at school and lifted weights all summer. She carried a broomstick behind her neck to work on keeping her arms up and back straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a freshman at Bridgeport High School, she qualified for the state tournament last May, and placed eighth in shot put and third in discus. West Virginia’s lawyers, citing state athletic statistics, said in just one season, she beat out and “displaced nearly 400 female competitors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Ms. Pepper-Jackson said she recognized that there were a limited number of spots for athletes in the championships, but she put in the work to earn one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think they’re understanding how much effort I am truly putting in behind the scenes,” she said in a Zoom interview, with her mother and two rambunctious Great Danes in the background. “I don’t think they care.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A teammate who initially beat Ms. Pepper-Jackson in throwing competitions later objected to her participation after Ms. Pepper-Jackson outperformed her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a filing at the Supreme Court, Adaleia Cross, 17, said she was angry and discouraged that Ms. Pepper-Jackson had “taken her spot” in a 2023 competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Cross said she was initially reluctant to speak out for fear that she would be labeled transphobic, but decided to do so in part because she alleged that Ms. Pepper-Jackson had made vulgar remarks in the middle school locker room, making her feel embarrassed and fearful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court, like all appellate courts, is not supposed to consider facts and allegations, like Ms. Cross’s, that were not part of the record in the lower courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Cross and her family declined to be interviewed but have shared their stories on a website maintained by her lawyers. They are represented by the Alliance Defending Freedom, the Christian conservative legal organization that is also assisting the attorneys general from Idaho and West Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The middle school investigated Ms. Cross’s complaint in 2023 and concluded that the allegations “could not be substantiated,” according to a letter from the school system’s lawyer reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pepper-Jackson denied the allegations as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was not raised like that,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pepper-Jackson’s case first reached the Supreme Court on an emergency basis in 2023. The justices at that time issued a brief order allowing her to compete while litigation continued. The order gave no reasons. Justices Clarence Thomas and Samuel A. Alito Jr. dissented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, a divided panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit said the law could not be enforced against Ms. Pepper-Jackson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority found that the law discriminated in violation of Title IX by preventing trans girls — but not trans boys — from participating on teams consistent with their gender identity and did so “regardless of whether any given girl possesses any inherent athletic advantages based on being transgender.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that Ms. Pepper-Jackson had not gone through male puberty, allowing her to play on a boys’ team would require her to share the field with boys who are “larger, stronger and faster than her because of the elevated levels of circulating testosterone she lacks,” wrote Judge Toby J. Heytens, joined by Judge Pamela A. Harris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In dissent, Judge G. Steven Agee said Ms. Pepper-Jackson’s participation had taken opportunities from girls who were born female, precisely what West Virginia’s law was intended to prevent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Allowing transgender girls — regardless of any advantage — as participants in biological girls’ sports turns Title IX on its head and reverses the monumental work Title IX has done to promote girls’ sports from its inception,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the litigation, West Virginia’s lawyers have said Ms. Pepper-Jackson could instead compete on the boys’ track and field team. But she insists that is not an option. Her reasoning: “I’m not a man.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/supreme-court-transgender-sports.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 05:59:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mary Peltola Runs for Senate in Alaska, Lifting Democrats’ Hopes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mary-peltola-senate-alaska.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/10/07/us/politics/pol-peltola-senate-hfo/pol-peltola-senate-hfo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Former Representative Mary Peltola of Alaska, a Democrat, announced on Monday that she was running for the state’s Senate seat, giving Democrats a big boost as they fight an uphill battle to win back the Senate in the midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Peltola, who was Alaska’s sole House member from 2022 until her defeat in 2024, is one of her red state’s few prominent Democrats. She has been considered perhaps the only person who could pose a threat to Senator Dan Sullivan, a Republican who is up for re-election this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her announcement video, Ms. Peltola made clear that she planned to position herself as a political outsider fixated on state and local issues like Alaska’s fishing industry and rising cost of living. She resurrected a slogan she used during her House campaigns — “fish, family and freedom” — and said she would propose term limits for members of Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not just that politicians in D.C. don’t care that we’re paying $17 a gallon for milk in rural Alaska — they don’t even believe us,” Ms. Peltola said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her entry is the final puzzle piece of the Senate recruitment map for Democrats, who need to flip four seats this fall to take a majority. The party has picked up top recruits to take on Republicans in Ohio, North Carolina and now Alaska, but faces intense primary contests in Maine, Iowa and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Peltola had been heavily coveted as a candidate by top Senate Democrats, led by Chuck Schumer of New York, the minority leader, as the party’s best chance to make Alaska competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans dismissed Ms. Peltola as “a defeated career politician-turned-lobbyist,” in the words of Alex Latcham, the executive director of the Senate Leadership Fund, the leading super PAC for Senate Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Democrats are desperately trying to revive a far-left politician, but Alaskans know why they fired Mary Peltola in the first place,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had been an open question in the state whether Ms. Peltola would opt to join the Senate race, seek to regain her House seat or run for governor, a seat that will be open because Gov. Mike Dunleavy, a Republican, is term-limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Peltola is considered a star of Democratic politics in Alaska, with others in the party suggesting they would step aside from the governor’s race if she had instead entered that field. She will be a heavy favorite to advance out of the state’s nonpartisan primary system, in which the top four vote-getters move onto the general election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite her popularity in the state, she is likely to be an underdog in a general election against Mr. Sullivan, because of the state’s longtime conservative lean. But Alaska has an independent streak, and its voters have repeatedly re-elected Senator Lisa Murkowski, one of the most moderate Republicans in Congress, over more conservative challengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Peltola pointedly praised two Alaska Republicans in her kickoff video and even borrowed a tagline from President Trump, saying that Alaskans needed to “teach the rest of the country what Alaska First and, really, America First looks like.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Murkowski crossed party lines to endorse Ms. Peltola during her two House races in 2022 and 2024, but she told Alaska Public Media in an interview published on Monday that this time around, she was endorsing her Senate colleague, Mr. Sullivan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve had a pretty solid team here in the Senate for the past 12 years, so we want to figure out how we’re going to keep in the majority,” Ms. Murkowski said. “And Dan delivers that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Peltola, the first Alaska Native elected to Congress and a former state legislator, beat former Gov. Sarah Palin in a 2022 special election to fill the seat of Don Young, a longtime congressman who died that year. It was an upset win that flipped the seat blue for the first time since the 1970s. She then won a full term that fall, with Alaska’s ranked-choice voting system vaulting her past Ms. Palin and Nick Begich III, another Republican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Begich won a rematch in 2024, ousting Ms. Peltola by two percentage points. Ms. Peltola, who in Congress sometimes bucked her party to back oil drilling projects, joined a law and lobbying firm last year that specializes in energy and mining issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats face a tough Senate map this year: Not only must they flip four Republican-held seats — including some in states that Mr. Trump won in 2024 — but they also need to defend vulnerable seats of their own in Michigan and Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their best pickup opportunities are in Maine — where Senator Susan Collins is the only Republican senator in a blue state — and in North Carolina, a battleground state where Senator Thom Tillis, also a Republican, is retiring. But Democrats will have to venture into red territory, with states like Ohio, Iowa, Texas and Alaska offering narrow but possible paths to retake a majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schumer has now secured several top-tier Senate recruits, including former Gov. Roy Cooper in North Carolina and former Senator Sherrod Brown in Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mary-peltola-senate-alaska.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 07:22:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Green Beret Went on a Shooting Rampage. Is the Army at Fault?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/blast-brain-injury-green-beret-shooting-duke-webb.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/01/us/xxnat-blasts-webb-1/xxnat-blasts-webb-1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sgt. First Class Duke Webb was an active-duty Green Beret with seven deployments and a flawless record when he entered a bowling alley in Rockford, Ill., one night and started shooting people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one had done anything to provoke him. He just seemed to snap. He shot a 14-year-old boy in the face by the front door, and a 16-year-old girl in the shoulder when she tried to hide. Then he walked into the snack bar and continued to fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time the police tackled him that evening in 2020, three people were wounded and three were dead. He has been awaiting trial for first-degree murder ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has admitted that he pulled the trigger. The question is why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PTSD is the obvious guess. But there is little in Sergeant Webb’s record to support it. He was only in one real firefight, and no one on his team was hit by enemy fire that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real cause, Sergeant Webb and people close to him say, had nothing to do with combat — but everything to do with his Army service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Operations troops train relentlessly, jumping from planes, firing shoulder-fired rockets and setting off explosives. The years of training exposes them to so many weapons blasts and knocks to the head that it can erode their ability to do the job, or even to function normally. Many end up with significant brain injuries — injuries that are often missed by the Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is what Sergeant Webb says happened to him. After 12 years in uniform, he was having splitting headaches and developed a facial tic. He often lost his train of thought and became so consumed by strange, conspiratorial anxiety that he began insisting that his girlfriend use a code name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army never diagnosed a brain injury, but medical officers grew so concerned that they prescribed for the sergeant a drug used to treat advanced Alzheimer’s disease. He was 37 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he walked into the bowling alley 16 days later, he told the police afterward, he didn’t understand where he was or what he was doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His lawyers have argued in court filings that the Alzheimer’s drug, called memantine, pushed his already injured brain past its limits, and that when he opened fire, he was in the grip of psychosis caused by the medication. He has pleaded not guilty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I know what I did was wrong, and I deserve to be in here suffering,” Sergeant Webb said in a telephone interview in the fall, in which he sometimes lost his train of thought and rambled. “But the military used me up, then abandoned me,” he said. “I feel left behind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to understand whether off-label medication and years of blast exposure had contributed to the killings, the Army quickly cut ties with Sergeant Webb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the bowling alley shooting, it sent a psychologist to assess Sergeant Webb in jail. The military wanted to force him out of the Army, but federal law required it to first determine whether he was medically fit to be discharged, or had a service-related injury that required Army care. The psychologist wrote that Sergeant Webb probably had experienced a “brief psychotic disorder,” and showed signs of PTSD and a brain injury. The Green Beret was not fit to be discharged, he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army discharged him anyway. The paperwork rated his service as “other than honorable,” cutting him off from veterans’ medical care and benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now three possible outcomes for Sergeant Webb’s criminal case. A jury could find him guilty and send him to prison for life. It could find him not guilty by reason of insanity, and send him to be confined in a state hospital where he would be treated and perhaps eventually released. Or it could decide that the drug prescribed by the Army temporarily made him insane through no fault of his own, and let him walk free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In none of those scenarios, though, would the Army learn whether blast exposure in training played a role in what happened, or how that training may be hurting other soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb has been in jail for five years, much of it in solitary confinement. In part because of his rattled mental state, he has replaced his legal team several times, delaying his trial and exhausting his savings — about $400,000. He has grown hopeless and at times suicidal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just get tired of living with myself,” Sergeant Webb said. “The people I served with, most of them seem to have forgotten about me. What I did was so horrible, no one wants to take the time to try to understand why it happened.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb joined the Green Berets in 2010 after two years in the regular Army. He was assigned to 7th Special Forces Group at Eglin Air Force Base in Florida and began a grueling decade of training and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army sent him to explosives school, sniper school, jump school and dive school. He learned to fire mortars and other heavy weapons that can cause brain injuries. He deployed three times to Latin America and four times to Afghanistan. Though combat exposure was minimal, blast exposure was constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Latin America, he taught partner armies how to create landing zones in the forest using explosives. In Afghanistan, he trained local troops to detonate mines, and blew up abandoned American military equipment to keep it out of Taliban hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“None of those blasts completely rocked you — they didn’t hurt,” Sergeant Webb said in the interview. “But you could feel them in every part of your body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In interviews, Sergeant Webb and several other Green Berets estimated that only 10 to 20 percent of their overall blast exposure had come in combat. The vast majority was from training, not war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brain is an exceptionally delicate network of some 100 trillion neural connections. Blast waves surging through repeatedly can fray its tiny fibers or break them. When damage piles up, the brain’s reactions can become hard to predict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in his career, Sergeant Webb had a reputation in Special Forces for being meticulous, calm and motivated. “He was a go-getter, very smart, well spoken, squared away, never in trouble,” said his former team leader, retired Master Sgt. Duane Flores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over time, Sergeant Webb started to unravel. It began with restless sleep and disturbing dreams, then headaches so severe that he worried he might have a brain tumor. His thoughts grew scattered, and he struggled to retain information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army treated the symptoms without diagnosing a larger cause. He got medicine for his headaches, and the stimulant Adderall for concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His girlfriend at the time, Monica Gonzales, watched him gradually grow so fearful and suspicious that he started to refer to her outside the house only by the code name Matilda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It got worse over time, to the point that it was really making me nervous,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb is an extreme case of a much larger problem in Special Operations that the military is largely blind to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years of intense training and exposure to weapons blast waves can cause profound scarring in the brain that makes top-performing soldiers fall apart. But in case after case, the military has missed the onset of these kinds of brain injuries, in part because there is usually no obvious single accident or attack to point to as a cause, and in part because the symptoms can resemble those of PTSD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In career Special Operations troops, insomnia, anxiety, confusion and other problems are so common that the pattern has been given a name: Operator Syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Murder and other violent crimes are a rare outcome, but when they occur, the military does little to understand whether brain injuries played a role. If troops are arrested in the civilian world, the military simply discharges them and moves on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to questions from The New York Times, Special Operations Command, which oversees all Green Berets and Navy SEALs, acknowledged that “years of routine training and weapons use, particularly exposure to blast overpressure, can pose risks for brain injuries in career operators.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for the command, Col. Allie Weiskopf, said it was changing some training to reduce exposure, and increasing screening for injuries. The changes, she said, exemplify Special Operations Command’s “commitment to supporting the well-being of its personnel throughout their entire careers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When blast-exposed troops have turned violent, though, the military has repeatedly dismissed the possible role of cumulative brain injury, in favor of explanations that don’t implicate its training or equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2002, four soldiers at Fort Bragg murdered their wives in a six-week span. Three were senior enlisted Special Forces soldiers just back from Afghanistan. The fourth was a combat engineer in a unit that had done extensive explosive disposal work in Kosovo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Army investigation initially focused on whether a malaria drug could be at fault, and eventually concluded that pre-existing marital problems were largely to blame. It never considered blast exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, an Army National Guard staff sergeant who had spent years as a grenade instructor killed 18 people in Maine, and then died by suicide. A civilian laboratory that examined tissue from his brain found damage that it said was consistent with repeated blast exposure. The Army said it saw no connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb wasn’t the only member of his Special Forces team who was struggling. His communications sergeant, Aaron Tugmon, started to have crippling panic attacks and insomnia. Reading became a struggle, and remembering nearly impossible. The Army prescribed drugs for sleep, anxiety, depression, and headaches, plus Adderall for concentration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Before I knew it, I was on, like, eight pills, and the Army never really looked at the cause,” said Mr. Tugmon, who retired as a chief warrant officer in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their former team leader, Sergeant Flores, had many of the same problems, and the Army put him on many of the same drugs. He fought to control his emotions, and one morning, he chased a man who had been tailgating him and got into a physical confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was clear something ain’t right,” he recalled in an interview. “That’s when I went for help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was medically retired from the Army in 2020. Afterward, he worked as a civilian for a Special Operations program that encourages soldiers to seek health care. The job revealed to him how widespread the problems were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I would say, 90 percent of our operators are driving with the engine light on, trying to ignore their problems until they can’t anymore,” he said. “Very little of it rises to the level of murder, but there are assaults, suicides, drugs, domestic problems. A lot of people are hurting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems also show up in career Navy SEALs, said Chris Frueh, a psychology professor at the University of Hawaii who encountered the pattern when working with SEALs transitioning to civilian life. Unsure how to properly categorize what he was seeing, in 2020 he proposed the “Operator Syndrome” designation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are probably many contributing causes, including chronic stress, sleep disturbance and exposure to combat, Mr. Frueh said, “but maybe the biggest factor is brain injury.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By his seventh deployment in 2020, Sergeant Webb was a wreck. He was in an intelligence job at a secure base in Afghanistan, working largely at a desk, but his headaches grew so intense that he often had to stop and lie down in a dark room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I felt like I could feel the synapses misfiring, like my brain was just scrambled eggs,” he recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he got home in August 2020, he seemed different in ways that friends found hard to explain. He had always been meticulously neat, but now his house was cluttered with unfinished projects. Commuting to work one morning, he saw a cardboard box on the roadside and was so sure the logo on it was a sign of communist activity that he filed a report with Special Forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He would cry over all sorts of things,” said Ms. Gonzales, who remained friends with him after they separated in 2019. “He was sure people were out to get him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2020, the pain and confusion grew so bad that he sought help from a Special Forces psychiatrist. The doctor scheduled him to come back in a month for a brain injury assessment, and prescribed memantine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drug is approved to treat late-stage Alzheimer’s, and is sometimes prescribed off-label for other forms of dementia and for headaches. But patients must be monitored carefully, because in rare cases, it can cause serious side effects, including psychotic delusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb never made it to his follow-up appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days after starting to take memantine, he traveled to Rockford, where his father was in a coma after an auto accident. He stayed with his half brother, Anthony Gonzales, who immediately noticed that something was off. The Green Beret had developed a stutter, blinked hard while speaking and peered constantly out windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I figured it was PTSD or something, and just tried to let him know it was all OK,” Mr. Gonzales said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb stayed in Illinois through Christmas. During that time, he said in an interview, he became convinced that the federal government had been replaced by a shadowy conspiracy of Communists, Russian operatives and violent street gangs, and that ordinary people he encountered — hospital workers, waitresses, delivery drivers — were in on the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Christmas night, he told the police, he sat awake with a gun, afraid that someone was going to attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before Sergeant Webb was scheduled to return to Florida, Mr. Gonzales had to go to work at a bowling alley called Don Carter Lanes, where he was the cook and night manager. He asked Sergeant Webb to come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the alley, Mr. Gonzales took his half brother to the snack bar, gave him a menu and told him to pick something out. Mr. Gonzales went to the kitchen to cook. Sergeant Webb quietly scanned the room, his thoughts reeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like the most extraordinarily vivid combat dream I’ve ever had, and I felt everyone was trying to kill me,” he said later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He became so agitated that he vomited in the snack bar, and then went to find his half brother in the kitchen. As he did, he pulled out a concealed handgun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I tried to calm him down,” Mr. Gonzales recalled. “I said, ‘You’re surrounded by good people. Ain’t nobody gonna hurt you.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Webb put his gun away, took a few deep breaths and appeared to relax. He left the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minute later, Mr. Gonzales heard a loud bang, as if someone had dropped a bowling ball. Then several more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the kitchen, he saw his brother pointing a gun. “I yelled, ‘Duke, no!’” Mr. Gonzales said. “He snapped his head and looked at me. But you could tell by his look that it wasn’t really him. I saw that look, and I took off running.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read by Dave Philipps&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio produced by Jack D’Isidoro and Sarah Diamond.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/blast-brain-injury-green-beret-shooting-duke-webb.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:14:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Inside Democrats’ Brewing Debate Over Which States Should Vote First in 2028</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/state-vote-democrats-president-2028.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/09/us/politics/pol-dems-2028/pol-dems-2028-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party insiders are beginning to puzzle over one of the more consequential decisions for the party’s future: which states should vote first in the 2028 presidential primary elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should Democrats begin the primary race with a battleground state? Is a racially diverse state like Nevada — with its big Latino population — the way to go? Or is a smaller state like New Hampshire, with its long tradition of town hall events and passionate voters, best?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the party should return to South Carolina, whose base of Black voters is the heart of the party in a region where Democrats desperately need to improve? Or maybe Democrats should go back to Iowa, full of the types of rural voters whom the party has so thoroughly lost touch with?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategists say the order of states will heavily influence how the primary campaign unfolds — and who ultimately winds up as the face of the Democratic Party in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The purpose of the order is to tell a story,” said Stuart Appelbaum, an influential union president who sits on the Democratic National Committee panel that will decide which states go first. “The importance of the Democratic primary calendar is establishing a narrative of what the Democratic Party is about.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Democratic National Committee has set a Friday deadline for states to apply to be placed in the so-called early window, the month leading up to Super Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate has only just begun. But early whisper campaigns about the weaknesses of the various options already offer a revealing window into some of the party’s racial, regional and rural-urban divides, according to interviews with more than a dozen state party chairs, D.N.C. members and others involved in the selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevada is too far to travel. New Hampshire is too entitled and too white. South Carolina is too Republican. Iowa is also too white — and its time has passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not a top battleground? Michigan entered the early window in 2024, but critics see it as too likely to bring attention to the party’s fractures over Israel. North Carolina or Georgia would need Republicans to change their election laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, Iowa and New Hampshire began the presidential nominating calendar for both parties. But President Joseph R. Biden Jr. shook that up for Democrats’ 2024 primary contest and put South Carolina first, after the state’s Black voters propelled him to the nomination in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three states are angling to stay at the front of the line, even as Nevada tries to leapfrog them. Other states, including Michigan and Georgia, are jockeying to be in the early mix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Party officials say they are starting from scratch for 2028. D.N.C. guidelines say one state each from four regions — the East, the Midwest, the South and the West — will be included in the early primaries before Super Tuesday, potentially along with a fifth bonus state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are going in with an open mind,” said Jane Kleeb, the chair of the Nebraska Democratic Party and an influential committee member who is also a national vice chair. Her state is not applying, she said. “Could it be a totally new calendar? Yes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kleeb said she was prioritizing not just general-election battlegrounds but also states where Democrats could compete in down-ballot races.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials said the most aggressive lobbying so far had come from Nevada, which has voted early in recent cycles but never first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the party’s December meeting in Los Angeles, Nevada’s advocates not-so-subtly dropped cactus-themed holiday cards on the seats of the 49 members of the D.N.C. Rules and Bylaws Committee, which will decide the order of the primaries. Later, the Nevada secretary of state, Cisco Aguilar, spoke to the full D.N.C. membership and rankled some with a presumptuous line about looking forward to the chance to run a first-in-the-nation primary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The D.N.C. has set three broad criteria for early states that are open to interpretation: “rigorousness,” “fairness” and “efficiency.” The party concluded that together, “the lineup of early states must be a comprehensive test of candidates with diverse groups of voters that are key to winning the general election.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules committee members are set to travel to Puerto Rico at the end of January to discuss the calendar, with a final decision still months away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevada’s supporters argue that the Western state has something to please everyone: It’s small. It’s a battleground. It has influential labor unions. It has a diverse population based in Las Vegas. But it also has many rural enclaves across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The case is clear,” said Hilary Barrett, the Nevada Democratic Party’s executive director. “If Democrats are serious about winning back working-class voters, Nevada should be first in the nation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Party officials also have to contend with a patchwork of state laws that have already set some primary calendars. New Hampshire, for instance, has a law that it must hold the first primary nationwide — which it did in 2024, even after Democrats threatened to bar the state’s delegation from the party’s convention. (The delegates were eventually seated.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our laws are clear,” said Ray Buckley, the New Hampshire Democratic Party’s veteran chairman. He said that his state’s voters took their responsibility to vet candidates as seriously as anyone and that “we certainly aren’t out to get any other state,” but that voting first was part of the state’s character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s in our DNA,” Mr. Buckley said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rita Hart, the Iowa Democratic Party chairwoman, said her state was applying to be in the early mix again, and was open to again holding a caucus so it would not conflict with New Hampshire’s law about primaries. The counting of votes in Iowa’s Democratic caucuses in 2020 was a disaster. “Lessons learned,” Ms. Hart said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was a mistake in the last go-around that we didn’t include a state in the middle of the country that had a rural electorate,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa has one other main argument: Republicans are set to caucus there first in 2028 no matter what the D.N.C. decides, meaning that skipping the state would leave all the attention there to Republicans. “Iowa is unique in that,” Ms. Hart said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Carolina’s spot at the very front of the line appears tenuous, according to party officials, largely because Democrats have not seriously competed in recent statewide races there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Christale Spain, the chair of South Carolina Democratic Party, said that putting a Southern state first would send a message about the importance of Black voters as well as the party’s geographic priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the party wants to change things nationally, we have to start winning in the South,” she said. “South Carolina going first is the South going first.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some states that might want to be considered would need approval from Republican-controlled state legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not an answer we can have right now,” Charlie Bailey, the chairman of the Georgia Democratic Party, said of changing his state’s laws. But he urged the inclusion of his state — along with South Carolina — in the kickoff group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are the definition of a battleground — it can be won and it can be lost,” Mr. Bailey said, pitching his state’s diversity. “If you can’t win in the South, you can’t have a national governing coalition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Carolina Democrats are also interested in an earlier primary. “You are not going to keep the presidency with just the blue wall,” said Anderson Clayton, the state party chair, referring to Pennsylvania, Michigan and Wisconsin. But her state would also need Republicans to sign off on moving up its primary, and it is uncertain if Democrats there will apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota, which applied to be in the early window four years ago, will not apply this year, according to its Democratic chairman, Richard Carlbom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One state that moved up its primary by law before 2024 was Michigan. Mr. Biden faced no serious Democratic rival that year, but his support for Israel in the Gaza war led to more than 100,000 “uncommitted” protest votes in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curtis Hertel, the chair of the Michigan Democratic Party, said no other state would be a better proving ground for an eventual nominee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re looking to win in America, it makes sense for states early on that reflect the diversity of America,” Mr. Hertel said. “The states that we have to win at the end of the day, it’s incredibly important to make sure they are early in the process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Democrats in some other states, however, Mr. Hertel isn’t pushing to be at the very front of the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not saying we have to be first!” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/state-vote-democrats-president-2028.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:02:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>3 Inmates Killed After Fight Erupts in Georgia Prison</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/georgia-prison-fight-inmates-killed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/us/12nat-georgia-prison/12nat-georgia-prison-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three inmates were killed on Sunday at a Georgia prison in an eruption of violence that left at least a dozen people injured, local officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Law enforcement officials said a large fight broke out in the early afternoon on Sunday at Washington State Prison, a medium-security facility with capacity for roughly 1,500 inmates in Davisboro, Ga., a small city about 135 miles southeast of Atlanta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circumstances of the episode, including a possible cause, remain unclear. Mark W. Hodges, a coroner in Washington County, confirmed on Monday that three inmates had been killed in the fight but did not specify how. At least one guard had been injured, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State corrections officials did not immediately respond to a request for comment on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The burst of unrest underscores the chronic problems with violence, disorder and severe staffing shortages that Georgia officials have struggled to handle at prisons across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Georgia directed hundreds of millions of dollars toward addressing the deteriorating conditions, which include a surge in deadly violence in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlanta Journal-Constitution reported in September that 42 deaths were being treated as homicides during the first half of 2025 — a rate that was outpacing the previous year, which had been one of the deadliest on record. In 2024, there were 66 suspected homicides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigation by the Justice Department found conditions across facilities that were “horrific and inhumane,” federal officials said when the findings were released in 2024. The state, with roughly 50,000 incarcerated people, has one of the largest inmate populations in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation found that state prison officials had failed — particularly in medium-security facilities, like Washington State Prison — to protect inmates from widespread physical violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical understaffing and aging facilities contributed to the violence and an environment where gangs could exert considerable influence, controlling entire housing units and running illegal schemes inside and outside of prison, investigators found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are assaulted, stabbed, raped and killed or left to languish inside facilities that are woefully understaffed,” Kristen Clarke, an assistant attorney general who oversaw the Justice Department’s civil rights division under President Joseph R. Biden Jr., said in a statement at the time. “Inmates are maimed and tortured, relegated to an existence of fear, filth and not so benign neglect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, state lawmakers voted to infuse more than $600 million into the prison system, responding to a special request from Gov. Brian Kemp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money was earmarked for hiring hundreds of additional corrections officers and increasing pay for prison workers to make it more competitive; wages for guards and other workers had lagged behind other Southern states. The state also plans to use the funds for emergency repairs and improvements to the physical conditions inside its facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/georgia-prison-fight-inmates-killed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:34:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Our Photographer Saw in MinneapolisWhat Our Photographer Saw in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010633079/what-our-photographer-saw-in-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/10/arts/guttenfelder-thumb/guttenfelder-thumb-facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
David Guttenfelder, a visual journalist for The New York Times, was at the scene in Minneapolis immediately after an ICE agent killed a 37-year-old woman in her vehicle. He walks us through the photos and videos he took over the next few days as outrage and protests mounted in the city.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010633079/what-our-photographer-saw-in-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>University of Michigan Picks Syracuse Leader as Its Next President</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/university-of-michigan-president-kent-syverud.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12nat-u-mich-wmjq/12nat-u-mich-wmjq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Michigan appointed Syracuse University’s chancellor as its president on Monday, a bid to end four years of leadership upheaval at one of the country’s most respected public schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kent D. Syverud, the Syracuse chancellor since 2014, is expected to take over at Michigan by July 1. Mr. Syverud is a familiar face at the university’s campus in Ann Arbor, where he married, received his law degree and was later an associate dean in the law school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michigan, which also has campuses in Dearborn and Flint, has more than 68,000 students and is one of the country’s biggest federally backed research operations. Now, months after Michigan’s interim president warned that “higher education in this country is currently under attack,” it will fall to Mr. Syverud to try to stave off funding cuts and counter mounting mistrust in top universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark J. Bernstein, the chair of the university’s Board of Regents, said Monday as he introduced Mr. Syverud that American academia was facing its most significant challenges since World War II and that “the stakes cannot be higher for our university and our society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking shortly after Mr. Bernstein, who described the Michigan presidency as “the best and most challenging job in higher education,” Mr. Syverud said the university could “curl up in a ball and say woe is me and whine, or we can do what Michigan has always done when it’s at its best: We can lead.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university, he added, could lead “not by arrogantly lecturing others, but by modeling each day, in small ways and in big ones, the values and the ideas and the innovation and the civil engagement that this world so badly needs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although pressure from President Trump has thrown parts of the higher education industry into crisis, some of Michigan’s turmoil predates Mr. Trump’s second term in the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Syverud will be the fifth person to run Michigan since the start of 2022, when regents suddenly fired Dr. Mark Schlissel after they learned of his relationship with a university employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary Sue Coleman, a previous Michigan president, led the university on an interim basis for much of 2022, when regents installed Santa J. Ono.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Ono left Michigan suddenly last May, when he was named the sole finalist to become the president of the University of Florida. But the Florida system’s board refused to confirm Dr. Ono, who had been a target of Republicans skeptical over his previous support of diversity initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michigan had once been seen as a model of diversity, equity and inclusion programs, but it began to back away after Mr. Trump was re-elected in 2024. The university eliminated its main program last March, while Dr. Ono was still in Ann Arbor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He left soon after, and Domenico Grasso became Michigan’s interim president. His short tenure included the firing of the university’s football coach over a relationship with an employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regents voted unanimously Monday to hire Mr. Syverud, who was a clerk to Justice Sandra Day O’Connor after law school. Following a brief stint in private practice, he began teaching law at Michigan. He went on to run the law schools at Vanderbilt University and at Washington University in St. Louis before winning the job at Syracuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Syverud was at the university’s helm in 2019 when a burst of racist episodes, including vandalism and slurs, rocked the campus and led to debates about Mr. Syverud's stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressured by students, some of whom held a sit-in at the campus center, and elected officials, Mr. Syverud agreed to many of the protesters’ demands, including mandatory diversity training and a pledge of at least $1 million for what demonstrators described as the “creation of a unified, required curriculum that educates the campus on diversity issues, specifically antiracism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Syverud, however, resisted calls for his resignation, even as he said he regretted the university’s initial response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hate testifying for myself, but my whole career has been about caring about students, particularly about international students and students of color,” Mr. Syverud told The New York Times that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past August, he announced that he would step down from Syracuse in June 2026. Mr. Syverud said he had been reluctant to interview for the Michigan job but, persuaded by his family, agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/university-of-michigan-president-kent-syverud.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:15:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Criminal Inquiry of Powell Draws Backlash From Some Republicans</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/jerome-powell-fed-investigation-republicans-backlash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12trump-news-powell-GOP-Tillis-fgjc/12trump-news-powell-GOP-Tillis-fgjc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some top Republican lawmakers on Monday assailed the Trump administration’s move to open a criminal investigation into Jerome H. Powell, the Federal Reserve chair, and warned that the central bank’s independence and credibility was at risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backlash could potentially constrain President Trump’s efforts to exert legal pressure on Mr. Powell, whose term as chair expires in May but who can remain on the Fed’s policy-setting board of governors until 2028. The Justice Department served the central bank with grand jury subpoenas late on Friday and is investigating whether Mr. Powell lied to Congress last year when testifying about the renovation of the Fed’s headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump Administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” Senator Thom Tillis, a North Carolina Republican and a member of the Senate Banking Committee, said. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Tillis added that he would oppose the confirmation of any nominee for the Fed, including the upcoming chair vacancy, until the legal matter is resolved. If Mr. Tillis follows through on that pledge, it could hinder, if not prevent, Mr. Trump’s pick from getting enough votes for the nomination to advance to the full Senate. The Senate Banking Committee must approve the next Fed nominee in order to receive full Senate consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Republican lawmakers were cautious, resisting outright criticism of the Trump administration while expressing support for Fed independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator John Thune, Republican of South Dakota and the majority leader, told reporters at the Capitol that he hadn’t “seen the allegations or what the various charges are, so it’s hard to react to” the investigation into Mr. Powell. But he said “it’s really important that it get resolved quickly and that there not be any appearance of political interference with the Fed or its activities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Kevin Cramer, a Republican from North Dakota who also sits on the Banking Committee, echoed those concerns on Monday. Although he expressed criticism of Mr. Powell’s performance as Fed chair, he said he did not believe that Mr. Powell was a criminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope this criminal investigation can be put to rest quickly along with the remainder of Jerome Powell’s term,” Mr. Cramer said in a statement. “We need to restore confidence in the Fed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lisa Murkowski, a Republican from Alaska, warned that the Trump administration’s threat to the Fed’s independence could jeopardize the stability of markets and the broader economy. She suggested that the investigation was an attempt at “coercion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the Department of Justice believes an investigation into Chair Powell is warranted based on project cost overruns — which are not unusual — then Congress needs to investigate the Department of Justice,” Ms. Murkowski wrote on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some House Republicans also defended Mr. Powell. Representative French Hill, Republican of Arkansas and the chairman of the Financial Services Committee, called a criminal inquiry into Jerome Powell “an unnecessary distraction.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hill, who said he has known Powell for decades, said in a statement that pursuing charges against the Fed chair “could undermine this and future administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.” He noted that the Fed is led by “strong, capable individuals appointed by President Trump.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Republicans in Congress appeared to go out of their way to avoid criticizing the investigation even as they declined to endorse it. Asked by a CNN reporter whether Mr. Trump was weaponizing the Justice Department against Mr. Powell, Mike Johnson, the House speaker, said: “Of course not,” and declined to say whether he thought the criminal inquiry was warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Roger Marshall, Republican of Kansas, a member of the banking panel, said there were “other issues that we should be focused on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the president throwing out one more — maybe he’s even, almost trolling here as well,” Mr. Marshall said on Fox Business. “We’ve got bigger issues to go after than this one, though.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump nominated Mr. Powell to lead the Fed during his first term in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Gold and Catie Edmondson contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/jerome-powell-fed-investigation-republicans-backlash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:10:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court Grapples With Louisiana Coastal Lawsuits Against Oil Companies</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/supreme-court-louisiana-oil.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-scotus-oil-lkwg/12dc-scotus-oil-lkwg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court justices on Monday heard arguments in a lawsuit seeking to hold oil companies liable for environmental damage to Louisiana’s coastline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument focused on a narrow question — whether the oil companies can remove cases over the damage from state to federal court — but the stakes are high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local officials in Louisiana have filed more than 40 related lawsuits seeking potentially billions of dollars in damages. The officials blame the oil companies for environmental damage to the Louisiana coast from decades of oil and gas production. They argue that the companies engaged in illegal activity, by drilling, dredging and engaging in waste disposal without proper permits. Those actions, state officials argue, have contributed to extensive coastal erosion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal court is seen as a friendlier venue for the oil companies. If the justices allow the companies to move their cases there, it could have implications for other climate change-related lawsuits. Such lawsuits have increased in recent years as states and local governments face increasing challenges with how to pay for environmental damage. Oil companies have argued they pose a threat to the country’s energy security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Brett M. Kavanaugh pressed the lawyer for a coalition of major oil companies, Paul D. Clement, about why they have sought to move the lawsuits out of state courts in local parishes, which are similar to counties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There seems to be a concern about the fairness of the state court system that underlies your position in this case,” Justice Kavanaugh said. “What is that concern?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Clement responded that a judgment issued in federal court would be more broadly accepted. If the plaintiffs can prove their case in federal court, then “everybody’s going to accept the outcome” and the decision would not be viewed “as something that’s a product of local prejudice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He cited examples where national policies have been locally unpopular, making it potentially difficult for the companies to get a fair trial with a local jury. Last April, a jury in Plaquemines Parish, the state’s southernmost parish, found Chevron Corporation liable for about $745 million for damage to the state’s coastal wetlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for Louisiana have fought to keep the cases in state courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louisiana’s solicitor general, J. Benjamin Aguiñaga, said state courts were best suited to judge whether the underlying law, a Louisiana environmental statute, had been violated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have the same reasons for wanting to be in state court that anybody who sues under state law wants to be in state court,” Mr. Aguiñaga told the justices. “We want the actual experts interpreting state law, especially when we get to the Louisiana Supreme Court on an important statute like this, and especially with respect to a problem that is so sweeping in scope.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument, which lasted more than an hour, was muted. Justice Samuel A. Alito Jr., who is often active in arguments and typically asks lively hypotheticals, recused himself from the case just days before the argument. He cited his financial ties to one of the companies involved in the dispute, ConocoPhillips, the parent corporation of Burlington Resources Oil and Gas Company. Although that company had withdrawn from the Supreme Court petition, it remained a party in federal court, according to a letter from the court clerk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question of whether the oil companies can successfully get the cases into federal court hinges on what’s known as the federal officer removal statute. This law gives federal courts jurisdiction over civil cases that concern the actions of federal officials or those acting under the orders of a federal official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oil companies argue the law applies in this matter because of World War II-era fuel-supply contracts. The Trump administration has joined the case in support of the oil companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal trial court rejected the companies’ argument, finding that they had failed to show their oil removal was done under the orders of a federal officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A divided panel of judges from the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit then upheld the lower court’s decision, blocking the companies from moving cases to federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the trial court, the judges found that the oil companies had been operating under federal officials at the time of the World War II oil extraction. But a majority concluded that the oil companies failed to show that actions the jury said caused environmental damage were related to the company’s World War II-era fuel contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Aguiñaga urged the justices to uphold that decision. He asserted that it was “an easy case,” that the oil companies had “dumped billions of gallons of produced water from oil wells directly into our marsh” and that it was “a massive deal for the state of Louisiana.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Clement pushed back aggressively on this idea, telling the justices that it was clear the oil companies had worked in support of the country’s war, both on the battlefield and on “the home front.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He called the war context of the oil company contracts “critical,” adding that the companies were fueling munitions factories, among other industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added that “if we are going to get in a big debate about exactly what happened in World War II,” that debate should happen in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/supreme-court-louisiana-oil.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:59:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Prosecutor Is Fired Amid Further Turmoil in Comey Case</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mcbride-halligan-us-attorney-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-comey-lgqc/12dc-comey-lgqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior federal prosecutor in Virginia was fired after a disagreement about whether he would take charge of the Trump administration’s effort to reindict James B. Comey, according to multiple people familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dismissal of the prosecutor, Robert K. McBride, is the latest fallout in the Justice Department over President Trump’s effort to punish Mr. Comey, the former F.B.I. director and his longtime nemesis, whom the president blames for past investigations of his conduct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. McBride had been in the U.S. attorney’s office for the Eastern District of Virginia for only a couple of months, temporarily serving as the top deputy to Lindsey Halligan after more than a decade as a federal prosecutor in Kentucky. Mr. Trump selected Ms. Halligan as the U.S. attorney after her predecessor resisted bringing charges against Mr. Comey, saying the evidence was not sufficient to warrant doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Halligan was put in the job through an unusual personnel maneuver that a judge later determined was unlawful. In doing so, the judge declared that she was not a valid U.S. attorney and dismissed two high-profile cases that she had brought, charging Mr. Comey with lying to Congress and charging the New York attorney general, Letitia James, with lying on mortgage paperwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration has tried to restart the Comey prosecution and wanted Mr. McBride to lead that effort, according to people familiar with the matter who spoke on the condition of anonymity to describe internal discussions. Mr. McBride said he could not do that while also running the prosecutor’s office as the first assistant U.S. attorney — he could do one or the other, these people said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person familiar with the events disputed that explanation, stating that Mr. McBride had been dismissed because he had secretly met with judges in the district to try to persuade them to appoint him as U.S. attorney. Mr. McBride, that person added, had resisted pursuing immigration-related investigations related to local jurisdictions’ sanctuary policies and drug enforcement. The person also said Justice Department leaders supported the decision to fire Mr. McBride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news of Mr. McBride’s dismissal was reported earlier by MS NOW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is common for the leaders of a U.S. attorney’s office, including the top deputy, known as a first assistant, to meet with judges in the district, particularly given that the court had declared Ms. Halligan unlawfully appointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, the Trump administration appealed the ruling, issued by Judge Cameron McGowan Currie, voiding Ms. Halligan’s appointment as U.S. attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia. Despite Judge Currie’s order, Ms. Halligan has continued to lay claim to that title, signing court papers as the district’s top prosecutor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in Richmond, Va., has given Ms. Halligan until Tuesday to explain in writing why doing so is not “a false or misleading statement.” Continuing to do so, the judge suggested, could lead to disciplinary measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior Justice Department officials have privately decided that because Judge Currie’s ruling did not expressly remove Ms. Halligan from office, she could remain, according to people familiar with their decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Currie’s decision to disqualify Ms. Halligan centered on Mr. Trump’s unorthodox move to appoint her in an interim capacity, replacing his previous pick, who was also serving in a temporary role. Judge Currie found that federal law did not allow the administration to appoint two interim prosecutors in succession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump fired Ms. Halligan’s predecessor, Erik S. Siebert, after he refused to bring charges against Mr. Comey and Ms. James.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other judges have rejected the administration’s efforts to install U.S. attorneys in a similar fashion. Federal judges in other states have made similar rulings against Alina Habba as the U.S. attorney in New Jersey and John A. Sarcone III in upstate New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julie Tate contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mcbride-halligan-us-attorney-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:13:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice Department Charges the Man Shot by Agents in Portland, Ore.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/portland-border-patrol-immigration-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12NAT-PORTLAND-SHOOTING-1-kgcj/12NAT-PORTLAND-SHOOTING-1-kgcj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man shot by U.S. Border Patrol officers last week in Portland, Ore., has been charged with trying to injure them with his pickup truck, the Justice Department said Monday, though so far investigators have not been able to find any surveillance footage that captured the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors said that Luis Nino-Moncada, 33, who was shot in the arm on Thursday, was being held in the Multnomah County Detention Center in Portland on charges of aggravated assault of a federal officer with a dangerous or deadly weapon. He was also charged with damaging federal property at a cost in excess of $1,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In court filings, prosecutors said Mr. Nino-Moncada tried to ram Border Patrol vehicles and officers with his red Toyota Tacoma after they stopped him near a Portland hospital on Thursday afternoon. Department of Homeland Security officials have said the agents were trying to find the passenger in the vehicle, Yorlenys Betzabeth Zambrano-Contreras, in connection with a prostitution ring that they said was run by Tren de Aragua, a Venezuelan gang, according to an affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department has said that both people in the car entered the country illegally and that Mr. Nino-Moncada had a removal order signed by a judge in Colorado in November 2024. Ms. Zambrano-Contreras, who was also shot by federal officers, has been released from the hospital and taken to the Immigration and Customs Enforcement detention facility in Tacoma, Wash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City and state leaders in Oregon expressed outrage at the shooting last week and demanded a transparent investigation. They also said federal immigration authorities should leave Portland. Federal officials said in court filings that they have not been able to find surveillance footage from surrounding businesses that captured the shooting and that the six Border Patrol agents who were involved were not wearing body cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal officials have said the shooting victims deserve no sympathy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Anyone who crosses the red line of assaulting law enforcement will be met with the full force of this Justice Department,” Attorney General Pam Bondi said in a statement Monday. “This man — an illegal alien with ties to a foreign terrorist organization — should never have been in our country to begin with, and we will ensure he never walks free in America again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Portland’s police chief, Bob Day, confirmed that the pair was connected to the gang, though he provided few details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nino-Moncada was scheduled to make his first federal court appearance before a magistrate judge at 1:30 p.m. Pacific on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In court filings based on interviews with federal agents, prosecutors said immigration officers used four vehicles to stop Mr. Nino-Moncada’s pickup after they spotted Ms. Zambrano-Contreras in the truck on Thursday. When they approached on foot and ordered the driver out of the truck, he moved it forward and backward several times, ramming other cars, to free the vehicle and then drove away. A Border Patrol officer fired twice into the car as the truck fled, according to the affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nino-Moncada was struck in the arm and Ms. Zambrano-Contreras in the chest. They are being represented by public defenders who declined to speak on the record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Rayfield, Oregon’s attorney general, has begun his own investigation into the shooting and has said he believed the F.B.I. would cooperate with that effort.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/portland-border-patrol-immigration-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:04:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With Democrats at a Crossroads, Elizabeth Warren Urges a Left Turn</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/elizabeth-warren-democrats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/us/politics/pol-warren/pol-warren-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Elizabeth Warren of Massachusetts on Monday let fly a wide-ranging attack on business-friendly Democrats and their billionaire supporters, warning that her party risked cozying up too much to corporate interests as it tries to shed perceptions that it has drifted too far to the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand the temptation — in this moment of national crisis — to sand down our edges to avoid offending anyone, especially the rich and powerful who might finance our candidates,” she said in a speech at the National Press Club in Washington. “But we can’t win unless we rebuild trust” with the working class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her speech sought to stake out a progressive economic vision for the Democratic Party as some of its leaders work to pull the party to the center in an effort to make it more competitive nationally. As an attempt to get attention, it worked in one way: Ms. Warren said on Monday afternoon that President Trump had called her after her speech and they had discussed affordability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now 76 and unlikely to run for president again in 2028, Ms. Warren has mostly taken a back seat as younger Democratic politicians jockey for the next presidential contest. She remains a prominent voice on the party’s left, however, and her remarks signaled worry among progressives that they may not have much of a say in Democrats’ future economic message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are five takeaways from her remarks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Democrats have won a string of elections since Mr. Trump took office a year ago, many of the party’s leaders have called for a “big tent” politics that can include both moderates and progressives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Ms. Warren argued on Monday that the party cannot afford to give billionaires too much room inside the tent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are two versions for what a big tent means,” Ms. Warren said. “The Democratic Party cannot pursue both visions at the same time. Either we politely nibble around the edges of change, or we throw ourselves into the fight.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren is trying to instigate this fight, she said during a question-and-answer session after her speech, so that she can build influence in Democratic primary races and help her favored candidates before this fall’s midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m trying to lay the foundation for how Democrats run in 2026, and I think we do that on a solid foundation that is based on our economics,” she said. “And this is the place where we are most at risk for the billionaires sweeping in and saying, ‘Dial that down.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren resurfaced a 2024 episode in which Reid Hoffman, the billionaire investor and one of the Democratic Party’s biggest donors, led an unsuccessful effort to push Vice President Kamala Harris to remove Lina Khan as the Federal Trade Commission chair if Ms. Harris became president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren argued that Ms. Khan, a pro-regulation progressive favorite, had been doing more to address prices than anyone else while Joseph R. Biden Jr. was president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There was Reid Hoffman, a man with close ties to two of the biggest corporations under fire from the F.T.C., Microsoft and Facebook, hectoring Harris to promise she would fire the F.T.C. chair,” Ms. Warren said. “To her credit, the vice president didn’t promise to fire Lina Khan. But she didn’t promise not to fire her, either.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hoffman has become a lightning rod in Democratic politics. His support became contentious in the election to lead the Democratic National Committee a year ago. But he is hardly a familiar name to voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Warren’s speech, Mr. Hoffman posted a response to social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Her politics shrinks the tent,” he wrote. “We need a bigger, smarter coalition that can beat Trump and deliver.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the Democratic Party adopted “affordability” as a mantra last year, a certain class of party leaders and thinkers evangelized about “Abundance,” the book published last March by Ezra Klein, a New York Times columnist, and the journalist Derek Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren suggested that the book’s thesis — that government regulations impede development — had been co-opted by elites at the potential expense of working people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“‘Abundance’ has become a rallying cry — not just for a few policy nerds worried about zoning, but for wealthy donors and other corporate-aligned Democrats who are putting big-time muscle behind making Democrats more favorable to big businesses,” Ms. Warren said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren also expressed disappointment that Ms. Harris had largely backed away from economic populism in the closing stages of her 2024 campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, Ms. Warren lamented that Ms. Harris abandoned a price-gouging proposal after complaints from Wall Street donors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The senator contrasted Ms. Harris’s economic policy with the message of Mr. Trump, who she said “loudly, day after day after day, promised that he would lower costs for families on Day 1.” Ms. Harris’s spokeswoman declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren’s speech largely skated over her influential role in the Biden administration — which presided over the inflation and other economic conditions that Mr. Trump capitalized on in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She pushed for her allies, like Ms. Khan, to be appointed to key administration posts, and the White House largely adopted her theories on economic policy and government spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Senator Warren and her allies led the inflation-denial wing of the party, and we are still paying the price,” said Matt Bennett, a co-founder of Third Way, a centrist Democratic think tank. “Going forward, Democrats must be obsessively focused on making life affordable. That includes increasing supply to bring down the costs of things like health care, energy and housing. It does not mean fighting old battles that Democrats lost in a rout last time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Warren, in brief remarks with reporters after her speech, declined to address her role advising Mr. Biden.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/elizabeth-warren-democrats.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:05:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About the Criminal Investigation of the Fed Chair</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/jerome-powell-investigation-fed-renovations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12trump-news-powell-GOP-reserve-reno-zwtf/12trump-news-powell-GOP-reserve-reno-zwtf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time in history, the chair of the Federal Reserve is now the subject of a criminal investigation by the Justice Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probe revolves around Jerome H. Powell, who has led the central bank since 2018, and his oversight of a $2.5 billion renovation of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell responded forcefully in a rare two-minute video message Sunday evening, accusing the administration of using legal threats as “pretexts” to coerce the central bank into ceding to the president’s demand for lower borrowing costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president has long treated Mr. Powell as an adversary. But the investigation represents a sharp escalation in his pressure campaign against the central bank, one that has raised questions about whether the Fed can continue to operate independently. That independence has allowed the Fed to make policy decisions that are in the best interest of the economy, rather than what’s politically popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inquiry into Mr. Powell’s actions was approved in November by Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for the District of Columbia and a longtime ally of President Trump, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the first time the administration has leaned on the weight of the Justice Department to go after political foes. Two of Mr. Trump’s top targets, the former F.B.I. director James B. Comey and Letitia James, the New York attorney general, have faced similar investigations by the Justice Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inquiry involving Mr. Powell rests on public statements he made regarding an extensive refurbishment of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington. The project is running roughly $700 million over budget and is expected to cost $2.5 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors in Ms. Pirro’s office, who served the central bank with grand jury subpoenas on Friday, are looking into whether the Fed chair misled Congress when he was questioned at a hearing in June about the project. They are also looking into spending records and have reached out multiple times to Mr. Powell’s staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renovations emerged as a focal point in the Trump administration’s attacks on the central bank last year. As the president’s anger grew over the Fed’s reluctance to cut interest rates, Mr. Trump seized on the cost overruns, going as far as to show up at the construction site for a tour, where he openly sparred with Mr. Powell about the total cost. After his tour, the president said of the Fed, “they have to get it done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, Mr. Trump had revisited the idea of ousting Mr. Powell, something he could only lawfully do if he had sufficient cause. That has typically meant gross malfeasance or a dereliction of duty while on the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renovations, which had started in 2022 and are set to be completed in 2027, became useful fodder for the administration. Russell T. Vought, the director of the Office of Management and Budget, compared the project to the Palace of Versailles in France, while another administration official, James Blair, dubbed it the “Taj Mahal on the National Mall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until Sunday, Mr. Powell had refused to publicly link questions about the renovations to the president’s pressure campaign against the Fed. Rather, the central bank sought to address the controversy by providing exhaustive details about the project, including publishing a virtual tour of the construction site alongside photos and a list of frequently asked questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The refurbishment involves expanding and modernizing the Marriner S. Eccles Building, which was built in 1935, and another building on Constitution Avenue, which was built in 1932.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed has said that neither of those buildings has been “comprehensively renovated” since their construction nearly 100 years ago. Part of the project includes removing asbestos and lead contamination as well as making the facilities compliant with laws related to accessibility for people with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plans for the complex, which was designed by the French architects Paul Philippe Cret and Jules Henri de Sibour, seek to preserve much of the classical features of the original buildings. But it also includes more modern additions like a new parking garage, atriums and skylights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An initial proposal submitted in 2021 to the National Capital Planning Commission, a little-known board that became a cudgel to pressure Mr. Powell, described the inclusion of private elevators and dining rooms for top policymakers, additional water fountains and new marble features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain amenities were later scrapped, including the addition of seating on a walkable green roof, fountains and planter boxes that were proposed to sit outside one of the buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In explaining the cost overruns, the central bank on its website cited expenses tied to materials, equipment and labor as well as unforeseen circumstances, such as more asbestos than anticipated and soil contamination. On a tour attended by The New York Times in July, Fed staff added that tariffs, which Mr. Trump has ratcheted up this year, led to the price tag being higher than what was estimated in 2018 and 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell last testified before Congress in June, and the renovations received little attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responding to Senator Tim Scott, Republican of South Carolina, Mr. Powell justified the project by saying the building “was not really safe and it was not waterproof.” He also denied many of the luxury features flagged by earlier media reports, calling them “misleading and inaccurate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no V.I.P. dining room; there’s no new marble,” he said. “We took down the old marble, we’re putting it back up. We’ll have to use new marble where some of the old marble broke. But there’s no special elevators. There’s just old elevators that have been there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell added that the project’s plans had “continued to evolve” and that some features that had been initially incorporated were scrapped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the fact that the building’s plans had changed gave Republicans an opening to criticize Mr. Powell, with some lawmakers accusing him of lying to Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Scott, who leads the powerful Senate Banking Committee, later followed up with more extensive questions that scrutinized the Fed chair’s responses and called out “distinct differences” from publicly available plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address his critics, Mr. Powell also called on the central bank’s internal watchdog to look into the renovations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell has received an outpouring of support since Sunday. Every living former Fed chair and several former Treasury secretaries signed a statement on Monday in support of the Fed’s independence, describing the Justice Department’s move as an “unprecedented attempt to use prosecutorial attacks to undermine” it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is how monetary policy is made in emerging markets with weak institutions, with highly negative consequences for inflation and the functioning of their economies more broadly,” the group of 13 signatories wrote. “It has no place in the United States, whose greatest strength is the rule of law, which is at the foundation of our economic success.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several Republican lawmakers, including three senators, also voiced support for Mr. Powell. Their votes will be critical if Mr. Trump is to successfully confirm a new chair to replace Mr. Powell when his term as chair ends in May. All members of the Fed’s board of governors are chosen by the president and eventually need to be confirmed by the Senate. The Senate Banking Committee, which oversees the Fed, leads the vetting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Thom Tillis, Republican of North Carolina and a member of the Banking Committee, vowed to oppose the confirmation of any nominee for the Fed, including any coming chair vacancy, citing reports of subpoenas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If there were any remaining doubt whether advisers within the Trump administration are actively pushing to end the independence of the Federal Reserve, there should now be none,” he said in a statement. “It is now the independence and credibility of the Department of Justice that are in question.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Kevin Cramer of North Dakota, who also sits on the Banking Committee, similarly expressed support for Mr. Powell, though he stopped short of saying he would oppose any nominee. Senator Lisa Murkowski, Republican of Alaska, said Monday that after speaking with the Fed chair “it’s clear the administration’s investigation is nothing more than an attempt at coercion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative French Hill, the Arkansas Republican who leads the House Financial Services Committee, on Monday said the probe “creates an unnecessary distraction” that “could undermine this and future administrations’ ability to make sound monetary policy decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is what comes next for Mr. Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One concern is that the president will use this investigation as justification to try to remove Mr. Powell for cause, in similar fashion to what Mr. Trump is trying to do with Lisa D. Cook, a governor whom he tried to fire last year citing allegations of mortgage fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for Ms. Cook, who has been able to stay on the Fed as her lawsuit against the president is litigated, will present their case before the Supreme Court on Jan. 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal experts say that this broadside against Mr. Powell will help shore up Ms. Cook’s case because it is yet another example of the president going after individual officials in his pursuit of lower borrowing costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump denied having any knowledge of the Justice Department’s probe, saying the subpoenas had nothing to do with interest rates. “I wouldn’t even think of doing it that way,” he told NBC News on Sunday. “What should pressure him is the fact that rates are far too high. That’s the only pressure he’s got.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Monday about the investigation, Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, took the opportunity to criticize Mr. Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do know one thing for sure, Jerome Powell is not very good at his job,” she said in an interview with Fox News. “As to whether he’s a criminal, that’s an answer the Department of Justice is going to have to find.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/jerome-powell-investigation-fed-renovations.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:03:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Illinois Doctor Charged With Murder in Shooting of Ex-Wife and Her Husband</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/tepe-couple-ohio-shooting-ex-husband-charged.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12xp-tepe1-lhtj/12xp-tepe1-lhtj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Illinois doctor has been charged in the fatal shooting of his former wife and her husband while they were at home with their two young children in Columbus, Ohio, last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor, Michael McKee, 39, of Chicago, was arrested on Saturday in Rockford, Ill., and has been charged with aggravated murder in the deaths of Monique Tepe, 39, and Spencer Tepe, 37.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police were called to the Tepe home at about 10 a.m. on Dec. 30 after Mr. Tepe, a dentist, did not show up for work. An officer initially went to the wrong address, the police said, before officers went to the right address about 40 minutes later and found the couple with gunshot wounds. Medical personnel pronounced them dead on the scene. The couple’s two children were found in the home, unharmed. They were 4 and 1 at the time, according to The Columbus Dispatch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detectives used neighborhood surveillance video to track Mr. McKee to a vehicle that had arrived just before the homicides and left shortly after, the police said in an affidavit. Detectives linked the vehicle to Mr. McKee and located it in Rockford, along with evidence that he had been “in possession” of it before and after the fatal shootings, according to the affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the police released surveillance video showing a person of interest walking near the Tepe home, wearing a dark jacket or sweatshirt, with the hood pulled up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a brief court hearing in Rockford on Monday, Mr. McKee appeared in shackles with a lawyer, who said that he had agreed to be transported to Ohio for a court hearing and intended to plead not guilty. The authorities have not released any information about a possible motive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. McKee is a vascular surgeon, with active medical licenses in Illinois and California, records show. He and Ms. Tepe were married in 2015 and divorced in 2017, Ohio court records show. They did not have any children together, according to court filings. Monique and Spencer Tepe were married in December 2020, records show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tepe family said in a statement to The Columbus Dispatch that Ms. Tepe was a “loving, patient, and joyful mother whose warmth defined her.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With a background in childhood education, she brought care and intention into everything she did,” the statement said. “She was an excellent baker, a thoughtful planner, and someone who found joy in bringing people together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Tepe was a proud father and loving partner, the family said. He was fluent in Spanish, worked with the Big Brothers Big Sisters of America and was a fan of the Cincinnati Bengals and the Ohio State Buckeyes, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. McKee was arrested, the Tepe family thanked the Columbus police for their work on the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nothing can undo the devastating loss of two lives taken far too soon,” the family said. “We thank the community for the continued support, prayers and compassion shown throughout this tragedy. As the case proceeds, we trust the justice system to hold the person responsible fully accountable.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/tepe-couple-ohio-shooting-ex-husband-charged.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:29:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kelly Sues Pentagon Over Threats of Punishment From Hegseth</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mark-kelly-pentagon-hegseth-suit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-cong-kelly-vmpj/12dc-cong-kelly-vmpj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mark Kelly, Democrat of Arizona, on Monday sued Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth and the Pentagon over a move to punish him for a video he released with other lawmakers reminding military members that they must not follow illegal orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Defense Department said last week that it was taking administrative action against Mr. Kelly, a retired Navy captain and astronaut who is serving his first full term in the Senate, that could reduce his retirement rank and military pension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hegseth has accused the senator, who is regarded as a potential 2028 presidential contender, of sedition and treason for posting a video along with five other Democratic lawmakers in which he did not name any specific order but said: “Our laws are clear. You can refuse illegal orders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit filed in Washington asked a federal judge to block the Pentagon’s efforts to punish Mr. Kelly and find them “unlawful and unconstitutional.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The First Amendment forbids the government and its officials from punishing disfavored expression or retaliating against protected speech,” the complaint stated. “That prohibition applies with particular force to legislators speaking on matters of public policy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Defense Department declined to comment on the ongoing litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a “formal letter of censure” that Mr. Hegseth released last week, he accused the senator of characterizing lawful military operations as “illegal” in a “sustained pattern” that began in June 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter cited the senator criticizing Mr. Hegseth for firing generals and admirals and saying that the defense secretary had surrounded himself with “yes men.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s my job,” Mr. Kelly said on the Senate floor on Monday. “I have every right to say these things as an American, as a retired service member and as a U.S. senator.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hegseth wrote on social media last week that Mr. Kelly’s status as a sitting senator “does not exempt him from accountability, and further violations could result in further action.” The defense secretary indicated that a decision on whether to reduce the senator’s rank and pension would be made by mid-February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the lawsuit argued that Mr. Kelly’s public statements about policy and personnel were lawful under a section of the Constitution known as the “speech or debate” clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That section has long been interpreted to protect members of Congress from executive or judicial discipline for not only their speech but also their legislative work broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kelly argued in his lawsuit that as a member of the Senate Armed Services Committee, he has a role to provide congressional oversight over Mr. Hegseth’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to block any disciplinary action against the senator “would invert the constitutional structure by subordinating the legislative branch to executive discipline and chilling congressional oversight of the armed forces,” the complaint stated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Uniform Code of Military Justice still applies to Mr. Kelly as a retired naval officer. The administration could recall him to active duty and discipline him, unless the court were to block such action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His fellow Democratic lawmakers in the video released last year did not serve long enough to retire and receive a pension, and are not subject to military law.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/mark-kelly-pentagon-hegseth-suit.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:14:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota and Illinois Sue Trump Administration Over ICE Deployments</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/minnesota-llinois-lawsuit-ice-trump-administration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12nat-minnesota-lawsuit-2-gcpq/12nat-minnesota-lawsuit-2-gcpq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State and city officials in Minnesota and Illinois filed federal lawsuits against the Trump administration on Monday, claiming that the mass deployment of immigration agents to the Minneapolis and Chicago regions violated the U.S. Constitution and infringed on states’ rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illinois asked a judge to block U.S. Customs and Border Protection “from conducting civil immigration enforcement” in the state without “express congressional authorization.” The Minnesota lawsuit asked a judge to block the federal government from “implementing the unprecedented surge in Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuits, filed separately in U.S. District Courts in the two Democratic-led states, came a week into a stepped-up immigration enforcement blitz in Minnesota and following a highly visible campaign in Chicago in recent months. Both the Illinois and Minnesota lawsuits claimed that the federal deployments violated state sovereignty under the Constitution’s 10th Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal officials have repeatedly defended their work in both states, calling the campaigns necessary to carry out President Trump’s immigration agenda in the face of uncooperative state and local governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricia McLaughlin, a spokeswoman for the Department of Homeland Security, said in a statement responding to the Illinois case that “this is a baseless lawsuit, and we look forward to proving that in court.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It really is astounding that the left can miraculously rediscover the 10th Amendment when they don’t want federal law enforcement officers to enforce federal law,” she said, adding that such enforcement was “a clear federal responsibility” under the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minneapolis area has been especially tense since an immigration agent shot and killed an American woman, Renee Nicole Good, on a residential street last Wednesday, touching off large protests. The federal government has defended the shooting as lawful and necessary, while local officials have dismissed that narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newly filed lawsuits ask federal judges to impose sweeping limits on the conduct of federal agents in both states. The Illinois case, filed by the state government and the city of Chicago, said that the “Trump administration has unleashed an organized bombardment” and was “imposing a climate of fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minnesota case, filed by the state and the cities of Minneapolis and St. Paul, said that “thousands of armed and masked D.H.S. agents have stormed the Twin Cities to conduct militarized raids and carry out dangerous, illegal and unconstitutional stops and arrests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are being racially profiled, harassed, terrorized and assaulted,” Attorney General Keith Ellison of Minnesota said in a statement. He added: “Minnesota police are spending countless hours dealing with the chaos ICE is causing. This federal invasion of the  Twin Cities has to stop.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Illinois lawsuit outlined a list of complaints about roving patrols, use of tear gas and the collection of photographs and fingerprints by immigration agents. It described a number of high-profile instances from the federal enforcement campaign last year, in which agents marched through Chicago’s downtown, used a helicopter in a raid on an apartment building and were involved in two shootings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The occupation of Illinois and Chicago is intended to coerce plaintiffs to abandon their policies, which value and respect the state’s immigrants, and devote their resources to further the immigration policies of the current administration,” the lawsuit asserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David A. Super, a Georgetown University law professor, said in an email, “I do not see any magic incantations that the administration can invoke to make these cases go away, but I also think plaintiffs will have to make strong cases on each of the policies they contest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Illinois case may turn on whether the court thinks Congress has granted these agencies broad enough authority to take these actions,” Mr. Super said. “The Minnesota case could turn on whether the court believes that the saturation of the state with unusual numbers of D.H.S. agents is unduly burdening the state and its cities and people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous lawsuits have challenged Mr. Trump’s decision to federalize National Guard troops over the objections of state Democratic leaders, or have challenged the specific tactics used by immigration agents in their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, a federal judge in Illinois temporarily blocked the president’s deployment of National Guard members over the governor’s objection, an effort that the president ultimately abandoned after an appellate court upheld the ruling. A different federal judge in Illinois also imposed sweeping restrictions on immigration agents’ use of force in a lawsuit filed by activists, clergy members and journalists. But an appellate panel struck down those restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump campaigned on a promise to deport illegal immigrants, and he has acted aggressively in the first year of his term to carry out those policies. In addition to Chicago and Minneapolis, immigration agents have conducted crackdowns in Los Angeles, New Orleans and Portland, Ore., among other Democratic-led areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest focus has been Minnesota, where federal officials have pointed to widespread fraud in state social service programs as a reason for sending large numbers of Border Patrol and Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents, among other officers. Those officers have patrolled streets and arrested people in the Minneapolis area in recent days, sometimes clashing with protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatal shooting of Ms. Good last week deepened the hostility between state and federal officials. The F.B.I. is investigating that shooting. Though a state law enforcement agency was initially part of the inquiry, that agency said it was denied access to evidence and withdrew after political attacks escalated between federal and Minnesota politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/minnesota-llinois-lawsuit-ice-trump-administration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:50:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arson Suspect Targeted Mississippi Synagogue for Its ‘Jewish Ties,’ F.B.I. Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/mississippi-synagogue-arson.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12nat-miss-synagogue-clvm/12nat-miss-synagogue-clvm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man charged with arson for setting a fire that severely damaged the oldest and largest synagogue in Mississippi told investigators that he had targeted the site because of its “Jewish ties,” federal officials disclosed on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man, identified as Stephen Spencer Pittman, 19, was arrested on Saturday for the fire early that morning that tore through Beth Israel, the lone synagogue in Jackson, the state capital, the authorities said. He was taken into custody at a hospital in the Jackson area, where he was being treated for burn injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators were led to Mr. Pittman after his father called the F.B.I. and said his son had told him that he was responsible, according to an affidavit filed in federal court on Monday. A location-tracking app that Mr. Pittman had running on his cellphone also documented his movements as he left his home in a suburb of Jackson, stopped at a gas station to buy fuel and continued on to the synagogue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sent his father, who was not named in the affidavit, text messages and photos from the synagogue before the fire, saying that he was wearing a hoodie and had taken the license plate off his vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a furnace in the back,” Mr. Pittman wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And they have the best cameras,” he added, noting how expensive he believed they were.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father pleaded for him to come home, the affidavit said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities said that Mr. Pittman had broken a window, gone inside, poured gasoline throughout the building and ignited the fire using a torch lighter. Security camera footage captured a man in a hood pouring liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts to reach a lawyer for Mr. Pittman on Monday were unsuccessful. He was set to have an initial court appearance in federal court on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire was set in the synagogue’s library and reduced it and surrounding rooms to charred ruins. Two Torahs were destroyed and several others were harmed. Smoke damage occurred throughout the building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pittman had been burned by the fire, the authorities said. Later in the day on Saturday, his father noticed the injuries to his face, hands and ankles, and he confronted his son, according to the affidavit. Mr. Pittman’s father told investigators that his son had said that he started a fire at the synagogue. The son laughed. He told his father he “finally got them,” according to the affidavit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his arrest, Mr. Pittman confessed again in an interview with local law enforcement officials. He called the place of worship the “synagogue of Satan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The synagogue was bombed in 1967 by the Ku Klux Klan.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/mississippi-synagogue-arson.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:40:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Feel-My-Pain Economic Message</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/newsletter-2-vflq/newsletter-2-vflq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reporters for The New York Times pressed President Trump last week about Americans’ economic anxieties, he insisted that the economy was actually “unbelievable.” He blamed his predecessor for high prices. He dismissed the polls and pivoted to bragging about his popularity on TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The greatest beneficiaries of my economy in my first term were low-income workers,” he told the reporters last Wednesday, adding the claim that right now, “blue-collar workers are doing better than anybody else, percentage-wise, as they measure that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That might be news to some of the blue-collar workers my colleagues and I have interviewed in recent months who feel that times are quite tough. And it’s not exactly the feel-your-pain kind of messaging that other politicians have used to reassure voters worried about the cost of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, other than the TikTok comments, the answers reminded me a bit of how former President Joe Biden and his allies would address economic concerns, citing statistics about positive indicators and declaring that Biden had inherited a mess from Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Democrats learned in 2024, voters don’t care about even the most glowing statistics if they feel those numbers don’t accurately reflect their own lives. And there are some rough statistics out there these days, even if the economic picture is complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump continues to face low approval ratings, including on the economy, typically the most important issue for voters. The White House is, however, urging affordability-focused policies like curbing credit card interest rates, reducing some prescription drug costs and efforts to make it easier to buy a home. On Monday, Senator Elizabeth Warren, a Massachusetts liberal, said that Trump had called her and they had discussed affordability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The president is also now at war with the Federal Reserve after federal prosecutors opened an investigation into its chairman, Jerome Powell, further escalating Trump’s pressure campaign to cut interest rates.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I caught up with my colleague Katie Rogers, who pressed Trump about what his message would be to disillusioned voters who are worried about their job prospects and the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Glueck: Katie, thanks for joining us. Did the president answer your question?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Rogers: The main thing I wanted to understand from him was, does he believe that a great deal of Americans are struggling to survive financially?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I could figure that out, I wanted to know what he would say to those people. Based on his responses to our questions, I think he really has a knee-jerk reaction when he is asked about the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line: He is not convinced people are suffering. But if they are, it’s not his fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: You and our colleagues tried to bring him back to this subject a few times. Why is it so important?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KR: It is, far and away, the topic that American voters care the most about. It is a major reason that the president was elected a second time. It is what has carried Democrats to victory in some closely watched recent elections. Even Republicans are warning that voters feel that the White House is more focused on international entanglements than American jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the president outright dismissed those warnings and then blamed his predecessor — even though this president is a year into his second term — was revealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quote of the day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s Mary Peltola, a Democrat who jumped into Alaska’s Senate race today and is running on a message of “fish, family and freedom.” Her entry completes the Senate recruitment picture for Democrats, who face a tough map and need to flip four seats this fall to win back a majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a tip?The Times offers several ways to send important information confidentially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;number of the day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the number of House seats in Virginia that Democratic state lawmakers are hoping to draw for their party, which now holds six of the state’s 11 seats. But Democrats are divided on just how much to gerrymander, my colleagues Nick Corasaniti and Reid Epstein reported today. Catch up on the battle over congressional maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ONE LAST THING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic insiders are beginning to debate that question, and the behind-the-scenes jockeying is in full swing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should the party’s next presidential primary contest start in South Carolina, with its base of Black voters? Or Iowa, full of rural voters? Maybe New Hampshire, with its long tradition of going first? Or Nevada, a battleground with many Latino voters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stakes are high: The order of the calendar will help determine who emerges as the face of the Democratic Party in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Shane Goldmacher interviewed more than a dozen state party chairs, D.N.C. members and other strategists to learn more. Read what he found about the questions and tensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Rogers, Shane Goldmacher, Taylor Robinson and Ama Sarpomaa contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:07:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Congressional Employee Accused of Stealing 240 Phones</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/congressional-employee-stolen-phones.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12xp-phones-kfph/12xp-phones-kfph-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man who worked as a system administrator for a congressional committee has been charged with stealing more than 200 new government cellphones worth over $150,000, federal prosecutors said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The employee, Christopher Southerland, 43, of Glen Burnie, Md., used his job to acquire 240 new cellphones between January and May 2023 and then sell them to a pawnshop, the United States Attorney’s Office for the District of Columbia said in a news release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Southerland was arrested on Friday in Washington and charged with one count of theft of government property in a federal indictment unsealed in U.S. District Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Southerland pleaded not guilty and was released. A lawyer listed for Mr. Southerland did not immediately respond to requests for comment. Magistrate Judge Matthew J. Sharbaugh of the U.S. District Court in Washington ordered Mr. Southerland to stay away from the U.S. Capitol grounds as part of the conditions of his release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney in Washington, called Mr. Southerland’s actions “a direct betrayal of the public trust.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s taxpayer money meant to serve Americans, not line someone’s pockets,” Ms. Pirro said. The government is seeking a monetary judgment in the case. If convicted, Mr. Southerland could face up to 10 years in jail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the news release, Mr. Southerland was a system administrator for the House Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure from April 2020 to July 2023. In that role, Mr. Southerland was authorized to order cellphones for committee staff members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors said that between January and May 2023, Mr. Southland “caused” 240 cellphones to be delivered to his Maryland home. There were only about 80 staff members on the committee at the time, the prosecutors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Southerland then sold more than 200 of the phones to a nearby pawnshop, where he told an employee to sell the phones “in parts” to evade the special security software that is installed for congressional use, federal prosecutors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Southerland’s scheme came to light after someone who had bought one of the phones on eBay called the number for the House of Representatives Technology Service Desk, which was displayed on the phone after it was turned on. House employees soon discovered that several phones Mr. Southerland had bought were missing, the news release said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/congressional-employee-stolen-phones.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:06:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Officials Are Sending 1,000 More Immigration Officers to Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/border-patrol-minnesota-surge.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-border-minnesota-chvk/12dc-border-minnesota-chvk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration is sending roughly 1,000 more immigration officers to Minnesota, expanding its law enforcement surge in the state and potentially escalating already tense relations between federal and local officials in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Customs and Border Protection officers are joining 2,000 other officers and agents at the Department of Homeland Security who have been deployed to the Minneapolis-St. Paul region recently, said Tricia McLaughlin, a spokeswoman for the department. U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement officials said last week that the effort was its “largest operation to date.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local officials in Minneapolis have urged federal forces to leave the city, saying their efforts to arrest immigrants were sowing chaos and danger. Protests have also erupted nationwide after the killing of Renee Good, a 37-year-old woman who was shot by an ICE officer in Minneapolis last week. Ms. Good had been participating in a protest in response to immigration agents who had been spotted in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, state and city officials in Minnesota and Illinois filed federal lawsuits against the Trump administration, arguing that the mass deployment of immigration officers to the Minneapolis and Chicago regions violated the U.S. Constitution. The Minnesota lawsuit asked a judge to block federal officials from “implementing the unprecedented surge” in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials have repeatedly defended their enforcement operations in both states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, said in an interview with Fox News on Sunday that the department was sending more immigration officers to the Minneapolis region, which would allow federal law enforcement there to work safely. Ms. Noem added that people who conducted “violent activities against law enforcement” or impeded operations would be held accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re going to keep doing our jobs,” Ms. Noem said. “Criminal illegal aliens in this country are going to be brought to justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increase in immigration officers adds to an already massive federal law enforcement presence in the Minneapolis region. In comparison, the Minneapolis Police Department has roughly 600 officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has intensified its focus on Minnesota in recent weeks, saying it was “unleashing a relentless assault” on the state to root out fraud. Federal officials have also vowed to ramp up enforcement operations in other Democratic-led states including California and New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration’s focus on Minnesota follows fraud investigations into a pandemic-era program meant to feed children and other safety net programs in the state. More than 90 people, most of them of Somali origin, have been charged with felonies in recent years. President Trump has used xenophobic language to attack Somalis who are living in the United States, saying, “We don’t want them in our country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security said on Friday that it was reviewing thousands of refugee cases in Minnesota, subjecting immigrants who had already been approved for status to new interviews and background checks. Groups that provide assistance to refugees criticized the effort and said it was an unnecessary attempt to scrutinize immigrants who had already completed a thorough vetting process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration also said it would suspend funding for food stamps in Minnesota. A similar effort to freeze billions in federal funding for child care and social service programs in five Democratic-led states, including Minnesota, was temporarily blocked by a federal judge in New York last week.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/border-patrol-minnesota-surge.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 14:36:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>F.B.I. Inquiry Into ICE Shooting Is Examining Victim’s Possible Ties to Activist Groups</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/fbi-renee-good-ice-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-minnesota-zpbf/12dc-minnesota-zpbf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal investigators assigned to the fatal shooting of a 37-year-old Minneapolis woman are looking into her possible connections to activist groups protesting the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration enforcement, in addition to the actions of the federal agent who killed her, people familiar with the situation said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems increasingly unlikely that the agent who fired three times at the unarmed woman, Renee Nicole Good, will face criminal charges, although that could change as investigators collect new evidence, the people added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, President Trump described Ms. Good and her wife, Becca Good, as being “professional agitators,” adding that the authorities would “find out who’s paying for it.” He offered no evidence to support his claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision by the F.B.I. and the Justice Department to scrutinize Ms. Good’s activities and her potential connections to local activists is in line with the White House’s strategy of deflecting blame for the shooting away from federal law enforcement and toward opponents they have described as domestic terrorists, often without providing evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Department officials under Mr. Trump have long maintained that investigating and punishing protesters who organized efforts to physically obstruct or disrupt immigration enforcement is a legitimate subject of federal inquiries. But casting a broad net over the activist community in Minneapolis, former department officials and critics of the administration said, raises the specter that forms of political protest traditionally protected by the First Amendment could be criminalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal officials, who have blocked local investigators from reviewing the evidence they are collecting, have said that they are conducting a thorough inquiry that includes an analysis of the actions of the Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent Jonathan Ross and of physical evidence, including the handgun he used to kill Ms. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and his adviser Stephen Miller have repeatedly described those protesting the administration’s immigration crackdown as a shadowy and violent cabal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, Trump administration officials have repeatedly vowed to crack down on left-wing activists. They have filed criminal charges against the purported members of what prosecutors described as an “antifa cell” in Texas who fired at immigration officers and activists in California accused of plotting to set off homemade bombs outside two companies near Los Angeles on New Year’s Eve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the investigation into protesters in Minneapolis might be different, if only because it has the potential to involve people not accused of committing any violence or even those without a close connection to Ms. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and many in his administration — particularly Vice President JD Vance — have already made clear that they believe Ms. Good, who was shot at three times at close range, was unambiguously responsible for her own death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to reporters on Sunday, when the inquiry was less than one week old, Mr. Trump called Ms. Good “very violent” and “very radical” even though a video analysis by The New York Times suggested it was likely that she was trying to drive away from officers, not to intentionally harm them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civil rights division of the Justice Department, which has investigated law enforcement officials for killing or injuring citizens in the past, has not opened an investigation into whether the agent violated Ms. Good’s rights under federal law, according to a federal law enforcement official who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss internal deliberations. The official added that the division was not expected to initiate a case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear how deeply Ms. Good was involved in activism in Minneapolis beyond participating with her wife in the protest against immigration officers on the day she was killed. In a group chat used by local residents to monitor ICE movements, her wife was described as a “helper” in that action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement issued to The Associated Press, Becca Good suggested that the two women took part in some sort of protest on the day of the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“On Wednesday, Jan. 7, we stopped to support our neighbors,” she said. “We had whistles. They had guns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even though investigators have not made public a specific allegation that anyone aside from Ms. Good and her wife were involved in an encounter with federal agents that day, the Justice Department is still planning to examine a wide group of activists who took part in the neighborhood watch activities, believing they were “instigators” of the shooting, the people familiar with the inquiry said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complicating matters further, some senior administration officials immediately labeled Ms. Good a “domestic terrorist” after she was killed — even though investigators barely had time to collect and assess the facts about the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, for example, Mr. Vance said that Ms. Good had interfered with a law enforcement operation, likening her actions to other acts of violence against immigration officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is classic terrorism,” Mr. Vance said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, echoed Mr. Vance’s remarks, asserting that Ms. Good had “weaponized” her vehicle and that the ICE agent, Mr. Ross, had “defended his life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you look at what the definition of domestic terrorism is,” Ms. Noem said, “it completely fits the situation on the ground.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts in domestic terrorism cases said the administration had jumped the gun in lodging accusations like that and failed to follow the traditional procedures for determining whether a case should be classified as domestic terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not appropriate for officials to characterize this incident as domestic terrorism before the investigation is complete,” said Thomas E. Brzozowski, the former counsel for domestic terrorism in the Justice Department’s national security division. “There used to be a process, deliberate and considered, to figure out if behavior could be legitimately described as domestic terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And when it’s not followed,” Mr. Brzozowski said, “then the term becomes little more than a political cudgel to bash one’s enemies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Brzozowski raised concerns that the inquiry in Minneapolis was coming a little more than a month after Attorney General Pam Bondi issued a memo that greatly expanded the traditional definition of domestic terrorism. Ms. Bondi’s memo classified as domestic terrorism not only recognizably violent crimes like rioting and looting, but also things like impeding law enforcement officers or even simply doxxing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The memo also asserted that domestic terrorists use violence or the threat of violence to advance certain “political and social agendas” — all of them traditionally associated with left-wing activism. Among the causes listed were opposition to immigration enforcement, anticapitalism and “hostility towards traditional views on family, religion and morality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear whether the inquiry in Minnesota will include allegations of domestic terrorism. But if it does, Ms. Bondi’s memo could give investigators latitude to move beyond the customary practice of focusing such investigations only on people engaged in or plotting violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When you have a memo like this, it complicates things because it builds in a set of assumptions about what domestic terrorism is and what it is not,” Mr. Brzozowski said. “If you’re an investigator in the field, you can’t simply run away from this new definition. You have to deal with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Bogel-Burroughs contributed reporting from Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/fbi-renee-good-ice-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:17:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Has Another Justification for the Shooting of Renee Good: Disrespect</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-shooting-renee-good-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-trump-minnesota-cbqj/12dc-trump-minnesota-cbqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has added another justification for the fatal shooting of Renee Good by an ICE agent in Minnesota: She behaved badly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At a very minimum, that woman was very, very disrespectful to law enforcement,” Mr. Trump told reporters aboard Air Force One on Sunday evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days since Ms. Good, 37, was shot and killed by Jonathan Ross, an ICE agent, Trump administration officials have used a variety of arguments as they have tried to justify the episode. They have called it an act of self-defense, and Mr. Trump has falsely claimed Ms. Good “ran over” the agent. JD Vance, the vice president, has argued that Mr. Ross has “absolute immunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Trump still says the ICE agent was acting in self-defense, his latest comments suggest that disrespecting law enforcement could help to justify the killing. The comments raise serious questions about the use of force by those carrying out Mr. Trump’s crackdown on immigration, and they underscore the extent to which Mr. Trump’s impulse is to condemn anything done by his critics and to defend the actions of his supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked by a reporter if he believed deadly force was necessary in this case, Mr. Trump said: “It was highly disrespectful of law enforcement. The woman and her friend were highly disrespectful of law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The federal government has defended the shooting as lawful and necessary, while local officials have dismissed that narrative. Mr. Trump referred to a “crunch” he heard in footage of the shooting to buttress his claim that the ICE agent was in danger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems like the big picture is to control the narrative and suggest to the public that she was in the wrong, and they were in the right,” said Barbara L. McQuade, a former U.S. attorney and a law professor at the University of Michigan. “And also, I think, to send a message that the public needs to obey law enforcement on the streets, and to intimidate protesters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added: “If people are afraid they’re going to be shot or arrested for observing or peacefully protesting, or even for mouthing off, I think the thought is that will cause people to self-censor or chill their behavior, cause them to stay home.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Fox, a legal fellow at the Cato Institute’s Project on Criminal Justice, said that even if Mr. Trump’s allegation that Ms. Good was a “professional agitator” were true, that would not justify her killing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As far as I can tell, they’re not professional agitators,” Mr. Fox said. “She’s just a local woman who lived in the community. But it doesn’t really matter, right? You don’t get to kill someone because they engage in conduct that you disagree with or find distasteful or deplorable. If cops could just kill people any time they get annoyed or frustrated, my God, we would be in trouble.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the moments before the shooting Wednesday in Minneapolis, Ms. Good tells the agent that she isn’t mad at him, and Mr. Ross begins to circle her vehicle. She reverses as he crosses in front of her S.U.V., then she starts to move forward, and turns to the right. Mr. Ross is near her left headlight when he opens fire three times, killing her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Wall Street Journal investigation found that Ms. Good’s killing was one of 13 episodes in which federal immigration agents have used deadly force against civilians in vehicles since July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aboard Air Force One, Mr. Trump said ICE agents have faced their own hardships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people have been harassed and threatened every day,” the president said. “They had bands out playing so they couldn’t sleep at the hotel. I see what they’re doing to them. They’re threatening them constantly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Mr. Trump, the White House press secretary, Karoline Leavitt, defended the actions of ICE on Monday, denigrating the protesters who oppose the agents’ actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This administration will continue to stand wholeheartedly by the brave men and women of ICE, including that officer in Minneapolis who was absolutely justified in using self-defense against a lunatic who is part of a group, an organized group, to interject and to impede on law enforcement operations,” Ms. Leavitt said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanita Gupta, a former associate attorney general who oversaw both the civil rights division that can prosecute federal agents and the civil division that can defend them, called the administration’s rush to disparage Ms. Good “unprecedented.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Being ‘disrespectful’ does not warrant the use of deadly force,” Ms. Gupta said. “The immediate public efforts by the White House to spin the facts, including denigrating the victim, does not change federal law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, contrasted Mr. Trump’s treatment of Ms. Good with his praise and support for the hundreds of pro-Trump rioters who stormed the Capitol on Jan. 6, 2021, and attacked the police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 6 this year, the Trump administration made a page on its website that accused the Capitol Police of instigating the riot, and said a pro-Trump rioter whom the police killed during the mayhem was “murdered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump just pardoned nearly 1,600 insurrectionists,” Mr. Raskin said, “hundreds of whom violently attacked police officers and called them everything from traitors to pigs to racial epithets, and ruthlessly taunted them and maligned them for hours.” He added that “Donald Trump’s very dubious characterization of Renee Good as having been disrespectful is not only factually suspect, but it’s legally irrelevant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The police do not have the right to shoot people in the head because they consider them having acted in a disrespectful way,” Mr. Raskin said. “That legal standard would have led to a slaughter on Jan. 6.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-shooting-renee-good-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:08:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Plans for Venezuelan Oil Run Headlong Into Reality</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-venezuela-oil-dominance-influence.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-assess-gwcj/12dc-assess-gwcj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a White House pursuing “energy dominance,” President Trump’s play for Venezuela’s oil holds considerable promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having effective control of Venezuela’s oil exports could expand the United States’ ability to project power around the world without worrying as much about the economic and political consequences of oil price shocks. It could reduce the influence of Middle Eastern oil producers and leave big consumers like China more dependent on the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The head of Russia’s sovereign wealth fund, Kirill Dmitriev, said that Washington could now have “huge market leverage” in the global oil trade. Tong Zhao, a China analyst at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, said there was concern in Beijing that expanding U.S. influence across Latin America could “enable the United States to cut off oil and other strategic resource supplies from the region to China at will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump’s grand plans for Venezuelan oil have already run headlong into reality, starting with the apparent reluctance of the major American oil companies to plunge immediately into Venezuela and the related fact that, unlike Russia or Saudi Arabia, the United States does not have a national oil company ready to do the government’s bidding. And he is waging his campaign for greater control of world oil markets in an era in which the United States is already less sensitive to shocks in the global oil supply than it was in decades past, when Mr. Trump honed his “take the oil” mentality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela has the world’s largest oil reserves, but currently produces only about 1 percent of the world’s oil because of years of sanctions and mismanagement. Mr. Trump has said that American companies will spend billions of dollars to improve the country’s infrastructure and increase its production — a process that analysts believe would take years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s strategy raises the question of how much “energy dominance” is really worth nowadays, given that many analysts believe that a vast oversupply of oil is already sloshing around global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Under Trump, the U.S. status as the world’s largest petrostate is growing,” said Cliff Kupchan, chairman of the Eurasia Group, a political risk assessment firm. “In my view, it’s a bad bet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, however, is projecting confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are open for business,” Mr. Trump said as he hosted oil executives at the White House on Friday, speaking as though he was already in charge of Venezuela’s oil exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments later, the chief executive of the largest U.S. oil company, Exxon Mobil, told Mr. Trump that Venezuela was “uninvestable” and did not commit to major spending. On Sunday, Mr. Trump told reporters aboard Air Force One that the U.S. oil giant was “playing too cute.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’d probably be inclined to keep Exxon out” of Venezuela, Mr. Trump said. “I didn’t like their response.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a back-and-forth that demonstrated Mr. Trump’s fixation on oil as the spoils of the United States’ attack on Venezuela and seizure of its leader, Nicolás Maduro, on Jan. 3. It also revealed the limits of his influence as the American president, in a world in which energy companies are far from eager to see even more fossil fuels on world markets. The U.S. benchmark oil price traded near $56 a barrel last week, close to its lowest level in five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“1973 is long gone,” said Amy Myers Jaffe, an energy and geopolitics scholar at New York University. “Oil is not our Achilles’ heel anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Jaffe was referring to the 1973 oil embargo, when Arab oil exporting countries punished the United States for its support of Israel and, in so doing, demonstrated the vulnerabilities of relying on foreign oil imports. Not only is the United States now the world’s largest oil producer, she said, but “much of our economy runs on other energy sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the view of oil as a driving force in geopolitics has been fixed in Mr. Trump’s mind since at least the 1980s. He touched on the 1973 oil crisis in his 1987 “Art of the Deal,” noting in the book that the oil embargo “devastated” U.S. airlines. After he returned to the White House last year, Mr. Trump announced the formation of a National Energy Dominance Council with the goal of reducing “our dependency on foreign imports.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s attack on Venezuela has emerged as a unique opportunity to put into action what he has long called for: taking another country’s oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re going to be going in with hundreds of billions of dollars in drilling oil, and it’s good for Venezuela and it’s great for the United States,” Mr. Trump said after meeting oil executives on Friday, without clarifying which companies would be making those investments and doing the drilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper, at least, having some measure of control over Venezuelan oil exports could indeed provide Mr. Trump with additional international leverage. Meghan L. O’Sullivan, director of the Geopolitics of Energy Project at the Harvard Kennedy School, said one result could be a decrease in the influence of the OPEC oil cartel and of “U.S. adversaries that might seek to influence oil markets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zhao, the Carnegie China analyst, said that Beijing appeared to be nervous about the increasing U.S. role in oil markets, even more so because of instability in Iran. While only about 5 percent of China’s total crude oil imports come from Venezuela, he said, Venezuela could become more important as a source “should China’s access to Iranian oil come under pressure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump considers yet another potential foreign military intervention — this time in Iran — the role of oil in geopolitics could become relevant again. Ms. O’Sullivan, who served in the George W. Bush administration during the Iraq war, said that Mr. Trump was less constrained by the threat of oil prices spiking as a result of military action in the Middle East than past presidents might have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, she said, Mr. Trump could still be challenged by Gulf oil producers like Saudi Arabia that are in need of higher oil prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They may not feel inclined to pump more oil to ensure low gas prices for the American consumer if Trump’s actions lead to further unrest,” Ms. O’Sullivan said in an email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kupchan, the Eurasia Group chairman, predicted that Mr. Trump could soon voice an interest in Iran’s oil, as well. He said the focus on oil appeared to be distracting the Trump administration from the need to make the United States more competitive in selling cutting-edge, electricity-based technologies to the world, an arena in which China excels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump’s not wrong that there’s some leverage to be derived from Venezuelan, Iranian oil,” Mr. Kupchan said. “What’s important, though, is that the trade-off is really severe.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-venezuela-oil-dominance-influence.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:15:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former U.S. Navy Sailor Gets Nearly 17 Years in Prison for Spying for China</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/us-navy-sailor-china-spy-sentenced.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12xp-sailor/12xp-sailor-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former U.S. Navy sailor was sentenced on Monday to nearly 17 years in prison, federal prosecutors said, after he was convicted of spying for China and using his security clearance to sell secrets about the capabilities of American warships, including their vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The onetime sailor, Jinchao Wei, known as Patrick Wei, 25, was a machinist’s mate aboard the Essex, an amphibious assault ship moored at Naval Base San Diego.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A jury in U.S. District Court in San Diego found Mr. Wei guilty in August on six of seven criminal counts he faced, including two spying charges brought under the Espionage Act, and four conspiracy counts in violation of the Arms Export Control Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Navy characterized some of the information sold by Mr. Wei, for a total of $12,000, as “critical technology.” He was dishonorably discharged from the military late last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second sailor, who was arrested at the same time as Mr. Wei, was sentenced in 2024 to 27 months in prison after pleading guilty to conspiring with a Chinese intelligence officer and accepting a bribe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors had argued that Mr. Wei, a naturalized U.S. citizen who was born in China, had betrayed his adopted country and had pushed for a sentence of nearly 22 years in prison. He had been facing a maximum possible sentence of life in prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sentencing memorandum, prosecutors wrote that he had “compromised the U.S. Navy’s entire fleet of amphibious assault ships by sending the Chinese government thousands of pages of technical information about the fleet’s complex ship systems and how the U.S. Navy operates and maintains those systems.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was sworn to protect the U.S. and the sensitive information he was given,” prosecutors wrote in the memorandum. “If necessary, he was called to fight and die for the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a handwritten letter filed with the court a few days before his sentencing, Mr. Wei apologized for his actions and asked for leniency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, I screwed up,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wei’s lawyers had sought a sentence of 30 months for their client, who they wrote in court documents had falsely believed that the Chinese intelligence officer who had recruited him was a naval enthusiast who worked for the state-owned China Shipbuilding Industry Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wei considered the man a mentor and had been eager to please him, his lawyers wrote, noting that he had spent his early childhood in isolation while being raised by his grandmother and uncle, both of whom were mentally unstable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mr. Wei’s actions were in no way the result of any hatred or animosity towards the U.S. government nor were they a means to get rich,” the lawyers wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2022, the Chinese intelligence officer recruited Mr. Wei on social media, offering him $500 for daily updates on which ships were docked at the base, investigators said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wei told a friend that he was “no idiot” and that what he was being asked “is quite obviously espionage,” adding an expletive, according to the Justice Department, which cited the comment during Mr. Wei’s trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one instance, Mr. Wei agreed to provide his Chinese contact with information about “the number and training of U.S. Marines during an upcoming international maritime warfare exercise,” according to a federal indictment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exchange for $5,000, prosecutors said, he gave the contact at least 30 technical and mechanical ship manuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Members of the United States military swear to support and defend the Constitution of the United States,” Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, said in a statement. “This active-duty U.S. Navy sailor betrayed his country and compromised the national security of the United States.” The Navy declined to comment, instead directing requests to the Justice Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguing that the documents shared by their client could be found online, Mr. Wei’s lawyers disputed that he was as important as prosecutors had contended. Mr. Wei spent most of his days in the Navy sanding and painting the ship that he was assigned to, his lawyers said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wei, who the prosecutors said was evidently seeking U.S. citizenship while working clandestinely with China, was acquitted on one count of unlawful procurement of citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/us-navy-sailor-china-spy-sentenced.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:09:53 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>