<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:18:02 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Cabbage, Radish, Mackerel Up to 50% Off... Lunar New Year Food Ingredient Measures Announced (배추·무·고등어 최대 50% 할인…설 명절 식재료 대책 발표)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241875.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cabbage, Radish, Mackerel Up to 50% Off... Lunar New Year Food Ingredient Measures Announced (배추·무·고등어 최대 50% 할인…설 명절 식재료 대책 발표)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/646/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502279.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;27일 서울의 한 전통시장에서 시민들이 장을 보고 있다. 이날 구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관은 설 민생안정 대책과 관련해 “할인 지원을 최대한 확대해 고등어 등 성수품에 대해서는 최대 50%까지 할인이 되도록 하겠다”고 밝혔다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government will sell popular items such as cabbage, radish, and mackerel at up to a 50% discount during this Lunar New Year holiday. It will supply 39.3 trillion won in holiday funds for small business owners and small and medium-sized enterprises. (정부가 이번 설 명절에 배추와 무, 고등어 등 성수품을 최대 50% 할인한 가격으로 판매한다. 소상공인과 중소기업을 위한 명절 자금은 39조3천억원 규모로 공급한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance Koo Yun-cheol reported on Lunar New Year livelihood stabilization measures at a Cabinet meeting presided over by President Lee Jae-myung on the 27th. Deputy Prime Minister Koo stated that for this Lunar New Year holiday, 270,000 tons of 16 major popular items will be supplied, the largest scale ever. The amount invested in the popular item discounts is up to 91 billion won. (구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관은 27일 이재명 대통령이 주재한 국무회의에서 설 민생안정 대책을 보고했다. 구 부총리는 이번 설 명절에 16대 성수품을 역대 최대 규모인 27만톤 공급할 예정이라고 밝혔다. 성수품 할인에 투입되는 금액은 최대 910억원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the government plans to import and supply 2.24 million fresh eggs and significantly expand the items eligible for the Onnuri gift certificate refund event. It also plans to accelerate the eradication of price gouging, which President Lee has pointed out, and investigations into collusion regarding sugar, flour, eggs, and starch syrup. The government plans to intensively issue 4 trillion won worth of regional love gift certificates, usable only within specific regions, in January and February through cooperation between the central and local governments. Deputy Prime Minister Koo particularly stated that they will pursue measures to increase the discount rate during the holiday period and raise purchase limits. (또 정부는 신선란 224만개를 수입해 공급하고, 온누리상품권 환급 행사 대상 품목도 대폭 확대할 예정이다. 이 대통령이 지적해 온 바가지요금 근절과 설탕·밀가루·계란·전분당 등에 대한 담합 조사에도 속도를 낼 계획이다. 지역 안에서만 사용할 수 있는 지역사랑상품권은 중앙정부와 지방정부가 협력해 1∼2월 4조원 규모로 집중적으로 발행할 계획이다. 특히 설 기간 할인율을 높이고, 구매 한도를 상향 조정하는 방안을 추진하겠다고 구 부총리는 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is also expanding financial support for small and medium-sized enterprises and small business owners. Deputy Prime Minister Koo explained, "We will newly supply 39.3 trillion won in holiday funds for small business owners and small and medium-sized enterprises," adding, "We will also increase loan guarantees to a scale of 58 trillion won." The worker holiday support project for employees of SMEs and others will support 50,000 people in January and February. In particular, it will provide additional support of up to 50,000 won during the holiday period and pursue measures such as exemption of highway tolls and discounts on some trains like KTX for returning home. (정부는 중소기업과 소상공인에 대한 자금 지원도 확대한다. 구 부총리는 “소상공인과 중소기업에 대한 명절 자금을 39조3천억원 규모로 신규 공급할 것”이라며 “대출 보증 역시 58조원 규모로 늘려가겠다”고 설명했다. 중소기업 등 근로자 휴가지원 사업은 1~2월에 5만명을 대상으로 지원한다. 특히 설 기간 최대 5만원까지 추가 지원하고 고속도로 통행료 면제, 케이티엑스(KTX) 역귀성 등 일부 열차 할인 등을 추진한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Koo said, "Since food prices among living costs are high and burdensome, we will focus on managing them," and added, "Although consumption is recovering, there are some difficulties in spreading this to vulnerable groups like small business owners and SMEs, so we will focus on this part." (구 부총리는 “생활물가 중에서 먹거리 가격이 높아 부담되기 때문에 중점 관리하겠다”며 “소비 회복이 되고 있지만 소상공인, 중소기업 등 취약 계층까지 확산하는 데 다소 어려움이 있기 때문에 이 부분에 중점을 두겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241875.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/646/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502279.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[News Dive] Jang Dong-hyeok to Return Soon, Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion Imminent? ([뉴스 다이브] 장동혁 곧 복귀, 한동훈 제명 임박?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241882.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[News Dive] Jang Dong-hyeok to Return Soon, Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion Imminent? ([뉴스 다이브] 장동혁 곧 복귀, 한동훈 제명 임박?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502469.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Featuring: Lawyer Yang Ji-yeol, Current Affairs Commentator Park Young-sik, Lawyer Shin In-gyu, Hankyoreh Editorial Chief Kwon Tae-ho; Hosted by: Ko Hyun-joon. Trump: "Tariffs on Korean cars and mutual tariffs to increase from 15% to 25%" / Park Seong-jae denies 'involvement in rebellion' in first trial... "Yoon would have declared it even if opposed" / KBS union reveals "President Park Jang-beom called news bureau chief just before martial law" / 45 People Power Party members who acted as 'human shields' to block Yoon's arrest... fall silent after verdict / Jang Dong-hyeok to return soon... Han Dong-hoon's expulsion seen as imminent, People Power Party on the eve of a storm / President Lee's relentless 'storm SNS state affairs' today (January 26) News Dive, we hope for many viewers. (출연: 양지열 변호사, 박영식 시사평론가, 신인규 변호사, 권태호 한겨레 논설실장, 진행: 고현준. 트럼프 “한국산 자동차 및 상호관세 15%-&amp;gt;25% 인상” / 박성재, 첫 재판서 ‘내란 가담’ 부인... “반대해도 윤이 선포” / KBS 노조 폭로 “박장범 사장, 계엄 직전 보도국장 전화” / 윤 체포 막던 ‘인간 방패’ 국힘 45인... 판결 나오자 ‘묵묵부답’ / 장동혁 곧 복귀... 한동훈 제명 임박 전망, 국힘 폭풍전야 / 이 대통령의 거침없는 ‘폭풍 SNS 국정’ 오늘 (1월 26일) 뉴스 다이브 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241882.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502469.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[On the Scene] "'Mr. Public Mind' Lee Hae-chan, Even His Death in the Line of Duty Was Fitting"... Condolences Continue ([현장] “‘미스터 퍼블릭마인드’ 이해찬, 순직도 그다워”…이어진 조문)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241889.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[On the Scene] "'Mr. Public Mind' Lee Hae-chan, Even His Death in the Line of Duty Was Fitting"... Condolences Continue ([현장] “‘미스터 퍼블릭마인드’ 이해찬, 순직도 그다워”…이어진 조문)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/448/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502742.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이해찬 전 국무총리의 시신과 영정이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 도착해 운구되고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, as the state and public funeral for the late Lee Hae-chan, Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council who passed away during a business trip to Vietnam, was held, fellow politicians—colleagues and seniors/juniors—who visited the funeral hall recalled the Senior Vice Chairman, who was called 'Mr. Public Mind' during his lifetime, and their eyes grew red. (베트남 출장 도중 별세한 고 이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의 수석부의장의 기관·사회장이 열린 27일, 빈소를 찾은 동료·선후배 정치인들은 생전 ‘미스터 퍼블릭 마인드(공인의식)’로 불린 이 수석부의장을 떠올리며 눈시울을 붉혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The body of the late Senior Vice Chairman Lee Hae-chan arrived at Incheon International Airport at 6:53 AM, just 4 hours and 30 minutes after departing from Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam, and was moved to the funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital in Jongno-gu, Seoul. On this day, the funeral hall was so crowded there was no room to step, with over 100 former and current politicians visiting alone. President Lee Jae-myung is also scheduled to visit the funeral hall this evening. (고 이해찬 수석부의장의 주검은 이날 베트남 호찌민시에서 출발한 지 4시간30분만인 아침 6시53분께 인천국제공항에 도착해 빈소인 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장으로 옮겨졌다. 이날 빈소는 전·현직 정치인만 해도 100명이 넘는 이들이 찾아오며 발 디딜 틈이 없었다. 이재명 대통령도 이날 저녁 빈소를 찾는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Cho Jung-sik of the Democratic Party, who oversaw the entire process of transporting the body from Vietnam in his capacity as a Presidential Special Advisor for Political Affairs, stated, "Senior Vice Chairman Lee had cold/flu symptoms before leaving his home on the 22nd, and his wife urged him not to go on the business trip. However, the Senior Vice Chairman said, 'It's an official schedule, I must go,' and departed. The next day, when his entourage suggested he return (considering his health condition), he said, 'Official duties are important. I will carry out at least some of the schedule.'" He added, "The deceased considered this Senior Vice Chairman position his last public office and sacrificed himself until the very end, dying in the line of duty." (대통령 정무특보 자격으로 베트남에서부터 운구 과정을 총괄한 조정식 민주당 의원은 “이 수석부의장은 지난 22일 자택 출발 전 감기몸살 증상이 있어 사모님이 출장을 만류했는데, 이 수석부의장이 ‘공식 일정이니 가야 한다’며 출장길에 나섰다. 다음날 수행진이 (건강 상태를 고려해) 귀국을 권유하자 ‘공무가 중요하다. 일부 일정이라도 소화하겠다’고 하셨다”며 “고인은 이번 수석부의장직을 본인의 마지막 공직으로 여기셨고, 마지막까지 몸을 불사르다 순직하셨다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Assembly Speaker Woo Won-shik, who accompanied the transportation of the deceased from Incheon Airport to the funeral hall, paid tribute, saying, "Above all, he was a great teacher of our times who tried to heal the pain of those suffering and in hardship." Han Byung-do, the Democratic Party's floor leader who served as chief of staff during the deceased's presidential primary campaign, said, "Senior Advisor Lee Hae-chan was a star of the Democratic Party. He played the most central role in creating successive democratic governments. I will work hard to ensure our country's democracy is never shaken again." (고인의 인천공항 도착부터 빈소까지 운구를 함께한 우원식 국회의장은 “무엇보다 힘들고 아픈 사람들의 고통을 치유하려고 했던 우리 시대의 큰 스승”이라며 추모했고, 고인의 대선 경선 후보 시절 비서실장을 지냈던 한병도 민주당 원내대표는 “이해찬 상임고문님은 민주당의 별 같은 분이셨다. 역대 민주 정부를 창출하는 데 가장 중심적인 역할을 해주셨다. 다시는 민주주의가 흔들리지 않는 나라를 만들기 위해 열심히 노력하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho said, "Seeing that he was engaged in public activities until the last moment of his life, I truly feel it's 'so like Lee Hae-chan.' I hope his great will continues." (우상호 전 청와대 정무수석은 “생애 마지막 순간까지 공적 활동을 하다 돌아가신 것을 보면 정말 ‘이해찬답다’고 느낀다. 이분의 큰 뜻이 계속 이어지길 소망한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funeral for the Senior Vice Chairman will be held as a state and public funeral jointly hosted by the Democratic Party and the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council until the 31st. Prime Minister Kim Min-seok serves as the standing funeral committee chairman, while the standing co-chairs of the civic society/political party funeral committee are Seoul National University Emeritus Professor Paik Nak-chung and Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae. Starting this afternoon, general citizens can also pay their respects at the Vice Chairman's funeral hall. (이 수석부의장의 장례는 오는 31일까지 민주당·민주평통이 공동 주관하는 기관·사회장으로 치러진다. 김민석 국무총리가 상임장례위원장을 맡고, 시민사회·정당 상임공동장례위원장은 백낙청 서울대 명예교수, 정청래 민주당 대표가 맡았다. 이날 오후부터 일반 시민도 이 부의장 빈소에 조문할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Soo-yeon &lt;a href="mailto:link@hani.co.kr"&gt;link@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김수연 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:link@hani.co.kr"&gt;link@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241889.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/448/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502742.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Good grief!" "You're just not interested!"... President Lee publicly reprimands NTS Commissioner twice in one week (“아이 참!” “관심이 없잖아요!”…이 대통령, 일주일 새 두번 국세청장 공개 질책)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241902.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Good grief!" "You're just not interested!"... President Lee publicly reprimands NTS Commissioner twice in one week (“아이 참!” “관심이 없잖아요!”…이 대통령, 일주일 새 두번 국세청장 공개 질책)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/413/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502935.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 27일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a discussion on measures to collect delinquent non-tax national revenue on the 27th, President Lee Jae-myung said to National Tax Service Commissioner Im Kwang-hyun, "The National Assembly is too slow right now, who knows when (the legislation) will be passed. Are you going to wait until then?" This was a public reprimand of Commissioner Im, who kept repeating that 'the matter requires a legal amendment' rather than actively seeking solutions. (이재명 대통령이 27일 체납된 국세 외 수입 징수 방안을 논의하는 과정에서 임광현 국세청장을 향해 “국회가 지금 너무 느려서 어느 세월에 (입법이) 될지 모른다. 그때까지 기다리실 거냐”고 말했다. 적극적으로 해법을 찾아내기보다 ‘법 개정이 필요한 사안’이라는 말만 반복하는 임 청장을 공개 질책한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the State Council meeting that day, President Lee raised the issue to Commissioner Im, saying, "Habitual delinquents should not receive benefits. We must make life difficult for those who dodge taxes," and "The currently delinquent non-tax national revenue is even less managed now." (이 대통령은 이날 국무회의에서 임 청장에게 “상습 체납자가 혜택을 보면 안 된다. 세금 떼먹고 못살게 해야 한다”며 “지금 체납된 국세 외 수입은 더 관리가 안 되고 있다”고 문제를 제기했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'non-tax national revenue' mentioned by President Lee refers to income the state obtains other than taxes, such as unfair trade surcharges, environmental regulation violation charges, and fees for using state-owned properties. The scale of non-tax national revenue is 284 trillion won (as of the end of 2024), making it as important a financial resource for the government as tax revenue (337 trillion won). However, because fiscal revenue is managed and collected separately by various ministries according to over 300 laws, even though the amount of uncollected revenue reaches 25 trillion won (as of 2024), there have been difficulties in enforcing collection. (이 대통령이 언급한 ‘국세 외 수입’은 불공정거래 과징금, 환경규제위반 부담금, 국유재산 사용로 등 조세 외에 국가가 얻는 수입을 말한다. 국세 외 수입의 규모는 284조원(2024년 말 기준)으로, 국세수입(337조원)만큼이나 정부의 중요한 재원이다. 하지만 재정 수입을 300여개 법률에 따라 여러 부처가 각각 관리·징수하는 바람에, 미수납액이 25조원(2024년 기준)에 달하는데도 강제 징수에 어려움을 겪어왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to this criticism, Commissioner Im said, "The National Tax Service can only collect national taxes," and "To conduct entrusted collection for delinquencies, an amendment to the National Claims Management Act is necessary." (임 청장은 이런 지적에 “국세청은 국세만 징수할 수 있다”며 “체납에 대해 위탁징수를 하려면 국가채권관리법 개정이 필요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "I fully understand, but the legislative speed of the National Assembly is too slow," and suggested an 'alternative', saying, "We can't just keep waiting, so before that, why not recruit and dispatch personnel under the name of each ministry or conduct joint management?" He added, "The National Assembly's legislative speed is too slow right now. It's been almost 8 months (since the government's inauguration), but even legislation on the so-called government's basic policy directions is less than 20% complete," and "The National Assembly is too slow right now, making it impossible to work." (이 대통령은 “충분히 이해하겠지만 국회의 입법 속도가 너무 느리다”며 “계속 기다릴 수는 없으니 그 전이라도 각 부처 명의로 (인력을) 뽑아서 파견하든지 합동 관리를 해 주면 되지 않느냐”고 ‘대안’을 제시했다. 그러면서 “지금 국회 입법 속도가 너무 느리다. (정부 출범) 8개월 다 되어가는데 소위 정부의 기본적인 정책 방침에 대한 입법조차도 20%도 안 됐다”며 “지금 국회가 너무 느려서 일할 수가 없는 상태”라고도 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, when Commissioner Im repeatedly replied, "It seems legislation would be faster," President Lee raised his voice, saying, "Good grief, what are you saying..." and "The National Assembly is too slow right now, who knows when (the legislation) will be passed. Are you going to wait until then?" President Lee then emphasized again, "Start now. There's no guarantee it will be done by February. There are hundreds of bills pending in the National Assembly right now, who knows when they'll be passed at that speed," and "Given this situation, don't delay, let's take some emergency measures." President Lee also said, "Speed is important in administration, we must not wait." (하지만 임 청장이 “입법하는 게 더 빠를 것 같다”고 거듭 답변하자, 이 대통령은 “아이, 참 말을…”이라며 “국회가 지금 너무 느려서 어느 세월에 (입법이) 될지 모른다. 그때까지 기다리실 거냐”고 언성을 높였다. 이 대통령은 이어 “지금부터 시작하라. 2월에 된다는 보장이 없다. 지금 국회에 계류된 법률이 수백개인데, 저런 속도로 해서 어느 세월에 될지 모른다”며 “상황이 이러니 미루지 말고 비상조치를 좀 하자”고 거듭 강조했다. 이 대통령은 “행정은 속도가 중요한데 기다리면 안 된다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his presidential campaign, President Lee pledged to "secure funds for fulfilling promises (approximately 210 trillion won over the 5-year term) without raising taxes," listing the cleanup and strengthened collection of delinquent and evaded taxes as one of the key means. President Lee's public reprimand of Commissioner Im came because, despite making similar criticisms multiple times, no improvement has been made. (이 대통령은 대선 후보 시절 “증세 없이 공약 이행 재원(임기 5년 동안 약 210조원)을 마련하겠다”며 핵심 수단 중 하나로 체납·탈루 세금 정리와 징수 강화를 공약한 바 있다. 이 대통령이 임 청장을 공개 질책한 건 비슷한 지적을 여러 차례했음에도, 개선이 전혀 이뤄지지 않은 데 따른 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On December 16 last year, during a National Tax Service work report, President Lee had said, "We talked about the need for integrated management of non-tax revenue, how is the progress?" and instructed research on an integrated management plan. Commissioner Im had also said at the time, "Legal grounds are important, but the related tax law amendment is under discussion in the National Assembly, so its reflection in this year's tax law is being delayed." (이 대통령은 지난해 12월16일 국세청 업무보고에서 “세외수입의 통합관리가 필요하다고 얘기했었는데 진척이 어떻게 되고 있느냐”며 통합관리방안 연구를 지시한 바 있다. 임 청장은 당시에도 “법적 근거가 중요한데 관련 세법 개정은 국회 논의가 진행 중이라 올해 세법에 반영이 늦어지고 있다”고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, at the State Council meeting on the 20th, when President Lee asked about the accumulated amount of delinquent non-tax revenue and Commissioner Im did not provide a proper answer, he raised his voice, saying, "You're just not interested." President Lee also directed sharp criticism at Commissioner Im, saying, "Recruit personnel on a large scale to proceed with, for example, making phone calls or chasing after them for asset investigations regarding the accumulated delinquent non-tax revenue," and "You're too timid. Is it because you're a civil servant?" (이 대통령은 이후 지난 20일 국무회의에서도 누적된 체납 세외수입 금액 등을 물으며 임 청장이 제대로 된 답변을 내놓지 않자 “관심이 없는 거잖아요”라며 목소리를 높이기도 했다. 이 대통령은 “누적된 세외수입 체납분을 전화라도 하든지, 쫓아다니면서 재산조사를 하든지, (뭐라도) 할 인력을 대대적으로 뽑아서 진행하라”며 임 청장을 향해 “너무 소심해. 공무원이셔서 그런가”라며 뼈있는 질책을 하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241902.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/413/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502935.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>JCS: "North Korea Fires Multiple Ballistic Missiles into East Sea" (합참 “북한, 탄도미사일 여러발 동해상 발사”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241905.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;JCS: "North Korea Fires Multiple Ballistic Missiles into East Sea" (합참 “북한, 탄도미사일 여러발 동해상 발사”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502954.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;북한군은 지난해 2022년 11월 2일부터 5일까지 탄도미사일 발사 등 나흘간 대남 군사 작전을 진행했다고 그해 11월7일 밝혔다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Joint Chiefs of Staff (JCS) announced on the 27th that North Korea fired short-range ballistic missiles into the East Sea. (합동참모본부는 27일 북한이 동해상으로 단거리 탄도미사일을 발사했다고 밝혔다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The JCS reported that it detected several short-range ballistic missiles launched by North Korea from an area north of Pyongyang toward the East Sea around 3:50 PM today. The JCS stated, "The detected North Korean missiles flew approximately 350 km, and precise specifications are being analyzed in detail by South Korea and the U.S.," adding, "South Korean and U.S. intelligence authorities tracked the launch activity and closely shared related information with the U.S. and Japan." ( 합참은 이날 오후 3시50분께 북한이 평양 북방 일대에서 동해상으로 발사한 단거리 탄도미사일 여러 발을 포착했다고 전했다. 합참은 “포착된 북한의 미사일은 약 350㎞를 비행했으며, 정확한 제원은 한·미가 정밀분석 중”이라며 “한·미 정보당국은 발사 동향을 추적했고, 미국·일본과 관련 정보를 긴밀하게 공유했다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This marks North Korea's first ballistic missile launch toward the East Sea in 23 days since the 4th. Japan's Ministry of Defense also announced today that North Korea launched objects presumed to be ballistic missiles twice. ( 북한은 지난 4일 이후 23일 만에 동해 방향으로 탄도미사일을 발사했다. 일본 방위성은 이날 북한이 탄도미사일로 추정되는 물체를 두차례 발사했다고 밝히기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The JCS added, "Our military, under a solid South Korea-U.S. combined defense posture, is closely monitoring various North Korean activities while maintaining the capability and posture to overwhelmingly respond to any provocation." ( 합참은 “우리 군은 굳건한 한·미 연합방위태세 하에 북한의 다양한 동향을 예의주시 하면서, 어떠한 도발에도 압도적으로 대응할 수 있는 능력과 태세를 유지하고 있다”고 덧붙였다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. Forces Korea (USFK) also stated today, "We are aware of the (North Korean) missile launch and are closely consulting with allies and partners." It further noted, "Current assessments indicate this event does not pose an immediate threat to U.S. personnel, territory, or allies." ( 이날 주한미군도 “(북한의) 미사일 발사 사실을 인지하고 있다”며 “동맹 및 파트너국과 긴밀히 협의 중”이라는 입장을 내놨다. 그러면서 “현재 평가에 따르면 이번 사안은 미국 쪽 인원, 영토 또는 동맹국에 대한 즉각적인 위협은 아니”라고도 밝혔다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Yang Moo-jin of the University of North Korean Studies commented on this launch, saying, "Internally, it could be aimed at inspecting defense achievements and solidifying the system as the 9th Party Congress approaches," and "Externally, it could be a reaction to the U.S. releasing its new National Defense Strategy (NDS) and U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Policy Elbridge Colby's visit to South Korea, where he highlighted the North Korean nuclear threat and discussed theories of South Korea's primary defense responsibility." Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby, who visited South Korea on the 25th, has been meeting with high-level officials from the foreign and defense ministries and security sectors through today. ( 양무진 북한대학원대학교 석좌교수는 북한의 이번 발사에 대해 “내부적으론 9차 당대회가 임박한 가운데 국방성과를 점검하고, 체제를 결속하려는 목적일 수 있다”며 “미국이 새 국방전략(NDS)을 공개하고, 엘브리지 콜비 미국 국방부 정책차관이 방한해 북한의 핵 위협을 부각하고 한국의 1차적 방어 책임론 등을 말한 데 대한 반발 차원일 가능성도 있다”고 말했다. 지난 25일 방한한 콜비 차관은 이날까지 외교·국방부 장관 및 안보분야 고위 당국자들과 회동했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241905.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502954.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The PPP said "National Interest, Bipartisan Cooperation"... But now they're hitting President Lee over Trump's whims (국힘 “국익, 초당적 협력” 하자더니…트럼프 변덕에 이 대통령 때리기)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241909.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;The PPP said "National Interest, Bipartisan Cooperation"... But now they're hitting President Lee over Trump's whims (국힘 “국익, 초당적 협력” 하자더니…트럼프 변덕에 이 대통령 때리기)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/403/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503070.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;27일 경기도 평택항에 컨테이너가 쌓여있는 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'enemy countries' in the economic war waged by U.S. President Donald Trump against the world do not exclude long-time friends and allies. Interpreting Trump's unpredictable, surreal mindset within the existing framework of diplomatic norms and alliances is increasingly becoming a gamble with a high chance of failure. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 전 세계를 상대로 벌이는 경제 전쟁의 ‘적국’은 오랜 우방과 동맹국도 예외가 아니다. 종잡을 수 없는 트럼프의 초현실적 정신세계를 기존 외교 문법과 동맹의 틀 안에서 해석하는 것은, 이제 실패할 가능성이 큰 도박이 되어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emphasizing that there are no factions before the national interest and calling for 'bipartisan cooperation' has long been a rhetorical staple of the Korean conservative camp. They point to the unified front in Washington, D.C., across the political aisle for the sake of national interest, even amidst extreme political polarization. The People Power Party (PPP) even tried to suppress voices questioning the risks and practical benefits of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration's 'value diplomacy,' which leans towards the U.S. and Japan, by advocating a 'bipartisan single voice.' (국익 앞에는 진영이 따로 없다며 ‘초당적 협력’을 강조하는 것은 한국 보수진영의 오랜 레토릭이었다. 극단의 정치 양극화에도 국익을 위해서는 하나로 뭉치는 미국 워싱턴 조야를 보라는 것이다. 국민의힘은 미국·일본에 편중된 윤석열 정부의 ‘가치 외교’ 위험성과 실익을 따지는 목소리까지 ‘초당적 원보이스’를 내세워 소거하려 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Korea and the U.S. began tariff negotiations at the end of April last year, the PPP issued an official statement saying, "We must unite in a bipartisan manner before the national interest." Warning the Democratic Party of Korea (DPK), they said, "Any negotiation strategy will inevitably lose its power amidst political division and strife," and urged them to "refrain from words and actions that weaken negotiating power." (지난해 4월 말 한국과 미국이 관세 협상을 시작하자 국민의힘은 “국익 앞에 초당적으로 힘을 모아야 한다”는 공식 입장을 냈다. “그 어떤 협상 전략도, 정치권의 분열과 정쟁 속에서는 힘을 잃을 수밖에 없다”며, 더불어민주당을 향해 “협상력을 약화시키는 언행을 자제”하라고 경고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now that the Lee Jae-myung administration has taken office, the principle of 'bipartisan cooperation before national interest,' which the PPP once held sacred, has vanished like a mirage. In its place appears to be 'supra-national interest political strife' aimed at attacking the government and ruling party at every opportunity. (이재명 정부가 들어서자 국민의힘이 금과옥조로 여기는 ‘국익 앞 초당적 협력’ 기조는 신기루처럼 사라졌다. 그 자리를 이번 기회에 정부·여당을 때리자는 ‘초국익적 정쟁’이 대신하는 모양새다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th (local time), President Trump announced he would reinstate a 25% tariff on Korean products, citing the Korean National Assembly's failure to complete the legal procedures for the tariff negotiation outcome. Reportedly, there was no prior notification or inquiry to the Korean government. This is a diplomatic discourtesy unimaginable in an alliance and a typical Trumpian whim that makes the world shake its head. Immediately, as uncertainty over U.S. tariffs increased that day, the Korean won depreciated by 5.6 won against the U.S. dollar compared to the previous day. (26일(현지시각) 트럼프 대통령은 관세협상 결과물에 대한 한국 국회의 법적 절차 미이행을 들어 한국산 제품 관세를 25%로 다시 인상하겠다고 했다. 한국 정부에 사전 통보나 문의도 없었다고 한다. 동맹 관계에서는 있을 수 없는 외교적 무례이자 전 세계가 고개를 젓는 트럼프식 변덕이다. 당장 이날 대미 관세 불확실성이 커지면서 미 달러화 대비 원화 환율은 전날보다 5.6원 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, five bills for the "Special Act on Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Management" to implement the Korea-U.S. tariff agreement have been proposed in the National Assembly. The DPK proposed four, and the PPP proposed one. They were proposed last November and December. Full-scale review is scheduled to begin next month. Until now, the DPK argued, citing examples like the Japan-U.S. tariff agreement, that there is no need for National Assembly ratification, which would be 'shackling ourselves.' The PPP countered that, as a major trade agreement, it requires National Assembly verification and ratification. Since both sides' arguments have valid points and counterarguments are possible, this was a moment when 'bipartisan cooperation for the national interest' was more crucial than ever. (현재 국회에는 한-미 관세협상 이행을 위한 ‘한·미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’이 5건 발의돼 있다. 민주당이 4건, 국민의힘이 1건을 발의했다. 지난해 11∼12월 발의된 것들이다. 다음달부터 본격 심사가 진행될 예정이라고 한다. 그간 민주당은 일본 등의 관세협상 사례를 들어 ‘우리 스스로 족쇄를 채우는’ 국회 비준을 거칠 필요가 없다고 했고, 국민의힘은 중대한 통상 합의이기 때문에 국회 검증과 비준이 필요하다고 맞섰다. 여야 주장 모두 타당한 지점이 있고, 반론도 가능하다는 점에서 ‘국익을 위한 초당적 협력’이 그 어느 때보다 절실한 시점이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, instead of closely examining the background, intent, and parliamentary-level response measures regarding President Trump's 25% tariff announcement, the PPP immediately brought out the framing of "the true face of the Lee Jae-myung administration's hasty trade diplomacy." They called it a "tariff disaster caused by bypassing National Assembly ratification." Floor Leader Song Eon-seok attacked that day, saying, "President Lee Jae-myung and the administration concluded a major trade agreement requiring National Assembly ratification but have ignored the ratification process. All responsibility lies with the President and the administration." (그러나 국민의힘은 트럼프 대통령의 관세 25% 선포 배경과 의도, 국회 차원의 대응 방안 등을 면밀히 따지는 대신 “이재명 정부의 졸속 통상 외교의 민낯”이라는 프레임부터 들고 나왔다. “국회 비준 패싱이 불러온 관세 참사”라는 것이다. 송언석 원내대표는 이날 “이재명 대통령과 정부는 국회의 비준이 필요한 중대한 통상 합의를 체결해놓고 비준 절차를 외면해 왔다. 모든 책임은 대통령과 정부에 있다”고 공격했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP members of the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee also stated, "The issue of passing on the enormous financial burden, amounting to $350 billion, to the people must undergo the National Assembly's verification and consent. The Lee Jae-myung administration and the ruling party have disparaged the PPP's demands as obstructionism." They added, "Based solely on national interest and people's livelihoods, we will become a safety device for the Republic of Korea's diplomacy and security to help our companies and economy overcome the current crisis." PPP leader Jang Dong-hyuk, who is recovering after ending a hunger strike, also attacked President Lee on Facebook that day, saying, "A 25% tariff bomb has fallen on the people's wallets, but they just get angry and blame the legislation of the National Assembly they control." (국회 외교통일위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들도 “3500억달러에 달하는 막대한 재정적 부담을 국민에게 떠넘기는 문제는 반드시 국회의 검증과 동의를 거쳐야 한다는 국민의힘의 요구를 이재명 정부와 집권 여당은 발목잡기로 매도해 왔다”고 했다. 그러면서 “오직 국익과 민생을 기준으로 우리 기업과 경제가 현재의 위기를 극복할 수 있도록 대한민국 외교·안보의 안전장치가 되겠다”고 했다. 단식을 마치고 회복 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표도 이날 페이스북에 “국민 지갑에는 25% 관세 폭탄이 떨어졌는데, 자기들이 장악한 국회의 입법을 탓하며 화만 낸다”고 이 대통령을 공격했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DPK criticized the PPP's attitude as 'only paying lip service to national interest while still busy with obstructionism.' DPK members of the Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee rebutted, "Japan, which concluded a tariff agreement with the U.S., also did not go through National Assembly ratification, and the U.S. likewise has no procedure like congressional ratification. While the U.S. does not ratify it, if only Korea ratifies it and elevates it to a binding treaty, it's like tying our own feet." Addressing the PPP, they said, "We hope you will stop insisting on ratification, which holds the national interest hostage, and actively cooperate in passing the special act." (민주당은 이런 국민의힘의 태도를 ‘입으로만 국익을 말하고 여전히 발목잡기에 바쁘다’고 비판했다. 민주당 외통위원들은 “미국과 관세협상을 맺은 일본도 국회 비준을 거치지 않았고, 미국 역시 국회 비준 같은 절차는 없다. 미국은 비준하지 않는데 우리나라만 비준해서 구속력 높은 조약으로 격상시키는 건 우리 발을 스스로 묶는 것이나 마찬가지”라고 반박했다. 국민의힘을 향해서는 “국익을 볼모 삼는 비준 고집을 멈추고 특별법 통과에 적극 협조하기 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Supreme Court is expected to issue a ruling soon on the legality of the Trump administration's reciprocal tariff measures. There is a possibility the Supreme Court could invalidate the tariff bomb measures imposed on Korea and others. There is also analysis that President Trump's pressure that day was intended to make Korea's annual $20 billion investment in the U.S. irreversible before the Supreme Court ruling. DPK members of the Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee stated, "No matter how urgent it is to protect the national interest, we will respond calmly without rushing." (미 연방대법원은 조만간 트럼프 행정부의 상호관세 조치 합법성 여부를 가르는 판결을 내놓을 예정이다. 연방대법원이 한국 등에 부과한 관세 폭탄 조처를 무효로 할 가능성도 있다. 트럼프 대통령의 이날 압박이 연방대법원 판결 전에 연간 200억달러에 달하는 한국의 대미투자를 불가역적으로 만들려는 의도라는 분석도 나온다. 민주당 외통위원들은 “국익 수호를 위해 아무리 급하더라도 서두르지 않고 차분하게 대응하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241909.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/403/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503070.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hae-chan's 'Friend of 50 Years' Jeong Dong-young Says "Hey, you..."... Former President Moon Jae-in Also Visits Funeral Home (이해찬 ‘50년 지기’ 정동영 “야 이 사람아”…문재인 전 대통령도 빈소에)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241919.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hae-chan's 'Friend of 50 Years' Jeong Dong-young Says "Hey, you..."... Former President Moon Jae-in Also Visits Funeral Home (이해찬 ‘50년 지기’ 정동영 “야 이 사람아”…문재인 전 대통령도 빈소에)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/688/imgdb/original/2026/0127/3817695033002004.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;문재인 전 대통령과 김정숙 여사가 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 마련된 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소에서 헌화하고 있다. 사진공동취재단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of the 27th, former President Moon Jae-in and his wife, former first lady Kwon Yang-sook, and other former presidential family members visited the funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital where the memorial altar for the late former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan was set up. Writer Yoo Si-min, who formed a connection with the former prime minister as his aide when Lee was a first-term lawmaker, also visited and wiped away tears. (고 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소가 차려진 서울대병원 장례식장에 27일 오후 문재인 전 대통령 부부와 권양숙 여사 등 전직 대통령 가족들이 찾았다. 이 전 총리가 초선의원을 할 때 보좌관으로 인연을 맺은 유시민 작가도 찾아와 눈물을 훔쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Moon, who arrived at the funeral hall around 4:24 PM, shook hands with the bereaved family members one by one and then took a seat in the reception room with a somber expression. Former President Moon exchanged greetings with other mourners who visited the altar around the same time, including former National Assembly Speaker Chung Sye-kyun, former Minister of SMEs and Startups Park Young-sun, and former National Security Office Director Chung Eui-yong. (오후 4시24분쯤 장례식장을 빈소를 찾은 문 전 대통령은 유족들과 차례로 악수를 나눈 뒤 침통한 표정으로 접객실에 자리를 잡았다. 문 전 대통령은 정세균 전 국회의장, 박영선 전 중소벤처기업부 장관, 정의용 전 안보실장 등 비슷한 시각 빈소를 찾은 조문객들과 인사를 나눴다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Writer Yoo Si-min, who had a special bond with the deceased spanning over 40 years, also visited the altar this afternoon. After facing the bereaved family and offering condolences, he burst into tears he had been holding back, repeatedly wiping them with a handkerchief while his shoulders shook. After paying his respects, Writer Yoo stood at the chief mourner's seat and personally greeted other mourners. (고인과 40년 넘게 각별한 인연을 맺어온 유시민 작가도 이날 오후 빈소를 찾았다. 유가족을 마주하고 위로를 건넨 그는 참았던 눈물을 터뜨린 뒤 연신 손수건으로 눈물을 닦아내며 어깨를 들썩였다. 유 작가는 조문 뒤 상주석에 서서 조문객들을 직접 맞이했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kwon Yang-sook, the wife of former President Roh Moo-hyun, also visited the altar this afternoon. Dressed in a coordinated black coat, black shoes, and a black muffler, she hugged and comforted a weeping family member. Jeong Dong-young, Minister of Unification and a Seoul National University classmate of the deceased, looked at the portrait of the deceased and said, "Hey, you..." before being unable to continue. (노무현 전 대통령의 부인인 권양숙 여사도 이날 오후 빈소를 방문했다. 검은 코트와 검은색 신발, 검은색 머플러를 맞춰 입고 온 그는 울음 짓는 유족을 끌어안으며 위로했다. 고인의 서울대 동기인 정동영 통일부 장관은 고인의 영정사진을 보고는 “야 이 사람아…”라며 말을 잇지 못했다.  )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 50 Democratic Party of Korea lawmakers also visited the deceased's altar in small groups to bid farewell on his final journey. Democratic Party floor leader Han Byung-do said, "Senior Advisor Lee Hae-chan was like a star of the Democratic Party," adding, "In those harsh times, he played the most central role in achieving democracy and creating democratic governments from former President Kim Dae-jung to President Lee Jae-myung." He further stated, "All of us lawmakers have no way to contain our sorrowful hearts." (민주당 의원 50여명도 삼삼오오 고인의 빈소를 찾아 고인의 마지막 길을 배웅했다. 한병도 민주당 원내대표는 “이해찬 상임 고문은 민주당의 별 같은 분이었다”며 “그 엄혹한 시절에 민주주의를 이뤄내고, 김대중 전 대통령부터 이재명 대통령까지 민주정부를 창출하는데 가장 중심적인 역할을 해주셨다”고 말했다. 그는 “우리 모든 의원은 비통할 마음을 가눌 길이 없다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, former Prime Minister Kim Boo-kyum, Gyeonggi Province Governor Kim Dong-yeon, former South Chungcheong Province Governor Ahn Hee-jung, and others also visited the altar. Leader Cho Kuk and former Prime Minister Kim Boo-kyum stood next to party leader Chung Cheong-rae and Prime Minister Kim Min-seok to personally greet mourners. (조국 조국혁신당 대표, 김부겸 전 총리, 김동연 경기도지사, 안희정 전 충남지사 등도 빈소를 찾았다. 조국 대표와 김부겸 전 총리는 정청래 대표와 김민석 총리 옆에 서서 조문객들을 직접 맞이했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241919.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/688/imgdb/original/2026/0127/3817695033002004.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoo Si-min, weeping until his eyes burned... 'Lifelong comrade' who added to the wedding trousseau by giving up the ring from Lee Hae-chan and his wife (유시민, 눈 짓무르게 오열…이해찬 부부 반지 빼 혼수 보태준 ‘평생 동지’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241922.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Yoo Si-min, weeping until his eyes burned... 'Lifelong comrade' who added to the wedding trousseau by giving up the ring from Lee Hae-chan and his wife (유시민, 눈 짓무르게 오열…이해찬 부부 반지 빼 혼수 보태준 ‘평생 동지’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/954/862/imgdb/child/2026/0127/17695046973608_20260127503238.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;유시민 전 노무현재단 이사장이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에서 고 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 조문하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Lee Hae-chan, Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council, passed away on the 25th at the age of 74, attention is also being drawn to his relationship with his 'lifelong comrade' Yoo Si-min, former chairman of the Roh Moo-hyun Foundation, with whom he shared life and death, joy and sorrow. (이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의 수석부의장이 74살을 일기로 25일 서거하면서 생사고락을 함께했던 ‘평생의 동지’ 유시민 전 노무현재단 이사장과의 관계에도 이목이 쏠리고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, the funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital, where the Senior Vice Chairman's mortuary was set up, was bustling with fellow politicians, seniors and juniors, who came to pay their respects. Among them, the most noticeable person was former Chairman Yoo. Captured by media cameras, former Chairman Yoo was immersed in grief, weeping incessantly. Former Prime Minister Han Myeong-sook patted his back as former Chairman Yoo sobbed and embraced her. Former Prime Minister Han was the successor to the Senior Vice Chairman, who was the second Prime Minister of the Participatory Government. (27일 이 수석부의장의 빈소가 마련된 서울대병원 장례식장은 조문 온 동료 선후배 정치인들로 북적거렸다. 그 가운데서도 가장 눈에 띈 사람은 유 전 이사장이었다. 언론사 카메라에 포착된 유 전 이사장은 슬픔에 잠겨 끊임없이 흐느꼈다. 한명숙 전 국무총리는 유 전 이사장이 흐느끼며 품에 안기자 등을 다독이기도 했다. 한 전 총리는 참여정부 두 번째 국무총리였던 이 수석부의장의 후임이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the two dates back to the 'Seoul Spring' of 1980. Yoo Si-min was a third-year economics student at Seoul National University and chairman of the Student Council Representative Assembly, while the Senior Vice Chairman was the president of the Seoul National University Re-enrolled Students Association. The two became comrades by throwing themselves into the student movement. There is also an anecdote that when former Chairman Yoo was in difficult circumstances and found it hard to prepare a wedding trousseau, Kim Jeong-ok, the wife of the then Senior Vice Chairman Lee, took off a ring she was wearing and gave it to him to give to former Chairman Yoo's wife, Hyun Kyung-hye. (두 사람의 관계는 1980년 ‘서울의봄’ 당시로 거슬러 올라간다. 서울대 경제학과 3학년생이었던 유시민은 총학생회 대의원회 의장이었고, 이 수석부의장은 서울대 복학생협의회 회장이었다. 두 사람은 학생운동에 투신하며 동지로 거듭났다. 유 전 이사장이 넉넉지 못한 사정에 혼수를 마련하기 어렵게 되자, 당시 이 수석부의장의 부인 김정옥씨가 손에 낀 반지를 유 전 이사장의 부인 현경혜씨에게 주라고 빼줬다는 일화도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was also the Senior Vice Chairman who led former Chairman Yoo into the political arena. In the 13th general election in 1988, the Senior Vice Chairman, who became a first-term lawmaker for the Peace Democratic Party, offered former Chairman Yoo a position as an aide. Former Chairman Yoo recalled the situation on KBS's 'The Joy of Conversation 2' in 2019, saying, "I was on the police wanted list and was on the run, renting a basement room and writing. At that time, first-term lawmaker Lee Hae-chan came and said, 'If you become an aide, I'll get the wanted notice lifted.' I fell for that." (유 전 이사장을 정치권으로 이끈 것도 이 수석부의장이었다. 1988년 13대 총선에서 평화민주당 소속 초선 의원이 된 이 수석부의장은 유 전 이사장에게 보좌관직을 제안했다. 유 전 이사장은 지난 2019년 한국방송(KBS) ‘대화의 희열2’에 나와 “경찰 수배가 걸려서 도망가 반지하방에 세 얻어 글 쓰고 있을 때다. 당시 이해찬 초선 의원이 와서 ‘보좌관 하면 수배를 풀어주겠다’고 하더라. 거기에 혹했다”며 당시 상황을 떠올리기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'chemistry' between the two was unparalleled. The Senior Vice Chairman made a name for himself as a 'star freshman' lawmaker, gaining attention for tenaciously grilling witnesses including Chun Doo-hwan to identify those responsible for the martial law troops' shooting during the 13th National Assembly's May 18 Gwangju Democratization Movement Truth Investigation hearing, and for his active role in the National Assembly's Labor Committee. Behind him was 'advisor' Yoo Si-min. During his lifetime, the Senior Vice Chairman jokingly said that former Chairman Yoo was the 'culprit' behind his passionate legislative activities, which made fellow lawmakers click their tongues in amazement. (두 사람의 ‘케미’는 더할 나위 없었다. 이 수석부의장은 13대 국회 5·18광주민주화운동 진상조사 청문회에서 계엄군의 발포 책임 소재를 규명하기 위해 전두환씨 등 증인들을 집요하게 추궁하는 모습과 국회 노동위원회에서 활약 등이 조명받으며 ‘스타 초선’으로 이름을 날렸다. 그 뒤엔 ‘참모’ 유시민이 있었다. 생전 이 수석부의장은 동료 의원들이 혀를 내두를 정도로 열정적이었던 의정 활동의 ‘원흉’이 유 전 이사장이었다고 장난스레 말하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two, who were key figures in the launch of the Participatory Government, worked together as Prime Minister and Minister of Health and Welfare. The Senior Vice Chairman was a strategist who designed half of the Participatory Government's state affairs as the 'powerful Prime Minister,' and former Chairman Yoo, a second-term ruling party lawmaker and Minister of Health and Welfare, was the central axis symbolizing the reformist identity of the Participatory Government. Ahead of the 17th presidential election in 2007, they both ran in the ruling party's primary and competed against each other. (참여정부 출범의 주역이었던 두 사람은 국무총리와 보건복지부 장관으로 호흡을 맞췄다. 이 수석부의장은 ‘실세 총리’로서 참여정부 국정 절반을 설계한 전략가였고, 여당 재선의원이자 보건복지부 장관이었던 유 전 이사장은 참여정부의 개혁적 정체성을 상징하는 중심축이었다. 2007년 17대 대선을 앞두고는 여당 대선 경선에 나란히 출마해 경쟁을 벌이기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even after former Chairman Yoo retired from politics in 2013, their partnership continued. In 2018, the Senior Vice Chairman, who was then the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, nominated former Chairman Yoo as his successor to the chairmanship of the Roh Moo-hyun Foundation, which he was holding. It is said that former Chairman Yoo initially declined, but after persistent persuasion from the Senior Vice Chairman, he eventually accepted the chairmanship. (유 전 이사장이 2013년 정계를 은퇴한 뒤에도, 두 사람의 동반자 관계는 지속했다. 2018년 더불어민주당 대표였던 이 수석부의장은 자신이 맡고 있던 노무현재단 이사장 후임으로 유 전 이사장을 지명했다. 유 전 이사장은 처음에는 고사했으나, 이 수석부의장의 끈질긴 설득 끝에 결국 이사장직을 수락한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To former Chairman Yoo, the Senior Vice Chairman was a life companion and a teacher. In the Senior Vice Chairman's autobiography published in 2007, former Chairman Yoo evaluated him, saying, "To me, he was a senior in the student movement and the democratization movement. I learned the principles of real politics and legislation from him. He gave me precious guidance at every important juncture in my life, and he is still a teacher in my life." That year marked the 28th year of their connection. Even until this day, 19 years later, their strong bond remained unchanged. (유 전 이사장에게 이 수석부의장은 인생의 동반자이자 스승이었다. 2007년 발간된 이 수석부의장의 자서전에서 유 전 이사장은 “나에게 그는 학생운동과 민주화운동의 선배였다. 나는 그에게서 현실 정치와 입법의 원리를 배웠다. 그는 내 삶의 중요한 고비마다 귀한 가르침을 주었고, 지금도 주고 있는 인생의 스승”이라고 이 수석부의장을 평가했다. 그해는 이 수석부의장과 인연을 맺은 지 28년째 되는 해였다. 이로부터 19년이 지난 이날까지도 두 사람의 끈끈한 관계는 변함이 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241922.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/954/862/imgdb/child/2026/0127/17695046973608_20260127503238.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's 'End of Transfer Tax Surcharge Exemption' Remarks Draw Backlash from People Power Party, Calling It "Revival of Punitive Taxation" (이 대통령 ‘양도세 중과 면제 종료’ 발언에 국힘 “징벌적 과세 부활” 반발)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241933.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee's 'End of Transfer Tax Surcharge Exemption' Remarks Draw Backlash from People Power Party, Calling It "Revival of Punitive Taxation" (이 대통령 ‘양도세 중과 면제 종료’ 발언에 국힘 “징벌적 과세 부활” 반발)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/523/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503402.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 오피스텔 가격이 12개월 연속 상승 중인 것으로 나타난 27일 서울 강남구 오피스텔 밀집지역의 한 부동산중개업소에 오피스텔 매물 시세표가 붙어있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party has claimed that President Lee Jae-myung's remarks regarding ending the suspension of the transfer income tax surcharge amount to "essentially a revival of punitive taxation." (국민의힘이 이재명 대통령의 양도소득세 중과 유예 종료 발언과 관련해 “사실상 징벌적 과세의 부활”이라고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choi Soo-jin, the PPP's chief floor spokesperson, met with reporters at the National Assembly on the 27th and said, "The biggest problem with our country's (real estate policies) is that they only use demand-suppression measures," adding, "Supply-side policies (for real estate) need to be introduced." She continued, "If you suppress demand, housing prices shouldn't rise, but Seoul housing prices are rising. While housing prices in regional areas are falling, prices in the Seoul and Gyeonggi areas are rising due to a balloon effect," and questioned, "In this situation, what will happen if you impose a tax surcharge?" (최수진 국민의힘 원내수석대변인은 27일 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “우리나라 (부동산 정책의) 가장 큰 문제점은 수요 억제책만 쓰는 것”이라며 “(부동산) 공급 정책이 나와야 한다”고 말했다. 이어 “수요를 억제하면 집값이 오르지 않아야 하는데, 서울 집값은 오른다. 지방 집값은 떨어지는 대신 서울·경기 지역 집값이 풍선효과로 오르고 있는 것”이라며 “(이런 상황에서) 세금을 중과하면 어떻게 되겠느냐”고 되물었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She stated, "If the transfer tax surcharge is revived, up to 82.5% of capital gains would have to be paid as tax. Multi-homeowners with blocked exit strategies are more likely to turn to gifting or long-term holding rather than putting their properties on the market." She argued, "Then, ironically, due to the 'property lock-in phenomenon,' transactions would dry up and prices would rise, and the pain from the resulting transaction cliff would inevitably be passed on entirely to actual demanders." This is the argument that multi-homeowners holding properties in areas like the three Gangnam districts, who are not in immediate need of cash, could resort to 'holding out, gifting, or long-term holding.' (그는 “양도세 중과가 부활하면 시세차익의 최대 82.5%를 세금으로 내야 한다. 퇴로가 막힌 다주택자들은 매물을 내놓기보다 증여나 장기 보유로 돌아설 가능성이 크다”며 “그러면 오히려 ‘매물 잠김 현상’으로 거래는 끊기고 가격은 상승해 거래 절벽 발생에 따른 고통은 고스란히 실수요자들에게 돌아갈 수밖에 없다”고 말했다. 당장 현금이 급하지 않은 강남 3구 등의 매물을 쥔 다주택자들이 ‘버티기·증여·장기 보유’로 돌아설 수 있다는 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Floor Spokesperson Choi also said, "It must be acknowledged that multi-homeowners are a major supply source for the private rental market," and added, "The punitive taxation imposed on them is passed on to tenants in the form of increased jeonse and monthly rent prices." (최 원내수석대변인은 “다주택자는 민간 임대차 시장의 주요 공급원임을 인정해야 한다”며 “이들에게 가해지는 징벌적 과세는 전·월세 가격 인상이라는 형태로 세입자에게 전가된다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP's Special Committee for Normalizing Real Estate Policy is discussing real estate supply measures. Yoo Sang-beom, the party's senior deputy floor leader for operations, said at the party's intra-party countermeasures meeting that day, "The most urgent issue for the real estate market is supply measures, not SNS political pressure." He asked, "Where did the Seoul apartment supply measures that the Lee Jae-myung administration said it would announce within 2025 go? Without substantial supply measures like revitalizing reconstruction, easing floor area ratios, and expanding supply, the real estate instability triggered by the Lee Jae-myung government can never be resolved." He continued, "The government cannot beat the market. While the market can be suppressed by the government in the short term, in the end, flawed policies only bring about adverse effects; this is a basic principle of economics." He strongly urged, "Instead of tinkering with taxes first, they must immediately present fundamental supply measures." (국민의힘 부동산정책 정상화특별위원회는 부동산 공급 방안을 논의하고 있다. 유상범 원내운영수석부대표는 이날 당 원내대책회의에서 “부동산 시장의 가장 시급한 것은 공급 대책이지 에스엔에스(SNS) 정치 압박이 아니”라며 “이재명 정권이 2025년 이내에 발표하겠다던 서울 아파트 공급 대책은 대체 어디로 갔나? 재건축 활성화, 용적률 완화 등 실질적인 공급 대책, 공급 확대 없이는 이재명 정부가 촉발한 부동산 불안을 결코 잡을 수 없다”고 말했다. 그는 이어 “정부는 시장을 이길 수 없다. 시장은 단기적으로는 정부에 짓눌릴 순 있어도 결국 잘못된 정책은 역효과만 불러오는 것이 경제의 기본 원리”라며 “세금부터 만지작거릴 것이 아니라 근본적인 공급 대책부터 즉각 내놓을 것을 강력히 촉구한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241933.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/523/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503402.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's Tariff Hike Announcement... "Established a Hotline with Vance" Kim Min-seok 'Embarrassed' (트럼프 관세인상 발표에…“밴스와 핫라인 구축” 김민석 ‘당황’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241955.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Trump's Tariff Hike Announcement... "Established a Hotline with Vance" Kim Min-seok 'Embarrassed' (트럼프 관세인상 발표에…“밴스와 핫라인 구축” 김민석 ‘당황’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503569.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김민석 국무총리가 23일(현지시각) 미국 워싱턴 디시(D.C) 백악관에서 제이디(JD) 밴스 부통령과 면담에 앞서 기념 촬영을 하고 있다. 총리실 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As U.S. President Donald Trump announced on the 26th (local time) his intention to raise tariffs on items like Korean automobiles from 15% to 25%, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who recently returned from a '2-night, 5-day' visit to the U.S. and stated that "the biggest purpose was to meet U.S. Vice President JD Vance and establish a 'hotline'," was left red-faced. This is because, despite establishing a 'direct line' with the number two figure in the U.S. administration, he received no prior hint whatsoever regarding President Trump's notification. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 26일(현지시각) 한국 자동차 품목 등 관세를 15%에서 25%로 인상하겠다고 밝히면서 최근 ‘2박5일’ 일정으로 미국을 방문하고 돌아온 뒤 “제이디 밴스 미국 부통령을 만나서 ‘핫라인’을 구축하는 게 제일 큰 목적이었다”고 말한 김민석 국무총리가 머쓱해졌다. 미국 행정부의 2인자와 ‘직통 라인’을 만들고도 사전에 트럼프 대통령의 통보와 관련한 어떤 언질도 받지 못했기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a pre-recorded interview with Sampo TV that day, when asked about the purpose of his U.S. visit, Prime Minister Kim said, "The main purpose was to establish a relationship with Vice President Vance and meet other necessary people," adding, "That's why we scheduled two days (for the local stay)." He continued, "After the Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations, there have been some delays in actually implementing the agreed-upon contents like the joint fact sheet, so we needed to take care of those," and "Recently, there have been signs of a new phase forming, like the semiconductor issue." He then boasted, "I also found out this time that since liberation, aside from two instances where the Prime Minister went to sign instead of the President, two instances of going to offer condolences, and one instance of visiting the White House coincidentally after a UN General Assembly, I am the first to visit for official duties." He repeatedly expressed satisfaction, saying, "The Ministry of Foreign Affairs, including Ambassador to the U.S. Kang Kyung-hwa and the Vice Foreign Minister, also went together, and they said we completely wrote a new piece of history." (김 총리는 이날 사전녹화된 삼프로 티브이 인터뷰에서 방미 목적 관련 질문에 “밴스 부통령과 관계를 설정하고 그 외 필요한 사람들을 만나는 게 큰 목적”이라며 “그렇기 때문에 (현지 체류 일정) 이틀을 잡은 것”이라고 말했다. 이어 “저희가 한-미 관세협상 이후에 조인트 팩트시트 등 타결된 내용을 실제로 이행하는 데 좀 지연된 것들이 있어서 그것들을 이제 챙겨야 했다”며 “최근에는 반도체 문제 등 새로운 국면이 형성될 조짐이 있지 않았냐”고 말했다. 그러면서 “저도 이번에 알았는데 해방 이후에 대통령 서명을 총리가 대신 가서 서명한 경우 두 번, 조문하러 간 경우 두 번, 유엔 총회 갔다가 우연히 백악관 방문한 경우 한 번 빼고는 고유 업무로 가서 방문한 건 제가 처음이라고 한다”고 자랑스러워 했다. 그러면서 “외교부에서 강경화 주미대사, 외교부 차관도 같이 가셨는데, 완전히 새로운 역사를 하나 썼다고 하시더라”고 거듭 만족감을 드러냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From his departure on the 22nd to his return to Incheon Airport on the 26th, Prime Minister Kim met with Vice President Vance and U.S. House of Representatives members locally in the U.S. Prime Minister Kim said, "(With Vice President Vance, etc.) we freely discussed various things. First, I suggested it would be good if we established a relationship (where we could contact each other anytime), and on the spot, he gave me his office's direct line number," and "Among the follow-up measures to the tariff negotiations, we are most interested in nuclear power, nuclear submarines, and the shipbuilding industry, but progress isn't going as well as expected, so I suggested it would be good if (Vice President Vance and I) paid a bit more attention to them." He added, "I received a more positive response than expected," and "I suggested we set schedules like one month, or three months, six months, and proceed with some plans." (김 총리는 22일 출국해 26일 인천공항으로 귀국하기까지 미국 현지에서 밴스 부통령과 미 하원 의원들을 만났다. 김 총리는 “(밴스 부통령 등과) 자유롭게 여러 가지 이야기를 했는데, 먼저 우리가 (언제라도 연락 가능한) 관계 설정을 하는 것이 좋겠다고 했고, 즉석에서 부통령 사무실 자기 직통 번호를 알려줬다”며 “관세 협상 후속 조처 가운데 우리는 원자력, 핵잠수함, 조선 산업에 제일 관심이 있는데 진도가 생각보다 잘 안 나가니 (밴스 부통령과 제가) 좀 챙겼으면 좋겠다고 했다”고 말했다. 이어 “생각 이상으로 적극적인 답을 들었다”며 “한 달, 혹은 석 달, 여섯 달 이런 식으로 일정을 잡아서 좀 계획을 진행해 갔으면 좋겠다고 했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, President Trump stated on social media Truth Social on the 26th (local time), "The Korean legislature is not implementing the agreement with the U.S.," and announced he would raise reciprocal tariffs on Korean products to 25%. The Presidential Office spokesperson's office said in a press release that morning, "There has been no official notification or explanation of details from the U.S. government yet." (그러나 트럼프 대통령은 26일(현지시각) 소셜미디어 트루스소셜에 “한국 입법부는 미국과 협정을 이행하지 않고 있다”며 한국산 제품에 대한 상호관세를 25%로 인상하겠다고 밝혔다. 청와대 대변인실은 이날 오전 언론공지를 통해 “미국 정부로부터 공식적인 통보나 세부 내용에 대한 설명은 아직 없는 상황”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers belonging to the People Power Party's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee issued a statement that day, sarcastically remarking, "Prime Minister Kim Min-seok announced as if all conversations and explanations during his U.S. visit went perfectly well and even praised himself for establishing a hotline with Vice President Vance," and "Did that hotline the Prime Minister boasted about become useless in just one day? Did Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, while having lunch with U.S. federal House members and holding talks with Vice President Vance in the U.S., not sense the atmosphere of crisis between Korea and the U.S. at all?" (국민의힘 외교통일위원회 소속 의원들은 이날 성명을 내어 “김민석 총리는 방미 당시 모든 대화와 설명이 다 잘 된 것처럼 발표하면서 밴스 부통령과의 핫라인까지 구축했다고 자화자찬했다”며 “총리가 자랑한 그 핫라인이 단 하루 만에 먹통이 된 것인가? 김민석 총리는 미국에서 연방 하원의원들과 오찬을 하고 밴스 부통령과 회담을 하면서도 한미 간 위기의 분위기는 전혀 감지하지 못한 것이냐”고 비꼬았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241955.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503569.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Breaking News] President Lee Visits Funeral of Former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan...Posthumous Bestowal of Mugunghwa Medal Planned ([속보] 이 대통령, 이해찬 전 총리 조문…무궁화장 추서 예정)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241957.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[Breaking News] President Lee Visits Funeral of Former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan...Posthumous Bestowal of Mugunghwa Medal Planned ([속보] 이 대통령, 이해찬 전 총리 조문…무궁화장 추서 예정)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/436/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503577.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장에 마련된 고 이해찬 전 민주평화통일자문회의 수석부의장의 빈소를 찾아 유가족을 위로하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung visited the funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital on the afternoon of the 27th, where the mortuary of the late Lee Hae-chan, former Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council, was set up. (이재명 대통령은 27일 오후 고 이해찬 전 민주평화통일자문회의 수석부의장의 빈소가 차려진 서울대병원 장례식장을 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee plans to posthumously bestow the Mugunghwa Medal, the highest grade of the Order of Civil Merit, upon the former Senior Vice Chairman. The Mugunghwa Medal is awarded to individuals who have made outstanding contributions to national and social development. (이 대통령은 이 전 수석부의장에게 최고 등급인 국민훈장 무궁화장을 추서할 예정이다. 무궁화장은 국가와 사회 발전에 현저한 공로가 있는 인물에게 수여된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241957.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/436/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503577.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Government: "China Moves West Sea Structure... A Change Beneficial to South Korea-China Relations" (정부 “중국 서해구조물 이동…한중관계 도움되는 변화”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241958.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Government: "China Moves West Sea Structure... A Change Beneficial to South Korea-China Relations" (정부 “중국 서해구조물 이동…한중관계 도움되는 변화”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/408/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503579.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;중국이 서해 한중 잠정조치수역에 설치한 구조물 선란2호에서 관리인들이 작업하고 있다. 민주당 이병진 의원실 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;China began work at 8 PM on the 27th to move a management facility, among the West Sea structures, outside the South Korea-China Provisional Measures Zone. This is China's actual implementation of matters discussed during the summit meeting between President Lee Jae-myung and Chinese President Xi Jinping on the 5th. (중국이 서해 구조물 가운데 관리시설을 한중 잠정조치수역 밖으로 이동시키는 작업을 27일 오후 8시부터 시작한다. 지난 5일 이재명 대통령과 시진핑 중국 국가주석의 정상회담에서 논의한 내용을 중국이 실제로 이행한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a regular briefing on the 27th, Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Guo Zhaokun stated, "Chinese enterprises are currently conducting work related to moving the management platform." However, Spokesperson Guo drew a line, clarifying that the structure's movement is not a measure due to diplomatic reasons or South Korean demands, but rather "an autonomous adjustment by the enterprise based on its own operational and development needs," and that "the position on fishery and aquaculture facility issues in the South China Sea and the Yellow Sea (West Sea) remains unchanged." Spokesperson Guo said, "As maritime neighbors, China and South Korea have maintained close and continuous communication on maritime issues, appropriately managed and controlled differences, and promoted mutually beneficial cooperation." This indicates that while considering the potential ripple effects of this relocation measure on issues like the South China Sea, there is also a shared recognition of the need for South Korea and China to manage conflicts surrounding the West Sea structures. (  궈자쿤 중국 외교부 대변인은 27일 정례 브리핑에서 “중국 기업이 현재 관리 플랫폼 이동과 관련한 작업을 진행하고 있다”고 밝혔다. 궈 대변인은 다만 구조물 이동이 외교적 이유나 한국 요구에 따른 조치가 아닌 “기업이 자체적 경영·발전 필요에 따라 자율적으로 조정하는 것”이라고 선을 긋고 “남중국해·황해(서해) 어업 및 양식 시설 문제에 대한 입장은 변함이 없다”고 했다. 궈 대변인은 “중국과 한국은 해상 이웃 국가로서 양국은 해양 문제에 대해 지속적으로 긴밀한 소통을 유지했고 이견을 적절히 관리·통제하며 상호 이익이 되는 협력을 촉진해 왔다”고 말했다. 이번 이동조치가 남중국해 문제 등에 미칠 여파 등을 고려하면서도, 한중이 서해 구조물 등을 둘러싼 갈등 관리 필요성에 공감대가 있음을 밝힌 것이다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kang Young-shin, Director-General of the Northeast Asian Affairs Bureau at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, stated, "This measure is a change beneficial to the development of South Korea-China relations," and "Our government, maintaining its stance of opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measures Zone, has consistently engaged in consultations with China, and therefore evaluates this measure as meaningful progress." She added, "Our government has maintained constructive consultations with the Chinese side and, based on our consistently held position, plans to continue seeking further progress." (  강영신 외교부 동북아 국장은 “이번 조치는 한중관계 발전에 도움이 되는 변화”라며 “우리 정부는 잠정조치 수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치 반대 입장 하에 그동안 대중국 협의를 이어온 만큼 이번 조치를 의미있는 진전으로 평가한다”고 밝혔다. 또 “그간 우리 정부는 중국 측과 건설적 협의를 이어왔고 일관되게 견지해 온 우리 입장을 바탕으로 앞으로도 계속 진전을 모색해 나갈 예정”이라고 했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a notice issued by the China Maritime Safety Administration on the evening of the 26th, work to move the 'Atlantic Amsterdam Platform,' a management facility among the West Sea structures, will be conducted from 19:00 on the 27th (20:00 Korean time) until 24:00 on the 31st. The management facility is scheduled to be moved from its current location at 35°11'26" N, 122°14'51" E to 37°27'69" N, 122°14'38" E. A South Korean official said, "We have confirmed that the management facility is moving outside the Provisional Measures Zone." (  중국 해사국이 26일 저녁 발표한 통지를 보면 서해 구조물 가운데 관리시설인 ‘아틀랜틱 암스테르담 플랫폼’을 이동시키는 작업을 27일 19시(한국시각 20시)부터 31일 24시까지 진행한다. 관리시설이 위치해 있던 북위 35.11.26, 동경 122.14.51 지점에서 북위 37.27.69, 동경 122.14.38로 이동할 예정이다. 우리 당국자는 “관리시설이 잠정조치 수역 밖으로 나가는 것은 확인했다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since early last year, when structures China unilaterally installed within the South Korea-China Provisional Measures Zone began receiving full attention, the South Korean government has raised the issue with the Chinese side and continued working-level consultations. President Lee Jae-myung also raised this issue during his two summit meetings with President Xi Jinping. Following the summit meeting on the 5th, President Lee told reporters, "(Regarding the structures installed by China) they say it's mainly aquaculture facilities, and there is a facility to manage them," and "It seems China has decided to move this management facility because it became controversial." (  지난해 초 중국이 한중 잠정조치 수역에 무단으로 설치한 구조물이 본격적으로 주목을 받으면서, 한국 정부는 중국 측에 문제를 제기하고 실무 협의를 계속해왔다. 이재명 대통령이 시진핑 주석과의 두 차례 정상회담에서도 이 문제를 제기했다. 이 대통령은 지난 5일 정상회담 뒤 기자간담회에서 “(중국이 설치한 구조물이) 주로 양식장 시설이라고 하고, 이것을 관리하는 시설이 있다고 한다”며 “중국 측에서 논란이 되니 이 관리 시설을 옮기기로 한 것 같다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;China has placed what it claims are aquaculture facilities, the steel-structure Xunlan No. 1 and No. 2, and what it claims is a management facility, a seabed-fixed structure, within the West Sea Provisional Measures Zone. All three structures are located within the Provisional Measures Zone where the Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ) of South Korea and China overlap, and are artificial maritime facilities built by China without consultation with South Korea. Particularly, the fixed management facility has been pointed out as having high potential for military use, making it a facility South Korea viewed more sensitively, and work to move this one first is now proceeding. Following progress made in discussing this issue during the South Korea-China summit, the foreign ministries of both countries have continued working-level negotiations. (  중국은 서해 잠정조치수역 내에 양식시설이라고 주장하는 철제 구조물 형태의 선란 1·2호와 관리시설이라고 주장하는 해저 고정식 구조물을 두고 있다. 구조물 3기 모두 한국과 중국의 배타적경제수역(EEZ)이 겹치는 잠정조치수역에 위치하고 있고, 한국과 협의 없이 중국이 세운 인공 해상 시설이다. 특히 고정식 관리시설은 군사적 전용이 높다는 지적이 있어 한국이 더 민감하게 여긴 시설인데 우선 이것을 이동시키는 작업이 진행되는 것이다. 한중 정상회담에서 이 문제 논의에서 진전이 만들어진 뒤 양국 외교부는 실무협상을 계속해 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Ministry of Foreign Affairs official explained, "After the West Sea structures first became an issue between South Korea and China in April last year, there were many suspicions raised that the management platform, among the three facilities, could be converted for various uses," and "A natural consensus formed during South Korea-China consultations that it would be good to first remove the management platform as a priority." (  외교부 당국자는 “지난해 4월 처음 서해구조물이 한중간 이슈가 된 뒤 세 가지 시설물들 가운데 관리 플랫폼에 대해 여러 시설로 전용될 수 있다는 의혹이 많이 제기됐다”며 “한중 협의 하에서 우선적으로 관리플랫폼을 먼저 빼는 것이 좋지 않겠느냐는 부분에 자연스럽게 공감대가 형성됐다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;China's current measure signifies taking the first step toward resolving the sensitive pending issue of the West Sea structures through diplomatic negotiation. However, the issue of the remaining two facilities, Xunlan No. 1 and No. 2, which China claims are salmon aquaculture facilities, remains. Regarding whether China will also move these two facilities outside the Provisional Zone, a Foreign Ministry official only responded, "Based on the position our government has maintained, we will continue to achieve progress going forward." (  중국의 이번 조치는 한중 관계의 민감한 현안인 서해 구조물 문제에 대해 외교 협상을 통해 해결의 첫발을 내디뎠다는 의미가 있다. 하지만, 중국이 연어 양식시설이라고 주장하는 나머지 두 개 시설인 선란 1호와 2호의 문제는 남아 있다. 중국이 이 두 시설도 잠정수역 밖으로 이동시킬지에 대해 외교부 당국자는 “우리 정부가 견지해온 입장을 바탕으로 앞으로도 진전을 이뤄나가겠다”고만 답했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the Chinese Foreign Ministry's emphasis on it being an 'autonomous measure by the enterprise,' the official said, "The fact that the Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson announced it is a clear fact," and "The movement of the management platform is not unrelated to the trend of South Korea-China relations being restored, so under this trend, the government will engage in constructive consultations with China to achieve meaningful progress." (  중국 외교부가 ‘기업의 자율적 조치’라고 강조한 데 대해 이 당국자는 “중국 외교부 대변인이 발표했다는 것은 명확한 팩트”라며 “ 관리 플랫폼 이동은 한중관계가 복원되고 있는 흐름과 무관하지 않기 때문에 이 흐름 하에서 정부는 의미 있는 진전을 이뤄나가기 위해 중국과 건설적 협의를 해 나가겠다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241958.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/408/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503579.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party's Self-Serving Political Offensive... Democratic Party Urges "Cooperate on Special Act Processing" (국힘 아전인수 정치공세…민주당 “특별법 처리 협조해야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241963.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;People Power Party's Self-Serving Political Offensive... Democratic Party Urges "Cooperate on Special Act Processing" (국힘 아전인수 정치공세…민주당 “특별법 처리 협조해야”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/727/402/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503600.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;임이자 재정경제기획위원회 위원장이 27일 국회 재경위원장실에서 구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관을 만나 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 관세 인상 언급에 따른 대응을 논의하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the People Power Party launched a self-serving offensive on the 27th, blaming the government and ruling party for "insisting only on processing a special act for U.S. investment instead of parliamentary ratification consent" following U.S. President Donald Trump's surprise announcement of planned tariff hikes, the Democratic Party of Korea countered, urging them not to politicize an issue involving national interest with "far-fetched arguments." (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 기습적인 관세 인상 예고를 두고 국민의힘이 27일 ‘비준 동의 대신 대미투자 특별법 처리만 고집한 정부·여당 탓’이라며 아전인수식 공세를 펼치자, 더불어민주당이 ‘억지 주장으로 국익이 걸린 문제를 정쟁화하지 말라’고 받아쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Song Eon-seok, the People Power Party's floor leader, argued at the party's intra-party countermeasures meeting that day, "Regarding the Korea-U.S. tariff agreement, our party has repeatedly emphasized that parliamentary ratification consent should come first, but the government and ruling party said parliamentary ratification was not needed." He claimed, "The responsibility for all situations lies with President Lee Jae-myung and the government, who concluded a major trade agreement requiring parliamentary ratification and have ignored the ratification process." Lim Lee-ja, the chairwoman of the Planning and Finance Committee, the standing committee in charge of legislation related to U.S. investment and a member of the same party, argued that parliamentary discussion had stalled because of "the Democratic Party, which insists on forcibly processing only the special act while avoiding the verification process." (  송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 이날 당 원내대책회의에서 “한-미 관세합의에 관해 우리 당에서는 국회 비준 동의가 우선이라는 점을 누차 강조했지만, 정부·여당에서는 국회 비준 동의가 없다고 했다”며 “모든 사태에 대한 책임은 국회 비준이 필요한 중대 통상 합의를 체결하고, 비준 절차를 외면해왔던 이재명 대통령과 정부에 있다”고 주장했다. 같은 당 소속으로 대미투자 관련 입법의 소관 상임위원회인 재정경제기획위원회 임이자 위원장은 “(대미투자) 검증 절차를 회피한 채 특별법 처리만 강행하겠다는 민주당” 때문에 국회 논의가 멈춰 섰다는 주장을 폈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party reaffirmed its existing position that the Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) from the Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations is not subject to parliamentary ratification and urged the People Power Party to immediately cooperate in processing the special act. Floor spokesperson Kim Hyun-jung refuted the People Power Party's claim that this situation was due to 'ignoring the ratification process,' stating, "President Trump also said it was not 'ratified' but 'enacted' into law." Democratic Party members of the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee also told the People Power Party, "While the U.S. is not ratifying it, if only our country ratifies it and elevates it to a binding treaty, it is like tying our own feet," and urged them to "stop insisting on ratification and cooperate for the swift passage of the special act." (  민주당은 한-미 관세협상에 따른 양해각서(MOU)는 국회 비준 대상이 아니라는 기존 입장을 재확인하면서 국민의힘에 특별법 처리에 즉각 협조할 것을 촉구했다. 김현정 원내대변인은 “트럼프 대통령도 ‘비준’이 아니라 ‘입법화’(enact)가 안 됐다고 했다”며 이번 사태가 ‘비준 절차 외면’ 때문이라는 국민의힘 주장을 일축했다. 국회 외교통일위원회 민주당 의원들도 국민의힘을 향해 “미국은 비준하지 않는데 우리나라만 비준해 구속력 높은 조약으로 격상시키는 건 우리 발을 스스로 묶는 것과 마찬가지”라며 “비준 고집을 중단하고 특별법 신속 통과에 협조하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once parliamentary discussions begin, it appears the People Power Party will not solely insist on the 'ratification consent' argument. Choi Eun-seok, the People Power Party's chief floor spokesperson, said, "Parliamentary ratification is necessary," but added, "Whether to do it through ratification or a special act will be discussed again after hearing the government and ruling party's position." (  국회 논의가 시작되면 국민의힘도 ‘비준 동의’ 주장만 고집하지는 않을 것으로 보인다. 최은석 국민의힘 원내수석대변인은 “국회 비준이 필요하다”면서도 “비준할지 특별법으로 할지는 정부·여당 입장을 듣고 다시 논의할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol and Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 고한솔 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241963.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/727/402/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503600.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Abnormal Resource Allocation to Real Estate Must Be Corrected" (이 대통령 “부동산에 비정상적 자원 배분, 반드시 바로잡아야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241965.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Abnormal Resource Allocation to Real Estate Must Be Corrected" (이 대통령 “부동산에 비정상적 자원 배분, 반드시 바로잡아야”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/687/469/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503605.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 27일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다.  연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 27th, "We must definitely correct the distortion in our society's resource allocation, which is abnormally concentrated in real estate." This is his fourth real estate-related remark in the week following his New Year's press conference on the 21st. ▶Related article page 5 (이재명 대통령이 27일 “부동산에 비정상적으로 집중된 우리 사회의 자원 배분 왜곡을 반드시 바로잡아야 한다”고 말했다. 지난 21일 신년 기자회견 이후 일주일 새 네번째 나온 부동산 관련 발언이다. ▶관련기사 5면)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his opening remarks at the Cabinet meeting held at the Blue House this day, President Lee stated, "The excessive expansion of unproductive real estate inevitably fuels bubbles," and added, "We must definitely take the painful example of a neighboring country that experienced great chaos, losing 20 to 30 years due to its failure to properly control real estate bubbles, as a lesson." This appears to be a reference to Japan's case, where growth momentum was undermined by its failure to properly control real estate bubbles. (  이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 열린 국무회의 머리발언에서 “비생산적인 부동산의 과도한 팽창은 필연적으로 거품을 키우게 된다”며 “부동산 거품을 제대로 통제하지 못해서 잃어버린 20년, 30년을 경험하며 큰 혼란을 겪은 가까운 이웃 나라의 뼈아픈 사례를 반드시 반면교사 삼아야 된다”고 말했다. 부동산 거품을 제대로 통제하지 못해 성장 동력이 훼손된 일본 사례를 거론한 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "To avoid difficulties, we must consistently and stably promote effective policies based on firm will," and "we must also actively pursue measures the market desires." This indicates an intent to accelerate supply-side measures to stabilize real estate prices. (  이 대통령은 “어려움을 피하려면 굳은 의지를 바탕으로 실효적인 정책을 지속적으로, 안정적으로 추진해 나가야 한다”며 “시장이 원하는 적극적인 대책도 추진해 나가야 한다”고 밝혔다. 부동산 가격을 잡기 위한 공급 대책에도 속도를 내겠다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also reaffirmed his stance on maintaining the taxation principle for multiple homeowners. He said, "Wasn't it clearly scheduled that the heavy taxation on capital gains for multiple homeowners, extended last year, would end on May 9th this year?" and continued, "Yet, there are unfair and mistaken expectations that it will naturally be extended, or even attacks on the policy as if a new heavy tax on real estate capital gains is being imposed." He added, "We must not be swayed by such things. By thoroughly supplementing the associated issues, even if the decision-making process involves intense debate, the policy must be implemented to create a predictable and rational society." (  이 대통령은 다주택자에 대한 과세 원칙을 유지하겠다는 입장도 재확인했다. “다주택자 양도세 중과는 지난해 연장할 때 올해 5월9일이 끝이라고 명백히 예정된 것 아니냐”며 “그런데 당연히 연장하겠지, 그런 부당한 기대와 잘못된 기대를 하거나, 마치 새롭게 부동산 양도세를 중과하는 것처럼 정책에 대한 공격도 있다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “이런 데 휘둘리면 안 되고, 그에 따른 문제점을 철저히 보완해서 결정 과정은 치열하게 논쟁하더라도 정책은 집행해야, 예측 가능한 합리적인 사회가 된다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's daily mentions of the real estate issue appear to stem from his judgment that if real estate price instability is not addressed, it could go beyond housing dissatisfaction to damage the nation's growth potential and seriously impact the overall national economy. Although President Lee said at his New Year's press conference that he was "not deeply considering real estate policy through taxation," he announced the resumption of heavy capital gains taxation for multiple homeowners on his social media on the 23rd and hinted at plans to increase property holding taxes on the 25th, escalating the level of his real estate-related remarks. (  이 대통령이 연일 부동산 문제를 언급하는 것은 부동산 가격 불안을 잡지 못하면 주거 불만을 넘어 국가의 성장잠재력을 훼손하고 국민경제 전반에 심각한 타격을 줄 수 있다고 판단하기 때문으로 보인다. 이 대통령은 신년 기자회견에서 “세제를 통한 부동산 정책을 깊이 고려하지 않고 있다”고 했지만, 23일 자신의 소셜미디어에 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 재개 방침을 밝혔고, 25일에는 보유세 인상 방침을 시사하는 등 부동산 관련 발언 수위를 높이고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Seo Young-ji, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241965.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/687/469/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503605.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Don't Just Wait for National Assembly Legislation, Take Emergency Measures Now"... Why Did President Lee Publicly Reprimand the NTS Commissioner? (“국회 입법 기다리지만 말고 당장 비상조치 해라”…이 대통령, 국세청장 공개 질책, 왜?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241966.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Don't Just Wait for National Assembly Legislation, Take Emergency Measures Now"... Why Did President Lee Publicly Reprimand the NTS Commissioner? (“국회 입법 기다리지만 말고 당장 비상조치 해라”…이 대통령, 국세청장 공개 질책, 왜?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/413/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503607.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 27일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다.  연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a discussion on measures to collect delinquent 'non-national tax revenue', President Lee Jae-myung said to National Tax Service (NTS) Commissioner Im Kwang-hyun, "Who knows when the National Assembly will pass the legislation. Are you going to wait until then?" He publicly reprimanded Commissioner Im for merely repeating that 'the matter requires legal amendment' instead of proactively seeking solutions. (이재명 대통령이 체납된 ‘국세 외 수입’ 징수 방안을 논의하는 과정에서 임광현 국세청장을 향해 “어느 세월에 국회 입법이 될지 모른다. 그때까지 기다리실 거냐”고 말했다. 적극적으로 해법을 찾아내기보다 ‘법 개정이 필요한 사안’이라는 말만 반복하는 임 청장을 공개 질책한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a Cabinet meeting held at the Blue House on the 27th, President Lee raised the issue to Commissioner Im, saying, "Habitual delinquents should not benefit. We must make life difficult for those who dodge taxes," and added, "Currently, delinquent non-national tax revenue is even less managed." (  이 대통령은 27일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 임 청장에게 “상습 체납자가 혜택을 보면 안 된다. 세금 떼먹고 못 살게 해야 한다”며 “지금 체납된 국세 외 수입은 더 관리가 안 되고 있다”고 문제를 제기했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He pointed out that while non-national tax revenue (284 trillion won), composed of unfair trade surcharges, environmental regulation violation fees, national property usage fees, etc., is nearly as large as national tax revenue (337 trillion won, as of end-2024), the problem of poorly collected delinquent taxes (25 trillion won) needs improvement because various ministries manage and collect taxes separately. (  불공정거래 과징금, 환경규제위반 부담금, 국유재산 사용료 등으로 구성된 국세 외 수입(284조원)이 국세 수입(337조원, 2024년 말 기준)에 버금갈 만큼 큰 상황이지만, 여러 부처가 세금을 각각 관리·징수하는 바람에 체납 세금(25조원)이 잘 걷히지 않는 문제를 개선해야 한다고 지적한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Commissioner Im said, "The National Tax Service can only collect national taxes," and "To entrust the collection of delinquent amounts, an amendment to the National Claims Management Act is necessary." President Lee suggested an 'alternative', saying, "I fully understand, but the National Assembly's legislative speed is too slow," and "We can't keep waiting, so before that, we could recruit and dispatch personnel under each ministry's name or conduct joint management, couldn't we?" However, Commissioner Im said, "It seems legislation would be faster," to which President Lee responded with frustration, "Oh, really..." He then raised his voice, saying, "The National Assembly is too slow now, who knows when (the legislation) will happen. Are you going to wait until then?" and urged, "Start now. Given the situation, don't delay and let's take some emergency measures." (  임 청장은 이에 “국세청은 국세만 징수할 수 있다”며 “체납에 대해 위탁징수를 하려면 국가채권관리법 개정이 필요하다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 “충분히 이해하겠지만 국회의 입법 속도가 너무 느리다”며 “계속 기다릴 수는 없으니 그 전이라도 각 부처 명의로 (인력을) 뽑아서 파견하든지 합동 관리를 해주면 되지 않느냐”고 ‘대안’을 제시했다. 하지만 임 청장은 “입법하는 게 더 빠를 것 같다”고 했고, 이 대통령은 “아이, 참 말을…”이라며 답답해했다. 그러면서 “국회가 지금 너무 느려서 어느 세월에 (입법이) 될지 모른다. 그때까지 기다리실 거냐”며 “지금부터 시작하라. 상황이 이러니 미루지 말고 비상조치를 좀 하자”고 목소리를 높였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reason President Lee publicly reprimanded Commissioner Im that day is because he has repeatedly instructed him to find measures for 'organizing and strengthening the collection of delinquent/evaded taxes', which is also a presidential election pledge, but he sees no improvement being made. During the Cabinet meeting on the 20th, President Lee also criticized Commissioner Im, who failed to provide accurate answers regarding the cumulative amount of delinquent non-tax revenue, saying, "It seems you're not interested." (  이 대통령이 이날 임 청장을 공개 질책한 건 대선 공약이기도 한 ‘체납·탈루 세금 정리 및 징수 강화’ 방안을 찾아보라고 여러 차례 지시했으나, 개선이 전혀 이뤄지지 않는다고 보고 있어서다. 이 대통령은 지난 20일 국무회의 때도 체납 세외 수입 누적 금액 등에 대해 정확한 답변을 내놓지 못하는 임 청장을 향해 “관심이 없는 거잖아요”라고 쓴소리를 하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following President Lee's repeated criticism, an NTS official stated that day, "We will review directions to conduct preliminary work, excluding actual collection, before the legal amendment." (  이 대통령의 지적이 거듭되자 국세청 관계자는 이날 “법 개정 이전에 징수를 제외한 사전 작업을 할 수 있는 방향으로 검토할 것”이라는 입장을 내놨다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji and Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  서영지 박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241966.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/413/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503607.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pro-Han Dong-hoon faction calls general meeting "a mess," "pathetic" – leadership issues "warning"... Major rift within People Power Party (친한계 “의총 개판” “거지 같아”-지도부 “경고”…국힘 큰 파열음)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241983.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Pro-Han Dong-hoon faction calls general meeting "a mess," "pathetic" – leadership issues "warning"... Major rift within People Power Party (친한계 “의총 개판” “거지 같아”-지도부 “경고”…국힘 큰 파열음)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/526/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503733.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;송언석 국민의힘 원내대표가 27일 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 발언하고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was reported on the 27th that the People Power Party's floor leadership issued a 'stern warning' to pro-Han Dong-hoon faction lawmaker Ko Dong-jin, who criticized the party's situation, where calls for the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon are emerging, as "hopeless and a mess." The atmosphere within the party is becoming increasingly fractured ahead of disciplinary action seeking the expulsion of former leader Han. (국민의힘 원내지도부가 한동훈 전 대표 제명 촉구가 나오는 당 상황을 두고 “희망이 없고 개판이다”라고 비판한 친한동훈계 고동진 의원에게 ‘엄중 경고’를 한 것으로 27일 전해졌다. 한 전 대표의 제명 징계를 앞두고 당내 파열음이 커지는 분위기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a closed-door general meeting of lawmakers on the 26th, Rep. Ko met with reporters and, mentioning the situation where a non-lawmaker party chapter chairman criticized former leader Han and urged his expulsion, said, "The general meeting has become a complete mess." He added, "There is no future here. There is no hope," and "Ugh, this pathetic..." The criticism was aimed at the fact that non-lawmaker party chapter chairmen were being invited to a general meeting typically attended only by lawmakers to create an atmosphere urging the expulsion of former leader Han. (고 의원은 지난 26일 열린 비공개 의원총회 뒤 기자들을 만나 원외 당협위원장이 한 전 대표를 비판하며 제명을 촉구한 상황을 거론하며 “의총이 아주 개판이 되고 있다”고 말했다. 그는 이어 “여기는 미래가 없다. 희망이 없다”며 “아휴, 이런 거지 같은…”이라고 말했다. 일반적으로 의원들만 참석하는 의총에 원외 당협위원장을 불러 한 전 대표 제명 촉구 분위기를 만들고 있다는 취지의 비판이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During that general meeting, Lee Sang-gyu, the Seoul Seongbuk-gu party chapter chairman, reportedly criticized former leader Han, stating in essence that "(former leader Han) is a person without the skill or ability to even stop the president's impeachment," and urged his expulsion. This chairman also reportedly shouted "He must be expelled!" in front of reporters as he left the meeting. (당시 의총에선 이상규 서울 성북을 당협위원장이 “(한 전 대표는) 대통령 탄핵도 못 막는 실력도, 능력도 없는 사람”이라는 취지로 비판하며 한 전 대표의 제명을 촉구한 것으로 알려졌다. 이 위원장은 의총에서 퇴장하면서 기자들 앞에서 “제명해야 한다”고 외치기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song Eon-seok, upon hearing during the meeting about what Rep. Ko reportedly said to reporters, is said to have sternly warned Rep. Ko, stating, "Belittling the general meeting is not something a National Assembly member should do. If you have complaints about the general meeting, please speak about them on the spot." (송언석 원내대표는 의총 도중 고 의원이 기자들에게 했다는 얘기를 전해듣고 “의총을 폄훼하는 건 국회의원으로서 할 일이 아니다. 의총에 불만이 있으면 현장에서 얘기해달라”며 고 의원을 엄중 경고했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, after the general meeting ended that day, Chief Deputy Floor Leader Yoo Sang-beom posted a message in the People Power Party lawmakers' group chatroom urging members to "be mindful of their words and actions to avoid self-deprecation." Rep. Ko reportedly retorted, "When Kwon Seong-dong was floor leader, he sanctioned remarks by Rep. Jo Kyung-tae who opposed him at the time, so why isn't this chairman sanctioning (Lee Sang-gyu's) remarks?" (또 이날 의총이 끝난 뒤 유상범 원내운영수석부대표는 국민의힘 의원 단체 대화방에 “스스로를 폄하하지 않도록 경각심을 갖고 언행을 해달라”는 취지의 글을 올렸다. 고 의원은 “권성동 원내대표 때는 당시 권 원내대표에 반발한 조경태 의원 발언을 제재했는데, 이 위원장은 발언은 왜 제재하지 않는 거냐”며 반박한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Ko met with reporters this morning and said, "Yesterday's general meeting was supposed to focus on how to wage a political battle regarding the 'dual special prosecutor probes,' but topics that shouldn't have been discussed were brought up, so that seemed a bit wrong (is what I meant)." (고 의원은 이날 오전 기자들을 만나 “어제 의총은 ‘쌍특검’과 관련해 어떻게 대여투쟁을 할 것이냐는 문제에 포커스가 맞춰졌는데, 거론되지 않아야 될 얘기가 거론돼서 그것이 좀 잘못된 것 같다(고 한 것)”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the participation of Chairman Lee, who is not a sitting lawmaker, in the general meeting, the floor leader's office stated, "We need to hear from outside the Assembly as well, but it's difficult to invite all party chapter chairmen, so we invited the party chapter chairman leadership," and added, "Chairman Lee didn't only criticize former leader Han; he targeted all lawmakers, telling them to 'straighten up.' Rep. Ko reacted sensitively only to the remarks related to former leader Han." (원내대표실 쪽에선 의총에 현직 의원이 아닌 이 위원장이 의총에 참여한 데 대해 “원외 얘기도 들어야 하는데, 모든 당협위원장을 부르긴 어려우니 당협위원장 운영진을 초청한 것”이라며 “이 위원장이 한 전 대표만 비판한 게 아니고 의원들 모두를 겨냥해 ‘똑바로 하라’고 했는데, 고 의원이 한 전 대표 관련 발언에만 민감하게 반응한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241983.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/526/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503733.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Five Pending 'Special Act on U.S. Investment' Bills Following 'Tariff Agreement'... Ruling Party Aims for "Passage Within Q1" (‘관세 타결 뒤’ 대미투자특별법안 5개 계류…여당 “1분기 내 통과”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241985.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Five Pending 'Special Act on U.S. Investment' Bills Following 'Tariff Agreement'... Ruling Party Aims for "Passage Within Q1" (‘관세 타결 뒤’ 대미투자특별법안 5개 계류…여당 “1분기 내 통과”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/403/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503748.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;27일 경기도 평택항에 컨테이너가 쌓여 있는 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations were concluded last November, a total of five related bills, including the 'Special Act on Strategic Investment Management between Korea and the U.S.' (Special Act on U.S. Investment), have been proposed and are pending in the National Assembly. The Democratic Party of Korea plans to proceed with the legislative process starting next month according to the Assembly's schedule. (지난해 11월 한-미 관세협상 타결 이후 국회에는 ‘한·미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’(대미투자특별법) 등 관련 법안이 모두 5건 발의돼 계류 중이다. 더불어민주당은 국회 일정에 따라 다음달부터 입법 절차를 진행한다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Special Act on U.S. Investment was first proposed on November 26 last year. At that time, then-floor leader of the Democratic Party, Rep. Kim Byeong-gi, proposed it as a representative bill 12 days after a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) on strategic investment between the two countries was signed. With the proposal of this bill, the U.S. reciprocal tariffs (country-specific tariffs) on Korean products were retroactively reduced starting from November 1 last year, in accordance with the bilateral agreement. (대미투자특별법이 처음 발의된 것은 지난해 11월26일이다. 당시 민주당 원내대표였던 김병기 의원이 양국의 전략적 투자에 관한 양해각서(MOU)가 체결되고 12일 뒤 대표 발의했다. 이 법안이 발의되면서, 양국 간 합의에 따라 한국산 제품에 대한 미국의 상호관세(국가별 관세)가 지난해 11월1일부터 소급해 인하됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This bill, proposed after consultations with the government, contains specific provisions for implementing Korea's $350 billion investment in the U.S. Representative provisions include establishing a Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Corporation to oversee the overall planning of strategic investments and manage the establishment and operation of the Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Fund as the investment source. It also stipulates setting up a Project Management Committee under the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy to review the commercial rationality and strategic/legal considerations of U.S. investment projects. (정부와 협의를 거쳐 발의된 이 법안에는 3500억달러 규모의 한국의 대미투자를 이행하기 위한 구체적인 조항들이 담겨 있다. 한·미 전략투자공사를 설치해 전략적 투자를 총괄 기획하고 투자 재원인 한·미 전략투자기금의 조성·운영을 맡기는 조항이 대표적이다. 산업통상부에 사업관리위원회를 설치해 대미투자 사업의 상업적 합리성과 전략적·법적 고려 사항을 검토하게 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the first bill proposal, four additional related bills were proposed in December last year by the Democratic Party (Reps. Ahn Do-geol, Jin Seong-jun, Hong Ki-won) and the People Power Party (Rep. Park Seong-hoon). These bills include provisions requiring the Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Corporation to report relevant details to the National Assembly or obtain prior consent from the Assembly before formally launching large-scale investment projects. This strengthens the National Assembly's oversight and monitoring authority compared to the initially proposed bill. (첫 법안 발의 뒤 지난해 12월 민주당(안도걸·진성준·홍기원)과 국민의힘(박성훈)에서 관련 법안 4건이 추가로 발의됐다. 이들 법안에는 대규모 투자 사업을 본격적으로 실시하기 전 한·미 전략투자공사가 국회에 관련 내용을 보고하거나 국회의 사전 동의를 받아야 한다는 내용이 담겼다. 국회의 견제·감시 권한을 처음 발의된 법안보다 키운 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All five special act bills have been referred to the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee but have not yet been placed on the plenary session agenda. The government and the National Assembly maintain that the review of the bills is not being intentionally delayed, as claimed by U.S. President Donald Trump, but is following the normal legislative process. Rep. Jeong Tae-ho, the ruling party's senior secretary on the Strategy and Finance Committee, met with reporters at the National Assembly today and stated, "Following the normal Assembly procedures, the special act will be deliberated in February." Han Jeong-ae, the Democratic Party's policy committee chairperson, met with reporters after a closed-door meeting with Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance Choo Kyung-ho today, saying, "We told the government that the National Assembly is proceeding according to its set schedule," and added, "Considering the public hearing (an essential step in the legislative review process) and the Lunar New Year holiday in February, the special act bills are likely to pass within the first quarter." (총 5건의 특별법안은 현재 국회 재정경제위원회에 회부됐지만 아직 전체회의에 상정되지 않은 상태다. 정부와 국회는 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 주장처럼 의도적으로 법안 심사를 지체한 것이 아니라, 일반적인 입법 절차를 밟고 있다는 입장이다. 국회 재경위 여당 간사인 정태호 의원은 이날 국회에서 기자들을 만나 “정상적인 국회 절차에 따라 2월에 특별법을 심의하게 될 것”이라고 말했다. 한정애 민주당 정책위의장은 이날 구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관과 비공개 면담 뒤 기자들을 만나 “정부에도 국회가 정해진 일정대로 진행하고 있다고 말했다”며 “(제정법 심사의 필수 절차인) 공청회와 2월 설 연휴를 고려하면 1분기 안에 특별법안이 통과되지 않을까 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hae-jeong, Kyunghyang Shinmun &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241985.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/403/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503748.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump's "Mutual Tariff Hike to 25%" Another Bomb... What's the Response Plan? [Gongdeok Pocha] (트럼프 “상호관세 25%로 인상” 또 폭탄…대응 방안은? [공덕포차])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241995.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Trump's "Mutual Tariff Hike to 25%" Another Bomb... What's the Response Plan? [Gongdeok Pocha] (트럼프 “상호관세 25%로 인상” 또 폭탄…대응 방안은? [공덕포차])&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503842.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th (local time), U.S. President Donald Trump stated on Truth Social, "We are raising the mutual tariffs on all items, including Korean automobiles, lumber, and pharmaceuticals, from 15% to 25%." President Trump cited the reason that "the Korean legislature is not implementing the agreement with the United States," which appears to be pointing to the situation where the 'Special Act for Strategic Investment Management between Korea and the U.S.' is pending in the National Assembly. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 26일(현지시각) 트루스소셜에 “한국의 자동차, 목재, 의약품을 비롯한 모든 품목에 대한 상호 관세를 15%에서 25%로 인상한다”고 밝혔습니다. 트럼프 대통령은 “한국 입법부는 미국과의 협정을 이행하지 않고 있다”는 이유를 댔는데요. ‘한·미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’이 국회에 계류중인 상황를 지적한 것으로 보입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the Blue House stated on the 27th, "The government plans to convey its willingness to implement the tariff agreement to the U.S. side while responding calmly." The government has decided to send government officials, including Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jeong-gwan, to the United States for close communication between Korean and U.S. authorities. (이에 청와대는 27일 “정부는 관세 합의 이행 의지를 미국 측에 전달하는 한편 차분히 대응해나갈 계획”이라고 밝혔는데요. 정부는 한·미 당국 간 긴밀한 소통을 위해 김정관 산업통상부 장관 등 정부 관계자들을 미국으로 보내기로 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is the real reason behind President Trump's 'bomb declaration'? What impact will the People Power Party's Ethics Committee's severe disciplinary action of 'recommending expulsion from the party' against former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyuk, who is considered pro-Han (pro-Han Dong-hoon faction), have on former People Power Party member Han Dong-hoon? Furthermore, what conclusion will the discussions on merging the Democratic Party of Korea and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party reach? Find out on &amp;lt;Gongdeok Pocha&amp;gt;. Check out the video! (트럼프 대통령이 ‘폭탄 선언’을 한 진짜 이유는 무엇일까요? 국민의힘 윤리위원회가 친한계(친한동훈계)인 김종혁 전 최고위원에게 ‘탈당 권유’라는 중징계를 내린 것은 한동훈 전 국민의힘에게 어떤 영향을 미칠까요? 더불어민주당과 조국혁신당의 합당 논의는 어떤 결말을 맺게 될까요? &amp;lt;공덕포차&amp;gt;에서 알아봅니다. 영상으로 확인하시죠!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Production Team&lt;br/&gt;Executive Producer: Lee Kyung-joo &lt;br/&gt;Writer: Park Yeon-shin &lt;br/&gt;Host: Song Chae-kyung-hwa&lt;br/&gt;Cast: Kim Geun-sik, Park Won-seok&lt;br/&gt;Title: Moon Seok-jin &lt;br/&gt;Technical: Park Seong-young &lt;br/&gt;Camera: Jang Seung-ho, Moon Jun-young &lt;br/&gt;Subtitle/Graphic Design: Jung Hyun-sun&lt;br/&gt;Administration: Kim Geun-young&lt;br/&gt;Directing: Jung Joo-yong, Lee Gyu-ho, Jang Ji-nam&lt;br/&gt;Production: Hankyoreh TV (제작진&lt;br/&gt;책임 프로듀서 : 이경주 &lt;br/&gt;작가 : 박연신 &lt;br/&gt;진행 : 송채경화&lt;br/&gt;출연 : 김근식 박원석&lt;br/&gt;타이틀 : 문석진 &lt;br/&gt;기술 : 박성영 &lt;br/&gt;카메라 : 장승호 문준영 &lt;br/&gt;자막그래픽디자인 : 정현선&lt;br/&gt;행정: 김근영&lt;br/&gt;연출 : 정주용 이규호 장지남&lt;br/&gt;제작 : 한겨레TV)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Chae-kyung-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송채경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241995.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503842.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Takes Out Handkerchief, Wipes Tears While Comforting Bereaved Family of Late Vice Chairman Lee Hae-chan (이 대통령, 손수건 꺼내 눈물 닦으며 이해찬 수석부의장 유족 위로)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241998.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee Takes Out Handkerchief, Wipes Tears While Comforting Bereaved Family of Late Vice Chairman Lee Hae-chan (이 대통령, 손수건 꺼내 눈물 닦으며 이해찬 수석부의장 유족 위로)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/913/639/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503870.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이해찬 전 국무총리의 주검과 영정이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 도착해 운구되고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung posthumously awarded the Order of Mugunghwa, the Republic of Korea's highest civilian honor, to the late Lee Hae-chan, Vice Chairman of the National Unification Advisory Council (NUAC). On the 27th, the first day of the funeral, fellow politicians, seniors, and juniors who gathered at the mourning site remembered the late Vice Chairman, who was called 'Mr. Public Mind' during his lifetime, with reddened eyes. (이재명 대통령이 이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의(민주평통) 수석부의장의 빈소를 찾아 고인에게 국민훈장 무궁화장을 추서했다. 고인의 장례 첫날인 27일, 빈소에 모인 동료·선후배 정치인들은 생전 ‘미스터 퍼블릭 마인드(공인의식)’로 불린 이 수석부의장을 떠올리며 눈시울을 붉혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee, accompanied by First Lady Kim Hye-kyung, visited the mourning site set up at Seoul National University Hospital's funeral hall in Jongno-gu, Seoul, that evening. The presidential couple laid flowers and paid their respects before the altar, then posthumously awarded the Order of Mugunghwa, placing it to the right of the portrait. The Order of Mugunghwa is considered the highest honor practically attainable by ordinary citizens. After awarding the order, President Lee took out a handkerchief, wiped away tears, and then held the hand of the late Vice Chairman's wife, Kim Jeong-ok, saying, "You must be going through so much heartache." First Lady Kim Hye-kyung also hugged the bereaved family to offer comfort. (이 대통령은 김혜경 여사와 함께 이날 저녁 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장에 마련된 이 수석부의장의 빈소를 방문했다. 이 대통령 부부는 고인에게 헌화한 뒤 분향했고, 영정 사진 오른편에 무궁화장을 추서했다. 무궁화장은 일반 국민이 받을 수 있는 사실상 최고 영예의 훈장으로 꼽힌다. 훈장 추서 뒤 이 대통령은 손수건을 꺼내 눈물을 닦은 다음 고인의 배우자인 김정옥 여사의 손을 잡으며 “얼마나 마음고생이 많으시겠습니까”라고 위로했다. 김혜경 여사도 유족을 끌어안으며 위로했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The body of the late Vice Chairman Lee arrived at Incheon International Airport at around 6:53 AM, 4 hours and 30 minutes after departing from Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam, and was transferred to Seoul National University Hospital. On this day, hundreds of people, including former and current politicians and ordinary citizens, visited the mourning site, leaving no room to stand. (이 수석부의장의 주검은 베트남 호찌민시에서 출발한 지 4시간30분 만인 아침 6시53분께 인천국제공항에 도착해 서울대병원으로 옮겨졌다. 이날 빈소에는 전현직 정치인과 일반인까지 수백명이 찾아 발 디딜 틈이 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Moon Jae-in and First Lady Kim Jung-sook, who visited the mourning site before President Lee, clasped hands with a sorrowful expression with Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who is serving as the chief mourner, Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae, Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, writer Yoo Si-min, and other bereaved family members. The former presidential couple met separately with the bereaved family for about 40 minutes after paying their respects before leaving the funeral hall. (이 대통령보다 먼저 빈소를 찾은 문재인 전 대통령과 김정숙 여사는 유가족과 상주 역할을 하고 있는 김민석 국무총리와 정청래 더불어민주당 대표, 조국 조국혁신당 대표, 유시민 작가 등의 손을 침통한 표정으로 맞잡았다. 문 전 대통령 부부는 조문 뒤 40분 정도 유가족들을 따로 만나 위로하고 장례식장을 떠났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Cho Jeong-sik stated, "Before leaving home, Vice Chairman Lee had cold and flu-like symptoms, and his wife urged him not to go on the business trip, but he said, 'It's an official schedule, I must go,' and departed." He added, "The late Vice Chairman considered this Vice Chairman position his last public office and sacrificed himself until the very end, dying in the line of duty." Former Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho said, "Seeing him pass away while engaged in public activities until his final moments truly makes one feel 'That's so Lee Hae-chan.' I hope his great aspirations continue." (조정식 대통령 정무특보는 “이 수석부의장은 자택 출발 전 감기 몸살 증상이 있어 사모님이 출장을 만류했는데, ‘공식 일정이니 가야 한다’며 출장길에 나섰다”며 “고인은 이번 수석부의장직을 본인의 마지막 공직으로 여기셨고, 마지막까지 몸을 불사르다 순직하셨다”고 밝혔다. 우상호 전 청와대 정무수석은 “생애 마지막 순간까지 공적 활동을 하다 돌아가신 것을 보면 정말 ‘이해찬답다’고 느낀다. 이분의 큰 뜻이 계속 이어지길 소망한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The mourning site also saw visits from figures across the political spectrum, including National Assembly Speaker Woo Won-shik, Democratic Party floor leader Han Byung-do, former Prime Ministers Kim Boo-kyum and Chung Sye-kyun from the ruling camp, as well as People Power Party lawmaker Joo Ho-young, who is a Deputy Speaker of the National Assembly, former Bareunmirae Party leader Sohn Hak-kyu, Lee Jae-oh, Chairman of the Memorial Foundation for the Democracy Movement, People Power Party lawmaker Kim Dae-sik from the conservative camp, and Chinese Ambassador to South Korea Xing Haiming. (빈소에는 우원식 국회의장, 한병도 민주당 원내대표, 김부겸·정세균 전 국무총리 등 여권 인사들과 국회부의장인 주호영 국민의힘 의원, 손학규 전 바른미래당 대표, 이재오 민주화운동기념사업회 이사장, 김대식 국민의힘 의원 등 보수 인사들도 조문을 왔다. 다이빙 주한중국대사도 빈소를 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Chae-woon, Ko Kyeong-ju, Kim Soo-yeon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 고경주 김수연 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241998.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/913/639/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127503870.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A string of visitors including Joo Ho-young, Jeong Won-o, and Kim Eo-jun... Condolence visits to the late Lee Hae-chan's funeral altar (주호영·정원오·김어준 등 줄이어…이해찬 수석부의장 빈소 조문)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241999.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;A string of visitors including Joo Ho-young, Jeong Won-o, and Kim Eo-jun... Condolence visits to the late Lee Hae-chan's funeral altar (주호영·정원오·김어준 등 줄이어…이해찬 수석부의장 빈소 조문)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500005.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;주호영 국회부의장(왼쪽 세 번째)과 김경수 지방시대위원회 위원장(왼쪽)이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 마련된 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 찾아 조문하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, the first day of the funeral for Lee Hae-chan, the late Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council (Minjupyeongtong), the line of mourners continued late into the night at the funeral hall of Seoul National University Hospital where the altar was set up. (이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의(민주평통) 수석부의장의 장례 첫날인 27일, 빈소가 차려진 서울대병원 장례식장에는 늦은 밤까지 조문 행렬이 이어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following President Lee Jae-myung's visit after 7 PM, opposition figures including Joo Ho-young, a People Power Party lawmaker and National Assembly Vice Speaker, and Kim Dae-sik, a People Power Party lawmaker, visited the altar. Lawmaker Kim said, "I served as the Secretary-General of Minjupyeongtong," adding, "The former Prime Minister devoted himself greatly to the democratization movement while serving seven terms. I believe he will continue to worry greatly for South Korea even in heaven." (이재명 대통령이 다녀간 오후 7시 이후 국회 부의장인 주호영 국민의힘 의원과 김대식 국민의힘 의원 등 야당 인사들이 빈소를 찾았다. 김 의원은 “제가 민주평통 사무처장을 역임했다”며 “총리께서는 그동안 7선을 하시며 민주화운동에 크게 헌신하셨다. 하늘나라에 가서도 대한민국을 위해 크게 걱정하시리라 생각한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Gyeong-soo, Chairman of the Local Era Committee, who worked with the deceased during the Roh Moo-hyun administration, also visited subsequently. With tears in his eyes, he said, "To me, former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan was a political mentor along with President Roh Moo-hyun," and pledged, "Our democracy is indebted to former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan. We will carry on his will for democracy, peace, and balanced national development." (노무현 정부에서 고인과 함께 일했던 김경수 지방시대위원장도 뒤이어 방문했다. 눈물이 맺힌 그는 “저에게 이해찬 총리님은 노무현 대통령님과 함께 정치적 스승이셨다”며 “우리 민주주의가 이해찬 총리님께 빚을 지고 있다. 민주주의와 평화, 국가균형발전이라는 총리님의 뜻을 잘 이어가겠다”고 다짐했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, the Presidential Office's Policy Chief, and Bong Wook, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Civil Affairs, also visited the altar. Chief Kim recalled the former Prime Minister by mentioning the bookstores 'Gwangjang Bookstore' and 'Dongbang Bookstore' that the former Prime Minister ran during his university days, saying, "In our time in the 80s, we learned all the books we read through those places. He was a bookstore owner with a clear historical consciousness." He also said, "It's hard to believe because he encouraged me when I met him at an event just three weeks ago." Chief Kim stated, "We are deeply saddened by the passing of a great elder who contributed so immensely to our nation's politics and democracy," adding, "I believe (the former Prime Minister) will be remembered as a towering figure in South Korea's democracy and history." (김용범 청와대 정책실장, 봉욱 민정수석도 빈소를 찾았다. 김 실장은 대학 시절 이 전 총리가 운영하던 서점 ‘광장서적’과 ‘동방서적’을 언급하며 “80년대 우리 시절에 읽는 책들을 다 거기 통해 배웠다. 카랑카랑한 역사의식을 가졌던 서점 주인이셨다”고 이 전 총리를 기억했다. 또 “3주 전에 한 행사에서 뵀을 때 (저를) 격려해주셨는데 너무 믿기지 않는다”고 했다. 김 실장은 “우리나라 정치와 민주주의에 너무나 큰 기여를 하신 큰 어른이 가셔서 상심이 크다”며 “(이 전 총리는) 대한민국 민주주의와 역사에서 두고두고 기억될 거목이라 생각한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Others who paid their condolences late into the night included Choo Kyung-ho, the Minister of Economy and Finance; Jeong Eun-kyeong, the Minister of Health and Welfare; Jeong Won-o, the Mayor of Seongdong District; and broadcaster Kim Eo-jun. Minister Choo said, "I recently saw (the former Prime Minister) at Minjupyeongtong," adding, "He was still healthy then, so it's heartbreaking that he left us so suddenly." He said, "I too will live a life dedicated to the public good and the nation, upholding the deceased's will." (이외에도 구윤철 기획재정부 장관, 정은경 보건복지부 장관, 정원오 성동구청장, 방송인 김어준씨 등이 늦은 시간까지 조문했다. 구 장관은 “최근에도 민주평통에서 (이 전 총리를) 뵀었다”며 “그때만 해도 정정하셨는데 이렇게 갑자기 가시니 가슴이 먹먹하다”고 말했다. 그는 “저도 고인의 뜻을 받들어서 공익을 생각하고 국가를 생각하는 삶을 살아가도록 하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Condolence visits ended at 10 PM that day. From the 28th, visits will be possible from 9 AM to 9 PM for four days. (이날 조문은 밤 10시 종료됐다. 28일부터 나흘간은 오전 9시부터 저녁 9시까지 조문이 가능하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Go Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241999.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500005.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Countdown to Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion...Young Members Demand "Reconsideration" While Party Leadership Faction Urges "Quick Conclusion" (한동훈 제명 초읽기…소장파 “재고” 요구에 당권파 “빨리 결론내야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242005.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Countdown to Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion...Young Members Demand "Reconsideration" While Party Leadership Faction Urges "Quick Conclusion" (한동훈 제명 초읽기…소장파 “재고” 요구에 당권파 “빨리 결론내야”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694820188682_53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민의힘 장동혁 대표, 한동훈(오른쪽) 전 대표. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The leadership of the People Power Party is expected to deliberate on the motion to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon on the 29th. Although not only pro-Han Dong-hoon faction members but also young lawmakers within the party are demanding a reconsideration of the disciplinary action, party leader Jang Dong-hyeok and other 'anti-impeachment mainstream' figures are poised to push through with the expulsion. (국민의힘 지도부가 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명안을 29일 의결할 것으로 보인다. 친한동훈계뿐 아니라 당내 소장파 의원들도 징계 재고를 요구하고 있지만, 장동혁 대표 등 ‘반탄(탄핵 반대) 주류’는 제명을 밀어붙일 태세다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang is considering a plan to return to party duties, starting with a visit to the Korea Agro-Fisheries &amp; Food Trade Corporation (aT) integrated situation room on the afternoon of the 28th to check on prices. It has been six days since he ended his hunger strike following former President Park Geun-hye's persuasion. A party leadership official told The Hankyoreh on the 27th, "If Leader Jang returns to party duties and attends the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th, (the disciplinary motion) will not be postponed further," adding, "It is the shared opinion of the leadership that the disciplinary motion should not be continuously delayed and a conclusion must be reached quickly." (장 대표는 28일 오후 한국농수산식품유통공사(aT) 종합상황실을 찾아 물가를 점검하는 것을 시작으로 당무에 복귀하는 방안을 검토하고 있다. 박근혜 전 대통령의 만류로 단식을 중단한 지 엿새 만이다. 당 지도부 관계자는 27일 한겨레에 “장 대표가 당무에 복귀해 29일 최고위에 참석한다면, (징계안) 처리를 더 미루지는 않을 것”이라며 “징계안 처리를 계속 미뤄선 안 되고, 빨리 결론을 내려야 한다는 게 지도부의 공통된 의견”이라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, it is viewed as almost certain that former leader Han Dong-hoon will be expelled, as evidenced by the party's Ethics Committee imposing the severe disciplinary measure of 'recommendation to leave the party' on pro-Han faction Goyang City Party chapter chairman Kim Jong-hyuk the previous day. Another party leadership official stated, "Former leader Han was given the opportunity to appeal the Ethics Committee's decision and had the chance to visit the hunger strike site, but he rejected them all himself," adding, "Former leader Han largely created the justification for the disciplinary action himself." (당내에선 전날 당 윤리위원회가 친한계 김종혁 고양시병 당협위원장에게 ‘탈당 권유’라는 초강수 징계를 내린 데서 알 수 있듯, 한동훈 전 대표의 제명 역시 확정적이라고 본다. 또 다른 당 지도부 관계자는 “한 전 대표에게는 윤리위 처분에 대해 재심을 할 기회도 줬고, 단식 농성장에 찾아올 기회도 있었지만 스스로 모두 차 버린 것”이라며 “징계에 대한 명분은 한 전 대표 스스로 만들어준 측면이 크다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han repeatedly protested against Chairman Kim's disciplinary action. In a post on Facebook the previous night, former leader Han strongly criticized, saying, "Shockingly, anti-democratic and anti-intellectual statements are being made openly in the Ethics Committee's decision document," and "(Recommending leaving the party) is not democracy but 'totalitarianism' or 'pseudo-democracy' like 'North Korean leader theory' or 'Nazism'." He then raised his voice, stating, "(The leadership's behavior) is not normal. It must be corrected. The People Power Party must be a liberal democratic party." (한 전 대표는 김 위원장 징계에 거듭 반발했다. 한 전 대표는 전날 밤 페이스북에 올린 글에서 “반민주, 반지성적인 말을 놀랍게도 윤리위 결정문에서 대놓고 하고 있다”며 “(탈당 권유는) 민주주의가 아니라 ‘북한 수령론’, ‘나치즘’ 같은 ‘전체주의’, ‘사이비 민주주의’”라고 강도 높은 비난을 쏟아냈다. 그러면서 “(지도부 행태가) 정상이 아니다. 바로잡아야 한다. 국민의힘은 자유민주주의 정당이어야 한다”고 목소리를 높였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, opinions are sharply divided over the deliberation of the motion to expel former leader Han. Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won said on YTN Radio that day, "Indefinitely postponing and continuing internal party disputes is not good for the party and only causes confusion for the public. The Supreme Council must deliberate (on the expulsion motion) within a short period of time." Jang Ye-chan, vice president of the Yeouido Research Institute close to Leader Jang, said on the radio the previous day, "The prevailing opinion within the Supreme Council is that former leader Han has become unable to avoid expulsion." 'Alternative and Future', a gathering of young members within the People Power Party, urged that day, "The Supreme Council should reconsider the deliberation on expelling former leader Han and seek a political solution for party unity." (당내에선 한 전 대표 제명안 의결을 두고 찬반이 팽팽하게 갈리는 모습이다. 김재원 최고위원은 이날 와이티엔(YTN) 라디오에서 “마냥 미루고 당내 논란만 계속되는 건 당을 위해서도 좋지 않고, 국민들에게도 혼란만 야기한다. 빠른 시일 안에 최고위에서 (제명안을) 의결해야 한다”고 했다. 장 대표와 가까운 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장은 전날 라디오에서 “한 전 대표가 제명을 피할 수 없게 됐다는 것이 최고위 내부의 중론”이라고 했다. 국민의힘 소장파 모임인 ‘대안과 미래’는 이날 “최고위가 한 전 대표 제명 의결을 재고하고, 당 통합을 위한 정치적 해법을 찾아야 한다”고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242005.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694820188682_53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:21:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Proposes "Introducing a Sugar Tax to Strengthen Regional and Public Healthcare" (이 대통령 “설탕세 도입해 지역·공공 의료 강화에 쓰자”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242013.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500375.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung proposed on the 28th to impose a so-called 'sugar tax', a health promotion levy, on foods and beverages high in sugar. The idea is to introduce a related tax to reduce sugar intake, which causes obesity and diabetes, and to use the revenue collected in this way for various regions and the national health insurance. (이재명 대통령이 28일 설탕이 많이 함유된 식품과 음료에 건강증진부담금을 부과하는 이른바 ‘설탕세’를 부과하자고 제안했다. 비만·당뇨 등을 부르는 설탕 섭취를 줄일 수 있도록 관련 세금을 도입하고, 이렇게 거둬들인 재정을 각 지역 및 건강보험 등에 사용하자는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee wrote on X (formerly Twitter) that day, "Like with cigarettes, suppress sugar use through a sugar levy, and reinvest that levy to strengthen regional and public healthcare... What are your thoughts?" He also shared an article stating that '80% of the public supports the introduction of a sugar tax.' (이 대통령은 이날 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 “담배처럼 설탕 부담금으로 설탕 사용 억제, 그 부담금으로 지역·공공 의료 강화에 재투자…여러분 의견은 어떠냐”고 적었다. 그러면서 ‘국민 80%가 설탕세 도입에 찬성한다’는 기사를 공유했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sugar tax has been implemented in over 120 countries since the World Health Organization (WHO) recommended its introduction in 2016. (설탕세는 2016년 세계보건기구(WHO)가 도입을 권고한 뒤 120여개국에서 시행되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, discussions took place in 2021, but it failed to be introduced due to opposition from the food industry and some consumers. At the time, the Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Rural Affairs and the Ministry of Health and Welfare also expressed the opinion that careful review was necessary, considering public acceptance and other factors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;After President Lee posted this on X, a Blue House official stated, "We plan to gather opinions from various sectors and review measures regarding the issue of public health rights caused by sugar intake and the use of funds for reinvestment to strengthen regional and public healthcare." The official added, "I understand that the National Assembly is also discussing ways to strengthen public health rights, such as disease prevention through the introduction of a sugar levy, including holding a hearing on the sugar tax." &lt;br/&gt;Previously, Representative Jeong Tae-ho of the Democratic Party of Korea held a 'Discussion on Tax for Excessive Sugar Use' at the National Assembly in October last year. (국내에서도 2021년 논의가 이뤄졌지만, 식품업계와 일부 소비자의 반발에 부딪혀 도입되지 못했다. 당시 농림축산식품부·보건복지부도 국민 수용성 등을 고려해 신중한 검토가 필요하다는 의견을 낸 바 있다.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;이 대통령이 이런 글을 엑스에 올린 뒤, 청와대 관계자는 “설탕 섭취로 인한 국민 건강권 문제 및 지역·공공의료 강화를 위한 재투자 재원으로의 활용 방안 등에 대해 각계의 의견을 수렴하여 검토해나갈 계획”이라고 밝혔다. 그러면서 “국회에서도 설탕세 토론회를 개최하는 등 설탕 부담금 도입을 통한 질병 예방 등 국민 건강권 강화 문제에 대해 논의 중인 것으로 알고 있다”고 덧붙였다. &lt;br/&gt;앞서 정태호 더불어민주당 의원은 지난해 10월 국회에서 ‘설탕 과다사용세 토론회’를 진행한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242013.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500375.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:20:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Calls for "Public Review" of Wildly Varying Interest Rates on Local Government Funds (이 대통령, 천차만별 지자체 금고 이자율에 “공개 검토하라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242017.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/733/572/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500519.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령 엑스(X) 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee Jae-myung commented on the fact that interest rates on funds operated by local governments show a disparity of up to more than double, saying, "It would be worth conducting a comparative study between the degree of democracy in the relevant city and its interest rate." (이재명 대통령은 28일 지방자치단체가 운영하는 금고 금리가 최대 2배 이상 편차가 나는 것을 두고 “해당도시의 민주주의 정도와 이자율을 비교 연구해볼 가치가 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The President made these remarks while sharing on X (formerly Twitter) an article analyzing the results of the first-ever public disclosure of interest rates on funds managed by local governments. (이 대통령은 이날 지자체가 운용하는 금고의 이자율이 처음으로 공개된 결과를 분석하는 기사를 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 공유하며 이렇게 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interest rates on funds from 243 local governments nationwide were disclosed on this day on the 'Local Finance Integrated Public System' website, following President Lee's directive last August during a 'National Fiscal Savings Meeting' to "investigate the interest rates on local government funds nationwide and review whether public disclosure is possible." His point is that the significant variation in interest rates by local government might be correlated with the degree of democracy in each locality. (이 대통령이 지난해 8월 ‘나라 재정 절약 간담회’에서 “전국 지자체 금고 이자율을 조사해 공개가 가능한지 검토하라”고 지시하면서 이날 ‘지방재정통합 공개시스템’ 누리집에 전국 243개 지자체의 금고 이자율이 공개됐다. 지자체별 금리가 크게 다른 것을 두고, 각 지자체의 민주주의 정도와 이자율에 상관관계가 있을 수도 있다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the early hours of the same day, President Lee also shared a related article titled 'Incheon 4.6%·Gyeongbuk 2.2% - A World of Difference' and wrote, "Even 1% on 1 trillion won is 10 billion won." He added, "This is all taxpayers' money." He was criticizing the fact that, despite being the same residents' taxes, while some cities receive interest in the 4% range, others barely reach the 1% range, showing very large regional disparities. Given that local government budgets typically exceed trillions of won, even a 1% difference in interest rates causes interest income to swing by tens of billions of won. (이 대통령은 이날 새벽에도 ‘인천 4.6%·경북 2.2% 천차만별’이라는 관련 기사를 공유하며 “1조원에 1%만 해도 100억원”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “이게 다 주민들의 혈세”라고 썼다. 똑같은 주민 세금임에도 어떤 도시는 4%대 이자를 받는 반면, 어떤 도시는 1%대에 그치는 등 지역별 편차가 매우 큰 것으로 나타났는데, 지자체 예산이 보통 조 단위가 넘다 보니, 금리 1% 차이만으로도 이자 수익이 수백억 원씩 왔다 갔다 한다는 점을 비판한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, looking at the interest rates on funds from 243 local governments nationwide, the average interest rate for time deposits with a maturity of 12 months or more was 2.53%. Among these, the average rate for the 17 metropolitan governments was calculated at 2.61%. Among metropolitan governments, Incheon City and Seoul City received relatively high interest rates at 4.57% and 3.45%, respectively. Sejong City (2.68%) and Daejeon City (2.64%) also exceeded the average. In contrast, North Gyeongsang Province (2.15%) and Daegu City (2.26%) remained in the low 2% range, placing them at the bottom. (한편, 전국 243개 지자체의 금고 이자율을 보면, 12개월 이상 정기예금 기준 평균 금리는 2.53%였다. 이 가운데 17개 광역자치단체의 평균 금리는 2.61%로 집계됐다. 광역단체 중에서는 인천시와 서울시가 각각 4.57%와 3.45%로 상대적으로 높은 이자율을 적용받았다. 세종시(2.68%)와 대전시(2.64%)도 평균을 웃돌았다. 반면 경북(2.15%)과 대구(2.26%)는 2%대 초반의 이자율에 머물며 최하위권에 위치했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242017.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/733/572/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500519.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:20:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[View Briefing] 'V0' Kim Gun-hee's First Trial Sentencing, What's the Outlook? ([뷰리핑] ‘V0’ 김건희 1심 선고, 전망은?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242018.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500540.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host: Kwon Tae-ho, Hankyoreh Editorial Board Director. Guests: Ha Eo-young, Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter; Park Jin-young, Political Critic; Gil Yun-hyeong, Hankyoreh Editorial Writer. (진행: 권태호 한겨레 논설위원실장. 출연: 하어영 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 박진영 정치비평가, 길윤형 한겨레 논설위원)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'V0' Kim Gun-hee's First Sentencing...Court Permits Live Broadcast / Yoon's Key Aide Kwon Seong-dong's First Trial Sentencing...'Allegations of Illegal Political Fund Receipt' / Kim Min-seok, on 'Merger Controversy'..."Welcoming Unification, But the Announcement Method is Questionable" / 'Suspicion of Nomination Bribes' Kim Kyeong...Need to Expand Investigation into 'Illegal Political Donations' / Turbulent People Power Party, Internal Feud over 'Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion' / China's 'West Sea Structure' Moves...A Signal for Korea-China 'Relationship Normalization'? / Trump Threatens to Scrap Tariff Agreement...Outlook for Exports to US 'Clouded'. Please tune in to today's (January 28th) View Briefing. (‘V0’ 김건희 첫 선고…법원, 생중계 허가 / 윤핵관 권성동 1심 선고…‘불법 정치자금 수수 혐의’ / 김민석, ‘합당 논란’에…“통합은 환영, 발표 방식은 글쎄” / ‘공천헌금 의혹’ 김경…‘불법 정치후원금’ 수사 확대 필요성 / 격동의 국힘, ‘한동훈 제명’ 집안 싸움 / 중국 ‘서해 구조물’ 이동…한·중 ‘관계 정상화’ 신호? / 트럼프 관세 합의 파기 위협…대미 수출 전망 ‘먹구름’. 오늘(01월 28일) 뷰리핑 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242018.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500540.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:20:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un and Kim Ju Ae personally observed yesterday's North Korean missile launch... "Will become a grave threat to enemies" (어제 북 미사일 쏠 때 김정은·김주애 직접 참관…“적들에 엄중한 위협될 것”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1242019.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695598347705_20260128500589.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장은 27일 미사일총국이 진행한 ‘대구경 방사포 무기체계’ 시험사격을 참관하며 “기술적 갱신을 해 특수한 공격사용에 적합화됐기 때문에 우리와 군사적 대결을 기도하는 세력에게 착잡한 고민거리, 엄중한 위협으로 다가갈 것”이라고 말했다고 28일 노동신문이 보도했다. 김정은 총비서의 딸 김주애양도 함께 참관했다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, observed a test-firing of a "large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapons system" and stated, "Because it has been technologically updated and adapted for special attack use, it will become a vexing concern and a grave threat to forces attempting military confrontation with us," Rodong Sinmun reported on the 28th. General Secretary Kim Jong Un's daughter, Ju Ae, also observed the event together. (김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장은 ‘대구경 방사포 무기체계’ 시험사격을 참관하며 “기술적 갱신을 해 특수한 공격사용에 적합화됐기 때문에 우리와 군사적 대결을 기도하는 세력에게 착잡한 고민거리, 엄중한 위협으로 다가갈 것”이라고 말했다고 28일 노동신문이 보도했다. 김정은 총비서의 딸 주애양도 함께 참관했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported, "The Missile General Bureau conducted a test-firing on the 27th for the effectiveness verification of the updated large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapons system with newly introduced technology," and that "Comrade Kim Jong Un observed the test." General Secretary Kim said, "Today's test holds very significant meaning in enhancing the effectiveness of strategic deterrence," adding, "This is because we have carried out technological updates to most accurately and effectively utilize the most powerful characteristics of this weapons system, and therefore it has been adapted for special attack use." He did not specify what exactly "special attack use" entails, but it is presumed to be related to 'tactical nuclear operation'. (노동신문은 “미사일총국은 27일 새로운 기술이 도입된 갱신형 대구경 방사포 무기체계의 효력검증을 위한 시험사격을 진행했다”며 “김정은 동지께서 시험을 참관하셨다”라고 보도했다. 김 총비서는 “오늘의 시험은 전략적 억제의 효과성을 제고해나가는 데서 대단히 중요한 의미를 가진다”며 “이 무기체계의 가장 위력한 특성을 가장 적중하고 효과적으로 활용하기 위한 기술적 갱신을 하였으며 따라서 특수한 공격 사용에 적합화되었기 때문”이라고 말했다. 그는 ‘특수한 공격 사용’이 구체적으로 어떤 내용인지 밝히지 않았으나, ‘전술핵 운용’과 관련된 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during an on-site guidance visit to an 'important munitions industry enterprise' on December 29 last year, General Secretary Kim inspected the "actual state of multiple rocket launcher vehicle production" and stated, "This multiple rocket launcher weapons system, which will become the main striking means of our military, can annihilate the enemy and can be used as a strategic attack means," calling it "an important new milestone in practically increasing war deterrence." Even earlier, on May 8 last year, he guided the 'joint strike training of long-range artillery and missile systems by units of the People's Army Eastern Front'. At the time, Rodong Sinmun reported that the training "was conducted with the aim of familiarizing the relevant units with the procedures for operating artillery and missile attack systems according to the national nuclear weapons comprehensive management system." 'Units' typically refer to small forces at the battalion level or below. (앞서 김 총비서는 지난해 12월29일 ‘중요 군수공업기업소’를 현지지도하며 “방사포차 생산 실태”를 점검하고는 “우리 군대의 주력 타격수단으로 될 이 방사포 무기체계는 적을 초토화시킬 수 있으며 전략적 공격수단으로 이용할 수 있는 것”이라며 “전쟁억제력을 실용적으로 증대시키는 데서 중요한 새 이정표”라고 말한 바 있다. 그보다 앞선 지난해 5월8일엔 ‘인민군 동부전선 구분대들의 장거리포 및 미사일체계 합동타격훈련’을 지도했는데, 당시 노동신문은 “국가핵무기종합관리체계에 따라 포 및 미사일공격체계를 운용하는 절차에 해당 구분대들을 숙달시키는 데 목적을 두고 진행”됐다고 전했다. ‘구분대’란 통상 대대급 이하 작은 부대를 뜻한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Secretary Kim, who observed the test-firing of the 'updated large-caliber multiple rocket launcher' on the 27th, "expressed satisfaction" and boasted, "I am convinced that for at least a few years, no other country will reach such technology or possess such capability." He then said, "As I have always emphasized, the purpose of our activities is to further advance nuclear war deterrence," adding, "Demonstrating this will and capability itself is the responsible exercise of deterrence." Judging by the expression "updated," it is presumed that a multiple rocket launcher with improved functions and performance compared to the existing "600mm multiple launch rocket system" has been developed. Indeed, General Secretary Kim praised it, saying, "The mobility, intelligence, and accuracy of the rocket shells have been updated incomparably," and "The mobility of the newly improved launch vehicle is also perfect." (27일 ‘갱신형 대구경 방사포’ 시험사격을 참관한 김 총비서는 “만족을 표시”했으며 “나는 최소 몇년 안에는 그 어느 나라도 이와 같은 기술에 도달하지 못할 것이며 그러한 능력을 가질 수 없을 것이라는 것을 확신한다”라고 자평했다. 그러곤 “늘 강조해왔지만 우리가 진행하는 활동이 목적은 핵전쟁억제력을 더욱 고도화해나가자는 데 있다”며 “이러한 의지와 능력을 보여주는 것 자체가 억제력의 책임적인 행사”라고 말했다. “갱신형”이라는 표현에 비춰, 기존의 “600㎜ 다연장 방사포”보다 기능·성능이 개선된 방사포를 개발했다는 뜻으로 추정된다. 실제 김 총비서는 “방사포탄의 기동성, 지능성, 명중성이 비할 바 없이 갱신됐다”며 “새로 개량된 포차의 기동성 또한 완벽하다”고 자찬했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported, "The fired rocket shells struck a sea target 358.5 km away from the launch point." Earlier, the Joint Chiefs of Staff announced to the press on the 27th, "We detected several short-range ballistic missiles launched from an area north of Pyongyang, North Korea, toward the East Sea," and "The detected North Korean missiles flew approximately 350 km." (노동신문은 “발사된 방사포탄들은 발사점으로부터 358.5㎞ 떨어진 해상표적을 강타했다”고 전했다. 앞서 합동참모본부는 27일 “북한 평양 북방 일대에서 동해상으로 발사된 단거리 탄도미사일 수발을 포착했다”며 “포착된 북한의 미사일은 약 350㎞를 비행했다”고 언론에 공지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported that General Secretary Kim stated, "Building the most reliable attack capability and implementing a deterrence strategy based on it is the immutable line of the national defense policy," and "The 9th Congress of the Workers' Party of Korea will proclaim the next-stage plans for further strengthening the country's nuclear war deterrence." (노동신문은 김 총비서가 “가장 확실한 공격 능력을 구축하고 그에 기초한 억제전략을 실시하는 것은 국가방위정책의 불변 노선”이라며 “조선노동당 9차 대회는 나라의 핵전쟁억제력을 가일층 강화하기 위한 다음 단계의 구상들을 천명하게 될 것”이라고 밝혔다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Je-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1242019.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695598347705_20260128500589.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:19:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Woo Sang-ho: "For a merger between the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party, behind-the-scenes contacts are needed... Quota negotiations are impossible these days" (우상호 “민주·혁신 합당, 물밑 접촉할 때…지분 협상 요즘은 불가능”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242021.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500658.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;우상호 전 청와대 정무수석. 김태형 기자 xogud555@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, former Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho commented on the ongoing controversy within the Democratic Party of Korea that party leader Chung Cheong-rae unilaterally proposed a merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, saying, "Rather than dragging this issue out, I think it's time to move on to the topic of whether integration is desirable or not." (우상호 전 청와대 정무수석이 28일 더불어민주당 내부에서 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 독단적으로 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안했다는 논란이 이어지는 것과 관련해 “그 문제를 오래 끄는 것보다는 통합이 바람직하냐, 바람직하지 않냐의 주제로 넘어갈 때가 된 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with YTN Radio that day, former Senior Secretary Woo said, "I believe there was a need for procedural legitimacy, such as (Leader Chung) secretly calling the Supreme Council members before making the merger proposal and asking, 'I'm thinking of making this proposal, what do you think?'" He added, "However, I hope the leadership will reconcile again and pool their wisdom on the methodology of how to push forward with this integration." (우 전 수석은 이날 와이티엔(YTN) 라디오에서 “(정 대표가) 합당 제안을 하기 전에 최고위원들을 비밀리에 불러서 ‘이런 제안을 하려고 하는데 어떻게 생각하느냐’고 물어보는 절차적인 정당성은 필요했다고 본다”면서도 “지도부가 다시 서로 화해하고 이 통합을 어떻게 추진할 건지에 대한 방법론으로 지혜를 모아줬으면 좋겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Senior Secretary Woo stated, "Looking at the past, when two parties integrate, they usually form a kind of integration promotion body, and that body needs to engage in various behind-the-scenes negotiations." He explained, "Even if they agree in principle to integrate, depending on the type of integration, it can break down or succeed." He continued, "So, we should see this as a process of moving into that phase," and added, "The war of words currently going on between Democratic Party Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae and Innovation Party floor leader Seo Wang-jin shows that we are entering this phase." (우 전 수석은 “과거에 보면 양당이 일종의 통합추진기구를 만들고, 통합추진기구가 물밑에서 다양한 교섭을 해야 된다”며 “원칙적으로 통합에 찬성한다 하더라도 어떤 통합이냐에 따라서 결렬되기도 하고 성사되기도 하다”고 했다. 이어 “그래서 그 문제로 넘어가고 있는 과정이라고 봐야 된다”며 “지금 조승래 민주당 사무총장 혹은 서왕진 혁신당 원내대표 사이에 오간 설전이 이 국면으로 넘어가고 있다는 것을 보여주는 것”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Senior Secretary Woo said, "Integration is not that easy," and added, "To integrate, there are many things to discuss, such as the leadership system and the party name." He then stated, "Now is not the time for public disputes, but for behind-the-scenes contacts between the integration negotiation representatives from both sides," and emphasized, "Otherwise, the merger will not happen." (우 전 수석은 “통합이 그렇게 쉽게 되지 않는다”며 “통합을 하려면 지도 체제, 당명 등 여러 가지 논의할 게 많다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “이제는 공개적인 설전을 할 때가 아니라 비밀리에 양쪽 통합 교섭 대표들이 물밑 접촉으로 해야 될 때”라며 “그렇지 않으면 합당이 안 이루어진다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "Even civilians fall in love and get married, but don't various conflicts arise during the marriage process? Integration goes through such a process." He said, "Therefore, it's time for those behind-the-scenes dialogues to narrow various differences of opinion." (그는 “민간인들끼리도 사랑해서 결혼을 하지만 결혼 과정에서 여러 가지 다툼이 생기지 않느냐. 통합이라는 게 그런 과정을 거친다”며 “그래서 여러 가지 견해 차이를 좁히기 위한 그런 물밑 대화를 해야 될 때”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to a question asking, 'Don't the two parties inevitably have to talk about quotas?', he said, "Quotas were discussed in past integrations 15 or 20 years ago, but these days, quota negotiations are difficult." He explained, "It's a matter that can be handled by establishing nomination rules, but negotiations involving give-and-take, for example, deciding 'local government heads will be allocated (Democratic Party) 7 to (Innovation Party) 3,' are impossible." (그는 ‘양당에서 지분 이야기를 할 수밖에 없지 않느냐’는 질문엔 “지분을 논의한 것은 과거 15년 전, 20년 전 통합 때는 그랬는데 요즘은 지분 협상은 어렵다”며 “공천룰을 가지고 진행하면 될 문제이지 주고 받는 협상을 통해서 예를 들어 ‘기초단체장을 (민주당) 7 대 (혁신당) 3으로 한다’ 이런 건 불가능하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the mention within the Democratic Party of regions where Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, might run, he said, "The issue of how to treat Leader Cho should involve listening to his opinion." He stated, "If the Democratic Party makes a proposal without even listening to Leader Cho's opinion, the negotiations will break down. We must do as Leader Cho wishes." (조국 조국혁신당 대표의 출마 지역 등이 민주당 내에서 거론되는 것 관련해서는 “조 대표를 어떻게 예우할 것인가의 문제는 조 대표의 의견을 들어야 한다”며 “조 대표의 의견도 듣지 않고 민주당이 제안하면 협상은 깨진다. 조 대표가 원하는 대로 해 줘야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242021.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500658.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:19:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Says Agreement on 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' Name "Befitting the Home of Democracy" (이 대통령, ‘전남광주특별시’ 명칭 합의에 “민주주의 본산답다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242023.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695612845995_20260128500713.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난 27일 청와대에서 국무회의를 주재하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung commented on Gwangju and Jeonnam's decision to name the integrated administrative city 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' after discussions, saying, "Dialogue, compromise, coexistence... truly befitting the home of democracy." (이재명 대통령이 광주·전남이 토론 끝에 행정통합시의 명칭을 ‘전남광주특별시’로 정한 것을 두고 “대화, 타협, 공존…과연 민주주의의 본산답다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee shared on 'X' (formerly Twitter) an article stating that Gwangju and Jeonnam, which are promoting integration, had decided on the official name of the local government as 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' and its abbreviation as 'Gwangju Special City'. He highly praised it as the 'home of democracy,' as the two local governments quickly decided on the name for the integrated administrative city after discussions. (이 대통령은 28일 ‘엑스’(X·옛 트위터)에 전날 통합을 추진 중인 광주와 전남이 자치단체 명칭을 ‘전남광주특별시’로, 약칭을 ‘광주특별시’로 정했다는 기사를 공유했다. 두 지방자치단체가 토론 끝에 행정통합시의 명칭을 빠르게 결정짓자 ‘민주주의 본산’이라며 한껏 치켜세운 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee is focusing efforts on reorganizing the country beyond the Seoul metropolitan area's single-pole system into five super-regions (Seoul metropolitan area, Southeast region, Daegu-Gyeongbuk region, Central region, Honam region) and three special self-governing provinces (Gangwon, Jeonbuk, Jeju). At a New Year's press conference on the 21st, he emphasized, "The great shift to 'region-led growth' has already begun," and added, "The 'regional integration' currently being pursued is a symbolic starting point for region-led growth and a national survival strategy that must succeed." (이 대통령은 수도권 일극 체제를 벗어나 전국을 5개의 초광역권(수도권·동남권·대경권·중부권·호남권)과 3개의 특별자치도(강원·전북·제주)로 재편하는 데 공을 들이고 있다. 이 대통령은 지난 21일 신년 기자회견에서 “‘지방 주도 성장’으로의 대전환은 이미 시작됐다”며 “현재 추진 중인 ‘광역 통합’은 지방 주도 성장의 상징적 출발점이자, 반드시 성공시켜야 할 국가 생존 전략”이라고 강조하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242023.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695612845995_20260128500713.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:19:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Nomination Contribution Woes' Democratic Party: "Excluding National Assembly Members from City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committees" (‘공천헌금 몸살’ 민주 “시·도당 공관위에 국회의원 배제”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/416/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500993.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에서 고 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 지키며 조문객을 맞이하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea decided on the 28th to form City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committees (NMCs) that largely exclude incumbent National Assembly members and regional party chairpersons. (더불어민주당이 28일 현역 국회의원과 지역위원장을 대부분 배제한 시도당 공직선거후보자추천관리위원회(공관위)를 구성하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a closed-door Supreme Council meeting at Seoul National University Hospital that day, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun met with reporters and announced that a proposal regarding the City/Provincial Party NMCs with this content had been passed. He explained, "It would be no exaggeration to say that in the past, City/Provincial Party NMCs were composed of more than half regional chairpersons, including incumbent National Assembly members, with the remaining external members being at a formalistic level." He added, "The central party had issued guidelines to City/Provincial parties to minimize the inclusion of incumbent Assembly members and regional chairpersons. Accordingly, a feature of this round of City/Provincial Party NMCs is that they are composed almost entirely of external figures, excluding incumbent Assembly members and regional chairpersons, aiming for objectivity and neutrality." (박수현 수석대변인은 이날 서울대병원에서 비공개 최고위원회를 마친 후 기자들과 만나 이런 내용의 시도당 공관위 건을 의결했다고 밝혔다. 그는 “과거 시도당 공관위는 현역 국회의원 포함한 지역위원장이 절반 이상이고 나머지 외부인사는 형식적인 수준에서 구성됐다고 해도 과언이 아니었다”며 “현역 국회의원과 지역위원장 최소화 방침을 중앙당이 시도당에 지침을 내린 바 있고, 그에 따라 이번 시도당 공관위는 현역 의원과 지역위원장을 거의 배제하고 외부 인사로 객관적, 중립적으로 구성된 것이 특징”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is interpreted as a measure to minimize the influence incumbent Assembly members can exert within the NMCs. This comes as the Democratic Party's nomination process is facing credibility issues, following allegations that Assembly member Kang Seon-woo, who was a member of the Seoul City Party NMC during the 2022 local elections, received 100 million won from then-Seoul City Council candidate Kim Kyeong. (이는 현역 의원이 공관위에 영향력을 행사하는 것을 최소화하려는 조치로 풀이된다. 2022년 지방선거 당시 서울시당 공관위원이었던 강선우 의원이 김경 당시 서울시의원 후보자로부터 1억원을 받았다는 의혹이 불거지면서 민주당 공천 과정에 대한 신뢰도가 지적받고 있는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park further explained, "The central party's NMC, through a resolution on the 'Rules for the Operation of Public Office Candidate Nominations' the previous day (27th), decided on rules related to the composition, meetings, reviews, and operation of candidate nomination bodies, as well as the preservation, inspection, and disposal of meeting and review records. This makes it clearer that these records must be preserved for the next four years." (박 수석대변인은 또 “중앙당 공관위가 전날(27일) 공직선거후보자추천운영규칙 의결을 통해 공직선거후보자추천기구의 구성, 회의, 심사 및 위원회 운영, 그리고 회의 심사 기록보존, 기록 열람 및 폐기 등 관련 규칙을 의결해 좀 더 명확하게 향후 4년까지 이 기록을 보존하도록 했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is seen as an attempt to address shortcomings, as the Democratic Party, ahead of the 2024 general election, not only lacked the 'petition' submitted to the party regarding allegations of Assembly member Kim Byeong-gi receiving money and valuables, but also had no records of the receipt and handling of all petitions, complaints, and tips at the time. After a Supreme Council meeting on people's livelihood issues in Songpa-gu, Seoul on the 7th, Chief Spokesperson Park had told reporters, "During nominations and elections, hundreds of petitions, complaints, tips, and defamations are received in a very short period. We are now looking back on whether those were handled properly." (이는 민주당이 2024년 총선을 앞두고 당에 제출된 김병기 의원의 금품 수수 의혹 ‘탄원서’뿐 아니라 당시 모든 탄원, 민원, 제보의 접수 및 처리 기록이 없다고 한 점을 보완하려는 시도로 풀이된다. 박 수석대변인은 지난 7일 서울 송파구 민생 현장 최고위원회의 뒤 기자들과 만나 “공천과 선거 때는 아주 짧은 시간에 수백 건 이상 탄원, 민원, 제보, 비방이 접수되는데 그것들을 잘 처리했는가 하는 점을 이번에 돌아보게 됐다”고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Chae-un &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242026.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/416/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500993.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:18:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoon Geon-young: "Kim Keon-hee Should Receive a Sentence 'Higher' Than the 15 Years Sought by Prosecution" (윤건영 “김건희, 구형 15년보다 형량 ‘올려치기’ 선고 받아야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242027.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/538/419/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695645931344_20260128501018.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김건희 여사가 지난해 9월24일 오후 서울 서초구 서울중앙지법에서 열린 첫 재판에 출석해 최지우 변호사와 이야기를 나누고 있다. 김 여사는 왼쪽 가슴에 ‘수용번호 4398’이 적힌 배지를 달았다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the first-instance sentencing for former President Yoon Suk-yeol's wife, Kim Keon-hee, the ruling party is urging that a sentence higher than the 15 years sought by the special prosecutor be handed down. (윤석열 전 대통령 부인 김건희 여사에 대한 1심 선고를 앞두고, 여당은 특검이 구형한 15년보다 더 높은 형량이 선고돼야 한다고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Yoon Geon-young said in an interview with CBS Radio's 'Park Jae-hong's Hanpan Victory' on the 27th, "The court should strictly enforce the law and hand down a sentence (higher than the prosecution's request)." Lawmaker Yoon stated, "(Kim Keon-hee) was essentially V0, wasn't she the one who meddled in state affairs?" and added, "Currently, the (15 years sought by the special prosecutor) is 11 years for stock price manipulation and 4 years for violating the Political Funds Act, making 15 years, but the charge of meddling in state affairs is missing." Lawmaker Yoon further added, "There are too many unrevealed additional crimes," and "(the sentence should be) higher than the prosecution's request." (윤건영 더불어민주당 의원은 27일 시비에스(CBS) 라디오 ‘박재홍의 한판승부’와의 인터뷰에서 “재판부에서 엄정하게 법을 집행해서 (구형보다) 올려치기 해야 한다”고 말했다. 윤 의원은 “(김건희는) 사실상 브이제로(V0)로서 국정농단을 한 것 아니냐”며 “지금 (특검이 구형한) 15년이 주가 조작 11년, 정치자금법 4년 해서 15년인데 국정농단죄가 빠져있다”고 말했다. 윤 의원은 “지금까지 밝혀지지 않은 여죄가 너무 많다”며 “(선고 형량은 구형보다) 올려치기가 필요하다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Seoul Central District Court's Criminal Division 27 (Presiding Judge Woo In-seong) will hold the first-instance sentencing hearing for Mrs. Kim's case involving violations of the Capital Markets Act and the Political Funds Act, and bribery mediation under the Act on the Aggravated Punishment of Specific Crimes, starting at 2:10 PM on the 28th. Last month on the 3rd, during the final trial arguments, the special prosecutor sought 11 years in prison, a fine of 2 billion won, and forfeiture of 811.44 million won for the charges related to Deutsche Motors stock price manipulation and receiving money and valuables from the Unification Church, and 4 years in prison and forfeiture of 137.2 million won for the charge of receiving unpaid opinion polls. (서울중앙지법 형사27부(재판장 우인성)는 28일 오후 2시10분부터 김 여사의 자본시장법·정치자금법 위반, 특정범죄가중처벌법의 알선수재 혐의 사건 1심 선고기일을 연다. 특검은 지난달 3일 결심공판에서 도이치모터스 주가조작과 통일교 금품 수수 혐의에 대해 징역 11년과 벌금 20억원, 추징금 8억1144만원을, 무상 여론조사 수수 혐의에 대해선 징역 4년과 추징금 1억3720만원을 각각 구형했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Jeon Hyeon-hee also urged severe punishment in an interview with MBC's 'News Extra' on the 27th, saying, "Kim Keon-hee has been widely evaluated as the de facto president with much more authority than President Yoon Suk-yeol." Lawmaker Jeon said, "(Kim Keon-hee's charges) are not simply personal crimes but power-type crimes that abused presidential power," and added, "Perhaps the sentence will be a bit more than that (the prosecution's request)." Lawmaker Jeon further stated, "Because the criminal charges Kim Keon-hee is facing are extremely serious and are crimes that have caused public anger and outrage, a slightly stronger sentence is expected." (전현희 민주당 의원도 27일 문화방송(MBC) ‘뉴스외전’과의 인터뷰에서 “김건희씨가 윤석열 대통령보다 훨씬 더 권한을 가진 사실상의 대통령이라는 평가를 많이 받았다”며 엄벌을 촉구했다. 전 의원은 “(김건희의 혐의는) 단순한 개인의 범죄가 아니라 대통령 권력을 악용한 권력형 범죄”라며 “아마 그(구형)보다 좀 더 많이 선고하지 않을까”라고 말했다. 전 의원은 “김건희씨가 받는 범죄 혐의가 굉장히 중대하고 또 국민들의 분노, 공분을 사는 그런 범죄였기 때문에 조금 더 강한 선고가 되지 않을까”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party spokesperson Jang Yun-mi said during a briefing at the National Assembly on the 27th, "For Kim Keon-hee, who placed herself above the law, severe punishment is the only way to establish judicial justice." Spokesperson Jang stated, "For Kim Keon-hee, who shook the foundations of the Republic of Korea—the capitalist market order, democracy, and the principle of separation of church and state—nothing remains but severe punishment," and added, "Kim Keon-hee consistently denied the charges throughout the trial, but when the evidence became overwhelming and denial was no longer possible, she belatedly confessed to receiving a Chanel bag. There is no room for leniency." (장윤미 민주당 대변인은 27일 국회에서 브리핑을 열고 “법 위에 군림한 김건희, 엄벌만이 사법정의를 세우는 길”이라고 말했다. 장 대변인은 “대한민국의 근간인 자본주의 시장질서, 민주주의, 정교분리의 원칙을 뒤흔든 김건희에게 남은 것은 엄벌밖에 없다”며 “김건희는 재판 내내 부인으로 일관하다 증거가 차고 넘쳐 더 이상은 부인하기가 어렵게 되자 샤넬 가방을 받은 사실을 뒤늦게 실토하기도 했다. 선처의 여지가 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the first-instance sentencing for Mrs. Kim is scheduled to be broadcast live. (한편, 김 여사에 대한 1심 선고는 생중계될 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Kyung-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242027.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/538/419/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695645931344_20260128501018.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:18:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong Wa Dae Welcomes "Meaningful Progress" as China Moves Some West Sea Structures (청와대, 중국 서해 구조물 일부 이동에 “의미 있는 진전 환영”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242032.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/889/567/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501214.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;중국이 서해 한중 잠정조치수역에 설치한 구조물 선란 2호에서 중국 쪽 인원들이 작업하는 모습. 이병진 더불어민주당 의원실 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheong Wa Dae stated that it "welcomes as meaningful progress" China's measure to move a management facility, among its West Sea structures, outside the Korea-China Provisional Measures Zone (PMZ). (중국이 서해구조물 가운데 관리시설을 한·중 잠정조치수역(PMZ) 밖으로 이동시키는 조처를 한 것에 대해 청와대가 “의미있는 진전으로 환영한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cheong Wa Dae spokesperson's office announced through a press release on the 28th, "The Chinese government announced yesterday that the management platform installed within the Provisional Measures Zone is being moved by a Chinese company according to its own needs," and added, "Our government, maintaining the position of opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measures Zone, has continued consultations with China. Given that this management platform has been a central point of various concerns, we welcome this measure as meaningful progress." (청와대 대변인실은 28일 언론 공지를 통해 “중국 정부는 어제 잠정조치수역 내에 설치된 관리플랫폼을 중국 측 기업이 자체적인 수요에 따라 이동시키고 있다고 발표했다”며 “우리 정부는 잠정조치수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치를 반대한다는 입장 아래 중국과의 협의를 이어왔으며 그간 해당 관리플랫폼이 여러 우려의 중심이 되어온 만큼, 이번 조치를 의미 있는 진전으로 환영한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;China has in the West Sea Provisional Measures Zone Seolan 1 and 2, which it claims are aquaculture facilities in the form of steel structures, and a seabed-fixed structure which it claims is a management facility. All three structures are located within the Provisional Measures Zone where the Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ) of Korea and China overlap, and are artificial maritime facilities built by China without consultation with Korea. (중국은 서해 잠정조치수역 내에 양식시설이라고 주장하는 철제 구조물 형태의 선란 1·2호와 관리시설이라고 주장하는 해저 고정식 구조물을 두고 있다. 구조물 3기 모두 한국과 중국의 배타적경제수역(EEZ)이 겹치는 잠정조치수역에 위치하고 있고, 한국과 협의 없이 중국이 세운 인공 해상 시설이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The previous day, Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Geng Shuang stated at a regular briefing, "Chinese companies are currently conducting work related to the management platform," and that "the companies have autonomously adjusted the deployment according to their own operational and development needs." This indicates that China has stated it moved the management facility among the structures installed in the Provisional Measures Zone. Kang Young-shin, Director-General of the Northeast Asian Affairs Bureau at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, who is in charge of China affairs, also stated on the same day, "This measure is a change helpful to the development of Korea-China relations," and "Our government, maintaining the position of opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measures Zone, has continued consultations with China. Therefore, we evaluate this measure as meaningful progress." (전날 궈자쿤 중국 외교부 대변인은 정례 브리핑에서 “중국 기업이 현재 관리 플랫폼과 관련된 작업을 진행 중”이라며 “기업이 자체적인 경영·발전 필요에 따라 자율적으로 배치를 조정한 것”이라고 밝혔다. 잠정조치수역에 설치된 구조물 중 관리시설을 옮겼다고 중국 쪽에서 밝힌 것이다. 중국을 담당하는 강영신 외교부 동북아 국장도 같은 날 “이번 조치는 한중관계 발전에 도움이 되는 변화”라며 “우리 정부는 잠정조치 수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치 반대 입장하에 그동안 대중국 협의를 이어온 만큼 이번 조치를 의미있는 진전으로 평가한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, as there was no mention from China regarding Seolan 1 and 2 among the structures, the embers of conflict remain. Cheong Wa Dae stated, "The government will continue its efforts to actively protect our maritime rights and interests in the West Sea and to make the West Sea a sea of peace and shared prosperity." (다만 구조물 가운데 선란 1, 2호에 대한 중국의 언급은 없어 갈등의 불씨는 남은 상태다. 청와대는 “정부는 서해에서 우리의 해양 권익을 적극 수호하는 가운데 서해를 평화롭고 공영하는 바다로 만들어나가기 위한 노력을 계속해 나갈 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242032.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/889/567/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501214.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:18:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>