<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:43:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>KOSDAQ Soars 7% in a Day, Easily Breaches '1000 KOSDAQ' Mark... Highest Since 2000 'Dot-com Bubble' (하루 7%↑ 코스닥, 가뿐히 ‘천스닥’ 돌파…2000년 ‘닷컴 버블’ 이후 최고)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241710.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSDAQ Soars 7% in a Day, Easily Breaches '1000 KOSDAQ' Mark... Highest Since 2000 'Dot-com Bubble' (하루 7%↑ 코스닥, 가뿐히 ‘천스닥’ 돌파…2000년 ‘닷컴 버블’ 이후 최고)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694156849616_3517694155614805.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;26일 오후 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸 전광판에 원-달러 환율과 코스피, 코스닥 지수가 표시돼 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ index surged 7% in a single day, reaching the '1000 KOSDAQ' level for the first time in four years. (코스닥지수가 하루 7% 급등하며 4년 만에 ‘천스닥’ 고지에 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Korea Exchange (KRX) data on the 26th, the KOSDAQ index closed at 1064.41, up 70.48 points (7.09%) from the previous trading day (23rd). This marks the highest closing level in 25 years and 5 months since September 6, 2000 (1074.10). The market capitalization increased by 38.9 trillion won to a record high of 582.9 trillion won. This is the first time the index has surpassed 1000 since January 5, 2021 (1009.62), a gap of four years. (26일 한국거래소 집계를 보면, 코스닥 지수는 전거래일(23일)보다 70.48(7.09%) 오른 1064.41에 장을 마쳤다. 종가 기준 2000년 9월6일(1074.10) 이후 25년5개월 만에 최고치다. 시가총액은 전날보다 38조9천억원 늘어난 582조9천억원으로 사상 최고치를 썼다. 지수가 1000을 넘은 건 2021년 1월5일(1009.62) 이후 4년 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ index opened at 1003.90, up 9.97 points (1.00%) from the previous close, and continued to widen its gains throughout the session. The sharp rise triggered a temporary halt in program sell orders, known as a 'buy-side circuit breaker', in the morning. In contrast, the KOSPI briefly surpassed 5000 in early trading but closed at 4949.59, down 40.48 points (0.81%) from the previous trading day. (이날 코스닥 지수는 장이 열리자마자 9.97(1.00%) 오른 1003.90으로 시작해 줄곧 상승 폭을 키웠다. 지수가 급등하면서 오전 한때 프로그램 매매호가 효력이 일시 정지되는 ‘매수 사이드카’가 발동되기도 했다. 반면 코스피는 장초반 다시 5000을 넘겼다가 전거래일 대비 40.48(0.81%) 내린 4949.59에 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ market gained strong momentum as ample market liquidity and investor sentiment, following the KOSPI's historic first breach of the 5000 level, spread to small and mid-cap growth stocks. Strong net buying, led by institutional investors (net purchase of 2.6 trillion won), flowed in as expectations for government policies supporting the KOSDAQ market grew. Analysts assess that expectations for policy support—such as the government/ruling party's 'KOSDAQ 3000' proposal, the launch of the 'National Growth Fund' to invest in venture companies and venture capital, and the expansion of the National Pension Service's investments—to benefit KOSDAQ companies played a role. (코스피가 사상 처음 5000선을 돌파한 뒤 풍부한 증시 대기 자금과 투자 심리가 중소형 성장주로 확산되면서 코스닥 시장도 강세 흐름을 탔다. 코스닥 시장에 대한 정부 정책 기대감이 커지면서 기관투자자(2조6천억 순매수) 중심으로 강한 순환매가 유입됐다. 정부·여당의 ‘코스닥 3000’ 제안과 함께 벤처기업과 모험자본에 투자하는 ‘국민성장펀드’ 출범, 국민연금의 투자 확대 등 정책적 뒷받침이 코스닥 기업들의 수혜로 이어질 것이란 기대감이 작용했다는 평가가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The won-dollar exchange rate fell sharply by over 25 won (won appreciation), influenced by the yen's strength. In the Seoul foreign exchange market, the won-dollar exchange rate closed the week's trading at 1440.6 won, down 25.2 won from the previous trading day (1465.80 won). It fell for four consecutive trading days since the 21st, dropping to levels seen in early November (1437.9 won on November 4th). It declined in tandem as the yen showed extreme strength over the weekend amid signs of intervention by US and Japanese foreign exchange authorities. The yen-dollar exchange rate, which approached 160 yen last week, fell to the low 155-yen range today. Amid the dollar's weak trend and heightened global geopolitical risks, the price of gold, a typical safe-haven asset, surpassed $5,000 per ounce for the first time ever. In the afternoon, the spot price in the international gold market traded at $5,069.5 per ounce, up $50 from the previous day. Gold prices have risen over 15% this year. (원-달러 환율은 엔화 강세 영향으로 25원 넘게 하락(원화 강세)했다. 이날 서울외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 전거래일(1465.80원) 대비 25.2원 급락한 1440.6원에 주간거래를 마쳤다. 지난 21일 이후 4거래일 연속 하락해 11월 초(11월4일 1437.9원) 수준으로 낮아졌다. 주말 사이 미국과 일본 외환당국의 개입 조짐에 엔화가 초강세를 보이면서 동반 하락했다. 지난주 160엔을 육박한 엔-달러 환율은 이날 155엔대 초반까지 떨어졌다. 달러 약세 흐름 속에 글로벌 지정학적 리스크가 가세하면서 대표적인 안전 자산인 금값은 사상 처음 온스당 5000달러를 넘어섰다. 이날 오후 국제 금시장 현물 가격은 전날보다 50달러 급등한 온스당 5069.5달러에 거래됐다. 올해 들어 금값은 15%이상 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 조계완 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241710.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694156849616_3517694155614805.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Kosdaq 1000' on Policy Hopes... For 'Individual Day-Trading Market' to Overcome Limits, Earnings Backing is Essential (정책 기대감에 ‘천스닥’…‘개인 단타시장’ 한계 넘으려면 실적 뒷받침 필수)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241721.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'Kosdaq 1000' on Policy Hopes... For 'Individual Day-Trading Market' to Overcome Limits, Earnings Backing is Essential (정책 기대감에 ‘천스닥’…‘개인 단타시장’ 한계 넘으려면 실적 뒷받침 필수)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503195.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스닥 지수가 1000을 넘은 26일 오후 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸에서 직원들이 기념 행사를 하고 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just three days after the KOSPI on the main board broke through '5,000-pi' (5000) during trading, the Kosdaq market also achieved '1,000-sdaq' (1000). (유가증권시장에서 코스피가 장중 ‘오천피’(5000)를 돌파한 지 사흘 만에 코스닥 시장도 ‘천스닥’(1000)을 달성했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, the Kosdaq index hit 1000 at the opening and continued to set new highs throughout the day, closing with a sharp gain of over 7%. While leading stocks like semiconductors and automobiles, which had surged sharply earlier this year, were taking a breather, bio and secondary battery stocks in the Kosdaq market pushed the index higher. Secondary battery stocks saw buying interest on expectations for demand for robot batteries, while bio stocks attracted buying as perceptions of undervaluation spread. Samsung Securities assessed, "As supply and demand shifted from large-cap stocks, which showed relative strength this year, to small and mid-cap stocks, the Kosdaq, which had underperformed compared to the KOSPI, recorded a high rate of increase." An analysis suggests that while the KOSPI rose 108% from its low in April last year, the Kosdaq only rose about 60%, and as the concentration in KOSPI large-caps eased, supply and demand are moving to previously neglected small and mid-cap stocks like bio and secondary batteries. (26일 코스닥지수는 개장과 동시에 1000을 찍고 줄곧 고점을 높여 7% 넘게 급등 마감했다. 올 들어 단기 급등한 반도체·자동차 등 대장주가 숨고르기를 하는 동안 코스닥 시장의 바이오와 이차전지 종목들이 지수를 밀어올렸다. 이차전지는 로봇용 배터리 수요 기대감에, 바이오주는 저평가 인식이 퍼지면서 매수세가 몰렸다. 삼성증권은 “올해 상대적 강세를 보였던 대형주에서 중소형주로 수급이 이동하면서 코스피 대비 부진했던 코스닥이 높은 상승률을 기록했다”고 평가했다. 지난해 4월 저점 기준 코스피가 108% 상승하는 동안 코스닥은 60%가량 오르는 데 그쳤는데, 코스피 대형주로 쏠림이 완화되자 그간 소외됐던 바이오와 이차전지 등 중소형주로 수급이 이동 중이란 분석이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domestic institutional investors showed explosive buying. In the Kosdaq market, institutions net purchased 2.6009 trillion won in a single day. This is the largest daily net purchase amount on record. Foreign investors also net purchased 443.4 billion won. Individual investors net sold a record 2.9072 trillion won, realizing profits. Top stocks by market capitalization surged simultaneously. Medytox (29.55%), Rainbow Robotics (25.97%), EcoPro (22.95%), ABL Bio (21.72%), EcoPro BM (19.91%), and Caregen (16.94%) showed relatively large gains. (국내 기관투자자가 폭발적인 매수세를 보였다. 코스닥 시장에서 기관은 이날 하루 2조6009억원을 순매수했다. 일별 순매수 규모 역대 최대치다. 외국인도 4434억원을 순매수했다. 개인은 역대 최대 규모인 2조9072억원을 순매도하며 차익을 실현했다. 시가총액 상위주는 일제히 급등했다. 메지온(29.55%), 레인보우로보틱스(25.97%), 에코프로(22.95%), 에이비엘바이오(21.72%), 에코프로비엠(19.91%), 케어젠(16.94%) 등의 상승률이 상대적으로 컸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until now, while the number of listed companies and market capitalization of the Kosdaq market have grown externally, it has solidified into a market centered on individual day-trading since the early 2000s IT bubble. Although the index rose about 30% last year due to the stock market boom, it fell short of half the KOSPI's increase (76%). In the securities industry, there is an assessment that the government's policies to vitalize the Kosdaq are behind the bullish trend. (그간 코스닥 시장은 상장기업 수와 시가총액 등 외형은 늘었지만 2000년대 초 정보통신(IT) 버블 이후 개인 중심 단타 시장으로 굳어져왔다. 지난해 증시 활황으로 약 30%가량 지수가 올랐지만, 코스피 상승률(76%)의 절반에 미치지 못했다. 증권가에선 정부의 코스닥 활성화 정책이 활황세의 배경이 되고 있다는 진단이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government announced a plan last month to improve the constitution of the Kosdaq market, and recently, the ruling Democratic Party of Korea set 'Kosdaq 3000' as a target. The government decided to introduce a special listing system for core technology companies to innovate the structure that makes it difficult for growth companies to enter. To facilitate the swift exit of underperforming companies, it decided to immediately strengthen the market capitalization threshold for delisting (from 4 billion to 15 billion won) starting this year. It also presented incentives for institutional investors like pension funds to invest in the Kosdaq. This is a plan to reflect the Kosdaq index in the performance benchmarks applied when evaluating major pension funds like the National Pension Service and the Government Employees Pension Service. In this case, pension funds would have a greater incentive to consider Kosdaq investments during their asset allocation process. (정부는 지난달 코스닥 시장 체질 개선 방안을 발표했고, 최근 여당인 더불어민주당이 ‘코스닥 3000’을 목표로 제시했다. 정부는 성장기업이 들어오기 어려운 구조를 혁신하기 위해 핵심기술 기업의 특례상장 제도를 도입하기로 했다. 부실기업의 신속한 퇴출을 위해 상장폐지 시가총액 기준은 당장 올해부터 강화(40억→150억원)하기로 했다. 연기금 등 기관투자자의 코스닥 투자 유인책도 내놨다. 국민연금·공무원연금 등 주요 연기금을 평가할 때 적용하는 성과 기준에 코스닥 지수를 반영하는 방안인데, 이 경우 연기금이 자산 배분 과정에서 코스닥 투자를 고려할 유인이 커질 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are observations that for the Kosdaq market to level up, earnings backing and an increase in the proportion of foreign and institutional investors are essential. Currently, the foreign ownership ratio in the Kosdaq market's total market capitalization has not exceeded 10% since 2020. The foreign ownership ratio in the KOSPI is 37.18%, the highest level in five years. Last year, foreigners also net sold 2.019 trillion won worth of stocks in the Kosdaq market. Kim Kyung-tae, a researcher at Sangsangin Securities, said, "The government's 'Kosdaq 1000' policy and the expansion of pension fund investment in the Kosdaq are positive, but the key drivers to attract foreigners and institutions are ultimately earnings and constitutional improvement." According to FnGuide's compilation, the operating profit of Kosdaq-listed companies this year is projected to be 14.9218 trillion won, a 62.9% increase compared to the previous year. (코스닥 시장이 한 단계 레벨업 하려면 실적 뒷받침과 외국인과 기관의 비중 확대가 필수적이라는 지적이 나온다. 현재 코스닥시장 시가총액 중 외국인 비중은 2020년 이후 10%를 넘지 못하고 있다. 코스피의 외국인 보유 비중은 37.18%로 5년 만에 최고 수준이다. 지난해에도 외국인은 코스닥 시장에서 2조19억원어치를 순매도했다. 김경태 상상인증권 연구원은 “정부의 ‘천스닥’ 정책과 연기금의 코스닥 투자 확대는 긍정적이지만, 외국인과 기관을 끌어들이는 핵심 동인은 결국 실적과 체질 개선”이라고 말했다. 에프앤가이드 집계를 보면, 코스닥 상장사의 올해 영업이익은 14조9218억원으로 전년 대비 62.9% 증가할 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241721.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503195.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] Police Launch Preliminary Investigation into AliExpress '86 Billion Won Settlement Fund' Hacking Incident ([단독] 경찰, 알리 ‘정산금 86억원’ 해킹사고 내사 착수)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241727.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[Exclusive] Police Launch Preliminary Investigation into AliExpress '86 Billion Won Settlement Fund' Hacking Incident ([단독] 경찰, 알리 ‘정산금 86억원’ 해킹사고 내사 착수)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694168311272_20260126503261.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지뱅크&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The police have launched a preliminary investigation into the hacking incident involving AliExpress (hereinafter referred to as Ali) sellers' settlement funds that occurred last October. (경찰이 지난해 10월 발생한 알리익스프레스(이하 알리)의 셀러 정산금 해킹 사고에 대해 내사에 착수했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to 'materials related to the Ali breach incident' received by the office of Representative Lee Hae-min of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party from the National Police Agency on the 26th, the Incheon Police Agency commenced a pre-case registration investigation into Ali's hacking incident on the 20th. In these materials, the National Police Agency stated, "We plan to investigate the specific intrusion methods, among other details," and clarified that "there has been no receipt of a complaint or accusation from Ali." An Ali official said on this day, "While reviewing whether to file a police report, we received a request for data submission from the police. We are submitting the relevant materials and cooperating with the investigation." ( 26일 이해민 조국혁신당 의원실이 경찰청에서 받은 ‘알리 침해사고 관련 자료’를 보면, 인천경찰청은 지난 20일 알리의 해킹 사고에 대해 입건 전 조사에 착수했다. 이 자료에서 경찰청은 “구체적인 침입 방법 등에 대해 조사 예정”이라며 “알리 측의 고소 및 고발 접수 사실은 없다”고 밝혔다. 알리 관계자는 이날 “경찰 신고 여부를 검토하는 과정에서 경찰의 자료 제출 요청이 있었다. 관련 자료를 제출하며 조사에 협조하고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hacking incident of Ali sellers' settlement funds was belatedly revealed through a Hankyoreh report on the 19th. It is a case where last October, the account information of sellers operating on Ali was hacked, and hackers intercepted 8.6 billion won in settlement funds that should have been paid to the sellers. (알리의 셀러 정산금 해킹 사고는 지난 19일 한겨레 보도로 뒤늦게 알려졌다. 지난해 10월 알리의 입점 판매자(셀러) 계좌 정보가 해킹당하면서 셀러들에게 지급해야 할 정산금 86억원을 해커가 가로챈 사건이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although Ali stated in a report submitted to the Korea Internet &amp; Security Agency immediately after the incident occurred that it "reported to the police," it was revealed through Hankyoreh's reporting that it had not actually reported the damage to investigative authorities. At the time, an Ali official said, "The financial loss incurred from this incident was fully borne by Ali, and with seller protection as the top priority, no actual financial loss occurred for the sellers." They also stated, "Customer data is safe, and it has been confirmed that no personal information was leaked or compromised due to this incident." (알리는 사건 발생 직후 한국인터넷진흥원에 제출한 신고서에서 “경찰에 신고했다”고 밝혔으나, 실제로는 수사기관에 피해 사실을 신고하지 않은 사실도 한겨레 취재로 드러난 바 있다. 당시 알리 관계자는 “이번 사안으로 발생한 재정적 손실은 알리가 전액 부담했으며, 셀러 보호를 최우선으로 해 셀러에게는 어떠한 실질적인 자금 손실도 발생하지 않았다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “고객 데이터는 안전하며, 이번 사안으로 인해 어떠한 개인정보도 유출되거나 침해된 사실은 없는 것으로 확인됐다”고 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, Representative Lee Hae-min said, "Ali wrote 'unconfirmed' for the time of the incident in its report. It is a perilous notion to conclude that 'there is no harm to the public' without even knowing the initial intrusion time of the hackers," adding, "The investigative authorities must thoroughly ascertain the basic facts, including when the hacking began." (이에 대해 이해민 의원은 “알리는 신고서에 사고 발생 시점을 ‘확인 불가’라고 적었다. 해커의 최초 침입 시점도 모르는 상태에서 ‘국민 피해는 없다’고 단정 짓는 건 위험천만한 발상”이라며 “수사당국은 해킹 시작 시점을 포함한 기본적인 사실들을 철저하게 규명해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241727.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694168311272_20260126503261.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fund Net Assets Reach 1,376 Trillion Won Amid Stock Market 'Bull Run'... Largest Growth in 18 Years (증시 ‘불장’에 펀드 순자산 1376조원…18년 만에 최대 성장)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241736.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Fund Net Assets Reach 1,376 Trillion Won Amid Stock Market 'Bull Run'... Largest Growth in 18 Years (증시 ‘불장’에 펀드 순자산 1376조원…18년 만에 최대 성장)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694176760687_20260126503306.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The total net asset value of all domestic and overseas investment funds (public and private) at the end of December last year was counted at 1,376.3 trillion won, an increase of 277.6 trillion won compared to the end of 2024 (1,098.7 trillion won). The total net asset value increased across all investment types, including equity and bond funds, with the proportion of equity funds significantly rising due to the strong performance of the KOSPI. (지난해 12월 말 국내 및 해외투자 전체 펀드(공·사모)의 순자산총액이 1376조3천억원으로 2024년 말(1098조7천억원) 대비 277조6천억원 증가한 것으로 집계됐다. 주식형·채권형 등 모든 투자유형에서 순자산총액이 증가했고, 코스피 호조로 주식형 펀드 비중이 크게 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Financial Investment Association, in its '2025 Fund Market Settlement' data released on the 26th, analyzed, "Both public and private funds saw their net assets increase rapidly compared to the end of the previous year, leading the entire fund market to record its highest growth rate (25.3%) since 2007 (31.9%)." By investment type, the increase in total net asset value compared to the end of the previous year was in the order of equity funds (102.5 trillion won), bond funds (42.9 trillion won), and fund-of-funds (28.2 trillion won). (금융투자협회는 26일 ‘2025년 펀드시장 결산’ 자료에서 “공·사모펀드 모두 전년 말 대비 순자산이 빠르게 증가해 전체 펀드시장은 2007년(31.9%) 이후 가장 높은 성장률(25.3%)을 기록했다”고 분석했다. 투자 유형별로 전년 말 대비 순자산총액 증가분은 주식형(102조5천억원), 채권형(42조9천억원), 재간접형(28조2천억원) 순이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, due to factors like last year's strong stock market performance, the proportion of equity funds among all funds reached 17.2%, a 5 percentage point increase from the end of the previous year (12.2%). The proportion by type within the total fund net asset value is equity funds (17.2%), bond funds (15.7%), and money market funds (MMF, 14.2%). At the end of 2024, this order was real estate (16.5%), bond funds (15.7%), and money market funds (15.4%). (특히 지난해 증시 호조 등으로 전체 펀드 중 주식형 펀드가 차지하는 비중은 17.2%로, 전년 말(12.2%)보다 5%p 증가했다. 전체 펀드 순자산총액에서 유형별 비중은 주식형(17.2%), 채권형(15.7%), 머니마켓펀드(MMF·14.2%) 순이다. 2024년 말에는 이 비중이 부동산(16.5%), 채권형(15.7%), 머니마켓펀드(15.4%) 순이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout last year, based on all funds (public and private), all types saw net inflows of funds (total 168.9 trillion won). (작년 한 해 동안 전체 펀드(공·사모) 기준 모든 유형에서 자금이 순유입(총 168조9천억원)됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of December last year, the total net asset value of domestic investment funds was 872.2 trillion won, accounting for 63.4% of the total. This is an increase of 174.9 trillion won compared to the previous year. The total net asset value of overseas investment funds was 504.1 trillion won, accounting for 36.6% of the total. (지난해 12월 말 국내 투자 펀드 순자산총액은 872조2천억원으로, 전체의 63.4%를 차지했다. 전년보다 174조9천억원 늘었다. 해외 투자 펀드 순자산총액은 504조1천억원으로 전체의 36.6%를 차지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The total net asset value of public funds was 609.4 trillion won, an increase of 173.8 trillion won (39.9%) compared to the end of the previous year (435.5 trillion won). The total net asset value of exchange-traded funds (ETFs) was 297.1 trillion won, an increase of 123.6 trillion won (71.2%) compared to the end of the previous year (173.6 trillion won). The total net asset value of private funds was 766.9 trillion won, an increase of 103.8 trillion won (15.6%) compared to the end of the previous year (663.2 trillion won). (공모펀드 순자산총액은 609조4천억원으로 전년 말(435조5천억원) 대비 173조8천억원(39.9%) 증가했다. 상장지수펀드(ETF) 순자산총액은 297조1천억원으로 전년 말(173조6천억원) 대비 123조6천억원(71.2%) 증가했다. 사모펀드 순자산총액은 766조9천억원으로 전년 말(663조2천억원) 대비 103조8천억원(15.6%) 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241736.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694176760687_20260126503306.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Diesel Exports Hit Record High Last Year... Aviation Fuel Exports to the U.S. Show Prominent Growth (지난해 경유 수출 사상 최대치…항공유, 대미 수출 증가세 두드러져)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241737.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Diesel Exports Hit Record High Last Year... Aviation Fuel Exports to the U.S. Show Prominent Growth (지난해 경유 수출 사상 최대치…항공유, 대미 수출 증가세 두드러져)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694177649131_20260126503315.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;전남 여수 석유비축기지 추가 지상탱크 전경. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, diesel exports from South Korea's four major refiners surpassed 202 million barrels, setting a new all-time high. This represents a 0.4% increase compared to the 201.66 million barrels exported the previous year. (지난해 국내 정유 4사의 경유 수출이 2억200만 배럴을 넘어서면서 역대 최대치를 기록했다. 이는 전년 2억166만 배럴 대비 0.4% 증가한 수준이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Petroleum Association announced on the 26th that the four refiners—SK Energy, GS Caltex, S-Oil, and HD Hyundai Oilbank—exported 202.37 million barrels of diesel last year, setting a new annual export record. (대한석유협회는 에스케이(SK)에너지, 지에스(GS)칼텍스, 에쓰오일, 에이치디(HD)현대오일뱅크 등 정유 4사가 지난해 수출한 경유가 2억237만 배럴로 연간 최대 수출량을 경신했다고 26일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diesel, a representative high-value-added product, accounted for the largest share of total petroleum product exports at 42%, followed by gasoline at 22%, aviation fuel at 18%, and naphtha at 7%. Australia (16.8%) was the top destination for South Korea's petroleum product exports last year for the fourth consecutive year. It was followed by Singapore (13.6%), Japan (11.3%), the United States (10.2%), and China (9.2%). (대표적인 고부가가치 제품인 경유가 전체 석유제품 수출량에서 차지하는 비중은 42%로 가장 높았고 휘발유 22%, 항공유 18%, 나프타 7% 순으로 집계됐다. 우리나라가 지난해 석유제품을 가장 많이 수출한 국가는 호주(16.8%)로 4년째 1위다. 이어 싱가포르(13.6%), 일본(11.3%), 미국(10.2%), 중국(9.2%) 순으로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exports to the United States showed particularly prominent growth last year. Aviation fuel exports reached a record high of 38.74 million barrels, and gasoline exports also increased by 22% compared to the previous year. This is interpreted as being due to a significant increase in aviation fuel demand as U.S. airport passenger traffic reached 906.74 million last year, coupled with reduced local production of petroleum products like gasoline and aviation fuel following the closure of some U.S. refining facilities and refinery fires. (지난해에는 특히 대미 수출 증가세가 두드러졌다. 항공유 수출량이 3874만 배럴로 역대 가장 많았고 휘발유 수출도 전년 대비 22% 증가했다. 지난해 미국 공항 이용객이 9억674만명에 이르면서 항공유 수요는 크게 늘어난 상황에서 미국 내 일부 정제설비 폐쇄, 정유공장 화재 여파 등으로 현지 휘발유, 항공유 등 석유제품 생산이 감소한 영향으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, total petroleum product exports decreased by 1.1% year-on-year to 485.35 million barrels. In terms of value, exports amounted to $40.7 billion (approximately 58 trillion won), a decrease of 9.9% over the same period. By product, naphtha export value decreased the most significantly by 24.4%, followed by gasoline (-15%) and aviation fuel (-11.7%). An official from the Korea Petroleum Association explained, "Exports deteriorated significantly in the first quarter, declining by 13%, amid a global trend of protectionist trade following the announcement of tariff policies at the start of the Trump administration in the U.S. last year." (다만, 전체 석유제품 수출량은 4억8535만 배럴로 전년 대비 1.1% 감소했다. 금액으로는 407억 달러(약 58조원)로 같은 기간 9.9% 줄어들었다. 제품별로는 나프타 수출액이 24.4% 감소하면서 가장 크게 줄었고 휘발유(-15%), 항공유(-11.7%)가 그 뒤를 이었다. 대한석유협회 관계자는 “지난해 초 미국 트럼프 정부 출범 시 관세 정책 발표에 따른 글로벌 보호무역 기조 속에 1분기 수출이 13% 감소하는 등 크게 악화했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite this situation, the Korea Petroleum Association assessed that the domestic refining industry is contributing to the improvement of the national trade balance through petroleum product exports. This is because 59.5% of the approximately $68.4 billion spent on crude oil imports last year was recovered through petroleum product exports. This is the second-highest level since 2022 (59.7%). Furthermore, according to the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy's data on export value and ranking of major national items, petroleum products ranked fourth for three consecutive years, following semiconductors, automobiles, and general machinery. (이러한 상황에서도 대한석유협회 쪽은 국내 정유업계가 석유제품 수출로 국가 무역 수지 개선에 기여하고 있다고 평가했다. 지난해 원유도입액 약 684억 달러 중 59.5%를 석유제품 수출로 회수했기 때문이다. 이는 2022년(59.7%) 이후 두 번째로 큰 수준이다. 또한 산업통상부의 국가 주요 품목 수출액 및 순위 현황 자료를 보면 석유제품은 반도체, 자동차, 일반기계에 이어 3년 연속 4위를 차지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An official from the Korea Petroleum Association stated, "This year, while global economic uncertainty and geopolitical issues persist and oil price volatility is high due to an oversupply of oil, making the petroleum product export environment challenging, the domestic refining industry will analyze the global market, focus on exporting high-value-added products, contribute to national exports, and enhance global competitiveness." (대한석유협회 관계자는 “올해는 세계 경제 불확실성과 지정학적 이슈가 상존하는 한편 석유공급과잉으로 유가 변동성이 높아 석유제품 수출 환경이 녹록지 않을 것”이라면서도 “국내 정유업계는 글로벌 시장을 분석해 고부가가치 제품 수출에 주력, 국가 수출에 기여하고 글로벌 경쟁력을 높여 나가겠다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Yu Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241737.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694177649131_20260126503315.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Amid Stock Market Rally, 'Illegal Investment Chat Rooms' Rampant, Even Employing AI (증시 불장에, AI까지 동원 ‘불법 리딩방’도 기승)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241739.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Amid Stock Market Rally, 'Illegal Investment Chat Rooms' Rampant, Even Employing AI (증시 불장에, AI까지 동원 ‘불법 리딩방’도 기승)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694179803852_20260126503330.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;26일 서울 영등포구 한국거래소 현황판에 코스닥 지수가 표시되고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taking advantage of the stock market boom, including the KOSPI surpassing 5000, operators engaging in illegal investment chat room scams are running rampant, prompting financial authorities to issue a consumer alert. (코스피 5000 돌파 등 주식시장 활황을 악용해 불법 리딩방 투자 사기에 나서는 업자들이 기승을 부려 금융당국이 소비자경보를 발령했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Financial Supervisory Service (FSS) urged investors to exercise special caution on the 26th, stating that illegal investment chat room scams exploiting the recent stock market rally are spreading. (금융감독원은 26일 최근 주식시장 활황을 빌미로 한 불법 리딩방 투자 사기가 확산하고 있다며 투자자들의 각별한 주의를 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Illegal operators use tactics such as luring investors on social networking services (SNS) like YouTube and messengers before pulling them into group chat rooms. Once investors join the chat room, individuals presumed to be shills build trust by showing successful investment cases. Some chat rooms use a method of providing small profits initially to lower vigilance before demanding additional investments. (불법업자들은 유튜브·메신저 등 사회관계망서비스(SNS)에서 투자자를 유인한 뒤 단체 채팅방으로 끌어들이는 수법을 쓰고 있다. 투자자가 채팅방에 참여하면 바람잡이로 추정되는 인물들이 투자 성공사례를 보여주며 신뢰를 쌓는다. 일부 리딩방에서는 초반에 적은 수익을 제공해 경계심을 낮춘 뒤 추가 투자를 요구하는 방식을 쓴다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FSS explained that there are also cases where they move to one-on-one chats to induce more aggressive investment or demand the installation of fake stock trading apps that are so sophisticated they are difficult to distinguish from official securities firm apps. (1대1 채팅으로 옮겨, 더 적극적인 투자를 유도하거나 공식 증권사 앱과 구분이 어려울 정도로 정교하게 만든 가짜 주식거래 앱 설치를 요구하는 사례도 있다고 금감원은 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scam tactics misusing artificial intelligence (AI) technology have also emerged. This involves conducting investment consultations using AI-imitated faces and voices of real experts or securities firm employees, disguising themselves as official financial company staff to avoid investor suspicion. (인공지능(AI) 기술을 악용한 사기 수법도 등장했다. 실존하는 전문가나 증권사 직원을 인공지능으로 흉내 낸 얼굴과 목소리를 활용해 투자 상담을 진행하고, 마치 공식 금융회사 직원인 것처럼 꾸며 투자자의 의심을 피하는 방식이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FSS urged special caution, stating that investment recommendations through group chat rooms, proposals emphasizing principal guarantees or fixed returns, and requests for app installation via links are typical scam signals. An FSS official emphasized, "Do not respond to investment recommendations from unclear sources, and if suspicious, immediately stop the transaction." (금감원은 단체 채팅방을 통한 투자 권유나 원금 보장·확정 수익을 강조하는 제안, 링크를 통한 앱 설치 요구 등은 대표적인 사기 신호라며 각별한 주의를 당부했다. 금감원 관계자는 “출처가 불분명한 투자 권유에는 응하지 말고, 의심스러운 경우 즉시 거래를 중단해야 한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Taeho An &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241739.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694179803852_20260126503330.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Even the World Gold Council Says "Inexplicable"... International Gold Price Breaks Through Even $5,000 (세계금협회조차 “설명 불가”…국제 금값, 5천달러마저 돌파)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241744.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Even the World Gold Council Says "Inexplicable"... International Gold Price Breaks Through Even $5,000 (세계금협회조차 “설명 불가”…국제 금값, 5천달러마저 돌파)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/444/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694185321084_20260126503357.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;1㎏짜리 골드바. 한겨레 자료사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The price of gold, which is continuing its sharpest rise since the second oil shock (1979), has broken through even $5,000 per ounce. As the correlation between the dollar's value and the gold price decreases and its character changes to that of an 'investment asset,' stocks and gold are showing a pattern of rallying together. There is even an assessment that traditional explanations for the factors behind international gold price fluctuations no longer hold. (제2차 오일쇼크(1979년) 이후 가장 급격한 오름세를 지속중인 금 가격이 온스당 5천달러마저 돌파했다. 달러 가치와 금 가격 사이의 연관성이 줄어들고, ‘투자자산’ 성격으로 바뀌면서 주식과 금이 동반 랠리를 이어가는 양상이다. 국제 금가격 변동 요인을 둘러싼 전통적인 설명이 더는 통하지 않는다는 진단마저 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;International gold prices, which surged 65% last year, have continued to soar sharply this year, with gold futures prices breaking through $5,000 per ounce for the first time in history. On the 23rd (local time), April delivery gold futures on the New York Mercantile Exchange (COMEX) closed trading at $5,017 per ounce. Global market analysis suggests gold prices are surging due to a sharp drop in US Treasury bond prices, the NATO system being shaken by the Greenland issue, and the weakening of economic cooperation between the US and Europe. (작년 한해 65% 급등한 국제 금값은 올해 들어서도 가파르게 치솟으면서 금 선물 가격이 사상 처음으로 온스당 5천달러를 돌파했다. 지난 23일(현지시각) 뉴욕 금속선물거래소(COMEX)에서 4월 인도분 금 선물은 온스당 5017달러에 거래를 마쳤다. 글로벌 시장에서는 미 국채 가격이 급락하고 있는데다 그린란드 사태로 나토 체제가 흔들리고 미국과 유럽의 경제협력관계가 약화되면서 금 가격이 급등세를 보이고 있다고 분석한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an international gold price report released by POSCO Management Research Institute on the 26th, citing analysis from the World Gold Council, gold prices last year surged 65% compared to the beginning of the year. This is the highest level in 47 years, since 1978 (88.6%), just before the outbreak of the second oil shock. Historically, gold prices have mainly surged sharply when: △key currencies like the US dollar turn weak, △geopolitical risks become prominent, and △real interest rates are low, raising inflation concerns. (26일 포스코경영연구원이 세계금협회 분석 등을 인용해 내놓은 국제 금값 리포트를 보면, 지난해 금 가격은 연초 대비 65% 폭등했다. 2차 오일 쇼크 발발 직전인 1978년(88.6%) 이후 47년 만에 가장 높은 수준이다. 역사적으로 금 가격은 △달러화 등 기축통화가 약세로 전환될 때 △지정학적 리스크가 부각될 때 △실질금리가 낮아 인플레이션이 우려될 때 주로 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the World Gold Council's assessment is that the recent sharp rise in gold prices cannot be explained by existing analytical methods. In fact, the World Gold Council stated, "We have been analyzing correlations with economic growth rates, risks and uncertainties, opportunity costs (interest rates/exchange rates), etc. since 2021, but recently the residual part (error in regression analysis) that cannot be explained by this model has become overwhelmingly large." The proportion (contribution rate) of residuals among gold price fluctuation factors averaged 1.5% for the entire period (2007-2025), but in the recent period (2023-2025), it averaged 56%, showing a tremendous difference. This means that existing factors can hardly explain even half of the recent gold price fluctuations. The correlation between the gold price and the US dollar index showed a clear negative correlation of -0.49 from 2002-2019, but changed to +0.11 from 2020-2025, going through COVID-19. This indicates a change in interpreting gold as a substitute asset for the US dollar, unlike in the past. (그런데 최근의 금 가격 급등은 기존 분석 방법으로 설명이 불가능하다는 게 세계금협회 평가다. 실제 세계금협회는 “2021년 이후 경제성장률, 리스크와 불확실성, 기회비용(금리·환율) 등과의 상관관계를 분석해왔는데 최근엔 이 모델로는 설명하지 못하는 잔차(회귀분석의 오차) 부분이 압도적으로 커졌다”고 밝혔다. 금가격 변동요인 중에 잔차가 차지하는 비중(기여율)은 전체 기간(2007~2025년)에 평균 1.5%였는데 최근(2023~2025년)에는 평균 56%로, 엄청난 차이가 발생했다. 기존 요인으로는 최근 금 가격 변동을 절반도 설명하기 어렵다는 뜻이다. 금 가격과 달러화 지수의 상관관계는 2002~2019년 -0.49로 명확한 음의 상관관계를 보였으나, 코로나19를 거치며 2020~2025년에는 +0.11로 바뀌었다. 과거처럼 금을 달러화의 대체자산으로 해석하는 데도 변동이 생긴 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structural changes in the global financial market are also influencing the backdrop of the gold price surge. Since the outbreak of the Ukraine war in 2022, central banks in emerging economies like China have engaged in large-scale gold purchases, showing a pattern of increasing gold reserves annually until last year. The central banks focusing on gold purchases are mostly emerging economies like China, Poland, India, Iraq, and Qatar. POSCO Management Research Institute explained, "Countries like China and India are nations with latent political and economic tensions with the US, attempting a gradual departure from the US dollar-centric financial system through diversification of reserve assets," and added, "Emerging economies focusing on gold purchases are massively selling off US long-term Treasury bonds, which have traditionally been treated as safe assets." From 2022 to the third quarter of last year, the net selling scale of US long-term Treasury bonds includes China ($290.1 billion), Brazil ($56.7 billion), India ($36.2 billion), and Saudi Arabia ($9.2 billion). (금 가격 폭등의 배후에는 글로벌 금융시장의 구조 변화도 영향을 미치고 있다. 우크라이나 전쟁이 발발한 2022년 이후 중국 등 신흥국 중앙은행들은 대규모 금 매입에 나서 지난해까지 매년 금 비축량을 늘리는 양상을 보였다. 금 매입에 집중하는 중앙은행은 대부분 중국·폴란드·인도·이라크·카타르 등 신흥국들이다. 포스코경영연구원은 “중국·인도 등은 미국과 정치경제적 긴장이 잠재하는 국가로, 준비자산 다변화를 통해 미국 달러 중심 금융시스템에서 점진적인 이탈을 시도하고 있다”며 “금 매입에 집중하는 신흥국들은 전통적으로 안전자산이라고 취급해오던 미국 장기국채를 대거 매도하고 있다”고 설명했다. 2022년 이후 지난해 3분기까지 미 장기국채 순매도 규모는 중국(2901억달러)·브라질(567억달러)·인도(362억달러)·사우디(92억달러) 등이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, developed countries like the UK, France, Canada, and South Korea are still continuously purchasing US long-term Treasury bonds. Japan also switched to large-scale net purchases in 2025. The safe assets perceived by emerging economies and those perceived by developed countries with high political and economic ties to the US have become distinctly different. The research institute analyzed that global safe assets are clearly dividing into developed countries centered on US Treasuries and emerging economies centered on physical gold, and that major emerging economies prefer gold purchases due to concerns that dollar assets could be frozen if political and economic disputes with the US occur. (반면 영국·프랑스·캐나다·한국 등 선진국들은 여전히 미국 장기국채를 지속적으로 매입하고 있는 중이다. 일본도 2025년에 대규모 순매입으로 전환했다. 신흥국들이 생각하는 안전자산과 미국과 정치경제적 연관관계가 높은 선진국이 생각하는 안전자산이 서로 확연히 달라진 것이다. 연구원은 글로벌 안전자산이 미 국채 중심의 선진국과 실물 금 중심의 신흥국으로 명확히 갈리고 있다며, 주요 신흥국들은 미국과 정치경제적 분쟁이 발생할 경우 달러 자산이 동결될 수 있다고 우려해 금 매입을 선호하고 있다고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, gold moved inversely to the returns of risky assets like stocks and served as a portfolio hedge, but recently, it has shown a tendency to move in sync with the trends of risky asset prices like stocks. In 2021, there was almost no correlation between gold prices and US S&amp;P 500 returns, but in 2024, this correlation reached 0.91, a record high. The research institute stated, "The function of the dollar, which historically served as a mirror for asset and commodity prices, is weakening," and added, "It is time to be cautious of the optimism that gold will act as a hedge when a crisis hits the market." (전통적으로 금은 주식 같은 위험자산 수익률과 반대로 움직이며 포트폴리오 방어막 역할을 수행했으나, 최근 들어서는 주식 등 위험자산 가격의 흐름과 동조화되는 경향이 나타나고 있다. 2021년에는 금 가격과 미국 에스앤피(S&amp;amp;P)500 수익률 사이에 상관관계가 거의 없었으나 2024년에는 이 상관관계가 0.91로 역대 최고치를 기록했다. 연구원은 “역사적으로 자산가격 및 원자재 가격의 거울 역할을 해온 달러의 기능이 약화되고 있다”며 “시장에 위기가 찾아왔을 때 금이 방어막이 되어줄 거라는 낙관론을 경계해야 할 시점”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241744.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/444/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694185321084_20260126503357.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Give Value and Experience Too"... Lunar New Year Gifts Evolving to be More Abundant (“가치·경험까지 드리세요”…풍성하게 진화한 설 선물)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241757.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Give Value and Experience Too"... Lunar New Year Gifts Evolving to be More Abundant (“가치·경험까지 드리세요”…풍성하게 진화한 설 선물)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503424.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이마트는 가치소비 자체브랜드(PB)인 ‘자연주의’ 선물세트 물량을 지난해보다 20% 늘렸다. 사진은 이마트 자연주의 매대. 이마트 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A wind of change is blowing through the Lunar New Year gift market, which had been polarized into high-end premium gifts and budget-friendly practical gifts. The distribution industry is presenting new gift options that combine value, meaning, and experience. The strategy is to win consumer choice with meaningful gifts that go beyond simple price competition. (고가의 프리미엄 선물과 실속형 선물로 양극화된 명절 선물 시장에 변화의 바람이 일고 있다. 유통업계가 가치와 의미, 경험을 결합한 새로운 선물 선택지를 제시하면서다. 단순한 가격 경쟁을 넘어 뜻이 담긴 선물로 소비자의 선택을 받겠다는 전략이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emart has increased the quantity of its 'Naturalism' gift sets, a value consumption private brand (PB), by 20% compared to last year. The eco-friendly elements such as low-carbon, organic, and zero-plastic have been further strengthened. The 'Low-Carbon Certified' fruit set changed its packaging cushioning material from plastic to 100% paper and applied a 30% discount. The price range was prepared broadly, from practical sets in the 30,000 to 50,000 won range to mid-priced gifts. (이마트는 가치소비 자체브랜드(PB)인 ‘자연주의’ 선물세트 물량을 지난해보다 20% 늘렸다. 저탄소·유기농·제로 플라스틱 등 친환경 요소가 한층 강화된 것이다. ‘저탄소 인증’ 과일 세트는 포장 완충재를 플라스틱에서 100% 종이로 바꾸고, 30% 할인 혜택을 적용했다. 가격대는 3만~5만원대 실속형부터 중가 선물까지 폭넓게 마련했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methods of gifting time and experience, beyond just exchanging physical items, are also noteworthy. Shinsegae Department Store is introducing a 'Make Your Own Jang' experience program for the Lunar New Year holiday, featuring Master Ki Sun-do, a representative artisan in the traditional jang (fermented soybean paste) field. Participating customers will put jang into a crock with their name engraved on it in Damyang, South Jeolla Province, experience the year-long fermentation process, and then receive the completed doenjang (soybean paste) and ganjang (soy sauce). (물건을 주고받는 차원을 넘어 시간과 경험을 선물하는 방식도 주목할 만하다. 신세계백화점은 설 명절을 맞아 전통장 분야 대표 장인인 기순도 명인과 함께하는 ‘나만의 장 만들기’ 체험 프로그램을 선보인다. 참여 고객은 전남 담양에서 자신의 이름이 새겨진 장독에 장을 담그고, 1년에 걸친 숙성 과정을 경험한 뒤 완성된 된장과 간장을 받게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gifts emphasizing experience are also noticeable in the hotel industry. Lotte Hotel &amp; Resort is targeting consumers who want to gift both hotel experience and relaxation by introducing a paid membership product in this year's Lunar New Year gift sets, which includes fitness and sauna usage benefits at Lotte Hotel and its top-tier brand, Signiel's main chains. (호텔업계에서도 경험을 강조하는 선물이 눈에 띈다. 롯데호텔앤리조트는 올해 설 선물세트에 롯데호텔과 이 호텔 최상급 브랜드인 시그니엘 주요 체인의 피트니스·사우나 이용 혜택을 포함한 유료 멤버십 상품을 선보이면서 호텔 체험과 휴식을 함께 선물하려는 소비층을 겨냥하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some have also strengthened curation strategies to help consumers easily decide on gifts among numerous choices. Lotte Department Store expanded the proportion of small packages and mixed assortments in this year's Lunar New Year gift pre-order sales, focusing on 'Best Products' that were popular with consumers during the previous holiday period. It promoted mixed sets of Hanwoo (Korean beef) cuts, convenient seafood products, seasonal fruits, and artisan brands to make it easier for consumers to choose gifts. It aims to provide its own criteria for customers hesitating between premium and practical products. A key feature is the enhanced editing function that explains 'why this product should be gifted' instead of engaging in excessive discount competition. (수많은 선택지 가운데 소비자가 쉽게 선물을 결정할 수 있도록 돕는 큐레이션 전략을 강화한 곳도 있다. 롯데백화점은 올해 설 선물 사전 예약 판매에서 앞선 명절 기간에 소비자들에게 인기를 끈 ‘베스트 상품’을 중심으로 소포장·혼합 구성 비중을 확대했다. 한우 부위 혼합 세트, 간편 수산물, 제철 과일과 장인 브랜드를 내세워 소비자가 보다 쉽게 선물을 고를 수 있도록 했다. 프리미엄과 실속 상품 사이에서 어떤 선물을 골라야 할지 망설이는 고객에게 나름의 기준을 제시하는 것이다. 과도한 할인 경쟁 대신 ‘왜 이 상품을 선물해야 하는지’를 설명해 주는 편집 기능을 강화한 점이 특징이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, practical gifts still form the central axis of holiday consumption. CU convenience store, operated by BGF Retail, has assembled its private brand 'PBICK Deuktem Series' and health functional foods as practical products in the 30,000 won range. GS25, operated by GS Retail, is targeting practical demand by expanding the proportion of agricultural, livestock, and fishery gift sets like fruits and Hanwoo priced below 50,000 won by 40% compared to last year. (다만, 실속형 선물은 여전히 명절 소비의 중심축이다. 비지에프(BGF)리테일이 운영하는 편의점 씨유(CU)는 3만원대 실속형 상품으로 자체브랜드 ‘피빅(PBICK) 득템 시리즈’와 건강기능식품을 구성했다. 지에스(GS)리테일이 운영하는 지에스25도 5만원 이하의 과일, 한우 등 농축수산 선물세트 비중을 지난해보다 40% 확대해 실속형 수요를 공략한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Hyemi &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서혜미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Return of 'BTS Jin Super Tuna'... Competing with Practical Sets in the 30,000 Won Range (‘BTS 진 슈퍼참치’의 귀환… 3만원대 실속 구성으로 승부)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dongwon F&amp;B has launched about 100 types of '2026 Lunar New Year Gift Sets' containing health and practicality. Comprehensive gift sets combining steady-selling items like Dongwon Tuna and Richam with highly usable various seasonings such as tuna liquid, cooking oil, and salt can be purchased for prices in the 30,000 won range. The 'BTS Jin Super Tuna Gift Set', which gained popularity during last year's Chuseok holiday, can also be found this Lunar New Year. This product, consisting of tuna cans containing photos of global idol group BTS member Jin, received high interest, selling 1,000 units in 40 seconds during pre-sales last year. Encouraged by this, about 10,000 sets were exported to the U.S. in December last year. Dongwon gift sets surpassed 100 million cumulative sets sold in 2006, and over 260 million sets were sold last year. (동원에프앤비(F&amp;amp;B)는 건강과 실속을 담은 ‘2026 설 선물세트’ 100여종을 출시했다. 동원참치·리챔 등 스테디셀러 품목에 참치액, 요리유, 소금 등 활용도 높은 각종 조미료를 함께 구성한 종합선물세트를 3만원대 가격으로 살 수 있다. 지난 추석 연휴에 인기를 끌었던 ‘비티에스(BTS) 진 슈퍼참치 선물세트’도 올 설에 만날 수 있다. 세계적인 아이돌 그룹 비티에스의 멤버 진 사진이 담긴 참치캔으로 구성한 이 제품은 지난해 사전 판매 당시 40초 만에 1천개가 팔리는 등 높은 관심을 받았다. 이에 힘입어 지난해 12월에는 미국에 약 1만 세트를 수출하기도 했다. 동원선물세트는 2006년에 누적 판매 1억 세트를 넘겼고, 지난해에는 2억6천만 세트 넘게 팔렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From 20,000 Won to 1.2 Million Won Hanwoo... Breaking Through High Prices Head-on with '100% Domestic'&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;2만원부터 120만원 한우까지… ‘국산 100%’로 고물가 정면돌파&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonghyup Moguchon is introducing a total of 81 types of gift sets made with 100% domestic raw meat for the Lunar New Year holiday. Nonghyup Moguchon explained that this Lunar New Year gift set is composed of various categories: △Hanwoo gift sets △Beef cattle gift sets △Korean pork gift sets △Handmade ham gift sets △Canned comprehensive gift sets △Convenient gift sets △Health gift sets. It has broadened the range of consumer choice by offering sets from the affordable price range of 20,000 won to premium Hanwoo sets costing 1.2 million won. A 'Pet Food Gift Set' for companion animals also stands out. (농협목우촌은 설 명절을 맞아 100% 국산 원료육으로 만든 총 81종의 선물세트를 선보인다. 이번 설 선물세트는 △한우선물세트 △육우선물세트 △한돈선물세트 △수제햄선물세트 △캔종합선물세트 △간편선물세트 △건강선물세트 등으로 다채롭게 구성했다고 농협목우촌은 설명했다. 부담 없는 가격대인 2만원대부터 120만원대 프리미엄 한우 세트까지 구성해 소비자 선택의 폭을 넓혔다. 반려동물을 위한 ‘펫푸드선물세트’도 눈에 띈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Cheol-jin, CEO of Nonghyup Moguchon, said, "In a situation where the burden of holiday gifts has increased due to high prices, we have introduced Lunar New Year gift sets that broaden the choice from practical to premium," adding, "We hope that Nonghyup Moguchon's Lunar New Year gift sets, which consider both price and quality, will be helpful in holiday preparations." (박철진 농협목우촌 대표이사는 “고물가로 명절 선물에 대한 부담이 커진 상황에서 실속형부터 프리미엄까지 선택의 폭을 넓힌 설 선물세트를 선보였다”며 “가격과 품질을 모두 고려한 농협목우촌 설 선물세트가 명절 준비에 도움이 되길 기대한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Lowering Sugar, Protecting the Environment"... Cheongjungwon's 'Safe &amp; Eco' Gift Sets (“당은 낮추고 환경은 지키고”…청정원 ‘안심·에코’ 선물세트)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daesang Cheongjungwon has launched Lunar New Year gift sets encompassing health and eco-friendly elements. Cheongjungwon explained that products like the △Low-Sugar Hongcho (Red Vinegar) Set and △Allulose Set minimize the burden of sugar and calorie intake by using the sugar substitute 'allulose' produced domestically with Daesang's own technology. It also paid attention to environmental protection value. Convenient item gift sets like seasonings and sauces, targeting home-cooking enthusiasts, are introduced in 'All Paper Package', from which plastic packaging has been removed by applying a pulp press method for the first time in the industry by Daesang. Those who purchase two types of 'Cheongjungwon Seasoning Complex Set' and two types of 'Premium Oil Edition' can receive an eco-bag. For premium sets, high-end Korean jang (fermented sauces) such as △Glutinous Rice Sprouted Brown Rice Gochujang (red chili paste) △Our Rice Brown Rice Gochujang △Premium Jang Mix Set △5-Year Aged Soy Sauce Set have been prepared. (대상 청정원은 건강과 친환경 요소를 아우른 설 선물 세트를 출시했다. △저당 홍초세트 △알룰로스 세트 등은 대상의 자체 기술로 국내에서 생산한 대체당 ‘알룰로스’를 활용해 당과 칼로리 섭취 부담을 최소화한 제품이라고 청정원은 설명했다. 환경 보호 가치에도 신경 썼다. 집밥족을 겨냥한 조미료·소스류 등 간편템 선물세트는 대상이 업계 최초로 펄프 프레스 공법을 적용해 플라스틱 포장을 제거한 ‘올 페이퍼 패키지’로 선보인다. ‘청정원 조미복합 세트’ 2종과 ‘프리미엄 오일에디션’ 2종을 사면, 에코백을 받을 수 있다. 프리미엄 세트로는 △찹쌀발아 현미고추장 △우리쌀 현미고추장 △프리미엄 장류 혼합세트 △5년 숙성간장 세트 등 한식 고급 장류가 마련됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;H&amp;Y Holds Health Gift Exhibition for Lunar New Year (에치와이, 설 맞아 건강 선물 기획전 진행)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;H&amp;Y is holding a Lunar New Year gift exhibition on its own mall, Preddit, for the Lunar New Year holiday. It is characterized by assembling gift sets centered on health functional foods together with practical products. For health gift sets, a total of 6 types including vitamins/minerals and probiotics have been prepared. It also introduces food gift sets with high holiday demand like traditional seaweed, manuka honey, and silver hairtail, as well as convenient meals. If ordered before the holiday, products can be received at the desired date and location before the holiday period. An event is also held where those who leave a review in the comments after purchasing a gift set can win a robot vacuum cleaner, massager, etc., through a lottery. (에치와이는 설 명절을 맞아 자사몰인 프레딧에서 설 선물 기획전을 진행한다. 건강기능식품 중심의 선물세트와 실속형 상품을 함께 구성한 것이 특징이다. 건강 선물세트로는 비타민·미네랄, 프로바이오틱스 등 모두 6종을 마련했다. 재래김, 마누카꿀, 은갈치 등 명절 수요가 높은 식품 선물세트와 간편식도 선보인다. 명절에 앞서 주문하면, 명절 연휴 전까지 원하는 날짜와 장소에 맞춰 상품을 받아볼 수 있다. 선물세트를 산 뒤 댓글로 후기를 남기면 추첨을 통해 로봇청소기, 마사지기 등을 받을 수 있는 행사도 열린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From Matcha Sand to Bellygom Spam... Premium Gifts 'Targeting Tastes' (말차 샌드부터 벨리곰 스팸까지… ‘취향 저격’ 프리미엄 선물)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CJ CheilJedang is introducing 209 types of gift sets with various compositions for the Lunar New Year. It newly launched a practical composite set where popular holiday gifts like Spam and tuna cans can be encountered at once. For premium desserts, 'Our Wheat Matcha Wafer Sand' targeting the matcha trend, 'Sand Cookie' which reinterprets traditional taste in a modern way in collaboration with Shinsegae Food, and 'Walnut &amp; Pecan Jeonggwa (traditional sweet) Set' introduced in partnership with nut specialty company HBAF stand out. The premium gift set brand 'Le Goûter' is launching 'Fiorini Balsamic Vinegar' as a new product. Products that can be seen again include 'Spam Gold Bar', which gained popularity as a Chuseok gift last year, the character collaboration product 'Spam Bellygom Edition', and 'Naver Happybean Spam Gift Set', a product that donates part of its sales proceeds. (씨제이(CJ)제일제당이 설을 맞아 다양한 구성의 선물세트 209종을 선보인다. 명절 인기 선물로 손꼽히는 스팸과 참치캔을 한 번에 만나볼 수 있는 실속형 복합 세트를 새롭게 출시했다. 프리미엄 디저트로는 말차 유행을 겨냥한 ‘우리밀 말차 웨이퍼샌드’, 신세계푸드와 협업해 전통의 맛을 현대적으로 재해석한 ‘샌드쿠키’, 견과류 전문기업 바프(HBAF)와 손잡고 선보이는 ‘호두&amp;amp;피칸 정과세트’ 등이 눈에 띈다. 프리미엄 선물세트 브랜드 ‘르 구떼’(Le Goûter)는 ‘피오리니 발사믹 식초’를 신제품으로 출시한다. 지난 추석 선물로 인기를 끈 ‘스팸 골드바’와 캐릭터 협업 제품인 ‘스팸 벨리곰 에디션’, 판매 수익금의 일부를 기부하는 방식의 상품인 ‘네이버 해피빈 스팸 선물세트’ 등도 다시 만날 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Interest in Health Management in the New Year... CheongKwanJang, Holiday Discount Event&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;건강 관리 관심 큰 새해…정관장, 명절 할인 행사&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Health-related products are long-standing holiday gifts. Especially in the new year, as the number of people paying attention to health management increases noticeably, health functional foods targeting them stand out. CheongKwanJang's red ginseng products are representative. CheongKwanJang's steady seller 'HongSamTon' is a product sold for over 30 years since its launch in 1993, a health functional food for fatigue improvement that adds traditional ingredients to red ginseng concentrate. CheongKwanJang is running the 'Say It with CheongKwanJang This Lunar New Year' promotion from the 23rd of this month to the 18th of next month for the Lunar New Year holiday. It provides purchase benefits not only for steady sellers like HongSamJung, Everytime, and HongSamTon, but for all CheongKwanJang items, including 'Gidarim' made with agarwood and the blood sugar management specialist brand GLPro. (건강 관련 상품은 오래된 명절 선물이다. 특히 새해에는 건강 관리에 관심을 두는 이들이 부쩍 늘어나는 만큼, 이들을 겨냥한 건강기능식품이 눈에 띈다. 정관장의 홍삼 제품이 대표적이다. 정관장의 스테디셀러인 ‘홍삼톤’은 1993년 출시 이후 30년 넘게 판매된 제품으로, 홍삼농축액에 전통 소재를 더한 피로 개선용 건강기능식품이다. 정관장은 설 명절을 맞아 이달 23일부터 다음달 18일까지 ‘올 설엔 정관장으로 말해요’ 프로모션을 진행한다. 홍삼정, 에브리타임, 홍삼톤과 같은 스테디셀러뿐 아니라, 침향으로 만든 기다림 침향, 혈당관리 전문 브랜드 지엘프로(GLPro) 등 정관장 전 품목을 대상으로 구매 혜택을 제공한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Hyemi ham@hani.co.kr Reporter Lee Jubin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서혜미 기자 ham@hani.co.kr 이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241757.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503424.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[On-site] "We've already transferred the land, what do we do if they move it?"... Endless debate over relocation for Yongin cluster ([현장] “이미 땅 넘겼는데, 옮기자면 어떡하냐”…이전론 ‘설왕설래’ 용인 클러스터)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241759.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[On-site] "We've already transferred the land, what do we do if they move it?"... Endless debate over relocation for Yongin cluster ([현장] “이미 땅 넘겼는데, 옮기자면 어떡하냐”…이전론 ‘설왕설래’ 용인 클러스터)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694207170332_20260126503457.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 22일 경기 용인시 원삼면 일반산업단지 내에 에스케이(SK)하이닉스의 용인 반도체 클러스터 1기 팹(반도체 공장)이 건설 중이다. 박종오 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Driving about 20km southeast from the Yongin City Hall, the heart of Gyeonggi Province's Yongin City, a large construction site flattened by cutting into hills comes into view. Amidst the tower cranes within the Wonsam-myeon general industrial complex, where dump trucks and concrete mixers kick up dust as they come and go, the framework of SK Hynix's first-phase factory (fab) for the Yongin semiconductor cluster emerges. Built on a foundation where 45,000 piles, each 45 meters long, were driven underground and over 2 meters of concrete was poured, this factory, set to rise up to 14 stories high, was in full swing on the 22nd, aiming for completion early next year. The basic construction progress rate for the general industrial complex has already surpassed 70%, and a substation to supply power to the first and second factories was also being built on one side of the complex. (경기 용인시 중심인 용인시청에서 차를 타고 남동쪽으로 20km 정도 달리자 구릉을 깎아 평탄화한 대형 공사 현장이 눈에 들어왔다. 덤프트럭과 레미콘이 흙먼지를 날리며 오가는 원삼면 일반산업단지 내 타워크레인들 사이로 에스케이(SK)하이닉스의 용인 반도체 클러스터 1기 공장(팹) 뼈대가 모습을 드러냈다. 지하에 45미터(m) 길이의 말뚝(파일) 4만5천개를 박고 2미터가 넘는 콘크리트를 타설한 지반 위에 최고 14층 높이로 들어설 이 공장은 내년 초 준공을 목표로 지난 22일 공사가 한창이었다. 일반산단의 기초 공사 공정률은 이미 70%를 넘었고, 산단 한쪽엔 1·2공장에 전력을 공급할 변전소도 함께 들어서고 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung stated his position the previous day, on the 21st, during his New Year's press conference, regarding the controversy over relocating the Yongin semiconductor cluster that has emerged ahead of the June 3 local elections. President Lee said, "Even if the government says to move (the Yongin cluster), can it be moved? However, persuasion or inducement is possible." While drawing a line at government intervention, he left the possibility of relocation open. (이재명 대통령은 전날인 21일 신년 기자회견에서 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 불거진 용인 반도체 클러스터의 지역 이전 논란에 관한 입장을 내놨다. 이 대통령은 “(용인 클러스터를) 정부가 옮기라고 한다고 해서 옮겨지나. 다만 설득이나 유도할 수는 있다”고 했다. 정부 개입엔 선을 그으면서도, 지역 이전 가능성을 열어둔 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this day, banners opposing the relocation of the semiconductor cluster were hung throughout major commercial districts and roads in downtown Yongin. Signature campaigns were also underway, with petitions listing residents' names opposing the relocation posted even within individual apartment complexes. With the election approaching, protecting the semiconductor cluster has emerged as Yongin's most pressing issue. (이날 찾은 용인 시내 주요 상권과 도로엔 반도체 클러스터의 지방 이전을 반대하는 현수막이 곳곳에 내걸려 있었다. 개별 아파트 단지 내에도 지방 이전에 반대하는 주민 이름을 적는 연명부가 붙는 등 서명 운동이 진행 중이었다. 선거를 앞두고 반도체 클러스터 지키기가 용인의 최대 현안으로 떠오른 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Yongin semiconductor cluster, being developed as the world's largest semiconductor industrial agglomeration, largely consists of two axes. In the general industrial complex in the Wonsam-myeon area in southeastern Yongin, Hynix is building, while in the national industrial complex within I-dong and Namsa-eup in southwestern Yongin, Samsung Electronics is constructing a mega semiconductor factory. The total number of new factories alone is a whopping 10. Production facilities approaching half of the currently operational domestic semiconductor factories, centered on Samsung's Giheung, Hwaseong, and Pyeongtaek plants and Hynix's Icheon and Cheongju plants, will be additionally established in these areas. (세계 최대 규모의 반도체 산업 집적지로 조성 중인 용인 반도체 클러스터는 크게 두 축으로 이뤄져 있다. 용인시 남동쪽의 원삼면 일대 일반산업단지엔 하이닉스가, 남서쪽의 이동·남사읍 내 국가산업단지엔 삼성전자가 초대형 반도체 공장을 짓는다. 전체 신설 공장 수만 무려 10개다. 삼성전자의 기흥·화성·평택 공장, 하이닉스의 이천·청주 공장 중심부에 현재 가동 중인 국내 반도체 공장들의 절반에 육박하는 생산시설이 이들 지역에 추가로 들어서는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among these, the one mentioned as a candidate for relocation is the Samsung Electronics side. This is because the national industrial complex where six Samsung Electronics semiconductor factories will be located has not even begun basic civil engineering work like land leveling by the project implementer, the Korea Land and Housing Corporation (LH). In contrast, Hynix began construction of its first factory in February last year, and the building is already largely erected. (이 가운데 지역 이전 대상으로 거론되는 곳은 삼성전자 쪽이다. 삼성전자 반도체 공장 6개가 자리 잡을 국가산단은 사업 시행자인 한국토지주택공사(LH)가 아직 땅을 다지는 기초 토목 공사도 시작하지 않았기 때문이다. 반면 하이닉스는 지난해 2월 1공장 건축 공사를 시작해 건물이 이미 상당 부분 올라간 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon of this day, about ten residents were gathered at the consultation window on the first floor of the 'Yongin Semiconductor Complex Project Headquarters' building in I-dong-eup, Cheoin-gu, Yongin. LH has been conducting land compensation negotiations for the national industrial complex site here since the end of last month. The compensation target is the 7.28 million square meters (approximately 2.2 million pyeong) in the I-dong-eup and Namsa-eup areas where six Samsung Electronics semiconductor factories are planned. An elderly couple visiting the consultation office on this day said, "We are satisfied with the compensation amount," and "We decided to sell our house." (이날 오후 용인시 처인구 이동읍의 ‘용인반도체산단사업본부’ 건물 1층 상담 창구엔 주민 10여명이 모여 있었다. 엘에이치는 지난달 말부터 이곳에서 국가산단 부지의 토지 보상 협의를 진행하고 있다. 보상 대상은 삼성전자 반도체 공장 6개가 들어설 예정인 이동읍과 남사읍 일대 728만㎡(약 220만평)이다. 이날 상담소를 찾은 한 노부부는 “보상금액에 만족한다”며 “집을 팔기로 했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leaving the office and looking around, the site for the Samsung Electronics semiconductor factory was close to a vast, sparsely populated plain with scattered factories and buildings among rice paddies and fields. One resident of I-dong-eup retorted, "Property rights have been restricted for about three years since the government announced the project promotion in early 2023, and compensation has only been about 30% recently. Now, if some political circles suggest moving the complex to Saemangeum, what are the residents who have already transferred their land ownership supposed to do?" Bang Do-gwan, head of the I-dong-eup Residents' Autonomy Committee, also said, "Many residents question why they are shaking up a project that is proceeding smoothly after careful preparation," adding, "They must have considered all aspects like power and water supply measures during the project preparation process, and I understand that power and water supply in Saemangeum (mentioned as a relocation candidate) is not smooth either." (사무소를 빠져나와 둘러본 삼성전자 반도체 공장 터는 논밭 사이에 드문드문 공장과 건물이 있는 허허벌판에 가까웠다. 이동읍의 한 주민은 “정부가 사업 추진을 발표했던 2023년 초부터 3년여간 재산권 행사가 제한되다가 최근에서야 보상이 30% 정도 이뤄진 상황”이라며 “이제 와서 일부 정치권을 중심으로 산단을 새만금으로 옮기자고 하면 이미 토지 소유권을 넘긴 주민들은 어떻게 하느냐”고 반문했다. 방도관 이동읍 주민자치위원장도 “주민들은 잘 준비해서 무난하게 진행 중인 사업을 왜 흔드냐는 의견이 많다”며 “사업 준비 과정에서 전력·용수 수급 대책 등을 다 고려했을 테고, (이전 대상으로 언급되는) 새만금의 전력·용수 공급이 원만한 것도 아닌 것으로 알고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yongin City also emphasized that the national industrial complex and infrastructure creation projects are gaining speed. A city official said, "The land compensation execution rate for the Yongin National Industrial Complex, which commenced on the 22nd of last month, is 27.7% (compared to the total compensation amount) as of the 12th of this month. It is expected to rise to 40-50% by the end of this month." An official from a nearby real estate brokerage office hinted, "The price of absolute farmland (agricultural promotion zone) land within the national industrial complex was originally about 500,000 to 600,000 won per 3.3㎡, but the compensation price is set at about twice the market price, so the atmosphere is not bad." (용인시도 국가산단과 인프라 조성 사업이 속도를 내고 있다고 강조했다. 시 관계자는 “지난달 22일 착수한 용인 국가산단의 토지 보상 이행률은 이달 12일 기준 27.7%(전체 보상액 대비)다. 이달 말엔 보상 이행률이 40∼50%까지 올라갈 것으로 보인다”고 말했다. 인근 ㄷ공인중개사사무소 관계자는 “국가산단 내 절대농지(농업진흥구역) 땅값이 기존 3.3㎡당 50만∼60만원 정도였으나, 보상가가 시세의 2배 정도로 책정돼 분위기가 나쁘지 않다”고 귀띔했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, it's not that relocating the Yongin semiconductor cluster is fundamentally impossible. Under the current Land Compensation Act, if the national industrial complex project plan is scaled down, landowners can exercise their right of repurchase, returning the compensation and reclaiming their land. Land for which the repurchase right is not exercised remains with the implementer, the Land and Housing Corporation. (다만 용인 반도체 클러스터의 지방 이전이 원천적으로 불가능한 것만은 아니다. 현행 토지보상법상 국가산단 사업 계획을 축소할 경우, 토지 소유자는 보상금을 돌려주고 땅을 되찾는 환매권을 행사할 수 있다. 환매권을 행사하지 않은 땅은 시행자인 토지주택공사 몫으로 남는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The companies' positions are different. While keeping their distance from the political controversy, the atmosphere is one of each considering their own situation and weighing practical benefits. For now, Hynix is speeding up the construction of new factories to respond to the recent surge in demand for AI memory (HBM). On the other hand, Samsung Electronics not only lacks a prepared factory site yet, but its originally planned foundry (semiconductor contract manufacturing) business has not gained full momentum, so it is not in a situation to accelerate the project. However, it is known that they have conveyed a negative stance on factory relocation to the government, as Yongin, being close to existing semiconductor factories like Giheung, Hwaseong, and Pyeongtaek, offers significant agglomeration effects. (기업들 입장은 다르다. 정치적 논란에 거리를 두면서도 각자 상황을 고려해 실리를 따지고 있는 분위기다. 일단 하이닉스는 최근 급증한 인공지능 메모리(HBM) 수요에 대응하기 위해 공장 신설에 속도를 내고 있다. 반면 삼성전자는 아직 공장 부지도 마련되지 않은 데다, 애초 계획했던 파운드리(반도체 수탁생산) 사업이 본궤도에 오르지 않은 터라 사업에 속도를 낼 수 있는 상황은 아니다. 다만 기존 기흥·화성·평택 반도체 공장 등과 가까운 용인이 집적 효과가 큰 만큼 공장 이전에도 부정적인 입장을 정부에 전달한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty surrounding the mega semiconductor cluster being built in the metropolitan area is expected to continue. This is because both Samsung Electronics and Hynix will need to draw massive amounts of power from regions like Gangwon-do and Honam in the mid to long term to operate the semiconductor factories within the complex. This means that in the process of supporting a national strategic project, excessive sacrifice by a specific region is inevitable, potentially escalating into inter-regional conflict at any time. (수도권에 조성하는 초대형 반도체 클러스터를 둘러싼 불확실성은 계속될 것으로 보인다. 삼성전자와 하이닉스 모두 중장기적으로 산단 내 반도체 공장들을 가동하기 위해서는 막대한 전력을 강원도와 호남 등의 지역에서 끌어와야 하기 때문이다. 국가 전략사업을 뒷받침하는 과정에서 특정 지역의 과도한 희생이 불가피해 언제든지 지역 간 갈등으로 비화할 수 있다는 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Jong-oh &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박종오 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241759.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0126/53_17694207170332_20260126503457.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Semiconductor Factories in the Capital Region, Electricity from the Provinces... 'Vote-Seeking' Fuels Imbalance Controversy (반도체 공장은 수도권, 전기는 지역에…‘표심’이 불균형 논란 키워)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241764.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Semiconductor Factories in the Capital Region, Electricity from the Provinces... 'Vote-Seeking' Fuels Imbalance Controversy (반도체 공장은 수도권, 전기는 지역에…‘표심’이 불균형 논란 키워)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503475.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 22일 경기 용인시 처인구 용인중앙시장 입구에 용인 반도체 클러스터의 지방 이전에 반대하는 펼침막이 걸려 있다. 박종오 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fundamental cause igniting the controversy over relocating the Yongin semiconductor cluster is 'imbalance'. Issues such as the concentration in the capital region due to deregulation and the resulting mismatch in power supply and demand have surfaced, intertwining with political interests ahead of the local elections. (용인 반도체 클러스터의 지방 이전 논란을 불붙인 근본 원인은 ‘불균형’이다. 수도권 규제 완화에 따른 수도권 집중 현상과 이로 인한 전력 수급 불일치 등의 문제가 지방선거를 앞두고 정치권 이해관계와 맞물리면서 표면화된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SK Hynix was able to build a semiconductor cluster in the Wonam-myeon area of Yongin City, Gyeonggi Province, a general industrial complex, thanks to the government allocating a special quota in 2019 by lifting the total volume regulation that limited factory floor area in the capital region. When Samsung Electronics announced its plan to create an advanced system semiconductor cluster in Yongin in 2023, concerns about 'favoring the capital region' were also raised. However, the government accepted Samsung's proposal, citing reasons such as the urgency of the global semiconductor hegemony competition. By rushing the permitting process to align with corporate interests prioritizing efficiency, issues like regional balanced development and power/water supply were pushed to the back burner. (에스케이(SK)하이닉스가 경기 용인시 원삼면 일대 일반산업단지에 반도체 클러스터를 지을 수 있었던 것은, 정부가 2019년 수도권의 공장 건축 면적을 제한하는 총량 규제를 풀어 특별 물량을 배정해준 덕분이다. 2023년 삼성전자가 용인 첨단 시스템반도체 클러스터 조성 계획을 발표했을 때도 ‘수도권 몰아주기’ 우려가 제기됐다. 그러나 정부는 글로벌 반도체 패권 경쟁의 시급성 등을 이유로 삼성 쪽 제안을 수용했다. 효율을 최우선으로 하는 기업의 이해관계에 맞춰 정부가 인허가 속도전에 나서면서 지역 균형 발전과 전력·용수 수급 문제 등이 뒷전이 된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consecutive measures to ease regulations in the capital region are worsening the centralization of power and fueling regional discontent. Even now, with the power demand in the capital region, including Seoul, which accounts for over 40% of domestic power consumption, surging due to the new Yongin semiconductor cluster, the provinces have been reduced to mere power suppliers for the capital region. (연이은 수도권 규제 완화 조처는 전력의 중앙집중 문제를 더욱 악화시키며 지역 사회의 불만을 키우고 있다. 지금도 국내 전력 소비량의 40% 이상을 차지하는 서울 등 수도권의 전력 수요가 용인 반도체 클러스터 신설로 폭증하며, 지역은 수도권 전기공급처로 전락한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 15 gigawatts (GW) of power facility capacity needed for the Yongin semiconductor cluster amounts to about 10% of South Korea's total power generation capacity. This is equivalent to the power produced by 10 to 11 nuclear power plants of 1.4 GW each. Excluding the 3 GW liquefied natural gas (LNG) power plant planned within the Yongin cluster, a significant portion must rely on power drawn from the provinces. (용인 반도체 클러스터에 필요한 전력 설비 용량 15기가와트(GW)는 국내 전체 발전 설비의 약 10%에 이른다. 이는 1.4기가와트급 원자력 발전소 10~11기가 생산하는 전력과 맞먹는 규모다. 용인 클러스터 안에 짓기로 한 3기가와트 규모 액화천연가스(LNG) 발전소를 제외하면 상당량은 지역에서 만든 전기를 끌어다 써야 하는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Korea Electric Power Corporation's 'Monthly Power Statistics Report', the cumulative power self-sufficiency rate (the ratio of regional power generation to consumption) for the capital region from January to November last year was only 60.7%. This means the capital region produces only slightly more than half of the power it consumes. In contrast, regions like Gyeongbuk (250.2%), Jeonnam (214.9%), Chungnam (203.8%), and Gangwon (179.9%) far exceed 150%. They have a significant surplus of power beyond their own consumption. The concentration of factories and jobs in the capital region creates a structure inherently vulnerable to power 'bottlenecks' and opposition from marginalized provincial residents. (한국전력공사의 ‘전력통계월보’를 보면, 지난해 1~11월 누적 기준 수도권의 전력자급률(지역의 발전량을 전력 소비량으로 나눈 비율)은 60.7%에 불과하다. 수도권에서 소비하는 전력의 절반 남짓만 자체 생산한다는 의미다. 반면 경북(250.2%), 전남(214.9%), 충남(203.8%), 강원(179.9%) 등은 이 비율이 150%를 훌쩍 넘는다. 자체 소비하고도 남는 잉여 전력이 상당하다. 공장과 일자리의 수도권 집중은 소외된 지방 주민들의 반대라는 전력의 ‘병목 현상’에 취약할 수밖에 없는 구조다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that this imbalance is bound to worsen. This is because power demand across industries is rapidly increasing not only due to semiconductors but also the spread of AI, data centers, robots, and electric vehicles. This gives weight to voices emphasizing the increased importance of transitioning the power supply system, including regional distribution of power demand and utilization of renewable energy. (문제는 앞으로 이런 불균형이 더욱 심해질 수밖에 없다는 점이다. 반도체뿐만 아니라 인공지능(AI)·데이터센터·로봇·전기차 등의 확산으로 산업계 전반의 전력 수요가 빠르게 늘고 있기 때문이다. 전력 수요의 지역 분산과 재생에너지 활용 등 전력 공급 체계의 전환이 더욱 중요해졌다는 목소리에 힘이 실리는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, some analyses suggest that if the current Yongin semiconductor cluster were to be entirely relocated to the provinces as some in the political sphere argue, individual regions would struggle to handle it with their own surplus power. The maximum annual power consumption when semiconductor factories within the Yongin cluster operate at full capacity is about 131 terawatt-hours (TWh). However, last year's surplus power (cumulative from Jan-Nov) in Gyeongbuk, the region with the most surplus power nationwide, was about 58.7 TWh. Chungnam (47.5 TWh) and Jeonnam (35.4 TWh) had less. This is the background for the argument that production facilities in power-intensive advanced industries and power/renewable energy infrastructure need to be strategically and evenly distributed across regions. (다만, 일각에서는 정치권 일각의 주장대로 현 용인 반도체 클러스터를 통째로 지방으로 옮길 경우, 이를 개별 지역이 자체 잉여 전력으로 감당하기 어렵다는 분석도 나온다. 용인 클러스터 내 반도체 공장들을 1년간 완전가동할 때의 최대 전력 소비량은 약 131테라와트시(TWh)에 이른다. 하지만 전국에서 남는 전기가 가장 많은 경북 지역의 지난해 잉여 전력(1~11월 누적 기준)은 58.7테라와트시 정도다. 충남(47.5테라와트시), 전남(35.4테라와트시) 등은 이보다 적다. 전력 소모가 큰 첨단 산업 분야의 생산 시설과 전력·재생에너지 기반 시설을 전략적으로 지역에 고루 분산해야 한다는 지적이 나오는 배경이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Jong-oh &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박종오 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241764.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503475.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>National Pension Service to Increase Domestic Stock Allocation, Reduce Overseas Holdings... Measures for Exchange Rate and Market Stability (국민연금 주식 비중, 국내 올리고 해외 내린다…환율·시장 안정 조처)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241770.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;National Pension Service to Increase Domestic Stock Allocation, Reduce Overseas Holdings... Measures for Exchange Rate and Market Stability (국민연금 주식 비중, 국내 올리고 해외 내린다…환율·시장 안정 조처)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/639/383/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503535.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민연금공단 건물 사진. 신소영 기자 viator@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Pension Service (NPS) will increase its domestic stock investment allocation in this year's portfolio from the existing 14.4% to 14.9%, a 0.5 percentage point rise, while reducing its overseas stock allocation (37.2%) by 1.7 percentage points from the initial plan. The domestic bond investment allocation will also increase by 1.2 percentage points. This move is interpreted as aligning with the government's policy direction to enhance returns in line with the 'KOSPI 5000' and 'KOSDAQ 1000' era and to seek stability in the foreign exchange market. (국민연금이 올해 포트폴리오에서 국내주식 투자 비중을 기존 14.4%에서 14.9%로 0.5%포인트 늘리고, 해외주식 비중(37.2%)을 당초보다 1.7%포인트 줄인다. 국내채권 투자 비중도 1.2%포인트 늘린다. ‘코스피 5000’, ‘코스닥 1000’ 시대에 맞게 수익률을 높이고 환율시장 안정을 꾀하는 등 정부 정책 기조에 발맞추기 위한 조처로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, the National Pension Fund Management Committee announced that it held its first meeting for 2026 and deliberated and approved the 'National Pension Fund Portfolio Improvement Plan'. The NPS changed its target portfolio in this year's fund management plan, adjusting the target allocation for overseas stocks to 37.2%, which is 1.7 percentage points lower than the initial plan (38.9%). Last year's target allocation was 35.9%. The Fund Management Committee explained, "We considered the burden of foreign exchange procurement due to the expansion of the fund size and the recent foreign exchange market environment characterized by strong dollar demand." ( 26일 국민연금기금운용위원회는 2026년도 제1차 회의를 열어 ‘국민연금기금 포트폴리오 개선방안’을 심의·의결했다고 밝혔다. 국민연금은 올해 기금운용계획상 목표 포트폴리오를 변경해, 해외주식 목표비중을 애초 계획(38.9%)보다 1.7%포인트 낮춘 37.2%로 조정했다. 지난해 목표비중은 35.9%였다. 기금운용위는 “기금 규모 확대에 따른 외환조달 부담과 최근의 달러 수요 우위의 외환시장 환경 등을 고려했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this year's target allocation for domestic stocks was adjusted to 14.9%, which is 0.5 percentage points higher than the initial plan (14.4%). This maintains the same level as last year's target allocation. The Fund Management Committee stated, "We comprehensively considered the impact on fund returns and the existing direction of fund management." ( 반면 올해 국내주식 목표비중은 애초 계획(14.4%)에서 0.5%포인트 높은 14.9%로 조정했다. 지난해 목표비중과 동일한 수준으로 유지되는 것이다. 기금운용위는 “기금수익률에 미치는 영향, 기존 기금운용 방향성 등을 종합적으로 고려했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, the Fund Management Committee decided to temporarily suspend the 'rebalancing' practice, which involves mechanically selling holdings when the domestic stock allocation exceeds the target to adjust to the target level. The reason is that in the current situation of high market volatility due to the recent sharp rise in domestic stock prices, a large-scale sell-off could have an excessive impact on the market. The current rebalancing method was established in 2019 when the fund size was about 713 trillion won. Given that the fund size has more than doubled to 1,438 trillion won (as of the end of November last year), applying the same method would have a significant impact on the market. The Fund Management Committee said, "We considered the recent situation where the domestic stock market and foreign exchange market have changed significantly in a short period, making it difficult to clearly assess market conditions." ( 특히 기금운용위는 국내주식 비중이 목표치를 넘어설 경우 기계적으로 매각해 목표치를 맞추는 ‘리밸런싱’은 한시적으로 하지 않기로 했다. 최근 국내 주가 급등세로 시장 변동성이 큰 상황에서 대규모 매도 물량이 나올 경우 시장에 과도한 영향을 줄 우려가 있다는 이유에서다. 현 리밸런싱 방식은 기금 규모가 약 713조원이던 2019년에 규정된 것인데, 기금 규모가 1438조원(지난해 11월 말 기준)으로 2배 이상 커진 상황에서 이를 그대로 적용하면 시장에 미치는 영향이 크다는 것이다. 기금운용위는 “최근 국내 주식시장과 외환시장이 단기간 크게 변화해 시장 상황에 대한 명확한 평가 등이 어려운 상황을 고려했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NPS will also increase its domestic bond investment allocation from the current 23.7% to 24.9%, a 1.2 percentage point rise. If the NPS's capacity to absorb newly issued government bond supply increases, the likelihood of a decline in bond yields (rise in prices) grows. This appears to be a response to the increasing demand for government bond issuance due to the government's expansionary fiscal policy and the need to secure up to $20 billion annually for investment in the United States. Park Sang-hyun, a senior expert at IM Securities, said, "In a situation where government bond supply is increasing this year, including through the issuance of fund bonds, the increase in the NPS's bond investment allocation is expected to lead to the purchase of some of that supply." However, some view that the management of the National Pension Fund, whose purpose is to secure citizens' retirement income, is being forced to align with policy goals such as 'KOSPI 5000' or exchange rate stability. ( 국민연금은 또 국내채권 투자 비중을 현행 23.7%에서 24.9%로 1.2%포인트 늘린다. 국민연금이 신규발행 국채 물량을 소화하는 여력이 커지면 채권금리 하락(가격 상승) 가능성이 커진다. 정부의 확장재정 및 연 최대 200억달러의 대미 투자 자금 확보를 위한 국채 발행 수요가 커지는 상황에 대응한 것으로 보인다. 박상현 아이엠증권 수석전문위원은 “올해 기금채 발행 등 국채 공급량이 늘어나는 상황인데 국민연금의 채권 투자 비중 증가로 일부 물량을 매입할 것으로 전망된다”고 말했다. 다만 일각에서는 국민의 노후소득 보장 목적인 국민연금기금 운용을 ‘코스피 5000’이나 환율 안정 등 정책 목표에 무리하게 맞추려는 것 아니냐는 시각도 있다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241770.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/639/383/imgdb/original/2026/0126/20260126503535.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Holding on is more expensive in taxes”… Will property holding taxes be raised targeting ‘a single smart property’? (“버티는 세금 비싸게”…‘똘똘한 한 채’ 겨냥 보유세 올리나)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241789.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;“Holding on is more expensive in taxes”… Will property holding taxes be raised targeting ‘a single smart property’? (“버티는 세금 비싸게”…‘똘똘한 한 채’ 겨냥 보유세 올리나)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694633232454_20260126503746.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;26일 서울 남산에서 바라본 아파트 단지 등 서울 시내의 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As President Lee Jae-myung hints at the possibility of strengthening 'property holding taxes,' a sensitive issue ahead of this year's local elections, attention is focused on the specific methods, timing, and impact on the market. Supplementing the side effects that emerged during the previous Moon Jae-in administration's process of strengthening holding taxes is seen as key to the success of the property tax reform. (이재명 대통령이 올해 지방선거를 앞두고 민감한 이슈인 ‘부동산 보유세 강화’ 가능성을 시사한 가운데 구체적인 방식과 시기, 시장에 미칠 영향에 관심이 쏠린다. 과거 문재인 정부의 보유세 강화 과정에서 나타난 부작용을 보완하는 것이&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;부동산 세제 개편의 성패를 좌우할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the night of the 25th, President Lee referenced an article on social media suggesting that the effectiveness of the heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners might be limited, writing, "Even if the tax for holding on is more expensive than the tax paid when selling, can they still do that?" This has been interpreted as a remark hinting at a holding tax increase. (이 대통령은 지난 25일 밤 소셜미디어에 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 효과가 신통치 않을 거라는 기사를 언급하며 “팔면서 내는 세금보다 들고 버티는 세금이 더 비싸도 그렇게 할 수 있을까요”라고 썼다. 이를 두고 보유세 인상을 시사하는 발언이라는 해석이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's repeated mentions of property tax reform stem from a sense of crisis as housing prices continue to rise despite high-intensity measures. Lee Gyu-yeon, Senior Presidential Secretary for Public Communication, said on the 26th, "President Lee has the idea of 'real estate ruining the country.' He is concerned that if things continue this way, we might face a 30-year recession like Japan," adding, "The President has a desperate feeling that this must not happen." (이 대통령이 부동산 세제 개편을 연일 언급하고 있는 것은 고강도 대책에도 집값 상승세가 꺾이지 않는 데 따른 위기감에서다. 이규연 청와대 홍보소통수석은 26일 “이 대통령은 ‘부동산 망국론’의 생각을 갖고 있다. 이대로 가다가는 일본처럼 30년 불황을 겪게 되는 게 아니냐는 것”이라며 “그렇게 되면 안 된다는 절실함을 대통령이 갖고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real estate market predicts that the Lee Jae-myung administration will focus on the comprehensive real estate holding tax (CRET) targeting high-value and multiple homeowners. (부동산 시장에서는 이재명 정부가 고가·다주택자를 겨냥한 종합부동산세(종부세)에 초점을 맞출 것으로 예측한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Methods to strengthen the CRET include △raising the basic tax rate, △lowering the basic deduction amount, △increasing the ratio of publicly announced prices to market prices, and △increasing the fair market value ratio (the ratio multiplied by the publicly announced price to determine the tax base). During the Moon Jae-in administration, the maximum CRET rate for multiple homeowners was raised to 6%, and the fair market value ratio was increased to 95%. This essentially strengthened the progressive structure where higher tax rates apply to higher-value and multiple properties. These measures were all eased under the Yoon Suk-yeol administration, and the Lee Jae-myung administration is expected to partially restore them. (종부세 강화 방식은 △기본세율 인상 △기본 공제액 하향 △공시가격 현실화율(시세 대비 공시가격 비율) 상향 △공정시장 가액비율(과세표준을 정할 때 공시가격에 곱하는 비율) 상향 등이 있다. 문재인 정부 때는 다주택자 종부세 최고세율을 6%까지 인상했고, 공정시장가액비율도 95%까지 올렸다. 고가주택·다주택일수록 더 높은 세율이 적용되는 누진 구조를 강화한 셈이다. 이런 조처들은 윤석열 정부에서 모두 완화됐는데, 이재명 정부는 이를 일부 원상 복구할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experts unanimously agree that a holding tax increase is needed in a way that addresses the so-called 'single smart property' phenomenon, where people own only one property in a core area with high investment value. During the Moon Jae-in administration, while the tax burden on multiple homeowners increased significantly, single homeowners were viewed as 'actual demanders' and protected. This led to a phenomenon where multiple homeowners in non-metropolitan areas, whose combined property values were lower than the price of a single high-value property in Seoul, paid more taxes. Consequently, the preference for a single high-value property, particularly in Seoul's Gangnam area, expanded. (전문가들은 투자 가치가 높은 핵심 지역의 한채만 보유하는 이른바 ‘똘똘한 한채’ 현상을 잡는 방식의 보유세 인상이 필요하다고 입을 모았다. 문재인 정부가 당시 다주택자 세 부담이 많이 늘어난 반면 1주택자는 ‘실수요자’로 보고 보호하면서, 보유 주택 가격을 합쳐도 서울 고가 주택 한채 가격보다 낮은 비수도권 다주택자가 세금을 더 많이 내는 현상이 나타났다. 이 때문에 서울 강남권을 중심으로 고가 1주택 선호 현상이 확대됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chae Sang-wook, CEO of Connected Ground, said, "The Moon Jae-in administration's holding tax actually encouraged the 'single smart property' phenomenon and contributed to rising housing prices," adding, "A paradigm shift from taxation based on the number of properties held to taxation based on value is necessary, and 'loopholes' like the long-term holding special deduction must also be closed." The long-term holding special deduction, which significantly reduces CRET and capital gains tax for owners of a single high-value property who have held and resided in it for a long time, has also been criticized for encouraging the 'single smart property' phenomenon. (채상욱 커넥티드그라운드 대표는 “문재인 정부의 보유세는 똘똘한 한채 현상을 부추겨 외려 집값 상승에 기여한 측면이 있다”며 “보유 주택 수 기준 과세에서 가액 기준 과세로 전환하는 패러다임 변화가 필요하고, 장기보유특별공제와 같은 ‘샛길’도 막아야 한다”고 말했다. 고가 1주택자가 오랫동안 보유·거주할 경우 종부세·양도소득세를 대폭 깎아주는 장기보유특별공제 역시 똘똘한 한채 현상을 부추기는 장치로 비판받아왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reflections are also being raised that a rapid tax increase could excessively fuel tax resistance. Woo Byung-tak, a senior expert at Shinhan Premier Passfinder, pointed out, "During the Moon Jae-in administration, when all holding tax strengthening measures were applied at once, the tax burden snowballed, ultimately leading to regression with the change of administration," and noted, "It is time for a comprehensive reform of the property taxation structure where the tax burden increases gradually over the long term." (급격한 증세는 조세저항을 과도하게 키울 수 있다는 반성도 함께 제기되고 있다. 우병탁 신한프리미어 패스파인더 전문위원은 “문재인 정부 때 보유세 강화 방안을 한꺼번에 쓰면서 세 부담이 눈덩이처럼 불어났고, 결국 정권이 바뀌며 퇴보를 낳았다”며 “장기적으로 세 부담이 완만하게 올라가는 방식의 부동산 과세 구조 전반에 대한 개편이 필요한 때”라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also a point made that a national consensus, including across political parties, is needed to ensure that once a tax increase plan is set, it cannot be reversed. Choi Eun-young, head of the Korea Urban Research Institute, said, "Social consensus is needed so that tax policies do not change with each administration, and it should be established by law through bipartisan agreement, not by enforcement decree." (한번 정해진 증세 계획을 되돌릴 수 없도록 여야를 비롯한 국민적 공감대 형성이 필요하다는 지적도 나온다. 최은영 한국도시연구소장은 “정권에 따라 과세 정책이 바뀌지 않도록 사회적 합의를 이룰 필요가 있고, 여야 합의를 통해 시행령이 아닌 법령으로 정해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike President Lee's series of declarative statements, the actual property tax reform is expected to come after the local elections. The Ministry of Economy and Finance is currently conducting a research service to prepare a holding tax reform plan, with the policy being to reflect the main results into the tax reform proposal in July, after the local elections. (이 대통령이 잇단 선전포고성 발언을 하는 것과 달리 실제 부동산 세제 개편은 지방선거 이후 나올 것으로 보인다. 재정경제부는 현재 보유세 개편 방안을 마련하기 위한 연구용역을 진행 중인데, 주요 결과를 지방선거 이후인 오는 7월 세제개편안에 반영한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241789.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694633232454_20260126503746.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Corporate Sentiment Breaks After Three Months...Manufacturing Up but Services 'Plummet' (기업 심리, 석 달 만에 꺾여...제조업 올라도 서비스업 ‘뚝’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241804.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Corporate Sentiment Breaks After Three Months...Manufacturing Up but Services 'Plummet' (기업 심리, 석 달 만에 꺾여...제조업 올라도 서비스업 ‘뚝’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127500466.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the export boom in semiconductors and other sectors, the perceived business conditions among companies slightly worsened for the first time in three months due to deteriorating performance in the service industry. (반도체 등 수출 호황에도 서비스업 실적 악화로 기업들의 체감 경기가 석달 만에 소폭 나빠졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the results of the Business Survey Index (BSI) released by the Bank of Korea on the 27th, the overall industry BSI for January recorded 94.0, down 0.2 points from the previous month. The BSI, which had rebounded in August and showed an upward trend before reversing to a decline in October, rose for two consecutive months in November and December, but fell again this month. This index quantifies companies' subjective perceptions of their business conditions, where a figure above the long-term average (100) indicates more optimistic responses. This survey was conducted from the 12th to the 19th of this month, with responses from 3,524 companies nationwide. (27일 한국은행이 발표한 기업경기조사를 결과를 보면, 1월 전산업 기업심리지수(CBSI)는 전달 대비 0.2 내린 94.0으로 집계됐다. 기업심리지수는 지난 8월 반등해 상승 흐름을 보이다 10월에 하락 반전했는데, 11·12월 두달 연속 상승하다 이달 다시 하락했다. 이 지수는 기업들의 경영 상황에 대한 주관적 인식을 조사해 지수화한 것으로, 장기 평균(100)을 웃돌면 낙관적 응답이 더 많은 것이다. 이번 조사는 이달 12∼19일 전국 3524개 업체가 응답한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By industry, the manufacturing BSI (97.5) rose by 2.8 points compared to the previous month, centered on production, new orders, and business conditions. In contrast, the non-manufacturing BSI (91.7) fell by 2.1 points due to worsening funding conditions and profitability. However, the forecasted BSI for February recorded increases of 1.0 point for both manufacturing (95.0) and non-manufacturing (88.4). The overall industry forecast also rose by 1.0 point to 91.0. (산업별로 제조업 기업심리지수(97.5)가 생산 및 신규수주, 업황 등을 중심으로 전월보다 2.8 상승했다. 반면 비제조업(91.7)은 자금사정과 채산성 등이 나빠져 2.1 하락했다. 다만, 2월 기업심리지수 전망치는 제조업(95.0)과 비제조업(88.4) 모두 1.0씩 오른 것으로 집계됐다. 전산업도 1.0 오른 91.0으로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-young, head of the Economic Survey Team at the Bank of Korea, stated, "While manufacturing improved in sectors like primary metals and other machinery equipment due to export expansion, the BSI declined compared to the previous month as year-end seasonal demand disappeared in some non-manufacturing sectors like information and communications." She added, "Next month, non-manufacturing is also expected to improve due to better performance in retail/wholesale and sports/leisure-related sectors during the Lunar New Year holiday period." (이혜영 한은 경제심리조사팀장은 “제조업이 1차 금속, 기타 기계장비 업종에서 수출 확대 등으로 개선됐지만 정보통신업 등 일부 비제조업의 연말 계절적 수요가 사라지면서 기업심리지수가 전월 대비 하락했다”며 “다음달에는 설 연휴 기간 도소매업과 스포츠·여가 관련 업종 실적 개선 등으로 비제조업도 개선될 것으로 전망됐다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241804.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127500466.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kyung Hee University Publishing &amp; Culture Center Publishes &lt;The Birth of China&gt; (경희대 출판문화원, &amp;lt;중국의 탄생&amp;gt; 출간)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241808.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kyung Hee University Publishing &amp; Culture Center Publishes &lt;The Birth of China&gt; (경희대 출판문화원, &amp;lt;중국의 탄생&amp;gt; 출간)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/895/imgdb/original/2026/0127/2317694731396065.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;중국의 탄생_표지(평면).경희대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Kyung Hee University (President Kim Jin-sang) Publishing &amp; Culture Center has published &lt;The Birth of China&gt;, a specialized research book on Liang Qichao (梁啓超, 1873–1929) written by Professor Jung Ji-ho of the Department of History at Kyung Hee University, who has served as president of the Ming-Qing History Society, the East Asian History Society, and the Chinese Modern and Contemporary History Society. This book, which provides a full-fledged examination of Liang Qichao's scholarship and thought, is the first in Korea to systematically explore Liang Qichao's views on history, economics, finance, and theories of empire and national character, as well as fundamental elements of the modern nation-state such as nationality law and the legal status of Koreans residing in China's northeastern region.&lt;br/&gt;Although Liang Qichao has long been criticized as a 'royalist advocating constitutional monarchy' and a 'conservative reformist,' the author of this book, Professor Jung Ji-ho, evaluates Liang Qichao's thought as being very bold and innovative. The author emphasizes that Liang Qichao's thought was an expression of practice aimed at solving the historical task of building a nation-state and a reformist attempt to drive fundamental change in Chinese society.&lt;br/&gt;Compared to the importance of Liang Qichao's thought in the formation of modern China, academic research on him has been insufficient. In this context, &lt;The Birth of China: Liang Qichao's Struggle to Build a Nation-State&gt; will serve not only as an important guide to Liang Qichao's thought but also as a handbook for understanding China's past, present, and even future, as well as the modernization of East Asia. (경희대학교(총장 김진상) 출판문화원이 명청사학회 회장을 역임하고 동양사학회와 중국 근현대사학회 회장인 경희대 사학과 정지호 교수가 쓴 량치차오(梁啓超, 1873~1929) 전문 연구서인 &amp;lt;중국의 탄생&amp;gt;을 출간했다. 량치차오의 학문과 사상을 본격적으로 조명한 이 책은 량치차오의 역사관, 경제관, 재정관, 제국론, 국성론을 비롯해 근대 국민국가의 기본 요소인 국적법과 중국 동북지역에 거주하던 조선인의 법적 지위 문제까지 체계적으로 고찰한 국내 최초의 책이다.&lt;br/&gt;그동안 량치차오는 &amp;#x27;입헌군주제를 지향한 보황파(보황파)&amp;#x27;, &amp;#x27;보수 개량주의자&amp;#x27; 등으로 비판받아 왔지만, 이 책의 저자 정지호 교수는 량치차오의 사상이 매우 과감하고 혁신적이었다고 평가한다. 저자는 량치차오의 사상이 국민국가 건설이라는 시대적 과제를 해결하기 위한 실천의 표현이자 중국 사회의 근본적 변화를 추동하려는 개혁적 시도였다고 강조한다.&lt;br/&gt;근대 중국의 형성 과정에서 량치차오 사상이 갖는 중요성에 비해 그에 관한 학술 연구는 부족한 실정이다. 이런 상황에서 &amp;lt;중국의 탄생: 량치차오의 국민국가 건설 분투기&amp;gt;는 량치차오의 사상에 대한 중요한 안내서일 뿐만 아니라, 중국의 과거와 현재, 나아가 미래까지, 그리고 동아시아의 근대화를 이해하는 지침서가 될 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kyung Hee University (* 자료제공 :  경희대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241808.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/895/imgdb/original/2026/0127/2317694731396065.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy: "Minister Kim Jeong-gwan to Visit U.S. Soon, Discuss Tariff Issues with Ruttnick" (산업부 “김정관 장관 곧 방미, 러트닉과 관세 문제 협의”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241815.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy: "Minister Kim Jeong-gwan to Visit U.S. Soon, Discuss Tariff Issues with Ruttnick" (산업부 “김정관 장관 곧 방미, 러트닉과 관세 문제 협의”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/718/500/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127500794.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김정관 산업통상부 장관(오른쪽)이 지난 26일 한화오션 등의 캐나다 잠수함 사업 수주 지원을 위해 함께 출국한 강훈식 대통령 비서실장 옆에 서 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid threats from U.S. President Donald Trump to raise the reciprocal tariff rate and the tariff rate on automobile items for South Korea back to 25%, Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jeong-gwan has decided to visit the U.S. soon to hold discussions with Secretary of Commerce Howard Ruttnick, among others. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 한국에 대한 상호관세율과 자동차 품목관세율을 25%로 다시 올리겠다고 위협한 가운데 김정관 산업통상부 장관이 곧 방미해 하워드 러트닉 상무장관 등과 협의에 나서기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy stated, "We are assessing the situation regarding the U.S. announcement," and added, "Minister Kim plans to visit the U.S. to assess the situation and pursue discussions with Secretary Ruttnick." Minister Kim is currently visiting Canada as a member of a presidential special envoy to support Hanwha Ocean and HD Hyundai Heavy Industries in securing a Canadian submarine project contract. (산업부는 27일 “미국의 발표에 대해 상황을 파악 중”이라며 “김 장관이 방미하여 상황 파악 및 러트닉 장관과의 협의를 추진할 계획”이라고 밝혔다. 김 장관은 현재 한화오션과 에이치디(HD)현대중공업의 캐나다 잠수함 사업 수주 지원을 위한 대통령 특사단 일원으로 캐나다를 방문 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 26th (local time), Trump posted on social media, "I made a great agreement for both countries with President Lee Jae-myung on July 30 last year and reconfirmed those terms when I visited South Korea on October 29 last year. So why hasn't the South Korean National Assembly approved it?" He stated, "I will increase the reciprocal tariffs on all items from South Korea, including automobiles, timber, and pharmaceuticals, from 15% to 25%." This is interpreted as expressing dissatisfaction that a special bill centered on a $350 billion (approximately 500 trillion won) investment in the U.S. was submitted to the South Korean National Assembly but has not been passed. (트럼프는 앞서 26일(현지시각) 소셜미디어를 통해 “이재명 대통령과 지난해 7월30일 양국 모두에 훌륭한 협정을 체결했으며, 지난해 10월29일 한국을 방문했을 때 그 조건을 다시 확인했다. 그런데 왜 한국 국회는 이를 승인하지 않고 있나”라며 “한국의 자동차, 목재, 의약품을 비롯한 모든 품목에 대한 상호 관세를 15%에서 25%로 인상한다”고 밝혔다. 이는 한국 국회에 3500억달러(약 500조원) 규모의 대미 투자를 중심으로 한 특별법안이 제출됐으나 통과되지 않고 있는 것에 대한 불만을 표출한 것으로 해석된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Bon-young &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이본영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241815.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/718/500/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127500794.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sahmyook University Successfully Concludes 'Nowon Children's English Camp' for Winter Vacation (삼육대, 겨울방학 맞아 ‘노원 어린이 영어캠프’ 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241817.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sahmyook University Successfully Concludes 'Nowon Children's English Camp' for Winter Vacation (삼육대, 겨울방학 맞아 ‘노원 어린이 영어캠프’ 성료)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/original/2026/0127/1517694761732244.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;삼육대 노원 어린이 영어캠프.삼육대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The '2026 Winter Vacation Nowon Children's Native English Camp,' jointly operated by Sahmyook University (President Je Hae-jong) and Nowon District, successfully concluded with a closing ceremony on the 25th.&lt;br/&gt;This camp is an intensive experiential program designed for elementary school students to learn practical English in an environment comparable to actual language study abroad during vacation, and to develop a global sense through various cultural and sports activities.&lt;br/&gt;It began in 2005 and has been held every summer and winter vacation, marking its 22nd year in 2026. The cumulative number of graduates to date is approximately 15,000.&lt;br/&gt;This year's camp was held over an 8-day, 7-night schedule from January 18th to 25th on the Sahmyook University campus. It recruited 160 students in grades 3 to 6 residing in Nowon District, dividing them into 8 classes of 20 students each. Students were placed in classes appropriate to their learning level based on a preliminary level test, enabling more effective learning.&lt;br/&gt;During the camp, students participated in classes led by native English teachers and Korean assistant teachers within an 'EOZ (English Only Zone)' environment where only English was used throughout the entire schedule. The program aimed to naturally foster cooperation, consideration, and international etiquette through communal living, in addition to English learning.&lt;br/&gt;The program consisted of listening, reading, writing, speaking, and pronunciation classes, along with experiential activities. Activities such as △art activities and cultural experiences with native teachers, △English learning through sports activities, and △practical English classes simulating daily situations like airports, hospitals, and restaurants increased student interest and participation.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, community programs like △campfires and △recreation with songs and dances provided opportunities for students to communicate naturally with peers and build camaraderie.&lt;br/&gt;President Je Hae-jong stated, "The camp has been successfully operated for a long time thanks to the combination of Sahmyook University's educational capabilities and Nowon District's active support," adding, "We hope the students grow into global talents who challenge themselves towards a broader world."
Nowon District Mayor Oh Seung-rok said, "I hope this camp served as a valuable experience for the children, not only improving their English skills but also building confidence through independent living," and expressed gratitude, saying, "I thank Sahmyook University for operating the camp safely and substantively, and the parents who trusted the district and sent their children to the camp." (삼육대(총장 제해종)와 노원구가 협력해 운영한 ‘2026년 겨울방학 노원 어린이 원어민 영어캠프’가 지난 25일 수료식을 끝으로 성황리에 마무리됐다.&lt;br/&gt;이 캠프는 방학 기간을 활용해 초등학생들이 실제 어학연수에 준하는 환경에서 실용 영어를 익히고, 다양한 문화·체육 활동을 하며 글로벌 감각을 키울 수 있도록 마련된 집중 체험형 프로그램이다. &lt;br/&gt;2005년 시작돼 매년 여름과 겨울방학마다 운영되고 있으며, 올해로 22년째를 맞았다. 지금까지 누적 수료생은 약 1만 5천 명에 달한다.&lt;br/&gt;올해 캠프는 1월 18일부터 25일까지 7박 8일 일정으로 삼육대 캠퍼스 일원에서 진행됐다. 노원구에 거주하는 초등학교 3~6학년 학생 160명을 모집해 20명씩 8개 반으로 나눠 운영했다. 학생들은 사전 레벨 테스트를 거쳐 학습 수준에 맞는 반에 배치돼 보다 효과적인 학습이 이뤄졌다.&lt;br/&gt;캠프 기간 동안 학생들은 전 일정 영어만 사용하는 ‘EOZ(English Only Zone)’ 환경 속에서 원어민 교사와 한국인 부교사가 함께 진행하는 수업에 참여했다. 영어 학습뿐만 아니라 공동체 생활을 하며 협력과 배려, 국제적 예절을 자연스럽게 익히도록 했다.&lt;br/&gt;프로그램은 듣기·읽기·쓰기·말하기·발음 수업과 함께 체험형 활동으로 구성됐다. △원어민 교사와 함께하는 예술 활동 및 문화 체험 △스포츠 활동을 통한 영어 학습 △공항·병원·식당 등 일상 상황을 재현한 실용 영어 수업 등이 학생들의 흥미와 참여도를 높였다.&lt;br/&gt;또한 △캠프파이어 △노래와 춤이 어우러진 레크리에이션 등 공동체 프로그램을 통해 또래 친구들과 자연스럽게 소통하고 친밀감을 쌓는 시간도 마련됐다.&lt;br/&gt;제해종 총장은 “삼육대의 교육 역량과 노원구의 적극적인 지원이 어우러져 캠프가 오랜 기간 성공적으로 운영될 수 있었다”며 “학생들이 더 넓은 세상을 향해 도전하는 글로벌 인재로 성장하길 기대한다”고 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;오승록 노원구청장은 “이번 캠프가 어린이들에게 영어 실력 향상은 물론, 스스로 생활하며 자신감을 키우는 소중한 경험이 됐기를 바란다”며 “안전하고 내실 있게 캠프를 운영해 준 삼육대와 구를 믿고 캠프에 자녀를 보내주신 학부모님들께 감사드린다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sahmyook University (* 자료제공 :  삼육대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241817.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/original/2026/0127/1517694761732244.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Small Business Owners Demand: "Coupang, Stop Your 'Bulletproof Lobbying' in the U.S. and Prepare Compensation Measures" (소상공인들 “쿠팡, 미국 ‘방탄 로비’ 중단하고 보상책 마련하라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241819.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Small Business Owners Demand: "Coupang, Stop Your 'Bulletproof Lobbying' in the U.S. and Prepare Compensation Measures" (소상공인들 “쿠팡, 미국 ‘방탄 로비’ 중단하고 보상책 마련하라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/542/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501019.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 23일 서울 광화문 광장 미국대사관 앞에서 안전한 쿠팡 만들기 공동행동 등 시민사회단체 회원들이 ‘불법기업 쿠팡 비호, 내정간섭 일삼는 미국 정·재계 규탄 긴급기자회견’을 열고 구호를 외치고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The small business industry has stepped forward to criticize Coupang's all-out lobbying activities in the United States and urge the preparation of measures for domestic partner small businesses. (소상공인 업계가 쿠팡의 전방위적인 미국 로비 활동을 비판하며 국내 입점 소상공인을 위한 대책 마련을 촉구하고 나섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Small Business Federation issued a commentary on the 27th, urging, "Coupang must stop its all-out 'bulletproof lobbying' targeting U.S. political circles and prepare substantial compensation measures for partner small businesses." The Federation pointed out, "Coupang is squeezing the lifeblood of Korean small businesses and pouring it into 'bulletproof lobbying' to curry favor with U.S. political circles," and added, "Coupang remains unmoved, ignoring the damages suffered by partner small businesses." (소상공인연합회는 27일 논평을 내어 “쿠팡은 미국 정가를 대상으로 한 전방위 ‘방탄 로비’를 중단하고 입점 소상공인에게 실질적 보상책을 마련하라”고 촉구했다. 연합회는 “쿠팡은 한국 소상공인들의 고혈을 짜내어 미국 정치권의 환심을 사는 ‘방탄 로비’에 쏟아붓고 있다”며 “쿠팡은 입점 소상공인의 피해는 나 몰라라 한 채 요지부동”이라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These organizations emphasized that Coupang is siphoning astronomical funds overseas to protect its own interests. The Federation claimed, "Coupang is leaking large-scale funds to the U.S., executing them as lobbying funds, and is solely preoccupied with protecting its own interests." It then added, "There are media reports that Coupang Inc. (Coupang's U.S. corporation) has spent approximately 15.9 billion won ($10.755 million) over the four years since its listing as lobbying funds to various offices including the U.S. Trade Representative (USTR), the Department of Commerce, the National Security Council (NSC), and the White House." (이들 단체는 쿠팡이 자사 이익 수호를 위해 천문학적인 자금을 해외로 유출하고 있다는 점을 강조했다. 연합회는 “쿠팡이 미국으로 대규모 자금을 유출해 로비 자금으로 집행하며 자사 이익 수호에만 골몰하고 있다”고 주장했다. 그러면서 “쿠팡아이엔씨(Inc·쿠팡 미국 법인)가 상장 이후 4년간 미국무역대표부(USTR), 상무부, 국가안전보장회의(NSC), 백악관 등 각 처에 약 159억원(1075만 5000달러)을 로비 자금으로 지출했다는 언론보도가 있다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the Federation mentioned △Item Winner (a system where the seller offering the lowest price can take the product photos and reviews of other sellers for the same product) △Preferential treatment of PB (private brand) products △Price pressure on partner companies, and criticized, "In the end, Coupang is exploiting the lifeblood of South Korean small businesses and using it as U.S. lobbying funds." (이어 연합회는 △아이템 위너(최저가를 내놓은 판매자가 같은 상품에 대한 다른 판매자의 상품 사진과 후기를 가져갈 수 있게 하는 제도) △피비(PB) 상품 우대 △입점업체 가격 압박 등을 언급하며 “결국 쿠팡은 대한민국 소상공인의 고혈을 착취해 미국 로비 자금으로 쓰고 있는 셈”이라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federation also hinted at a strong legal response. The Federation stated, "The damages suffered by Coupang's partner small businesses are snowballing," and declared, "If visible measures from Coupang are not prepared within a short period, we will respond strongly by mobilizing all legal means, including collective lawsuits, through legal support for Coupang's partner small businesses." (연합회는 강력한 법적 대응 의사도 내비쳤다. 연합회는 “쿠팡 입점 소상공인들의 피해는 눈덩이처럼 불어나고 있다”며 “조속한 시일 내에 쿠팡 측의 가시적인 대책 마련이 이뤄지지 않을 경우, 쿠팡 입점 소상공인의 법률지원 등을 통해 집단소송 등 모든 법적수단을 동원해 강력 대응할 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federation demanded a responsible stance from Coupang's management. The Federation strongly urged, "We strongly urge Coupang and Kim Beom-seok, Chairman of the Board of Coupang Inc., to no longer hide behind the U.S. but to come forward openly and show a responsible attitude towards South Korean small businesses." (연합회는 쿠팡 경영진의 책임 있는 자세를 요구했다. 연합회는 “쿠팡과 김범석 쿠팡아이엔씨 이사회 의장이 더 이상 미국 뒤에 숨지 말고 떳떳이 나와 대한민국 소상공인들에게 책임지는 자세를 보일 것을 강력히 촉구한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241819.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/542/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501019.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Even with '5,000 points', the circulating stock ratio of top market cap companies is only around half (‘오천피’에도 시총 상위 기업 유통주식은 절반 수준)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241827.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Even with '5,000 points', the circulating stock ratio of top market cap companies is only around half (‘오천피’에도 시총 상위 기업 유통주식은 절반 수준)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/360/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501176.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;26일 오후 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸 전광판에 코스닥 지수가 나타나고 있다. 코스닥 종가가 1000을 넘어선 것은 2022년 이후 4년 만이다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the KOSPI index is eyeing the 5,000-point level, it has been found that the ratio of shares circulating in the market among the stocks of top market capitalization companies is only around half. Particularly, the larger the business group, the more shares are tied up for purposes such as defending the controlling family's management control and securing dominance, raising concerns that this could reduce the overall market's liquidity. (코스피(KOSPI) 지수가 5000선을 넘보고 있는 가운데, 시가총액 상위 기업의 주식 중 시장에서 유통되는 주식 비율은 절반 남짓한 수준인 것으로 나타났다. 특히 대기업집단일수록 총수 일가의 경영권 방어, 지배력 확보 등을 위해 주식 지분이 묶여 있어, 전체 시장의 유동성을 떨어뜨릴 수 있다는 우려가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the 'Analysis Results of Actual Circulating Shares of Top 300 Market Cap Companies' released by corporate analysis research institute Leaders Index on the 27th, the average actual circulating share ratio for the 266 analyzed companies was 57.1%. This is a 0.2 percentage point decrease compared to three years ago (57.3%) when the KOSPI index was hovering around the 2,000-3,000 point level. Actual circulating shares refer to shares released into the stock market that general investors can freely buy and sell. The higher the circulating shares, the more active trading can occur in the market, leading to higher liquidity. Conversely, liquidity decreases when shares are held by controlling families of large corporations or special related parties for purposes like defending management control and maintaining dominance, and not released to the market. (  기업분석 연구소 리더스인덱스가 27일 발표한 ‘시총(시가총액) 상위 300대 기업 실질 유통주식 분석 결과’를 보면, 분석 대상 266개 기업의 실질 유통주식 비율은 평균 57.1%로 집계됐다. 이는 코스피 지수가 2000~3000선을 맴돌던 3년 전(57.3%)보다 0.2%포인트 낮아진 수치다. 실질 유통주식은 주식 시장에 풀려 일반 투자자들이 자유롭게 사고팔 수 있는 주식을 말한다. 유통주식이 많을수록 시장에서 활발하게 거래가 이뤄질 수 있어 유동성이 높아진다. 반면 대기업 총수 일가나 특수관계인 등이 주식을 경영권 방어와 지배력 유지 등을 위해 보유한 채 시장에 내놓지 않으면 유동성은 낮아진다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, narrowing the focus to large business groups reveals that the actual circulating share ratio decreases even further. The circulating share ratio for 148 listed companies belonging to large business groups was 53.5%, a 0.8 percentage point drop from three years ago. This falls below the average actual circulating share ratio (57.1%) of all analyzed companies. (  실제로 대기업집단으로 대상을 좁혀보면 실질 유통주식 비율은 더욱 줄어든다는 점을 확인할 수 있다. 대기업집단 소속 상장사 148곳의 유통주식 비율은 53.5%로, 3년 전보다 0.8%포인트 낮아졌다. 전체 분석 대상 기업의 실질 유통주식 비율 평균(57.1%)을 밑도는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the circulating share ratio for listed companies not part of large business groups was 61.7%, exceeding the average. It also increased by 0.7 percentage points over the three years. Leaders Index analyzed that "the large corporate affiliates leading the total market capitalization are instead blocking the stock market's liquidity." (  반면 대기업집단이 아닌 상장사의 유통주식 비율은 61.7%로 평균을 웃돌았다. 3년 사이 0.7%포인트 높아지기도 했다. 리더스인덱스는 “전체 시총을 주도하는 대기업 계열사들이 오히려 증시의 유동성을 막고 있다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among individual companies, Dongwon Business, the holding company of the Dongwon Group, had the lowest circulating share ratio. The company's circulating share ratio was 12.1%, the lowest among the surveyed subjects. It was followed by Kyobo Securities (14.3%), Mirae Asset Life Insurance (15.1%), LG Energy Solution (18.2%), Gaon Cable (18.4%), and Samsung Card (20.2%). (개별기업 중 유통주식 비율이 가장 낮은 곳은 동원그룹의 지주사인 동원사업이다. 이 회사의 유통주식 비율은 12.1%로 조사 대상 중 가장 낮았다. 이어 교보증권(14.3%), 미래에셋생명(15.1%), 엘지(LG)에너지솔루션(18.2%), 가온전선(18.4%), 삼성카드(20.2%) 등이 뒤를 이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company with the highest circulating share ratio was Hyulim Robot at 92.9%. It was followed by Woory Industrial Technology (91.5%), Peptron (91.2%), Shinhan Financial Group (91.1%), and Woori Financial Group (90.8%) in the top ranks. It is interpreted that financial holding companies have high circulating share ratios because they have no controlling shareholders due to the principle of separating banking and industrial capital (the 'bank-commerce separation' principle). (  유통주식 비율이 가장 높은 기업은 휴림로봇으로 92.9%였다. 이어 우리기술(91.5%), 펩트론(91.2%), 신한지주(91.1%), 우리금융지주(90.8%) 등도 상위권에 이름을 올렸다. 금융지주사는 은행과 산업자본 분리 원칙(은산분리)에 따라 지배주주가 없기 때문에 유통주식 비율이 높은 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241827.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/360/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501176.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Government's Lax Self-Assessment of Fiscal Projects... 150 Private Experts Deployed (정부 재정사업 느슨한 자기평가에…민간 전문가 150명 투입)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241830.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/454/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501298.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has decided to unify the performance evaluation of major fiscal projects this year into a joint inter-ministerial assessment and involve around 150 private experts in the evaluation process. The evaluation results will be reflected in budget formulation, and the evaluation reports will be made public. (정부가 올해부터 주요 재정사업 성과평가를 부처 합동 평가로 일원화하고, 150명 규모의 민간 전문가들을 평가에 참여시키기로 했다. 평가 결과는 예산 편성에 반영하고 평가보고서는 공개하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Economy and Finance (MOEF) reported the '2026 Fiscal Project Performance Management Implementation Plan' at a Cabinet meeting held at the Blue House on the 27th. Fiscal project performance management refers to the annual plan established according to the five-year basic plan for fiscal project performance management. It serves as a blueprint for evaluating each ministry's fiscal projects and utilizing the results in fiscal operations. Fiscal projects worth 184 trillion won based on this year's budget are subject to evaluation. (기획예산처는 27일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 ‘2026년 재정사업 성과관리 추진계획’을 보고했다. 재정사업 성과관리란 5년 단위의 재정사업 성과관리 기본계획에 따라 매년 수립하는 것으로, 각 부처의 재정사업을 평가하고 이를 재정운용에 활용하기 위한 밑그림이다. 올해 예산 기준으로 184조원의 재정사업이 평가 대상이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government decided to unify this year's performance evaluation into a joint inter-ministerial assessment involving external experts, moving away from the previous dual-track system where evaluations were conducted separately by ministries and the fiscal authority. Currently, after each ministry conducts a self-assessment of its fiscal projects, the MOEF reviews it, creating a dual-evaluation system. However, there have been criticisms that ministries tend to be lenient in their self-assessments, and the fiscal authority conducting the second-stage review has limitations in thoroughly examining them. (정부는 올해 성과평가를 그동안 부처·재정당국으로 이원화됐던 평가 방식을 외부 전문가가 참여하는 관계부처 합동 평가로 일원화하기로 했다. 현재는 각 부처에서 재정사업에 대해 자체평가를 하면, 기획처가 이를 점검하는 이중평가 방식이었다. 그러나 부처들이 자체 평가에서 스스로 관대한 평가를 하고, 2단계 평가를 맡은 재정당국에서도 이를 검토하는 데에 한계가 있다는 지적이 제기돼 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, the government decided to conduct joint inter-ministerial assessments but involve a private expert evaluation panel to ensure assessments are made from a neutral perspective. The expert panel will consist of around 150 members across 15 fields, including individuals recommended by ministries and civil society. The relevant ministry will participate in the entire evaluation process to present its self-check results. (이에 따라 정부는 부처 합동 평가를 하되 중립적 관점에서 평가하도록 민간 전문가 평가단을 참여시키기로 했다. 전문가 평가단은 15개 분야 150명 안팎으로 꾸려지며, 부처별 추천인사와 시민사회 추천인사 등이 참여하게 된다. 소관 부처는 평가 전 과정에 참여해 자체 점검 결과를 개진하게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the change in the evaluation system, the current evaluation results of 'Excellent, Average, Deficient' issued by departments themselves will also change to 'Normal Progress, Project Improvement, Budget Reduction, Abolition/Integration'. The intent is to categorize evaluation results and link them directly to the budget. The MOEF stated, "For projects with poor performance, the budget will in principle be cut. However, for cases where reduction is difficult, such as support for vulnerable groups or mandatory expenditures, penalties (sanctions) will be imposed on operational costs, etc. For projects with excellent performance, budget increase recommendations, deferral of evaluation for the following year, and awards for responsible personnel will be pursued." Evaluation reports and performance records of expenditure restructuring by project will be disclosed on the 'Open Information' system, a fiscal information disclosure platform. Additionally, the government plans to conduct a comprehensive evaluation this year on state subsidy projects subject to sunset provisions. (평가 체계가 바뀌면서 현재 부서 자체적으로 ‘우수, 보통, 미흡’으로 내놓던 평가결과도 ‘정상추진, 사업개선, 감액, 폐지·통합’으로 바뀐다. 평가결과를 유형화해 예산에 직접 연계한다는 취지다. 기획처는 “성과 부실사업은 원칙적으로 삭감하되 취약계층지원·의무지출 성격 등 감액이 곤란한 경우는 사업운영비 등에서 페널티(제재)를 부여하고, 성과 우수사업은 증액 권고, 차년도 평가유예 및 담당자 포상을 추진한다”고 밝혔다. 평가보고서와 사업별 지출구조조정 실적 등은 재정정보 공개시스템인 ‘열린정보’에 공개된다. 이 밖에도 정부는 일몰제가 적용되는 국가보조사업에 대해서도 올해 전수 평가한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The MOEF stated it aims to complete the evaluations before each ministry submits its budget request proposal in May. An MOEF official said, "There have been issues raised regarding the objectivity and reliability of each ministry's self-assessments. Therefore, we are forming a neutral evaluation panel to assess all ministry projects based on uniform standards," adding, "I think the scale of restructuring will inevitably be larger than the expenditure restructuring based on the previous self-assessments by ministries." Acting Vice Minister Lim Ki-geun of the MOEF said, "To support the active role of fiscal policy, a strict and systematic expenditure restructuring system acceptable to both ministries and the public is essential," and added, "Through the integrated performance evaluation, we will overcome the limitations revealed during the operational process over the past 20 years and support substantial restructuring." (기획처는 각 부처가 오는 5월 예산요구안을 제출하기 전까지 평가를 끝내겠다고 밝혔다. 기획처 관계자는 “그동안 각 부처의 자체 평가에 대해 객관성과 신뢰성 문제가 제기됐고, 이에 중립적인 평가단을 구성해 모든 부처의 사업을 일률적인 기준에서 평가하겠다는 것”이라며 “기존 부처들의 자체평가에 따른 지출 구조조정보다 구조조정 규모는 높아질 수밖에 없지 않을까 생각한다”고 했다. 임기근 기획처 장관 직무대행 차관은 “재정의 적극적 역할을 뒷받침하기 위해서는 부처·국민이 함께 수용할 수 있는 엄격하고 체계적인 지출구조조정 시스템이 필수적”이라며 “통합 성과평가를 통해 지난 20여 년의 운영 과정에서 드러난 한계를 극복해 실질적인 구조조정을 뒷받침하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241830.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/454/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501298.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Professor Joohee Park of Kookmin University's Asia Olympic Graduate School Receives the 37th Yungok Kim Un-yong Women's Sports Award for Meritorious Service (국민대 아시아올림픽대학원 박주희 교수, 제37회 윤곡 김운용 여성체육대상 공로상 수상)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241834.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/618/804/imgdb/original/2026/0127/1417694796858962.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;박주희 교수.국민대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Joohee Park of the Asia Olympic Governance &amp; Policy major at Kookmin University's (President Seungryul Jeong) Asia Olympic Graduate School received the Meritorious Service Award at the 37th Yungok Kim Un-yong Women's Sports Award ceremony held on Monday, January 26.&lt;br/&gt;The Yungok Kim Un-yong Women's Sports Award is Korea's first women's sports award ceremony, established in 1989 by the late Kim Un-yong, Vice Chairman of the International Olympic Committee (IOC), for the successful hosting of the 1988 Seoul Olympics and the development of Korean women's sports.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Joohee Park of Kookmin University was recognized for her contributions to enhancing the international status of Korean sports and expanding the role and leadership of women in sports, as Korea's first female FINA Executive Committee member and an international sports expert.&lt;br/&gt;In particular, through her activities centered around international sports organizations, she has consistently participated in policy and institutional discussions for sports governance, ethics, athlete protection, and creating a fair sports environment. Based on her practical experience on the international stage, she has worked towards structural improvements and raising awareness to expand women's participation in sports and strengthen their leadership.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Park expressed her feelings, saying, "I am grateful to receive this meaningful award," and added, "I will continue to contribute to creating an environment where women and the next generation can grow sustainably, based on fairness and responsibility in the international sports field." (국민대학교(총장 정승렬) 아시아올림픽대학원 아시아올림픽거버넌스 · 정책전공 박주희 교수가 지난 1월 26일(월) 개최된 제37회 윤곡 김운용 여성체육대상 시상식에서 공로상을 수상했다.&lt;br/&gt;윤곡 김운용 여성체육대상은 고(故) 김운용 국제올림픽위원회(IOC) 부위원장이 1988 서울 올림픽의 성공적 개최와 한국 여성체육 발전을 위해 1989년 제정한 한국 최초의 여성 스포츠 시상식이다.&lt;br/&gt;국민대 박주희 교수는 한국 여성 최초의 세계수영연맹 집행위원이자 국제 스포츠 전문가로서, 대한민국 스포츠의 국제적 위상을 제고하고 여성 체육인의 역할과 리더십 확대에 기여해 온 공로를 인정받았다. &lt;br/&gt;특히, 국제 스포츠 기구를 중심으로 한 활동을 통해 스포츠 거버넌스와 윤리, 선수 보호, 공정한 스포츠 환경 조성을 위한 정책·제도 논의에 지속적으로 참여해 왔으며, 국제 무대에서의 실무 경험을 바탕으로 여성의 스포츠 참여 확대와 리더십 강화를 위한 구조적 개선과 인식 제고에 힘써 왔다.&lt;br/&gt;박 교수는 &amp;quot;뜻깊은 상을 받게 되어 감사하게 생각한다&amp;quot;며, &amp;quot;앞으로도 국제 스포츠 현장에서 공정성과 책임을 바탕으로 여성과 차세대가 지속적으로 성장할 수 있는 환경을 만드는 데 기여하겠다&amp;quot;고 소감을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kookmin University (* 자료제공 :  국민대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241834.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/618/804/imgdb/original/2026/0127/1417694796858962.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:47:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Recovers to 5000... Rebounds After Stumbling on Trump Tariff Shock, KOSDAQ Also Rises (코스피 5000 회복…트럼프발 관세 쇼크에 주춤 뒤 반등, 코스닥도↑)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241835.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/597/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501361.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;27일 오전 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸에서 직원들이 증시와 환율을 모니터하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI started sharply lower on the 27th, plummeting on remarks by U.S. President Donald Trump that he would revert tariffs on Korean products to pre-trade agreement levels, but it soon significantly recovered most of its losses and is trading again above the 5,000 mark. (한국산 제품에 대한 관세를 무역합의 이전으로 되돌리겠다는 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 발언에 코스피가 27일 급락하며 출발했으나 곧바로 낙폭을 크게 만회해 재차 5천선을 회복하며 거래되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 10:50 AM, the KOSPI is at 5009.02, up 59.79 points (1.21%) from the previous day. After opening lower at 4932.89, down 16.70 points (0.34%), the index fell to as low as 4890.72 at one point before recovering all losses and shifting to a significant upward trend. (이날 오전 10시50분 현재 코스피는 전날보다 59.79(1.21%) 오른 5009.02를 나타내고 있다. 지수는 16.70(0.34%) 내린 4932.89로 개장한 이후 한때 4890.72까지 밀렸다가 낙폭을 전부 회복하고 오히려 크게 상승하는 흐름으로 돌아섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Seoul foreign exchange market, the won-dollar exchange rate is at 1449.10 won, up 8.5 won from the previous day's closing price during daytime trading (3:30 PM at 1440.60 won). The exchange rate had fallen for four consecutive days after President Lee Jae-myung said on the 21st that "the exchange rate will fall to around 1,400 won within a month or two," but turned upward on this day for the first time in five days. This appears to be due to increased risk-averse sentiment as uncertainty over tariffs triggered by President Trump has grown again. (서울 외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 전날 주간거래 종가(오후 3시30분 1440.60원)보다 8.5원 오른 1449.10원을 나타내고 있다. 환율은 지난 21일 이재명 대통령이 “한두 달 새 환율이 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것”이라고 말한 뒤 나흘 연속 하락했다가 이날 닷새 만에 상승세로 돌아섰다. 트럼프 대통령발 관세 불확실성이 다시 커지면서 위험 회피 심리가 커진 영향으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The domestic stock market started with a sharp decline after President Trump stated in a post on the social media platform Truth Social that he would raise tariffs on Korean products back to pre-trade agreement levels. President Trump said, "The Korean legislature is not upholding the agreement between Korea and the United States. Accordingly, I am raising all reciprocal tariffs (country-specific tariffs) on automobiles, lumber, pharmaceuticals, and everything else from 15% to 25%." He appears to be referring to the 'Special Act on Strategic Investment Management with the United States' (U.S. Investment Special Act), which must be passed by the National Assembly to fulfill Korea's promised investment to the U.S. (트럼프 대통령이 이날 사회관계망서비스(SNS) 트루스소셜에 올린 글에서 한국산 제품에 대한 관세를 무역합의 이전 수준으로 다시 인상하겠다고 밝히면서 국내 증시는 큰 폭 하락하며 시작했다. 트럼프 대통령은 “한국 입법부가 한국과 미국과의 합의를 지키지 않고 있다. 이에 따라 나는 자동차, 목재, 의약품 및 기타 모든 상호관세(국가별 관세)를 15%에서 25%로 인상한다”고 밝혔다. 한국이 미국에 약속한 투자를 이행하기 위해 국회에서 통과시켜야 하는 ‘한미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’(대미투자특별법)을 거론한 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid concerns about being directly hit by the tariff hike, Hyundai Motor and Kia plummeted by 6.8% and 5.9%, respectively, as soon as the market opened. However, Hyundai Motor later turned upward again, rising to around 500,000 won. (관세인상 직격탄을 맞을 것이란 우려에 현대차와 기아는 장이 열리자마자 각각 6.8%, 5.9% 급락했다. 하지만 그 뒤 현대차는 다시 상승세로 돌아서 50만원 근처까지 오르는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the KOSDAQ index is at 1068.45, up 4.04 points (0.38%) from the previous day. After surpassing the 1,000 mark for the first time in four years the previous day and hitting a record high since the KOSDAQ index reorganization in 2004, the index started the day down 10.22 points (0.96%) at 1054.19 but soon turned upward, rising to as high as 1081.20 at one point. (같은 시각 코스닥 지수는 전날보다 4.04(0.38%) 오른 1068.45를 보이고 있다. 전날 4년 만에 처음으로 1000선을 넘은 데 이어 2004년 코스닥 지수 개편 이후 최고치를 경신한 코스닥 지수는 이날 10.22(0.96%) 내린 1054.19로 출발했으나 곧 상승전환해 한때 1081.20까지 오르기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241835.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/597/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501361.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:46:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada Submarine Bid: Attempting a Breakthrough with Automotive, Steel, and Space Investment Cooperation (캐나다 잠수함 수주전, 자동차·철강·우주 투자협력으로 돌파 시도)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241840.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/451/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501443.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김희철 한화오션(앞줄 왼쪽) 대표와 라자트 마라와 알고마스틸 대표가 26일 투자·협력 양해각서(MOU)를 들어 보이고 있다. 뒷줄은 왼쪽부터 필립 제닝스 캐나다 혁신과학경제개발부 차관, 김정관 산업통상부 장관, 빅터 피델리 온타리오주 경제개발부 장관. 한화 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy announced on the 27th that it held the 'Korea-Canada Industrial Cooperation Forum' in Toronto, Canada, on the 26th (local time), and six Memorandums of Understanding (MOUs) for cooperation were signed between companies of the two countries. This is a step to promise investment and industrial cooperation in Canada, following the Canadian government's request for offset trade related to its submarine project, worth up to 60 trillion won. (산업통상부는 26일(현지시각) 캐나다 토론토에서 ‘한·캐나다 산업 협력 포럼’을 개최했고, 양국 기업들 간에 6건의 협력 양해각서(MOU)가 체결됐다고 27일 밝혔다. 최대 60조원 규모의 잠수함 사업을 발주한 캐나다 정부의 절충교역 요구에 따라 캐나다에 대한 투자와 산업 협력을 약속하는 차원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry stated that the forum proceeded in two parts: the 'Korea-Canada Automotive Industry Cooperation Forum' (Part 1) and the 'Korea-Canada CEO Dialogue' (Part 2) co-hosted by the Federation of Korean Industries and the Business Council of Canada. Attendees included Kang Ho-sik, Chief of Staff to the President dispatched as a special envoy to support winning the submarine project, Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jeong-gwan, and Commissioner Lee Yong-cheol of the Defense Acquisition Program Administration. From the Canadian side, Philip Jennings, Deputy Minister of Innovation, Science and Economic Development, and Victor Fedeli, Ontario's Minister of Economic Development, Job Creation and Trade, attended. (산업부는 이번 포럼은 ‘한·캐나다 자동차 산업 협력 포럼’(1부) 및 한국경제인협회와 캐나다기업연합회가 함께 주최한 ‘한·캐나다 시이오(CEO) 대화’(2부)로 진행됐다고 밝혔다. 포럼에는 잠수함 사업 수주 지원을 위한 대통령 특사로 파견된 강훈식 대통령 비서실장, 김정관 산업통상부 장관, 이용철 방위사업청장 등이 참석했다. 캐나다 쪽에서는 필립 제닝스 혁신과학경제개발부 차관과 빅터 피델리 온타리오주 경제개발부 장관 등이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry reported that various measures to strengthen cooperation in areas such as eco-friendly vehicles and autonomous vehicles between the two countries were explored at the forum. Chung Eui-sun, Chairman of Hyundai Motor Group, also participated in the special envoy delegation to discuss cooperation in these fields. Minister Kim stated, "The automotive industry is a key backbone industry for both countries, and we will help the automotive industries of both countries seek opportunities and grow together." (포럼에서는 양국 간 친환경차와 자율주행차 등의 협력 강화를 위한 다양한 방안이 모색됐다고 산업부는 전했다. 특사단에는 정의선 현대차그룹 회장도 참여해 이런 분야의 협력을 논의했다. 김 장관은 “자동차 산업은 양국을 관통하는 핵심 기간산업으로, 양국 자동차 업계가 함께 기회를 모색하고 성장할 수 있도록 돕겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the occasion of the special envoy's visit, six MOUs for cooperation were signed between companies of the two countries, centered around Hanwha Group, in the fields of steel, artificial intelligence (AI), satellite communications, space, and electro-optics. Hanwha Ocean agreed to contribute 345 million Canadian dollars (approximately 3.646 trillion won) with a Canadian steel company for the construction of a local steel plant for submarine building, among other purposes. Hanwha Systems decided to promote cooperation in the satellite field with a local company and also cooperate in command and communication system areas linked to the submarine project. POSCO International will pursue rare earth development with a local company. (특사단 방문을 계기로 한화그룹을 중심으로 양국 기업들 사이에 철강, 인공지능(AI), 위성통신, 우주, 전자광학 분야에서 6건의 협력 양해각서(MOU)가 체결됐다. 한화오션의 경우 잠수함 건조에 들어갈 현지 강재 공장 건설 등을 위해 3억4500만 캐나다달러(약 3646억원)를 출연하기로 캐나다 철강 업체와 약정했다. 한화시스템은 현지 업체와 인공위성 분야 협력을 추진하면서 잠수함 사업과 연계된 지휘·통신체계 관련 분야에서도 협력하기로 했다. 포스코인터내셔널은 현지 업체와 함께 희토류 개발을 추진한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanwha Ocean, jointly with HD Hyundai Heavy Industries, is bidding for the Canadian submarine project and is currently a final candidate alongside Germany's ThyssenKrupp Marine Systems. The Canadian government is requesting offset trade, seeking reciprocal benefits such as investment in the automotive sector in return for the arms purchase. (한화오션은 에이치디(HD)현대중공업과 공동으로 캐나다 잠수함 사업 수주에 나서 독일의 티센크루프마린시스템과 함께 최종 후보에 오른 상태다. 캐나다 정부는 자동차 분야 투자 등 무기 구매의 반대급부를 챙기는 절충교역을 요구하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Bon-young &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이본영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241840.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/451/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501443.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:46:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Wonkwang Digital University Extends Beyond 'Act 2' to 'Act 3' of Life... Recruiting for the 2nd Round of New and Transfer Students for the First Semester of the 2026 Academic Year (원광디지털대, ‘인생 2막’ 넘어 ‘3막’까지… 2026학년도 1학기 2차 신·편입생 모집)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241844.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/3717694812395045.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;원광디지털대 전경 (원광디지털대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid the recent entry into a super-aged society and the trend of early retirement, 'lifelong education' is emerging as a survival strategy. In line with this trend, Wonkwang Digital University (President Kim Yun-cheol) is conducting its second round of recruitment for new and transfer students for the first semester of the 2026 academic year until February 11, capturing the attention of adult learners dreaming of a new turning point in their lives. (최근 초고령사회 진입과 조기 퇴직 열풍 속에 ‘평생교육’이 생존 전략으로 떠오르고 있다. 이러한 흐름에 발맞춰 원광디지털대학교(총장 김윤철)가 오는 2월 11일까지 2026학년도 1학기 신·편입생 2차 모집을 진행하며, 인생의 새로운 전환점을 꿈꾸는 성인 학습자들의 이목을 집중시키고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Offering a Path to 'Expertise' with Unique Specialized Departments (독보적 특성화 학과로 ‘전문가’의 길 제시)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University operates 18 departments based on three major specialization pillars: well-being &amp; health, Korean culture, and practical welfare. In particular, the Department of Eastern Studies, the Department of Yoga &amp; Meditation, and the Department of Korean Medicine Health &amp; Dietary Therapy, which are gaining increasing interest every year, showcase the university's expertise. Additionally, departments such as Tea Culture Management, Traditional Performing Arts, Korean Clothing Science, Korean Language &amp; Culture, and Taekwondo Sports &amp; Rehabilitation, which are hard to find at other cyber universities, are cultivating key talent to lead the globalization of K-content and the inheritance of Korean traditional culture in line with the globally spreading K-culture syndrome. (원광디지털대는 웰빙건강, 한국문화, 실용복지라는 3대 특성화 축을 바탕으로 18개 학과를 운영 중이다. 특히 매년 관심이 높아지고 있는 동양학과와 요가명상학과, 한방건강약선학과는 원광디지털대학교의 전문성을 보여주고 있다. 이 외에도 타 사이버대에서 찾아보기 힘든 차(茶)문화경영학과, 전통공연예술학과, 한국복식과학학과, 한국어문화학과, 태권도스포츠재활학과에서는 전 세계적으로 확산 중인 K-컬처 신드롬에 발맞춰 K-콘텐츠의 세계화와 한국 전통문화 계승을 이끌어갈 핵심 인재를 양성하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Establishment of the 'Department of Industrial Safety and Health' (‘산업안전보건학과’ 신설)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University is establishing a new 'Department of Industrial Safety and Health' starting from the first semester of the 2026 academic year, taking the lead in spreading safety culture in industrial fields. The Department of Industrial Safety and Health aims to 'cultivate industrial safety and health experts who lead workplace well-being culture,' combining theoretical and practical education to protect workers' health and safety. It complements the limitations of online education through experience-based learning and offline special lectures and supports the acquisition of related certifications such as Industrial Safety Engineer and Industrial Hygiene Manager. (원광디지털대는 2026학년도 1학기부터 ‘산업안전보건학과’를 신설하며, 산업현장의 안전 문화 확산에 앞장서고 있다. 산업안전보건학과는 ‘직장 내 웰빙 문화를 선도하는 산업안전보건 전문가 양성’을 목표로, 근로자의 건강과 안전을 보호하기 위한 이론 및 실무 교육을 병행한다. 체험 중심 교육과 오프라인 특강을 통해 온라인 교육의 한계를 보완하고, 산업안전기사·산업위생관리기사 등 관련 자격증 취득도 지원한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leading Future-Oriented Education Utilizing State-of-the-Art Educational Infrastructure (최첨단 교육 인프라를 활용한 미래형 교육 선도)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University was recently selected for the Ministry of Education's '2025 Cyber University Digital Educational Environment Advancement Support Project,' solidifying its position as a leader in future-oriented educational models. In particular, the 'HyperXR Studio' established through this project provides 360-degree immersive lecture content, receiving praise for overcoming the limitations of online education and creating a vivid practice environment as if in an actual field. Furthermore, the university has introduced and operates a data-based 'AI Learning Analytics System' to support students' self-directed learning. This system analyzes learning patterns and tendencies to recommend customized courses and proactively predicts the possibility of academic dropout for close management, thereby maximizing learning efficiency. Wonkwang Digital University is focusing all its capabilities on enhancing individual student learning outcomes by combining its unique XR content production technology with AI analytics systems. (원광디지털대는 최근 교육부 주관 ‘2025년 사이버대학 디지털 교육환경 고도화 지원사업’에 선정되며 미래형 교육 모델의 선두주자로 자리매김했다. 특히 이번 사업으로 구축한 ‘HyperXR 스튜디오’를 통해 360도 실감형 강의 콘텐츠를 제공함으로써, 온라인 교육의 한계를 뛰어넘어 실제 현장에 있는 듯한 생생한 실습 환경을 구현했다는 찬사를 받고 있다. 아울러 대학은 학생들의 자기주도학습을 지원하고자 데이터 기반의 ‘AI 학습분석 시스템’을 도입해 운영 중이다. 이 시스템은 학습 패턴과 성향을 분석해 맞춤형 교과목을 추천할 뿐만 아니라, 학업 중도 포기 가능성을 선제적으로 예측해 밀착 관리함으로써 학습 효율을 극대화한다. 원광디지털대학교는 이처럼 독보적인 XR 콘텐츠 제작 기술과 AI 분석 시스템을 결합하여 학생 개개인의 학습 성과를 높이는 데 모든 역량을 집중하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Customized Scholarship System that Lowers the 'Barrier to Learning' (‘배움 장벽’ 낮춘 맞춤형 장학금 제도)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University operates groundbreaking scholarship systems to alleviate financial burdens. All new and transfer students receive a 'Learning Scholarship.' Particularly eye-catching are scholarship benefits that reflect social changes. The 'SOLO Head of Household Scholarship' and the 'Single-Person Household Scholarship' are operated as scholarship systems to support learners in welfare blind spots. Not only office workers but also homemakers and mature students aged 56 and above can receive a 20% tuition reduction benefit, and this can be combined with the National Scholarship. Thanks to these various scholarship systems, 6 out of 10 actual enrolled students at Wonkwang Digital University receive full scholarships. (원광디지털대는 경제적 부담을 덜어주기 위한 파격적인 장학 제도를 운용한다. 모든 신·편입생에게는 ‘배움장학금’이 지급되며 된다. 특히 사회적 변화를 반영한 장학 혜택이 눈길을 끈다. ‘SOLO 가장 장학금’과 ‘1인 가구 장학금’등은 복지 사각지대에 놓인 학습자들을 지원하기 위한 장학 제도로 운영된다. 직장인뿐만 아니라 주부와 만 56세 이상 만학도 역시 20%의 수업료 감면 혜택을 받을 수 있으며, 국가장학금과 중복 수혜도 가능하다. 이러한 다양한 장학제도 덕분에 원광디지털대 실제 재학생 10명 중 6명이 전액 장학금을 받고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online Admission Information Session on January 28-29... Application Fee Waived for Participants (1월 28~29일 온라인 입학설명회… 참가자 전형료 면제)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University will hold an online admission information session over two days, on January 28 and 29, to address prospective students' questions. Prospective students wishing to participate can freely choose one of the two days that fits their schedule.&lt;br/&gt;For the admission information session, participants can freely watch online videos introducing the university, admission process, and scholarships, and then verify their participation via KakaoTalk chat to have their application fee waived. After watching the videos, real-time consultation on admission, scholarships, and university life is also available via KakaoTalk chat. (원광디지털대는 예비입학생들의 궁금증을 해소하기 위해 오는 1월 28일과 29일 양일간 온라인 입학설명회를 개최한다. 참가를 희망하는 예비입학생은 양일 중 본인 일정에 맞는 하루를 선택하여 자유롭게 참여하면 된다.&lt;br/&gt;입학설명회는 온라인으로 자유롭게 대학소개와 입학전형 안내, 장학안내 영상을 시청한 후 카카오톡 채팅으로 참가 인증을 하면 전형료가 면제된다. 영상 시청 후 입학, 장학뿐만 아니라 대학 생활에 대한 궁금한 내용을 카카오톡 채팅을 통해 실시간 상담도 가능하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second round of recruitment for new and transfer students closes at 9 PM on February 11. Detailed information can be found on the Admission Support Center website (&lt;a href="https://go.wdu.ac.kr" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;go.wdu.ac.kr&lt;/a&gt;) or by calling the main number (1588-2854). (2차 신·편입생 모집은 2월 11일 오후 9시에 마감되며, 자세한 사항은 입학지원센터 홈페이지(&lt;a href="https://go.wdu.ac.kr" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;go.wdu.ac.kr&lt;/a&gt;) 또는 대표전화(1588-2854)를 통해 확인할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;This article is a provided information article from the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241844.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0127/3717694812395045.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:45:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Silver Banking Balance Hits 377.3 Billion Won Amid Silver Price Soaring... Increases Nearly 8-Fold in One Year (은값 고공행진에 실버뱅킹 잔액 3773억원…1년 새 8배 증가)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241847.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501564.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지뱅크&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The balance of 'Silver Banking,' a financial product that invests in silver, has increased nearly eightfold in the past year. This appears to be due to concentrated investor interest as silver prices have risen sharply. (최근 은에 투자하는 금융상품인 ‘실버뱅킹’ 잔액이 1년 새 8배 가까이 늘었다. 은 가격이 가파르게 오르면서 투자자 관심이 집중된 영향으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shinhan Bank announced on the 27th that, as of the 26th, the total Silver Banking balance was recorded at 377.3 billion won. Silver Banking is a product that allows indirect investment in silver through a bank account, and currently, only Shinhan Bank sells it among major commercial banks. (신한은행은 지난 26일 기준 실버뱅킹 잔액이 총 3773억원으로 집계됐다고 27일 밝혔다. 실버뱅킹은 통장 계좌를 통해 은에 간접 투자하는 상품으로, 주요 시중은행 가운데 현재 신한은행만 판매하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The balance was only 47.7 billion won at the end of January last year, but it has since increased rapidly, growing nearly eightfold in just one year. The Silver Banking balance showed a steep monthly increase: 75.3 billion won at the end of August, 105.2 billion won at the end of September, 128.6 billion won at the end of October, 145 billion won at the end of November, and 241 billion won at the end of December last year. (지난해 1월 말 잔액은 477억원에 그쳤지만, 이후 빠르게 증가해 1년 만에 8배 가까이 불어난 것이다. 실버뱅킹 잔액은 지난해 8월 말 753억원, 9월 말 1052억원, 10월 말 1286억원, 11월 말 1450억원, 12월 말 2410억원 등으로 매달 가파른 증가세를 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increase in the number of accounts is also notable. The number of Silver Banking accounts exceeded 30,000 for the first time this month, reaching 31,669 as of the 26th. After remaining at around 16,000 for several years since January 2022, the number of accounts began to increase from February last year and surpassed 20,000 in September of the same year. The sharp rise in the Silver Banking balance is attributed not only to the price appreciation effect in existing accounts but also significantly to the inflow of new funds. (계좌 수 증가도 두드러진다. 실버뱅킹 계좌 수는 이달 들어 처음으로 3만개를 넘어 26일 기준 3만1669개에 이른다. 2022년 1월 이후 수년간 1만6천개 수준에 머물던 계좌 수는 지난해 2월부터 증가하기 시작해 같은 해 9월 2만개를 돌파했다. 실버뱅킹의 잔액 급증은 기존 계좌의 가격 상승 효과뿐 아니라 신규 자금 유입의 영향도 크게 작용한 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Silver bars, which gained popularity alongside Silver Banking, have been suspended from sale at all banks since October 20 last year due to shortages and supply instability. Shinhan Bank's silver bar sales volume increased from 297 kg in August to 898 kg in September last year. Subsequently, a total of 3,016 kg was sold by October 17 alone in October, worth approximately 8.7 billion won. (실버뱅킹과 함께 인기를 끌었던 실버바는 수급 불안에 따른 품귀 현상으로 지난해 10월20일 이후 모든 은행에서 판매가 중단된 상태다. 신한은행의 실버바 판매량은 지난해 8월 297㎏에서 9월 898㎏으로 늘었다. 이후 10월에만 17일까지 총 3016㎏이 판매됐다. 87억여원 어치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This investment frenzy appears to be influenced by the sharp rise in the spot price of silver. After surpassing $40 per ounce in September last year, the silver price showed a moderate upward trend, broke through $60 in December, and then rose sharply, exceeding $100 for the first time on the 24th. As of 11:30 AM on the 26th, the silver price was recorded at $111 per ounce. (이 같은 투자 열풍은 은 현물 가격 급등의 영향으로 보인다. 은 가격은 지난해 9월 온스당 40달러를 넘어선 뒤 완만한 상승세를 보이다가 12월에 60달러를 돌파한 뒤 가파르게 상승해 지난 24일 처음으로 100달러를 넘어섰다. 26일 오전 11시30분 기준 은 가격은 온스당 111달러를 기록하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241847.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501564.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:45:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cyber Incidents Increased 26.3% Last Year... This Year's Threat is 'Artificial Intelligence' (지난해 사이버 침해사고 26.3% 증가…올해 위협은 ‘인공지능’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241855.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694837905271_20260127501671.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of reported incidents involving personal information leaks and other breaches last year was recorded at 2,383 cases, a 26.3% increase compared to the previous year. This appears to be influenced by large-scale personal information leak incidents that occurred at companies like SK Telecom (SKT), KT, and Coupang. (지난해 개인정보유출 등 침해사고 신고 건수가 전년 대비 26.3% 오른 2383건을 기록한 것으로 집계됐다. 에스케이텔레콤(SKT)과 케이티(KT), 쿠팡 등에서 발생한 대규모 개인정보유출 사고 등의 영향으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the '2025 Cyber Threat Trends and 2026 Cyber Threat Outlook Report' released on the 27th by the Ministry of Science and ICT and the Korea Internet &amp; Security Agency (KISA), the number of reported incidents last year was 2,383, a 26.3% increase from 1,887 cases in 2024. In the first half of last year, the number of reports increased by only 15% compared to the previous year, but in the second half, it surged to 1,349 cases, a 36.5% increase compared to the same period the previous year (988 cases). (과학기술정보통신부와 한국인터넷진흥원(KISA)이 27일 발표한 ‘2025년 사이버 위협 동향과 2026년 사이버위협 전망 보고서’를 보면, 지난해 침해사고 신고 건수는 2383건으로 2024년 1887건에서 26.3% 증가한 것으로 나타났다. 지난해 상반기 기준 신고 건수는 전년 대비 15% 증가하는 것에 그쳤으나, 하반기에는 1349건으로 전년 같은 기간 대비(988건) 36.5% 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year's cyber incidents were largely analyzed as follows: △Incidents targeting daily life infrastructure that threatens everyday life; △Supply chain attacks exploiting open-source and low-cost Internet of Things (IoT) ecosystems; △Expansion of ransomware attack targets and strengthening of attacks linking companies and customers. Notably, consecutive incidents occurred last year in sectors closely related to people's lives, such as telecommunications, distribution, and finance, leading to the leakage of millions to tens of millions of pieces of personal information. (지난해 사이버 침해사고는 크게 △일상을 위협하는 생활 밀접 인프라에 대한 침해사고 △오픈소스 및 저가형 사물인터넷(IoT) 생태계를 악용한 공급망 공격 △랜섬웨어 공격 대상 확대와 기업-고객 연계 공격 강화로 분석됐다. 특히 지난해 통신·유통·금융 등 국민 생활에 밀접한 분야에서 연달아 침해사고가 발생하면서 수백만건에서 수천만건의 개인정보가 유출된 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expected cyber threats for this year include an increase in AI-based cyber threats and cyberattacks targeting AI services. As attackers' use of AI becomes full-fledged, more sophisticated and diversified attacks are anticipated. In particular, as deepfake voice/video-based phishing could expand to real-time calls, caution is needed even in communications with acquaintances or family members. (올해 예상되는 사이버 위협으로는 인공지능(AI)에 기반을 둔 사이버 위협 및 인공지능 서비스에 대한 사이버 공격 증가가 꼽혔다. 공격자들의 인공지능 활용이 본격화되면서 더욱 정교하고 다양화된 공격이 예상된다. 특히 딥페이크 음성·영상 기반 피싱이 실시간 통화에도 확대될 수 있는 만큼, 지인이나 가족 간 연락에도 주의가 필요하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the use of AI services increases, attacks targeting the AI models themselves are also expected to become full-fledged. Attackers could inject malicious content into chatbots or manipulate a model's training data to induce the exposure of sensitive information. Other cited cyber threats include: △Cases where systems like 'Windows 10', whose service has ended or are neglected, are exploited as hacking channels; △Increased attacks on vulnerabilities in cloud environments; △Secondary cyber threats exploiting leaked personal information. (인공지능 서비스 활용이 늘어나면서 인공지능 모델 자체를 대상으로 하는 공격도 본격화할 것으로 보인다. 공격자들이 챗봇에 악의적인 내용을 주입하거나, 모델의 학습데이터를 조작해 민감한 정보 노출을 유도하는 것도 가능하다. 이밖에 사이버 위협으로는 △‘윈도우 10’ 등 서비스가 종료되거나 방치된 시스템이 해킹 통로로 악용되는 경우 △클라우드 환경의 취약 요소 공격 증가 △유출된 개인정보를 악용한 2차 사이버 위협이 꼽혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choi Woo-hyuk, Director of the Information Protection Network Policy Office at the Ministry of Science and ICT, said, "It is anticipated that attacks utilizing AI will materialize in the future, and cyber threats such as attacks exploiting vulnerabilities in cloud environments will become more intelligent and advanced." He added, "The government will also operate an AI-based prevention and response system, proactively manage security blind spots, and create a cyber environment where the public can feel safe." (최우혁 과기정통부 정보보호네트워크정책실장은 “향후 인공지능을 활용한 공격이 현실화되고 클라우드 환경 취약점을 악용한 공격 등 사이버 위협이 더욱 지능화·고도화될 것으로 전망된다”며 “정부 또한 인공지능 기반의 예방·대응체계를 운영하고, 보안 사각지대를 선제적으로 관리하여 국민이 안심할 수 있는 사이버 환경을 조성해 나가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Chae Ban-seok &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241855.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694837905271_20260127501671.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:44:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Savings Banks to Strengthen Guidance on 'Loan Withdrawal Rights'... Provision of Early Repayment Cost Comparison Tables (저축은행 ‘대출 청약철회권’ 안내 강화…중도상환 비용 비교표 제공)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241857.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/642/252/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501682.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;저축은행중앙회 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starting in February, the guidance on 'loan withdrawal rights' at savings banks will be strengthened. Customers who take out loans will be provided with detailed comparisons of the costs and differences associated with withdrawal and early repayment. (오는 2월부터 저축은행의 ‘대출 청약철회권’ 안내가 강화된다. 대출을 받은 고객은 청약철회와 중도상환에 따른 비용과 차이를 구체적으로 비교한 내역을 안내받을 수 있게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Financial Supervisory Service announced on the 27th, "From February 1st, we will fully computerize the loan withdrawal process for savings banks, expand comparison and guidance between withdrawal and early repayment, and strengthen financial consumer protection and guidance related to the exercise of loan withdrawal rights." (금융감독원은 “2월1일부터 저축은행 대출 청약철회 업무 프로세스를 전면 전산화하고, 청약철회와 중도상환 간 비교·안내를 확대하는 등 대출 청약철회권 행사와 관련한 금융소비자 보호·안내를 강화한다”고 27일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Financial Consumer Protection Act, financial consumers can freely withdraw from a loan contract within 14 days of receiving the loan. However, after the FSS inspected the actual practices of savings banks last year, it found inadequate cases in the withdrawal processing procedures of some savings banks, prompting the move to improve the system. (금융소비자보호법에 따라 금융소비자는 대출을 받은 날로부터 14일 이내에 자유롭게 대출계약을 철회할 수 있다. 그러나 금감원이 지난해 저축은행의 관련 실태를 점검한 결과, 일부 저축은행의 청약철회 처리 과정에서 미흡한 사례가 확인되면서 제도 개선에 나선 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, the FSS decided to strengthen the provision of relevant information. When a loan customer intends to make an early repayment or apply for withdrawal within the eligible withdrawal period, the savings bank must present a comparison of the advantages, disadvantages, and specific costs of the two systems. (먼저 금감원은 관련 정보 제공을 강화하기로 했다. 대출 고객이 청약철회가 가능한 기간 내 중도상환하거나 청약철회를 신청하려는 경우, 저축은행은 두 제도의 장·단점과 구체적인 소요 비용을 비교해 제시해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Customers who choose early repayment bear early repayment fees but do not have to pay ancillary costs such as stamp duty. Conversely, choosing withdrawal means no early repayment fees, but the customer must directly bear the ancillary costs incurred during the loan process. Also, withdrawal results in the deletion of the loan record, while early repayment keeps the loan record. Financial consumers can compare these differences and choose the option more favorable to them. (중도상환을 선택한 고객은 중도상환수수료를 부담하지만 인지세 등 부대비용은 내지 않아도 된다. 반대로 청약철회를 선택하면 중도상환수수료는 없지만 대출 과정에서 발생한 부대비용은 직접 부담해야 한다. 또 청약철회를 하면 대출 기록이 삭제되지만, 중도상환을 할 경우 대출 기록은 유지된다. 금융소비자는 이러한 차이를 비교해 자신에게 유리한 쪽을 선택할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A computerized management system for withdrawal operations will also be fully introduced. This is because some savings banks managed related tasks manually, leading to procedural omissions and processing errors. It was also confirmed that even when a customer withdrew within the eligible period after partially repaying the loan early, they could not receive a refund of the already paid early repayment fee due to poor management from manual record-keeping. (청약철회 업무에 전산 관리 체계도 전면 도입한다. 일부 저축은행은 관련 업무를 수기로 관리하면서 절차 누락과 처리 오류 등이 발생한 것으로 나타나서다. 대출금 일부를 중도상환한 경우에도 청약철회 가능 기간 내 청약을 철회하면 이미 납부한 중도상환수수료를 돌려받을 수 있음에도, 수기 작성에 따른 관리 부실로 이를 지급하지 못한 사례도 확인됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FSS stated, "We will continuously monitor the implementation status of the system within the savings bank sector and expand inspections of the operational status of withdrawal rights to other financial companies." (금감원은 “앞으로 저축은행권의 제도 이행 상황을 지속해서 점검하고, 다른 금융회사로도 청약철회권 운영 실태 점검을 확대해 나가겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241857.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/642/252/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501682.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:44:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Upgrading is just an excuse"... National Tax Service launches tax audit on sanitary pad manufacturers and others that inflated costs (고급화는 핑계…국세청, 원가 부풀린 생리대 제조사 등 세무조사 착수)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241858.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/924/554/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694839966426_20260127501673.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Tax Service (NTS) will conduct tax audits on 'daily necessity profiteering tax evaders' who led the rise in the cost of living through unfair practices. In particular, it plans to closely investigate cases where monopolistic or oligopolistic companies dominating the market took excessive profits by raising prices of daily necessities under the pretext of rising raw material costs. (국세청이 불공정행위로 생활물가 상승을 주도한 ‘생필품 폭리 탈세자’에 대한 세무조사를 실시한다. 특히 시장을 장악한 독과점 기업들이 원자재 가격 상승 등을 핑계로 생필품 가격을 인상하며 폭리를 취한 경우를 면밀히 조사한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NTS announced on the 27th that it will conduct tax audits on 17 companies involved in profiteering on daily necessities and tax evasion, including 5 monopolistic or oligopolistic companies involved in price-fixing. The total amount of suspected tax evasion by these companies reaches about 400 billion won. In addition to companies that colluded on prices, manufacturers and distributors of daily necessities that inflated costs (6 companies) and food distributors that disrupted transaction order (6 companies), which raised prices of essential living goods, are the main targets of the investigation. Among the 17 companies, 2 are large corporations, 2 are mid-sized companies, and the remaining 13 are small and medium-sized enterprises. (국세청은 27일 가격담합 등 독·과점 기업 5곳 등 생필품 폭리 탈세업체 17곳에 대한 세무조사를 벌인다고 밝혔다. 이들의 전체 탈루 혐의 금액은 약 4천억원에 이른다. 가격을 짬짜미한 업체들 외에도 원가를 부풀린 생필품 제조·유통업체(6곳), 거래질서를 어지럽힌 먹거리 유통업체(6곳) 등 생활 필수품 가격을 인상한 업체가 주요 조사 대상이다. 17곳 기업 중 대기업은 2곳, 중견기업 2곳, 나머지 13곳은 중소기업이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NTS explained that for this audit, it selected not only those who simply evaded taxes but also those who funneled company funds to the owner's family. One large corporation manufacturing food additives was found to have inflated purchase prices by cross-purchasing raw materials with colluding companies at amounts higher than market prices, thereby raising prices and reducing profits by tens of billions of won. To receive a share of the profits from participating in the collusion, it received collusion rewards (cooperation fees) from affiliates of the colluding companies, and to hide these collusion profits, it received false purchase tax invoices from the companies' disguised affiliates. Furthermore, it was found to have improperly supported living expenses for the owner's children staying in the U.S. by excessively paying operating costs for a local U.S. office. (국세청은 이번 조사 대상으로 단순히 세금 탈루뿐만 아니라 사주 일가로 회삿돈을 빼돌린 이들을 선정했다는 설명이다. 식품첨가물을 제조하는 한 대기업은 시세보다 높은 금액으로 담합업체와 원재료를 교차 구매하는 형태로 매입단가를 부풀려 가격은 올리고 수십억원의 이익을 축소한 것으로 나타났다. 담합 참여에 대한 이익을 나눠받기 위해 담합업체의 계열사로부터 담합 대가(협력 수수료)를 챙기고, 해당 담합 이익을 숨기려고 업체의 위장계열사로부터 거짓 매입세금계산서를 받았다. 또한 미국 현지사무소 운영비를 과다하게 지급하는 방식으로 미국에 체류 중인 사주 자녀들에게 체재비를 부당 지원한 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A sanitary pad manufacturer recently embroiled in controversy over high prices was also found to have inflated costs by excessively paying over 30 billion won in sales incentives and over 5 billion won in sales commissions, respectively, to its exclusive distributor, a specially related corporation, despite raising product prices by 33.9% citing 'product premiumization'. It was also confirmed that it established a disguised affiliate under the name of a retiree and excessively paid for services like material movement and packaging, thereby siphoning off corporate funds. (최근 고가 논란을 빚는 한 생리대 제조사도 ‘제품 고급화’를 이유로 제품 가격을 33.9% 인상했으나, 판매 총판인 특수관계법인에 판매장려금과 판매수수료를 각각 300억원, 50억원 이상씩 과다 지급해 비용을 부풀린 것으로 나타났다. 퇴직자 명의로 위장계열사도 설립해 자재 이동 및 포장 등 용역대가를 과다 지급해 법인자금도 빼돌린 것으로 확인됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One company manufacturing and distributing daily necessities like eyeglasses and wet wipes raised prices using the excuse of rising raw material costs due to high inflation and high exchange rates. However, it was investigated that it inflated costs by inserting a non-existent specially related corporation into the transaction process and falsely claiming to have received services. It was found to have improperly used corporate funds, such as providing a high-end apartment worth about 2 billion won acquired with corporate funds to the owner's children for free and privately using corporate credit cards for luxury and personal expenses like golf courses and entertainment establishments. (안경·물티슈 등 생필품을 제조·유통하는 한 업체는 고물가·고환율로 인한 원재료 가격 상승을 핑계로 가격을 인상했다. 그러나 실체 없는 특수관계법인을 거래 과정에 끼워넣고 허위로 용역을 제공받은 것처럼 원가를 부풀린 것으로 조사됐다. 사주 자녀에게 법인자금으로 취득한 약 20억원대의 고급 아파트를 무상 제공하고, 법인 신용카드를 골프장･유흥업소 등 호화·사치에 사적으로 사용하는 등 법인자금을 부당하게 쓴 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, one deep-sea fishing company also inserted a one-person specially related corporation controlled by the owner's family into the middle of transactions, attributing profits to the owner's family. It remitted about 5 billion won in corporate funds overseas under the guise of deep-sea fishing vessel operating expenses, but it was investigated that the money was actually used for private purposes, such as paying for the owner's children's study abroad expenses. (이밖에 한 원양어업 업체도 거래 중간에 사주 일가가 지배하는 1인 특수관계법인을 끼워 넣어, 이익을 사주 일가에게 귀속시켰다. 원양어선 조업경비를 가장해 법인자금 약 50억원을 국외 송금했으나, 실제로는 사주 자녀 유학 비용을 지출하는 등 사적 사용한 것으로 조사됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NTS stated, "If illegal acts such as tax evasion or receipt of false tax invoices are discovered during the investigation process, we will strictly take measures leading to criminal punishment according to the Tax Offenders Punishment Act," and added, "We plan to conduct continuous monitoring and tax verification on the moral hazard of companies that raise prices of essential daily necessities through unfair practices to take excessive profits while reducing and reporting less tax." (국세청은 “조사 과정에서 조세포탈, 거짓 세금계산서 수수 등 범칙행위 적발 시 조세범 처벌법에 따라 형사처벌로 이어지도록 엄정히 조처하겠다”며 “불공정행위로 생활필수품 가격을 인상하며 폭리를 취하고, 세금은 줄여 신고하는 업체의 도덕적 해이에 대해 지속적인 모니터링과 세무검증을 실시할 계획”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241858.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/924/554/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694839966426_20260127501673.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:44:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Mortgage Rates Rise for Third Month to 4.23%... Credit Loan Rates Surge to 5.87% (주담대 금리 석달째 올라 4.23%…신용대출은 5.87%로 급등)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241860.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501867.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As market interest rates increased, household loan rates in the banking sector rose for the third consecutive month last month. (시장금리가 오르면서 지난달 은행권 가계대출 금리가 석달째 상승했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the 'Weighted Average Interest Rates of Financial Institutions' statistics released by the Bank of Korea on the 27th, the weighted average interest rate on new household loans at deposit banks in December last year was 4.35% per annum, 0.03 percentage points higher than in November. This marks an upward trend for the third consecutive month since October. (27일 한국은행이 발표한 ‘금융기관 가중평균금리’ 통계를 보면, 작년 12월 중 예금은행의 가계대출 가중평균금리(신규취급액 기준)는 연 4.35%로 11월보다 0.03%포인트 높았다. 10월 이후 3개월째 오름세다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among household loans, interest rates for home mortgage loans (4.23%) and jeonse (lump-sum deposit rental) loans (3.99%) rose by 0.06 percentage points and 0.09 percentage points, respectively. The credit loan rate (5.87%) surged by 0.41 percentage points. This is the highest level since December 2024 (6.15%). The increase was the largest since November 2022 (0.63 percentage points). (가계대출 가운데 주택담보대출(주담대·4.23%)과 전세자금대출(3.99%) 금리가 각각 0.06%포인트, 0.09%포인트씩 올랐다. 신용대출 금리(5.87%)는 0.41%포인트 급등했다. 2024년 12월(6.15%) 이후 가장 높은 수준이다. 오름 폭이 2022년 11월(0.63%포인트) 이후 가장 컸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Min-su, head of the Financial Statistics Team at the Bank of Korea, explained, "Home mortgage rates rose due to the increase in the benchmark rate, bank bond rates, but the increase was smaller than the benchmark rate as the proportion of lower-interest 'Bogeumjari' loans grew." He added, "Credit loan rates also increased as the short-term bank bond benchmark rate rose and loans to mid-to-low credit borrowers, which carry higher rates, expanded." Regarding the interest rate outlook, he responded, "This month, the benchmark rate for home mortgages has risen slightly, while the short-term market rate, a benchmark for credit loans, has fallen slightly. However, with banks setting new total volume management targets and handling new loans at the beginning of the year, the trend needs to be monitored." (김민수 한은 금융통계팀장은 “주담대 금리는 지표금리인 은행채 금리 상승 영향으로 올랐는데, 상대적으로 금리 수준이 낮은 보금자리론 대출 비중이 커져 상승 폭은 지표금리보다 작았다”며 “신용대출 금리 역시 지표인 은행채 단기물 금리가 오른데다 높은 금리가 적용되는 중저 신용자 대출이 늘면서 높아졌다”고 설명했다. 금리 전망에 대해서는 “이달 들어 주담대 지표금리는 소폭 오르고 신용대출 지표인 단기 시장금리는 소폭 떨어지는 흐름인데, 연초 은행들이 총량 관리 목표를 새로 설정하고 대출을 새로 취급하는 변수가 있어 추세는 지켜봐야 한다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In December, corporate loan rates (4.16%) also rose by 0.06 percentage points, marking a second consecutive month of increase. Loan rates for large corporations (4.08%) rose by 0.02 percentage points, and those for small and medium-sized enterprises (4.24%) rose by 0.10 percentage points. The overall loan rate for the banking sector, encompassing both households and corporations, was calculated at 4.19%, up 0.04 percentage points. (12월 중 기업 대출금리(4.16%)도 0.06%포인트 올라 두달째 상승세했다. 대기업(4.08%) 대출금리가 0.02%포인트, 중소기업(4.24%) 대출 금리가 0.10%포인트 각각 높아졌다. 가계와 기업을 통틀어 전체 은행권 대출금리는 0.04%포인트 오른 4.19%로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interest rate on savings deposits (new transactions basis) rose to 2.90% per annum in December, up 0.09 percentage points from November (2.81%). This is the fourth consecutive month of increase. As the increase in deposit rates outpaced that of loan rates, the interest rate margin on a new transaction basis (1.29 percentage points) narrowed by 0.05 percentage points compared to the previous month. The interest rate margin based on outstanding balances (2.23 percentage points) widened by an additional 0.04 percentage points. (저축성 수신(예금) 금리(신규취급액 기준)는 연 2.90%로 11월(2.81%)보다 0.09%포인트 상승했다. 4개월째 오름세다. 예금금리 상승 폭이 대출금리를 웃돌면서 신규취급액 기준 예대금리차(1.29%포인트)는 전달보다 0.05%포인트 축소됐다. 잔액 기준 예대금리차(2.23%포인트)는 0.04%포인트 더 커졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241860.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127501867.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:43:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Market Value 120 Billion Won' Luxury Online Shopping Mall, All Fake... Ring Distributing Counterfeit Goods Busted (‘시가 1200억’ 명품 온라인 쇼핑몰, 다 가짜…위조 상품 유통 일당 검거)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241865.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694897560426_20260127501952.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;관세청이 적발한 위조 상품. 관세청 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ring that distributed counterfeit goods with a genuine market value of approximately 120 billion won into South Korea through an online shopping mall has been caught by customs authorities. (온라인 쇼핑몰을 통해 정품 시가 1200억원 상당의 위조 상품을 국내로 유통한 일당이 세관당국에 적발됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Incheon Main Customs Office of the Korea Customs Service announced on the 27th that it has arrested and sent to the Incheon District Prosecutors' Office a man in his 40s, identified as Mr. G, the ringleader, on charges of violating the Customs Act, Trademark Act, and the Act on Regulation and Punishment of Criminal Proceeds Concealment. He is accused of distributing counterfeit goods with a genuine market value of 120 billion won domestically and concealing and laundering 16.5 billion won in criminal proceeds into bank accounts under other people's names. Three related individuals were sent to prosecutors without detention on charges of conspiracy. (관세청 인천본부세관은 27일 정품 시가 1200억원 상당의 위조 상품을 국내로 유통하고, 범죄수익 165억원을 타인 명의의 계좌로 은닉·세탁한 총책 40대 ㄱ씨를 관세법, 상표법, 범죄수익은닉규제법 위반 혐의로 인천지방검찰청에 구속 송치했다고 밝혔다. 관련자 3명은 공모 혐의로 불구속 송치했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed that they established an organized counterfeit goods distribution system by dividing roles into teams such as management support, trade, and product planning. They took orders through an online shopping mall and app, then illegally distributed the goods by either smuggling counterfeit products from China and delivering them domestically or having them shipped directly from China to the customer. They sold a total of 77,000 various counterfeit items including bags, clothing, and shoes. (이들은 경영지원팀, 무역팀, 상품기획팀 등으로 역할을 분담해 조직적인 위조 상품 유통 체계를 구축한 것으로 드러났다. 온라인 쇼핑몰과 앱으로 주문을 받은 뒤 중국에서 밀수한 위조 상품을 국내에서 배송하거나 중국에서 주문자에게 직배송하는 방식으로 불법 유통했다. 이들은 가방, 의류, 신발 등 각종 위조 상품 7만7천점을 판매했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Incheon Main Customs Office seized about 5,000 counterfeit items that were being stored in their secret warehouse. They also took pre-indictment preservation measures for criminal proceeds worth approximately 8 billion won, including a luxury apartment, hotel, and sports car acquired with the concealed criminal profits. (인천본부세관은 이들이 비밀 창고에 보관 중이던 위조 상품 5천여점을 압수했다. 은닉한 범죄수익으로 취득한 고급 아파트, 호텔, 스포츠카 등 시가 80억원 상당의 범죄수익은 기소 전 추징보전 조처했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, they confirmed that Mr. G had acquired about 500 million won worth of cryptocurrency, such as Bitcoin and Ethereum, stored in a hardware wallet (an offline electronic wallet like a USB) to avoid confiscation of criminal proceeds, and seized that hardware wallet as well. This marks the first time the Korea Customs Service has seized virtual assets concealed in a hardware wallet. (특히 ㄱ씨가 범죄수익 추징을 회피하기 위해 비트코인, 이더리움 등 5억원 상당의 가상화폐를 취득해 하드월렛(유에스비 등 오프라인 상태의 전자지갑)에 보관하던 사실을 확인하고, 해당 하드월렛도 압수했다. 관세청이 하드월렛에 은닉한 가상자산을 압수한 것은 이번이 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The customs investigation team also discovered that, even while the investigation was ongoing, an associate of the arrested main culprit continued selling counterfeit goods by merely changing the name of the online shopping mall. The investigation team is conducting additional investigations into the related individuals and the full scale of the crimes. (세관 수사팀은 수사가 진행되는 중에도 구속된 주범의 관계자가 온라인 쇼핑몰의 상호만 변경해 위조 상품을 계속 판매하고 있다는 사실을 확인했다. 수사팀은 관련자 및 범행 규모에 대해 추가 수사를 진행 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241865.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694897560426_20260127501952.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:43:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Institutions to Hire 28,000 Regular Employees This Year... Largest Since COVID-19 (공공기관 올해 정규직 2만8천명 채용…코로나19 이후 최대)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241869.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/433/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502136.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2026 공공기관 채용정보박람회 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public institutions have decided to hire 28,000 regular employees this year. They will also hire 24,000 youth interns. (공공기관이 올해 2만8천명의 정규직을 채용하기로 했다. 청년인턴은 2만4천명 채용한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance Choo Kyung-ho said in his opening remarks at the 2026 Public Institution Recruitment Information Fair held at the aT Center in Seocho-gu, Seoul, on the afternoon of the 27th, "Public institutions plan to hire 28,000 regular employees this year, the largest scale since 2020," adding, "We will further expand job opportunities for young people by hiring around 24,000 youth interns, which serve as a stepping stone to regular employment." (구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관은 27일 오후 서울 서초구 에이티(aT)센터에서 열린 2026 공공기관 채용정보 박람회 개회사에서 “올해 공공기관은 2020년 이래 최대 규모인 2만8천명의 정규직을 채용할 계획”이라며 “정규직 채용의 징검다리 역할을 하는 청년인턴은 2만4천명 수준으로 청년들의 취업 기회를 보다 확대하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public institution hiring plans were 26,000-27,000 from 2020 to 2022, then slightly decreased to 22,000-24,000 from 2023 to 2025 after the end of COVID-19. This year's figure increased by 4,000 compared to last year. An official from the Ministry of Economy and Finance explained, "There is workforce expansion, and hiring has increased due to factors like the retirement of existing personnel." (공공기관 채용 계획은 2020~2022년 2만6천~2만7천명이었다가 코로나19 종식 이후인 2023~2025년에는 2만2천~2만4천명으로 소폭 감소한 바 있다. 올해는 전년보다 4천명이 늘었는데 재경부 관계자는 “인력증원도 있고, 기존 인력의 정년퇴직 등으로 채용 인력이 늘었다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In terms of regular hiring scale, Korea Railroad Corporation (KORAIL) (1,800) was the largest, followed by the National Health Insurance Service (1,138), Seoul National University Hospital (1,076), Korea Electric Power Corporation (KEPCO) (1,042), and the Korea Workers' Compensation &amp; Welfare Service (993). About half of the top 20 public institutions by hiring scale were medical institutions like university hospitals, with a significant portion being nursing staff hires. (정규직 채용 규모로는 한국철도공사(1800명)가 가장 많고 국민건강보험공단(1138명), 서울대학교병원(1076명), 한국전력공사(1042명), 근로복지공단(993명)이 뒤를 이었다. 채용규모 상위 20개 공공기관 중 절반가량은 대학병원 등 의료기관이었는데, 상당수가 간호인력 채용이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of youth interns to be hired this year increased by 3,000 compared to last year. They are divided into 'employment-linked interns' connected to hiring and 'experience-type interns' for job experience, with the Ministry of Economy and Finance explaining that the scale of experience-type intern hiring is larger. (올해 채용하는 청년인턴은 지난해보다 3천명 증가했다. 채용과 연계되는 ‘채용형 인턴’과 직무를 경험하는 ‘체험형 인턴’으로 나뉘며, 체험형 인턴 채용 규모가 더 크다는 게 재경부 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Economy and Finance stated that 148 public institutions are participating in the fair, which runs until the 29th. Starting this year, a new 'AI on-site matching' service will be introduced, where job seekers input data such as desired salary and region, and the system matches them with public institutions meeting those conditions. An 'interview rebuild' program will also be conducted, where experts analyze the reasons for rejection and suggest improvements if job seekers submit their failed interview cases. (재경부는 오는 29일까지 열리는 박람회에 148개 공공기관이 참여한다고 밝혔다. 올해부터는 구직자가 희망연봉·지역 등 데이터를 입력하면 해당 조건에 맞는 공공기관을 매칭해주는 ‘인공지능(AI) 현장 매칭’이 새로 도입된다. 구직자가 면접 탈락사례를 제출하면 전문가가 탈락 원인을 분석하고 개선 방향을 제안하는 ‘면접 리빌드’ 프로그램도 진행한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Prime Minister Choo said, "Youth jobs are not just a matter of employment; they are the growth engine and foundation of hope that will shoulder the future of South Korea," adding, "The government will respond to this demand of the times by placing youth job creation as the top priority in state affairs and focusing all capabilities." (구 부총리는 “청년 일자리는 단순히 고용의 문제를 넘어 대한민국의 미래를 짊어질 성장 엔진이자 희망의 근간”이라며 “정부는 이러한 시대적 요구에 부응해 청년 일자리 창출을 국정운영의 최우선 순위로 두고 모든 역량을 집중하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241869.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/433/imgdb/original/2026/0127/20260127502136.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:43:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>