<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:10:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>A string of visitors including Joo Ho-young, Jeong Won-o, and Kim Eo-jun... Condolence visits to the late Lee Hae-chan's funeral altar (주호영·정원오·김어준 등 줄이어…이해찬 수석부의장 빈소 조문)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241999.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;A string of visitors including Joo Ho-young, Jeong Won-o, and Kim Eo-jun... Condolence visits to the late Lee Hae-chan's funeral altar (주호영·정원오·김어준 등 줄이어…이해찬 수석부의장 빈소 조문)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500005.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;주호영 국회부의장(왼쪽 세 번째)과 김경수 지방시대위원회 위원장(왼쪽)이 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 마련된 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 찾아 조문하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, the first day of the funeral for Lee Hae-chan, the late Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council (Minjupyeongtong), the line of mourners continued late into the night at the funeral hall of Seoul National University Hospital where the altar was set up. (이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의(민주평통) 수석부의장의 장례 첫날인 27일, 빈소가 차려진 서울대병원 장례식장에는 늦은 밤까지 조문 행렬이 이어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following President Lee Jae-myung's visit after 7 PM, opposition figures including Joo Ho-young, a People Power Party lawmaker and National Assembly Vice Speaker, and Kim Dae-sik, a People Power Party lawmaker, visited the altar. Lawmaker Kim said, "I served as the Secretary-General of Minjupyeongtong," adding, "The former Prime Minister devoted himself greatly to the democratization movement while serving seven terms. I believe he will continue to worry greatly for South Korea even in heaven." (이재명 대통령이 다녀간 오후 7시 이후 국회 부의장인 주호영 국민의힘 의원과 김대식 국민의힘 의원 등 야당 인사들이 빈소를 찾았다. 김 의원은 “제가 민주평통 사무처장을 역임했다”며 “총리께서는 그동안 7선을 하시며 민주화운동에 크게 헌신하셨다. 하늘나라에 가서도 대한민국을 위해 크게 걱정하시리라 생각한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Gyeong-soo, Chairman of the Local Era Committee, who worked with the deceased during the Roh Moo-hyun administration, also visited subsequently. With tears in his eyes, he said, "To me, former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan was a political mentor along with President Roh Moo-hyun," and pledged, "Our democracy is indebted to former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan. We will carry on his will for democracy, peace, and balanced national development." (노무현 정부에서 고인과 함께 일했던 김경수 지방시대위원장도 뒤이어 방문했다. 눈물이 맺힌 그는 “저에게 이해찬 총리님은 노무현 대통령님과 함께 정치적 스승이셨다”며 “우리 민주주의가 이해찬 총리님께 빚을 지고 있다. 민주주의와 평화, 국가균형발전이라는 총리님의 뜻을 잘 이어가겠다”고 다짐했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, the Presidential Office's Policy Chief, and Bong Wook, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Civil Affairs, also visited the altar. Chief Kim recalled the former Prime Minister by mentioning the bookstores 'Gwangjang Bookstore' and 'Dongbang Bookstore' that the former Prime Minister ran during his university days, saying, "In our time in the 80s, we learned all the books we read through those places. He was a bookstore owner with a clear historical consciousness." He also said, "It's hard to believe because he encouraged me when I met him at an event just three weeks ago." Chief Kim stated, "We are deeply saddened by the passing of a great elder who contributed so immensely to our nation's politics and democracy," adding, "I believe (the former Prime Minister) will be remembered as a towering figure in South Korea's democracy and history." (김용범 청와대 정책실장, 봉욱 민정수석도 빈소를 찾았다. 김 실장은 대학 시절 이 전 총리가 운영하던 서점 ‘광장서적’과 ‘동방서적’을 언급하며 “80년대 우리 시절에 읽는 책들을 다 거기 통해 배웠다. 카랑카랑한 역사의식을 가졌던 서점 주인이셨다”고 이 전 총리를 기억했다. 또 “3주 전에 한 행사에서 뵀을 때 (저를) 격려해주셨는데 너무 믿기지 않는다”고 했다. 김 실장은 “우리나라 정치와 민주주의에 너무나 큰 기여를 하신 큰 어른이 가셔서 상심이 크다”며 “(이 전 총리는) 대한민국 민주주의와 역사에서 두고두고 기억될 거목이라 생각한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Others who paid their condolences late into the night included Choo Kyung-ho, the Minister of Economy and Finance; Jeong Eun-kyeong, the Minister of Health and Welfare; Jeong Won-o, the Mayor of Seongdong District; and broadcaster Kim Eo-jun. Minister Choo said, "I recently saw (the former Prime Minister) at Minjupyeongtong," adding, "He was still healthy then, so it's heartbreaking that he left us so suddenly." He said, "I too will live a life dedicated to the public good and the nation, upholding the deceased's will." (이외에도 구윤철 기획재정부 장관, 정은경 보건복지부 장관, 정원오 성동구청장, 방송인 김어준씨 등이 늦은 시간까지 조문했다. 구 장관은 “최근에도 민주평통에서 (이 전 총리를) 뵀었다”며 “그때만 해도 정정하셨는데 이렇게 갑자기 가시니 가슴이 먹먹하다”고 말했다. 그는 “저도 고인의 뜻을 받들어서 공익을 생각하고 국가를 생각하는 삶을 살아가도록 하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Condolence visits ended at 10 PM that day. From the 28th, visits will be possible from 9 AM to 9 PM for four days. (이날 조문은 밤 10시 종료됐다. 28일부터 나흘간은 오전 9시부터 저녁 9시까지 조문이 가능하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Go Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241999.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500005.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Countdown to Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion...Young Members Demand "Reconsideration" While Party Leadership Faction Urges "Quick Conclusion" (한동훈 제명 초읽기…소장파 “재고” 요구에 당권파 “빨리 결론내야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242005.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Countdown to Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion...Young Members Demand "Reconsideration" While Party Leadership Faction Urges "Quick Conclusion" (한동훈 제명 초읽기…소장파 “재고” 요구에 당권파 “빨리 결론내야”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694820188682_53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민의힘 장동혁 대표, 한동훈(오른쪽) 전 대표. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The leadership of the People Power Party is expected to deliberate on the motion to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon on the 29th. Although not only pro-Han Dong-hoon faction members but also young lawmakers within the party are demanding a reconsideration of the disciplinary action, party leader Jang Dong-hyeok and other 'anti-impeachment mainstream' figures are poised to push through with the expulsion. (국민의힘 지도부가 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명안을 29일 의결할 것으로 보인다. 친한동훈계뿐 아니라 당내 소장파 의원들도 징계 재고를 요구하고 있지만, 장동혁 대표 등 ‘반탄(탄핵 반대) 주류’는 제명을 밀어붙일 태세다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang is considering a plan to return to party duties, starting with a visit to the Korea Agro-Fisheries &amp; Food Trade Corporation (aT) integrated situation room on the afternoon of the 28th to check on prices. It has been six days since he ended his hunger strike following former President Park Geun-hye's persuasion. A party leadership official told The Hankyoreh on the 27th, "If Leader Jang returns to party duties and attends the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th, (the disciplinary motion) will not be postponed further," adding, "It is the shared opinion of the leadership that the disciplinary motion should not be continuously delayed and a conclusion must be reached quickly." (장 대표는 28일 오후 한국농수산식품유통공사(aT) 종합상황실을 찾아 물가를 점검하는 것을 시작으로 당무에 복귀하는 방안을 검토하고 있다. 박근혜 전 대통령의 만류로 단식을 중단한 지 엿새 만이다. 당 지도부 관계자는 27일 한겨레에 “장 대표가 당무에 복귀해 29일 최고위에 참석한다면, (징계안) 처리를 더 미루지는 않을 것”이라며 “징계안 처리를 계속 미뤄선 안 되고, 빨리 결론을 내려야 한다는 게 지도부의 공통된 의견”이라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, it is viewed as almost certain that former leader Han Dong-hoon will be expelled, as evidenced by the party's Ethics Committee imposing the severe disciplinary measure of 'recommendation to leave the party' on pro-Han faction Goyang City Party chapter chairman Kim Jong-hyuk the previous day. Another party leadership official stated, "Former leader Han was given the opportunity to appeal the Ethics Committee's decision and had the chance to visit the hunger strike site, but he rejected them all himself," adding, "Former leader Han largely created the justification for the disciplinary action himself." (당내에선 전날 당 윤리위원회가 친한계 김종혁 고양시병 당협위원장에게 ‘탈당 권유’라는 초강수 징계를 내린 데서 알 수 있듯, 한동훈 전 대표의 제명 역시 확정적이라고 본다. 또 다른 당 지도부 관계자는 “한 전 대표에게는 윤리위 처분에 대해 재심을 할 기회도 줬고, 단식 농성장에 찾아올 기회도 있었지만 스스로 모두 차 버린 것”이라며 “징계에 대한 명분은 한 전 대표 스스로 만들어준 측면이 크다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han repeatedly protested against Chairman Kim's disciplinary action. In a post on Facebook the previous night, former leader Han strongly criticized, saying, "Shockingly, anti-democratic and anti-intellectual statements are being made openly in the Ethics Committee's decision document," and "(Recommending leaving the party) is not democracy but 'totalitarianism' or 'pseudo-democracy' like 'North Korean leader theory' or 'Nazism'." He then raised his voice, stating, "(The leadership's behavior) is not normal. It must be corrected. The People Power Party must be a liberal democratic party." (한 전 대표는 김 위원장 징계에 거듭 반발했다. 한 전 대표는 전날 밤 페이스북에 올린 글에서 “반민주, 반지성적인 말을 놀랍게도 윤리위 결정문에서 대놓고 하고 있다”며 “(탈당 권유는) 민주주의가 아니라 ‘북한 수령론’, ‘나치즘’ 같은 ‘전체주의’, ‘사이비 민주주의’”라고 강도 높은 비난을 쏟아냈다. 그러면서 “(지도부 행태가) 정상이 아니다. 바로잡아야 한다. 국민의힘은 자유민주주의 정당이어야 한다”고 목소리를 높였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, opinions are sharply divided over the deliberation of the motion to expel former leader Han. Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won said on YTN Radio that day, "Indefinitely postponing and continuing internal party disputes is not good for the party and only causes confusion for the public. The Supreme Council must deliberate (on the expulsion motion) within a short period of time." Jang Ye-chan, vice president of the Yeouido Research Institute close to Leader Jang, said on the radio the previous day, "The prevailing opinion within the Supreme Council is that former leader Han has become unable to avoid expulsion." 'Alternative and Future', a gathering of young members within the People Power Party, urged that day, "The Supreme Council should reconsider the deliberation on expelling former leader Han and seek a political solution for party unity." (당내에선 한 전 대표 제명안 의결을 두고 찬반이 팽팽하게 갈리는 모습이다. 김재원 최고위원은 이날 와이티엔(YTN) 라디오에서 “마냥 미루고 당내 논란만 계속되는 건 당을 위해서도 좋지 않고, 국민들에게도 혼란만 야기한다. 빠른 시일 안에 최고위에서 (제명안을) 의결해야 한다”고 했다. 장 대표와 가까운 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장은 전날 라디오에서 “한 전 대표가 제명을 피할 수 없게 됐다는 것이 최고위 내부의 중론”이라고 했다. 국민의힘 소장파 모임인 ‘대안과 미래’는 이날 “최고위가 한 전 대표 제명 의결을 재고하고, 당 통합을 위한 정치적 해법을 찾아야 한다”고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242005.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0127/53_17694820188682_53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Proposes "Introducing a Sugar Tax to Strengthen Regional and Public Healthcare" (이 대통령 “설탕세 도입해 지역·공공 의료 강화에 쓰자”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242013.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee Proposes "Introducing a Sugar Tax to Strengthen Regional and Public Healthcare" (이 대통령 “설탕세 도입해 지역·공공 의료 강화에 쓰자”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500375.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung proposed on the 28th to impose a so-called 'sugar tax', a health promotion levy, on foods and beverages high in sugar. The idea is to introduce a related tax to reduce sugar intake, which causes obesity and diabetes, and to use the revenue collected in this way for various regions and the national health insurance. (이재명 대통령이 28일 설탕이 많이 함유된 식품과 음료에 건강증진부담금을 부과하는 이른바 ‘설탕세’를 부과하자고 제안했다. 비만·당뇨 등을 부르는 설탕 섭취를 줄일 수 있도록 관련 세금을 도입하고, 이렇게 거둬들인 재정을 각 지역 및 건강보험 등에 사용하자는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee wrote on X (formerly Twitter) that day, "Like with cigarettes, suppress sugar use through a sugar levy, and reinvest that levy to strengthen regional and public healthcare... What are your thoughts?" He also shared an article stating that '80% of the public supports the introduction of a sugar tax.' (이 대통령은 이날 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 “담배처럼 설탕 부담금으로 설탕 사용 억제, 그 부담금으로 지역·공공 의료 강화에 재투자…여러분 의견은 어떠냐”고 적었다. 그러면서 ‘국민 80%가 설탕세 도입에 찬성한다’는 기사를 공유했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sugar tax has been implemented in over 120 countries since the World Health Organization (WHO) recommended its introduction in 2016. (설탕세는 2016년 세계보건기구(WHO)가 도입을 권고한 뒤 120여개국에서 시행되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, discussions took place in 2021, but it failed to be introduced due to opposition from the food industry and some consumers. At the time, the Ministry of Agriculture, Food and Rural Affairs and the Ministry of Health and Welfare also expressed the opinion that careful review was necessary, considering public acceptance and other factors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;After President Lee posted this on X, a Blue House official stated, "We plan to gather opinions from various sectors and review measures regarding the issue of public health rights caused by sugar intake and the use of funds for reinvestment to strengthen regional and public healthcare." The official added, "I understand that the National Assembly is also discussing ways to strengthen public health rights, such as disease prevention through the introduction of a sugar levy, including holding a hearing on the sugar tax." &lt;br/&gt;Previously, Representative Jeong Tae-ho of the Democratic Party of Korea held a 'Discussion on Tax for Excessive Sugar Use' at the National Assembly in October last year. (국내에서도 2021년 논의가 이뤄졌지만, 식품업계와 일부 소비자의 반발에 부딪혀 도입되지 못했다. 당시 농림축산식품부·보건복지부도 국민 수용성 등을 고려해 신중한 검토가 필요하다는 의견을 낸 바 있다.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;이 대통령이 이런 글을 엑스에 올린 뒤, 청와대 관계자는 “설탕 섭취로 인한 국민 건강권 문제 및 지역·공공의료 강화를 위한 재투자 재원으로의 활용 방안 등에 대해 각계의 의견을 수렴하여 검토해나갈 계획”이라고 밝혔다. 그러면서 “국회에서도 설탕세 토론회를 개최하는 등 설탕 부담금 도입을 통한 질병 예방 등 국민 건강권 강화 문제에 대해 논의 중인 것으로 알고 있다”고 덧붙였다. &lt;br/&gt;앞서 정태호 더불어민주당 의원은 지난해 10월 국회에서 ‘설탕 과다사용세 토론회’를 진행한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242013.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500375.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Calls for "Public Review" of Wildly Varying Interest Rates on Local Government Funds (이 대통령, 천차만별 지자체 금고 이자율에 “공개 검토하라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242017.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee Calls for "Public Review" of Wildly Varying Interest Rates on Local Government Funds (이 대통령, 천차만별 지자체 금고 이자율에 “공개 검토하라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/733/572/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500519.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령 엑스(X) 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee Jae-myung commented on the fact that interest rates on funds operated by local governments show a disparity of up to more than double, saying, "It would be worth conducting a comparative study between the degree of democracy in the relevant city and its interest rate." (이재명 대통령은 28일 지방자치단체가 운영하는 금고 금리가 최대 2배 이상 편차가 나는 것을 두고 “해당도시의 민주주의 정도와 이자율을 비교 연구해볼 가치가 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The President made these remarks while sharing on X (formerly Twitter) an article analyzing the results of the first-ever public disclosure of interest rates on funds managed by local governments. (이 대통령은 이날 지자체가 운용하는 금고의 이자율이 처음으로 공개된 결과를 분석하는 기사를 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 공유하며 이렇게 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interest rates on funds from 243 local governments nationwide were disclosed on this day on the 'Local Finance Integrated Public System' website, following President Lee's directive last August during a 'National Fiscal Savings Meeting' to "investigate the interest rates on local government funds nationwide and review whether public disclosure is possible." His point is that the significant variation in interest rates by local government might be correlated with the degree of democracy in each locality. (이 대통령이 지난해 8월 ‘나라 재정 절약 간담회’에서 “전국 지자체 금고 이자율을 조사해 공개가 가능한지 검토하라”고 지시하면서 이날 ‘지방재정통합 공개시스템’ 누리집에 전국 243개 지자체의 금고 이자율이 공개됐다. 지자체별 금리가 크게 다른 것을 두고, 각 지자체의 민주주의 정도와 이자율에 상관관계가 있을 수도 있다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the early hours of the same day, President Lee also shared a related article titled 'Incheon 4.6%·Gyeongbuk 2.2% - A World of Difference' and wrote, "Even 1% on 1 trillion won is 10 billion won." He added, "This is all taxpayers' money." He was criticizing the fact that, despite being the same residents' taxes, while some cities receive interest in the 4% range, others barely reach the 1% range, showing very large regional disparities. Given that local government budgets typically exceed trillions of won, even a 1% difference in interest rates causes interest income to swing by tens of billions of won. (이 대통령은 이날 새벽에도 ‘인천 4.6%·경북 2.2% 천차만별’이라는 관련 기사를 공유하며 “1조원에 1%만 해도 100억원”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “이게 다 주민들의 혈세”라고 썼다. 똑같은 주민 세금임에도 어떤 도시는 4%대 이자를 받는 반면, 어떤 도시는 1%대에 그치는 등 지역별 편차가 매우 큰 것으로 나타났는데, 지자체 예산이 보통 조 단위가 넘다 보니, 금리 1% 차이만으로도 이자 수익이 수백억 원씩 왔다 갔다 한다는 점을 비판한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, looking at the interest rates on funds from 243 local governments nationwide, the average interest rate for time deposits with a maturity of 12 months or more was 2.53%. Among these, the average rate for the 17 metropolitan governments was calculated at 2.61%. Among metropolitan governments, Incheon City and Seoul City received relatively high interest rates at 4.57% and 3.45%, respectively. Sejong City (2.68%) and Daejeon City (2.64%) also exceeded the average. In contrast, North Gyeongsang Province (2.15%) and Daegu City (2.26%) remained in the low 2% range, placing them at the bottom. (한편, 전국 243개 지자체의 금고 이자율을 보면, 12개월 이상 정기예금 기준 평균 금리는 2.53%였다. 이 가운데 17개 광역자치단체의 평균 금리는 2.61%로 집계됐다. 광역단체 중에서는 인천시와 서울시가 각각 4.57%와 3.45%로 상대적으로 높은 이자율을 적용받았다. 세종시(2.68%)와 대전시(2.64%)도 평균을 웃돌았다. 반면 경북(2.15%)과 대구(2.26%)는 2%대 초반의 이자율에 머물며 최하위권에 위치했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242017.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/733/572/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500519.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[View Briefing] 'V0' Kim Gun-hee's First Trial Sentencing, What's the Outlook? ([뷰리핑] ‘V0’ 김건희 1심 선고, 전망은?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242018.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[View Briefing] 'V0' Kim Gun-hee's First Trial Sentencing, What's the Outlook? ([뷰리핑] ‘V0’ 김건희 1심 선고, 전망은?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500540.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host: Kwon Tae-ho, Hankyoreh Editorial Board Director. Guests: Ha Eo-young, Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter; Park Jin-young, Political Critic; Gil Yun-hyeong, Hankyoreh Editorial Writer. (진행: 권태호 한겨레 논설위원실장. 출연: 하어영 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 박진영 정치비평가, 길윤형 한겨레 논설위원)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'V0' Kim Gun-hee's First Sentencing...Court Permits Live Broadcast / Yoon's Key Aide Kwon Seong-dong's First Trial Sentencing...'Allegations of Illegal Political Fund Receipt' / Kim Min-seok, on 'Merger Controversy'..."Welcoming Unification, But the Announcement Method is Questionable" / 'Suspicion of Nomination Bribes' Kim Kyeong...Need to Expand Investigation into 'Illegal Political Donations' / Turbulent People Power Party, Internal Feud over 'Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion' / China's 'West Sea Structure' Moves...A Signal for Korea-China 'Relationship Normalization'? / Trump Threatens to Scrap Tariff Agreement...Outlook for Exports to US 'Clouded'. Please tune in to today's (January 28th) View Briefing. (‘V0’ 김건희 첫 선고…법원, 생중계 허가 / 윤핵관 권성동 1심 선고…‘불법 정치자금 수수 혐의’ / 김민석, ‘합당 논란’에…“통합은 환영, 발표 방식은 글쎄” / ‘공천헌금 의혹’ 김경…‘불법 정치후원금’ 수사 확대 필요성 / 격동의 국힘, ‘한동훈 제명’ 집안 싸움 / 중국 ‘서해 구조물’ 이동…한·중 ‘관계 정상화’ 신호? / 트럼프 관세 합의 파기 위협…대미 수출 전망 ‘먹구름’. 오늘(01월 28일) 뷰리핑 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242018.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500540.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un and Kim Ju Ae personally observed yesterday's North Korean missile launch... "Will become a grave threat to enemies" (어제 북 미사일 쏠 때 김정은·김주애 직접 참관…“적들에 엄중한 위협될 것”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1242019.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kim Jong Un and Kim Ju Ae personally observed yesterday's North Korean missile launch... "Will become a grave threat to enemies" (어제 북 미사일 쏠 때 김정은·김주애 직접 참관…“적들에 엄중한 위협될 것”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695598347705_20260128500589.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장은 27일 미사일총국이 진행한 ‘대구경 방사포 무기체계’ 시험사격을 참관하며 “기술적 갱신을 해 특수한 공격사용에 적합화됐기 때문에 우리와 군사적 대결을 기도하는 세력에게 착잡한 고민거리, 엄중한 위협으로 다가갈 것”이라고 말했다고 28일 노동신문이 보도했다. 김정은 총비서의 딸 김주애양도 함께 참관했다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, observed a test-firing of a "large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapons system" and stated, "Because it has been technologically updated and adapted for special attack use, it will become a vexing concern and a grave threat to forces attempting military confrontation with us," Rodong Sinmun reported on the 28th. General Secretary Kim Jong Un's daughter, Ju Ae, also observed the event together. (김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장은 ‘대구경 방사포 무기체계’ 시험사격을 참관하며 “기술적 갱신을 해 특수한 공격사용에 적합화됐기 때문에 우리와 군사적 대결을 기도하는 세력에게 착잡한 고민거리, 엄중한 위협으로 다가갈 것”이라고 말했다고 28일 노동신문이 보도했다. 김정은 총비서의 딸 주애양도 함께 참관했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported, "The Missile General Bureau conducted a test-firing on the 27th for the effectiveness verification of the updated large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapons system with newly introduced technology," and that "Comrade Kim Jong Un observed the test." General Secretary Kim said, "Today's test holds very significant meaning in enhancing the effectiveness of strategic deterrence," adding, "This is because we have carried out technological updates to most accurately and effectively utilize the most powerful characteristics of this weapons system, and therefore it has been adapted for special attack use." He did not specify what exactly "special attack use" entails, but it is presumed to be related to 'tactical nuclear operation'. (노동신문은 “미사일총국은 27일 새로운 기술이 도입된 갱신형 대구경 방사포 무기체계의 효력검증을 위한 시험사격을 진행했다”며 “김정은 동지께서 시험을 참관하셨다”라고 보도했다. 김 총비서는 “오늘의 시험은 전략적 억제의 효과성을 제고해나가는 데서 대단히 중요한 의미를 가진다”며 “이 무기체계의 가장 위력한 특성을 가장 적중하고 효과적으로 활용하기 위한 기술적 갱신을 하였으며 따라서 특수한 공격 사용에 적합화되었기 때문”이라고 말했다. 그는 ‘특수한 공격 사용’이 구체적으로 어떤 내용인지 밝히지 않았으나, ‘전술핵 운용’과 관련된 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during an on-site guidance visit to an 'important munitions industry enterprise' on December 29 last year, General Secretary Kim inspected the "actual state of multiple rocket launcher vehicle production" and stated, "This multiple rocket launcher weapons system, which will become the main striking means of our military, can annihilate the enemy and can be used as a strategic attack means," calling it "an important new milestone in practically increasing war deterrence." Even earlier, on May 8 last year, he guided the 'joint strike training of long-range artillery and missile systems by units of the People's Army Eastern Front'. At the time, Rodong Sinmun reported that the training "was conducted with the aim of familiarizing the relevant units with the procedures for operating artillery and missile attack systems according to the national nuclear weapons comprehensive management system." 'Units' typically refer to small forces at the battalion level or below. (앞서 김 총비서는 지난해 12월29일 ‘중요 군수공업기업소’를 현지지도하며 “방사포차 생산 실태”를 점검하고는 “우리 군대의 주력 타격수단으로 될 이 방사포 무기체계는 적을 초토화시킬 수 있으며 전략적 공격수단으로 이용할 수 있는 것”이라며 “전쟁억제력을 실용적으로 증대시키는 데서 중요한 새 이정표”라고 말한 바 있다. 그보다 앞선 지난해 5월8일엔 ‘인민군 동부전선 구분대들의 장거리포 및 미사일체계 합동타격훈련’을 지도했는데, 당시 노동신문은 “국가핵무기종합관리체계에 따라 포 및 미사일공격체계를 운용하는 절차에 해당 구분대들을 숙달시키는 데 목적을 두고 진행”됐다고 전했다. ‘구분대’란 통상 대대급 이하 작은 부대를 뜻한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Secretary Kim, who observed the test-firing of the 'updated large-caliber multiple rocket launcher' on the 27th, "expressed satisfaction" and boasted, "I am convinced that for at least a few years, no other country will reach such technology or possess such capability." He then said, "As I have always emphasized, the purpose of our activities is to further advance nuclear war deterrence," adding, "Demonstrating this will and capability itself is the responsible exercise of deterrence." Judging by the expression "updated," it is presumed that a multiple rocket launcher with improved functions and performance compared to the existing "600mm multiple launch rocket system" has been developed. Indeed, General Secretary Kim praised it, saying, "The mobility, intelligence, and accuracy of the rocket shells have been updated incomparably," and "The mobility of the newly improved launch vehicle is also perfect." (27일 ‘갱신형 대구경 방사포’ 시험사격을 참관한 김 총비서는 “만족을 표시”했으며 “나는 최소 몇년 안에는 그 어느 나라도 이와 같은 기술에 도달하지 못할 것이며 그러한 능력을 가질 수 없을 것이라는 것을 확신한다”라고 자평했다. 그러곤 “늘 강조해왔지만 우리가 진행하는 활동이 목적은 핵전쟁억제력을 더욱 고도화해나가자는 데 있다”며 “이러한 의지와 능력을 보여주는 것 자체가 억제력의 책임적인 행사”라고 말했다. “갱신형”이라는 표현에 비춰, 기존의 “600㎜ 다연장 방사포”보다 기능·성능이 개선된 방사포를 개발했다는 뜻으로 추정된다. 실제 김 총비서는 “방사포탄의 기동성, 지능성, 명중성이 비할 바 없이 갱신됐다”며 “새로 개량된 포차의 기동성 또한 완벽하다”고 자찬했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported, "The fired rocket shells struck a sea target 358.5 km away from the launch point." Earlier, the Joint Chiefs of Staff announced to the press on the 27th, "We detected several short-range ballistic missiles launched from an area north of Pyongyang, North Korea, toward the East Sea," and "The detected North Korean missiles flew approximately 350 km." (노동신문은 “발사된 방사포탄들은 발사점으로부터 358.5㎞ 떨어진 해상표적을 강타했다”고 전했다. 앞서 합동참모본부는 27일 “북한 평양 북방 일대에서 동해상으로 발사된 단거리 탄도미사일 수발을 포착했다”며 “포착된 북한의 미사일은 약 350㎞를 비행했다”고 언론에 공지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported that General Secretary Kim stated, "Building the most reliable attack capability and implementing a deterrence strategy based on it is the immutable line of the national defense policy," and "The 9th Congress of the Workers' Party of Korea will proclaim the next-stage plans for further strengthening the country's nuclear war deterrence." (노동신문은 김 총비서가 “가장 확실한 공격 능력을 구축하고 그에 기초한 억제전략을 실시하는 것은 국가방위정책의 불변 노선”이라며 “조선노동당 9차 대회는 나라의 핵전쟁억제력을 가일층 강화하기 위한 다음 단계의 구상들을 천명하게 될 것”이라고 밝혔다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Je-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1242019.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695598347705_20260128500589.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Woo Sang-ho: "For a merger between the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party, behind-the-scenes contacts are needed... Quota negotiations are impossible these days" (우상호 “민주·혁신 합당, 물밑 접촉할 때…지분 협상 요즘은 불가능”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242021.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Woo Sang-ho: "For a merger between the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party, behind-the-scenes contacts are needed... Quota negotiations are impossible these days" (우상호 “민주·혁신 합당, 물밑 접촉할 때…지분 협상 요즘은 불가능”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500658.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;우상호 전 청와대 정무수석. 김태형 기자 xogud555@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, former Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho commented on the ongoing controversy within the Democratic Party of Korea that party leader Chung Cheong-rae unilaterally proposed a merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, saying, "Rather than dragging this issue out, I think it's time to move on to the topic of whether integration is desirable or not." (우상호 전 청와대 정무수석이 28일 더불어민주당 내부에서 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 독단적으로 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안했다는 논란이 이어지는 것과 관련해 “그 문제를 오래 끄는 것보다는 통합이 바람직하냐, 바람직하지 않냐의 주제로 넘어갈 때가 된 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with YTN Radio that day, former Senior Secretary Woo said, "I believe there was a need for procedural legitimacy, such as (Leader Chung) secretly calling the Supreme Council members before making the merger proposal and asking, 'I'm thinking of making this proposal, what do you think?'" He added, "However, I hope the leadership will reconcile again and pool their wisdom on the methodology of how to push forward with this integration." (우 전 수석은 이날 와이티엔(YTN) 라디오에서 “(정 대표가) 합당 제안을 하기 전에 최고위원들을 비밀리에 불러서 ‘이런 제안을 하려고 하는데 어떻게 생각하느냐’고 물어보는 절차적인 정당성은 필요했다고 본다”면서도 “지도부가 다시 서로 화해하고 이 통합을 어떻게 추진할 건지에 대한 방법론으로 지혜를 모아줬으면 좋겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Senior Secretary Woo stated, "Looking at the past, when two parties integrate, they usually form a kind of integration promotion body, and that body needs to engage in various behind-the-scenes negotiations." He explained, "Even if they agree in principle to integrate, depending on the type of integration, it can break down or succeed." He continued, "So, we should see this as a process of moving into that phase," and added, "The war of words currently going on between Democratic Party Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae and Innovation Party floor leader Seo Wang-jin shows that we are entering this phase." (우 전 수석은 “과거에 보면 양당이 일종의 통합추진기구를 만들고, 통합추진기구가 물밑에서 다양한 교섭을 해야 된다”며 “원칙적으로 통합에 찬성한다 하더라도 어떤 통합이냐에 따라서 결렬되기도 하고 성사되기도 하다”고 했다. 이어 “그래서 그 문제로 넘어가고 있는 과정이라고 봐야 된다”며 “지금 조승래 민주당 사무총장 혹은 서왕진 혁신당 원내대표 사이에 오간 설전이 이 국면으로 넘어가고 있다는 것을 보여주는 것”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Senior Secretary Woo said, "Integration is not that easy," and added, "To integrate, there are many things to discuss, such as the leadership system and the party name." He then stated, "Now is not the time for public disputes, but for behind-the-scenes contacts between the integration negotiation representatives from both sides," and emphasized, "Otherwise, the merger will not happen." (우 전 수석은 “통합이 그렇게 쉽게 되지 않는다”며 “통합을 하려면 지도 체제, 당명 등 여러 가지 논의할 게 많다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “이제는 공개적인 설전을 할 때가 아니라 비밀리에 양쪽 통합 교섭 대표들이 물밑 접촉으로 해야 될 때”라며 “그렇지 않으면 합당이 안 이루어진다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "Even civilians fall in love and get married, but don't various conflicts arise during the marriage process? Integration goes through such a process." He said, "Therefore, it's time for those behind-the-scenes dialogues to narrow various differences of opinion." (그는 “민간인들끼리도 사랑해서 결혼을 하지만 결혼 과정에서 여러 가지 다툼이 생기지 않느냐. 통합이라는 게 그런 과정을 거친다”며 “그래서 여러 가지 견해 차이를 좁히기 위한 그런 물밑 대화를 해야 될 때”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to a question asking, 'Don't the two parties inevitably have to talk about quotas?', he said, "Quotas were discussed in past integrations 15 or 20 years ago, but these days, quota negotiations are difficult." He explained, "It's a matter that can be handled by establishing nomination rules, but negotiations involving give-and-take, for example, deciding 'local government heads will be allocated (Democratic Party) 7 to (Innovation Party) 3,' are impossible." (그는 ‘양당에서 지분 이야기를 할 수밖에 없지 않느냐’는 질문엔 “지분을 논의한 것은 과거 15년 전, 20년 전 통합 때는 그랬는데 요즘은 지분 협상은 어렵다”며 “공천룰을 가지고 진행하면 될 문제이지 주고 받는 협상을 통해서 예를 들어 ‘기초단체장을 (민주당) 7 대 (혁신당) 3으로 한다’ 이런 건 불가능하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the mention within the Democratic Party of regions where Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, might run, he said, "The issue of how to treat Leader Cho should involve listening to his opinion." He stated, "If the Democratic Party makes a proposal without even listening to Leader Cho's opinion, the negotiations will break down. We must do as Leader Cho wishes." (조국 조국혁신당 대표의 출마 지역 등이 민주당 내에서 거론되는 것 관련해서는 “조 대표를 어떻게 예우할 것인가의 문제는 조 대표의 의견을 들어야 한다”며 “조 대표의 의견도 듣지 않고 민주당이 제안하면 협상은 깨진다. 조 대표가 원하는 대로 해 줘야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242021.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500658.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Says Agreement on 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' Name "Befitting the Home of Democracy" (이 대통령, ‘전남광주특별시’ 명칭 합의에 “민주주의 본산답다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242023.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee Says Agreement on 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' Name "Befitting the Home of Democracy" (이 대통령, ‘전남광주특별시’ 명칭 합의에 “민주주의 본산답다”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695612845995_20260128500713.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난 27일 청와대에서 국무회의를 주재하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung commented on Gwangju and Jeonnam's decision to name the integrated administrative city 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' after discussions, saying, "Dialogue, compromise, coexistence... truly befitting the home of democracy." (이재명 대통령이 광주·전남이 토론 끝에 행정통합시의 명칭을 ‘전남광주특별시’로 정한 것을 두고 “대화, 타협, 공존…과연 민주주의의 본산답다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee shared on 'X' (formerly Twitter) an article stating that Gwangju and Jeonnam, which are promoting integration, had decided on the official name of the local government as 'Jeonnam-Gwangju Special City' and its abbreviation as 'Gwangju Special City'. He highly praised it as the 'home of democracy,' as the two local governments quickly decided on the name for the integrated administrative city after discussions. (이 대통령은 28일 ‘엑스’(X·옛 트위터)에 전날 통합을 추진 중인 광주와 전남이 자치단체 명칭을 ‘전남광주특별시’로, 약칭을 ‘광주특별시’로 정했다는 기사를 공유했다. 두 지방자치단체가 토론 끝에 행정통합시의 명칭을 빠르게 결정짓자 ‘민주주의 본산’이라며 한껏 치켜세운 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee is focusing efforts on reorganizing the country beyond the Seoul metropolitan area's single-pole system into five super-regions (Seoul metropolitan area, Southeast region, Daegu-Gyeongbuk region, Central region, Honam region) and three special self-governing provinces (Gangwon, Jeonbuk, Jeju). At a New Year's press conference on the 21st, he emphasized, "The great shift to 'region-led growth' has already begun," and added, "The 'regional integration' currently being pursued is a symbolic starting point for region-led growth and a national survival strategy that must succeed." (이 대통령은 수도권 일극 체제를 벗어나 전국을 5개의 초광역권(수도권·동남권·대경권·중부권·호남권)과 3개의 특별자치도(강원·전북·제주)로 재편하는 데 공을 들이고 있다. 이 대통령은 지난 21일 신년 기자회견에서 “‘지방 주도 성장’으로의 대전환은 이미 시작됐다”며 “현재 추진 중인 ‘광역 통합’은 지방 주도 성장의 상징적 출발점이자, 반드시 성공시켜야 할 국가 생존 전략”이라고 강조하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242023.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695612845995_20260128500713.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Nomination Contribution Woes' Democratic Party: "Excluding National Assembly Members from City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committees" (‘공천헌금 몸살’ 민주 “시·도당 공관위에 국회의원 배제”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'Nomination Contribution Woes' Democratic Party: "Excluding National Assembly Members from City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committees" (‘공천헌금 몸살’ 민주 “시·도당 공관위에 국회의원 배제”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/416/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500993.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 27일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에서 고 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 지키며 조문객을 맞이하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea decided on the 28th to form City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committees (NMCs) that largely exclude incumbent National Assembly members and regional party chairpersons. (더불어민주당이 28일 현역 국회의원과 지역위원장을 대부분 배제한 시도당 공직선거후보자추천관리위원회(공관위)를 구성하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a closed-door Supreme Council meeting at Seoul National University Hospital that day, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun met with reporters and announced that a proposal regarding the City/Provincial Party NMCs with this content had been passed. He explained, "It would be no exaggeration to say that in the past, City/Provincial Party NMCs were composed of more than half regional chairpersons, including incumbent National Assembly members, with the remaining external members being at a formalistic level." He added, "The central party had issued guidelines to City/Provincial parties to minimize the inclusion of incumbent Assembly members and regional chairpersons. Accordingly, a feature of this round of City/Provincial Party NMCs is that they are composed almost entirely of external figures, excluding incumbent Assembly members and regional chairpersons, aiming for objectivity and neutrality." (박수현 수석대변인은 이날 서울대병원에서 비공개 최고위원회를 마친 후 기자들과 만나 이런 내용의 시도당 공관위 건을 의결했다고 밝혔다. 그는 “과거 시도당 공관위는 현역 국회의원 포함한 지역위원장이 절반 이상이고 나머지 외부인사는 형식적인 수준에서 구성됐다고 해도 과언이 아니었다”며 “현역 국회의원과 지역위원장 최소화 방침을 중앙당이 시도당에 지침을 내린 바 있고, 그에 따라 이번 시도당 공관위는 현역 의원과 지역위원장을 거의 배제하고 외부 인사로 객관적, 중립적으로 구성된 것이 특징”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is interpreted as a measure to minimize the influence incumbent Assembly members can exert within the NMCs. This comes as the Democratic Party's nomination process is facing credibility issues, following allegations that Assembly member Kang Seon-woo, who was a member of the Seoul City Party NMC during the 2022 local elections, received 100 million won from then-Seoul City Council candidate Kim Kyeong. (이는 현역 의원이 공관위에 영향력을 행사하는 것을 최소화하려는 조치로 풀이된다. 2022년 지방선거 당시 서울시당 공관위원이었던 강선우 의원이 김경 당시 서울시의원 후보자로부터 1억원을 받았다는 의혹이 불거지면서 민주당 공천 과정에 대한 신뢰도가 지적받고 있는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park further explained, "The central party's NMC, through a resolution on the 'Rules for the Operation of Public Office Candidate Nominations' the previous day (27th), decided on rules related to the composition, meetings, reviews, and operation of candidate nomination bodies, as well as the preservation, inspection, and disposal of meeting and review records. This makes it clearer that these records must be preserved for the next four years." (박 수석대변인은 또 “중앙당 공관위가 전날(27일) 공직선거후보자추천운영규칙 의결을 통해 공직선거후보자추천기구의 구성, 회의, 심사 및 위원회 운영, 그리고 회의 심사 기록보존, 기록 열람 및 폐기 등 관련 규칙을 의결해 좀 더 명확하게 향후 4년까지 이 기록을 보존하도록 했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is seen as an attempt to address shortcomings, as the Democratic Party, ahead of the 2024 general election, not only lacked the 'petition' submitted to the party regarding allegations of Assembly member Kim Byeong-gi receiving money and valuables, but also had no records of the receipt and handling of all petitions, complaints, and tips at the time. After a Supreme Council meeting on people's livelihood issues in Songpa-gu, Seoul on the 7th, Chief Spokesperson Park had told reporters, "During nominations and elections, hundreds of petitions, complaints, tips, and defamations are received in a very short period. We are now looking back on whether those were handled properly." (이는 민주당이 2024년 총선을 앞두고 당에 제출된 김병기 의원의 금품 수수 의혹 ‘탄원서’뿐 아니라 당시 모든 탄원, 민원, 제보의 접수 및 처리 기록이 없다고 한 점을 보완하려는 시도로 풀이된다. 박 수석대변인은 지난 7일 서울 송파구 민생 현장 최고위원회의 뒤 기자들과 만나 “공천과 선거 때는 아주 짧은 시간에 수백 건 이상 탄원, 민원, 제보, 비방이 접수되는데 그것들을 잘 처리했는가 하는 점을 이번에 돌아보게 됐다”고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Chae-un &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242026.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/416/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128500993.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoon Geon-young: "Kim Keon-hee Should Receive a Sentence 'Higher' Than the 15 Years Sought by Prosecution" (윤건영 “김건희, 구형 15년보다 형량 ‘올려치기’ 선고 받아야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242027.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Yoon Geon-young: "Kim Keon-hee Should Receive a Sentence 'Higher' Than the 15 Years Sought by Prosecution" (윤건영 “김건희, 구형 15년보다 형량 ‘올려치기’ 선고 받아야”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/538/419/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695645931344_20260128501018.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김건희 여사가 지난해 9월24일 오후 서울 서초구 서울중앙지법에서 열린 첫 재판에 출석해 최지우 변호사와 이야기를 나누고 있다. 김 여사는 왼쪽 가슴에 ‘수용번호 4398’이 적힌 배지를 달았다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the first-instance sentencing for former President Yoon Suk-yeol's wife, Kim Keon-hee, the ruling party is urging that a sentence higher than the 15 years sought by the special prosecutor be handed down. (윤석열 전 대통령 부인 김건희 여사에 대한 1심 선고를 앞두고, 여당은 특검이 구형한 15년보다 더 높은 형량이 선고돼야 한다고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Yoon Geon-young said in an interview with CBS Radio's 'Park Jae-hong's Hanpan Victory' on the 27th, "The court should strictly enforce the law and hand down a sentence (higher than the prosecution's request)." Lawmaker Yoon stated, "(Kim Keon-hee) was essentially V0, wasn't she the one who meddled in state affairs?" and added, "Currently, the (15 years sought by the special prosecutor) is 11 years for stock price manipulation and 4 years for violating the Political Funds Act, making 15 years, but the charge of meddling in state affairs is missing." Lawmaker Yoon further added, "There are too many unrevealed additional crimes," and "(the sentence should be) higher than the prosecution's request." (윤건영 더불어민주당 의원은 27일 시비에스(CBS) 라디오 ‘박재홍의 한판승부’와의 인터뷰에서 “재판부에서 엄정하게 법을 집행해서 (구형보다) 올려치기 해야 한다”고 말했다. 윤 의원은 “(김건희는) 사실상 브이제로(V0)로서 국정농단을 한 것 아니냐”며 “지금 (특검이 구형한) 15년이 주가 조작 11년, 정치자금법 4년 해서 15년인데 국정농단죄가 빠져있다”고 말했다. 윤 의원은 “지금까지 밝혀지지 않은 여죄가 너무 많다”며 “(선고 형량은 구형보다) 올려치기가 필요하다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Seoul Central District Court's Criminal Division 27 (Presiding Judge Woo In-seong) will hold the first-instance sentencing hearing for Mrs. Kim's case involving violations of the Capital Markets Act and the Political Funds Act, and bribery mediation under the Act on the Aggravated Punishment of Specific Crimes, starting at 2:10 PM on the 28th. Last month on the 3rd, during the final trial arguments, the special prosecutor sought 11 years in prison, a fine of 2 billion won, and forfeiture of 811.44 million won for the charges related to Deutsche Motors stock price manipulation and receiving money and valuables from the Unification Church, and 4 years in prison and forfeiture of 137.2 million won for the charge of receiving unpaid opinion polls. (서울중앙지법 형사27부(재판장 우인성)는 28일 오후 2시10분부터 김 여사의 자본시장법·정치자금법 위반, 특정범죄가중처벌법의 알선수재 혐의 사건 1심 선고기일을 연다. 특검은 지난달 3일 결심공판에서 도이치모터스 주가조작과 통일교 금품 수수 혐의에 대해 징역 11년과 벌금 20억원, 추징금 8억1144만원을, 무상 여론조사 수수 혐의에 대해선 징역 4년과 추징금 1억3720만원을 각각 구형했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Jeon Hyeon-hee also urged severe punishment in an interview with MBC's 'News Extra' on the 27th, saying, "Kim Keon-hee has been widely evaluated as the de facto president with much more authority than President Yoon Suk-yeol." Lawmaker Jeon said, "(Kim Keon-hee's charges) are not simply personal crimes but power-type crimes that abused presidential power," and added, "Perhaps the sentence will be a bit more than that (the prosecution's request)." Lawmaker Jeon further stated, "Because the criminal charges Kim Keon-hee is facing are extremely serious and are crimes that have caused public anger and outrage, a slightly stronger sentence is expected." (전현희 민주당 의원도 27일 문화방송(MBC) ‘뉴스외전’과의 인터뷰에서 “김건희씨가 윤석열 대통령보다 훨씬 더 권한을 가진 사실상의 대통령이라는 평가를 많이 받았다”며 엄벌을 촉구했다. 전 의원은 “(김건희의 혐의는) 단순한 개인의 범죄가 아니라 대통령 권력을 악용한 권력형 범죄”라며 “아마 그(구형)보다 좀 더 많이 선고하지 않을까”라고 말했다. 전 의원은 “김건희씨가 받는 범죄 혐의가 굉장히 중대하고 또 국민들의 분노, 공분을 사는 그런 범죄였기 때문에 조금 더 강한 선고가 되지 않을까”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party spokesperson Jang Yun-mi said during a briefing at the National Assembly on the 27th, "For Kim Keon-hee, who placed herself above the law, severe punishment is the only way to establish judicial justice." Spokesperson Jang stated, "For Kim Keon-hee, who shook the foundations of the Republic of Korea—the capitalist market order, democracy, and the principle of separation of church and state—nothing remains but severe punishment," and added, "Kim Keon-hee consistently denied the charges throughout the trial, but when the evidence became overwhelming and denial was no longer possible, she belatedly confessed to receiving a Chanel bag. There is no room for leniency." (장윤미 민주당 대변인은 27일 국회에서 브리핑을 열고 “법 위에 군림한 김건희, 엄벌만이 사법정의를 세우는 길”이라고 말했다. 장 대변인은 “대한민국의 근간인 자본주의 시장질서, 민주주의, 정교분리의 원칙을 뒤흔든 김건희에게 남은 것은 엄벌밖에 없다”며 “김건희는 재판 내내 부인으로 일관하다 증거가 차고 넘쳐 더 이상은 부인하기가 어렵게 되자 샤넬 가방을 받은 사실을 뒤늦게 실토하기도 했다. 선처의 여지가 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the first-instance sentencing for Mrs. Kim is scheduled to be broadcast live. (한편, 김 여사에 대한 1심 선고는 생중계될 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Kyung-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242027.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/538/419/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695645931344_20260128501018.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong Wa Dae Welcomes "Meaningful Progress" as China Moves Some West Sea Structures (청와대, 중국 서해 구조물 일부 이동에 “의미 있는 진전 환영”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242032.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cheong Wa Dae Welcomes "Meaningful Progress" as China Moves Some West Sea Structures (청와대, 중국 서해 구조물 일부 이동에 “의미 있는 진전 환영”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/889/567/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501214.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;중국이 서해 한중 잠정조치수역에 설치한 구조물 선란 2호에서 중국 쪽 인원들이 작업하는 모습. 이병진 더불어민주당 의원실 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheong Wa Dae stated that it "welcomes as meaningful progress" China's measure to move a management facility, among its West Sea structures, outside the Korea-China Provisional Measures Zone (PMZ). (중국이 서해구조물 가운데 관리시설을 한·중 잠정조치수역(PMZ) 밖으로 이동시키는 조처를 한 것에 대해 청와대가 “의미있는 진전으로 환영한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cheong Wa Dae spokesperson's office announced through a press release on the 28th, "The Chinese government announced yesterday that the management platform installed within the Provisional Measures Zone is being moved by a Chinese company according to its own needs," and added, "Our government, maintaining the position of opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measures Zone, has continued consultations with China. Given that this management platform has been a central point of various concerns, we welcome this measure as meaningful progress." (청와대 대변인실은 28일 언론 공지를 통해 “중국 정부는 어제 잠정조치수역 내에 설치된 관리플랫폼을 중국 측 기업이 자체적인 수요에 따라 이동시키고 있다고 발표했다”며 “우리 정부는 잠정조치수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치를 반대한다는 입장 아래 중국과의 협의를 이어왔으며 그간 해당 관리플랫폼이 여러 우려의 중심이 되어온 만큼, 이번 조치를 의미 있는 진전으로 환영한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;China has in the West Sea Provisional Measures Zone Seolan 1 and 2, which it claims are aquaculture facilities in the form of steel structures, and a seabed-fixed structure which it claims is a management facility. All three structures are located within the Provisional Measures Zone where the Exclusive Economic Zones (EEZ) of Korea and China overlap, and are artificial maritime facilities built by China without consultation with Korea. (중국은 서해 잠정조치수역 내에 양식시설이라고 주장하는 철제 구조물 형태의 선란 1·2호와 관리시설이라고 주장하는 해저 고정식 구조물을 두고 있다. 구조물 3기 모두 한국과 중국의 배타적경제수역(EEZ)이 겹치는 잠정조치수역에 위치하고 있고, 한국과 협의 없이 중국이 세운 인공 해상 시설이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The previous day, Chinese Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Geng Shuang stated at a regular briefing, "Chinese companies are currently conducting work related to the management platform," and that "the companies have autonomously adjusted the deployment according to their own operational and development needs." This indicates that China has stated it moved the management facility among the structures installed in the Provisional Measures Zone. Kang Young-shin, Director-General of the Northeast Asian Affairs Bureau at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, who is in charge of China affairs, also stated on the same day, "This measure is a change helpful to the development of Korea-China relations," and "Our government, maintaining the position of opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measures Zone, has continued consultations with China. Therefore, we evaluate this measure as meaningful progress." (전날 궈자쿤 중국 외교부 대변인은 정례 브리핑에서 “중국 기업이 현재 관리 플랫폼과 관련된 작업을 진행 중”이라며 “기업이 자체적인 경영·발전 필요에 따라 자율적으로 배치를 조정한 것”이라고 밝혔다. 잠정조치수역에 설치된 구조물 중 관리시설을 옮겼다고 중국 쪽에서 밝힌 것이다. 중국을 담당하는 강영신 외교부 동북아 국장도 같은 날 “이번 조치는 한중관계 발전에 도움이 되는 변화”라며 “우리 정부는 잠정조치 수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치 반대 입장하에 그동안 대중국 협의를 이어온 만큼 이번 조치를 의미있는 진전으로 평가한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, as there was no mention from China regarding Seolan 1 and 2 among the structures, the embers of conflict remain. Cheong Wa Dae stated, "The government will continue its efforts to actively protect our maritime rights and interests in the West Sea and to make the West Sea a sea of peace and shared prosperity." (다만 구조물 가운데 선란 1, 2호에 대한 중국의 언급은 없어 갈등의 불씨는 남은 상태다. 청와대는 “정부는 서해에서 우리의 해양 권익을 적극 수호하는 가운데 서해를 평화롭고 공영하는 바다로 만들어나가기 위한 노력을 계속해 나갈 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242032.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/889/567/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501214.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:18:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Foreign Minister Cho Hyun-dong Concludes "No Direct Link Between Coupang and Trump's Tariff Hike" (조현 장관 “쿠팡, 트럼프 관세 인상과 직접 관계 없다고 결론”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242051.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695782081309_20260128501748.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;조현 외교부 장관이 28일 국회 외교통상위원회 전체회의에 출석해 트럼프 미국 대통령의 관세 발언에 대한 의원들의 질문에 답변하고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Cho Hyun-dong stated regarding the background of U.S. President Donald Trump's surprise announcement of a tariff hike, "We are concluding that it has no direct connection with Coupang." (조현 외교부 장관이 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 기습적인 관세 인상 예고의 배경에 대해 “쿠팡과는 직접적인 관계가 없는 것으로 결론 내리고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At an emergency current affairs question-and-answer session of the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee on the 28th, Minister Cho said, "Based on our contact with the U.S. State Department after that message (from President Trump) came out, we, for our part, are concluding that it has no direct connection with Coupang or the Online Platform Act." (조 장관은 28일 국회 외교통일위원회 긴급 현안질의에서 “(트럼프 대통령의) 그 메시지가 나온 뒤에 저희들이 (미국) 국무부와 접촉한 바로는 쿠팡이나 온플법(온라인플랫폼법)과는 직접적인 관계가 없는 것으로 그렇게 결론을 저희들로서는 내리고 있다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Cho's response came in answer to a question from independent lawmaker Lee Chun-seok, who asked whether President Trump's message was an indirect expression of U.S. dissatisfaction with the Korean government's sanctions over the 'Coupang incident' and regulations on online platforms. (조 장관의 답변은 트럼프 대통령의 메시지가 ‘쿠팡 사태’에 대한 한국 정부의 제재와 온라인 플랫폼 규제 등에 대해 미국이 우회적으로 불만을 표현한 것 아닌가 묻는 이춘석 무소속 의원의 질의에 대한 답변으로 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Cho added, "Regarding the Coupang issue, we have been carefully explaining to the U.S. side from the beginning so that it does not escalate into a diplomatic issue," and further stated, "Moreover, now that the related companies (U.S. investors in Coupang) have filed an international investment dispute (ISDS), I would like to add that we are being cautious and sparing in our words, including myself and other government officials, so that our statements are not judged or evaluated more favorably for them in their lawsuit process later on." (조 장관은 “쿠팡 문제는 저희들이 처음부터 이것이 외교 문제로 비화되지 않도록 미국 측에 잘 설명을 해왔다”며 “더군다나 이제 관련 회사(쿠팡의 미국 투자사들)가 국제투자분쟁(ISDS)을 제소한 만큼 나중에 행여라도 우리 정부, 저를 포함한 정부 관계자의 발언이 그들의 소송 과정에서 그들에게 더 유리하게 판단이나 평가되지 않도록 말을 조심하고 아끼고 있다는 점을 추가로 말씀드린다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to a question asking whether President Trump's message was made with the U.S. Supreme Court's ruling on reciprocal tariffs in mind, to confirm South Korea's investment in the U.S., Minister Cho replied, "One could analyze it that way, but from the government's standpoint, as this is an internal matter of the U.S. government, we intend to avoid commenting as much as possible." (또 조 장관은 트럼프 대통령이 미국 연방대법원의 상호관세 관련 판결을 염두에 두고, 한국의 대미 투자를 확정짓기 위해 메시지를 낸 것 아닌지 묻는 질의에는 “그렇게 분석할 수도 있는데, 정부 입장에서는 이게 미국 정부 내에 있는 일이라서 언급을 가급적 회피하고자 한다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To a question from People Power Party lawmaker Song Eon-seok, who said, '(President Trump's remarks) can be read as asking why the Korean legislature did not approve this, why it did not give its consent to ratification,' Minister Cho drew a line, saying, "It clearly does not appear that President Trump made that statement this time because there was no National Assembly consent to ratification of our joint fact sheet." He then cited President Trump's statement that he would 'work with South Korea to find a solution,' saying, "If it were (because of the lack of National Assembly consent), then our position hasn't changed either, so he wouldn't have sent such a message again today saying he would handle it amicably with the Korean government, would he?" (조 장관은 ‘(트럼프 대통령의 발언이) 왜 한국 입법부가 이것을 어프루브(approve), 승인을 안 했느냐, 왜 비준 동의 안 했느냐, 이런 취지로 읽힌다’는 송언석 국민의힘 의원의 질문에 “트럼프 대통령이 우리 조인트 팩트시트에 대한 국회 비준 동의가 없어 이번에 저런 입장을 밝힌 것은 분명히 아닌 것으로 보인다”고 선을 그었다. 이어 트럼프 대통령이 ‘한국과 함께 해결책을 마련할 것’이라고 밝힌 것을 들어 “만약 (한국 국회의 비준 동의가 없어) 그런 것이라면 우리 입장이 바뀌지도 않았는데 한국 정부와 원만하게 처리하겠다고 오늘 다시 그런 메시지를 냈을 리 없지 않겠냐”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to a question from People Power Party lawmaker Ahn Cheol-soo asking if the problem arose because there was no National Assembly ratification procedure, Minister Cho said, "Not at all," adding, "In diplomatic practice in normal state-to-state relations, regardless of the form in which an agreement is made, the domestic procedures concerning it are not questioned. I am telling you this is not a problem." (조 장관은 국회 비준 절차가 없어 문제가 된 것 아니냐는 안철수 국민의힘 의원의 질의에도 “전혀 아니다”라며 “통상 국가 간 관계에서 합의를 어떤 형태로 했든 그것에 관한 국내적 절차에 관해서는 따지지 않는 것이 외교 관례다. 이게 문제 되지 않는다고 말씀드린다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242051.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695782081309_20260128501748.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:17:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Live Broadcast] Kim Keon-hee's First Trial Sentencing... First Ruling on Deutsche Motors/Unification Church Money Suspicions ([생중계] 김건희 1심 선고…도이치·통일교 금품 의혹 첫 판단)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242055.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501795.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first trial sentencing for Kim Keon-hee, indicted on charges including Deutsche Motors stock price manipulation and receiving money from the Unification Church, will be broadcast live from the Seoul Central District Court at 2:10 PM on January 28. We appreciate your viewership. (1월 28일 오후 2시 10분 서울중앙지법에서 도이치모터스 주가조작 및 통일교 금품 수수 혐의 등으로 기소된 김건희의 1심 선고 현장이 생중계됩니다. 많은 시청 바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242055.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128501795.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:17:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling Party and Government to Comprehensively Legalize Single-Family Homes Under 50 Pyeong (당정, 50평 미만 단독주택 일괄 양성화)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242064.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502012.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 마포구 공덕동 일대 단독주택, 빌라촌. 김혜윤 기자 unique@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea and the government have decided on a policy to comprehensively legalize single-family homes under 165㎡ (approximately 50 pyeong) as part of a temporary measure to legalize illegal (non-compliant) residential structures. (더불어민주당과 정부가 주거용 불법(위반) 건축물의 한시적 양성화를 위해 165㎡(약 50평) 미만의 단독주택을 일괄 양성화하기로 방침을 정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Bok Ki-wang, the ruling party's secretary on the National Assembly's Land, Infrastructure and Transport Committee, met with reporters after a party-government consultation meeting at the National Assembly on the 28th and announced that such legalization standards had been established. Illegal structures refer to buildings constructed without permission or notification to the state or local governments, or buildings used differently from their permitted purpose. (국회 국토교통위원회 여당 간사인 복기왕 의원은 28일 국회에서 열린 당·정 협의회 뒤 기자들을 만나 이런 내용의 양성화 기준을 마련했다고 밝혔다. 불법 건축물이란 국가나 지방자치단체의 허가를 받지 않거나 신고를 하지 않고 지어진 건물, 또는 허가받은 내용과 다르게 사용되는 건물을 뜻한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport announced a 'Reasonable Management Plan for Non-compliant Buildings' in October last year to temporarily resolve illegal structures and fundamentally block new illegal activities. Since then, the government has been discussing legislative measures with the Democratic Party, and broadly set the comprehensive legalization standards on this day. (앞서 국토교통부는 지난해 10월 불법 건축물을 일시 해소하고 신규 불법 행위를 원천 차단하기 위해 ‘위반 건축물 합리적 관리 방안’을 발표한 바 있다. 이후 정부는 민주당과 입법 방안을 논의해 왔고, 이날 일괄 양성화 기준을 큰 틀에서 정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarizing Rep. Bok's explanation, the ruling party and government plan to comprehensively legalize single-family homes under 165㎡, and to allow local governments to set legalization standards via ordinance for homes under 330㎡ according to their local circumstances. For multi-family homes, legalization will be allowed for structures under 660㎡, and for neighborhood living facilities, legalization will be permitted on the condition that parking lots are secured. (복 의원 설명을 종합하면, 당정은 165㎡ 미만 단독주택은 일괄 양성화하고, 각 지방자치단체 상황에 따라 330㎡ 미만의 주택에 대해서도 조례를 통해 양성화 기준을 정할 수 있도록 할 방침이다. 다가구 주택의 경우 660㎡ 미만까지 양성화를 허용하고, 근린생활시설은 주차장이 확보된다는 조건 안에서 양성화를 허용하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A likely condition for legalization is the payment of five times the enforcement penalty. The enforcement penalty is calculated by multiplying the standard market value of the building by the non-compliant area and the imposition rate. Rep. Bok stated, "We will organize the standards and push forward so that the bill can be realized within the first half of this year at the latest." (양성화 조건으로는 강제 이행금 5회분 납부가 유력하다. 강제 이행금은 건물 시가표준액에 위반 면적과 부과요율을 곱해 산출된다. 복 의원은 “기준을 정리해서 최대한 (올해) 상반기 중으로는 법안이 현실화할 수 있도록 추진하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242064.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502012.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:17:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Watching YS Documentary, Han Dong-hoon Says "Unfair Expulsion... Even If You Wring a Chicken's Neck, Dawn Will Come" (YS 다큐 본 한동훈 “부당한 제명…닭 목 비틀어도 새벽 와”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242074.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695795276682_7117695793668817.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 28일 오전 서울 영등포구 타임스퀘어 영화관에서 잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁시대를 관람하기 위해 자리에 앉아 있다. 정용일 선임기자 yongil@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon said, "Having faced an unfair expulsion, I will, like the words of President Kim Young-sam who said, 'Even if you wring a chicken's neck, dawn will come,' continue forward with an unbroken spirit, trusting the people." (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 28일 “부당한 제명을 당하면서 ‘닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다’고 했던 김영삼 대통령의 말씀처럼 꺾이지 않는 마음으로 국민을 믿고 계속 가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After watching the film 'The Forgotten President: Kim Young-sam's Era of Reform' at a cinema in Seoul's Yeongdeungpo District that day, the former leader met with reporters. Regarding speculation that his expulsion motion might be processed at the People Power Party's Supreme Council meeting on the 29th, he said, "As I am on my way out after watching the movie, I will not make lengthy remarks," and made the above statement. He also added, "I have a sense of mission that I must certainly achieve good politics for the people." (한 전 대표는 이날 서울 영등포구의 한 영화관에서 ‘잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁 시대’ 영화를 관람한 뒤 기자들을 만나 오는 29일 국민의힘 최고위원회에서 자신의 제명안이 처리될 수도 있다는 관측에 대해 “영화를 보고 나오는 길이라 긴 말씀을 드리지 않겠다”며 이렇게 말했다. 그러면서 “저는 국민을 위한 좋은 정치를 꼭 해내야겠다는 사명감을 가지고 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Choosing to watch a documentary film depicting the life of former President Kim as his first public appearance since the party's Central Ethics Committee recommended his expulsion, he likened his own situation—facing a vote on the expulsion disciplinary motion—to that of former President Kim, who was expelled from his parliamentary seat while opposing Park Chung-hee's Yushin dictatorship. (당 중앙윤리위원회의 제명 권고 이후 첫 공개 행보로 김 전 대통령의 일생을 그린 다큐 영화 관람을 선택해, 제명 징계안 의결을 앞둔 자신의 상황을 박정희 유신 독재에 맞서다 의원직에서 제명당한 김 전 대통령에 빗댄 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the screening that day were pro-Han Dong-hoon lawmakers Kim Hyung-dong, Park Jeong-hoon, Jeong Seong-guk, and Jin Jong-oh, as well as Kim Hyun-chul, chairman of the Kim Young-sam Presidential Foundation. (이날 시사회에는 친한동훈계인 김형동, 박정훈, 정성국, 진종오 의원 등과 김현철 김영삼대통령기념재단 이사장 등이 함께했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242074.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695795276682_7117695793668817.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:17:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[News Dive] Kim Gun-hee Sentenced to 1 Year and 8 Months in Prison ([뉴스 다이브] 김건희 징역 1년 8개월 선고)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242083.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502447.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Featuring: Jang Yun-seon, Political Affairs Specialist; Park Ji-hoon, Attorney; Kim Jeong-hwan, Attorney; Kim Gyu-hyun, Attorney; Kim Nam-il, Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter; Hosted by: Ko Hyeon-jun. Breaking News! 'V0' Kim Gun-hee sentenced to 1 year and 8 months in prison... Aftermath expected to be severe / 'Unification Church cash' suspects Kwon Sung-dong and Yoon Young-ho also face their day of fate... First trial sentencing / 'V0' Kim Gun-hee above the law... 'Deutsch' stock manipulation 'not guilty' / Chanel bag, Graff necklace... "Pursued profit using First Lady status" / 'Myeong Tae-gyun gate' not guilty... Verdict leaves various questions. Please tune in to today's (January 28th) News Dive. (출연: 장윤선 정치전문기자, 박지훈 변호사, 김정환 변호사, 김규현 변호사, 김남일 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 진행: 고현준. 속보! ‘V0’ 김건희, 징역 1년 8개월 선고... 후폭풍 거셀 듯 / ‘통일교 금품’ 혐의 권성동·윤영호도 운명의 날... 1심 선고 / 법 위의 ‘V0’ 김건희...도이치 주가조작 ‘무죄’ / 샤넬백·그라프 목걸이... “영부인 지위로 영리 추구” / ‘명태균 게이트’ 무죄... 각종 의문 남는 판결문. 오늘 (1월 28일) 뉴스 다이브 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242083.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502447.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:16:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Says "Stock Price Rise Too Fast, Even I'm Surprised...Will Eliminate Korean Peninsula Geopolitical Risk" (이 대통령 “주가 상승 너무 빨라 저도 놀라…한반도 지정학 리스크 없앨 것”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242084.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/648/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502453.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 28일 청와대에서 열린 외국인투자기업 간담회에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 28th, "We will not unnecessarily engage in military confrontation or escalate conflict with North Korea," encouraging investment from foreign-invested companies. Regarding the recent stock price rise, President Lee said, "Even I am surprised because it is faster than expected." (이재명 대통령은 28일 “이제 불필요하게 북한과 군사적으로 대결하거나 갈등이 강화되거나 그러지는 않을 것”이라며 외국인 투자기업들의 투자를 독려했다. 이 대통령은 최근 주가 상승과 관련해 “저도 예상보다 너무 빨라서 놀랍다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a meeting with foreign-invested companies at the Blue House that day, President Lee stated, "Even if we make some concessions, we will maintain stability so that geopolitical risks on the Korean Peninsula will disappear due to political and peace stability." Representatives from seven foreign chambers of commerce in Korea, including those from the US and the European Union, and representatives from 31 foreign-invested companies attended the meeting. (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 외국인 투자기업 간담회를 주재하고 “우리가 조금 양보하더라도 안정을 유지해서 정치, 평화 안정 때문에 한반도의 지정학적 리스크가 없어질 것”이라고 밝혔다. 이날 간담회에는 미국, 유럽연합을 비롯한 7개 주한 외국 상의 대표와 외국인 투자기업 31개사 대표가 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee added, "We will reform the governance structure to create a rational corporate management governance structure where shareholders are properly treated. Companies should be operated with shareholders at the center; that is democracy. Just as the people are the masters of the nation, shareholders should be the masters of the company, but it seems these shareholders have not actually been treated as masters." (이 대통령은 “지배 구조를 개혁해서 주주가 제대로 대접받는 합리적인 기업경영 지배 구조를 만들겠다. 주주 중심으로 회사를 운영해야 하는데 이게 민주주의”라며 “국가의 주인은 국민인 것처럼 회사의 주인은 주주라야 되는데 이 주주가 실제로 주인 취급을 받지 못한 거 같다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee emphasized, "Should the market become unfair and opaque? There have been cases where Korea was greatly disgraced by so-called stock price manipulation, but from now on, there will be none of that. We will thoroughly monitor and ensure the fairness and transparency of the stock market." He continued, "Regarding the most fundamental part about new investment, the state must clearly present the direction and content of industrial and economic policy. Until now, that has been unclear, but Korea is going in this direction." (이 대통령은 “시장이 불공정하고 불투명해져야겠느냐, 소위 주가 조작이니 이런 거로 대한민국이 참 망신 사는 사례인데 지금부터 그런 건 없다”며 “철저하게 주식 시장의 공정성, 투명성을 보고 확보하겠다”고 강조했다. 이어 “가장 근본적인 신규 투자에 관한 부분이라면 국가가 산업경제 정책 방향이나 내용을 명확하게 제시해 줘야 한다”며 “지금까지는 그게 불명확했는데 대한민국은 이런 방향으로 간다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the recently surging Korean stock market, President Lee said, "Perhaps, as you are also on the ground, you see aspects of Korea's current economic situation that are different from the past. Particularly, what reveals this is, after all, the unprecedented fluctuations in the capital market and stock market." He added, "Our Korean people are also surprised, but honestly, I knew it would come to this, yet I also think it's surprising because it's faster than expected." He then said, "On the other hand, when you think about it, since this is a process of normalization, it seems that what was being evaluated below Korea's original fundamental strength is now in the process of being evaluated a bit more properly." (이 대통령은 최근 급등하는 한국 주식시장과 관련해 “아마 여러분께서는 대한민국의 현재 경제 상황에 대해서 현장에 또 계시기도 하기 때문에 과거와는 다른 면모를 보시는 측면이 있을 것이다. 특히 그게 드러나는 게 아무래도 자본시장, 주식시장의 전례 없는 변동”이라며 “우리 대한민국 국민도 놀라고 있지만 사실 저도 이렇게 될 줄은 알긴 했는데 예상보다 너무 빨라서 놀랍다는 생각도 한다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “또 한편으로 생각해 보면 이게 정상화의 과정이기 때문에 대한민국이 가지고 있는 원래 기초 체력 이하로 평가되고 있던 것이 이제는 조금 제대로 평가받는 과정에 있는 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242084.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/648/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502453.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:16:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea, US, Japan call North Korea's ballistic missile launch a "violation of UNSC resolutions"... telephone consultation held yesterday (한미일, 북 탄도미사일 발사에 “안보리 결의 위반”…어제 전화협의)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242093.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695822931885_2417695822814605.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김정은 북한 국무위원장이 지난 27일 ‘갱신형 대구경 방사포 무기체계’의 효력 검증을 위한 시험사격을 참관했다고 조선중앙TV가 28일 보도했다. 김정식 당 중앙위원회 제1부부장, 장창하 미사일총국장이 동행했다. 조선중앙TV 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was belatedly revealed that South Korea, the United States, and Japan held a telephone consultation on the 27th, the same day North Korea launched a ballistic missile. (북한이 27일 탄도미사일을 발사한 당일 한·미·일 3국이 전화협의를 한 것으로 뒤늦게 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Japan's Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced on the 28th that Baek Yong-jin, Director-General for Korean Peninsula Peace and Security Affairs at South Korea's Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Dan Sintron, Acting Deputy Assistant Secretary of State at the U.S. Department of State, and Kengo Otsuka, Counsellor at the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs' Asian and Oceanian Affairs Bureau, held a telephone consultation the previous day. They stated that North Korea's ballistic missile launch violates United Nations Security Council resolutions and threatens international peace and security, and agreed that South Korea, the US, and Japan will continue to closely cooperate in responding to North Korea's provocative actions. (일본 외무성은 28일 백용진 한국 외교부 한반도정책국장과 댄 신트론 미국 국무부 부차관보 대행, 오쓰카 겐고 일본 외무성 아시아대양주국 참사관이 전날 전화 협의를 진행했다고 밝혔다. 이들은 북한의 탄도미사일 발사가 유엔(UN) 안전보장이사회 결의를 위반하고 국제 사회의 평화와 안전을 위협하는 것이라며 한·미·일이 북한의 도발 행동에 대응하기 위해 앞으로도 긴밀히 공조하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Korea's Ministry of Foreign Affairs belatedly confirmed the fact of the trilateral telephone consultation after the Japanese Foreign Ministry's announcement. A Foreign Ministry official stated, "The diplomatic authorities of South Korea, the US, and Japan operate a channel to swiftly share related information and situation assessments whenever North Korea launches a ballistic missile, and there was communication regarding this recent North Korean ballistic missile launch as well." (한국 외교부는 일본 외무성 발표가 나온 뒤 뒤늦게 3국 전화협의 사실을 확인했다. 외교부 당국자는 “한·미·일 외교당국 간에는 북한의 탄도미사일 발사 때마다 관련 정보 및 상황 평가를 신속하게 공유하는 채널을 운영하고 있으며, 이번 북한의 탄도미사일 발사 건에 대해서도 소통이 있었다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the past, trilateral consultations in response to North Korean ballistic missile launches were often announced immediately after they took place. Regarding the decision not to disclose this consultation on the day it occurred, the Foreign Ministry official explained, "As the National Security Office and the Joint Chiefs of Staff had already stated our government's position, the Foreign Ministry did not issue a separate statement," adding, "The Foreign Ministry does not issue a statement for every single missile launch by North Korea." (과거엔 북한 탄도미사일 발사에 대응한 3국 협의는 진행 직후 공지되는 경우가 많았다. 외교부 당국자는 이번에는 협의 당일 공개하지 않은 데 대해 “국가안보실과 합참에서 이미 우리 정부 입장을 밝힌 만큼, 외교부가 별도 입장 표명을 하지 않았다”면서 “외교부가 북한의 모든 미사일 발사에 대해 매 차례 입장을 발표한 것은 아니”라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The official also said, "The U.S. side also issued a statement in the name of the Indo-Pacific Command without a separate statement from the Department of State that would include details such as the South Korea-U.S.-Japan consultation." The official added, "North Korea's ballistic missile launch violates multiple UN Security Council resolutions, and our position of responding firmly together with the international community remains unchanged." (또 “미측도 한·미·일 협의 등 내용을 포함하는 국무부 명의 입장 발표 없이, 인도태평양사령부 명의 성명을 발표했다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “북한의 탄도미사일 발사는 다수 유엔 안보리 결의를 위반하는 것으로, 국제 사회와 함께 단호하게 대응해 나간다는 우리 입장에는 변화가 없다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of the 28th, the U.S. Department of State had also not officially announced that South Korea, the US, and Japan held a telephone consultation regarding North Korea's ballistic missile launch. (미 국무부도 28일까지 한·미·일이 북한 탄도미사일 발사에 대해 전화 협의를 했다는 내용을 공식 발표하지 않고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Central News Agency reported the previous day that the Missile General Bureau conducted a test-firing to verify the effectiveness of a large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapons system with "new technology introduced," and that Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, observed this test. General Secretary Kim said, "Technical updates have been made to most accurately and effectively utilize the most powerful characteristics of this weapons system, and therefore it has been optimized for special attack use." 'Special attack use' is presumed to be related to 'tactical nuclear operation.' (조선중앙통신은 전날 미사일총국이 “새로운 기술이 도입된” 대구경 방사포 무기체계의 효력 검증을 위한 시험사격을 진행했고, 김정은 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장이 이 시험을 참관했다고 보도했다. 김 총비서는 “이 무기체계의 가장 위력한 특성을 가장 적중하고 효과적으로 활용하기 위한 기술적 갱신을 하였으며 따라서 특수한 공격 사용에 적합화되었기 때문”이라고 말했다. ‘특수한 공격 사용’은 ‘전술핵 운용’과 관련된 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242093.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695822931885_2417695822814605.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:16:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. State Department Sanctions Six Entities for Nonproliferation Act Violations... Korean Company 'JS Research' Included (미 국무부, 비확산법 위반 6곳 제재…한국 기업 ‘JS 리서치’ 포함)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242097.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/361/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502689.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;미국 국무부 청사. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of State on the 27th (local time) imposed sanctions on six individuals and entities for allegedly engaging in illegal trade of technology or goods related to weapons of mass destruction (WMD) and missile development with North Korea, Iran, and Syria. A South Korean company, JS Research, was also included on the sanctions list. (미국 국무부가 27일(현지시각) 북한·이란·시리아 등과 대량살상무기(WMD) 및 미사일 개발 기술이나 물품을 불법 거래한 혐의로 개인·단체 6곳을 제재 대상에 올렸다. 한국 국적 기업 제이에스(JS)리서치도 제재 명단에 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The State Department announced the sanctions against those who violated the 'Iran, North Korea, and Syria Nonproliferation Act' (INKSNA) through the Federal Register on this day. The sanctions list includes South Korean company JS Research, North Korean national Choe Chol-min, the Foreign Affairs Bureau of North Korea's Second Academy of Natural Sciences (SANS FAB), and one company each from China, Lebanon, and the United Arab Emirates. (국무부는 이날 연방정부 관보를 통해 ‘이란·북한·시리아 비확산법’(INKSNA·비확산법)을 위반한 이들을 제재한다고 밝혔다. 제재 명단에는 한국 국적 기업 제이에스리서치를 포함해, 북한 국적의 최철민, 북한 제2자연과학원 외사국(SANS FAB) 그리고 중국과 레바논, 아랍에미리트 국적 기업 1곳씩 이름을 올렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The State Department did not disclose the countries involved in the transactions or the specific details regarding these sanctioned entities. However, it is reported that JS Research is suspected of engaging in illegal transactions with Syria. (국무부는 이들 제재 대상의 거래 국가와 세부 내용에 대해선 공개하지 않았으나, 제이에스 리서치는 시리아와 불법 거래했다는 혐의를 받는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the inclusion of the South Korean company JS Research on the sanctions list, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated, "We have been in continuous communication with the U.S. and were aware in advance," and added, "Our relevant authorities are also investigating the company, including verifying the facts." It further emphasized, "As a responsible member of the international community, the government has been actively participating in international efforts to prevent the transfer of materials that could contribute to the development of weapons of mass destruction (WMD)," and "We will continue these efforts and maintain close communication with the United States going forward." (외교부는 한국 기업 제이에스리서치가 제재 대상에 포함된 데 대해 “한·미 간 지속 소통해왔고 사전에 인지하고 있었다”며 “우리 관계 당국도 사실 관계를 확인하는 등 해당 기업에 대해 조사 중”이라고 밝혔다. 이어 “정부는 국제 사회의 책임 있는 일원으로서 대량살상무기(WMD) 개발에 기여할 수 있는 물자의 이전을 방지하기 위한 국제적 노력에 적극 동참해오고 있다”며 “앞으로도 관련 노력을 지속하면서 미국과도 계속 긴밀히 소통해 나갈 것”이라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;JS Research is a scientific and medical equipment manufacturer established in 2004, known for producing various products needed in the fields of science, technology, and industrial research and development. This marks the first time in approximately 18 years, since 2008, that a South Korean company has been sanctioned by the U.S. government for violating the Nonproliferation Act. (제이에스리서치는 2004년 설립된 과학 의료 기기 제조업체로, 과학 기술과 산업 연구개발 분야에 필요한 다양한 제품을 생산해온 것으로 알려졌다. 한국 기업이 비확산법 위반으로 미국 정부의 제재 대상에 오른 것은 2008년 이후 약 18년 만에 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a result of these sanctions, these entities are prohibited from entering into procurement contracts for goods or services with U.S. government agencies, participating in U.S. government assistance programs, or engaging in transactions involving items listed on the U.S. Munitions List. Additionally, they cannot obtain new licenses to receive items controlled under the Export Control Reform Act (ECRA), and all existing licenses are suspended. These sanctions took effect as of January 22nd and will be maintained for two years. (이번 제재에 따라 이들은 미국 정부 기관의 물품 및 서비스 조달 계약이 금지되며, 미국 정부 지원 프로그램 참여나 미국 군수품 목록에 등재된 항목의 거래를 할 수 없게 된다. 아울러 수출통제개혁법(ECRA)에 따른 수출 통제 품목을 이전받기 위한 신규 허가를 받을 수 없으며, 기존 허가도 모두 정지된다. 이번 제재는 1월22일치로 발효돼 2년 간 유지된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Nonproliferation Act provides for sanctions against companies and individuals trading WMD-related materials or technology with Iran, Syria, and North Korea. The Act was enacted in 2000 and was expanded and amended in 2006 to include North Korea. (비확산법은 이란과 시리아, 북한에 대량살상무기 관련 물자나 기술을 거래하는 기업과 개인을 제재할 수 있도록 규정하고 있다. 비확산법은 2000년 제정됐으며 2006년 북한까지 포함해 확대 개정됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242097.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/361/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502689.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:15:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Raises 'Sugar Tax' Discussion... People Power Party Retorts, "Is a Salt Tax Next?" (‘설탕세’ 논의 띄운 이 대통령…국힘 “다음은 소금세냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242101.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/484/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502806.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 28일 청와대에서 열린 외국인투자기업 간담회에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung has proposed introducing a so-called 'sugar tax,' a levy on foods and beverages high in sugar content. (이재명 대통령이 설탕이 많이 함유된 식품과 음료에 부담금을 매기는 이른바 ‘설탕세’ 도입을 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee shared an article on social media X (formerly Twitter) stating '80% of the public supports introducing a sugar tax' and wrote, "Like with cigarettes, suppress sugar use through a sugar levy, and reinvest that levy into strengthening local and public healthcare... What are your thoughts?" The shared article contained the results of a survey conducted by Seoul National University's Health Culture Business Unit from the 12th to the 19th on 1,030 citizens, which showed 80.1% in favor of introducing a sugar tax. (이 대통령은 28일 소셜미디어 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 ‘국민 80%가 설탕세 도입에 찬성한다’는 기사를 공유하며 “담배처럼 설탕 부담금으로 설탕 사용 억제, 그 부담금으로 지역·공공 의료 강화에 재투자…여러분 의견은 어떠냐”고 적었다. 공유된 기사에는 서울대 건강문화사업단이 지난 12~19일 국민 1030명을 대상으로 시행한 설문조사에서 80.1%가 설탕세 도입에 찬성했다는 내용이 담겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A sugar tax is a separate levy imposed on beverages and foods high in sugar content, with the aim of reducing sugar intake to prevent health issues like obesity and diabetes. The World Health Organization (WHO) recommended its introduction in 2016, and it is applied in over 120 countries, including the UK, France, and Norway. In South Korea, discussions for its introduction took place in 2021 but were scrapped due to opposition from the food industry and others. (설탕세는 당류가 많이 들어간 음료·식품에 별도로 매기는 부담금으로, 설탕 섭취를 줄여 비만·당뇨 같은 건강 문제를 예방하려는 목적이다. 2016년 세계보건기구(WHO)가 도입을 권고했고, 영국·프랑스·노르웨이 등 120여국이 적용하고 있다. 국내에서는 2021년 도입 논의가 이뤄졌지만, 식품 업계 등의 반발에 부딪혀 무산됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's mention of introducing a sugar tax appears to be aimed at reducing excessive sugar consumption to improve public health and also securing funds for local and public healthcare. A Blue House official stated, "We plan to gather opinions from various sectors and review measures regarding public health rights issues caused by sugar intake and the use of funds as reinvestment resources for strengthening local and public healthcare." (이 대통령이 설탕세 도입을 꺼내 든 것은 설탕 과다 섭취를 줄여 국민 건강을 증진하고 지역·공공의료를 위한 재원도 확보하자는 취지로 보인다. 청와대 관계자는 “설탕 섭취로 인한 국민 건강권 문제 및 지역·공공의료 강화를 위한 재투자 재원으로의 활용 방안 등에 대해 각계의 의견을 수렴하여 검토해나갈 계획”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, President Lee has recently been focusing on securing tax revenue. The day before, at a Cabinet meeting, he instructed National Tax Service Commissioner Lim Kwang-hyun to "make it impossible to live by dodging taxes" and to prepare measures for collecting delinquent national tax revenue. Following the collection of delinquent taxes, he is now proceeding to review the introduction of a sugar tax, showing a drive to secure finances. (특히 이 대통령은 최근 세금 확보에 공을 들이고 있다. 전날 이 대통령은 국무회의에서 임광현 국세청장에게 “세금 떼먹고 못살게 해야 한다”며 체납된 국세 외 수입의 징수 방안을 마련하라고 지시했다. 체납 세금 징수에 이어 설탕세 도입 검토에 나서면서 재정 확보에 드라이브를 거는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party issued a commentary in the name of its spokesperson, arguing, "After splurging the people's tax money and showing off all sorts of gestures, now that the financial burden has grown, they are trying to control even the people's dining tables with taxes," and asked, "What comes after the sugar tax? Will you also collect a salt tax to prevent hypertension?" (국민의힘은 대변인 명의 논평을 내어 “국민 혈세를 뿌리며 온갖 생색을 내더니 재정 부담이 커지자 이젠 국민 식탁까지 세금으로 통제하려 한다”며 “설탕세 다음은 무엇인가. 고혈압 예방을 위해 소금세도 걷겠느냐”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242101.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/484/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502806.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:15:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Despite Trump's Whims, People Power Party Blames Government: "Can't Even Speak Up to the U.S." (트럼프 변덕에도 정부 탓하는 국힘에 “미국엔 말도 못 하고”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242104.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502877.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령. 로이터 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jun-hyeong, a lawmaker of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, strongly criticized the People Power Party (PPP) for only pushing a narrative of government and ruling party responsibility after U.S. President Donald Trump announced he would impose a 25% tariff on Korean products. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 한국산 제품에 25% 관세를 부과하겠다고 밝힌 뒤 정부·여당 책임론만 펴는 국민의힘을 김준형 조국혁신당 의원이 강하게 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a current affairs question-and-answer session held by the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee on the 28th, Representative Kim said, "The actions of the People Power Party are utterly incomprehensible," adding, "They can't say a word to the U.S., which stabbed us in the back, and are only relentlessly harassing the government that got stabbed." He was pointing out the PPP's behavior of claiming the responsibility for President Trump's surprise announcement on the 26th (local time) — that he would raise reciprocal and item-specific tariffs on Korean products to 25%, citing the Korean National Assembly's failure to implement the Korea-U.S. trade agreement — lies with the government and ruling party. (김 의원은 28일 국회 외교통일위원회가 연 현안질의에서 “국민의힘의 행보가 도저히 이해가 가지 않는다”며 “뒤통수 때린 미국엔 한마디도 못 하고, 뒤통수 맞은 정부만 들들 볶고 있다”고 말했다. 트럼프 대통령이 26일(현지시각) 한국 국회가 한-미 무역 합의를 이행하지 않고 있다며, 한국산 제품에 대한 상호 및 품목 관세를 25%로 인상하겠다고 기습적으로 밝힌 책임이 정부와 여당에 있다는 국민의힘의 행태를 꼬집은 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP floor leader Song Eon-seok launched an offensive on the 27th, stating, "President Lee Jae-myung and the government concluded a major trade agreement requiring National Assembly ratification and have ignored the ratification process. All responsibility lies with the president and the government." Conversely, there was no mention of President Trump, who reneged on the tariff agreement. (송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 27일 “이재명 대통령과 정부는 국회의 비준이 필요한 중대한 통상 합의를 체결해 놓고 비준 절차를 외면해 왔다. 모든 책임은 대통령과 정부에 있다”며 공세를 폈다. 반면 관세 합의를 뒤집은 트럼프 대통령에 대한 언급은 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim pinpointed the U.S. government's responsibility for this situation. He said, "We have not violated the agreement," adding, "It is President Trump who is violating the agreement." Indeed, neither the Korea-U.S. joint fact sheet nor the memorandum of understanding specifies a timeline for the National Assembly's legislative process. Representative Kim stated, "Raising tariffs is a violation of the agreement," calling it "Trump being Trump." He also referred to President Trump's signature impulsive diplomatic style as a "natural disaster." (김 의원은 이번 사태의 책임이 미국 정부에 있다고 짚었다. 그는 “우리는 합의를 어긴 적이 없다”며 “트럼프 대통령이 합의를 어기고 있다”고 말했다. 실제로 한-미 공동 설명자료(조인트 팩트시트)나 양해각서에는 국회의 법안 처리 일정이 명시되어 있지 않다. 김 의원은 “관세를 올리는 게 합의 위반”이라며 “트럼프가 트럼프한 것”이라고 말했다. 트럼프 대통령 특유의 즉흥적 외교 스타일을 두고 “자연재해”라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim added, "We should protest the (U.S. government's) disregard for the legislative branch. I don't understand why (the PPP) is relentlessly harassing our government when both ruling and opposition parties should be angry," and questioned, "Will that help negotiations with the U.S.?" (김 의원은 “(미국 정부의) 입법부 무시에 항의를 해야 한다. 여야 전부 화를 내야 하는 입장에 (국민의힘은) 왜 우리 정부를 들들 볶는지 모르겠다”며 “그게 대미 협상에 도움이 되겠느냐”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242104.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502877.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:15:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[On-site] Kim Seong-tae pays respects to Lee Hae-chan: "He gave great help in difficult times"...Visits by Yoon Sang-hyun and Ban Ki-moon ([현장] 이해찬 조문한 김성태 “힘들 때 큰 도움 주셔”…윤상현·반기문 찾아)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242109.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502990.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김성태 손기정기념재단 이사장이 28일 서울 종로구 서울대학교병원 장례식장에 마련된 고 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소에서 헌화하고 있다. 사진공동취재단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, the second day of the funeral for Lee Hae-chan, Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council (Minjupyeongtong), conservative figures lined up to visit the funeral hall to mourn the deceased. Former and current People Power Party-affiliated lawmakers including Chung Mong-joon, Yoon Sang-hyun, Kim Seong-tae, Won Yoo-chul, and Tae Young-ho, as well as former UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon, visited the mourning site. (이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의(민주평통) 수석부의장의 장례 이틀째인 28일 보수 인사들이 줄이어 장례식장을 찾아 고인의 마지막을 애도했다. 정몽준·윤상현·김성태·원유철·태영호 등 전·현직 국민의힘 계열 의원들과 반기문 전 유엔사무총장 등이 빈소를 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital in Jongno-gu, Seoul, where the Senior Vice Chairman's mourning site was set up, was bustling with former and current politicians and citizens again today. After 3 PM, the number of mourners increased significantly, forming lines stretching from the third-floor mourning site to the stairs on the basement first floor. Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae, and writer Yoo Si-min kept vigil with the bereaved family as they did the previous day, while former Prime Ministers Kim Boo-kyum and Chung Un-chan, former National Assembly Speakers Kim Jin-pyo, Moon Hee-sang, and Park Byeong-seok, and Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, visited the mourning site. (이 수석부의장의 빈소가 마련된 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장은 이날도 전·현직 정치인들과 시민들로 붐볐다. 오후 3시를 넘어가면서는 조문객이 크게 늘며 3층 빈소부터 지하 1층 계단까지 줄이 늘어섰다. 김민석 국무총리와 정청래 더불어민주당 대표, 유시민 작가 등이 전날에 이어 상주 자리를 지켰고, 김부겸·정운찬 전 총리와 김진표·문희상·박병석 전 국회의장, 조국 조국혁신당 대표 등이 빈소를 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particularly noticeable were several conservative politicians. People Power Party lawmaker Yoon Sang-hyun said, "My grandfather and the deceased's father had a special bond. My grandfather served as a rural myeon (township) chief and gave a lot of help to the deceased's father, and I heard the deceased was always very grateful for that." He added, "Even if our political camps are different, I think it is the duty of politics to express deep condolences for the deceased's dedication and service to politics and the nation, and to honor his footsteps for democracy and parliamentary politics." Former Liberty Korea Party lawmaker Kim Seong-tae also said, "He is a great elder who cannot be omitted when discussing South Korea's democracy and democratization," and "I could not forget his humane side, as he gave me much help when I was struggling in the labor field, so I really wanted to be with him on his final journey." (특히 보수 계열 정치인들이 여럿 눈에 띄었다. 윤상현 국민의힘 의원은 “제 조부님하고 고인의 부친하고 각별한 인연이 있다. 제 조부께서 시골 면장을 하셨는데 고인의 부친께 많은 도움을 주셨다고, 고인께서 평소 그걸 되게 고마워하셨다”며 “진영은 다르더라도 정치와 국가에 대한 고인의 헌신과 봉사에 깊은 애도의 뜻을 표하고, 민주주의와 의회 정치에 대한 그분의 발자취를 기리는 게 정치의 도리라고 생각한다”고 말했다. 김성태 전 자유한국당 의원도 “대한민국 민주주의와 민주화를 얘기할 때 빼놓을 수 없는 큰 어른”이라며 “제가 노동 현장에서 어려울 때 많은 도움을 주신 인간적인 면을 잊지 못해 마지막 가시는 길을 꼭 함께하고 싶었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon also visited the mourning site. He said, "From 2004, I worked serving then Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan as Minister of Foreign Affairs and was deeply impressed. I always respected him for his very quick judgment." He added, "Our country's democracy, administration, and politics have developed a lot, and the economy needs to advance further, but it is regrettable that he passed away too soon. We have lost a great leader." (반기문 전 유엔사무총장도 빈소를 찾았다. 그는 “2004년부터 외교부 장관으로 당시 이해찬 총리님을 모시고 일하며 많은 감명을 받았다. 판단이 아주 빠르셔서 늘 존경했다”며 “우리나라의 민주주의·행정·정치가 많이 발전하고 있고 경제도 더 나아가야 하는데, 안타깝게 일찍 돌아가셨다. 큰 지도자를 잃었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current ministers including Jeong Seung-ho (Justice), Yoon Ho-joong (Public Administration and Security), and Kim Young-hoon (Employment and Labor), as well as business figures such as Hyun Jeong-eun (Hyundai), Seo Jung-jin (Celltrion), and Son Kyung-shik (Korea Employers Federation) paid their respects. Koichi Mizushima, the Japanese Ambassador to South Korea, also visited the mourning site. (이날 정성호(법무부)·윤호중(행정안전부)·김영훈(고용노동부) 등 현직 장관들과 현정은(현대)·서정진(셀트리온)·손경식(한국경영자총협회) 회장 등 재계 인사들이 조문했다. 미즈시마 고이치 주한일본대사도 빈소를 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funeral for the Senior Vice Chairman will last until the 31st, and general citizens can pay their respects from 9 AM to 9 PM. After the departure of the funeral procession on the morning of the 31st, the body will visit the Minjupyeongtong and the Democratic Party headquarters where the deceased was involved, followed by a public funeral ceremony at the National Assembly. Afterwards, the deceased's remains will be cremated, then taken to his home in Sejong City before being buried at Sejong Eunhasu Park. Lee Hae-sik, a Democratic Party lawmaker serving as vice-chairman of the funeral committee, stated, "Although (burial at) the National Cemetery was suggested, we decided to respect the family's wishes to lay him to rest where his father and mother are." (이 수석부의장의 장례는 오는 31일까지로, 일반 시민도 아침 9시부터 밤 9시까지 조문할 수 있다. 31일 아침 발인 뒤에는 고인이 몸담았던 민주평통과 민주당사를 들른 뒤 국회에서 사회장 영결식이 열린다. 이후 고인의 주검은 화장을 마친 뒤 세종시 자택을 들렀다가 세종 은하수공원에 묻힐 예정이다. 장례집행위원회 부위원장을 맡은 이해식 민주당 의원은 “국립묘지 (안장을) 권유받기도 했지만, 가족들의 의사를 존중해 고인의 부친·모친이 계시는 곳에 모시기로 결정했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242109.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128502990.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:14:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Kim Kun-hee sentenced to 1 year and 8 months in prison, a 'red carpet rolled out for V0' verdict," Democratic Party of Korea protests (“김건희 징역 1년8개월, V0 양탄자 깔아준 판결” 민주당 반발)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242110.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/964/579/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503012.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;28일 선고 공판에 출석 중인 김건희 여사. 유튜브 한겨레TV 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea protested against the first-instance court's sentencing of Kim Kun-hee, who was indicted and detained on charges including violations of the Capital Markets Act and the Political Funds Act, to 1 year and 8 months in prison on the 28th, calling it an "absurd verdict." (자본시장법과 정치자금법 등을 위반한 혐의로 구속기소된 김건희 여사에 대해 1심 법원이 28일 징역 1년8개월을 선고한 데 대해 더불어민주당은 “터무니없는 판결”이라며 반발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Lee Seong-yun posted on Facebook that day, stating, "Kim Kun-hee sentenced to 1 year and 8 months! Throughout the live broadcast, it felt as if the court was like Kim Kun-hee's defense attorney," and added, "The special prosecutor must immediately appeal." This lawmaker previously served as the head of the Seoul Central District Prosecutors' Office from 2020 to 2021. (이성윤 민주당 의원은 이날 페이스북에서 글을 올려 “김건희 1년8개월 선고! 생중계를 보는 내내 마치 재판부가 김건희 변호인 같은 느낌이었다”며 “특검은 즉각 항소하라”고 말했다. 이 의원은 2020~2021년 서울중앙지검장을 지낸 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Park Ji-won also criticized on Facebook, "The first-instance ruling on Kim Kun-hee is shocking and infuriating," and said, "It's a verdict that rolled out the red carpet for V0 (Kim Kun-hee) to walk out soon." He stated, "Today's verdict is a bad ruling that ignited the fire for a second special prosecution," and added, "It's going too far, even by excessive standards." (박지원 민주당 의원도 페이스북에서 “김건희 1심, 충격과 분노다”라며 “브이제로(V0) 김건희가 곧 걸어 나오도록 양탄자를 깔아준 판결”이라고 비판했다. 그는 “오늘 판결은 2차 특검의 불을 지른 나쁜 판결”이라며 “해도 해도 너무하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party chief spokesperson, lawmaker Park Soo-hyun, sarcastically remarked on Facebook, "Prosecution sought 15 years in prison! Sentenced to 1 year and 8 months?" and said, "It's a verdict designed for Kim Kun-hee to appeal, out of concern for damaging V0's prestige." (민주당 수석대변인인 박수현 의원은 페이스북에서 “징역 15년 구형! 징역 1년8개월 선고?”라며 “브이제로의 위상 훼손을 염려하여 김건희가 항소할 판결”이라고 비꼬았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Park Ju-min said on Facebook, "It's unbelievable. In a word, it's beyond words. Suspicions were overflowing, yet no responsibility remains." Lawmaker Park Ju-min added, "Arrest warrants were repeatedly blocked, the special prosecution's investigation was suspected of prosecutors' negligence, and ultimately, the first-instance verdict left only a reprimand," and stated, "The public has witnessed the three stages of deep-rooted evils." (박주민 의원은 페이스북에서 “어이가 없다. 한마디로 언어도단이다. 의혹은 차고 넘쳤는데 책임은 남지 않았다”고 말했다. 박주민 의원은 “영장은 번번이 막혔었고 특검 수사는 검사들의 태업이 의심되었고 결국 1심 판결은 훈계만 남았다”며 “국민은 적폐 3단계를 목격했다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Young-ho also said on Facebook, "We cannot solely blame the court," and added, "I have doubts about whether the special prosecution conducted a proper investigation." He further stated, "Regarding unresolved suspicions, a second special prosecution must proceed with a firm and thorough investigation." (김영호 민주당 의원 역시 “법원을 탓할 수만은 없다”며 “특검이 과연 제대로 수사를 한 건지 의구심이 든다”고 페이스북에서 말했다. 그는 “석연찮은 의혹에 대해서는 2차 특검이 단호하고 철저한 수사에 나서야 할 것”이라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Yong-min posted an article on Facebook titled "The judiciary's 'determination to go easy on Kim Kun-hee'," saying, "This verdict was not a realization of justice but a result of leniency." Lawmaker Kim said, "The judiciary's decision not to acknowledge Kim Kun-hee's collusion in the stock price manipulation case is difficult for the public to accept based on common sense," and added, "The suspicion regarding the free public opinion polls provided by Myeong Tae-gyun is also a serious criminal allegation involving the privatization of state affairs and damaging national trust. Nevertheless, the decision not to acknowledge this is also difficult for the public to accept." (김용민 민주당 의원은 페이스북에 “사법부의 ‘김건희 봐줄 결심’”이란 제목의 글을 올려 “이번 판결은 정의의 실현이 아니라 봐주기 결과였다”고 말했다. 김 의원은 “사법부가 주가조작 사건에서 김건희와의 공모 관계를 인정하지 않은 판단은 국민 상식으로 납득하기 어렵다”며 “명태균 무상 여론조사 수수 의혹 또한 국정을 사유화하고 국가 신뢰를 훼손한 중대한 범죄 혐의다. 그럼에도 이를 인정하지 않은 판단 역시 국민이 받아들이기 어렵다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Young-bae also said on Facebook, "Considering that he (Kim Kun-hee), backed by Yoon Suk Yeol and acting arrogantly, has disrupted the entire country, this verdict is absurd," and stated, "He has existed outside the law of the Republic of Korea and attempted to stand above it. He must be made an example of to ensure no second or third Kim Kun-hee appears again." (김영배 민주당 의원도 페이스북에서 “그(김건희)가 윤석열을 등에 업고 호가호위하며 온 나라를 헤집어놓은 것을 감안하면 터무니없는 판결”이라며 “대한민국 법 밖에 존재해 왔고 법 위에 서 있으려 했던 그를 일벌백계하여 다시는 제 2, 3의 김건희가 등장하지 않도록 해야 할 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kang Deuk-gu wrote on Facebook, "Only 1 year and 8 months for receiving money and valuables from the Unification Church, while stock price manipulation and violations of the Political Funds Act are found not guilty? This is a clear legal contradiction and a biased verdict that disregards public common sense," and added, "I share the public's anger." (강득구 민주당 의원은 페이스북에 “통일교 금품 수수에만 징역 1년8개월, 주가조작과 정치자금법은 무죄라니요? 이는 법리적으로 명백한 모순이자, 국민 상식을 무시한 편파 판결이다”라며 “국민과 함께 분노한다”고 적었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, the Seoul Central District Court's Criminal Agreement Division 27 (Presiding Judge Woo In-seong) found Kim not guilty of charges related to participating in the manipulation of Deutsche Motors' stock price, gaining unfair profits of 810 million won (violation of the Capital Markets Act), and receiving free public opinion polls for the presidential election worth 270 million won from Myeong Tae-gyun (violation of the Political Funds Act). However, the court found her guilty of receiving valuables such as a Chanel bag in return for receiving requests regarding pending issues from the Unification Church (mediation bribery under the Act on the Aggravated Punishment of Specific Crimes) and sentenced her to 1 year and 8 months in prison. (이날 서울중앙지법 형사합의27부(재판장 우인성)는 김 여사가 도이치모터스 주가 조작에 가담해 8억1천만원의 부당이득을 거둔 혐의(자본시장법 위반)와 명태균씨로부터 2억7천만원 상당의 대선 여론조사를 무상으로 제공받은 혐의(정치자금법 위반)에 대해 무죄를 선고했다. 다만 통일교로부터 현안 청탁을 받은 대가로 샤넬 가방 등 금품을 받은 혐의(특정범죄가중처벌법상 알선수재)는 유죄로 인정해 징역 1년8개월을 선고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Kyung-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242110.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/964/579/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503012.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:13:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Yong-beom: "U.S. dissatisfaction stems from legislative delay... MOU ratification unnecessary, no disagreement between South Korea and U.S." (김용범 “미국 불만은 입법 지연…MOU 비준 불필요, 한미 이견 없다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242133.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/906/599/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695886801326_20260128503327.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김용범 청와대 정책실장이 2026년 1월14일 오후 청와대에서 한겨레와 인터뷰를 하고 있다. 한겨레 류우종 선임기자 wjryu@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, Senior Presidential Secretary for Policy, stated regarding U.S. President Donald Trump's recent surprise announcement of planned tariff hikes that "U.S. dissatisfaction stems from delays in legislative action by the National Assembly." (김용범 청와대 정책실장이 최근 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 기습적인 관세 인상 예고와 관련해 “미국의 불만은 국회의 입법 지연에 따른 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a press briefing at the Chunchugwan press center of the Blue House that day, Secretary Kim said, "From the U.S. perspective, they understand that the legislative process related to the U.S. investment fund begins once South Korea submits a bill and it undergoes deliberation in the National Assembly. It seems they think the progress speed and overall procedure are slower than the U.S. expected," adding, "We understand the U.S. wants to quickly launch the U.S. investment project based on the Memorandum of Understanding (MOU)." (김 실장은 이날 청와대 춘추관에서 기자 브리핑을 열어 “미국 입장에선 한국이 법안을 제출해 국회에서 심의가 이뤄져야 대미투자펀드와 관련한 입법 절차가 시작되는 것으로 알고 있는데, 진척 속도와 전반적 절차가 미국 기대한 것보다 느리다고 생각하는 것 같다”며 “미국은 양해각서(MOU)에 근거한 대미투자 프로젝트를 빨리 가동하고 싶다는 것으로 이해한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim also clarified that the South Korea-U.S. tariff agreement is not a matter requiring parliamentary ratification. He said, "The MOU (Memorandum of Understanding) signed at the time of the tariff agreement has no legal binding force. Therefore, there was no disagreement between South Korea and the U.S. on the point that parliamentary ratification is unnecessary." He further reiterated, "No country anywhere in the world ratifies an MOU in its parliament. I do not believe the ratification issue is the cause of what happened between South Korea and the U.S." Secretary Kim said, "There has been communication (between South Korea and the U.S.) to the extent that once the law passes the National Assembly and the U.S. investment process proceeds, we could discuss such projects (as investment targets)," adding, "As a standing committee schedule is set for February in the National Assembly, we are expecting (the law's passage), and before the National Assembly's legislation is finalized, it is difficult to formally review or officially discuss the project." (김 실장은 한-미 관세합의는 국회의 비준동의 사안이 아니란 점도 분명히 했다. 그는 “관세합의 당시 체결한 엠오유(MOU·양해각서)는 법적 구속력이 없다. 따라서 국회의 비준 동의가 필요없다는 점에 대해선 한미 간에 아무런 이견이 없었다”고 했다. 그러면서 “세계 어디에도 엠오유를 의회에서 비준하는 나라는 없다. 비준 문제가 한-미 간에 일어난 일의 원인은 아니라고 생각한다”고 거듭 밝혔다. 김 실장은 “국회에서 법이 통과되고, 대미투자 절차가 진행되면 (투자 대상으로) 이런 사업을 논의해볼 수도 있다는 정도의 의사소통은 (한미 간에) 있었다”며 “오는 2월에 국회 상임위 일정이 잡혀 있어서 (법 통과를) 기대하고 있고, 국회 입법이 마무리되기 전에는 정식으로 프로젝트에 대해 심사거나 논의를 공식화하는 것은 쉽지 않다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'Special Act on Strategic Investment Management between South Korea and the U.S.' (U.S. Investment Special Act) primarily aims to establish the necessary legal and institutional framework for implementing investments in the U.S., including the creation of a South Korea-U.S. strategic investment fund and the establishment of a South Korea-U.S. strategic investment corporation. (‘한미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’(대미투자특별법)은 한미전략투자기금 조성과 한미전략투자 공사 설치 등 대미 투자를 이행하는 데 필요한 법·제도적 장치를 마련하는 내용을 골자로 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim said, "Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jung-gwan will meet with U.S. Under Secretary of Commerce for International Trade Howard Rothman in Washington, D.C., after completing his schedule in Toronto, Canada, and Trade Negotiations Head Yeo Han-koo also plans to move up his schedule to discuss with U.S. Trade Representative (USTR) James Greer," adding, "We will respond calmly and, as President Trump said, seek solutions together." (김 실장은 “김정관 산업통상부 장관이 캐나다 토론토 일정을 마치고, 미국 워싱턴에 가서 하워드 러트닉 상무장관과 면담할 것이고, 여한구 통상교섭본부장도 (일정을) 당겨서 제이미스 그리어 미국 무역대표부(USTR) 대표와 논의할 예정”이라며 “차분히 대응하며, 트럼프 대통령 말대로 함께 해결책을 모색해 나가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242133.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/906/599/imgdb/child/2026/0128/17695886801326_20260128503327.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:13:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon, Facing Imminent Expulsion, Says "Even If You Twist a Chicken's Neck"... Critics Slam: "How Dare You Compare Opinion Manipulation to YS's Resistance Against Dictatorship" (제명 코앞 한동훈 “닭 목 비틀어도”…“여론조작을 YS 독재저항에 갖다붙이냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242134.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695887348604_20260128503352.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 28일 오전 서울 영등포구 타임스퀘어 영화관에서 ‘잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁시대‘를 관람하기 위해 자리에 앉아 있다. 정용일 선임기자 yongil@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Like the words of former President Kim Young-sam, who said 'Even if you twist a chicken's neck, dawn will come' while facing unjust expulsion, I will trust the people with an unyielding heart and continue forward." (“부당한 제명을 당하면서 ‘닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다’고 했던 김영삼 대통령의 말씀처럼, 꺾이지 않는 마음으로 국민을 믿고 계속 가겠다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon watched the documentary film 'The Forgotten President: Kim Young-sam's Era of Reform' at a movie theater in Seoul's Yeongdeungpo District on the 28th. This was his first public appearance since receiving an 'expulsion' disciplinary measure from the party's Central Ethics Committee, attending a preview screening of a film depicting the life of former President Kim Young-sam. Pro-Han lawmakers such as Kim Hyung-dong, Park Jeong-hoon, Ahn Sang-hoon, Jeong Seong-guk, and Jin Jong-oh were also present. (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표는 28일 서울 영등포구의 한 영화관에서 다큐 영화 ‘잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁 시대’를 관람했다. 당 중앙윤리위원회로부터 ‘제명’ 처분을 받은 이후 첫 공개 행보로, 김영삼 전 대통령의 일대기를 그린 영화 시사회에 참석한 것이다. 이 자리에는 친한동훈계인 김형동·박정훈·안상훈·정성국·진종오 의원 등이 함께했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, there is an expectation that the disciplinary motion to expel former leader Han will be passed as soon as leader Jang Dong-hyuk returns to the Supreme Council. By reciting a 'famous quote' left by former President Kim, Han compared his current situation to that of former President Kim, who was expelled from his parliamentary seat while resisting Park Chung-hee's Yushin dictatorship. Within the party, reactions emerged stating, "It's absurd to compare an extremely personal opinion manipulation incident to the spirit of the times." (당 안에선 장동혁 대표가 최고위원회에 복귀하는대로 한 전 대표 제명 징계안이 의결될 것이란 전망이 나오고 있는 상황. 그는 김 전 대통령이 남긴 ‘명언’을 읊으며, 현재 자신이 처한 상황을 박정희 유신 독재에 맞서다 의원직에서 제명당한 김 전 대통령에 빗댄 것이다. 당 안에선 “지극히 개인적인 여론조작 사건을 시대정신에 비유하는 게 황당하다”는 반응이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han appeared at the theater in a black suit, maintaining a solemn atmosphere throughout. He signed autographs and greeted waiting supporters, but refrained from answering questions about the expulsion disciplinary measure. During the screening, when a scene depicting former President Yoon Suk-yeol's declaration of a state of emergency on December 3rd appeared, some of Han's supporters shouted profanities, causing a stir in the theater. Former leader Han watched the film without saying a word, and when it ended, he stood up and applauded along with the audience. (한 전 대표는 이날 검은색 정장 차림으로 극장에 등장해 시종일관 엄숙한 분위기를 연출했다. 기다리던 지지자들에게 사인을 해주거나 인사를 건넸지만, 제명 징계에 대한 생각을 묻는 질문에는 답변을 아꼈다. 이날 극장에선 윤석열 전 대통령의 12·3 비상계엄 선포 장면이 나올 때 한 전 대표 지지자 일부가 욕설을 내뱉으며 상영관이 술렁이기도 했다. 한 전 대표는 아무 말 없이 영화를 관람했고, 영화가 끝나자 관객들과 함께 일어나 박수를 치기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The news focus seems to be entirely on former leader Han," said Kim Hyun-chul, the second son of former President Kim and chairman of the Kim Young-sam Presidential Foundation, introducing Han after the film. Chairman Kim said, "(Former leader Han) stated he would seek the spirit of conservatism in the 'Kim Young-sam (YS) spirit,' and I hope he continues to uphold that well." He added, "Former President Kim's political philosophy is 'Dae-domu-mun (politics where if you follow the right path, there is nothing to fear) politics.' That political philosophy includes courage and determination, dialogue and compromise, as well as integration and harmony." He emphasized, "Politics in this country is so chaotic and messy, precisely at times like this, the Kim Young-sam spirit should be summoned once again." (“뉴스 초점이 한 전 대표에게 쏠려있네요.” 김 전 대통령의 차남인 김현철 김영삼대통령기념재단 이사장은 영화가 끝난 뒤 이렇게 말하며 한 전 대표를 소개했다. 김 이사장은 “(한 전 대표가) 보수의 정신을 ‘김영삼(YS) 정신’에서 찾겠다고 했는데, 이를 지속적으로 잘 이어나갔으면 좋겠다”고 했다. 그러면서 “김 전 대통령의 정치 철학은 ‘대도무문(바른 길을 가면 거칠 것이 없다는 뜻) 정치’다. 그 정치 철학에는 용기와 결단도, 대화와 타협도, 통합과 화합도 있다”고 말했다. 그는 “이 나라의 정치가 너무나도 혼란스럽고 어지럽기 때문에, 이럴 때일수록 김영삼 정신이 다시 한번 소환돼야 하는 것 아니겠냐”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han only expressed his stance on the expulsion speculation after the film ended. He said, "I have a sense of mission that I must certainly achieve good politics for the people," adding, "Like the words of former President Kim Young-sam, who said 'Even if you twist a chicken's neck, dawn will come' while facing unjust expulsion, I will trust the people with an unyielding heart and continue forward." (한 전 대표는 영화가 끝난 뒤에야 제명 관측에 대한 입장을 내놨다. 그는 “저는 국민을 위한 좋은 정치를 꼭 해내야겠다는 사명감을 가지고 있다”며 “부당한 제명을 당하면서 ‘닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다’고 했던 김영삼 대통령의 말씀처럼, 꺾이지 않는 마음으로 국민을 믿고 계속 가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former President Kim quote he referenced was spoken in 1979, during the late Yushin period, when former President Kim, then the leader of the New Democratic Party, was expelled from his parliamentary seat. At the time, former President Kim clashed with the government by protecting YH Trade workers who had flocked to the New Democratic Party headquarters, complaining they were at risk of being illegally forced out of their company through factory relocation and disguised shutdowns. In a foreign media interview, he even demanded the US "cut off support for President Park Chung-hee." The Park Chung-hee regime, angered by this, sought to expel former President Kim from his parliamentary seat. The disciplinary reason was 'spreading false facts and engaging in anti-state speech, thereby insulting sovereignty, impairing the dignity of the National Assembly, and damaging the dignity of a National Assembly member.' On October 4th of that year, the Democratic Republican Party and the Yushin Jeongwoohoe unilaterally passed a motion in the National Assembly to strip former President Kim of his parliamentary seat. (그가 인용한 김 전 대통령 발언은 유신 말기인 1979년 신민당 총재이던 김 전 대통령이 의원직에서 제명당하면서 한 말이다. 김 전 대통령은 당시 신민당사로 몰려와 공장이전·위장휴업 등 불법적인 방식으로 회사에서 쫓겨날 위기에 놓였다고 호소하는 와이에이치(YH)무역 노동자들을 보호하며 정부와 각을 세웠다. 외신 인터뷰에선 미국에 “박정희 대통령에 대한 지지를 끊으라”고 요구까지 했다. 박정희 정권은 이에 분노해 김 전 대통령을 의원직에서 제명하려고 했다. 징계 사유는 ‘허위사실을 유포하는 등 반국가적 언동을 함으로써 주권을 모독해 국회 위신을 실추시키고 국회의원으로서의 품위를 손상시켰다’는 것이었다. 그리고 그해 10월4일, 민주공화당·유신정우회는 국회에서 김 전 대통령의 의원직 박탈을 단독 의결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phrase "Even if you twist a chicken's neck, dawn will come," which emerged during this process, symbolizes resistance, refusing to yield to the Yushin dictatorship. With the party's expulsion decision looming, former leader Han quoted this statement by former President Kim, equating himself with former President Kim, who did not yield to the expulsion and oppression by the Park Chung-hee regime. Previously, regarding the disciplinary measure of 'urging to leave the party' against pro-Han Gyeonggi Goyang-gap party chapter chairman Kim Jong-hyuk, former leader Han had stated, "It's like the North Korean leader theory, totalitarianism such as Nazism, and pseudo-democracy," adding, "Our People Power Party should be a liberal democratic party, but it is not normal." (이 과정에서 나온 ‘닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다’는 말은 유신독재에 굴하지 않겠다는 저항을 상징한다. 당의 제명 결정을 앞두고 있는 한 전 대표는 김 전 대통령의 이 발언을 인용하며, 박정희 정권의 의원직 제명 탄압에도 굴하지 않았던 김 전 대통령과 자신을 등치한 것이다. 앞서 한 전 대표는 친한계 김종혁 경기 고양병 당협위원장에 대한 ‘탈당 권유’ 징계에 “북한 수령론, 나치즘 같은 전체주의, 사이비 민주주의”라며 “우리 국민의힘은 자유민주주의 정당이어야 하는데 정상이 아니다”라고 언급한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inside and outside the party, criticism arose that it was inappropriate for former leader Han, who is embroiled in controversy over allegations that he or his family posted numerous articles slandering former President Yoon Suk-yeol and his wife on the party member bulletin board to manipulate intra-party opinion, to compare his situation to that of former President Kim, who resisted the Yushin dictatorship. (당 안팎에선 한 전 대표 본인 또는 가족들이 윤석열 전 대통령 부부를 비방하는 다수의 글을 당원게시판에 올려 당내 여론을 조작하려고 한 의혹으로 논란을 빚고 있는 한 전 대표가 자신의 처지를 유신독재에 저항했던 김 전 대통령에 빗댄 것은 부적절하다는 비판이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lawmaker with a district in the Yeongnam region said, "Does it befit to compare a personal matter where family members intervened to manipulate public opinion to a phrase symbolizing the spirit of the times?" adding, "Not all expulsions are the same; why attach dirty opinion manipulation to former President Kim, who resisted the Yushin dictatorship?" (영남에 지역구를 둔 한 의원은 “가족들이 개입해 여론을 조작한 개인적 사안을 시대정신을 상징하는 문장에 빗대는 게 어울리냐”며 “제명이라고 해서 다 같은 제명이 아닌데, 추잡한 여론조작을 왜 유신독재에 저항한 김 전 대통령한테 갖다붙이냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok also criticized, "One must be as humble as possible before history," stating, "Watching a biographical film about President Kim Young-sam and then trying to equate it with oneself is not political courtesy." Leader Lee said, "Until dawn came, there were efforts by many people, including former President Kim Young-sam, and there was truly a lot of pain within that. (Former leader Han) spoke too lightly about it," adding, "It's not like confronting a huge barrier like former President Park Chung-hee or Chun Doo-hwan; aren't you just fighting with leader Jang Dong-hyuk, whom you yourself called a staff member?" (이준석 개혁신당 대표도 “역사 앞에서는 최대한 겸손해져야 한다”며 “김영삼 대통령의 이런 일대기 영화를 보고 나서 그걸 본인과 일치시키려고 하는 것은 정치권의 예의가 아니다”라고 비판했다. 이 대표는 “새벽이 오기까지 김영삼 (전) 대통령을 포함해서 많은 분들의 노력이 있었고, 그 안에서 정말 많은 아픔이 있었는데 (한 전 대표가) 너무 가볍게 얘기하지 않았냐”며 “박정희 (전) 대통령이나 전두환 같은 거대한 장벽과 맞서는 것도 아니고 본인이 스태프라고 했던 장동혁 대표와 싸우고 있는 것 아니냐”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee visited the film screening venue for the next showing time after former leader Han left the theater. Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram, former Minister of Employment and Labor Kim Moon-soo, and former UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon were also present. (이 대표는 이날 한 전 대표가 극장을 떠난 뒤 다음 상영 시간대에 맞춰 영화 시사회장을 찾았다. 이 자리에는 천하람 개혁신당 원내대표, 김문수 전 고용노동부 장관, 반기문 전 유엔 사무총장 등도 함께 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, as news emerged that both former leader Han and leader Lee would attend the film screening that day, a potential meeting between the two drew attention. However, leader Lee flatly stated, "I have no plans to meet former leader Han" (in a TV Chosun YouTube interview). He added, "If former leader Han does not change his way of doing politics, it will be difficult to win back the hearts of internal members." (앞서 한 전 대표와 이 대표가 이날 영화 시사회에 참석한다는 얘기가 나오면서 두 사람의 만남도 주목을 받았다. 하지만 이 대표는 “한 전 대표와 만날 계획이 없다”(티브이 조선 유튜브 인터뷰)고 잘라 말했다. 그러면서 “한 전 대표가 정치하는 방식을 바꾸지 않으면 내부 구성원들의 마음을 돌리기 어려울 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242134.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695887348604_20260128503352.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:12:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Command Says DMZ Bill "Violates Armistice Agreement"... Jeong Dong-young: "Access is Territorial Sovereignty" (DMZ법에 유엔사 “정전협정 침해”…정동영 “출입은 영토주권”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242136.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/730/466/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503391.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 2016년 6월 최전방 비무장지대(DMZ) 감시초소(GP)에 푸른색의 유엔기와 태극기가 걸려 있다. 유엔기는 지피가 유엔사의 시설이고 관할구역임을 뜻한다. 비무장지대의 물리적 현장 관리는 국군이 하지만 출입하는 모든 인원과 병력 통제권은 유엔사가 행사하고 있다. 육군본부 누리집&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Command (UNC) has expressed opposition to the Demilitarized Zone (DMZ) Act being promoted by the Democratic Party of Korea. (유엔군사령부(유엔사)가 더불어민주당이 추진하는 디엠제트(DMZ)법 제정에 반대한다는 입장을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A UNC official, meeting with reporters at the Dragon Hill Lodge on the U.S. military base in Yongsan, Seoul, this afternoon, stated, "(The DMZ Act) completely negates the UN Commander's authority to decide who can enter the Demilitarized Zone for what purpose, especially regarding civilian access," adding, "If this law passes, it would be tantamount to the South Korean government declaring it is not subject to the Armistice Agreement, infringing upon the authority of the UN Commander who manages and supervises the Armistiate Agreement." (유엔사 관계자는 이날 오후 서울 용산구 주한미군 기지에 있는 드래곤힐 로지에서 기자들과 만나 “(디엠제트법은) 비무장지대에 누가 어떤 목적으로 출입할 수 있는지, 특히 민간인이 출입할 수 있는지에 대한 유엔군 사령관의 결정권한을 모두 부정하고 있다”며 “이 법이 통과된다면 한국 정부가 정전협정의 (적용) 대상이 되지 않겠다고 선언하는 것이나 마찬가지로, 정전협정을 관리·감독하는 유엔군사령관의 권한을 침해하게 될 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UNC's remarks target the 'Act on the Peaceful Use of the Demilitarized Zone' recently proposed by Democratic Party lawmakers Lee Jae-myung and Han Jeong-ae. This bill stipulates that the South Korean government, not the UNC which manages the Armistice Agreement, should exercise the authority to permit access to and use of the DMZ, limited to non-military and peaceful purposes. The UNC views this bill as directly conflicting with the authority of the UN Commander specified in the Armistice Agreement. (유엔사 쪽의 이런 발언은 최근 민주당의 이재강·한정애 의원이 발의한 ‘비무장지대의 평화적 이용에 관한 법률&amp;#x27;을 겨냥한 것이다. 이 법안은 비군사적·평화적 목적에 한해 비무장지대(DMZ) 출입·이용에 대한 허가 권한을 정전협정 관리 주체인 유엔사가 아니라 한국 정부가 행사하도록 하는 내용을 담고 있다. 유엔사는 이 법안이 정전협정이 명시한 유엔군사령관의 권한과 정면으로 충돌한다고 본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another UNC official also emphasized, "Under the Armistice Agreement, jurisdiction over the Demilitarized Zone south of the Military Demarcation Line lies with the UN Commander, and (this authority) has not changed for over 70 years." The official added, "If an unfortunate incident occurs within the DMZ leading to the resumption of war, the responsibility would fall on the UN Commander, not the current President of the Republic of Korea," and urged, "I hope everyone remembers that the Armistice Agreement must be observed as long as a (permanent) peace agreement is not concluded." (또 다른 유엔사 관계자도 “정전협정상 군사분계선 이남의 비무장지대 관할권은 유엔군사령관에게 있으며, (이 권한에는) 지난 70여년간 어떤 변화도 없었다”고 강조했다. 이 관계자는 “만약 비무장지대 안에서 불미스러운 사건이 발생해 다시 전쟁이 발발하면, 그에 대한 책임은 현재 대한민국 대통령에 대해 있는 게 아니라 유엔군사령관에게 지워진다”며 “(항구적) 평화 협정이 체결되지 않은 상황에서는 정전협정을 준수해야 한다는 점을 꼭 기억하길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young, attending a current affairs question session at the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee, commented on the UNC's stated position, saying, "(The DMZ Act) seems intended for us to exercise our territorial sovereignty regarding access to the Demilitarized Zone," and added, "What the UNC said is the UNC's position, and the National Assembly's legislation is the authority of the legislative branch." (이날 국회 외교통일위원회 현안질의에 참석한 정동영 통일부 장관은 이날 유엔사가 밝힌 입장에 대해 “(디엠제트법은) 비무장지대 출입과 관련해 우리의 영토주권을 행사해야 한다는 취지로 보인다”며 “유엔사가 이야기한 건 유엔사의 입장이고, 국회의 법 제정은 입법부의 권한”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242136.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/730/466/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503391.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:12:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Meets with Special Envoy of Qatar's King…"Strengthen Mutually Beneficial Cooperation in Defense Industry, etc." (이 대통령, 카타르 국왕 특사 접견…“방산 등 호혜적 협력 강화”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242141.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503430.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 28일 청와대에서 모하메드 빈 압둘아지즈 알-쿨라이피 카타르 국왕 특사와 접견 전 기념촬영을 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, President Lee Jae-myung met with Qatar's Minister of State, Mohammed bin Abdulaziz Al-Khulaifi, the special envoy of Qatar's King, at the Presidential Office and agreed to further strengthen mutually beneficial cooperation in strategic areas such as defense, the defense industry, investment, and energy. (이재명 대통령은 28일 청와대에서 카타르 국왕 특사인 모하메드 빈 압둘아지즈 알-쿨라이피 카타르 국무장관을 접견하고, 국방·방산과 투자, 에너지 등 전략 분야에서의 호혜적 협력을 한층 강화해 나가기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, President Lee assessed that "the special envoy's prompt visit to Korea following the phone call with His Highness the Amir Tamim bin Hamad Al Thani on the 20th demonstrates the firm will for cooperation between our two countries." (이 대통령은 이날 “지난 20일 타밈 국왕과의 통화 이후 특사의 방한이 신속히 이뤄진 것은 양국의 굳건한 협력 의지를 보여주는 것”이라고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during the phone call with His Highness the Amir, President Lee had said, "I expect Korea and Qatar to continue expanding the horizons of cooperation in various fields such as defense, the defense industry, energy, and infrastructure." His Highness the Amir also responded, stating, "Based on trust and expectations for Korea, Qatar's 'Comprehensive Strategic Partner,' Korea is making significant contributions to Qatar's national development." (앞서 이 대통령은 타밈 국왕과의 통화에서 “한국과 카타르가 국방·방산, 에너지, 인프라 등 다양한 분야에서 협력의 지평을 지속적으로 확대해 나가길 기대한다”고 말한 바 있다. 타밈 국왕도 “카타르의 ‘포괄적 전략 동반자’인 한국에 대한 신뢰와 기대를 바탕으로, 한국이 카타르의 국가 발전에 크게 기여하고 있다”고 화답한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Special Envoy Al-Khulaifi explained during the meeting that he visited Korea to personally convey His Highness the Amir's special trust in Korea and his will to strengthen bilateral cooperation. He added that he would actively strive to realize the two leaders' shared will for the development of Korea-Qatar relations. (알-쿨라이피 특사는 이날 접견에서 한국에 대한 타밈 국왕의 각별한 신뢰와 양국 협력 강화를 향한 의지를 직접 전달하기 위해 방한했다고 설명했다. 그러면서 한-카타르 관계 발전에 대한 양 정상의 공동 의지를 실현하기 위해 적극 노력하겠다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also stated, "Our two countries have elevated our relations to a 'Comprehensive Strategic Partnership,' going beyond over 50 years of diplomatic ties," and expressed his hope that "even amidst the complex international situation, we will contribute together to regional and international peace as true friends who help each other in times of difficulty." (이 대통령은 또 “양국은 수교 50여년을 넘어 관계를 ‘포괄적 전략 동반자 관계’로 격상시켰다”며 “복잡한 국제정세 속에서도 어려울 때 서로 돕는 진정한 친구로서 지역과 국제 평화에 함께 기여해 나가길 바란다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then asked the special envoy to convey his wish to "frankly discuss ways to develop bilateral relations with His Highness the Amir in Seoul," proposing a summit meeting in Korea. (그러면서 “타밈 국왕과 서울에서 양국 관계 발전 방안에 대해 허심탄회하게 논의하고 싶다”는 뜻을 전해 달라며, 한국에서의 정상회담 개최를 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242141.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503430.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:11:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Yong-beom: "Multiple-Homeowners' Heavier Capital Gains Tax Grace Period Ends May 9th... Considering a One or Two Month Extension" (김용범 “다주택 중과 유예, 5월9일 종료…한두 달 연기 검토”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242150.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/715/467/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503499.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김용범 청와대 정책실장이 지난 14일 오후 청와대에서 한겨레와 인터뷰를 하고 있다. 류우종 선임기자 wjryu@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Policy, stated regarding the 'grace period for heavier capital gains tax on multiple-homeowners' which is set to expire on May 9th, "We are internally reviewing ending it not on May 9th, but one or two months later." He also hinted at additional tax system reforms, saying that for stabilizing the real estate market, "the tax system is also an important part." (김용범 청와대 정책실장이 오는 5월9일 일몰되는 ‘다주택자 양도세 중과 유예’와 관련해 “5월9일이 아닌 한 두 달 뒤에 종료하는 것을 내부적으로 검토중”이라고 밝혔다. 그러면서 부동산 시장 안정화를 위해 “세제도 중요한 파트”라며 추가 세제 개편을 시사했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a briefing held at the Chunchugwan press center in the presidential office on the 28th, Secretary Kim said, "To sell a house in advance, since there may be tenants and such, a considerable period might be needed. We also reflect that we should have made the decision a bit earlier," adding, "Even if we end (the heavier tax grace period measure) one or two months later, it does not undermine the principle." He continued, "To apply (the heavier capital gains tax grace period) to cases where a contract is signed by May 9th and the final sale is completed afterwards, we need to amend the enforcement decree. We are reviewing how long after the contract is signed to recognize the completion (of the sale)." This means that for cases where a sales contract is made on May 9th, the heavier capital gains tax can be deferred until a certain point when the remaining payment is made and the contract is finalized. (김 실장은 28일 청와대 춘추관에서 열린 브리핑에서 “미리 집을 팔려면, 세입자도 있고 하니, 상당 기간 필요할 수 있는데 결정을 좀 더 일찍 했으면 하는 반성도 한다”며 “(중과 유예 조치를) 한 두 달 뒤 종료하더라도 원칙을 훼손하는 건 아니다”라고 말했다. 이어 김 실장은 “5월9일까지 계약이 맺어지고, 그 뒤 최종적으로 매각이 이뤄진 것을 (양도세 중과 유예)하려면 시행령을 고쳐야 한다. 계약 체결된 이후에 어느 정도 뒤까지 (매매) 완료되는 것을 인정할지 검토중”이라고 덧붙였다. 5월9일 매매 계약을 한 경우 실제 잔금을 치르고 계약을 완료하는 일정 시점까지 양도세 중과를 유예할 수 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim also stated that, as the October 15th measures last year designated the entire Seoul area and 12 regions in Gyeonggi Province as land transaction permit zones, they are considering a plan to grant a longer grace period for the heavier capital gains tax in areas other than the three Gangnam districts (Gangnam, Seocho, Songpa). He said, "The heavier tax on multiple-homeowners in regulated zones was expanded quite widely due to the October 15th measures. For areas like the three Gangnam districts, which have long remained (as regulated zones), people knew the heavier tax system applied. However, it is highly likely that people in areas newly expanded due to the October 15th measures did not clearly recognize they became eligible for the heavier tax grace period," adding, "We are reviewing including giving these people a bit more of a grace period." (김 실장은 또 지난해 10·15 대책을 통해 서울 전역과 경기도 12개 지역이 토지거래 허가구역으로 묶인 만큼 강남 3구를 제외한 지역의 경우 양도세 중과 유예 기간을 더 주는 방안을 검토하고 있다고 밝혔다. 그는 “조정지역의 다주택자 중과는 10·15 대책으로 상당히 넓게 확대됐다. 강남 3구 등은 오랜 상태 (조정지역으로) 머물러서 중과 제도가 적용된다는 것을 알았는데, 10·15 대책 때문에 넓어진 지역의 분들은 중과 유예 대상이 된다는 것을 명확하게 인식 못 했을 가능성이 높다”며 “이분들은 조금 더 일정 기간 더 주는 내용을 포함해서 검토하고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also foreshadowed additional tax system reforms. Secretary Kim said, "At the time of the October 15th measures, we mentioned we would commission a research study (regarding tax system reform). The tax system is something that must be handled very cautiously, and it also has an impact on the real estate market. It is not something to be announced in one or two months; it is a topic that requires in-depth discussion by multiple agencies and ministries." He added, "President Lee also used the expression 'real estate ruining the country.' He is looking at the tax system seriously. It doesn't mean it's the top priority, but I hope you understand it as an intention to prepare." President Lee had previously stated on the 23rd that the reduction of the long-term holding special deduction for capital gains tax, which reduces tax based on holding period for non-resident single homeowners, should also be reviewed. (추가적인 세제 개편도 예고했다. 김 실장은 “10·15 대책 당시 (세제 개편과 관련해) 연구 용역을 한다고 말한 바 있다”며 “세제라는 게 정말 조심스럽게 다뤄야 하고, 부동산 시장에 미치는 영향도 있다. 한두 달 만에 발표할 내용은 아니고, 여러 기관 심층적으로 여러 부처가 논의해야 할 주제”라고 말했다. 이어 김 실장은 “이 대통령이 ‘부동산 망국론’이라는 표현도 했다. 세제를 진지하게 보는데, 우선으로 하겠다는 이야기는 아니고, 준비는 하겠다는 취지라고 이해해주면 좋겠다”고 덧붙였다. 이 대통령은 지난 23일 비거주 1주택에 대해서도 보유 기간에 따라 양도소득세를 깎아주는 장기보유특별공제(장특공제) 축소를 검토해야 한다고 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242150.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/715/467/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503499.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:11:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Returned Jang Dong-hyeok says "Will follow procedures for Han Dong-hoon's expulsion"... Vote expected on the 29th (돌아온 장동혁 “한동훈 제명 절차따라”…29일 의결 전망)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242153.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695910864017_20260128503519.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;장동혁 대표와 송언석 원내대표 등 국민의힘 의원들이 28일 서울 서초구 하나로마트 양재점을 방문해 박혜성 지사장의 설명을 들으며 물가 점검 현장 방문을 하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, stated on the 28th regarding the vote on the expulsion motion for former leader Han Dong-hoon, "Sufficient time has been given," and "We will proceed according to procedures." Leader Jang returned to party duties today, six days after ending an eight-day hunger strike. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 28일 한동훈 전 대표의 제명안 의결 여부에 대해 “충분한 시간이 주어졌다”며 “절차에 따라서 진행하겠다”고 밝혔다. 장 대표는 이날 8일 간의 단식 농성 종료 이후 엿새 만에 당무에 복귀했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a 'field briefing on price inspections' held at the Korea Agro-Fisheries &amp; Food Trade Corporation in Seocho-gu, Seoul today, Leader Jang responded to reporters' questions about the vote on the expulsion motion for former leader Han, saying, "Tariff negotiations are at risk of returning to square one, and people's livelihoods are burning up. The special investigation demanded (by the People Power Party) is also not being properly carried through. What's important now is the lives of the people, the economy, and people's livelihoods," and added, "Internal party matters will proceed according to procedures." (장 대표는 이날 서울 서초구 한국농수산식품유통공사에서 열린 ‘물가 점검 현장 간담회’ 이후 한 전 대표 제명안 의결 여부를 묻는 기자들의 질문에 “관세 협상이 원점으로 돌아갈 위기에 있고 민생이 타들어 가고 있다. (국민의힘이) 요구한 특검도 제대로 관철되지 않고 있다. 지금 중요한 건 국민 삶이고, 경제이고, 민생”이라며 “당내 문제는 절차에 따라서 진행될 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the party's ethics committee imposed an 'expulsion' penalty on former leader Han on the 13th, and only the Supreme Council's vote remains. Leader Jang granted a reconsideration period (10 days) after the ethics committee's decision, and the Supreme Council vote had been delayed due to overlapping with Leader Jang's recovery period following his hunger strike. With Leader Jang returning to party duties today, it is anticipated that the expulsion motion for former leader Han will be voted on at the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th. (앞서 당 윤리위원회는 지난 13일 한 전 대표에게 ‘제명’ 처분을 했고, 최고위원회 의결만 남아있는 상태다. 장 대표는 윤리위 결정 이후 재심 기간(10일)을 부여했고, 장 대표의 단식 농성에 따른 회복 기간까지 겹치면서 최고위 의결이 미뤄져왔다. 장 대표가 이날 당무에 복귀함에 따라, 오는 29일 최고위원회에서 한 전 대표의 제명안이 의결될 것이라는 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At today's briefing, Leader Jang held the government and ruling party responsible for the recent high inflation situation. Leader Jang said, "The excessive release of cash and coupons into the market is a major cause of high inflation," and "Continuing to distribute cash while inflation threatens the lives of our ordinary citizens is like feeding sugar water only to a diabetes patient." He further criticized, "High inflation is a destroyer that shatters ordinary meals and daily happiness," and "For the economic organism, high inflation is the root of all evils." (장 대표는 이날 간담회에서 최근 고물가 상황에 대해 정부·여당에 책임을 물었다. 장 대표는 “현금, 쿠폰 이런 것들이 시장에 너무 많이 풀리는 것이 고물가의 큰 원인”이라며 “물가가 우리 서민의 삶을 위협하는데도 계속해서 현금을 살포하는 것은 당뇨 환자에게 설탕물만 먹이는 것과 같다”고 했다. 그러면서 “고물가는 평범한 밥상, 일상의 행복을 깨는 파괴자”라고 했고 “경제유기체에 있어 고물가는 만병의 근원”이라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He stated, "The most important thing for stabilizing agricultural and fisheries product prices is supply-demand stability," and "We must adjust supply so that producers who work hard and sweat can receive fair prices, and ensure our ordinary citizens do not feel the burden of grocery prices." He also added, "What's important for price stability is reforming the distribution structure." (그는 “농수산물 가격 안정에 있어서 가장 중요한 것은 수급 안정”이라며 “땀 흘려 노력한 생산자들은 제값을 받을 수 있도록 수급을 조정하고 우리 서민들은 장바구니 물가가 무겁지 않도록 해야 한다”고 했다. 이어 “물가 안정에 있어서 중요한 것은 유통 구조를 개혁하는 것”이라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before the briefing, Leader Jang toured the livestock, vegetable, rice, and fruit sales sections of a Hanaro Mart in Seocho-gu, Seoul, checking prices one by one. He also greeted citizens who cheered him on with words like "Hang in there" and "Stay healthy." (간담회에 앞서 장 대표는 서울 서초구 하나로마트의 축산, 야채, 쌀, 과일 판매 코너를 돌아보며 물가를 일일이 확인했다. 그는 “힘내세요”, “건강하세요”라고 응원하는 시민들에게 인사하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1242153.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0128/53_17695910864017_20260128503519.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:10:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Yong-beom says, "KOSDAQ is disappointing compared to KOSPI... Will seek upgrade plans including for Korea Exchange" (김용범 “코스닥, 코스피에 견주면 아쉬워…한국거래소 등 업그레이드 방안 찾을 것”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242156.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/708/482/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503538.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김용범 청와대 정책실장이 지난 14일 오후 청와대에서 한겨레와 인터뷰를 하고 있다. 류우종 선임기자 wjryu@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Policy, revealed on the 28th that President Lee Jae-myung recently instructed on plans for capital market system reform, stating, "Although KOSDAQ has recently improved, even briefly reaching '1000-sdaq', it is quite disappointing compared to KOSPI." (김용범 청와대 정책실장이 28일 “코스닥이 이번에 잠깐 ‘1000스닥’도 되고 나아졌지만, 코스피에 비하면 상당히 아쉽다”며 최근 이재명 대통령이 자본시장 제도개혁 방안을 지시한 사실을 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press briefing held at the Chunchugwan that day, Secretary Kim said, "The President instructed, with the vision of creating a world-class capital market system, that there is a need to examine the entire system," and added, "Including the Financial Services Commission and the Korea Exchange, we are reviewing plans to fundamentally upgrade such a system." (  김 실장은 이날 춘추관에서 열린 기자간담회에서 이 대통령이 “세계 최고 자본시장 제도로 만드는 비전을 갖고 제도 전반을 들여다볼 필요가 있겠다는 취지의 지시를 했다”며 “금융위원회, 한국거래소를 포함해 그런 제도를 근본적으로 업그레이드할 수 있는 방안에 대해 검토하고 있다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim mentioned that the KOSPI rose even after President Donald Trump announced the re-raising of mutual tariffs on Korea, stating, "I think the reaction of the Korean capital market to such major news has changed significantly. I thought that if we do structural reform well, we could really try something in productive finance." (  김 실장은 도널드 트럼프 대통령이 한국에 대한 상호관세를 재인상한다고 밝힌 뒤에도 코스피가 상승한 점을 거론하며 “이런 큰 뉴스에 대한민국 자본시장이 반응하는 게 많이 달라졌다고 생각한다. 구조개혁을 잘하면 정말 생산적 금융 쪽도 한 번 해볼 수 있겠다는 생각이 들었다”고 했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim said, "Companies that fail to meet maintenance requirements or are difficult to call listed companies should be sorted out promptly so that new companies can enter," and added, "We will quickly create plans to restore KOSDAQ to its most quintessential era and transform it into a market that accommodates startups (companies) the government focuses on in various aspects such as AI or energy, to continue the momentum of 'breaking through KOSPI 5000'." (  김 실장은 “유지 요건이나 이런 걸 채우지 못한 기업들, 상장회사라고 말하기 좀 어려운 기업들은 그때그때 정리가 돼야 새로운 기업들이 들어올 것”이라며 “코스닥을 당초 가장 코스닥다웠던 시절로 되돌릴 수 있는 방안, 인공지능(AI)이나 에너지 등 여러 측면에서 정부가 주안점을 둔 창업(기업)을 담아낼 시장으로 코스닥을 탈바꿈시킬 방안을 빠른 속도로 만들어서 ‘코스피 5000 돌파’의 모멘텀을 이어가겠다”고 말했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1242156.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/708/482/imgdb/original/2026/0128/20260128503538.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:10:35 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>