<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:43:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Metropolitan Area Council for University Innovation Support Project Successfully Concludes '2025 Metropolitan Area Innovation Networking &amp; Performance Diffusion Forum' (대학혁신지원사업 수도권역협의회, ‘2025 대학혁신지원사업 수도권역 혁신 네트워킹·성과확산 포럼’ 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240719.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Metropolitan Area Council for University Innovation Support Project Successfully Concludes '2025 Metropolitan Area Innovation Networking &amp; Performance Diffusion Forum' (대학혁신지원사업 수도권역협의회, ‘2025 대학혁신지원사업 수도권역 혁신 네트워킹·성과확산 포럼’ 성료)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/449/imgdb/original/2026/0120/5417688936384917.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;▲지난 1월 14일부터 16일까지 메종글래드 제주에서 열린 ‘2025 대학혁신지원사업 수도권역 혁신 네트워킹·성과확산 포럼’ 참석자들이 기념촬영을 하고 있다.세종대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Area Council for the University Innovation Support Project held the '2025 Metropolitan Area Innovation Networking &amp; Performance Diffusion Forum' at Maison Glad Jeju over three days from January 14th to 16th. &lt;br/&gt;Hosted by the Metropolitan Area Council and sponsored by the Ministry of Education and the National Research Foundation of Korea, this forum was a large-scale exchange event bringing together 58 member universities of the Council. &lt;br/&gt;The event aimed to share each university's innovation achievements while enhancing networking and expanding inter-university exchanges to improve the outcomes of the University Innovation Support Project in the metropolitan area. &lt;br/&gt;The event began with opening remarks by Kim Hee-yeon, Chairperson of the Metropolitan Area Council (Dean of the Educational Innovation Center at Sejong University). This was followed by a keynote lecture of approximately 60 minutes by Professor Lee Min-seok of Kookmin University (Member of the Science &amp; Talent Subcommittee, National AI Strategy Committee) on the theme of 'University Education in the Age of AI Transformation'. &lt;br/&gt;Following the keynote lecture, Ahn Sang-hoon, Section Chief of the Private University Support Division at the Ministry of Education, explained the 3rd Cycle University Innovation Support Project and held a Q&amp;A session with metropolitan area universities. This created a communication channel to share policy directions between the Ministry and member universities and exchange opinions from the field.&lt;br/&gt;During the forum period, innovation case presentations involving all 58 universities continued alongside networking programs by innovation field. Each university shared the outcomes of their specialized innovation projects, reaffirming their commitment to driving university innovation. &lt;br/&gt;Particularly notable was the information sharing and exchange between newly participating universities in the 3rd Cycle and existing participating universities, which took place in a free and open atmosphere. Participants confirmed the potential for solidarity and cooperation as an 'educational innovation community' through active networking. &lt;br/&gt;A university official who attended the event said, "It was a meaningful time where we could share each other's achievements and concerns through networking with other universities and explore possibilities for cooperation," adding, "It served as an opportunity to deeply contemplate the direction universities should take." (대학혁신지원사업 수도권역협의회는 지난 1월 14일부터 16일까지 3일간, 메종글래드 제주에서 ‘2025 대학혁신지원사업 수도권역 혁신 네트워킹·성과확산 포럼’을 개최했다. &lt;br/&gt;수도권역협의회가 주최하고 교육부와 한국연구재단이 후원한 이번 포럼은 수도권역협의회 소속 58개 대학이 한자리에 모인 대규모 교류 행사로 마련됐다. &lt;br/&gt;이번 행사는 대학별 혁신 성과를 공유하는 한편, 네트워킹 강화와 대학 간 교류 확대를 통해 수도권역 대학혁신지원사업의 성과를 높이는 데 목적을 뒀다. &lt;br/&gt;행사는 김희연 수도권역협의회장(세종대학교 교육혁신처장)의 개회사로 시작됐다. 이어 이민석 국민대학교 교수(국가AI전략위원회 과학·인재분과 위원)가 ‘AI 전환 시대의 대학교육’을 주제로 약 60분간 기조강연을 진행했다. &lt;br/&gt;기조강연에 이어 교육부 사립대학지원과 안상훈 과장이 3주기 대학혁신지원사업에 대해 설명하고 수도권대학들과 질의응답을 하는 시간이 마련됐다. 이를 통해 교육부와 수도권역 회원교 간 정책 방향을 공유하고 현장의 의견을 나누는 소통의 장이 형성됐다.&lt;br/&gt;포럼 기간 동안에는 58개 대학이 참여한 혁신 사례 발표와 함께 혁신 분야별 네트워킹 프로그램이 이어졌다. 각 대학은 특화된 혁신사업의 성과를 공유하며 대학 혁신 추진 의지를 재확인했다. &lt;br/&gt;특히 자유로운 분위기 속에서 진행된 3주기 신규 진입 대학과 기존 참여 대학 간의 정보 공유 및 교류가 눈길을 끌었다. 참석자들은 활발한 네트워킹을 통해 ‘교육혁신 공동체’로서의 연대와 협력 가능성을 확인했다. &lt;br/&gt;행사에 참석한 한 대학 관계자는 “타 대학과의 네트워킹을 통해 서로의 성과와 고민을 공유하고 협력 가능성을 모색할 수 있었던 의미 있는 시간이었다”며 “대학이 나아가야 할 방향을 심도 있게 고민하는 계기가 됐다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sejong University (* 자료제공 :  세종대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by a university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240719.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/449/imgdb/original/2026/0120/5417688936384917.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dongduk Women's University Holds Launch Ceremony for 'Mokhwa Volunteer Corps'… "Contributing to Solving Community Problems" (동덕여대 ‘목화봉사단’ 발대식 개최… "지역사회 문제 해소 기여")</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240721.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Dongduk Women's University Holds Launch Ceremony for 'Mokhwa Volunteer Corps'… "Contributing to Solving Community Problems" (동덕여대 ‘목화봉사단’ 발대식 개최… "지역사회 문제 해소 기여")&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/431/imgdb/original/2026/0120/1117688939667443.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;목화봉사단 발대식.동덕여대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Dongduk Women's University Social Service Center held the 'Mokhwa Volunteer Corps Launch Ceremony' at the university's main building on January 15. &lt;br/&gt;The Mokhwa Volunteer Corps is an on-campus volunteer organization established with the purpose of having faculty, staff, and students contribute to the local community through continuous and effective volunteer service. It is composed of Dongduk members who voluntarily applied to participate. They will carry out volunteer activities in areas including Seongbuk-gu, Jongno-gu, and Gangnam-gu, where the campus is located, not only during the semester but also during vacations. &lt;br/&gt;The launch ceremony was prepared as the first event to announce the official start, where members participated to share the operational purpose and goals and discuss future activity plans. &lt;br/&gt;President Kim Myung-ae of Dongduk Women's University, who participated in the launch ceremony, said, "With the establishment of the Mokhwa Volunteer Corps, a path has opened for all of Dongduk's students, professors, and staff to step forward and play a good role for the community," particularly emphasizing the pride of Dongduk members equipped with ethical sensitivity and a sense of social responsibility. Kang Soo-mi, head of the Dongduk Women's University Social Service Center, introduced the outline and methods of the volunteer program while requesting the participation and cooperation of more members going forward.&lt;br/&gt;After the launch ceremony, the Mokhwa Volunteer Corps visited a senior care center and continued with meal service volunteering. The corps' future core plan is to contribute to solving the community's immediate problems, going beyond simple volunteer work. Basic activities include volunteer work centered on social welfare facilities and public institutions within the jurisdiction, visiting volunteer work for the socially vulnerable, environmental cleanup activities and volunteer work responding to the climate crisis, and holding volunteer service-related education and seminars. They also plan to organize programs to build and exchange networks with citizen volunteers.&lt;br/&gt;Any university member with interest and willingness in social service can participate in the Mokhwa Volunteer Corps on a year-round, ongoing basis, and participating students receive extracurricular mileage points. (동덕여자대학교 사회봉사센터는 지난 1월 15일 동덕여대 본관에서 &amp;#x27;목화봉사단 발대식&amp;#x27;을 개최하였다. &lt;br/&gt;목화봉사단은 교원, 직원, 학생이 지역사회에 지속적이고 실효적인 봉사를 통해 기여한다는 목적으로 설립한 교내 봉사 단체다. 자발적으로 참여를 신청한 동덕인으로 구성되었다. 학기 중은 물론 방학에도 캠퍼스가 위치한 성북구, 종로구, 강남구를 비롯한 지역에서 봉사활동을 전개한다. &lt;br/&gt;발대식은 공식 출범을 알리는 첫 행사로서 구성원들이 참여해 운영 취지와 목표를 공유하고 향후 활동 계획을 논의하는 자리로 마련되었다. &lt;br/&gt;발대식에 참여한 김명애 동덕여대 총장은 “목화봉사단 설립을 통해 동덕의 학생, 교수, 직원 모두가 나서서 지역사회를 위해 좋은 역할을 할 길이 열렸다”며, 특히 윤리적 감수성과 사회적 책임 의식을 갖춘 동덕인의 자부심을 강조했다. 강수미 동덕여대 사회봉사센터 센터장은 봉사 프로그램의 개요와 활동 방식을 소개하면서, 앞으로 더 많은 구성원의 참여와 협조를 요청하였다.&lt;br/&gt;목화봉사단은 발대식 후 노인요양센터를 방문해 급식 봉사를 이어갔다. 봉사단의 향후 핵심 계획은 단순 봉사를 넘어 지역사회의 당면 문제를 푸는데 기여하는 것이다. 관내 사회복지시설 및 공공기관 중심 봉사, 사회적 약자 방문 봉사, 환경 정화 활동 및 기후 위기 대응 봉사, 사회봉사 관련 교육 및 세미나 개최 등이 기본 활동이다. 시민 봉사자 네트워크를 구축하고 교류하는 프로그램도 꾸려갈 예정이다.&lt;br/&gt;목화봉사단에는 사회봉사에 관심과 의지가 있는 대학 구성원 누구나 연중 상시로 참여할 수 있으며, 학생 참여자의 경우 비교과 마일리지를 지급받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Dongduk Women's University (* 자료제공 :  동덕여자대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240721.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/431/imgdb/original/2026/0120/1117688939667443.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Korea Development Bank Secures Final Operating License for Hanoi Branch in Vietnam (산업은행, 베트남 하노이지점 최종 본인가 획득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240724.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Korea Development Bank Secures Final Operating License for Hanoi Branch in Vietnam (산업은행, 베트남 하노이지점 최종 본인가 획득)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/909/545/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688943336917_20260120503280.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Development Bank (KDB) has obtained an operating license to establish a branch in Hanoi, Vietnam. This is expected to expand funding for Korean companies operating in Vietnam. (한국산업은행이 베트남 하노이지점 설립 본인가를 획득했다. 베트남에 진출한 한국계 기업에 대한 자금공급이 확대될 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, KDB announced that it had secured the final operating license for its Hanoi branch from the State Bank of Vietnam on the 14th, marking the last step in the foreign bank branch establishment process. This license was obtained approximately six and a half years after applying for branch establishment approval in July 2019. KDB stated, "This is the first operating license issued to a foreign bank in Vietnam since 2021, achieved through two summit meetings, prime ministerial meetings, and high-level discussions between financial authorities and foreign ministries of both governments. From now on, we can conduct business and financial operations under the supervision of Vietnamese financial authorities." (산업은행은 지난 14일 베트남 중앙은행으로부터 외국은행 지점 설립 절차의 최종단계인 하노이지점 설립 본인가를 획득했다고 20일 밝혔다. 2019년 7월 지점 설립 인가를 신청한 이후 약 6년 반 만에 본인가를 얻어냈다. 산업은행은 “2021년 이후 베트남에서 외국계 은행에 발급한 최초 본인가 사례로, 한국정부의 두 차례 양국 정상회담, 총리회담, 금융당국 및 외교부 고위급 면담을 통해 이룬 것”이라며 “앞으로 베트남 금융당국의 감독 아래 영업과 금융업무 수행이 가능해졌다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through the Hanoi branch, KDB plans to provide financial services leveraging its strengths as a policy financial institution, including corporate finance, investment finance, and project financing (PF). KDB emphasized, "This operating license is more than just approval to open a branch; it is a milestone signifying our official entry into the Vietnamese financial market as a long-term, institutional partner. We will stably support the overseas expansion of domestic companies through the Hanoi branch." (산업은행은 하노이지점을 통해 기업금융, 투자금융, 프로젝트 파이낸싱(PF) 등 정책금융기관의 강점을 살린 금융 서비스를 제공할 예정이다. 산은은 “이번 본인가는 단순한 지점 개설 승인을 넘어, 베트남 금융시장에 장기적·제도적 파트너로 공식 진입했음을 의미하는 이정표”라며 “하노이지점을 통해 국내 기업의 해외 진출을 안정적으로 지원하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of May last year, 41 Korean financial companies, including banks, insurance firms, securities companies, card companies, capital firms, and asset managers, were operating 55 local outlets (local subsidiaries, branches, and offices) in Vietnam. (지난해 5월 기준 베트남에서는 은행·보험·증권·카드·캐피탈·자산운용사 등 41개 한국 금융회사가 55개 현지점포(현지법인·지점·사무소)를 운영하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240724.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/909/545/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688943336917_20260120503280.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix Fall Over 2% Together... KOSPI Struggles to Hold 5,000 (삼성전자·하이닉스 2%대 동반 하락 여파…코스피 ‘5천피 힘드네’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240726.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix Fall Over 2% Together... KOSPI Struggles to Hold 5,000 (삼성전자·하이닉스 2%대 동반 하락 여파…코스피 ‘5천피 힘드네’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/556/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503293.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스피가 13일 거래일 만에 내림세로 돌아선 20일 서울 중구 우리은행 딜링룸 현황판. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI halted its record-breaking rally after 13 trading days and fell below the 4,900 mark. The won-dollar exchange rate rose for the third consecutive trading day, approaching the 1,480 won level. (코스피가 13거래일 만에 사상 최고치 행진을 멈추고 4900선 밑으로 밀려났다. 원-달러 환율은 3거래일 연속 올라 1480원선 바짝 다가섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Korea Exchange data on the 20th, the KOSPI closed at 4,885.75, down 18.91 points (0.39%) from the previous trading day. The index started flat, fluctuated around the 4,900 level, and then fell over 1% in the morning to as low as 4,823.88. In the afternoon, the decline narrowed, and the index touched its intraday all-time high of 4,935.48, but it reversed course to close lower as profit-taking selling emerged late in the session. The daily fluctuation range (111.6 points) was very wide. (20일 한국거래소 집계를 보면, 코스피는 전거래일 대비 18.91(0.39%) 내린 4885.75에 주간거래를 마쳤다. 코스피는 보합권에서 출발한 뒤 4900선에서 공방을 벌이다 오전 한때 1% 넘게 하락해 4823.88까지 밀렸다. 오후 들어 낙폭을 줄이며 장중 사상 최고치인 4935.48을 터치했지만 장 막판 차익실현 매물이 나오면서 하락 반전했다. 이날 하루 변동 폭(111.6)이 매우 컸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI had risen for 12 consecutive trading days without a single decline from the market's opening day on the 2nd until the previous day, but it failed to achieve a record 13-day winning streak. The KOSPI has previously recorded 13 consecutive days of gains three times: in 1984 (Jan 19–Feb 2), and in 2019 (Mar 29–Apr 16, Sep 4–Sep 24). Lee Jae-won, a researcher at Shinhan Investment &amp; Securities, analyzed, "Amid the closure of the New York stock market, a cooling-off trend appeared, but rotational buying continued, centered on stocks that had been overlooked." (코스피는 새해 들어 증시 시작일인 2일부터 전날까지 하루도 빠짐없이 12거래일 연속 상승했는데 역대 최장 기록인 13거래일 연속 상승하진 못했다. 코스피는 1984년(1월19일~2월2일), 2019년(3월29일~4월16일, 9월4일~9월24일) 모두 세 차례 13거래일 연속 상승한 바 있다. 이재원 신한투자증권 연구원은 “뉴욕 증시 휴장 속에 과열 해소 흐름이 나타났지만 그동안 소외됐던 종목들 중심으로 순환매 흐름이 이어졌다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By investor type, individuals and foreigners were net buyers of 354.6 billion won and 78.9 billion won, respectively, while institutions were net sellers of 607.7 billion won. (투자자별로는 개인과 외국인이 각각 3546억원, 789억원을 순매수했고, 기관이 6077억원 순매도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major semiconductor stocks fell sharply due to concerns about potential US tariffs. Samsung Electronics closed down 4,100 won (2.75%) at 145,200 won, and SK Hynix fell 21,000 won (2.75%) to close at 743,000 won. In contrast, robot-related stocks surged significantly. Hyundai Mobis (11.44%) and Doosan Robotics (9.66%) jumped around 10%. (미국의 관세 부과 우려로 반도체 대장주들은 낙폭이 컸다. 삼성전자는 4100원(2.75%) 내린 14만5200원, 에스케이(SK)하이닉스는 2만1000원(2.75%) 하락한 74만3000원에 마감했다. 대신 로봇주가 크게 올랐다. 현대무벡스(11.44%), 두산로보틱스(9.66%)가 10% 안팎 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the top market capitalization stocks declined. Hyundai Motor (-0.21%), Samsung Biologics (-0.05%), Hanwha Aerospace (-1.58%), HD Hyundai Heavy Industries (-1.08%), Kia (-3.30%), and Doosan Enerbility (-0.10%) all closed lower. LG Energy Solution (1.13%) closed higher. (시가총액 상위종목 대부분이 내렸다. 현대차(-0.21%), 삼성바이오로직스(-0.05%), 한화에어로스페이스(-1.58%), 에이치디(HD)현대중공업(-1.08%), 기아(-3.30%), 두산에너빌리티(-0.10%) 등이 내렸다. 엘지(LG)에너지솔루션(1.13%)은 상승 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ index closed at 976.37, up 8.01 points (0.83%) from the previous trading day. During the session, the index hit 985.79, surpassing the 980 level for the first time in four years since January 13, 2022 (983.25). Closing above the 970 level is also the first time since January 14, 2022 (971.39). (코스닥지수는 전거래일 대비 8.01(0.83%) 오른 976.37에 마감했다. 지수는 장중 985.79를 찍어 2022년 1월13일(983.25) 이후 4년 만에 980선을 넘어섰다. 종가 기준 970선을 넘은 것도 2022년 1월14일(971.39) 이후 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The won-dollar exchange rate rose for the third consecutive trading day. In the Seoul foreign exchange market, the won-dollar exchange rate closed at 1,478.1 won, up 4.4 won from the previous trading day (1,473.7 won). It opened at 1,474.5 won, up 0.8 won from the previous day, and rose to as high as 1,479.65 won in the morning, threatening the 1,480 won level. Following verbal intervention by US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent on the 14th (local time), it had briefly fallen to the 1,460 won range but has since risen back to the high 1,470 won range. Despite the dollar's weak trend, the won faced simultaneous depreciation pressure due to the weak Japanese yen. As of the closing time, the yen-dollar exchange rate in the Tokyo forex market was trading around 158.4 yen, up 0.3 yen from the previous day. (원-달러 환율은 3거래일 연속 상승했다. 이날 서울외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 전거래일(1473.7원)보다 4.4원 오른 1478.1원에 주간거래를 마감했다. 전날보다 0.8원 오른 1474.5원에 개장해 오전 한 때 1479.65원까지 올라 1480원선을 위협했다. 지난 14일(현지시간) 스콧 베선트 미국 재무부 장관의 구두개입으로 한때 1460원대로 낮아졌는데 다시 1470원대 후반까지 상승했다. 달러 약세 흐름에도 일본 엔화 약세 영향으로 원화 가치가 동반 약세 압력을 받았다. 마감 시각 기준 도쿄 외환시장에서 엔-달러 환율은 전날보다 0.3엔 오른 158.4엔대에서 거래중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240726.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/556/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503293.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Concerns About a New Era of Military-Economics Driven by State-Capital Collusion (국가-자본 결탁한 새로운 군사경제 시대를 우려한다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240754.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Concerns About a New Era of Military-Economics Driven by State-Capital Collusion (국가-자본 결탁한 새로운 군사경제 시대를 우려한다)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/495/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503715.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;젠슨 황 엔비디아 최고경영자(오른쪽)가 지난해 4월30일 미국 워싱턴 백악관에서 열린 ‘미국 투자’ 행사에서 발표하는 모습을 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 지켜보고 있다. 워싱턴/UPI 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In just one year, U.S. President Trump has uprooted the international economic and political order that had been formed over the preceding century. He began his term by declaring tariff wars against all trading partners and has now committed the outrageous act of sending his country's military to abduct the president of an independent nation. Amidst this, the world is cheering the development of new technologies like artificial intelligence (AI). Governments are staking their survival on the AI race, pouring vast resources into it, while the stock prices of Big Tech companies are skyrocketing. These phenomena clearly characterize today's world, yet they also seem to have faint connections with each other. (트럼프 미국 대통령은 불과 1년 사이에 그 이전 100년 동안 형성된 국제 경제·정치 질서를 뿌리째 뒤흔들고 있다. 그는 모든 교역국을 상대로 관세전쟁을 선포하며 임기를 시작하더니, 자국 군대를 보내 독립국의 대통령을 납치하는 엽기 행각을 벌였다. 이 와중에 세계는 인공지능(AI) 등 신기술 발달에 환호하고 있다. 각국 정부는 AI 경쟁에 사활을 걸고 막대한 자원을 투입하는 중이며, 빅테크 기업의 주가는 천정부지로 치솟고 있다. 이런 현상들은 분명 오늘의 세계를 특징 짓는 사태들이지만 서로 연관성이 희미해 보이기도 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the tariff war. While Trump's method was unique, the liberal international economic order that collapsed because of him was not an absolute truth. Originally, capitalism emerged as a single 'world economy,' but it simultaneously operates organized within individual nation-states. This duality was insightfully developed by Bukharin, who participated in the Russian Revolution. In actual history, periods where capitalism's 'worldliness' was maximized and periods where its 'national character' was emphasized have alternated. If the 1870s to early 1910s and the 1980s to around 2010 were eras of 'globalization,' the interim periods, especially from the mid-1940s to the 1970s, were times when state-led internal consolidation and 'national character' were prominent. (관세 전쟁에서 시작해 보자. 트럼프의 방식이 독특하긴 했지만, 그에 따라 무너진 자유주의 국제경제질서가 절대적 진리는 아니다. 본래 자본주의는 하나의 ‘세계경제’로 등장했지만, 동시에 개별 국민국가 단위로 조직되어 작동한다. 이런 이중성에 대한 통찰은 러시아혁명에 투신했던 부하린이 발전시켰는데, 실제 역사에서도 자본주의의 ‘세계성’이 극대화되는 시기와 ‘국민성’이 강조되는 시기는 교차해 왔다. 1870년대~1910년대 초반, 1980년대~2010년께를 ‘세계화’의 시대였다고 한다면, 그 사이의 공백기 특히 1940년대 중반~1970년대까지는 국가 주도의 내실 다지기와 ‘국민성’이 두드러진 시기였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meaning of this alternation becomes clear from the perspective of capital. At the turn of the 19th and 20th centuries, great powers fattened themselves through economic rivalry (imperialism) over securing colonies, and when that growth strategy reached its limits, World War I broke out. This was followed by a period of rebuilding nations devastated by two wars and the Great Depression and consolidating economic foundations, a model that also met its end when it hit the stagnation of the 1970s. Capital then rearmed itself with finance and set out to conquer the world, where the main 'prey' became the public assets accumulated internally by each country in the preceding period, as well as the former socialist bloc, which was newly incorporated after being outside capitalism. The recent second 'retreat' from globalization suggests the expiration of this model's effectiveness. Indeed, while global capitalism has been floundering in a prolonged stagnation for over a decade since the 2008 global financial crisis, various market-centric solutions like monetary policy have not been the answer. A fundamental breakthrough is needed. (이러한 교차의 의미는 자본의 관점에서 보았을 때 명확해진다. 19~20세기 전환기에 강대국들은 식민지 확보를 둘러싼 경제적 각축(제국주의)을 통해 제 살을 찌워 나갔고, 그런 성장전략이 한계에 다다랐을 때 1차 세계대전이 벌어졌다. 이후 두 차례의 전쟁과 대불황으로 피폐해진 나라를 재건하고 경제의 내실을 다지는 기간이 뒤를 이었는데, 이 모형도 1970년대 불황에 막혀 종말을 고했다. 자본은 다시 금융을 무기로 장착하고 세계 개척에 나섰는데, 여기서는 앞선 시기에 각국이 내적으로 축적한 공적 자산, 그리고 종전엔 자본주의 바깥에 있다가 새로이 편입된 구 사회주의권 등이 주된 ‘먹잇감’이 되었다. 최근 세계화로부터의 두 번째 ‘후퇴’는 이 모형의 효력 만료를 시사한다. 실제로, 세계 자본주의가 2008년 글로벌 금융위기 이후 십수년째 장기 정체의 늪에서 허우적대고 있지만, 그간의 통화 정책 등 다양한 시장 중심의 해법은 해결책이 되지 못했다. 근본적 차원의 돌파구가 필요한 거다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Against this backdrop, the COVID-19 pandemic became a convenient pretext for the world economy to stagnate as much as it liked, and thus seemingly provided an opportunity for internal realignment for countries worldwide and a new growth platform for capital. The idea is to rebuild destroyed socio-economic infrastructure, but place it on a foundation of new technology (AI) and value systems (eco-friendliness). This is impossible without state support, as seen in cases like the U.S. Biden administration's 'Build Back Better (BBB)' or South Korea's Moon Jae-in administration's 'Korean New Deal.' This internal adjustment resembles the past U.S. 'New Deal' or the development of welfare states in Western countries. However, such opportunities gradually faded during the recovery from the pandemic. Trump's trade war and the resulting resurgence of protectionism are, in a bizarre way, restoring that opportunity. (이런 배경에서, 코로나19 팬데믹은 세계경제가 얼마든 침체 해도 좋을 핑곗거리가 되었고, 그리하여 외려 세계 각국에 내부 정비의 기회를, 자본에 새로운 성장의 발판을 제공하는 듯했다. 파괴된 사회·경제 인프라를 재건하되, 이를 새로운 기술(AI)과 가치체계(친환경)의 기반 위에 올려놓자는 것이다. 이건 국가의 지원 없이는 불가능한 일로, 미국 바이든 정부의 ‘더 나은 재건(BBB)’이나 한국 문재인 정부의 ‘한국판 뉴딜’이 그런 사례다. 이런 내적 조정은 과거 미국의 ‘뉴딜’이나 서구 각국의 복지국가 발달과 비슷하다. 그러나 위와 같은 기회는 팬데믹에서 회복되는 과정에서 시나브로 사라졌다. 트럼프의 무역전쟁과 그에 따른 보호주의 회귀는 그 기회를 기괴한 방식으로 복구하고 있는 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But for countries to move towards strengthening their internal foundations rather than globalization is not as easy as it was 80 years ago. First, because countries are entangled within the dense web of global supply and finance. Even the superpower United States now finds it difficult to independently pursue a domestically-centered development strategy. Second, because it is difficult to mobilize domestic support bases for change. Currently, the grand causes that united societies in the mid-last century, such as post-war reconstruction or anti-communism, are absent; the power representing social forces like labor unions has become fragmented; and the interests of the people have become complex and diverse. (하지만 각국이 세계화보다는 자국의 내실을 다지는 쪽으로 나아가는 게 80년 전만큼 쉽지는 않다. 첫째, 각국이 글로벌 공급과 금융의 촘촘한 망 안에 얽혀 들어와서다. 최강대국 미국조차도 이제는 자국 중심의 발전전략을 자력으로 구사하기가 어려울 정도다. 둘째, 국내적으로 변화의 지지 세력을 동원하기가 어려워서다. 지금은 전후 복구나 반공 등 지난 세기 중반에 사회를 응집했던 대의가 부재하고, 노조 등 사회세력을 대표하는 힘이 지리멸렬해졌으며, 국민의 이해관계도 복잡다기해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, state-led initiative cannot be abandoned. For capital to escape stagnation, the potential of new technologies and the eco-friendly paradigm must explode, and realizing this requires state assistance. What is the alternative? Where is today's new state-capital alliance headed? (그래도 국가 주도성은 포기될 수 없다. 자본이 침체에서 빠져나가려면 새로운 기술과 친환경 패러다임의 잠재력이 폭발해야 하는데, 이의 실현을 위해서는 국가의 도움이 필수적이기 때문이다. 대안은 무엇인가? 오늘의 새로운 국가-자본 동맹은 어디로 향하고 있는가?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, we must pay attention to the recent collusion between the economy and the military. In the past, this was called the 'military-industrial complex.' The military-industrial complex refers to a massive power bloc formed by the combination of a state's military organization, giant defense industries, and the political interests supporting them. Beyond mere weapons production, it takes on the character of an 'institutionalized war economy' that determines the state's resource allocation priorities and controls the direction of technological innovation. In the past, the Cold War-era military-industrial complex maintained a permanent wartime state, solving capitalism's overproduction problem and achieving leaps in technology. We are now witnessing the revival of that mechanism. (이 대목에서 우리는 최근 경제와 군사의 결탁을 눈여겨봐야 한다. 과거 이는 ‘군산복합체’라고 불렸다. 군산복합체란 국가의 군사 조직과 거대 방위 산업, 그리고 이를 뒷받침하는 정치적 이해관계가 결합하여 형성된 거대한 권력 블록을 가리킨다. 이는 단순한 무기 생산을 넘어, 국가의 자원 배분 우선순위를 결정하고 기술 혁신의 방향을 통제하는 ‘제도화된 전쟁 경제’의 성격을 띤다. 과거 냉전기 군산복합체가 상시적인 전시 상태를 유지함으로써 자본주의의 과잉 생산 문제를 해결하고 비약적인 기술 도약을 이뤄냈다. 지금 우리는 그 메커니즘의 부활을 목격하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conflicts around the world are already intensifying in the form of direct intervention by great powers. The recent U.S. invasion of Venezuela suggests that the geopolitical order has crossed a certain decisive 'threshold.' As the U.S. steps down from its 'world police' status, every country is pouring funds into defense for self-reliance. Even former Axis powers like Germany are naturally being accepted as they embark on rearmament. According to the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI), global military spending in 2024 continued its increase for the tenth consecutive year, surpassing a record high of $2.718 trillion annually. It is no coincidence that President Trump, just after the abduction of President Maduro, demanded on the 8th of last month that next year's defense budget be increased to $1.5 trillion (about 2170 trillion won), 1.5 times the current level. (이미 세계 곳곳의 분쟁은 강대국들이 직접 개입하는 형태로 격화되고 있다. 최근 미국의 베네수엘라 침공은 지정학적 질서가 어떤 결정적 ‘문턱’을 넘었음을 시사한다. 미국이 ‘세계 경찰’의 지위를 내려놓으니, 모든 국가가 자구책 마련을 위해 국방비를 쏟아붓는다. 독일 같은 전범국조차 재무장의 길로 들어서는 것이 자연스레 용인되는 분위기다. 실제로 스톡홀름국제평화연구소(SIPRI)에 따르면 2024년 세계 군사비 지출은 10년째 증가를 이어가며 사상 최고치인 연간 2조7180억 달러를 돌파했다. 마두로 대통령 납치 직후인 지난 8일 트럼프 대통령이 내년도 국방예산을 현재의 1.5배 수준인 1조5000억 달러(약 2170조원)로 증액할 것을 요구한 것은 우연이 아니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expanding the concept of military leads to 'Security.' However, today's security is expanding infinitely, transcending domestic and international boundaries as well as politics and economics, and is becoming closely intertwined with new technologies like AI and semiconductors, as seen in the U.S.-China conflict. Could we call this era where military, economy, and technology have fused into one the era of the 'Second Military-Industrial Complex'? Professor Elke Schwarz of Queen Mary University of London pointed out that venture capital investment in military technology startups in the U.S. quadrupled from 2019 to 2022, and that $130 billion in venture capital has been invested in defense technology since 2021, calling this the 'venture capital-military-Silicon Valley nexus.' Its economic significance can be summarized as follows. (군사 개념을 확장하면 ‘안보(Security)’가 된다. 그런데 오늘날 안보는 나라 안팎은 물론 정치와 경제를 넘나들며 무한 확장 중이며, 미·중 갈등에서 드러나듯 AI와 반도체 같은 신기술과 밀접해지고 있다. 군사와 경제, 테크놀로지가 하나로 용해된 이 시대를 ‘2차 군산복합체’의 시대라고 해도 좋지 않을까. 영국 퀸메리대의 엘케 슈워츠 교수는 미국에서 2019~2022년에 군사기술 스타트업에 대한 벤처자본 투자가 곱절이 되었고, 2021년 이후 1300억 달러의 벤처자본이 국방기술 분야에 투입되었음을 꼽으며, 이를 ‘벤처자본-군-실리콘밸리 연계’라고 불렀다. 그 경제적 의의를 요약하면 다음과 같다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, it creates powerful effective demand for a stagnant economy. The necessity of the commodity called security is difficult to define objectively. Even if the enemy's reality is unclear, if the public is convinced of a threat, that enemy gains reality. The expansion of the security concept through AI and data hegemony—the military's 'tech washing'—also increases the social acceptability of security. Because it is considered highly necessary, no one objects when governments and companies invest hundreds of trillions annually into security, even if today's security competition is later proven to be unproductive 'futile work.' (첫째, 정체된 경제에 강력한 유효수요를 창출한다. 안보라는 상품의 필요성은 객관적으로 정의되기 어렵다. 적의 실체가 불분명해도 대중이 위협을 확신하면 그 적은 실체를 갖게 된다. AI와 데이터 패권으로 안보 개념의 확장―군의 ‘테크 워싱’―또한 안보의 사회적 수용성을 높인다. 필요성이 높은 일이므로, 정부와 기업이 매년 수백조원을 안보에 투입해도 누구도 토를 달지 않는다. 지금의 안보 경쟁이 훗날 비생산적인 ‘헛된 일’로 판명되더라도 말이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, it provides an opportunity for companies to legally privatize public resources under the state's active support. In a reality where it is difficult to apply technology to actual production to generate profit, security becomes the most certain and stable market. The higher the hierarchy of security, the stronger the legitimacy for the state to use citizens' tax money to subsidize companies' uncertain and risky technological development. Simultaneously, a structure becomes normalized where the cost of failure is shared by the whole society while profits are monopolized by capital. (둘째, 국가의 적극적 지원 아래 기업이 공적 자원을 합법적으로 사유화할 기회가 된다. 기술을 실제 생산에 적용해 이윤을 창출하기 어려운 현실에서, 안보는 가장 확실하고 안정적인 시장이 된다. 안보의 위계가 높아질수록 국가가 시민의 혈세로 기업의 불확실하고 위험천만한 기술 개발을 보조하는 행위는 강력한 정당성을 얻는다. 동시에 실패의 비용은 사회 전체가 나누어지고 이익은 자본이 독점하는 구조가 상례화된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third, this process ultimately accelerates technological innovation and leaves behind useful byproducts. Look at the core technologies of the iPhone, praised by Mariana Mazzucato as 'state success stories,' or the achievements of the Apollo program. In fact, these were not so much 'success stories' of the state leading development for economic purposes themselves, but rather byproducts left by a war economy carrying out the highly regrettable 'mission' of defense and security. It is not uncommon for AI technologies developed for immediate warfare and control to paradoxically transform into harmless tools for humanity in the distant future. (셋째, 이 과정은 결과적으로 기술 혁신을 가속화하며 유용한 부산물을 남긴다. 마리아나 마추카토가 ‘국가의 성공사례’로 상찬한 아이폰의 핵심 기술이나 아폴로 계획의 성과들을 보라. 사실 이들은 그 자체로 국가가 경제적 목적을 가지고 개발을 주도한 ‘성공사례’라기보단 국방과 안보라는, 다분히 유감스러운 ‘미션’을 수행하던 전쟁경제가 남긴 부산물이었다. 당장은 전쟁과 통제를 위해 개발되는 AI 기술들이, 역설적으로 먼 미래에 인류를 위한 무해한 도구로 변모하는 것은 드문 일이 아니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is this mere anxiety? The current development pattern of new technologies adds empirical grounds to these concerns. While AI will ultimately revolutionize industrial sites, its realization is expected to take considerable time due to public backlash against job losses and labor disintegration. Many economists also point to the 'productivity paradox' of AI, noting that technology investment is not leading to actual productivity growth. (이것은 기우일까? 현재 신기술의 전개 양상은 이러한 우려에 실증적인 근거를 더한다. 종국엔 AI가 산업 현장을 혁명적으로 바꿀 테지만, 그 실현에는 고용 감소와 노동 해체에 대한 시민들의 반발로 인해 상당한 시간이 걸릴 것으로 예상된다. 많은 경제학자들 역시 AI의 ‘생산성 역설’에 주목하며 기술 투자가 실제 생산성 증대로 이어지지 못하고 있다고 지적하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the field where AI demonstrates its most powerful force is the surveillance and control of citizens. Furthermore, under the pretext of dealing with external enemies or guaranteeing national survival, bold technological experiments will be relentlessly carried out in the name of security. The already massive U.S. defense budget will increasingly be spent on contracts with Silicon Valley tech companies like Palantir rather than traditional defense contractors like Lockheed Martin. (반면, AI가 가장 강력한 위력을 발휘하는 분야는 시민에 대한 감시와 통제다. 또한 자국 바깥의 적을 상대하거나 국가적 생존을 담보한다는 명분 아래서는 과감한 기술적 실험들이 안보의 이름으로 거침없이 자행될 것이다. 이미 막대한 수준인 미국 국방비는, 록히드 마틴 같은 전통적 방산기업보단 팔란티어 같은 실리콘밸리 테크기업과의 계약에 점차 더 쓰일 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are moving away from the ideal of 'global capitalism' that characterized an era and entering a phase of reorganizing infrastructure and consolidating internal capabilities at the national level. However, its manifestation seems to be taking shape more as a new military economy through state-capital collusion rather than a 'New Deal' based on agreements among domestic social forces. The fact that this process is led by states, especially the governments of great powers like the U.S., heightens vigilance. (우리는 한 시대를 풍미했던 ‘글로벌 자본주의’의 이상에서는 멀어지는 대신 국가 단위에서 인프라를 재정비하고 내부 역량을 결집하는 국면으로 진입하고 있다. 그러나 그 양상은 국내 사회세력들 사이의 협약에 기반을 둔 ‘뉴딜’보다는 국가-자본 결탁을 통한 새로운 군사경제의 형태로 구체화되고 있는 것 같다. 이 과정이 국가, 특히 미국 등 강대국 정부에 의해 주도되는 점이 경계심을 키운다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Kim Gong-hoe, Gyeongsang National University (Economics) (김공회 경상대 교수(경제학))&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240754.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/495/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503715.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI-Driven DRAM Prices Soar, Expected to Remain High This Year... Price Stabilization Around Next Year (AI발 디램 가격 폭등, 올해도 여전…내년쯤 가격 안정)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240755.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;AI-Driven DRAM Prices Soar, Expected to Remain High This Year... Price Stabilization Around Next Year (AI발 디램 가격 폭등, 올해도 여전…내년쯤 가격 안정)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/475/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503722.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;20일 경기도 용인시 처인구 원삼면 용인반도체클러스터 일반산업단지 공사현장. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the global competition for artificial intelligence (AI) development intensifies, the price of general-purpose memory semiconductors has surged nearly sixfold over the past year. Due to increased demand for memory semiconductors driven by expanded AI investment, this price strength is projected to continue this year. Within the industry, the prevailing view is that price stabilization will occur in the latter half of next year or later. (전 세계적으로 인공지능(AI) 개발 경쟁이 치열해지면서 범용 메모리 반도체 가격이 지난 1년 동안 6배 가까이 급등한 것으로 나타났다. 인공지능 투자 확대에 따른 메모리 반도체 수요 증가로 올해에도 이런 가격 강세는 이어질 것으로 전망된다. 업계에서는 가격 안정화 시점을 내년 하반기 이후로 보는 시각이 우세하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to data from market research firm DRAMeXchange on the 20th, the price of general-purpose DRAM (DDR4, 8Gb basis) rose by 589% last year. This is because semiconductor companies have focused on producing High Bandwidth Memory (HBM), needed for AI accelerators and other applications, leading to a shortage in the supply of general-purpose DRAM. As DRAM is also used in household computers and laptops, it is recently cited as a major factor driving up the prices of these digital devices. (20일 시장조사업체 디램익스체인지의 자료를 보면, 지난해 메모리 반도체인 범용 디램(디디알4, 8Gb 기준) 가격은 589% 오른 것으로 집계됐다. 반도체 업체들이 인공지능 가속기 등에 필요한 고대역폭메모리(HBM) 생산에 집중하면서 범용 디램 공급이 부족해진 탓이다. 디램은 가정용 컴퓨터, 노트북 등에도 들어가기 때문에 최근에는 이들 디지털기기 가격을 끌어올리는 주요 원인으로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, major semiconductor companies are busy expanding their production capacity. U.S.-based Micron Technology, the world's third-largest memory semiconductor company, announced on the 19th (local time) that it would acquire the semiconductor production facilities of Taiwanese company Powerchip Semiconductor Manufacturing Corporation (PSMC) for $1.8 billion (approximately 2.655 trillion won). Upon completion of the acquisition, DRAM production volume could increase starting in the second half of next year. (이에 따라 주요 반도체 기업들은 생산 능력(캐파)을 늘리기 위해 분주한 상황이다. 메모리 반도체 업계 3위 기업 미국 마이크론 테크놀로지는 19일(현지시각) 대만 기업 피에스엠시(PSMC)의 반도체 생산시설을 18억달러(약 2조6550억원)에 인수하겠다고 밝혔다. 인수를 마치면 내년 하반기부터 디램 생산량이 늘 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bloomberg, citing remarks from Manish Bhatia, Micron's Executive Vice President of Global Operations, reported that "the (DRAM) shortage we are seeing now is unprecedented." Executive Vice President Bhatia stated, "Now even computer and smartphone companies are entering the competition to secure memory, and demand will be further spurred by autonomous vehicles and humanoid robots." (블룸버그는 마니쉬 바티아 마이크론 글로벌 운용총괄 부사장의 발언을 인용해 “지금 우리가 보고 있는 (디램) 부족 현상은 전례 없는 일”이라고 보도했다. 바티아 부사장은 “이젠 컴퓨터와 스마트폰 업체들까지 메모리 확보를 위한 경쟁에 나서고 있으며, 자율주행차와 휴머노이드(인간형 로봇)까지 관련 수요를 촉진할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, although it is only January, Micron and SK Hynix have already pre-sold all the memory semiconductor volume they plan to produce this year. Samsung Electronics is also reported to have sold most of its volume. This adds weight to the observation that memory semiconductor prices, including DRAM, will continue their steep climb this year. (실제로 아직 1월이지만 마이크론과 에스케이(SK)하이닉스는 올해 생산할 메모리 반도체 물량을 모두 선판매한 상태다. 삼성전자 역시 물량 대부분을 소진한 것으로 전해졌다. 올해도 디램 등 메모리 반도체 가격이 고공행진 할 것이란 관측에 무게가 실리는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The market anticipates that memory prices will not stabilize until around 2027, when semiconductor companies' production capacities expand. Ryu Hyun-keun, a researcher at Daishin Securities, said, "The memory supply shortage will continue within the year, and meaningful signals for resolving the supply shortage will only appear after the first half of next year." This is because Micron has announced its intention to acquire PSMC's semiconductor production facilities, and SK Hynix is building its first fab (factory) in the Yongin semiconductor cluster, aiming for completion in May next year. (시장에서는 반도체 기업들의 생산 능력이 확대되는 오는 2027년께는 돼야 메모리 가격이 안정될 것이란 관측이 나온다. 류형근 대신증권 연구원은 “연내에는 메모리 부족 공급이 이어지고, 내년 상반기 이후에야 유의미한 공급 부족 해소에 대한 신호가 나타날 것”이라고 말했다. 마이크론이 피에스엠시 반도체 생산시설을 인수하겠다고 밝힌 데다, 에스케이하이닉스가 내년 5월 준공을 목표로 용인 반도체 클러스터에 1기 팹(공장)을 짓고 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240755.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/475/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503722.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Samsung is back'?... Lowest quarterly operating profit margin among the three memory giants (‘삼성이 돌아왔다’?…메모리 3사 중 분기 영업이익률 ‘꼴찌’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240769.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'Samsung is back'?... Lowest quarterly operating profit margin among the three memory giants (‘삼성이 돌아왔다’?…메모리 3사 중 분기 영업이익률 ‘꼴찌’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503829.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;반도체. 클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the market is buzzing with the AI-driven semiconductor supercycle, the situations of major semiconductor companies vary. On the surface, it may seem like everyone is raking in money, but it's said that even wealthy households have their own worries. Comparing the profitability of the global 'Big Three' memory companies—Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, and Micron—with foundry company Taiwan's TSMC and AI chip design company (fabless) Nvidia of the U.S., these underlying circumstances become even clearer. The company that likely has the deepest immediate concerns is Samsung Electronics. (인공지능(AI)발 반도체 슈퍼사이클(초호황)로 시장이 들썩이지만 주요 반도체 기업별 사정은 제각각이다. 겉만 보면 모두가 돈을 쓸어 담는 듯하지만, 부잣집도 저마다의 고민거리가 있다는 얘기다. 삼성전자·에스케이(SK)하이닉스·마이크론 등 글로벌 ‘메모리 3사’와 파운드리(반도체 수탁생산) 기업인 대만 티에스엠시(TSMC), 인공지능 칩 설계기업(팹리스)인 미국 엔비디아 등의 수익성을 서로 견줘 보면 이런 속사정은 더욱 뚜렷하게 드러난다. 당장 고민이 깊을 수밖에 없는 기업은 삼성전자다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparing the quarterly operating profit margins of these five semiconductor companies over the past two years reveals that among the Big Three memory makers, Hynix has the highest profitability. The company's operating profit margin exceeded 40% in Q3 2024 and reached 46.6% in Q3 last year. The operating profit margin, calculated by dividing operating profit by revenue, is a key indicator for assessing a company's profitability. An operating profit margin of 46.6% means that for every 1 million won memory chip sold, 466,000 won remains as the company's margin. (20일 이들 반도체 5개사의 지난 2년 치 분기 영업이익률을 비교해 보니, 메모리 3사 중 수익성이 가장 높은 기업은 하이닉스였다. 이 회사의 영업이익률은 2024년 3분기 40%를 돌파해 지난해 3분기 46.6%를 기록했다. 영업이익률은 매출액을 영업이익으로 나눈 비율로 기업의 수익성을 따져보는 핵심 지표다. 영업이익률이 46.6%라는 것은 100만원짜리 메모리칩 1개를 팔아 46만6천원을 회사의 마진으로 남겼다는 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The average estimate by securities firms for Hynix's Q4 last year operating profit margin, compiled by financial information provider FnGuide, is 52.7%. Hynix will announce its Q4 results on the 29th. The profitability of U.S.-based Micron, ranked third in global memory market share, is also nothing to scoff at. Its most recently announced operating profit margin for Q1 of fiscal year 2026 (September-November 2025) was 45.0% (U.S. accounting standards), a 12.7 percentage point increase from the previous quarter. While its total revenue is about two-thirds of Hynix's, its profitability is closely trailing. (금융정보업체인 에프앤가이드가 집계한 증권사들의 지난해 4분기 하이닉스의 영업이익률 추정값 평균은 52.7%다. 하이닉스는 오는 29일 지난해 4분기 실적을 발표한다. 글로벌 메모리 시장 점유율 3위인 미국 마이크론의 수익성도 만만치 않다. 가장 최근 발표한 2026회계연도 1분기(2025년 9~11월) 영업이익률은 전기 대비 12.7%포인트 상승한 45.0%(미국 회계기준)였다. 전체 매출은 하이닉스의 3분의 2 수준이지만 수익성만큼은 뒤를 바짝 추격하는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Samsung Electronics' situation is different. Among the record-high operating profit of 20 trillion won in Q4 last year, securities analysts estimate that the semiconductor division's profit alone exceeded 16 trillion won. During this period, the semiconductor division's operating profit margin was 36.8% (based on Hyundai Motor Securities' estimate), about 10 percentage points lower than its competitors. This is analyzed to be due to the losses in the System LSI and foundry businesses within the semiconductor division expanding to over 1 trillion won, and the company not yet generating significant profits in the high-margin AI high-bandwidth memory (HBM) field. It's closer to growth driven by a sharp price surge in general-purpose memory, where supply shortages became extreme as the three memory giants focused on AI memory production, rather than a clear improvement in technological competitiveness. (반면 삼성전자 사정은 다르다. 지난해 4분기에 기록한 사상 최대 영업이익 20조원 중 반도체 사업부 이익만 16조원 이상으로 증권가는 추산한다. 이 기간 반도체 부문의 영업이익률은 36.8%(현대차증권 추정값 기준)로 경쟁사에 견줘 10%포인트가량 낮다. 이는 반도체사업부 내 시스템반도체(LSI)와 파운드리 적자가 1조원 이상으로 확대되고, 마진이 높은 인공지능용 고대역폭메모리 분야에서도 아직 뚜렷한 이익을 얻지 못하고 있기 때문으로 분석된다. 기술 경쟁력이 뚜렷하게 개선됐다기보다는 메모리 3사가 인공지능 메모리 생산에 집중한 결과, 공급 부족이 극심해진 일반 범용 메모리의 가격 폭등에 힘입은 성장에 가깝다는 이야기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this reason, there are internal voices cautioning against the self-praise by Samsung Electronics Vice Chairman and CEO Jun Young-hyun in his New Year's address earlier this month, where he said, "We are even receiving evaluations from customers that 'Samsung is back'." This is because challenges remain: improving yield rates (ratio of good products) and expanding customer orders to catch up with competitor TSMC in the foundry market, as well as enhancing competitiveness in next-generation AI semiconductor technologies including high-bandwidth memory. (이런 까닭에 이달 초 전영현 삼성전자 대표이사 부회장이 신년사를 통해 “고객들에게 ‘삼성이 돌아왔다’는 평가까지 받고 있다”며 자평한 것을 경계하는 내부 목소리도 있다. 파운드리 시장에서 경쟁사인 대만 티에스엠시 대비 뒤떨어지는 수율(양품 비율) 제고 및 고객사 수주 확대는 물론, 고대역폭메모리를 비롯한 차세대 인공지능 반도체 기술 경쟁력 등 넘어야 할 과제가 여전하기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Noh Geun-chang, head of the research center at Hyundai Motor Securities, said, "Samsung Electronics' lower operating profit margin compared to peers is due to its foundry business," adding, "Currently, it is in the process of resolving and overcoming these challenges, and we expect it to improve going forward." (노근창 현대차증권 리서치센터장은 “삼성전자의 영업이익률이 타사 대비 낮은 건 파운드리 때문”이라며 “현재는 이 같은 과제가 해소되고 극복되는 과정이며 앞으로 좋아질 것으로 기대한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While not memory manufacturers, other semiconductor companies with unique 'technological moats' are already achieving dream-like operating profit margins. TSMC, with an average operating profit margin of 50.7% over the last four quarters, is a prime example. Nvidia of the U.S., which opened a new market with its Graphics Processing Units (GPUs) optimized for AI computing, has a quarterly operating profit margin exceeding 60%. While semiconductor design companies like Nvidia generally have high profitability because they don't require massive equipment investment and maintenance costs, Nvidia is generating astronomical profits due to its overwhelming market share. (메모리 제조기업은 아니지만 독보적인 ‘기술적 해자(진입 장벽)’를 보유한 다른 반도체 기업들은 이미 꿈의 영업이익률을 달성하고 있다. 최근 4개 분기 영업이익률 평균이 50.7%에 이르는 티에스엠시가 대표적이다. 인공지능 연산에 최적화한 그래픽처리장치(GPU)로 새 시장을 연 미국 엔비디아는 분기 영업이익률이 60%를 웃돌고 있다. 엔비디아 같은 반도체 설계기업은 막대한 설비투자 및 유지 비용이 들지 않는 까닭에 수익성이 높은 편이지만, 엔비디아는 압도적인 시장 점유율로 천문학적 이익을 남기고 있는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Jong-oh &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박종오 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:pjo2@hani.co.kr"&gt;pjo2@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240769.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503829.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Support Doubled for Large and Small/Medium Enterprises Jointly Entering the U.S. Market (대·중소기업 미국 동반 진출하면 지원 2배 확대)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240819.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Support Doubled for Large and Small/Medium Enterprises Jointly Entering the U.S. Market (대·중소기업 미국 동반 진출하면 지원 2배 확대)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120504145.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;미국 펜실베이니아주 필라델피아의 한화필리조선소. 한화오션 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has decided to provide support of up to 2 billion won over three years, double the previous level, when large enterprises and small/medium enterprises (SMEs) jointly enter the United States for investment projects. It will expand a win-win finance program where large enterprises and financial institutions contribute funds and guarantee institutions link up to support partners, and also establish a new corporate tax credit related to this. (대기업과 중소기업이 대미 투자프로젝트를 위해 미국에 동반 진출하면 정부가 기존의 2배 수준인 3년간 최대 20억원을 지원하기로 했다. 대기업·금융권이 출연하고 보증기관이 연계해 협력사 등을 지원하는 상생 금융 프로그램을 확대하고, 이와 관련한 법인세 세액공제도 신설한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government announced the 'Large and Small/Medium Enterprise Win-Win Growth Strategy' containing these measures, jointly prepared by relevant ministries, at an economic ministers' meeting chaired by Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance Choo Kyung-ho on the 21st. This plan is a follow-up implementation measure for the large/SME win-win tasks included in the '2026 Economic Growth Strategy' announced by the government on the 9th. (정부는 21일 구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관 주재로 열린 경제관계장관회의에서 관계부처 합동으로 이 같은 내용의 ‘대·중소기업 상생 성장전략’을 발표했다. 이번 대책은 정부가 지난 9일 발표한 ‘2026년 경제성장전략’에 담긴 대·중소기업 상생 관련 과제의 후속 이행 방안이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, the government decided to double its support when large enterprises and SMEs jointly enter the U.S. to pursue investment projects there. Previously, when large enterprises and SMEs jointly entered overseas markets for medium- to long-term projects, they could receive up to 1 billion won over three years. This will be increased to up to 2 billion won for entry into the U.S. and up to 1.5 billion won for other countries. A guarantee of up to 20 billion won will also be linked. Cooperative projects between large enterprises and SMEs will also receive preferential treatment in terms of limits and interest rates for export/order financing support from institutions like the Export-Import Bank of Korea, the Korea Development Bank, and the Korea Trade Insurance Corporation. (우선 정부는 대기업과 중소기업이 대미 투자프로젝트 추진을 위해 미국에 동반 진출하면 정부 지원을 기존의 2배 수준으로 확대하기로 했다. 기존에는 대·중소기업이 중장기 프로젝트로 국외에 동반 진출하면 3년간 최대 10억원을 지원했는데, 이를 미국 진출 시 최대 20억원, 그 외 국가는 최대 15억원으로 늘리기로 했다. 200억원 규모 보증도 연계한다. 대·중소기업 협력 프로젝트는 한국수출입은행·한국산업은행·한국무역보험공사 등의 수출·수주금융 지원에서 한도·금리 등도 우대받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The win-win finance program, where large enterprises and financial institutions contribute funds and guarantee institutions link up to support partners, will be supplied on a scale of 1.7 trillion won. The win-win finance program where Hyundai Motor, Kia, Woori Bank, and Kookmin Bank contribute funds and the Korea Credit Guarantee Fund, Korea Technology Finance Corporation, and the Mutual Aid Association for Credit Guarantee Foundations guarantee, will be expanded from the original 1 trillion won to 1.3 trillion won. A 15 billion won win-win finance program where POSCO International contributes funds and the Korea Credit Guarantee Fund provides guarantees will be newly established this month. A 400 billion won preferential fund for the steel industry export supply chain, where POSCO and the Industrial Bank of Korea contribute funds and the Mutual Aid Association for Credit Guarantee Foundations provides guarantees, is already in operation this month. (대기업·금융권이 출연하고 보증기관이 연계해 협력사 등을 지원하는 상생 금융 프로그램은 1조7천억원 규모로 공급된다. 현대차·기아와, 우리·국민은행이 출연하고 신용보증기금·기술보증기금·무보 등이 보증하는 상생 금융 프로그램이 당초 1조원에서 1조3천억원 규모로 확대된다. 포스코인터내셔널이 출연하고 신보가 보증하는 150억원 규모의 상생 금융 프로그램은 이달 신설된다. 포스코·기업은행이 출연하고 무보가 보증하는 4천억원 규모의 철강산업 수출공급망 우대 자금도 이달 현재 시행 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In relation to this, a new tax credit system will be established to reduce corporate tax by 5-10% on contributions made by large enterprises, etc., to the Mutual Aid Association for Credit Guarantee Foundations for win-win cooperation. It was decided to grant a 5% reduction for contributions aimed at supporting mid-sized enterprises and a 10% reduction for contributions aimed at supporting SMEs until 2028. Currently, a 10% corporate tax reduction is applied to contributions to the Korea Credit Guarantee Fund and Korea Technology Finance Corporation for the purpose of supporting SMEs. (이와 관련해 대기업 등이 상생 협력을 위해 무보에 출연하는 경우 출연금의 5∼10%를 법인세에서 감면해주는 세액공제도 신설된다. 2028년까지 중견기업 지원 목적에 대해서는 5%, 중소기업 지원 목적에 대해서는 10% 감면하기로 했다. 현재 중소기업 지원 목적의 신보·기보 출연금에는 법인세 10%를 감면하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scale of the Win-Win Cooperation Fund, to which large enterprises, etc., contribute for co-prosperity with SMEs, will be formed to an annual average of over 300 billion won for the next five years (2026-2030). To this end, the proportion of government matching projects will be expanded, and tailored incentives such as preferential evaluation in win-win related assessments will be given to financial companies and defense system companies (large enterprises). The plan is to expand the usage of contribution support from being primarily for partners to the entire ecosystem, including support for non-partners. (대기업 등이 중소기업과의 동반성장을 위해 출연하는 상생협력기금 규모는 향후 5년간(2026∼2030년) 연평균 3천억원 이상으로 조성한다. 이를 위해 정부매칭 사업 비중을 확대하고, 금융회사와 방산 체계기업(대기업)에는 상생 관련 평가 우대 등 맞춤형 인센티브를 부여한다. 출연금 지원 용도는 협력사 위주에서 비협력사 지원 등 생태계 전반으로 확대하겠다는 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, a 'Strategic Export Finance Fund' will be newly established to support large-scale, long-term export projects while investing a portion of the beneficiary companies' profits into SMEs and mid-sized enterprises, etc., and the enabling law will be enacted within the first half of the year. To supplement the weak negotiating power of individual SMEs, the Small and Medium Enterprise Cooperatives Act will be revised within the first half of the year to establish a system where SME cooperatives can have the right to request negotiations and discuss transaction terms, etc., with large enterprises. Within the second half of this year, the Small and Medium Enterprise Technology Protection Act will be revised to pursue imposing fines of up to 5 billion won for serious illegal acts of technology theft. (이 밖에 대규모·장기 수출 프로젝트를 지원하면서 수혜기업의 이익 일부를 중소·중견기업 등에 투자하는 ‘전략수출금융기금’을 신설하고 상반기 중 근거법을 제정한다. 개별 중소기업의 열악한 협상력을 보완하기 위해 상반기 중 중소기업협동조합법을 개정해 중소기업협동조합이 협의요청권을 갖고 대기업 등과 거래조건 등을 협의할 수 있는 제도 마련을 추진한다. 올해 하반기 중에는 중소기업기술보호법을 개정해 기술탈취 중대 위법행위에 대해 최대 50억원의 과징금 부과를 추진한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To monitor the progress of these tasks, the government decided to newly establish a 'Public-Private Joint Win-Win Cooperation Review Meeting' chaired by the President, with participation from the government, the Commission on Shared Growth for Large and Small Companies, major large enterprises, and cooperating SMEs. (정부는 이 같은 과제 추진을 점검하기 위해 정부와 동반성장위원회, 주요 대기업 및 협력 중소기업 등이 참석하는 대통령 주재 ‘민관합동 상생협력 점검회의’를 신설하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yun-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240819.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120504145.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exports from January 1-20 Hit 'All-Time High'... Boosted by 70% Semiconductor Increase (1월 1∼20일 수출 ‘역대 최대’…반도체 70% 증가에 힘입어)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240834.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Exports from January 1-20 Hit 'All-Time High'... Boosted by 70% Semiconductor Increase (1월 1∼20일 수출 ‘역대 최대’…반도체 70% 증가에 힘입어)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/382/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121500623.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;경기도 평택항에 수출용 컨테이너가 쌓여 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Korea's exports from January 1 to 20 this year recorded their highest performance for the period, boosted by strong semiconductor performance. (올해 1월 1~20일까지 한국 수출이 반도체 호조에 힘입어 동기 최대 실적을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Customs Service announced on the 21st that, based on preliminary figures for import and export trends from the 1st to the 20th of this month, exports amounted to $36.4 billion, a 14.9% increase compared to the same period last year. This is the highest figure ever recorded for the period (January 1-20). The daily average export amount, adjusted for the number of working days (14.5 days), was $2.51 billion, also a 14.9% increase from a year ago. (관세청은 이달 1~20일 수출입 현황 잠정치를 집계한 결과 수출액이 364억달러로 전년 동기 대비 14.9% 증가했다고 21일 밝혔다. 동기간(1월 1~20일)으로 보면 역대 최대다. 조업일수(14.5일)를 고려한 일평균 수출액은 25억1천만달러로 역시 1년 전보다 14.9% 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semiconductors, a key item, led the export growth with a sharp increase of 70.2% compared to the same period last year. The share of semiconductors in total exports also rose to 29.5%, up 9.6 percentage points from a year ago (19.9%). Petroleum products (17.6%) and wireless communication devices (47.6%) also showed growth. On the other hand, passenger cars (-10.8%) and auto parts (-11.8%) declined. (주요 품목인 반도체가 전년 동기 대비 70.2%나 늘며 수출 증가세를 이끌었다. 전체 수출에서 반도체가 차지하는 비중도 29.5%로 1년 전(19.9%)보다 9.6%포인트 늘었다. 석유제품(17.6%), 무선통신기기(47.6%)도 증가세를 보였다. 반면 승용차(-10.8%), 자동차 부품(-11.8%) 등은 감소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By export destination, exports increased to China (30.2%), the United States (19.3%), and Vietnam (25.3%), while decreasing to the European Union (-14.8%) and Japan (-13.3%). The combined export share of the top three countries (China, the U.S., and Vietnam) was 52.1%. (수출국은 중국(30.2%), 미국(19.3%), 베트남(25.3%)에서 증가하고 유럽연합(-14.8%), 일본(-13.3%)에서 감소했다. 상위 3국(중국·미국·베트남)의 수출 비중은 52.1%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the same period, imports amounted to $37.0 billion, a 4.2% increase compared to the same period last year. Imports increased for semiconductors (13.1%) and semiconductor manufacturing equipment (42.3%), while decreasing for crude oil (-10.7%), gas (-23.1%), and machinery (-0.7%). Among import origins, imports increased from China (3.1%), the United States (5.3%), and the European Union (26.6%), while decreasing from Japan (-0.1%). (같은 기간 수입액은 370억달러로 전년 동기 대비 4.2% 증가했다. 반도체(13.1%), 반도체 제조장비(42.3%)에서 증가하고 원유(-10.7%), 가스(-23.1%), 기계류(-0.7%) 등에서 감소했다. 수입국 중에선 중국(3.1%), 미국(5.3%), 유럽연합(26.6%)에서 증가하고 일본(-0.1%)에선 감소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trade balance recorded a deficit of $600 million, as imports exceeded exports. (무역수지는 수입액이 수출액보다 커 6억달러 적자를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240834.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/382/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121500623.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sahmyook University Professor Yang Min-gyu's Team Develops 'SOM Device' for Next-Generation CXL Memory (삼육대 양민규 교수팀, 차세대 CXL 메모리용 ‘SOM 소자’ 개발)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240841.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sahmyook University Professor Yang Min-gyu's Team Develops 'SOM Device' for Next-Generation CXL Memory (삼육대 양민규 교수팀, 차세대 CXL 메모리용 ‘SOM 소자’ 개발)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/400/imgdb/original/2026/0121/491768958130582.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;왼쪽부터 삼육대 인공지능융합학부 인공지능반도체공정연구실 양민규 교수(교신저자), 서현규 연구원(제1저자). 서 연구원은 삼육대에서 학·석사 과정을 마친 뒤 현재 서울대 재료공학과 박사과정에서 연구를 이어가고 있다.삼육대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A research team led by Professor Yang Min-gyu from the Artificial Intelligence Semiconductor Process Research Lab in the Department of Artificial Intelligence Convergence at Sahmyook University has developed a Selector-Only Memory (SOM) device suitable for CXL (Compute Express Link) memory, a key technology attracting attention for next-generation high-performance computing environments, and has demonstrated its stable operation at a large-scale array level.&lt;br/&gt;This research achievement was officially published in the January issue of 'Materials Science &amp; Engineering R (IF=26.8)', the world's most influential top-tier review journal in the field of materials and electronic devices, receiving international recognition for its academic and technological importance.&lt;br/&gt;The title of the published paper is 'Selector-Only-Memory Device Using Chalcogenide Thin Film in a 4k Crossbar Array', with Professor Yang Min-gyu serving as the corresponding author and Researcher Seo Hyeon-gyu as the first author. Researcher Seo completed his bachelor's and master's degrees at Sahmyook University and is currently continuing his research in the doctoral program at Seoul National University's Department of Materials Science and Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;Link to the paper▷https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0927796X25002475&lt;br/&gt;The research team implemented a chalcogenide (GSST) thin-film-based SOM device, proving that stable memory operation is possible while eliminating the separate selector device that was previously essential in conventional memory structures. SOM is a structure that maintains volatility in current characteristics while allowing non-volatile adjustment of the threshold voltage (Vth), and is evaluated as a technology suitable for next-generation memory environments requiring high density and low power characteristics.&lt;br/&gt;Particularly, in this research, the team precisely analyzed the operating mechanism of SOM and discovered that the change in threshold voltage is caused by a change in electron trap depth, not by the previously known ion movement. This result clearly presents the fundamental operating principle of SOM and provides an important theoretical foundation for future research on material and process optimization and device reliability improvement.&lt;br/&gt;The research team integrated the developed SOM device into a 4k (64×64) crossbar array and demonstrated △endurance of over 2×10⁷ cycles △stable data retention at 85°C △array operation yield of over 95%.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, they implemented 3-bit (8-state) multi-bit operation in a single device, showing that storage density can be dramatically improved. This is evaluated as an achievement that experimentally proves the potential for expansion into CXL-based Storage Class Memory and memory pooling structures, going beyond simple device performance verification.&lt;br/&gt;While research and development on next-generation CXL memory technology is actively underway, led by global major semiconductor companies, this research is drawing attention as a promising candidate for next-generation memory device technology in preparation for the post-CXL era.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Yang Min-gyu stated, "Next-generation memory technology requires a paradigm shift across the entire computing structure, beyond simple storage devices," and added, "This research suggests the direction for device technology applicable in next-generation memory environments where high density, low power, and scalability are simultaneously required."&lt;br/&gt;This research achievement is expected to expand into various next-generation semiconductor application fields such as AI accelerator memory, Compute-in-Memory (CIM), and neuromorphic systems, and is evaluated as research that can elevate the competitiveness of domestic memory and system semiconductor research by a step.&lt;br/&gt;This research was conducted with support from the National Research and Development Project in the Nano/Materials field promoted by the Ministry of Science and ICT and the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF). The research involved participation from the research team of Professor Kim Geon-hwan from Yonsei University's Department of System Semiconductor Engineering and the research team of Professor Park Min-hyeok from Seoul National University's Department of Materials Science and Engineering. (삼육대 인공지능융합학부 인공지능반도체공정연구실 양민규 교수 연구팀이 차세대 고성능 컴퓨팅 환경의 핵심 기술로 주목받는 CXL(Compute Express Link) 메모리에 적합한 셀렉터-온리 메모리(Selector-Only Memory, SOM) 소자를 개발하고, 대규모 어레이 수준에서의 안정적인 동작을 실증했다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 연구 성과는 재료·전자소자 분야에서 세계적으로 가장 영향력 있는 최상위 리뷰 저널인 ‘머티리얼즈 사이언스 &amp;amp; 엔지니어링-R(Materials Science &amp;amp; Engineering R, IF=26.8)에 1월자로 공식 게재되며, 기술의 학술적·기술적 중요성을 국제적으로 인정받았다.&lt;br/&gt;게재 논문의 제목은 ‘Selector-Only-Memory Device Using Chalcogenide Thin Film in a 4k Crossbar Array(4k 크로스바 어레이에서 칼코게나이드 박막을 이용한 셀렉터 전용 메모리 소자)’로, 양민규 교수가 교신저자, 서현규 연구원이 제1저자로 참여했다. 서 연구원은 삼육대에서 학·석사 과정을 마친 뒤 현재 서울대 재료공학과 박사과정에서 연구를 이어가고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;논문 바로가기▷https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0927796X25002475&lt;br/&gt;연구팀은 칼코게나이드(GSST) 박막 기반 SOM 소자를 구현해, 기존 메모리 구조에서 필수적으로 요구되던 별도의 셀렉터 소자를 제거하면서도 안정적인 메모리 동작이 가능함을 입증했다. SOM은 전류 특성에서는 휘발성을 유지하면서도 임계전압(Vth)을 비휘발적으로 조절할 수 있는 구조로, 고집적·저전력 특성이 요구되는 차세대 메모리 환경에 적합한 기술로 평가된다.&lt;br/&gt;특히 이번 연구에서는 SOM의 동작 메커니즘을 정밀 분석해, 임계전압 변화가 기존에 알려진 이온 이동이 아닌 전자 트랩 깊이 변화에 의해 발생함을 규명했다. 이는 SOM의 근본적인 작동 원리를 명확히 제시한 결과로, 향후 소재 및 공정 최적화, 소자 신뢰성 향상 연구를 위한 중요한 이론적 기반을 제공한다.&lt;br/&gt;연구팀은 개발한 SOM 소자를 4k(64×64) 크로스바 어레이로 집적해 △2×10⁷회 이상의 내구성 △85℃ 조건에서의 안정적인 데이터 유지 △95% 이상의 어레이 동작 수율을 실증했다.&lt;br/&gt;또한 단일 소자에서 3비트(8상태) 멀티비트 동작을 구현해, 저장 밀도를 획기적으로 향상시킬 수 있음을 보여줬다. 이는 단순한 소자 성능 검증을 넘어, CXL 기반 저장계층메모리(Storage Class Memory) 및 메모리 풀링 구조로의 확장 가능성을 실험적으로 입증한 성과로 평가된다. &lt;br/&gt;글로벌 대형 반도체 기업들을 중심으로 차세대 CXL 메모리 기술에 대한 연구·개발이 활발히 진행되고 있는 가운데, 이번 연구는 CXL 이후 세대를 대비한 유력한 차세대 메모리 소자 기술 후보로 주목받고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;양민규 교수는 “차세대 메모리 기술은 단순한 저장 소자를 넘어 컴퓨팅 구조 전반의 패러다임 변화를 요구한다”며 “이번 연구는 고집적·저전력·확장성이 동시에 요구되는 차세대 메모리 환경에서 적용 가능한 소자 기술의 방향성을 제시한 것”이라고 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 연구 성과는 향후 AI 가속기용 메모리, 컴퓨트-인-메모리(CIM), 뉴로모픽 시스템 등 다양한 차세대 반도체 응용 분야로의 확장이 기대되며, 국내 메모리 및 시스템반도체 연구 경쟁력을 한 단계 끌어올릴 수 있는 연구로 평가된다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 연구는 과학기술정보통신부와 한국연구재단(NRF)이 추진하는 나노·소재 분야 국가연구개발사업의 지원을 받아 수행됐다. 연구에는 연세대 시스템반도체공학과 김건환 교수 연구팀, 서울대 재료공학과 박민혁 교수 연구팀이 함께 참여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sahmyook University (* 자료제공 :  삼육대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240841.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/400/imgdb/original/2026/0121/491768958130582.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Wonkwang Digital University Real Estate Department Holds Special Lecture 'Everything About Brokerage Practice for Beginner Licensed Real Estate Agents' (원광디지털대 부동산학과, '초보 공인중개사를 위한 중개 실무의 모든 것' 특강 진행)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240846.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Wonkwang Digital University Real Estate Department Holds Special Lecture 'Everything About Brokerage Practice for Beginner Licensed Real Estate Agents' (원광디지털대 부동산학과, '초보 공인중개사를 위한 중개 실무의 모든 것' 특강 진행)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/301768959419437.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;강남훈 학과장 (원광디지털대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University's Real Estate Department (Department Head Kang Nam-hoon) will hold a 'Special Lecture on Brokerage Practice for Beginner Licensed Real Estate Agents' at its Seoul Campus at 3 PM on February 3rd. (원광디지털대학교 부동산학과(학과장 강남훈)는 오는 2월3일 15시에 ‘초보 공인중개사를 위한 중개 실무 특강’을 서울캠퍼스에서 진행한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This special lecture is aimed at licensed real estate agents who have recently passed the qualification exam but lack practical experience, causing them to delay opening their own business or feel apprehensive. It will introduce practice-essential content centered on real cases and present solutions for each case. (이번 특강은 최근에 공인중개사 자격시험에 합격하였으나 실무 경험이 부족하여 개업을 미루거나 두려움이 있는 공인중개사를 대상으로 실무에 필요한 내용을 사례 중심으로 소개하고 사례별 해결책을 제시하는 내용으로 진행한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lectures will be conducted by Professors Hyun Moon-gil and Kang Nam-hoon, who have extensive real estate practical experience. (강의는 부동산 실무 경험이 풍부한 현문길 교수와 강남훈 교수가 맡는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Hyun Moon-gil of the Real Estate Department has numerous educational experiences, including serving as △ a professor for the Korea Association of Licensed Real Estate Agents' Buyer Application Agent program, △ a professor for practical training and real estate consulting, △ a professor for auction experts and advanced courses, and △ the auction professor for the RIA Real Estate Investment Analyst highest-level course. (부동산학과 현문길 교수는 △한국공인중개사협회 매수신청대리인 교수 △실무교육·부동산컨설팅 교수 △경매전문가 및 심화과정 교수 △RIA 부동산투자분석사 최고위과정 경매담당교수 등으로 다수의 교육 경험을 가지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Kang Nam-hoon has served in roles such as △ a director of the Korea Real Estate Policy Association, △ a full member of the Korean Society of Land and City Planning, △ a member of the Incheon Metropolitan City Urban Regeneration Committee, and △ a member of the Incheon Metropolitan City Redevelopment Selection Committee. He currently serves as the head of Wonkwang Digital University's Real Estate Department. (강남훈 교수는 △한국부동산정책학회 이사 △대한국토·도시계획학회 정회원 △인천광역시 도시재생위원회 위원 △인천광역시 재개발 선정위원 등으로 활동하며, 현재 원광디지털대 부동산학과 학과장을 맡고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those wishing to participate in the special lecture can apply via a Google Form (&lt;a href="https://forms.gle/stLdJFHHoL9ZuxPB9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://forms.gle/stLdJFHHoL9ZuxPB9&lt;/a&gt;). The application quota is 30 people on a first-come, first-served basis. Applicants' registration is completed after approval by the department, and individual notifications will follow. (특강 참가 희망자는 구글폼(&lt;a href="https://forms.gle/stLdJFHHoL9ZuxPB9" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;https://forms.gle/stLdJFHHoL9ZuxPB9&lt;/a&gt;)을 통해 신청할 수 있고 신청 정원은 선착순 30명이다. 신청자는 학과의 승인을 거쳐 접수가 완료되며, 추후 개별 안내된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Department Head Kang Nam-hoon said, "I hope this practical training on rights analysis for beginner licensed real estate agents becomes an opportunity for them to more deeply understand the field of rights analysis, which beginner agents must know, and to develop practical competencies that can be immediately applied in the field, by learning the knowledge essential for agents in practice in an easy-to-understand way." (강남훈 학과장은 “초보 공인중개사를 위한 권리분석 실무 교육은 공인중개사들이 실무에서 반드시 필요한 지식을 이해하기 쉽게 학습함으로써 초보 공인중개사들이 반드시 알아야 할 권리분석 분야를 보다 깊이 이해하고, 실무에 바로 적용할 수 있는 실질적 역량을 키우는 계기가 되길 바란다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240846.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/301768959419437.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cyber University of Foreign Studies (CUFS) Japanese Studies Department Successfully Completes 2025 Academic Year Winter Short-term Overseas History and Culture Exploration Program in Kumamoto Prefecture, Japan (사이버한국외국어대학교 일본어학부, 일본 구마모토현에서 2025학년도 동계 단기 해외역사문화탐방 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240852.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies (CUFS) Japanese Studies Department Successfully Completes 2025 Academic Year Winter Short-term Overseas History and Culture Exploration Program in Kumamoto Prefecture, Japan (사이버한국외국어대학교 일본어학부, 일본 구마모토현에서 2025학년도 동계 단기 해외역사문화탐방 성료)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/463/imgdb/original/2026/0121/8117689598796869.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;▲ 사이버한국외국어대학교 일본어학부는 1월 8일부터 3박 4일간 일본 구마모토현 일대에서 2025학년도 동계 단기 해외역사문화탐방을 성료했다.사이버한국외대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies (CUFS, Acting President Kim Byeong-cheol) announced that its Japanese Studies Department successfully conducted the 2025 academic year winter short-term overseas history and culture exploration program over three nights and four days from January 8th to 11th. &lt;br/&gt;CUFS's short-term overseas culture exploration is an extracurricular program that utilizes vacation periods to visit foreign countries and examine their history and culture. With faculty members from the major accompanying the entire schedule and including time for cultural exchange with local university students, participants can experience aspects of local life difficult to encounter on ordinary trips, leading to high student satisfaction. This overseas culture exploration, themed 'The History and Culture of Christianity in Japan,' was led by CUFS Japanese Studies Department Head Jeong Hyeon-hyeok and Professor Yun Ho-sook, with 36 enrolled students participating. &lt;br/&gt;The exploration group visited Kumamoto Prefecture, located in central Kyushu, Japan, touring Kumamoto City, Amakusa City, Aso City, and other areas in sequence to broaden their understanding of Japan. Kumamoto Prefecture is a region possessing historic sites like Kumamoto Castle and Suizenji Jojuen Garden, as well as diverse natural and cultural resources including Mt. Aso, which features one of the world's largest caldera topographies. It is also evaluated as a suitable place for a three-dimensional understanding of Japanese history and culture as it includes the Amakusa region, which holds the history of the introduction and suppression of Christianity in Japan and the 'Hidden Christians' (Kakure Kirishitan). &lt;br/&gt;Before departing for Japan, participating students attended several pre-departure meetings where they watched the film "Silence (2016)" (based on the novel by Shusaku Endo) and attended related lectures, building background knowledge on the process of Christianity's introduction to Japan and the 'Hidden Christians' who continued their faith in secret despite persecution. Based on this, they were able to directly encounter sites of Japanese Christian history at places like the Kirishitan Museum and cemetery in the Amakusa region, the Collegio and Rosario buildings, and the Sakitsu settlement, a UNESCO World Heritage site. Subsequently, in Kumamoto City, they visited Kumamoto Castle, considered one of Japan's three great castles, and Suizenji Jojuen Garden, designated as a National Place of Scenic Beauty, to examine Japanese castle culture and traditional garden styles. In Aso City, they toured the Daikanbo Observatory, the crater of Mt. Aso, and Kusasenri, experiencing the grand nature of the Aso region where an active volcano and grasslands harmonize.&lt;br/&gt;One participating student shared their impressions, saying, "Through this exploration of Kumamoto Prefecture, I learned about a part of Japanese history that is difficult to easily understand and properly felt the essence of Japanese culture." Professor Jeong Hyeon-hyeok, Head of the CUFS Japanese Studies Department, added, "This exploration was operated as a process of directly confirming the theoretical understanding built through pre-learning on-site, so it must have been an even more meaningful time for the students," and stated, "We will continue to operate field-centered programs linked to major education and enhance students' major competencies and cultural understanding."&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, CUFS is recruiting new and transfer students for the first semester of the 2026 academic year from Wednesday, January 28th to Thursday, February 12th. It will select freshmen and transfer students for the second and third years across ten departments: ▲English Studies ▲Chinese Studies ▲Japanese Studies ▲Korean Studies ▲Spanish Studies ▲Vietnamese &amp; Indonesian Studies ▲Business Administration ▲Industrial Safety &amp; Housing Management ▲Counseling Psychology ▲K-Beauty Studies. Anyone with a high school diploma or higher qualification is eligible to apply. Detailed information can be found on the university's admissions support center website (go.cufs.ac.kr), and inquiries can be made by phone (02-2173-2580), KakaoTalk (cufs), or email (ipsi@cufs.ac.kr). (사이버한국외국어대학교(총장직무대행 김병철) 일본어학부는 지난 1월 8일부터 11일까지 3박 4일간 2025학년도 동계 단기 해외역사문화탐방을 성공적으로 진행했다고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;사이버한국외대의 단기 해외문화탐방은 방학 기간을 활용해 해외를 방문, 각국의 역사와 문화를 살펴보는 비교과 프로그램이다. 전공 교수진이 전체 일정에 동행하며 해당국 대학생들과 함께하는 문화 교류의 시간도 마련되는 등 일반적인 여행에서는 접하기 힘든 현지의 생활상을 경험할 수 있어 학생들의 만족도가 높다. ‘일본 기독교의 역사와 문화’를 주제로 진행된 이번 해외문화탐방은 사이버한국외대 정현혁 일본어학부장과 윤호숙 교수가 인솔을 맡은 가운데 재학생 36명이 참여했다. &lt;br/&gt;탐방단은 일본 규슈 중부에 위치한 구마모토현을 찾아 구마모토시와 아마쿠사시, 아소시 등을 차례로 탐방하며 일본에 대한 식견을 넓혔다. 구마모토현은 구마모토성과 스이젠지 조주엔 등 유서 깊은 역사 유적과 함께 세계 최대급 칼데라 지형을 품은 아소산을 비롯해 다양한 자연·문화 자원을 보유한 지역이다. 또한 일본 기독교의 전래와 탄압, 잠복 기리시탄의 역사가 남아 있는 아마쿠사 지역을 포함하고 있어 일본의 역사와 문화를 입체적으로 이해하기에 적합한 곳으로 평가된다. &lt;br/&gt;탐방에 참가한 학생들은 일본으로 떠나기 전 여러 차례의 사전 모임을 통해 영화 「침묵(Silence, 2016)」(엔도슈사쿠 원작)을 감상하고 관련 강의를 듣는 등 일본 기독교 전래 과정과, 탄압 속에서도 숨어서 신앙을 이어간 신자들인 ‘잠복 기리시탄’에 대한 배경 지식을 쌓았다. 이를 바탕으로 이들은 아마쿠사 지역의 기리시탄관 및 묘지, 코레지오관·로자리오관, 세계문화유산 사키쓰 취락 등에서 일본 기독교 역사의 현장을 직접 마주할 수 있었다. 이어 구마모토시에서는 일본 3대 명성 중 하나로 꼽히는 구마모토성과 국가 명승으로 지정된 스이젠지 조주엔을 방문해 일본의 성곽 문화와 전통 정원 양식을 살펴봤으며, 아소시에서는 다이칸보 전망대, 아소산 분화구, 쿠사센리 등을 둘러보며 활화산과 초원이 어우러진 아소 지역의 대자연을 체험했다.&lt;br/&gt;탐방에 참여한 한 학생은 “일본의 역사 중에서도 쉽게 알기 어려운 부분을 이번 구마모토현 탐방을 통해 배웠고 일본 문화의 정수를 제대로 느꼈다”라고 소감을 전했다. 사이버한국외국어대학교 일본어학부장 정현혁 교수는 “이번 탐방은 사전 학습을 통해 쌓은 이론적 이해를 현장에서 직접 확인하는 과정으로 운영했기에 학생들에게 더욱 의미 깊은 시간이었을 것”이라며 “앞으로도 전공 교육과 연계한 현장 중심 프로그램을 지속적으로 운영하며 학생들의 전공 역량과 문화적 이해를 높여 나가겠다”라고 덧붙였다.&lt;br/&gt;한편 사이버한국외대는 오는 1월 28일(수)부터 2월 12일(목)까지 2026학년도 1학기 신·편입생을 모집한다. ▲영어학부 ▲중국어학부 ▲일본어학부 ▲한국어학부 ▲스페인어학부 ▲베트남·인도네시아학부 ▲경영학부 ▲산업안전·주택관리학부 ▲상담심리학부 ▲K뷰티학부 등 10개 학부에서 신입생과 2학년 및 3학년 편입생을 선발하며 고등학교 졸업 이상의 학력 보유자라면 누구나 지원이 가능하다. 자세한 내용은 대학 입학지원센터(go.cufs.ac.kr)에서 확인할 수 있고, 궁금한 점은 전화(02-2173-2580)나 카카오톡(cufs), 이메일(ipsi@cufs.ac.kr)로 문의하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Cyber University of Foreign Studies (* 자료제공 :  사이버한국외국어대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240852.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/463/imgdb/original/2026/0121/8117689598796869.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gwangju to Become 'Korea's San Francisco'... 200 Autonomous Vehicles to Roam the City Center (광주, ‘한국판 샌프란시스코’로…자율주행차 200대 도심 누빈다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240856.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Gwangju to Become 'Korea's San Francisco'... 200 Autonomous Vehicles to Roam the City Center (광주, ‘한국판 샌프란시스코’로…자율주행차 200대 도심 누빈다)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/333/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501324.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;미국 샌프란시스코에서 무인 자율주행 형태로 운영되고 있는 ‘로보택시’. 웨이모 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gwangju Metropolitan City has been selected as the site for the nation's first autonomous driving demonstration city, set to become 'Korea's San Francisco.' The government plans to deploy 200 demonstration vehicles in Gwangju, a mix of urban and rural areas, to accelerate the advancement of autonomous driving technology. It has also decided to create an autonomous driving ecosystem, which includes relaxing regulations across the entire city, collecting large-scale driving data, and fostering specialized talent. (‘한국판 샌프란시스코’가 될 국내 첫 자율주행 실증도시에 광주광역시가 선정됐다. 정부는 대도시와 농촌이 섞인 광주에 실증 차량 200대를 투입해 자율주행 기술 고도화를 촉진한다는 방침이다. 도시 전역에 관련 규제를 풀고, 대규모 주행 데이터 수집부터 특화 인재 양성까지 이어지는 자율주행 생태계도 조성하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport announced on the 21st, through its 'Plan to Promote Autonomous Driving Demonstration Cities,' that it will operate the entire area of Gwangju as a demonstration space for autonomous vehicles. This is a follow-up measure to the government's announcement last year that it would pursue the 'commercialization of Level 4 autonomous vehicles by 2027.' Autonomous driving levels are divided into six stages from Level 0 (fully manual) to Level 5 (fully autonomous). The government plans to elevate domestic autonomous driving technology, currently at Level 3 (autonomous driving possible on highways, etc., but driver intervention required in specific situations like weather anomalies), to Level 4 (autonomous driving possible on most roads without driver intervention). (국토교통부는 21일 ‘자율주행 실증도시 추진방안’을 통해 광주 전역을 자율주행차 실증공간으로 운영한다고 밝혔다. 지난해 정부가 ‘2027년 레벨4 자율주행차 상용화’를 추진하겠다고 한 데 따른 후속 조처다. 자율주행 단계는 레벨0(완전수동)부터 레벨5(완전 자율주행)까지 6단계로 나뉘는데, 정부는 현재 레벨3(고속도로 등에서 자율주행이 가능하지만 기상이변 등 특정 상황에서 운전자 개입이 필요한 수준) 단계인 국내 자율주행 기술을 레벨4(대부분의 도로에서 자율주행이 가능하며 운전자 개입이 불필요한 수준)로 끌어올린다는 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To this end, the government stated it will designate the entire city of Gwangju as an autonomous driving testbed and embark on large-scale real-road demonstrations. Previously, autonomous driving pilot operation zones were operated at 55 locations across 17 cities and provinces nationwide. However, many were on highways without pedestrians or traffic signals, and demonstrations were only possible outside of commuting hours, limiting learning for various exceptional situations (edge cases). In Gwangju, like in San Francisco, USA, and Wuhan, China, 24-hour demonstrations will be possible across the entire city. The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport said, "By designating the entire city as a pilot operation zone at once, diverse edge case learning is needed from alleys to overpasses, underpasses, and intersections," adding, "Gwangju is a large city with a population of over 1.3 million and has mixed urban and rural characteristics, making large-scale demonstrations in various environments possible." (정부는 이를 위해 광주 전체를 자율주행 테스트베드로 지정하고 대규모 실도로 실증에 나선다고 밝혔다. 그동안 전국 17개 시·도 55곳에 자율주행 시범운행지구를 운영했지만, 상당수가 보행자나 신호등이 없는 고속도로인 데다 출퇴근 시간이 아닌 시간에만 실증이 가능해서 다양한 예외적 상황(엣지 케이스)에 대한 학습에 한계가 있었다. 광주에서는 미국 샌프란시스코·중국 우한처럼 도시 전역에서 24시간 실증이 가능해진다. 국토부는 “도시 전역을 시범운행지구로 일괄 지정해 골목길부터 고가도로, 지하차도, 교차로 등에서 다양한 엣지케이스 학습이 필요하다”며 “광주는 인구 130만명 이상의 대도시이면서 도·농 복합적 특성을 보유해, 다양한 환경에서의 대규모 실증이 가능할 것으로 보인다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this purpose, the government will hold a public contest in early February and select about three autonomous driving companies by April to distribute 200 dedicated demonstration vehicles. The plan is to distribute vehicles differentially based on the selected companies' technological levels and have them operate on actual roads used by citizens, including general roads, residential areas, city centers, and night environments. Selected companies will receive support not only for vehicles but also for learning data necessary for technology development, technology/operation control, and dedicated insurance. (이를 위해 정부는 2월 초 공모를 진행해 4월 안에 3개 안팎의 자율주행 기업을 선정해 실증 전용 차량 200대를 배분하기로 했다. 선정 기업의 기술 수준에 따라 차량을 차등배분해 일반 도로와 주택가·도심·야간 환경 등 실제 시민 생활도로에서 운행하도록 한다는 방침이다. 선정된 기업은 차량뿐 아니라 기술 개발에 필요한 학습데이터, 기술·운영관제, 전용보험 등 지원을 받게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, considering it is still a technology development stage, demonstrations will be conducted step by step. This year, demonstrations will first be conducted in new towns and city outskirts with low traffic volume and good infrastructure (parts of Gwangsan-gu, Buk-gu, and Seo-gu). Starting next year, the demonstration area will be expanded to old towns and city centers with heavy traffic (all of Nam-gu, Dong-gu, and Seo-gu). The demonstration method will also proceed in stages according to the participating companies' technological levels: test driver in the driver's seat (Stage 1) → test driver in the passenger seat (Stage 2) → unmanned (Stage 3). Companies failing to meet standards will have their vehicles reduced or must return them. (다만 아직 기술개발 단계임을 고려해 실증은 단계적으로 이뤄질 예정이다. 올해는 교통량이 적고 인프라가 양호한 신시가지·도심 외곽(광산구, 북구, 서구 일부)에서 우선 실증하고 내년부터 교통량이 많은 구시가지·도심(남구, 동구, 서구 전역)으로 실증구역을 확대하기로 했다. 실증 방식도 참여 기업의 기술 수준에 따라 시험운전자가 운전석에 탑승(1단계)→시험운전자가 조수석에 탑승(2단계)→무인(3단계) 순으로 진행하며, 기준에 미달한 기업은 차량을 축소 또는 반납해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An autonomous driving regulatory sandbox, designating the entire city of Gwangju as a special regulatory zone for autonomous driving, will also be operated. Through revisions to related laws, representative measures include: △ allowing autonomous driving companies to use video data collected for research and development without anonymization (mosaic processing), and △ relaxing regulations to allow autonomous driving even in traffic-vulnerable protection zones where only manual driving by drivers was previously permitted. Gwangju City will provide necessary facilities like laboratories for demonstrations and support industrial activation by forming an industry-academia-research council along with administrative and financial support. (광주 전체를 자율주행 규제특례 지역으로 하는 자율주행 샌드박스도 운영된다. 관련법 개정을 통해 △자율주행 업체가 연구·개발을 위해 수집하는 영상데이터는 가명 처리(모자이크 처리) 없이 사용할 수 있게 하고 △운전자의 수동주행만 가능한 교통약자 보호구역에서도 자율주행이 가능하도록 완화하는 것 등이 대표적이다. 광주시는 실증에 필요한 연구실 등을 제공하고, 행정·재정적 지원과 함께 산학연 협의체를 구성해 산업 활성화를 지원하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of Land, Infrastructure and Transport Kim Yun-deok said, "We plan to operate the entire city as a demonstration space but expand the scope step by step according to technological maturity," and urged, "If the autonomous driving technology level of the US and China is that of an adult, ours is at an elementary school level. Please make efforts to leap to the level of advanced countries quickly, thinking this is the last opportunity to overcome the autonomous driving technology gap." (김윤덕 국토부 장관은 “도시 전체를 실증 공간으로 운영하되 기술 성숙도에 따라 단계적으로 범위를 넓히는 방식으로 추진할 계획”이라며 “미국·중국의 자율주행 기술 수준이 성인이라면 우리는 초등학생 수준이다. 이번이 자율주행 기술격차를 극복할 수 있는 마지막 기회라는 생각으로 선진국 수준으로 빠르게 도약할 수 있도록 노력해달라”고 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240856.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/333/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501324.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Olive Young to Launch 'K-Beauty Zone' at Sephora... Kicks Off Global Expansion (올리브영, 세포라에 ‘K뷰티존’ 선보인다…글로벌 확장 시동)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1240864.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Olive Young to Launch 'K-Beauty Zone' at Sephora... Kicks Off Global Expansion (올리브영, 세포라에 ‘K뷰티존’ 선보인다…글로벌 확장 시동)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/646/388/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689626828996_20260121501532.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;씨제이올리브영이 연간 4회 진행하는 ‘올영세일’ 모습. 씨제이올리브영 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;CJ Olive Young is accelerating its global expansion by joining hands with Sephora, the world's largest cosmetics distribution channel. (씨제이(CJ)올리브영이 세계 최대 화장품 유통 채널인 세포라와 손잡고 세계 진출에 속도를 높인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Olive Young announced on the 20th that it has formed an official partnership with Sephora and will launch a directly curated 'K-Beauty Zone' on Sephora's online and offline channels. The K-Beauty Zone, established by Olive Young and Sephora, is scheduled to start in six regions including North America (USA, Canada) and major Asian countries in the second half of this year, and will later expand to Sephora stores worldwide, including the Middle East, the UK, and Australia. Olive Young will be responsible for the overall planning of the K-Beauty Zone, including product selection, display planning, and marketing direction, while Sephora will provide store space and handle local distribution and sales. (올리브영은 세포라와 공식 파트너십을 맺고, 직접 큐레이션한 ‘케이뷰티존’을 세포라의 온오프라인 채널에 선보인다고 20일 밝혔다. 올리브영과 세포라가 마련하는 케이뷰티존은 오는 하반기 북미(미국·캐나다)와 아시아 주요 국가 등 6개 지역을 시작으로, 중동·영국·호주 등 전 세계 세포라 매장으로 확대될 예정이다. 올리브영은 상품 구성과 매대 기획, 마케팅 방향 설정 등 케이뷰티존 기획 전반을 담당하고, 세포라는 매장 공간 제공과 현지 유통·판매를 맡는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The K-Beauty industry has been noted for its high proportion of small, medium, and indie brands, making entry into major overseas retail stores a challenge. Olive Young explained, "We pursued this collaboration with Sephora to lower the barriers to global entry for K-Beauty brands and accelerate their spread." Based on its experience operating large-scale marketing and promotions like the 'Olive Young Sale,' Olive Young plans to implement an integrated marketing strategy in the global market as well. In particular, it aims to maximize local market exposure for brands selected for the K-Beauty Zone by actively utilizing Sephora's marketing and sales infrastructure. Through this, domestic cosmetics brands are expected to directly meet local consumers to expand brand awareness and even explore plans to expand into other local distribution channels. (케이뷰티 산업은 중소·인디 브랜드 비중이 높아 국외의 주요한 소매점 진입이 한계로 거론돼왔다. 올리브영은 “케이뷰티 브랜드의 글로벌 진입 장벽을 낮추고 확산 속도를 낮추기 위해 세포라와의 협업을 추진했다” 고 설명했다. 올리브영은 ‘올영세일’ 등 대형 마케팅·프로모션 운영 경험을 바탕으로 세계 시장에서도 통합 마케팅 전략을 펼칠 계획이다. 특히 세포라의 마케팅·판매 기반을 적극 활용해 올리브영이 선정한 케이뷰티존에 포함된 브랜드의 현지 시장 노출을 극대화하겠다는 것이다. 이를 통해 국내 화장품 브랜드들은 현지 소비자와 직접 만나 인지도를 확대하고, 현지의 다른 유통 채널에 확장하는 기획까지 모색할 수 있을 것으로 기대된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Olive Young is also pushing forward with opening its own offline stores in the global market. It plans to open its first store in Pasadena, California, USA, in May. By simultaneously pursuing collaboration with Sephora and opening its own stores, the strategy is to gradually complete a 'K-Beauty global distribution infrastructure' that encompasses both online and offline channels. (한편, 올리브영은 직접 오프라인 매장 세계시장 출점도 추진하고 있다. 오는 5월 미국 캘리포니아주 패서디나에 1호점을 개점할 예정이다. 세포라의 협업과 자체 매장 출점을 동시에 추진하면서 온·오프라인을 아우르는 ‘케이뷰티 글로벌 유통 인프라’를 단계적으로 완성해 나간다는 전략이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Seo Hyemi, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서혜미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1240864.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/646/388/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689626828996_20260121501532.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Autonomous Driving Level 4 and Above Considered High-Impact AI"... AI Basic Act, a 'Testing Ground' for Balancing Innovation and Safety (“자율주행 4레벨 이상은 고영향 AI”…AI 기본법, 혁신·안전 균형 ‘시험대’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240869.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Autonomous Driving Level 4 and Above Considered High-Impact AI"... AI Basic Act, a 'Testing Ground' for Balancing Innovation and Safety (“자율주행 4레벨 이상은 고영향 AI”…AI 기본법, 혁신·안전 균형 ‘시험대’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/645/429/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501688.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;생성형 인공지능(AI) ‘챗지피티’(Chat GPT)에 “이 기사에 어울리는 이미지를 생성해주세요”라는 지시어를 입력해 생성한 이미지.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd of this month, the 'Framework Act on Artificial Intelligence Development and Trust-building' (AI Basic Act), which will become a new milestone for South Korea's artificial intelligence industry, will be fully implemented. The government's policy is to apply 'minimum necessary regulations' to the extent that they do not hinder industrial innovation, in order to catch both rabbits of AI technology 'development' and 'safety'. However, to ensure the system settles in, sanctions such as fact-finding and imposition of fines will be deferred for at least one year, and plans are in place to supplement the system by reflecting overseas regulatory trends and the level of technological development. (오는 22일 대한민국 인공지능 산업의 새 이정표가 될 ‘인공지능 발전과 신뢰 기반 조성 등에 관한 기본법’(인공지능 기본법)이 전면 시행된다. 정부는 인공지능 기술의 ‘발전’과 ‘안전’이라는 두 마리 토끼를 잡기 위해 산업 혁신을 저해하지 않는 선에서 ‘필요 최소한의 규제’를 적용한다는 방침이다. 다만, 제도 안착을 위해 사실 조사와 과태료 부과 등의 제재는 최소 1년간 유예하고, 해외 규제 동향과 기술 발전 수준을 반영해 제도를 보완할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Excluded from Regulation if Human Intervention Exists"... What are the Criteria for Judging High-Impact AI? (“사람 개입하면 규제 제외”…고영향 AI 판단 기준은?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The AI Basic Act establishes regulations centered on three main axes: transparency, safety, and high-impact (high-risk). Its most significant feature is the introduction of the concept of 'high-impact artificial intelligence' that can significantly affect fundamental human rights. Providers of high-impact AI will bear responsibilities such as establishing and operating risk management plans. The government has selected 10 sectors where the use of AI could have a major impact on people's lives or pose risks, such as energy, hiring, loan screening, and transportation. (인공지능 기본법은 크게 투명성·안전성·고영향(고위험) 등 세 가지 축을 중심으로 규제가 마련됐다. 가장 큰 특징은 인간의 기본권에 큰 영향을 미칠 수 있는 ‘고영향 인공지능’ 개념의 도입이다. 고영향 인공지능 제공 사업자는 위험관리방안의 수립·운영 등의 책무를 지게 된다. 정부는 에너지·채용·대출심사·교통 등 인공지능 활용으로 인해 국민 생활에 중대한 영향을 주거나 위험을 초래할 수 있는 10개 분야를 선정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among these, it was decided that only "fully automated AI systems without human intervention" would be judged as high-impact AI. For example, even if there is a possibility of discrimination due to biased AI criteria in hiring or loan screening processes, if a human intervenes at the final stage to control the outcome, it will not be subject to high-impact AI regulations. The Ministry of Science and ICT cited 'autonomous driving level 4 and above' systems as examples among currently commercialized technologies that meet this criterion. This means that only systems capable of judging all situations and driving on their own without driver intervention, even in emergencies, become subjects of strict management. Tesla's Full Self-Driving (FSD) feature, launched in Korea last November, is at level 2. (이 가운데 “사람이 개입하지 않는 전자동 인공지능 시스템”에 한해서만 고영향 인공지능으로 판단하기로 했다. 한 예로, 채용이나 대출심사 과정에서 인공지능의 편향된 기준으로 차별이 발생할 가능성이 있더라도, 최종 단계에서 사람이 개입해 결과를 통제할 수 있다면 고영향 인공지능 규제를 적용받지 않는다. 과학기술정보통신부는 현재 상용화된 기술 중 이런 기준에 부합하는 사례로 ‘자율주행 레벨4 이상’ 시스템을 꼽았다. 비상시에도 운전자 개입 없이 시스템이 모든 상황을 스스로 판단하고 주행하는 정도라야 엄격한 관리 대상이 된다는 의미다. 지난해 11월 한국에 출시된 테슬라의 완전자율주행(FSD) 기능은 레벨2 수준이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"This Was Made by AI"... Watermark Display Mandated (“이것은 AI가 만들었습니다”…워터마크 표시 의무화)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A change that users will immediately feel in their daily lives after the law's implementation is the 'transparency' regulation. From now on, photos, videos, etc., created within services using generative AI like ChatGPT, Gemini chatbots, or games must bear a mark (such as a watermark) indicating they are 'AI-generated content'. This applies regardless of whether it is deepfake or not, and is expected to be displayed in various forms such as on user screens or through audio. (이용자들이 법 시행 이후 일상에서 즉각적으로 체감할 변화는 ‘투명성’ 규제다. 앞으로 챗지피티(Chat GPT)와 제미나이 같은 챗봇, 게임 등 생성형 인공지능이 적용된 서비스 내에서 만들어진 사진·영상 등에는 반드시 ‘인공지능 생성물’임을 알리는 표시(워터마크 등)가 붙어야 한다. 이는 딥페이크 여부와 관계없이 적용되며, 이용자 화면이나 음성 등 다양한 형태로 표시될 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particularly, stricter standards apply when distributing AI-generated content to external platforms. When exporting deepfake creations, which meticulously manipulate a real person's face, voice, or actions using AI to appear genuine, to external platforms, they must be marked in a way that people can clearly perceive (visibly or audibly). However, to respect creative autonomy, 'non-visible markings' are also permitted for artistic expressions like movies or dramas. The intent is to prevent the spread of false information through deepfake distribution while guaranteeing freedom of content creation. (특히, 인공지능 생성물을 외부 플랫폼으로 유통할 땐 더 엄격한 기준이 적용된다. 인공지능을 이용해 실제 사람의 얼굴·목소리·행동을 정교하게 변조해 진짜처럼 보이게 만든 딥페이크 생성물을 외부로 반출할 경우, 사람이 명확하게 인식할 수 있는 방식(가시적·가청적)으로 표시해야 한다. 다만, 창작의 자율성을 존중해 영화나 드라마 같은 예술 표현물의 경우 눈에 보이지 않는 ‘비가시적 표시’도 허용하기로 했다. 딥페이크 유통에 따른 허위 정보 확산은 막으면서도, 콘텐츠 창작의 자유는 보장하겠다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Safety Regulations More Flexible Than the US, Giving the Industry Breathing Room (미국보다도 유연한 안전 규제, 산업계 숨통 트여)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Safety regulations have also been established to preemptively manage the potential risks of highly advanced AI. This is a clause imposing safety assurance obligations on high-performance (frontier) AI models with a cumulative computational scale of '10^26 floating-point operations (FLOP) or more'. It applies the same cumulative computational scale standard as the 'Frontier AI Transparency Act' implemented earlier this month in California, USA. Considering that the computational scale of the latest Big Tech models is currently around 10^15, there are virtually no models, domestic or foreign, that would immediately fall under this regulatory net. (고도로 발전한 인공지능의 잠재적 위험을 사전에 관리하기 위한 안전성 규제도 마련됐다. 누적 학습량 기준 ‘10의 26승 부동소수점 연산(FLOP) 이상’ 고성능(프론티어) 인공지능 모델에 대해 안전성 확보 의무를 부여하는 조항이다. 이달 초 미국 캘리포니아주에서 시행된 ‘프론티어 인공지능 투명법’과 동일한 누적 학습량 기준을 적용했다. 현재 빅테크 최신 모델의 학습량이 10의 15승 수준임을 고려하면, 당장 규제망에 걸리는 모델은 국내외 모두 전무한 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government went a step further and prepared the enforcement decree of the AI Basic Act to relax regulations if the safety of the technology is verified or the actual scale of social harm is judged to be not significant. (정부는 여기서 한발 더 나아가 기술의 안전성이 검증됐거나 실제 사회적 피해 규모가 크지 않다고 판단될 경우 규제를 완화하는 방향으로 인공지능 기본법 시행령을 마련했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Challenges Remain: 'Human Rights Protection' and Eliminating 'Regulatory Blind Spots' (과제는 ‘인권 보호’와 ‘규제 사각지대’ 해소)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there are still tasks to be solved. In December last year, the National Human Rights Commission of Korea submitted an opinion to the Ministry of Science and ICT stating that the enforcement decree of the AI Basic Act is biased towards industrial promotion and needs supplementation from a human rights protection perspective. The Commission suggested that specific domains of high-impact AI should be stipulated in the enforcement decree and that the high-performance AI threshold should be lowered to a level like the European Union's (EU) '10^25'. It also pointed out the need to expand the participation of human rights experts in the 'National AI Committee', the control tower for national AI policy. (하지만 해결해야 할 숙제도 남아 있다. 국가인권위원회는 지난해 12월 인공지능 기본법 시행령이 산업 진흥에 치우쳐 인권 보호 관점에서 보완이 필요하다는 의견을 과기정통부에 제시했다. 인권위는 고영향 인공지능의 구체적 영역을 시행령에 규정하고, 고성능 인공지능 기준을 유럽연합(EU)과 같은 ‘10의 25승’ 수준으로 하향 조정해야 한다는 의견을 냈다. 아울러 국가 인공지능 정책 컨트롤타워인 ‘국가인공지능위원회’에 인권 전문가 참여 확대 등이 필요하다고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the regulatory grace period, the Ministry of Science and ICT plans to operate an 'AI Basic Act Support Desk' to provide consulting for SMEs and startups, while continuously supplementing the law in line with overseas regulatory trends. Kim Kyung-man, Director of the AI Policy Office at the Ministry of Science and ICT, said at a press briefing on the 20th, "The work of amending and revising the AI Basic Act is open to make it more developed and complete," adding, "We will operate a consultative body with participation from industry, civic groups, academia, etc., to proceed with the revision work." (과기정통부는 규제 유예 기간 동안 ‘인공지능 기본법 지원 데스크’를 운영해 중소기업과 스타트업을 대상으로 컨설팅을 제공하는 한편, 해외 규제 동향에 맞춰 법안을 지속적으로 보완해 나갈 방침이다. 김경만 과기정통부 인공지능정책실장은 20일 기자 간담회에서 “인공지능 기본법이 보다 발전하고 완전할 수 있도록 재·개정 작업이 열려 있다”며 “산업계와 시민단체, 학계 등이 함께 참여해 논의하는 회의체를 운영해 개정 작업을 진행할 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Sun Dam, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (선담은 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240869.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/645/429/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501688.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Exchanging Documents for LTV Collusion"... 272 Billion Won in Fines Imposed on Kookmin, Shinhan, Woori, and Hana Banks (“서류 돌려가며 LTV 담합”…국민·신한·우리·하나은행에 과징금 2720억원)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240871.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Exchanging Documents for LTV Collusion"... 272 Billion Won in Fines Imposed on Kookmin, Shinhan, Woori, and Hana Banks (“서류 돌려가며 LTV 담합”…국민·신한·우리·하나은행에 과징금 2720억원)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/318/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501692.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;4개 시중은행의 간판. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Four commercial banks have been fined a total of 272 billion won for colluding by exchanging information related to the Loan-to-Value (LTV) ratio for real estate collateral. (4개 시중은행이 부동산 담보인정비율(LTV)에 관한 정보교환 담합행위로 과징금 2720억원을 부과받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Fair Trade Commission (FTC) announced on the 21st that it decided to impose a total of 272 billion won in fines along with a cease and desist order on Kookmin, Shinhan, Woori, and Hana banks for exchanging and utilizing LTV-related information, thereby restricting competition in the real estate collateral loan market. (공정거래위원회는 21일 국민·신한·우리·하나은행이 엘티브이에 관한 정보를 서로 교환하고 활용해 부동산 담보대출 시장에서 경쟁을 제한한 행위에 대해 법 위반행위 금지명령과 함께 과징금 총 2720억원을 부과하기로 결정했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LTV is the ratio that indicates the maximum loan amount a bank can lend when using real estate as collateral. The FTC stated, "LTV is an important transaction condition that affects the possible loan amount and interest rates," adding, "If the LTV decreases, borrowers may face worsened transaction conditions, such as having to use relatively higher-interest credit loans to secure the desired amount of funds. In particular, small and medium-sized enterprises and small business owners, who heavily rely on collateral loans, are significantly affected by banks' LTV decisions in terms of their funding possibilities and scale." (엘티브이는 은행이 부동산을 담보로 돈을 빌려줄 때 대출 가능한 한도를 나타내는 비율이다. 공정위는 “엘티브이는 대출 가능 금액, 대출금리 등에 영향을 미치는 중요한 거래조건”이라며 “엘티브이가 낮아지면 차주가 원하는 규모의 자금을 조달하기 위해 상대적으로 대출금리가 높은 신용대출을 이용해야 하는 등 거래조건이 악화할 수 있다. 특히 담보대출 의존도가 높은 중소기업, 소상공인 등은 은행의 엘티브이 결정에 따라 자금 조달 가능성 및 규모에 크게 영향을 받는다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the FTC investigation, the four commercial banks frequently exchanged all of their LTV information over a long period, ranging from a minimum of 736 cases to a maximum of 7,500 cases per bank. They exchanged not aggregated data but the complete LTV information applied to each type and location of individual real estate. Consequently, each bank could learn the other's LTV plans to be applied to all domestic real estate, including apartments, multi-family housing, general commercial buildings, officetels, and factories, categorized by city, county, and district. (공정위 조사 결과, 4개 시중은행은 최소 736건에서 최대 7500건에 이르는 각 은행의 엘티브이 정보 전체를 장기간에 걸쳐 수시로 교환했다. 이들 은행은 가공된 정보가 아닌 개별 부동산의 종류 및 소재지별로 적용되는 엘티브이 정보 전체를 그대로 교환했다. 이에 따라 상대방이 시군구별 아파트, 다세대주택, 일반 상가, 오피스텔, 공장 등 국내 모든 부동산에 적용할 엘티브이 계획을 알 수 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC considered actions after December 30, 2021, the enforcement date of the revised Fair Trade Act which newly established a prohibition on collusive information exchange that restricts competition, as subject to sanctions. This sanction is the first case where the regulation has been applied. Furthermore, revenue from collateral loans where the banks' set LTV was not applied due to government regulations on household loan LTV was not reflected in the fine calculation. (공정위는 경쟁제한적 정보교환 담합행위 금지 규정이 신설된 개정 공정거래법 시행일인 2021년 12월30일 이후의 행위를 제재 대상으로 봤다. 이번 제재는 해당 규정이 적용된 첫 사례다. 또 정부의 가계대출 엘티브이 규제로 인해 은행이 설정한 엘티브이가 적용되지 않은 담보대출과 관련한 매출액은 과징금 산정에 반영하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC determined that the LTV managers at each bank clearly recognized the possibility of legal violation and actively erased traces of the information exchange. The managers met in person to receive LTV information in printed form and manually input the data, up to 7,500 cases, into Excel files. They also destroyed the printed materials they received. Moreover, to ensure the information exchange continued even when personnel changed, they documented and handed over details such as the designated information exchange contact person for each bank and the exchange methods. (공정위는 각 은행의 엘티브이 담당 실무자들이 법 위반 가능성을 명확하게 인식하고 정보교환의 흔적을 적극적으로 제거했다고 판단했다. 실무자들은 직접 만나서 엘티브이 정보를 인쇄물로 받고, 최대 7500건에 이르는 해당 정보를 일일이 엑셀 파일에 입력했다. 받아온 인쇄물은 파기하기도 했다. 또 담당자가 교체되더라도 정보교환이 계속 이뤄질 수 있도록 은행별 정보교환 담당자, 교환 방법 등을 정리해 인수인계했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All four commercial banks reflected other banks' information when adjusting their own LTV, resulting in their LTVs being maintained at similar levels over a long period. Their average LTV was 7.5 percentage points lower compared to banks like IBK, NongHyup, and Busan Bank, which did not participate in the information exchange. In particular, the average LTV for non-residential real estate like factories and land, which are highly relevant to corporate loans, was 8.8 percentage points lower. (4개 시중은행은 모두 자신의 엘티브이를 조정할 때 다른 은행의 정보를 반영해, 이들의 엘티브이가 장기간 유사한 수준으로 유지됐다. 이들의 엘티브이 평균은 정보교환에 참여하지 않은 기업·농협·부산은행 등에 견줘 7.5%포인트 낮았다. 특히 공장, 토지 등 기업대출과 연관성이 큰 비주택 부동산의 엘티브이 평균은 8.8%포인트 낮았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC pointed out, "Each bank was able to avoid competition through LTV, and as a result, could stably generate operating profits," adding, "Borrowers inevitably suffered damage as their choice of transaction banks was limited due to the similar LTV levels maintained by the four commercial banks, which hold about a 60% share in the real estate collateral loan market." (공정위는 “각 은행은 엘티브이를 통한 경쟁을 회피할 수 있었고, 그 결과 영업이익을 안정적으로 창출할 수 있었다”며 “차주들은 부동산 담보대출 시장에서 약 60%의 점유율을 차지하는 4개 시중은행의 엘티브이가 유사한 수준으로 유지됨에 따라 거래 은행 선택권이 제한되는 피해를 볼 수밖에 없었다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fines imposed on the four major banks are known to be of nearly similar size. While the banks are relieved that the fine amount is smaller than initially anticipated by the market, they are also considering filing an administrative lawsuit against the penalty. The banks argue that they are unfairly penalized, stating they did not intentionally collude but were practically forced to refer to other banks' LTV ratios due to circumstances. A bank official said, "For housing, market prices are publicly announced and LTV regulations apply, making it clear. However, for commercial buildings, factories, and land nationwide, assessed values vary case by case and are not subject to LTV regulations, so we have no choice but to refer to the appraised value for each property," adding, "Since appraised values also differ, we inevitably have to refer to other banks' LTV ratios." The banks suggest that, perhaps on this occasion, the Korea Federation of Banks could consider a method where all banks publicly disclose their real estate LTV ratios as a solution. (4대 은행들이 받은 과징금액은 거의 엇비슷한 규모로 알려진다. 은행들은 과징금 규모가 당초 시장에서 예상했던 것보다는 작아 안도하면서도 과징금 처분에 대해 행정소송을 검토할 수 있다는 입장이다. 은행들은 의도적으로 담합을 한 것이 아니고 현실적으로 다른 은행들의 담보인정비율을 참고할 수밖에 없는 형편이라서 억울하다는 입장이다. 한 은행 관계자는 “담보인정비율이 주택은 시세가 공시돼 뚜렷이 나와 있고 담보인정비율 규제가 적용되는데, 전국의 상가·공장·토지는 산정되는 시세가 제각각이고 담보인정비율 규제도 받지 않아 건마다 이뤄지는 감정평가액을 참고할 수밖에 없다”며 “감정평가액도 제각각 달라서 어쩔 수 없이 다른 은행들의 담보인정비율을 참고할 수밖에 없다”고 말했다. 은행들은 차라리 이참에 은행연합회에 각 은행이 부동산 담보인정비율을 다 같이 공시하는 방식을 문제 해결 방법으로 검토해볼 수 있겠다고 제시한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo kyj@hani.co.kr Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan kyewan@hani.co.kr (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr  조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240871.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/318/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121501692.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Exporting Companies Cite 'Exchange Rate Stability' as Top Priority... 40% "Face Pressure to Lower Prices" (수출 기업들 ‘환율 안정’ 최우선 과제 꼽아…40% “가격 인하 압박받아”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240887.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Exporting Companies Cite 'Exchange Rate Stability' as Top Priority... 40% "Face Pressure to Lower Prices" (수출 기업들 ‘환율 안정’ 최우선 과제 꼽아…40% “가격 인하 압박받아”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/394/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502023.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;14일 경기도 평택항에 컨테이너들이 쌓여 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A survey has found that even exporting companies, which are perceived to benefit from a rising won-dollar exchange rate, most desire exchange rate stability, citing reasons such as rising raw material prices and demands from overseas buyers for price reductions. (원·달러 환율 상승의 혜택을 보는 것으로 인식되는 수출 기업들도 원자재 가격 상승과 해외 바이어들의 단가 인하 요구 등을 이유로 환율 안정을 가장 바란다는 설문조사 결과가 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the '2026 Business Environment Outlook for Exporting Companies' report published on the 21st, the Korea International Trade Association's International Trade and Commerce Research Institute stated that 'increased exchange rate volatility' (43.5%) ranked first as the biggest external risk cited by exporting companies this year (multiple responses allowed). This was followed by 'U.S. tariff increases' (40.1%), 'decreased import demand from major countries' (28.3%), and 'intensified competition with China' (23.5%). Regarding government policies needed to improve the business environment, 'exchange rate stability' (47.7%) also ranked first. It was followed by 'minimizing trade risks through negotiations with major countries' (27.8%) and 'expanding support programs for entering new markets' (18.3%). (한국무역협회 국제무역통상연구원은 21일 발간한 ‘수출 기업의 2026년 경영 환경 전망’ 보고서에서 수출 기업들이 꼽은 올해 가장 큰 대외 리스크(복수 응답)로 ‘환율 변동성 확대’(43.5%)가 1위를 차지했다고 밝혔다. 다음으로는 ‘미국 관세 인상’(40.1%), ‘주요국 수입 수요 감소’(28.3%), ‘중국과의 경쟁 심화’(23.5%)를 많이 꼽았다. 경영 환경 개선을 위해 필요하다는 정부 정책도 ‘환율 안정’(47.7%)이 1위였다. 이어 ‘주요국과의 협상을 통한 통상 리스크 최소화’(27.8%)와 ‘신규 시장 진출 지원 사업 확대’(18.3%)가 뒤를 이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on a survey of 1,193 exporting companies, the report stated, "Many opinions indicated that exporting companies face significant burdens due to rising import raw material prices caused by the exchange rate increase, pressure for price reductions from overseas buyers, and overall domestic inflation." It also added, "If exchange rate volatility increases, additional time and costs are required for adjusting business plans and prices, and hedging costs such as insurance, forward exchange contracts, and options may rise, potentially acting as an additional cost burden." (수출 기업 1193곳에 대한 설문조사를 바탕으로 쓴 보고서는 “수출 기업은 환율 상승으로 인한 수입 원자재 가격 상승, 해외 바이어로부터의 단가 인하 압박, 국내 물가의 전체적인 상승 등으로 부담이 크다는 의견이 많았다”고 밝혔다. 또 “환율 변동성이 커지면 경영 계획 및 가격 재조정에 추가적인 시간과 비용이 소요되며, 보험·선물환·옵션 등 헤지 비용이 증가해 추가적인 비용 부담으로 작용할 가능성이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among exporting companies, 40.5% responded that they had received requests for price reductions from overseas buyers due to the rising exchange rate. Nearly half of these companies stated they had partially accepted the requests. 37.6% responded that they had not yet received such requests but were highly likely to face price reduction demands in the future. It is expected that many buyers demand or will demand price reductions from exporting companies that receive payments in dollars, arguing that the won-converted amount has increased due to the exchange rate rise. However, the report noted, "It was found that most exporting companies lack the capacity to lower export prices despite the exchange rate rise, due to increased production costs such as import raw materials, labor costs, and logistics expenses." (수출 기업들 중 40.5%는 환율 상승을 이유로 해외 바이어로부터 가격 인하 요구를 받았다고 응답했다. 이들 중 절반 가까이가 요구를 일부 수용했다고 밝혔다. 37.6%는 아직 요구를 받지 않았지만 향후 가격 인하 요구를 받을 가능성이 높다고 답했다. 상당수 바이어들이 달러로 대금을 받는 수출 기업들에게 환율 상승으로 원화 환산액이 늘었으니까 가격을 낮추라고 요구하거나 그럴 것으로 예상된다는 것이다. 하지만 보고서는 “수출 기업들은 환율 상승에도 불구하고 수입 원자재, 인건비, 물류비 등 생산 비용 상승으로 대부분 수출 단가 인하 여력이 없는 것으로 조사됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exporting companies are considering responses for their U.S. export strategy following the conclusion of Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations, including 'exploring export markets other than the U.S.' (39.8%), 'accepting cost reduction and worsening profitability' (33.8%), and 'reflecting tariffs in selling prices' (29.6%). (수출 기업들은 한·미 관세 협상 타결 이후 대미 수출 전략으로 ‘미국 외 수출시장 발굴’(39.8%), ‘원가 절감과 수익성 악화 감수’(33.8%), ‘관세분 판매가 반영’(29.6%) 등의 대응을 고려하고 있다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Bon-young &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이본영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240887.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/394/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502023.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Did Musk Praise "Koreans Move Quickly on New Technology"? (머스크 “한국인은 신기술에 빠르게 움직여” 칭찬 왜?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1240893.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Why Did Musk Praise "Koreans Move Quickly on New Technology"? (머스크 “한국인은 신기술에 빠르게 움직여” 칭찬 왜?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/535/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502233.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;일론 머스크가 지난해 9월 극우 운동가인 찰리 커크의 추모식에 참석한 모습. 연합뉴스/AP&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk, CEO of Tesla, posted on social media, evaluating 'Koreans' as early adopters, drawing attention to the background behind his comment. (일론 머스크 테슬라 최고경영자(CEO)가 사회관계망서비스(SNS)에 글을 올려 ‘한국인’을 얼리어답터로 평가하면서 그 배경에 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th (local time), Musk wrote on his X account, "Koreans are often a step ahead in appreciating new technology." Regarding this, the automotive industry analyzes that it is a positive assessment of the fact that, while Tesla's global sales stagnated and its business performance deteriorated last year, its performance in the Korean market alone showed 'solitary growth'. (머스크는 20일(현지시각) 자신의 엑스(X) 계정에 “한국인들은 새로운 기술을 받아들이는 데 종종 한발 앞서 있다”(Koreans are often a step ahead in appreciating new technology)고 썼다. 이를 두고 자동차 업계에선 지난해 세계 시장에서 테슬라 판매가 주춤하고 경영 실적이 악화한 가운데 한국 시장 실적만 ‘나 홀로 성장’한 것을 긍정적으로 평가했다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Tesla's investor relations (IR) materials, last year's sales volume was 1,636,129 units, a decrease of 8.56% compared to the previous year's (2024) performance. Looking at it quarterly, except for the third quarter, which saw a last-minute surge in demand ahead of September 30th when the Trump administration abolished electric vehicle subsidies of up to $7,500 (approximately 11 million won), sales performance declined in all quarters. Reasons cited for Tesla's declining sales include its relatively high price, the global policy trend of abolishing electric vehicle purchase subsidies, and the expanding market share of inexpensive Chinese-made electric vehicles. (테슬라의 기업활동(IR) 자료를 보면, 지난해 판매량은 163만6129대로 전년도(2024년) 실적에 견줘 8.56% 감소했다. 분기별로 살펴보면 트럼프 행정부가 최대 7500달러(약1100만원)에 이르는 전기차 보조금을 폐지한 9월30일을 앞두고 막판 수요가 몰렸던 3분기를 제외하고 모든 분기 판매 실적이 줄어든 것으로 집계됐다. 테슬라의 판매량이 감소하는 이유로는 상대적으로 비싼 가격, 전기차 구입 보조금을 폐지하는 세계적 정책 기조, 값싼 중국산 전기차의 시장 점유율 확대 등이 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Tesla's sales volume surged in the Korean market last year. According to an analysis of Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport data by Kaizu Data Research Institute, Tesla sold 59,949 units in the Korean market last year, a 101.5% increase in sales compared to 2024. The Model Y sold 50,405 units, a 169.3% increase compared to 2024. (반면 한국 시장에선 지난해 테슬라 판매량이 급증했다. 카이즈유 데이터연구소가 국토교통부 자료를 분석한 내용을 보면, 테슬라는 지난해 한국 시장에서 5만9949대를 팔아 2024년에 견줘 판매량이 101.5% 증가했다. 모델와이(Y)는 5만405대가 팔려 판매량이 2024년 대비 169.3% 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fact that sales increased only in Korea is attributed to growing consumer interest following the results of the Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations last November, which allowed the Full Self-Driving (FSD) feature domestically. (지난해 11월 한미 관세협상의 결과로 감독형 완전자율주행(FSD) 기능이 국내에 허용되면서 소비자들의 관심이 커진 것이 한국에서만 판매량이 증가한 배경으로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there are also voices saying that domestic consumers should consider that the FSD feature is not in a completed state, that development and updates are ongoing, and that safety verification procedures by U.S. government authorities are in progress, and thus should be cautious about purchasing. Professor Kim Pil-soo of Daelim University (Future Automotive Studies) said, "Regarding Tesla's autonomous driving function, voices demanding recalls are growing in global markets like the U.S. and Japan, and as sales are declining, domestic consumers should also be cautious." (하지만 에프에스디 기능이 완성된 상태가 아니고 개발·업데이트가 계속되고 있는 점과 미국 정부 당국의 안전성 검증 절차 등이 진행되는 점 등을 국내 소비자가 고려하고 구매에 신중해야 한다는 목소리도 나온다. 김필수 대림대 교수(미래자동차학부)는 “테슬라의 자율주행기능과 관련해 미국과 일본 등 세계 시장에서 리콜을 요구하는 목소리가 높고, 판매량이 감소하고 있는 만큼 국내 소비자들도 주의해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Jae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이재호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1240893.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/535/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502233.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>HUG Corporate Rental Deposit Guarantee Incidents and Reimbursement Payments Hit Record High (HUG 법인 임대보증금 사고·대위변제액 사상 최대)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1240897.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;HUG Corporate Rental Deposit Guarantee Incidents and Reimbursement Payments Hit Record High (HUG 법인 임대보증금 사고·대위변제액 사상 최대)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502277.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The amount of guarantee incidents and the amount of deposit reimbursements (subrogation payments) made by the Korea Housing &amp; Urban Guarantee Corporation (HUG) for corporate rental deposit guarantees reached an all-time high last year. The incident rate also exceeded 1% for the first time. (주택도시보증공사(HUG)가 보증한 법인 임대보증금의 보증 사고액과 공사가 대신 갚아준 보증금(대위변제액)이 지난해 사상 최대치를 기록했다. 사고율도 처음으로 1%대를 넘어섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to data from the Korea Housing &amp; Urban Guarantee Corporation and the office of People Power Party lawmaker Kim Jong-yang on the 21st, the amount of corporate rental deposit guarantee incidents and subrogation payments by HUG last year reached 679.8 billion won and 519.7 billion won respectively, setting new record highs. First launched in 2003, the rental deposit guarantee is a product where the corporation pays the deposit to the tenant on behalf of the landlord if the individual or corporate rental business operator fails to return the deposit. Unlike the jeonse deposit return guarantee, which tenants must subscribe to, the rental business operator and the tenant share the guarantee premium in a 75% to 25% ratio. Since August 2020, subscription to the rental guarantee has been fully mandatory for registered rental business operators. (21일 주택도시보증공사와 김종양 국민의힘 의원실 자료를 보면, 지난해 주택도시보증공사의 법인 임대보증금 사고액과 대위변제액이 각각 6798억원, 5197억원으로 사상 최대치를 경신했다. 2003년 처음 출시한 임대보증은 개인·법인 임대사업자가 임대보증금을 임차인에게 반환하지 않는 경우에 공사가 임차인에게 대신 보증금을 지급하는 상품이다. 임차인이 가입해야 하는 전세보증금반환보증과 달리 임대사업자와 임차인이 75%대 25%의 비율로 보증료를 부담한다. 2020년 8월부터 등록 임대사업자의 임대보증 가입이 전면 의무화된 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past five years, the amount and number of households affected by corporate rental deposit guarantee incidents have surged: 40.9 billion won (524 households) in 2021, 51 billion won (767 households) in 2022, 138.7 billion won (1,256 households) in 2023, 330.8 billion won (2,668 households) in 2024, and 679.5 billion won (4,489 households) last year. The incident rate, calculated by dividing the incident amount by the outstanding guarantee balance, was 0.2% in 2021, 0.1% in 2022, 0.4% in 2023, and around 0.8% in 2024, before rising to 1.6% last year, exceeding 1% for the first time. HUG's subrogation payments due to corporate rental guarantee incidents also surged sharply: 46.3 billion won in both 2021 and 2022, 80.2 billion won in 2023, 214.8 billion won in 2024, and 519.7 billion won last year. (지난 5년간 법인 임대보증금 보증사고 금액과 가구는 2021년 409억원(524가구), 2022년 510억(767가구), 2023년 1387억원(1256가구), 2024년 3308억원(2668가구), 지난해 6795억원(4489가구)으로 급증해왔다. 사고금액을 보증잔액으로 나눈 사고율은 2021년 0.2%, 2022년 0.1%, 2023년 0.4%, 2024년 0.8% 수준을 보이다가 지난해에는 처음으로 1%대를 넘어선 1.6%로 집계됐다. 법인 임대보증 사고에 따른 주택도시보증공사의 대위변제액도 2021년과 2022년 463억원, 2023년 802억원, 2024년 2148억원, 지난해 5197억원으로 급증했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The prolonged slump in regional real estate is behind the increase in rental guarantee incidents. Last year, 96% of corporate rental guarantee incidents occurred outside the Seoul metropolitan area. The incident amounts by region were in the order of Gwangju (221.9 billion won), South Jeolla (132.1 billion won), North Jeolla (73.6 billion won), Busan (71.5 billion won), South Chungcheong (48.2 billion won), Daegu (33.8 billion won), and North Gyeongsang (33.7 billion won). HUG explained, "Corporate landlords, with relatively larger business scales and financial capacity, had been able to withstand the real estate downturn for a certain period. However, it is estimated that the cumulative impact of the prolonged real estate slump in non-metropolitan areas led to the sharp increase in guarantee incidents last year." (임대보증 사고가 증가하는 배경에는 지방 부동산의 침체 장기화가 있다. 지난해 법인 임대보증 사고의 96%는 비수도권에서 발생했다. 지역별 사고액은 광주(2219억원), 전남(1321억원), 전북(736억원), 부산(715억원), 충남(482억원), 대구(338억원), 경북(337억원) 등의 순이었다. 주택도시보증공사는 “법인 임대인은 상대적으로 사업 규모가 크고 자금 여력이 있어 부동산 경기 침체에도 일정 기간 버텨왔으나, 비수도권 부동산 침체 장기화로 그 영향이 누적되어 지난해 보증사고가 급증한 것으로 추정된다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, HUG analyzed that while guarantee incidents for jeonse guarantees have recently been on a declining trend since the debt-to-income (DTI) ratio requirement for subscription was tightened from 100% to 90% starting May 2023, the same DTI requirement for rental guarantees was implemented only from this month, so the policy effect has not yet materialized. HUG diagnosed, "If the real estate downturn in non-metropolitan areas continues, the increasing trend of corporate rental business operators' rental deposit guarantee incidents is likely to persist for the time being." (또 전세보증의 경우 2023년 5월부터 가입 시 부채비율 요건이 기존 100%에서 90%로 강화되면서 최근 보증 사고가 감소세로 접어들었으나, 임대보증의 경우 동일한 부채비율 요건을 이달부터 시행해 아직 정책 효과가 나타나지 않은 영향도 있다고 주택도시보증공사는 분석했다. 주택도시보증공사는 “비수도권 부동산 경기 침체가 지속할 경우 법인 임대 사업자의 임대보증금 보증사고 증가세는 당분간 이어질 가능성이 있다”고 진단했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1240897.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502277.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bank of Korea Officially Operates 'Sovereign AI'... First Case Among Central Banks Worldwide (한국은행 ‘소버린 AI’ 공식 운영…전 세계 중앙은행 첫 사례)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240900.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Bank of Korea Officially Operates 'Sovereign AI'... First Case Among Central Banks Worldwide (한국은행 ‘소버린 AI’ 공식 운영…전 세계 중앙은행 첫 사례)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/439/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502315.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bank of Korea has officially introduced and is operating a self-developed generative artificial intelligence (AI) platform on its internal work network. This is the first such case among central banks worldwide. (한국은행이 자체 개발한 생성형 인공지능(AI) 플랫폼을 사내 업무망에 공식 도입해 운영한다. 전세계 중앙은행 중 첫 사례다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BOK unveiled its sovereign artificial intelligence platform 'BOKI' (Bank of Korea Intelligence, tentative name) on the 21st. This platform was built on the Bank of Korea's internal network, where data security is ensured, based on Naver Cloud's AI model HyperClova X. Naver provided the cloud infrastructure and large language model (LLM), while the BOK developed AI applications specialized in finance and economics. To introduce the AI platform, the BOK standardized approximately 1.4 million internal documents into a format understandable by AI. (  한은은 소버린 인공지능 플랫폼 ‘BOKI’(Bank of Korea Intelligence·가칭)를 21일 공개했다. 이 플랫폼은 데이터 보안이 확보된 한은 내부망에 네이버클라우드의 인공지능 모형 하이퍼클로바엑스(X)를 기반으로 구축됐다. 네이버는 클라우드 인프라와 거대언어모델(LLM)을 제공하고 한은은 금융·경제에 특화된 인공지능 어플리케이션을 개발했다. 한은은 인공지능 플랫폼 도입을 위해 약 140만건의 내부 문서를 인공지능이 이해할 수 있는 형태로 표준화했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, the first version will provide services such as a work chatbot that assists with checking investigation research laws and regulations and utilizing personal documents, finance/economics-specialized translation, and analysis services linking Bank of Korea data with AI. There are plans to expand the platform by subdividing it according to different work areas in the future. The BOK expressed expectations, stating, "Utilizing the AI platform will shorten work processes and aid in decision-making based on vast internal knowledge and data." (  일단 첫 버전에서는 조사연구 법규 및 규정 확인, 개인문서 활용을 지원하는 업무용 챗봇, 금융·경제 특화 번역, 한국은행 데이터와 인공지능을 연계한 분석 서비스 등을 제공한다. 향후 업무 영역별로 세분화하여 확대할 계획이다. 한은은 “인공지능 플랫폼을 활용하면 업무 프로세스를 단축하고 방대한 내부 지식과 데이터에 기반한 의사 결정에 도움이 될 것”이라고 기대했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bank of Korea Governor Lee Chang-yong said, "We have become the first institution to simultaneously pursue the construction of sovereign AI and network improvement, and the first public institution to attempt a change in the network separation policy," adding, "When the network separation improvement is completed in March, the scope of utilization and performance will be significantly enhanced." (  이창용 한은 총재는 “소버린 인공지능 구축과 망 개선을 동시에 추진하는 최초의 기관이자 망 분리 정책의 변화를 시도하는 첫번째 공공기관이 됐다”며 “오는 3월 망 분리 개선이 완료되면 활용 범위와 성능이 크게 향상될 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240900.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/439/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502315.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year's Drug Smuggling Seizures Hit Record High of 3.3 Tons… 'Club Drug' Ketamine Seizures Triple (작년 마약 밀수 적발 3.3t ‘역대 최대’…‘클럽 마약’ 케타민은 3배↑)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240908.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/480/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502535.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난해 적발된 마약들. 관세청 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The amount of drugs seized at the border stage last year reached 3.3 tons, setting a record high. Seizures of ketamine, known as a 'club drug,' increased significantly. (지난 한해 동안 국경 단계에서 적발된 마약류가 3.3t에 달하며 역대 최대치를 기록했다. ‘클럽 마약’이라 불리는 케타민 적발량이 큰 폭으로 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Customs Service announced on the 21st that it seized a total of 1,256 cases, amounting to 3,318 kg, of drugs last year. Compared to the previous year, the number of cases increased by 46% and the weight by 321%, marking the highest figures on record. (관세청은 지난해 총 1256건, 3318㎏의 마약류를 적발했다고 21일 밝혔다. 전년 대비 적발 건수는 46%, 중량은 321% 증가하며 역대 최고치로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By item, cocaine (2,602 kg), which saw large-scale smuggling busts originating from Peru and Ecuador, showed the highest increase rate, surging by 3,750% compared to the previous year. Ketamine, primarily consumed in clubs and similar venues, also increased more than threefold compared to the previous year, with seizures totaling 144 kg. The Customs Service stated, "Ketamine smuggling is becoming larger in scale, with a sharp increase in large-scale seizures of 1 kg or more. Analysis suggests that smuggling for personal use is spreading among individuals in their 20s to 40s." Meanwhile, methamphetamine (Philopon), which had been the most frequently seized drug, saw a 36% decrease to 313 kg due to a decline in seizures of methamphetamine originating from Thailand. (품목별로는 페루·에콰도르발 대형 밀수 적발이 있었던 코카인(2602㎏)이 전년 대비 3750% 늘어나며 가장 높은 증가율을 보였다. 클럽 등에서 주로 소비되는 케타민도 전년 대비 3배 이상 증가한 144㎏으로 집계됐다. 관세청은 “케타민은 1㎏ 이상의 대형 밀수 적발 건이 급증하는 등 밀수 규모가 대형화하고 있다. 20~40대에서 자기소비 목적의 밀반입이 확산된 것으로 분석된다”고 말했다. 그동안 가장 많이 적발됐던 필로폰은 태국발 필로폰 적발 감소로 전년보다 36% 줄어든 313㎏이 적발됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding smuggling routes, the method involving travelers carrying drugs saw a substantial increase in both the number of cases and weight compared to a year ago. Over the past year, the number of smuggling cases involving travelers was 624, more than triple the previous year, and the amount seized was 280 kg, double that of a year ago. Excluding Peru and Ecuador, where large-scale smuggling busts occurred, the countries of origin for the seized drugs were, in order, Thailand, the United States, and Canada. (밀수 경로는 여행자가 운반하는 방식이 건수와 중량 모두 1년 전보다 대폭 증가했다. 지난 한해 동안 여행자 밀수 적발 건수는 624건으로 전년 대비 3배 이상 늘었고, 적발량은 1년 전의 2배인 280㎏으로 집계됐다. 걸린 마약류의 출발 국가로는 대형 밀수 적발이 있었던 페루·에콰도르를 제외하면 태국·미국·캐나다 순으로 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As drug seizures increase, the Customs Service announced that it is launching a 'Drug Eradication Response Headquarters' on this day, headed by Commissioner Lee Myung-goo. The Response Headquarters will serve as a control tower for drug crackdowns, involving all drug enforcement organizations from customs offices nationwide. It plans to hold weekly meetings to share trends in drug seizures and review the performance of related countermeasures. (마약 적발량이 늘면서 관세청은 이날 이명구 관세청장을 본부장으로 하는 ‘마약척결 대응본부’를 출범한다고 밝혔다. 대응본부는 전국세관의 마약 단속 조직이 모두 참여하는 마약 단속 컨트롤타워로, 매주 회의를 열어 마약 적발 동향을 공유하고 관련 대책 성과를 점검하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commissioner Lee said, "I urge all customs officers nationwide to approach their duties with a sense of urgency and grave responsibility to meet society's expectation for 'a healthy Republic of Korea free of drugs.'" He added, "I also ask the public to recognize the serious harms of drugs and participate in eradicating drug crimes, such as by actively reporting drug smuggling." (이 청장은 “전국세관 직원들은 ‘마약 없는 건강한 대한민국’이라는 사회적 기대 부응을 위해 절박하고 막중한 책임감을 갖고 업무에 임해 달라”며 “국민께서도 마약의 심각한 폐해를 인식하고 적극적인 마약 밀수신고 등 마약범죄 근절에 동참해달라”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240908.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/480/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121502535.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:47:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's 'Verbal Intervention' Cuts Exchange Rate by Over 10 Won... Trump Tariff Threat 'Bumps It Up' Again? (이 대통령 ‘구두 개입’에 환율 10원 넘게 뚝…트럼프 관세 위협이 또 ‘끌올’?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240945.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/589/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503406.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21일 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸 현황판. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The won-dollar exchange rate, which had been threatening its previous high, plunged by over 10 won during the trading session on the 21st due to President Lee Jae-myung's 'verbal intervention'. (전고점을 위협하던 원-달러 환율이 21일 이재명 대통령의 ‘구두 개입’으로 장중 10원 이상 뚝 떨어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Seoul foreign exchange market that day, the won-dollar exchange rate started at 1,480.4 won, up 2.3 won from the previous trading day. It was the first time in 17 trading days that the intraday exchange rate exceeded 1,480 won since the foreign exchange authorities officially intervened on December 24 last year. After fierce back-and-forth trading around the 1,480 won level, which is considered a defense line by the authorities, the won-dollar rate plummeted vertically immediately following President Lee's remarks on the exchange rate. At a New Year's press conference held that day, when asked about measures against the high exchange rate after noting 'the exchange rate just exceeded 1,480 won,' President Lee stated, "According to the responsible authorities, it is predicted that (the exchange rate) will fall to around 1,400 won in a month or two. We will continuously explore possible measures and strive to stabilize the exchange rate." (이날 서울외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 전거래일 대비 2.3원 오른 1480.4원으로 출발했다. 장중 환율이 1480원을 넘은 것은 외환당국이 공식 개입에 나선 지난해 12월24일 이후 17거래일 만이다. 원-달러 환율은 외환당국의 방어선인 1480원에서 치열한 공방을 벌이다 이 대통령의 환율 발언이 나온 직후 수직 하락했다. 이 대통령은 이날 열린 신년 기자회견에서 ‘환율이 방금 1480원을 넘었다’며 고환율 대책을 묻자 “책임당국에 의하면 한두 달 정도 지나면 (환율이) 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다. 지속적으로 가능한 수단을 발굴하고 환율이 안정되도록 노력하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following President Lee's remarks, the won-dollar exchange rate plummeted by over 10 won in just about 20 minutes, falling to the 1,469 won range. There were also market observations that intervention volumes from the foreign exchange authorities and the National Pension Service amplified the decline. The won-dollar exchange rate fell for the first time in four trading days, closing the weekly trading at 1,471.3 won, down 6.8 won. A foreign exchange (FX) analyst at a commercial bank said, "As the President directly mentioned a specific exchange rate level and expressed his will for market stabilization, caution over market intervention by the foreign exchange authorities increased, leading to a rapid spread of selling sentiment," adding, "However, it seems strong bargain-hunting for dollars is providing solid support below 1,470 won." (이 대통령의 발언 이후 원-달러 환율은 불과 20여분 만에 10원 이상 급락해 1469원대까지 떨어졌다. 시장에서는 외환당국과 국민연금의 개입 물량이 하락 폭을 키웠다는 관측도 나왔다. 이날 원-달러 환율은 4거래일 만에 하락해 6.8원 내린 1471.3원에 주간거래를 마감했다. 시중은행 외환(FX)분석가는 “대통령이 특정 환율 수준을 언급하며 시장 안정 의지를 직접 밝히자 외환당국의 시장 개입 경계감이 커지면서 매도 심리가 급격히 확산됐다”며 “다만, 1470원 미만에선 달러 저가 매수세가 강하게 받치고 있는 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreign exchange market faces a situation where domestic supply-demand imbalances continue, while external conditions are increasing upward pressure. This is because uncertainty is rising in international financial markets, with phenomena like 'Sell America' (selling dollar assets) appearing as former U.S. President Donald Trump has again resorted to tariff threats over the Greenland issue. Although the dollar is showing weakness, the value of the Korean won is reacting more sensitively to risk-off sentiment and the yen's depreciation. (외환시장은 국내 수급 쏠림이 계속되는 가운데 대외 여건은 상방 압력이 커진 형국이다. 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 그린란드 문제로 또다시 관세 위협에 나서자 국제금융시장에서 &amp;#x27;셀 아메리카&amp;#x27;(달러 자산 매도) 양상이 나타나는 등 불확실성이 높아지고 있어서다. 달러가 약세를 보이고 있지만 원화 가치는 위험자산 회피 심리와 엔화 약세에 더 민감하게 반응하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240945.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/589/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503406.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:46:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In the AI Era, Home Appliances and Autonomous Vehicles Also Exposed to Hacking Risks... "Safety Nets Must Be Built from the Design Stage" (AI시대, 가전도 자율주행차도 해킹 위험 노출…“설계부터 안전망 구축해야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240946.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/859/516/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689812554218_20260121503413.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;중국 유니트리의 휴머노이드 ‘지(G)1’. 유니트리 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As artificial intelligence (AI) is being embedded in home appliances and entering the real world through humanoid robots and autonomous vehicles, new security concerns are being raised. This is because the personal daily life remembered by products becomes sensitive information, and 'physical AIs' that learn and act based on this can become targets for hacking. Suggestions have emerged that security must be maintained from the design stage to address this. (인공지능(AI)이 가전제품에 탑재되고, 휴머노이드(인간형 로봇)나 자율주행차 등을 통해 현실 세계로 들어오며 새로운 보안 우려가 제기되고 있다. 제품이 기억하는 개인의 일상이 곧 민감정보가 되고, 이를 학습하며 활동하는 ‘피지컬 인공지능’들이 해킹의 대상이 될 수 있기 때문이다. 이를 위해서는 설계 단계부터 보안을 유지해야 한다는 제언이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Summarizing explanations from foreign media like Bloomberg on the 21st, hacking threats were discovered in major robots such as 'B2' and 'G1' from China's leading humanoid company 'Unitree' last September. Hackers successfully took control of the robots and remotely manipulated them by exploiting Bluetooth settings. Unitree reportedly took security measures, including updating software and blocking backdoor connections. (21일 블룸버그 등 외신의 설명을 종합하면, 중국의 대표적인 휴머노이드 기업 ‘유니트리’의 ‘비(B)2’, ‘G(지)1’ 등 주요 로봇에서 지난해 9월 해킹 위협이 발견됐다. 해커들이 블루투스 설정을 통해 로봇의 주도권을 뺏고 원격 조정에 성공한 것이다. 유니트리는 소프트웨어를 업데이트하고 백도어(뒷문) 연결을 차단하는 등 보안 조처를 한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Autonomous vehicles are not safe either. A representative case occurred in 2016 when China's Tencent-affiliated Keen Security Lab became the first in the world to hack a US Tesla Model S vehicle, opening and closing its doors and manipulating the brakes. Since then, Tesla has been regularly updating its security software. With not only Tesla but most vehicles expected to be equipped with software-based systems and autonomous driving capabilities, the task of strengthening security has emerged. (자율주행차도 안전하지 않다. 지난 2016년 중국 텐센트 산하의 킨 보안연구소가 세계에서 처음으로 미국 테슬라의 모델에스(S) 차량을 해킹해 문을 여닫고 브레이크를 움직인 것이 대표적인 사례다. 이후 테슬라는 정기적으로 보안 소프트웨어를 업데이트하고 있다. 테슬라는 물론, 대부분의 차량이 소프트웨어 기반 시스템과 자율주행을 탑재할 예정인 만큼 보안 강화라는 숙제가 생겨난 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, if AI enters household appliances in every home, the threat could spread across daily life. The 'AI appliances' recently promoted by the home appliance industry understand users' daily routines, learn from them, and provide customized convenience, collecting information on schedules and health for this purpose. While this can make daily life more convenient, if leaked, it could combine with other personal information to harm users. (더욱이 인공지능이 각 집안의 가전제품까지 들어오면 위협은 일상 전반에 퍼질 수 있다. 최근 가전업계가 내세우는 ‘인공지능 가전’은 사용자의 일상을 파악하고 이를 학습해 맞춤형으로 편의를 제공하는데, 이를 위해 일과, 건강 정보 등을 수집한다. 이는 일상을 편리하게 만들 수도 있지만, 유출될 경우 다른 개인정보들과 맞물려 사용자에게 피해를 줄 수도 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The industry is trending towards emphasizing 'AI security.' Samsung Electronics showcased its security platform 'Knox' and security chipsets alongside AI appliances at this year's Consumer Electronics Show (CES) in the US. This chipsets, which incorporate 'Post-Quantum Cryptography (PQC)' technology to protect against hacking even by quantum computers surpassing supercomputers, won the top innovation award at this year's CES. This demonstrates that security is also a crucial task for enjoying AI technology. (업계에서는 ‘인공지능 보안’을 강조하는 추세다. 삼성전자는 올해 미국 소비자가전전시회(CES)에서 인공지능 가전과 함께 보안 플랫폼 ‘녹스’와 보안 칩셋을 선보였다. 슈퍼컴퓨터를 넘어 양자 컴퓨터의 해킹까지 막는 ‘양자 내성 암호(PQC)’ 기술이 적용된 이 칩셋은 올해 시이에스 최고 혁신상을 받았다. 인공지능 기술을 누리기 위해서는 보안 역시 중요한 과제라는 점을 보여준 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experts pointed out that for physical AIs operating in the real world, 'Secure by Design' is important. This means security features should not be the last line of defense but must be considered from the design stage. Lee Ji-min, a senior researcher at the Korea Institute of Science and Technology Information, stated, "Hacking of physical AI leads directly to real-world damage," adding, "The system itself must be designed safely from the beginning, and simultaneously, AI should be utilized to block security threats." (전문가들은 현실에서 활동하는 피지컬 인공지능은 ‘설계에 의한 보안’(Secure by Design)이 중요하다고 짚었다. 보안 기능이 마지막 방어선이 아닌, 설계 단계부터 고려돼야 한다는 의미다. 이지민 한국과학기술정보연구원 선임연구원은 “피지컬 인공지능 해킹은 현실의 피해로 곧 이어진다”며 “시스템 자체를 처음부터 안전하게 설계하고, 동시에 인공지능을 활용해 보안 위협을 막아야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1240946.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/859/516/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689812554218_20260121503413.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:46:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Compared to Japan, the exchange rate is less depreciated and holding up relatively well" (이 대통령 “환율, 일본에 비하면 평가절하 덜 되고 잘 견디는 편”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240951.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503495.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;원-달러 환율이 2.3원 오른 1480.4원에 개장한 21일 하나은행 본점 딜링룸에서 딜러가 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the high exchange rate situation fluctuating around the 1480 won level, President Lee Jae-myung said, "According to the authorities, it is predicted that the exchange rate will fall to around 1400 won in about one or two months." It is unusual for the President to publicly mention an exchange rate forecast, and it is interpreted that he is placing expectations on major events such as tax support for domestic market re-entry starting as early as February and inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI) in April. (1480원대를 오르내리는 고환율 상황에 대해 이재명 대통령이 “당국에 의하면, 한두 달 정도 지나면 (환율이) 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”고 말했다. 대통령이 환율 전망을 공개적으로 언급한 것은 이례적으로, 이르면 2월 시작될 국내시장 복귀 세제 지원과 4월 세계국채지수 편입 등 대형 이벤트에 기대를 거는 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about 'measures against the high exchange rate' during the New Year's press conference held at the Cheong Wa Dae State Guest House on the 21st, President Lee stated as above, saying, "Compared to Japan, our exchange rate is less depreciated and is holding up relatively well." He implied that the recent high exchange rate is also influenced by external factors and is not an exception only for Korea. (이 대통령은 21일 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서 ‘고환율 대책’에 대한 질문이 나오자 “일본에 비하면 우리는 (환율은) 평가 절하가 덜 되고, 잘 견디고 있는 편”이라며 이처럼 밝혔다. 최근 고환율은 국외 변수 영향도 있어, 한국만 예외적이지 않다는 뜻이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the President's mention of the timing for a downward adjustment in the exchange rate as 'about one or two months,' foreign exchange authorities explained, "This is based on a synthesis of objective forecasts from investment banks (IBs) that a downward adjustment will occur around the end of March." According to the exchange rate forecast consensus by Yonhap Infomax as of that day, the average for the first quarter (January-March) of this year is 1,417.09 won. A Ministry of Finance and Economy official said, "Although individual investors' purchases of overseas stocks, which had somewhat slowed in terms of foreign exchange supply and demand, have been strong this month, we expect it to gradually ease with the introduction of the domestic market re-entry account (RIA) in February, among other factors." Foreign exchange authorities believe that foreign currency conversion by exporting companies and strategic foreign exchange hedging by the National Pension Service are also contributing to reducing exchange rate volatility. (대통령이 환율 하향화 전망 시점을 ‘한두 달’ 정도로 언급한 것을 두고 외환당국에선 “투자은행(IB)에서도 오는 3월 말께 하향화된다는 객관적 전망을 종합한 것”이라고 설명했다. 이날 기준 연합인포맥스의 환율 전망 컨센서스를 보면, 올해 1분기(1~3월) 평균은 1417.09원이다. 재정경제부 관계자는 “외환 수급 면에서 다소 주춤했던 개인투자자의 해외주식 매수세가 이달 거센 편이지만, 2월 중 국내시장 복귀계좌(RIA) 도입 등으로 차츰 완화될 것으로 기대한다”고 말했다. 외환당국은 수출기업들의 환전, 국민연금의 전략적 환헤지 등도 환율 변동성을 줄이는데 기여하고 있다고 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Finance and Economy is soon proposing a bill to promote passage in the February extraordinary National Assembly session. The bill would grant a 50-100% reduction in capital gains tax on overseas stocks for funds reinvested in domestic stocks this year using proceeds from the sale of overseas stocks. The expectation is a tax incentive effect that will encourage funds converted to dollars and sent abroad to be reconverted to won and brought back in. Hopes are also pinned on the scheduled inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI) in April. Following the index inclusion, global bond-tracking funds flowing into Korea are estimated to reach approximately $60 billion over an eight-month period starting from April this year. However, there is also a view that the level of 'retail investors who ventured overseas' returning to the domestic market is still a question mark, and the impact of bond funds on the foreign exchange market will be limited. (재경부는 올해 중 해외주식을 매도한 자금으로 국내 주식에 투자하면 해외주식 양도소득을 50~100% 감면해주는 법안을 곧 발의해 2월 임시국회 통과를 추진 중이다. 세제 혜택으로 달러로 바꿔 나간 자금을 다시 원화로 환전해 들어오는 효과를 기대하는 것이다. 4월로 예정된 세계국채지수(WGBI) 편입에도 기대를 걸고 있다. 지수 편입에 따라 국내 유입되는 글로벌 채권 추종 자금은 올해 4월부터 8개월간 약 600억달러에 달할 것으로 추산된다. 다만 ‘서학개미’들의 국내 시장 복귀 수준이 아직 물음표인데다 채권 자금이 환율 시장에 미칠 영향은 제한적이라는 시각도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's remarks immediately impacted the market that day. The exchange rate, which had risen to the 1480 won level in early trading, fell to 1,467.7 won during the session and closed at 1,471.3 won, down 6.8 won from the previous day. (이날 이 대통령 발언은 즉각 시장에 영향을 미쳤다. 이날 장 초반 1480원대로 상승하던 환율은 장중 1467.7원까지 떨어졌다가 전날 대비 6.8원 내린 1471.3원에 주간거래를 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240951.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503495.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:46:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NH Investment &amp; Securities, Another Case of Stock Trading Using 'Undisclosed Information' Uncovered... 33 Billion Won in Unfair Gains (NH투자증권, ‘미공개 정보’ 이용 주식 거래 또 적발…33억 부당이득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240960.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/573/343/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503580.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;NH투자증권.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another case of unfair trading using undisclosed information related to public tender offers has been uncovered at NH Investment &amp; Securities. The unfair gains they reaped are estimated to reach approximately 33 billion won. (엔에이치(NH)투자증권에서 공개매수 관련 미공개 정보를 이용한 불공정거래가 추가 적발됐다. 이들이 챙긴 부당이득은 약 33억원에 이르는 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Securities and Futures Commission (SFC) under the Financial Services Commission announced on the 21st that it has uncovered allegations that two former and current executives/employees of NH Investment &amp; Securities and acquaintances who received information from them obtained public tender offer information in advance and purchased stocks beforehand, thereby gaining unfair profits amounting to tens of billions of won. A public tender offer is a system for publicly purchasing stocks outside the market to secure management rights or increase shareholding ratios of a specific company. (금융위원회 산하 증권선물위원회(증선위)는 21일 엔에이치투자증권 전·현직 임직원 2명과 이들로부터 정보를 전달받은 지인 등이 공개매수 정보를 사전에 입수해 주식을 선매수하는 방식으로 수십억원대 부당이득을 취한 혐의를 적발했다고 밝혔다. 공개매수는 특정 기업의 경영권 확보나 지분율 확대를 위해 주식을 시장 밖에서 공개적으로 매수하는 제도다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the SFC, employee Mr. A used undisclosed information related to public tender offers of three listed companies, which he learned in the course of his work, to purchase stocks, and conveyed this information to former employee Mr. B, instructing him to also purchase. During this process, the two are investigated to have reaped a total of 370 million won in unfair gains. Furthermore, six secondary and tertiary recipients who received the information through Mr. B are also found to have traded in the same manner, gaining a total of 2.9 billion won in unfair profits. (증선위에 따르면, 직원 ㄱ씨는 업무 과정에서 알게 된 3개 상장사의 공개매수 관련 미공개 정보를 이용해 주식을 매수했고, 이를 전직 직원인 ㄴ씨에게 전달해 함께 매수하도록 했다. 이 과정에서 두 사람은 총 3억7천만원의 부당이득을 챙긴 것으로 조사됐다. 또 ㄴ씨를 통해 정보를 전달받은 2·3차 수령자 6명도 같은 방식으로 거래해 총 29억원의 부당이득을 취한 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SFC has reported employee Mr. A, an insider at the securities firm, and primary information recipient Mr. B to the prosecution on charges of violating the prohibition on using undisclosed material information under the Capital Markets Act. Additional financial sanctions such as fines may be imposed during the subsequent prosecution investigation and trial process. For the six secondary and tertiary recipients who traded after receiving information from them, a total fine of 3.7 billion won has been imposed for market order disruption. (증선위는 증권사 내부자인 ㄱ씨와 1차 정보 수령자인 ㄴ씨를 자본시장법상 미공개중요정보 이용 금지 위반 혐의로 검찰에 고발했다. 향후 검찰 수사와 재판 과정에서 벌금형 등 추가적인 금전적 제재가 내려질 수 있다. 이들로부터 정보를 전달받아 거래한 2·3차 수령자 6명에 대해서는 시장질서 교란행위로 총 37억원의 과징금을 부과했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This disciplinary action is separate from the &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1225825.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; where an executive in charge of public tender offers at NH Investment &amp; Securities was subject to a search and seizure on charges of leaking information on public tender offers for 11 stocks and reaping about 2 billion won in unfair gains. Following the executive in charge, an employee has now been serially implicated in unfair trading. (이번 조처는 앞서 엔에이치투자증권 공개매수 담당 임원이 11개 종목의 공개매수 정보를 유출해 약 20억원의 부당이득을 챙긴 혐의로 압수수색을 받은 &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1225825.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;사건&lt;/a&gt;과는 별개다. 공개매수 담당 임원에 이어 직원까지 연쇄적으로 불공정거래에 연루된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NH Investment &amp; Securities is the top operator in the domestic public tender offer market. Since 2022, it has acted as the lead manager for 30 out of 47 public tender offers conducted domestically, maintaining a dominant position. Because of this, there are criticisms that the poor internal control related to public tender offers has been revealed as a structural problem. (엔에이치투자증권은 국내 공개매수 시장 1위 사업자다. 지난 2022년 이후 국내에서 진행된 공개매수 47건 가운데 30건을 수임하며 독보적인 주관사 지위를 유지해왔다. 이 때문에 공개매수 관련 내부통제 부실이 구조적인 문제로 드러났다는 지적이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on the same day, the SFC also reported to the prosecution three individuals, including a controlling shareholder of a listed company, who defended against a drop in the stock price of pledged shares through price-manipulating orders and gained 29.4 billion won in unfair profits. (한편 증선위는 이날 시세조종 주문으로 담보주식의 주가 하락을 방어한 뒤 294억원의 부당이득을 취한 상장사 지배주주 등 3명도 검찰에 고발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SFC stated, "We will respond to acts by insiders such as executives and employees of financial companies, who have an information advantage, using undisclosed information to undermine market order, with severe criminal punishment and administrative sanctions." (증선위는 “금융회사 임직원 등 정보 우위에 있는 내부자가 미공개 정보를 이용해 시장 질서를 훼손하는 행위에 대해서는 엄중한 형사처벌과 행정제재로 대응하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240960.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/573/343/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503580.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:45:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Getting Properties Listed is Also Supply"... Hint at Extending the Multi-Homeowner Capital Gains Tax Surcharge Grace Period? (이 대통령 “매물 내놓게 하는 게 공급”…다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 연장 뜻?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240962.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689835089661_20260121503614.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21일 오전 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸 전광판에 이재명 대통령 신년 기자회견 뉴스화면이 나오고 있다. 정용일 선임기자 yongil@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung stated regarding housing supply measures that "getting properties listed for sale is also supply." The market is anticipating that the grace period for the capital gains tax surcharge on multi-homeowners, set to end in May, will be extended again. President Lee also expressed an optimistic outlook on the foreign exchange market, saying, "I predict the exchange rate will fall to around 1,400 won." (이재명 대통령이 주택 공급 대책과 관련해 “매물이 나오게 하는 것도 공급”이라고 밝혔다. 시장에서는 5월 종료를 앞둔 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 유예가 재차 연장될 것이란 전망이 나온다. 이 대통령은 또 “환율이 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”며 외환시장에 대한 낙관적 전망을 공개하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a New Year's press conference held at the Cheong Wa Dae State Guest House on the 21st, regarding the possibility of introducing tax regulations to curb real estate prices, President Lee said, "Taxes are a burden on the people to secure national finances; if they are diverted for other policy purposes, side effects occur," adding, "At this point, we are not deeply considering implementing real estate policy through the tax system." He then discussed supply measures, stating, "Regarding supply, there are also supply measures that involve getting people who own many houses to list them. We are looking for such methods as well." (이 대통령은 21일 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서 부동산 가격 억제를 위해 세금 규제를 도입할 가능성과 관련해 “세금은 국가재정 확보를 위해 국민에 부담을 지우는 것인데, 다른 정책 목표를 위해 전용하면 부작용이 발생한다”며 “지금으로선 세제를 통해 부동산 정책을 하는 것은 깊이 고려하고 있지 않다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 공급대책을 두고 “공급에는 주택을 많이 가지고 있는 사람들이 내놓게 하는 공급책도 있다. 그런 방법도 찾고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The market is interpreting President Lee's remarks as a signal to extend the grace period for the capital gains tax surcharge on multi-homeowners, which is set to end on May 9th. The intention is seen as using the carrot of a tax reduction with a deadline to encourage property listings to come onto the market. Woo Byung-tak, a senior expert at Shinhan Premier Passfinder, explained, "The President's remarks this time could be groundwork for the multi-homeowner capital gains tax surcharge grace period," adding, "However, even if the surcharge grace period is extended, a signal firmly setting the termination point of the grace period must also be given to effectively encourage multi-homeowners to list their properties." (이 대통령의 발언을 시장에서는 오는 5월9일 종료를 앞둔 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예의 연장 신호로 받아들이고 있다. 시한을 두고 양도세 감면이라는 당근을 제시해 매물이 시장에 나오도록 유도하는 뜻이라는 것이다. 우병탁 신한프리미어 패스파인더 전문위원은 “이번 대통령의 발언은 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예에 대한 포석일 가능성이 있다”며 “다만 중과 유예를 연장하더라도 유예 중단 시점을 못 박는 시그널이 반드시 함께 나와줘야만 다주택자들이 매물을 내놓게 하는 효과를 볼 수 있을 것”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also announced that "the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport will soon announce realistic measures to expand (housing) supply." He stated, "We intend to present very specific and realistic figures, not abstract numbers. We will announce measures to increase supply based on permits issued and construction starts, not just planning levels, so please wait." The market predicts that this supply measure will include new sites such as the Taereung Physical Training Center (Taereung CC) in Nowon-gu, Seoul, and the Yongsan International Business District. (이 대통령은 “곧 국토(교통)부에서 현실적인 (주택) 공급 확대 방안을 발표할 것”이라고 예고하기도 했다. 이 대통령은 “추상적 수치보다는 아주 구체적이고 현실적인 수치를 제시하려고 한다. 계획 수준이 아니라 인허가·착공 기준으로 공급을 늘리는 방안을 발표할 테니 기다려달라”고 밝혔다. 시장에서는 이번 공급 대책에 서울 노원구 태릉체력단련장(태릉CC)과 용산국제업무지구 등 신규 부지가 포함될 것이란 예측이 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the 'high exchange rate' fluctuating around the 1,470 won level, President Lee unusually disclosed his exchange rate forecast, saying, "Compared to Japan, our (exchange rate) is less devalued and holding up relatively well," and "I predict it will fall to around 1,400 won in a month or two." The President's mention of a 'month or two' timeline for the downward exchange rate forecast is interpreted as reflecting expectations that the Returning Investor Account (RIA), which offers a 50-100% reduction on capital gains from overseas stocks, could be implemented as early as February, and that from April, up to $60 billion in global bond-tracking funds will flow in due to inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI). President Lee's remarks immediately impacted the market. The exchange rate, which rose to the 1,480 won level early in the session, fell to 1,467.7 won during the day and closed at 1,471.3 won, down 6.8 won from the previous day. (이 대통령은 1470원대를 오르내리는 ‘고환율’에 대해서도 “일본에 비하면 우리 (환율은) 평가 절하가 덜 되고 잘 견디고 있는 편”이라며 “한두 달 정도 지나면 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”고 이례적으로 환율 전망을 공개했다. 이 대통령이 환율 하향화 전망 시점을 ‘한두 달’로 이야기한 것은 해외주식 양도소득을 50~100% 감면해주는 국내시장 복귀계좌(RIA)가 빠르면 2월 시행되고, 4월부터 세계국채지수(WGBI) 편입으로 글로벌 채권 추종 자금이 최대 600억달러 규모 유입될 것이란 기대감을 표시한 것으로 읽힌다. 이날 이 대통령 발언은 즉각 시장에 영향을 미쳤다. 장 초반 1480원대로 상승하던 환율은 장중 1467.7원까지 떨어졌다가 전날 대비 6.8원 내린 1471.3원에 주간거래를 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, regarding the recent U.S. plan to impose 100% tariffs on semiconductors, President Lee said, "If that happens, U.S. semiconductor prices will rise by 100%," adding, "I am not that seriously concerned." Responding to a related question, he stated, "If we get overly excited or worried with every change, we cannot maintain our center. Precisely at times like these, we must respond based on our own center and 'principles'." Previously, South Korea and the U.S. agreed through last year's tariff negotiations to apply tariffs on the semiconductor sector that are 'no less favorable than those for Taiwan'. Mentioning this, President Lee also said, "I hope Taiwan endures well." (한편 이 대통령은 최근 미국의 반도체 100% 관세 부과 계획에 대해서도 “그러면 미국 반도체 물가가 100% 오를 것”이라며 “그렇게 심각하게 우려하지 않는다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 관련 질문에 “일희일비하면 중심을 잡을 수 없다. 이럴 때일수록 자기 중심을 가지고 ‘원칙’에 따라 대응해 나가야 한다”며 이같이 말했다. 앞서 한국과 미국은 지난해 관세협상을 통해 반도체 부문에 대해 ‘대만보다 불리하지 않은 관세’ 적용을 합의한 바 있다. 이 대통령은 이를 거론하며 “대만이 잘 견뎌내길 바란다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Lee Ji-hye, Park Su-ji, Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 박수지 김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240962.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689835089661_20260121503614.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:45:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PIPC Chairperson: "We deployed a record 14 investigators for Coupang probe... trade issues not considered" (개보위원장 “쿠팡 조사에 역대 최다 14명 투입…통상 문제 고려 안 해”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240965.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/946/567/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689836320155_20260121503642.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21일 서울 중구 프레스센터에서 개최된 출입기자단 신년간담회에서 인사말 중인 송경희 개인정보보호위원회 위원장. 개인정보보호위원회 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Song Kyung-hee, the Chairperson of the Personal Information Protection Commission (PIPC), criticized Coupang, which caused a data breach affecting 33.7 million customers, for being uncooperative in the related investigation. She stated the intention to swiftly conclude the investigation by deploying a record 14 investigators. Regarding concerns that the 'Coupang incident' could escalate into a trade issue between South Korea and the US, she said it is "not a consideration" and that they will handle the matter according to principle. (송경희 개인정보보호위원회(개보위) 위원장이 ‘고객 3370만명의 개인정보 유출사고를 낸 쿠팡이 관련 조사에 비협조적’이라고 비판하며 역대 최다인 14명의 조사관을 투입해 조사를 조속히 마무리하겠다는 뜻을 밝혔다. 그는 ‘쿠팡 사태’가 한미 간 통상 문제로 번질 수 있다는 우려에 대해서는 “고려 대상이 아니”라며 원칙에 따라 조처하겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairperson Song Kyung-hee disclosed the investigation status and future plans regarding data breach incidents involving domestic and foreign companies last year, including Coupang, SK Telecom (SKT), and KT, at a press briefing held at the Press Center in Jung-gu, Seoul on the 21st. (송경희 위원장은 21일 서울 중구 프레스센터에서 열린 기자간담회에서 쿠팡과 에스케이텔레콤(SKT), 케이티(KT) 등 지난해 발생한 국내외 기업에 대한 개인정보유출사고 조사 현황과 향후 계획을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the briefing, she stated regarding the scale of Coupang's data breach, "It's over 30 million people, and there is a sufficient possibility that non-member information was also leaked." She then revealed that 14 investigators have been deployed for this case investigation. This is a 'record high' number, three more than the personnel deployed for the investigation into SK Telecom, which caused a data breach affecting 23 million people last year. Chairperson Song said, "The investigation has progressed considerably," but added, "If asked whether (Coupang is being) 'cooperative,' (I would answer) it is not sufficient," and "For speeding up the investigation, how the other party responds is also important." (그는 이 자리에서 쿠팡의 개인정보 유출 규모에 대해 “3천만명 이상이고 비회원 정보도 충분히 유출됐을 가능성이 있다”고 말했다. 그러면서 이 사건 조사를 위해 조사관 14명을 투입했다고 밝혔다. 이는 지난해 2300만명의 개인정보 유출 사고를 낸 에스케이텔레콤 조사 인력보다 3명 많은 ‘역대 최다’ 규모다. 송 위원장은 “조사가 상당히 진행된 상황”이라면서도 “(쿠팡이 조사에) ‘협조적인가’라고 묻는다면 충분하지 않다(고 답하겠다)”며 “(조사 속도를 내기 위해서는) 상대방도 어떻게 대응하는가가 중요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the point that there is concern about attempts by the US political sphere to interfere with the investigation given Coupang is a US company, she answered, "The company's nationality is not important," and "We will handle it strictly based on the Personal Information Protection Act. (Trade issues with the US) are not being considered as a variable." (그는 쿠팡이 미국 기업이라는 점에서 미국 정치권의 조사 방해 시도가 우려된다는 지적에는 “기업 국적은 중요하지 않다”며 “개인정보보호법에 근거해서 엄격하게 조처하겠다. (미국과의) 통상 문제는 변수로 고려하고 있지 않다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding SK Telecom, which received a record 134.8 billion won administrative fine for violating the Personal Information Protection Act and has filed an administrative lawsuit contesting the penalty, Chairperson Song stated it was "a penalty issued after thorough review" and expressed the position to actively respond. She pointed out, "The argument that the fine is excessive or unfair because no actual damage occurred is not correct," and "The fine is of a nature that holds (the company) responsible for harming data subjects in the process of utilizing personal information." (송 위원장은 개인정보보호법 위반으로 역대 최다인 1348억원의 과징금을 부과받은 에스케이텔레콤이 처분에 불복해 행정소송을 낸 것을 두고서는 “철저하게 검토한 처분”이라며 적극적으로 대응하겠단 입장을 밝혔다. 그는 “실제 피해가 발생하지 않았다고 과징금이 과분하다거나 부당하다는 것(주장)은 맞지 않는다”며 “과징금은 개인정보를 활용하는 과정에서 정보주체에 피해를 끼치는 것에 대한 책임 성격”이라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Chae Ban-seok &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240965.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/946/567/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689836320155_20260121503642.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:44:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Wonkwang Digital University's Yoga and Meditation Department Successfully Concludes Scoliosis-Specific Exercise Schroth Therapy Workshop (원광디지털대 요가명상학과, 척추측만 전문운동 슈로스테라피 워크숍 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240972.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/4017689849092719.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;원광디지털대 요가명상학과, 슈로스테라피 워크숍 (원광디지털대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University's Department of Yoga and Meditation (Department Head Seung-tae Park) successfully held the 'Scoliosis-Specific Exercise Schroth Therapy Workshop' at its Seoul Campus on Saturday, January 17th. (원광디지털대학교 요가명상학과(학과장 박승태)는 지난 1월 17일(토) 서울캠퍼스에서 ‘척추측만 전문운동 슈로스테라피 워크숍’을 성공적으로 개최했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This workshop was designed to systematically learn the principles of scoliosis correction and postural alignment and to strengthen professional capabilities for applying these principles in yoga therapy practice. (이번 워크숍은 척추측만 교정과 자세 정렬의 원리를 체계적으로 학습하고, 이를 요가테라피 현장에 적용할 수 있도록 전문 역량을 강화하기 위해 마련됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The training was directly instructed by lecturer Sang-gil Lee (CEO of SchrothSpine Co., Ltd., Ph.D. in Sports Medicine), who holds the only German Schroth Master qualification in Korea. The program focused on practical skills, covering posture assessment, breathing assessment methods, and distinguishing between exercises beneficial for scoliosis and those requiring caution. (이번 교육은 국내 유일의 독일 슈로스마스터 자격을 보유한 이상길 강사(㈜슈로스파인 대표, 스포츠의학 박사)가 직접 지도했으며, 자세 평가와 호흡 평가법, 그리고 척추측만증에 도움이 되는 운동과 주의해야 할 운동을 구분하는 실전 중심 내용으로 진행됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The morning session, themed 'Schroth Therapy 1: Posture Assessment and Breathing Assessment Methods,' involved understanding the structural characteristics of scoliosis and practicing professional evaluation methods based on this understanding. Participants directly experienced individual posture analysis and breathing pattern assessment, gaining an in-depth understanding of the scientific principles behind scoliosis correction exercises. (오전 강의에서는 ‘슈로스테라피1: 자세평가와 호흡평가법’을 주제로, 척추측만증의 구조적 특징을 이해하고 이를 바탕으로 한 전문적인 평가 방법을 실습했다. 참가자들은 개별 자세 분석과 호흡 패턴 평가를 직접 경험하며, 척추측만 교정 운동의 과학적 원리를 깊이 있게 이해하는 시간을 가졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The afternoon featured a more advanced practical session themed 'Schroth Therapy 2: Exercises Harmful and Beneficial for Scoliosis.' The lecture presented customized exercise methods for different types of scoliosis based on actual clinical cases and specifically explained the impact of incorrect exercises on spinal alignment. The sharing of various case analyses and practical know-how from Schroth therapy settings garnered a highly positive response from participants. (오후에는 ‘슈로스테라피2: 척추측만에 해가 되는 운동과 약이 되는 운동’을 주제로 보다 심화된 실습이 이루어졌다. 강의에서는 실제 임상 사례를 바탕으로 척추측만 유형별 맞춤 운동법을 제시하고, 잘못된 운동이 척추 정렬에 미치는 영향을 구체적으로 설명했다. 특히 슈로스테라피 현장에서 나타나는 다양한 케이스 분석과 실전 노하우가 공유되어 참가자들의 큰 호응을 얻었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participating students shared their impressions, stating, "It was very beneficial to learn an accurate understanding and assessment methods for scoliosis," and "There was a lot of practical content applicable to yoga instruction settings." This course issued a certificate of completion to those who attended both the first and second workshops and was operated as a continuous program to cultivate professional yoga therapy instructors. (워크숍에 참가한 학생들은 “척추측만증에 대한 정확한 이해와 평가법을 배울 수 있어 매우 유익했다”, “요가 지도 현장에 적용할 수 있는 실질적인 내용이 많았다”는 소감을 전했다. 이번 과정은 1차와 2차 워크숍을 모두 수강할 경우 수료증이 발급되며, 전문성을 갖춘 요가테라피 지도자 양성을 위한 연속 프로그램으로 운영되었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seung-tae Park, Department Head of Wonkwang Digital University's Yoga and Meditation Department, stated, "This Schroth therapy workshop was an important educational program that elevated the level of expertise in the field of yoga therapy," adding, "We will continue to expand practical, field-oriented educational programs to strengthen the capabilities of our current students and graduates." (원광디지털대학교 요가명상학과 박승태학과장은 “이번 슈로스테라피 워크숍은 요가테라피 분야의 전문성을 한 단계 높이는 중요한 교육 과정이었다”며, “앞으로도 재학생과 졸업생의 현장 역량 강화를 위한 실무 중심 교육 프로그램을 지속적으로 확대해 나가겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240972.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/4017689849092719.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:44:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic Autonomous Driving Entering 'Level 4'... Securing Real-World Road Data is Key (국내 자율주행 ‘레벨4’ 진입중…실제 도로 데이터 확보 관건)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240998.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503953.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 강남구 자율주행 시범운행지구에서 자율주행차량이 시험운행을 위해 대기하고 있다. 업체 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;I couldn't lean back in the seat due to anxiety. Sitting upright in the back seat, I alternately watched the person in the driver's seat and the windshield. As the autonomous electric vehicle gradually increased speed and entered near a construction site in Seoul's Gangnam district, my body instinctively tensed up. This was because traffic controllers were directing vehicles in the middle of the road. However, the autonomous vehicle came to a smooth stop, then slightly turned its direction to the left and continued driving. Later, in an alleyway it entered, it moved slowly to avoid a person coming from the roadway, not the sidewalk. Soon, I leaned back in the seat. It felt as stable as if driven by a driver with ten years of experience. (불안함에 좌석 등받이에 등을 기대지 못했다. 뒷자리에 곧게 앉아 운전석에 앉은 이와 앞유리를 번갈아 살폈다. 자율주행 전기차가 서서히 속도를 높여 서울 강남의 공사장 근처로 들어서자 절로 몸에 힘이 들어갔다. 신호수들이 도로 한가운데서 차량을 통제하고 있었기 때문이다. 하지만 자율주행차는 부드럽게 멈춰선 뒤, 방향을 왼쪽으로 살짝 틀어 주행을 이어갔다. 뒤이어 들어선 골목길에서는 인도가 아닌 차도로 오는 사람을 피해 천천히 움직였다. 이내 등받이에 등을 기대고 앉았다. 경력 10년 차 운전자가 모는 듯한 안정감이 느껴졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a sports car approached from the left rear with a loud roar during the test drive by autonomous driving specialist company G, this car slightly reduced its speed. When a bus approached from the right, it changed lanes once to maintain distance. During a recent approximately 1-hour, 10km drive around the Gangnam area, there were quite a few unexpected variables. However, the person in the driver's seat merely sat there; except for school zones, they did not manually operate the steering wheel or brake pedal even once throughout the entire route. (  자율주행 전문기업 ㄱ사가 시험 운행 중인 이 차는 스포츠카가 왼쪽 뒤쪽에서 큰 굉음을 내며 달려오자 살짝 속도를 줄였고, 버스가 오른쪽에서 다가오자 차선을 한 번 변경해 거리를 유지하기도 했다. 최근 강남 일대를 10km가량 주행하는 약 1시간 동안 돌발 변수가 적지 않았지만, 운전자는 운전석에 앉아 있기만 할 뿐 어린이보호구역을 뺀 전 구간에서 운전대나 브레이크 페달을 단 한 번도 직접 조작하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Such autonomous driving demonstration operations are being conducted in various locations through collaboration between companies and central/local governments. According to a Hankyoreh investigation compiled on the 21st, based on the 'Act on Promotion and Support of Commercialization of Autonomous Vehicles', the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport (MOLIT) has designated 55 locations nationwide, including Seoul's Gangnam-gu, Jongno-gu, Jung-gu, and Busan, as autonomous vehicle demonstration operation zones as of the end of last year, providing regulatory sandbox (real-world testing) exceptions. A regulatory sandbox is a system that exempts new products or services from existing regulations under certain conditions to test and verify safety, etc. In these areas, autonomous driving startups and others are conducting test operations mainly on designated routes/sections. However, testing is only possible outside of commuting hours, and a significant portion of these areas are highways without pedestrians or traffic lights, which has limited learning for various exceptional situations (edge cases). (  이런 자율주행 시범 운행은 중앙 정부와 지방정부를 중심으로 기업과의 협업을 통해 곳곳에서 이뤄지고 있다. 21일 한겨레 취재를 종합하면, 국토교통부는 ‘자율주행자동차 상용화 촉진 및 지원에 관한 법률’에 따라 지난해 말 기준 서울 강남구·종로구·중구, 부산시 등 전국 55곳을 자율주행자동차 시범운행지구로 지정해 실증 특례를 제공하고 있다. 실증 특례란 새로운 제품이나 서비스에 대해 일정 조건에서 기존 규제를 면제해주고 안전성 등을 시험·검증하는 제도다. 이들 지역에서는 지정된 노선·구간 중심으로 자율주행 스타트업 등이 시험 운행을 추진 중이다. 다만, 출퇴근 시간대를 피해서만 실증이 가능하고, 이들 지역 상당수가 보행자나 신호등이 없는 고속도로여서 다양한 예외적 상황(엣지 케이스)에 대한 학습에 한계가 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this reason, MOLIT selected Gwangju Metropolitan City as the nation's first autonomous driving regulatory sandbox city on this day. The plan is to relax related regulations across the entire city and create an autonomous driving ecosystem linking large-scale driving data collection to specialized talent cultivation. In Gwangju, like San Francisco, USA or Wuhan, China, 24/7 real-world testing becomes possible across the entire city. This is a follow-up measure following the government's announcement last year to pursue 'commercialization of Level 4 autonomous vehicles by 2027'. Autonomous driving levels are divided into six stages from Level 0 (fully manual) to Level 5 (fully autonomous). The government plans to elevate domestic autonomous driving technology, currently at Level 3 (autonomous driving possible on highways, etc., but driver intervention required in specific situations like weather anomalies), to Level 4 (autonomous driving possible on most roads, driver intervention unnecessary). MOLIT stated, "By designating the entire city as a demonstration operation zone at once, diverse edge case learning is needed from alleyways to overpasses, underpasses, and intersections," adding, "Gwangju is a large city with a population over 1.3 million and has mixed urban-rural characteristics, making large-scale real-world testing in diverse environments seem possible." (이런 이유에서 국토부는 이날 국내 첫 자율주행 실증도시로 광주광역시를 선정했다. 도시 전역에 관련 규제를 풀고, 대규모 주행 데이터 수집부터 특화 인재 양성까지 이어지는 자율주행 생태계를 조성하기로 한 것이다. 광주에서는 미국 샌프란시스코·중국 우한처럼 도시 전역에서 24시간 실증이 가능해진다. 이는 지난해 정부가 ‘2027년 레벨4 자율주행차 상용화’를 추진하겠다고 한 데 따른 후속 조처다. 자율주행 단계는 레벨0(완전수동)부터 레벨5(완전 자율주행)까지 6단계로 나뉘는데, 정부는 현재 레벨3(고속도로 등에서 자율주행이 가능하지만 기상이변 등 특정 상황에서 운전자 개입이 필요한 수준) 단계인 국내 자율주행 기술을 레벨4(대부분의 도로에서 자율주행이 가능하며 운전자 개입이 불필요한 수준)로 끌어올린다는 계획이다. 국토부는 “도시 전역을 시범운행지구로 일괄 지정해 골목길부터 고가도로, 지하차도, 교차로 등에서 다양한 엣지케이스 학습이 필요하다”며 “광주는 인구 130만명 이상의 대도시이면서 도·농 복합적 특성을 보유해, 다양한 환경에서의 대규모 실증이 가능할 것으로 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local governments are also conducting their own autonomous vehicle trial operations. Seoul Metropolitan Government's 'Late-Night Autonomous Taxi' is a prime example. The city has been operating this taxi, limited to the Gangnam area, since September 26, 2024. As of the end of November last year, the cumulative number of rides over more than a year was 6,343, and the cumulative driving distance was 30,000 km. The city plans to convert the autonomous taxi, which has been operating as a free trial, to a paid service as early as next month. An autonomous vehicle in the form of a village bus began operation in Dongjak-gu in July last year, and expanded its operating area to Dongdaemun-gu and Seodaemun-gu starting in October of the same year. (  지방정부가 자체적으로 자율주행차를 시범 운행하기도 한다. 서울시의 ‘심야 자율주행 택시’가 대표적이다. 시는 강남 지역에 한정해 2024년 9월26일부터 이 택시를 운행해왔다. 지난해 11월 말 기준 1년여 넘는 기간 누적 탑승 건수는 6343건, 누적 운행 거리는 3만km다. 시는 무료로 시범 운영해 온 자율주행 택시를 이르면 다음달 안에 유료로 전환할 예정이다. 마을버스 형태의 자율주행차는 지난해 7월 동작구에서 운행을 시작했고, 같은 해 10월부터 운행 지역을 동대문구·서대문구로 확대했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is an assessment that there is still 'a long way to go' until the commercialization of autonomous driving in Korea. First, the absolute volume of data is small. Looking at data from Waymo, Google's autonomous robotaxi service in the US, this company, operating over 2,000 autonomous vehicles, had a cumulative driving distance exceeding 200 million km as of September last year. Chinese IT company Baidu is collecting related data by operating over 1,000 vehicles for more than 100 million km. In contrast, in Korea, the cumulative driving distance of all companies combined is only 13.06 million km. The number of operating vehicles is also limited to 132. Furthermore, it is pointed out as a limitation that Korea remains at the demonstration project stage, centered on startups' limited real-world testing with conditions of free transportation and manned operation. This is because China and the US have already entered the phase of paid transportation and unmanned operation, focusing on user experience and driving stability. (  다만, 국내 자율주행 상용화까지는 여전히 ‘갈 길이 멀다’는 평가가 나온다. 우선 절대적인 데이터양이 적기 때문이다. 미국 구글의 자율주행 로보택시 서비스 웨이모 자료를 보면, 2천대가 넘는 자율주행차를 운행하는 이 기업의 지난해 9월 기준 누적 주행거리는 2억㎞를 웃돈다. 중국 정보기술(IT) 기업인 바이두는 1천대로 1억㎞ 이상 운행하며 관련 데이터를 모으고 있다. 반면 한국의 경우, 전체 기업의 누적 주행거리는 1306만km에 불과하다. 운행대수도 132대에 그친다. 또한 한국은 스타트업 중심의 제한적 실증을 통해 무상운송·유인운행을 조건으로 한 시범 사업 단계에 머물러 있다는 점도 한계로 꼽힌다. 중국과 미국에서는 이미 유상운송·무인운행에 돌입해 사용자 경험과 주행 안정성에 초점을 두고 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experts point out that the task of securing high-quality data is paramount. It's not about accumulating data from simple driving on obstacle-free roads according to signals, but data that responds to variables actually encountered on Korean roads, such as near construction sites, pedestrians, buses, and other vehicles obstructing the path. Professor Choi Jun-won of Seoul National University (School of Electrical and Computer Engineering) said, "We must accumulate large-scale data based on the development of End-to-End (E2E) autonomous driving technology (a method where AI makes all driving decisions from start to finish)," adding, "The government should provide companies with opportunities to test their technology in the real world and develop it further, create a competitive arena, and support companies so they can freely accumulate data and develop AI models." (  전문가들은 양질의 데이터를 확보하는 작업이 무엇보다 중요하다고 지적한다. 방해 요소가 없는 도로를 신호에 맞춰 단순 주행하는 데이터가 아니라, 공사 현장 인근, 보행자와 버스, 다른 차량의 진로 방해 등 실제 한국 도로에서 마주하는 변수에 대응하는 데이터가 쌓여야 한다는 것이다. 최준원 서울대 교수(전기·정보공학부)는 “엔드투엔드(E2E) 자율주행 기술(인공지능이 처음부터 끝까지 직접 운전을 결정하는 방식) 개발을 기반으로 대규모 데이터를 쌓아야 한다”며 “정부는 기업들이 기술을 실증하고 이를 발전시킬 기회를 제공하고, 경쟁의 장을 만들어 기업들이 자유롭게 데이터를 쌓고 인공지능 모델 개발을 할 수 있도록 지원해줘야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240998.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503953.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:43:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FutureLink CEO: "Development of Autonomous Driving Industry Requires Cooperation Among Manufacturers, Government, and Insurers" (퓨처링크 대표 “자율주행 산업 발전, 제조사·정부·보험사 협력 필요”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241001.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503958.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;차두원 퓨처링크 대표가 지난달 31일 경기도 성남시 회사 사무실에서 한겨레와 인터뷰를 하고 있다. 유하영 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike the United States or China, where big tech (large technology companies) lead the industry, the domestic autonomous vehicle sector in Korea shows a pattern of small, unlisted, and new companies struggling against the odds. FutureLink is one such company. According to the company's explanation, it has conducted test operations with nine autonomous vehicles in the Gangnam District of Seoul, an autonomous driving pilot zone designated by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, covering approximately 40,000 kilometers in less than a year without any accidents. (빅테크(거대 기술기업)가 산업을 주도하는 미국이나 중국과 달리 국내 자율주행차 분야에서는 영세한 비상장·신규 기업들이 고군분투 중인 양상을 보인다. 퓨처링크도 이런 기업 가운데 하나다. 국토교통부가 지정한 자율주행 시범운행 지구인 서울 강남구 일대에서 자율주행차 9대로 시험운행을 해 1년이 채 되지 않는 기간에 약 4만km를 달렸고, 이 과정에서 사고가 나지 않았다는 것이 회사 쪽 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting at FutureLink's office in Seongnam, Gyeonggi Province on the 31st of last month, CEO Cha Du-won stated, "In a rapidly evolving field like autonomous driving, the speed of market entry is itself a competitive edge and a survival skill." CEO Cha previously worked at Hyundai Mobis and the Hyundai Motor Group, followed by the Korea Institute of Science &amp; Technology Evaluation and Planning (KISTEP) and the New Industry Regulatory Innovation Committee under the Office for Government Policy Coordination. This is why he is regarded in the industry as an expert with comprehensive experience across the entire spectrum of autonomous driving technology, from the technology itself to regulations. (  지난달 31일 경기도 성남시 퓨처링크 사무실에서 만난 차두원 대표는 이를 두고 “자율주행처럼 빠르게 진화하는 분야에서는 시장진입 속도가 곧 경쟁력이자 생존의 기술”이라고 했다. 차 대표는 앞서 현대모비스와 현대자동차그룹을 거쳐 한국과학기술기획평가원, 국무조정실 신산업규제혁신위원회 등에서 근무했다. 그가 업계에서 기술부터 규제까지 자율주행 기술 전반에 대한 경험을 두루 갖춘 전문가로 평가받는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CEO Cha stated that for the development of the autonomous driving industry, not only must the industry's technological development progress, but government deregulation and the creation of an initial market must also occur simultaneously and in parallel. He said, "The reason Google's autonomous robotaxi service, Waymo, receives massive investment is because it has already proven its business viability with hundreds of thousands of paid ride instances," adding, "It is also crucial to collaborate with automakers, telecommunications companies, local governments, insurance companies, etc., to achieve things that cannot be done alone." (  차 대표는 자율주행 산업 발전을 위해서는 업계의 기술 개발은 물론, 정부의 규제 완화·초기 시장 창출이 동시다발적으로 이뤄져야 한다고 했다. 그는 “미국 구글의 자율주행 로보택시 서비스 웨이모가 대규모 투자를 받는 이유는 이미 수십만 건의 유료 탑승 실적으로 비즈니스가 작동함을 증명했기 때문”이라며 “완성차 제조사, 통신사, 지방정부, 보험사 등과의 협력해 단독으로 할 수 없는 일을 함께 해내는 것도 중요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also emphasized the role of the government. He said, "For companies to decide on investments, matters such as liability in case of accidents, the insurance framework, and data management standards must be clear," adding, "Currently, there is still significant legal uncertainty, and this causes hesitation in market investment decisions." He further added, "If the government builds public infrastructure like high-definition maps and 5G networks, concerns and burdens about redundant investments by individual companies will be reduced." He also stated, "Public-sector initiatives, such as mandating the introduction of autonomous shuttles in public institutions, university campuses, and new cities, or filling late-night public transportation gaps with robotaxis, must continue." (그는 정부의 역할도 강조했다. 그는 “사고가 일어났을 때 책임 소재, 보험 체계, 데이터 관리 기준 등이 명확해야 기업들이 투자를 결정할 수 있다”며 “현재는 여전히 법적 불확실성이 크고 이것이 시장의 투자 결정을 주저하게 한다”고 말했다. 이어 “정밀 지도, 5지(G) 네트워크 같은 공공인프라를 정부가 구축해야 개별 기업의 중복투자 우려와 부담이 줄어든다”고 덧붙였다. 그는 또한 “공공기관, 대학 캠퍼스, 신도시 등에서 자율주행 셔틀을 의무 도입하거나 심야 대중교통 공백을 로보택시로 메우는 식의 공공형 움직임이 계속돼야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To secure technological completeness, FutureLink selected Pony.ai, a Level 4 autonomous driving technology company (capable of driverless operation in specific areas), as its partner. The strategy is to utilize technology already validated in the global market and localize it for Korea's road environment. He said, "Our goal is to contribute to creating a Korean autonomous driving service model by the time of Level 4 commercialization, which the government aims for by 2027." (  퓨처링크는 기술 완성도를 확보하고자 자율주행 레벨4(특정 구간에서 운전자 없이 자율주행이 가능한 수준) 기술 기업 포니에이아이(AI)를 파트너로 선정했다. 이미 글로벌 시장에서 검증된 기술을 활용해 한국의 도로 환경에 맞게 현지화한다는 전략이다. 그는 “정부가 2027년 목표로 하는 레벨4 상용화 시점에 한국형 자율주행 서비스 모델 제작에 기여하는 것이 목표”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241001.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503958.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:43:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>