<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>[Breaking News] KOSPI Breaches 5,000 for the First Time in 46 Years ([속보] 코스피, 46년 만에 첫 ‘5000’ 돌파)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241056.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[Breaking News] KOSPI Breaches 5,000 for the First Time in 46 Years ([속보] 코스피, 46년 만에 첫 ‘5000’ 돌파)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/554/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500462.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;우리은행 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, the KOSPI index breached the 5,000 mark for the first time ever during intraday trading. This comes 46 years after the market opened at 100 points on January 4, 1980. (코스피가 22일 장중 사상 처음으로 5000을 돌파했다. 1980년 1월 4일 코스피 100으로 장을 연지 46년 만의 일이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the Korea Exchange, the KOSPI opened at 4,987.06, up 1.57% from the previous session, and immediately hit 5,002.88, breaking through the 5,000 level. As of 9:10 a.m., it is fluctuating around the 5,000 mark. After historically surpassing the 4,000 level for the first time last year, the KOSPI has continued its steep upward trend this year, setting new record highs almost daily. (이날 유가증권 시장에서 코스피는 전장보다 1.57% 오른 4987.06에 개장해 곧바로 5002.88을 찍으며 5000을 돌파했다. 9시10분 현재 5000선에서 등락을 거듭하고 있다. 지난해 사상 처음 4000선을 돌파한 코스피는 올해 들어 연일 최고치를 경신하며 가파른 상승세를 이어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI first broke through the 1,000 mark in 1989, taking nine years after the index's calculation began. It then took over 30 years to surpass the 3,000 level, first reaching the 3,000-point milestone on January 7, 2021. Following the end of internal conflicts and improvements in the semiconductor industry's conditions, it broke above 4,000 on October 27 last year for the first time in four years, and has now reached the 5,000 mark in just three months. (코스피가 처음으로 1000선을 뚫은 것은 1989년이었다. 지수 산출 뒤 9년이 걸렸다. 이후 3000선을 넘기까지 30년 넘게 걸려 2021년 1월7일 처음 3000고지를 밟았다. 내란 종식과 반도체 업황 개선 등으로 지난해 10월27일 4년 만에 4000선을 넘더니, 불과 석 달 만에 5000선에 도달한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semiconductor stocks rose sharply in the New York stock market overnight after U.S. President Donald Trump withdrew tariffs on Greenland. Today, Samsung Electronics is trading at 154,500 won, up 3.34%, and SK Hynix is trading at 768,000 won, up 3.78%. Hyundai Motor is also trading at 577,000 won, up 5.10%. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 그린란드 관세를 철회하면서 간밤 뉴욕증시에서 반도체주가 크게 올랐다. 이날 삼성전자가 3.34% 오른 15만4500원, 에스케이하이닉스가 3.78% 오른 76만8000원에 거래 중이다. 현대차도 5.10% 오른 57만7000원에 거래 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Kyung-mi &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이경미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241056.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/554/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500462.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Presenting a Practical Graduate School Model Linking Industry, Academia, and Research... Seoul City University's Early Employment Contract Department Info Session Successfully Concludes (산학연 연계 실무형 대학원 모델 제시… 서울시립대 조기취업형 계약학과 설명회 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241066.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Presenting a Practical Graduate School Model Linking Industry, Academia, and Research... Seoul City University's Early Employment Contract Department Info Session Successfully Concludes (산학연 연계 실무형 대학원 모델 제시… 서울시립대 조기취업형 계약학과 설명회 성료)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/468/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3717690455463015.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;궤도 행사 사진.서울시립대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Seoul City University Graduate School Early Employment Contract Department Project Team (Biohealth &amp; Eco Convergence Department) held an information session for the Early Employment Contract Department on January 21st at the main campus and invited 'Orbit', a creator in the science and engineering field, to give a special lecture. This session was held to enhance students' understanding of the Early Employment Contract Department and to establish a support system linking career paths, graduate studies, and employment.&lt;br/&gt;The event began with an introduction to the practical graduate school model, covering the operational purpose, curriculum, corporate participation structure, employment linkage, and industry-academia projects of the Early Employment Contract Department. In the following special lecture, Orbit shared cases of change and innovation in future technology fields under the theme 'Can Unconventional Curiosity Change the World?', presenting various possibilities for science and engineering students to explore career paths in technology-based industries.&lt;br/&gt;The atmosphere was particularly lively as explanations about the competencies and experiences needed in trending future industrial fields such as biohealth, eco-friendliness, AI, and data-based industries were followed by student questions. A vibrant Q&amp;A session addressed practical concerns regarding graduate school attendance, industry field experience, career planning, balancing research and practical work, and corporate-participation education models.&lt;br/&gt;Reflecting high student interest in the Early Employment Contract Department, this info session showed strong participation, with the first 200 spots filled within two days of promotion opening. Consultations and inquiries about additional sessions continued before and after the event, confirming undergraduate demand for linking graduate studies and careers.&lt;br/&gt;Jeong Yeon-du, head of the Seoul City University Graduate School Early Employment Contract Department Project Team, stated, "The industry needs talent equipped with both practical and research capabilities in innovative fields, and social demand for an educational model supporting this is growing." He added, "I hope this info session helps students actively design their graduate studies and careers." He continued, "Seoul City University will play a role in nurturing talent amid industrial transformation through industry-academia linked practical education."&lt;br/&gt;The Biohealth &amp; Eco Convergence Department operates as part of the Ministry of Education's Leading Graduate School Fostering Project for Early Employment Contract Departments. It runs a curriculum reflecting industry demands in convergence areas like biohealth, environment, and data, aiming to cultivate talent with immediately applicable practical skills by combining experiments, projects, corporate internships, and field-based education.&lt;br/&gt;Seoul City University plans to expand student participation in the Early Employment Contract Department through follow-up programs such as counseling, open campus events, admissions info sessions, and corporate mentoring. It also plans to develop the practical graduate school model that connects graduate studies, employment, and research by strengthening cooperation with industry. (서울시립대학교 대학원 조기취업형 계약학과 사업단(바이오헬스·에코 융합학과)은 1월 21일 본교에서 조기취업형 계약학과 설명회를 개최하고 이공계 분야 크리에이터 ‘궤도’를 초청해 특강을 진행했다. 이번 설명회는 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생들의 이해를 높이고 진로·진학·취업을 연계한 지원 체계를 마련하기 위해 개최됐다.&lt;br/&gt;행사에서는 먼저 조기취업형 계약학과의 운영 목적, 교육 과정, 기업 참여 구조, 취업 연계, 산학 프로젝트 등 실무 중심 대학원 모델에 대한 소개가 진행됐다. 이어진 특강에서 궤도는 ‘엉뚱한 호기심이 세상을 바꿀 수 있을까?’를 주제로 미래 기술 분야의 변화와 혁신 사례를 공유하며, 이공계 학생들이 기술 기반 산업에서 진로를 탐색할 수 있는 다양한 가능성을 제시했다.&lt;br/&gt;특히 바이오헬스, 친환경, AI, 데이터 기반 산업 등 이슈가 되는 미래 산업 분야에서 어떤 역량과 경험이 필요한지에 대한 설명과 함께 학생들의 질문이 이어지며 현장 분위기가 뜨거웠다. 대학원 진학 여부, 산업 현장 경험, 커리어 설계, 연구와 실무 간 균형, 기업 참여형 교육 모델 등 현실적인 고민에 대한 질의응답이 활발하게 진행됐다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 설명회는 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생들의 높은 관심을 반영하듯 홍보 시작 이틀 만에 선착순 200명이 마감되며 높은 참여 열기를 보였다. 행사 전후로 상담 및 추가 설명회 문의가 이어지며 진학과 커리어를 연계하려는 학부생 수요가 확인됐다.&lt;br/&gt;서울시립대학교 대학원 조기취업형 계약학과 사업단 정연두 단장은 “산업계는 혁신 분야에서 실무와 연구 역량을 모두 갖춘 인재를 필요로 하고 있으며, 이를 뒷받침하는 교육 모델에 대한 사회적 수요가 커지고 있다”고 밝히며 “이번 설명회가 학생들이 진학과 커리어를 능동적으로 설계하는 데 도움이 되길 바란다”고 말했다. 이어 “서울시립대학교는 산학 연계 기반 실무형 교육을 통해 산업 전환 속 인재양성 역할을 수행할 것”이라고 덧붙였다.&lt;br/&gt;바이오헬스·에코융합학과는 교육부가 주관하는 조기취업형 계약학과 선도대학원 육성사업의 일환으로 바이오헬스·환경·데이터 등 융합 영역에서 산업 수요를 반영한 교육과정을 운영하고 있으며, 실험·프로젝트·기업 실습·현장 기반 교육을 결합해 실무에서 바로 활용 가능한 역량을 갖춘 인재 양성을 목표로 하고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;서울시립대학교는 향후 상담 프로그램, 오픈캠퍼스, 입시 설명회, 기업 멘토링 등 후속 사업을 통해 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생 참여를 확대할 계획이며 산업계와의 협력을 강화해 진학·취업·연구가 연결되는 실무형 대학원 모델을 발전시킬 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul City University (* 자료제공 :  서울시립대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241066.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/468/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3717690455463015.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sejong University Sejong Museum Gallery Hall 1 to Hold Ahn Jung-sook's Invitational Planning Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 1관,안정숙 기획초대전 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241068.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sejong University Sejong Museum Gallery Hall 1 to Hold Ahn Jung-sook's Invitational Planning Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 1관,안정숙 기획초대전 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0122/5817690458445583.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;안정숙 포스터.세종대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sejong University (President Eom Jong-hwa) Sejong Museum Gallery Hall 1 will hold artist Ahn Jung-sook's solo exhibition 'Thread Drawing: A 32-Day Journey' from Wednesday, January 21, to Sunday, February 8, 2026. The exhibition unravels motifs from nature into abstract canvases. This exhibition will feature over 70 abstract paintings that translate the bodily memories and emotions experienced in nature into pictorial language, including the artist's representative '32-Day Journey' series.&lt;br/&gt;Artist Ahn Jung-sook graduated from the Graduate School of Painting at Hongik University and has expanded painting into a record of physical action and sensation, using thread as her primary material. The sensations internalized from the changing seasons and within nature manifest as abstract canvases woven with diverse colors, lines, and rhythms, forming free-flowing movements within consistent patterns.&lt;br/&gt;'Thread drawing,' the process of laying colored thread like a brush onto thick canvases built up with layers of various materials, is central to Ahn Jung-sook's painting. This repeated action, involving moving her body around a canvas placed on the floor, simultaneously draws lines and imprints the artist's bodily rhythm and time directly onto the canvas. Art critic Seo Seong-rok commented, "By wandering around the canvas, the artist reconstructs the experience of nature into a cognitive unconscious," adding, "Within this flow, the presence or absence of an image holds little significance; the act itself already embodies the motive force of nature and represents vital meaning."&lt;br/&gt;A representative from Sejong Museum Gallery stated, "Ahn Jung-sook's paintings are works that transform the gaze toward nature from representation into bodily memory and action," and expressed hope that "this exhibition will be a time for audiences to open their senses and expand their contemplation." (세종대학교(총장 엄종화) 세종뮤지엄갤러리 1관은 2026년 1월 21일(수)부터 2월 8일(일)까지 자연의 모티브를 추상적 화면으로 풀어내는 안정숙 작가의 개인전 ‘실 drawing: 32일의 여행’을 개최한다. 이번 전시에는 작가의 대표작인 ‘32일의 여행’ 시리즈를 포함해, 자연을 경험한 몸의 기억과 정서를 회화적 언어로 풀어낸 추상화 70여 점이 선보인다.&lt;br/&gt;안정숙 작가는 홍익대학교 미술대학원 회화과를 졸업했으며, 실(thread)을 주재료로 삼아 회화를 신체적 행위와 감각의 기록으로 확장해 왔다. 사계절의 변화와 자연 속에서 체득한 감각은 다채로운 색과 선, 리듬으로 직조된 추상적 화면으로 나타나며, 화면은 일정한 패턴 속에서 자유로운 흐름을 형성한다.&lt;br/&gt;여러 재료를 쌓아 올린 두터운 화면 위에 색실을 붓처럼 얹는 ‘실 드로잉’ 작업은 안정숙 회화의 핵심이다. 바닥에 놓인 캔버스를 중심으로 몸을 이동시키며 반복되는 이 행위는 선을 그리는 동시에, 작가의 신체 리듬과 시간을 화면에 고스란히 각인시킨다. 미술평론가 서성록은 “작가가 캔버스 주위를 배회함으로써 자연의 체험을 인지적 무의식으로 재구성하게 된다”며 “이러한 흐름 속에서 이미지의 유무는 큰 의미를 지니지 않으며, 행위 자체가 이미 자연의 동인(動因)을 품고 생명적인 의미를 표상한다”고 평했다.&lt;br/&gt;세종뮤지엄갤러리 관계자는 “안정숙의 회화는 자연을 바라보는 시선을 재현이 아닌 몸의 기억과 행위로 전환한 작업”이라며 “이번 전시가 관객들에게 감각을 열고 사유를 확장하는 시간이 되길 기대한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sejong University (* 자료제공 :  세종대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241068.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0122/5817690458445583.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sejong University's Sejong Museum Gallery 2 Holds Go Yong-seok's Invitational Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 2관,고용석 기획초대전 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241069.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sejong University's Sejong Museum Gallery 2 Holds Go Yong-seok's Invitational Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 2관,고용석 기획초대전 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8617690461468171.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;고용석 포스터.세종대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sejong University (President Eom Jong-hwa) Sejong Museum Gallery 2 will hold a solo exhibition by ceramic artist Go Yong-seok, who presents ceramic works based on the aesthetic sense of Joseon white porcelain and imbued with nature, time, and emotion, from Wednesday, January 21 to Wednesday, February 11, 2026. &lt;br/&gt;Artist Go Yong-seok, who is based in Jeju, graduated from Chung-Ang University's Department of Craft Arts and its graduate school, completed a research course in ceramics at Tokyo University of the Arts Graduate School, and earned a doctorate from the Graduate School of Design Management at Chosun University. He has been continuously working on reinterpreting the formative qualities and aesthetic sense of traditional white porcelain in a modern language, metaphorically capturing the breath and rhythm of nature.&lt;br/&gt;The approximately 40 works presented in this exhibition, centered around the 'Bal-a' and 'Neoul' series featuring circular vessel forms, and the 'skein' series, reveal subtle asymmetry, surface textures, and the flow of glaze rather than perfectly closed forms. This reflects the artist's perception of a naturally existing state. The traces on the surface and the empty spaces seen in his ceramics symbolize nature and humans as living beings, not as imperfections.&lt;br/&gt;A representative of Sejong Museum Gallery stated, "The artist's white porcelain works, which hold the traces left by nature and the grain of time, leave a depth and space that allows viewers to project their own memories and emotions," adding, "This exhibition will be a time to look again at the meaning of existence itself with a quiet yet solid resonance." (세종대학교(총장 엄종화) 세종뮤지엄갤러리 2관은 조선 백자의 미감을 바탕으로 자연과 시간, 감성이 담긴 도자 작업을 선보이는 도예가 고용석의 개인전을 2026년 1월 21일(수)부터 2월 11일(수)까지 개최한다. &lt;br/&gt;제주를 기반으로 활동하는 고용석 작가는 중앙대학교 공예학과 및 동 대학원을 졸업하고, 동경예술대학 대학원 도예전공 연구과정을 거쳐 조선대학교 대학원 디자인경영학과 박사과정을 졸업했다. 그는 전통 백자의 조형성과 미감을 현대적인 언어로 재해석하며, 자연의 호흡과 리듬을 은유적으로 담아내는 작업을 지속해 오고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 전시에서 선보이는 40여 점의 작품들은 원형의 기물 형태인 ‘발아’와 ‘너울’, 그리고 ‘skein’ 연작을 중심으로, 완벽하게 닫힌 형태보다는 미묘한 비대칭과 표면의 결, 유약의 흐름을 그대로 드러낸다. 이는 자연스럽게 존재하는 상태에 대한 작가의 인식을 반영한다. 그의 도자에서 보이는 표면의 흔적과 여백은 불완전함이 아닌, 살아 있는 존재로서의 자연과 인간을 상징한다.&lt;br/&gt;세종뮤지엄갤러리 관계자는 “자연이 남긴 흔적과 시간의 결을 품은 작가의 백자 작품들은 관람자가 각자의 기억과 감정을 투영할 수 있는 깊이와 여백을 남기고 있다”며, “이번 전시는 조용하지만 단단한 울림으로, 존재하는 것 그 자체의 의미를 다시 바라보게 하는 시간이 될 것”이라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sejong University (* 자료제공 :  세종대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241069.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8617690461468171.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Duksung Women's University's University Job Plus Center Receives 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Annual Performance Evaluation (덕성여대 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 연차성과평가 '우수' 등급 획득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241072.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Duksung Women's University's University Job Plus Center Receives 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Annual Performance Evaluation (덕성여대 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 연차성과평가 '우수' 등급 획득)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/387/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3917690464735306.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대학일자리본부_사진.덕성여대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Duksung Women's University (Acting President Kim Jong-gil) announced on the 21st that its University Job Plus Center received the highest grade of 'Excellent' in the 2025 University Job Plus Center Annual Performance Evaluation.&lt;br/&gt;This evaluation, conducted by the Ministry of Employment and Labor and the Korea Employment Information Service, comprehensively assessed the quality of youth employment services across various areas, including the status of university youth employment services, customized employment services for enrolled students, and the operation of counseling and employment programs.&lt;br/&gt;Duksung Women's University's University Job Plus Center was highly praised for its systematic operation of step-by-step, customized employment support programs covering enrolled students, graduates, and local youth.&lt;br/&gt;In particular, the restructuring of its career support system and the stable operation of its own programs were cited as excellent examples. Its contribution to revitalizing local youth employment through collaboration with related institutions also received positive evaluation.&lt;br/&gt;Lee Ho-rim, Director of the Duksung Women's University Job Plus Center (Professor of Bioengineering), stated, "Achieving this excellent grade is the result of our members' professionalism and practical employment support tailored to each individual youth," adding, "We will continue to expand customized employment services to prepare students for successful employment and social advancement." (덕성여자대학교(총장 직무대리 김종길) 대학일자리플러스센터가 2025년 대학일자리플러스센터 연차성과평가에서 최고등급인 &amp;#x27;우수&amp;#x27;를 받았다고 21일 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;고용노동부와 한국고용정보원이 주관한 이번 평가는 대학청년고용서비스 현황, 재학생 맞춤형 고용서비스, 상담 및 취업프로그램 운영 등 다양한 영역에서 청년 고용서비스의 질을 종합적으로 평가했다.&lt;br/&gt;덕성여자대학교 대학일자리플러스센터는 재학생부터 졸업생, 지역 청년까지 포괄하는 단계별 맞춤형 취업지원 프로그램을 체계적으로 운영해 온 점이 높은 평가를 받았다.&lt;br/&gt;특히 진로지원체계를 재구조화하고 자체 프로그램을 안정적으로 운영한 점이 우수 사례로 꼽혔다. 또한 유관기관과의 협업을 통해 지역 청년 고용 활성화에 기여한 점도 긍정적인 평가를 받았다.&lt;br/&gt;덕성여자대학교 이호림 대학일자리플러스센터장(바이오공학전공 교수)는 &amp;quot;이번 우수 등급 달성은 구성원들의 전문성과 청년 개개인에 맞춘 실질적인 취업지원의 결과&amp;quot;라며 &amp;quot;앞으로도 학생들의 성공적인 취업 준비와 사회 진출을 위한 맞춤형 고용서비스를 지속적으로 확대해 나가겠다&amp;quot;고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Duksung Women's University (* 자료제공 :  덕성여자대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241072.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/387/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3917690464735306.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year, 'Online Real Estate Contracts' Surpassed 500,000 for the First Time... Driven by Private Brokerage Transactions (작년 ‘부동산 온라인 계약’ 첫 50만건 체결…민간 중개거래가 견인)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241079.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Last Year, 'Online Real Estate Contracts' Surpassed 500,000 for the First Time... Driven by Private Brokerage Transactions (작년 ‘부동산 온라인 계약’ 첫 50만건 체결…민간 중개거래가 견인)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501276.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of 'real estate electronic contracts,' which allow people to buy, sell, or sign lease contracts online without complicated paperwork, is rapidly increasing. (집을 사고팔거나 전·월세 계약을 할 때 복잡한 서류 없이 온라인으로 계약하는 ‘부동산 전자계약’ 이용이 빠르게 늘고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport announced on the 22nd that the number of real estate transactions concluded via electronic contracts last year reached 507,431, surpassing 500,000 for the first time. This is more than double the figure from 2024 (231,074). The 'electronic contract utilization rate,' calculated by dividing the total number of real estate transactions by the number of electronic contracts concluded, also rose significantly compared to 2024, breaking through the 10% range for the first time. The electronic contract utilization rate started at 0.77% in 2018, gradually increased to 5.95% in 2024, and then surged to 12.04% (as of November) last year. (국토교통부는 지난해 한 해 동안 전자계약으로 체결된 부동산 거래가 50만7431건으로 처음 50만건을 넘어섰다고 22일 밝혔다. 이는 2024년(23만1074건)과 견줘 2배 이상 급증한 수치다. 전체 부동산 거래량을 전자계약 체결 건수로 나눈 ‘전자계약 활용률’ 또한 2024년 대비 크게 상승해 처음 10%대를 돌파했다. 전자계약 활용률은 2018년 0.77%로 시작해 2024년 5.95%로 서서히 늘다가 지난해 12.04%(11월 기준)까지 급증했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The growth is particularly noticeable in the private brokerage transaction market. The number of electronic contracts in private brokerage transactions increased approximately 4.5 times, from 73,622 in 2024 to 327,974 last year, driving the activation of electronic contracts. Electronic contracts in the public sector also increased by 17.97%, from 138,550 in 2024 to 163,447 last year. (특히 민간 중개거래 시장에서의 증가세가 눈에 띈다. 민간 중개거래 가운데 전자계약 실적은 2024년 7만3622건에서 지난해 32만7974건으로 약 4.5배 증가해 전자계약 활성화를 견인했다. 공공 분야 전자계약 역시 2024년 13만8550건에서 지난해 16만3447건으로 17.97% 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport has continuously promoted system improvements and incentive expansion to activate electronic contracts. In the second half of last year, it enhanced transaction convenience by adding features such as the transmission of contract information for the Housing and Urban Guarantee Corporation (HUG) rental guarantee review and linking contract document modifications with the private brokerage platform 'Hanbang.' Furthermore, server replacements were made to prepare for the surge in users, ensuring service stability. (그간 국토부는 전자계약 활성화를 위해 시스템 개선과 인센티브 확대를 지속적으로 추진해왔다. 지난해 하반기에는 주택도시보증공사(HUG) 임대보증심사 계약정보 전송 기능 추가, 민간 중개플랫폼 ‘한방’과의 양방향 계약서 수정 연계 등을 통해 거래 편의성을 높였다. 아울러 이용자 급증에 대비한 서버 교체로 서비스 안정성도 확보했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starting from the end of January this year, the identity verification methods required for electronic contracts will become more convenient. Currently, identity verification is only possible through three methods: telecom carriers (mobile phones), i-PIN, and public certificates. In the future, 15 types of simple authentication will also be available, including Naver, Kakao, and Toss authentication, KB Bank and Shinhan Bank financial certificates, and telecom carrier PASS. (올해 1월 말부터는 전자계약에 필요한 본인인증 방식도 한결 간편해진다. 지금은 통신사(휴대폰), 아이핀, 공동인증서 등 3가지 방식으로만 본인인증을 할 수 있는데, 앞으로는 네이버·카카오·토스 인증과 케이비(KB)은행·신한은행 금융인증서, 통신사 패스(PASS) 등 15종의 간편인증도 가능해진다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using electronic contracts provides economic incentives such as financial benefits. For landlords, there is a 10% reduction in the Housing and Urban Guarantee Corporation's rental guarantee fee. Buyers and tenants receive a 0.1 to 0.2 percentage point interest rate reduction when obtaining loans from commercial banks (10 banks). Other benefits include a 30% reduction in registration agency fees and interest-free installment payments (2 to 6 months) for brokerage fees via card payment. (전자계약을 이용하면 금융 혜택 등 경제적 인센티브가 제공된다. 임대인의 경우 주택도시보증공사 임대보증수수료를 10% 인하받을 수 있고, 매수인과 임차인은 시중은행(10곳) 대출 시 0.1∼0.2%포인트 금리 인하 혜택을 받는다. 이외에도 등기대행수수료 30% 절감, 중개보수 카드결제 무이자 할부(2∼6개월) 등의 혜택도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Jun-hyung, Director General of Land Policy at the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, stated, "We will continue to promote system improvements and expand incentives to broaden the base of electronic contracts," adding, "We will do our best to create a digital environment where the public can trade real estate more safely and conveniently." (박준형 국토부 토지정책관은 “앞으로도 시스템 개선과 인센티브 확대를 지속 추진하여 전자계약 저변을 넓히겠다”며 “국민들이 더욱 안전하고 편리하게 부동산을 거래할 수 있는 디지털 환경 조성에 최선을 다할 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241079.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501276.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Even '3,000 points' was tough during the global crisis... But with the semiconductor boom, '5,000 points' in just 9 months (글로벌 위기에 ‘3천피’도 버거웠는데…반도체 호황에 9개월 만에 ‘5천피’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241082.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Even '3,000 points' was tough during the global crisis... But with the semiconductor boom, '5,000 points' in just 9 months (글로벌 위기에 ‘3천피’도 버거웠는데…반도체 호황에 9개월 만에 ‘5천피’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690488830037_20260122501476.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 오전 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 코스피가 장중 5,000을 넘어서자 기뻐하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"If the administration changes, the stock market could break through 3,000 next year. If things go well, it's normal for it to reach 5,000 during the term." (“정권이 교체되면 내년에 증시가 3000을 돌파할 수 있을 것이다. 제대로 되면 임기 중 5000까지 가는 게 정상이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are not the words of President Lee Jae-myung. They are remarks made a whopping 19 years ago, on December 14, 2007, by then-presidential candidate Lee Myung-bak of the Grand National Party. Like this, 'KOSPI 5,000' has long been a goal of successive presidents to revitalize the economy by boosting the Korean stock market, which has been weighed down by chronic undervaluation. (이재명 대통령의 얘기가 아니다. 무려 19년 전인 2007년 12월14일 이명박 대통령이 한나라당 대선 후보시절 한 발언이다. 이처럼 ‘코스피 5000’은 오랫동안 고질적인 저평가에 눌려온 한국 증시를 부양해 경제를 활성화시키겠다는 역대 대통령들의 목표였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of former President Lee's remarks, the KOSPI closing price was 1,895.05. Former President Lee sought economic revival with the so-called '747 pledge', but due to the shock of the 2008 global financial crisis in October-November 2008, the KOSPI broke below 1,000, even falling to 983.32. However, by the end of his term, it had recovered to the 2,000 level again. (이 전 대통령의 발언 당시 코스피 종가는 1895.05였다. 이 전 대통령은 이른바 ‘747 공약’으로 경제 부흥을 꾀했지만 2008년 10~11월 글로벌 금융위기 충격으로 코스피가 1000이 깨져 983.32까지 내려가기도 했다. 다만 퇴임 무렵엔 다시 2000선을 회복했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park Geun-hye, who took office in 2013, set a more 'realistic' goal of 'KOSPI 3,000 within the term'. However, as the United States ended its massive quantitative easing, implemented in response to the global financial crisis, and shifted its monetary policy to tightening, the domestic stock market also froze. Throughout former President Park's term, the KOSPI remained in the 1,000-2,000 range, dubbed 'Box-pi'. (2013년 취임한 박근혜 전 대통령은 좀 더 ‘현실적인’ 목표인 ‘임기 내 코스피 3000’을 내걸었다. 하지만 미국이 글로벌 금융위기에 대응해 막대한 돈을 풀던 양적 완화를 종료하고 통화정책을 긴축으로 전환하면서 국내 증시도 얼어붙었다. 박 전 대통령 임기 내내 코스피는 1000~2000대 ‘박스피’에 머물렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even after former President Moon Jae-in took office in 2017, the 'Box-pi' phenomenon of staying in the 2,000s continued. Then, in 2020, as the global economy took a direct hit from the COVID-19 pandemic, the KOSPI fell to the 1,500 level. However, with massive economic stimulus measures by various countries flooding the market with funds, it began to rebound, breaking through 3,000 for the first time in history in January 2021. But the money released during COVID-19 caused global inflation, leading to a shift back to monetary tightening policies from 2022, and with the Russia-Ukraine war breaking out in 2022, it fell back to the 2,100 level. (2017년 문재인 전 대통령 취임 뒤에도 2000대에 머무르는 박스피는 계속 됐다. 그러다 2020년 코로나19 팬데믹 사태로 세계 경제가 직격탄을 맞아 코스피가 1500선까지 떨어졌다가, 각국의 대규모 경기부양책으로 시중에 자금이 대거 풀리면서 반등하기 시작해 2021년 1월 사상 처음 3000을 돌파했다. 하지만 코로나19 때 풀린 돈이 세계적으로 인플레이션을 일으켜 2022년부터 다시 통화 긴축 정책으로 전환되고 2022년 러시아-우크라이나 전쟁까지 터져 다시 2100선으로 내려갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Yoon Suk-yeol administration, which took office in May of that year, also expressed its intention to boost stock prices with the goal of 'Korea stock market value-up', but with the December 3rd insurrection incident erupting in 2024, stock prices remained around the 2,300 level. (그해 5월 취임한 윤석열 정부도 코리아 증시 밸류업을 목표로 주가 부양 의지를 밝혔으나 2024년 12·3 내란 사태가 터지면서 주가는 2300선에서 머물렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stock market atmosphere changed rapidly after the Constitutional Court's impeachment decision against former President Yoon, who instigated the insurrection on April 4 last year, and the situation shifted to an early presidential election. The Lee Jae-myung administration, launched in June, showed strong determination to achieve 'KOSPI 5,000' and implemented active stock market boosting policies such as revising the Commercial Act. Furthermore, starting in the second half of the year, semiconductor demand exploded due to the AI boom, entering a long-term semiconductor boom (super cycle) phase. From its low on April 9 last year (2,293.70), the KOSPI continued its upward trend, reaching 4,000 on October 27 last year, and touching the historic first 5,000 level during trading on the 22nd, just three months later. Thus, the KOSPI, which started at an index of 100 on January 4, 1980, has opened the era of 'KOSPI 5,000' after 46 years. (지난해 4월4일 내란을 일으킨 윤 전 대통령에 대한 헌법재판소의 탄핵 결정이 나오고 조기대선 국면으로 넘어가면서 증시 분위기는 빠르게 바뀌었다. 6월 출범한 이재명 정부가 ‘코스피 5000’ 달성에 강한 의지를 보이며 상법 개정 등 적극적인 증시 부양 정책을 폈고, 하반기부터 인공지능 붐에 따른 반도체 수요가 폭발하기 시작하면서 반도체 장기호황(슈퍼사이클) 국면에 진입했다. 그해 4월9일 저점(2293.70)부터 코스피는 상승 추세를 지속해 지난해 10월27일 4000을 달성했고, 불과 석 달 만인 22일 장중에 사상 첫 5000을 터치했다. 이로써 지난 1980년 1월4일 지수 100에서 시작한 코스피는 46년 만에 ‘코스피 5000’ 시대를 열었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Kyung-mi &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이경미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241082.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690488830037_20260122501476.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>520,000 'Seohakgaemi' (Korean retail investors in overseas stocks) filed capital gains tax returns... Earned 28 million won per person on average (양도세 신고한 ‘서학개미’ 52만명…1인당 2800만원 벌었다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241089.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;520,000 'Seohakgaemi' (Korean retail investors in overseas stocks) filed capital gains tax returns... Earned 28 million won per person on average (양도세 신고한 ‘서학개미’ 52만명…1인당 2800만원 벌었다)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501561.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;뉴욕증권거래소. AFP 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of people filing capital gains tax returns on profits from overseas stock investments has exceeded 500,000 for the first time on an annual basis. (해외주식에 투자해 얻은 차익으로 양도소득세를 신고한 이가 연간 기준 처음으로 50만명을 넘어섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to data submitted by the National Tax Service to Park Sung-hoon, a lawmaker of the People Power Party who is a member of the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, the number of people filing capital gains tax returns on overseas stocks for the 2024 tax year was 520,709. This represents a sharp increase of 152.7% compared to the previous year (207,231) and is the first time the figure has surpassed 500,000. The number of filers for overseas stock capital gains tax was 139,909 in 2020, 242,862 in 2021, 100,374 in 2022, and 207,231 in 2023, remaining in the range of 100,000 to 200,000 over the previous four years. (22일 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 박성훈 국민의힘 의원이 국세청에서 제출받은 자료를 보면, 2024년 귀속 해외주식 양도소득세 신고 인원은 52만3709명으로 집계됐다. 전년(20만7231명) 대비 152.7% 폭증하며 사상 처음으로 50만명을 돌파했다. 해외주식 양도소득세 신고자는 2020년 13만9909명, 2021년 24만2862명, 2022년 10만374명, 2023년 20만7231명으로 직전 4년간은 10∼20만명대 수준이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals are required to file a capital gains tax return if the profit from selling overseas stocks exceeds 2.5 million won. A basic deduction of up to 2.5 million won is applied annually, and a 22% tax is levied on the remaining profit after the deduction. (해외주식을 팔아 얻은 양도차익이 250만원이 넘으면 양도소득세 신고 대상이 된다. 매년 250만원까지 기본공제가 적용되고, 공제 후 남은 차익에 22% 세금을 내야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increase in the number of filers in 2024 is analyzed to be due to the bullish U.S. stock market. In 2024, the U.S. S&amp;P 500 index rose 23.3%, and the Nasdaq index rose 28.6%. During the same period, the KOSPI fell 9.6%, and the KOSDAQ index fell 21.7%. (2024년에 신고 인원이 늘어난 것은 미국 증시 활황에 따른 영향으로 분석된다. 2024년 미국 스탠더드앤드푸어스(S&amp;amp;P)500 지수는 23.3%, 나스닥 지수는 28.6% 상승했다. 같은 기간 코스피는 9.6%, 코스닥 지수는 21.7% 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The total reported capital gains from overseas stocks in 2024 was 144.212 trillion won. This is an increase of 303.1% compared to the previous year (35.772 trillion won). The per capita capital gain, calculated by dividing the total capital gains by the number of filers, was approximately 28 million won. The per capita capital gain decreased from 28 million won in 2021 to 11 million won in 2022. It then increased to 17 million won in 2023 before rising by more than 10 million won in 2024. (2024년 신고된 해외주식 총 양도차익은 14조4212억원이었다. 전년(3조5772억원)보다 303.1% 늘어난 수준이다. 양도차익을 신고자 수로 나눈 1인당 양도차익은 2800만원꼴이었다. 1인당 양도차익은 2021년 2800만원에서 2022년 1100만원으로 줄었다. 2023년 1700만원으로 늘어난 뒤 2024년 1000만원 이상 더 증가한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, it is estimated that investors increased their scale of overseas stock investments despite the high exchange rate. According to the Korea Securities Depository, the custody amount of U.S. stocks, which was around $44.2 billion in 2022, increased to $68.0 billion in 2023 and surged to $112.1 billion in 2024. By the end of last year, it was recorded at an even higher $163.6 billion. (지난해에는 투자자들이 고환율에도 해외주식 투자 규모를 더 늘렸을 것으로 추정된다. 한국예탁결제원에 따르면 2022년 442억달러 수준이던 미국 주식 보관액은 2023년 680억달러로 늘었고, 2024년 1121억달러로 급증했다. 지난해 말에는 이보다 늘어난 1636억달러로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241089.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501561.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hanyang University Professor Kim Hak-sung Wins the 16th Haedong Young Engineer Award in the Academic Category (한양대 김학성 교수, 제16회 해동젊은공학인상 학술부문 수상)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241105.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hanyang University Professor Kim Hak-sung Wins the 16th Haedong Young Engineer Award in the Academic Category (한양대 김학성 교수, 제16회 해동젊은공학인상 학술부문 수상)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/827/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2017690570429784.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한양대학교 공과대학 기계공학부 김학성 교수.한양대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanyang University (President Lee Ki-jeong) announced on the 21st that Professor Kim Hak-sung of the College of Engineering has been selected as the winner of the academic category of the '16th Haedong Young Engineer Award,' organized by the Korean Microelectronics and Packaging Society.&lt;br/&gt;The Haedong Young Engineer Award is a prestigious prize awarded to young engineers who have contributed to the development of engineering technology and achieved outstanding accomplishments, in accordance with the wishes of the late Kim Jeong-sik, founder of Daeduk Electronics and chairman of the Haedong Science and Culture Foundation.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim Hak-sung, selected as this year's winner in the academic category, is a world-renowned researcher who has achieved unparalleled academic accomplishments in the field of advanced semiconductor packaging over the past 20 years. Professor Kim has published over 240 papers and holds more than 230 domestic and international patents, demonstrating overwhelming research achievements. He has played a key role in enhancing the reliability and productivity of semiconductor manufacturing processes.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim's research is highly regarded for not remaining theoretical but driving practical technological advancements through close collaboration with industry. He has successfully developed next-generation packaging processes and high-bandwidth memory (HBM) stacking reliability evaluation technologies through industry-academia collaboration projects with major domestic semiconductor companies such as Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, Hanwha Semiconductor, LG Chem, and Dongjin Semichem.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim Hak-sung expressed his gratitude, stating, "I am honored to receive such a meaningful award at a time when semiconductor packaging technology is emerging as a core element of national competitiveness," and added, "I will continue to dedicate myself to research and nurturing the next generation to contribute to solidifying the technological foundation of South Korea's semiconductor industry."&lt;br/&gt;Hanyang University plans to use this award as an opportunity to further strengthen its research capabilities in the semiconductor packaging field and accelerate the development of innovative technologies and talent cultivation to lead the global semiconductor market. (한양대학교(총장 이기정)는 공과대학 김학성 교수가 한국마이크로전자및패키징학회에서 주관하는‘제16회 해동젊은공학인상’ 학술부문 수상자로 선정됐다고, 21일 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;해동젊은공학인상은 대덕전자 창업주인 고(故) 김정식 해동과학문화재단 이사장의 뜻에 따라 공학 기술 발전에 기여하고 탁월한 업적을 세운 젊은 공학인에게 수여하는 권위 있는 상이다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 학술부문 수상자로 선정된 김학성 교수는 지난20여 년간 첨단 반도체 패키징 분야에서 독보적인 학문적 성취를 이룬 세계적 연구자다. 김 교수는 현재까지240여 편의 논문을 발표하고 국내외 특허230건을 보유하는 등 압도적인 연구 성과를 거두었으며, 특히 반도체 생산 공정의 신뢰성과 생산성을 높이는 데 핵심적인 역할을 해왔다.&lt;br/&gt;김 교수의 연구는 이론에 그치지 않고 산업 현장과의 긴밀한 협력을 통해 실질적인 기술 진보를 이끌어냈다는 점에서 높은 평가를 받는다. 그는 삼성전자, SK하이닉스, 한화세미텍, LG화학, 동진쎄미켐 등 국내 주요 반도체 기업들과의 산학협력 과제를 통해 차세대 패키징 공정 및 고대역폭메모리(HBM) 적층 신뢰성 평가 기술 등을 성공적으로 개발해 왔다.&lt;br/&gt;김학성 교수는&amp;quot;반도체 패키징 기술이 국가 경쟁력의 핵심으로 부상한 시기에 이처럼 뜻깊은 상을 받게 되어 영광&amp;quot;이라며&amp;quot;앞으로도 연구와 후학 양성에 매진하여 대한민국 반도체 산업의 기술적 토대를 공고히 하는 데 기여하겠다&amp;quot;고 소감을 전했다.&lt;br/&gt;한양대학교는 이번 수상을 계기로 반도체 패키징 분야의 연구 역량을 더욱 강화하고, 글로벌 반도체 시장을 선도할 혁신 기술 개발과 인재 육성에 박차를 가할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Hanyang University (* 자료제공 :  한양대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241105.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/827/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2017690570429784.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dyson Launches a 1.79 Million Won 'AI Robot Cleaner'... "Cleans with 60°C Water" (다이슨, 179만원짜리 ‘AI 로봇 청소기’ 내놨다…“60℃ 물청소”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241110.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Dyson Launches a 1.79 Million Won 'AI Robot Cleaner'... "Cleans with 60°C Water" (다이슨, 179만원짜리 ‘AI 로봇 청소기’ 내놨다…“60℃ 물청소”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/450/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502083.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;다이슨의 신형 인공지능(AI) 로봇 청소기 ‘스팟 앤 스크럽’. 권효중 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the green laser light attached to the robot cleaner illuminated the floor, dust and debris became clearly visible. The artificial intelligence (AI) can distinguish not only debris but also the type of liquid stains on the floor to clean efficiently. For example, if sticky juice is spilled, it wipes multiple times, while for water, it wipes once. The UK-based premium home appliance company Dyson announced on the 22nd that it is launching three new products in the Korean market, including its first AI robot cleaner. (로봇 청소기에 달린 초록색 레이저 불빛이 바닥을 비추자 먼지와 이물질이 눈에 확 띄었다. 인공지능(AI)은 이물질은 물론, 바닥에 묻은 액체 얼룩의 종류를 구분해 효율적인 청소를 할 수 있다. 예컨대 끈적한 주스를 흘린 경우에는 여러 번을 닦고, 물이라면 한 번을 닦는 것이다. 영국 고급 가전 기업 다이슨은 한국 시장에 첫 인공지능 로봇 청소기를 포함, 3종의 신제품을 출시한다고 22일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, Dyson opened an experiential pop-up store called 'The Next Home Lab' at The Hyundai Seoul in Yeouido. Visitors can directly experience three products: the AI robot cleaner 'Spot &amp; Scrub,' which was launched in the domestic market on the 12th, the stick-type cleaner 'Clean &amp; Wash High-Gen Water Cleaner,' and the 'Hushjet Compact Air Purifier.' (이날 찾은 서울 여의도 더현대에서 다이슨은 체험형 팝업 스토어 ‘더 넥스트 홈 랩’을 열었다. 지난 12일 국내 시장에 출시된 인공지능 로봇 청소기 ‘스팟 앤 스크럽’과 스틱형 청소기 ‘클린앤워시 하이진 물청소기’, ‘허쉬젯 콤팩트 공기청정기’ 3종의 제품을 직접 체험할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, the domestic robot cleaner market is estimated to be dominated by Chinese products like Roborock and Dreame, with a market share of around 70%. Dyson is targeting the premium niche market with the Spot &amp; Scrub. Priced at 1.79 million won, it is about three times more expensive than Chinese products, but the company emphasizes its technological strength, where AI identifies contamination and stains for efficient cleaning. (현재 국내 로봇 청소기 시장은 로보락, 드리미 등 중국산 점유율이 약 70%에 달하는 것으로 추정된다. 다이슨은 스팟 앤 스크럽으로 프리미엄 틈새시장을 노렸다. 179만원으로 중국 제품보다 3배가량 비싸지만, 인공지능이 오염과 얼룩을 파악해 효율적으로 청소한다는 기술력에 방점을 뒀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nathan Lawson McClain, Senior Design Manager for Home Research, Design, and Development Software at Dyson, personally demonstrated and introduced the product. Manager McClain stated, "The AI automatically analyzes contamination and, based on necessity, makes its own judgment to wipe up to 15 times." (다이슨의 네이슨 로슨 맥클린 홈 연구·설계·개발 소프트웨어 시니어 디자인 매니저는 직접 제품을 사용하며 소개했다. 맥클린 매니저는 “인공지능이 자동으로 오염을 분석하고, 필요에 따라 스스로 판단, 최대 15번까지 닦는다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another feature of the product is its 12 water supply points attached to the roller. During cleaning, as the roller turns, 60°C hot water is dispensed from various points, maintaining a consistently clean state of the water and roller even with repeated floor wiping. The docking station it returns to after cleaning not only charges the device but also dries the roller using hot air. (또한 총 12개의 물 공급 지점이 롤러와 달린 것도 제품의 특징이다. 청소 시 롤러가 굴러갈 때마다 곳곳에서 60℃의 뜨거운 물이 나와, 반복해서 바닥을 닦아도 늘 깨끗한 물과 롤러의 상태를 유지한다. 청소를 마친 후 들어가는 도킹 스테이션’에는 충전과 함께 열풍으로 롤러를 말린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These specialized 'water cleaning' features align with Korean cleaning habits. According to Dyson's 'Global Water Cleaning Research' conducted last year across 28 countries with 23,311 participants, the average cleaning time for Koreans is one hour, with 36% of that time spent on water cleaning. This exceeds the global average of 29%. (이러한 ‘물청소’ 특화 기능은 한국인의 청소 방식과 맞닿아 있다. 다이슨이 지난해 전세계 28개국, 2만3311명을 대상으로 진행한 ‘글로벌 물청소 연구’ 결과에 보면, 한국인의 평균 청소 시간은 1시간이고. 이 중 36%를 물청소에 썼다. 이는 세계 평균 29%를 웃도는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To match this Korean cleaning style, the new stick-type cleaner, the Clean &amp; Wash High-Gen (699,000 won), can perform dust and water cleaning simultaneously. This product uses a wastewater treatment system instead of a filter, automatically separating and sending down dirty water and contaminants used during cleaning. The cleaner head can be laid flat to clean corners, and the product weighs 3.82 kg, making it light enough to clean with one hand. (이와 같은 한국인의 청소 방식에 맞춰 스틱형 청소기 신제품인 클린앤워시 하이진(69만9000원)도 먼지와 물청소를 동시에 할 수 있다. 이 제품은 필터 대신 오수 처리 시스템을 적용해 청소에 사용된 더러운 물과 오염 물질을 아래로 보내 자동으로 분리한다. 청소기 머리 부분이 눕혀져 구석구석 청소를 할 수 있고, 제품 무게도 3.82㎏로 한 손으로 들고 청소하기에 충분하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Dyson also unveiled its first compact air purifier, the Hushjet. Its strength is 'low noise' at 19 dB, which is at the level of a person whispering. Consumers can experience the products at the pop-up event venue until February 1st. (한편, 다이슨은 첫 소형 공기청정기 허쉬젯도 공개했다. 19㏈(데시벨)로 사람이 속삭이는 수준의 ‘저소음’이 강점이다. 소비자들은 오는 2월1일까지 팝업 행사장에서 제품을 체험할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241110.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/450/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502083.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul Apartment Price Increase Widens for Second Consecutive Week... Strong Performance in Gwanak, Dongjak, Yangcheon, and Gangdong Districts (서울 아파트값 오름폭 2주째 확대…관악·동작·양천·강동구 등 강세)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241120.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Seoul Apartment Price Increase Widens for Second Consecutive Week... Strong Performance in Gwanak, Dongjak, Yangcheon, and Gangdong Districts (서울 아파트값 오름폭 2주째 확대…관악·동작·양천·강동구 등 강세)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690615940986_20260122502341.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 마포구 일대 아파트단지. 김명진 기자 littleprince@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seoul apartment sale prices, which had briefly slowed their upward trend at the beginning of the new year, are once again widening their increase. (새해 초 상승세가 잠시 주춤했던 서울 아파트 매매가격이 다시 오름폭을 키우고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the 'Weekly Apartment Price Trends' released by the Korea Real Estate Board on the 22nd, Seoul apartment sale prices in the third week of January (as of January 19) rose 0.29% compared to the previous week. The fluctuation rate for Seoul apartment sale prices, which was 0.21% in the last week of last year, slowed to 0.18% in the first week of January this year. However, after slightly increasing to 0.21% in the second week, the upward trend continued to widen this week as well. (22일 한국부동산원이 발표한 ‘주간 아파트값 동향’을 보면, 1월 셋째 주(1월19일 기준) 서울 아파트 매매가격은 직전 주 대비 0.29% 올랐다. 지난해 마지막 주 0.21%를 기록했던 서울 아파트 매매가격 변동률은 새해 1월 첫째 주 0.18%로 둔화했으나 둘째 주 0.21%로 소폭 커진 데 이어 이번 주에도 확대 흐름을 이어간 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week, Dongjak District (0.51%), part of the Han River Belt, recorded the highest increase rate in Seoul, with prices rising mainly in Sangdo and Sadang-dong. Yangcheon District (0.43%) saw price increases mainly for small and medium-sized units in Sinjeong and Mok-dong, while Gangdong District (0.41%) saw increases centered on redevelopment-promoting complexes in Myeongil and Gil-dong. Gwanak District (0.44%) also showed a relatively high increase. (이번 주에는 한강벨트에 속한 동작구(0.51%)가 상도·사당동 위주로 가격이 오르며 서울에서 가장 높은 상승률을 기록했다. 양천구(0.43%)는 신정·목동 중소형 규모 위주로, 강동구(0.41%)는 명일·길동 재건축 추진 단지 중심으로 가격이 올랐으며, 관악구(0.44%)도 비교적 높은 상승 폭을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Real Estate Board explained, "Amid a steady increase in purchase inquiries centered on preferred complexes such as redevelopment-promoting complexes and new/large-scale complexes, the expansion of rising transactions led to an overall increase in Seoul." (부동산원은 “재건축 추진 단지, 신축·대단지 등 선호 단지 중심으로 매수 문의가 꾸준히 증가하는 가운데 상승 거래가 확대되며 서울 전체적으로 상승했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gyeonggi Province (0.09%→0.13%) also saw its increase widen compared to the previous week. The steep rise in some southern regions newly designated as regulated areas and land transaction permit zones after the October 15 measures drove the overall increase. Suji District, Yongin City (0.68%) increased its rise rate by 0.23 percentage points compared to the previous week, recording the highest increase since the third week of March 2020 (0.85%). Giheung District, Yongin City (0.24%→0.39%), which avoided regulation, also saw a significant expansion in its rise rate. (경기(0.09%→0.13%) 역시 직전 주 대비 상승폭이 확대됐다. 10·15 대책 이후 규제지역과 토지거래허가구역으로 신규 지정된 남부권 일부 지역의 가파른 오름세가 전체 상승을 이끌었다. 용인시 수지구(0.68%)가 직전 주 대비 상승률을 0.23%포인트 키우며 2020년 3월 셋째 주(0.85%) 이후 가장 높은 오름폭을 기록했다. 규제를 피한 용인시 기흥구(0.24%→0.39%)도 상승률이 크게 확대됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundang District, Seongnam City (0.59%) increased its rise rate by 0.20 percentage points compared to the previous week, with prices rising mainly for small and medium-sized units in Geumgok and Gumi-dong. Dongan District, Anyang City (0.48%) also saw its rise rate increase by 0.15 percentage points compared to the previous week, and Sujeong District, Seongnam City (0.06%→0.46%) showed a notable expansion in its increase. Gwangmyeong City (0.39%) and Hanam City (0.38%) also recorded high rise rates. (성남시 분당구(0.59%)는 금곡·구미동 중소형 규모 위주로 가격이 오르면서 상승률을 직전 주보다 0.20%포인트 키웠다. 안양시 동안구(0.48%)도 전주 대비 상승률이 0.15%포인트 커졌고, 성남시 수정구(0.06%→0.46%)는 오름폭 확대가 두드러졌다. 광명시(0.39%)와 하남시(0.38%) 등도 높은 상승률을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The apartment jeonse (deposit-based lease) market continued its strong sideways trend. In the case of Seoul (0.14%), it showed a weekly rise rate similar to last week while the trend of shortage of listings continued. Seocho District (0.40%) continued its jeonse price rise mainly in Jamwon and Banpo-dong old complexes, while Dongjak District (0.21%), Yangcheon District (0.20%), Gangdong District (0.20%), and Gwangjin District (0.19%) also rose, centered on school districts and large-scale complexes. Gyeonggi Province rose 0.10% and Incheon rose 0.08% each compared to the previous week. (아파트 전세시장은 강보합 장세가 이어졌다. 서울(0.14%)의 경우 지난주와 비슷한 주간 상승률을 보인 가운데 매물 부족 흐름이 지속됐다. 서초구(0.40%)가 잠원·반포동 구축 위주로 전세가격 상승세가 이어지고 있고 동작구(0.21%), 양천구(0.20%), 강동구(0.20%), 광진구(0.19%) 등도 학군지와 대단지 등을 중심으로 상승했다. 경기는 직전 주 대비 0.10%, 인천은 0.08% 각각 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Choi Jong-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최종훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241120.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690615940986_20260122502341.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pistachio Prices Pushed Up by Dubai Chewy Cookie Craze... Surge 84% in One Year (두쫀쿠가 밀어올린 피스타치오 몸값…1년 새 84% 급등)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241122.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Pistachio Prices Pushed Up by Dubai Chewy Cookie Craze... Surge 84% in One Year (두쫀쿠가 밀어올린 피스타치오 몸값…1년 새 84% 급등)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690619676893_20260122502424.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 경기도 고양 킨텍스에서 열린 2026 카페디저트페어에서 디저트 두바이 쫀득쿠키가 참관인들의 시선을 끌고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The import price of pistachios, which are causing shortages due to the craze for the dessert 'Dubai Chewy Cookie (Dubai Cheon-deuk Cookie or Du-jjeon-ku)', has surged 84% in one year. (디저트 ‘두바이 쫀득쿠키(두쫀쿠)’ 열풍에 품절 현상도 빚는 피스타치오 수입가격이 1년새 84% 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an analysis of Korea Customs Service data by Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Jeong Il-young, a member of the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, the import unit price of pistachios surged 84% in one year as imports of raw materials like pistachios and kadaif (kataifi) skyrocketed due to the Dubai Chewy Cookie craze, which recently spread primarily through social media. The Dubai Chewy Cookie is characterized by a chewy, rice cake-like texture, made with a filling of kadaif (a key ingredient in Dubai chocolate) and pistachio cream, wrapped in marshmallow mixed with cocoa powder. (22일 국회 재정경제위원회 소속 정일영 더불어민주당 의원이 관세청 자료를 분석한 결과를 보면, 최근 에스엔에스(SNS)를 중심으로 확산된 두쫀쿠 열풍으로 피스타치오와 카다이프 등 원재료 수입이 급증하면서 피스타치오 수입 단가가 1년새 84% 급등했다. 두쫀쿠는 두바이 초콜릿의 주재료인 카다이프와 피스타치오 크림으로 속을 만들고, 이를 코코아 가루를 섞은 마시멜로로 감싸 쫀득한 떡과 같은 식감이 특징이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pistachio imports last year reached 2,001 tons (approximately 33 billion won), representing a roughly 2.4-fold increase in volume and a 2.5-fold increase in value compared to 833 tons (approximately 13 billion won) in 2020, five years ago. The Dubai Chewy Cookie craze, which began around the end of last year, was fully reflected in pistachio import volumes. While the average monthly import volume for pistachios in 2025 was about 167 tons, the import volume for December last year alone was about 372 tons, 2.2 times the monthly average. As demand overlapped due to the 'Dubai Chewy Cookie trend', price and supply volatility simultaneously expanded during specific periods. (피스타치오 수입은 지난해 2001t(약 330억원)으로, 5년전인 2020년 833t(약 130억원)보다 수입량이 약 2.4배, 수입액도 2.5배 증가했다. 특히 지난 연말 무렵 시작된 두쫀쿠 열풍은 피스타치오 수입량에 고스란히 반영됐다. 2025년 피스타치오의 월평균 수입량은 약 167t이었지만, 지난해 12월 한 달 수입량은 약 372t으로 월평균의 2.2배에 달했다. ‘두쫀쿠 유행’에 따른 수요가 겹치며, 특정 시기에 가격과 물량 변동성이 동시에 확대된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, the import unit price of pistachios, which was 15 million won per ton in January last year, rose to about 28 million won per ton in January this year, a surge of 84% in one year. Although import volumes decreased during the same period due to shortages, the cost burden increased significantly instead. The sharp rise in raw material prices could pose a more direct burden on small business owners, small and medium-sized confectionery companies, and individual cafes rather than large corporations. Given the structural difficulty in absorbing rising costs, it is hard to rule out the possibility of price increases for desserts, baked goods, and ice cream. (이에 따라 지난해 1월 t당 1500만원이던 피스타치오 수입단가는 올 1월 약 2800만원으로 1년새 84% 급등했다. 품귀 현상으로 같은 기간 수입량은 줄었지만 원가 부담은 오히려 크게 늘었다. 원재료 가격 급등은 대기업보다 소상공인·중소 제과업체와 개인 카페에 더 직접적인 부담으로 작용할 수 있다. 원가 상승을 흡수하기 어려운 구조상, 디저트·베이커리·아이스크림 가격 인상으로 이어질 가능성도 배제하기 어렵다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Jeong pointed out, "In the case of imported raw materials like pistachios, where demand surges rapidly due to trends, simultaneous price spikes and supply concentration can cause double damage to consumers, small business owners, and the self-employed," adding, "It is important for relevant ministries to closely monitor the situation and swiftly share necessary information to prevent the spread of damage caused by sharp price fluctuations and supply instability." (정 의원은 “피스타치오처럼 유행에 따라 수요가 급격히 몰리는 수입 원재료의 경우 가격 급등과 물량 쏠림이 동시에 발생하면서 소비자와 소상공인·자영업자가 이중으로 피해를 입을 수 있다”며 “급격한 가격 변동과 수급 불안으로 인한 피해가 확산되지 않도록 관계 부처가 상황을 면밀히 점검하고 필요한 정보를 신속히 공유하는 것이 중요하다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241122.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690619676893_20260122502424.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Forum on 'Shareholder Engagement Activities and Measures to Activate Shareholder Proposals' to be Held on the 30th (‘주주 관여활동 및 주주제한 활성화 방안’ 간담회 30일 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241129.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Forum on 'Shareholder Engagement Activities and Measures to Activate Shareholder Proposals' to be Held on the 30th (‘주주 관여활동 및 주주제한 활성화 방안’ 간담회 30일 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/755/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502587.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Economic Reform Solidarity (Director: Professor Kim Woo-chan of Korea University) will co-host a forum on 'Shareholder Engagement Activities and Measures to Activate Shareholder Proposals' with Democratic Party of Korea members including Representative Oh Ki-hyung, Chairman of the KOSPI 5000 Committee, Representative Kim Nam-geun, and Representative Lee Kang-il. The forum will be held on the 30th at 2 PM in Conference Room 8 of the National Assembly Members' Office Building in Yeouido, Seoul. (경제개혁연대(소장 김우찬 고려대 교수)는 오는 30일 오후 2시 서울 여의도 국회의원회관 제8간담회의실에서 더불어민주당의 오기형 코스피5000위원장, 김남근 의원, 이강일 의원과 공동으로 ‘주주 관여활동 및 주주제한 활성화 방안’ 간담회를 개최한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This forum plans to share experiences regarding engagement activities and shareholder proposals on various issues involving institutional investors, activist funds, and small shareholder alliances. It will also examine the significance, practical limitations, and institutional challenges of engagement activities. Furthermore, it will discuss improvement measures to activate shareholder engagement and proposals. The forum will be chaired by Professor Kim Woo-chan of Korea University. Panelists include Choi Yong-hwan, Head of the Research Team at NH-Amundi Asset Management; Lee Chang-hwan, CEO of Align Partners; Kim Ji-yeol, Director at Quad Asset Management; Lee Bo-yeol, Representative of the Sam Mok S-Form Small Shareholders Alliance; Lee Sang-mok, Representative of the small shareholder platform Act; and Noh Jong-hwa, Policy Committee Member of the Economic Reform Solidarity. (  이번 간담회에서는 기관투자자, 행동주의펀드, 소액주주연대 등의 다양한 이슈에 관한 관여활동, 주주제안 경험을 공유하고, 관여활동의 의의와 현실적 한계, 제도적 어려움을 짚어볼 계획이다. 또 주주 관여활동 및 주주제안 활성화를 위한 개선방안을 논의한다. 간담회는 김우찬 고려대 교수를 좌장으로 하고, 최용환 엔에이치(NH)아문디자사운용 리서치팀장, 이창환 얼라인파트너스 대표, 김지열 쿼드자산운용 이사, 이보열 삼목에스폼 소액주주연대 대표, 이상목 소액주주 플랫폼 액트 대표, 노종화 경제개혁연대 정책위원이 패널로 참여한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Engagement activities refer to active shareholder actions where institutional investors, small shareholders, etc., actively communicate opinions to companies and demand improvements to protect and enhance medium-to-long-term corporate value and the interests of clients/beneficiaries. They are divided into informal engagement, such as private meetings with management and the board, written inquiries, and requests for additional information, and formal engagement, such as public expression of opinions, speaking at shareholder meetings, exercising voting rights, submitting shareholder proposals, and requesting the convening of shareholder meetings. (  관여활동은 기관투자자, 소액주주 등이 중장기 기업가치와 고객·수익자의 이익을 보호·증진하기 위해 기업에 적극적으로 의견을 전달하고 개선을 요구하는 적극적 주주활동을 뜻한다. 경영진과 이사회와의 비공개 미팅, 서면 질의, 추가 정보 요청 등과 같은 비공식 관여와, 공개적인 의견 표명, 주주총회에서의 발언, 의결권 행사, 주주제안, 주총소집 청구 등의 공식 관여로 구분한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Kwak Jeong-su, Senior Reporter, The Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 곽정수 한겨레경제사회연구원 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241129.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/755/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502587.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kookmin University Techno Design Graduate School's Original Musical 'Mr. Bojangles' to be Performed from January 23rd to 25th (국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원, 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스’ 1월 23~25일 공연)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241141.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kookmin University Techno Design Graduate School's Original Musical 'Mr. Bojangles' to be Performed from January 23rd to 25th (국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원, 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스’ 1월 23~25일 공연)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/804/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8817690656889717.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;▲사진 국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원 X TapeeTepee, 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스’.국민대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kookmin University (President Seungryeol Jeong) will present the original musical 'Mr. Bojangles,' planned and produced in collaboration with the performing arts organization TapeeTepee by the Department of Convergence Design at the Techno Design Graduate School, from January 23rd (Fri) to 25th (Sun), 2026, at the Staircase Lecture Hall in the Annex of the College of Fine Arts Building at Kookmin University.&lt;br/&gt;This performance is an experimental collaborative project intersecting 'performing arts' and 'design research.' Led by Professor Kim Min and master's/doctoral students from the Department of Convergence Design at Kookmin University's Techno Design Graduate School, who form the core of the planning and execution, it presents a new educational and creative model that combines academic research with creative practice.&lt;br/&gt;'Mr. Bojangles' is a work based on the life story of the legendary American tap dancer and musical actor Bill Robinson. It features an AI-reborn Bill Robinson character along with four actors: tapper Don_K (Kim Seong-hoon), Bee (Kim Joo-hwan), musical actor Hidden (Kim Tae-gyun), and guitarist Hooon (Kim Ji-hoon). The script by Kim Min and Hong Seung-wan and direction by Kim Seong-hoon enhance the work's completeness.&lt;br/&gt;The performance also aims to spread social and cultural value through the collaboration of art and academia. On the final day, January 25th (Sun) at 3 PM, a special performance will be held, inviting children from Seondeokwon, a social welfare childcare facility in Jongno-gu, providing them an opportunity to experience culture and art. This is expected to be a meaningful time to convey dreams and hope to future generations, continuing the legacy of Kookmin University's ongoing social contribution activities such as the College of Fine Arts' 'Fly Design Camp' and the College of Physical Education's 'Happy Sports Camp.'&lt;br/&gt;The performance schedule consists of three shows: January 23rd (Fri) at 7 PM, January 24th (Sat) at 3 PM, and January 25th (Sun) at 3 PM (special performance for Seondeokwon). The venue is the Staircase Lecture Hall in the Annex of the College of Fine Arts Building at Kookmin University. (국민대학교(총장 정승렬) 테크노디자인전문대학원 융합디자인학과에서 공연예술전문기관 TapeeTepee(태피티피)와 협력해 기획·제작한 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스(Mr. Bojangles)’를 2026년 1월 23일(금)부터 25일(일)까지 국민대 조형관 별관 계단강의실에서 선보인다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 공연은 ‘공연예술’과 ‘디자인 연구’가 교차하는 실험적 협업 프로젝트로, 국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원 융합디자인학과 김민 교수와 석·박사과정 학생들이 기획과 실행의 주축이 되어 학문적 연구와 창의적 실천이 결합하는 새로운 교육·창작 모델을 제시한다.&lt;br/&gt;‘미스터 보쟁글스’는 미국의 전설적 탭댄서이자 뮤지컬 배우인 빌 로빈슨(Bill Robinson)의 일대기를 바탕으로 한 작품으로, AI로 재탄생한 빌 로빈슨 캐릭터와 함께 태퍼 Don_K(김성훈), Bee(김주환), 뮤지컬 배우 Hidden(김태균), 기타리스트 Hooon(김지훈) 등 4명의 배우가 출연한다. 극본은 김민·홍승완이, 연출은 김성훈이 맡아 작품의 완성도를 높였다.&lt;br/&gt;공연은 예술과 학문의 협력을 통해 사회적·문화적 가치를 확산하는 데에도 의의를 둔다. 마지막 날인 1월 25일(일) 오후 3시에는 종로구 사회복지 보육시설 선덕원 보육원생을 초청한 특별공연을 진행해 문화예술을 접할 기회를 제공한다. 이는 국민대 조형대학의 ‘날아라 디자인캠프’, 체육대학의 ‘행복한 스포츠캠프’ 등 지속적인 사회공헌 활동의 연장선상에서 미래 세대에 꿈과 희망을 전하는 뜻깊은 시간이 될 것으로 기대된다.&lt;br/&gt;공연 일정은 1월 23일(금) 오후 7시, 24일(토) 오후 3시, 25일(일) 오후 3시(선덕원 초청 특별공연) 총 3회이며, 장소는 국민대 조형관 별관 계단강의실이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kookmin University (* 자료제공 :  국민대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241141.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/804/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8817690656889717.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pledge Fulfilled in Just 7 Months as 'KOSPI 5000' Becomes Reality... Mixed Views on "Still Undervalued" vs. "Overheated" (공약 7달 만에 ‘코스피 5000’ 현실로…“여전히 저평가”-“과열” 엇갈려)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241143.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Pledge Fulfilled in Just 7 Months as 'KOSPI 5000' Becomes Reality... Mixed Views on "Still Undervalued" vs. "Overheated" (공약 7달 만에 ‘코스피 5000’ 현실로…“여전히 저평가”-“과열” 엇갈려)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/447/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502943.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 오전 코스피가 장중 5000을 넘어자 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 기뻐하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The force that drove the KOSPI to record its first-ever intraday high of '5000' (peaking at 5019.54) in the securities market on the 22nd is the semiconductor and robotics industries, which are riding the artificial intelligence (AI) boom and entering a historic memory supercycle. The defense, shipbuilding, and nuclear power sectors, where investment sentiment has heated up on expectations of strong future performance, also joined the rally. Additionally, the Lee Jae-myung administration's proactive push for value-up (corporate value enhancement plan) policies, aimed at breaking the persistent undervaluation of the Korean stock market, is cited as a factor. The KOSPI has surged relentlessly, rising 85.97% (based on the intraday high) from June 2 last year, when the bull market began, to this day. Forecasts suggest the KOSPI could rise further as the effects of the government's policies to encourage the return of 'Seohak Ants' (Korean retail investors in overseas markets) and expand foreign investment in the domestic stock market become visible. (22일 유가증권시장에서 장중에 사상 첫 ‘코스피 5000’(최고 5019.54) 기록을 만들어낸 힘은 인공지능(AI) 붐을 타고 역사적인 메모리 수퍼사이클에 진입한 반도체와 로봇 산업이다. 향후 좋은 실적이 기대되면서 투자 심리가 가열된 방산·조선·원전도 가세했다. 여기에 한국 증시의 고질적 저평가를 타개하겠다는 이재명 정부의 적극적인 밸류업(기업가치제고계획) 정책 추진이 꼽힌다. 코스피는 거침없이 질주하며 ‘불장’에 돌입한 지난해 6월 2일부터 이날까지 85.97%(장중 최고가 기준) 올랐다. 정부의 ‘서학개미’ 유턴과 외국인 국내 증시 투자 확대 정책효과가 가시화되면 코스피가 추가로 상승할 수 있다는 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main drivers behind the historic KOSPI rally were foreign and institutional investors. Foreign investors scooped up shipbuilding and nuclear power stocks, while institutions bought up large-cap semiconductor stocks, pulling the index higher. According to Korea Exchange's Information Data System statistics, the total KOSPI trading volume over the roughly seven-month period from the inauguration day of the Lee Jae-myung administration (June 4 last year), when the historic bull market had just begun, until the 20th of this month, reached 2,339.381 trillion won. The buy-side volume was 817.708 trillion won for foreigners, 463.992 trillion won for institutions, and 1,021.184 trillion won for individuals. (역사적인 코스피 상승을 이끈 주역은 외국인과 기관 투자자였다. 외국인은 조선·원전주를, 기관은 대형 반도체주를 쓸어 담으며 지수를 끌어 올렸다. 한국거래소 정보데이터시스템 집계를 보면 역사적인 ‘불장’이 막 시작된 이재명 정부 출범일(지난해 6월4일) 이후 지난 20일까지 7개월 남짓 기간에 코스피 거래대금은 총 2339조3810억원에 이른다. 매수대금은 외국인 817조7080억원, 기관 463조9920억원, 개인은 1021조1840억원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this period, the net purchase volume of major KOSPI investors reached 11.886 trillion won for foreigners and 12.629 trillion won for institutions. In contrast, individuals were net sellers of approximately 30.381 trillion won worth of stocks during this period. It appears that foreign and institutional investors played an absolutely crucial role in the KOSPI achieving 5000 for the first time in history. Foreign investors were net sellers of 14.456 trillion won in November last year due to concerns about an AI bubble, but switched to a net buying position of 4.148 trillion won in December. They have continued to be net buyers for two consecutive months since then, including this month. Institutions joined the index rally by leading the semiconductor stock surge with large-scale net purchases of Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix in the KOSPI market. (이 기간에 코스피 주요 투자자의 순매수 거래대금은 외국인 11조8860억원, 기관 12조6290억원에 이른다. 반면 개인은 이 기간에 30조3810억원어치를 순매도했다. 코스피가 사상 처음 5000을 달성하게 된 데는 외국인과 기관의 힘이 절대적으로 작용한 셈이다. 외국인은 지난해 11월 인공지능(AI) 거품 우려 등에 14조4560억원 순매도했으나 12월 들어 4조1480억원 매수 우위로 돌아섰다. 이후 이달까지 두 달 연속 ‘사자’를 이어가고 있다. 기관은 코스피 시장에서 삼성전자와 에스케이(SK)하이닉스를 대거 순매수하며 반도체주 상승세를 주도하며 지수 상승에 가세했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is analyzed that they bought semiconductor stocks in bulk on expectations that memory prices will continue to rise due to increasing global AI demand. As institutions pushed up semiconductor stock prices and foreign investors lifted nuclear power and shipbuilding stocks, warmth is spreading across the large-cap sector. Kim Jae-seung, a researcher at Hyundai Motor Securities, assessed, "Until December, the KOSPI saw a large concentration in semiconductors, but since January, the strength has expanded to surrounding industries. With a favorable funding environment including foreign net buying, the entire KOSPI market is in an upward-trending environment." However, individuals viewed the KOSPI's rise as a profit-taking opportunity and sold heavily. (글로벌 인공지능 수요 증가로 메모리 가격 상승세가 지속될 거라는 기대감에 반도체주를 대거 쓸어 담은 것으로 분석된다. 기관이 반도체주 주가를 밀고, 외국인은 원전·조선주를 끌어 올리면서 대형주 전반으로 온기가 번지는 모습이다. 김재승 현대차증권 연구원은 “코스피는 12월까지는 반도체 쏠림이 커졌지만 1월 들어 주변 업종으로 강세가 확장되고 있다. 외국인 순매수 등 우호적인 자금 환경에 코스피 시장 전체가 우상향하는 환경”이라고 평가했다. 다만 개인은 코스피 상승세를 오히려 차익 실현 기회로 여기고 대거 파는 모습을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government value-up policies such as strengthened shareholder returns, and institutional reforms like the effective tax cut from the separate taxation of dividend income, also seem to have contributed to 'KOSPI 5000'. As it became known that 'Seohak Ants' were shunning the Korean stock market due to low dividends and high taxes, the Lee Jae-myung administration has taken groundbreaking measures in several stages to change this perception. Recently, to encourage investment funds that had flowed out to foreign stock markets, including the US, to return to the domestic market, the government newly created a 'Return to the Domestic Market Account' (RIA), which exempts capital gains tax on foreign stocks if the funds from selling those stocks are converted to Korean won and invested domestically. (주주환원 강화 등 정부 밸류업 정책과 배당소득 분리과세에 따른 실질적 세금 인하 등 제도 개편도 ‘코스피 5000’에 한몫한 것으로 보인다. 서학개미들이 배당금이 적고 세금이 높다며 한국 증시를 외면한 것으로 알려지자 이재명 정부에서 이런 인식을 바꾸는 획기적인 조치를 여러 차례에 걸쳐 내놓았다. 최근에는 미국을 비롯한 외국 증시로 빠져나간 서학개미 투자금이 국내 증시로 돌아오도록 해외주식을 매도한 자금을 원화로 환전해 국내에 투자하면 해외주식 양도소득을 비과세해주는 ‘국내시장 복귀 계좌’(RIA)를 새로 만들었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the securities industry, there is anticipation that individual investors may flow in going forward, as the government is currently promoting policies to induce the return of 'Seohak Ants' to the domestic stock market. Yeom Dong-chan, a researcher at Korea Investment &amp; Securities, predicted, "As of the end of last year, Korea's overseas stock assets were 256 trillion won. Applying the case of Indonesia, which implemented a similar policy in the past, we can expect about 12.4%, or 31.7 trillion won, to be repatriated to Korea," adding, "The Return to the Domestic Market Account policy will be favorable for exchange rate stability and the domestic capital market." (증권가에서는 최근 정부가 ‘서학개미’의 국내 증시 복귀를 유도하기 위한 정책을 추진 중인 만큼 향후 개인 투자자들이 유입될 수 있다는 기대감이 나온다. 염동찬 한국투자증권 연구원은 “지난해 말 기준 한국의 해외 주식 자산은 256조원인데 과거 유사한 정책을 실시한 인도네시아 사례를 적용한다면 12.4%인 31조7천억원이 국내로 환입될 것으로 기대할 수 있다”며 “국내시장 복귀계좌 정책은 환율 안정과 국내 자본시장에 우호적일 것”이라고 내다봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although President Lee Jae-myung's pledge of a 'KOSPI 5000 era' has materialized in just over seven months, assessments follow that the domestic stock market is still undervalued compared to global markets. This is because earnings forecasts for domestic large-caps, centered on semiconductors, are being revised upward at a fearsome pace. The consensus for this year's consolidated operating profit for the 28 stocks in the KOSPI Electrical &amp; Electronics sector, which includes Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix, has skyrocketed 141% from 94.6648 trillion won six months ago (July 22 last year) to a recent 228.1435 trillion won. In other words, the market interprets that while the KOSPI index has risen 85.97% compared to seven months ago, the valuation burden is not yet heavy. According to the Korea Exchange Information Data System, the KOSPI's price-to-earnings ratio (PER) as of the previous day was 20.52x. This is a 53.2% increase from June 2 last year (13.39x), but is much lower than the KOSPI's rise of 81.9% over the same period. During this period, the price-to-book ratio (PBR) of KOSPI-listed companies also soared vertically from 0.92x to 1.58x. However, compared to the PER (31.05x) and PBR (5.51x) of stocks included in the US S&amp;P 500, the prevailing view in the securities industry is that it is still significantly undervalued by global standards. (이재명 대통령의 ‘코스피 5000 시대’ 공약이 불과 7개월 남짓 만에 현실화했지만, 국내증시는 글로벌 대비 여전히 저평가됐다는 진단도 이어진다. 반도체를 중심으로 국내 대형주의 실적 전망이 무서운 속도로 상향되고 있기 때문이다. 삼성전자·에스케이하이닉스 등이 속한 코스피 전기·전자 업종 28개 종목의 올해 연결 영업이익 컨센서스는 6개월 전(지난해 7월22일) 94조6648억원에서 최근 228조1435억원으로 141% 급등했다. 즉 시장에서는 코스피 지수가 7개월 전 대비 85.97% 올랐지만 밸류에이션(평가가치) 부담은 아직 크지 않은 것으로 해석한다. 한국거래소 정보데이터시스템에 따르면 전날까지 코스피의 주가수익비율(PER)은 20.52배를 나타내고 있다. 지난해 6월2일(13.39배)보다 53.2% 증가했으나, 같은 기간 코스피 상승률(81.9%)보다는 훨씬 낮은 수준이다. 이 기간에 코스피 상장사들의 주가순자산비율(PBR)도 0.92배에서 1.58배로 수직상승했다. 하지만 미국 스탠더드앤드푸어스(S&amp;amp;P)500 편입종목의 주가수익비율(31.05배) 및 주가순자산비율(5.51배)에 견주면 글로벌 기준으로는 여전히 한참 저평가된 편이라는 게 증권가의 대체적인 시각이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, advice has also emerged that, in the short term, the KOSPI has entered a phase where speed adjustment should be considered. It is pointed out that the earnings-driven rally led by semiconductors is excessive, and since the beginning of this year, the domestic stock market's rise has been so steep that technical overheating burdens have accumulated. Based on the 9th of this month, when the KOSPI index was approaching the 4600 level, it was calculated that excluding Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix, the index would have remained only around the 3400 level. Kiwoom Securities noted, "Various indicators point to the KOSPI currently being in a technical overheating phase. To continue the additional rally, it is necessary to alleviate the current overheating burden to some extent." (그러나 단기적으로 코스피 속도 조절을 염두에 두어야 할 구간에 진입했다는 조언도 나온다. 반도체가 주도하는 실적 독주가 지나친 데다 올해 들어 국내 증시 상승 속도가 워낙 가팔라 기술적으로 과열 부담이 누적돼 있다는 지적이다. 코스피 지수는 4600선에 육박했던 지난 9일 당시 기준으로 보면 삼성전자·에스케이하이닉스를 제외할 경우 3400선에 그쳤던 것으로 집계됐다. 키움증권은 “여러 지표는 코스피가 현재 기술적 과열 국면에 들어가 있음을 가리킨다. 추가적인 랠리를 이어가려면 현재의 과열 부담을 어느 정도 해소할 필요가 있다“고 짚었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241143.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/447/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502943.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Muan Airport Officials, Having Received Requests to Fix 'Concrete Embankment', Say "We Don't Remember" (무안공항 책임자들, ‘콘크리트 둔덕’ 보완요구 받아놓고 “기억 안 난다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241147.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Muan Airport Officials, Having Received Requests to Fix 'Concrete Embankment', Say "We Don't Remember" (무안공항 책임자들, ‘콘크리트 둔덕’ 보완요구 받아놓고 “기억 안 난다”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690670116759_20260122503061.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 국회에서 열린 12.29 여객기 참사 진상규명을 위한 국정조사특별위원회 회의에서 유가족 협의회 회원들이 지켜보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers from both ruling and opposition parties summoned and jointly criticized officials regarding the concrete embankment at Jeonnam's Muan International Airport, which exacerbated the December 29 Jeju Air passenger plane disaster. It was also pointed out that although police investigations have been ongoing for over a year, not a single case of referral or indictment of those responsible has yet been made. (12·29 제주항공 여객기 참사를 키운 전남 무안국제공항 콘크리트 둔덕을 놓고 여야가 관계자들을 불러 한목소리로 질타했다. 경찰 수사가 1년 넘게 이어지고 있지만, 책임자에 대한 송치나 기소가 아직 한 건도 이뤄지지 않았다는 점도 도마에 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly's Special Committee for the State Investigation into the Truth of the December 29 Passenger Plane Disaster held a hearing at the National Assembly on the 22nd, grilling the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, the Aviation and Railway Accident Investigation Board (ARAIB), the police, and related companies, focusing on why there was a concrete embankment at Muan Airport. At the time of the accident, there was a concrete embankment near the Muan Airport runway to support a localizer facility. According to an ARAIB research service report, it is estimated that all 179 victims would have survived had the embankment not been there. (국회 12·29 여객기 참사 진상규명 국정조사특별위원회(특위)는 22일 국회에서 국토교통부와 항공철도사고조사위원회(조사위), 경찰과 관련업체를 상대로 청문회를 열고 무안공항에 콘크리트 둔덕이 있었던 이유를 집중적으로 따져물었다. 사고 당시 무안공항 활주로 인근에는 방위각시설(로컬라이저)을 지지하기 위해 콘크리트 둔덕이 있었는데, 사조위 연구용역 보고서에 따르면 둔덕이 없었을 경우 179명의 희생자 전원이 생존했을 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the hearing, officials from the Seoul Regional Aviation Office, which was the ordering agency during the construction of Muan Airport, repeatedly offered only the explanation that they "did not remember" when pressed about responsibility for the embankment issue. Former Director Lee Seok-am, who was the head of the Seoul Aviation Office in 2004, responded to the question, 'At the time, the Korea Airports Corporation requested a fix for the Muan Airport concrete embankment due to non-compliance with standards; what was the reason for not accepting it?' by saying, "I don't recall any issues being raised regarding the localizer. I never heard about it once during my one-year tenure." Former Director Jang Jong-sik, who received a request to fix the concrete embankment in 2007, also said regarding the embankment, "I don't recall it being a matter of discussion." (이날 무안공항 건설 당시 발주처였던 서울지방항공청 관계자들은 둔덕 문제에 대해 책임을 추궁하자 “기억이 없다”는 해명만을 반복했다. 2004년 서울항공청장이었던 이석암 전 청장은 ‘당시 한국공항공사가 무안공항 콘크리트 둔덕에 대해 기준 부적합으로 보완요청을 했는데 불수용한 이유가 무엇이냐’는 질문에 “로컬라이저에 관한 문제가 제기된 기억이 없다. 제가 재직하는 1년 동안 한 번도 얘기를 들은 적이 없다”고 말했다. 2007년 콘크리트 둔덕 보완을 요구받았던 장종식 전 청장도 둔덕에 대해 “논의한 사항은 없는 것으로 기억한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticism of the police's 'slow investigation' also continued. Democratic Party lawmaker Lee Kwang-hee pointed out to the police, who said 'investigation results from the ARAIB are needed regarding engine defects and aircraft defects,' that "judicial investigations and accident investigations should proceed independently of each other, and one should not be delayed due to the other according to international standards," and "even though ARAIB accident investigation results are not data for determining criminal responsibility, using them as a premise does not conform to international standards." Lawmaker Lee Yeon-hee of the same party criticized, "Even a special prosecutor's investigation period is 90 days. Who would understand that the police haven't even produced results after a year has passed?" People Power Party lawmaker Seo Cheon-ho, a former police officer, also said, "The most crucial points are why the embankment was installed, why it was made of concrete, and why it was left unattended," adding, "However, those key aspects are largely missing from the (investigation of) main figures." (경찰의 ‘늑장 수사’에 대한 비판도 이어졌다. 이광희 민주당 의원은 ‘엔진 결함, 기체 결함 관련해서는 사조위 조사 결과가 필요하다’는 경찰 쪽에 “사법조사와 사고조사는 상호 독립적으로 진행돼야 하고 어느 한쪽에 다른 한쪽을 이유로 지연해선 안 된다는 게 국제 기준”이라며 “사조위 사고조사 결과는 형사 책임 판단을 위한 자료가 아님에도 이를 전제로 삼는 건 국제기준에 부합하지 않는다”고 지적했다. 같은 당 이연희 의원은 “특검도 수사기간이 90일이다. 그런데 경찰이 1년이 지나도록 결과조차 못 내는 걸 누가 납득하겠나”라고 비판했다. 경찰 출신인 서천호 국민의힘 의원도 “가장 핵심적인 내용은 둔덕이 왜 설치됐고 왜 콘크리트로 설치됐으며 방치됐냐는 것”이라며 “그런데 (수사) 주요인물 안에 그 부분이 대폭 빠져있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of Land, Infrastructure and Transport Kim Yun-deok, who attended the hearing, said, "I think it is a wrongful incident to the point where, as the Minister, I have nothing to say about the fact that regulations (related to the embankment) could have been improved several times but were not properly addressed," and added, "I sincerely apologize to the bereaved families, and I will do my utmost to examine regulations not only regarding the embankment issue but across all aviation facility safety and establish measures so that things can proceed properly." (이날 청문회에 나온 김윤덕 국토부 장관은 “여러 차례에 걸쳐서 (둔덕 관련) 규정을 개선할 수 있었음에도 제대로 되지 못한 점에 대해 장관으로서 할말이 없을 정도로 잘못된 일이라고 생각한다”며 “유가족께 진심으로 사과드리고, 둔덕 문제 뿐 아니라 항공시설 안전 전반에 걸쳐서 규정 등을 살펴보고 대책을 세워서 제대로 진행될 수 있도록 최선의 노력을 다하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241147.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690670116759_20260122503061.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>5,000 Points Ridden on Debt... Warning Bells Sound Over 'KRW 29 Trillion in Credit Transactions' (빚으로 올라탄 오천피…‘신용거래 29조’ 과열 경고음)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241156.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;5,000 Points Ridden on Debt... Warning Bells Sound Over 'KRW 29 Trillion in Credit Transactions' (빚으로 올라탄 오천피…‘신용거래 29조’ 과열 경고음)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/488/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503211.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스피 지수가 장중 사상 처음으로 5019.54를 기록한 22일 서울 중구 우리은행 본점 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 코스피 지수 5000선 돌파를 축하하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI enters the '5,000-point' era, the scale of individual investors' 'debt-fueled investing' (investing using borrowed money) has surpassed KRW 29 trillion, hitting a record high. This is interpreted as a result of increased chase buying driven by anxiety over potentially missing out on the upward trend. (코스피가 ‘오천피’(코스피 5000) 시대를 맞은 가운데 개인투자자들의 ‘빚투’(빚내서 투자) 규모가 29조원을 넘어 사상 최대치를 기록했다. 상승 흐름에서 소외될 수 있다는 불안 심리에 추격 매수가 늘어난 결과로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Korea Financial Investment Association on the 22nd, the outstanding balance of credit transaction loans stood at KRW 29.0821 trillion as of the 21st. This increased further in just one day after it first exceeded KRW 29 trillion, recording KRW 29.0586 trillion the previous day. The outstanding balance of credit transaction loans represents the amount investors have not yet repaid after borrowing funds from securities firms to buy stocks, serving as a key indicator to gauge the scale of individual investors' debt-fueled investing. (22일 금융투자협회에 따르면, 지난 21일 기준 신용거래융자 잔고는 29조821억원으로 집계됐다. 전날 29조586억원을 기록하며 사상 처음으로 29조원을 넘어선 데 이어 하루 만에 더 늘어났다. 신용거래융자 잔고는 투자자가 증권사에서 자금을 빌려 주식을 매수한 뒤 아직 상환하지 않은 금액으로, 개인투자자의 빚투 규모를 가늠할 수 있는 대표 지표다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just six months ago, in August of last year, the outstanding balance of credit transaction loans was around KRW 21 trillion. However, it has steadily increased amid the stock market boom. It recorded KRW 24.8 trillion on October 27 last year, when the KOSPI first surpassed 4,000 points historically, and first exceeded KRW 27 trillion on December 5. Subsequently, it broke through KRW 28 trillion on the 8th of this month, just over a month later, and then surpassed KRW 29 trillion in just over 10 days. As expectations grew for the KOSPI to break through 5,000 points, individual investors actively jumped into investing by taking on debt. (6개월 전인 지난해 8월만 해도 신용거래융자 잔고는 21조원대 수준이었지만, 증시 호황 속에 꾸준히 불어났다. 코스피가 사상 처음 4000을 돌파한 지난해 10월27일 24조8천억원을 기록했고, 12월5일에는 처음 27조원을 넘어섰다. 이후 1개월여 만인 이달 8일 28조원을 돌파한 데 이어, 불과 10여일 만에 29조원을 넘긴 것이다. 코스피 5000 돌파에 대한 기대감이 커지면서 개인투자자들의 빚을 내어 적극적으로 투자에 뛰어든 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, debt-fueled investing has been concentrated in large-cap stocks that led the KOSPI's rise. As of the 20th of this month, SK Hynix and Samsung Electronics saw their credit balances increase by KRW 325.1 billion and KRW 138.6 billion, respectively, compared to the previous month, showing the highest growth rates. The total credit balance stands at approximately KRW 1.8584 trillion for Samsung Electronics and KRW 1.3069 trillion for SK Hynix. Hyundai Motor, which recently showed strong performance and rose to third place in market capitalization, also saw its credit balance increase to KRW 407.9 billion, growing by KRW 124 billion just this month. (특히 코스피 상승을 이끈 대형주에 빚투가 집중됐다. 이달 20일까지 에스케이하이닉스와 삼성전자의 신용잔고는 전월에 견줘 각각 3251억원, 1386억원 순증하며 가장 높은 증가세를 보였다. 전체 신용잔액 규모는 삼성전자가 1조8584억원, 에스케이하이닉스가 1조3069억원 수준이다. 최근 강세를 보이며 시가총액 3위로 올라선 현대차도 신용잔고가 4079억원으로, 이달 들어서만 1240억원 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, voices of concern are growing. This is because credit buying can lead to forced liquidation if stock prices fall beyond a certain level. Particularly in a situation where the index has surged sharply in a short period, if the KOSPI enters a correction phase, a large volume of forced liquidation could pour out all at once, potentially widening the decline and amplifying investor losses. (이에 따라 우려의 목소리도 커지고 있다. 신용매수는 주가가 일정 수준 이상 하락하면 반대매매(강제 청산)로 이어질 수 있기 때문이다. 특히 단기간에 지수가 급등한 상황이어서, 코스피가 조정 국면에 접어들 경우 대규모 반대매매 물량이 한꺼번에 쏟아지며 하락 폭을 키우고 투자자 손실을 확대시키는 리스크로 작용할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lee Hyo-seop of the Capital Market Institute stated, "In a situation where the scale of credit transactions has become excessively large, if stock prices plummet sharply, credit volumes could be liquidated all at once through forced selling, triggering additional stock price declines." He added, "Even if stock prices do not rise again in the short term or move sideways, high interest burdens could occur, significantly expanding investor losses." (이효섭 자본시장연구원 박사는 “신용거래 규모가 과도하게 커진 상황에서 주가가 급락할 경우, 신용 물량이 반대매매로 한꺼번에 청산되면서 추가적인 주가 하락을 불러올 수 있다”며 “주가가 단기간에 다시 오르지 않거나 횡보할 경우에도 높은 이자 부담이 발생해 투자자 손실이 크게 확대될 수 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241156.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/488/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503211.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>While the KOSPI is in a Bull Market, the Real Economy is Chilly... 'K-Shaped Growth' Deepens (‘코스피 불장’인데 실물 경제는 찬바람…‘K자형 성장’ 심화)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241161.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;While the KOSPI is in a Bull Market, the Real Economy is Chilly... 'K-Shaped Growth' Deepens (‘코스피 불장’인데 실물 경제는 찬바람…‘K자형 성장’ 심화)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503276.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 아래에 5000 돌파 당시 사용했던 꽃종이가 떨어져 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean economy shrank in the fourth quarter of last year, barely achieving an annual growth rate of '1%'. While the KOSPI broke through 5,000 during trading and asset markets are experiencing a historic rally, the real economy actually posted its most sluggish performance in five years since the COVID-19 pandemic. Although growth at the potential rate level is expected this year, the shadow of 'K-shaped growth'—characterized by slow domestic demand recovery and increasing dependence on semiconductors and exports—is projected to deepen. (우리나라 경제가 지난해 4분기 역성장하며 연간 ‘1% 성장률’에 턱걸이했다. 코스피가 장중 5000을 돌파하며 자산 시장이 역사적 랠리를 펼치고 있지만, 정작 실물 경제는 코로나 팬데믹 이후 5년 만에 가장 저조한 성적을 낸 것이다. 올해는 잠재성장률 수준이 예상되지만 내수 회복세는 더디고 반도체와 수출 의존도는 높아지는 ‘케이(K)자 성장’의 그림자는 짙어질 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bank of Korea announced on the 22nd that the real GDP growth rate for the fourth quarter of last year (quarter-on-quarter, preliminary) was -0.3%. The quarterly growth rate contracted in the first quarter of last year, rebounded in the second quarter (0.7%), rose sharply in the third quarter (1.3%), and then contracted again in the fourth quarter. The fourth-quarter growth rate is 0.5 percentage points lower than the BOK's forecast (0.2%). It is the lowest level in three years since the fourth quarter of 2022 (-0.4%). (  한국은행은 지난해 4분기 실질 국내총생산(GDP) 성장률(전분기 대비·속보치)이 -0.3%로 집계됐다고 22일 밝혔다. 분기 성장률은 작년 1분기 역성장했다가 2분기 반등(0.7%)해 3분기에는 큰 폭 상승(1.3%)했는데 4분기 다시 역성장했다. 4분기 성장률은 한은 예상(0.2%)보다 0.5%포인트나 낮은 것이다. 2022년 4분기(-0.4%) 이후 3년 만에 최저치다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The annual growth rate for last year barely reached 1.0%. It narrowly hit 1% through rounding to two decimal places (0.97%). The government and the BOK explained the reason for the fourth-quarter contraction as "base effects from the high growth in the third quarter and the impact of the construction investment slump." They explained that a technical adjustment appeared due to base effects from the largest quarterly growth in 15 quarters in the third quarter of last year (1.3%, annualized 5.4%). For the entire second half of last year (0.5%), it is said to be at the potential growth rate level (0.4~0.5%). (  작년 한 해 연간 성장률은 1.0%에 턱걸이했다. 소수점 둘째자리 반올림(0.97%)으로 가까스로 1%를 맞췄다. 정부와 한은은 4분기 역성장 이유를 “3분기 높은 성장률에 따른 기저효과와 건설투자 침체 영향”이라고 밝혔다. 지난해 3분기 15분기 만에 최대 폭 성장(1.3%, 연환산 5.4%)한 기저효과로 기술적 조정이 나타났다는 설명이다. 작년 하반기 전체(0.5%)로는 잠재성장률 수준(0.4~0.5%)이라는 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They also offered the assessment that it wasn't that bad if construction investment was excluded. Construction investment decreased by nearly 10% last year, dragging down the annual growth rate by 1.4 percentage points. Excluding construction investment, the annual growth rate is calculated to reach 2.4%. Construction investment has declined for nine consecutive quarters due to factors such as rising raw material prices. (건설투자를 빼면 그리 나쁘지 않았다는 평가도 내놨다. 건설투자는 지난해 10% 가까이 감소해 연간 성장률을 1.4%포인트나 끌어내렸다. 건설투자를 제외하면 연간 성장률이 2.4%에 이른다는 계산이 나온다. 건설투자는 원자재 가격 상승 등의 영향으로 9분기 연속 감소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering the recovery trend in private consumption and the increase in exports since the second half of last year, the growth rate this year is expected to be higher than last year. The BOK forecasts 1.8%, and the government forecasts 2.0%. These are figures set higher than the initial forecasts. The BOK predicted, "This year's government budget has increased by 3.5% compared to last year, so the contribution of government expenditure to growth will be higher than last year (0.5 percentage points), and the constraint on growth from construction investment will decrease significantly." (  지난해 하반기 이후 민간소비 회복세와 수출 증가세를 감안할 때 올해 성장률은 작년보다 높아질 전망이다. 한은은 1.8%, 정부는 2.0%를 예상한다. 애초 전망치보다 높여 잡은 수치다. 한은은 “올해 정부 예산이 작년보다 3.5% 늘어 정부 지출의 성장 기여도가 작년(0.5%포인트) 보다 높아지고 건설투자의 성장률 제약은 상당 폭 줄어들 것”이라고 전망했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BOK estimates Korea's potential growth rate to be 'below 2%' (1.8~2.0%). The growth rate forecasts for this year and next (1.8%, 1.9%) are projected to remain at the potential growth rate level. They also fall significantly short of the global economic growth forecasts for this year and next (2.9%, 3.1%). This is why concerns are arising that the Korean economy may have fallen into a long-term low-growth trend. (한은은 우리나라 잠재성장률이 ‘2%를 밑도는 수준’(1.8~2.0%)이라고 추산한다. 올해와 내년 성장률 전망(1.8%, 1.9%)은 잠재성장률 수준에 머물 것이란 전망이다. 올해와 내년 세계경제 성장률 전망(2.9%, 3.1%)에도 크게 미치지 못한다. 우리 경제가 장기 저성장 기조에 빠져든 게 아니냐는 우려가 나오는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particularly concerning is the 'quality of growth'. What drove growth last year was semiconductors. The contribution of semiconductor exports to last year's growth rate (1%) is estimated at 0.9 percentage points. This means the increase in value-added in the semiconductor sector accounted for 90% of the entire economic growth. This year as well, semiconductors remain the variable affecting the rise and fall of the growth rate. The BOK anticipated "expansion of semiconductor factory facilities and increased investment related to artificial intelligence." (  특히 우려되는 것은 ‘성장의 질’이다. 지난해 성장을 이끈 건 반도체였다. 지난해 성장률(1%)에서 반도체 수출 기여도는 0.9%포인트로 추산된다. 반도체 부문의 부가가치 증가가 전체 경제 성장의 90%를 차지한 셈이다. 올해도 성장률 등락의 변수는 여전히 반도체다. 한은은 “반도체 공장 증설과 인공지능 관련 투자 확대”를 예상했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the semiconductor super cycle, the greater the numerical improvement, the more inevitable the concentration phenomenon becomes. As of the end of last year, semiconductors and automobiles accounted for over 30% of exports, with semiconductors alone responsible for a quarter of total exports. On the other hand, the construction industry, which has a significant impact on domestic demand such as employment and consumption, and traditional manufacturing sectors like petrochemicals, steel, and machinery, are struggling to find a turning point. According to BOK estimates, excluding the information technology (IT) sector, this year's growth forecast (1.8%) drops to 1.4%. BOK Governor Lee Chang-yong recently warned, "The recovery gap between sectors is large, so there will be a significant discrepancy with the perceived economic conditions," and "A K-shaped recovery can hardly be seen as sustainable and complete." (  반도체 슈퍼 사이클 덕분에 수치상 개선 폭이 커질수록 쏠림 현상은 더 심해질 수 밖에 없다. 지난해 말 기준 반도체와 자동차가 차지하는 수출 비중은 30%를 넘어섰고, 반도체가 전체 수출의 4분의 1을 담당했다. 반면, 고용과 소비 등 내수 영향이 큰 건설업과 석유화학·철강·기계 등 전통 제조업은 좀처럼 반전의 계기를 찾지 못하고 있다. 한은 추산을 보면, 정보기술(IT) 부문을 제외하면 올해 성장률 전망(1.8%)은 1.4%로 떨어진다. 이창용 한은 총재는 최근 “부문간 회복 격차가 커 체감 경기와는 괴리가 클 것”이라며 “케이자형 회복은 결코 지속 가능하고 완전한 회복으로 보기 어렵다”고 경고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241161.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503276.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple's Siri, an 'Outdated Innovation'... Can a 'Google Collaboration Chatbot' Restore Its Honor? (‘철 지난 혁신’ 애플 시리…‘구글 합작 챗봇’으로 명예회복?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241165.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/446/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503331.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apple appears poised to transform its AI voice assistant 'Siri' into a chatbot form, similar to Google's Gemini or OpenAI's ChatGPT. (애플이 인공지능(AI) 음성비서 ‘시리’(Siri)를 구글의 제미나이나 오픈에이아이(AI)의 챗지피티(Chat GPT)와 같은 챗봇 형태로 바꿀 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bloomberg reported on the 21st (local time) that Apple plans to change Siri into an AI chatbot by the end of this year. This plan, codenamed 'Compos', is the result of the collaboration between Apple and Google announced on the 12th. (블룸버그는 애플이 올해 말께 시리를 인공지능 챗봇 형태로 바꿀 계획 21일(현지시각) 보도했다. 코드명 ‘캄포스’라(Compos) 불리는 이 계획은 지난 12일 발표된 애플과 구글의 협업 결과물이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new chatbot, Compos, is reportedly based on the 'Apple Foundation Model Version 11', a custom model for Apple developed by the Gemini team. It will be provided with Apple's existing user interface design, and the invocation method will remain the same as the current Siri, where users call out "Siri". Compos is expected to be included as a new feature in the next-generation operating systems for Apple's major platforms. It will be integrated not only into iOS 27 for iPhones but also into iPadOS 27 and macOS 27. Bloomberg pointed out that this new Siri is "a key element of Apple's plan to rebound in the AI market." (새로운 챗봇 캄포스는 제미나이팀이 개발한 애플 맞춤형 모델인 ‘애플 파운데이션 모델 버전 11’로 알려졌다. 기존 애플 사용자 인터페이스 디자인으로 제공되고, 호출 방법도 지금 시리를 사용할 때와 같이 사용자가 ‘시리’라고 부르면 된다. 캄포스는 애플 주요 플랫폼의 차세대 운영체제에 신기능으로 포함될 예정이다. 아이폰 운영체제인 아이오에스(iOS)27뿐 아니라 아이패드오에스(iPadOS)27, 맥오에스(macOS)27에도 통합된다. 블룸버그는 이런 새로운 시리를 두고 “인공지능 시장에서 애플이 반등할 수 있는 계획의 핵심요소”라고 짚었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This move appears to be part of Apple's effort to revise the various AI strategies it has pursued so far. Until now, Apple has used AI by integrating it into existing features. For example, in writing, AI would assist with 'rewriting' or 'proofreading'. However, as most popular AIs like ChatGPT, Gemini, and Anthropic's Claude are in chatbot form, it is interpreted that Apple had no choice but to adopt a similar format. Competitors like Samsung Electronics have already released products with AI integrated into their operating systems. (이는 애플이 그동안 추진했던 다양한 인공지능 전략을 수정하려는 움직임의 일환으로 보인다. 그간 애플은 인공지능을 기존 기능에 통합시키는 형식으로 사용했다. 예컨대 글쓰기의 경우, 인공지능이 ‘재작성’이나 ‘교정’을 돕는 식이었다. 하지만 챗지피티, 제미나이, 앤스로픽의 클로드 등 대중화된 인공지능 대부분이 챗봇 형태인 만큼, 애플도 이와 유사한 형식을 도입할 수밖에 없었던 것으로 풀이된다. 이미 삼성전자 등 경쟁업체들은 운영체제에 인공지능을 통합한 제품을 내놓고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apple is also considering including this feature in models sold in China. It is known that Compos's base model is designed to be replaceable. In fact, Apple is reported to have also tested a chatbot using a Chinese AI model instead of the Gemini-based model. AI, formed based on training data, is considered a kind of ideological tool in the context of U.S.-China competition. If the 'AI brain' can be swapped, it seems iPhones can continue to be sold in China even if they are 'Made in the USA'. (애플은 중국에 판매하는 모델에도 해당 기능의 탑재를 염두에 두고 있다. 캄포스의 기본 모델은 교체할 수 있게 설계되는 것으로 알려졌는데, 실제 애플은 제미나이 기반의 모델 대신 중국의 인공지능 모델을 사용한 챗봇 테스트도 진행한 것으로 알려졌다. 학습데이터를 바탕으로 형성되는 인공지능은 미∙중 경쟁 상황에서 일종의 이데올로기 도구로 여겨진다. ‘인공지능 뇌’를 교체할 수 있다면 아이폰이 ‘미국산’이더라도 계속 중국에 팔 수 있을 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This feature is expected to be unveiled at Apple's developer event, the Worldwide Developers Conference (WWDC26), in June. Its official rollout is anticipated in the second half of the year. (해당 기능은 오늘 6월 애플의 개발자 행사인 세계개발자대회(WWDC26)에서 공개될 것으로 보인다. 정식 적용은 하반기로 예상된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Chae Ban-seok &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241165.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/446/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503331.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:48:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] K-luxury brand 'Wooyoungmi' disguises leftover stock as new products... "We trusted them, it's shocking" ([단독] 이월 상품 신제품 둔갑시킨 K 명품 ‘우영미’…“믿었는데 충격”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241170.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690702503609_20260122503384.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;조아무개(38)씨가 선물 받은 우영미 후드티셔츠(왼쪽), 김아무개(33)씨가 구매한 우영미 후드티셔츠(오른쪽). 흰색 플라워 자수 안쪽에 야자수 프린트가 새겨져 있다. 각각 조씨, 김씨 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The designer brand 'Wooyoungmi', considered a leader in K-luxury fashion, is facing controversy for selling leftover stock from previous seasons as new products by methods such as overlaying embroidery on the items. The company stated regarding the products in question that they are "new products that have undergone additional processing and redesign to minimize resource waste," but also added, "As we have caused confusion for some consumers, we will establish clear notification standards." (명품 케이(K)-패션 선두주자로 꼽히는 디자이너 브랜드 ‘우영미(WOOYOUNGMI)’가 상품에 자수를 덧씌우는 방식 등으로 이월상품을 신제품으로 둔갑시켜 판매해 논란이 일고 있다. 이 업체 쪽은 해당 상품을 두고 “자원 낭비를 최소화하기 위해 추가 가공과 재디자인을 거친 새로운 상품”이라면서도 “일부 소비자에게 혼란을 드렸다는 점에서 명확한 안내 기준을 마련하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a Hankyoreh investigation compiled on the 22nd, the company released the 'Black Flower Patch Hooded T-shirt' (regular price 520,000 won) in the second half of last year. The problem is that this product was made by reprocessing the 'Black Palm Tree Hooded T-shirt' (regular price in the 500,000 won range) released in the first half of the same year and sold to consumers without separate notification. The small palm tree print on the front panel of the previously released 'Black Palm Tree Hooded T-shirt' was covered with white flower embroidery, and then sewn together with the plain back panel of the t-shirt to be released as a second-half product. Typically, t-shirts are made by cutting the front panel, back panel, and sleeves separately and then sewing the side seams, shoulder seams, armholes, etc. (22일 한겨레 취재를 종합하면, 이 업체는 지난해 하반기 ‘블랙 플라워 패치 후드 티셔츠’(정가 52만원)를 출시했다. 문제는 이 상품이 같은 해 상반기에 출시한 ‘블랙 야자수 후드 티셔츠’(정가 50만원 대) 상품을 재가공한 뒤 소비자에게 별도의 고지를 하지 않은 채 판매했다는 점이다. 앞서 출시한 ‘블랙 야자수 후드 티셔츠’ 앞판의 작은 야자수 프린트를 흰색 꽃 자수로 덮은 뒤 무늬가 없는 티셔츠 뒷면부와 봉제해 하반기 상품으로 내놓은 것이다. 통상 티셔츠는 앞판과 뒤판, 소매를 각각 재단해서 옆선, 어깨선, 암홀 등을 봉제하는 방식으로 만든다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voices of dissatisfaction have erupted among consumers. Kim (33), who bought this product at the 'Manmade' store in Gangnam-gu, Seoul last October, said they discovered a different print inside because their pet scratched the embroidery. They said, "I thought the material on the front and back of the clothes felt subtly different, but I thought it was just my imagination," adding, "I never imagined a luxury brand would disguise old stock and sell it as new." Cho (38), who received this hooded t-shirt as a gift last November, said, "While trying to remove a stain on the embroidery at a repair shop I visited, I was told 'there's a different print under the embroidery'," and added, "I trusted them because it's a high-end designer brand, so it was shocking to learn they had disguised old clothes as new without notifying consumers." (소비자들 사이에선 불만의 목소리가 터져 나왔다. 지난해 10월 서울 강남구 ‘맨메이드’ 매장에서 이 상품을 샀다는 김아무개(33)씨는 반려동물이 자수를 긁는 바람에 안에 든 다른 프린트를 발견하게 됐다고 했다. 그는 “옷 앞뒷면 소재가 미묘하게 다른 것 같았지만, 기분 탓이라고 생각했다“며 “고급 브랜드에서 묵은 제품을 새 제품으로 둔갑시켜 판매할 줄은 상상도 못 했다”고 말했다. 지난해 11월 이 후드티셔츠를 선물 받은 조아무개(38)씨는 “자수에 묻은 얼룩을 지우기 위해 찾았던 수선집에서 ‘자수 안에 다른 프린트가 있다’는 이야기를 들었다”며 “고급 디자이너 브랜드라 믿었는데, 소비자에게 고지도 하지 않고 예전 옷을 새 옷처럼 둔갑시켰다는 사실이 충격적이었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, 'Wooyoungmi' stated this was part of a process to minimize resource waste and fulfill the company's social responsibility. A 'Wooyoungmi' official said, "In order to minimize resource waste during the production process, we introduced a new product line in the second half of last year based on fabric presented in the first half, which underwent additional processing and redesign," adding, "This move aligns with the government's policies for achieving carbon neutrality and revitalizing the circular economy, and is part of fulfilling the company's social responsibility." (이에 대해 ‘우영미’ 쪽은 자원 낭비를 최소화하고 기업의 사회적 책무를 다하는 과정이라고 밝혔다. ‘우영미’ 관계자는 “제작 과정에서 자원 낭비를 최소화하기 위해 지난해 상반기에 선보인 원단을 기반으로 추가 가공과 재디자인을 거친 새로운 상품 라인을 그해 하반기에 선보인 바 있다”며 “이런 행보는 정부의 탄소중립 실현 및 순환경제 활성화 정책과도 궤를 같이하며, 기업의 사회적 책무를 다하는 과정”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They further added, "We judged that this constitutes a new product in terms of the manufacturing process and believed there was no separate legal or internal obligation to notify, but through this incident, we have come to recognize that it may have caused confusion or disappointment for some consumers," and stated, "We will establish clearer notification standards for this line going forward and will continue to regularly present sustainable projects." (그는 이어 “이는 제작 공정상 새로운 상품에 해당한다고 판단해 법적·내부적으로 별도의 고지 의무는 없다고 봤으나, 이번 계기를 통해 일부 소비자분들께 혼란이나 아쉬움을 드릴 수 있다는 점을 인지하게 됐다”며 “향후 해당 라인에 대해 보다 명확한 안내 기준을 마련하고, 앞으로도 지속가능한 프로젝트를 정기적으로 선보이겠다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Wooyoungmi', which focuses on menswear, is a designer brand launched by designer Woo Young-mi in Paris, France in 2002, and currently operates about 80 global stores. (남성복을 주력으로 하고 있는 ‘우영미’는 디자이너 우영미가 2002년에 프랑스 파리에서 출시한 디자이너 브랜드로, 현재 80여개의 글로벌 매장을 운영하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241170.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690702503609_20260122503384.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:48:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade Commission "Domestic industry harmed by dumping imports of Chinese optical fiber, etc... Requests tariff imposition" (무역위 “중국산 광섬유 등 덤핑 수입으로 국내 피해…관세부과 요청”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241174.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/499/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503429.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;경기도 평택항에 철강 제품이 쌓여 있는 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Trade Commission under the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy announced on the 22nd that it has decided to recommend to the Minister of Economy and Finance the imposition of anti-dumping duties, judging that the domestic industry is being harmed by the dumping of Chinese optical fiber and some Thai copper pipes. As countries worldwide are raising tariff and non-tariff trade barriers, the dumping exports of overproduced products from some countries, including China, are increasing, thereby amplifying the role of the Trade Commission which investigates such cases. (산업통상자원부 무역위원회는 중국산 광섬유와 태국산 동관 일부의 덤핑 수입으로 국내 산업이 피해를 보고 있다고 판단해 재정경제부 장관에게 덤핑방지관세 부과를 건의하기로 의결했다고 22일 밝혔다. 세계 각국이 관세·비관세 무역 장벽을 높이는 가운데 중국을 포함한 일부 국가에서 과잉 생산된 제품의 덤핑 수출이 증가하면서 이를 조사하는 무역위의 역할도 커지는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Trade Commission held a meeting today and determined that the domestic industry has suffered harm due to the dumping of Chinese 'single-mode optical fiber'. It decided to recommend to the Minister of Economy and Finance the imposition of a 43.35% anti-dumping duty for the next five years. A provisional anti-dumping duty (43.35%) has been applied to this product since September last year. Single-mode optical fiber is the raw material for optical cables used in communication network equipment such as telephones, internet, and cable TV. It has gained attention as an essential material for building 5G and 6G communication networks, leading to a rapid increase in production within China. However, as domestic demand in China recently stagnated and inventories piled up, some companies began selling at rock-bottom prices. In response, the domestic company LS Cable applied for a dumping investigation in January last year regarding single-mode optical fiber manufactured by three Chinese companies: Hengtong, Yangtze, and Jinsintong. (  무역위는 이날 회의를 열어 중국산 ‘단일모드 광섬유’의 덤핑 수입으로 국내 산업에 피해가 발생했다고 판단하고, 향후 5년 동안 43.35% 덤핑방지관세를 부과해줄 것을 재경부 장관에게 건의하기로 의결했다. 해당 제품에 대해서 지난해 9월부터 잠정덤핑방지관세(43.35%)가 부과 중이다. 단일모드 광섬유는 전화·인터넷·케이블티브이(TV) 등 통신네트워크 설비에 사용되는 광케이블의 원료다. 5세대(G), 6세대 통신망 구축 등에 필수적인 소재로 주목받으면서 중국 내에서 생산량이 빠르게 늘었지만, 최근 들어 중국 내부 수요가 정체되면서 재고가 쌓이자 일부 기업이 헐값에 밀어내기 판매에 나선 것이다. 이에 지난해 1월 국내 기업인 엘에스(LS)전선이 중국의 형통·양쯔·진씽통 등 세 개사가 제조한 단일모드 광섬유에 대해 덤핑 조사를 신청했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the Trade Commission also determined that the domestic industry is being harmed by the dumping of Thai 'seamless copper pipes'. It recommended to the Minister of Economy and Finance the imposition of provisional anti-dumping duties: 3.64% on products from Hong Kong Hailiang and 8.41% on products from Fine Metal. Seamless copper pipes, used in home appliances like air conditioners and refrigerators, as well as apartment heating pipes, are reportedly causing damage to the domestic industry as dumping imports continue despite decreasing domestic construction demand. The Trade Commission was also briefed on the re-examination of anti-dumping duties for Chinese 'flat photo plates for printing plates' and the initiation of an investigation into unfair trade practices regarding 'patent infringement of automotive battery packs'. (  무역위는 아울러 태국산 ‘이음매 없는 동관’에 대해서도 덤핑 수입으로 국내 산업이 피해를 보고 있다고 판단해, 홍콩하이량의 제품에 대해 3.64%, 파인메탈 제품에 대해 8.41%의 잠정덤핑방지관세 부과를 재경부 장관에 건의했다. 에어컨, 냉장고 등 가전제품과 아파트 난방 배관 등에 사용되는 이음매 없는 동관은 국내 건설 수요가 감소하고 있는데도 덤핑 수입이 지속되면서 국내 산업에 피해를 주고 있는 것으로 알려졌다. 무역위는 중국산 ‘인쇄제판용 평면모양 사진플레이트’ 덤핑 방지관세부과 재심사와 ‘자동차용 배터리팩 특허권 침해’ 불공정무역행위 조사개시에 대해서도 보고받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having received a report on the '2025 Investigation Results on Unfair Trade Practices such as Dumping and Intellectual Property Infringement', the Trade Commission stated that last year, applications for dumping investigations were received for 13 items, investigations were conducted on 22 cases, and anti-dumping measures were additionally implemented on 8 items. As of the end of 2025, anti-dumping duties are being imposed on 28 items from 15 countries. (이날 ‘2025년 덤핑 및 지식재산권 침해 등 불공정무역행위 조사성과’를 보고받은 무역위는 지난해 13개 품목에 대한 덤핑조사 신청이 접수됐고, 22건에 대한 조사를 벌여 8개 품목에 덤핑방지 조치를 추가 시행했다고 밝혔다. 2025년 말 기준 15개국 28개 품목에 대해 덤핑방지관세가 부과되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The receipt of applications for dumping investigations on 13 items in one year is the largest scale since the establishment of the Trade Commission in 1987. By product, steel and chemical products accounted for the most with 10 cases. By country, Chinese products accounted for the most with 9 cases. The average market size of products subject to dumping investigation applications, which was 150.3 billion won in 2021, grew more than tenfold to 1.8 trillion won last year. Analysis suggests that as the number of dumping investigations increases, the scale of each case is also growing larger and the content becoming more complex, thereby increasing the importance of the Trade Commission. (  1년 동안 13개 품목에 대한 덤핑조사 신청이 접수된 것은 1987년 무역위원회가 출범한 이후 최대 규모다. 제품별로 살펴보면 철강·화학제품이 10건으로 가장 많았고, 국가별로는 중국산 제품이 9건을 차지해 가장 많았다. 2021년 1503억원 규모였던 덤핑 조사신청된 제품의 시장규모 평균액수가 지난해에는 1조8천억원 규모로 10배 이상 커졌는데, 덤핑 조사 건수가 증가하는 동시에 각 사건의 규모가 점점 커지고 내용도 복잡해지고 있어 무역위의 중요성도 커지고 있다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To respond to these changes, the Trade Commission plans to enhance the expertise of data analysis through testing and certification agencies and to investigate dumping cases more professionally by linking with external specialized agencies and experts in the fields of the Korean Intellectual Property Office and intellectual property rights. An official from the Trade Commission said, "We will strengthen the management of sanction measures such as fines imposed as a result of unfair trade practice investigations and improve follow-up systems including responses to administrative lawsuits," adding, "We plan to continue efforts to establish fair trade order and provide timely relief to damages suffered by the domestic industry." (  이런 변화에 대응하기 위해 무역위는 시험인증기관을 통해 자료 분석의 전문성을 높이고, 특허청·지식재산권 분야 외부전문기관·전문가 연계를 통해서도 보다 전문적으로 덤핑 사건을 조사할 계획이다. 무역위 관계자는 “불공정무역행위 조사 결과로 부과되는 과징금 등 제재 조치의 관리를 강화하고, 행정 소송 대응을 비롯한 후속 조치 제도도 정비하겠다”며 “공정한 무역 질서를 확립해 국내 산업의 피해를 적기에 구제할 수 있도록 지속적으로 노력할 예정”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Jae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  이재호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241174.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/499/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503429.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:47:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Black &amp; White Chef' Show Has Ended, But... A Collaboration Product Sales War Ahead of Lunar New Year (‘흑백요리사’ 방송은 끝났지만…설 앞두고 협업상품 판매 전쟁)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241179.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503471.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;흑백요리사 시즌2의 우승자인 최강록 셰프 협업 상품을 보고 있는 고객의 모습. 롯데마트 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the Netflix cooking entertainment program 'Black &amp; White Chef: The Culinary Class War' (hereafter Black &amp; White Chef 2) concluded on the 13th, the buzz surrounding the chefs who appeared on the show remains strong in the distribution sector ahead of the Lunar New Year holiday. This is because distribution companies are launching collaboration products with the featured chefs and intensifying related marketing. (넷플릭스 요리 예능 프로그램 ‘흑백요리사: 요리 계급 전쟁’(이하 흑백요리사2)이 지난 13일 막을 내렸지만, 출연한 요리사들의 화제성은 설 명절을 앞둔 유통가에서는 여전하다. 유통업계가 출연 셰프와의 협업 상품을 출시하며 관련 마케팅을 강화하고 있어서다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GS Shop, the home shopping channel operated by GS Retail, announced on the 22nd that it will continue its 'Fantasy New Year' event from the 23rd until February 11th. It stated it has strengthened its Lunar New Year gift lineup, focusing on premium foods including the 'Crispy Barley Shrimp Gim-bugak' (seaweed cracker) made in collaboration with Chef Son Jong-won, who appeared on the program, as well as bellflower root syrup and olive oil. (지에스(GS)리테일이 운영하는 홈쇼핑 채널 지에스(GS)샵은 23일부터 다음 달 11일까지 ‘판타지 설날’ 행사를 이어간다. 이 프로그램에 출연한 손종원 셰프와 협업한 ‘바삭 보리새우 김부각’을 비롯해 도라지청, 올리브오일 등 프리미엄 식품을 중심으로 설 선물 종류를 강화했다고 22일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large supermarkets and the hotel industry are also stepping up to capture holiday gift demand by promoting chef collaboration products. Lotte Mart is selling exclusive Lunar New Year gift sets, created in collaboration with Chef Choi Kang-rok, the winner of 'Black &amp; White Chef 2', during the pre-order period for this Lunar New Year holiday. The Mayfield Hotel Seoul announced on the 21st that it has launched premium Lunar New Year gift sets centered around the traditional Korean restaurant 'Bongnaeheon'. The signature product is the 'Bongnaeheon Sechan' set, for which Chef Lee Geum-hee, the Korean cuisine executive chef at Mayfield Seoul who gained attention on the program, oversaw the entire cooking process. (대형마트와 호텔업계도 요리사 협업 상품을 앞세워 명절 선물 수요 잡기에 나서고 있다. 롯데마트는 이번 설 명절 사전 예약 기간에 ‘흑백요리사2’ 우승자인 최강록 셰프와 단독으로 협업한 설 선물세트를 판매한다. 메이필드호텔 서울은 전통 한식당 ‘봉래헌’을 중심으로 한 프리미엄 설 선물세트를 출시했다고 지난 21일 밝혔다. 이번 프로그램에 출연해 주목받은 이금희 메이필드 서울 한식 총괄 조리장이 모든 조리 과정을 총괄했다는 ‘봉래헌 세찬’이 대표 상품이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cases of expanding collaboration scope with famous chefs to include cooking tools and kitchenware are also emerging. Hanssem, an interior specialist company, is running advertisements featuring program judge Chef Ahn Sung-jae, and kitchenware brand Whirlpool Korea is promoting pressure cookers, pots, and frying pan products used by the chefs. (조리도구와 주방용품 등으로 유명 요리사와의 협업 범위를 넓히는 사례도 잇따르고 있다. 인테리어 전문기업 한샘은 프로그램 심사위원 안성재 셰프를 앞세워 광고 중이고, 주방용품 브랜드인 휘슬러코리아는 셰프들이 사용한 압력솥·냄비·프라이팬 제품 등을 앞세워 홍보하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Hye-mi &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서혜미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241179.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503471.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:47:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, Hyundai Motor 'On Fire'... Combined Market Cap Triples in 7 Months (불타오른 ‘삼전·하이닉스·현대차’…시총 합산, 7개월 만에 3배)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241181.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690714368754_20260122503476.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스피가 4950대에서 장을 마친 22일 서울 영등포구 한국거래소 홍보관 현황판에 코스피 지수 등이 표시돼 있다.연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over approximately seven months from June 4 last year to the 22nd of this month, the combined market capitalization of three major KOSPI-listed stocks (Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, Hyundai Motor) has increased by 200%. (지난해 6월4일부터 22일까지 약 7개월 동안 코스피 상장 주요 3개 종목(삼성전자·에스케이하이닉스·현대차)의 합산 시가총액이 200% 증가한 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Korea Exchange's Information Data System screen on the 22nd, the combined market cap of these three stocks as of that day is 1,559.52 trillion won. Compared to the combined market cap of the three stocks on the trading day just before KOSPI began its relentless 'bull market' run (June 2 last year), which was 524.98 trillion won, it has increased by 1,034.54 trillion won. The growth rate is 197.06%, meaning their combined size has roughly tripled. (22일 한국거래소 정보데이터시스템 화면을 보면, 이날 기준 이 3개 종목 합산 시가총액은 1559조5200억원이다. 코스피가 거침없는 ‘불장’ 질주를 시작하기 직전 거래일(지난해 6월2일)의 3개 종목 합산 시가총액(524조9800억원)에 견줘 1034조5400억원 불어났다. 증가율은 197.06%로, 몸집이 약 세 배 늘어난 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of this day, these three stocks account for 38.0% of the total KOSPI market capitalization (4,095.874 trillion won). This share surged from 23.7% on June 2 last year to 31.4% on October 27 last year when KOSPI surpassed 4,000 on a closing basis, and then grew further to 37.8% on the 6th of this month when it surpassed 4,500. The number of KOSPI-listed stocks currently stands at 954 as of this day. (이날 기준 코스피 전체 시가총액(4095조8740억원)에서 이 3개 종목이 차지하는 비중은 38.0%에 이른다. 이 비중은 지난해 6월2일 23.7%에서 코스피가 종가기준 4000을 돌파한 지난해 10월27일 31.4%로 급증한 뒤, 4500을 돌파한 지난 6일에는 37.8%까지 커졌다. 코스피 상장종목은 이날 현재 954개에 이른다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The total KOSPI market capitalization increased from 2,211.661 trillion won on June 2 last year to 4,095.874 trillion won on this day, a rise of 1,884.213 trillion won, representing a growth rate of 85.19%. (코스피 시가총액은 지난해 6월2일 2211조6610억원에서 이날 4095조8740억원으로 1884조2130억원 늘어나 상승률은 85.19%에 달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the same period, the market cap growth rates for the three individual stocks were: Samsung Electronics at 168.12% (336.245 trillion won → 901.561 trillion won), SK Hynix at 263.85% (151.06 trillion won → 549.642 trillion won), and Hyundai Motor at 187.50% (37.675 trillion won → 108.317 trillion won). (같은 기간 3개 종목 시가총액 상승률은 삼성전자가 168.12%(336조2450억원→901조5610억원), 에스케이하이닉스 263.85%(151조600억원→549조6420억원), 현대차 187.50%(37조6750억원 →108조3170억원)에 이른다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241181.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690714368754_20260122503476.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:47:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Min-young, CEO of IBK Asset Management, Nominated as Next CEO of Industrial Bank of Korea (차기 기업은행장에 장민영 IBK자산운용 대표)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241188.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/269/291/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503518.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;장민영 기업은행장 내정자. 기업은행&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Min-young, CEO of IBK Asset Management, has been nominated as the new CEO of the Industrial Bank of Korea (IBK). If appointed, she will be the sixth CEO to be promoted from within the bank. (신임 아이비케이(IBK)기업은행 은행장으로 장민영 아이비케이자산운용 대표이사가 내정됐다. 장 내정자는 기업은행 여섯 번째 내부 출신 행장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Financial Services Commission announced on the 22nd that it has recommended the appointment of Jang Min-young, CEO of IBK Asset Management, as the 28th CEO of the Industrial Bank of Korea. (금융위원회는 22일 장민영 아이비케이자산운용 대표를 28대 기업은행장으로 임명 제청했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee joined the Industrial Bank of Korea in 1989 and has held key positions including Head of the Risk Management Group (Vice President), Head of the Gangbuk Regional Headquarters, Head of the Economic Research Institute, and Head of the Fund Management Department. She moved to the subsidiary IBK Asset Management as Vice President in 2023 and has been serving as CEO since June 2024. (장 내정자는 1989년 기업은행에 입행한 뒤 리스크관리그룹장(부행장), 강북지역본부장, 경제연구소장, 자금운용부장 등 주요 보직을 두루 거쳤다. 2023년 자회사 아비이케이자산운용 부사장으로 자리를 옮긴 뒤, 2024년 6월부터 대표이사를 맡고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Financial Services Commission stated, "The nominee is a financial expert with a deep understanding of financial markets and expertise in risk management. Having served at the Industrial Bank of Korea and IBK Asset Management for approximately 35 years, she has a high level of understanding of the organization and is expected to provide stable leadership." The Commission further assessed, "She is the right person to lead a major shift towards productive finance through policy finance, by strengthening financial support for SMEs and small business owners, and expanding investment and loans for venture companies in advanced strategic industries." (금융위는 “장 내정자는 금융시장에 대한 높은 이해와 리스크관리 전문성을 갖춘 금융전문가로, 약 35년간 기업은행과 아이비케이자산운용에 재직하며 조직에 대한 이해도가 높아 안정적인 리더십을 펼칠 것으로 기대된다”고 밝혔다. 금융위는 이어 “중소기업·소상공인 금융 지원을 강화하고, 첨단전략산업 분야 벤처기업 투·융자 확대 등을 통해 정책금융을 통한 생산적 금융의 대전환을 이끌 적임자”라고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the nominee is finally appointed, she will become the sixth CEO of the Industrial Bank of Korea promoted from within, following former CEOs Kim Seung-kyung, Jo Jun-hee, Kwon Sun-joo, Kim Do-jin, and Kim Sung-tae. Under the Lee Jae-myung administration, the chairman of the Korea Development Bank and the president of the Export-Import Bank of Korea have also been appointed from within their respective institutions. (장 내정자가 최종 임명될 경우 김승경, 조준희, 권선주, 김도진, 김성태 전 행장에 이어 여섯 번째 내부 출신 기업은행장이 된다. 이재명 정부 들어 산업은행 회장과 수출입은행장 역시 내부 출신 인사가 선임된 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The CEO of the Industrial Bank of Korea is appointed by the President upon the recommendation of the Chairman of the Financial Services Commission, without a separate public recruitment process or formation of a nomination committee. Following the end of former CEO Kim Sung-tae's term on the 2nd, the appointment of a successor was delayed, and the bank has been operating under an acting CEO system for about 20 days. (기업은행장은 별도의 공모나 임원추천위원회 구성 없이 금융위원장이 제청하면 대통령이 임명한다. 김성태 전 행장이 지난 2일 임기를 마친 뒤 후임 인선이 지연되면서, 기업은행은 20여 일간 직무대행 체제로 운영돼 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241188.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/269/291/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503518.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:46:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple Starts Developing 'AI Wearable Pin'... Competition with OpenAI to Dominate the Market (애플 ‘AI 웨어러블 핀’ 개발 시동…오픈AI와 시장 선점 경쟁)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241193.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690726980173_20260122503542.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;미 아이티(IT) 전문매체 디인포메이션은 21일(현지시각) 애플이 분실물 위치 추적 기기인 ‘에어태그’ 크기의 인공지능(AI) 기반 웨어러블 기기를 개발 중이라고 보도했다. 디인포메이션 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Apple has kicked off the development of an artificial intelligence-based wearable device. This move targets the next-generation personal device market, following PCs and smartphones, and signals the intensification of a market dominance race with OpenAI, which has announced plans to unveil AI-specialized hardware devices in the latter half of this year. (애플이 인공지능 기반 웨어러블 기기 개발에 시동을 걸었다. 피시(PC)와 스마트폰에 이은 차세대 개인용 디바이스 시장을 겨냥한 행보로, 올 하반기 인공지능 특화 하드웨어 기기 공개를 예고한 오픈에이아이(AI)와의 시장 선점 경쟁이 본격화하는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. IT specialty media The Information reported on the 21st (local time) that Apple is developing an AI-based wearable pin the size of its lost item tracker, 'AirTag'. The product is expected to be released as early as 2027. (미국 아이티(IT) 전문매체 디인포메이션은 애플이 자사의 분실물 위치 추적 기기인 ‘에어태그’ 크기의 인공지능 기반 웨어러블 핀을 개발 중이라고 21일(현지시각) 보도했다. 이 제품은 이르면 2027년 출시될 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The AI-based pin Apple is developing has a thin, flat circular form, with two cameras mounted on the front for users to capture their surroundings. It also features three microphones and speakers to detect the voice of the user wearing the device, and the back of the device incorporates a magnetic induction wireless charging interface, similar to the Apple Watch. Considering the AirTag's dimensions of 31.9mm in diameter, 8.0mm in thickness, and 11g in weight, it is expected to be a small product about the size of a 500-won coin. (애플이 개발 중인 인공지능 기반 핀은 얇고 평평한 원형 형태로, 전면에 이용자가 주변 풍경을 촬영할 수 있는 2개의 카메라가 탑재된다. 또한 기기를 착용한 이용자의 목소리 등을 감지하기 위한 3개의 마이크와 스피커를 갖췄으며, 기기 뒷면에는 애플워치처럼 자석을 활용한 자기유도식 무선 충전 인터페이스가 적용됐다. 지름 31.9mm, 두께 8.0mm, 무게 11g인 에어태그의 크기를 고려할 때 500원짜리 동전만한 소형 제품이 될 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As it is still in the early stages of development, the possibility of the project being canceled cannot be ruled out. However, the media outlet, citing sources, reported that "Apple is pushing development at a faster pace than usual, conscious of competition with OpenAI." If the product is released, initial production volume is known to reach about 20 million units. (아직 개발 초기 단계인 만큼 프로젝트가 취소될 가능성도 배제할 수 없지만, 이 매체는 소식통을 인용해 “애플이 오픈에이아이와의 경쟁을 의식해 평소보다 더 빠른 속도로 개발을 추진하고 있다”고 전했다. 제품이 출시될 경우 초기 생산 물량은 약 2천만대에 이를 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, big tech companies are intensifying their competition to develop AI devices to seize leadership in the next-generation personal device market following smartphones. Meta Platforms, the parent company of Facebook, which was the first to jump into this market, has been selling smart glasses equipped with AI assistant functions since 2023. OpenAI, the developer of ChatGPT, also revealed its intention to enter the hardware market by acquiring the startup 'io', founded by former Apple design chief Jony Ive, last May. Google also plans to launch smart glasses based on its AI model Gemini in partnership with Samsung Electronics within the year. (최근 빅테크 기업(거대 기술기업)들은 스마트폰 이후 차세대 개인용 디바이스 시장 주도권을 잡기 위해 인공지능 기기 개발 경쟁을 본격화하고 있다. 이 시장에 가장 먼저 뛰어든 페이스북 모회사 메타 플랫폼스는 2023년부터 인공지능 비서 기능을 탑재한 스마트 안경을 판매 중이다. 챗지피티(Chat GPT) 개발사 오픈에이아이도 지난해 5월 애플 아이폰 디자인을 총괄했던 조니 아이브가 설립한 스타트업 ‘아이오’(io)를 인수하며 하드웨어 시장 진출 의지를 드러냈다. 구글 역시 삼성전자와 손잡고 인공지능 모델 제미나이(Gemini) 기반 스마트 안경을 연내 출시할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the industry, the prevailing view is that Apple and OpenAI are the key competitors in the AI device market. There is an interpretation that the changed relationship with OpenAI is also reflected in the background of Apple's recent contract with Google to improve its AI voice assistant 'Siri' based on the Gemini model. Although Apple signed a contract just two years ago to integrate ChatGPT into its own AI system 'Apple Intelligence', analysis suggests the relationship between the two companies is shifting from a former 'alliance' to 'competitors', as the AI device OpenAI is preparing to launch could absorb potential iPhone customers. (업계에선 애플과 오픈에이아이를 인공지능 디바이스 시장의 핵심 경쟁자로 보는 시각이 우세하다. 최근 애플이 구글과 제미나이 모델을 기반으로 자사 인공지능 음성 비서 ‘시리’(Siri)를 개선하는 계약을 맺은 배경에도, 오픈에이아이와의 달라진 관계가 반영된 것이 아니냐는 해석이 나온다. 애플은 불과 2년 전 챗지피티를 자사 인공지능 시스템 ‘애플 인텔리전스’에 통합하는 계약을 맺었지만, 오픈에이아이가 출시를 준비 중인 인공지능 디바이스가 아이폰의 잠재적 고객을 흡수할 수 있는 만큼 두 회사의 관계가 기존 ‘동맹’에서 ‘경쟁자’로 전환되고 있다는 분석이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In relation to this, the Financial Times (FT) recently cited sources familiar with OpenAI's situation, reporting that the company made a strategic decision last fall "not to become a provider of custom models for Apple," and instead decided to focus on developing its own AI devices that could surpass big tech companies. (이와 관련해 파이낸셜타임스(FT)는 최근 오픈에이아이 사정에 정통한 관계자를 인용해 이 회사가 지난해 가을 “애플을 위한 맞춤형 모델 제공 사업자가 되지 않겠다는 전략적 결정을 내렸다”며, 대신 빅테크 기업들을 뛰어넘을 수 있는 자체 인공지능 기기 개발에 집중하기로 했다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Bloomberg reported on the same day that Apple plans to completely overhaul its voice assistant Siri into a chatbot form like ChatGPT by the end of this year. This service, to be provided through its own custom AI model 'Apple Foundation Model Version 11' being developed based on Google Gemini, is expected to be unveiled at Apple's annual developer conference, the Worldwide Developers Conference (WWDC26), in June. (한편, 애플은 올해 말 음성 비서 시리를 챗지피티와 같은 챗봇 형태로 전면 개편할 예정이라고 이날 블룸버그가 전했다. 구글 제미나이를 기반으로 개발하는 자사 맞춤형 인공지능 모델 ‘애플 파운데이션 모델 버전 11’을 통해 제공될 이 서비스는 오는 6월 애플의 연례 개발자 행사인 ‘세계개발자대회’(WWDC26)에서 공개될 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Sun Dam, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; By Chae Ban-seok, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (선담은 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241193.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690726980173_20260122503542.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:46:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Rising Even More Than Jeonse"... Sparks from Government's 'Gap Investment Block' Fly to Villa and Officetel Monthly Rents (“전세보다 더 올라”…정부 ‘갭투자 차단’ 불똥, 빌라·오피스텔 월세로)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241197.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690730490726_20260122503589.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 송파구 롯데월드타워 전망대 서울스카이에서 바라본 서울 시내 빌라 단지의 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr. Park, a 32-year-old office worker who started his newlywed life in a newly built villa with a dedicated area of 30㎡ in Seongdong-gu, Seoul, is only afraid of the upcoming lease contract expiration date. He has lived for nearly two years paying a monthly rent of 1.3 million won (with a 50 million won deposit), bearing the worry of jeonse fraud, but recently heard that monthly rents for similar-sized units have soared to the 1.6 million won range. (서울 성동구의 전용면적 30㎡ 신축 빌라에서 신혼 생활을 시작한 직장인 박아무개(32)씨는 조만간 다가올 임차계약 만료일이 두렵기만 하다. 전세사기 걱정에 월세 130만원(보증금 5천만원)을 감당하며 2년 가까이 살았는데, 최근 같은 평형 월세가 160만원대까지 치솟았다는 소식을 들었기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Park exercises his right to request contract renewal this time, the rent will increase by within 5%, or 65,000 won. However, his housing cost burden is already at a critical level. He said, "Due to work, I want to live somewhere not too far from here, but everywhere has become expensive, so it's a desperate situation. I don't even dream of an apartment, but it's just absurd that finding a house is this difficult." (이번에 박씨가 계약갱신청구권을 행사한다면 임대료는 5%인 6만5천원 이내로 오르겠지만, 이미 박씨의 주거비 부담은 턱밑까지 차오른 상태다. 그는 “직장 때문에 되도록 여기서 멀지 않은 곳에 살고 싶은데 어디든 다 올라버려서 막막한 상황이다. 아파트는 바라지도 않는데 이렇게 집 구하기 어렵다는 게 황당할 따름”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An analysis by Hankyoreh and the Korea Urban Research Institute of the recent five years (2021~2025) of reported monthly rent contracts for small non-apartments in Seoul from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport's actual transaction price disclosure system on the 22nd showed that monthly rents for small villas and officetels, common housing forms for the lower-middle class and those starting their careers, are rising sharply. Concerns are emerging that the housing cost burden for young people and low-income households who have not accumulated assets will increase ahead of the spring moving season. (22일 한겨레가 한국도시연구소와 함께 국토교통부 실거래가 공개시스템의 최근 5년(2021∼2025년) 서울 소형 비아파트 월세 계약 신고분을 분석해보니, 중하위층과 사회초년생의 흔한 주거 형태인 소형빌라와 오피스텔 월세가 가파르게 오르고 있는 것으로 나타났다. 봄 이사철을 앞두고 자산을 축적하지 못한 청년층·서민의 주거비 부담이 가중될 것이란 우려가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This analysis targeted monthly rent contracts with deposits of 50 million won or less among detached/multi-family houses, row/multi-unit houses, and officetels with a dedicated area of 60㎡ (approximately 18 pyeong) or less in Seoul. This is a residential area where relatively little statistical and policy development has occurred, as attention from policymakers and the media has been focused on the trends of apartment sales and jeonse prices in Seoul. (이번 분석은 서울 내 전용면적 60㎡(약 18평) 이하 단독·다가구, 연립·다세대, 오피스텔 가운데 보증금 5천만원 이하 월세 계약을 대상으로 했다. 서울 아파트에 대한 매매, 전세가 추이에 정책 당국과 언론 등의 관심이 쏠리며 상대적으로 통계 및 정책 개발이 이뤄지지 않은 주거 영역이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis results showed that last year's average monthly rent for small non-apartments in Seoul was 654,000 won, having risen 10.3% over the recent two years. In 2021 alone, it was 538,000 won, meaning it increased 21.6% over four years. When the deposit is converted to a monthly amount at the legal upper limit conversion rate of 6% and added to the monthly rent, the average combined price last year was 734,000 won, which translates to about 95,000 won per pyeong in rent. (분석 결과 지난해 서울 시내 소형 비아파트 평균 월세는 65만4천원으로 최근 2년 사이 10.3% 올랐다. 2021년만 해도 53만8천원이었는데, 4년 새 21.6%가 올랐다. 보증금을 법정 상한선인 전·월세전환율 6%로 환산해 월세와 합산한 평균 가격은 지난해 73만4천원으로, 평당 임대료로 따지면 9만5천원 꼴이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the 'gap investment' was completely blocked by the October 15 real estate market stabilization measures last year, leading to a contraction in the supply of jeonse apartments, the sparks are flying to the non-apartment monthly rent market. Ahn Myung-sook, CEO of the real estate marketing solution firm Ojirak, said, "The significant impact is from apartment rental demand flowing into non-apartments due to accumulated supply shortages and rising jeonse prices and reduced jeonse listings caused by the October 15 measures," adding, "The upward trend in monthly rents will continue for the time being." (지난해 10·15 부동산 시장 안정화 대책으로 ‘갭투자’가 전면 차단돼 아파트 전세매물 공급이 위축되면서 그 불똥이 비아파트 월세 시장에까지 튀고 있다. 안명숙 부동산 마케팅 솔루션제작소 오지랖 대표는 “그동안 누적된 공급 부족과 10·15 대책으로 아파트 전셋값이 오르고 전세 매물이 줄어들면서 아파트 임차 수요가 비아파트로 유입된 영향이 크다”며 “당분간 월세 상승세가 이어질 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon of 'jeonse shifting to monthly rent' following the aftermath of the 2023 jeonse frauds also had a considerable impact. In a situation where demand for monthly rent in the non-apartment market increased due to aversion to villa jeonse, the slow conversion to monthly rent by existing jeonse landlords who find it difficult to return deposits has created a kind of supply-demand gap (demand &gt; supply), causing monthly rents to rise significantly. Cho Jung-hoon, chairman of the Land and Housing Committee at the Citizens' Coalition for Economic Justice, said, "It appears that landlords with leeway are setting higher rents through new contracts, to which the upper limit system for jeonse and monthly rent does not apply, during the conversion process to monthly rent." (2023년 전세사기 여파로 인한 ‘전세의 월세화’ 현상도 적지 않은 영향을 미쳤다. 빌라 전세 기피 심리로 비아파트 시장에서 월세 수요가 늘어난 상황에, 기존 보증금을 돌려주기 어려운 전세 임대인들의 월세 전환이 더뎌지면서, 일종의 수급차(수요&amp;gt;공급)가 나타나 월세가 크게 오르고 있다는 것이다. 조정흔 경제정의실천시민연합 토지주택위원장은 “여유가 있는 임대인들은 월세로 전환하는 과정에서 전·월세 상한제가 적용되지 않는 신규 계약을 통해 임차료를 높게 책정하고 있는 것으로 보인다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Korea Real Estate Board, the monthly rent price index for Seoul row/multi-unit houses was 102.95 last December, with a cumulative increase rate of 3.4% for 2025. In contrast, the jeonse price index rose 2.1% during the same period. The proportion of monthly rent for Seoul non-apartments increased by over 10 percentage points in two years, from 63.6% in 2023 to 74.5% in 2025 as of November. Compared to the gradual increase in the proportion of monthly rent for Seoul apartments from 42.2% to 44.3% during the same period, the 'shift from jeonse to monthly rent' appears to have progressed rapidly, centered on non-apartments. (한국부동산원에 따르면 서울 연립·다세대 월세가격지수는 지난해 12월 102.95로 2025년 누적 상승률은 3.4%였다. 반면 전세가격지수는 같은 기간 2.1% 올랐다. 서울 비아파트 월세 비율은 11월 기준으로 2023년 63.6%에서 2025년 74.5%로 2년 새 10%포인트 넘게 늘었다. 서울 아파트 월세 비율이 같은 기간 42.2%에서 44.3%로 점진적으로 늘어나고 있는 것과 견주면 ‘전세의 월세화’ 현상은 비아파트를 중심으로 빠르게 진행된 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rise in officetel monthly rents is also unstoppable. Mr. Yoon, a 35-year-old office worker living in an officetel with a dedicated area of 30㎡ in Gangseo-gu, Seoul, for a monthly rent of 700,000 won, recently received a call from the landlord to either raise the rent to 850,000 won or vacate. Mr. Yoon said, "When I said I would exercise the right to request contract renewal, they said the landlord's child would then move in," adding, "Since jeonse and monthly rents have already risen a lot elsewhere, I don't know what to do." Last year's average monthly rent for officetels in Seoul was 802,000 won, having risen 12.5% over the recent two years, surpassing the 800,000 won line for the first time. The four-year cumulative increase rate is 26.6%. The average monthly rent for Seoul row/multi-unit houses was 731,000 won, and for detached/multi-family houses, it was 547,000 won. (오피스텔 월세 상승세도 파죽지세다. 서울 강서구에서 전용면적 30㎡ 오피스텔을 월세 70만원에 살고 있는 직장인 윤아무개(35)씨는 최근 집주인으로부터 월세를 85만원으로 올리거나 방을 빼달라는 전화를 받았다. 윤씨는 “계약갱신청구권을 쓰겠다고 했더니 그럼 집주인 자녀가 들어와 살 거라고 했다”며 “다른 곳도 전·월세가 이미 많이 오른 상황이라 어떻게 해야 할지 모르겠다”고 말했다. 지난해 서울 내 오피스텔 평균 월세는 최근 2년 사이 12.5% 오른 80만2천원으로, 처음 80만원 선을 넘어섰다. 4년 누적 상승률은 26.6%다. 서울 연립·다세대 월세는 평균 73만1천원, 단독·다가구는 54만7천원이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The areas with the highest monthly rent increase rates over the recent two years within Seoul were Yeongdeungpo-gu and Dongdaemun-gu, where the proportion of young population is relatively high, each rising 13.7%. They were followed by Gangseo-gu (13.5%), Geumcheon-gu (13.0%), Seocho-gu (12.8%), and Seongdong-gu (12.7%). In terms of average monthly rent, Gangnam-gu was the highest at 910,000 won, followed by Seocho-gu (861,000 won), Yongsan-gu (805,000 won), Songpa-gu (783,000 won), and Jung-gu (782,000 won). Within Seoul, Dobong-gu had the lowest average monthly rent at 537,000 won. (서울 내에서 최근 2년 월세 상승률이 가장 높았던 곳은 청년 인구 비중이 상대적으로 높은 영등포구와 동대문구로 각 13.7% 올랐다. 그 뒤로는 강서구(13.5%), 금천구(13.0%), 서초구(12.8%), 성동구(12.7%) 등 순이었다. 월세 평균으로 따지면 강남구가 91만원으로 가장 높았고, 서초구(86만1천원), 용산구(80만5천원), 송파구(78만3천원), 중구(78만2천원) 등 순이었다. 서울 내에서는 도봉구가 53만7천원으로 월세 평균이 가장 낮았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid the trend of rising monthly rents, 'one-room' units were no exception. A separate analysis of non-apartments with a dedicated area under 30㎡ showed that the average monthly rent for one-rooms in Seoul last year was 619,000 won, a 19.3% increase compared to 519,000 won four years ago. In terms of rent per pyeong, one-rooms cost 110,000 won, which was much more expensive than small villas (67,000 won). (월세 상승 흐름 속에서 ‘원룸’ 역시 예외는 아니었다. 전용면적 30㎡ 미만 비아파트를 별도로 분석해보니, 서울 원룸 평균 월세는 지난해 61만9천원으로, 4년 전 51만9천원에 견줘 19.3% 증가했다. 평당임대료로 치면 원룸은 11만원으로, 소형빌라(6만7천원)보다 훨씬 비쌌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite this situation, government support measures to alleviate the monthly rent burden for the lower-middle class and young people are severely lacking. While housing benefits that partially support monthly rent for basic livelihood security recipient households and partial monthly rent support for low-income young people and newlyweds are being implemented, these have limitations such as narrow eligibility or being temporary. The annual monthly rent tax credit system is also gradually expanding, but this also only benefits wage workers who have enough income to pay taxes. (상황이 이렇지만, 중하위층과 청년층의 월세 부담을 덜어줄 정부 지원책은 턱없이 부족하다. 기초생활수급가구의 월세를 일부 지원하는 주거급여와 저소득 청년층과 신혼부부를 대상으로 한 부분적 월세 지원 정도가 시행되고 있지만, 이는 지원 대상이 좁거나 지원 기간이 한시적이라는 한계가 있다. 매년 월세 세액공제 제도도 조금씩 확대되고 있지만, 이 역시 세금을 낼 정도의 소득이 있는 임금노동자만 혜택을 보는 방식이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Jung-hoon, a researcher at the Korea Urban Research Institute, said, "The lack of attention to the non-apartment monthly rent market is one of the biggest problems of officials looking at the housing market," adding, "It is time for active support measures to emerge that can alleviate the housing cost burden of households living in low-quality housing while paying high monthly rent." (홍정훈 한국도시연구소 연구원은 “비아파트 월세 시장에 대한 관심 부족은 주택 시장을 바라보는 당국자들의 가장 큰 문제 중 하나”라며 “높은 월세를 내며 낮은 품질의 주택에 살고 있는 가구들의 주거비 부담을 덜어줄 수 있는 지원 대책이 적극적으로 나와야 할 때”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241197.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690730490726_20260122503589.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:45:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Villas and Officetels 'Expensive Even When New'... 4-Year Rent Increase Rate for New Buildings is 2.2 Times That of Old Buildings (빌라도 ‘얼죽신’…월세 4년 상승률, 신축이 구축의 2.2배)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241200.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/396/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503603.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The steep rise in monthly rents for non-apartment housing is being led by 'newly built housing'. The analysis indicates that areas with a higher concentration of new villas and officetels see rents for older buildings rise as well, leading to a higher average rent increase rate. This implies that unless the government intervenes with price controls through measures like public supply, private sector-led supply of new housing could act as upward pressure on rents. (가파른 비아파트 월세 상승세는 ‘신축 주택’이 주도하고 있다. 신축 빌라·오피스텔이 많은 지역일수록 구축까지 월세가 함께 올라 평균 월세 상승률이 높아진다는 것이다. 공공 공급 등을 통해 정부가 가격 통제에 나서지 않으면, 민간 중심의 신축 주택 공급이 월세 상방 압력으로 작동할 수 있다는 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An analysis by The Hankyoreh and the Korea Urban Research Institute of monthly rent contract filings for small non-apartment units in Seoul over the recent five years (2021~2025) from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport's actual transaction price disclosure system, released on the 22nd, showed that the average monthly rent for 'new' non-apartment buildings completed after 2020 was 916,000 won. This is a sharp 39.1% increase compared to the price in 2021 (659,000 won). Compared to the 17.6% rise over the last four years for 'old' non-apartment buildings completed before 1999, the rent increase rate for new buildings is more than double. Even in 2021, the average rent difference between new and old buildings was around 200,000 won, but last year the gap widened to 400,000 won. The average monthly rent for non-apartment buildings built in the 2010s was 667,000 won, for those from the 2000s it was 647,000 won, and for those from before 1999 it was 552,000 won. (22일 한겨레가 한국도시연구소와 함께 국토교통부 실거래가 공개시스템의 최근 5년(2021∼2025년) 서울 내 소형 비아파트 월세 계약 신고분을 분석해보니, 2020년 이후 준공된 ‘신축’ 비아파트 평균 월세는 91만6천원이었다. 이는 2021년(65만9천원)과 견줘 39.1%나 치솟은 가격이다. 1999년 이전에 준공된 ‘구축’ 비아파트가 최근 4년동안 17.6% 오른 것과 견주면 신축 월세 상승률은 2배 이상 높다. 2021년만 해도 신축과 구축의 평균 월세 차이는 20만원 선에 그쳤으나 지난해에는 40만원까지 벌어졌다. 2010년대에 지어진 비아파트 월세는 평균 66만7천원, 2000년대는 64만7천원, 1999년 이전은 55만2천원이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A trend also emerged showing that autonomous districts with a higher proportion of new monthly rent contracts tend to have higher rent increase rates. This analysis suggests that new villas and officetels have pulled up rents for older buildings as well. In Geumcheon-gu, which has the highest proportion of new buildings in Seoul at 20.7%, the cumulative four-year rent increase rate (based on conversion from deposit to monthly rent) was 25.1%, the third highest among Seoul's 25 autonomous districts. In contrast, Nowon-gu, which has the lowest proportion of new buildings in Seoul at 2.9%, saw its cumulative four-year rent increase rate remain at just 8.4%. Furthermore, Yeongdeungpo-gu, where the proportion of new buildings reaches 16.0%, had the highest cumulative increase rate in Seoul at 27.2%. This appears to show an 'anchoring effect' where new building-led rent increases pull up surrounding market prices. The average proportion of new contracts across Seoul's 25 autonomous districts is around 10.8%. (신축 월세 계약 비율이 높은 자치구일수록 월세 상승률이 높아지는 경향도 나타났다. 신축 빌라·오피스텔이 구축 월세까지도 함께 끌어올렸다는 분석이다. 신축 비중이 20.7%로 서울에서 가장 높은 금천구의 경우, 4년 누적 월세 상승률(보증금 월세 전환 기준)이 25.1%로 서울 25개 자치구 가운데 세 번째로 높게 나타났다. 반면 신축 비중이 2.9%로 서울에서 가장 낮은 노원구의 4년 누적 월세 상승률은 8.4%에 그쳤다. 이밖에도 신축 비중이 16.0%에 이르는 영등포구는 누적 상승률이 27.2%로 서울에서 가장 높았다. 신축 중심 월세 상승이 주변 시세를 끌어올리는 ‘앵커링 효과’가 나타난 셈이다. 서울 25개 자치구의 평균 신축 계약 비율은 10.8% 수준이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government has previously promoted the activation of non-apartment housing supply by offering tax benefits to small-scale construction businesses supplying non-apartment housing for low-income household residential stability. However, the supply of new housing has had the effect of increasing the rental burden for low-income households by raising rents for surrounding older buildings. Hong Jeong-hoon, a researcher at the Korea Urban Research Institute, said, "The government has focused its policy on activating new non-apartment housing through deregulation of construction, and it seems tenants have borne the side effects of such policies," adding, "Policies where the public intervenes to provide housing cheaper than market rents should be pursued together." (그간 정부는 저소득층 주거 안정을 위해 비아파트를 공급하는 소규모 건설사업자에 대해 세제 혜택을 부여하는 등 비아파트 공급 활성화에 나서왔다. 하지만 신축 주택 공급이 주변 구축의 임대료를 끌어올려 저소득층 주거비 부담을 가중시키는 효과를 낸 것이다. 홍정훈 한국도시연구소 연구원은 “정부는 건축 규제 완화를 통한 신축 비아파트 활성화에 정책적 초점을 맞춰왔는데, 이러한 정책의 부작용을 임차인들이 감당한 셈”이라며 “공공이 개입해 시장 임대료보다 저렴한 주택을 제공하도록 하는 정책이 함께 추진되어야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This analysis targeted monthly rent contracts with deposits of 50 million won or less for detached/multi-family houses, row/multi-unit houses, and officetels with a dedicated area of 60㎡ (approximately 18 pyeong) or less within Seoul. (이번 분석은 서울 내 전용면적 60㎡(약 18평) 이하 단독·다가구, 연립·다세대, 오피스텔 가운데 보증금 5천만원 이하 월세 계약을 대상으로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241200.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/396/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503603.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:44:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NHN Union Says "40% of Affiliates Evaporated Over 5 Years... Stop the Opaque Restructuring" (NHN 노조 “5년간 계열사 40% 증발…불투명한 구조조정 중단하라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241204.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/645/484/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503631.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;민주노총 화학섬유식품산업노조 엔에이치엔(NHN)지회는 22일 경기 성남시 엔에이치엔 사옥 앞에서 기자회견을 열어 그룹사 내 구조조정 및 소극적 전환배치를 규탄했다. 민주노총 화학섬유식품산업노조 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The labor union is strongly protesting, calling the workforce reduction at NHN, an IT company operating the easy payment service 'Payco' and the popular game 'Hangame Poker', an 'opaque restructuring'. (간편결제 서비스 ‘페이코’와 인기 게임 ‘한게임 포커’ 등을 운영하는 아이티(IT) 기업 엔에이치엔(NHN)의 인력 감축을 두고 노동조합이 ‘불투명한 구조조정’이라며 강하게 반발하고 나섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NHN branch of the Korean Federation of Chemical, Textile, and Food Industries Unions under the Korean Confederation of Trade Unions held a press conference in front of the NHN headquarters in Seongnam, Gyeonggi Province on the 22nd, urging the company to "immediately halt the unilateral restructuring and workforce reduction being carried out under the pretext of 'sound management'" and demanding substantial group-level employment stability measures. (민주노총 화학섬유식품산업노조 엔에이치엔지회는 22일 경기 성남시 엔에이치엔 사옥 앞에서 기자회견을 열고 “‘내실 경영’이라는 명분 아래 진행되는 일방적인 구조조정과 인력 감축을 즉각 중단하라”며 그룹 차원의 실질적인 고용 안정 대책 마련을 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The union criticized, "Despite steady increases in sales and operating profit over the past four years, the NHN Group has liquidated about 20 subsidiaries under the banner of 'sound management'," adding, "Voluntary retirement has been repeatedly offered at various corporations including NHN Cloud, Payco, Wetoo, and NHN Edu, citing business termination and organizational restructuring." Furthermore, they stated, "Last week, with the sale of NHN Bucks, affiliated workers faced employment instability," and added, "Workers who have dedicated themselves for years under the management strategy of 'selection and concentration' are being treated like replaceable resources." (노조는 “엔에이치엔그룹은 최근 4년간 매출과 영업이익이 꾸준히 증가했음에도 ‘내실 경영’을 내세워 약 20개 자회사를 정리했다”며 “엔에이치엔클라우드, 페이코, 위투(Wetoo), 엔에이치엔에듀 등 여러 법인에서 사업 종료와 조직 개편을 이유로 권고사직이 반복돼 왔다”고 비판했다. 이어 “지난주에는 엔에이치엔벅스가 매각되면서 소속 노동자들이 고용 불안에 직면했다”며 “‘선택과 집중’이라는 경영 전략 아래 수년간 헌신한 노동자들이 교체 가능한 자원처럼 취급받고 있다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NHN has recently embarked on business restructuring focusing on game, cloud, and payment services, while liquidating non-core businesses. On the 15th, it signed a contract to sell its music platform subsidiary NHN Bucks to NDT Engineering, a non-destructive testing solution company. (엔에이치엔은 최근 게임·클라우드·결제 서비스를 중심으로 사업 구조 재편에 나서며 비주력 사업을 정리하고 있다. 지난 15일에는 음악 플랫폼 자회사 엔에이치엔벅스를 비파괴 검사 솔루션 업체 엔디티(NDT)엔지니어링에 매각하는 계약을 체결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company is conducting reassignments for workers facing employment instability during the business restructuring process, but the union's position is that the effectiveness is low. Regarding NHN Edu, which operates the school notification application 'I am School' whose service termination was decided last year, the union revealed that the number of people successfully reassigned is only "around 10%" of the total. (회사 쪽은 사업 재편 과정에서 고용 불안에 놓인 노동자들을 대상으로 전환 배치를 진행하고 있으나, 실효성이 떨어진다는 게 노조의 입장이다. 노조는 지난해 서비스 종료가 결정된 알림장 애플리케이션 ‘아이엠스쿨’을 운영하는 엔에이치엔에듀의 경우, 전환 배치에 성공한 인원이 전체의 “10% 내외”에 불과하다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, the union is demanding that the company: △Stop restructuring and workforce reduction, △Prepare substantial group-level employment succession measures, △Improve reassignment procedures and establish an employment stability system. Lee Dong-gyo, head of the NHN union branch, said, "We have requested the establishment of an employment stability consultative body with NHN and NHN Edu," and added, "If the company does not respond, we will continue to publicize the issue through rallies, etc." (현재 노조는 회사에 △구조조정 및 인력 감축 중단 △그룹 차원의 실질적인 고용 승계 대책 마련 △전환 배치 절차 개선 및 고용 안정 시스템 구축 등을 요구하고 있다. 이동교 엔에이치엔 노조 지회장은 “엔에이치엔과 엔에이치엔에듀에 고용 안정 협의체 구성을 요청한 상황”이라며 “회사 측이 응답하지 않을 경우 집회 등을 통해 공론화를 이어갈 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, NHN stated, "Currently, the NHN Edu corporation and headquarters are actively communicating and sincerely continuing efforts for employment stability, such as group company reassignments," and added, "We plan to faithfully communicate with members during this process and strictly comply with relevant laws and regulations." (이에 대해 엔에이치엔 쪽은 “현재 엔에이치엔에듀 법인과 본사가 적극적으로 소통하며 그룹사 전환 배치 등 고용 안정을 위한 노력을 진정성 있게 이어가고 있다”며 “해당 과정에서 구성원과 충실히 소통하고 관련 법규와 규정을 철저히 준수할 방침”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Seon Dam, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (선담은 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241204.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/645/484/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503631.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:44:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Semiconductors and Automobiles Pull and Push... '5,000 P' Touched (반도체·자동차가 끌고 밀어…‘오천피’ 터치)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241207.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503658.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스피가 22일 장중 사상 처음으로 5000선을 돌파했다. 이날 서울 영등포구 한국거래소 홍보관 건물 외벽에 이를 기념하는 ‘코스피 5000’ 돌파 대형 펼침막이 내걸려 있다. 이날 코스피는 전장보다 42.60(0.87%) 오른 4952.53으로 장을 마쳤다. 류우종 선임기자 wjryu@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI broke through the 5,000-point level during the trading session. This is a new milestone in the 46-year history of the domestic stock market. However, the Korean economy experienced negative growth in the fourth quarter of last year, barely achieving annual growth of '1%'. It appears to have taken on the task of overcoming 'K-shaped growth'. (코스피가 장중 5000선을 돌파했다. 46년 국내 주식시장 역사의 새 이정표다. 다만 우리나라 경제는 지난해 4분기 역성장하며 연간 ‘1% 성장’에 턱걸이했다. ‘케이(K)자 성장’ 극복이라는 숙제를 받아든 모양새다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, on the KOSPI market, the KOSPI index opened at 4,987.06, up 1.57% (77.13 points) from the previous close. In the early session, it surpassed the 5,000-point level for the first time ever, recording an intraday high of 5,019.54. The KOSPI fluctuated around the 5,000-point level and then closed at 4,952.53, up 0.87% (42.60 points) from the previous close, pressured by profit-taking selling in the afternoon. Although it did not reach '5,000 P', this is the highest closing price on record. Samsung Electronics, the top company by market capitalization, touched 157,000 won during the session and finished trading at 152,300 won (up 1.87%). The combined market capitalization of its common and preferred shares exceeded 1,000 trillion won for the first time ever for a single company. SK Hynix also rose by 2.03%. (22일 유가증권시장에서 코스피는 전장보다 1.57%(77.13) 오른 4987.06으로 출발해 장 초반 역대 처음 5000선을 넘어서며 장중 최고가 5019.54를 기록했다. 코스피는 5000선 안팎을 오르내리다 오후 들어 차익 실현 매물에 밀려 전장보다 0.87%(42.60) 오른 4952.53에 주간거래를 마감했다. ‘오천피’에 이르지 못했지만 종가 기준 사상 최고치다. 시가총액 최상위 기업인 삼성전자는 장중 15만7000원을 터치한 뒤 15만2300원(1.87%)에 거래를 마쳐 보통주와 우선주를 합산한 시가총액이 단일 기업으로는 사상 처음 1000조원을 넘겼다. 에스케이(SK)하이닉스도 2.03% 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI's sprint this year has been unrivaled. From the 2nd to this day, the KOSPI continued its upward march for 14 days, with the exception of one day (the 20th). Its increase rate compared to the year-end closing price on December 30th (4,214.17) is 17.52%, the highest among the representative stock indices of 40 major countries. (올해 들어 코스피의 질주는 독보적이다. 코스피는 지난 2일부터 이날까지 하루(20일)를 제외하고 14일간 상승 행진을 이어갔다. 지난달 30일 연말 종가(4214.17) 대비 상승률은 17.52%로 주요 40개국 대표 주가지수 중 가장 높다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI has more than doubled in less than a year. It broke through the 4,000-point level (on October 27th) in half a year from its low point in April last year (2,293.70), and then touched the 5,000-point level intraday in about three more months. During this period, the domestic stock market continuously raised the index level by sustaining a rotational buying trend led by large-cap stocks, starting with semiconductors and followed by 'defense, shipbuilding, nuclear power - automobiles - robotics'. When semiconductor stocks took a breather due to the weakness of U.S. tech stocks, buying momentum shifted to automobile and robotics stocks. Last year, the KOSPI's increase rate was 75.6%, ranking first among the G20 major economies and OECD member countries. During the same period, Japan rose 27%, China 18%, and the U.S. 17%. However, the concentration phenomenon, where mid- and small-cap stocks were relatively neglected, intensified. Han Ji-young, a researcher at Kiwoom Securities, assessed, "During the sharp rise at the beginning of the year, the number of declining stocks was greater than the number of rising stocks. This suggests that the rally's warmth was concentrated only in a few sectors like semiconductors, shipbuilding, defense, and automobiles." (코스피는 1년이 채 안 돼 두배 넘게 올랐다. 지난해 4월 연저점(2293.70)에서 반년 만에 4000선(10월27일)을 돌파했고 다시 약 석달 만에 장중 5000선을 밟았다. 이 기간 국내 증시는 반도체를 필두로 ‘방조원(방산·조선·원전)-자동차-로봇’ 등 대형 주도주로 순환매 장세를 이어가며 지수 수준을 계속해서 끌어올렸다. 미국 기술주 약세로 반도체주가 숨고르기를 하는 시기엔 자동차와 로봇주로 매수세가 옮겨붙는 식이었다. 지난해 코스피 상승률은 75.6%로 주요 20개국(G20) 및 경제협력개발기구(OECD) 회원국 중 1위다. 같은 기간 일본은 27%, 중국은 18%, 미국은 17% 상승했다. 다만 중·소형주는 상대적으로 소외되는 쏠림 현상이 심화됐다. 한지영 키움증권 연구원은 “연초 급등기에 하락 종목 수가 상승 종목 수보다 많았다. 반도체, 조선, 방산, 자동차 등 소수 업종에만 랠리 온기가 집중됐음을 시사한다”고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, unlike the domestic stock market which rose to a record high, the Korean economy experienced negative growth in the fourth quarter of last year, barely achieving annual growth of '1%', the lowest level since the COVID-19 pandemic. According to Bank of Korea statistics, the real GDP growth rate for the fourth quarter of last year (quarter-on-quarter, preliminary) was -0.3%. The quarterly growth rate showed negative growth in the first quarter of last year, rebounded in the second quarter (0.7%), rose sharply in the third quarter (1.3%), and then turned negative again in the fourth quarter. The fourth-quarter growth rate is the lowest in three years since the fourth quarter of 2022 (-0.4%). The annual growth rate for last year barely reached 1.0%. This is a figure rounded from 0.97%. (다만 사상 최고치까지 오른 국내 증시와 달리 우리나라 경제는 지난해 4분기 역성장하며 코로나19 팬데믹 이후 최저 수준인 연간 ‘1% 성장’에 턱걸이했다. 한국은행 집계를 보면, 지난해 4분기 실질 국내총생산(GDP) 성장률(전 분기 대비, 속보치)은 -0.3%로 나타났다. 분기 성장률은 작년 1분기 역성장했다가 2분기 반등(0.7%)해 3분기에는 큰 폭 상승(1.3%)했는데, 4분기 다시 역성장한 것이다. 4분기 성장률은 2022년 4분기(-0.4%) 이후 3년 만에 최저치다. 작년 한해 연간 성장률은 1.0%에 턱걸이했다. 0.97%로 소수점 둘째자리에서 반올림을 한 수치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241207.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503658.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FSS, Amid Growing Controversy Over 'Expansion of Special Judicial Police Powers', Says "Introduction into Accounting and Inspection Areas Requires Caution" (금감원, 커지는 ‘특사경 확대’ 논란에 “회계·검사 부문 도입은 신중히”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241211.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/383/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503668.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 여의도 금융감독원. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Financial Supervisory Service (FSS) has submitted its opinion to the National Assembly regarding a plan to grant special judicial police authority for investigating/supervising accounting fraud and inspecting financial companies, stating that "it could be criticized as an excessive exercise of power, requiring careful review." This is interpreted as a measure to explain the review process as controversy surrounding the expansion of special judicial police powers spreads. (금융감독원이 회계 부정에 대한 조사·감리와 금융회사 검사 업무에 특별사법경찰 권한을 부여하는 방안에 대해 “과도한 권한 행사라는 비판이 제기될 수 있어 신중한 검토가 필요하다”는 의견을 국회에 제출했다. 특사경 권한 확대를 둘러싼 논란이 확산하자 검토 경위를 설명하기 위한 조처로 해석된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the 'FSS's Practical Review Opinion on Special Judicial Police' submitted by the FSS to the office of Representative Lee Jung-moon of the Democratic Party of Korea, a member of the National Assembly's Legislation and Judiciary Committee, on the 22nd, the FSS stated it had reviewed matters including △granting investigative initiation authority to capital market special judicial police and control measures △introduction of special judicial police for public livelihood financial crimes △additional measures for other areas. (22일 국회 정무위원회 소속 이정문 더불어민주당 의원실이 금융감독원으로부터 제출받은 ‘금감원 특사경 관련 실무 검토의견’을 보면, 금감원은 △자본시장 특사경에 대한 인지수사권 부여 및 통제 방안 △민생금융범죄 특사경 도입 △기타 부문 추가 방안 등을 검토했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding 'other areas,' the FSS mentioned that a plan to grant special judicial police authority for investigating/supervising accounting fraud and inspecting financial companies was also part of the review. However, the FSS stated, "It could be criticized as an excessive exercise of power, etc., requiring careful review," effectively indicating that introduction would not be easy. (이 중 ‘기타 부문’과 관련해 금감원은 회계 부정에 대한 조사·감리와 금융회사 검사 업무에 특사경 권한을 부여하는 방안도 검토 대상으로 언급했다. 다만 금감원은 “과도한 권한 행사 등의 비판이 제기될 수 있어 신중한 검토가 필요하다”며, 사실상 도입이 쉽지 않다는 판단을 함께 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Special judicial police refer to judicial police granted investigative authority limited to specific fields of crime. The FSS currently operates special judicial police to respond to unfair trading in capital markets. However, as criticisms persist that the initiation of cases is delayed because they are not granted investigative initiation authority, the introduction of such authority is being pursued. A plan to newly introduce special judicial police targeting public livelihood financial crimes, such as illegal private lending, is also under review. (특사경은 특정 분야 범죄에 한해 수사권을 부여받은 사법경찰을 말한다. 금감원은 현재 자본시장 불공정거래 대응을 위한 특사경을 운영하고 있다. 그러나 인지수사권이 부여되지 않아 사건 착수가 지연된다는 지적이 이어지면서, 인지수사권 도입을 추진 중이다. 불법 사금융 등 민생금융범죄를 대상으로 한 특사경을 새로 도입하는 방안도 함께 검토하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung, during the Financial Services Commission (FSC)/FSS work report last December, instructed to review granting investigative initiation authority to FSS special judicial police and additional introduction measures. Related discussions have since gained momentum. Following the presidential instruction, the Office of the Prime Minister is checking the operational status and scope of authority of special judicial police across all ministries. (이재명 대통령은 지난해 12월 금융위·금감원 업무보고에서 금감원 특사경 인지수사권 부여와 추가 도입 방안 검토를 지시했다. 이후 관련 논의가 탄력을 받고 있다. 대통령 지시에 따라 국무총리실은 전 부처의 특사경 운영 실태와 권한 범위를 점검하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, controversy spread as reports emerged that a review opinion report on introducing special judicial police, recently submitted by the FSS to the FSC, included accounting fraud/financial company inspection duties—areas not initially discussed—as targets for introduction. This led to criticism that the FSS might be attempting to excessively expand its authority and also created a situation that appeared to intensify conflict between the FSC and the FSS. (이런 가운데 최근 금감원이 금융위에 제출한 특사경 도입 검토 의견 보고서에, 당초 논의된 바 없던 회계 부정·금융회사 검사 업무까지 특사경 도입 대상으로 포함됐다는 보도가 나오며 논란이 확산됐다. 금감원이 권한을 과도하게 확장하려는 것 아니냐는 비판과 함께, 금융위와 금감원 간 갈등이 격화하는 것처럼 비치는 상황도 연출됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, the FSS explained in the document submitted to the lawmaker's office, "The institution's official position has not been finalized yet," and "We are sending the material in a summarized form of the practical review opinion on FSS special judicial police submitted unavoidably to the FSC." The intent is that although the plan to introduce special judicial police related to accounting fraud and financial company inspection duties was mentioned during discussions with the FSC, the judgment that it is practically difficult to pursue was also conveyed. (이에 대해 금감원은 의원실에 제출한 문서에서 “현재 기관의 공식 입장이 정리되지 않은 상황”이라며 “부득이하게 금융위에 제출한 금감원 특사경 관련 실무 검토의견을 요약한 형태로 자료를 송부한다”고 설명했다. 금융위와의 협의 과정에서도 회계 부정 및 금융회사 검사 업무와 관련한 특사경 도입 방안을 언급하긴 했으나, 사실상 추진이 어렵다는 판단을 함께 전달했다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the burden of the conflict situation between the two institutions grew, an interpretation emerged that the FSS submitted the materials to the National Assembly to explain the review process and calm the controversy. It was also reported that FSS Governor Lee Chan-jin, at an executive meeting held on the 20th, mentioned the conflict controversy with the FSC several times and requested, "Please manage it specially so it does not appear as a conflict externally." (두 기관 간 갈등 국면에 대한 부담이 커지자, 금감원이 검토 경위를 설명하며 논란을 진정시키려는 차원에서 국회에 자료를 제출했다는 해석이 나온다. 이찬진 금융감독원장도 지난 20일 열린 임원회의에서 금융위와의 갈등 논란을 수차례 언급하며 “외부에 갈등처럼 비치지 않도록 특별히 관리해달라”고 주문한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the document submitted to the lawmaker's office, the FSS stated, "We are conducting practical discussions with the Financial Services Commission, the supervising agency over the FSS," and "We plan to deliver the final plan, derived through sufficient discussions to ensure FSS special judicial police can operate according to the public's expectations, to the Prime Minister's Office." (금감원은 의원실 제출 문서에서 “금감원에 대한 지도·감독기관인 금융위와 실무적인 협의를 진행 중”이라며 “국민의 눈높이에 맞게 금감원 특사경이 운영될 수 있도록 충분한 협의를 거쳐 도출한 최종안을 총리실에 전달할 예정”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241211.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/383/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503668.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:22 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>