<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon: "With Four Consecutive Quarters of 0% Growth, Proactive Fiscal Policy is Needed Now... It's Different from the Past" (이혜훈 “4분기 연속 0%대 성장, 지금은 적극적 재정 필요…과거와 달라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241322.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon: "With Four Consecutive Quarters of 0% Growth, Proactive Fiscal Policy is Needed Now... It's Different from the Past" (이혜훈 “4분기 연속 0%대 성장, 지금은 적극적 재정 필요…과거와 달라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691389069067_20260123501380.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 재정경제기획위원회의 인사청문회에서 의원 질의에 답하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, stated on the 23rd, "In a situation where we are experiencing four consecutive quarters of 0% growth, proactive fiscal policy is more necessary than anything else." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 “4분기 연속으로 0%대 성장을 하고 있는 상황에서는 적극적 재정이 무엇보다 필요하다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee gave this response at a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee when asked about her stance on current fiscal policy, adding that "prices are also stable in the 2% range." (이 후보자는 이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회 인사청문회에서 현재 재정정책에 대한 입장을 묻는 말에 “물가도 2%대로 안정적”이라며 이처럼 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding lawmakers' comments that she 'positively evaluated sound fiscal policy during the Yoon Suk Yeol administration,' she explained, "My stance on fiscal policy is no different now than it was then," adding, "The criteria for deciding between expansion or austerity must comprehensively consider economic variables such as economic conditions, fiscal balance, monetary policy, and prices." She continued, "During the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, the growth rate was enjoying the 2% range, but instead, prices were very high at 5.1%. In that situation, austerity was appropriate." (그는 ‘윤석열 정부 당시 건전 재정에 대해 긍정적으로 평가했다’는 의원들 지적에 대해서는 “재정정책에 대한 입장은 그때나 지금이나 다름이 없다”며 “확장이냐 긴축이냐 결정하는 기준은 경제 여건과 재정수지, 통화정책, 물가 등 경제 변수를 종합 고려해야 하기 때문”이라고 설명했다. 이어 “윤석열 정부 때에는 성장률이 2%대를 구가하고 있었고 대신 물가는 5.1%로 굉장히 높았다. 그런 상황에서는 긴축이 적절했다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She reiterated, "What has changed is the economic situation, not my principles." This emphasis on the changed economic situation addresses criticism that the nominee, known as a fiscal conservative who had not previously advocated for proactive fiscal policy, may have shifted her stance upon being nominated as a minister in the new government. (그는 “경제 상황이 그때와 지금 달라진 것이지 저의 원칙이 달라진 것은 아니다”라고 거듭 말했다. 재정 보수론자로 그동안 적극적 재정을 옹호하지 않던 이 후보자가 새 정부 장관 후보자로 지명되자 입장을 선회한 것이 아니냐는 지적에 대해 경제 상황 변화를 강조한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241322.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691389069067_20260123501380.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Homeplus to Close Jamsil and Incheon Sungui Stores... Will KDB Step in with Loans? (홈플러스, 잠실·인천숭의점도 영업종료…산은, 대출 나설까)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241343.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Homeplus to Close Jamsil and Incheon Sungui Stores... Will KDB Step in with Loans? (홈플러스, 잠실·인천숭의점도 영업종료…산은, 대출 나설까)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501764.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울시내 한 홈플러스 매장. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus, which is undergoing corporate rehabilitation procedures and has been sequentially deciding to close stores, has decided to also end operations at its Jamsil store in Seoul and its Incheon Sungui store. As a consensus has formed that government-level cooperation is necessary to resolve the Homeplus situation, attention is focused on whether the Korea Development Bank (KDB) will accept the emergency operating funds (DIP loan) requested by Homeplus. (기업회생 절차를 밟으며 순차적으로 지점 영업종료를 결정하고 있는 홈플러스가 서울 잠실점·인천숭의점 영업도 종료하기로 했다. 홈플러스 사태 해결을 위해 정부 차원의 협력이 필요하다는 공감대가 형성된 가운데, 홈플러스가 요청한 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출을 한국산업은행이 수용할지에 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Homeplus official said on the 23rd, "We have decided to close the Jamsil and Incheon Sungui stores due to the expiration of their contract periods. These two stores have been chronically unprofitable, and we expect improvements in cash flow and business viability from their closure." The specific closure schedule has not been decided. (홈플러스 관계자는 23일 “계약 기간 만료로 잠실점·인천숭의점 영업을 종료하기로 했다. 두 곳은 장기적자 점포여서 영업종료에 따른 현금흐름과 사업성 개선을 기대하고 있다”고 말했다. 구체적인 종료 일정은 결정되지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From last month until recently, Homeplus has decided to close a total of 17 stores. These include stores in Gyesan, Siheung, Ansan Gojan, Cheonan Sinbang, Dongchon, Gayang, Jangnim, Ilsan, Woncheon, Ulsan Buk-gu, Munhwa, Busan Gamman, Ulsan Nam-gu, Jeonju Wansan, Hwaseong Dongtan, Cheonan, and Jochiwon. With the inclusion of the Jamsil and Incheon Sungui stores this time, the number of stores confirmed for closure has increased to 19. (홈플러스는 지난달부터 최근까지 모두 17개 점포의 영업종료를 결정했다. 계산·시흥·안산고잔·천안신방·동촌·가양·장림·일산·원천·울산북구·문화점·부산감만점·울산남구점·전주완산점·화성동탄점·천안점·조치원점 등이다. 이번에 잠실점·인천숭의점이 포함되면서 영업종료가 확정된 점포는 모두 19곳으로 늘어났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus, which was unable to pay its employees' January salaries due to financial difficulties, stated on the 22nd that "emergency operating funds (DIP loan) are necessary for business normalization." Homeplus has requested an emergency operating funds (DIP) loan of 100 billion won each from its major shareholder MBK Partners, its largest creditor Meritz Financial Group, and the policy financial institution KDB. Currently, only MBK Partners has indicated it will respond to this request, while Meritz Securities and KDB have not stated their positions. (자금난으로 임직원의 1월 급여를 지급하지 못한 홈플러스 쪽은 “경영 정상화를 위해 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출이 필요하다”는 입장을 지난 22일 밝힌 바 있다. 홈플러스는 주주사인 엠비케이(MBK)파트너스와 최대 채권자인 메리츠금융그룹, 정책금융기관인 산업은행에 각 1천억원씩 부담하는 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출을 요청한 상태다. 현재 엠비케이파트너스만 이런 요청에 응하겠다는 뜻을 밝혔고, 메리츠증권과 산업은행은 입장을 밝히지 않고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus CEO Jo Joo-yeon appealed at an emergency forum on Homeplus held at the National Assembly on the 21st, saying, "Please allow us to operate stably until we can prevent the imminent payment default situation and the effects of the rehabilitation plan become visible," and added, "As Homeplus is in a difficult situation, we have no choice but to plead with Meritz Securities, which represents the creditors, and the policy financial institution KDB to participate (in the emergency operating funds loan), and we ask for your understanding." (조주연 홈플러스 대표는 지난 21일 국회에서 열린 홈플러스 긴급 좌담회에서 “눈앞에 닥친 지급 불능 사태를 막고 회생안 효과가 가시화될 때까지 안정적으로 운영할 수 있게 해달라”며 “어려운 상황인 홈플러스로서는 채권자들의 대표 격인 메리츠증권과 정책금융기관인 산업은행에 (긴급운영자금 대출에) 참가해 주실 것을 간청드릴 수밖에 없는 점 양해를 부탁드린다”고 호소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241343.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501764.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cyber University of Foreign Studies Holds "5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program" (사이버한국외국어대학교, “제5회 사이버한국외대-니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램” 진행)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241351.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies Holds "5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program" (사이버한국외국어대학교, “제5회 사이버한국외대-니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램” 진행)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/394/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691479093591.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;사이버한국외국어대학교 전경.사이버한국외대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies (Acting President Kim Byeong-cheol) held the '5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program' with Japan's Niigata Prefectural University on Saturday, January 17th.&lt;br/&gt;This exchange program between CUFS and Niigata Prefectural University is the fifth event in the Korea-Japan online exchange that began in 2022, operated in a format where students from both universities meet online and communicate in Korean. This program saw participation from 15 CUFS undergraduate and graduate students and 22 students majoring in Korean language in the Faculty of International and Regional Studies at Niigata Prefectural University. CUFS students completed pre-program training before participating, finishing their preparations with anticipation and excitement. During the actual program, they actively exchanged opinions on daily life, interests, careers, and more using Korean as the medium.&lt;br/&gt;CUFS participating students, who broadened their mutual understanding even through a non-face-to-face environment, unanimously shared their impressions, stating, "Despite the online setting, conversations filled with laughter and empathy continued," and "We experienced that the exchange with Niigata Prefectural University students was built on focus and sincerity towards each other, more than physical distance." Niigata Prefectural University also highly praised the educational outcomes of the exchange program. Professor Kim Sae-rang of Niigata Prefectural University said, "It was a time, as a Korean language educator, that I felt great reward, confirming students actively communicating in Korean without fear of 'making mistakes' and building confidence in language learning."&lt;br/&gt;Regarding this, Professor Park Ki-seon of the CUFS Korean Language Department, who conducted the program, added, "It became an opportunity for students learning Korean and prospective teachers wanting to teach Korean to communicate freely, understand each other's cultures, and advance towards their respective goals," and "I hope the cooperation between the two universities continues to expand such exchange programs." CUFS plans to continue striving for the international spread of Korean language education and providing learner-centered, practical educational experiences through various exchange programs with overseas universities.&lt;br/&gt;The CUFS Korean Language Department aims to be a 'Hub for Global Korean Language Education,' cultivating Korean language and Korean culture professionals equipped with both theory and practice. Based on differentiated Korean language education know-how, it operates a 'Korean Language Education' major for training Korean language teachers who teach Korean as a foreign language and Korean culture, and a 'Korean Language' major where foreign learners can systematically learn Korean language and Korean culture.&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, Cyber University of Foreign Studies is recruiting new and transfer students for the first semester of the 2026 academic year from Wednesday, January 28th to Thursday, February 12th. It selects students across 10 departments: ▲English Department ▲Chinese Department ▲Japanese Department ▲Korean Language Department ▲Spanish Department ▲Vietnamese &amp; Indonesian Department ▲Business Administration Department ▲Industrial Safety &amp; Housing Management Department ▲Counseling Psychology Department ▲K-Beauty Department. Anyone with a high school diploma or higher qualification can apply. Detailed information can be found on the university's Admissions Support Center website (go.cufs.ac.kr), and individual admissions counseling is also available via phone (02-2173-2580), KakaoTalk (cufs), or email (ipsi@cufs.ac.kr). (사이버한국외국어대학교(총장직무대행 김병철)는 1월 17일(토) 일본 니가타현립대학과 함께 ‘제5회 사이버한국외대–니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램’을 진행했다.&lt;br/&gt;사이버한국외국어대학교와 니가타현립대학의 교류 프로그램은 2022년 시작된 한‧일 온라인 교류의 다섯 번째 행사로, 양교 학생들이 온라인으로 만나 한국어로 소통하는 방식으로 운영됐다. 이번 프로그램에는 사이버한국외대 학부 및 대학원생 15명과 니가타현립대학 국제지역학부 한국어전공 재학생 22명이 참가했다. 사이버한국외대 학생들은 프로그램 참여에 앞서 사전 교육을 이수하여 기대와 설렘을 가지고 교류 준비를 마쳤으며, 실제 프로그램에서는 한국어를 매개로 일상과 관심사, 진로 등에 대해 활발한 의견을 나눴다. &lt;br/&gt;비대면 환경을 통해서도 상호에 대한 이해를 넓혔다는 사이버한국외대의 참가 학생들은 “온라인이라는 환경에도 불구하고 웃음과 공감이 오가는 대화가 이어졌다”며 “니가타현립대학 학생들과의 교류는 물리적 거리보다 서로를 향한 집중과 진심으로 이어진다는 것을 경험할 수 있었다”고 입을 모아 소감을 전했다. 니가타현립대학 측에서도 교류 프로그램의 교육적 성과를 높이 평가했다. 니가타현립대학 김세랑 교수는 “학생들이 ‘틀림’을 두려워하지 않고 적극적으로 한국어로 소통하며 언어 학습에 대한 자신감을 키우는 모습을 확인한, 한국어 교육자로서 큰 보람을 느끼는 시간”이었다고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;이에 프로그램을 진행한 사이버한국외국어대학교 한국어학부 박기선 교수는 “한국어를 배우는 학생들과, 한국어를 가르치고자 하는 예비 교원들이 자유롭게 소통하며 서로의 문화를 이해하고 각자의 목표를 향해 나아가는 계기가 됐다”며 “이러한 교류 프로그램의 확대를 위해 양교의 협력이 지속되기를 바란다”고 덧붙였다. 사이버한국외대는 앞으로도 해외 대학과의 다양한 교류 프로그램을 통해 한국어 교육의 국제적 확산과 학습자 중심의 실질적인 교육 경험 제공에 힘쓸 계획이다.&lt;br/&gt;사이버한국외대 한국어학부는 ‘세계 한국어교육의 허브’를 목표로 이론과 실제를 겸비한 한국어와 한국 문화 전문 인력을 양성하고 있다. 차별화된 한국어교육 노하우를 바탕으로 외국어로서의 한국어와 한국 문화를 가르치는 한국어 교원을 양성하는 ‘한국어교육’ 전공과, 외국인 학습자가 체계적으로 한국어와 한국 문화를 배울 수 있는 ‘한국어’ 전공을 운영한다.&lt;br/&gt;한편 사이버한국외국어대학교는 1월 28일(수)부터 2월 12일(목)까지 2026학년도 1학기 신·편입생을 모집한다. ▲영어학부 ▲중국어학부 ▲일본어학부 ▲한국어학부 ▲스페인어학부 ▲베트남·인도네시아학부 ▲경영학부 ▲산업안전·주택관리학부 ▲상담심리학부 ▲K뷰티학부 등 10개 학부에서 학생을 선발하며, 고등학교 졸업 이상 학력의 소유자라면 누구나 지원할 수 있다. 자세한 내용은 대학 입학지원센터(go.cufs.ac.kr)에서 확인하면 되며, 전화(02-2173-2580)나 카카오톡(cufs), 이메일(ipsi@cufs.ac.kr)을 통해 개별 입학 상담도 가능하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Cyber University of Foreign Studies (* 자료제공 :  사이버한국외국어대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241351.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/394/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691479093591.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul National University of Science and Technology's University Job Plus Center Receives Top 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Ministry of Employment and Labor Evaluation (서울과학기술대학교 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 고용노동부 평가 최고 등급‘우수’획득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241353.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Seoul National University of Science and Technology's University Job Plus Center Receives Top 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Ministry of Employment and Labor Evaluation (서울과학기술대학교 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 고용노동부 평가 최고 등급‘우수’획득)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/311/232/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3917691482555027.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대학일자리플러스센터 홍보포스터 전경.서울과기대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;□ The University Job Plus Center at Seoul National University of Science and Technology (President Kim Dong-hwan, hereinafter referred to as SeoulTech) has received the highest grade of 'Excellent' in the 2025 University Job Plus Center project performance evaluation conducted by the Ministry of Employment and Labor and the Korea Employment Information Service. &lt;br/&gt;□ SeoulTech has been operating the University Job Plus Center project since 2021, marking its fifth year this year. It is currently running both the University Job Plus Center (hub-type) and the Customized Employment Service Project for enrolled students. Through these, it operates career counseling, employment support programs, and recruitment connection services for enrolled students, graduates, and local youth.&lt;br/&gt;□ Kim Byeong-il, Head of the SeoulTech Employment and Career Headquarters (Director of the University Job Plus Center), stated, "Starting from this achievement of the 'Excellent' grade, we will actively expand career and employment support services tailored to industrial changes and youth demands to help students fully utilize their capabilities in society." (□ 서울과학기술대학교(총장 김동환, 이하 서울과기대) 대학일자리플러스센터는 고용노동부와 한국고용정보원이 주관한 2025년 대학일자리플러스센터 사업 성과 평가에서 최고 등급인‘우수’를 획득했다. &lt;br/&gt;□ 서울과기대는 2021년부터 대학일자리플러스센터 사업을 시작해 올해로 5년째 사업을 운영중이며, 현재 대학일자리플러스센터(거점형)와 재학생 맞춤형 고용서비스 사업을 함께 수행하고 있다. 이를 통해 재학생·졸업생·지역 청년을 대상으로 진로상담, 취업지원 프로그램, 채용 연계 서비스 등을 운영하고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;□ 김병일 서울과기대 취업진로본부장(대학일자리플러스센터장)은“이번‘우수’등급 획득을 기점으로“앞으로도 산업 변화와 청년 수요에 맞춘 진로·취업지원서비스를 확대해 학생들이 자신의 역량을 사회에서 충분히 발휘할 수 있도록 적극 지원하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul National University of Science and Technology (* 자료제공 :  서울과학기술대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241353.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/311/232/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3917691482555027.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul Women's University Holds AX Vision Declaration Ceremony, Aiming to Become a "University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People" (서울여대, “사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학으로…” AX 비전 선포식 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241354.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Seoul Women's University Holds AX Vision Declaration Ceremony, Aiming to Become a "University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People" (서울여대, “사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학으로…” AX 비전 선포식 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8417691486855201.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울여대 AX 비전 선포 퍼모먼스 참여자(왼쪽부터) 서울여대 김경원 대학원장, 염지원 총학생회 비상대책위원장, 이윤선 총장, 학교법인 정의학원 김경진 이사장, 이귀운 총동문회장, 박남춘 기획처장, 조현미 노동조합 지부장).서울여대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seoul Women's University (President Lee Yun-sun) has declared its 'AX (AI Transformation) Vision,' redefining the university's fundamental role and educational values in the face of the AI era, and has embarked on full-fledged steps to leap forward as a center for future education.&lt;br/&gt;On Thursday, January 22nd, at 1:30 PM, Seoul Women's University held the 'Seoul Women's University AX Vision Declaration Ceremony' at the International Conference Hall of the 50th Anniversary Memorial Building, with about 200 attendees including key guests, faculty, and students filling the venue. This event was prepared to publicly announce Seoul Women's University's unique AX educational vision, which proactively responds to the innovation and changes created by the AI era to enhance educational quality and strengthen unwavering human dignity even in the technological age.&lt;br/&gt;■ 'A University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People'... Embodying a Human-Centered Technology Philosophy&lt;br/&gt;On this day, Seoul Women's University announced its AX vision with the slogans 'AI to Learn, Human to Share (AI that aids human growth, Humans that connect communities)' and 'A University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People,' containing the aspirations of a new AX-leading university.&lt;br/&gt;President Lee Yun-sun, who presented the vision declaration, stated, 'The faster technology develops, the more universities must question whether the direction of development is correct,' emphasizing that in the AI era, Seoul Women's University's language is about speaking of people, direction, and responsibility amidst an age of speed and efficiency. Introducing the university's educational philosophy that has always placed the value of 'us' at the center as much as the value of 'me,' she declared, "Based on the philosophy that AI is not a tool to replace humans but a technology to aid human growth, and that humans are not beings who possess that growth alone but beings who share it with the community, we will establish education for the AI era."&lt;br/&gt;The AX vision presented by Seoul Women's University is planned to operate centered on seven major principles: ▲Human Values First ▲Social Innovation Orientation ▲Participation and Experience Focus ▲Convergence and Collaborative Education ▲Strengthening Women's Leadership and Inclusivity ▲Research•Education•Administration Linkage ▲AI Education Based on Global Cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;■ 'AI to Learn, Human to Share' Specific AX Promotion Strategy and University Innovation Roadmap Revealed&lt;br/&gt;Following this, Planning Director Park Nam-chun announced the specific 'AX Promotion Strategy.' Seoul Women's University announced its specific strategies and roadmap, including: advancing a data-based personalized learning support system; establishing a President-direct AX control tower; innovating the academic structure to lead AI convergence education; data-centric intelligent administrative innovation; building an AI convergence curriculum and hyper-connected liberal arts convergence AX system that transcends major boundaries; establishing a Future Advanced Research Institute for human-centered AI education; and AX education for instructors. Director Park expressed the aspiration, "Seoul Women's University will carry out innovation across all areas, from internal administrative systems to teaching methods, to set a new standard for universities in the AI era."&lt;br/&gt;■ Keynote Speech by President Yum Jae-ho of Taejae University ... "A University Where Humans and AI Coexist, the Power to Question is Key"&lt;br/&gt;In the second part of the event, a conference sharing insights from AI and education experts continued. President Yum Jae-ho of Taejae University gave a keynote speech on the theme.&lt;br/&gt;President Yum stated, "In an era where AI takes over the role of delivering knowledge, universities must become spaces that cultivate students' 'ability to question' and 'the work of joyfully mastering skills,'" and evaluated that the human-centered AX vision declared by Seoul Women's University will be an important answer for the future university model.&lt;br/&gt;■ In-Depth Discussion with AI Experts from Academia and Industry&lt;br/&gt;In the roundtable that proceeded as the final session, moderated by Seoul Women's University's Industry-Academic Research Director Han Won-sik, participants including Professor Hong Helen of the Software Convergence Department, Director Kim Myung-joo of the AI Safety Research Institute (Professor, School of Intelligent Information Security), and Director Kim Ji-seop of Lutein Technologies exchanged opinions on strategies for how the AX vision presented by Seoul Women's University can be implemented in actual education and research fields, and on the values universities must uphold amidst rapid technological advancement. Director Kim Myung-joo noted, "Coincidentally, it is the first day the 'Framework Act on Artificial Intelligence' takes effect in Korea, the world's first, making it even more meaningful to discuss human-centered AX. While AX is an inevitable global trend, it has a dual nature. Therefore, at universities nurturing the next generation of talent, efforts to actively respond to the shadowy side of AX and cultivate it into human-centered, sustainable technology are absolutely necessary," urging Seoul Women's University's leading role.&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the event featured congratulatory speeches from Chairman Kim Kyung-jin of the Jeongui Academy School Foundation, National Assembly Speaker Woo Won-shik, Nowon District Mayor Oh Seung-rok, Seoul Metropolitan Council Members Oh Geum-ran and Seo Jun-oh, CEO Lee Yong-kwan of Bluepoint, and President Yoon Do-young of Kwangwoon University. A large number of local university presidents, government and political figures, and industry and academia representatives attended to celebrate Seoul Women's University's new vision. Starting from this vision declaration, Seoul Women's University plans to play a pivotal role in presenting the direction for a human-centered AI era and continue the university's growth. (서울여자대학교(총장 이윤선)가 AI 시대를 직면한 대학의 근본적인 역할과 교육 가치를 재정의하는 ‘AX(AI Transformation) 비전’을 선포하고, 미래 교육의 중심지로 도약하기 위한 본격적인 행보에 나섰다.&lt;br/&gt;서울여자대학교는 1월 22일(목) 오후 1시 30분, 서울여대 50주년 기념관 국제회의실에서 주요 내외빈과 교직원, 학생 등 200여 명이 자리를 가득 메운 가운데 ‘서울여자대학교 AX 비전 선포식’을 개최했다. 이 행사는 AI 시대가 만들어내는 혁신과 변화에 능동적으로 대응해 교육의 질을 높이고, 기술 시대에도 흔들리지 않는 인간 존엄성을 강화하는 서울여대만의 독창적인 AX 교육 비전을 대내외에 공포하기 위해 마련되었다.&lt;br/&gt;■ ‘사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학’... 인간 중심의 기술 철학 담아&lt;br/&gt;서울여대는 이날 새로운 AX 선도대학의 포부를 담은 슬로건으로 ‘AI to Learn, Human to Share(인간의 성장을 돕는 AI, 공동체를 잇는 인간)’, 그리고 ‘사람을 향한 기술로 사회혁신을 이끄는 대학’을 AX 비전으로 발표했다.&lt;br/&gt;비전 선포 발표자로 나선 이윤선 총장은 ‘기술의 발전 속도가 빠를수록, 대학은 발전의 방향이 맞는지 질문해야 한다’고 말하며, AI 시대에 서울여대의 언어는 속도와 효율의 시대 한가운데서 다시 사람과 방향, 그리고 책임을 말하는 것이라고 강조했다. 또한 ‘나’의 가치만큼 ‘우리’의 가치를 중심에 두어 온 서울여대의 교육 철학을 소개하면서 “AI는 인간을 대체하기 위한 도구가 아니라 인간의 성장을 돕기 위한 기술이고, 인간은 그 성장을 혼자 소유하는 존재가 아니라 공동체와 나누는 존재여야한다는 철학을 기반에 두고 AI 시대의 교육을 세우겠다”고 선언했다.&lt;br/&gt;서울여대가 제시한 AX 비전은 ▲인간 가치 우선 ▲사회 혁신 지향 ▲참여와 경험 중심 ▲융합과 협력 교육 ▲여성 리더십과 포용성 강화 ▲연구•교육•행정 연동 ▲글로벌 협력 기반의 AI교육 7대 원칙을 중심으로 운영될 예정이다.&lt;br/&gt;■ ‘AI to Learn, Human to Share’ 구체적인 AX 추진 전략 및 대학 혁신 로드맵 공개&lt;br/&gt;이어 박남춘 기획처장은 구체적인 ‘AX 추진 전략’을 발표했다. 서울여대는 데이터 기반의 개인화된 학습 지원 시스템을 고도화하고, 총장 직속 AX 컨트롤 타워 설치, AI 융합교육을 선도하는 학사구조로의 혁신, 데이터 중심의 지능형 행정 혁신, 전공의 경계를 넘나드는 AI 융합 커리큘럼과 초연결형 교양 융합 AX 체계 구축, 인간 중심 AI 교육을 위한 미래첨단연구원 설립, 교수자를 위한 AX 교육 등 서울여자대학교의 구체적인 전략과 로드맵을 발표했다. 박 처장은 “서울여대는 학내 행정 시스템부터 교수법까지 전 영역에 걸쳐 혁신을 단행해 AI 시대 대학의 새로운 표준을 만들겠다”는 포부를 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;■ 염재호 태재대 총장 기조 강연 ... “인간과 AI가 공존하는 대학, 질문하는 힘이 핵심”&lt;br/&gt;행사 2부에서는 AI와 교육 전문가들의 통찰을 공유하는 컨퍼런스가 이어졌다. 기조 강연 자로 나선 태재대학교 염재호 총장은 를 주제로 발표를 진행했다.&lt;br/&gt;염 총장은 “AI가 지식을 전달하는 역할을 대신하게 되는 시대에 대학은 학생들에게 ‘질문하는 능력’과 ‘즐겁게 숙련하는 일’을 길러주는 공간이 되어야 한다”며, 서울여대가 선포한 인간 중심의 AX 비전이 미래 대학 모델의 중요한 해답이 될 것이라고 평가했다.&lt;br/&gt;■ 학계와 산업계 AI 전문가들과의 깊이 있는 토론&lt;br/&gt;마지막 순서로 진행된 라운드테이블에서는 서울여대 한원식 산학연구처장의 진행 아래 홍헬렌 소프트웨어융합학과 교수, 김명주 AI안전연구소장(지능정보보호학부 교수), 김지섭 뤼튼테크놀로지스 이사 등이 참여해 서울여대가 제시한 AX 비전이 실제 교육과 연구 현장에서 어떻게 구현될 수 있는지에 대한 전략과, 급격한 기술 발전 속에서 대학이 지켜야 할 가치가 무엇인지에 대해 의견을 교환했다. 김명주 소장은 “마침 한국에서 ‘인공지능기본법’이 세계 최초로 시행되는 첫날, 인간 중심의 AX를 논할 수 있어 더욱 뜻깊다. AX는 피할 수 없는 세계의 흐름이지만, 양면성이 있으므로, 다음 세대 인재를 기르는 대학에서 AX의 그늘진 면에 적극적으로 대응하며 인간중심의 지속 가능한 기술로 가꿔가는 노력이 반드시 필요하다” 라며 서울여대의 선도적인 역할을 당부했다.&lt;br/&gt;한편, 이날 행사에는 김경진 학교법인 정의학원 이사장을 비롯해 우원식 국회의장과 오승록 노원구청장, 오금란·서준오 서울시의원, 이용관 블루포인트 대표, 윤도영 광운대학교 총장이 축사를 전하고, 지역 대학 총장과 정·관계, 산업계·학계 관계자들이 대거 참석해 서울여자대학교의 새로운 비전을 축하했다. 서울여대는 이번 비전 선포를 기점으로, 인간 중심의 AI 시대의 방향을 제시하는 중추적인 역할을 수행하며 대학의 성장을 이어갈 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul Women's University (* 자료제공 :  서울여자대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241354.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8417691486855201.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hanyang University Launches Physician-Scientist Training Unit... Cultivating Full-Cycle Convergence-Type Talents (한양대, 의사과학자 양성사업단 발족…전주기적 융합형 인재 양성)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241359.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hanyang University Launches Physician-Scientist Training Unit... Cultivating Full-Cycle Convergence-Type Talents (한양대, 의사과학자 양성사업단 발족…전주기적 융합형 인재 양성)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0123/2917691491616775.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;[한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단 설립기념 사진]제1의학관 3층 의과대학 행정팀 내 사업단 현판 앞에서 설립 기념 촬영을 진행했다. 사진 왼쪽부터 의과대학 한호철 차장, 엄유진 교수, 박훈기 학장, 김영서 사업단장, 김인아 의예과장, 이제연 교수.한양대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanyang University College of Medicine announced that, having been selected for the Ministry of Health and Welfare's 'Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Project' in the latter half of 2025, it has established the Hanyang University Physician-Scientist Training Unit under the Future Talent Development Group and is formally embarking on cultivating full-cycle convergence-type physician-scientists. Professor Kim Young-seo from the Department of Neurology at the College of Medicine will serve as the inaugural unit director.&lt;br/&gt;The newly launched unit aims to systematically cultivate medical students into physician-scientists. It plans to nurture talents who will lead in the fields of convergence medicine and biomedical sciences through education and research that integrate medicine, engineering, and natural sciences. In particular, it plans to jointly provide convergence medicine education to students from the College of Engineering and Interdisciplinary Programs, allowing students early exposure to collaborative medical research environments.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, it will operate a convergence-type physician-scientist graduate program for various clinical specialty graduate students even after graduation from medical school. Moving away from the existing consortium format, it will be operated solely by Hanyang University starting in 2026. The plan is to actively support research capacity enhancement by providing participating graduate students with research funds of 20 million won per person.&lt;br/&gt;Hanyang University is currently operating various educational and practical programs for physician-scientist training throughout the entire medical education cycle. Medical students complete required courses related to convergence medicine such as data science, biomedical engineering, and life sciences, and can also electively take convergence medicine-related courses offered by the College of Engineering and Interdisciplinary Programs. Alongside this, the curriculum will be continuously expanded through various programs such as Medical Science Camps, Basic Medicine Practice Camps, and dispatch to overseas basic medicine education programs.&lt;br/&gt;Unit Director Kim Young-seo stated, "The cultivation of physician-scientists perfectly aligns with Hanyang University's founding philosophy of 'Love in Deed and Truth' and the educational purpose of the College of Medicine, which is to cultivate professional medical personnel who, while actively pursuing self-development, utilize creative research to apply specialized medical knowledge practically and practice love for the local community, the nation, and ultimately, human society." He added, "This opening ceremony is an important first step in establishing a physician-scientist training ecosystem, and we expect talents who will play a leading role in the development of the national biomedical field to be cultivated going forward."&lt;br/&gt;Park Hun-ki, Dean of Hanyang University College of Medicine, said, "We expect the excellent professors from Hanyang University's basic and clinical medicine departments to act as capable mentors through their high interest and affection for students." He added, "We will actively support students so they can be nurtured into physician-scientists who can lead the future by strengthening programs to allow for more convergence medicine education choices in line with the 6-year curriculum reform."&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the Hanyang University Physician-Scientist Training Unit, with support from the Ministry of Health and Welfare, plans to operate the following programs: ▲Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Undergraduate Program (Responsible: Prof. Kim Young-seo, Dept. of Neurology, College of Medicine) ▲Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Graduate Program (Responsible: Prof. Kim Bong-young, Dept. of Infectious Diseases, College of Medicine) ▲Postdoctoral Research Growth Support Program (Responsible: Prof. Sung Yoon-kyung, Dept. of Rheumatology, College of Medicine). An operating committee, with participation from the College of Medicine, College of Engineering, Interdisciplinary Programs, and Hanyang University Medical Center, will promote educational programs, academic camps, and research achievement exchanges. Furthermore, plans are in place to continuously expand the educational foundation through future collaboration with global medical schools. (한양대학교 의과대학은 2025년 하반기 보건복지부 ‘융합형 의사과학자 양성 사업’에 선정됨에 따라 미래인재양성단 산하에 한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단을 설립하고, 전주기적 융합형 의사과학자 양성에 본격적으로 나선다고 밝혔다. 초대 사업단장은 의과대학 신경과 김영서 교수가 맡았다.&lt;br/&gt;이번에 발족한 사업단은 의과대학 학생을 의사과학자(Physician-Scientist)로 체계적으로 육성하는 것을 목표로, 의학과 공학, 자연과학을 융합한 교육과 연구를 통해 융합의학 및 의생명과학 분야를 선도할 인재를 양성할 계획이다. 특히 공과대학과 인터칼리지 학생들에게도 융합의학 교육을 공동으로 제공해, 학생들이 조기에 의학 협동연구 환경에 노출될 수 있도록 할 예정이다.&lt;br/&gt;또한 의과대학 졸업 이후에도 다양한 임상 전공의 대학원생을 대상으로 한 융합형 의사과학자 대학원 과정을 운영한다. 기존 컨소시엄 형태에서 벗어나 2026년부터는 한양대학교 단독으로 운영하며, 참여 대학원생에게는 개인당 2천만 원 규모의 연구비를 지원해 연구 역량 강화를 적극적으로 뒷받침할 계획이다.&lt;br/&gt;한양대학교는 현재 의학교육 전주기에 걸쳐 의사과학자 양성을 위한 다양한 교육과 실습을 운영하고 있다. 의과대학 학생들은 데이터사이언스, 의공학, 생명과학 등 융합의학 관련 필수과목을 이수하며, 공과대학과 인터칼리지에서 개설된 융합의학 관련 교과목도 선택 수강할 수 있다. 이와 함께 메디컬 사이언스 캠프, 기초의학 실습 캠프, 해외 기초의학 교육과정 파견 등 다양한 프로그램을 통해 교육과정을 지속적으로 확대해 나갈 예정이다. &lt;br/&gt;김영서 사업단장은 “의사과학자 양성은 사랑의 실천이라는 한양대학교의 건학이념과 능동적으로 자개개발을 추구하면서 창의적인 연구로 의학전문지식을 실용화하고 지역사회와 국가, 나아가 인류사회에 사랑을 실천하는 전문의료인을 양성한다는 한양대학교 의과대학의 교육목적과 정확히 부합한다”며 “이번 개소식은 의사과학자 양성 생태계를 구축하기 위한 중요한 첫 출발로 앞으로 국가 바이오메디컬 분야 발전에 선도적인 역할을 할 인재들이 양성될 것으로 기대한다”고 말했다. &lt;br/&gt;박훈기 한양대학교 의과대학장은 “한양대학교의 우수한 기초의학교실과 임상의학교실 교수들이 높은 학생에 대한 관심과 사랑을 통해 유능한 멘토로 활동할 것으로 기대한다”며 “6년제 학제 개편에 보다 많은 융합의학 교육을 선택할 수 있도록 프로그램을 보강해서 학생들이 미래를 선도할 수 있는 의사과학자로 육성될 수 있도록 적극 지원하겠다” 고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;한편, 한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단은 보건복지부의 지원을 받아 ▲융합형 의사과학자 양성 학부과정(책임자: 의과대학 신경과 김영서 교수) ▲융합형 의사과학자 양성 대학원과정(책임자: 의과대학 감염내과학교실 김봉영 교수) ▲박사후 연구성장지원 과정(책임자: 의과대학 류마티스내과학교실 성윤경 교수)을 운영할 예정이다. 운영위원회는 의과대학을 비롯해 공과대학, 인터칼리지, 한양대학교 의료원이 함께 참여해 교육 프로그램과 학술 캠프, 연구성과 교류회를 추진하며, 향후 글로벌 의과대학과의 협력을 통해 교육 기반을 지속적으로 확대해 나갈 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Hanyang University (* 자료제공 :  한양대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241359.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0123/2917691491616775.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Closes in the 4990s, Fails to Settle Above '5,000-pi'... KOSDAQ Approaches 'Cheon-sdaq' (코스피, 4990대 마감 ‘오천피’ 안착 실패…코스닥은 ‘천스닥’ 눈앞)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241371.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSPI Closes in the 4990s, Fails to Settle Above '5,000-pi'... KOSDAQ Approaches 'Cheon-sdaq' (코스피, 4990대 마감 ‘오천피’ 안착 실패…코스닥은 ‘천스닥’ 눈앞)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502344.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 서울 중구 우리은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 코스피 지수 등이 표시되고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, the KOSPI recovered the 5,000-point level in early trading but reduced its gains to close in the 4990s. It failed to settle above '5,000-pi' on a closing basis for the second consecutive day. Meanwhile, the KOSDAQ index surged over 2%, closing in on 'Cheon-sdaq' (KOSDAQ 1,000). (코스피가 23일 장 초반 5000선을 회복한 뒤 오름폭을 줄여 4990대에서 장을 마쳤다. 전날에 이어 종가 기준 ‘오천피’ 안착에는 실패했다. 반면 코스닥지수는 2% 넘게 급등해 ’천스닥’(코스닥 1000)에 바짝 다가섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI closed at 4,990.07, up 37.54 points (0.76%) from the previous day. It once again set a new all-time closing high, surpassing the record set the day before. It opened at 4,984.08, up 31.55 points (0.64%), and expanded its gains to reach an intraday high of 5,021.13, setting a new all-time intraday record. However, the gains were trimmed later as profit-taking selling emerged. (  이날 코스피는 전날보다 37.54(0.76%) 오른 4990.07에 장을 마쳤다. 전날 기록한 종가 기준 최고치를 재차 경신했다. 전날보다 31.55(0.64%) 오른 4984.08로 출발해 상승폭을 키워 한 때 5021.13까지 올라 장중 기준 사상 최고치를 경신했다. 이후 차익 실현 매물이 출회되면서 상승폭은 축소됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the opening of the 'KOSPI 5,000 era', securities stocks surged sharply, with Mirae Asset Securities rising 16.58% on the day. (  ‘코스피 5000 시대’가 열리자 이날 미래에셋증권이 16.58% 오르는 등 증권주들이 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ index closed at 993.93, up 23.58 points (2.43%) from the previous day, marking its highest level in over four years since January 7, 2022 (995.16). Analysts suggest that expectations for the institutionalization of stablecoins stimulated investor sentiment in the KOSDAQ market. Kakao Pay, classified as a stablecoin-themed stock, hit the upper price limit on the day. (  코스닥지수는 전날보다 23.58(2.43%) 오른 993.93에 장을 마치며 2022년 1월 7일(995.16) 이후 4년여 만에 최고치를 기록했다. 이날 코스닥은 스테이블코인 제도화에 대한 기대감이 투자심리를 자극한 것으로 분석된다. 스테이블코인 테마주로 분류돼온 카카오페이는 이날 상한가를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Seoul foreign exchange market, the won-dollar exchange rate closed at 1,465.8 won at the end of daytime trading (3:30 PM), down 4.1 won from the previous day's closing rate. (  이날 서울 외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 주간거래 종가(오후 3시 30분) 기준으로 전날 주간거래 종가보다 4.1원 내린 1465.8원을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241371.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502344.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hyundai Motor's Labor-Management Conflict Over 'Atlas' Deployment... A Déjà Vu from 30 Years Ago (‘아틀라스’ 현장 배치 두고 현대차 노사갈등…30여년 전 데자뷔)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241381.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hyundai Motor's Labor-Management Conflict Over 'Atlas' Deployment... A Déjà Vu from 30 Years Ago (‘아틀라스’ 현장 배치 두고 현대차 노사갈등…30여년 전 데자뷔)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;현대자동차그룹의 휴머노이드 로봇 아틀라스. 현대차 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rift has erupted over Hyundai Motor Group's announcement that it will deploy the humanoid robot 'Atlas' on production lines. The Hyundai Motor labor union is pushing back, stating that "not a single robot can enter the production site without agreement," with the situation poised to escalate into a full-blown labor-management conflict. With the company's stance of reducing costs and increasing production efficiency pitted against the union's demand for job security, it's a pattern of similar debates that repeats with each technological transition. (인간형(휴머노이드) 로봇 ‘아틀라스’를 생산 현장에 투입하겠다는 현대차그룹의 발표를 두고 파열음이 터져 나오고 있다. 현대차 노조가 “합의 없이는 단 한 대의 로봇도 (생산) 현장에 들어 올 수 없다”고 반발하면서, 노사 갈등으로까지 번질 기세다. 비용 절감과 생산 효율을 높이려는 회사쪽과 고용 안정을 요구하는 노조쪽 입장이 맞서면서, 기술 혁신 과도기마다 비슷한 논쟁이 되풀이되는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Metal Workers' Union Hyundai Motor Branch stated in its newsletter on the 22nd, "The introduction of new technology (robot automation) is a one-way street without labor-management agreement," adding, "It is absolutely unacceptable, and mass production and deployment of robots into production sites is expected to cause employment shock." It further noted, "After the initial purchase cost, robots only incur maintenance fees, making them a good pretext for capitalists seeking long-term profit maximization," and concluded, "From the workers' perspective, this is not a welcome situation." (전국금속노조 현대차지부는 지난 22일 소식지를 내어 “신기술 도입(로봇 자동화)은 노사 합의 없는 일방통행”이라며 “절대 용납할 수 없고 (로봇을) 대량 양산해 생산 현장에 투입할 시 고용충격이 예상된다”고 했다. 이어 “로봇은 초기 구입비 이후 유지비만 발생하므로 장기적으로 이익 극대화를 노리는 자본가에 좋은 명분이 된다”며 “노동자 입장에선 반갑지 않은 상황”이라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The robot the union is taking issue with is Atlas. It is a humanoid robot developed by Boston Dynamics, a robotics company acquired by Hyundai Motor Group, and was first unveiled earlier this month at CES 2026, the world's largest consumer electronics and IT trade show held in Las Vegas, USA. At CES, Hyundai Motor Group announced that it would deploy Atlas starting in 2028 at its Hyundai Motor Group Metaplant America (HMGMA) in Georgia, USA, and gradually apply it to manufacturing sites. (노조 쪽이 문제 삼은 로봇은 아틀라스다. 현대차그룹이 인수한 로보틱스 기업 보스턴다이나믹스가 개발한 휴머노이드 로봇으로 이달 초 미국 라스베이거스에서 열린 세계 최대 가전·정보통신(IT) 전시회 ‘시이에스(CES) 2026’에서 처음 공개됐다. 현대차그룹은 아틀라스를 2028년부터 미국 조지아주에 있는 현대차그룹 메타플랜트 아메리카(HMGMA)에 투입하고, 제조 현장에 단계적으로 적용하겠다고 시이에스에서 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the plan is to deploy it in various parts assembly processes by 2030 and subsequently expand its application scope to more complex processes like repetitive tasks and handling heavy objects. The company explained that Atlas can learn most tasks within a day and autonomously handle a variety of high-intensity labor, from delicate work to tasks requiring lifting objects weighing up to 50 kilograms over 2 meters. Hyundai Motor Group also announced plans to establish a system capable of mass-producing 30,000 robots annually by 2028 and to mass-produce Atlas. (구체적으로 2030년까지 각종 부품 조립 공정에 배치하고 이후 반복 작업, 중량물 취급 등 더욱 복잡한 공정으로 적용 범위를 확대할 계획이다. 회사는 아틀라스가 대부분의 작업을 하루 안에 학습할 수 있고 섬세한 작업부터 최대 50킬로그램(kg)의 물건을 2미터(m)가 넘게 들어올려야 하는 작업까지 다양한 고강도 노동을 자율적으로 처리할 수 있다고 설명했다. 현대차그룹은 2028년까지 연간 3만대의 로봇을 양산할 수 있는 시스템을 구축하고, 아틀라스를 대량 생산하겠다는 계획도 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company explains this move by saying it will "make the work environment safer for employees and accelerate smart factory innovation." However, as it is a general-purpose robot developed with the goal of real-world manufacturing site application, if its use expands across the group's global production bases, there is a high possibility that humans will be replaced by robots in some processes. This is why the union has taken a firm stance, stating, "We cannot accept even a single unit without labor-management agreement." (회사 쪽은 이를 두고 “근로자의 작업환경을 더욱 안전하게 하고 스마트 팩토리 혁신을 가속화할 것”이라고 설명한다. 하지만 실제 제조 현장 적용을 목표로 개발된 범용 로봇인 만큼 그룹 글로벌 생산거점 전반으로 확대 적용될 경우 일부 공정에서 사람이 로봇으로 대체될 가능성이 크다. 노조 쪽에서 “노사 합의 없이는 단 한 대도 받아들일 수 없다”며 강경한 반대 입장을 내놓은 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is not the first conflict between a company and a union over new technology. A similar conflict arose in the early 1990s when factory automation began in earnest in Korean industrial sites. A Hankyoreh report from January 15, 1991, highlighted the 'light' and 'shadow' of factory automation. In an article titled "Worker alienation obscured by the 'light' of productivity increase - Factory automation in full swing," The Hankyoreh wrote that as the introduction of informatization and computer technology progressed rapidly, the reorganization of factory production lines accelerated. While this brought the 'light' of machines taking over 'difficult, tedious, and dirty work,' it also cast the 'shadow' of worker alienation. (신기술을 둘러싼 기업-노조 간 갈등은 이번이 처음이 아니다. 1990년대 초 한국 산업 현장에서 공장 자동화가 본격화할 때에도 비슷한 갈등 국면이 빚어졌다. 1991년 1월15일치 한겨레 보도는 공장 자동화에 따른 ‘빛’과 ‘그늘’을 짚었다. 한겨레는 “생산성 증대 ‘빛’에 가린 노동자 소외-본격화되는 공장자동화”란 제목의 기사에서 정보화·컴퓨터 기술 도입이 빠르게 진행되면서 공장의 생산라인 개편이 가속화했고 이에 따라 ‘힘들고 지루하고 더러운 작업’을 기계가 대신해주는 ‘빛’이 생겼지만, 동시에 노동자 소외라는 ‘그림자’를 드리운다고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the recurring labor-management conflicts due to technological innovation, experts have repeatedly emphasized the importance of tripartite consultation (labor, management, government). In its 2017 report 'Tasks and Response Strategies for Labor-Management Relations in the 4th Industrial Revolution,' the Korea Labor Institute stated, "Concerns and fears about jobs observed in industries like automotive are issues that require policy intervention, not a wait-and-see approach," and described that "it is important for labor and management from key industries to directly participate in and cooperate, compromise, and discuss within government or social institutions and organizations." (기술혁신에 따라 반복되는 노사 갈등과 관련해, 전문가들은 노사정 협의의 중요성을 여러 차례 강조해왔다. 한국노동연구원은 2017년 발표한 ‘4차 산업혁명의 노사관계 차원 과제와 대응전략’에서 “자동차 산업 등에서 관찰되는 일자리 우려와 공포는 관망이 아니라 정책적으로 관여해야 할 이슈”라며 “정부나 사회적 기구, 조직에 주요 산업의 노사가 직접 참여해서 협력하고 타협, 논의하는 것이 중요하다”고 서술했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Professor Lee Byung-hoon of Chung-Ang University (Department of Sociology) wrote in his 2018 paper 'The 4th Industrial Revolution and Labor-Management Relations: Focusing on Labor-Management Conflict Issues and Western Unions' Response Strategies,' "With the widespread replacement of human labor by AI and robots through digital technological innovation, referred to as the 4th Industrial Revolution, there are concerns that the future of labor will result in a very unfortunate 'dystopia.'" However, he also noted, "The ripple effects of digital technology can vary significantly depending on the strategic choices of labor and management and their mutual response processes." He added, "As shown by the cases of German unions, an approach that devises union policy formation strategies and proactively prepares for the disruptive damage caused by digital technological innovation through social dialogue among labor, management, and government to minimize labor-management conflict is desirable." (앞서 이병훈 중앙대 교수(사회학과)는 2018년 발간한 ‘4차 산업혁명과 노사관계 : 노사갈등 이슈와 서구 노조들의 대응전략을 중심으로’ 논문에서 “4차 산업혁명으로 일컬어지는 디지털 기술혁신을 통해 인공지능과 로봇 등에 의한 인력 대체가 광범위하게 전개되면서 노동의 미래는 매우 불행한 ‘디스토피아’로 귀결될 것으로 우려되고 있다”면서도 “노사의 전략적 선택과 상호 간의 대응과정을 통해 디지털 기술의 파급효과는 상당히 달라질 수 있다”고 썼다. 그러면서 “독일 노조들의 사례가 보여주듯 노조의 정책 형성 전략을 강구, 노사정 간의 사회적 대화를 통해 디지털 기술혁신으로 인한 파괴적 피해를 선제적으로 대비하고 노사갈등을 최소화하려는 접근이 바람직하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the research, when Volkswagen announced 'Strategy 2025' in 2016, with production process digitalization as a core element, labor and management concluded a 'Future Pact,' reaching an agreement to address job reductions. Key elements of the labor-management agreement included a ban on layoffs for operational reasons, utilization of part-time systems for older workers, and retraining/reassignment. (해당 연구에 따르면 폭스바겐이 2016년 생산공정 디지털화 등을 핵심 내용으로 한 ‘전략 2025’를 발표했을 때, 노사는 ‘미래 협약’을 맺고 일자리 감소에 대응하는 노사합의를 이뤄냈다. 경영상 해고 금지와 고령자 파트타임 제도 활용, 재교육·전환 배치 등이 대표적인 노사합의 내용이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement between Germany's IG Metall union and aircraft manufacturer Airbus is also noteworthy. Previously, in 2017, IG Metall and Airbus agreed to implement production tasks using a cobot (collaborative robot) method at the Hamburg site. This is not about robots replacing workers, but about introducing wearable robots so that workers and robots become 'partners,' interlinked and cooperating with each other. Furthermore, to maintain employment for surplus personnel resulting from this, an agreement was reached on reducing working hours, natural attrition, and job retraining. (독일 금속산별노조와 항공기 제조사인 에어버스의 노사 합의도 눈에 띄는 대목이다. 앞서 독일 금속산별노조는 2017년 에어버스와 함부르크 사업장에서 코봇(cobot·협동로봇) 방식으로 생산작업을 수행하는 것에 합의했다. 로봇이 작업자를 대체하는 것이 아니라, 사람이 착용할 수 있는 로봇을 도입해 노동자와 로봇이 ‘짝’이 되어 상호 연계해 협동하는 방식이다. 또한 이에 따른 잉여 인력의 고용 유지를 위해 근로 시간 단축과 자연퇴직 및 직무 재훈련에 대한 노사 합의도 이뤄냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241381.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Naver 'Strengthens C-Level' and Kakao 'Reduces Control Tower'... Why the Divergent Organizational Restructurings? (네이버 ‘C레벨 강화’·카카오 ‘컨트롤타워 축소’…엇갈린 조직개편 왜?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241384.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Naver 'Strengthens C-Level' and Kakao 'Reduces Control Tower'... Why the Divergent Organizational Restructurings? (네이버 ‘C레벨 강화’·카카오 ‘컨트롤타워 축소’…엇갈린 조직개편 왜?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/789/461/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502548.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;생성형 인공지능(AI) ‘제미나이’(Gemini)에 “네이버와 카카오의 기업 이미지(CI)를 반영해 이 기사에 어울리는 이미지를 생성해주세요”라는 지시어를 입력해 생성한 이미지.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naver and Kakao are embarking on establishing new management systems to open the door to the '20 trillion won revenue era' through organizational restructurings in opposite directions, effective December 1st. Naver is significantly strengthening its C-level (Chief-level) executive system to drive integration between businesses and enhance AI competitiveness, while Kakao is downsizing its group control tower and shifting to a management structure focused on swift decision-making and execution. (네이버와 카카오가 다음달 1일 상반된 방향의 조직개편을 통해 ‘매출 20조원 시대’ 문을 여는 새 경영 체제 구축에 나선다. 네이버는 최고경영진(C레벨) 체계를 대폭 강화해 사업 간 통합과 인공지능(AI) 경쟁력 고도화를 추진하는 반면, 카카오는 그룹 컨트롤타워를 축소하며 빠른 의사결정과 실행력 중심의 경영 구조로 전환한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kakao announced on the 23rd that it will reorganize its group control tower, the CA (Corporate Alignment) Council, from the existing structure of '4 committees, 2 heads, 1 office' to a '3 divisions, 4 managers' structure. The intent is to increase flexibility by reducing the organizational scale and slimming down the structure. (카카오는 그룹 컨트롤타워인 시에이(CA)협의체를 기존 ‘4개 위원회·2개 총괄·1개 단’ 체제에서 ‘3개 실·4개 담당’ 구조로 개편한다고 23일 밝혔다. 조직 규모를 줄여 구조를 슬림화하는 대신, 유연성을 높이겠다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This restructuring is interpreted as readjusting the role of the CA Council, which was launched to exert centralized control over affiliated companies after founder and Future Initiative Center head Kim Beom-soo became embroiled in allegations of stock price manipulation involving SM Entertainment in 2023. Having largely completed structural adjustments, such as drastically reducing the number of affiliates from 174 (as of the end of Q3 2021) to 94 (as of the end of last year), Kakao's strategy is now to increase decision-making speed and execution power to match a growth phase. Accordingly, organizations previously under the CA Council responsible for risk management—ESG (Environmental, Social, and Governance), public relations, government relations, and compliance—will be transferred to Kakao's headquarters. The CA Council will then focus on supporting the company's mid-to-long-term investment, finance, and HR strategies, centered around the newly established Group Investment Strategy Division, Group Finance Strategy Division, and Group HR Strategy Division. (이번 개편은 2023년 김범수 창업자 겸 미래이니셔티브센터장이 에스엠(SM)엔터테인먼트 주가 시세 조종 의혹에 휩싸인 뒤, 각 계열사에 대한 중앙집권적 통제를 위해 출범한 시에이협의체의 역할을 재조정하는 차원으로 해석된다. 카카오는 2021년 3분기 말 기준 174개에 달했던 계열사 수를 94개(지난해 말 기준)로 대폭 줄이는 등 구조조정 작업을 마무리한 만큼, 이제는 성장 국면에 맞춰 의사결정 속도와 실행력을 높이겠다는 전략이다. 이에 따라 기존에 시에이협의체에서 리스크 관리를 담당해 온 이에스지(ESG, 환경·사회·지배구조), 홍보, 대관, 준법경영 조직은 카카오 본사로 이관되고, 시에이협의체는 신설된 그룹투자전략실·그룹재무전략실·그룹인사전략실을 중심으로 회사의 중장기 투자·재무·인사 전략을 지원하는 데 집중한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Naver also announced a full-scale leadership reorganization on the 20th by newly appointing three C-level executives: Chief Data &amp; Content Officer (CDO), Chief Responsibility Officer (CRO), and Chief Human Resources Officer (CHRO). This expands the C-suite from the previous three-member system—CEO Choi Soo-yeon, COO Kim Beom-jun, and CFO Kim Hee-cheol—to a total of six members. This is the largest in Naver's corporate history. (앞서 네이버도 지난 20일 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자(CDO), 최고책임경영책임자(CRO), 최고인사책임자(CHRO) 등 3명의 시레벨 임원을 새로 선임하며 리더십 체계를 전면 개편했다. 이로써 기존 최수연 최고경영자(CEO), 김범준 최고운영책임자(COO), 김희철 최고재무책임자(CFO) 등 3명 체제였던 최고경영진은 모두 6명으로 늘었다. 이는 네이버 창사 이래 최대 규모다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naver's strategy is to establish focal points for each major area to maximize integrated synergy as the company's scale and business domains rapidly expand. In particular, the Chief Data &amp; Content Officer will be responsible for integrating user data and content accumulated across Naver to implement 'AI assistants' (AI agents) across all services. Consequently, some organizations within the existing CEO's direct 'specialized units' related to search and user-generated content (UGC) will be incorporated under the Chief Data &amp; Content Officer. The Chief Responsibility Officer will oversee policy and risk management amidst rapidly changing external environments, and the Chief Human Resources Officer will lead mid-to-long-term HR strategies for domestic and international business expansion and strengthen organizational competitiveness in the AI era. A Naver official explained, "As the organizational scale grows and the pace of technological change accelerates, the need to concentrate the company's capabilities through focal points for each major area has increased." (네이버는 회사 규모와 사업 영역이 빠르게 확장되는 상황에서, 부문별 구심점을 세워 통합 시너지를 극대화하겠다는 전략이다. 특히 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자는 네이버 전반에 축적된 사용자 데이터와 콘텐츠를 융합해 전 서비스에 ‘인공지능 비서’(AI 에이전트)를 구현하는 역할을 맡는다. 이에 따라 기존 최고경영자 직속 ‘전문조직’ 가운데 검색, 사용자 제작 콘텐츠(UGC) 관련 일부 조직은 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자 산하로 편입된다. 최고책임경영책임자는 급변하는 대외 환경 변화 속 정책·리스크 관리를 총괄하고, 최고인사책임자는 국내외 사업 확장에 따른 중장기 인사 전략과 인공지능 시대의 조직 경쟁력 강화를 주도한다. 네이버 관계자는 “조직 규모가 커지고 기술 변화 속도가 빨라지면서 부문별 구심점을 통해 회사 역량을 집중할 필요성이 커졌다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An industry insider said, "While Naver is strengthening its C-suite following the return of Chairman Lee Hae-jin to the board, amid an aggressive business expansion process including M&amp;A, Kakao is promoting an organizational restructuring towards an execution-centric system as it needs to secure new growth engines after concluding over two years of legal risks and management renewal efforts." (업계 한 관계자는 “네이버는 이해진 이사회 의장 복귀 뒤 공격적인 인수·합병(M&amp;amp;A) 등 사업 확장 과정에서 최고경영진 강화하는 반면, 카카오는 2년 넘게 이어진 사법 리스크와 경영 쇄신 작업을 끝내고 새 성장 동력을 확보해야 하는 만큼 실행 중심 체제로 조직 개편을 추진하는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, according to consensus (market forecasts) from financial information provider FnGuide on this day, Kakao is estimated to have recorded revenues of 8.0875 trillion won last year, and Naver 12.1022 trillion won, with the combined annual revenue of the two companies expected to surpass 20 trillion won for the first time ever. (한편, 이날 금융정보업체 에프엔가이드의 컨센서스(시장 전망치)에 따르면, 카카오는 지난해 매출 8조875억원, 네이버는 12조1022억원을 기록할 것으로 추정돼 두 회사 연간 매출 합계가 사상 첫 20조원을 돌파할 것으로 전망된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Sun Dam &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (선담은 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241384.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/789/461/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502548.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI 5000 Era... "If Capital Market Reform Slows, Could Fall Back to 3500" (코스피 5000 시대…“자본시장 개혁 늦추면 3500으로 회귀할 수도”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241401.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSPI 5000 Era... "If Capital Market Reform Slows, Could Fall Back to 3500" (코스피 5000 시대…“자본시장 개혁 늦추면 3500으로 회귀할 수도”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502665.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한국기업거버넌스포럼이 23일 서울 종로구 프레스센터에서 개최한 ‘코스피 5000시대 지속가능한 코리아 프리미엄을 위한 긴급 좌담회’에서 참석자들이 토론을 하고 있다.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI temporarily broke above the 5000 mark on the 22nd, a point was raised that to prevent the Korean stock market from falling back to 3500 and to continue its rise towards 7000, the pace of capital market reform must not be slowed. (코스피가 지난 22일 장중 한때 5000선을 돌파한 가운데 한국 증시가 3500으로 다시 떨어지지 않고 7000을 향해 계속 상승하려면 자본시장 개혁의 고삐를 늦춰서는 안된다는 지적이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the 'Emergency Symposium for a Sustainable Korea Premium in the KOSPI 5000 Era' held by the Korea Corporate Governance Forum on the 23rd at the Korea Press Center in Jongno-gu, Seoul, Forum Chairman Lee Nam-woo stated in his presentation, "The KOSPI breaking 5000 is due to expectations for corporate governance improvement following the 1st and 2nd revisions of the Commercial Act, and strong performance by semiconductor and automobile companies." He added, "However, semiconductor companies' operating profits cannot remain strong forever. Considering that stock prices typically peak 6-12 months ahead of corporate earnings, there is a high risk of stock prices falling around the end of this year or early next year." He emphasized, "The KOSPI is currently at a crossroads, either falling back to 3500 or rising further to 7000. To increase the downside rigidity of stock prices, we must not slow down but must continue capital market reform." (한국기업거버넌스포럼이 23일 서울 종로구 한국프레스센터에서 개최한 ‘코스피 5000시대 지속가능한 코리아 프리미엄을 위한 긴급 좌담회’에서 이남우 포럼 회장은 발제를 통해 “코스피 5000 돌파는 1·2차 상법 개정에 따른 기업지배구조 개선에 대한 기대감과, 반도체·자동차 기업들의 실적 호조 때문”이라며 “하지만 반도체 기업의 영업이익이 계속 좋을 수는 없고, 통상 주가의 고점이 기업 이익보다 6~12개월 앞서 반영되는 선행성을 감안하면, 올해 말이나 내년초에는 주가가 하락할 리스크가 높다”고 진단했다. 그는 “코스피는 현재 3500으로 다시 떨어지거나 7000까지 더욱 상승하는 갈림길에 있다”며 “주가의 하방 경직성을 높이려면 자본시장 개혁의 고삐를 늦춰서는 안되고 지속해야 한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Lee Nam-woo pointed out, "Last April, we proposed seven capital market reform tasks to the new government. Over the past eight months, the ruling party and government have implemented the introduction of directors' duty of loyalty to shareholders, the introduction of separate taxation for dividend income and tax rate reduction, and the mandatory cumulative voting system. However, the introduction of a discovery system (evidence disclosure system) to activate relief for minority shareholders, mandatory share buybacks, the principle of prohibiting subsidiary listings and protecting parent company shareholders in exceptional cases, fair value assessment during mergers between listed affiliates, and the mandatory announcement and implementation of value-up plans for all listed companies have not yet been achieved." He emphasized, "While the ruling party is pushing for mandatory share buybacks through the 3rd Commercial Act revision, recognizing two exceptions—management purposes like new technology introduction and financial structure improvement, and free contributions to employee stock ownership associations—raises significant concerns about potential abuse by companies." He also stressed, "A 'stock price suppression prevention law' is also needed to prevent owner-managers from artificially keeping stock prices low to reduce inheritance taxes." (이남우 회장은 “지난해 4월 새정부에 7가지의 자본시장 개혁과제를 제언했는데, 정부여당이 지난 8개월 동안 이사의 주주 충실 의무 도입, 배당소득 분리과세 도입과 세율인하, 집중투표제 의무화를 시행했지만, 아직 (소액주주 피해구제 활성화를 위한) 디스커버리제도(증거개시제도) 도입, 자사주 소각 의무화, 자회사 상장의 원칙 금지와 예외시 모회사 주주 보호, 상장 계열사 간 합병 때 공정가치로 평가, 모든 상장사에 밸류업계획 발표 및 실천 의무화는 아직 이뤄지지 않았다”고 지적했다. 그는 “(정부여당이 3차 상법 개정으로) 자사주 소각 의무화를 추진하면서 신기술 도입과 재무구조의 개선 등 경영상 목적과, 우리사주조합 등에 무상출연 등 2가지를 예외로 인정하려는 것은 기업들이 악용할 우려가 크다”며 “(오너 경영진이) 상속세를 낮추기 위해 주가를 인위적으로 낮게 유지하는 것을 방지하는 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’도 필요하다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding exchange rate defense measures, Chairman Lee Nam-woo said, "The exchange rate is a relative price and has a large psychological component. International investors have a very high wall of distrust, feeling they have been deceived by the Korean government and companies over the past 30 years. To overcome this, we need a direct approach: strongly and persistently continuing capital market and corporate governance reforms to firmly establish the perception that Korea is an advanced country that protects investors." He added, "Once this perception takes root, domestic investors will also increase their investment in the Korean stock market instead of the U.S. market." (이남우 회장은 환율 방어 대책과 관련 “환율은 상대가격이고 심리적 요소가 크다”며 “국제 투자자들은 지난 30년간 한국 정부 및 기업에 속아왔다는 불신의 벽이 매우 높은데, 이를 극복하려면 자본시장과 기업지배구조 개혁을 강력히 지속해서 한국이 투자자 보호가 되는 선진국가라는 인식을 확실히 심어주는 정공법이 필요하다”고 말했다. 그는 “이런 인식이 자리잡으면 국내 투자자도 미국 증시 대신 한국 증시에 투자를 늘릴 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on the 22nd, the ruling party and members of the Democratic Party of Korea's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee met with President Lee Jae-myung at the Presidential Office. They agreed not to be satisfied with achieving KOSPI 5000 and to continue reform efforts, including the 3rd Commercial Act revision for mandatory share buybacks. (한편 정부여당은 지난 22일 이재명 대통령과 더불어민주당의 코스피5000 특별위원회 소속 의원들이 청와대에서 만나 코스피 5000 달성에 만족하지 않고, 자사주 소각 의무화를 위한 3차 상법개정 등 개혁 노력을 지속하기로 뜻을 같이했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the symposium, Oh Ki-hyung, Chairman of the Democratic Party's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee, gave a congratulatory speech. The discussion was joined by Choi Jun-cheol, CEO of VIP Asset Management; Chun Jun-beom, Attorney at Law, CEO of Wiseforest; Lee Chang-hwan, CEO of Align Partners; Shim Hye-seop, Attorney at Law; and Kim Hyung-kyun, Head of Department at Cha Partners Asset Management. (이날 좌담회에서는 오기형 더불어민주당 코스피5000 특별위원장이 축사를 하고, 토론에 최준철 브이아이피(VIP)자산운용 대표, 천준범 와이즈포레스트 대표 변호사, 이창환 얼라인파트너스 대표, 심혜섭 변호사, 김형균 차파트너스자산운용 본부장이 참여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article and photos · Senior Reporter Kwak Jeong-su, Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (글·사진 ·곽정수 한겨레경제사회연구원 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241401.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502665.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Korean Air passenger plane malfunctions after landing at Jeju Airport...runway closed for 20 minutes (대한항공 여객기, 제주공항 착륙 후 고장…활주로 20분간 폐쇄)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241404.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Korean Air passenger plane malfunctions after landing at Jeju Airport...runway closed for 20 minutes (대한항공 여객기, 제주공항 착륙 후 고장…활주로 20분간 폐쇄)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/860/516/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502686.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대한항공 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operations at Jeju International Airport's runway were suspended for about 20 minutes due to a malfunction on a Korean Air passenger plane. (대한항공 여객기 고장으로 제주국제공항 활주로 운영이 약 20분간 중단되는 일이 발생했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Korean Air stated on the 23rd, "Flight KE1105, which departed from Gimpo International Airport at 12:40 PM and arrived at Jeju Airport at 1:55 PM today, experienced a hydraulic system abnormality during the landing preparation phase and occupied the runway for approximately 20 minutes." (대한항공은 23일 “이날 오후 12시40분 김포국제공항에서 출발해 오후 1시55분 제주공항에 도착하는 KE1105편 여객기가 착륙 준비 단계에서 유압계통 이상이 생겨 약 20분간 활주로를 점유했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The passenger plane landed normally on the Jeju Airport runway. However, it came to a stop on the 'taxiway'—the area for moving from the runway to the apron—after a hydraulic system warning light illuminated, rendering it unable to move under its own power. As the plane was towed away by a towing tractor (tow car), runway operations were suspended from 2:00 PM to 2:20 PM, a period of 20 minutes. (여객기는 제주공항 활주로에 정상적으로 착륙했지만, 유압계통에 이상 메시지가 점등되면서 활주로에서 계류장으로 이동하는 공간인 ‘유도로’에 멈춰 섰다. 자력으로 이동하지 못하는 여객기를 견인차량인 토잉 트랙터(토잉카)로 끌어 이동시키면서 활주로 운영이 이날 오후 2시부터 2시20분까지 20분간 중단됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 278 passengers on the affected flight disembarked safely. However, the temporary suspension of runway use caused subsequent delays for aircraft using Jeju Airport. A Korean Air official said, "The aircraft in question is currently under inspection." (사고 여객기에 탑승한 승객 278명은 안전하게 내렸으나, 활주로 사용이 일시적으로 중단되면서 제주공항을 이용하는 항공기들이 잇따라 지연됐다. 대한항공 관계자는 “해당 여객기는 현재 점검 중”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241404.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/860/516/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502686.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon, when asked "Are you willing to give up the apartment acquired through fraudulent subscription?" replies "Yes" "Yes" "Yes" (이혜훈, “부정청약 아파트 포기할 뜻 있나” 묻자 “네” “네” “네”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241412.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, when asked "Are you willing to give up the apartment acquired through fraudulent subscription?" replies "Yes" "Yes" "Yes" (이혜훈, “부정청약 아파트 포기할 뜻 있나” 묻자 “네” “네” “네”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에 출석해 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, ruling and opposition party lawmakers intensely criticized the nominee over suspicions of 'fraudulent subscription' for an apartment. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회에서 여야 의원들은 이 후보자의 아파트 ‘부정 청약’ 의혹을 집중적으로 질타했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the hearing on the 23rd, when Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Jung Il-young said, "You must be prepared to admit it was wrong, accept any punishment, and if necessary, give up this apartment. Only with that level of resolve do I believe you are qualified to be the first Minister of Planning and Budget of the Lee Jae-myung administration," the nominee replied, "Yes, I understand." The nominee is suspected of having falsely presented her married eldest son as single to increase the number of dependents, thereby winning the subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul. (이 후보자는 23일 인사청문회에서 정일영 더불어민주당 의원이 “잘못됐다, 어떤 처벌이라도 받겠다, 필요하면 이 아파트를 내가 포기하겠다, 이 정도 각오는 가지셔야 이재명 정부의 초대 기획예산처 장관의 자격이 있는 것으로 본다”고 말하자 “네, 알겠습니다”라고 했다. 이 후보자는 결혼식을 올린 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 부양가족 수를 늘린 뒤 서울 서초구 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹을 받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Rep. Jung subsequently asked, "Do you have such an intention?" Nominee Lee only nodded her head. Rep. Jung then said, "No, please answer. No one will know if you just nod. It needs to be on the official record." He pressed again, asking, "Do you (have the intention to give up the apartment) or not?" This time, the nominee simply replied, "Yes." When Rep. Jung said, "What does 'yes' mean? Continue," the nominee engaged in a tense exchange, saying, "Yes, I do." (이어 정 의원이 “그런 용의가 있으신 것이냐”고 묻자, 이 후보자는 고개만 끄덕였다. 이에 정 의원은 “아니, 대답을 하세요. 고개 끄덕끄덕하시면 누가 압니까. 속기록에 남겨야지”라고 말했다. 그러면서 “(아파트를 포기할 용의가) 있으신 거예요, 없으신 거예요”라고 재차 질의하자, 이 후보자는 이번에는 “네”라고만 답했다. 정 의원이 “네가 뭐예요, 계속”이라고 하자 이 후보자는 “네, 있다고요”라며 신경전을 벌였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that morning, in response to Democratic Party lawmaker Jin Sung-jun's question, "Are you willing to give up the (said) house?" the nominee had answered, "I will follow the results of the investigative authorities." (이 후보자는 앞서 이날 오전 “(해당)집을 내놓을 용의가 있는가”라는 진성준 민주당 의원의 질문에는 “수사기관의 결과에 따르겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the fraudulent subscription suspicions that day, the nominee began by saying, "To be honest, I earnestly hoped I wouldn't have to talk about this publicly, but since things have come to this, it seems I have no choice but to talk about my family's situation." She said, "In December 2023, my eldest son prepared a newlywed home (in Yongsan, Seoul), but right after the wedding ceremony, problems arose," adding, "The relationship between the two broke down, reaching the worst point. At the time, it was judged difficult to maintain the marriage." She continued, "At that time, my eldest son had no choice but to continue living with us." Her remarks were intended to convey that while her son, who had held a wedding ceremony, did not move out to the Yongsan newlywed home, it was not a fabricated change of residence aimed at gaining subscription points. (이 후보자는 이날 부정 청약 의혹에 대해 “사실은 제가 이런 이야기를 공개적으로 하게 되지 않기를 간절히 바랐는데, 일이 이렇게 된 이상 저희 가족 이야기를 할 수밖에 없는 상황인 것 같다”고 운을 뗐다. 그는 “2023년 12월 장남은 (서울 용산에) 신혼집을 마련했지만, 혼례를 올리고 곧바로 문제가 생겼다”며 “두 사람의 관계가 깨어진 상황으로, 최악으로 치달았다. 당시에는 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단했다”고 말했다. 이어 “당시 장남은 저희와 함께 계속 있을 수밖에 없는 상황이었다”고 덧붙였다. 결혼식을 올린 장남이 용산 신혼집으로 분가하지 않았을 뿐, 청약 가점을 노린 위장 전입이 아니란 취지의 발언이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked by Rep. Jin Sung-jun, "Did the relationship between the eldest son and his wife recover after a year and a half?" the nominee effectively affirmed it by saying, "The (son and his wife) themselves, and many people, made efforts." (이 후보자는 “장남 부부 사이가 1년 반 만에 다시 회복된 것인가”라는 진성준 의원의 물음에 “(장남 부부)본인들도, 많은 사람도 노력했다”며 이를 사실상 긍정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While explaining the related suspicions, the nominee did not disclose a specific diagnosis but did reveal that her son had developed an illness. When Democratic Party lawmaker Lee So-young pointed out, "For 1 year and 5 months after marriage, the registered addresses of the eldest son and his wife did not overlap at all," the nominee explained during her clarification, "My son developed an illness during that period and is still receiving treatment." The nominee said, "As the relationship reached a breaking point, (my son) fell into an extremely worst situation due to mental pressure and stress, which led to the onset of the illness, and he is still receiving treatment." The nominee showed tears during her answer. (이 후보자는 관련 의혹을 해명하는 과정에서 구체적인 병명을 밝히진 않았지만 장남의 발병 사실을 공개하기도 했다. 이 후보자는 이소영 민주당 의원이 “장남 부부가 결혼 이후 1년5개월간 주민등록상 주소가 전혀 겹치지 않았다”고 지적하자 이를 해명하는 과정에서 “아들이 그 시기에 발병해서 지금까지 치료받고 있다”고 말했다. 이 후보자는 “관계가 파경이 되면서 (장남이) 정신적인 압박과 스트레스 등으로 굉장히 최악의 상황으로 치달아서 발병했고, 지금까지 치료를 받고 있다”고 말했다. 이 후보자는 답변 도중 눈물을 보이기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241412.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling and Opposition Parties Unite in Criticism: "Lee Hye-hoon's Eldest Son's University Admission Process and Apartment Application Were Inappropriate" (여야, 한목소리로 “이혜훈 장남 입학 경위·아파트 청약 부적절”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241419.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Ruling and Opposition Parties Unite in Criticism: "Lee Hye-hoon's Eldest Son's University Admission Process and Apartment Application Were Inappropriate" (여야, 한목소리로 “이혜훈 장남 입학 경위·아파트 청약 부적절”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691676463439.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 발언하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the confirmation hearing for Minister of Economy and Finance nominee Lee Hye-hoon, which opened after much delay, questions from ruling and opposition party lawmakers focused on the circumstances of the nominee's eldest son's admission to Yonsei University and suspicions of improper apartment subscription. Typically, at ministerial confirmation hearings, the ruling party defends against opposition attacks and focuses on policy questions, but at this hearing, not only opposition lawmakers but also ruling party members sharpened their knives for scrutiny. (진통끝에 열린 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회에서는 이 후보자 장남의 연세대 입학 경위와 아파트 부정 청약 의혹에 대한 여야 의원들의 질의가 집중됐다. 통상 국무위원 인사청문회에서 여당은 야당의 공격을 방어하고 정책질의에 집중하는 모습을 보이지만, 이번 청문회에서는 야당뿐만 아니라 여당 의원들도 검증의 날을 세웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both ruling and opposition parties raised issues at the nominee's confirmation hearing held on the 23rd by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee regarding the circumstances of her eldest son's admission to Yonsei University in 2010. The controversy began with nominee Lee's explanation that "my eldest son was admitted (to Yonsei University at the time) not through the multi-child household track, but through the 'National Prestige Enhancer' track." Nominee Lee stated, "My father-in-law (former Minister of Home Affairs Kim Tae-ho) received the Order of Civil Merit (Cheongjo Geunjeong Medal) in recognition of his various public service achievements during his lifelong career as a public official, which qualified him (for the track)." Although nominee Lee stated in a written response submitted to the National Assembly prior to the hearing that "my eldest son was admitted to Yonsei University through the multi-child household track," it was revealed that there was no multi-child household track in the 2010 academic year when her son was admitted, sparking controversy over improper admission. (여야는 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 이 후보자 인사청문회에서 후보자 장남의 2010년 연세대 입학 경위를 문제 삼았다. 논란의 발단은 “장남이 다자녀 전형이 아니라, 국위선양자 전형으로 (당시 연세대에) 입학했다”는 이 후보자 해명이었다. 이 후보자는 “시부(김태호 전 내무부 장관)께서 공무원으로 평생 봉직한 여러 공적을 인정받아 청조근정훈장을 받으셨기 때문에 (전형) 자격 요건이 됐다”고 했다. 이 후보자는 인사청문회에 앞서 국회에 낸 답변서에서 “장남이 다자녀가구 전형으로 연세대에 입학했다”고 밝혔지만, 이 후보자 장남이 입학한 2010학년도에는 다자녀전형이 없었던 것으로 드러나 부정입학 논란이 불거진 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, People Power Party lawmaker Choi Eun-seok said, "Can we say that (nominee Lee's) eldest son's grandfather enhanced our nation's prestige by serving as Minister of Home Affairs and receiving a medal?" adding, "Through this, the nominee is essentially confessing to improper admission." The nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho, is a former four-term lawmaker who received the Order of Civil Merit. (이에 최은석 국민의힘 의원은 “(이 후보자)장남의 할아버지가 내무부 장관을 해서 훈장을 받은 게 우리나라의 국위를 선양했다고 할 수 있는가”라며 “이런 걸 통해 부정 입학을 했다는 걸 후보자가 그대로 자백하고 있는 것”이라고 말했다. 이 후보자의 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관은 4선 의원 출신으로 청조근정훈장을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To Rep. Choi's point, nominee Lee retorted, "It's not a regulation I created, but a regulation the school created." Rep. Choi continued raising suspicions, stating, "At the time, the nominee's husband was the head of the Academic Affairs Office at Yonsei University," and "It appears nominee Lee Hye-hoon's eldest son seized a spot meant for a social contributor." (최 의원의 지적에 이 후보자는 “제가 만든 규정이 아니고 학교가 만든 규정”이라고 반박했다. 최 의원은 “당시 후보자 남편은 연세대 교무부처장”이라며 “사회 기여자 자리를 이혜훈 후보자의 장남이 강탈한 것”이라고 의혹 제기를 이어갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party lawmaker also joined in. Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Ahn Do-gul pointed out problems with the eldest son's university admission process, stating, "Article 11, Clause 3 of the Constitution stipulates that decorations, medals, and other honors are effective only for the recipients and do not grant any privileges." (여당 의원도 가세했다. 안도걸 더불어민주당 의원은 “헌법 제11조 3항은 훈장 등의 영전은 이를 받은 자에게만 효력이 있고 어떠한 특권도 이에 따르지 아니한다고 규정하고 있다”며 장남의 대학 입학 과정에 문제가 있다고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When nominee Lee later got a chance to explain, she again specifically mentioned her son's admission issue. She said, "The school conducts a comprehensive evaluation mainly based on the CSAT (college entrance exam), school records, then various English scores, written exams, and oral interviews," and added, "In my son's case, he was an outstanding student academically; for English tests like TOEFL, SAT, and AP (Advanced Placement) exams taken in advance for U.S. college courses, he submitted scores all at the highest level (grade 5)." She continued, "If this student received a GPA of 3.85 after entering the school, I believe that is sufficient proof," and said, "As the (Planning and Finance Committee) Chairman (Im I-jae) mentioned earlier, the school no longer has any materials as the document retention period has passed. We are in a truly frustrating situation wondering how to clear this false accusation." (이 후보자는 이후 해명 기회를 얻자 다시 구체적으로 장남의 입학 문제를 언급했다. 그는 “주로 수능, 내신, 그 다음에 영어 각종 성적, 그리고 필기시험, 구술시험으로 학교에서 종합평가를 한다”며 “장남의 경우에 성적 우수자이고, 영어시험의 경우에는 토플, 에스에이티(SAT), 그다음에 에이피(AP)라고 미국 대학 과목을 먼저 시험 보는 것들이 있는데 다 5등급을 받아서 냈다”고 했다. 이어 “이 학생이 학교에 들어가서 3.85 학점을 받았으면 저는 그걸로 충분히 입증됐다고 본다”며 “아까 (임이자 재경경제기획위원회) 위원장님이 말씀하신 것처럼 학교는 자료 폐기 보존 기간이 지나서 아무 자료를 가지고 있지 않다는데, 저희는 어떻게 이 누명을 벗어야 될지 정말 답답한 상황”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Suspected improper subscription' was also put under scrutiny. Nominee Lee faces suspicions that she falsely represented her married eldest son as single to increase the number of dependents, leading to his winning a subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul. Regarding these suspicions, nominee Lee explained, "At the time, the relationship between the two (son and his wife) had deteriorated to the worst point," and "At the time, we thought it would be difficult for them to maintain their marriage." (‘부정 청약’도 도마 위에 올랐다. 이 후보자는 결혼식을 올린 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 부양가족 수를 늘린 뒤, 서울 서초구 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹을 받는다. 이런 의혹과 관련해 이 후보자는 “당시 두 사람(아들 부부)의 관계가 최악으로 치달았다”며 “당시 저희는 (아들 부부가) 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 생각했다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominee Lee shed tears while responding to related suspicions. When Democratic Party lawmaker Lee So-young pointed out that "the addresses on the resident registrations of the eldest son and his wife did not overlap at all for 1 year and 5 months after their marriage," nominee Lee, while explaining this, said, "My son fell ill during that period and has been receiving treatment ever since." She added, "As the relationship reached a breaking point, (my eldest son) fell into a very worst state due to mental pressure and stress, which led to his illness, and he has been receiving treatment until now." Nominee Lee shed tears as she continued this story. (이 후보자는 관련 의혹에 대해 답변하는 과정에 눈물을 보이기도 했다. 그는 이소영 민주당 의원이 “장남 부부가 결혼 이후 1년5개월간 주민등록상 주소가 전혀 겹치지 않았다”고 지적하자, 이를 해명하는 과정에서 “아들이 그 시기에 발병해서 지금까지 치료받고 있다”고 말했다. 이어 “관계가 파경이 되면서 (장남이) 정신적인 압박과 스트레스 등으로 굉장히 최악의 상황으로 치달아서 발병했고, 지금까지 치료를 받고 있다”고 덧붙였다. 이 후보자는 이런 이야기를 이어가며 눈물을 흘렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport stated regarding the suspicions of improper subscription surrounding nominee Lee that if the related suspicions are true, there is a possibility of improper subscription. Jeong Su-ho, head of the Housing Finance Division at the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, who attended the hearing as a witness, responded to a question from Reform Party lawmaker Cheon Ha-ram, who asked, "Even in the case of a common-law marriage that broke down, shouldn't it be treated the same as divorce and not counted as a dependent?", by saying, "If the suspicions raised by the National Assembly or the media are true, there is a possibility of improper subscription." (이날 국토교통부는 이 후보자를 둘러싼 부정 청약 의혹을 두고, 관련 의혹이 사실이라면 부정 청약 소지가 있다고 밝혔다. 청문회에 증인으로 출석한 정수호 국토부 주택기금과장은 “사실혼 관계였다가 파탄 난 경우도 (이혼과) 동일하게 부양가족으로 넣으면 안 되는 것 아닌가”라는 천하람 개혁신당 의원 질의에 “국회나 언론에서 제기되는 의혹이 사실이면, 부정 청약 소지가 있다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the authenticity of the so-called 'memorandum' containing content such as wishes for other lawmakers to lose elections, nominee Lee denied it, saying, "I did not write it. I do not create such things (memorandums) as HWP (Hangul Word Processor) files." Nominee Lee also said, "It seems someone mixed their own guesses and rumors based on various schedules shared by our office staff," and added, "(The author) seems to be someone from our office nearby who is well aware of my every move." (이 후보자는 다른 의원에 대한 낙선 기도 등의 내용이 담긴 이른바 ‘비망록’의 진위를 놓고선 “제가 작성하지 않았다. 한글 파일로 이런 것(비망록)을 만들지 않는다”며 부인했다. 이 후보자는 “사무실 직원들이 공유하는 여러 일정을 기반으로 누군가가 본인의 짐작과 소문을 버무린 것으로 보인다”며 “(작성자는) 저의 일거수일투족을 잘 아는 지근거리에 있는 우리 사무실 직원인 것 같다”고 말하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241419.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691676463439.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For KOSPI to Leap Beyond 5000... 'Fire on One's Feet' is Substantializing the Stewardship Code (코스피 5000 넘어 도약하려면…스튜어드십 코드 내실화 ‘발등의 불’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241425.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;For KOSPI to Leap Beyond 5000... 'Fire on One's Feet' is Substantializing the Stewardship Code (코스피 5000 넘어 도약하려면…스튜어드십 코드 내실화 ‘발등의 불’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0124/53_17692114886627_20260124500134.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;1월 23일 국회 의원회관에서 ‘스튜어드십코드 실효성 제고를 위한 내실화 방안 모색 토론회’ 가 열려 참석자들이 오기형 더불어민주당 코스피 5000 특위 위원장의 인사말을 듣고 있다.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a point being made that for the KOSPI 5000 point not to become just a 'turning point' that is briefly touched and then recedes, a transparent and fair corporate governance structure must be established. As one of the methods, the reorganization of the 'Lee Jae-myung administration version Stewardship Code', which includes strengthening the responsible investment of pension funds, building a cooperation platform among institutional investors, and improving laws and systems, has emerged as a key task. (코스피 5000 포인트가 한번 갔다 오는 ‘반환점’이 되지 않으려면 투명하고 공정한 기업지배구조가 자리 잡아야 한다는 지적이 나온다. 그 방안의 하나로 연기금의 책임투자 강화와 기관투자자 간 협력플랫폼 구축, 법·제도 정비를 포함한 ‘이재명 정부판 스튜어드십 코드’ 재정비가 핵심 과제로 떠올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Stewardship Code refers to the rules where institutions that invest others' money, such as pension/funds and asset management companies, promise to "protect the interests of the people who invested by responsibly and actively monitoring and participating in companies like a steward." Korea's Stewardship Code has been criticized for remaining a formal operation without a single revision even as it approaches 10 years since its introduction. (스튜어드십 코드는 남의 돈을 맡아 투자하는 연·기금, 자산운용사 같은 기관들이 “집사처럼 책임 있게, 적극적으로 기업을 감시·참여해서 투자한 사람들의 이익을 지키자”고 약속한 규칙을 말한다. 국내 스튜어드십 코드는 도입된 지 10년을 앞두고도 개정 한 번 없이 형식적 운영에 머물렀다는 비판을 받아왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A discussion forum on the topic of 'Substantialization Measures to Enhance the Effectiveness of the Stewardship Code' was held on the morning of the 23rd at the National Assembly Members' Office Building. Co-hosted by the Democratic Party of Korea's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee and Representative Kim Yun, the forum was attended by the Financial Services Commission, the National Pension Service, asset management companies, and civic groups to examine the actual implementation status of the code and discuss revision directions for more effective operation, an implementation monitoring system, and measures to strengthen the role of pension funds. (23일 오전 국회의원회관에서 ‘스튜어드십 코드 실효성 제고를 위한 내실화 방안’을 주제로 한 토론회가 열렸다. 더불어민주당 코스피 5000 특별 위원회와 김윤 의원이 공동주최한 토론회는 금융위원회, 국민연금, 자산운용사, 시민단체 등이 참여해 코드 이행 실태를 점검하고, 더 효과적으로 작동하기 위한 개정 방향과 이행점검 체계, 연기금 역할 강화 방안을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, Hwang Hyun-young, a research fellow at the Capital Market Research Institute, defined the Stewardship Code as "a code of conduct that encourages institutional investors to go beyond simply holding shares and engage in the long-term value creation of the companies they invest in," stating it is "a key tool for improving governance, expanding shareholder interests, and developing the capital market by having institutional investors with professional knowledge and resources play an active role." (황현영 자본시장 연구원 연구위원은 발제에서 “스튜어드십 코드는 기관투자자가 단순 주식 보유를 넘어 투자대상 회사의 장기 가치 형성에 관여하도록 하는 행동지침”이라며 “전문지식과 자원을 가진 기관투자자가 적극적 역할을 함으로써 지배구조 개선과 주주 이익 확대, 자본시장 발전을 위한 핵심 수단”이라고 정의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, since the system's introduction in 2016, the shareholder activities of private institutional investors participating in the code have seemingly become more active. The rate of voting against regular shareholder meeting agenda items increased from around 1% in 2014 to 4.59% in 2024, and the opposition rate of code-participating institutions was found to be more than three times higher than that of non-participating institutions. The National Pension Service also saw significant increases in its rate of voting against and the number of shareholder engagement activities such as letters and meetings with companies after participating in the code. (실제 2016년 제도 도입 이후 코드 참여 민간 기관투자자의 주주활동은 외견상 활발해졌다. 정기주총 안건에 대한 반대 의결권 행사 비율이 2014년 1%대에서 2024년에는 4.59%까지 늘었고 코드 참여기관의 반대율은 미참여 기관보다 3배 이상 높은 것으로 나타났다. 국민연금 역시 코드 참여 이후 반대의결권 행사 비율과 기업과의 서신·면담 등 주주 관여활동 건수가 많이 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, its effectiveness is lacking in reporting, disclosure, and execution. Only about 10 institutions on average annually regularly publish Stewardship implementation reports, and for insurers, banks, and securities firms excluding pension funds and asset management companies, no cases of report publication have been confirmed. In particular, private equity fund managers, investment advisory firms, and service institutions do not even have a website related to the Stewardship Code. (하지만 보고·공시·실행 면에서는 실효성이 떨어진다. 스튜어드십 이행 보고서를 정기적으로 발간하는 기관은 연간 평균 10여건에 불과하고, 연기금과 자산운용사를 제외한 보험사·은행·증권사는 보고서 발간 사례가 확인되지 않는다. 특히 사모펀드 운용사, 투자자문사, 서비스 기관 등은 스튜어드십 코드 관련한 홈페이지조차 없는 실정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voting rights disclosure is also poor. According to a Financial Supervisory Service inspection in August 2024, 96.7% of the inspected asset management companies filled the reasons for exercising or not exercising voting rights with formal phrases like "no infringement of shareholder rights," and many companies did not properly state even the agenda name, proposal type, or relationship with the target corporation. Over 40% of management companies also disclosed only basic policies at the legal level for internal guidelines related to voting rights exercise and did not disclose detailed guidelines for each agenda item. (의결권 공시도 부실하다. 2024년 8월 금융감독원 점검에 따르면, 점검 대상 자산운용사의 96.7%가 의결권 행사·불행사 사유를 “주주권 침해 없음” 등 형식적인 문구로 채웠고, 안건명·의안 유형·대상 법인과의 관계조차 제대로 적지 않은 회사가 다수였다. 의결권 행사 관련 내부 지침도 법령 수준의 기본정책만 공시하고 안건별 세부 지침을 공개하지 않은 운용사도 40%가 넘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Hwang pointed out that there are almost no incentives to be gained even by faithfully implementing the code, while the costs for personnel, research, and legal review are significant. He assessed that ultimately, within a structure where the market cannot distinguish between code implementation and non-implementation, "the 'rational indifference' of institutional investors is solidifying." (황 연구위원은 코드를 충실히 이행해도 얻을 수 있는 인센티브는 거의 없는데, 인력·리서치·법률 검토 비용은 상당하다고 지적했다. 결국 코드 이행과 비이행을 시장이 구분하지 못하는 구조 속에서 “기관 투자자의 ‘합리적 무관심’이 굳어지고 있다”고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the forum, a suggestion was made to first 'establish a management system premised on substantial implementation from the registration stage.' It is a proposal to abolish the current system where about 50 institutions remain only in a 'planned participation' status and to allow registration only for institutions that submit specific implementation plans approved by their boards, etc. (토론회에서는 우선 ‘등록 단계부터 실질 이행을 전제로 한 관리체계’를 구축하자는 제언이 나왔다. 현재 50여개 기관이 ‘참여 예정’ 상태로만 남아있는 제도는 폐지하고, 이사회 승인 등을 거친 구체적 이행계획을 제출한 기관만 등록을 허용하자는 제안이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After code participation, opinions were presented that package-type management including regular implementation checks, disclosure, and sanctions is necessary. That is, △integrating and disclosing participating institutions' implementation reports and inspection results so investors can compare at a glance, △giving incentives to excellent implementers in the selection of entrusted managers and fee calculation by pension funds, etc., and △considering measures to exclude institutions that persistently fail to implement despite improvement requests from the list of participating institutions. (코드 참여 이후에는 정기적 이행점검과 공시, 제재까지 포함하는 패키지형 관리가 필요하다는 의견이 제시됐다. 즉 △ 참여기관의 이행보고서와 점검결과를 통합 공시해 투자자가 한눈에 비교할 수 있게 하고 △ 이행 우수 기관은 연기금 등의 위탁운용사 선정과 수수료 산정에서 인센티브를 부여하며 △개선 요구에도 미이행이 지속하는 기관은 참여기관 명단에서 제외하는 방안까지 검토해야 한다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, revision directions were suggested to expand the scope of the Stewardship Code beyond listed stocks to bonds, real estate, infrastructure, etc., and to explicitly include ESG and sustainability factors. In particular, opinions were raised to re-establish 'engagement activities' such as dialogue with companies, sending letters, public letters, shareholder proposals, and lawsuits as a core axis beyond simply voting for or against shareholder meeting agendas, and to include detailed procedures, escalation stages, and termination criteria for engagement activities in the code and guidelines. (아울러 스튜어드십 코드의 적용 범위를 상장주식 외에 채권·부동산·인프라 등으로 확대하고, 이에스지(ESG)·지속가능성 요소를 명시적으로 포함하자는 개정방향도 제시됐다. 특히 주주총회 안건 찬반을 넘어 기업과의 대화·서신 발송·공개서한·주주제안·소송 등 ‘관여활동’(engagement)을 핵심축으로 재정립하고, 관여활동 절차·격상 단계·종료 기준을 코드와 지침에 상세히 담자는 의견도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Seung-hee, a research fellow at the Economic Reform Institute, argued that "the current 'comply or explain' method uniformly applied to the seven principles should be improved to enhance effectiveness by making principles mandatory and allowing exception explanations only for some detailed guidance." (이승희 경제개혁연대 연구위원은 “현행 7대 원칙에 일괄 적용된 ‘준수 또는 설명’ 방식을 개선해, 원칙은 의무 준수, 세부 안내지침 일부에만 예외 설명을 허용하는 방식으로 실효성을 높여야 한다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussants unanimously called for strengthening the role of pension funds, especially the National Pension Service. The case of Japan's Government Pension Investment Fund (GPIF) expanding the proportion of stewardship activities in its evaluation of entrusted managers and entrusting funds to activist funds to promote engagement activities was cited as a representative benchmark. In entrusted manager management, the National Pension Service gives a 2-point bonus in selection if an institution participates in the code and prepares guidelines, but the structure of evaluating the quality and performance of actual engagement activities and reflecting them in the entrusted scale or fees is still insufficient. In contrast, Japan's GPIF includes stewardship activities as a separate item in its selection/evaluation criteria for entrusted managers, checking in detail ESG integration status, engagement methods, and voting principles. (토론자들은 한목소리로 연기금, 특히 국민연금의 역할 강화를 주문했다. 일본 국민연금(GPIF)이 위탁운용사 평가에 스튜어드십 활동 비중을 확대하고, 행동주의 펀드에도 자금을 맡겨 관여 활동을 촉진한 사례가 대표적 베치마크로 거론됐다. 위탁운용사 관리에서도 국민연금은 코드에 참여해 지침만 마련해도 선정 시 2점 가점을 부여하지만, 실제 관여 활동의 질·성과를 평가해 위탁규모나 수수료에 반영하는 구조는 아직 미흡하다. 이에 비해 일본 국민연금은 위탁사 선정·평가 기준에 스튜어드십 활동을 별도 항목으로 포함해, 이에스지 통합 여부·관여활동 방식·의결권 행사 원칙 등을 상세히 점검한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Dong-seop, head of the Fiduciary Responsibility Department at the National Pension Service Fund Management Headquarters, introduced that they are conducting fiduciary responsibility activities such as dialogue with companies, focusing on six key management issues including dividend policy, executive compensation, and legal violations. He said, "Dialogue with companies is based on the principle of confidentiality, so most of it is not disclosed externally," and did not agree with the assessment that the National Pension Service has "passively conducted fiduciary responsibility activities." However, he acknowledged that there are not a few unresolved issues, such as △the opacity of capital allocation plans after dividends, △the refusal to specifically disclose executive compensation policies, and △passive compensation and recurrence prevention measures in incidents involving controlling shareholders. (이동섭 국민연금공단 기금운용본부 수탁자책임실장은 배당정책, 임원 보수, 법령위반 등 6대 중점관리 사안을 중심으로 기업과의 대화 등 수탁자책임 활동을 수행하고 있다고 소개했다. 그는 “기업과의 대화는 비공개를 원칙으로 해서 대부분 외부에 공개되지 않았다”며 국민연금이 수탁자책임활동을 “소극적으로 행해 왔다는 평가에 동의하지 않는다”고 말했다. 하지만 그는 △배당 이후 잔여 자본배치 계획의 불투명성 △경영진 보수정책의 구체적 공개 거부 △ 지배주주가 연루된 사건에서의 소극적 손해배상·재발방지 조치 등 해결되지 않는 과제가 적지 않다고 인정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Lee Seung-hee emphasized that "the National Pension Service should strengthen the engagement activities it directly performs, such as selecting engagement targets," and "it is necessary to utilize the expertise activist funds have in corporate governance improvement by also entrusting funds to activist funds." (이승희 연구위원은 “국민연금이 관여활동 대상 선정 등 직접 수행하는 관여활동을 강화해야 한다”며 “행동주의 펀드에도 자금을 위탁해 기업지배구조 개선에서 행동주의 펀드가 가진 전문성을 활용”할 필요가 있다고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal and institutional risks were also pointed out as obstacles hindering the active exercise of shareholder rights. It is pointed out that the current large shareholding reporting system (5% rule) and proxy solicitation regulations under the Capital Markets Act vaguely define concepts like 'management participation' and 'joint holding,' making it difficult for institutions to engage in lawsuits, shareholder proposals, or joint actions. (법·제도 리스크 역시 적극적인 주주권 행사를 가로막는 장애물로 지목됐다. 현행 자본시장법상 주식 등 대량보유 보고 제도(5%룰) 와 의결권 대리행사 권유 규정이 ‘경영 참여’와 ‘공동보유’ 개념을 모호하게 정의하고 있어, 기관들이 소송·주주제안·연대 행동에 나서기 어렵게 만든다는 지적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Hwang said, "Uncertainty exists where even a request to appoint one outside director or jointly raising an issue about a merger that damages shareholder value could be interpreted as management participation." He added, "As violations can lead to fines, criminal penalties, and even restrictions on voting rights, it becomes an obstacle to active shareholder rights exercise." He stated, "These two systems were introduced in the early days of the capital market and do not consider the current level of capital market development and active shareholder activities," and "It is difficult to find a country (on Earth) with a system designed like this." (황 연구위원은 “사외이사 한 명 선임 요구나 주주가치를 훼손하는 합병에 대한 공동문제제기까지 경영 참여로 해석될 수 있는 불확실성이 존재한다.”라며 “위반 시 과징금·형사처벌·심지어 의결권 제한까지 가능해 적극적 주주권 행사에 장애가 된다”고 말했다. 그는 “두 제도는 자본시장 초창기 도입된 제도로 현재와 같은 자본시장 발전과 적극적 주주활동을 고려하지 못하고 있다”며 “이렇게 제도가 설계된 나라는 (지구 위에서) 찾기 어렵다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Seung-hee, research fellow at the Economic Reform Institute, introduced overseas cases, saying, "The UK effectively excludes joint voting rights exercise limited to specific shareholder meeting proposals from large holding disclosure obligations to ensure cooperative engagement activities, and Japan also revised its Financial Instruments and Exchange Act in 2024 to broadly recognize exceptions for joint engagement activities among financial institutions." He said, "Korea should also revise the 5% rule enforcement decree and legal interpretation books to exclude general governance improvement demands, dividend policy improvement demands, etc., which are not aimed at seizing management control, from rapid reporting requirements, allowing management companies and pension funds to actively negotiate with companies." (이승희 경제개혁연대 연구위원은 해외 사례를 들며 “영국은 특정 주주총회 의안에 한정된 공동 의결권 행사를 대량보유 공시의무에서 사실상 제외해 협력적 관여활동을 보장하고, 일본도 2024년 금융상품 거래법을 개정해 금융기관 간 공동 관여활동에 폭넓은 예외를 인정했다”고 소개했다. 그는 “한국도 5%룰 시행령과 법령해석집을 개정해, 경영권 장악 목적이 아닌 일반적인 지배구조 개선, 배당정책 개선 요구 등은 신속신고 대상에서 제외해 운용사와 연기금이 적극적으로 기업과 교섭하게 해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his opening remarks, Representative Oh Ki-hyung (Chairman of the Democratic Party's KOSPI 5000 Committee) said, "Japan has revised its Stewardship Code three times since its introduction in 2014, but Korea has not touched it once since introduction," and "We must revise the code to induce more long-term investment rather than short-term trading and move towards a structure where shareholders can share in the company's innovation performance." (오기형 의원(민주당 코스피 5000 위원장)은 인삿말에서 “일본은 2014년 도입 이후 세차례나 스튜어드십 코드를 개정했지만 한국은 도입 이후 단 한번도 손질하지 않았다”며 “코드를 개정해 단타투자가 아니라 좀더 장기적 투자를 유도하고 주주들이 기업의 혁신 성과를 공유할 수 있는 구조로 가야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim Yun (Democratic Party of Korea) also emphasized, "The Stewardship Code must now move beyond the stage of asking about participation to asking about the quality of implementation." He said, "As the National Pension Service manages over 1,400 trillion won of the people's retirement assets, it is time to meticulously design an implementation check and evaluation/feedback structure so that its fiduciary responsibility activities do not stop at formality but lead to changes in corporate behavior." (김윤 의원(더불어민주당)도 “스튜어드십 코드는 이제 참여여부가 아니라 이행의 질을 묻는 단계로 넘어가야 한다”고 강조했다. 그는 “국민연금이 1400조원이 넘는 국민의 노후 자산을 운용하는 만큼, 그 수탁자책임 활동이 형식에 그치지 않고 기업 행동 변화를 이끌도록 이행점검과 평가·환류 구조를 정교하게 설계”할 때라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article and photo by Lee Bong-hyun, Research Fellow at The Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:bhlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;bhlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (글·사진 이봉현 한겨레경제사회연구원 연구위원 &lt;a href="mailto:bhlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;bhlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241425.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0124/53_17692114886627_20260124500134.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Samsung Electronics, which sharpened its competitive resolve with 'Lee Kun-hee video'... Lee Jae-yong says, "This is not the time for complacency" (‘이건희 영상’으로 경쟁력 각오 다진 삼성전자…이재용 “자만할 때 아냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241470.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Samsung Electronics, which sharpened its competitive resolve with 'Lee Kun-hee video'... Lee Jae-yong says, "This is not the time for complacency" (‘이건희 영상’으로 경쟁력 각오 다진 삼성전자…이재용 “자만할 때 아냐”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/389/imgdb/child/2026/0125/53_17693049175825_20260125500672.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재용 삼성전자 회장이 6일 2박 3일간의 중국 출장을 마치고 서울 강서구 서울김포비즈니스항공센터(SGBAC)를 통해 입국하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that Samsung Electronics Chairman Lee Jae-yong emphasized to Samsung Group executives, "This is not the time to become complacent just because the numbers have improved a bit," stating, "Now is the last opportunity to restore our competitiveness." He urged them not to be overly optimistic about the performance improvement driven by the AI boom and to secure fundamental technological competitiveness. (이재용 삼성전자 회장이 삼성그룹 임원들에게 “숫자가 좀 나아졌다고 자만할 때가 아니다”라며 “지금이 경쟁력을 회복할 수 있는 마지막 기회”라고 강조한 것으로 전해졌다. 인공지능(AI) 열풍에 힘입은 실적 개선에 낙관하지 말고, 근본적인 기술 경쟁력을 확보하라고 주문한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to business community sources on the 25th, Samsung Group recently shared the Chairman's message with this core content during an executive seminar. Since last week, Samsung has been conducting 'value education for restoring Samsung's identity' for about 2,000 executives at the vice president level and below from all affiliates, including Samsung Electronics. (25일 재계의 설명을 들어보면, 삼성그룹은 최근 임원 대상 세미나에서 이와 같은 내용을 뼈대로 한 이 회장의 메시지를 공유했다. 삼성은 지난주부터 삼성전자 등 전 계열사의 부사장 이하 임원 2천여명을 대상으로 ‘삼성다움 복원을 위한 가치 교육’을 하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is known that this year's seminar featured not only Chairman Lee's message but also a video containing the management philosophy of the late former Chairman Lee Kun-hee. The video mentioned the former Chairman's 'sandwich crisis theory.' At a meeting of the Federation of Korean Industries (now the Korea Enterprises Federation) chairman's committee in January 2007, the former Chairman said, "With China catching up and Japan ahead, the Korean economy is in a sandwich situation." (올해 세미나에서는 이 회장의 메시지와 함께 고 이건희 선대회장의 경영 철학이 담긴 영상도 상영된 것으로 알려졌다. 영상 속에는 이 선대회장의 ‘샌드위치 위기론’이 언급됐다. 이 선대회장은 지난 2007년 1월 전경련(현 한국경제인협회) 회장단 회의에서 “중국은 쫓아오고, 일본은 앞서가는 상황에서 한국 경제는 샌드위치 신세”라고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The re-citation of the former Chairman's remarks is interpreted as referencing Korea's current situation, caught between the two superpowers, the US and China. It reveals a sense of crisis regarding China's technological pursuit and US tariff pressure, among other factors. (이 선대회장의 발언이 다시 인용된 것은 최근 중국과 미국이라는 양강의 경쟁 구도 속 끼어 있는 한국의 상황을 언급한 것으로 풀이된다. 중국의 기술 추격, 미국의 관세 압박 등에 대한 위기 의식을 드러낸 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Lee's request not to be satisfied with numbers is also connected to this fundamental sense of crisis. Last year, Samsung Electronics' operating profit increased by 33% year-on-year to 43.53 trillion won. However, this was largely thanks to memory semiconductors benefiting from the surge in AI-related demand. There are limitations, such as failing to catch up with SK Hynix's market share in advanced semiconductor areas like High Bandwidth Memory (HBM). (이 회장이 숫자에 안주하지 말 것을 요청한 것 역시 이와 같은 근본적인 위기의식과 맞닿아 있다. 지난해 삼성전자의 영업이익은 1년 전에 견줘 33% 늘어난 43조5300억원을 기록했다. 그러나 이는 인공지능발 수요 급증에 수혜를 본 메모리 반도체 덕분이지, 고대역폭메모리(HBM) 등 첨단 반도체 영역에서는 에스케이(SK)하이닉스의 시장 점유율을 따라잡지 못한다는 한계가 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Samsung resumed its group-wide executive seminars starting in 2025, the first time in nine years since 2016. (한편, 삼성은 2016년 이후 9년 만인 지난 2025년부터 전 계열사 임원 대상 세미나를 재개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241470.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/389/imgdb/child/2026/0125/53_17693049175825_20260125500672.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virtual Asset Exchanges with '97% Oligopoly'... Will 'Limiting Major Shareholder Stakes' Hinder Innovation? (‘97% 독과점’ 가상자산 거래소…‘대주주 지분 제한’은 혁신 저해?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241471.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Virtual Asset Exchanges with '97% Oligopoly'... Will 'Limiting Major Shareholder Stakes' Hinder Innovation? (‘97% 독과점’ 가상자산 거래소…‘대주주 지분 제한’은 혁신 저해?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/738/443/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500707.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;가상자산 투자가가 거래소에서 코인 시세를 살펴보고 있다. 업비트 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;'97.44%.' (‘97.44%.’)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the combined market share of South Korea's top two virtual asset exchanges, Upbit and Bithumb. The issue of exchange oligopoly, which had been submerged for a while, is resurfacing as the Financial Services Commission (FSC) proposed measures including limiting major shareholder stakes in virtual asset exchanges. The Fair Trade Commission (FTC) also recently submitted a research report to the National Assembly warning of the solidification of the monopoly structure. The responses from both ministries are underpinned by a recognition of the problem that the virtual asset trading market's oligopoly system is becoming entrenched. (국내 1·2위 가상자산거래소 업비트와 빗썸의 점유율을 더한 숫자다. 금융위원회가 가상자산 거래소의 대주주 지분 제한 등을 제시하며 한동안 수면 아래로 가라앉았던 거래소 독과점 이슈가 다시 떠오르고 있다. 공정거래위원회도 최근 독점 구조의 고착화를 경고하는 내용의 연구용역 보고서를 국회에 제출했다. 두 부처의 대응에는 가상자산 거래시장의 독과점 체제가 굳어지고 있다는 문제의식이 깔려 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to research reports conducted by the FTC and FSC as of the 25th, Upbit's market share (government tally) as of December 2024 was 76.77%, and Bithumb's was 20.67%. Combined, they reach 97.44%. The third-place exchange, Coinone, remains at only 1.49%. The Monopoly Regulation and Fair Trade Act presumes a business operator to be a monopolistic entity if one company's market share is 50% or more, or if the combined market share of three or fewer companies is 75% or more. (25일 공정위·금융위가 진행한 연구용역 보고서를 보면, 2024년 12월 업비트 점유율(정부 집계)은 76.77%, 빗썸은 20.67%다. 두 곳 합쳐 97.44%에 이른다. 3위 코인원은 1.49%에 그친다. 공정거래법은 1개 업체의 점유율이 50% 이상이거나, 3개 이하 업체의 점유율이 75% 이상이면 독점적 사업자로 추정한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report judged that "the domestic KRW-based virtual asset trading market is a highly concentrated market centered around the top and top two business operators, and it can be seen that the solidification of the oligopoly has progressed to some extent." It further suggested that "through second-stage virtual asset legislation, (the bill) should explicitly state that market concentration and competition issues can be actively addressed." The intent is that the second-stage virtual asset law, being promoted by the National Assembly and the government, should include provisions for resolving oligopoly and promoting competition. It also proposed measures such as introducing order routing/interconnection functions to increase competition among exchanges, expanding business areas (FSC's measures), and strengthening the FTC's review of business combinations. (보고서는 “국내 원화 기반 가상자산 거래시장은 1위 및 1·2위 사업자 중심으로 상당히 집중된 시장으로, 독과점 고착화가 어느 정도 진행된 것으로 볼 수 있다”고 판단했다. 이어 보고서는 “가상자산 2단계 입법을 통해 시장 집중 및 경쟁 문제를 적극적으로 다룰 수 있도록 (법안에) 명시해야 한다”고 제언했다. 국회와 정부가 추진 중인 2단계 가상자산법에 독과점 해소 및 경쟁 촉진을 위한 문구가 반영돼야 한다는 취지다. 아울러 거래소 간 경쟁을 높이기 위한 주문 중개·연결 기능 도입과 사업 영역 확대 등 금융위 대책과 공정위의 기업결합 심사 강화 등을 함께 제시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This oligopoly issue leads to problems in the governance structure within individual exchanges. When a few companies dominate the market, the decision-making of controlling shareholders can have an excessive impact on the entire market. Furthermore, the large-scale fee revenue generated from exchanges, which have already established themselves as social infrastructure, can all be taken by a few controlling shareholders. (이러한 독과점 문제는 단일 거래소 내부의 지배구조 문제로 이어진다. 소수 업체가 시장을 장악할 때 지배주주의 의사결정이 시장 전반에 과도한 영향을 미칠 수 있고, 이미 사회 인프라로 자리 잡은 거래소에서 발생하는 대규모 수수료 수익도 소수 지배주주가 모두 가져갈 수 있어서다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The domestic virtual asset market capitalization, which was 55 trillion won at the end of 2021, nearly doubled to 95 trillion won by the end of June 2025. The top operator, Dunamu, with total assets of 15.869 trillion won, ranked 36th in the business group rankings (based on 2025 FTC corporate group standards). Dunamu's annual revenue in 2024 was 1.7 trillion won, and its operating profit margin reached 68.5% as it does not bear significant burdens for large-scale facility investment or employment. The average operating profit margin for KOSPI-listed companies in 2024 was 6.74%. (2021년 말 55조원이던 국내 가상자산 시가총액은 2025년 6월 말 95조원으로 두 배 가까이 늘었다. 1위 사업자인 두나무는 자산총액 15조8690억원으로 재계 순위 36위(2025년 공정위 기업집단 기준)에 이름을 올렸다. 두나무의 2024년 연간 매출은 1조7천억원으로, 대규모 설비 투자와 고용 부담이 크지 않아 영업이익률은 68.5%에 달한다. 2024년 코스피 상장사 평균 영업이익률은 6.74%다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the background behind the FSC's report to the National Assembly last December that regulations limiting exchange major shareholder stakes to the 15-20% level should be reflected in the second-stage virtual asset legislation. The FSC explained the need for ownership dispersion, stating, "Exchanges used by 11 million people are key infrastructure for distribution, yet a small number of founders/shareholders still exercise control, and there is a structural problem where operating profits such as fees are concentrated on specific shareholders." (금융위가 지난해 12월 거래소 대주주 지분을 15~20% 수준으로 제한하는 규제를 가상자산 2단계 입법에 반영해야 한다고 국회에 &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1238448.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;보고&lt;/a&gt;한 배경이다. 금융위는 “1100만명이 이용하는 거래소는 유통의 핵심 인프라인데도 여전히 소수의 창업자·주주가 지배력을 행사하고 있고, 수수료 등 운용 수익이 특정 주주에게 집중되는 구조적 문제점이 있다”며 소유 분산의 필요성을 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The industry immediately protested. They argue it risks being an unconstitutional infringement of property rights and is excessive regulation that hinders innovation. They say it's difficult to view the market structure as having entered a solidified stage yet, and the possibility of reorganization into a new market structure remains due to factors like the emergence of stablecoins. It's an argument that the market can restore competitive functions on its own without government intervention. (업계는 즉각 &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1239423.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;반발&lt;/a&gt;했다. 재산권 침해 위헌 논란이 있는데다가 혁신을 저해하는 과도한 규제라는 것이다. 시장 구조가 아직 고착화 단계에 접어들었다고 보기 어렵고, 스테이블코인 등장 등으로 새로운 시장 구조로 재편될 가능성도 남아 있다고 말한다. 정부 개입 없이도 시장 스스로 경쟁 기능을 회복할 수 있다는 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at recent estimated market shares and market conditions, this argument gains some weight. According to 'CoinGecko,' which shows estimated real-time trading volume by exchange, Upbit's market share (private estimate) as of January this year has decreased to 63.78%. Bithumb and Coinone have increased their market shares to 28.83% and 6.64%, respectively. Mirae Asset Group's push to acquire the fourth-largest exchange 'Korbit,' and the global exchange Binance's acquisition of the fifth-largest exchange 'Gopax' are also cited as changes supporting the possibility of market reorganization. (최근 추정 점유율과 시장 상황을 보면 이런 주장에 일정 부분 힘이 실린다. 거래소별 실시간 거래량을 추정해 보여주는 ‘코인게코’를 보면, 올해 1월 기준 업비트의 점유율(민간 추정)은 63.78%로 내려왔다. 빗썸과 코인원은 각각 28.83%, 6.64%까지 점유율을 끌어올렸다. 미래에셋그룹이 4위 거래소 ‘코빗’ 인수를 추진하고, 글로벌 거래소 바이낸스가 5위 거래소 ‘고팍스’를 품은 점 역시 시장 재편 가능성을 뒷받침하는 변화로 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is no small amount of skepticism about whether such changes can lead to structural competition. An exchange official said, "While there are evaluations that the market has entered a full-fledged competitive landscape as the market shares of the 2nd and 3rd place operators have risen, the mood is that the gap could widen again at any time if the top operator, Upbit, changes its strategy." They added, "There is also an interpretation that Upbit, conscious of monopoly controversy, is refraining from aggressive marketing and is intentionally managing the pursuit of latecomers." The research report also stated, "While it is not a market where competitive pressure has disappeared, as fee reductions/free events cause short-term market share changes," it noted that "due to strong network effects (the characteristic of platforms where demand concentrates as the number of users increases), there are fundamental limitations to changing the long-term structure through short-term price competition alone." (이런 변화가 구조적인 경쟁으로 이어질 수 있을지를 두고 회의적인 시각도 적지 않다. 한 거래소 관계자는 “2·3위 사업자 점유율이 올라오면서 본격적인 경쟁 구도로 진입했다는 평가도 나오지만, 1위 사업자인 업비트가 전략을 바꿀 경우 격차는 언제든 다시 벌어질 수 있다는 분위기”라며 “업비트가 독점 논란을 의식해 공격적인 마케팅을 자제하며 후발주자의 추격을 의도적으로 관리하고 있다는 해석도 나온다”고 말했다. 용역보고서 역시 “수수료 인하·무료 이벤트가 단기적으로 점유율 변화를 유발하는 등 경쟁 압력이 소멸된 시장은 아니”라면서도 “네트워크 효과(이용자가 많을수록 수요가 몰리는 플랫폼의 특성)가 강해 단기적 가격 경쟁만으로 장기적 구조를 바꾸는 것은 근본적으로 한계가 있다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, both ruling and opposition parties in the National Assembly are placing weight on revitalizing the virtual asset industry. However, until last year, the monopoly structure of the virtual asset trading market was a regular topic in parliamentary audits. The fact that the FSC and FTC recently elevated the exchange oligopoly issue as a policy agenda is also close to a follow-up measure in response to lawmakers' criticisms during the parliamentary audits. (현재 국회 여야 모두 가상자산 산업의 활성화에 무게를 두고 있지만, 지난해까지만 해도 가상자산 거래 시장의 독점 구조는 국정감사의 단골 주제였다. 금융위와 공정위가 최근 거래소의 독과점 문제를 정책 의제로 끌어올린 것도 국정감사 당시 의원들의 질타에 따른 후속 조처에 가깝다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, it is expected that the major shareholder stake limit will not be included in this second-stage bill. This is because the ruling Democratic Party of Korea decided on the 20th not to include the stake limit regulation in this legislative process. However, as the FSC has raised the issue, there is a possibility it could resurface if problems such as market structure solidification, large-scale hacking/security issues, or governance issues arise in the future. (다만 대주주 지분 제한은 이번 2단계 법안에 담기지 않을 전망이다. 여당인 더불어민주당이 지난 20일 지분 제한 규제를 이번 입법 과정에 포함하지 않기로 결정했기 때문이다. 하지만 금융위가 화두를 던진 만큼 향후 시장 구조의 고착화나 대규모 해킹 등 보안 문제, 지배구조 이슈가 불거질 경우 재부상할 가능성도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An expert who has long participated in discussions on virtual asset regulation said, "Virtual asset exchanges grew organically, but currently, they are closer to a licensed industry that operates after reporting/registration with the Financial Intelligence Unit (FIU). Given that they are already under public discipline, it is difficult to view stake limit regulations as unconstitutional." They added, "Considering the public nature of trading platforms, the necessity of stake limits within a certain range can be discussed." (오랜 기간 가상자산 규제 논의에 참여해온 전문가는 “가상자산 거래소는 자생적으로 성장하긴 했으나, 현재는 금융정보분석원(FIU)에 신고·등록을 거쳐 영업하는 인허가 산업에 가깝다. 이미 공적 규율 아래 들어와 있는 만큼, 지분 제한 규제를 위헌으로 보기는 어렵다”며 “거래 플랫폼으로서의 공공성을 고려하면 일정한 범위에서 지분 제한의 필요성을 논의해볼 수 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241471.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/738/443/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500707.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"It's hard to believe as is"... Declining informativeness of securities firm corporate analysis reports (“그대로 믿기 어렵겠네”…증권사 기업 분석 보고서 정보력 하락)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241476.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"It's hard to believe as is"... Declining informativeness of securities firm corporate analysis reports (“그대로 믿기 어렵겠네”…증권사 기업 분석 보고서 정보력 하락)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/696/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500760.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 서울 중구 우리은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 금융시장 지표들이 표시돼 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;An assessment has emerged that the distinctiveness and informativeness of corporate analysis reports provided by securities firms are increasingly declining, having little impact on investment returns. (증권사들이 제공하는 기업 분석 보고서의 변별력과 정보력이 갈수록 떨어져 투자 수익률에 별다른 영향을 끼치지 않는다는 평가가 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Capital Market Research Institute, in its recently published report 'Investment Value of Analyst Investment Opinions and Target Stock Prices' (Senior Research Fellow Kim Jun-seok), constructed portfolios based on investment opinions and target price consensus from approximately 700,000 listed company analysis reports published by domestic analysts from 2000 to 2024, analyzing whether the investment returns outperformed the market average. The analysis results showed that, on average, portfolios with high investment opinion and expected return consensus observed statistically significant excess returns. However, after 2013, excess returns dropped sharply, and their statistical significance disappeared. (자본시장연구원은 최근 발표한 ‘애널리스트 투자 의견과 목표 주가의 투자 가치’ 보고서(김준석 선임연구위원)에서 2000∼2024년 국내 애널리스트가 발표한 상장 기업 분석 보고서 약 70만 건의 투자 의견 및 목표 주가 컨센서스를 바탕으로 포트폴리오를 구성해 투자 수익률이 시장 평균을 웃돌았는지 분석했다. 분석 결과, 평균적으로 투자 의견과 예상 수익률 컨센서스가 높은 포트폴리오에서는 통계적으로 유의미한 초과 수익률이 관찰됐으나, 2013년 이후에는 초과 수익률이 급격하게 하락해 통계적 유의성이 사라지는 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particularly, even when portfolios were constructed with stocks that received positive evaluations, statistically significant negative (-) excess returns appeared during some periods after 2013. The report assessed that this means the investment value of investment opinion and expected return consensus has disappeared since 2013. (특히 긍정적인 평가를 받은 종목으로 포트폴리오를 구성했더라도 2013년 이후 일부 기간에서는 통계적으로 유의미한 음(-)의 초과 수익률이 나타나기도 했다. 이는 투자 의견과 예상 수익률 컨센서스의 투자 가치가 2013년 이후 소멸됐다는 의미라고 보고서는 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report cited the weakening distinctiveness of investment opinions and target prices as the background. The proportion of stocks with an investment opinion consensus of 'Buy' increased significantly from 38% before 2012 to 69% after 2013. The difference in investment opinion scores between the top and bottom consensus portfolios also decreased sharply from 1.12 before 2012 to 0.75 after 2013. The report explained, "This is a result of the deepening buy-side bias in investment opinions, suggesting that the optimistic bias in investment opinions and the resulting weakening distinctiveness may be the cause of the decline in investment value." (보고서는 그 배경으로 투자 의견과 목표 주가의 변별력 약화를 꼽았다. 투자 의견 컨센서스가 ‘매수’인 종목 비중은 2012년 이전에는 38%에서 2013년 이후 69%로 크게 증가했고, 컨센서스 최상위 및 최하위 포트폴리오의 투자 의견 점수 차이는 2012년 이전 1.12에서 2013년 이후 0.75로 대폭 줄어들었다. 보고서는 “이는 투자 의견의 매수 편향이 심화되면서 나타난 결과로, 투자 의견의 낙관적 편향과 이에 따른 변별력 약화가 투자 가치 하락의 원인일 가능성을 시사한다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The weakening of analysts' information power was also cited. As the legal risks associated with acquiring and producing corporate-related information increased, communication between analysts and companies shrank, which may have led to weakened information power. The report diagnosed, "The absence of analysts' proprietary information makes independent evaluation, especially negative evaluation, difficult and increases reliance on public information such as earnings disclosures. This can cause clustering of investment opinions or target prices, i.e., weakening distinctiveness," adding, "If the shrinking of information acquisition channels strengthens the incentive to build friendly relationships with companies, it can be a cause of optimistic bias." (애널리스트의 정보력 약화도 꼽았다. 기업 관련 정보의 취득과 생산에 따르는 법적 위험이 커지면서 애널리스트와 기업 간 소통이 위축됐고 이는 정보력 약화로 이어졌을 가능성이 있다는 것이다. 보고서는 “애널리스트 고유 정보의 부재는 독자적인 평가, 특히 부정적 평가를 어렵게 만들고 실적 공시와 같은 공적 정보에 대한 의존도를 높여 투자 의견이나 목표 주가의 군집화, 즉 변별력의 약화를 유발할 수 있다”며 “정보 취득 경로의 위축이 기업과의 우호적 관계를 구축하고자 하는 유인을 강화시킨다면 낙관적 편향의 원인이 될 수 있다”고 진단했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Research Fellow Kim Jun-seok stated, "This analysis raises concerns about the essential function and role of analysts as producers and intermediaries of information and as market monitors," and suggested, "Rather than contribution to securities firm profits, evaluation and compensation based on the objectivity, accuracy, and usefulness of predictions and assessments, strengthening the independence of the research division, and expanding disclosure of information quality and conflict-of-interest factors are necessary." (김준석 선임연구위원은 “이번 분석은 정보의 생산 및 중개자이자 시장의 감시자로서 애널리스트의 본질적 기능과 역할에 대한 우려를 낳는다”며 “증권사 수익에 대한 기여도보다는 예측과 평가의 객관성, 정확성, 유용성에 근거한 평가와 보상, 리서치 부문의 독립성 강화, 정보 품질과 이해상충 요소에 대한 정보 공개 확대 등이 필요하다”고 제언했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241476.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/696/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500760.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fair Trade Commission imposes 5 million won fine on KT over 'Galaxy S25 pre-order cancellation incident' (공정위, ‘갤럭시 S25 사전예약 취소 사태’ KT에 과태료 500만원)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241489.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Fair Trade Commission imposes 5 million won fine on KT over 'Galaxy S25 pre-order cancellation incident' (공정위, ‘갤럭시 S25 사전예약 취소 사태’ KT에 과태료 500만원)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500915.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 종로구 케이티(KT) 광화문 사옥 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;KT, which caused the Galaxy S25 pre-order cancellation incident, has been fined 5 million won. (갤럭시 에스(S)25 사전예약 취소 사태를 빚은 케이티(KT)가 과태료 500만원을 부과받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Fair Trade Commission announced on the 25th that it has issued a corrective order and imposed a 5 million won fine on KT for violating the Electronic Commerce Act. KT is accused of misleading consumers by advertising on the event page of its online mall (shop.kt.com) from January 24 to 25 last year, suggesting that all consumers who pre-ordered the Galaxy S25 series could purchase the product, despite there being a limit on the pre-order sales quantity. (공정거래위원회는 25일 케이티의 전자상거래법 위반행위에 시정명령과 과태료 500만원을 부과한다고 밝혔다. 케이티는 지난해 1월 24∼25일 온라인몰(shop.kt.com) 이벤트 페이지에서 갤럭시 에스25 시리즈의 사전예약 판매 물량에 제한이 있음에도 예약한 모든 소비자가 제품을 구매할 수 있는 것처럼 알린 혐의를 받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KT initially planned to accept 1,000 Galaxy S25 pre-orders through six channels. Of these, the planned quantity for acceptance through two channels, Genie TV and Allight Studio, was 400 units. However, the online mall event page linked to the banners posted on Genie TV and Allight Studio stated, 'For various first-come, first-served events, you can receive benefits unless there is a separate closing notice.' Later, when the number of applications exceeded the planned quantity, KT canceled 7,127 orders received through the banners, despite there being no separate closing notice. (케이티는 당초 6개 채널을 통해 갤럭시 에스25 사전예약 1000건을 접수할 계획이었다. 이 가운데 지니티브이와 오라잇스튜디오 두 곳을 통한 접수 계획 물량은 400건이었다. 하지만 지니티브이와 오라잇스튜디오에 게시한 배너와 연결된 온라인몰 이벤트 페이지에는 ‘각종 선착순 이벤트는 별도의 마감 표시가 없다면 혜택을 받아보실 수 있습니다’라고 안내했다. 이후 계획 물량을 초과하자 별도 마감 표시가 없었던 상황에서 배너를 통해 접수된 물량 중 7127건을 취소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KT sent a text message to customers whose pre-orders were accepted and then canceled on January 25 last year, explaining that the situation occurred because the notice 'limited to the first 1,000 people' was omitted. As compensation, they provided a 30,000 won Naver Pay voucher. Later, on February 20 last year, they additionally provided a one-year subscription to TVING Basic and Millie's Library, worth approximately 200,000 won. (케이티는 사전예약을 접수했다가 취소당한 고객들에게 지난해 1월25일 문자를 발송해 “‘선착순 1천명 한정’이라는 안내가 누락돼 발생한 상황”이라고 설명했다. 그러면서 네이버페이 3만원권을 보상으로 지급했다. 이후 지난해 2월20일에는 20만원 상당의 티빙 베이직과 밀리의 서재 1년 구독권을 추가 지급했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Fair Trade Commission stated, "Despite the planned acceptance quantity through Genie TV and Allight Studio being 400 units, KT displayed on the online mall event page that consumers who pre-ordered could purchase the product, leading consumers to misunderstand the product's supply conditions." They judged this as "an act of attracting consumers by providing false or exaggerated information or using deceptive methods." (공정위는 “케이티는 지니티브이와 오라잇스튜디오를 통한 접수 계획 물량이 400건임에도 온라인몰의 이벤트 페이지를 통해 예약한 경우 제품을 구매할 수 있는 것처럼 표시해 소비자로 하여금 제품의 공급 조건을 잘못 인식하게 했다”며 “거짓 또는 과장된 사실을 알리거나 기만적인 방법을 사용해 소비자를 유인하는 행위”라고 판단했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241489.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500915.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>National Tax Service Investigates 'Inheritance Tax Evasion' Bakery Cafes... "Tax Audits if Tax Evasion Suspected" (국세청, ‘상속세 회피용’ 베이커리카페 실태조사…“탈세 혐의 시 세무조사”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241491.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;National Tax Service Investigates 'Inheritance Tax Evasion' Bakery Cafes... "Tax Audits if Tax Evasion Suspected" (국세청, ‘상속세 회피용’ 베이커리카페 실태조사…“탈세 혐의 시 세무조사”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500913.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아 ※사진과 기사 내용은 관련 없음&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is launching a fact-finding investigation into large bakery cafes in the metropolitan area suspected of being used for 'inheritance tax evasion'. This follows President Lee Jae-myung's recent directive to check whether the large cafe/bakery sector is being utilized as a means for wealthy individuals to engage in illicit inheritance or gifting practices. The policy is to conduct tax audits if tax evasion suspicions are confirmed. (정부가 ‘상속세 회피용’ 의혹을 받는 수도권 대형 베이커리 카페에 대해 실태조사에 들어간다. 이재명 대통령이 최근 대형 카페·베이커리 업종이 부유층의 편법 상속이나 증여 수단으로 활용되고 있지 않은지 점검을 지시한 데 따른 것으로, 탈세 혐의가 확인되면 세무조사도 진행한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Tax Service (NTS) announced on the 25th that it will investigate the operational status of large bakery cafes in the Seoul and Gyeonggi area suspected of being used as a means to avoid inheritance tax. The targets are selected cafes based on factors like asset size, real estate proportion, and sales revenue. The NTS explained, "This is not a tax audit for tax collection, but a status check considering society's overall concerns about the abuse of the family business inheritance deduction system." (국세청은 서울·경기권 소재 대형 베이커리 카페 중 상속세 회피 수단으로 의심받는 곳들에 대해 운영실태를 조사한다고 25일 밝혔다. 조사 대상은 자산규모·부동산 비중·매출액 등을 고려한 일부 카페들로, 국세청은 “세금추징을 위한 세무조사가 아니라 가업상속공제 제도 악용에 대한 사회 전반의 우려를 감안한 현황 파악”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government suspects that the rapidly increasing number of large bakery cafes, particularly around the outskirts of Seoul, may be a loophole method for high-net-worth individuals to utilize the family business inheritance deduction. The family business inheritance deduction is a system that allows a deduction of up to 60 billion won from inherited assets when a small or medium-sized enterprise (SME) or mid-sized company, operated by the deceased for over 10 years, is passed on to an heir. It aims to prevent the closure or sale of long-standing businesses due to high inheritance tax burdens. Eligible business types include restaurants and bakeries, but coffee specialty shops are not included. (정부는 서울근교를 중심으로 급증하는 대형 베이커리 카페가 고액 자산가의 가업상속공제를 위한 편법 수단이 아닌지 의심하고 있다. 가업상속공제란 피상속인이 10년 이상 경영한 중소·중견기업을 상속인에게 승계한 경우 최대 600억원까지 상속재산에서 공제하는 제도다. 고액의 상속세 부담으로 장수기업을 폐업하거나 매각하는 사태를 방지하기 위한 것으로, 공제 대상 업종은 음식점·제과점 등이다. 커피전문점은 포함되지 않는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there are criticisms that a 'trick' is spreading among asset holders whose wealth is mostly in real estate. They formally open a bakery cafe (a bakery) and then pass it on to their children to receive inheritance tax exemption. For example, if parents owning land worth 30 billion won on the outskirts of Seoul inherit it to one child normally, they would have to pay about 13.6 billion won in inheritance tax. But if they open a large bakery cafe there, operate it for 10 years, and then pass it on to the child, the child can pay zero inheritance tax if they maintain the cafe for just 5 years, thanks to the family business inheritance deduction. President Lee had previously instructed at a senior secretary meeting on the 15th to inspect such cases and prepare countermeasures. (그러나 자산 대부분이 부동산인 자산가들 사이에서 형식적으로 베이커리카페(제과점)를 개업한 뒤 이를 자녀에게 물려주고 상속세를 면제받는 ‘꼼수’가 번지고 있다는 지적이 나온다. 가령 서울 근교에 300억원 상당의 토지를 보유한 부모가 이를 자녀 1명에게 상속할 경우 정상적이라면 136억원의 상속세를 내야 한다. 하지만 이곳에 대형 베이커리 카페를 개업하고 10년간 운영한 뒤 자녀에게 물려주면, 자녀는 5년만 카페를 유지할 경우 가업상속공제 덕에 상속세를 한푼도 내지 않아도 된다. 앞서 이 대통령은 지난 15일 수석보좌관회의에서 이런 사례에 대한 점검 및 대비책 마련을 지시한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NTS stated that in this fact-finding investigation, it will focus on: △Whether businesses registered as bakeries (an eligible business type for the deduction) are actually disguised coffee shops in operation; △Whether the business premises, extensive ancillary land, facilities, parking lots, etc., are indeed business assets included in the family business inheritance assets; △Whether the business is operating normally based on sales revenue or regular employee count relative to real estate asset value, sales/purchase records, and the actual business owner. It also said that for bakery cafes in corporate form eligible for special gift tax treatment upon business succession, it will examine whether the CEO is actually managing the business and their shareholding ratio. (국세청은 이번 실태조사에서 △가업상속공제 대상 업종인 제과점으로 사업자등록을 해놓고 사실상 커피전문점으로 위장 운영하는지 여부 △사업장 및 넓은 부수토지·시설·주차장 등이 가업상속재산에 포함되는 사업용 자산이 맞는지 여부 △부동산 자산가액 대비 매출액이나 상시 고용인원, 매출·매입 내역, 실제 사업주 등 정상적으로 운영되고 있는지 여부를 집중 조사하겠다고 밝혔다. 또 가업승계 증여세 특례를 적용받을 수 있는 법인형태의 베이커리카페의 경우에도 대표이사의 실제 경영 여부, 지분율 등을 살펴보겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NTS stated that based on the investigation results, it will strengthen pre- and post-verification of eligibility for the family business inheritance deduction and pursue system improvements. An NTS official said, "Applying the family business inheritance deduction to cases where a bakery cafe, whose assets are mostly just real estate, is opened and operated formally for the purpose of reducing inheritance tax before being passed on, goes against the original purpose of the deduction—which is to support the succession of know-how and technology of SMEs and mid-sized companies—and is against tax justice." They added, "During the status check, if suspicions of tax evasion such as gift of startup funds or lack of fund sources are confirmed, strict tax audits will be conducted according to separate plans." (국세청은 이번 조사결과를 바탕으로 가업상속공제 요건에 대한 사전·사후 검증을 강화하고 제도 개선을 추진한다고 밝혔다. 국세청 관계자는 “상속세를 줄일 목적으로 자산 대부분이 부동산뿐인 베이커리카페를 개업해 형식적으로 운영하다 승계하는 경우까지 가업상속공제를 적용하는 것은 중소·중견기업의 노하우와 기술 승계를 지원하는 가업상속공제 본래 취지에 어긋나고 조세정의에도 반한다”며 “현황 파악 중 창업자금 증여, 자금출처 부족 등 탈세 혐의가 확인되는 경우에는 별도 계획에 따라 엄정하게 세무조사를 실시할 예정”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241491.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125500913.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla Discontinues Standard Inclusion of Autopilot in North American Models... Requires Monthly FSD Subscription Fee of 140,000 Won (북미판 테슬라 오토파일럿 기본 제공 중단…월 14만원 FSD 구독료 내야)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1241496.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Tesla Discontinues Standard Inclusion of Autopilot in North American Models... Requires Monthly FSD Subscription Fee of 140,000 Won (북미판 테슬라 오토파일럿 기본 제공 중단…월 14만원 FSD 구독료 내야)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/580/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501068.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;테슬라 모델와이(Y). 테슬라 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As it became known that electric vehicle company Tesla will not provide the driving assistance system 'Autopilot' feature, which was previously offered for free, on new models sold in North America, attention is focused on whether this policy will also apply to domestic vehicles. (전기차 기업 테슬라가 기존에 무료로 제공했던 주행보조 시스템 ‘오토파일럿’ 기능을 북미 지역 신규 판매 모델에는 제공하지 않는다는 사실이 알려지면서, 국내 차량에도 이러한 정책이 적용될지 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to reports from American automotive technology media outlets like Electrek, Tesla recently removed the Autopilot feature from the standard options for Model 3 and Model Y sold in North America. Autopilot was a feature applied as a standard option to all vehicles Tesla sold from April 2019, consisting of 'Cruise Control,' which adjusts driving speed to match the speed of the vehicle ahead, and 'Autosteer,' which keeps the vehicle centered in its lane. Tesla has removed Autosteer from the standard specifications, meaning that to use this feature going forward, one must subscribe to the Full Self-Driving (FSD) service for a monthly fee of $99 (approximately 140,000 won). (미국 자동차 기술 전문 보도매체인 일렉트렉 등을 보면 테슬라는 최근 북미 지역에서 판매하는 모델3과 모델와이(Y)의 기본 옵션에서 오토파일럿 기능을 제외했다. 오토파일럿은 테슬라가 2019년 4월부터 판매한 모든 차량에 기본 옵션으로 적용한 기능으로, 전방의 차량 속도에 맞춰 주행 속도를 조절하는 ‘크루즈 컨트롤’ 기능과 차량을 차선 중앙에 유지하는 기능인 ‘오토스티어’로 구성됐다. 테슬라는 이 두 기능 가운데 오토스티어를 기본 표준 사양에서 제외했는데 앞으로 이 기능을 사용하려면 월 구독료 99달러(약 14만원)를 내고 감독형 완전자율주행기능(FSD·이하 에프에스디) 서비스를 구독해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analysis suggests that a decision by the California transportation authorities at the end of last year significantly influenced Tesla's move. According to the California Department of Motor Vehicles (DMV) website, an administrative law judge ruled in December last year that Tesla's advertising of the advanced driving assistance feature Autopilot using terms like "full self-driving capability" and "autonomous" was false advertising that did not match reality. The judge stated that if Tesla did not correct the advertising within 60 days, its manufacturing and sales license would be suspended for 30 days. (테슬라의 이러한 결정에는 지난해 말 캘리포니아주 교통 당국의 결정이 큰 영향을 미쳤다는 분석이 나온다. 캘리포니아 교통관리국(DMV) 누리집을 보면, 주 행정판사가 지난해 12월 테슬라가 첨단주행보조기능인 오토파일럿을 광고하면서 “완전자율주행 능력”, “자동운항”이라는 단어를 사용한 것은 사실과 다른 허위 광고라고 판단하면서 테슬라가 해당 광고를 60일 이내 시정하지 않으면 제조·판매 면허를 30일간 정지한다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By deleting the name 'Autopilot' (self-driving) itself, which government authorities took issue with, and integrating all features related to autonomous driving into the paid subscription product called Supervised FSD, Tesla appears to be implementing corrective measures while also restructuring its revenue model. Elon Musk, Tesla's CEO, shared the news about the removal of the Autopilot feature in a post on X (formerly Twitter) on the 23rd (local time), stating, "The $99 monthly fee for Supervised FSD will inevitably have to increase as the functionality improves." (정부 당국이 문제 삼은 ‘오토파일럿’(자율주행)이라는 명칭 자체를 삭제하고, 모든 자율 운행과 관련된 기능을 감독형 에프에스디라는 유료 구독 상품에 통합함으로써 테슬라는 시정조치를 이행하는 동시에 수익 모델을 개편할 것으로 보인다. 일론 머스크 테슬라 최고경영자(CEO)는 23일(현지시각) 자신의 엑스(X) 게시글에서 오토파일럿 기능 제외 소식을 공유하면서 “감독형 에프에스디의 월 구독료 99달러는 그 기능이 개선됨에 따라 인상될 수 밖에 없을 것”이라고 말하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Tesla vehicles sold in the Korean market still include the Autopilot feature as a standard option, the possibility that it will be removed from standard options following the changes in North America is high, drawing consumer interest. If lane-keeping assistance, a feature that global automakers including Hyundai and Kia provide as standard, becomes part of FSD and a paid option, consumer burden is bound to increase. (한국 시장에서 판매하는 테슬라 차량에는 여전히 오토파일럿 기능이 기본 옵션으로 포함되고 있지만, 북미 지역의 변화를 따라 기본 옵션에서 제외될 가능성이 커 소비자들의 관심이 쏠린다. 현대차·기아를 비롯한 글로벌 자동차 업계가 기본적으로 제공하고 있는 차선 유지 기능이 에프에스디에 포함돼 유료 옵션이 되면 소비자들의 부담이 커질 수 밖에 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Musk announced, "Tesla will discontinue the one-time payment sale of FSD after February 14th, and from then on, it will only be available via monthly subscription." Until now, consumers could use the self-driving feature by either paying $8,000 (approximately 11.8 million won) upfront when purchasing a Tesla car or by paying a subscription fee starting at $99 (approximately 140,000 won) per month. The company has now announced it will operate solely on a monthly subscription basis. The automotive industry views this change in Tesla's self-driving feature policy as an effort to enhance consumer interest and improve business performance. (앞서 머스크는 “테슬라는 2월14일 이후 에프에스디 일시불 판매를 중단하고, 이후부터 월간 구독제로만 이용할 수 있게 된다”고 밝혔다. 지금까지 소비자는 테슬라 자동차를 구입할 때 8천달러(약 1180만원)를 한번에 내거나 매월 99달러(약 14만원)부터 시작하는 구독료를 내고 자율주행기능을 이용할 수 있었는데 월 구독제로만 운영하겠다고 공지한 것이다. 자동차 업계는 테슬라의 이러한 자율주행기능 정책 변화에 대해 소비자들의 관심을 제고하고, 경영 실적을 개선하려는 노력으로 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Jae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이재호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1241496.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/580/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501068.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Expectations for 'Won-Dollar Rate Rise' Wane... Companies Reduce Dollar Holdings, While Retail Investors' Dollar Purchases Remain Steady (한풀 꺾인 ‘환율 상승’ 기대…달러 잔고 줄인 기업들, ‘서학개미’ 환전은 여전)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241500.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Expectations for 'Won-Dollar Rate Rise' Wane... Companies Reduce Dollar Holdings, While Retail Investors' Dollar Purchases Remain Steady (한풀 꺾인 ‘환율 상승’ 기대…달러 잔고 줄인 기업들, ‘서학개미’ 환전은 여전)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501113.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Expectations for a rise in the won-dollar exchange rate appear to have somewhat weakened this month, as evidenced by a significant decrease in dollar deposit balances at commercial banks. On the other hand, demand pressure for dollars remains due to a sharp resurgence in individual investments in U.S. stocks. (이달 들어 시중은행의 달러 예금 잔액이 크게 감소하는 등 환율 상승 기대가 다소 약해진 것으로 나타났다. 반면, 개인들의 미국 주식 투자가 다시 급증세여서 달러 수요 압력은 여전한 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to banking sector tallies on the 25th, as of the 22nd, the dollar deposit balance at the five major banks (KB Kookmin, Shinhan, Hana, Woori, NH Nonghyup) stood at $63.20483 billion, a decrease of $2.47674 billion (3.8%) compared to the end of last month ($65.68157 billion). Dollar deposits fluctuate based on corporate needs for export/import payment settlements or overseas investment/remittances. Typically, when the won strengthens (dollar weakens), they tend to decrease as companies seek to avoid foreign exchange losses or realize gains. (25일 은행권 집계를 보면, 지난 22일 기준 5대 은행(국민·신한·하나·우리·농협)의 달러 예금 잔액은 632억483만달러로 지난달 말(656억8157만달러)보다 24억7674만달러(3.8%) 감소했다. 달러 예금은 기업의 수출·수입 대금 입출금이나 해외 투자·송금 수요에 따라 증감하는데, 통상 환율이 내려갈 때(달러 약세)는 환손실을 피하거나 차익실현을 위해 감소하는 양상을 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dollar deposit balance had surged for two consecutive months in November and December last year when the won-dollar rate began to rise sharply, but turned to a decrease this month. Notably, corporate deposit balances, which constitute the majority of total dollar deposits, decreased significantly. Corporate dollar deposit balances had increased substantially by $2.24 billion in November and $5.84 billion in December last year, but decreased by $2.58 billion from the beginning of this month through the 22nd. Individual dollar deposit balances have increased for six consecutive months from August last year through this month, but the rate of increase has shrunk considerably. Individual balances increased by $106.4 million from the beginning of this month through the 22nd, which is only about one-tenth of the increase ($1.09871 billion) seen during the entire previous month. This appears to be the result of a combination of factors: authorities' recommendations for dollar spot sales to resolve foreign exchange supply-demand imbalances and the perception that the exchange rate has neared its peak. (달러 예금 잔액은 원-달러 환율이 가파르게 오르기 시작한 지난해 11·12월 두 달 연속 급증하다 이달 들어 감소 전환했다. 특히 전체 달러 예금의 대부분인 기업 예금 잔액이 많이 줄었다. 기업들의 달러 예금 잔액은 지난해 11월(22억4천만달러)과 12월(58억4천만달러) 크게 늘었는데 이달 들어 22일까지는 25억8천만달러 감소했다. 개인들의 달러 예금 잔액은 지난해 8월부터 이달까지 6개월 연속 늘었으나 증가 폭이 크게 축소됐다. 개인 잔액은 이달 들어 22일까지 1억964만달러 늘었는데, 지난달 한 달 동안 증가액(10억9871만달러)에 견줘 10분의 1 수준이다. 외환 수급 불균형 해소를 위한 당국의 달러 현물 매도 권고와 함께 환율이 고점 부근에 다다랐다는 인식이 복합적으로 작용한 결과로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, demand pressure for dollar conversion persists due to the influence of U.S. stock investments. According to Korea Securities Depository statistics, from the beginning of this month through the 23rd, the net purchase amount of U.S. stocks by domestic individuals was $3.917 billion (approximately 5.72 trillion won), more than double the net purchase amount ($1.87 billion) for the entire previous month. Individual investment in U.S. stocks, which had paused briefly last month, is surging again, acting as a source of domestic dollar conversion demand and upward pressure on the exchange rate. (반면, 미국 주식 투자 영향으로 달러 환전 수요 압력은 지속되고 있다. 한국예탁결제원 집계를 보면, 이달 들어 23일까지 국내 개인의 미국 주식 순매수액은 39억1700만달러(약 5조7200억원)로, 지난달 한달 간 순매수액(18억7000만달러)보다 두 배 이상 늘었다. 개인의 미국 주식 투자는 지난달 잠시 주춤했다 다시 급증세인데, 국내 달러 환전 수요와 환율 상승 압력으로 작용한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individual sentiment to buy dollars also remains strong. The amount converted from won to dollars (cash basis) by individuals at the five major banks from the beginning of this month through the 22nd totaled $363.82 million. The daily average conversion amount during this period was $16.54 million, still about 50% higher than last year's daily average ($10.18 million). However, the amount converted from dollars to won during the same period also surged to a daily average of $5.2 million, significantly exceeding last year's daily average ($3.78 million). This is interpreted as an increase in dollar sales for profit-taking due to the perception that the won-dollar rate is near its peak. (개인의 달러 매수 심리도 여전히 강한 편이다. 5대 은행에서 개인이 원화를 달러로 환전(현찰 기준)한 금액은 이달 들어 22일까지 3억6382만달러로 집계됐다. 이 기간 일평균 환전액은 1654만달러로 여전히 지난해 일평균 환전액(1018만달러) 보다 50%가량 많은 것이다. 다만, 같은 기간 달러를 원화로 환전한 금액도 일평균 520만달러로 지난해 일평균 환전액(378만달러)을 큰 폭 웃돌았다. 원-달러 환율 고점 심리로 차익실현을 위한 달러 매도 역시 늘어난 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commercial banks have been significantly lowering interest rates on foreign currency deposits this month following government recommendations. Shinhan Bank will lower the pre-tax interest rates on dollar and euro deposits from the current 1.5% and 0.75% per annum, respectively, to 0.1% and 0.02% starting on the 30th. This is effectively almost no interest. Hana Bank also plans to lower its dollar deposit interest rate from the current 2.0% per annum to 0.05% starting on the 30th. Previously, Woori Bank lowered its dollar interest rate from 1.0% to 0.1%, one-tenth of the previous rate. An official from Hana Bank stated, "From the perspective of financial consumer protection, we plan to refrain as much as possible from offering preferential exchange rates or excessive events." The intent is to help supply dollars to the domestic foreign exchange market by reducing incentives for dollar deposits. (시중은행들은 이달 들어 정부 권고에 따라 외화예금에 주는 이자를 크게 낮추고 있다. 신한은행은 현재 달러와 유로화 예금에 연 1.5%, 0.75%씩 주던 이자(세전)를 30일부터 0.1%, 0.02%로 낮춘다. 거의 이자가 붙지 않는 셈이다. 하나은행 역시 30일부터 달러 예금 이자율을 현행 연 2.0%에서 0.05%로 내릴 예정이다. 앞서 우리은행은 달러 금리를 1.0%에서 10분의 1 수준인 0.1%로 인하했다. 하나은행 관계자는 “금융소비자 보호 차원에서 환율 우대나 과도한 이벤트 등을 최대한 자제할 계획”이라고 밝혔다. 달러 예금 유인을 줄여 국내 외환시장 달러 공급에 도움을 주자는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241500.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501113.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Amid Stock Market Boom and Interest Rate Burden... Over 24 Trillion Won Flees Bank Demand Deposits This Year (증시 호조·금리 부담에…올해 들어 은행 요구불예금  24조원 이탈)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241507.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Amid Stock Market Boom and Interest Rate Burden... Over 24 Trillion Won Flees Bank Demand Deposits This Year (증시 호조·금리 부담에…올해 들어 은행 요구불예금  24조원 이탈)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/510/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501187.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 23일 오전 서울 중구 우리은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year, demand deposits at the five major commercial banks have decreased by over 24 trillion won. Time deposits also fell by 2.7 trillion won, and time installment savings have also turned to a decline. Analysis suggests that the outflow of funds from bank deposits continues, driven by an increase in short-term investment products that serve as alternatives to bank deposits amid a strong stock market, coupled with rising loan interest rates increasing household burdens. (올해 들어 5대 시중은행의 요구불예금이 24조원 넘게 줄었다. 정기예금은 2조7천억원 감소했고, 정기적금도 감소세로 돌아섰다. 주식시장이 강세를 보이는 가운데 은행 예금을 대체할 단기 투자상품이 늘어난 데다 대출 금리 상승으로 가계 부담이 커지면서 은행 예금에서 자금이 빠져나가는 흐름이 이어지고 있다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the financial sector on the 25th, the balance of demand deposits at the five major banks—KB Kookmin, Shinhan, Hana, Woori, and NH Nonghyup—stood at 649.654 trillion won as of the 22nd of this month, a sharp decrease of 24.3544 trillion won compared to the end of last year. After a decrease of 21.8674 trillion won at the end of October last year, deposits increased by 1.8968 trillion won and 24.2552 trillion won in November and December respectively, but after three months, they have returned to a sharp decline. (25일 금융권에 따르면 국민·신한·하나·우리·농협 등 5대 은행의 요구불예금 잔액은 이달 22일 기준 649조6540억원으로, 지난해 말보다 24조3544억원 급감했다. 지난해 10월 말 21조8674억원이 줄어든 이후 11월과 12월에 각각 1조8968억원, 24조2552억원씩 늘었지만, 3개월 만에 다시 큰 폭의 감소세로 돌아선 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this declining trend continues until the end of the month, the scale of the decrease in demand deposits is highly likely to reach its highest level in a year and six months since July 2024 (29.1395 trillion won). Demand deposits are largely characterized as idle funds seeking investment destinations and are considered a key indicator for gauging fund flow trends within the banking sector. (이 같은 감소 추세가 월말까지 이어질 경우 요구불예금 감소 폭은 2024년 7월(29조1395억원) 이후 1년6개월 만에 최대 수준을 기록할 가능성이 크다. 요구불예금은 투자처를 찾지 못한 대기성 자금 성격이 강해, 은행권 자금 이동 흐름을 가늠하는 대표적인 지표로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Outflows are also continuing from time deposits. As of the 22nd of this month, the balance of time deposits at the five major banks decreased by 2.7624 trillion won. Compared to the previous month's decrease of 32.7034 trillion won, the outflow has significantly narrowed, but this marks two consecutive months of decline. The balance of time installment savings also decreased by 57.5 billion won, shifting to a decline. (정기예금에서도 자금 이탈이 이어지고 있다. 이달 22일까지 5대 은행의 정기예금 잔액은 2조7624억원 줄었다. 전월에 32조7034억원 줄어든 것과 비교하면 유출 폭은 크게 줄었지만, 두 달 연속 감소세다. 정기적금 잔액도 575억원 줄며 감소세로 전환했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The financial sector views that funds exiting bank deposits have moved to investment products with relatively higher yields. Recently, the KOSPI index has continued its bullish trend, fluctuating above the 5,000 level during trading hours, leading to sustained fund inflows. It is also estimated that funds have moved to securities firms' short-term financial products, such as Integrated Investment Accounts (IMA) and Comprehensive Asset Management Accounts (CMA), which offer expected returns higher than deposit interest. The recent rise in loan interest rates, increasing household interest burdens, is also cited as a factor contributing to the deposit decline. (금융권에서는 은행 예금에서 빠져나간 자금이 상대적으로 수익률이 높은 투자상품으로 이동한 것으로 보고 있다. 최근 코스피지수는 장중 5000선을 넘나드는 등 강세 흐름을 이어가며 자금 유입이 이어지고 있다. 종합투자계좌(IMA), 종합자산관리계좌(CMA) 등 예금 이자보다 높은 수익률을 기대할 수 있는 증권사의 단기 금융상품으로도 자금이 이동한 것으로 추정된다. 최근 대출 금리 상승으로 가계의 이자 부담이 커진 점도 예금 감소의 한 요인으로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Hyung-jung, an analyst at Woori Bank, said, "Bank deposits are flowing out as the stock market trend is relatively favorable and securities firms' products that replace deposits are becoming more diverse." He further explained, "There is also a possibility that the demand for deposit withdrawals was high due to increased household financial burdens from rising loan interest rates." (박형중 우리은행 애널리스트는 “증시 흐름이 비교적 양호한 데다 예금을 대체하는 증권사 상품이 다양해지면서 은행 예금이 빠져나가고 있다”고 말했다. 또 그는 “대출 금리 상승으로 가계의 자금 부담이 커지며 예금 인출 수요가 컸을 가능성도 있다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241507.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/510/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501187.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI Boom Brings Strong Performance to Electronic Component Industry... High Expectations for Automotive Electronics as Well (AI 열풍에 전자 부품 업계도 호실적…차량용 전장도 실적 기대감)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241511.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;AI Boom Brings Strong Performance to Electronic Component Industry... High Expectations for Automotive Electronics as Well (AI 열풍에 전자 부품 업계도 호실적…차량용 전장도 실적 기대감)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/400/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501297.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As investments in AI-related data centers and servers expand, a boom is anticipated not only for semiconductors but also for companies producing related components. Thanks to AI, demand is increasing for products ranging from semiconductors to automotive electronics, and companies manufacturing the necessary parts and sensors for these are also benefiting. (인공지능(AI) 관련 데이터센터·서버 등 투자가 확대되며 반도체는 물론, 관련 부품을 생산하는 회사들에게도 활황이 기대되고 있다. 인공지능 덕택에 반도체부터 자동차용 전장 제품 수요가 늘고, 여기에 필요한 부품과 센서 등을 만드는 회사들도 수혜를 보게 된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samsung Electro-Mechanics announced on the 23rd that its sales for the fourth quarter of last year were 2.9021 trillion won, with an operating profit of 239.5 billion won. Compared to the same period a year earlier, these figures increased by 16% and 108%, respectively. On an annual basis, sales reached 11.3145 trillion won, a record high, and operating profit was 913.3 billion won, the third highest since the IT industry boom period (2021-2022) during the COVID-19 pandemic. (삼성전기는 지난 23일 지난해 4분기 매출액이 2조9021억원, 영업이익은 2395억원을 기록했다고 밝혔다. 1년 전 같은 기간에 견줘 각각 16%, 108% 늘었다. 연간 기준 매출액은 11조3145억원으로 역대 최대치였고, 영업이익은 9133억원으로 코로나19 대유행으로 인한 정보기술(IT) 업계 호황 시기(2021∼2022년) 이후 세 번째로 높았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Samsung Electro-Mechanics produces components such as Multi-Layer Ceramic Capacitors (MLCCs) and package substrates used in semiconductors. Demand for these components rises with the AI investment boom. This is because AI servers and semiconductors require more MLCCs to perform more computations, and package substrates are also essential. In other words, the AI craze has boosted the performance of component companies. (삼성전기는 반도체에 들어가는 적층세라믹콘덴서(MLCC), 패키지 기판 등 부품을 만든다. 이 부품들은 인공지능 투자 활황세에 수요가 높아진다. 인공지능 서버와 반도체는 보다 많은 연산을 수행하기 때문에 더 많은 엠엘시시가 필요하며, 패키지 기판도 필수로 들어가기 때문이다. 즉 인공지능 열풍이 부품사의 실적을 끌어올린 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LG Innotek, which is scheduled to announce its earnings on the 26th, is another component company expected to benefit from AI. LG Innotek, like Samsung Electro-Mechanics, manufactures semiconductor substrates, optical solutions such as camera sensors, and automotive electronics components like autonomous driving sensors. (26일 실적 발표가 예정된 엘지(LG)이노텍 역시 인공지능 수혜가 기대되는 부품 기업이다. 엘지이노텍은 삼성전기처럼 반도체 기판을 만들고, 카메라용 센서와 같은 광학 솔루션, 자율주행 센서 등 자동차용 전장 부품을 제조한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a key supplier of camera sensors to Apple, this company's growth is anticipated not only due to the special features of the 'iPhone 17' launched this year but also because of increasing demand for software-centric vehicles and autonomous driving enabled by AI. The consensus estimate for fourth-quarter operating profit compiled by financial information provider FnGuide on the 25th is 203.7 billion won, which is expected to be about double the figure from the same period a year earlier (103.4 billion won). (이 회사는 애플에 카메라 센서를 납품하는 주요 고객사로 올해 출시한 ‘아이폰17’ 특수에 더해, 인공지능을 통한 소프트웨어 중심 차량, 자율주행 수요가 늘어남에 따라 성장세가 기대된다. 25일 금융정보업체 에프앤가이드가 취합한 4분기 영업이익 예상치(컨센서스)는 2037억원으로, 1년 전 같은 기간(1034억원)보다 2배가량 늘어날 것으로 전망됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of various parts and materials companies seeing improved performance thanks to AI are also noticeable overseas. On the 22nd (local time), Bloomberg reported on the Japanese company TOTO, which makes toilets and bidets, stating it "could benefit from the memory shortage era." This is because the ceramics TOTO uses in toilet manufacturing are also used to secure the 'wafers' that are the base material for semiconductors. (인공지능 덕택에 각종 부품·소재기업들의 실적이 빛을 보는 사례는 해외에서도 눈에 띈다. 지난 22일(현지시각) 블룸버그는 변기와 비데 등을 만드는 일본 회사 토토(TOTO)에 대해 “메모리 부족 시대 수혜를 볼 수 있다”고 보도했다. 토토가 변기 제조에 사용하는 세라믹이 반도체의 원판인 ‘웨이퍼’를 고정하는 데에도 쓰이기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bloomberg also pointed out that "Ajinomoto," which makes seasonings, is attracting attention for its semiconductor insulating film material made using amino acids, and "Kao," which produces daily necessities like soap and facial cleansers, is also drawing interest for its semiconductor wafer cleaning materials." The astronomical investment boom in the AI field is leading to a shortage of memory semiconductors, expanding market demand not only to traditional related component companies but also into areas that were difficult to predict. (블룸버그는 “조미료를 만드는 ‘아지노모도’가 아미노산을 활용해 만든 반도체 절연막 소재, 비누와 세안제 등 생활용품을 만드는 ‘카오’의 반도체 웨이퍼 세척 소재도 관심을 받고 있다”고 짚었다. 인공지능 분야에 대한 천문학적인 투자 붐으로 메모리 반도체 품귀 현상까지 빚어지면서, 전통적인 관련 부품 업체는 물론, 쉽게 예상하기 어려웠던 영역으로도 시장 수요가 확대되는 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241511.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/400/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501297.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Smartphones, Glasses, Speakers, Pins?... The 'Form Factor War' of Next-Generation AI Devices (핸드폰 다음은 안경·스피커·핀?…차세대 AI 기기의 ‘폼팩터 전쟁’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241514.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;After Smartphones, Glasses, Speakers, Pins?... The 'Form Factor War' of Next-Generation AI Devices (핸드폰 다음은 안경·스피커·핀?…차세대 AI 기기의 ‘폼팩터 전쟁’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/547/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501371.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;메타 레이밴 디스플레이. 메타 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Various forms of devices are gaining attention in the race for next-generation artificial intelligence (AI) hardware. With the rise of generative AI, useful glasses and speakers are seeing increased interest, along with a pin-shaped wearable device reportedly under development by Apple, and OpenAI's hardware, whose form remains unknown, sparking curiosity. (차세대 인공지능(AI) 하드웨어를 놓고 다양한 형태의 기기들이 주목 받고 있다. 생성형 인공지능이 부상하며 유용성 높아진 안경과 스피커부터 애플이 개발하는 것으로 알려진 ‘핀’ 형태의 웨어러블 기기, 아직 형태가 알려지지 않아 궁금증을 유발하고 있는 오픈에이아이의 하드웨어에도 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Demis Hassabis, CEO of Google DeepMind and known as the 'father of AlphaGo', pointed to glasses as the next form factor (a term referring to a product's physical specifications). In an interview with the Big Technology podcast on the 21st (local time) at the World Economic Forum (WEF) in Davos, Switzerland, he said, "I can't say for sure that glasses are the final form factor, but at this point where AI has become good enough, it's a very natural next step." (‘알파고의 아버지’ 데미스 허사비스 구글 딥마인드 최고경영자(CEO)는 차기 폼팩터(제품의 물리적 규격을 이르는 말)로 안경을 꼽았다. 그는 지난 21일(현지시각) 스위스 다보스에서 진행되고 있는 세계경제포럼(WEF) 현장에서 이뤄진 빅테크놀로지 팟캐스트와의 인터뷰에서 “안경이 최종적인 폼팩터라고 확신할 순 없지만, 지금처럼 인공지능이 충분히 좋아진 시점에서는 다음 단계로 매우 자연스러운 선택이다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glasses are not a recently emerged form factor. Google launched 'Google Glass' back in 2013. However, it failed to become an item used in daily life. Not only did its appearance differ significantly from everyday glasses and it had a short battery life of around 3 to 5 hours, but there was simply nothing compelling enough to do with glasses, eliminating the need to wear them. CEO Hassabis stated, "Back then, above all, there was no killer use case." (안경이 최근 등장한 폼팩터는 아니다. 구글은 지난 2013년 ‘구글 글래스’를 출시한 바 있다. 다만 실생활에 사용되는 물건이 되진 못했다. 일상적으로 착용하는 안경과 동떨어진 외형은 물론 3~5시간 정도의 짧은 배터리 시간도 문제였지만, 안경으로 할 수 있는 것이 딱히 없어 안경을 쓸 필요 자체가 없었다. 허사비스 최고경영자는 “당시엔 무엇보다 중요한 사용 사례가 없었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, with the rapid advancement of AI, glasses are being highlighted as a representative form of AI devices. Meta is currently leading the market. Meta is collaborating with the sunglasses brand 'Ray-Ban' to release various forms of AI glasses. Meta's AI glasses, which take the form of horn-rimmed glasses or sunglasses, not only allow users to view information with AI through built-in cameras but also hear answers via speakers embedded in the frames. The 'Meta Ray-Ban Display', unveiled last September, even inserted a display within the lenses, enabling users to see responses with their eyes. Google also announced plans to re-enter the augmented reality headset and glasses market by unveiling its Android XR platform in May last year. (인공지능의 비약적 발전한 지금 안경은 인공지능 기기의 대표적인 형태로 손꼽히고 있다. 시장에서 가장 앞서있는 것은 메타다. 메타는 선글라스 브랜드인 ‘레이밴’과 협업해 다양한 형태의 인공지능 안경을 내놓고 있다. 뿔테안경이나 선글라스의 형태를 취하고 있는 메타의 인공지능 안경은 내장된 카메라로 인공지능과 함께 정보를 볼 수 있을 뿐 아니라 프레임에 내장된 스피커로 답을 들을 수 있다. 지난해 9월 공개된 ‘메타 레이밴 디스플레이’의 경우엔 렌즈 내 디스플레이를 삽입해 눈으로 답변을 볼 수도 있다. 구글도 지난해 5월 안드로이드 엑스알(XR)이라는 플랫폼을 공개하며 증강현실 헤드셋과 안경 시장에 재진입하겠다는 계획을 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI speakers, which gained attention with Amazon's 'Alexa' in 2014, are also drawing interest again. In South Korea, Naver and Kakao each released AI speakers in 2017. At the time, AI was merely a voice control device capable of simple tasks like playing music or providing weather updates, resulting in low utility. As AI performance has improved, speakers, positioned as the center of smart homes in various household environments, are now expected to have broader applications. (2014년 아마존의 ‘알렉사’로 주목받았던 인공지능 스피커에도 다시 관심이 쏠린다. 국내에서도 2017년 네이버와 카카오가 각각 인공지능 스피커를 내놓은 바 있다. 당시 인공지능은 음악 재생이나 날씨 안내 등 단순작업 위주로 수행하는 음성 제어 장치 수준에 불과해 활용도가 낮았다. 인공지능의 성능이 올라간 만큼 가정 내 다양한 환경에서 스마트홈의 중심이 스피커 역시 더 폭넓은 활용도를 기대할 수 있게 된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the unveiling of its generative AI-based 'Alexa Plus' early last year, Amazon launched a new Echo speaker series in the second half of the year equipped with its own chip capable of running AI models. Google has also introduced 'Gemini for Home', promoted as a next-generation home assistant, and plans to release a new Google Home speaker capable of running Gemini this spring. CEO Hassabis said, "Rather than Google betting on one specific device, the key is making AI work in every meaningful environment." (아마존은 지난해 초 생성형 인공지능 기반인 ‘알렉사 플러스’를 공개한 데 이어, 하반기에는 자체개발한 칩을 탑재해 인공지능 모델을 구동할 수 있는 새로운 에코 스피커 시리즈도 출시했다. 구글도 차세대 가정 도우미를 내세우는 ‘제미나이 포 홈’을 소개한 바 있으며, 올 봄 제미나이를 구동할 수 있는 새로운 구글 홈 스피커도 출시할 예정이다. 허사비스 최고경영자는 “구글이 특정 하나의 기기에 베팅하기보단 인공지능이 의미 있는 모든 환경에서 작동하도록 만드는 것이 핵심”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, OpenAI's AI device, which opened the era of generative AI with ChatGPT, is expected to launch in the second half of this year, but its form remains shrouded in secrecy. According to various foreign media reports, it is likely to be a small device without a screen. Apple is also reportedly developing a coin-sized, AI-based pin-shaped device. (한편 챗지피티로 생성형 인공지능 시대를 연 오픈에이아이의 인공지능 기기는 올 하반기 출시가 예상되지만 아직도 형태는 베일에 싸여있다. 여러 외신 보도에 따르면 스크린이 없는 소형 기기일 가능성이 높다. 애플도 동전 크기인 인공지능 기반 핀 형태의 기기를 개발 중이라고 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Chae Ban-seok, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241514.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/547/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501371.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Civic Groups: "U.S. Political and Business Circles Turn Blind Eye to Coupang's Illegal Acts and Interfere in Internal Affairs" (시민단체 “미국 정·재계 쿠팡 불법 외면한 채 내정 간섭”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241516.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Civic Groups: "U.S. Political and Business Circles Turn Blind Eye to Coupang's Illegal Acts and Interfere in Internal Affairs" (시민단체 “미국 정·재계 쿠팡 불법 외면한 채 내정 간섭”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/642/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501397.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 23일 서울 광화문 광장 미국대사관 앞에서 안전한 쿠팡 만들기 공동행동 등 시민사회단체 회원들이 ‘불법기업 쿠팡 비호, 내정간섭 일삼는 미국 정·재계 규탄 긴급기자회견’을 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attention is focused on whether the 'Talpang' (exiting Coupang) trend will reignite, as it has been revealed that two U.S. investors in Coupang submitted a notice of intent for an Investor-State Dispute Settlement (ISDS) arbitration against the Korean government and requested an investigation by the U.S. Trade Representative (USTR). Domestic civil society groups are strongly protesting, viewing this as an 'infringement of sovereignty'. (쿠팡의 미국 투자사 2곳이 한국 정부를 상대로 국제투자분쟁(ISDS) 중재 의향서를 제출하고, 미 무역대표부(USTR)에 조사를 요청한 사실이 알려지면서 ‘탈팡’(쿠팡 탈퇴) 흐름이 재점화할지 주목된다. 국내 시민사회단체들은 이를 ‘주권 침해’로 판단하고 강하게 반발하는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'Joint Action for a Safe Coupang', comprised of 135 civil society groups, and the Online Platform Legislation Solidarity held an emergency press conference in front of the U.S. Embassy in Jongno-gu, Seoul on the 23rd, criticizing that "U.S. political and business circles are turning a blind eye to Coupang's illegal acts and recklessly interfering in internal affairs." The Korea Federation of Small and Medium Business and Self-Employed, which issued a statement on the same day, also urged, "Coupang must stop its cowardly behavior of hiding behind U.S. political circles to pressure the government and apologize to the public for its exploitation and illegal acts against small business owners and the self-employed." (135개 시민사회단체가 모인 ‘안전한 쿠팡 만들기 공동행동’과 온라인플랫폼 제정연대는 지난 23일 서울 종로구 미국 대사관 앞에서 긴급 기자회견을 열고 “미국의 정·재계가 쿠팡의 불법 행위는 외면하고 내정 간섭을 함부로 하고 있다”고 비판했다. 같은 날 성명을 낸 한국중소상인자영업자총연합회도 “쿠팡은 미국 정치권 뒤에 숨어 정부를 압박하는 비겁한 행태를 멈추고 소상공인·자영업자에 대한 수탈과 불법 행위에 대해 국민 앞에 사죄하라”고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This backlash follows the submission of a notice of intent for ISDS arbitration against the Korean government by Greenoaks and Altimeter, investors in Coupang, on the 22nd (local time). The two companies claim that after Coupang's massive personal data leak last year, the Korean government and National Assembly violated the Korea-U.S. Free Trade Agreement (FTA) by pressuring Coupang on all fronts, causing billions of dollars in damages. They are also separately proceeding with a petition to the U.S. Trade Representative, requesting an investigation into the Korean government and trade protection measures. (이 같은 반발은 앞서 22일(현지시각) 쿠팡의 투자사인 그린옥스와 알티미터가 한국 정부에 국제투자분쟁 중재의향서를 제출한 데 따른 것이다. 두 회사는 지난해 쿠팡의 대규모 개인정보 유출 사고 이후, 한국 정부와 국회가 한-미 자유무역협정(FTA)을 위반하며 쿠팡을 전방위적으로 압박해 수십억달러의 손해가 발생했다고 주장했다. 이들은 이와 별도로 미국 무역대표부에 한국 정부에 대한 조사와 통상 보호 조처를 요구하는 제소도 진행 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Coupang drew a line on the 23rd, stating, "The submission of the ISDS arbitration notice by U.S. investors is unrelated to our company's position." However, consumers' views are not favorable. This is because the 'Talpang' trend has continued domestically, fueled by accumulated resentment over Coupang's response to the data leak and the attitude shown by Harold Rogers, the head of Coupang Korea, during the National Assembly hearing. (이에 대해 쿠팡은 지난 23일 “미국 투자사의 국제투자분쟁 중재의향서 제출은 당사의 입장과는 무관하다”고 선을 그었지만, 소비자들의 시선은 곱지 않다. 개인정보 유출 사태 이후 쿠팡의 대응과 국회 청문회 과정에서 해럴드 로저스 한국 쿠팡 대표가 보인 태도에 대한 반감이 누적되면서 국내에선 ‘탈팡’ 흐름이 이어져 왔기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although indicators showed that Coupang temporarily recovered its user numbers from the 15th by issuing 50,000-won purchase vouchers as compensation, some assessments say it is too early to conclude that consumer trust has been restored. In online communities like mom cafes, posts are continuing, such as worries about "whether we should really quit Coupang after this incident" or posts stating they quit after using all the coupons they received. An e-commerce industry official said, "Looking at the increase in customer numbers and payment amounts at other e-commerce companies, I think the way consumers use Coupang has changed slightly from before," adding, "We are watching to see if (the change) is temporary or will continue in the mid-to-long term." (지난 15일부터 쿠팡이 보상 차원에서 5만원 구매이용권 지급하며 단기적으로 이용자 수를 회복했다는 지표도 나타났지만, 소비자들의 신뢰가 회복됐다고 보긴 이르다는 평가도 나온다. 맘 카페 등 온라인 커뮤니티에서는 이번 사건 이후 ‘쿠팡을 진짜 탈퇴해야 하는 것 아니냐’는 고민 글이나, 받은 쿠폰을 모두 사용한 뒤 탈퇴했다는 게시글이 이어지고 있다. 한 이커머스 업계 관계자는 “다른 이커머스 업체의 고객 수와 결제 금액이 늘어난 점을 보면, 쿠팡을 이용하는 소비 방식이 이전과는 조금 달라졌다고 본다”며 “(변화가) 일시적일지 중장기적으로 이어질지 지켜보고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Hye-mi &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서혜미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ham@hani.co.kr"&gt;ham@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/consumer/1241516.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/642/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501397.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As the 5,000-point era opens, 'revival of financial investment income tax' discussion resurfaces... "Opinion for gradual implementation also exists" (5천피 시대 열리자 ‘금투세 부활’ 논의 재소환…“단계적 정착 의견도”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241517.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;As the 5,000-point era opens, 'revival of financial investment income tax' discussion resurfaces... "Opinion for gradual implementation also exists" (5천피 시대 열리자 ‘금투세 부활’ 논의 재소환…“단계적 정착 의견도”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/408/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501413.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 오전 서울 중구 우리은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"According to principle and value, pushing ahead is correct, but the stock market is too difficult, and we cannot ignore the position of stock investors, so we agreed to abolish (the financial investment income tax)." (“원칙과 가치에 따르면 강행하는 것이 맞지만 주식시장이 너무 어렵고, 주식투자자의 입장을 고려하지 않을 수 없어서 (금융투자소득세) 폐지에 동의하기로 했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a statement made by then-Democratic Party leader, now President Lee Jae-myung, on November 4, 2024. That day, the KOSPI closed at 2,588.97. About a year and two months later, on the 22nd, as the KOSPI broke through the 5,000-point level for the first time ever during trading, voices calling for the 'normalization of financial taxation' are emerging again. There is criticism that the government and political circles, which have postponed the implementation of the financial investment income tax citing 'market conditions' until now, should now implement the principle of 'where there is income, there is tax'. (2024년 11월4일, 당시 더불어민주당 대표였던 이재명 대통령의 발언이다. 그날 코스피는 2588.97에 거래를 마감했다. 그로부터 약 1년2개월이 흐른 지난 22일, 코스피가 장중 사상 처음으로 5000선을 돌파하자 ‘금융과세 정상화’를 요구하는 목소리가 다시 나오고 있다. 그동안 ‘시장 여건’을 이유로 금투세 시행을 미뤄온 정부와 정치권이 이제는 ‘소득 있는 곳에 세금 있다’는 원칙을 실행해야 한다는 지적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally promoted to enhance tax equity, the financial investment income tax is a system that comprehensively taxes profits and losses from financial investments on a net basis. It began with the Moon Jae-in administration's 'Financial Tax System Advancement Plan' in 2020, and an amendment to the Income Tax Act was processed through bipartisan agreement in December of that year. According to the original plan, from 2023, income from financial products like stocks and bonds exceeding 50 million won should have been taxed at a rate of 22-27.5%. However, its introduction was postponed after the launch of the Yoon Suk-yeol administration, and following a bipartisan agreement at the end of 2024, it ultimately proceeded towards abolition. (본래 조세 형평성을 높이기 위해 추진된 금투세는 금융투자로 발생한 이익과 손실을 합산해 포괄적으로 과세하는 제도다. 2020년 문재인 정부의 ‘금융세제 선진화 방안’으로 시작돼 그해 12월 여야 합의로 소득세법 개정안이 처리됐다. 당초 계획대로라면 2023년부터 주식·채권 등 금융상품 소득이 5천만원을 넘을 경우 22~27.5%의 세율을 적용해야 했다. 그러나 윤석열 정부 출범 이후 도입이 유예됐고, 2024년 말 여야가 합의하며 결국 폐지 수순을 밟았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a result, the current domestic stock market maintains a distorted structure where capital gains tax is imposed only on major shareholders of listed stocks (holding over 5 billion won per stock, etc.). This also contrasts with the overseas stock taxation system, which imposes a 22% tax on capital gains excluding a basic deduction of 2.5 million won annually. (이로 인해 현재 국내 주식시장은 상장주식 대주주(종목당 50억원 이상 등)에게만 양도소득세를 부과하는 기형적 구조를 유지하고 있다. 이는 연간 250만원 기본공제를 제외한 양도차익에 22%의 세금을 매기는 해외주식 과세 체계와도 대조적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even after the launch of the Lee Jae-myng administration, the financial investment income tax has not been seriously discussed. Instead, attempts were made to increase the securities transaction tax rate (0.15% → 0.2%) and expand the scope of the major shareholder capital gains tax (5 billion won → 1 billion won) as part of 'restoring Yoon Suk-yeol's tax cuts', but even these faced backlash from investors and fell through. The government's stance also remains cautious. Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance Koo Yun-cheol drew a line on inquiries regarding the financial investment income tax, stating, "There is no separate part currently under review." Kim Yong-beom, head of the Presidential Office's Policy Office, also expressed a reserved stance in a recent interview with SisaIN, saying, "Discussion should take place at a stage where we gain confidence that the capital market is on solid ground." (이재명 정부 출범 이후에도 금투세는 진지하게 논의되지 못했다. 대신 ‘윤석열 감세 원상복구’ 차원에서 증권거래세율 인상(0.15→0.2%)과 대주주 양도세 대상 확대(50억→10억원)를 시도했으나, 이마저도 투자자들의 반발에 부딪혀 무산됐다. 정부 입장도 신중론에 머물러 있다. 구윤철 부총리 겸 재정경제부 장관은 금투세 관련 문의에 “현재 별도 검토 중인 부분은 없다”고 선을 그었고, 김용범 대통령실 정책실장 역시 최근 시사인과 한 인터뷰에서 “자본시장이 반석 위에 올라갔다는 확신이 생기는 단계에서 논의해봐야 한다”며 유보적인 입장을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, experts say that now that the government's target of 'KOSPI 5000' has been achieved, it is time to move towards normalizing financial taxation. Professor Chung Se-eun of Chungnam National University (Economics) told The Hankyoreh, "The logic that 'we must not tax to induce investment' does not align with tax justice. It's the same as saying 'we must cut labor income tax to boost the will to work'," adding, "Normalizing financial taxation is also necessary from the perspectives of fairness in the tax system, securing tax revenue, and alleviating asset inequality." The People's Solidarity for Participatory Democracy issued a commentary on the 22nd, stating, "Now that the KOSPI has surpassed 5000, we urge the government and the National Assembly to initiate discussions on normalizing financial taxation to establish the principle of fair taxation and sustain the healthy growth of the capital market." (그러나 전문가들은 정부의 목표였던 ‘코스피 5000’을 달성한 만큼 이제는 금융과세 정상화에 나서야 한다고 말한다. 정세은 충남대 교수(경제학)는 한겨레에 “‘과세하지 않아야 투자를 유도할 수 있다’라는 논리는 조세 정의와 맞지 않다. 마치 ‘근로의욕 고취를 위해 근로소득세를 깎아줘야 한다’는 것과 동일한 얘기”라며 “조세 체계의 공평성이나 세수 확보, 자산 불평등 완화 차원에서도 금융과세 정상화가 필요하다”고 말했다. 참여연대는 지난 22일 논평을 내어 “코스피 5000을 돌파한 지금이야말로 공평과세의 원칙을 확립하고 자본시장의 건강한 성장을 지속하기 위해 정부와 국회가 금융과세 정상화 논의에 나설 것을 촉구한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also suggestions that the financial investment income tax should be gradually established initially by easing the tax burden. The National Assembly Budget Office pointed out in its report 'Tax Policy Improvement Tasks for Enhancing Social Inclusiveness' last month, "Considering the maturity of our capital market, it is uncertain whether abolishing the financial investment income tax can be a fundamental solution." It advised, "While preparing a comprehensive taxation system for financial investment income, measures such as setting a relatively high level of basic deduction in the early stages of the system's introduction, considering the impact on the capital market, etc., can be reviewed." (초기엔 세 부담을 완화하는 방식으로 차츰 금투세를 정착시켜야 한다는 제언도 나온다. 국회예산정책처는 지난달 낸 ‘사회적 포용성 제고를 위한 조세정책 개선과제’ 보고서에서 “우리 자본시장의 성숙도를 고려할 때 금투세 폐지가 본질적인 대책이 될 수 있는지는 불확실하다”고 짚었다. 그러면서 “금융투자소득에 대한 포괄적인 과세체계를 마련하되, 자본시장에 미칠 충격 등을 감안해 제도 도입 초기에는 비교적 높은 수준의 기본공제를 설정하는 방안 등을 검토할 수 있다”고 조언했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241517.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/408/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501413.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Lee Hye-hoon's Fall' Inevitable Long Vacancy at the Helm of the Planning and Budget Office... Concerns Over 'Loss of Presence' Also Raised (‘이혜훈 낙마’ 기획예산처 수장 장기 공백 불가피…“존재감 상실” 우려도)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241520.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'Lee Hye-hoon's Fall' Inevitable Long Vacancy at the Helm of the Planning and Budget Office... Concerns Over 'Loss of Presence' Also Raised (‘이혜훈 낙마’ 기획예산처 수장 장기 공백 불가피…“존재감 상실” 우려도)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501489.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한겨레 자료사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;With President Lee Jae-myung withdrawing the nomination of former Saenuri Party (predecessor of the People Power Party) lawmaker Lee Hye-hoon as a candidate for Minister of the Planning and Budget Office on the 25th, the vacancy at the helm of the Office appears to be prolonged. At a time when strong momentum is required to stabilize the organization of the newly established ministry, the extended absence of a minister is also increasing internal confusion. (이재명 대통령이 25일 이혜훈 전 새누리당(국민의힘 전신) 의원에 대한 기획예산처 장관 후보자 지명을 철회하면서 기획처 수장 공백이 장기화하는 모양새다. 신생 부처로서 조직을 안정시키기 위한 강력한 추진력이 요구되는 시기에 장관 부재가 길어지면서 내부 혼란도 커지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the withdrawal of the ministerial candidate nomination on this day, the leadership vacancy that has persisted since the Office's launch on January 2nd is expected to last at least until the end of February. This is because the prevailing view is that it will take at least a month for President Lee Jae-myung to search for a new candidate, send the appointment consent motion to the National Assembly, and for the Assembly to hold a confirmation hearing, adopt a hearing report, and for the presidential appointment process to be completed. (이날 장관 후보자 지명이 철회되면서 1월2일 기획처 출범 직후부터 이어진 수장 공백은 최소 2월 말까지 이어질 것으로 보인다. 이재명 대통령이 새 후보자를 물색해 국회에 임명동의안을 송부하고, 국회의 인사청문회 개최 및 청문보고서를 채택한 뒤 대통령 임명 절차까지 밟으려면 적어도 한달은 소요될 거란 전망이 지배적이기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the Planning and Budget Office, voices are emerging that the prolonged ministerial vacancy is preventing the ministry from demonstrating its presence. The Planning and Budget Office is responsible for tasks such as establishing mid-to-long-term development strategies, budget formulation, and fiscal performance evaluation, which require strong policy leadership to coordinate interests among ministries and establish national growth strategies. However, concerns are being raised that the extended system of Deputy Minister Im Gi-geun acting as minister is relatively lacking in authority. An official from the Planning and Budget Office said, "For the organization's presence and authority to grow, the minister must lead from the front, but given the current situation, that aspect is inevitably lacking." (기획처 내부에서는 장관 공백이 길어지면서 부처가 존재감을 드러내지 못한다는 목소리가 나온다. 기획처는 중장기 발전 전략 수립과 예산 편성, 재정성과 평가 등의 업무를 담당하는데, 부처별 이해관계 조율 및 국가성장전략 수립을 위해선 강한 정책 리더십이 요구된다. 그러나 임기근 기획처 차관의 장관 직무대행 체제가 길어지면서 상대적으로 힘을 받지 못하고 있다는 우려가 나온다. 한 기획처 관계자는 “장관이 진두지휘해야 조직의 존재감도 커지고 힘을 받는데, 현재로선 그런 부분이 부족할 수밖에 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the withdrawal of the nomination of former lawmaker Lee leading to a prolonged leadership vacuum, the Planning and Budget Office decided to hold an expanded executive meeting chaired by Acting Minister Im on the 26th, which was not originally scheduled. The Planning and Budget Office stated, "We plan to hold an expanded executive meeting to review the progress of major tasks and future plans," adding, "All employees of the Planning and Budget Office deeply recognize the seriousness of fundamental institutional improvement through economic leap forward and structural reform, and will steadfastly carry out their core duties to ensure there is no disruption in stabilizing people's livelihoods and implementing state affairs tasks." (이 전 의원 지명 철회로 리더십 부재가 장기화된 기획처는 26일 당초 예정에 없던 임 직무대행 주재 확대간부회의를 개최하기로 했다. 기획처는 “확대간부회의를 개최해 주요업무 추진상황과 향후 계획을 점검할 예정”이라며 “기획처 전 직원은 경제 대도약과 구조개혁을 통한 근본적인 체질개선의 엄중함을 깊이 인식하고, 민생안정과 국정과제 실행에 차질이 없도록 본연의 업무를 흔들림 없이 추진하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241520.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501489.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hyundai Motor's 'Atlas' Sparks Job Debate... Industry and Labor Circles Pay Close Attention (현대차 ‘아틀라스’가 물꼬 튼 일자리 논쟁…산업·노동계 이목 쏠린다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241527.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hyundai Motor's 'Atlas' Sparks Job Debate... Industry and Labor Circles Pay Close Attention (현대차 ‘아틀라스’가 물꼬 튼 일자리 논쟁…산업·노동계 이목 쏠린다)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501583.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;현대자동차그룹의 휴머노이드 로봇 아틀라스. 현대차 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hyundai Motor Group's announcement of a plan to deploy the humanoid robot 'Atlas' in production sites has led to conflict as the labor union opposes it. Observers in the industrial sector note that since South Korea already has one of the world's highest densities of robots in manufacturing sites, there is significant potential for their widespread future use, and related controversies could expand more broadly accordingly. (현대차그룹이 인간형(휴머노이드) 로봇 ‘아틀라스’를 생산 현장에 투입하겠다는 계획을 발표하자 노동조합이 반대하면서 갈등을 겪고 있다. 산업계에선 이미 한국에선 제조 현장 로봇 밀집률이 세계에서 가장 높을 만큼 향후 광범위하게 활용될 여지가 크고, 이에 따라 관련 논란도 더 광범위하게 확대될 수 있다는 관측이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Hyundai Motor Branch of the Korean Metal Workers' Union stated in its newsletter on the 22nd, regarding the transfer of production volume to Hyundai Motor Group Metaplant America (HMGMA) in Georgia, USA, and the introduction of new robotic automation technology, that "unilateral action without labor-management agreement is absolutely unacceptable," and took a hardline stance that "not a single robot can enter the (production) site without agreement." This signals a head-on collision with the company side, which pursues cost reduction and production efficiency. (전국금속노조 현대차지부는 지난 22일 소식지에서 미국 조지아주의 현대차 메타플랜트(HMGMA)로 생산물량 이관과 로봇자동화 신기술 도입과 관련해 “노사합의 없는 일방통행은 절대 용납할 수 없다”며 “합의 없이는 단 한 대의 로봇도 (생산) 현장에 들어 올 수 없다”는 강경한 입장을 밝혔다. 비용 절감과 생산 효율을 추구하는 회사 쪽과 정면 충돌을 예고한 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The robotic automation that the union side is strongly wary of is represented by the humanoid robot called Atlas. Boston Dynamics, a U.S. robotics company acquired by Hyundai Motor Group, first unveiled Atlas at 'CES 2026' earlier this month. Hyundai Motor Group announced a plan to deploy Atlas at Metaplant America (HMGMA) in Georgia, USA, starting in 2028, and to build a system capable of mass-producing 30,000 robots annually by 2030, deploying them to various parts assembly processes. Boston Dynamics emphasizes that Atlas can learn most tasks within a day and autonomously handle various high-intensity labor, including tasks requiring lifting objects weighing up to 50 kilograms (kg) over 2 meters (m). (노조 쪽이 강한 경계심을 보이고 있는 로봇자동화는 아틀라스라는 인간형 로봇으로 대표된다. 현대차그룹이 인수한 미국 로보틱스 기업 보스턴다이나믹스는 아틀라스를 이달 초 ‘시이에스(CES) 2026’에서 처음 공개했다. 현대차그룹은 아틀라스를 2028년부터 미국 조지아주에 있는 메타플랜트 아메리카(HMGMA)에 투입하고 2030년까지 연간 3만대의 로봇을 양산할 수 있는 시스템을 구축해, 각종 부품 조립 공정에 배치하겠다는 계획을 발표했다. 보스턴다이나믹스는 아틀라스가 대부분의 작업을 하루 안에 학습할 수 있고, 최대 50킬로그램(kg)의 물건을 2미터(m) 넘게 들어올려야 하는 작업까지 다양한 고강도 노동을 자율적으로 처리할 수 있다고 강조하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the deployment of such humanoid robots could cause employment insecurity for workers and deepen inequality. According to a survey (by Global Research) conducted by Workplace Bullying 119 in October last year targeting 1,000 workers nationwide aged 19 and over, one in two workers (48.2%) answered that "AI will replace my job." Furthermore, eight out of ten total respondents (77.9%) predicted that the spread of AI would deepen labor market inequality and wealth polarization. Concerns are growing that the use of physical AI utilizing artificial intelligence will begin to replace human labor. (문제는 이러한 인간형 로봇의 투입이 노동자의 고용 불안을 야기하고 불평등을 심화시킬 수 있다는 점이다. 직장갑질119가 지난해 10월 전국 만 19살 이상 직장인 1000명을 대상으로 실시한 설문조사(글로벌리서치)를 보면, 직장인 2명 중 1명(48.2%)은 “인공지능이 나의 일자리를 대체할 것”이라고 대답했다. 또 전체 응답자 10명 중 8명(77.9%)은 인공지능 확산이 노동시장 불평등과 부의 양극화를 심화시킬 것으로 내다봤다. 인공지능을 활용한 피지컬 인공지능의 활용이 인간의 노동을 대체하기 시작할거란 우려가 점점 커지는 양상이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the introduction of Atlas has triggered related debates, South Korea already has one of the world's highest utilization rates of robots in industrial sites. According to 2024 data from the International Federation of Robotics (IFR), South Korea's 'robot density index,' which indicates the number of robots operated per 10,000 workers, was the highest in the world at 1,012. Singapore (770), China (470), Germany (429), and Japan (419) followed, with the world average being 162. (아틀라스의 도입을 계기로 관련 논쟁이 촉발되긴 했지만 이미 한국은 산업 현장에서 로봇 활용률이 세계적으로 가장 높은 편이다. 국제로봇연맹(IFR)의 2024년 자료를 보면, 노동자 1만명당 로봇 운용 대수를 의미하는 ‘로봇 밀집도 지수’는 한국이 1012대로 세계에서 가장 높았다. 싱가포르(770대), 중국(470대), 독일(429대), 일본(419대) 등이 뒤를 이었고 세계 평균은 162대였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, the introduction of robots is progressing rapidly not only in the automotive industry but also in industrial sites with many high-intensity and high-risk tasks, such as shipbuilding and steel. Hanwha Ocean, which confirmed the possibility of automating collaboration between welding workers and robots in indoor processes, has a plan to gradually increase the shipyard's automation rate to twice the current level by 2030, including achieving 100% automation of welding processes. POSCO Group also introduced the quadruped walking robot 'Spot' from Boston Dynamics in 2023 and is using it to diagnose and inspect hard-to-access equipment, such as around blast furnaces in steel mills. A shipbuilding industry official told The Hankyoreh on the 25th, "If we maximize the use of current technology, we can replace a significant portion of dangerous process work, where many fatal accidents occur, with robots," adding, "However, due to concerns such as backlash from labor unions, companies are being cautious while also watching how the discussion on Hyundai's Atlas unfolds." (실제 자동차 뿐만 아니라, 조선과 철강 등 고강도·고위험 작업이 많은 산업 현장에서 로봇 도입은 빠른 속도로 이뤄지고 있다. 실내 공정에서 용접 노동자와 로봇의 협업을 자동화 가능성을 확인한 한화오션은 2030년까지 용접 공정을 100% 자동화하는 등 점진적으로 조선소의 자동화율을 현재의 두배 수준까지 끌어올린다는 계획을 갖고 있다. 포스코그룹도 지난 2023년 보스턴다이나믹스로부터 4족 보행 로봇 ‘스팟’을 도입해 제철소 용광로 주변 등 접근하기 어려운 설비를 진단·점검하는 데 활용하고 있다. 조선업계 관계자는 25일 한겨레에 “현재의 기술력을 최대한 활용하면 인명사고가 많이 발생하는 위험 공정 작업을 상당 부분 로봇으로 대체할 수 있다”면서 “하지만 노동조합의 반발 등의 우려로 기업들이 조심스러워 하면서도 현대차의 아틀라스 논의가 어떻게 흘러가는지 주시하는 상황”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Byung-hoon, a professor emeritus at Chung-Ang University (Sociology) and a labor-management relations expert, emphasized, "The issue of introducing Atlas and robots into industrial sites is a massive change that completely shifts the industrial paradigm, so labor and management are bound to experience conflict, but it is also an opportunity to create an exemplary case of negotiation," and that "companies and unions must find ways to minimize negative impacts on jobs and working conditions through communication and consultation." A Metal Workers' Union official said, "If changes occur in employment and work methods, discussing them with the union is the purpose of the collective agreement," and "The core of the Hyundai Motor Branch's position is to (have labor and management) consult regarding the introduction of 'Atlas'." (노사 관계 전문가인 이병훈 중앙대 명예교수(사회학)는 “아틀라스와 로봇의 산업 현장 도입 문제는 산업 패러다임을 송두리째 바꾸는 거대한 변화이기 때문에 노사가 갈등을 겪을 수밖에 없지만, 모범적인 협상의 사례를 만들 수 있는 기회이기도 하다”며 “기업과 노조가 소통과 협의를 통해서 일자리와 노동조건에 부정적인 폐해를 최소화 할 수 있는 방안을 찾아야 한다”고 강조했다. 금속노조 관계자는 “고용과 작업방식에 변화가 생기면 노조와 논의하는 것이 단체협약의 취지”라며 “현대차지부 입장의 핵심은 ‘아틀라스’ 도입과 관련해 (노사가) 협의하자는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Jae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Yu Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Park Da-hae &lt;a href="mailto:doall@hani.co.kr"&gt;doall@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이재호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 박다해 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:doall@hani.co.kr"&gt;doall@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241527.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501583.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Strengthening 'Stewardship' for Active Exercise of Shareholder Rights by Institutions (기관의 적극적 주주권 행사 위해 ‘스튜어드십’ 강화를)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241538.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Strengthening 'Stewardship' for Active Exercise of Shareholder Rights by Institutions (기관의 적극적 주주권 행사 위해 ‘스튜어드십’ 강화를)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/494/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501763.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In previous columns, I have conveyed the opinion that for a revaluation of the Korean stock market, shareholders' interest in corporate management strategies and active 'exercise of voting rights' on shareholder meeting agendas are necessary. This is because it can check or support management's decision-making, and this process can limit actions that erode shareholder value. (앞선 몇 차례의 기고에서 한국 증시 재평가를 위해선 기업의 경영 전략에 대한 주주들의 관심과 주주총회 안건에 대한 적극적인 ‘의결권 행사’가 필요하다는 의견을 전달한 바 있다. 경영진의 의사결정을 견제하거나 지지할 수 있고, 이러한 과정이 주주가치 훼손 행위를 제한할 수 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the upcoming shareholder meeting season in March, movements for change that could stimulate active voting rights exercise and shareholder engagement activities by institutional investors are gaining momentum. This is precisely the revision of the Stewardship Code. The Stewardship Code is a set of action principles for institutional investors, who are stewards managing others' assets, to fulfill their responsibilities not merely by holding shares but by actively exercising shareholder rights, thereby enhancing the medium- to long-term value of companies and returning those benefits to beneficiaries. While it may be a somewhat unfamiliar concept to individual investors, it is a value that institutional investors such as pension funds, insurance companies, asset managers, and banks—who are stewards managing others' assets—as well as related investment advisory firms and proxy advisory agencies, must emphasize. (오는 3월 도래할 주주총회 시즌을 앞두고 최근 기관투자자들의 적극적인 의결권 행사, 주주관여 활동을 자극할 만한 변화의 움직임이 본격화되고 있다. 바로 스튜어드십 코드의 개정이다. 스튜어드십 코드는 기관투자자가 타인의 자산을 맡은 수탁자(Steward)로서, 단순히 주식을 보유하는 것을 넘어 타인의 자산을 관리·운용하는 수탁자로서 책임을 다하기 위해 적극적으로 주주권을 행사하고 이를 통해 기업의 중장기 가치를 제고하는 한편 그 이익을 수익자에게 환원하기 위한 행동 원칙이다. 개인투자자들에게는 다소 생소한 개념일 수 있지만, 타인의 자산을 관리·운용하는 수탁자인 연기금, 보험사, 자산운용사, 은행 등의 기관투자자들과 관련 투자자문사, 의결권 자문기관 등은 중시해야 하는 가치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First established in the UK in 2010, the Stewardship Code has since been introduced and is being implemented in 23 countries, including Germany, Canada, Japan, Korea, and Singapore. While there are differences among countries in the timing of the code's introduction, implementation methods, and specific details, the common goal is 'to enhance medium- to long-term corporate value through active exercise of shareholder rights by institutional investors and to return this to investors (beneficiaries).' (2010년 영국에서 처음 제정된 스튜어드십 코드는 이후 독일, 캐나다, 일본, 한국, 싱가포르 등 23개 국가에서 도입해 시행 중이다. 나라마다 스튜어드십 코드의 도입 시기와 이행 방식, 구체적인 내용 등에 차이가 존재하지만 ‘기관투자자의 적극적인 주주권 행사를 통해 중장기 기업가치를 제고하고 이를 투자자(수익자)에게 환원하는 것’이라는 목표는 공통적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examining the voting rights exercise activities of Korean institutional investors in practice confirms the effect of the Stewardship Code. For the 2024 shareholder meetings, the voting rights exercise rate of institutional investors participating in the Stewardship Code was 95%, whereas the rate for non-participating institutional investors was only 62%. Since the code's implementation, the rate of opposing votes has also gradually increased, and the number of shareholder activities has been rising annually. While participation in the Stewardship Code is voluntary for institutional investors, it can be interpreted that those who have declared participation recognize this and strive to fulfill their responsibilities more diligently. (실제로 우리나라 기관투자자의 의결권 행사 활동을 살펴보면 스튜어드십 코드의 효과를 확인할 수 있다. 2024년 주주총회를 기준으로 스튜어드십 코드에 참여한 기관투자자의 의결권 행사비율은 95%인 반면, 미참여 기관투자자의 의결권 행사비율은 62%에 불과했다. 코드 시행 이후, 반대 의결권 행사 비율도 점진적으로 상승했고, 주주활동 횟수도 매년 증가하는 양상이다. 스튜어드십 코드 참여 여부는 기관투자자의 자율이지만 일단 참여를 선언한 기관투자자라면 이를 인지하고 더 책임을 이행하기 위해 노력한 것으로 해석할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, for the advancement of Korea's capital market, it is crucial for institutional investors to perform their role as stewards in the changed market environment and to engage in active shareholder engagement activities that involve deeply understanding companies and communicating constructively to enhance medium- to long-term value. (다만 우리나라 자본시장의 선진화를 위해선 기관투자자가 변화된 시장 환경에서 수탁자로서의 역할을 수행하는 한편, 중장기 가치 제고를 위해 기업에 대해 깊이 이해하고 건설적으로 소통하는 적극적 주주관여 활동이 절실하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since its establishment in 2016, Korea's Stewardship Code started with the participation of 16 institutions and has grown to 250 by 2025, but over its ten-year operation period, only a partial revision of the guidelines has been made once. This differs from other advanced countries that have created and strengthened a responsible investment environment by undergoing two or three revisions since establishment, integrating investment strategy and steward responsibility activities, reflecting issues related to sustainable management, and expanding the scope of application to asset classes beyond listed stocks. (우리나라의 스튜어드십 코드는 2016년 제정된 이후, 초기 16개 기관의 참여로 시작해 2025년 250개까지 늘어났지만 10년에 걸친 운영 기간 중 한차례 가이드라인이 부분 개정된 게 전부다. 제정 이후 두세 번의 개정을 거치며 투자 전략과 수탁자 책임 활동의 통합, 지속가능 경영에 관한 이슈 반영, 상장 주식 이외의 투자 자산군까지 적용 영역을 확대하는 등 책임투자 환경을 조성하고 강화해 온 여타 선진국과는 다른 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now is the opportune time to encourage responsible investment activities by institutional investors, as government-led value-up policies are being implemented, the Commercial Act is being revised, and the retirement pension market is blooming, leading to an increase in the scale of managed assets, centered on pension funds. I hope to soon see a revision of the Stewardship Code that includes checking the implementation status of voting rights exercise and shareholder engagement activities for participating institutions, as well as evaluating their level of active participation. Furthermore, I expect institutional support to enhance awareness so that stakeholders such as companies and shareholders can view institutional investors as collaborative partners for sustainable growth. (정부 주도하에 진행된 밸류업 정책의 시행과 상법 개정, 그리고 퇴직연금 시장이 개화하며 연기금을 중심으로 운용 자산의 규모가 커지고 있는 지금이 기관투자자의 책임투자 활동을 독려해야 하는 적기다. 스튜어드십 코드 참여 기관에 대한 의결권 행사, 주주관여 활동 등 이행현황 점검, 적극적 참여 여부에 대한 평가가 담긴 스튜어드십 코드의 개정을 조속히 확인할 수 있길 바란다. 또 기업과 주주 등의 이해관계자가 기관투자자를 지속가능한 성장을 위한 협력적 파트너로 여길 수 있도록 인식 제고를 위한 제도적 지원도 병행되길 기대한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Na-Ye Lee, Research Fellow, Korea Investment &amp; Securities (이나예 한국투자증권 연구위원)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241538.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/494/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501763.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Squeezing Multi-Homeowners to Control Housing Prices… Even 'Well-Positioned Single Homes' of Non-Residents Under Scrutiny (다주택자 옥죄 집값 잡기…비거주 ‘똘똘한 한채’도 도마에)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241563.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Squeezing Multi-Homeowners to Control Housing Prices… Even 'Well-Positioned Single Homes' of Non-Residents Under Scrutiny (다주택자 옥죄 집값 잡기…비거주 ‘똘똘한 한채’도 도마에)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/348/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501977.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;25일 서울 남산 전망대에서 바라본 시내 곳곳에 아파트 단지가 빼곡하다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"A prospective homebuyer who was looking at properties to purchase contacted me saying they will hold off on buying for now to see how the government's real estate tax reform unfolds. Now, homeowners are getting anxious that they might not be able to sell their houses." (A certified real estate agent in Yeomni-dong, Mapo-gu, Seoul) (“주택 구입을 위해 매물을 보고 있던 실수요자가 일단 정부의 부동산 세제 개편을 지켜보겠다면서 매수를 보류하겠다고 연락이 왔습니다. 이제는 집주인이 집을 못 팔까 봐 다급한 상황이 된 거죠.”(서울 마포구 염리동의 한 공인중개사))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real estate market is in a stir as President Lee Jae-myung reaffirmed on the 25th that the temporary suspension of the heavy capital gains tax on multi-homeowners is set to end on May 9th. President Lee also stated that he would discuss at a cabinet meeting the possibility of granting a suspension of the heavy tax for transactions contracted by May 9th, acknowledging that the government bears some responsibility for leading people to believe it would be suspended again due to repeated suspensions over the past four years. This indicates an intention to provide a bit more grace period to allow multi-homeowners to list their properties. Following President Lee's remark at a press conference on the 21st that he is "looking for supply-side measures to make those who own many houses release them," attention is now focused on whether multi-homeowner listings will appear in the Seoul apartment market due to this latest statement. (25일 이재명 대통령이 오는 5월9일로 예정된 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 유예 종료를 재확인하면서 부동산 시장이 술렁이고 있다. 이 대통령은 이날 지난 4년간의 반복된 유예로 이번에도 유예될 것으로 믿게 한 정부 잘못도 있으니 5월9일까지 매매계약하는 경우에는 중과세 유예를 해주도록 국무회의에서 의논해보겠다는 방침도 밝혔다. 다주택자의 매물이 나올 수 있도록 유예 기간을 좀 더 주겠다는 뜻이다. 지난 21일 이 대통령이 기자회견에서 “주택을 많이 가지고 있는 사람들이 내놓게 하는 공급책을 찾고 있다”고 말했는데, 이번 언급을 통해 서울 아파트 시장에 다주택자 매물이 출현할지에도 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the real estate industry points out a limitation: even if multi-homeowners want to sell, the roughly three months remaining until May 9th is too short, even based on the contract date. This is because, under last October's measures, the entire Seoul area is designated as a Land Transaction Permit Zone, requiring at least 20 days just from signing a preliminary contract to obtaining district office approval. Furthermore, due to the land transaction permit system which mandates the buyer's actual residence, transactions are impossible for homes where the tenant's lease period is still ongoing. A certified real estate agent in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, said, "Many multi-homeowners living in Gangnam were convinced the suspension of the heavy capital gains tax would end with the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration, so quite a few sold homes they owned elsewhere last year, keeping only their 'well-positioned single home' in Gangnam." (다만 부동산 업계에선 다주택자가 집을 팔려고 해도 5월9일까지 남은 3개월 남짓 기간은 계약일 기준으로도 너무 짧다는 점이 한계로 지적된다. 지난해 10·15 대책에 따라 서울 전역이 토지거래허가구역으로 묶이면서 거래 약정부터 구청 허가를 받는 데만 최소 20일 이상이 소요되고, 매수자의 실거주를 의무화한 토허제로 인해 임차인의 계약기간이 남아 있는 집은 거래 자체가 불가능하기 때문이다. 서초구 반포동의 한 공인중개사는 “강남 거주 다주택자들은 이재명 정부 출범 때 양도세 중과 유예가 종료될 것으로 확신해서 지난해 강남의 ‘똘똘한 한 채’를 남기고 다른 곳에 보유했던 주택을 매각한 사람들이 꽤 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has led to discussions that a grace period of at least six months to one year is needed to induce multi-homeowners to put their homes on the market. Park Won-gap, Chief Real Estate Expert at KB Kookmin Bank, said, "To enable multi-homeowners to sell their homes, it would be desirable to grant a grace period of about one year, considering lease contract periods," adding, "It's important to increase predictability for market participants." The government did not mention the plan to end the suspension of the heavy capital gains tax for multi-homeowners in its '2026 Economic Policy Direction' announced at the beginning of the year, and as recently as lately, Kim Yong-beom, the Presidential Chief of Staff for Policy, stated, "There is time for that issue, and it is still under review." (이 때문에 다주택자들이 집을 내놓도록 유도하려면 유예 기간이 최소 6개월~1년은 되어야 한다는 이야기도 나온다. 박원갑 케이비(KB)국민은행 부동산수석전문위원은 “다주택자들이 집을 팔 수 있도록 하려면 임대차 계약 기간을 고려해 1년 정도는 유예기간을 주는 게 바람직하다”며 “시장 참여자들의 예측 가능성을 높이는 게 중요하다”고 말했다. 정부는 연초 ‘2026년 경제정책방향’에서 다주택 양도세 중과 유예 종료 방침에 관해 밝히지 않았고 최근까지만 해도 김용범 청와대 정책실장은 “그 문제는 시간이 있어 아직 검토 중”이라고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also many concerns in the market that after the implementation of the heavy capital gains tax, a 'listing freeze' phenomenon will occur, where homeowners choose to hold onto their properties without selling or turn to gifting instead. According to statistics from the Court Registry Information Plaza, the number of real estate gift applications in Seoul last December was 2,047, the highest in about three years since May 2022. As it appears that capital gains tax will be heavily imposed in the future, there is an interpretation that people have preemptively arranged their 'multi-home situation' through methods like intra-family gifting. (시장에선 양도세 중과 시행 이후 집을 팔지 않고 버티기나 증여로 돌아서는 ‘매물 잠김’ 현상이 나타날 것이란 우려도 많다. 법원등기정보광장 집계를 보면, 지난해 12월 서울의 부동산 증여 신청 건수는 2047건으로, 2022년 5월 이후 3년여 만에 가장 많았다. 향후 양도소득세가 중과될 것으로 보이는 만큼, 가족 내 증여 등으로 ‘다주택 상황’을 미리 정리한 것 아니냐는 해석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also forecasts that holding taxes will emerge as a variable. Since the government already hinted at holding tax reform in the October measures, the possibility has increased that holding taxes for high-value homes and multi-homeowners, which were significantly lowered under the previous Yoon Suk-yeol administration, will be normalized. In this case, not only multi-homeowners but also single homeowners of high-value properties who find the holding tax burden difficult may put their homes up for sale. However, there are also concerns that in a situation of housing supply shortage, the increased taxes will be passed on to tenants, destabilizing the jeonse (lump-sum deposit) and monthly rent market. (보유세가 변수로 떠오를 것이라는 전망도 나온다. 정부가 10·15 대책에서 이미 보유세 개편을 예고한 만큼, 지난 윤석열 정부에서 크게 낮춰진 고가주택·다주택자의 보유세가 정상화될 가능성이 높아졌기 때문이다. 이 경우 다주택자는 물론 보유세 부담이 어려운 고가 1주택자도 주택 매도에 나설 수 있다. 다만 주택 공급이 부족한 상황에서 늘어난 세금은 임차인에게 전가돼 전월세 시장이 불안해질 것이라는 우려도 함께 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as President Lee stated, "It doesn't seem right to give tax benefits even to homes that are not occupied by single homeowners," it is expected that the reduction of the long-term holding special deduction for capital gains tax (up to 80% for residents, up to 40% for non-residents) for non-occupying single homeowners will also be included in the tax reform menu. The real estate industry believes that while non-occupying single homeowners may not sell their homes in large numbers due to increased capital gains tax burden, speculative purchases of homes in non-occupied, rising-price areas for future investment will decrease. Some also forecast that measures to strengthen the comprehensive real estate tax for non-occupying single homeowners of high-value properties may be considered in this tax reform. (한편 이 대통령이 “1주택자라도 거주하지 않는 주택까지 세제 혜택을 주는 것은 맞지 않는 것 같다”고 말해, 비거주 1주택자의 양도세 장기보유특별공제(최대 80%, 비거주자는 최대 40%) 축소도 세제 개편 메뉴에 오를 것으로 예상된다. 부동산 업계에선 비거주 1주택자의 양도세 부담이 커진다고 집을 파는 경우는 많지 않겠지만 앞으로 거주하지 않는 집값 상승지역에 미리 집을 사두는 투자성 매입은 줄어들 것으로 보고 있다. 또 일각에서는 이번 세제 개편에서 비거주하는 고가 1주택자의 종합부동산세를 강화하는 방안이 검토될 수 있다는 전망도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Choi Jong-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최종훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241563.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/348/imgdb/original/2026/0125/20260125501977.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:18 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>