<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 06:59:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>President Lee on Prosecution Reform Controversy: "Reform is Not About Clinging to Justification and Increasing Confusion" (이 대통령, 검찰개혁 논란에 “명분에 매달려 혼란 가중시키는 건 개혁 아냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241232.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee on Prosecution Reform Controversy: "Reform is Not About Clinging to Justification and Increasing Confusion" (이 대통령, 검찰개혁 논란에 “명분에 매달려 혼란 가중시키는 건 개혁 아냐”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/371/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503772.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관 회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, President Lee Jae-myung said, "If a reform measure, by clinging only to justification and the greater cause, increases suffering and confusion, it cannot be called reform." This statement is interpreted as expressing his position that prosecution reform should not be solely fixated on the grand justification of stripping the prosecution of its power, amid ongoing debates within the ruling party over issues such as retaining the prosecution's supplementary investigation rights. (이재명 대통령이 22일 “개혁 조치가 명분과 대의에만 매달려 고통과 혼란을 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다. 여권 내에서 검찰의 보완수사권 존치 등을 놓고 갑론을박이 이어지는 것과 관련해, 검찰개혁이 검찰의 권력 박탈이라는 대의명분에만 매몰돼서는 안 된다는 입장을 밝힌 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks while outlining the direction of state affairs and commending the hard work of his senior secretaries during a meeting he presided over at the Blue House that day. President Lee said, "You have done well so far, but I ask you to pick up the pace a bit more from now on," adding, "Operating state affairs on behalf of the sovereign people must be, first and foremost, for the practical improvement of people's lives and livelihoods." He continued, "We must carefully judge from a practical and effective perspective which measures help protect people's human rights and guarantee their substantive rights, and meticulously check them," stating, "If any reform measure, far from improving people's lives, only increases suffering and confusion by clinging to justification and the greater cause, it cannot be called reform." (이 대통령의 이런 발언은 이날 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 수석들의 노고를 치하하며 국정 운영의 방향을 밝히는 과정에서 나왔다. 이 대통령은 “지금까지도 잘해주셨는데 지금보다는 조금 더 속도를 내주시길 부탁한다”며 “주권자를 대리해 국정을 운영하는 것은 첫째도 둘째도 국민 삶, 민생의 실질적인 개선을 위한 것이어야 한다”고 말했다. 그는 이어 “어떤 방안이 국민 인권을 보호하고 실질적인 권리 보장에 도움이 되는지를 실용적인 관점에서, 실효적 관점에서 신중히 판단하고 꼼꼼하게 챙겨 봐야 한다”며 “국민 삶을 개선하기는커녕 어떤 개혁 조치가 명분과 대의에 매달려서 고통과 혼란만 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's remarks appear to reiterate the principles of prosecution reform he mentioned during his New Year's press conference the previous day. The day before, President Lee stated, "The core of prosecution reform is not about taking away the prosecution's power, but about providing remedies for people's rights," and mentioned that the controversial prosecution's supplementary investigation rights are "exceptionally necessary in some cases." This signifies that we should not face a situation where people's rights are harmed due to an obsession solely with the grand justification of stripping the prosecution of its investigative authority. In a press conference marking one month in office last July, President Lee also questioned the complete and unconditional deprivation of the prosecution's investigative rights, saying, "Can the police handle all (investigations)? There is debate over how to solve the issue of police overexpansion." (이 대통령의 발언은 전날 신년 기자회견에서 언급한 검찰개혁의 원칙을 거듭 강조한 것으로 보인다. 이 대통령은 전날 “검찰개혁의 핵심은 검찰 권력을 빼앗는 게 아니라 국민의 권리 구제”라며 논란이 되고 있는 검사의 보완수사권이 “예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”고 밝힌 바 있다. 검사의 수사 권한을 뺏는 대의명분에만 집착하다가, 국민의 권리가 피해받는 상황을 맞아서는 안 된다는 뜻을 밝힌 것이다. 이 대통령은 지난해 7월 취임 한달 기자회견에서도 “(수사권을) 경찰이 다 감당할 수 있느냐. 경찰 비대화는 어떻게 해결할 것이냐는 논쟁이 있다”며 검사의 수사권을 예외 없이 완전히 박탈하는 데 대해 의문을 제기한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's clarification of the meaning that "people's rights come first" within a day appears to also contain the intention of clearly sorting out the differences in opinion within the ruling party. During the Democratic Party of Korea's policy general meeting of lawmakers held that morning, opinions advocating for exceptionally recognizing the prosecution's supplementary investigation rights increased compared to before, but opinions centered on hardliners still emerged calling for the complete deprivation of those rights. A Blue House official said, "President Lee's position is that reform tasks should be viewed from the standpoint of the sovereign people; it is not right to legislate from a stance of fighting the prosecution or intending to fight the prosecution," adding, "Granting exceptional supplementary investigation rights is a necessary system from the people's perspective, so he means we should discuss it from this viewpoint." (이 대통령이 하루 만에 ‘국민 권리가 우선한다’는 뜻을 밝힌 것은 여권 내부의 입장 차이를 분명하게 정리하려는 의도도 담긴 것으로 보인다. 이날 오전 열린 더불어민주당 정책 의원총회에서 검사의 보완수사권을 예외적으로 인정해야 한다는 의견이 전보다 늘었지만, 여전히 강경파를 중심으로 검사의 보완수사권을 완전히 박탈해야 한다는 의견이 나왔다. 한 청와대 관계자는 “이 대통령의 입장은 개혁과제를 주권자인 국민 입장에서 바라봐야지, 검찰하고 싸웠거나, 검찰과 싸우려는 입장에서 입법을 하는 것은 맞지 않다는 취지”라며 “예외적인 보완수사권 부여는 국민들 입장에서 필요한 제도인 만큼 이 관점에서 토론을 해보자는 뜻”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's attitude of prioritizing 'people's rights' serves as a basic guideline not only for prosecution reform but for state affairs as a whole. The previous day, regarding sensitive issues such as new nuclear power plant construction and the North Korean nuclear problem, President Lee expressed his thoughts based on pragmatism, stating, "We must keep options open and judge," and "Will North Korea give up its nukes? We must approach it pragmatically." (‘국민 권리’를 앞세우는 이 대통령의 태도는 검찰개혁뿐만 아니라 국정 전반에 대한 기본적인 지침이기도 하다. 이 대통령은 전날 신규 원전 건설과 북핵 문제 등 민감한 사안에 대해 “열어놓고 판단해야 한다”, “북한이 핵을 포기하겠나. 실용적으로 접근해야 한다” 등 실용주의를 바탕으로 한 자신의 생각을 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241232.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/371/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503772.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Within the Ruling Party, "Exceptional Need for Prosecutors' Supplementary Investigation Rights"... A 'Reversal' Following President Lee's Remarks (여당 내부 “보완수사권 예외적 필요”…이 대통령 한마디에 ‘반전’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241233.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Within the Ruling Party, "Exceptional Need for Prosecutors' Supplementary Investigation Rights"... A 'Reversal' Following President Lee's Remarks (여당 내부 “보완수사권 예외적 필요”…이 대통령 한마디에 ‘반전’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503774.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 국회의원들이 22일 국회에서 열린 중대범죄수사청·공소청 설치법 관련 정책 의원총회 회의장에 들어서고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day after President Lee Jae-myung stated that prosecutors' rights to conduct supplementary investigations should exceptionally be guaranteed, various voices within the ruling party, which had been suppressed by the 'hardline prosecution reform faction', erupted. Various opinions also emerged regarding the scope of investigation for the Major Crime Investigation Bureau (MCIB), which has been expanded to nine categories. (이재명 대통령이 예외적으로 검사의 보완수사권을 보장해야 한다고 밝힌 다음날, 여당에서는 그동안 ‘검찰 개혁 강경파’에 억눌려 있었던 다양한 목소리가 분출했다. 9가지로 확대된 중대범죄수사청(중수청)의 수사 범위를 두고도 여러 의견이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea held a policy general meeting of lawmakers at the National Assembly on the 22nd regarding the bills to establish the MCIB and the Public Prosecution Service. A noticeable change compared to previous meetings was the prevalence of opinions that prosecutors' rights to conduct supplementary investigations should exceptionally be permitted. Lawmaker Park Gyun-taek, a former prosecutor, said, 'If we do not even recognize prosecutors' exceptional and conditional supplementary investigations, it will be difficult to protect defendants or victims appealing their innocence.' Lawmaker Hong Ki-won reportedly also said, "Didn't the President cite examples like situations where the statute of limitations for prosecution is imminent? He spoke specifically, reasonably, and well." (더불어민주당은 22일 국회에서 중수청·공소청 설치 법안 관련 정책 의원총회를 열었다. 이전 총회와 비교해 눈에 띄는 변화는 검사의 보완수사권을 예외적으로 허용해야 한다는 의견이 많았다는 점이다. 검사 출신 박균택 의원은 ‘검사의 예외적·조건부 보완수사조차 인정하지 않으면 억울함을 호소하는 피의자나 피해자를 보호하기 힘들다’고 말했고, 홍기원 의원도 “대통령께서 공소시효 만료가 코앞으로 다가온 상황 등을 예로 들지 않았나. 구체적으로 합당하게 잘 얘기하셨다”고 말했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Han-gyu, the party's chief deputy floor leader for policy, met with reporters after the meeting and explained, "(Unlike usual) there were many opinions in favor of the government's proposal. Many people used the President's remarks (yesterday) as a basis for their own arguments." Regarding this, Lawmaker Hong Ki-won said, "Until now, it was difficult to raise objections to the so-called hardline lawmakers' arguments. Yesterday, the President opened the floodgates first, creating an atmosphere where we can speak freely." President Lee mentioned the necessity of retaining prosecutors' supplementary investigation rights at a New Year's press conference the previous day, stating there are "cases where it is exceptionally necessary." (김한규 원내정책수석부대표는 의총 뒤 취재진을 만나 “(평소와 달리) 정부안에 대한 찬성 의견이 많았다. 본인들의 주장에 (어제) 대통령의 발언을 근거로 삼는 분들이 많았다”고 설명했다. 이에 대해 홍기원 의원은 “그동안 소위 강성 의원들의 주장에 이의를 제기하기 어려운 상황이었다. 어제 대통령이 먼저 물꼬를 트면서 자유롭게 말할 수 있는 분위기가 됐다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 전날 신년 기자회견에서 검사 보완수사권이 “예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”며 존치 필요성을 언급한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Various opinions were also presented regarding the MCIB's investigative scope. According to the government bill, the MCIB's investigative targets are '9 major crimes' (corruption, economic crimes, public official crimes, election crimes, defense industry crimes, major disasters, drugs, national crimes such as insurrection, and cyber crimes). Within the ruling party, opinions centered around hardliners had previously dominated, arguing that the investigative scope 'must be unconditionally reduced.' However, on this day, Chief Deputy Floor Leader Kim explained that opinions varied from "limiting targets to corruption and economic crimes" to "keeping it at nine but restricting the scope through enforcement decrees." (중수청의 수사 범위를 놓고도 다양한 의견이 나왔다. 정부 법안상 중수청의 수사 대상은 ‘9개 중대범죄’(부패, 경제, 공직자, 선거, 방위사업, 대형참사, 마약, 내란 등 국가범죄, 사이버 범죄)이다. 여당에서는 그동안 강경파를 중심으로 수사 범위를 ‘무조건 줄여야 한다’는 의견이 주를 이뤘지만 이날은 수사 대상을 “부패·경제 범죄로 제한해야 한다는 의견부터, 9개로 하되 시행령으로 범위를 제한해야 한다는 의견까지 다양했다”는 게 김 수석부대표의 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The legislative notice period for the MCIB/Public Prosecution Service bills lasts until the 26th of this month. The Democratic Party plans to "try to meet the legislative notice timeline as much as possible, but without being bound by the deadline, we will gather various opinions within the party." Once opinions are consolidated, it is expected that the government will submit a revised bill around early to mid-February after party-government consultations. (중수청·공소청 법안의 입법예고 기간은 오는 26일까지다. 민주당은 “입법예고 시점을 가능하면 맞추되, 기한에 구애받지 않고 다양한 당내 의견을 수렴하겠다”는 계획이다. 의견이 모이면 당정 협의를 거쳐 2월 초·중순께 정부가 수정안을 다시 낼 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241233.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503774.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Those who harm our citizens will face ruin"... Largest repatriation of Cambodia scam organization members (이 대통령 “우리 국민 가해하면 패가망신”…캄보디아 조직원 최대 송환)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241234.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Those who harm our citizens will face ruin"... Largest repatriation of Cambodia scam organization members (이 대통령 “우리 국민 가해하면 패가망신”…캄보디아 조직원 최대 송환)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/296/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503777.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;청와대는 캄보디아 스캠 조직 한국 국적 피의자 73명을 22일 강제송환한다고 밝혔다. 사진은 검거 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is repatriating 73 Korean suspects, who were arrested for operating in scam organizations in Cambodia, to South Korea on a chartered plane on the 23rd. This is the largest single-case repatriation in history. President Lee Jae-myung instructed, "Make it clear that those who harm Korean citizens will face ruin, whether domestically or internationally." (정부가 캄보디아 스캠 조직에서 활동하다 검거된 한국인 피의자 73명을 전세기에 태워 23일 국내로 송환한다. 송환 규모는 단일 사건 기준으로 역대 최대다. 이재명 대통령은 “대한민국 국민을 가해하면 국내든 국외든 패가망신한다는 점을 확실하게 보여달라”고 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kang Yu-jeong, the presidential spokesperson, announced at a briefing on the 22nd, "Following President Lee's directive, the Special Task Force (TF) on Transnational Crime will forcibly repatriate 73 Korean suspects on the morning of the 23rd. They are accused of defrauding approximately 48.6 billion won from 869 of our citizens, operating from bases in Cambodia." The chartered plane carrying the suspects departed from Incheon International Airport in the afternoon of the same day. ( 강유정 청와대 대변인은 22일 브리핑을 통해 “이 대통령의 지시로 구성된 초국가범죄 특별대응 티에프(TF)가 캄보디아를 거점으로 우리 국민 869명에게 약 486억원을 편취한 한국 국적 피의자 73명을 23일 오전 강제 송환한다”고 밝혔다. 피의자들을 태울 전용기는 이날 오후 인천국제공항을 출발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Kang assessed, "This repatriation of crime suspects is the largest in scale to date. It is the result of a long-term investigation by a team dispatched to Cambodia, including a dedicated Korea unit, the National Intelligence Service, and local police." The investigation team identified seven scam compounds and, after a prolonged pursuit, arrested 92 individuals last December in the southwestern port city of Sihanoukville (51 people), the Thai border city of Poipet (15 people), and the eastern highland region of Mondulkiri (26 people) in Cambodia. They decided to repatriate 73 of them. ( 강 대변인은 “이번 범죄 피의자 국내 송환은 역대 최대 규모로 캄보디아 현지에 파견된 코리아 전담반, 국가정보원, 현지 경찰 등 수사팀이 장기간 추적 끝에 거둔 성과”라고 평가했다. 수사팀은 스캠 단지 7곳을 확인한 뒤 지난해 12월 캄보디아 남서부 항구도시 시아누크빌(51명)과 타이 접경 도시 포이페트(15명), 동부 고원 지역 몬둘키리(26명)에서 92명을 검거한 뒤 이 가운데 73명을 송환하기로 한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The repatriation targets include a romance scam couple who could not be repatriated last October. They are suspected of using deepfake technology while posing as fictional characters to defraud approximately 12 billion won from 104 Korean citizens. Also included are fugitive criminals who fled to Cambodia after committing sex crimes against minors and then participated in local scam operations. The ringleader of a fraud organization, who posed as an investment expert to defraud around 19.4 billion won from young adults starting their careers and retirees, and members who committed inhumane crimes by holding victims confined in scam compounds hostage to threaten their families in Korea and extort money and valuables are also being repatriated. ( 이번 송환 대상에는 지난해 10월 국내로 송환되지 못한 로맨스 스캠 부부 사기단도 포함됐다. 이들은 가상 인물로 위장한 뒤 딥페이크 기술을 활용해 우리 국민 104명에게 약 120억원 상당을 뜯어낸 혐의를 받고 있다. 미성년자를 대상으로 성범죄를 저지른 뒤 캄보디아로 도주해 현지 스캠 범죄에 가담한 도피 사범도 이번 송환 대상에 포함됐다. 투자 전문가를 사칭해 사회 초년생과 은퇴자를 상대로 약 194억원을 뜯어낸 사기 조직의 총책, 스캠 단지에 감금된 피해자를 인질 삼아 국내에 있는 가족을 협박하고 금품을 갈취한 반인륜적 범죄를 저지른 조직원들도 함께 송환된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee mentioned the repatriation of these crime organization members at a meeting of senior secretaries presided over at the presidential office in the afternoon. He stated, "Such transnational crimes are extremely malicious and threatening, not only destroying citizens' lives but also undermining the foundation of trust in the community and even causing diplomatic disputes. We must pursue them to the end and completely eradicate their roots." He then instructed the Office of the Senior Secretary for Civil Affairs, which oversees the TF, saying, "Make it clear that committing crimes against Korean citizens will result in greater losses, not profits. Based on cooperation with foreign governments, do your utmost to recover every last penny of the criminal proceeds so that the damages suffered by our citizens can be restored." ( 이 대통령은 이날 오후 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 이번 범죄조직원 송환을 거론하며 “이러한 초국가범죄는 국민의 삶을 파괴할 뿐만 아니라 공동체의 신뢰 기반을 훼손하고 외교 분쟁까지도 야기하는 아주 악질적이고 위협적인 범죄다. 끝까지 추적해 그 뿌리를 완전히 뽑아야 하겠다”고 했다. 그러면서 티에프를 총괄하는 민정수석실에 “대한민국 국민을 상대로 범죄 행위를 하면 이익은커녕 더 큰 손해를 본다는 점을 확실하게 보여달라. 외국 정부와의 공조를 바탕으로 범죄수익을 한푼도 빠짐없이 환수해 국민 피해가 회복될 수 있도록 최선을 다해달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241234.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/296/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503777.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party Calls for 'Election Alliance' Amid Ruling Bloc Merger Moves, While Reform Party Draws a Line (여권발 합당 움직임 속 ‘선거연대’ 외치는 국힘, 선긋는 개혁신당)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241235.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;People Power Party Calls for 'Election Alliance' Amid Ruling Bloc Merger Moves, While Reform Party Draws a Line (여권발 합당 움직임 속 ‘선거연대’ 외치는 국힘, 선긋는 개혁신당)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/397/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503779.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이준석 개혁신당 대표가 지난 21일 서울 여의도 국회 중앙홀에서 단식투쟁 일주일째를 맞은 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 농성장을 찾아 대화를 하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the People Power Party and the Reform Party are downplaying the significance of the ruling bloc's merger moves that surfaced on the 22nd, calling them "an attempt to cover up mistakes with sheer size" and "the same Chinese restaurant," while closely monitoring the impact of the ruling camp's consolidation. Within the People Power Party, voices are emerging that they should accelerate efforts for an election alliance to counter the large ruling party, especially since the push for a 'double special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds has opened the door for cooperation with the Reform Party. However, the Reform Party is signaling a line should be drawn, mentioning the remaining 'Yoon Again' faction within the People Power Party. (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 22일 터져 나온 여권발 합당 움직임에 “과오를 덩치로 덮으려는 것”, “같은 중국집”이라고 의미를 폄하하면서도 여권 결집의 파장을 예의주시하는 분위기다. 당 안에선 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 추진으로 개혁신당과의 공조에 물꼬를 튼 만큼, 거대 여당에 맞서기 위한 선거 연대에 속도를 내야 한다는 말들이 나온다. 하지만 개혁신당은 국민의힘에 남아 있는 ‘윤 어게인’ 세력을 언급하며 선을 긋는 분위기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ham In-kyung, spokesperson for the People Power Party, criticized in a commentary released that day, "If the two parties merge and contest the local elections, it would not be a united team but a losing team. It would merely be seat-based coalition politics, covering up each other's mistakes with size and evading responsibility by pushing through with numbers," adding, "They are treating the local elections solely as a tool for extending power." Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, also said after the party's Supreme Council meeting that morning, "The Democratic Party and the Innovation Party are clearly the same Chinese restaurant. Politics shouldn't be conducted like having two phones on the table." This was a dismissal and minimization of the meaning of the merger proposal between the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party put forward by Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae that day, framing it as a "tool for extending power" and essentially a merger between the same party. (함인경 국민의힘 대변인은 이날 논평을 내어 “두 당이 합쳐 지방선거를 치른다면 원팀이 아니라 망팀이다. 서로의 과오를 덩치로 덮고, 책임을 회피하기 위해 숫자로 밀어붙이는 의석 연합 정치가 될 뿐”이라며 “지방선거를 권력 연장의 도구로만 취급하고 있다”고 비판했다. 이준석 개혁신당 대표도 이날 오전 당 최고위원회의 뒤 “민주당과 혁신당은 분명히 같은 중국집이다. 전화기 두 대 놓고 하는 식으로 정치를 하면 안 된다”고 말했다. 이날 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 내놓은 조국혁신당과의 합당 제안의 의미를 “권력 연장의 도구”이자 사실상 같은 당끼리의 합당으로 폄하하고 축소한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the People Power Party, there are voices saying that to counter the ruling bloc's unification moves, they must accelerate 'conservative integration'. A second-term lawmaker said, "Representative Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike brought former President Park Geun-hye and former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min together, showing a vision of conservative integration. This should be used as an opportunity to lead to an alliance with the Reform Party." Another first-term lawmaker said, "If a merger with the Reform Party is difficult, we should at least pursue a realistic election alliance." Yet another second-term lawmaker said, "President Lee Jae-myung's recruitment of conservative figures and the merger of the two parties could be signals of a political realignment, but the party doesn't seem to be giving it much thought," adding, "Given that the Reform Party is also drawing a line at an 'election alliance', I'm worried the People Power Party might become isolated like a Galapagos party." (국민의힘 안에선 여권 통합 움직임에 맞서기 위해서라도 ‘보수통합’에 박차를 가해야 한다는 얘기가 나온다. 한 재선 의원은 “장동혁 대표의 단식으로 박근혜 전 대통령과 유승민 전 의원까지 한자리에 모여 보수 통합의 모습을 보여준 것을 계기로 개혁신당과의 연대까지 이끌어내야 한다”고 말했다. 또 다른 초선 의원은 “개혁신당과의 합당이 쉽지 않다면, 현실적인 선거 연대라도 해야 한다”고 말했다. 또다른 재선 의원은 “이재명 대통령의 보수 인사 영입, 두 당의 합당 등이 정계 개편 시작의 신호일 수 있는데 당은 별다른 고민이 없는 모습”이라며 “개혁신당도 ‘선거 연대’에는 선을 긋는 상황이라 국민의힘만 갈라파고스 정당처럼 고립될까 걱정”이라고 말했다.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;개혁신당은 일단 선거 연대 필요성에 공감하지 않는 분위기다. 이준석 대표는 이날 당 최고위에서 국민의힘을 겨냥해 “명백한 내란을 계몽령이라는 궤변으로 국민을 우롱하는 이른바 윤 어게인 세력이 숨 쉬고 있다”며 “보수 진영이 궤멸의 늪에서 빠져나오려면 윤석열과 검찰주의자들과 철저히 단절해야 한다”고 지적했다. 개혁신당 관계자는 “조국혁신당이 사라지면 선명한 제3당으로서 우리 입지를 더욱 다질 수 있다”며 “우리로서 최악의 선택은 국민의힘과 연대했는데, 선거에서 지는 것 아니겠나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform Party, for now, does not seem to share the sense of necessity for an election alliance. Leader Lee Jun-seok pointed out at the party's Supreme Council meeting that day, targeting the People Power Party, "The so-called 'Yoon Again' faction, which deceives the people by calling a clear insurrection an 'enlightenment decree', is still breathing within it," and stated, "For the conservative camp to escape the swamp of collapse, it must thoroughly sever ties with Yoon Suk-yeol and the prosecutorial supremacists." A Reform Party official said, "If the Cho Kuk Innovation Party disappears, we can further solidify our position as a clear third party," adding, "For us, the worst choice would be to ally with the People Power Party and then lose the election, wouldn't it?" (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241235.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/397/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503779.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike with Park Geun-hye's Help... So What About Han Dong-hoon? [Gongdeok Pocha] (박근혜 도움으로 단식 끝낸 장동혁…그래서 한동훈은요? [공덕포차])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241243.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike with Park Geun-hye's Help... So What About Han Dong-hoon? [Gongdeok Pocha] (박근혜 도움으로 단식 끝낸 장동혁…그래서 한동훈은요? [공덕포차])&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503860.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae made a surprise proposal for a merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, saying, "Let's join us." In response, Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, replied, "We will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and will." Regarding the merger proposal, Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs, stated, "I was contacted in advance by leader Chung," and added, "The integration of the two parties and political integration have long been President Lee Jae-myung's established position." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 조국혁신당에 “우리와 합치자”며 합당을 전격 제안했습니다. 이에 조국 조국혁신당 대표는 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정하겠다”고 답했는데요. 홍익표 청와대 정무수석은 정 대표의 합당 제안에 대해 “사전에 정 대표에게 연락을 받았다”며 “양당 통합과 정치적 통합은 평소 이재명 대통령의 지론이었다”고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that morning, former President Park Geun-hye visited People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who had been continuing a hunger strike for eight days, and requested he stop. In response, leader Jang stated, "I am stopping the hunger strike today for a longer and bigger fight." (이날 오전 박근혜 전 대통령이 8일 간 단식을 이어온 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 찾아 단식 중단을 요청했는데요. 이에 장 대표는 “좀 더 길고 큰 싸움을 위해서 오늘 단식을 중단한다”고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What decision will leader Jang, who has ended his hunger strike, make regarding the expulsion of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon? Will the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party ultimately merge? What explanations will candidate Lee Hye-hoon, whose confirmation hearing as Minister of Planning and Finance is scheduled for the 23rd, provide regarding the suspicions raised against her so far? Let's find out on &amp;lt;Gongdeok Pocha&amp;gt;. Check out the video! (단식을 중단한 장 대표는 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표에 대한 제명을 두고 어떤 결정을 내릴까요? 민주당과 혁신당은 결국 합당을 하게 될까요? 23일 열릴 예정인 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회에서 이 후보자는 그동안 제기된 의혹들에 대해 어떤 해명을 내놓을까요? &amp;lt;공덕포차&amp;gt;에서 알아봅니다. 영상으로 확인하시죠!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Production Team&lt;br/&gt;Executive Producer: Lee Kyung-joo &lt;br/&gt;Writer: Park Yeon-shin&lt;br/&gt;Host: Song Chae-kyeonghwa&lt;br/&gt;Cast: Jang Seong-cheol, Kim Jun-il &lt;br/&gt;Title: Moon Seok-jin &lt;br/&gt;Technical Director: Park Seong-young &lt;br/&gt;Camera: Jang Seung-ho&lt;br/&gt;Subtitles/Graphics Design: Jung Hyun-sun&lt;br/&gt;Administration: Kim Geun-young&lt;br/&gt;Directors: Jung Joo-yong, Lee Gyu-ho, Jang Ji-nam&lt;br/&gt;Production: Hankyoreh TV (제작진&lt;br/&gt;책임 프로듀서 : 이경주 &lt;br/&gt;작가 : 박연신&lt;br/&gt;진행 : 송채경화&lt;br/&gt;출연 : 장성철 김준일 &lt;br/&gt;타이틀 : 문석진 &lt;br/&gt;기술 : 박성영 &lt;br/&gt;카메라 : 장승호&lt;br/&gt;자막그래픽디자인 : 정현선&lt;br/&gt;행정 : 김근영&lt;br/&gt;연출 : 정주용 이규호 장지남&lt;br/&gt;제작 : 한겨레TV)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Chae-kyeonghwa &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송채경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241243.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503860.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Mentions LS Group's Dual Listing, Calling It a "Cause of the Korea Discount" (이 대통령, LS 중복상장 언급하며 “코리아 디스카운트 원인”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241245.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee Mentions LS Group's Dual Listing, Calling It a "Cause of the Korea Discount" (이 대통령, LS 중복상장 언급하며 “코리아 디스카운트 원인”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503949.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 당내 기구인 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’ 소속 의원들이 22일 청와대 초청 오찬을 한 뒤 국회 소통관에서 브리핑을 하고 있다. 왼쪽부터 박홍배·이강일·오기형·정준호 의원. 오기형 의원 페이스북 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed that on the 22nd, the day the KOSPI index surpassed 5,000 for the first time in history, President Lee Jae-myung met with lawmakers from the Democratic Party of Korea's 'KOSPI 5,000 Special Committee' (Ocheon Committee) and mentioned the controversy surrounding LS Group's 'dual listing,' urging continued efforts for institutional improvements to protect minority shareholders' rights. At the meeting, President Lee discussed additional legislative matters, including the swift passage of the third revision to the Commercial Act, to solidify the KOSPI 5,000 era. (이재명 대통령이 코스피 지수가 사상 처음 5000을 돌파한 22일 더불어민주당 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’(오천특위) 의원들과 만나 엘에스(LS)그룹의 ‘중복상장’을 둘러싼 논란을 언급하며 소액주주 권리 보호를 위한 제도적 개선 노력을 계속할 것을 당부한 것으로 확인됐다. 이 대통령은 이 자리에서 코스피 5000 시대 안착을 위해 3차 상법 개정안의 조속한 통과 등 추가 입법 사안을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A participating lawmaker relayed that during a luncheon with the Ocheon Committee members that day, when a participant mentioned a news report titled "Don't buy stocks with an 'L' in their name," President Lee said, in essence, "Such dual listing issues become a cause of the Korea Discount," and urged, "Let's ensure we do not neglect institutional efforts (to protect minority shareholders)." (이 대통령은 이날 오천특위 의원들과 한 오찬 자리에서 “‘엘’(L)자가 들어간 주식은 안 사”라는 제목의 언론 보도를 한 참석자가 언급하자, “그런 중복상장 문제가 코리아 디스카운트의 원인이 된다”며 “(소액주주 보호를 위한) 제도적 노력에 소홀이 없도록 하자”는 취지로 말했다고 한 참석 의원이 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article President Lee referred to covered the issue of LS Group's dual listing. LS Group recently pursued the listing of its unlisted great-grandchild company, Essex Solutions. Furthermore, it is known that LS's core unlisted companies, such as LS MnM and LS Cable &amp; System, are also considering going public. However, if the parent company and an unlisted great-grandchild company are listed simultaneously, problems arise, such as the dilution of the parent company's minority shareholders' equity value and a reduction in benefits for the great-grandchild company's shareholders. (이 대통령이 언급한 기사는 엘에스그룹 중복상장 문제를 다룬 것이다. 엘에스 그룹은 최근 비상장 증손회사인 에식스솔루션즈의 상장을 추진했다. 그뿐만 아니라 엘에스엠엔엠(MnM), 엘에스전선 등 엘에스의 핵심 비상장사들도 상장을 검토하고 있는 것으로 알려졌다. 하지만 모회사와 비상장 증손회사가 동시에 상장되면 모회사 소액주주의 지분 가치가 희석되고 증손회사 주주들의 이익도 줄어드는 문제가 발생한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Oh Ki-hyung, chairman of the Ocheon Committee, later met with reporters and stated, "We discussed the need to be proactive in institutional improvements to resolve corporate dual listing issues." Additionally, during the luncheon, a consensus was formed that the third revision to the Commercial Act, which mandates companies to cancel their treasury shares, "should not be delayed any further." Discussions on institutional improvements also took place regarding the so-called 'stock price suppression prevention law' (a partial amendment to the Inheritance and Gift Tax Act) aimed at preventing listed companies facing inheritance from intentionally lowering their stock prices for inheritance tax reduction purposes. (오천특위 위원장인 오기형 의원은 이후 기자들을 만나 “기업 중복상장 문제를 해결하기 위한 제도 개선에 적극적이어야 한다는 얘기를 나눴다”고 전했다. 아울러 이날 오찬에서는 기업의 자기 주식을 의무적으로 소각하게 하는 내용을 담은 3차 상법 개정안과 관련해 “더 이상 미루면 안 된다”는 공감대가 형성됐고, 상속을 앞둔 상장기업이 상속세 절세를 위해 의도적으로 주가를 낮추는 것을 막기 위한 이른바 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’(상속세 및 증여세법 일부개정법률안)에 대한 제도 개선 논의도 이뤄졌다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol, Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241245.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503949.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "No consideration at all for extending 'exemption from additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners'" (이 대통령 “‘다주택자 양도세 중과 면제’ 연장, 전혀 고려 안해”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241269.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "No consideration at all for extending 'exemption from additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners'" (이 대통령 “‘다주택자 양도세 중과 면제’ 연장, 전혀 고려 안해”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691231511452_20260123500202.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said regarding the 'exemption from additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners' which ends on May 9, "We are not considering an extension at all." (이재명 대통령이 오는 5월9일 종료되는 ‘다주택자 양도세 중과 면제’에 대해 “연장을 전혀 고려하지 않고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee posted his thoughts on real estate policy on X (formerly Twitter) on the 23rd. The additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners adds 20 percentage points to the base tax rate (6-45%) for two-homeowners in adjustment target areas, and 30 percentage points for owners of three or more homes. When combined with the local income tax of 10%, the effective tax rate for a three-homeowner reaches 82.5%. This system was introduced by the Moon Jae-in administration in 2021, but the Yoon Suk Yeol administration deferred the additional tax for one year in May 2022 and has been extending it annually since. However, President Lee has made clear his position that he will not extend it further and will abolish it. (이 대통령은 23일 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 글을 올려 부동산 정책에 대한 생각을 밝혔다. 다주택자 양도세 중과는 기본세율 6~45%에, 조정대상지역에서는 2주택자에게 기본세율 20%포인트, 3주택 이상 소유자는 30%포인트를 각각 중과한다. 여기에 지방소득세 10%까지 합치면 3주택자가 부담하는 실효세율은 82.5%다. 이 제도는 2021년 문재인 정부에서 도입됐지만, 윤석열 정부는 2022년 5월 양도세 중과를 1년간 유예하고, 매년 이를 1년씩 연장해왔다. 하지만 이 대통령은 이를 더 이상 연장하지 않고, 폐지하겠다는 입장을 분명히 밝힌 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also stated, "Not only for multiple homes, but even a single non-owner-occupied home is for investment or speculation, not for residence, so it seems odd to grant tax reductions for long-term holding," adding, "The long-term holding special deduction system ends up blocking supply and encouraging speculation." Furthermore, President Lee added, "If we must adjust the tax system, wouldn't it be fair to treat non-owner-occupied and owner-occupied properties differently?" (이 대통령은 또 “다주택은 물론, 비거주 1주택도 주거용이 아닌 투자 투기용이라면 장기보유했다고 세금감면 (하는 건) 이상해 보인다”며 “장기보유특별공제 제도가 매물을 막고 투기를 권장하는 꼴”이라고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “만약 부득이 세제를 손보게 된다면 비거주용과 거주용은 달리 취급해야 공정하지 않겠냐”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241269.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691231511452_20260123500202.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[View Briefing] Democratic Party and Cho Kuk Innovation Party, Merger? ([뷰리핑] 민주·조국혁신, 합당?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241279.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[View Briefing] Democratic Party and Cho Kuk Innovation Party, Merger? ([뷰리핑] 민주·조국혁신, 합당?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500385.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host: Kwon Tae-ho, Editorial Director of The Hankyoreh. Guests: Ha Eo-young, The Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter, and Jang Hyun-joo, Attorney. (진행: 권태호 한겨레 논설위원실장. 출연: 하어영 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 장현주 변호사)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'December 3 Martial Law' in Han Deok-soo's court ruling... Park Seong-jae and Lee Sang-min face heavy sentences / The full story behind Jeong Cheong-rae's controversial unilateral decision and 'merger proposal'? / 'Nomination donation' investigation accelerates... Police secure Kim Kyeong's 'Golden PC' / 'Park Geun-hye effect'? Jang Dong-hyeok stops hunger strike after 8 days, "to fight a bigger battle..." / Lee Hye-hoon's confirmation hearing today... Heated debate expected over numerous suspicions / 'KOSPI 5000' becomes reality... Is it 'overheated' or 'undervalued'? Please tune in for today's (January 23) View Briefing. (한덕수 판결문 속 ‘12·3 계엄’…박성재·이상민 중형 전망 / 독단 결정 논란 빠진 정청래, ‘합당 제안’ 전말은? / ‘공천 헌금’ 수사 가속화…경찰, 김경 ‘황금PC’ 확보 / ‘박근혜 효과’? 장동혁, 8일만 단식 중단 “더 큰 싸움하려…” / 오늘 이혜훈 청문회…숱한 의혹 두고 공방 예상 / 현실화 된 ‘코스피 5000’…‘과열’일까 ‘저평가’일까? 오늘(01월 23일) 뷰리핑 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241279.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500385.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Amid Jang Dong-hyeok's Dramatic Comeback and Isolation Crisis, Pro-Han Dong-hoon Faction Urges "Han Dong-hoon Must Be Nominated for By-election" (장동혁 기사회생에 고립위기 친한계 “한동훈 보궐선거 공천 줘야”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241284.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/591/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500732.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 지난 14일 당 윤리위원회가 본인을 제명 결정한 것과 관련한 기자회견을 마친 뒤 의원들과 회견장을 빠져나오고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Jeong-hoon, a People Power Party lawmaker belonging to the pro-Han Dong-hoon faction, demanded on the 23rd that Party Leader Jang Dong-hyeok consider nominating former leader Han Dong-hoon for a by-election. This is the first response from the pro-Han faction following Leader Jang's dramatic 'one-week hunger strike' comeback, after he faced a leadership crisis for pushing hard for former leader Han's expulsion. (친한동훈계인 박정훈 국민의힘 의원은 23일 장동혁 대표에게 한동훈 전 대표의 보궐선거 공천을 검토해야 한다고 요구했다. 한 전 대표 제명을 밀어붙이다 리더십 위기를 맞았던 장동혁 대표가 ‘일주일 단식’으로 기사회생한 뒤 나온 친한계의 첫 반응이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post that day, Rep. Park argued, "To bring former leader Han's supporters to the polls, we must also actively consider nominating him for a by-election," adding, "If things continue like this, a significant number of supporters may abstain, which could be a fatal blow to the election." He further emphasized, "We must not overlook that former leader Han is a major shareholder of our party, having won 43% in the last presidential primary, and that he has fought the Lee Jae-myung administration most effectively." As former leader Han's sense of isolation within the party grew—he was the only one who did not visit the protest tent during Leader Jang's hunger strike period—key pro-Han figure Rep. Park appears to have launched a 'save Han Dong-hoon' campaign, leveraging the sense of crisis following the party's crushing defeat in the local elections. (박 의원은 이날 페이스북에 글을 올려 “한 전 대표 지지자들을 투표장으로 이끌어 내기 위해 보궐선거 공천도 적극 검토해야 한다”며 “이대로라면 지지자 상당수가 기권해 선거에 치명타가 될 수 있다”고 주장했다. 그러면서 “한 전 대표는 지난 대선후보 경선에서 43%를 얻은 우리당의 대주주라는 점, 그리고 이재명 정부와 가장 잘 싸워온 분이라는 걸 간과해서는 안 된다”고 강조했다. 장 대표의 ‘위기 탈출’로 단식 기간 유일하게 농성 텐트를 찾지 않았던 한 전 대표의 당내 고립감이 커지자, 친한계 핵심인 박 의원이 지방선거 참패에 대한 위기감을 앞세워 ‘한동훈 구하기’에 나선 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Park demanded, "The disciplinary action against former leader Han must be withdrawn," and "Those who attempted a fabricated disciplinary action must also be held accountable." He then stressed, "We must unite to achieve results in the fight against the ruling party," adding, "Unless the entire party unites as one, the momentum for the fight will inevitably weaken." (박 의원은 “한 전 대표에 대한 징계를 철회해야 한다”며 “조작징계를 시도한 자들에 대한 책임도 물어야 한다”고 요구했다. 이어 “대여투쟁에 성과를 내기 위해 단결해야 한다”며 “당 전체가 하나로 뭉치지 않고서는 투쟁의 동력이 떨어질 수밖에 없다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, floor spokesperson Kwon Gyu-taek, when asked by reporters whether the party's Supreme Council meeting on the 26th would deliberate on the motion to expel former leader Han, said, "Nothing has been decided yet on what agenda items will be raised," and "I understand the deadline for former leader Han's request for a retrial is today." (이와 관련해 곽규택 원내대변인은 ‘26일 당 최고위원회의에서 한 전 대표 제명안을 의결하느냐’는 기자들 물음에 “아직 무엇을 의제로 올릴지 정해진 바가 없다”며 “한 전 대표 재심 청구 시한은 오늘까지로 알고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241284.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/591/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500732.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:06:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Opens Another Coastal Tourist Area on East Coast... Yeombunjin Park District Completed After 15 Years (북, 동해안에 또 해안관광지…염분진공원지구 15년만에 준공)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1241285.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500749.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;함경북도 경성군 염분리에서 ‘염분진해안공원지구’ 준공식이 21일 진행됐으며, 박명호 함경북도인민위원회 위원장이 준공사를 했다고 23일 노동신문이 보도했다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea's Rodong Sinmun reported on the 23rd that the 'Yeombunjin Coastal Park District' has been completed in Yeombun-ri, Kyongsong County, North Hamgyong Province. It was finally completed after a difficult 15-year construction period that began in July 2011. This marks the opening of another beach tourism area on North Korea's east coast, following the 'Wonsan Kalma Coastal Tourist Area' which opened on July 1, 2025. (북한 함경북도 경성군 염분리에 ‘염분진해안공원지구’가 준공됐다고 23일 노동신문이 보도했다. 2011년 7월 착공한 지 15년 만에 어렵사리 완공됐다. 2025년 7월1일 개장한 ‘원산갈마해안관광지구’에 이어 북한 동해안에 또다른 해변관광지가 문을 연 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun reported that the completion ceremony for the Yeombunjin Coastal Park District was held on the 21st, with Pak Myong Ho, Chairman of the North Hamgyong Provincial People's Committee, presiding over the ceremony. The newspaper stated, "The Yeombunjin Marine Resort and Beach, featuring comprehensive service facilities including accommodation for several hundred people, a cinema, shops, electronic game rooms, and a water park, have been splendidly constructed in the Yeombunjin district, renowned as a scenic spot of the East Sea." It further emphasized, "The Yeombunjin Coastal Park District is a monumental creation that embodies the Workers' Party of Korea's ideology of prioritizing the masses." Compared to Rodong Sinmun's report that the Wonsan Kalma Coastal Tourist Area has an accommodation capacity of "20,000 people," the Yeombunjin Coastal Park District with its "accommodation for several hundred people" is estimated to be much smaller in scale. (노동신문은 염분진해안공원지구 준공식이 21일 진행됐으며, 박명호 함경북도인민위원회 위원장이 준공사를 했다고 보도했다. 신문은 “동해명승으로 자랑높은 염분진지구에 수백명의 숙박능력과 영화관, 상점, 전자오락장, 물놀이장을 비롯한 종합적인 봉사시설이 꾸려진 염분진해양려관과 해수욕장 등이 훌륭히 건설됐다”고 전했다. 이어 “염분진해안공원지구는 조선로동당의 인민대중제일주의 사상이 집대성된 기념비적 창조물”이라고 강조했다. 원산갈마해안관광지구의 숙박능력이 “2만명”이라는 노동신문의 보도에 비춰 “수백명 숙박능력”의 염분진해안공원지구는 규모가 훨씬 작은 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Yeombunjin Coastal Park District project originally began in July 2011 with the groundbreaking of the 'Yeombunjin Hotel' under the instruction of then-Chairman of the National Defence Commission Kim Jong Il. Later, in July 2018, Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and President of the State Affairs Commission, visited the site and "pointed out that even six years after the completion of the framework construction, the interior finishing had not been completed." He instructed to "rally for the struggle to carry out the instructions of the leader (Kim Jong Il) and splendidly complete the Yeombunjin Hotel by October 10th (the Party Foundation Day) of the following year (2019)." At the time, Rodong Sinmun reported that General Secretary Kim Jong Un "presented the direction and methods for construction to uniquely develop the Yeombunjin district into an excellent cultural and recreational site for the people." Considering that at this recent completion ceremony, Chairman Pak Myong Ho stated in his address that "the respected Marshal (Kim Jong Un), who personally visited the construction site, concretely clarified the methods for building a modern coastal park with various service facilities," it is presumed that in 2018, General Secretary Kim instructed to expand the 'Yeombunjin Hotel' construction project into the 'Yeombunjin Coastal Park District' project. (염분진해안공원지구는 애초 김정일 국방위원장의 지시에 따라 2011년 7월 ‘염분진호텔’ 착공으로 시작됐다. 그러다 김정은 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장이 2018년 7월 이곳을 찾아 “골조공사를 끝낸 때로부터 6년이 지나도록 내부미장도 완성하지 못하고 있는데 대하여 지적”하고 ”수령(김정일)의 유훈관철전에로 총궐기시켜 다음해(2019년) 10월10일(노동당 창건 기념일)까지 염분진호텔을 보란듯이 일떠세워라”라고 지시했다. 김정은 총비서는 “염분진지구를 인민들의 훌륭한 문화휴식터로 이채롭게 꾸리기 위한 건설방향과 방도를 제시”했다고 당시 노동신문이 전했다. 이번 준공식에서 박명호 함북인민위 위원장이 준공사를 통해 “몸소 공사장에 찾아오신 경애하는 (김정은) 원수님께서 여러가지 봉사시설을 갖춘 현대적인 해안공원을 꾸리기 위한 방도들을 구체적으로 밝혀주셨다”고 밝힌 데 비춰, 2018년 김 총비서가 ‘염분진호텔’ 건설 사업을 ‘염분진해안공원지구’ 건설 사업으로 확장하라 지시한 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, General Secretary Kim Jong Un did not attend this completion ceremony. The Korean Central News Agency reported that Premier Pak Pong Ju attended the ceremony. Previously, General Secretary Kim attended the completion ceremony for the 'Onpho Workers' Resort' in Kyongsong County, North Hamgyong Province on the 20th, but was absent from the 'Yeombunjin Coastal Park District' completion ceremony, which is not far from there. Compared to the precedent set in July 2018 when General Secretary Kim visited Kyongsong County, North Hamgyong Province and conducted on-site guidance at both the 'Onpho Resort' and 'Yeombunjin Hotel' construction sites, this is a noticeable 'difference in treatment.' It is unclear whether this is due to the smaller scale of the 'Yeombunjin Coastal Park District' or other reasons. (다만 김정은 총비서는 이날 준공식에는 참석하지 않았다. 조선중앙통신은 박태성 내각총리가 준공식에 참석했다고 전했다. 앞서 김 총비서는 지난 20일 함경북도 경성군의 ‘온포근로자휴양소’ 준공식에 참석했으나 그곳에서 멀지 않은 ‘염분진해안공원지구’ 준공식엔 불참한 것이다. 김 총비서가 2018년 7월 함북 경성군을 찾아 ‘온포휴양소’와 ‘염분진호텔’ 건설장을 함께 현지지도한 선례에 비춰, 눈에 띄는 ‘차별 대우’다. ‘염분진해안공원지구’의 규모가 작아서인지, 아니면 다른 이유가 있는지는 확인되지 않는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Jae-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1241285.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500749.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:06:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's Approval Rating at 61% Amid '5,000 P'... Democratic Party 43%, People Power Party 22% [Gallup] (‘오천피’에 이 대통령 지지율 61%…민주 43%, 국힘 22% [갤럽])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241290.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691316030187_20260123500896.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A public opinion poll result shows President Lee Jae-myung's approval rating rebounding and re-entering the 60% range. The positive impact of the KOSPI breaking through 5,000 was significant despite high exchange rates and a worsening real economy. The approval rating for the Democratic Party of Korea, which proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, rose, while the approval rating for the People Power Party fell despite its self-assessment of conservative consolidation through the party leader's hunger strike. (이재명 대통령 지지율이 반등하며 60%대로 재진입한 여론조사 결과가 나왔다. 고환율과 실물경제 악화에도 코스피 5000 돌파 호재가 컸다. 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 더불어민주당 지지율은 상승했고, 당대표 단식을 통한 보수 결집 자평에도 국민의힘 지지율은 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gallup Korea released the poll on the 23rd, conducted from the 20th to the 22nd among 1,000 eligible voters aged 18 and over nationwide (sampling error ±3.1%p at a 95% confidence level, response rate 12.3%, telephone interview using virtual mobile numbers). (한국갤럽은 20∼22일 전국 만 18살 이상 유권자 1000명을 대상으로 실시한 여론조사(표본오차는 95% 신뢰수준에서 ±3.1%포인트, 응답률 12.3%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화 인터뷰)를 23일 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evaluation of President Lee's job performance was 61% 'doing well' and 30% 'doing poorly'. Compared to last week, positive evaluation increased by 3 percentage points and negative evaluation decreased by 2 percentage points. Reasons cited for positive evaluation included diplomacy (27%) and economy/livelihoods (14%), while reasons for negative evaluation included economy/livelihoods/high exchange rates (22%) and dictatorship/arbitrariness (7%). Among moderates, positive evaluation (64%) was nearly three times higher than negative evaluation (23%). (이 대통령 직무 수행 평가는 ‘잘하고 있다’ 61%, ‘잘못하고 있다’ 30%였다. 지난주에 견줘 긍정 평가는 3%포인트 늘고 부정 평가는 2%포인트 줄었다. 긍정 평가 이유로는 외교(27%), 경제·민생(14%)을, 부정 평가 이유로는 경제·민생·고환율(22%), 독재·독단(7%)을 꼽았다. 중도층의 경우 긍정 평가(64%)가 부정 평가(23%)보다 3배 가까이 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party support rates were in the order of: Democratic Party 43%, People Power Party 22%, Cho Kuk Innovation Party 3%, Reform Party 2%, and Progressive Party 1%. The Democratic Party's support rate rose by 2 percentage points compared to last week, while the People Power Party's fell by 2 percentage points. The People Power Party's support rate has declined for two consecutive weeks (26%→24%→22%). The eight-day hunger strike by People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok failed to resonate with conservative and moderate voters. (정당 지지도는 민주당 43%, 국민의힘 22%, 조국혁신당 3%, 개혁신당 2%, 진보당 1% 순이었다. 민주당 지지율은 지난주에 견줘 2%포인트 올랐고, 국민의힘은 2%포인트 하락했다. 국민의힘 지지율은 2주 연속 하락했다.(26%→24%→22%) 8일간 이어진 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식이 보수·중도 유권자에게 반향을 일으키지 못한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed contents of this poll result, please refer to the websites of Gallup Korea and the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (이번 여론조사 결과의 자세한 내용은 한국갤럽과 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241290.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691316030187_20260123500896.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:06:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Woo Sang-ho: "Merger of Democratic and Innovation Parties is an old story... Not a surprise announcement by Chung Cheong-rae alone" (우상호 “민주-혁신 합당, 오래된 이야기…정청래 혼자 기습 발표 아냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241291.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500910.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;우상호 전 대통령실 정무수석. 김태형 기자 xogud555@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, former Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho, who is preparing to run for the governor of Gangwon Province, commented on the merger discussions between the Democratic Party of Korea and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, stating, "It's a fairly old story," and "I understand it has been progressing under the surface for several months." (강원지사 출마를 준비하는 우상호 전 청와대 정무수석이 더불어민주당과 조국혁신당의 합당 논의와 관련해 “꽤 오래된 얘기”라며 “물 밑에서 수개월간 진행돼왔다 알고 있다”고 23일 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appearing on SBS Radio's 'Kim Tae-hyun's Political Show' that day, the former senior secretary said, "I understand that discussions on whether to merge or integrate the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party have been progressing under the surface for several months." He added, "Regarding the concept of integration and whether it is desirable or not, I have also had conversations with Representative Chung Cheong-rae, and I have spoken with Representative Cho Kuk as well. I have even once asked President Lee Jae-myung for his opinion. Therefore, I don't think it's a completely new topic." (우 전 수석은 이날 에스비에스(SBS)라디오 김태현의 정치쇼에 출연해 “(민주당과 혁신당이) 합당하는 게 어떻겠냐, 통합하는 게 어떻겠냐 하는 논의는 물밑에서 수개월간 진행돼왔다고 알고 있다”고 말했다. 우 전 수석은 “통합에 대한 구상이나 그게 바람직한가, 하지 않은가에 대해서는 저도 정청래 대표와 대화를 나눈 적이 있고, 조국 대표와도 대화를 나눈 적이 있고, (이재명) 대통령께도 의견을 한 번 물어본 적도 있다. 그렇기 때문에 아주 없던 얘기는 아니라고 본다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the perception that Representative Chung made the merger proposal 'surprisingly,' he said, "I have no information on whether the announcement was perfectly coordinated," but added, "What our party's supporters and lawmakers should know is that it was not a sudden, surprise announcement made by Representative Chung alone." Regarding President Lee Jae-myung's reaction to the merger discussions, the former senior secretary stated, "In principle, I have heard remarks to the effect that, while it's unclear when exactly integration and moving forward together will happen, eventually we will have to go together," and clarified, "He has never said anything like 'push for it right now in this or that way.'" (정 대표가 합당을 ‘기습적으로’ 제안한 것과 관련해선 “발표가 완벽하게 조율된 것이냐에 대해서는 정보가 없다”면서도 “우리 당 지지층이나 국회의원들이 알아두셔야 할 것은 정 대표 혼자서 갑자기 기습적으로 발표한 게 아니다”라고 했다. 우 전 수석은 합당 논의에 대한 이재명 대통령의 반응과 관련해 “원칙적으로 통합해서 같이 가는 게 언제가 될지는 모르겠지만, 언젠가는 같이 갈 수밖에 없지 않겠냐 하는 정도의 말씀을 들은 적 있다”며 “‘지금 바로 어떻게 어떻게 추진해봐라’ 이렇게 얘기하신 적은 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241291.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/583/350/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500910.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:05:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Still Insufficient”… President Lee’s First Reaction on the Day the KOSPI Touched 5,000 (“아직 부족해”…이 대통령 ‘코스피 5천’ 터치한 날 첫 반응)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241293.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/723/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500955.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령(왼쪽)과 22일 장중 5000을 돌파한 코스피 모습(오른쪽). 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI intraday broke through 5,000 for the first time in history, it was reported that President Lee Jae-myung called for additional market reform measures, stating, "It is still far from sufficient," and "We must not become complacent." (코스피가 장중 사상 처음으로 5000을 돌파한 가운데 이재명 대통령이 “아직 많이 부족하다”, “느슨해지지 말라”며 추가적인 시장 개혁 조처를 주문한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview on the YouTube broadcast 'Kim Eo-jun's News Factory: Humility is Difficult' on the 23rd, Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Lee So-young shared the behind-the-scenes story of a luncheon the previous day at the Blue House attended by President Lee and members of the Democratic Party's 'KOSPI 5,000 Special Committee' (5,000 Special Committee). The luncheon, held at President Lee's invitation, was planned to reaffirm the resolve to achieve KOSPI 5,000. However, it garnered significant attention as the KOSPI broke through 5,000 just before the luncheon. (이소영 더불어민주당 의원은 23일 유튜브 방송 ‘김어준의 겸손은 힘들다 뉴스공장’과 인터뷰에서 전날 청와대에서 이 대통령과 ‘민주당 코스피 5000 특별위원회’(오천특위) 위원들이 함께한 오찬 뒷이야기를 전했다. 이 대통령 초청으로 이뤄진 오찬은 코스피 5000 달성 전 결의를 다지는 차원에서 계획된 것이었는데, 오찬에 앞서 코스피가 5000을 돌파하면서 큰 주목을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, it is said that President Lee's first reaction was closer to caution than celebration. Lawmaker Lee relayed, "We thought he would start by saying 'You've worked hard,' but our president did not do so." She stated, "(President Lee's) first words were, 'I think we are still far from sufficient,' 'I hope we do not become complacent,' 'I hope we properly carry out market reforms now that we have started. If we don't do it while our government is cheering us on, we may never get another chance.'" He reportedly urged them to steadily continue market reform measures aimed at improving corporate governance and protecting shareholder value, following the first and second revisions of the Commercial Act. Indeed, the Blue House and President Lee have not issued any separate public statement regarding KOSPI 5,000. (하지만 이 대통령의 첫 반응은 자축이 아닌 경계에 가까웠다고 한다. 이 의원은 “고생했다, 수고했다는 얘기로 시작할 줄 알았는데 우리 대통령이 그러시지 않더라”라고 전했다. 이 의원은 “(이 대통령의) 첫 말씀이 ‘아직 많이 부족하다 생각한다’, ‘느슨해지지 않았으면 좋겠다’, ‘이번에 시작한 김에 시장 개혁 제대로 했으면 좋겠다. 우리 정부 때 응원해 줄 때 하지 않으면 다시는 기회가 없을 수도 있다’(였다)”고 말했다. 1, 2차 상법 개정안에 이어 기업 지배구조를 개선하고 주주 가치를 보호하는 시장 개혁 조처를 차분히 이어가 달라고 당부했다는 것이다. 실제로 청와대와 이 대통령은 코스피 5000과 관련해 별다른 공개 입장을 내지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Nam-geun, also a member of the 5,000 Special Committee, appeared on the same broadcast and explained that the price-to-book ratio (PBR) of KOSPI-listed companies is still low compared to emerging markets, adding, "(President Lee) suggested that the Korea Discount has not been fully resolved." (오천특위 소속 김남근 민주당 의원도 같은 방송에 나와 코스피 상장사들의 주가순자산비율(PBR)이 신흥국들에 견줘 여전히 낮다는 점을 설명하면서 “(이 대통령이) 코리아 디스카운트가 다 해소되지 않은 게 아니냐(는 취지로 말했다)”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the luncheon, President Lee and the Democratic Party agreed to promptly process the third revision of the Commercial Act, which centers on mandatory treasury stock cancellation. Discussions were also held on institutional improvements such as the 'Stock Price Suppression Prevention Act' (revision of the Inheritance and Gift Tax Act) and the 'Dual Listing Prevention Act' (revision of the Capital Markets Act). (오찬 자리에서 이 대통령과 민주당은 자사주 의무소각을 골자로 하는 3차 상법 개정안을 조속히 처리하기로 의견을 모았다. 주가 누르기 방지법(상속세 및 증여세법 개정안), 중복상장 방지법(자본시장법 개정안) 등의 제도 개선 논의도 이뤄졌다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the luncheon on the 22nd, Representative Oh Gi-hyeong, chairman of the 5,000 Special Committee, met with reporters at the National Assembly and stated, "There was an assessment that (the KOSPI breaking 5,000) is the result of consistent policy efforts, including forming a task force for capital market revitalization and pushing for Commercial Act revisions, which President Lee Jae-myung has dedicated himself to since his time as party leader." He added, "We shared the understanding that the party and the Blue House must continuously make efforts for institutional reforms to strengthen the fundamental health of the capital market." (오천특위 위원장인 오기형 의원은 오찬 뒤 22일 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “(코스피 5000 돌파는) 자본시장 활성화 티에프(TF) 구성, 상법 개정 추진 등 이재명 대통령이 당대표 시절부터 공을 들여온 일관된 정책 의지의 결과물이라는 평가가 있었다”며 “당과 청와대가 자본시장의 기초 체력을 강화하기 위한 제도 개혁의 노력을 지속적으로 해야 한다는 데 공감을 가졌다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241293.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/723/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123500955.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:05:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>33% say Han Dong-hoon's expulsion 'appropriate', 48% among PPP supporters... Intra-party rejection resurfaces (한동훈 제명 ‘적절’ 33%, 국힘 지지층에선 48%…당내 거부감 또 드러나)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241299.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/763/416/imgdb/child/2026/0123/17691424471509_20260114503696.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 14일 국회 소통관에서 제명 결정을 한 당 윤리위원회 결정에 대해 기자회견을 한 뒤 회견장을 나오고 있다. 윤운식 기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;While some in the pro-Han Dong-hoon faction are demanding &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/politics/politics_general/1241284.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;'Han Dong-hoon nominations'&lt;/a&gt; as a relief pitcher to save the party from the crushing defeat in the local elections, opinion polls continue to show that the sentiment of 'vetoing Han Dong-hoon' is strong among supporters of the People Power Party (PPP). (친한동훈계 일부에서 지방선거 참패에서 당을 구할 구원투수로 &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/politics/politics_general/1241284.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;‘한동훈 공천’을 요구&lt;/a&gt;하고 있지만, 국민의힘 지지층의 ‘한동훈 비토’ 정서가 크다는 여론조사 결과가 거듭 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gallup Korea released a poll on the 23rd, conducted from the 20th to the 22nd on 1,000 voters aged 18 and over nationwide (margin of error ±3.1%p at a 95% confidence level, response rate 12.3%, virtual mobile number telephone interview). (한국갤럽은 20∼22일 전국 만 18살 이상 유권자 1000명을 대상으로 실시한 여론조사(표본오차는 95% 신뢰수준에서 ±3.1%포인트, 응답률 12.3%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화 인터뷰)를 23일 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP Ethics Committee decided on the 14th to expel former PPP leader Han Dong-hoon, citing the party member bulletin board incident. Voter opinions on the expulsion were divided: 33% said it was appropriate, 34% said it was inappropriate, and 33% reserved their answer. (국민의힘 윤리위원회는 지난 14일 당원게시판 사태를 이유로 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표 제명을 결정했다. 제명에 대한 유권자 의견은 갈렸다. 적절했다 33%, 부적절했다 34%, 답변 유보는 33%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking only at PPP supporters (223 people, margin of error ±7%p at a 95% confidence level), the result is even more painful for the former leader. This is because nearly half, 48%, responded that the expulsion was appropriate. Only 35% said it was inappropriate. (국민의힘 지지층(223명, 95% 신뢰수준에 표본오차 ±7%포인트)만 떼어놓고 보면, 한 전 대표에게 더 뼈아픈 결과가 나온다. 절반 가까운 48%가 제명이 적절했다고 답했기 때문이다. 부적절하다는 응답은 35%에 그쳤다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gallup analyzed public opinion on the former leader's expulsion by dividing voters' political leanings into five levels. Among the strongly conservative (very conservative), 62% said appropriate and 27% said inappropriate. Among the moderately conservative (somewhat conservative), 40% said appropriate and 36% said inappropriate. Among moderates, more held the opinion that it was inappropriate (37%) than appropriate (26%). (갤럽은 유권자 정치 성향을 5단계로 나눠 한 전 대표 제명 여론을 분석했다. 극보수층(매우 보수적)에서는 적절 62%, 부적절 27%, 약보수층(약간 보수적)에서는 적절 40%, 부적절 36%였다. 중도층에서는 부적절 의견(37%)이 적절 의견(26%)보다 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gallup Korea stated, "Currently, the PPP faces the task of attracting moderates in preparation for the local elections while also responding to the demands of its hardcore supporters." However, the poll results lean towards suggesting it is difficult to satisfy both demands simultaneously. &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/politics/politics_general/1241084.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;A national indicator survey released the previous day&lt;/a&gt; (margin of error ±3.1%p at a 95% confidence level, response rate 20.2%, virtual mobile number telephone interview) also confirms the rejection sentiment towards the former leader among conservatives. Among PPP supporters, positive evaluation of Han Dong-hoon's expulsion was 53%, while negative evaluation was 39%. (한국갤럽은 “현재 국민의힘은 강성 지지층 요구에 부응함과 동시에 지방선거를 대비해 중도층 유인이라는 과제를 안고 있다”고 했다. 다만 여론조사 결과는 이런 요구를 동시에 만족시키기 어렵다는 쪽으로 기운다. &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/politics/politics_general/1241084.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;전날 나온 전국지표조사&lt;/a&gt;(표본오차 95% 신뢰수준에 ±3.1%포인트·응답률 20.2%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화면접)에서도 보수층의 한 전 대표 거부 정서가 확인된다. 국민의힘 지지층의 한동훈 제명 긍정 평가는 53%, 부정 평가는 39%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed contents of the opinion poll results, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (여론조사 결과의 자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241299.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/763/416/imgdb/child/2026/0123/17691424471509_20260114503696.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:04:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Six Military Personnel Including Former 707th Special Mission Group Commander Kim Hyun-tae Face Disciplinary Committee Today for 'Involvement in Rebellion' Charges (김현태 전 707단장 등 ‘내란가담 혐의’ 군인 6명 오늘 징계위)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241301.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/659/395/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501115.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;12·3 내란 당시 국회에 투입됐던 육군 특수전사령부 707특수임무단을 이끈 김현태 특임단장이 지난해 2월6일 서울 종로구 헌법재판소에서 열린 탄핵 심판 6차 변론기일에 증인 출석하며 취재진의 질문에 답하고 있다. 사진공동취재단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of National Defense announced it will hold a disciplinary committee on the 23rd for six military personnel accused of involvement in the December 3 rebellion. (국방부가 12·3 내란에 가담한 혐의를 받는 군인 6명의 징계위원회를 23일 개최한다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those referred to the disciplinary committee are two generals and four colonels: former 1st Airborne Special Forces Brigade Commander Lee Sang-hyun (Brigadier General), former Counterintelligence Command Counterintelligence Investigation Group Commander Kim Dae-woo (Brigadier General), former 707th Special Mission Group Commander Kim Hyun-tae (Colonel), former Defense Intelligence Agency Planning Department Chief Go Dong-hee (Colonel), former Central Media Group Commander Kim Bong-gyu (Colonel), and former 100th Brigade 2nd Project Group Commander Jeong Seong-uk (Colonel). (징계위에 회부된 이들은 이상현 전 제1공수특전여단장(준장), 김대우 전 국군방첩사령부 방첩수사단장(준장), 김현태 전 707특수임무단장(대령), 고동희 전 국군정보사령부 계획처장(대령), 김봉규 전 중앙신문단장(대령), 정성욱 전 100여단 2사업단장(대령) 등 장군 2명과 대령 4명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colonel Kim Hyun-tae, who led the 707th Special Mission Group during the deployment to the National Assembly at the time of the December 3 emergency martial law declaration and served as the on-site commander of the martial law forces, and Brigadier General Lee Sang-hyun are accused of involvement in the blockade and infiltration of the National Assembly (performing important tasks for rebellion). Brigadier General Kim Dae-woo of the Counterintelligence Command is accused of ordering the arrest of politicians, while Colonel Go Dong-hee of the Defense Intelligence Agency and two others are accused of involvement in plans to occupy the National Election Commission and arrest its staff. (12·3 비상계엄 선포 때 707특수임무단을 이끌고 국회에 출동한 계엄군의 현장지휘관이었던 김현태 대령과 이상현 준장은 국회 봉쇄와 침투에 관여한 혐의(내란 중요임무종사)를 받는다. 방첩사 김대우 준장은 정치인 체포조를 지시한 혐의를, 정보사의 고동희 대령 등 3명은 중앙선거관리위원회 점거 및 선관위 직원 체포 계획에 관여한 혐의를 받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These individuals were indicted without detention last March, removed from their positions, and are currently on trial in a military court. Their former superiors, former Counterintelligence Command Commander Yeo In-hyeong and former Defense Intelligence Agency Commander Moon Sang-ho, received dismissal disciplinary actions, and former Special Warfare Command Commander Kwak Jong-geun was removed from his post. (이들은 지난해 3월 불구속 기소된 뒤 보직해임된 상태에서 군사법원 재판을 받고 있다. 방첩사 및 정보사 상관이었던 여인형 전 방첩사령관과 문상호 전 정보사령관은 파면 징계를 받았고, 곽종근 전 특전사령관은 해임됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241301.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/659/395/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501115.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon: "Confused with second son... Eldest son's Yonsei University admission was through social contributor track" (이혜훈 “차남과 헷갈려…장남 연세대 입학, 사회기여자 전형”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241314.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/816/490/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691375045225_20260123501289.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 재정경제기획위원회의 인사청문회에서 머리카락을 넘기고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, clarified that her statement on the 23rd that her eldest son was admitted to Yonsei University through the multi-child admissions track was a mistake, and that he was actually admitted through the social contributor track, as his grandfather was recognized as a national prestige enhancer. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 장남이 다자녀 전형으로 연세대에 입학했다고 답변한 것은 실수였으며, 시아버지가 국위선양자로 인정돼 사회기여자전형으로 입학한 것이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, the nominee responded to a question from People Power Party lawmaker Choi Eun-seok regarding her eldest son's admission to Yonsei University. She stated, "It was 17 years ago, and I have three sons, so I couldn't remember which one it was. (The multi-child track) was for my second son; confusing him with my eldest son was a mistake," adding, "(My eldest son) was admitted through the social contributor track, and it appears he was admitted as a national prestige enhancer." Previously, the nominee had told her confirmation hearing preparation team that her eldest son, who entered Yonsei University's Department of Economics in 2010, was "admitted not through the special admissions track for social contributors, but through the multi-child track." Controversy arose over potential 'daddy's chance' favoritism as the nominee's husband was a professor in the Yonsei University Department of Economics at the time. (이 후보자는 이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 장남의 연세대 입학과 관련한 최은석 국민의힘 의원 질의에 “17년 전이고 아들이 셋이라 그중에 누군지 기억하지 못했다. (다자녀 전형은) 차남이었는데, 차남과 헷갈린 것은 실수”라며 “(장남은) 사회기여자 전형이고, 국위선양자로 입학한 것으로 보인다”고 했다. 앞서 이 후보자는 인사청문준비단에 2010년 연세대 경제학부에 입학한 장남에 대해 “사회적 기여자 특별전형이 아닌, 다자녀 전형으로 입학했다”라고 답변한 바 있다. 이 후보자의 남편이 연세대 경제학부에 재직 중이어서 ‘아빠 찬스’ 논란이 불거졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee further explained, "Yonsei University's criteria for national prestige enhancers are based on specific types of medals. My father-in-law's qualification was not due to his achievements as a politician, but because he received the Order of Service Merit, Green Stripes, for his public service as a civil servant, which met the requirements." She emphasized, "That is a qualification requirement, but Yonsei University has consistently stated that it is not reflected at all in the evaluation determining student selection." She continued, "For selection, he submitted six items including his school records, CSAT scores, and various English test scores. (Admission) is evaluated through written and oral exams." (이 후보자는 이어 “국위선양자의 연세대 기준은 훈장 종류를 정해놓고 있다. 시부가 정치인으로의 공적이 아니고, 공무원일 때의 공적을 인정받아 청조근정훈장을 받아 자격요건이 됐다”며 “그건 자격요건이지 학생 선발 여부를 따지는 평가에는 일절 반영되지 않는다는 게 연세대가 계속 공표하고 있는 사항”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “선발은 내신과 수능, 각종 영어시험(성적) 6개를 냈다. (합격 여부는) 필기시험과 구술시험으로 평가한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Choi questioned, "Can we say that the grandfather enhanced national prestige because he served as Minister of Home Affairs and received a medal? Through this, the nominee is essentially admitting to an unfair admission." In response, the nominee rebutted, "It's not a rule I made; it's a rule the university made." Lawmaker Choi countered, "At the time, the nominee's husband was the head of the Academic Affairs Office at Yonsei University," adding, "Lee Hye-hoon's eldest son essentially seized a spot meant for a social contributor." (최 의원은 “장남의 할아버지가 내무부 장관을 해서 훈장을 받은 게 우리나라의 국위를 선양했다고 할 수 있나”라며 “이런 걸 통해 부정 입학을 했다는 걸 후보자가 그대로 자백하고 있는 것”이라고 했다. 이에 이 후보자는 “제가 만든 규정이 아니고 학교가 만든 규정”이라고 반박했다. 최 의원은 “당시 후보자 남편은 연세대 교무부처장”이라며 “사회 기여자 자리를 이혜훈 후보자의 장남이 강탈한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241314.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/816/490/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691375045225_20260123501289.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:04:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Centrist and Progressive Voters Far More Likely to Predict 'Stock Price Rise'... Conservative Voters Predominantly Predict Decline [Gallup Korea] (중도·진보 ‘주가 상승’ 전망 크게 앞서…보수층은 하락  우세 [한국갤럽])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241316.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/419/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501315.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 오전 서울 중구 우리은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In September of last year, Gallup Korea asked voters whether they thought the KOSPI reaching 5000 would be possible under the Lee Jae-myung administration. At the time, the KOSPI was around 3100. 50% of voters predicted it would be impossible. About a month later, when the KOSPI was around the 4000 level, they asked again. This time, nearly half (45%) said reaching KOSPI 5000 was possible. (지난해 9월 한국갤럽은 이재명 정부 내 코스피 5000 달성이 가능할지 유권자 의견을 물었다. 당시 코스피는 3100 정도였다. 유권자 50%는 불가능할 것으로 내다봤다. 한달여 뒤 코스피 4000선 때 다시 물었다. 이번에는 절반 가까운(45%) 이들이 코스피 5000도 가능하다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, as the KOSPI reached 5000 for the first time in history, a public opinion survey result showed that forecasts for continued domestic stock price increases significantly outnumbered forecasts for declines. Among stock holders, expectations for price increases were even higher. (22일 사상 처음으로 코스피 5000을 달성한 가운데, 앞으로 국내 주가가 계속 오를 것이라는 전망이 하락 전망을 크게 앞서는 여론조사 결과가 나왔다. 주식 보유층에서 주가 상승 전망이 더 높게 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gallup Korea, which regularly surveys stock price outlooks, released the results of a public opinion survey (conducted from the 20th to the 22nd) on the outlook for domestic stock index fluctuations over the next year on the 23rd. The forecast that it 'will rise from current levels' was 45%. This led the forecast that it 'will fall' (25%) by 20 percentage points. 20% responded that there would be no change. (주가 전망을 주기적으로 조사해온 한국갤럽은 23일 앞으로 1년 국내 주가지수 등락 전망 여론조사 결과(20∼22일 조사)를 공개했다. ‘현재보다 오를 것’이라는 전망은 45%였다. ‘내릴 것’이라는 전망(25%)을 20%포인트 앞섰다. 변화가 없을 것이라는 응답은 20%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nearly half of voters (48%) said they invest in stocks or ETFs. Excluding respondents who do not invest in stocks and looking only at stock holders, the expectation for a rise becomes stronger. 55% of stock holders predicted a stock price increase. Only 27% of stock holders forecast a decline. (유권자 절반 가까이(48%)가 주식이나 ETF 투자를 하고 있다고 했다. 주식투자를 하지 않는 응답자를 빼고, 주식 보유자만 놓고 보면 상승 전망이 더 강해진다. 주식 보유자의 55%가 주가 상승을 내다봤다. 하락을 전망한 주식 보유자는 27%에 그쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is a difference from the economic outlook opinions surveyed together by Gallup (38% said it will improve, 36% said it will worsen, 23% said it will be similar). Gallup analyzed, "Overall, the KOSPI outlook is more positive than the economic outlook. This is interpreted as a perceived disconnect between the real economy and the financial economy." (다만 갤럽이 함께 조사한 경기 전망 의견(좋아질 것 38%, 나빠질 것 36%, 비슷할 것 23%)과는 차이가 있다. 갤럽은 “전반적으로 경기 전망보다 코스피 전망이 더 긍정적이다. 이는 실물경제와 금융경제의 체감적 괴리로 읽힌다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tendency to forecast positively among supporters of the Lee Jae-myung administration and negatively among opponents was clear. Among conservative voters, the forecast for a decline (39%) was higher than the forecast for a rise (31%). Looking only at supporters of the People Power Party, the gap between the decline forecast (42%) and the rise forecast (24%) widened further. In contrast, among centrist voters (rise 46%, decline 26%) and progressive voters (rise 67%, decline 12%), the rise forecast led significantly. The rise forecast among supporters of the Democratic Party of Korea (64%) was 53 percentage points higher than the decline forecast (11%). The contrast was also stark between those who positively evaluate President Lee Jae-myung's job performance (rise 62%, decline 12%) and those who negatively evaluate it (rise 21%, decline 50%). Gallup interpreted this as "showing the inseparability of economic outlook and political perception." The stock ownership ratio by political inclination showed no significant difference, hovering around 50%. (이재명 정부 지지층에서는 잘 되는 쪽으로, 비토층에서는 안 되는 쪽으로 전망하는 경향은 뚜렷했다. 보수층에서는 하락 전망(39%)이 상승 전망(31%)보다 많았다. 국민의힘 지지층만 놓고 보면 하락 전망(42%)과 상승 전망(24%) 차이가 더 벌어졌다. 반면 중도층(상승 46%, 하락 26%), 진보층(상승 67%, 하락 12%)에서는 상승 전망이 크게 앞섰다. 더불어민주당 지지층의 상승 전망(64%)은 하락 전망(11%)보다 53%포인트나 높았다. 이재명 대통령 직무 긍정 평가자(상승 62%, 하락 12%)와 부정 평가자(상승 21%, 하락 50%) 간에도 대비가 뚜렷했다. 갤럽은 “경제 전망과 정치 인식의 불가분성을 보여준다”고 해석했다. 정치 성향별 주식 보유 비율은 50% 안팎으로 큰 차이가 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although expectations for a domestic stock price rise were dominant, buoyed by the KOSPI breaking 5000, the preference for the 'U.S. market' over the 'domestic market' did not change. Only 32% pointed to domestic stocks as the 'more advantageous investment destination,' while 46% of respondents pointed to overseas stocks like those in the U.S. Even among stock holders (domestic market 42%, U.S. market 51%), sentiment for foreign stock investment was stronger. Gallup analyzed, "Even at the point of the KOSPI breaking 5000, overseas investment is still prioritized, and the younger the age, the higher the ratio." The U.S. market investment ratio was 75% for those in their 20s and 70% for those in their 30s. Among those in their 40s (domestic market 38%, U.S. market 51%), 50s (domestic market 46%, U.S. market 36%), and 60s (domestic market 41%, U.S. market 34%), the domestic market investment ratio was relatively higher. (코스피 5000 돌파에 힘입어 국내 주가 상승 전망이 우세했지만, ‘국장’(국내 증시)보다 ‘미장’(미국 증시)을 선호하는 경향은 바뀌지 않았다. ‘더 유리한 투자처’로 국내 주식을 꼽은 이들은 32%에 그쳤지만, 미국 등 해외 주식을 꼽은 응답자는 46%였다. 주식 보유층(국장 42%, 미장 51%)에서도 외국 주식 투자심리가 더 셌다. 갤럽은 “코스피 5000 돌파한 시점에도 여전히 해외 투자를 우선시하며, 특히 저연령일수록 그 비율이 높다”고 분석했다. 20대의 미장 투자 비율은 75%, 30대는 70%에 달했다. 40대(국장 38%, 미장 51%), 50대(국장 46%, 미장 36%), 60대(국장 41%, 미장 34%)에서는 국장 투자 비율이 상대적으로 높았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This survey was conducted on 1,000 voters nationwide aged 18 and over. The sampling error is ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level, with a response rate of 12.3%. It was conducted via telephone interview using virtual mobile numbers. For detailed information, please refer to the websites of Gallup Korea and the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (이번 조사는 전국 만 18살 이상 유권자 1000명을 대상으로 실시했다. 표본오차는 95% 신뢰수준에서 ±3.1%포인트, 응답률 12.3%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화 인터뷰 방식으로 진행했다. 자세한 내용은 한국갤럽과 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241316.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/419/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501315.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:03:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae: "Regarding the Merger Proposal, I Made the First Move with a Mindset to Apologize... I Ask Party Members to Make the Final Decision" (정청래 “합당, 사과할 각오로 먼저 제안…당원이 최종 결정해달라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241317.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/646/456/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501318.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 23일 충북 진천 국가대표선수촌에서 열린 현장 최고위원회의에서 박지원 최고위원의 조국혁신당과의 합당 추진을 우려하는 발언을 듣고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, regarding his proposal for a party merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party the previous day, stated, "I am deeply sorry for not being able to share this sufficiently in advance," but also explained, "I made the proposal with a mindset to apologize, thinking that if the party leader did not propose it first, it might be impossible due to time constraints." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표는 23일 자신이 전날 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 것과 관련해 “사전에 충분히 공유하지 못해 송구스럽다”면서도 “당 대표가 먼저 제안하지 않으면 시간상 불가능할지 모르겠다는 생각으로, 사과할 각오로 제안했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the on-site Supreme Council meeting held at the Jincheon National Training Center in North Chungcheong Province that day, Representative Chung said, "Many people seemed surprised and taken aback by my merger proposal yesterday (22nd). I am deeply sorry for not being able to share it sufficiently in advance due to various unavoidable circumstances and physical limitations." He continued, "However, despite that feeling of regret, I made the proposal with a mindset to apologize, thinking that if the party leader did not propose it first, a merger might be impossible before the June local elections due to time constraints." (정 대표는 이날 충북 진천국가대표선수촌에서 열린 현장 최고위원회의에서 “어제(22일) 저의 합당 제안으로 놀라고 당황하신 분들이 많았던 것 같다. 여러 불가피성과 물리적 한계 등으로 사전에 충분히 공유해드리지 못한 부분에 대해서는 송구스럽다”고 했다. 정 대표는 이어 “그런데 저는 그 송구스러움이 있었지만 이 부분은 당 대표가 먼저 제안하지 않고서는 (6월) 지방선거 전에 시간상 (합당이) 불가능할지도 모르겠다는 생각으로, 사과할 각오로 제가 제안을 했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung stated, "(The merger of the two parties) is something someone must cut the tape on someday," adding, "Now that the starting gun has sounded, the process and final destination will all be decided according to the will of the party members. If it passes in the all-member vote, we proceed; if it fails, we stop." He further said, "I also find it difficult to predict what the (party member vote) result will be. I have thrown myself into the sea of party sentiment and public sentiment." He added, "This should operate for the benefit of the entire party and its members, not for the benefit of a specific individual. I also hope party members will decide on the merger issue." (정 대표는 “(두 당의 합당은) 언젠가 누군가는 테이프를 끊어야 하는 일”이라며 “이제 시작종이 울렸으니 가는 과정과 최종 종착지는 모두 당원 뜻에 따라 결정될 것이다. 전 당원 투표에서 가결되면 가는 것이고 부결되면 멈추는 것”이라고 했다. 이어 “저도 (당원 투표) 결과가 어떻게 나올지는 예단하기 어렵다. 저는 당심과 민심의 바다에 몸을 던졌다”고 했다. 그러면서 “이는 특정 개인의 이익이 아니라, 당 전체, 당원의 이익으로 작동해야 한다. 합당 문제도 당원들께서 결정해주시길 바란다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Supreme Council meeting that day, Supreme Council members Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu did not attend. These three Supreme Council members had publicly expressed opposition after Representative Chung proposed the merger the previous day, with comments such as "He has crossed the line, and by a long way" (Kang Deuk-gu) and "I cannot shake the suspicion that this is groundwork considering the leader's re-election" (Lee Eon-joo). (이날 최고위원회의에는 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 참석하지 않았다. 세 최고위원은 정 대표가 전날 합당을 제안한 뒤 “선을 넘어도 한참 넘었다”(강득구) “대표 연임을 염두에 둔 포석이라는 의구심을 지울 수 없다”(이언주)고 공개 반발한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting that day, debates for and against the merger proposal also ensued. Supreme Council member Park Ji-won, who comes from the rank-and-file party members, pointed out, "Not only among party members but also among many lawmakers and Supreme Council members, there seems to be considerable regret that 'prior opinion gathering and deliberation were insufficient,' and the absence of some Supreme Council members also seems related to this." Supreme Council member Park cited past examples of 'surprise' integration pushes within the democratic-progressive camp, saying, "At that time too, the problem of insufficient public discussion repeatedly surfaced. Now, the scale and nature of party members are also different (from then)." He urged, "Please uphold the principles of democracy: procedure and deliberation." (이날 회의에서도 합당 제안에 대한 갑론을박이 오갔다. 평당원 출신인 박지원 최고위원은 “당원들은 물론, 여러 의원과 최고위원들 사이에서 ‘사전 의견 수렴과 숙의가 부족했다’는 아쉬움이 적지 않아 보이고, 일부 최고위원님들 불참도 이와 무관치 않아 보인다”고 짚었다. 박 최고위원은 과거 민주 진보 진영의 ‘깜짝’ 통합 추진 사례를 거론하며 “당시에도 공론화가 부족했다는 문제가 번번이 불거졌다. 지금은 (그때와) 당원의 규모와 성격도 다르다”며 “절차와 숙의라는 민주주의 원칙을 지켜달라”고 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Lee Yeon-hee (Cheongju Heungdeok-eul), a key figure in the pro-Lee Jae-myung faction who attended the on-site Supreme Council meeting that day, defended the merger proposal, saying, "Appointing Lee Hye-hoon as the candidate for Minister of Planning and Finance and proposing a merger with the Innovation Party are part of the expansion strategy being pursued by the ruling party." The lawmaker attributed significance to it, stating, "The expansion strategy of integrating healthy progressives and rational conservatives is a clear direction for national integration by the Lee Jae-myung administration, looking beyond factions to the entire nation. The merger with the Innovation Party is also not about simply adding up factions but is responsible solidarity and a choice of the times to grow solutions for people's lives." (이날 현장 최고위원회에 참석한 친이재명계 핵심 이연희(청주 흥덕을) 의원은 “이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자를 지명하고 혁신당과의 합당을 제안하는 것은 집권여당이 추진하는 확장 전략의 일환”이라고 합당 제안을 옹호했다. 이 의원은 “건전한 진보와 합리적 보수가 통합하는 확장 전략은 진영을 넘어 국민 전체를 바라보는, 이재명 정부의 분명한 국민통합의 방향”이라며 “혁신당과의 합당 역시 진영 합산이 아니라 국민 삶의 해법을 키우는 책임있는 연대이자 시대적 선택”이라고 의미를 부여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241317.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/646/456/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501318.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:03:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Min-seok Meets U.S. House Members, Says "Coupang is Not Facing Any Discrimination" (미 하원 의원들 만난 김민석 “쿠팡, 전혀 차별받지 않고 있다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241323.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691390571873_20260123501406.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;미국을 방문 중인 김민석 국무총리가 22일(현지사각) 미국 워싱턴 디.시(D.C)에서 미국 하원의원들과 오찬을 하고 있다. 총리실 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his visit to the United States, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok told some U.S. lawmakers on the 23rd that "there is absolutely no discrimination against Coupang," adding, "The Korea-U.S. relationship is one of trust to the extent that concerns about discriminatory treatment are unnecessary." (미국을 방문 중인 김민석 국무총리가 23일 미국 일부 의원들에게 “쿠팡에 대한 차별은 전혀 없다”며 “차별적인 대우는 걱정하지 않아도 될 만큼 한미관계는 신뢰관계에 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister's Office stated that during a luncheon in Washington D.C. with seven key U.S. House members, including Young Kim and Ami Bera, Prime Minister Kim responded this way when some lawmakers inquired about the Korean government's response to the current Coupang situation. Prime Minister Kim said, "Korea does not consider the Georgia incident a case of discrimination because it involved Korean workers," and added, "Similarly, the measures taken regarding Coupang are not because it is a U.S. company, and it is not facing any discrimination at all." (김 총리는 이날 미국 워싱턴 디시(D.C) 에서 미 하원의원 주요 인사인 영 킴, 아미 베라 등 7명과 오찬을 하며 일부 의원들이 현재 쿠팡 사태 관련 한국 정부의 대응에 대해 문의하자 이렇게 답했다고 총리실은 밝혔다. 김 총리는 “한국은 조지아 사건이 한국 노동자들이기 때문에 차별받은 사건이라고 생각하지 않는다”며 “마찬가지로 쿠팡도 미국 기업이라는 이유로 취한 조치가 아니며 전혀 차별받지 않고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, Prime Minister Kim expressed his pleasure, saying, "As the Prime Minister of Korea, I am delighted to have the opportunity to make a solo visit to the U.S. and meet key congressional figures for the first time in about 40 years." He added, "Through this visit to the U.S., I hope to further stabilize and continuously develop the Korea-U.S. relationship, including accelerating the implementation of follow-up measures to the Korea-U.S. customs negotiations." (김 총리는 이 자리에서 “한국 국무총리로서 40여년 만에 미국을 단독 방문해 주요 의회 인사들을 만나게 된 것을 기쁘게 생각한다”며 “이번 방미를 통해 한미 관세협상 후속조치의 이행을 가속화하는 등 한미관계를 더욱 안정적이고 지속적으로 발전시켜 나갈 수 있기를 기대한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the U.S. lawmakers emphasized the unwavering bipartisan support of the U.S. Congress for the Korea-U.S. alliance, stating, "We hope to strengthen cooperation in various areas, including economic security such as critical mineral supply chains and shipbuilding cooperation, and also expand Korea-U.S.-Japan cooperation." They also mentioned, "The 'Korea Partnership Act,' proposed by Representative Young Kim to issue up to 15,000 professional visas for Koreans annually, is currently pending in the House, and we will work towards its passage." (이에 미국 의원들은 한미동맹에 대한 미 의회의 흔들림 없는 초당적 지지를 강조하면서 “한미 간 핵심광물 공급망 등 경제안보와 조선 협력을 포함한 다양한 영역에서 협력을 강화하고, 한미일 협력 또한 확대해 나가기를 희망한다”고 화답했다. 또한 “연간 최대 1만5천 건의 한국인 전문직 비자 발급을 위해 영 킴 의원이 발의한 ‘한국 동반자법’이 현재 하원에 계류 중인바, 동 법안의 통과를 위해 노력해나갈 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241323.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691390571873_20260123501406.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:02:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk: "Public Discussion on Party Merger Just Beginning... Will Definitely Run in June Election" (조국 “합당 공론화 이제 시작…6월 선거, 무조건 출마”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241327.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691424992827_20260123501484.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 광주 동구 전일빌딩 245에서 열린 조국혁신당-광주시민단체협의회 간담회에서 조국 대표가 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, responded on the 23rd to Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae's proposal for a party merger made the previous day, stating, "We cannot merge by abandoning the Innovation Party's independent vision and values," and "We will break through the current situation by preserving and expanding the Innovation Party's DNA." (조국 조국혁신당 대표가 23일 정청래 더불어민주당 대표의 전날 합당 제안에 대해 “혁신당의 독자적인 비전과 가치를 포기하면서 합당할 수는 없다”며 “혁신당의 디엔에이(DNA)를 지키고 확장하는 방식으로 현 국면을 돌파하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a meeting with the Gwangju Citizens' Group Council at the Jeonil Building in Gwangju on the 23rd, Leader Cho said during a Q&amp;A session, "Both the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party must go through a public discussion process regarding the merger, and that procedure has just begun for both parties." He added, "Our consistent position is to judge the merger issue in a way that maintains and preserves, then develops and expands, the Innovation Party's political DNA." Cho stated, "While the two parties share the same stance on issues like the impeachment of former President Yoon, prosecutorial reform, or judicial reform, we cannot merge by abandoning the Innovation Party's independent vision and policies on political reform, constitutional amendment, social rights issues, and the public concept of land." He continued, "It should not be viewed from a political engineering perspective as merely the sum of 162 (Democratic Party) seats and 12 (Innovation Party) seats, but as a union of vision and values. If this cannot be achieved, then a merger is not possible." (조 대표는 23일 광주 전일빌딩에서 광주시민단체협의회와 간담회를 마친 뒤 진행된 질의응답에서 “민주당도, 혁신당도 (합당에 대한) 공론화 과정을 반드시 거쳐야 하고, 그 절차가 양당 모두 이제 시작된 것”이라며 “혁신당의 정치적 디엔에이(DNA)를 유지·보존하고, 발전·확대하는 방식으로 합당 문제를 판단한다는 게 일관된 입장”이라고 밝혔다. 조 대표는 “(윤 전 대통령) 탄핵 문제, 검찰 개혁이나 사법개혁은 두 당의 입장이 같지만 정치 개혁과 개헌, 사회권 문제, 토지공개념 문제 등 혁신당의 독자적 비전과 정책을 포기하면서 (합당)할 수는 없다”고 했다. 이어 “단지 (민주당) 162석과 (혁신당) 12석의 합으로 보는 (정치) 공학적 관점이 아니라 비전과 가치의 합으로 봐야 한다. 이것이 이뤄지지 못하면 합당이 안 되는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding his own future political moves, Cho said, "I have stated many times for a long time that I will definitely run in the June election, and regardless of Leader Chung's merger proposal, I will run." (조 대표 개인의 향후 정치 행보에 대해서는 “오래전부터 (이번 6월 선거에) 반드시 출마한다는 이야기를 여러 번 했고, 정 대표의 합당 제안과 관계없이 (저는) 출마한다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho mentioned plans to hold a general assembly of lawmakers on the 24th and a party affairs committee meeting on the 26th, saying, "Just as there were positions from civil society groups saying 'Absolutely not' or 'You must do it from within (the Democratic Party),' I presume there will be differing opinions within the party as well. I will listen to all discussions and, as party leader, make and pursue a responsible decision." Cho reiterated, "We will break through the current situation by preserving and expanding the Innovation Party's vision, values, and DNA." (조 대표는 오는 24일 의원총회, 26일 당무위원회의를 개최할 예정이라며 “시민사회단체에서도 ‘절대 안 된다’ ‘(민주당에) 들어가서 해야 한다’는 입장이 있었듯 당 내부에도 (이견이) 있을 거라 추측한다. 논의를 다 듣고 당 대표로서 책임 있는 결정하고 추진하겠다”고 했다. 조 대표는 “혁신당의 비전과 가치, 디엔이이를 지키고 확장하는 방식으로 현 국면을 돌파하겠다”고 재차 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241327.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691424992827_20260123501484.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:02:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Foreign Minister Cho Hyun holds Korea-EU Strategic Dialogue in Brussels…"Enhancing cooperation, including summit meetings" (조현 장관, 브뤼셀 한-EU 전략대화…“정상회담 비롯 협력 증진”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241339.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501710.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;조현 외교부 장관이 벨기에 브뤼셀 유럽연합(EU) 대외관계청(EEAS)에서 22일(현지시각) 오전 카야 칼라스 유럽연합 외교안보 고위대표와 제2차 한-EU 전략대화를 개최했다. 사진 외교부 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced on the 23rd that Foreign Minister Cho Hyun held the second Korea-European Union Strategic Dialogue with EU High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy Kaja Kallas in Brussels, Belgium, discussing plans to promote summit meetings, among other topics. (조현 외교부 장관이 벨기에 브뤼셀에서 카야 칼라스 유럽연합(EU) 외교안보 고위대표와 제2차 한-유럽연합 전략대화를 열어 정상회담 추진 계획 등을 논의했다고 23일 외교부가 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated that Minister Cho and High Representative Kallas met at the European External Action Service (EEAS) on the 22nd (local time) and "agreed to continue high-level exchanges, including summit meetings, and held in-depth consultations on ways to enhance substantive cooperation in various fields, including security and defense, and economic and trade issues." In the second year of President Lee Jae-myung's term, the South Korean government plans to pursue a visit by President Lee to Brussels or visits by EU leaders to South Korea to hold a summit with the EU. This strategic dialogue is the second one, following the first Korea-EU Strategic Dialogue held in Seoul in November 2024. In June last year, President Lee Jae-myung held a summit meeting with European Council President António Costa and European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen in Canada on the occasion of attending the G7 summit. (외교부는 조 장관과 카야 칼라스 대표가 22일(현지시각) 유럽연합 대외관계청(EEAS)에서 만나 “정상회담을 비롯한 고위급 교류를 이어나가기로 하고, 안보방위, 경제통상 분야 현안을 포함하여 다양한 분야에서의 실질협력 증진 방안에 대해 심도있는 협의를 했다”고 전했다. 이재명 대통령 취임 2년차인 올해 우리 정부는 유럽연합과 정상회담 개최를 위해 이 대통령의 브뤼셀 방문이나 유럽연합 정상들의 방한을 추진할 계획이다. 이번 전략대화는 지난 2024년 11월 서울에서 제1차 한-유럽연합 전략대화를 개최한 뒤 두번째다. 지난해 6월 이재명 대통령은 주요 7개국(G7) 정상회의 참석을 계기로 캐나다에서 안토니우 코스타 유럽연합 정상회의 상임의장 및 우르술라 폰데어라이엔 유럽연합 집행위원장과 정상회담을 한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs relayed that "Minister Cho assessed that Korea and the EU, as strategic partners, have steadily developed friendly and cooperative relations in various fields, and High Representative Kallas stated that amid the rapidly changing international situation, including the war in Ukraine, there is a need to further expand communication and cooperation between Korea and the EU as strategic partners." (외교부는 “조 장관은 한국과 유럽연합이 전략적 동반자로서 각 분야에서 우호협력 관계를 꾸준히 발전시켜온 점을 평가하였으며, 칼라스 고위대표는 우크라이나 전쟁 등 급변하는 국제정세 속에서 전략적 파트너로서 한-유럽연합 간 소통과 협력을 더욱 확대할 필요가 있다”고 했다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this meeting, opinions were exchanged on security, economic issues, as well as major regional situation issues such as the situation on the Korean Peninsula and in Northeast Asia, the war in Ukraine, and the Middle East situation. The two foreign ministers are believed to have discussed not only Korea-EU relations but also each side's responses to shared diplomatic and economic issues, such as pressure from the United States regarding high tariffs and President Donald Trump's proposal to join the Gaza Peace Committee. (이번 회의에선 안보, 경제와 더불어 한반도 및 동북아 정세, 우크라이나 전쟁, 중동정세 등 주요 지역정세 현안에 대한 의견이 오갔다. 두 외교장관은 한-유럽연합 관계 뿐 아니라, 미국의 고율 관세 압박과 도널드 트럼프 대통령이 제안한 가자 평화위원회 가입 등 양쪽이 공유하는 외교·경제 현안에 대한 서로의 대응을 논의했을 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241339.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501710.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:02:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Coup Apology' Lee Hye-hoon: "I Have Changed, But What About the People Power Party? It Hasn't." (‘내란 사과’ 이혜훈 “나는 변했다, 국힘은? 안 변해”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241344.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501767.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2020년 4월3일 미래통합당(국민의힘 전신) 서울 동대문을 이혜훈 당시 국회의원 후보가 동대문구 장안동 일대에서 유세차량을 타고 지지를 호소하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Has the People Power Party sincerely apologized and changed regarding its past defense of the December 3rd coup and former President Yoon Seok-youl? The answer given by Lee Hye-hoon, nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, who was a member of the People Power Party until about a month ago, was "No." (국민의힘은 12·3 내란과 윤석열 전 대통령을 두둔해 온 것에 대해 진정으로 사과하고 변화했을까. 약 한 달 전까지 국민의힘에 몸담았던 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 내놓은 답은 “아니요”였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee on the 23rd, the nominee apologized for her past record of defending the coup. In response to a question from Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Kim Young-hwan asking, "Are you willing to apologize to the public here and now for remarks that denied democracy and praised the December 3rd coup?", the nominee lowered her stance again, saying, "I will continue to apologize repeatedly until the public says it's okay." Earlier, in her opening statement at the hearing, she also said, "I once again apologize for having taken a position of flawed judgment from which it is difficult to escape criticism of having sympathized with the coup," and added, "I will make no excuses. The responsibility lies solely with me." (이 후보자는 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 연 인사청문회에서 자신의 내란 옹호 전력을 사과했다. 이 후보자는 ‘지금 이 자리에서 민주주의를 부정하고 12·3 내란을 찬양한 발언들을 국민들께 사과할 용의가 있느냐’는 김영환 더불어민주당 의원 질의에 “사과는 국민들이 오케이 할 때까지 끊임없이 반복하겠다”며 거듭 자세를 낮췄다. 이 후보자는 앞서 청문회 모두발언에서도 “내란에 동조했다는 비판을 피하기 어려운 잘못된 판단의 자리에 서 있었음을 다시 한번 사과드린다”며 “어떠한 변명도 하지 않겠다. 책임은 오롯이 저에게 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee, in her capacity as chairperson of the People Power Party's Seoul Junggu-Seongdong-gu Gap district committee, had defended former President Yoon's unconstitutional and illegal declaration of a state of emergency as a "high-level act of governance" and faced fierce criticism for attending a rally opposing the impeachment of former President Yoon. After being nominated as the first Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination on the 30th of last month, her first apology was saying, "I bow my head and apologize to all those who worked hard to overcome the coup in the bitter cold of winter a year ago," and "I was immersed in partisanship and missed the essence of the matter." (이 후보자는 국민의힘 서울 중구성동구을 당협위원장 신분으로 윤 전 대통령의 위헌·위법적 비상계엄 선포를 “고도의 통치행위”라며 두둔하고, 윤 전 대통령 탄핵 반대 집회에 참석한 이력으로 거센 비판을 받았다. 지난달 30일 초대 기획예산처 장관 후보자로 지명되고 난 뒤 “1년 전 엄동설한에 내란 극복을 위해 애쓴 모든 분께 머리 숙여 사과드린다”며 “당파성에 매몰돼 사안의 본질을 놓쳤다”고 말한 것이 첫 사과였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, on this day, the nominee clearly drew a line regarding her former party, the People Power Party. When asked by lawmaker Kim, "Do you believe the People Power Party has apologized, just as you have apologized?", she replied, "Not yet." When asked if she had seen the People Power Party apologize after the court's guilty verdict on the 21st against former Prime Minister Han Duck-soo on charges of performing important tasks for the coup, the nominee said, "I have not seen it." The People Power Party, which had even tried to elevate former Prime Minister Han as a presidential candidate, has not apologized despite the court's ruling that "the December 3rd state of emergency was a coup." (하지만 이날 이 후보자는 친정이었던 국민의힘에 대해서는 확실히 선을 그었다. 그는 ‘이 후보자가 사과한 것처럼 국민의힘도 사과를 했다고 보시냐’는 김 의원의 질의에 “아직은”이라고 답했다. 지난 21일 법원이 한덕수 전 국무총리의 내란 중요임무 종사 혐의에 유죄를 선고한 뒤 국민의힘이 사과한 것을 본 적 있느냐는 질문에도, 이 후보자는 “제가 본 적은 없다”고 말했다. 한 전 총리를 대선 후보로까지 옹립하려 했던 국민의힘은 ‘12·3 비상계엄은 내란’이라는 법원의 판단이 나왔음에도 사과하지 않고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When lawmaker Kim asked again, "Do you admit that the People Power Party has not changed?", the nominee replied, "That is my view." The People Power Party expelled the nominee on the 28th of last month, stating that her agreement to be appointed as a minister in the Lee Jae-myung administration while serving as an incumbent district party committee chairperson was an "act of collaboration" and "the corresponding act." (김 의원이 ‘국민의힘이 변화되지 않았다는 것을 인정하느냐’고 재차 묻자, 이 후보자는 “저는 그렇게 보고 있다”고 말했다. 국민의힘은 현역 당협위원장 신분으로 이재명 정부 국무위원장 임명에 동의한 것은 “부역 행위” “해당 행위”라며 지난달 28일 이 후보자를 제명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241344.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501767.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:01:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party to Recommend Professor Ko Min-soo as Standing Member of the Broadcasting and Communications Commission (민주당, 방미통위 상임위원으로 고민수 교수 추천키로)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/assembly/1241349.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/559/618/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501912.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;고민수 강릉원주대 교수. 민주언론시민연합 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea held its Supreme Council meeting on the 23rd and decided to recommend Professor Ko Min-soo of the Department of Law at Gangneung-Wonju National University as the party's standing member of the Broadcasting and Communications Commission. (더불어민주당은 23일 최고위원회의를 열어 방송미디어통신위원회(방미통위) 민주당몫 상임위원으로 고민수 강릉원주대 법학과 교수를 추천하기로 의결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Ko, a constitutional scholar and former journalist for Jeonju Broadcasting, has served as an investigator for the Korea Communications Commission, a director of the Korean Constitutional Law Association, a research director of the Korean Society for Journalism and Communication Studies, and a director of the Korean Association of Law Professors. The Democratic Party plans to finalize discussions on recommending its non-standing members to the commission soon and pass the recommendation motion at a plenary session of the National Assembly, potentially as early as next week. (고 교수는 전주방송 기자 출신의 헌법학자로 방송위원회 조사관, 한국헌법학회 이사, 한국방송학회 연구이사, 한국법학교수회 이사 등을 지냈다. 민주당은 조만간 자당 몫의 방미통위 비상임위원 추천 논의를 마무리지은 뒤 이르면 다음주 열리는 국회 본회의에서 추천안을 의결할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, the Broadcasting and Communications Commission is operating under a 'two-person system' with Chairman Kim Jong-cheol, recommended by President Lee Jae-myung, and non-standing member Ryu Shin-hwan. If the Democratic Party recommends two members, the commission will secure a quorum for meetings. Commission meetings can be convened with the attendance of four or more members, and agenda items can be passed with the approval of a majority of attending members. The commission is composed of seven members: two (including the chairman) recommended by the President, two by the ruling party, and three by the opposition parties. (현재 방미통위는 이재명 대통령이 추천한 김종철 위원장과 류신환 비상임위원 ‘2인 체제’로 운영되고 있다. 민주당이 위원 2명을 추천하면 방미통위는 개의 정족수를 확보하게 된다. 방미통위 회의는 4명 이상 위원의 출석으로 개의하고, 출석위원 과반 찬성으로 안건을 의결할 수 있다. 방미통위는 대통령이 2명(위원장 포함), 여당이 2명, 야당이 3명을 추천해 7명의 위원으로 구성된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Se-young &lt;a href="mailto:monad@hani.co.kr"&gt;monad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이세영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:monad@hani.co.kr"&gt;monad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/assembly/1241349.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/559/618/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501912.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:01:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "KOSPI at 5,000, National Pension Fund Grows by 250 Trillion Won... Concerns About Depletion Have Eased" (이 대통령 “코스피 5천, 국민연금 250조 늘어…고갈 걱정 덜었다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241350.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691480456709_20260123501920.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 23일 울산전시컨벤션센터에서 열린 ‘울산의 마음을 듣다’ 타운홀미팅 간담회에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the KOSPI index surpassing 5,000, President Lee Jae-myung said, "When Korean companies are properly valued, the wealth of all our citizens increases." (이재명 대통령이 코스피 지수가 5000을 돌파한 것과 관련해 “대한민국 기업들이 제대로 평가받으면, 우리 국민 모두의 재산이 늘어나는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a 'Town Hall Meeting' held in Ulsan on the 23rd, President Lee said, "Everyone is happy and praising the fact that the stock index surpassed 5,000 points yesterday. But on the other hand, some say, 'What does the stock market rising have to do with me? Why am I only falling? Am I completely falling into ruin because I invested in 'Kopbus' or 'Inverse'?' That's the way of the world." 'Inverse' refers to an Exchange-Traded Fund (ETF) that yields profits when the stock index falls, and 'Kopbus' is a portmanteau of 'multiply' and 'inverse,' referring to a product that yields double the profit when the index falls. (이 대통령은 23일 울산에서 열린 ‘타운홀 미팅’에서 “전날 주가지수가 5000포인트를 돌파했다고 다들 기뻐하기도 하고, 칭찬해주기도 한다. 또 그러면서 한편으론 ‘주가가 오른 것과 나랑 뭔 상관이냐. 나는 왜 떨어지기만 하느냐, 나는 ‘곱버스’, ‘인버스’를 타서 완전히 나락으로 떨어지고 있냐’고 (얘기한다.) 세상의 이치가 그런 것”이라고 말했다. 인버스는 주가지수가 하락하면 수익이 나는 상장지수펀드(ETF)를 말하며, 곱버스는 ‘곱하기+인버스’의 합성어로 지수 하락에 2배로 수익을 내는 상품이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He emphasized that even if people who predicted stocks would fall and invested accordingly are incurring losses, the National Pension Fund is making profits. President Lee said, "The National Pension Fund holds stocks of Korean companies, and its (profits) have increased by about 250 trillion won," adding, "Concerns that the National Pension Fund would be depleted in a certain year or that people would die without receiving their pensions have almost disappeared. At the very least, most people here no longer need to worry about pension depletion." (주식이 떨어질 것이라고 예측해 투자한 사람들은 손해를 보고 있다고 하더라도 국민연금은 수익을 내고 있다고 강조했다. 이 대통령은 “국민연금이 우리나라 기업 주식을 가지고 있는데 250조원 정도 (수익이) 늘어났다”며 “국민연금이 몇 년도에 고갈되느니, (연금을) 못 받고 죽을 거 같다고 (걱정하던 게) 거의 다 없어져 버렸다. 최소한 여기 있는 분들은 대부분 연금 고갈 걱정을 안 해도 되는 상황이 됐다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at this event, President Lee directly mentioned Lee Sun-ho, the Presidential Secretary for Autonomous Development, who is resigning on the 25th to run for Mayor of Ulsan, and Jeon Eun-soo, the Deputy Spokesperson who is from Ulsan. When President Lee said, "Deputy Spokesperson Jeon's hometown is here in Ulsan, right? Is Secretary Lee also from Ulsan?" attendees applauded. (한편 이 대통령은 이 자리에서 울산시장 출마를 위해 25일 사직하는 이선호 청와대 자치발전비서관과 울산 출신인 전은수 부대변인을 직접 거론했다. 이 대통령은 “전 부대변인 고향이 여기 울산이죠? 이 비서관도 울산 사람인가요”라고 말하자 참석자들은 박수를 치기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241350.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691480456709_20260123501920.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:01:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[News Dive] Controversy over the Merger of the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party ([뉴스 다이브] 민주·조국혁신 합당 논란)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241356.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502030.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Featuring: Attorney Roh Young-hee, Attorney Jang Yun-mi, Democratic Party Senior Deputy Spokesperson Lim Se-eun; Host: Ko Hyun-joon. Why now? Controversy over the Merger of the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party / President Lee's approval rating at 61% amid '5,000 P'...Democratic Party at 43% / People Power Party's 'Yoon Again, Park Again'...approval rating after hunger strike at 22% / Testimony of 'Private Meeting between Yoon Suk-yeol and Lee Man-hee Two Months Before Presidential Election' / Hong Joon-pyo: "Yoon Became Presidential Candidate with 50,000 Shincheonji Votes" / Signal Sent by Han Duck-soo's 23-Year Sentence to Kim Yong-hyun, Lee Sang-min, and Park Seong-jae / Will He Step Down or Hold On?...What is the 'Fate' of Lee Hye-hoon Amid Controversy? Please tune in to today's (January 23) News Dive. (출연: 노영희 변호사, 장윤미 변호사, 임세은 민주당 선임부대변인, 진행: 고현준. 왜 지금? 민주·조국혁신 합당 논란 / ‘오천피’에 이 대통령 지지율 61%...민주 43% / ‘윤어게인·박어게인’ 국힘...단식 결과는 지지율 22% / ‘대선 2월 전, 윤석열-이만희 독대’ 증언 / 홍준표 “윤, 신천지 5만표로 대선 후보 됐다” / 한덕수 23년형, 김용현·이상민·박성재에 던진 신호 / 물러나나 버티나...논란 속 이혜훈 ‘운명’은? 오늘 (1월 23일) 뉴스 다이브 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241356.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502030.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:00:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party's 'Anti-Chung' Trio: "The Blue House Coordination Theory Is Not True...Reveal the Full Picture of the Merger Proposal" (민주 ‘반청’ 3인방 “청와대 교감설 사실 아냐…합당설 전모 밝혀라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241362.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/770/446/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502113.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원이 23일 국회 소통관에서 정청래 대표의 조국혁신당 합당 제안과 관련해 입장을 밝히고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, Supreme Council Members Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Eon-joo, and Hwang Myeong-seon of the Democratic Party of Korea demanded an "official apology" and a full disclosure of the circumstances behind the merger proposal from party leader Chung Cheong-rae, who had abruptly proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party on the 22nd. These members, classified as part of the 'anti-Chung Cheong-rae faction' within the party leadership, raised their voices regarding the theory of prior coordination with the Blue House emerging from Chung's side, stating, "It is not true," and urged, "Do not drag the Blue House into this." (지난 22일 조국혁신당에 합당을 전격 제안한 정청래 더불어민주당 대표를 향해 같은 당 강득구·이언주·황명선 최고위원이 ‘공식 사과’와 함께 합당 제안의 전모를 밝히라고 23일 요구했다. 민주당 지도부 내 ‘반정청래계’로 분류되는 이들은 청와대와 사전 조율설이 정 대표 쪽에서 나오는 것과 관련해 “사실이 아니”라며 “청와대를 끌어들이지 말라”고 목소리를 높였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They held a press conference at the National Assembly Communication Center and criticized, "The problem is that merger discussions proceeded even without the knowledge of the Supreme Council members, and the undemocratic nature of its procedure and process," adding, "A structure where even elected Supreme Council members cannot voice their opinions, a structure that only forces agreement on the leader's decisions, is not democratic party operation. It is a clear overreach and abuse of authority by the party leader." Regarding reports that Chung had prior discussions with the Blue House before announcing the merger proposal, the three Supreme Council members refuted, "According to our verification, it is not true." They stated, "(The claim that the two-party merger was President Lee Jae-myung's usual stance) was merely a past, principled remark; yesterday's announcement was not at all an issue shared in advance with the Presidential Office," and added, "Dragging the President into the center of political controversy is neither serving the President nor the party." (이들은 국회 소통관에서 기자회견을 열어 “최고위원들조차 모르는 사이에 합당 논의가 진행됐다는 점, 그 절차와 과정의 비민주성이 문제”라며 “선출된 최고위원들이 의견조차 낼 수 없는 구조, 대표 결정에 동의만 강요하는 구조는 민주적 당 운영이 아니다. 당 대표자의 명백한 월권이며 직권남용”이라고 비판했다. 세 최고위원은 정 대표가 합당 제안 발표 전 청와대와 사전 교감을 나눴다는 보도와 관련해 “확인 결과, 사실이 아니다”라고 반박했다. 이들은 “(양당 합당은 이재명 대통령의 평소 지론이었다는) 과거 원론적 언급 수준이었을 뿐, 어제 발표는 대통령실과 사전 공유된 사안이 전혀 아니었다”며 “대통령을 정치적 논란의 한가운데로 끌어들이는 일은 대통령을 위하는 일도, 당을 위하는 일도 아니”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three Supreme Council members presented demands to Leader Chung, including △an official apology, △measures to prevent the recurrence of autocratic party operation, and △disclosure of the full picture leading up to the merger proposal. They further stated, "We sternly warn against Chung Cheong-rae's 'selective party member sovereignty'," and said, "Chung Cheong-rae-style unilateralism must end now. It can no longer be tolerated." (세 최고위원은 정 대표를 향해 △공식 사과 △독선적 당 운영에 대한 재발방지 대책 △합당 제안이 나오기까지의 전모 공개 등의 요구 사항을 내놨다. 그러면서 “정청래 대표의 ‘선택적 당원주권’에 대해 엄중히 경고한다”며 “정청래식 독단은 이제 끝나야 한다. 더이상 용납할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Q&amp;A with reporters after the conference, they strongly criticized Leader Chung with high-intensity remarks such as "one-sided ruling-style leadership from the dictatorship era" and "arrogant and unilateral." They also dismissed Chung's statement made earlier that day at a Supreme Council meeting in Jincheon, North Chungcheong Province, which the three members did not attend, where he said, "I am sorry," but also "I made the proposal prepared to apologize," calling it "talk not worth a penny." (이들은 회견 뒤 취재진과의 질의·응답에서 “독재정권 때 해왔던 일방통치식 리더십” “독선이고 독단”이라는 강도 높은 발언으로 정 대표를 강하게 비판했다. 이날 정청래 대표가 세 최고위원이 불참한 충북 진천 현장 최고위원회의에서 “송구하다”면서도 “사과할 각오로 제안했다”고 말한 데 대해서도 “일고의 가치가 없는 얘기”라고 일축했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council Member Hwang Myeong-seon criticized, "The form of unilaterally meeting and announcing with Representative Cho Kuk without seeking opinions from the Supreme Council members elected by party members or from the party members themselves is not the proper conduct for someone who advocates for a party based on party member sovereignty," adding, "This is the 'top-down,' one-sided ruling-style leadership practiced during past dictatorship regimes." (황명선 최고위원은 “당원들이 선출한 최고위원이나 당원들에게 의견을 구하지 않고 일방적으로 조국 대표를 만나 이야기하고 발표하는 형태가 당원주권정당을 표방하는 분으로서 해야 할 도리가 아닌 것”이라며 “이는 과거 독재 정권 때 해왔던 ‘탑-다운’식, 일방통치식 리더십”이라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241362.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/770/446/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502113.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon: "I am hearing all about how much pressure is being put on my former aides within the People Power Party" (이혜훈 “국힘에서 옛 보좌진 얼마나 압박하는지 다 듣고 있다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241363.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502140.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 재정경제기획위원회의 인사청문회에서 의원 질의에 답하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, stated, "I am also hearing all about how much pressure is being put on my former aides who are still affiliated with the People Power Party within the party." This is an assertion that pressure and persuasion are being applied to her former aides remaining in the People Power Party to make negative statements about her. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 “지금 국민의힘에서 국민의힘에 소속돼 있는 옛날 제 보좌진들에게 얼마나 압박을 하는지 저도 다 듣고 있다”고 말했다. 국민의힘에 남아 있는 옛 보좌진에게 자신에 대한 부정적 진술을 하도록 압박과 회유가 이뤄지고 있다는 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee that day, in response to questions from People Power Party lawmaker Park Dae-chul regarding allegations of power abuse towards aides, the nominee said, "I sincerely apologize and will continue to apologize to the many staff members I have hurt." However, she added, "Many of those (allegations) are also untrue." In response, Rep. Park retorted, "Are you saying that those individuals (the aides) are now making false statements?" and "You are now insulting the members of the hearing committee." The nominee then said, "If I caused any misunderstanding on that part, I apologize," and "I will not use the expression 'pressure'." Nevertheless, she reiterated, "There are far too many stories that differ from the facts." (이 후보자는 이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 보좌진 갑질 의혹과 관련한 박대출 국민의힘 의원 질의에 “제가 상처를 준 많은 우리 직원들에게 제가 진심으로 사과하고, 계속 사과하겠다”면서도 “그중에 사실이 아닌 것들도 많다”고 말했다. 이에 박 의원은 “지금 그분(보좌진)들이 허위진술을 했다고 이야기를 하시는 거냐”며 “지금 청문위원들을 모독하고 있다”며 반발했다. 그러자 이 후보자는 “그 부분은 위원님께 오해하게 했다면 죄송하다”며 “압박이라는 표현은 안 하겠다”고 했다. 그러면서도 “사실과 다른 이야기가 너무 많다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Park disclosed statements from the nominee's former aides that day, saying, "It is said there were several employees who worked while taking psychiatric medication. It is said that when the nominee's name suddenly appeared on their mobile phones, their hands would tremble violently. It is said that because staff changed so frequently, they referred to themselves among themselves as the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd generations of the Lee Hye-hoon office." (박 의원은 이날 “정신과 약 먹으면서 근무했던 직원들이 여럿 있었다고 한다. 휴대폰에 (이 후보자) 이름이 딱 뜬다 그러면 두 손이 벌벌 떨렸다고 한다. 직원들이 너무 바뀌니까 우리끼리는 이혜훈실 1기, 2기, 3기 이런 식으로 불렀다고 한다”는 이 후보자의 옛 보좌진 진술을 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241363.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502140.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:00:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President states 'suspension of the multi-homeowner capital gains tax surcharge deferral'; will he also touch 'well-off single homeowners'? (‘다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 중단’ 밝힌 대통령, ‘똘똘한 한 채’도 손댈까)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241368.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502309.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관회의에서 참석자들과 국민의례를 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, President Lee Jae-myung stated that he will not extend the 'deferral of the capital gains tax surcharge for multi-homeowners', which ends on May 9. He also hinted that the capital gains tax for houses used for 'speculation', even if owned by a single homeowner who does not actually reside there, could be adjusted. Initially, President Lee had said, "I will avoid using taxes to control housing prices if possible," but as the upward trend in Seoul real estate prices continues, he appears to be considering tax reform measures. (이재명 대통령이 오는 5월9일 종료되는 ‘다주택자 양도세 중과 유예’를 연장하지 않겠다고 23일 밝혔다. 또 1주택자라 하더라도 실제 거주하지 않는 ‘투기용’ 주택의 양도세는 손볼 수 있다는 뜻을 내비쳤다. 애초 이 대통령은 “세금으로 집값을 잡는 것은 가능하면 하지 않겠다”고 했지만, 서울 부동산 상승세가 멈추지 않자 세제개편 카드를 검토하는 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, President Lee stated on X (formerly Twitter), "Extending the deferral of the capital gains tax surcharge for multi-homeowners, which expires on May 9, is not being considered at all." The multi-homeowner capital gains tax surcharge is a system that adds, on top of the basic tax rate (6-45%), an extra 20 percentage points for owners of two homes and 30 percentage points for owners of three or more homes in regulated areas like Seoul. When combined with the local income tax of 10%, the effective tax rate for owners of three or more homes can reach up to 82.5%. This system was introduced in 2021 under the Moon Jae-in administration, but the Yoon Suk-yeol administration has deferred the surcharge for one year starting May 2022 and has extended it annually since then. (  이 대통령은 이날 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 “5월9일 만기인 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 연장은 전혀 고려하지 않고 있다”고 밝혔다. 다주택자 양도세 중과는 기본세율(6~45%)에 더해 서울 등 조정대상지역에서 2주택자는 20%포인트, 3주택 이상 보유자는 30%포인트를 추가로 부과하는 제도다. 여기에 지방소득세 10%까지 합치면 3주택자의 실효세율은 최대 82.5%에 이른다. 이 제도는 2021년 문재인 정부에서 도입됐지만, 윤석열 정부는 2022년 5월부터 양도세 중과를 1년간 유예한 뒤 매년 이를 연장해 왔다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government's decision not to extend the deferral of the surcharge this time is largely aimed at inducing multi-homeowners to list their properties on the market. Since the surcharge will be applied starting May 10, it is believed that multi-homeowners may list their properties before that date to avoid it. (  정부가 이번에 양도세 중과 유예 연장을 않기로 결정한 데는, 이를 통해 다주택자 매물이 시장에 나오도록 유도하려 했던 측면이 크다. 5월10일부터 중과세가 이뤄지는 만큼, 이를 피하려는 다주택자들이 그 전에 매물을 내놓을 가능성이 있다고 본 것이다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also hinted at tax reform for 'speculative single homes'. He said, "Not only for multi-homes, but even for a single non-owner-occupied home, if it's for investment or speculation, it seems odd to grant tax reductions just for long-term holding," adding, "The long-term holding special deduction system ends up blocking supply and encouraging speculation." President Lee added, "We won't reform the tax system immediately, but these are topics that should be discussed." Currently, single homeowners receive a deduction of 24% of capital gains if the holding period is over 3 years, and up to 80% if over 10 years. However, his remarks imply that granting tax reductions even for speculative purposes does not align with tax justice. (  이 대통령은 ‘투기용 1주택’에 대한 세제 개편도 시사했다. 이 대통령은 “다주택은 물론, 비거주 1주택도 주거용이 아닌 투자·투기용이라면 장기보유했다고 세금감면 (하는 건) 이상해 보인다”며 “장기보유특별공제(장특공제) 제도가 매물을 막고 투기를 권장하는 꼴”이라고 했다. 이 대통령은 “당장 세제를 고칠 건 아니지만, 토론해봐야 할 주제들”이라고 덧붙였다. 현재 1주택자는 보유 기간이 3년 이상이면 양도차익의 24%를, 10년 이상은 최대 80%를 공제받는다. 하지만 투기용에 대해서까지 세금 감면을 해주는 건 조세정의에 부합하지 않는다는 뜻이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With President Lee's remarks, discussions on taxing 'well-off single homeowners' are also expected to gain momentum. At a New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee said, "(Real estate tax reform) would be the last resort, wouldn't it be the least desirable?" and added, "You might have heard of the '5 billion won property tax' idea, which suggests imposing a holding tax only on properties worth over 5 billion won. I didn't propose it, but I mean there are such rumors." While not explicitly suggesting a tax increase on high-value single homes, his remarks did not rule out the possibility. Kim Yong-beom, the Presidential Office's Policy Chief, also said in an interview with The Hankyoreh on the 14th, "There are proposals to apply holding taxes differently by creating more detailed brackets, like with income tax, for example, 2 billion, 3 billion, 4 billion won, even for a single home. It's an issue that should be seriously considered." (  이 대통령의 발언으로 ‘똘똘한 한 채’에 대한 과세 논의도 본격화될 것으로 보인다. 이 대통령은 지난 21일 신년 기자회견에서 “(부동산 세제 개편은) 마지막 수단으로 제일 좋지 않겠냐”면서도 “(집값이) 50억 넘는 데만 보유세를 부담시키자는 ‘50억 보유세’를 들어봤을 것이다. 제가 한단 건 아니지만, 그런 소문이 있더라는 뜻”이라고 했다. 고가 1주택에 대한 증세를 시사한 것은 아니지만, 그 가능성을 배제하지 않겠다는 뜻이다. 김용범 청와대 정책실장도 지난 14일 한겨레와 한 인터뷰에서 “같은 한 채라도 소득세처럼 20억, 30억, 40억원 등 구간을 더 촘촘히 해 보유세를 달리 적용하자는 제안이 있는데, 진지하게 고민해봐야 할 문제”라고 말한 바 있다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, during his presidential campaign, President Lee said, "I will not use taxes to control housing prices." However, as Seoul housing prices remain unchecked despite strong regulatory policies like the Land Transaction Permit System, he appears to be considering tax reform as well. Nevertheless, the Presidential Office's stance is to maintain the existing policy of avoiding the use of tax measures, but not to rule out tax reform as an option if it becomes difficult to control the rising trend in Seoul housing prices through supply expansion alone. (  애초 이 대통령은 대선 후보 시절 “세금으로 집값 잡는 일은 하지 않겠다”고 했지만, 토지거래허가제(토허제) 등 강력한 규제정책에도 서울 집값이 잡히지 않자 세제 개편도 검토하는 것으로 보인다. 다만 세제 카드는 쓰지 않는다는 기존 방침을 유지하되, 공급 확대만으로 서울 집값 상승세를 제어하기 어렵다고 판단할 경우 세제 개편도 선택지에서 배제하지 않겠다는 게 청와대의 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Seo Young-ji, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241368.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502309.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 06:59:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>