<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:05:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>President Lee: "Compared to Japan, the exchange rate is less depreciated and holding up relatively well" (이 대통령 “환율, 일본에 비하면 평가절하 덜 되고 잘 견디는 편”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240951.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Compared to Japan, the exchange rate is less depreciated and holding up relatively well" (이 대통령 “환율, 일본에 비하면 평가절하 덜 되고 잘 견디는 편”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503495.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;원-달러 환율이 2.3원 오른 1480.4원에 개장한 21일 하나은행 본점 딜링룸에서 딜러가 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the high exchange rate situation fluctuating around the 1480 won level, President Lee Jae-myung said, "According to the authorities, it is predicted that the exchange rate will fall to around 1400 won in about one or two months." It is unusual for the President to publicly mention an exchange rate forecast, and it is interpreted that he is placing expectations on major events such as tax support for domestic market re-entry starting as early as February and inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI) in April. (1480원대를 오르내리는 고환율 상황에 대해 이재명 대통령이 “당국에 의하면, 한두 달 정도 지나면 (환율이) 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”고 말했다. 대통령이 환율 전망을 공개적으로 언급한 것은 이례적으로, 이르면 2월 시작될 국내시장 복귀 세제 지원과 4월 세계국채지수 편입 등 대형 이벤트에 기대를 거는 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about 'measures against the high exchange rate' during the New Year's press conference held at the Cheong Wa Dae State Guest House on the 21st, President Lee stated as above, saying, "Compared to Japan, our exchange rate is less depreciated and is holding up relatively well." He implied that the recent high exchange rate is also influenced by external factors and is not an exception only for Korea. (이 대통령은 21일 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서 ‘고환율 대책’에 대한 질문이 나오자 “일본에 비하면 우리는 (환율은) 평가 절하가 덜 되고, 잘 견디고 있는 편”이라며 이처럼 밝혔다. 최근 고환율은 국외 변수 영향도 있어, 한국만 예외적이지 않다는 뜻이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the President's mention of the timing for a downward adjustment in the exchange rate as 'about one or two months,' foreign exchange authorities explained, "This is based on a synthesis of objective forecasts from investment banks (IBs) that a downward adjustment will occur around the end of March." According to the exchange rate forecast consensus by Yonhap Infomax as of that day, the average for the first quarter (January-March) of this year is 1,417.09 won. A Ministry of Finance and Economy official said, "Although individual investors' purchases of overseas stocks, which had somewhat slowed in terms of foreign exchange supply and demand, have been strong this month, we expect it to gradually ease with the introduction of the domestic market re-entry account (RIA) in February, among other factors." Foreign exchange authorities believe that foreign currency conversion by exporting companies and strategic foreign exchange hedging by the National Pension Service are also contributing to reducing exchange rate volatility. (대통령이 환율 하향화 전망 시점을 ‘한두 달’ 정도로 언급한 것을 두고 외환당국에선 “투자은행(IB)에서도 오는 3월 말께 하향화된다는 객관적 전망을 종합한 것”이라고 설명했다. 이날 기준 연합인포맥스의 환율 전망 컨센서스를 보면, 올해 1분기(1~3월) 평균은 1417.09원이다. 재정경제부 관계자는 “외환 수급 면에서 다소 주춤했던 개인투자자의 해외주식 매수세가 이달 거센 편이지만, 2월 중 국내시장 복귀계좌(RIA) 도입 등으로 차츰 완화될 것으로 기대한다”고 말했다. 외환당국은 수출기업들의 환전, 국민연금의 전략적 환헤지 등도 환율 변동성을 줄이는데 기여하고 있다고 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Finance and Economy is soon proposing a bill to promote passage in the February extraordinary National Assembly session. The bill would grant a 50-100% reduction in capital gains tax on overseas stocks for funds reinvested in domestic stocks this year using proceeds from the sale of overseas stocks. The expectation is a tax incentive effect that will encourage funds converted to dollars and sent abroad to be reconverted to won and brought back in. Hopes are also pinned on the scheduled inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI) in April. Following the index inclusion, global bond-tracking funds flowing into Korea are estimated to reach approximately $60 billion over an eight-month period starting from April this year. However, there is also a view that the level of 'retail investors who ventured overseas' returning to the domestic market is still a question mark, and the impact of bond funds on the foreign exchange market will be limited. (재경부는 올해 중 해외주식을 매도한 자금으로 국내 주식에 투자하면 해외주식 양도소득을 50~100% 감면해주는 법안을 곧 발의해 2월 임시국회 통과를 추진 중이다. 세제 혜택으로 달러로 바꿔 나간 자금을 다시 원화로 환전해 들어오는 효과를 기대하는 것이다. 4월로 예정된 세계국채지수(WGBI) 편입에도 기대를 걸고 있다. 지수 편입에 따라 국내 유입되는 글로벌 채권 추종 자금은 올해 4월부터 8개월간 약 600억달러에 달할 것으로 추산된다. 다만 ‘서학개미’들의 국내 시장 복귀 수준이 아직 물음표인데다 채권 자금이 환율 시장에 미칠 영향은 제한적이라는 시각도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's remarks immediately impacted the market that day. The exchange rate, which had risen to the 1480 won level in early trading, fell to 1,467.7 won during the session and closed at 1,471.3 won, down 6.8 won from the previous day. (이날 이 대통령 발언은 즉각 시장에 영향을 미쳤다. 이날 장 초반 1480원대로 상승하던 환율은 장중 1467.7원까지 떨어졌다가 전날 대비 6.8원 내린 1471.3원에 주간거래를 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240951.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/493/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503495.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NH Investment &amp; Securities, Another Case of Stock Trading Using 'Undisclosed Information' Uncovered... 33 Billion Won in Unfair Gains (NH투자증권, ‘미공개 정보’ 이용 주식 거래 또 적발…33억 부당이득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240960.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;NH Investment &amp; Securities, Another Case of Stock Trading Using 'Undisclosed Information' Uncovered... 33 Billion Won in Unfair Gains (NH투자증권, ‘미공개 정보’ 이용 주식 거래 또 적발…33억 부당이득)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/573/343/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503580.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;NH투자증권.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another case of unfair trading using undisclosed information related to public tender offers has been uncovered at NH Investment &amp; Securities. The unfair gains they reaped are estimated to reach approximately 33 billion won. (엔에이치(NH)투자증권에서 공개매수 관련 미공개 정보를 이용한 불공정거래가 추가 적발됐다. 이들이 챙긴 부당이득은 약 33억원에 이르는 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Securities and Futures Commission (SFC) under the Financial Services Commission announced on the 21st that it has uncovered allegations that two former and current executives/employees of NH Investment &amp; Securities and acquaintances who received information from them obtained public tender offer information in advance and purchased stocks beforehand, thereby gaining unfair profits amounting to tens of billions of won. A public tender offer is a system for publicly purchasing stocks outside the market to secure management rights or increase shareholding ratios of a specific company. (금융위원회 산하 증권선물위원회(증선위)는 21일 엔에이치투자증권 전·현직 임직원 2명과 이들로부터 정보를 전달받은 지인 등이 공개매수 정보를 사전에 입수해 주식을 선매수하는 방식으로 수십억원대 부당이득을 취한 혐의를 적발했다고 밝혔다. 공개매수는 특정 기업의 경영권 확보나 지분율 확대를 위해 주식을 시장 밖에서 공개적으로 매수하는 제도다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the SFC, employee Mr. A used undisclosed information related to public tender offers of three listed companies, which he learned in the course of his work, to purchase stocks, and conveyed this information to former employee Mr. B, instructing him to also purchase. During this process, the two are investigated to have reaped a total of 370 million won in unfair gains. Furthermore, six secondary and tertiary recipients who received the information through Mr. B are also found to have traded in the same manner, gaining a total of 2.9 billion won in unfair profits. (증선위에 따르면, 직원 ㄱ씨는 업무 과정에서 알게 된 3개 상장사의 공개매수 관련 미공개 정보를 이용해 주식을 매수했고, 이를 전직 직원인 ㄴ씨에게 전달해 함께 매수하도록 했다. 이 과정에서 두 사람은 총 3억7천만원의 부당이득을 챙긴 것으로 조사됐다. 또 ㄴ씨를 통해 정보를 전달받은 2·3차 수령자 6명도 같은 방식으로 거래해 총 29억원의 부당이득을 취한 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SFC has reported employee Mr. A, an insider at the securities firm, and primary information recipient Mr. B to the prosecution on charges of violating the prohibition on using undisclosed material information under the Capital Markets Act. Additional financial sanctions such as fines may be imposed during the subsequent prosecution investigation and trial process. For the six secondary and tertiary recipients who traded after receiving information from them, a total fine of 3.7 billion won has been imposed for market order disruption. (증선위는 증권사 내부자인 ㄱ씨와 1차 정보 수령자인 ㄴ씨를 자본시장법상 미공개중요정보 이용 금지 위반 혐의로 검찰에 고발했다. 향후 검찰 수사와 재판 과정에서 벌금형 등 추가적인 금전적 제재가 내려질 수 있다. 이들로부터 정보를 전달받아 거래한 2·3차 수령자 6명에 대해서는 시장질서 교란행위로 총 37억원의 과징금을 부과했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This disciplinary action is separate from the &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1225825.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; where an executive in charge of public tender offers at NH Investment &amp; Securities was subject to a search and seizure on charges of leaking information on public tender offers for 11 stocks and reaping about 2 billion won in unfair gains. Following the executive in charge, an employee has now been serially implicated in unfair trading. (이번 조처는 앞서 엔에이치투자증권 공개매수 담당 임원이 11개 종목의 공개매수 정보를 유출해 약 20억원의 부당이득을 챙긴 혐의로 압수수색을 받은 &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/economy/finance/1225825.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;사건&lt;/a&gt;과는 별개다. 공개매수 담당 임원에 이어 직원까지 연쇄적으로 불공정거래에 연루된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;NH Investment &amp; Securities is the top operator in the domestic public tender offer market. Since 2022, it has acted as the lead manager for 30 out of 47 public tender offers conducted domestically, maintaining a dominant position. Because of this, there are criticisms that the poor internal control related to public tender offers has been revealed as a structural problem. (엔에이치투자증권은 국내 공개매수 시장 1위 사업자다. 지난 2022년 이후 국내에서 진행된 공개매수 47건 가운데 30건을 수임하며 독보적인 주관사 지위를 유지해왔다. 이 때문에 공개매수 관련 내부통제 부실이 구조적인 문제로 드러났다는 지적이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on the same day, the SFC also reported to the prosecution three individuals, including a controlling shareholder of a listed company, who defended against a drop in the stock price of pledged shares through price-manipulating orders and gained 29.4 billion won in unfair profits. (한편 증선위는 이날 시세조종 주문으로 담보주식의 주가 하락을 방어한 뒤 294억원의 부당이득을 취한 상장사 지배주주 등 3명도 검찰에 고발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The SFC stated, "We will respond to acts by insiders such as executives and employees of financial companies, who have an information advantage, using undisclosed information to undermine market order, with severe criminal punishment and administrative sanctions." (증선위는 “금융회사 임직원 등 정보 우위에 있는 내부자가 미공개 정보를 이용해 시장 질서를 훼손하는 행위에 대해서는 엄중한 형사처벌과 행정제재로 대응하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1240960.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/573/343/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503580.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Getting Properties Listed is Also Supply"... Hint at Extending the Multi-Homeowner Capital Gains Tax Surcharge Grace Period? (이 대통령 “매물 내놓게 하는 게 공급”…다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 연장 뜻?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240962.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Getting Properties Listed is Also Supply"... Hint at Extending the Multi-Homeowner Capital Gains Tax Surcharge Grace Period? (이 대통령 “매물 내놓게 하는 게 공급”…다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 연장 뜻?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689835089661_20260121503614.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21일 오전 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸 전광판에 이재명 대통령 신년 기자회견 뉴스화면이 나오고 있다. 정용일 선임기자 yongil@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung stated regarding housing supply measures that "getting properties listed for sale is also supply." The market is anticipating that the grace period for the capital gains tax surcharge on multi-homeowners, set to end in May, will be extended again. President Lee also expressed an optimistic outlook on the foreign exchange market, saying, "I predict the exchange rate will fall to around 1,400 won." (이재명 대통령이 주택 공급 대책과 관련해 “매물이 나오게 하는 것도 공급”이라고 밝혔다. 시장에서는 5월 종료를 앞둔 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 유예가 재차 연장될 것이란 전망이 나온다. 이 대통령은 또 “환율이 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”며 외환시장에 대한 낙관적 전망을 공개하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a New Year's press conference held at the Cheong Wa Dae State Guest House on the 21st, regarding the possibility of introducing tax regulations to curb real estate prices, President Lee said, "Taxes are a burden on the people to secure national finances; if they are diverted for other policy purposes, side effects occur," adding, "At this point, we are not deeply considering implementing real estate policy through the tax system." He then discussed supply measures, stating, "Regarding supply, there are also supply measures that involve getting people who own many houses to list them. We are looking for such methods as well." (이 대통령은 21일 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서 부동산 가격 억제를 위해 세금 규제를 도입할 가능성과 관련해 “세금은 국가재정 확보를 위해 국민에 부담을 지우는 것인데, 다른 정책 목표를 위해 전용하면 부작용이 발생한다”며 “지금으로선 세제를 통해 부동산 정책을 하는 것은 깊이 고려하고 있지 않다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 공급대책을 두고 “공급에는 주택을 많이 가지고 있는 사람들이 내놓게 하는 공급책도 있다. 그런 방법도 찾고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The market is interpreting President Lee's remarks as a signal to extend the grace period for the capital gains tax surcharge on multi-homeowners, which is set to end on May 9th. The intention is seen as using the carrot of a tax reduction with a deadline to encourage property listings to come onto the market. Woo Byung-tak, a senior expert at Shinhan Premier Passfinder, explained, "The President's remarks this time could be groundwork for the multi-homeowner capital gains tax surcharge grace period," adding, "However, even if the surcharge grace period is extended, a signal firmly setting the termination point of the grace period must also be given to effectively encourage multi-homeowners to list their properties." (이 대통령의 발언을 시장에서는 오는 5월9일 종료를 앞둔 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예의 연장 신호로 받아들이고 있다. 시한을 두고 양도세 감면이라는 당근을 제시해 매물이 시장에 나오도록 유도하는 뜻이라는 것이다. 우병탁 신한프리미어 패스파인더 전문위원은 “이번 대통령의 발언은 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예에 대한 포석일 가능성이 있다”며 “다만 중과 유예를 연장하더라도 유예 중단 시점을 못 박는 시그널이 반드시 함께 나와줘야만 다주택자들이 매물을 내놓게 하는 효과를 볼 수 있을 것”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also announced that "the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport will soon announce realistic measures to expand (housing) supply." He stated, "We intend to present very specific and realistic figures, not abstract numbers. We will announce measures to increase supply based on permits issued and construction starts, not just planning levels, so please wait." The market predicts that this supply measure will include new sites such as the Taereung Physical Training Center (Taereung CC) in Nowon-gu, Seoul, and the Yongsan International Business District. (이 대통령은 “곧 국토(교통)부에서 현실적인 (주택) 공급 확대 방안을 발표할 것”이라고 예고하기도 했다. 이 대통령은 “추상적 수치보다는 아주 구체적이고 현실적인 수치를 제시하려고 한다. 계획 수준이 아니라 인허가·착공 기준으로 공급을 늘리는 방안을 발표할 테니 기다려달라”고 밝혔다. 시장에서는 이번 공급 대책에 서울 노원구 태릉체력단련장(태릉CC)과 용산국제업무지구 등 신규 부지가 포함될 것이란 예측이 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the 'high exchange rate' fluctuating around the 1,470 won level, President Lee unusually disclosed his exchange rate forecast, saying, "Compared to Japan, our (exchange rate) is less devalued and holding up relatively well," and "I predict it will fall to around 1,400 won in a month or two." The President's mention of a 'month or two' timeline for the downward exchange rate forecast is interpreted as reflecting expectations that the Returning Investor Account (RIA), which offers a 50-100% reduction on capital gains from overseas stocks, could be implemented as early as February, and that from April, up to $60 billion in global bond-tracking funds will flow in due to inclusion in the World Government Bond Index (WGBI). President Lee's remarks immediately impacted the market. The exchange rate, which rose to the 1,480 won level early in the session, fell to 1,467.7 won during the day and closed at 1,471.3 won, down 6.8 won from the previous day. (이 대통령은 1470원대를 오르내리는 ‘고환율’에 대해서도 “일본에 비하면 우리 (환율은) 평가 절하가 덜 되고 잘 견디고 있는 편”이라며 “한두 달 정도 지나면 1400원 전후로 떨어질 것이라 예측하고 있다”고 이례적으로 환율 전망을 공개했다. 이 대통령이 환율 하향화 전망 시점을 ‘한두 달’로 이야기한 것은 해외주식 양도소득을 50~100% 감면해주는 국내시장 복귀계좌(RIA)가 빠르면 2월 시행되고, 4월부터 세계국채지수(WGBI) 편입으로 글로벌 채권 추종 자금이 최대 600억달러 규모 유입될 것이란 기대감을 표시한 것으로 읽힌다. 이날 이 대통령 발언은 즉각 시장에 영향을 미쳤다. 장 초반 1480원대로 상승하던 환율은 장중 1467.7원까지 떨어졌다가 전날 대비 6.8원 내린 1471.3원에 주간거래를 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, regarding the recent U.S. plan to impose 100% tariffs on semiconductors, President Lee said, "If that happens, U.S. semiconductor prices will rise by 100%," adding, "I am not that seriously concerned." Responding to a related question, he stated, "If we get overly excited or worried with every change, we cannot maintain our center. Precisely at times like these, we must respond based on our own center and 'principles'." Previously, South Korea and the U.S. agreed through last year's tariff negotiations to apply tariffs on the semiconductor sector that are 'no less favorable than those for Taiwan'. Mentioning this, President Lee also said, "I hope Taiwan endures well." (한편 이 대통령은 최근 미국의 반도체 100% 관세 부과 계획에 대해서도 “그러면 미국 반도체 물가가 100% 오를 것”이라며 “그렇게 심각하게 우려하지 않는다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 관련 질문에 “일희일비하면 중심을 잡을 수 없다. 이럴 때일수록 자기 중심을 가지고 ‘원칙’에 따라 대응해 나가야 한다”며 이같이 말했다. 앞서 한국과 미국은 지난해 관세협상을 통해 반도체 부문에 대해 ‘대만보다 불리하지 않은 관세’ 적용을 합의한 바 있다. 이 대통령은 이를 거론하며 “대만이 잘 견뎌내길 바란다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Lee Ji-hye, Park Su-ji, Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 박수지 김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240962.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689835089661_20260121503614.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>PIPC Chairperson: "We deployed a record 14 investigators for Coupang probe... trade issues not considered" (개보위원장 “쿠팡 조사에 역대 최다 14명 투입…통상 문제 고려 안 해”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240965.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;PIPC Chairperson: "We deployed a record 14 investigators for Coupang probe... trade issues not considered" (개보위원장 “쿠팡 조사에 역대 최다 14명 투입…통상 문제 고려 안 해”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/946/567/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689836320155_20260121503642.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;21일 서울 중구 프레스센터에서 개최된 출입기자단 신년간담회에서 인사말 중인 송경희 개인정보보호위원회 위원장. 개인정보보호위원회 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Song Kyung-hee, the Chairperson of the Personal Information Protection Commission (PIPC), criticized Coupang, which caused a data breach affecting 33.7 million customers, for being uncooperative in the related investigation. She stated the intention to swiftly conclude the investigation by deploying a record 14 investigators. Regarding concerns that the 'Coupang incident' could escalate into a trade issue between South Korea and the US, she said it is "not a consideration" and that they will handle the matter according to principle. (송경희 개인정보보호위원회(개보위) 위원장이 ‘고객 3370만명의 개인정보 유출사고를 낸 쿠팡이 관련 조사에 비협조적’이라고 비판하며 역대 최다인 14명의 조사관을 투입해 조사를 조속히 마무리하겠다는 뜻을 밝혔다. 그는 ‘쿠팡 사태’가 한미 간 통상 문제로 번질 수 있다는 우려에 대해서는 “고려 대상이 아니”라며 원칙에 따라 조처하겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairperson Song Kyung-hee disclosed the investigation status and future plans regarding data breach incidents involving domestic and foreign companies last year, including Coupang, SK Telecom (SKT), and KT, at a press briefing held at the Press Center in Jung-gu, Seoul on the 21st. (송경희 위원장은 21일 서울 중구 프레스센터에서 열린 기자간담회에서 쿠팡과 에스케이텔레콤(SKT), 케이티(KT) 등 지난해 발생한 국내외 기업에 대한 개인정보유출사고 조사 현황과 향후 계획을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the briefing, she stated regarding the scale of Coupang's data breach, "It's over 30 million people, and there is a sufficient possibility that non-member information was also leaked." She then revealed that 14 investigators have been deployed for this case investigation. This is a 'record high' number, three more than the personnel deployed for the investigation into SK Telecom, which caused a data breach affecting 23 million people last year. Chairperson Song said, "The investigation has progressed considerably," but added, "If asked whether (Coupang is being) 'cooperative,' (I would answer) it is not sufficient," and "For speeding up the investigation, how the other party responds is also important." (그는 이 자리에서 쿠팡의 개인정보 유출 규모에 대해 “3천만명 이상이고 비회원 정보도 충분히 유출됐을 가능성이 있다”고 말했다. 그러면서 이 사건 조사를 위해 조사관 14명을 투입했다고 밝혔다. 이는 지난해 2300만명의 개인정보 유출 사고를 낸 에스케이텔레콤 조사 인력보다 3명 많은 ‘역대 최다’ 규모다. 송 위원장은 “조사가 상당히 진행된 상황”이라면서도 “(쿠팡이 조사에) ‘협조적인가’라고 묻는다면 충분하지 않다(고 답하겠다)”며 “(조사 속도를 내기 위해서는) 상대방도 어떻게 대응하는가가 중요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the point that there is concern about attempts by the US political sphere to interfere with the investigation given Coupang is a US company, she answered, "The company's nationality is not important," and "We will handle it strictly based on the Personal Information Protection Act. (Trade issues with the US) are not being considered as a variable." (그는 쿠팡이 미국 기업이라는 점에서 미국 정치권의 조사 방해 시도가 우려된다는 지적에는 “기업 국적은 중요하지 않다”며 “개인정보보호법에 근거해서 엄격하게 조처하겠다. (미국과의) 통상 문제는 변수로 고려하고 있지 않다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding SK Telecom, which received a record 134.8 billion won administrative fine for violating the Personal Information Protection Act and has filed an administrative lawsuit contesting the penalty, Chairperson Song stated it was "a penalty issued after thorough review" and expressed the position to actively respond. She pointed out, "The argument that the fine is excessive or unfair because no actual damage occurred is not correct," and "The fine is of a nature that holds (the company) responsible for harming data subjects in the process of utilizing personal information." (송 위원장은 개인정보보호법 위반으로 역대 최다인 1348억원의 과징금을 부과받은 에스케이텔레콤이 처분에 불복해 행정소송을 낸 것을 두고서는 “철저하게 검토한 처분”이라며 적극적으로 대응하겠단 입장을 밝혔다. 그는 “실제 피해가 발생하지 않았다고 과징금이 과분하다거나 부당하다는 것(주장)은 맞지 않는다”며 “과징금은 개인정보를 활용하는 과정에서 정보주체에 피해를 끼치는 것에 대한 책임 성격”이라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Chae Ban-seok &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (채반석 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chaibs@hani.co.kr"&gt;chaibs@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1240965.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/946/567/imgdb/child/2026/0121/53_17689836320155_20260121503642.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Wonkwang Digital University's Yoga and Meditation Department Successfully Concludes Scoliosis-Specific Exercise Schroth Therapy Workshop (원광디지털대 요가명상학과, 척추측만 전문운동 슈로스테라피 워크숍 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240972.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Wonkwang Digital University's Yoga and Meditation Department Successfully Concludes Scoliosis-Specific Exercise Schroth Therapy Workshop (원광디지털대 요가명상학과, 척추측만 전문운동 슈로스테라피 워크숍 성료)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/4017689849092719.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;원광디지털대 요가명상학과, 슈로스테라피 워크숍 (원광디지털대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wonkwang Digital University's Department of Yoga and Meditation (Department Head Seung-tae Park) successfully held the 'Scoliosis-Specific Exercise Schroth Therapy Workshop' at its Seoul Campus on Saturday, January 17th. (원광디지털대학교 요가명상학과(학과장 박승태)는 지난 1월 17일(토) 서울캠퍼스에서 ‘척추측만 전문운동 슈로스테라피 워크숍’을 성공적으로 개최했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This workshop was designed to systematically learn the principles of scoliosis correction and postural alignment and to strengthen professional capabilities for applying these principles in yoga therapy practice. (이번 워크숍은 척추측만 교정과 자세 정렬의 원리를 체계적으로 학습하고, 이를 요가테라피 현장에 적용할 수 있도록 전문 역량을 강화하기 위해 마련됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The training was directly instructed by lecturer Sang-gil Lee (CEO of SchrothSpine Co., Ltd., Ph.D. in Sports Medicine), who holds the only German Schroth Master qualification in Korea. The program focused on practical skills, covering posture assessment, breathing assessment methods, and distinguishing between exercises beneficial for scoliosis and those requiring caution. (이번 교육은 국내 유일의 독일 슈로스마스터 자격을 보유한 이상길 강사(㈜슈로스파인 대표, 스포츠의학 박사)가 직접 지도했으며, 자세 평가와 호흡 평가법, 그리고 척추측만증에 도움이 되는 운동과 주의해야 할 운동을 구분하는 실전 중심 내용으로 진행됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The morning session, themed 'Schroth Therapy 1: Posture Assessment and Breathing Assessment Methods,' involved understanding the structural characteristics of scoliosis and practicing professional evaluation methods based on this understanding. Participants directly experienced individual posture analysis and breathing pattern assessment, gaining an in-depth understanding of the scientific principles behind scoliosis correction exercises. (오전 강의에서는 ‘슈로스테라피1: 자세평가와 호흡평가법’을 주제로, 척추측만증의 구조적 특징을 이해하고 이를 바탕으로 한 전문적인 평가 방법을 실습했다. 참가자들은 개별 자세 분석과 호흡 패턴 평가를 직접 경험하며, 척추측만 교정 운동의 과학적 원리를 깊이 있게 이해하는 시간을 가졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The afternoon featured a more advanced practical session themed 'Schroth Therapy 2: Exercises Harmful and Beneficial for Scoliosis.' The lecture presented customized exercise methods for different types of scoliosis based on actual clinical cases and specifically explained the impact of incorrect exercises on spinal alignment. The sharing of various case analyses and practical know-how from Schroth therapy settings garnered a highly positive response from participants. (오후에는 ‘슈로스테라피2: 척추측만에 해가 되는 운동과 약이 되는 운동’을 주제로 보다 심화된 실습이 이루어졌다. 강의에서는 실제 임상 사례를 바탕으로 척추측만 유형별 맞춤 운동법을 제시하고, 잘못된 운동이 척추 정렬에 미치는 영향을 구체적으로 설명했다. 특히 슈로스테라피 현장에서 나타나는 다양한 케이스 분석과 실전 노하우가 공유되어 참가자들의 큰 호응을 얻었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Participating students shared their impressions, stating, "It was very beneficial to learn an accurate understanding and assessment methods for scoliosis," and "There was a lot of practical content applicable to yoga instruction settings." This course issued a certificate of completion to those who attended both the first and second workshops and was operated as a continuous program to cultivate professional yoga therapy instructors. (워크숍에 참가한 학생들은 “척추측만증에 대한 정확한 이해와 평가법을 배울 수 있어 매우 유익했다”, “요가 지도 현장에 적용할 수 있는 실질적인 내용이 많았다”는 소감을 전했다. 이번 과정은 1차와 2차 워크숍을 모두 수강할 경우 수료증이 발급되며, 전문성을 갖춘 요가테라피 지도자 양성을 위한 연속 프로그램으로 운영되었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seung-tae Park, Department Head of Wonkwang Digital University's Yoga and Meditation Department, stated, "This Schroth therapy workshop was an important educational program that elevated the level of expertise in the field of yoga therapy," adding, "We will continue to expand practical, field-oriented educational programs to strengthen the capabilities of our current students and graduates." (원광디지털대학교 요가명상학과 박승태학과장은 “이번 슈로스테라피 워크숍은 요가테라피 분야의 전문성을 한 단계 높이는 중요한 교육 과정이었다”며, “앞으로도 재학생과 졸업생의 현장 역량 강화를 위한 실무 중심 교육 프로그램을 지속적으로 확대해 나가겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1240972.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0121/4017689849092719.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic Autonomous Driving Entering 'Level 4'... Securing Real-World Road Data is Key (국내 자율주행 ‘레벨4’ 진입중…실제 도로 데이터 확보 관건)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240998.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Domestic Autonomous Driving Entering 'Level 4'... Securing Real-World Road Data is Key (국내 자율주행 ‘레벨4’ 진입중…실제 도로 데이터 확보 관건)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503953.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 강남구 자율주행 시범운행지구에서 자율주행차량이 시험운행을 위해 대기하고 있다. 업체 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;I couldn't lean back in the seat due to anxiety. Sitting upright in the back seat, I alternately watched the person in the driver's seat and the windshield. As the autonomous electric vehicle gradually increased speed and entered near a construction site in Seoul's Gangnam district, my body instinctively tensed up. This was because traffic controllers were directing vehicles in the middle of the road. However, the autonomous vehicle came to a smooth stop, then slightly turned its direction to the left and continued driving. Later, in an alleyway it entered, it moved slowly to avoid a person coming from the roadway, not the sidewalk. Soon, I leaned back in the seat. It felt as stable as if driven by a driver with ten years of experience. (불안함에 좌석 등받이에 등을 기대지 못했다. 뒷자리에 곧게 앉아 운전석에 앉은 이와 앞유리를 번갈아 살폈다. 자율주행 전기차가 서서히 속도를 높여 서울 강남의 공사장 근처로 들어서자 절로 몸에 힘이 들어갔다. 신호수들이 도로 한가운데서 차량을 통제하고 있었기 때문이다. 하지만 자율주행차는 부드럽게 멈춰선 뒤, 방향을 왼쪽으로 살짝 틀어 주행을 이어갔다. 뒤이어 들어선 골목길에서는 인도가 아닌 차도로 오는 사람을 피해 천천히 움직였다. 이내 등받이에 등을 기대고 앉았다. 경력 10년 차 운전자가 모는 듯한 안정감이 느껴졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a sports car approached from the left rear with a loud roar during the test drive by autonomous driving specialist company G, this car slightly reduced its speed. When a bus approached from the right, it changed lanes once to maintain distance. During a recent approximately 1-hour, 10km drive around the Gangnam area, there were quite a few unexpected variables. However, the person in the driver's seat merely sat there; except for school zones, they did not manually operate the steering wheel or brake pedal even once throughout the entire route. (  자율주행 전문기업 ㄱ사가 시험 운행 중인 이 차는 스포츠카가 왼쪽 뒤쪽에서 큰 굉음을 내며 달려오자 살짝 속도를 줄였고, 버스가 오른쪽에서 다가오자 차선을 한 번 변경해 거리를 유지하기도 했다. 최근 강남 일대를 10km가량 주행하는 약 1시간 동안 돌발 변수가 적지 않았지만, 운전자는 운전석에 앉아 있기만 할 뿐 어린이보호구역을 뺀 전 구간에서 운전대나 브레이크 페달을 단 한 번도 직접 조작하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Such autonomous driving demonstration operations are being conducted in various locations through collaboration between companies and central/local governments. According to a Hankyoreh investigation compiled on the 21st, based on the 'Act on Promotion and Support of Commercialization of Autonomous Vehicles', the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport (MOLIT) has designated 55 locations nationwide, including Seoul's Gangnam-gu, Jongno-gu, Jung-gu, and Busan, as autonomous vehicle demonstration operation zones as of the end of last year, providing regulatory sandbox (real-world testing) exceptions. A regulatory sandbox is a system that exempts new products or services from existing regulations under certain conditions to test and verify safety, etc. In these areas, autonomous driving startups and others are conducting test operations mainly on designated routes/sections. However, testing is only possible outside of commuting hours, and a significant portion of these areas are highways without pedestrians or traffic lights, which has limited learning for various exceptional situations (edge cases). (  이런 자율주행 시범 운행은 중앙 정부와 지방정부를 중심으로 기업과의 협업을 통해 곳곳에서 이뤄지고 있다. 21일 한겨레 취재를 종합하면, 국토교통부는 ‘자율주행자동차 상용화 촉진 및 지원에 관한 법률’에 따라 지난해 말 기준 서울 강남구·종로구·중구, 부산시 등 전국 55곳을 자율주행자동차 시범운행지구로 지정해 실증 특례를 제공하고 있다. 실증 특례란 새로운 제품이나 서비스에 대해 일정 조건에서 기존 규제를 면제해주고 안전성 등을 시험·검증하는 제도다. 이들 지역에서는 지정된 노선·구간 중심으로 자율주행 스타트업 등이 시험 운행을 추진 중이다. 다만, 출퇴근 시간대를 피해서만 실증이 가능하고, 이들 지역 상당수가 보행자나 신호등이 없는 고속도로여서 다양한 예외적 상황(엣지 케이스)에 대한 학습에 한계가 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this reason, MOLIT selected Gwangju Metropolitan City as the nation's first autonomous driving regulatory sandbox city on this day. The plan is to relax related regulations across the entire city and create an autonomous driving ecosystem linking large-scale driving data collection to specialized talent cultivation. In Gwangju, like San Francisco, USA or Wuhan, China, 24/7 real-world testing becomes possible across the entire city. This is a follow-up measure following the government's announcement last year to pursue 'commercialization of Level 4 autonomous vehicles by 2027'. Autonomous driving levels are divided into six stages from Level 0 (fully manual) to Level 5 (fully autonomous). The government plans to elevate domestic autonomous driving technology, currently at Level 3 (autonomous driving possible on highways, etc., but driver intervention required in specific situations like weather anomalies), to Level 4 (autonomous driving possible on most roads, driver intervention unnecessary). MOLIT stated, "By designating the entire city as a demonstration operation zone at once, diverse edge case learning is needed from alleyways to overpasses, underpasses, and intersections," adding, "Gwangju is a large city with a population over 1.3 million and has mixed urban-rural characteristics, making large-scale real-world testing in diverse environments seem possible." (이런 이유에서 국토부는 이날 국내 첫 자율주행 실증도시로 광주광역시를 선정했다. 도시 전역에 관련 규제를 풀고, 대규모 주행 데이터 수집부터 특화 인재 양성까지 이어지는 자율주행 생태계를 조성하기로 한 것이다. 광주에서는 미국 샌프란시스코·중국 우한처럼 도시 전역에서 24시간 실증이 가능해진다. 이는 지난해 정부가 ‘2027년 레벨4 자율주행차 상용화’를 추진하겠다고 한 데 따른 후속 조처다. 자율주행 단계는 레벨0(완전수동)부터 레벨5(완전 자율주행)까지 6단계로 나뉘는데, 정부는 현재 레벨3(고속도로 등에서 자율주행이 가능하지만 기상이변 등 특정 상황에서 운전자 개입이 필요한 수준) 단계인 국내 자율주행 기술을 레벨4(대부분의 도로에서 자율주행이 가능하며 운전자 개입이 불필요한 수준)로 끌어올린다는 계획이다. 국토부는 “도시 전역을 시범운행지구로 일괄 지정해 골목길부터 고가도로, 지하차도, 교차로 등에서 다양한 엣지케이스 학습이 필요하다”며 “광주는 인구 130만명 이상의 대도시이면서 도·농 복합적 특성을 보유해, 다양한 환경에서의 대규모 실증이 가능할 것으로 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local governments are also conducting their own autonomous vehicle trial operations. Seoul Metropolitan Government's 'Late-Night Autonomous Taxi' is a prime example. The city has been operating this taxi, limited to the Gangnam area, since September 26, 2024. As of the end of November last year, the cumulative number of rides over more than a year was 6,343, and the cumulative driving distance was 30,000 km. The city plans to convert the autonomous taxi, which has been operating as a free trial, to a paid service as early as next month. An autonomous vehicle in the form of a village bus began operation in Dongjak-gu in July last year, and expanded its operating area to Dongdaemun-gu and Seodaemun-gu starting in October of the same year. (  지방정부가 자체적으로 자율주행차를 시범 운행하기도 한다. 서울시의 ‘심야 자율주행 택시’가 대표적이다. 시는 강남 지역에 한정해 2024년 9월26일부터 이 택시를 운행해왔다. 지난해 11월 말 기준 1년여 넘는 기간 누적 탑승 건수는 6343건, 누적 운행 거리는 3만km다. 시는 무료로 시범 운영해 온 자율주행 택시를 이르면 다음달 안에 유료로 전환할 예정이다. 마을버스 형태의 자율주행차는 지난해 7월 동작구에서 운행을 시작했고, 같은 해 10월부터 운행 지역을 동대문구·서대문구로 확대했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is an assessment that there is still 'a long way to go' until the commercialization of autonomous driving in Korea. First, the absolute volume of data is small. Looking at data from Waymo, Google's autonomous robotaxi service in the US, this company, operating over 2,000 autonomous vehicles, had a cumulative driving distance exceeding 200 million km as of September last year. Chinese IT company Baidu is collecting related data by operating over 1,000 vehicles for more than 100 million km. In contrast, in Korea, the cumulative driving distance of all companies combined is only 13.06 million km. The number of operating vehicles is also limited to 132. Furthermore, it is pointed out as a limitation that Korea remains at the demonstration project stage, centered on startups' limited real-world testing with conditions of free transportation and manned operation. This is because China and the US have already entered the phase of paid transportation and unmanned operation, focusing on user experience and driving stability. (  다만, 국내 자율주행 상용화까지는 여전히 ‘갈 길이 멀다’는 평가가 나온다. 우선 절대적인 데이터양이 적기 때문이다. 미국 구글의 자율주행 로보택시 서비스 웨이모 자료를 보면, 2천대가 넘는 자율주행차를 운행하는 이 기업의 지난해 9월 기준 누적 주행거리는 2억㎞를 웃돈다. 중국 정보기술(IT) 기업인 바이두는 1천대로 1억㎞ 이상 운행하며 관련 데이터를 모으고 있다. 반면 한국의 경우, 전체 기업의 누적 주행거리는 1306만km에 불과하다. 운행대수도 132대에 그친다. 또한 한국은 스타트업 중심의 제한적 실증을 통해 무상운송·유인운행을 조건으로 한 시범 사업 단계에 머물러 있다는 점도 한계로 꼽힌다. 중국과 미국에서는 이미 유상운송·무인운행에 돌입해 사용자 경험과 주행 안정성에 초점을 두고 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experts point out that the task of securing high-quality data is paramount. It's not about accumulating data from simple driving on obstacle-free roads according to signals, but data that responds to variables actually encountered on Korean roads, such as near construction sites, pedestrians, buses, and other vehicles obstructing the path. Professor Choi Jun-won of Seoul National University (School of Electrical and Computer Engineering) said, "We must accumulate large-scale data based on the development of End-to-End (E2E) autonomous driving technology (a method where AI makes all driving decisions from start to finish)," adding, "The government should provide companies with opportunities to test their technology in the real world and develop it further, create a competitive arena, and support companies so they can freely accumulate data and develop AI models." (  전문가들은 양질의 데이터를 확보하는 작업이 무엇보다 중요하다고 지적한다. 방해 요소가 없는 도로를 신호에 맞춰 단순 주행하는 데이터가 아니라, 공사 현장 인근, 보행자와 버스, 다른 차량의 진로 방해 등 실제 한국 도로에서 마주하는 변수에 대응하는 데이터가 쌓여야 한다는 것이다. 최준원 서울대 교수(전기·정보공학부)는 “엔드투엔드(E2E) 자율주행 기술(인공지능이 처음부터 끝까지 직접 운전을 결정하는 방식) 개발을 기반으로 대규모 데이터를 쌓아야 한다”며 “정부는 기업들이 기술을 실증하고 이를 발전시킬 기회를 제공하고, 경쟁의 장을 만들어 기업들이 자유롭게 데이터를 쌓고 인공지능 모델 개발을 할 수 있도록 지원해줘야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1240998.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503953.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>FutureLink CEO: "Development of Autonomous Driving Industry Requires Cooperation Among Manufacturers, Government, and Insurers" (퓨처링크 대표 “자율주행 산업 발전, 제조사·정부·보험사 협력 필요”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241001.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;FutureLink CEO: "Development of Autonomous Driving Industry Requires Cooperation Among Manufacturers, Government, and Insurers" (퓨처링크 대표 “자율주행 산업 발전, 제조사·정부·보험사 협력 필요”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503958.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;차두원 퓨처링크 대표가 지난달 31일 경기도 성남시 회사 사무실에서 한겨레와 인터뷰를 하고 있다. 유하영 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike the United States or China, where big tech (large technology companies) lead the industry, the domestic autonomous vehicle sector in Korea shows a pattern of small, unlisted, and new companies struggling against the odds. FutureLink is one such company. According to the company's explanation, it has conducted test operations with nine autonomous vehicles in the Gangnam District of Seoul, an autonomous driving pilot zone designated by the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, covering approximately 40,000 kilometers in less than a year without any accidents. (빅테크(거대 기술기업)가 산업을 주도하는 미국이나 중국과 달리 국내 자율주행차 분야에서는 영세한 비상장·신규 기업들이 고군분투 중인 양상을 보인다. 퓨처링크도 이런 기업 가운데 하나다. 국토교통부가 지정한 자율주행 시범운행 지구인 서울 강남구 일대에서 자율주행차 9대로 시험운행을 해 1년이 채 되지 않는 기간에 약 4만km를 달렸고, 이 과정에서 사고가 나지 않았다는 것이 회사 쪽 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting at FutureLink's office in Seongnam, Gyeonggi Province on the 31st of last month, CEO Cha Du-won stated, "In a rapidly evolving field like autonomous driving, the speed of market entry is itself a competitive edge and a survival skill." CEO Cha previously worked at Hyundai Mobis and the Hyundai Motor Group, followed by the Korea Institute of Science &amp; Technology Evaluation and Planning (KISTEP) and the New Industry Regulatory Innovation Committee under the Office for Government Policy Coordination. This is why he is regarded in the industry as an expert with comprehensive experience across the entire spectrum of autonomous driving technology, from the technology itself to regulations. (  지난달 31일 경기도 성남시 퓨처링크 사무실에서 만난 차두원 대표는 이를 두고 “자율주행처럼 빠르게 진화하는 분야에서는 시장진입 속도가 곧 경쟁력이자 생존의 기술”이라고 했다. 차 대표는 앞서 현대모비스와 현대자동차그룹을 거쳐 한국과학기술기획평가원, 국무조정실 신산업규제혁신위원회 등에서 근무했다. 그가 업계에서 기술부터 규제까지 자율주행 기술 전반에 대한 경험을 두루 갖춘 전문가로 평가받는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CEO Cha stated that for the development of the autonomous driving industry, not only must the industry's technological development progress, but government deregulation and the creation of an initial market must also occur simultaneously and in parallel. He said, "The reason Google's autonomous robotaxi service, Waymo, receives massive investment is because it has already proven its business viability with hundreds of thousands of paid ride instances," adding, "It is also crucial to collaborate with automakers, telecommunications companies, local governments, insurance companies, etc., to achieve things that cannot be done alone." (  차 대표는 자율주행 산업 발전을 위해서는 업계의 기술 개발은 물론, 정부의 규제 완화·초기 시장 창출이 동시다발적으로 이뤄져야 한다고 했다. 그는 “미국 구글의 자율주행 로보택시 서비스 웨이모가 대규모 투자를 받는 이유는 이미 수십만 건의 유료 탑승 실적으로 비즈니스가 작동함을 증명했기 때문”이라며 “완성차 제조사, 통신사, 지방정부, 보험사 등과의 협력해 단독으로 할 수 없는 일을 함께 해내는 것도 중요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also emphasized the role of the government. He said, "For companies to decide on investments, matters such as liability in case of accidents, the insurance framework, and data management standards must be clear," adding, "Currently, there is still significant legal uncertainty, and this causes hesitation in market investment decisions." He further added, "If the government builds public infrastructure like high-definition maps and 5G networks, concerns and burdens about redundant investments by individual companies will be reduced." He also stated, "Public-sector initiatives, such as mandating the introduction of autonomous shuttles in public institutions, university campuses, and new cities, or filling late-night public transportation gaps with robotaxis, must continue." (그는 정부의 역할도 강조했다. 그는 “사고가 일어났을 때 책임 소재, 보험 체계, 데이터 관리 기준 등이 명확해야 기업들이 투자를 결정할 수 있다”며 “현재는 여전히 법적 불확실성이 크고 이것이 시장의 투자 결정을 주저하게 한다”고 말했다. 이어 “정밀 지도, 5지(G) 네트워크 같은 공공인프라를 정부가 구축해야 개별 기업의 중복투자 우려와 부담이 줄어든다”고 덧붙였다. 그는 또한 “공공기관, 대학 캠퍼스, 신도시 등에서 자율주행 셔틀을 의무 도입하거나 심야 대중교통 공백을 로보택시로 메우는 식의 공공형 움직임이 계속돼야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To secure technological completeness, FutureLink selected Pony.ai, a Level 4 autonomous driving technology company (capable of driverless operation in specific areas), as its partner. The strategy is to utilize technology already validated in the global market and localize it for Korea's road environment. He said, "Our goal is to contribute to creating a Korean autonomous driving service model by the time of Level 4 commercialization, which the government aims for by 2027." (  퓨처링크는 기술 완성도를 확보하고자 자율주행 레벨4(특정 구간에서 운전자 없이 자율주행이 가능한 수준) 기술 기업 포니에이아이(AI)를 파트너로 선정했다. 이미 글로벌 시장에서 검증된 기술을 활용해 한국의 도로 환경에 맞게 현지화한다는 전략이다. 그는 “정부가 2027년 목표로 하는 레벨4 상용화 시점에 한국형 자율주행 서비스 모델 제작에 기여하는 것이 목표”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241001.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/600/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503958.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Why did Musk praise Korean consumers?"... "Koreans are early adopters" (“한국인은 얼리어답터”…머스크가 왜 한국 소비자를 상찬하지?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1241003.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Why did Musk praise Korean consumers?"... "Koreans are early adopters" (“한국인은 얼리어답터”…머스크가 왜 한국 소비자를 상찬하지?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/580/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503985.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;테슬라 모델와이(Y). 테슬라 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interest is growing in the background behind Tesla CEO Elon Musk praising 'Koreans' as early adopters on social media. With Tesla lowering car prices in the Korean market this new year and expanding its customer base for the supervised Full Self-Driving (FSD) feature, forecasts suggest the company may focus more on the Korean market. (일론 머스크 테슬라 최고경영자(CEO)가 사회관계망서비스(SNS)에서 ‘한국인’을 얼리어답터로 추켜세우고 나서 그 배경에 관심이 쏠린다. 새해 들어 한국 시장에서 자동차 가격을 낮춘 테슬라가, 감독형 완전자율주행기능(FSD·이하 에프에스디) 고객도 확대하면서 한국 시장에 집중할 수 있다는 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th (local time), Musk posted on his X account, "Koreans are often one step ahead in adopting new technology." This is interpreted as him expressing gratitude that Tesla, which has recently been struggling with poor performance, has achieved 'solitary growth' in the domestic electric vehicle market. (머스크는 20일(현지시각) 자신의 엑스(X) 계정에 “한국인들은 새로운 기술을 받아들이는 데 종종 한발 앞서 있다”는 글을 올렸다. 최근 실적 부진에 시달리는 테슬라가 국내 전기차 시장에서 ‘나 홀로 성장’한 것을 고맙게 여기고 있다는 뜻이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, Tesla's sales last year were 1,636,129 units, an 8.56% decrease compared to the previous year (2024). Looking at it quarterly, sales declined in all quarters except the third quarter, which saw a last-minute surge in demand ahead of September 30th, when the Trump administration abolished electric vehicle subsidies of up to $7,500 (approximately 11 million won). Reasons cited for Tesla's sales decline include the abolition of electric vehicle subsidies by various governments and the expansion of market share by cheap Chinese-made electric vehicles. (실제 테슬라의 지난해 판매량은 163만6129대로 전년도(2024년)에 견줘 8.56% 감소했다. 분기별로 살펴보면 트럼프 행정부가 최대 7500달러(약 1100만원)에 이르는 전기차 보조금을 폐지한 9월30일을 앞두고 막판 수요가 몰렸던 3분기를 제외하고 모든 분기 판매 실적이 감소했다. 테슬라 판매량이 감소하는 이유로는 각국 정부의 전기차 보조금 폐지, 값싼 중국산 전기차의 시장 점유율 확대 등이 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Low trust in Tesla's FSD is also one of the causes of the poor performance. According to data from the American consulting firm SlingShot Strategy, which surveyed 8,000 American consumers last year, 35% of respondents answered that "FSD has a negative impact." In the United States, where FSD is widely used, more than 10 traffic accidents have already occurred, and investigations into the causes are underway. (테슬라가 내놓은 에프에스디에 대한 낮은 신뢰 역시 부진의 원인 가운데 하나다. 미국 컨설팅업체인 슬링샷 스트래티지가 지난해 미국 소비자 8천명을 대상으로 조사한 자료를 보면, 응답자의 35%가 “에프에스디가 부정적인 영향을 준다”고 답했다. 에프에스디가 널리 활용되는 미국에선 이미 10건이 넘는 교통사고가 발생해 사고 원인에 대한 조사가 진행중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Korea, where the number of vehicles capable of using FSD is limited to only a few hundred (estimated by the Korea Expressway Corporation, limited to Tesla Model S/X), safety issues have not yet surfaced, and the market share of Chinese electric vehicles is minimal, making Tesla's growth particularly robust. According to data from Kaizu Data Research Institute, Tesla sold 59,949 units in the Korean market last year, a sharp increase of 101.5% compared to 2024. Model Y sales also reached 50,405 units, a 169.3% increase compared to 2024. (에프에스디를 사용할 수 있는 차량이 수백대(테슬라 모델S·X 한정, 한국도로공사 추정치)에 불과한 한국에선 아직까지 안전 문제가 불거지지 않았고, 중국 전기차의 시장 점유율도 미미한 편이어서 유독 테슬라의 성장세가 견조하다. 카이즈유 데이터연구소 자료를 보면 테슬라는 지난해 한국 시장에서 5만9949대를 팔아 2024년에 견줘 101.5% 판매량이 폭증했다. 모델와이(Y)도 5만405대가 팔려 판매량이 2024년 대비 169.3% 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, Tesla is attracting consumer interest this year by significantly lowering car sales prices in the Korean market. According to Tesla's website, the Model 3 Performance All-Wheel Drive (AWD) has been reduced by 9.4 million won this year, and the Model Y Premium Rear-Wheel Drive (RWD) is being sold for 3 million won less. The Model 3 Standard Range Rear-Wheel Drive (RWD) was launched at 41.99 million won, but with subsidies and support funds applied, it can be purchased for around 30 million won. (이에 테슬라는 올해 들어 한국 시장 자동차 판매 가격을 대폭 낮추면서 소비자들의 관심을 끌고 있다. 테슬라 누리집을 보면 모델3 퍼포먼스 사륜구동(AWD)은 올해 들어 940만원을 낮췄고, 모델와이(Y)프리미엄 후륜구동(RWD)은 300만원을 낮춰 판매하고 있다. 모델3 스탠다드 후륜구동(RWD)은 4199만원에 출시했는데 보조금과 지원금 등을 적용하면 3000만원대에도 구매할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tesla's discontinuation of one-time sales for the FSD system and its shift to a subscription model is also highly likely to be an opportunity to broaden its connection with Korean consumers. Until now, when purchasing a Tesla vehicle, one could pay $8,000 (approximately 11.8 million won) upfront or use the feature by paying a subscription fee starting from $99 (approximately 140,000 won) per month. Tesla has announced that from now on, FSD will only be available via subscription. An automotive industry official said, "As Tesla spreads the monthly subscription model, there is a possibility it will open FSD to the low-cost Model Y produced in China," adding, "It appears to be a strategy where Tesla lowers the 'car price' to increase software sales and boost market share." (테슬라가 에프에스디 시스템에 대한 일시불 판매를 중단하고, 구독제로 전환하는 것도 한국 소비자들과의 접점을 넓히는 계기가 될 가능성이 크다. 지금까지는 테슬라 자동차를 구입할 때 8천달러(약 1180만원)를 한번에 내거나 매월 99달러(약 14만원)부터 시작하는 구독료를 내고 기능을 이용할 수 있었는데, 테슬라는 앞으로 구독제로만 에프에스디를 사용할 수 있다고 공지했다. 자동차 업계 관계자는 “테슬라가 월 구독제를 확산하면서 중국에서 생산된 저가형 모델와이에도 에프에스디를 열어 줄 가능성이 있다”며 “테슬라가 ‘자동차 가격’을 낮추면서 소프트웨어 판매를 늘려 시장 점유율을 높이려는 전략으로 보인다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Kim Pil-soo of Daelim University (Future Automotive Department) said, "Considering the shift of the FSD function to a subscription model, lowering the car price is nothing more than 'robbing Peter to pay Paul'," and added, "As global sales are declining and voices demanding recalls are growing, domestic consumers should also be cautious." (김필수 대림대 교수(미래자동차학부)는 “에프에스디 기능을 구독제로 전환한 것을 고려하면 찻값을 낮춘 것은 ‘조삼모사’에 불과하다”며 “세계 판매량이 감소하고 있고, 리콜을 요구하는 목소리도 높은 만큼 국내 소비자들도 주의해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Jae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이재호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ph@hani.co.kr"&gt;ph@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/car/1241003.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/580/imgdb/original/2026/0121/20260121503985.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sookmyung Women's University Students Visit Global Apparel Industry Sites in Bangladesh (숙명여대 학생들, 방글라데시서 글로벌 의류산업 현장 견학)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241031.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sookmyung Women's University Students Visit Global Apparel Industry Sites in Bangladesh (숙명여대 학생들, 방글라데시서 글로벌 의류산업 현장 견학)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0121/2417689941956116.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;방글라데시 영원무역 산업단지 견학 프로그램에 참여한 숙명여대 김영선 생활과학대학 학장과 학생들 (숙명여자대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A student exploration team from Sookmyung Women's University (President Si-yeon Moon) visited industrial sites in Bangladesh, a major production hub of the global apparel industry. (숙명여자대학교(총장 문시연) 학생 탐방단이 글로벌 의류 산업의 주요 생산 거점인 방글라데시에서 산업 현장을 견학했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nine students from the university's Department of Clothing and Textiles and the campus broadcasting station visited the Korean Export Processing Zone (KEPZ) and the Chittagong Export Processing Zone (CEPZ) in the southeastern Chittagong region of Bangladesh from Friday, January 9th to Saturday, January 17th. (숙명여대 의류학과와 교내 방송국 등 학생 9명은 1월 9일(금)부터 17일(토)까지 방글라데시 남동부 치타공 지역의 한국수출가공공단(KEPZ)과 치타공수출가공공단(CEPZ)을 방문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The students toured the production facilities of Youngone Corporation located within the zones, observing the overall production structure and operational processes of the apparel industry. At the KSI factory, which operates on solar energy, they received explanations about the eco-friendly production system and renewable energy-based operations. They sequentially observed the production processes for textiles, footwear, and packaging materials, gaining a broad understanding of the apparel industry's value chain. (학생들은 해당 공단에 있는 영원무역의 생산 시설을 둘러보며, 의류 산업의 전반적인 생산 구조와 운영 과정을 살펴봤다. 태양광 에너지로 운영되는 KSI 공장에서는 친환경 생산 시스템과 재생 에너지 기반의 운영 방식에 대한 설명을 들었으며, 섬유, 신발, 포장재 생산 공정을 차례로 견학하며 의류 산업의 가치사슬을 폭넓게 이해했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Student Han-joo Lee (Media Studies '24 / Sookmyung Women's University Educational Broadcasting Station SBS), who participated in the visit, said, "I was most impressed by the fact that all processes, from fabric production to finished goods manufacturing and quality inspection, are systematically carried out within a single industrial complex." Student Ji-a Kim (Clothing and Textiles '22) said, "Touring Youngone Corporation's production site was a meaningful experience that made me view the apparel industry not as a simple end product but as a complex process." (탐방에 참여한 이한주 학생(미디어학부 24/숙명여대 교육방송국 SBS)은 &amp;quot;원단 제작부터 완제품 생산, 품질 검사까지 모든 과정이 한 공단 안에서 체계적으로 진행되고 있다는 점이 가장 인상 깊었다&amp;quot;고 말했다. 김지아 학생(의류학과 22)은 &amp;quot;영원무역의 생산 현장을 둘러보며 의류 산업을 단순한 결과물이 아닌 복합적인 과정으로 바라보게 된 의미 있는 경험이었다&amp;quot;고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this visit, a program was also held where students visited the local Chittagong Independent University, and a Sookmyung Women's University Clothing and Textiles student presented her graduation project, sharing her major competencies. The students also had the opportunity to understand the trends of the global apparel industry and the management philosophy of the Youngone Group, learning about the mindset of entrepreneurs challenging the global market. (이번 견학에서는 현지의 치타공독립대학교를 방문해 숙명여대 의류학과 학생이 자신의 졸업 프로젝트를 발표하며 전공 역량을 공유하는 프로그램도 진행됐다. 학생들은 글로벌 의류산업의 흐름과 영원무역그룹의 경영 철학을 이해하고, 세계 시장에 도전하는 경영자의 자세를 배우는 기회를 얻기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Young-sun Kim, Dean of the College of Human Ecology at Sookmyung Women's University, who led the group, stated, "The Korean Export Processing Zone, which was developed by reclaiming wasteland in an organized manner, was completely different from the conventional image of a factory," and added, "It was an educationally meaningful site where we could directly witness the process of creating global products." (인솔을 맡은 김영선 숙명여대 생활과학대학 학장은 &amp;quot;황무지를 개간해 짜임새 있게 조성한 한국수출가공공단은 기존의 공장 이미지와는 전혀 달랐다&amp;quot;며 &amp;quot;세계적인 상품이 만들어지는 과정을 직접 확인할 수 있어 교육적으로 의미 있는 현장이었다&amp;quot;고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, this visit was conducted as part of an industry-academia cooperation program operated by Sookmyung Women's University and the Youngone Group. Sookmyung Women's University signed a business agreement with the Youngone Group in 2008 and continues to cooperate in nurturing female talent in the apparel and fashion industry through field education and scholarship support. (한편, 이번 방문은 숙명여대와 영원무역그룹이 운영 중인 산학협력 프로그램의 일환으로 진행됐다. 숙명여대는 2008년 영원무역그룹과 업무협약을 체결하고, 현장 교육과 장학 지원 등을 통해 의류·패션 산업 분야의 여성 인재 양성에 지속적으로 협력하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is a provided information article from the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241031.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0121/2417689941956116.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kyung Hee University Develops AI for Predicting Trauma Deaths Based on Korean Data (경희대, 한국 데이터 기반 구급 외상 사망 예측 AI 개발)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241050.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kyung Hee University Develops AI for Predicting Trauma Deaths Based on Korean Data (경희대, 한국 데이터 기반 구급 외상 사망 예측 AI 개발)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/521/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2917690379632758.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;경희대 생체의공학과 이진석 교수 연구팀이 병원 도착 전 환자 상태를 평가하는 인공지능 모델을 개발했다. 그림 설명. 실시간 외상 대응 흐름 개념도.경희대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A research team led by Professor Jinseok Lee from the Department of Biomedical Engineering at Kyung Hee University (President Jin-sang Kim) has developed an artificial intelligence model that predicts the mortality risk of trauma patients in real-time during the pre-hospital, emergency stage, and validated it using multi-center and multinational data from Korea and abroad. The results of this research were published in the internationally top-tier academic journal 『Nature Communications(IF=15.7)』 in January. This study, a representative achievement supported by the Ministry of Science and ICT's Global AI Frontier Lab project, was conducted as an international joint research with the Department of Emergency Medicine at New York University (NYU) School of Medicine and Australia's Westmead Hospital (a Level 1 trauma center).&lt;br/&gt;Professor Jinseok Lee's research team developed the AI model using data from approximately 200,000 patients stored in the Korea Trauma Data Bank (KTDB). The developed AI model predicts emergency room mortality risk in real-time using only basic information that paramedics can obtain at the scene. While existing trauma severity assessment indicators relied on information after hospital arrival, this newly developed model quantitatively presents mortality risk even before hospital arrival, helping medical staff proactively prepare the necessary personnel and resources for response.&lt;br/&gt;The developed model underwent external validation using data from four regional trauma centers in Korea, including Gachon University Gil Medical Center (Professor Woo-sung Kang), and data from an Australian trauma center. As a result, it maintained high predictive performance not only on domestic data but also on foreign data with different healthcare systems and data structures, showing superior performance compared to existing traditional classification indicators.&lt;br/&gt;Na-eun Oh, a student in the Department of Biomedical Engineering at Kyung Hee University and the first author of the paper (4th term master's student), played a key role in AI model development, statistical analysis, and establishing overseas validation strategies. As part of the Global AI Frontier Lab project in 2026, student Oh Na-eun plans to be dispatched to New York University to conduct overseas joint research and model enhancement using U.S. medical data. Student Oh Na-eun expressed her feelings, stating, "I felt great reward in the fact that we can quantitatively predict a patient's risk even in the very limited information environment of the emergency stage. Through my upcoming dispatch to NYU, I want to further develop technology that can actually contribute to international medical settings."&lt;br/&gt;Professor Jinseok Lee stated, "This is a case that scientifically proves that emergency medical AI technology designed in Korea operates reliably even in overseas medical settings, including the U.S. and Australia. Based on the Global AI Frontier Lab project and cooperation with NYU, our goal is to expand the scope of validation in the future and apply it to clinical settings to dramatically reduce preventable trauma mortality rates."&lt;br/&gt;Professor Jinseok Lee's research team has built the developed AI model into a web-based real-time system that can be used in actual trauma centers, and plans to expand it into a multimodal emergency medical AI platform that combines wearable sensors, voice recognition, and image-based AI. Professor Jinseok Lee forecasted, "It will develop into a next-generation emergency medical AI system that encompasses the entire process from the moment of an accident to hospital arrival and initial treatment." (경희대학교(총장 김진상) 생체의공학과 이진석 교수 연구팀이 병원 이송 전, 구급 단계에서 외상 환자의 사망 위험을 실시간으로 예측하는 인공지능 모델을 개발하고, 국내외 다기관·다국가 데이터로 검증했다. 이번 연구 결과는 국제 최고 권위 학술지 『Nature Communications(IF=15.7)』에 1월 발표됐다. 이번 연구는 과학기술정보통신부가 추진하는 글로벌 AI 프론티어 사업(Global AI Frontier Lab)의 지원을 받아 수행된 대표적인 성과로 뉴욕대학교(NYU) 의과대학 응급의학과, 호주 Westmead Hospital(레벨1 외상센터)과 국제 공동연구를 진행했다.&lt;br/&gt;이진석 교수 연구팀은 한국 국가 외상 데이터베이스(KTDB)에 보관된 약 20만 명의 데이터를 활용해 인공지능 모델을 개발했다. 개발된 인공지능 모델은 구급대원이 현장에서 확보할 수 있는 기본 정보만을 활용해 응급실 사망 위험을 실시간으로 예측한다. 기존 외상 중증도 평가지표는 병원 도착 이후 정보에 의존했지만, 이번에 개발된 모델은 병원 도착 이전부터 사망 위험을 정량적으로 제시해 의료진이 대응에 필요한 인력과 자원을 선제적으로 준비하도록 돕는다. &lt;br/&gt;개발한 모델은 가천대 길병원(강우성 교수) 등 국내 4개 권역외상센터와 호주 외상센터 데이터를 활용해 외부 검증을 수행했다. 그 결과 국내 데이터뿐 아니라 의료 시스템과 데이터 구조가 다른 해외 데이터에서도 높은 예측 성능을 유지하며, 기존의 전통적 분류 지표보다 우수한 성능을 보였다.&lt;br/&gt;논문의 제1저자인 경희대 생체의공학과 오나은 학생(석사 4기)은 인공지능 모델 개발, 통계 분석, 해외 검증 전략 수립에 핵심적인 역할을 맡았다. 오나은 학생은 2026년 글로벌 AI 프론티어 사업의 일환으로 뉴욕대에 파견돼 미국 의료 데이터를 활용한 해외 공동연구와 모델 고도화를 수행할 계획이다. 오나은 학생은 “구급 단계라는 매우 제한된 정보 환경에서도 환자의 위험도를 정량적으로 예측할 수 있다는 점에서 큰 보람을 느꼈다. 향후 뉴욕대 파견을 통해 국제 의료 현장에 실제로 보탬되는 기술을 더욱 발전시키고 싶다”는 소감을 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;이진석 교수는 “한국이 설계한 응급의료 인공지능 기술이 미국과 호주를 포함한 해외 의료 현장에서도 신뢰성 있게 작동함을 과학적으로 입증한 사례다. 글로벌 AI 프론티어 사업과 뉴욕대와의 협력을 바탕으로 향후 검증 범위를 확대하고, 임상 현장에 적용해 예방 가능한 외상 사망률을 획기적으로 낮추는 것이 목표”라고 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;이진석 교수 연구팀은 개발한 인공지능 모델을 실제 외상센터에서 활용할 수 있는 웹 기반 실시간 시스템으로 구축했으며, 향후 웨어러블 센서, 음성 인식, 영상 기반 인공지능을 결합한 멀티모달 응급의료 AI 플랫폼으로 확장할 계획이다. 이진석 교수는 “사고 발생 순간부터 병원 도착, 초기 치료에 이르기까지 전 과정을 아우르는 차세대 응급의료 인공지능 체계로 발전할 것”이라고 전망했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kyung Hee University (* 자료제공 :  경희대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh&amp;gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241050.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/521/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2917690379632758.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kyung Hee University and Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation Support Early-Career Researchers in Korean Linguistics and Korean Studies (경희대-용운장학재단, 국어학·한국학 신진 연구자 지원)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241051.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kyung Hee University and Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation Support Early-Career Researchers in Korean Linguistics and Korean Studies (경희대-용운장학재단, 국어학·한국학 신진 연구자 지원)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/original/2026/0122/7217690382846098.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국어학·한국학 분야 신진 연구자를 지원하기 위해 경희대학교와 용운장학재단은 ‘용운연구교수’ 연구지원 협약을 맺었다. 지난 16일 경희대학교 서울캠퍼스에서 열린 협약식에서 홍인기 경희대학교 산학협력단장, 조홍로 용운장학재단 이사장, 고봉준 후마니타스칼리지 교양교육연구소장이 협약 후 기념촬영을 하고 있다.(사진 좌로부터).경희대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kyung Hee University (President Jin Sang Kim) and the Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation (Chairman Hong Ro Cho) have signed a research support agreement for the 'Yongwoon Research Professor' program to foster a stable research environment for early-career researchers in Korean linguistics or Korean studies. &lt;br/&gt;According to this agreement, the Institute of General Education Research at Kyung Hee University's College of Humanities will select one academic research professor as the 'Yongwoon Research Professor,' and the Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation will provide 30 million won per year for two years. &lt;br/&gt;The signing ceremony held on Friday, January 16, at the main building of Kyung Hee University's Seoul Campus was attended by Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation Chairman Hong Ro Cho, Kyung Hee University Industry-Academic Cooperation Foundation Director In Ki Hong, and Institute of General Education Research Director Bong Jun Ko. &lt;br/&gt;Chairman Hong Ro Cho stated, "The foundation's founder and former chairman had a great interest in supporting research related to Korean language, literature, and ethnic culture—matters pertaining to Korean identity. That interest has continued, and we have steadily maintained related projects with various universities. The humanities education represented by Kyung Hee University's College of Humanities aligns with our foundation's aspirations. I hope that, together with the Institute of General Education Research, which has conducted excellent research, achievements will accumulate that connect the present with future generations of scholars." &lt;br/&gt;Director In Ki Hong said, "We will do our utmost to ensure the research support funds are used transparently and stably for their intended purpose. We will fulfill our role to help the researchers who receive substantial support through this agreement produce outstanding results." &lt;br/&gt;Director Bong Jun Ko remarked, "Our society, facing various unprecedented challenges, is demanding a comprehensive transformation in higher education to keep pace with the changing world. In response, academic fields are also rapidly reorganizing, leading to some areas being marginalized in the process. We will accept this agreement not merely as financial support but as an encouragement to steadfastly continue the university's fundamental role." &lt;br/&gt;The two institutions had previously signed an agreement and operated the same program in November 2023. Kim Nang-yae, a lecturer in the Department of Korean Language and Literature who was selected as the 2024 Yongwoon Research Professor and received research funding, expressed her gratitude, saying, "The support from the Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation was a great help during a difficult time when I was juggling research and household duties while managing my high school senior child. As a result, I was able to complete seven papers in one year." &lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the Yongwoon Scholarship Foundation was established in 1986 by the late Chairman Rak Kyo Cho of Samryung Moolsan to alleviate university students' tuition burdens. Starting with scholarship support programs, it has expanded to various talent development initiatives, including academic/research support and awards for outstanding researchers. (경희대학교(총장 김진상)와 용운장학재단(이사장 조홍로)은 국어학 또는 한국학 분야 신진 연구자의 안정적인 연구 환경 조성을 위해 ‘용운연구교수’ 연구지원 협약을 체결했다. &lt;br/&gt;이번 협약에 따라 경희대학교 후마니타스칼리지 교양교육연구소는 학술 연구교수인 ‘용운연구교수’ 1인을 선발하고, 용운장학재단은 2년간 매해 3,000만 원을 지원한다. &lt;br/&gt;지난 1월 16일(금) 경희대학교 서울캠퍼스 본관에서 열린 협약식에는 용운장학재단 조홍로 이사장, 경희대학교 산학협력단 홍인기 단장, 후마니타스칼리지 교양교육연구소 고봉준 소장 등이 참석했다. &lt;br/&gt;조홍로 이사장은 “재단 설립자이자 선대 이사장이 한국어, 문학, 민족 문화 등 한국적인 것에 관한 연구지원에 관심이 많았다. 그러한 관심이 계속 이어져서 여러 대학과 관련 사업을 꾸준히 유지해 오고 있다. 후마니타스칼리지로 대표되는 경희대학교의 인문학 교육이 우리 재단의 뜻과 상통한다. 그동안 훌륭하게 연구해 온 후마니타스칼리지 교양교육연구소와 함께 현재와 학문 후속세대를 잇는 연구 성과가 축적되기를 바란다”고 말했다. &lt;br/&gt;홍인기 단장은 “연구지원비가 목적에 맞게 투명하고 안정적으로 집행될 수 있도록 최선을 다하겠다. 이번 협약을 통해 실질적으로 지원을 받는 연구자들의 탁월한 성과가 도출될 수 있도록 역할을 다하겠다”고 말했다. &lt;br/&gt;고봉준 소장은 “지금껏 경험하지 못했던 다양한 난제에 직면한 우리 사회는 세상의 변화에 맞춰 고등 교육의 전면적인 변화를 요청하고 있다. 이에 대한 대응으로 학문 분야 역시 빠르게 재편되고 있으며 그 과정에서 소외되는 분야가 생기게 됐다. 이 협약은 금전적 지원만이 아니라 대학의 본래적 역할을 잘 지속해 나아가라는 뜻으로 받아들이겠다”고 말했다. &lt;br/&gt;양 기관은 지난 2023년 11월에도 협약을 맺고 동일한 프로그램을 운영한 바 있다. 2024년에 용운연구교수로 선발되어 연구비를 지원받은 김낭예 국어국문학과 강사는 “연구와 가사 병행, 고등학교 3학년 자녀 관리 등으로 힘들었던 시기에 용운장학재단의 지원금이 큰 힘이 됐다. 그 결과로 한 해 동안 7편의 논문을 완성할 수 있었다”며 고마움을 표했다. &lt;br/&gt;한편 용운장학재단은 삼륭물산 故 조락교 회장이 대학생의 등록금 부담을 덜어주고자 1986년에 설립했다. 장학금 지원사업으로 시작해 학술·연구 지원, 우수 연구자 시상 등 다양한 인재 육성 사업을 펼쳐오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kyung Hee University (* 자료제공 :  경희대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241051.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/original/2026/0122/7217690382846098.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year's Economic Growth Rate Barely Reaches 1%... 4th Quarter Sees -0.3% Contraction (지난해 경제성장률 1% 턱걸이…4분기 -0.3% 역성장)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241052.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Last Year's Economic Growth Rate Barely Reaches 1%... 4th Quarter Sees -0.3% Contraction (지난해 경제성장률 1% 턱걸이…4분기 -0.3% 역성장)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500369.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지뱅크&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, the Korean economy grew by 1% amid sluggish domestic demand, including in construction and facility investment. (지난해 우리 경제가 건설·설비투자 등 내수 부진 속에 1% 성장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bank of Korea announced on the 22nd that the real Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth rate (quarter-on-quarter, preliminary) for the fourth quarter of 2025 was -0.3%. The quarterly growth rate contracted in the first quarter of last year, rebounded successfully in the second quarter (0.7%), and then rose sharply in the third quarter (1.3%), but contracted again in the fourth quarter. The fourth-quarter growth rate is 0.5 percentage points lower than the BOK's forecast (0.2%). It is the lowest figure in three years since the fourth quarter of 2022 (-0.4%). The BOK explained, "The fourth-quarter growth rate turned negative due to base effects from the high growth in the third quarter and a slump in construction investment." (한국은행은 2025년 4분기 실질 국내총생산(GDP) 성장률(직전분기대비·속보치)이 -0.3%로 집계됐다고 22일 밝혔다. 분기 성장률은 작년 1분기역성장했다가 2분기(0.7%) 반등에 성공한 뒤 3분기(1.3%) 큰 폭 상승했지만 4분기 다시 역성장을 나타냈다. 4분기 성장률은 한은 예상치(0.2%)보다 0.5%포인트나 낮은 것이다. 2022년 4분기(-0.4%) 이후 3년만에 최저치다. 한은은 “3분기 높은 성장률에 따른 기저효과와 건설투자 침체 등으로 4분기 성장률이 마이너스를 나타냈다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the fourth-quarter growth rate by sector last year, private consumption increased by 0.3% compared to the third quarter, centered on services such as medical care, despite a decrease in goods like passenger cars. Government consumption also increased by 0.6%, mainly due to health insurance benefit payments. However, construction investment decreased by 3.9% as both building and civil engineering construction were sluggish, and facility investment also retreated by 1.8%, centered on transport equipment such as automobiles. (지난해 4분기 성장률을 부문별로 보면, 민간소비는 승용차 등 재화 부문 감소에도 의료 등 서비스를 중심으로 3분기보다 0.3% 늘었다. 정부소비도 건강보험 급여비 위주로 0.6% 증가했다. 하지만 건설투자가 건물·토목 건설이 모두 부진한 가운데 3.9% 감소했고, 설비투자 역시 자동차 등 운송장비 중심으로 1.8% 뒷걸음쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exports shrank by 2.1% due to decreases in automobiles, machinery, and equipment, and imports also decreased by 1.7%, mainly in natural gas and automobiles. Looking at the contribution to the fourth-quarter growth rate, domestic demand and net exports (exports-imports) each dragged down the growth rate by 0.1 percentage points and 0.2 percentage points, respectively. In particular, the contribution of domestic demand plummeted by 1.3 percentage points compared to the previous third quarter (1.2 percentage points). Within domestic demand, private consumption and government consumption each contributed 0.1 percentage points to growth. In contrast, construction investment and facility investment shaved off 0.5 percentage points and 0.2 percentage points from the growth rate, respectively. (수출은 자동차·기계·장비 등이 줄어 2.1% 위축됐고, 수입도 천연가스·자동차위주로 1.7% 감소했다. 4분기 성장률 기여도를 보면, 내수와 순수출(수출-수입)이 각각 0.1%포인트, 0.2%포인트씩 성장률을 끌어내렸다. 특히 내수 기여도가 직전 3분기(1.2%포인트)에 견줘 1.3%포인트 급락했다. 내수 중에서도 민간소비와 정부소비는 0.1%포인트씩 성장에 기여했다. 반면 건설투자와 설비투자가 각각 0.5%포인트, 0.2%포인트 성장률을 깎아내렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real Gross Domestic Income (GDI) growth rate for the fourth quarter of last year was 0.8%, surpassing the real GDP growth rate (-0.3%). (작년 4분기 실질 국내총소득(GDI) 증가율은 0.8%로 실질 국내총생산 성장률(-0.3%)을 웃돌았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241052.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500369.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Breaking News] KOSPI Breaches 5,000 for the First Time in 46 Years ([속보] 코스피, 46년 만에 첫 ‘5000’ 돌파)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241056.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[Breaking News] KOSPI Breaches 5,000 for the First Time in 46 Years ([속보] 코스피, 46년 만에 첫 ‘5000’ 돌파)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/554/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500462.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;우리은행 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, the KOSPI index breached the 5,000 mark for the first time ever during intraday trading. This comes 46 years after the market opened at 100 points on January 4, 1980. (코스피가 22일 장중 사상 처음으로 5000을 돌파했다. 1980년 1월 4일 코스피 100으로 장을 연지 46년 만의 일이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the Korea Exchange, the KOSPI opened at 4,987.06, up 1.57% from the previous session, and immediately hit 5,002.88, breaking through the 5,000 level. As of 9:10 a.m., it is fluctuating around the 5,000 mark. After historically surpassing the 4,000 level for the first time last year, the KOSPI has continued its steep upward trend this year, setting new record highs almost daily. (이날 유가증권 시장에서 코스피는 전장보다 1.57% 오른 4987.06에 개장해 곧바로 5002.88을 찍으며 5000을 돌파했다. 9시10분 현재 5000선에서 등락을 거듭하고 있다. 지난해 사상 처음 4000선을 돌파한 코스피는 올해 들어 연일 최고치를 경신하며 가파른 상승세를 이어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI first broke through the 1,000 mark in 1989, taking nine years after the index's calculation began. It then took over 30 years to surpass the 3,000 level, first reaching the 3,000-point milestone on January 7, 2021. Following the end of internal conflicts and improvements in the semiconductor industry's conditions, it broke above 4,000 on October 27 last year for the first time in four years, and has now reached the 5,000 mark in just three months. (코스피가 처음으로 1000선을 뚫은 것은 1989년이었다. 지수 산출 뒤 9년이 걸렸다. 이후 3000선을 넘기까지 30년 넘게 걸려 2021년 1월7일 처음 3000고지를 밟았다. 내란 종식과 반도체 업황 개선 등으로 지난해 10월27일 4년 만에 4000선을 넘더니, 불과 석 달 만에 5000선에 도달한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Semiconductor stocks rose sharply in the New York stock market overnight after U.S. President Donald Trump withdrew tariffs on Greenland. Today, Samsung Electronics is trading at 154,500 won, up 3.34%, and SK Hynix is trading at 768,000 won, up 3.78%. Hyundai Motor is also trading at 577,000 won, up 5.10%. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 그린란드 관세를 철회하면서 간밤 뉴욕증시에서 반도체주가 크게 올랐다. 이날 삼성전자가 3.34% 오른 15만4500원, 에스케이하이닉스가 3.78% 오른 76만8000원에 거래 중이다. 현대차도 5.10% 오른 57만7000원에 거래 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Kyung-mi &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이경미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241056.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/554/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122500462.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Presenting a Practical Graduate School Model Linking Industry, Academia, and Research... Seoul City University's Early Employment Contract Department Info Session Successfully Concludes (산학연 연계 실무형 대학원 모델 제시… 서울시립대 조기취업형 계약학과 설명회 성료)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241066.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/468/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3717690455463015.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;궤도 행사 사진.서울시립대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Seoul City University Graduate School Early Employment Contract Department Project Team (Biohealth &amp; Eco Convergence Department) held an information session for the Early Employment Contract Department on January 21st at the main campus and invited 'Orbit', a creator in the science and engineering field, to give a special lecture. This session was held to enhance students' understanding of the Early Employment Contract Department and to establish a support system linking career paths, graduate studies, and employment.&lt;br/&gt;The event began with an introduction to the practical graduate school model, covering the operational purpose, curriculum, corporate participation structure, employment linkage, and industry-academia projects of the Early Employment Contract Department. In the following special lecture, Orbit shared cases of change and innovation in future technology fields under the theme 'Can Unconventional Curiosity Change the World?', presenting various possibilities for science and engineering students to explore career paths in technology-based industries.&lt;br/&gt;The atmosphere was particularly lively as explanations about the competencies and experiences needed in trending future industrial fields such as biohealth, eco-friendliness, AI, and data-based industries were followed by student questions. A vibrant Q&amp;A session addressed practical concerns regarding graduate school attendance, industry field experience, career planning, balancing research and practical work, and corporate-participation education models.&lt;br/&gt;Reflecting high student interest in the Early Employment Contract Department, this info session showed strong participation, with the first 200 spots filled within two days of promotion opening. Consultations and inquiries about additional sessions continued before and after the event, confirming undergraduate demand for linking graduate studies and careers.&lt;br/&gt;Jeong Yeon-du, head of the Seoul City University Graduate School Early Employment Contract Department Project Team, stated, "The industry needs talent equipped with both practical and research capabilities in innovative fields, and social demand for an educational model supporting this is growing." He added, "I hope this info session helps students actively design their graduate studies and careers." He continued, "Seoul City University will play a role in nurturing talent amid industrial transformation through industry-academia linked practical education."&lt;br/&gt;The Biohealth &amp; Eco Convergence Department operates as part of the Ministry of Education's Leading Graduate School Fostering Project for Early Employment Contract Departments. It runs a curriculum reflecting industry demands in convergence areas like biohealth, environment, and data, aiming to cultivate talent with immediately applicable practical skills by combining experiments, projects, corporate internships, and field-based education.&lt;br/&gt;Seoul City University plans to expand student participation in the Early Employment Contract Department through follow-up programs such as counseling, open campus events, admissions info sessions, and corporate mentoring. It also plans to develop the practical graduate school model that connects graduate studies, employment, and research by strengthening cooperation with industry. (서울시립대학교 대학원 조기취업형 계약학과 사업단(바이오헬스·에코 융합학과)은 1월 21일 본교에서 조기취업형 계약학과 설명회를 개최하고 이공계 분야 크리에이터 ‘궤도’를 초청해 특강을 진행했다. 이번 설명회는 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생들의 이해를 높이고 진로·진학·취업을 연계한 지원 체계를 마련하기 위해 개최됐다.&lt;br/&gt;행사에서는 먼저 조기취업형 계약학과의 운영 목적, 교육 과정, 기업 참여 구조, 취업 연계, 산학 프로젝트 등 실무 중심 대학원 모델에 대한 소개가 진행됐다. 이어진 특강에서 궤도는 ‘엉뚱한 호기심이 세상을 바꿀 수 있을까?’를 주제로 미래 기술 분야의 변화와 혁신 사례를 공유하며, 이공계 학생들이 기술 기반 산업에서 진로를 탐색할 수 있는 다양한 가능성을 제시했다.&lt;br/&gt;특히 바이오헬스, 친환경, AI, 데이터 기반 산업 등 이슈가 되는 미래 산업 분야에서 어떤 역량과 경험이 필요한지에 대한 설명과 함께 학생들의 질문이 이어지며 현장 분위기가 뜨거웠다. 대학원 진학 여부, 산업 현장 경험, 커리어 설계, 연구와 실무 간 균형, 기업 참여형 교육 모델 등 현실적인 고민에 대한 질의응답이 활발하게 진행됐다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 설명회는 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생들의 높은 관심을 반영하듯 홍보 시작 이틀 만에 선착순 200명이 마감되며 높은 참여 열기를 보였다. 행사 전후로 상담 및 추가 설명회 문의가 이어지며 진학과 커리어를 연계하려는 학부생 수요가 확인됐다.&lt;br/&gt;서울시립대학교 대학원 조기취업형 계약학과 사업단 정연두 단장은 “산업계는 혁신 분야에서 실무와 연구 역량을 모두 갖춘 인재를 필요로 하고 있으며, 이를 뒷받침하는 교육 모델에 대한 사회적 수요가 커지고 있다”고 밝히며 “이번 설명회가 학생들이 진학과 커리어를 능동적으로 설계하는 데 도움이 되길 바란다”고 말했다. 이어 “서울시립대학교는 산학 연계 기반 실무형 교육을 통해 산업 전환 속 인재양성 역할을 수행할 것”이라고 덧붙였다.&lt;br/&gt;바이오헬스·에코융합학과는 교육부가 주관하는 조기취업형 계약학과 선도대학원 육성사업의 일환으로 바이오헬스·환경·데이터 등 융합 영역에서 산업 수요를 반영한 교육과정을 운영하고 있으며, 실험·프로젝트·기업 실습·현장 기반 교육을 결합해 실무에서 바로 활용 가능한 역량을 갖춘 인재 양성을 목표로 하고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;서울시립대학교는 향후 상담 프로그램, 오픈캠퍼스, 입시 설명회, 기업 멘토링 등 후속 사업을 통해 조기취업형 계약학과에 대한 학생 참여를 확대할 계획이며 산업계와의 협력을 강화해 진학·취업·연구가 연결되는 실무형 대학원 모델을 발전시킬 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul City University (* 자료제공 :  서울시립대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241066.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/468/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3717690455463015.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sejong University Sejong Museum Gallery Hall 1 to Hold Ahn Jung-sook's Invitational Planning Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 1관,안정숙 기획초대전 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241068.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0122/5817690458445583.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;안정숙 포스터.세종대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sejong University (President Eom Jong-hwa) Sejong Museum Gallery Hall 1 will hold artist Ahn Jung-sook's solo exhibition 'Thread Drawing: A 32-Day Journey' from Wednesday, January 21, to Sunday, February 8, 2026. The exhibition unravels motifs from nature into abstract canvases. This exhibition will feature over 70 abstract paintings that translate the bodily memories and emotions experienced in nature into pictorial language, including the artist's representative '32-Day Journey' series.&lt;br/&gt;Artist Ahn Jung-sook graduated from the Graduate School of Painting at Hongik University and has expanded painting into a record of physical action and sensation, using thread as her primary material. The sensations internalized from the changing seasons and within nature manifest as abstract canvases woven with diverse colors, lines, and rhythms, forming free-flowing movements within consistent patterns.&lt;br/&gt;'Thread drawing,' the process of laying colored thread like a brush onto thick canvases built up with layers of various materials, is central to Ahn Jung-sook's painting. This repeated action, involving moving her body around a canvas placed on the floor, simultaneously draws lines and imprints the artist's bodily rhythm and time directly onto the canvas. Art critic Seo Seong-rok commented, "By wandering around the canvas, the artist reconstructs the experience of nature into a cognitive unconscious," adding, "Within this flow, the presence or absence of an image holds little significance; the act itself already embodies the motive force of nature and represents vital meaning."&lt;br/&gt;A representative from Sejong Museum Gallery stated, "Ahn Jung-sook's paintings are works that transform the gaze toward nature from representation into bodily memory and action," and expressed hope that "this exhibition will be a time for audiences to open their senses and expand their contemplation." (세종대학교(총장 엄종화) 세종뮤지엄갤러리 1관은 2026년 1월 21일(수)부터 2월 8일(일)까지 자연의 모티브를 추상적 화면으로 풀어내는 안정숙 작가의 개인전 ‘실 drawing: 32일의 여행’을 개최한다. 이번 전시에는 작가의 대표작인 ‘32일의 여행’ 시리즈를 포함해, 자연을 경험한 몸의 기억과 정서를 회화적 언어로 풀어낸 추상화 70여 점이 선보인다.&lt;br/&gt;안정숙 작가는 홍익대학교 미술대학원 회화과를 졸업했으며, 실(thread)을 주재료로 삼아 회화를 신체적 행위와 감각의 기록으로 확장해 왔다. 사계절의 변화와 자연 속에서 체득한 감각은 다채로운 색과 선, 리듬으로 직조된 추상적 화면으로 나타나며, 화면은 일정한 패턴 속에서 자유로운 흐름을 형성한다.&lt;br/&gt;여러 재료를 쌓아 올린 두터운 화면 위에 색실을 붓처럼 얹는 ‘실 드로잉’ 작업은 안정숙 회화의 핵심이다. 바닥에 놓인 캔버스를 중심으로 몸을 이동시키며 반복되는 이 행위는 선을 그리는 동시에, 작가의 신체 리듬과 시간을 화면에 고스란히 각인시킨다. 미술평론가 서성록은 “작가가 캔버스 주위를 배회함으로써 자연의 체험을 인지적 무의식으로 재구성하게 된다”며 “이러한 흐름 속에서 이미지의 유무는 큰 의미를 지니지 않으며, 행위 자체가 이미 자연의 동인(動因)을 품고 생명적인 의미를 표상한다”고 평했다.&lt;br/&gt;세종뮤지엄갤러리 관계자는 “안정숙의 회화는 자연을 바라보는 시선을 재현이 아닌 몸의 기억과 행위로 전환한 작업”이라며 “이번 전시가 관객들에게 감각을 열고 사유를 확장하는 시간이 되길 기대한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sejong University (* 자료제공 :  세종대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241068.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0122/5817690458445583.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:12:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sejong University's Sejong Museum Gallery 2 Holds Go Yong-seok's Invitational Exhibition (세종대 세종뮤지엄갤러리 2관,고용석 기획초대전 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241069.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8617690461468171.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;고용석 포스터.세종대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sejong University (President Eom Jong-hwa) Sejong Museum Gallery 2 will hold a solo exhibition by ceramic artist Go Yong-seok, who presents ceramic works based on the aesthetic sense of Joseon white porcelain and imbued with nature, time, and emotion, from Wednesday, January 21 to Wednesday, February 11, 2026. &lt;br/&gt;Artist Go Yong-seok, who is based in Jeju, graduated from Chung-Ang University's Department of Craft Arts and its graduate school, completed a research course in ceramics at Tokyo University of the Arts Graduate School, and earned a doctorate from the Graduate School of Design Management at Chosun University. He has been continuously working on reinterpreting the formative qualities and aesthetic sense of traditional white porcelain in a modern language, metaphorically capturing the breath and rhythm of nature.&lt;br/&gt;The approximately 40 works presented in this exhibition, centered around the 'Bal-a' and 'Neoul' series featuring circular vessel forms, and the 'skein' series, reveal subtle asymmetry, surface textures, and the flow of glaze rather than perfectly closed forms. This reflects the artist's perception of a naturally existing state. The traces on the surface and the empty spaces seen in his ceramics symbolize nature and humans as living beings, not as imperfections.&lt;br/&gt;A representative of Sejong Museum Gallery stated, "The artist's white porcelain works, which hold the traces left by nature and the grain of time, leave a depth and space that allows viewers to project their own memories and emotions," adding, "This exhibition will be a time to look again at the meaning of existence itself with a quiet yet solid resonance." (세종대학교(총장 엄종화) 세종뮤지엄갤러리 2관은 조선 백자의 미감을 바탕으로 자연과 시간, 감성이 담긴 도자 작업을 선보이는 도예가 고용석의 개인전을 2026년 1월 21일(수)부터 2월 11일(수)까지 개최한다. &lt;br/&gt;제주를 기반으로 활동하는 고용석 작가는 중앙대학교 공예학과 및 동 대학원을 졸업하고, 동경예술대학 대학원 도예전공 연구과정을 거쳐 조선대학교 대학원 디자인경영학과 박사과정을 졸업했다. 그는 전통 백자의 조형성과 미감을 현대적인 언어로 재해석하며, 자연의 호흡과 리듬을 은유적으로 담아내는 작업을 지속해 오고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 전시에서 선보이는 40여 점의 작품들은 원형의 기물 형태인 ‘발아’와 ‘너울’, 그리고 ‘skein’ 연작을 중심으로, 완벽하게 닫힌 형태보다는 미묘한 비대칭과 표면의 결, 유약의 흐름을 그대로 드러낸다. 이는 자연스럽게 존재하는 상태에 대한 작가의 인식을 반영한다. 그의 도자에서 보이는 표면의 흔적과 여백은 불완전함이 아닌, 살아 있는 존재로서의 자연과 인간을 상징한다.&lt;br/&gt;세종뮤지엄갤러리 관계자는 “자연이 남긴 흔적과 시간의 결을 품은 작가의 백자 작품들은 관람자가 각자의 기억과 감정을 투영할 수 있는 깊이와 여백을 남기고 있다”며, “이번 전시는 조용하지만 단단한 울림으로, 존재하는 것 그 자체의 의미를 다시 바라보게 하는 시간이 될 것”이라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Sejong University (* 자료제공 :  세종대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241069.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/976/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8617690461468171.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:11:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Duksung Women's University's University Job Plus Center Receives 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Annual Performance Evaluation (덕성여대 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 연차성과평가 '우수' 등급 획득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241072.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/387/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3917690464735306.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대학일자리본부_사진.덕성여대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Duksung Women's University (Acting President Kim Jong-gil) announced on the 21st that its University Job Plus Center received the highest grade of 'Excellent' in the 2025 University Job Plus Center Annual Performance Evaluation.&lt;br/&gt;This evaluation, conducted by the Ministry of Employment and Labor and the Korea Employment Information Service, comprehensively assessed the quality of youth employment services across various areas, including the status of university youth employment services, customized employment services for enrolled students, and the operation of counseling and employment programs.&lt;br/&gt;Duksung Women's University's University Job Plus Center was highly praised for its systematic operation of step-by-step, customized employment support programs covering enrolled students, graduates, and local youth.&lt;br/&gt;In particular, the restructuring of its career support system and the stable operation of its own programs were cited as excellent examples. Its contribution to revitalizing local youth employment through collaboration with related institutions also received positive evaluation.&lt;br/&gt;Lee Ho-rim, Director of the Duksung Women's University Job Plus Center (Professor of Bioengineering), stated, "Achieving this excellent grade is the result of our members' professionalism and practical employment support tailored to each individual youth," adding, "We will continue to expand customized employment services to prepare students for successful employment and social advancement." (덕성여자대학교(총장 직무대리 김종길) 대학일자리플러스센터가 2025년 대학일자리플러스센터 연차성과평가에서 최고등급인 &amp;#x27;우수&amp;#x27;를 받았다고 21일 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;고용노동부와 한국고용정보원이 주관한 이번 평가는 대학청년고용서비스 현황, 재학생 맞춤형 고용서비스, 상담 및 취업프로그램 운영 등 다양한 영역에서 청년 고용서비스의 질을 종합적으로 평가했다.&lt;br/&gt;덕성여자대학교 대학일자리플러스센터는 재학생부터 졸업생, 지역 청년까지 포괄하는 단계별 맞춤형 취업지원 프로그램을 체계적으로 운영해 온 점이 높은 평가를 받았다.&lt;br/&gt;특히 진로지원체계를 재구조화하고 자체 프로그램을 안정적으로 운영한 점이 우수 사례로 꼽혔다. 또한 유관기관과의 협업을 통해 지역 청년 고용 활성화에 기여한 점도 긍정적인 평가를 받았다.&lt;br/&gt;덕성여자대학교 이호림 대학일자리플러스센터장(바이오공학전공 교수)는 &amp;quot;이번 우수 등급 달성은 구성원들의 전문성과 청년 개개인에 맞춘 실질적인 취업지원의 결과&amp;quot;라며 &amp;quot;앞으로도 학생들의 성공적인 취업 준비와 사회 진출을 위한 맞춤형 고용서비스를 지속적으로 확대해 나가겠다&amp;quot;고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Duksung Women's University (* 자료제공 :  덕성여자대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241072.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/387/imgdb/original/2026/0122/3917690464735306.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:11:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Last Year, 'Online Real Estate Contracts' Surpassed 500,000 for the First Time... Driven by Private Brokerage Transactions (작년 ‘부동산 온라인 계약’ 첫 50만건 체결…민간 중개거래가 견인)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241079.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501276.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;클립아트코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of 'real estate electronic contracts,' which allow people to buy, sell, or sign lease contracts online without complicated paperwork, is rapidly increasing. (집을 사고팔거나 전·월세 계약을 할 때 복잡한 서류 없이 온라인으로 계약하는 ‘부동산 전자계약’ 이용이 빠르게 늘고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport announced on the 22nd that the number of real estate transactions concluded via electronic contracts last year reached 507,431, surpassing 500,000 for the first time. This is more than double the figure from 2024 (231,074). The 'electronic contract utilization rate,' calculated by dividing the total number of real estate transactions by the number of electronic contracts concluded, also rose significantly compared to 2024, breaking through the 10% range for the first time. The electronic contract utilization rate started at 0.77% in 2018, gradually increased to 5.95% in 2024, and then surged to 12.04% (as of November) last year. (국토교통부는 지난해 한 해 동안 전자계약으로 체결된 부동산 거래가 50만7431건으로 처음 50만건을 넘어섰다고 22일 밝혔다. 이는 2024년(23만1074건)과 견줘 2배 이상 급증한 수치다. 전체 부동산 거래량을 전자계약 체결 건수로 나눈 ‘전자계약 활용률’ 또한 2024년 대비 크게 상승해 처음 10%대를 돌파했다. 전자계약 활용률은 2018년 0.77%로 시작해 2024년 5.95%로 서서히 늘다가 지난해 12.04%(11월 기준)까지 급증했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The growth is particularly noticeable in the private brokerage transaction market. The number of electronic contracts in private brokerage transactions increased approximately 4.5 times, from 73,622 in 2024 to 327,974 last year, driving the activation of electronic contracts. Electronic contracts in the public sector also increased by 17.97%, from 138,550 in 2024 to 163,447 last year. (특히 민간 중개거래 시장에서의 증가세가 눈에 띈다. 민간 중개거래 가운데 전자계약 실적은 2024년 7만3622건에서 지난해 32만7974건으로 약 4.5배 증가해 전자계약 활성화를 견인했다. 공공 분야 전자계약 역시 2024년 13만8550건에서 지난해 16만3447건으로 17.97% 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport has continuously promoted system improvements and incentive expansion to activate electronic contracts. In the second half of last year, it enhanced transaction convenience by adding features such as the transmission of contract information for the Housing and Urban Guarantee Corporation (HUG) rental guarantee review and linking contract document modifications with the private brokerage platform 'Hanbang.' Furthermore, server replacements were made to prepare for the surge in users, ensuring service stability. (그간 국토부는 전자계약 활성화를 위해 시스템 개선과 인센티브 확대를 지속적으로 추진해왔다. 지난해 하반기에는 주택도시보증공사(HUG) 임대보증심사 계약정보 전송 기능 추가, 민간 중개플랫폼 ‘한방’과의 양방향 계약서 수정 연계 등을 통해 거래 편의성을 높였다. 아울러 이용자 급증에 대비한 서버 교체로 서비스 안정성도 확보했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starting from the end of January this year, the identity verification methods required for electronic contracts will become more convenient. Currently, identity verification is only possible through three methods: telecom carriers (mobile phones), i-PIN, and public certificates. In the future, 15 types of simple authentication will also be available, including Naver, Kakao, and Toss authentication, KB Bank and Shinhan Bank financial certificates, and telecom carrier PASS. (올해 1월 말부터는 전자계약에 필요한 본인인증 방식도 한결 간편해진다. 지금은 통신사(휴대폰), 아이핀, 공동인증서 등 3가지 방식으로만 본인인증을 할 수 있는데, 앞으로는 네이버·카카오·토스 인증과 케이비(KB)은행·신한은행 금융인증서, 통신사 패스(PASS) 등 15종의 간편인증도 가능해진다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using electronic contracts provides economic incentives such as financial benefits. For landlords, there is a 10% reduction in the Housing and Urban Guarantee Corporation's rental guarantee fee. Buyers and tenants receive a 0.1 to 0.2 percentage point interest rate reduction when obtaining loans from commercial banks (10 banks). Other benefits include a 30% reduction in registration agency fees and interest-free installment payments (2 to 6 months) for brokerage fees via card payment. (전자계약을 이용하면 금융 혜택 등 경제적 인센티브가 제공된다. 임대인의 경우 주택도시보증공사 임대보증수수료를 10% 인하받을 수 있고, 매수인과 임차인은 시중은행(10곳) 대출 시 0.1∼0.2%포인트 금리 인하 혜택을 받는다. 이외에도 등기대행수수료 30% 절감, 중개보수 카드결제 무이자 할부(2∼6개월) 등의 혜택도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Jun-hyung, Director General of Land Policy at the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, stated, "We will continue to promote system improvements and expand incentives to broaden the base of electronic contracts," adding, "We will do our best to create a digital environment where the public can trade real estate more safely and conveniently." (박준형 국토부 토지정책관은 “앞으로도 시스템 개선과 인센티브 확대를 지속 추진하여 전자계약 저변을 넓히겠다”며 “국민들이 더욱 안전하고 편리하게 부동산을 거래할 수 있는 디지털 환경 조성에 최선을 다할 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241079.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501276.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:11:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Even '3,000 points' was tough during the global crisis... But with the semiconductor boom, '5,000 points' in just 9 months (글로벌 위기에 ‘3천피’도 버거웠는데…반도체 호황에 9개월 만에 ‘5천피’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241082.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690488830037_20260122501476.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 오전 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 코스피가 장중 5,000을 넘어서자 기뻐하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"If the administration changes, the stock market could break through 3,000 next year. If things go well, it's normal for it to reach 5,000 during the term." (“정권이 교체되면 내년에 증시가 3000을 돌파할 수 있을 것이다. 제대로 되면 임기 중 5000까지 가는 게 정상이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are not the words of President Lee Jae-myung. They are remarks made a whopping 19 years ago, on December 14, 2007, by then-presidential candidate Lee Myung-bak of the Grand National Party. Like this, 'KOSPI 5,000' has long been a goal of successive presidents to revitalize the economy by boosting the Korean stock market, which has been weighed down by chronic undervaluation. (이재명 대통령의 얘기가 아니다. 무려 19년 전인 2007년 12월14일 이명박 대통령이 한나라당 대선 후보시절 한 발언이다. 이처럼 ‘코스피 5000’은 오랫동안 고질적인 저평가에 눌려온 한국 증시를 부양해 경제를 활성화시키겠다는 역대 대통령들의 목표였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of former President Lee's remarks, the KOSPI closing price was 1,895.05. Former President Lee sought economic revival with the so-called '747 pledge', but due to the shock of the 2008 global financial crisis in October-November 2008, the KOSPI broke below 1,000, even falling to 983.32. However, by the end of his term, it had recovered to the 2,000 level again. (이 전 대통령의 발언 당시 코스피 종가는 1895.05였다. 이 전 대통령은 이른바 ‘747 공약’으로 경제 부흥을 꾀했지만 2008년 10~11월 글로벌 금융위기 충격으로 코스피가 1000이 깨져 983.32까지 내려가기도 했다. 다만 퇴임 무렵엔 다시 2000선을 회복했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park Geun-hye, who took office in 2013, set a more 'realistic' goal of 'KOSPI 3,000 within the term'. However, as the United States ended its massive quantitative easing, implemented in response to the global financial crisis, and shifted its monetary policy to tightening, the domestic stock market also froze. Throughout former President Park's term, the KOSPI remained in the 1,000-2,000 range, dubbed 'Box-pi'. (2013년 취임한 박근혜 전 대통령은 좀 더 ‘현실적인’ 목표인 ‘임기 내 코스피 3000’을 내걸었다. 하지만 미국이 글로벌 금융위기에 대응해 막대한 돈을 풀던 양적 완화를 종료하고 통화정책을 긴축으로 전환하면서 국내 증시도 얼어붙었다. 박 전 대통령 임기 내내 코스피는 1000~2000대 ‘박스피’에 머물렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even after former President Moon Jae-in took office in 2017, the 'Box-pi' phenomenon of staying in the 2,000s continued. Then, in 2020, as the global economy took a direct hit from the COVID-19 pandemic, the KOSPI fell to the 1,500 level. However, with massive economic stimulus measures by various countries flooding the market with funds, it began to rebound, breaking through 3,000 for the first time in history in January 2021. But the money released during COVID-19 caused global inflation, leading to a shift back to monetary tightening policies from 2022, and with the Russia-Ukraine war breaking out in 2022, it fell back to the 2,100 level. (2017년 문재인 전 대통령 취임 뒤에도 2000대에 머무르는 박스피는 계속 됐다. 그러다 2020년 코로나19 팬데믹 사태로 세계 경제가 직격탄을 맞아 코스피가 1500선까지 떨어졌다가, 각국의 대규모 경기부양책으로 시중에 자금이 대거 풀리면서 반등하기 시작해 2021년 1월 사상 처음 3000을 돌파했다. 하지만 코로나19 때 풀린 돈이 세계적으로 인플레이션을 일으켜 2022년부터 다시 통화 긴축 정책으로 전환되고 2022년 러시아-우크라이나 전쟁까지 터져 다시 2100선으로 내려갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Yoon Suk-yeol administration, which took office in May of that year, also expressed its intention to boost stock prices with the goal of 'Korea stock market value-up', but with the December 3rd insurrection incident erupting in 2024, stock prices remained around the 2,300 level. (그해 5월 취임한 윤석열 정부도 코리아 증시 밸류업을 목표로 주가 부양 의지를 밝혔으나 2024년 12·3 내란 사태가 터지면서 주가는 2300선에서 머물렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stock market atmosphere changed rapidly after the Constitutional Court's impeachment decision against former President Yoon, who instigated the insurrection on April 4 last year, and the situation shifted to an early presidential election. The Lee Jae-myung administration, launched in June, showed strong determination to achieve 'KOSPI 5,000' and implemented active stock market boosting policies such as revising the Commercial Act. Furthermore, starting in the second half of the year, semiconductor demand exploded due to the AI boom, entering a long-term semiconductor boom (super cycle) phase. From its low on April 9 last year (2,293.70), the KOSPI continued its upward trend, reaching 4,000 on October 27 last year, and touching the historic first 5,000 level during trading on the 22nd, just three months later. Thus, the KOSPI, which started at an index of 100 on January 4, 1980, has opened the era of 'KOSPI 5,000' after 46 years. (지난해 4월4일 내란을 일으킨 윤 전 대통령에 대한 헌법재판소의 탄핵 결정이 나오고 조기대선 국면으로 넘어가면서 증시 분위기는 빠르게 바뀌었다. 6월 출범한 이재명 정부가 ‘코스피 5000’ 달성에 강한 의지를 보이며 상법 개정 등 적극적인 증시 부양 정책을 폈고, 하반기부터 인공지능 붐에 따른 반도체 수요가 폭발하기 시작하면서 반도체 장기호황(슈퍼사이클) 국면에 진입했다. 그해 4월9일 저점(2293.70)부터 코스피는 상승 추세를 지속해 지난해 10월27일 4000을 달성했고, 불과 석 달 만인 22일 장중에 사상 첫 5000을 터치했다. 이로써 지난 1980년 1월4일 지수 100에서 시작한 코스피는 46년 만에 ‘코스피 5000’ 시대를 열었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Kyung-mi &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이경미 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kmlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;kmlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241082.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690488830037_20260122501476.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:10:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>520,000 'Seohakgaemi' (Korean retail investors in overseas stocks) filed capital gains tax returns... Earned 28 million won per person on average (양도세 신고한 ‘서학개미’ 52만명…1인당 2800만원 벌었다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241089.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501561.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;뉴욕증권거래소. AFP 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The number of people filing capital gains tax returns on profits from overseas stock investments has exceeded 500,000 for the first time on an annual basis. (해외주식에 투자해 얻은 차익으로 양도소득세를 신고한 이가 연간 기준 처음으로 50만명을 넘어섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to data submitted by the National Tax Service to Park Sung-hoon, a lawmaker of the People Power Party who is a member of the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, the number of people filing capital gains tax returns on overseas stocks for the 2024 tax year was 520,709. This represents a sharp increase of 152.7% compared to the previous year (207,231) and is the first time the figure has surpassed 500,000. The number of filers for overseas stock capital gains tax was 139,909 in 2020, 242,862 in 2021, 100,374 in 2022, and 207,231 in 2023, remaining in the range of 100,000 to 200,000 over the previous four years. (22일 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 박성훈 국민의힘 의원이 국세청에서 제출받은 자료를 보면, 2024년 귀속 해외주식 양도소득세 신고 인원은 52만3709명으로 집계됐다. 전년(20만7231명) 대비 152.7% 폭증하며 사상 처음으로 50만명을 돌파했다. 해외주식 양도소득세 신고자는 2020년 13만9909명, 2021년 24만2862명, 2022년 10만374명, 2023년 20만7231명으로 직전 4년간은 10∼20만명대 수준이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Individuals are required to file a capital gains tax return if the profit from selling overseas stocks exceeds 2.5 million won. A basic deduction of up to 2.5 million won is applied annually, and a 22% tax is levied on the remaining profit after the deduction. (해외주식을 팔아 얻은 양도차익이 250만원이 넘으면 양도소득세 신고 대상이 된다. 매년 250만원까지 기본공제가 적용되고, 공제 후 남은 차익에 22% 세금을 내야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The increase in the number of filers in 2024 is analyzed to be due to the bullish U.S. stock market. In 2024, the U.S. S&amp;P 500 index rose 23.3%, and the Nasdaq index rose 28.6%. During the same period, the KOSPI fell 9.6%, and the KOSDAQ index fell 21.7%. (2024년에 신고 인원이 늘어난 것은 미국 증시 활황에 따른 영향으로 분석된다. 2024년 미국 스탠더드앤드푸어스(S&amp;amp;P)500 지수는 23.3%, 나스닥 지수는 28.6% 상승했다. 같은 기간 코스피는 9.6%, 코스닥 지수는 21.7% 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The total reported capital gains from overseas stocks in 2024 was 144.212 trillion won. This is an increase of 303.1% compared to the previous year (35.772 trillion won). The per capita capital gain, calculated by dividing the total capital gains by the number of filers, was approximately 28 million won. The per capita capital gain decreased from 28 million won in 2021 to 11 million won in 2022. It then increased to 17 million won in 2023 before rising by more than 10 million won in 2024. (2024년 신고된 해외주식 총 양도차익은 14조4212억원이었다. 전년(3조5772억원)보다 303.1% 늘어난 수준이다. 양도차익을 신고자 수로 나눈 1인당 양도차익은 2800만원꼴이었다. 1인당 양도차익은 2021년 2800만원에서 2022년 1100만원으로 줄었다. 2023년 1700만원으로 늘어난 뒤 2024년 1000만원 이상 더 증가한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, it is estimated that investors increased their scale of overseas stock investments despite the high exchange rate. According to the Korea Securities Depository, the custody amount of U.S. stocks, which was around $44.2 billion in 2022, increased to $68.0 billion in 2023 and surged to $112.1 billion in 2024. By the end of last year, it was recorded at an even higher $163.6 billion. (지난해에는 투자자들이 고환율에도 해외주식 투자 규모를 더 늘렸을 것으로 추정된다. 한국예탁결제원에 따르면 2022년 442억달러 수준이던 미국 주식 보관액은 2023년 680억달러로 늘었고, 2024년 1121억달러로 급증했다. 지난해 말에는 이보다 늘어난 1636억달러로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241089.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501561.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:10:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hanyang University Professor Kim Hak-sung Wins the 16th Haedong Young Engineer Award in the Academic Category (한양대 김학성 교수, 제16회 해동젊은공학인상 학술부문 수상)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241105.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/827/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2017690570429784.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한양대학교 공과대학 기계공학부 김학성 교수.한양대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanyang University (President Lee Ki-jeong) announced on the 21st that Professor Kim Hak-sung of the College of Engineering has been selected as the winner of the academic category of the '16th Haedong Young Engineer Award,' organized by the Korean Microelectronics and Packaging Society.&lt;br/&gt;The Haedong Young Engineer Award is a prestigious prize awarded to young engineers who have contributed to the development of engineering technology and achieved outstanding accomplishments, in accordance with the wishes of the late Kim Jeong-sik, founder of Daeduk Electronics and chairman of the Haedong Science and Culture Foundation.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim Hak-sung, selected as this year's winner in the academic category, is a world-renowned researcher who has achieved unparalleled academic accomplishments in the field of advanced semiconductor packaging over the past 20 years. Professor Kim has published over 240 papers and holds more than 230 domestic and international patents, demonstrating overwhelming research achievements. He has played a key role in enhancing the reliability and productivity of semiconductor manufacturing processes.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim's research is highly regarded for not remaining theoretical but driving practical technological advancements through close collaboration with industry. He has successfully developed next-generation packaging processes and high-bandwidth memory (HBM) stacking reliability evaluation technologies through industry-academia collaboration projects with major domestic semiconductor companies such as Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, Hanwha Semiconductor, LG Chem, and Dongjin Semichem.&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kim Hak-sung expressed his gratitude, stating, "I am honored to receive such a meaningful award at a time when semiconductor packaging technology is emerging as a core element of national competitiveness," and added, "I will continue to dedicate myself to research and nurturing the next generation to contribute to solidifying the technological foundation of South Korea's semiconductor industry."&lt;br/&gt;Hanyang University plans to use this award as an opportunity to further strengthen its research capabilities in the semiconductor packaging field and accelerate the development of innovative technologies and talent cultivation to lead the global semiconductor market. (한양대학교(총장 이기정)는 공과대학 김학성 교수가 한국마이크로전자및패키징학회에서 주관하는‘제16회 해동젊은공학인상’ 학술부문 수상자로 선정됐다고, 21일 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;해동젊은공학인상은 대덕전자 창업주인 고(故) 김정식 해동과학문화재단 이사장의 뜻에 따라 공학 기술 발전에 기여하고 탁월한 업적을 세운 젊은 공학인에게 수여하는 권위 있는 상이다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 학술부문 수상자로 선정된 김학성 교수는 지난20여 년간 첨단 반도체 패키징 분야에서 독보적인 학문적 성취를 이룬 세계적 연구자다. 김 교수는 현재까지240여 편의 논문을 발표하고 국내외 특허230건을 보유하는 등 압도적인 연구 성과를 거두었으며, 특히 반도체 생산 공정의 신뢰성과 생산성을 높이는 데 핵심적인 역할을 해왔다.&lt;br/&gt;김 교수의 연구는 이론에 그치지 않고 산업 현장과의 긴밀한 협력을 통해 실질적인 기술 진보를 이끌어냈다는 점에서 높은 평가를 받는다. 그는 삼성전자, SK하이닉스, 한화세미텍, LG화학, 동진쎄미켐 등 국내 주요 반도체 기업들과의 산학협력 과제를 통해 차세대 패키징 공정 및 고대역폭메모리(HBM) 적층 신뢰성 평가 기술 등을 성공적으로 개발해 왔다.&lt;br/&gt;김학성 교수는&amp;quot;반도체 패키징 기술이 국가 경쟁력의 핵심으로 부상한 시기에 이처럼 뜻깊은 상을 받게 되어 영광&amp;quot;이라며&amp;quot;앞으로도 연구와 후학 양성에 매진하여 대한민국 반도체 산업의 기술적 토대를 공고히 하는 데 기여하겠다&amp;quot;고 소감을 전했다.&lt;br/&gt;한양대학교는 이번 수상을 계기로 반도체 패키징 분야의 연구 역량을 더욱 강화하고, 글로벌 반도체 시장을 선도할 혁신 기술 개발과 인재 육성에 박차를 가할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Hanyang University (* 자료제공 :  한양대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241105.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/827/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2017690570429784.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:09:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dyson Launches a 1.79 Million Won 'AI Robot Cleaner'... "Cleans with 60°C Water" (다이슨, 179만원짜리 ‘AI 로봇 청소기’ 내놨다…“60℃ 물청소”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241110.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/450/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502083.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;다이슨의 신형 인공지능(AI) 로봇 청소기 ‘스팟 앤 스크럽’. 권효중 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the green laser light attached to the robot cleaner illuminated the floor, dust and debris became clearly visible. The artificial intelligence (AI) can distinguish not only debris but also the type of liquid stains on the floor to clean efficiently. For example, if sticky juice is spilled, it wipes multiple times, while for water, it wipes once. The UK-based premium home appliance company Dyson announced on the 22nd that it is launching three new products in the Korean market, including its first AI robot cleaner. (로봇 청소기에 달린 초록색 레이저 불빛이 바닥을 비추자 먼지와 이물질이 눈에 확 띄었다. 인공지능(AI)은 이물질은 물론, 바닥에 묻은 액체 얼룩의 종류를 구분해 효율적인 청소를 할 수 있다. 예컨대 끈적한 주스를 흘린 경우에는 여러 번을 닦고, 물이라면 한 번을 닦는 것이다. 영국 고급 가전 기업 다이슨은 한국 시장에 첫 인공지능 로봇 청소기를 포함, 3종의 신제품을 출시한다고 22일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, Dyson opened an experiential pop-up store called 'The Next Home Lab' at The Hyundai Seoul in Yeouido. Visitors can directly experience three products: the AI robot cleaner 'Spot &amp; Scrub,' which was launched in the domestic market on the 12th, the stick-type cleaner 'Clean &amp; Wash High-Gen Water Cleaner,' and the 'Hushjet Compact Air Purifier.' (이날 찾은 서울 여의도 더현대에서 다이슨은 체험형 팝업 스토어 ‘더 넥스트 홈 랩’을 열었다. 지난 12일 국내 시장에 출시된 인공지능 로봇 청소기 ‘스팟 앤 스크럽’과 스틱형 청소기 ‘클린앤워시 하이진 물청소기’, ‘허쉬젯 콤팩트 공기청정기’ 3종의 제품을 직접 체험할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, the domestic robot cleaner market is estimated to be dominated by Chinese products like Roborock and Dreame, with a market share of around 70%. Dyson is targeting the premium niche market with the Spot &amp; Scrub. Priced at 1.79 million won, it is about three times more expensive than Chinese products, but the company emphasizes its technological strength, where AI identifies contamination and stains for efficient cleaning. (현재 국내 로봇 청소기 시장은 로보락, 드리미 등 중국산 점유율이 약 70%에 달하는 것으로 추정된다. 다이슨은 스팟 앤 스크럽으로 프리미엄 틈새시장을 노렸다. 179만원으로 중국 제품보다 3배가량 비싸지만, 인공지능이 오염과 얼룩을 파악해 효율적으로 청소한다는 기술력에 방점을 뒀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nathan Lawson McClain, Senior Design Manager for Home Research, Design, and Development Software at Dyson, personally demonstrated and introduced the product. Manager McClain stated, "The AI automatically analyzes contamination and, based on necessity, makes its own judgment to wipe up to 15 times." (다이슨의 네이슨 로슨 맥클린 홈 연구·설계·개발 소프트웨어 시니어 디자인 매니저는 직접 제품을 사용하며 소개했다. 맥클린 매니저는 “인공지능이 자동으로 오염을 분석하고, 필요에 따라 스스로 판단, 최대 15번까지 닦는다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another feature of the product is its 12 water supply points attached to the roller. During cleaning, as the roller turns, 60°C hot water is dispensed from various points, maintaining a consistently clean state of the water and roller even with repeated floor wiping. The docking station it returns to after cleaning not only charges the device but also dries the roller using hot air. (또한 총 12개의 물 공급 지점이 롤러와 달린 것도 제품의 특징이다. 청소 시 롤러가 굴러갈 때마다 곳곳에서 60℃의 뜨거운 물이 나와, 반복해서 바닥을 닦아도 늘 깨끗한 물과 롤러의 상태를 유지한다. 청소를 마친 후 들어가는 도킹 스테이션’에는 충전과 함께 열풍으로 롤러를 말린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These specialized 'water cleaning' features align with Korean cleaning habits. According to Dyson's 'Global Water Cleaning Research' conducted last year across 28 countries with 23,311 participants, the average cleaning time for Koreans is one hour, with 36% of that time spent on water cleaning. This exceeds the global average of 29%. (이러한 ‘물청소’ 특화 기능은 한국인의 청소 방식과 맞닿아 있다. 다이슨이 지난해 전세계 28개국, 2만3311명을 대상으로 진행한 ‘글로벌 물청소 연구’ 결과에 보면, 한국인의 평균 청소 시간은 1시간이고. 이 중 36%를 물청소에 썼다. 이는 세계 평균 29%를 웃도는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To match this Korean cleaning style, the new stick-type cleaner, the Clean &amp; Wash High-Gen (699,000 won), can perform dust and water cleaning simultaneously. This product uses a wastewater treatment system instead of a filter, automatically separating and sending down dirty water and contaminants used during cleaning. The cleaner head can be laid flat to clean corners, and the product weighs 3.82 kg, making it light enough to clean with one hand. (이와 같은 한국인의 청소 방식에 맞춰 스틱형 청소기 신제품인 클린앤워시 하이진(69만9000원)도 먼지와 물청소를 동시에 할 수 있다. 이 제품은 필터 대신 오수 처리 시스템을 적용해 청소에 사용된 더러운 물과 오염 물질을 아래로 보내 자동으로 분리한다. 청소기 머리 부분이 눕혀져 구석구석 청소를 할 수 있고, 제품 무게도 3.82㎏로 한 손으로 들고 청소하기에 충분하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Dyson also unveiled its first compact air purifier, the Hushjet. Its strength is 'low noise' at 19 dB, which is at the level of a person whispering. Consumers can experience the products at the pop-up event venue until February 1st. (한편, 다이슨은 첫 소형 공기청정기 허쉬젯도 공개했다. 19㏈(데시벨)로 사람이 속삭이는 수준의 ‘저소음’이 강점이다. 소비자들은 오는 2월1일까지 팝업 행사장에서 제품을 체험할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyo-jung &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권효중 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:harry@hani.co.kr"&gt;harry@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/marketing/1241110.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/450/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502083.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:09:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul Apartment Price Increase Widens for Second Consecutive Week... Strong Performance in Gwanak, Dongjak, Yangcheon, and Gangdong Districts (서울 아파트값 오름폭 2주째 확대…관악·동작·양천·강동구 등 강세)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241120.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690615940986_20260122502341.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울 마포구 일대 아파트단지. 김명진 기자 littleprince@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seoul apartment sale prices, which had briefly slowed their upward trend at the beginning of the new year, are once again widening their increase. (새해 초 상승세가 잠시 주춤했던 서울 아파트 매매가격이 다시 오름폭을 키우고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the 'Weekly Apartment Price Trends' released by the Korea Real Estate Board on the 22nd, Seoul apartment sale prices in the third week of January (as of January 19) rose 0.29% compared to the previous week. The fluctuation rate for Seoul apartment sale prices, which was 0.21% in the last week of last year, slowed to 0.18% in the first week of January this year. However, after slightly increasing to 0.21% in the second week, the upward trend continued to widen this week as well. (22일 한국부동산원이 발표한 ‘주간 아파트값 동향’을 보면, 1월 셋째 주(1월19일 기준) 서울 아파트 매매가격은 직전 주 대비 0.29% 올랐다. 지난해 마지막 주 0.21%를 기록했던 서울 아파트 매매가격 변동률은 새해 1월 첫째 주 0.18%로 둔화했으나 둘째 주 0.21%로 소폭 커진 데 이어 이번 주에도 확대 흐름을 이어간 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This week, Dongjak District (0.51%), part of the Han River Belt, recorded the highest increase rate in Seoul, with prices rising mainly in Sangdo and Sadang-dong. Yangcheon District (0.43%) saw price increases mainly for small and medium-sized units in Sinjeong and Mok-dong, while Gangdong District (0.41%) saw increases centered on redevelopment-promoting complexes in Myeongil and Gil-dong. Gwanak District (0.44%) also showed a relatively high increase. (이번 주에는 한강벨트에 속한 동작구(0.51%)가 상도·사당동 위주로 가격이 오르며 서울에서 가장 높은 상승률을 기록했다. 양천구(0.43%)는 신정·목동 중소형 규모 위주로, 강동구(0.41%)는 명일·길동 재건축 추진 단지 중심으로 가격이 올랐으며, 관악구(0.44%)도 비교적 높은 상승 폭을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Real Estate Board explained, "Amid a steady increase in purchase inquiries centered on preferred complexes such as redevelopment-promoting complexes and new/large-scale complexes, the expansion of rising transactions led to an overall increase in Seoul." (부동산원은 “재건축 추진 단지, 신축·대단지 등 선호 단지 중심으로 매수 문의가 꾸준히 증가하는 가운데 상승 거래가 확대되며 서울 전체적으로 상승했다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gyeonggi Province (0.09%→0.13%) also saw its increase widen compared to the previous week. The steep rise in some southern regions newly designated as regulated areas and land transaction permit zones after the October 15 measures drove the overall increase. Suji District, Yongin City (0.68%) increased its rise rate by 0.23 percentage points compared to the previous week, recording the highest increase since the third week of March 2020 (0.85%). Giheung District, Yongin City (0.24%→0.39%), which avoided regulation, also saw a significant expansion in its rise rate. (경기(0.09%→0.13%) 역시 직전 주 대비 상승폭이 확대됐다. 10·15 대책 이후 규제지역과 토지거래허가구역으로 신규 지정된 남부권 일부 지역의 가파른 오름세가 전체 상승을 이끌었다. 용인시 수지구(0.68%)가 직전 주 대비 상승률을 0.23%포인트 키우며 2020년 3월 셋째 주(0.85%) 이후 가장 높은 오름폭을 기록했다. 규제를 피한 용인시 기흥구(0.24%→0.39%)도 상승률이 크게 확대됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bundang District, Seongnam City (0.59%) increased its rise rate by 0.20 percentage points compared to the previous week, with prices rising mainly for small and medium-sized units in Geumgok and Gumi-dong. Dongan District, Anyang City (0.48%) also saw its rise rate increase by 0.15 percentage points compared to the previous week, and Sujeong District, Seongnam City (0.06%→0.46%) showed a notable expansion in its increase. Gwangmyeong City (0.39%) and Hanam City (0.38%) also recorded high rise rates. (성남시 분당구(0.59%)는 금곡·구미동 중소형 규모 위주로 가격이 오르면서 상승률을 직전 주보다 0.20%포인트 키웠다. 안양시 동안구(0.48%)도 전주 대비 상승률이 0.15%포인트 커졌고, 성남시 수정구(0.06%→0.46%)는 오름폭 확대가 두드러졌다. 광명시(0.39%)와 하남시(0.38%) 등도 높은 상승률을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The apartment jeonse (deposit-based lease) market continued its strong sideways trend. In the case of Seoul (0.14%), it showed a weekly rise rate similar to last week while the trend of shortage of listings continued. Seocho District (0.40%) continued its jeonse price rise mainly in Jamwon and Banpo-dong old complexes, while Dongjak District (0.21%), Yangcheon District (0.20%), Gangdong District (0.20%), and Gwangjin District (0.19%) also rose, centered on school districts and large-scale complexes. Gyeonggi Province rose 0.10% and Incheon rose 0.08% each compared to the previous week. (아파트 전세시장은 강보합 장세가 이어졌다. 서울(0.14%)의 경우 지난주와 비슷한 주간 상승률을 보인 가운데 매물 부족 흐름이 지속됐다. 서초구(0.40%)가 잠원·반포동 구축 위주로 전세가격 상승세가 이어지고 있고 동작구(0.21%), 양천구(0.20%), 강동구(0.20%), 광진구(0.19%) 등도 학군지와 대단지 등을 중심으로 상승했다. 경기는 직전 주 대비 0.10%, 인천은 0.08% 각각 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Choi Jong-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최종훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cjhoon@hani.co.kr"&gt;cjhoon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/property/1241120.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690615940986_20260122502341.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:08:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pistachio Prices Pushed Up by Dubai Chewy Cookie Craze... Surge 84% in One Year (두쫀쿠가 밀어올린 피스타치오 몸값…1년 새 84% 급등)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241122.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690619676893_20260122502424.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 경기도 고양 킨텍스에서 열린 2026 카페디저트페어에서 디저트 두바이 쫀득쿠키가 참관인들의 시선을 끌고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The import price of pistachios, which are causing shortages due to the craze for the dessert 'Dubai Chewy Cookie (Dubai Cheon-deuk Cookie or Du-jjeon-ku)', has surged 84% in one year. (디저트 ‘두바이 쫀득쿠키(두쫀쿠)’ 열풍에 품절 현상도 빚는 피스타치오 수입가격이 1년새 84% 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an analysis of Korea Customs Service data by Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Jeong Il-young, a member of the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, the import unit price of pistachios surged 84% in one year as imports of raw materials like pistachios and kadaif (kataifi) skyrocketed due to the Dubai Chewy Cookie craze, which recently spread primarily through social media. The Dubai Chewy Cookie is characterized by a chewy, rice cake-like texture, made with a filling of kadaif (a key ingredient in Dubai chocolate) and pistachio cream, wrapped in marshmallow mixed with cocoa powder. (22일 국회 재정경제위원회 소속 정일영 더불어민주당 의원이 관세청 자료를 분석한 결과를 보면, 최근 에스엔에스(SNS)를 중심으로 확산된 두쫀쿠 열풍으로 피스타치오와 카다이프 등 원재료 수입이 급증하면서 피스타치오 수입 단가가 1년새 84% 급등했다. 두쫀쿠는 두바이 초콜릿의 주재료인 카다이프와 피스타치오 크림으로 속을 만들고, 이를 코코아 가루를 섞은 마시멜로로 감싸 쫀득한 떡과 같은 식감이 특징이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pistachio imports last year reached 2,001 tons (approximately 33 billion won), representing a roughly 2.4-fold increase in volume and a 2.5-fold increase in value compared to 833 tons (approximately 13 billion won) in 2020, five years ago. The Dubai Chewy Cookie craze, which began around the end of last year, was fully reflected in pistachio import volumes. While the average monthly import volume for pistachios in 2025 was about 167 tons, the import volume for December last year alone was about 372 tons, 2.2 times the monthly average. As demand overlapped due to the 'Dubai Chewy Cookie trend', price and supply volatility simultaneously expanded during specific periods. (피스타치오 수입은 지난해 2001t(약 330억원)으로, 5년전인 2020년 833t(약 130억원)보다 수입량이 약 2.4배, 수입액도 2.5배 증가했다. 특히 지난 연말 무렵 시작된 두쫀쿠 열풍은 피스타치오 수입량에 고스란히 반영됐다. 2025년 피스타치오의 월평균 수입량은 약 167t이었지만, 지난해 12월 한 달 수입량은 약 372t으로 월평균의 2.2배에 달했다. ‘두쫀쿠 유행’에 따른 수요가 겹치며, 특정 시기에 가격과 물량 변동성이 동시에 확대된 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, the import unit price of pistachios, which was 15 million won per ton in January last year, rose to about 28 million won per ton in January this year, a surge of 84% in one year. Although import volumes decreased during the same period due to shortages, the cost burden increased significantly instead. The sharp rise in raw material prices could pose a more direct burden on small business owners, small and medium-sized confectionery companies, and individual cafes rather than large corporations. Given the structural difficulty in absorbing rising costs, it is hard to rule out the possibility of price increases for desserts, baked goods, and ice cream. (이에 따라 지난해 1월 t당 1500만원이던 피스타치오 수입단가는 올 1월 약 2800만원으로 1년새 84% 급등했다. 품귀 현상으로 같은 기간 수입량은 줄었지만 원가 부담은 오히려 크게 늘었다. 원재료 가격 급등은 대기업보다 소상공인·중소 제과업체와 개인 카페에 더 직접적인 부담으로 작용할 수 있다. 원가 상승을 흡수하기 어려운 구조상, 디저트·베이커리·아이스크림 가격 인상으로 이어질 가능성도 배제하기 어렵다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Jeong pointed out, "In the case of imported raw materials like pistachios, where demand surges rapidly due to trends, simultaneous price spikes and supply concentration can cause double damage to consumers, small business owners, and the self-employed," adding, "It is important for relevant ministries to closely monitor the situation and swiftly share necessary information to prevent the spread of damage caused by sharp price fluctuations and supply instability." (정 의원은 “피스타치오처럼 유행에 따라 수요가 급격히 몰리는 수입 원재료의 경우 가격 급등과 물량 쏠림이 동시에 발생하면서 소비자와 소상공인·자영업자가 이중으로 피해를 입을 수 있다”며 “급격한 가격 변동과 수급 불안으로 인한 피해가 확산되지 않도록 관계 부처가 상황을 면밀히 점검하고 필요한 정보를 신속히 공유하는 것이 중요하다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241122.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690619676893_20260122502424.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:08:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Forum on 'Shareholder Engagement Activities and Measures to Activate Shareholder Proposals' to be Held on the 30th (‘주주 관여활동 및 주주제한 활성화 방안’ 간담회 30일 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241129.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/755/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502587.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Economic Reform Solidarity (Director: Professor Kim Woo-chan of Korea University) will co-host a forum on 'Shareholder Engagement Activities and Measures to Activate Shareholder Proposals' with Democratic Party of Korea members including Representative Oh Ki-hyung, Chairman of the KOSPI 5000 Committee, Representative Kim Nam-geun, and Representative Lee Kang-il. The forum will be held on the 30th at 2 PM in Conference Room 8 of the National Assembly Members' Office Building in Yeouido, Seoul. (경제개혁연대(소장 김우찬 고려대 교수)는 오는 30일 오후 2시 서울 여의도 국회의원회관 제8간담회의실에서 더불어민주당의 오기형 코스피5000위원장, 김남근 의원, 이강일 의원과 공동으로 ‘주주 관여활동 및 주주제한 활성화 방안’ 간담회를 개최한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This forum plans to share experiences regarding engagement activities and shareholder proposals on various issues involving institutional investors, activist funds, and small shareholder alliances. It will also examine the significance, practical limitations, and institutional challenges of engagement activities. Furthermore, it will discuss improvement measures to activate shareholder engagement and proposals. The forum will be chaired by Professor Kim Woo-chan of Korea University. Panelists include Choi Yong-hwan, Head of the Research Team at NH-Amundi Asset Management; Lee Chang-hwan, CEO of Align Partners; Kim Ji-yeol, Director at Quad Asset Management; Lee Bo-yeol, Representative of the Sam Mok S-Form Small Shareholders Alliance; Lee Sang-mok, Representative of the small shareholder platform Act; and Noh Jong-hwa, Policy Committee Member of the Economic Reform Solidarity. (  이번 간담회에서는 기관투자자, 행동주의펀드, 소액주주연대 등의 다양한 이슈에 관한 관여활동, 주주제안 경험을 공유하고, 관여활동의 의의와 현실적 한계, 제도적 어려움을 짚어볼 계획이다. 또 주주 관여활동 및 주주제안 활성화를 위한 개선방안을 논의한다. 간담회는 김우찬 고려대 교수를 좌장으로 하고, 최용환 엔에이치(NH)아문디자사운용 리서치팀장, 이창환 얼라인파트너스 대표, 김지열 쿼드자산운용 이사, 이보열 삼목에스폼 소액주주연대 대표, 이상목 소액주주 플랫폼 액트 대표, 노종화 경제개혁연대 정책위원이 패널로 참여한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Engagement activities refer to active shareholder actions where institutional investors, small shareholders, etc., actively communicate opinions to companies and demand improvements to protect and enhance medium-to-long-term corporate value and the interests of clients/beneficiaries. They are divided into informal engagement, such as private meetings with management and the board, written inquiries, and requests for additional information, and formal engagement, such as public expression of opinions, speaking at shareholder meetings, exercising voting rights, submitting shareholder proposals, and requesting the convening of shareholder meetings. (  관여활동은 기관투자자, 소액주주 등이 중장기 기업가치와 고객·수익자의 이익을 보호·증진하기 위해 기업에 적극적으로 의견을 전달하고 개선을 요구하는 적극적 주주활동을 뜻한다. 경영진과 이사회와의 비공개 미팅, 서면 질의, 추가 정보 요청 등과 같은 비공식 관여와, 공개적인 의견 표명, 주주총회에서의 발언, 의결권 행사, 주주제안, 주총소집 청구 등의 공식 관여로 구분한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Kwak Jeong-su, Senior Reporter, The Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 곽정수 한겨레경제사회연구원 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241129.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/600/755/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502587.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:08:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kookmin University Techno Design Graduate School's Original Musical 'Mr. Bojangles' to be Performed from January 23rd to 25th (국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원, 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스’ 1월 23~25일 공연)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241141.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/804/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8817690656889717.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;▲사진 국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원 X TapeeTepee, 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스’.국민대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kookmin University (President Seungryeol Jeong) will present the original musical 'Mr. Bojangles,' planned and produced in collaboration with the performing arts organization TapeeTepee by the Department of Convergence Design at the Techno Design Graduate School, from January 23rd (Fri) to 25th (Sun), 2026, at the Staircase Lecture Hall in the Annex of the College of Fine Arts Building at Kookmin University.&lt;br/&gt;This performance is an experimental collaborative project intersecting 'performing arts' and 'design research.' Led by Professor Kim Min and master's/doctoral students from the Department of Convergence Design at Kookmin University's Techno Design Graduate School, who form the core of the planning and execution, it presents a new educational and creative model that combines academic research with creative practice.&lt;br/&gt;'Mr. Bojangles' is a work based on the life story of the legendary American tap dancer and musical actor Bill Robinson. It features an AI-reborn Bill Robinson character along with four actors: tapper Don_K (Kim Seong-hoon), Bee (Kim Joo-hwan), musical actor Hidden (Kim Tae-gyun), and guitarist Hooon (Kim Ji-hoon). The script by Kim Min and Hong Seung-wan and direction by Kim Seong-hoon enhance the work's completeness.&lt;br/&gt;The performance also aims to spread social and cultural value through the collaboration of art and academia. On the final day, January 25th (Sun) at 3 PM, a special performance will be held, inviting children from Seondeokwon, a social welfare childcare facility in Jongno-gu, providing them an opportunity to experience culture and art. This is expected to be a meaningful time to convey dreams and hope to future generations, continuing the legacy of Kookmin University's ongoing social contribution activities such as the College of Fine Arts' 'Fly Design Camp' and the College of Physical Education's 'Happy Sports Camp.'&lt;br/&gt;The performance schedule consists of three shows: January 23rd (Fri) at 7 PM, January 24th (Sat) at 3 PM, and January 25th (Sun) at 3 PM (special performance for Seondeokwon). The venue is the Staircase Lecture Hall in the Annex of the College of Fine Arts Building at Kookmin University. (국민대학교(총장 정승렬) 테크노디자인전문대학원 융합디자인학과에서 공연예술전문기관 TapeeTepee(태피티피)와 협력해 기획·제작한 창작 뮤지컬 ‘미스터 보쟁글스(Mr. Bojangles)’를 2026년 1월 23일(금)부터 25일(일)까지 국민대 조형관 별관 계단강의실에서 선보인다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 공연은 ‘공연예술’과 ‘디자인 연구’가 교차하는 실험적 협업 프로젝트로, 국민대 테크노디자인전문대학원 융합디자인학과 김민 교수와 석·박사과정 학생들이 기획과 실행의 주축이 되어 학문적 연구와 창의적 실천이 결합하는 새로운 교육·창작 모델을 제시한다.&lt;br/&gt;‘미스터 보쟁글스’는 미국의 전설적 탭댄서이자 뮤지컬 배우인 빌 로빈슨(Bill Robinson)의 일대기를 바탕으로 한 작품으로, AI로 재탄생한 빌 로빈슨 캐릭터와 함께 태퍼 Don_K(김성훈), Bee(김주환), 뮤지컬 배우 Hidden(김태균), 기타리스트 Hooon(김지훈) 등 4명의 배우가 출연한다. 극본은 김민·홍승완이, 연출은 김성훈이 맡아 작품의 완성도를 높였다.&lt;br/&gt;공연은 예술과 학문의 협력을 통해 사회적·문화적 가치를 확산하는 데에도 의의를 둔다. 마지막 날인 1월 25일(일) 오후 3시에는 종로구 사회복지 보육시설 선덕원 보육원생을 초청한 특별공연을 진행해 문화예술을 접할 기회를 제공한다. 이는 국민대 조형대학의 ‘날아라 디자인캠프’, 체육대학의 ‘행복한 스포츠캠프’ 등 지속적인 사회공헌 활동의 연장선상에서 미래 세대에 꿈과 희망을 전하는 뜻깊은 시간이 될 것으로 기대된다.&lt;br/&gt;공연 일정은 1월 23일(금) 오후 7시, 24일(토) 오후 3시, 25일(일) 오후 3시(선덕원 초청 특별공연) 총 3회이며, 장소는 국민대 조형관 별관 계단강의실이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kookmin University (* 자료제공 :  국민대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241141.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/648/804/imgdb/original/2026/0122/8817690656889717.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:07:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pledge Fulfilled in Just 7 Months as 'KOSPI 5000' Becomes Reality... Mixed Views on "Still Undervalued" vs. "Overheated" (공약 7달 만에 ‘코스피 5000’ 현실로…“여전히 저평가”-“과열” 엇갈려)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241143.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/447/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502943.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 오전 코스피가 장중 5000을 넘어자 서울 중구 하나은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 기뻐하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The force that drove the KOSPI to record its first-ever intraday high of '5000' (peaking at 5019.54) in the securities market on the 22nd is the semiconductor and robotics industries, which are riding the artificial intelligence (AI) boom and entering a historic memory supercycle. The defense, shipbuilding, and nuclear power sectors, where investment sentiment has heated up on expectations of strong future performance, also joined the rally. Additionally, the Lee Jae-myung administration's proactive push for value-up (corporate value enhancement plan) policies, aimed at breaking the persistent undervaluation of the Korean stock market, is cited as a factor. The KOSPI has surged relentlessly, rising 85.97% (based on the intraday high) from June 2 last year, when the bull market began, to this day. Forecasts suggest the KOSPI could rise further as the effects of the government's policies to encourage the return of 'Seohak Ants' (Korean retail investors in overseas markets) and expand foreign investment in the domestic stock market become visible. (22일 유가증권시장에서 장중에 사상 첫 ‘코스피 5000’(최고 5019.54) 기록을 만들어낸 힘은 인공지능(AI) 붐을 타고 역사적인 메모리 수퍼사이클에 진입한 반도체와 로봇 산업이다. 향후 좋은 실적이 기대되면서 투자 심리가 가열된 방산·조선·원전도 가세했다. 여기에 한국 증시의 고질적 저평가를 타개하겠다는 이재명 정부의 적극적인 밸류업(기업가치제고계획) 정책 추진이 꼽힌다. 코스피는 거침없이 질주하며 ‘불장’에 돌입한 지난해 6월 2일부터 이날까지 85.97%(장중 최고가 기준) 올랐다. 정부의 ‘서학개미’ 유턴과 외국인 국내 증시 투자 확대 정책효과가 가시화되면 코스피가 추가로 상승할 수 있다는 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main drivers behind the historic KOSPI rally were foreign and institutional investors. Foreign investors scooped up shipbuilding and nuclear power stocks, while institutions bought up large-cap semiconductor stocks, pulling the index higher. According to Korea Exchange's Information Data System statistics, the total KOSPI trading volume over the roughly seven-month period from the inauguration day of the Lee Jae-myung administration (June 4 last year), when the historic bull market had just begun, until the 20th of this month, reached 2,339.381 trillion won. The buy-side volume was 817.708 trillion won for foreigners, 463.992 trillion won for institutions, and 1,021.184 trillion won for individuals. (역사적인 코스피 상승을 이끈 주역은 외국인과 기관 투자자였다. 외국인은 조선·원전주를, 기관은 대형 반도체주를 쓸어 담으며 지수를 끌어 올렸다. 한국거래소 정보데이터시스템 집계를 보면 역사적인 ‘불장’이 막 시작된 이재명 정부 출범일(지난해 6월4일) 이후 지난 20일까지 7개월 남짓 기간에 코스피 거래대금은 총 2339조3810억원에 이른다. 매수대금은 외국인 817조7080억원, 기관 463조9920억원, 개인은 1021조1840억원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this period, the net purchase volume of major KOSPI investors reached 11.886 trillion won for foreigners and 12.629 trillion won for institutions. In contrast, individuals were net sellers of approximately 30.381 trillion won worth of stocks during this period. It appears that foreign and institutional investors played an absolutely crucial role in the KOSPI achieving 5000 for the first time in history. Foreign investors were net sellers of 14.456 trillion won in November last year due to concerns about an AI bubble, but switched to a net buying position of 4.148 trillion won in December. They have continued to be net buyers for two consecutive months since then, including this month. Institutions joined the index rally by leading the semiconductor stock surge with large-scale net purchases of Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix in the KOSPI market. (이 기간에 코스피 주요 투자자의 순매수 거래대금은 외국인 11조8860억원, 기관 12조6290억원에 이른다. 반면 개인은 이 기간에 30조3810억원어치를 순매도했다. 코스피가 사상 처음 5000을 달성하게 된 데는 외국인과 기관의 힘이 절대적으로 작용한 셈이다. 외국인은 지난해 11월 인공지능(AI) 거품 우려 등에 14조4560억원 순매도했으나 12월 들어 4조1480억원 매수 우위로 돌아섰다. 이후 이달까지 두 달 연속 ‘사자’를 이어가고 있다. 기관은 코스피 시장에서 삼성전자와 에스케이(SK)하이닉스를 대거 순매수하며 반도체주 상승세를 주도하며 지수 상승에 가세했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is analyzed that they bought semiconductor stocks in bulk on expectations that memory prices will continue to rise due to increasing global AI demand. As institutions pushed up semiconductor stock prices and foreign investors lifted nuclear power and shipbuilding stocks, warmth is spreading across the large-cap sector. Kim Jae-seung, a researcher at Hyundai Motor Securities, assessed, "Until December, the KOSPI saw a large concentration in semiconductors, but since January, the strength has expanded to surrounding industries. With a favorable funding environment including foreign net buying, the entire KOSPI market is in an upward-trending environment." However, individuals viewed the KOSPI's rise as a profit-taking opportunity and sold heavily. (글로벌 인공지능 수요 증가로 메모리 가격 상승세가 지속될 거라는 기대감에 반도체주를 대거 쓸어 담은 것으로 분석된다. 기관이 반도체주 주가를 밀고, 외국인은 원전·조선주를 끌어 올리면서 대형주 전반으로 온기가 번지는 모습이다. 김재승 현대차증권 연구원은 “코스피는 12월까지는 반도체 쏠림이 커졌지만 1월 들어 주변 업종으로 강세가 확장되고 있다. 외국인 순매수 등 우호적인 자금 환경에 코스피 시장 전체가 우상향하는 환경”이라고 평가했다. 다만 개인은 코스피 상승세를 오히려 차익 실현 기회로 여기고 대거 파는 모습을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government value-up policies such as strengthened shareholder returns, and institutional reforms like the effective tax cut from the separate taxation of dividend income, also seem to have contributed to 'KOSPI 5000'. As it became known that 'Seohak Ants' were shunning the Korean stock market due to low dividends and high taxes, the Lee Jae-myung administration has taken groundbreaking measures in several stages to change this perception. Recently, to encourage investment funds that had flowed out to foreign stock markets, including the US, to return to the domestic market, the government newly created a 'Return to the Domestic Market Account' (RIA), which exempts capital gains tax on foreign stocks if the funds from selling those stocks are converted to Korean won and invested domestically. (주주환원 강화 등 정부 밸류업 정책과 배당소득 분리과세에 따른 실질적 세금 인하 등 제도 개편도 ‘코스피 5000’에 한몫한 것으로 보인다. 서학개미들이 배당금이 적고 세금이 높다며 한국 증시를 외면한 것으로 알려지자 이재명 정부에서 이런 인식을 바꾸는 획기적인 조치를 여러 차례에 걸쳐 내놓았다. 최근에는 미국을 비롯한 외국 증시로 빠져나간 서학개미 투자금이 국내 증시로 돌아오도록 해외주식을 매도한 자금을 원화로 환전해 국내에 투자하면 해외주식 양도소득을 비과세해주는 ‘국내시장 복귀 계좌’(RIA)를 새로 만들었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the securities industry, there is anticipation that individual investors may flow in going forward, as the government is currently promoting policies to induce the return of 'Seohak Ants' to the domestic stock market. Yeom Dong-chan, a researcher at Korea Investment &amp; Securities, predicted, "As of the end of last year, Korea's overseas stock assets were 256 trillion won. Applying the case of Indonesia, which implemented a similar policy in the past, we can expect about 12.4%, or 31.7 trillion won, to be repatriated to Korea," adding, "The Return to the Domestic Market Account policy will be favorable for exchange rate stability and the domestic capital market." (증권가에서는 최근 정부가 ‘서학개미’의 국내 증시 복귀를 유도하기 위한 정책을 추진 중인 만큼 향후 개인 투자자들이 유입될 수 있다는 기대감이 나온다. 염동찬 한국투자증권 연구원은 “지난해 말 기준 한국의 해외 주식 자산은 256조원인데 과거 유사한 정책을 실시한 인도네시아 사례를 적용한다면 12.4%인 31조7천억원이 국내로 환입될 것으로 기대할 수 있다”며 “국내시장 복귀계좌 정책은 환율 안정과 국내 자본시장에 우호적일 것”이라고 내다봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although President Lee Jae-myung's pledge of a 'KOSPI 5000 era' has materialized in just over seven months, assessments follow that the domestic stock market is still undervalued compared to global markets. This is because earnings forecasts for domestic large-caps, centered on semiconductors, are being revised upward at a fearsome pace. The consensus for this year's consolidated operating profit for the 28 stocks in the KOSPI Electrical &amp; Electronics sector, which includes Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix, has skyrocketed 141% from 94.6648 trillion won six months ago (July 22 last year) to a recent 228.1435 trillion won. In other words, the market interprets that while the KOSPI index has risen 85.97% compared to seven months ago, the valuation burden is not yet heavy. According to the Korea Exchange Information Data System, the KOSPI's price-to-earnings ratio (PER) as of the previous day was 20.52x. This is a 53.2% increase from June 2 last year (13.39x), but is much lower than the KOSPI's rise of 81.9% over the same period. During this period, the price-to-book ratio (PBR) of KOSPI-listed companies also soared vertically from 0.92x to 1.58x. However, compared to the PER (31.05x) and PBR (5.51x) of stocks included in the US S&amp;P 500, the prevailing view in the securities industry is that it is still significantly undervalued by global standards. (이재명 대통령의 ‘코스피 5000 시대’ 공약이 불과 7개월 남짓 만에 현실화했지만, 국내증시는 글로벌 대비 여전히 저평가됐다는 진단도 이어진다. 반도체를 중심으로 국내 대형주의 실적 전망이 무서운 속도로 상향되고 있기 때문이다. 삼성전자·에스케이하이닉스 등이 속한 코스피 전기·전자 업종 28개 종목의 올해 연결 영업이익 컨센서스는 6개월 전(지난해 7월22일) 94조6648억원에서 최근 228조1435억원으로 141% 급등했다. 즉 시장에서는 코스피 지수가 7개월 전 대비 85.97% 올랐지만 밸류에이션(평가가치) 부담은 아직 크지 않은 것으로 해석한다. 한국거래소 정보데이터시스템에 따르면 전날까지 코스피의 주가수익비율(PER)은 20.52배를 나타내고 있다. 지난해 6월2일(13.39배)보다 53.2% 증가했으나, 같은 기간 코스피 상승률(81.9%)보다는 훨씬 낮은 수준이다. 이 기간에 코스피 상장사들의 주가순자산비율(PBR)도 0.92배에서 1.58배로 수직상승했다. 하지만 미국 스탠더드앤드푸어스(S&amp;amp;P)500 편입종목의 주가수익비율(31.05배) 및 주가순자산비율(5.51배)에 견주면 글로벌 기준으로는 여전히 한참 저평가된 편이라는 게 증권가의 대체적인 시각이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, advice has also emerged that, in the short term, the KOSPI has entered a phase where speed adjustment should be considered. It is pointed out that the earnings-driven rally led by semiconductors is excessive, and since the beginning of this year, the domestic stock market's rise has been so steep that technical overheating burdens have accumulated. Based on the 9th of this month, when the KOSPI index was approaching the 4600 level, it was calculated that excluding Samsung Electronics and SK Hynix, the index would have remained only around the 3400 level. Kiwoom Securities noted, "Various indicators point to the KOSPI currently being in a technical overheating phase. To continue the additional rally, it is necessary to alleviate the current overheating burden to some extent." (그러나 단기적으로 코스피 속도 조절을 염두에 두어야 할 구간에 진입했다는 조언도 나온다. 반도체가 주도하는 실적 독주가 지나친 데다 올해 들어 국내 증시 상승 속도가 워낙 가팔라 기술적으로 과열 부담이 누적돼 있다는 지적이다. 코스피 지수는 4600선에 육박했던 지난 9일 당시 기준으로 보면 삼성전자·에스케이하이닉스를 제외할 경우 3400선에 그쳤던 것으로 집계됐다. 키움증권은 “여러 지표는 코스피가 현재 기술적 과열 국면에 들어가 있음을 가리킨다. 추가적인 랠리를 이어가려면 현재의 과열 부담을 어느 정도 해소할 필요가 있다“고 짚었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241143.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/740/447/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502943.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:06:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Muan Airport Officials, Having Received Requests to Fix 'Concrete Embankment', Say "We Don't Remember" (무안공항 책임자들, ‘콘크리트 둔덕’ 보완요구 받아놓고 “기억 안 난다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241147.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690670116759_20260122503061.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 국회에서 열린 12.29 여객기 참사 진상규명을 위한 국정조사특별위원회 회의에서 유가족 협의회 회원들이 지켜보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers from both ruling and opposition parties summoned and jointly criticized officials regarding the concrete embankment at Jeonnam's Muan International Airport, which exacerbated the December 29 Jeju Air passenger plane disaster. It was also pointed out that although police investigations have been ongoing for over a year, not a single case of referral or indictment of those responsible has yet been made. (12·29 제주항공 여객기 참사를 키운 전남 무안국제공항 콘크리트 둔덕을 놓고 여야가 관계자들을 불러 한목소리로 질타했다. 경찰 수사가 1년 넘게 이어지고 있지만, 책임자에 대한 송치나 기소가 아직 한 건도 이뤄지지 않았다는 점도 도마에 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly's Special Committee for the State Investigation into the Truth of the December 29 Passenger Plane Disaster held a hearing at the National Assembly on the 22nd, grilling the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, the Aviation and Railway Accident Investigation Board (ARAIB), the police, and related companies, focusing on why there was a concrete embankment at Muan Airport. At the time of the accident, there was a concrete embankment near the Muan Airport runway to support a localizer facility. According to an ARAIB research service report, it is estimated that all 179 victims would have survived had the embankment not been there. (국회 12·29 여객기 참사 진상규명 국정조사특별위원회(특위)는 22일 국회에서 국토교통부와 항공철도사고조사위원회(조사위), 경찰과 관련업체를 상대로 청문회를 열고 무안공항에 콘크리트 둔덕이 있었던 이유를 집중적으로 따져물었다. 사고 당시 무안공항 활주로 인근에는 방위각시설(로컬라이저)을 지지하기 위해 콘크리트 둔덕이 있었는데, 사조위 연구용역 보고서에 따르면 둔덕이 없었을 경우 179명의 희생자 전원이 생존했을 것으로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the hearing, officials from the Seoul Regional Aviation Office, which was the ordering agency during the construction of Muan Airport, repeatedly offered only the explanation that they "did not remember" when pressed about responsibility for the embankment issue. Former Director Lee Seok-am, who was the head of the Seoul Aviation Office in 2004, responded to the question, 'At the time, the Korea Airports Corporation requested a fix for the Muan Airport concrete embankment due to non-compliance with standards; what was the reason for not accepting it?' by saying, "I don't recall any issues being raised regarding the localizer. I never heard about it once during my one-year tenure." Former Director Jang Jong-sik, who received a request to fix the concrete embankment in 2007, also said regarding the embankment, "I don't recall it being a matter of discussion." (이날 무안공항 건설 당시 발주처였던 서울지방항공청 관계자들은 둔덕 문제에 대해 책임을 추궁하자 “기억이 없다”는 해명만을 반복했다. 2004년 서울항공청장이었던 이석암 전 청장은 ‘당시 한국공항공사가 무안공항 콘크리트 둔덕에 대해 기준 부적합으로 보완요청을 했는데 불수용한 이유가 무엇이냐’는 질문에 “로컬라이저에 관한 문제가 제기된 기억이 없다. 제가 재직하는 1년 동안 한 번도 얘기를 들은 적이 없다”고 말했다. 2007년 콘크리트 둔덕 보완을 요구받았던 장종식 전 청장도 둔덕에 대해 “논의한 사항은 없는 것으로 기억한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticism of the police's 'slow investigation' also continued. Democratic Party lawmaker Lee Kwang-hee pointed out to the police, who said 'investigation results from the ARAIB are needed regarding engine defects and aircraft defects,' that "judicial investigations and accident investigations should proceed independently of each other, and one should not be delayed due to the other according to international standards," and "even though ARAIB accident investigation results are not data for determining criminal responsibility, using them as a premise does not conform to international standards." Lawmaker Lee Yeon-hee of the same party criticized, "Even a special prosecutor's investigation period is 90 days. Who would understand that the police haven't even produced results after a year has passed?" People Power Party lawmaker Seo Cheon-ho, a former police officer, also said, "The most crucial points are why the embankment was installed, why it was made of concrete, and why it was left unattended," adding, "However, those key aspects are largely missing from the (investigation of) main figures." (경찰의 ‘늑장 수사’에 대한 비판도 이어졌다. 이광희 민주당 의원은 ‘엔진 결함, 기체 결함 관련해서는 사조위 조사 결과가 필요하다’는 경찰 쪽에 “사법조사와 사고조사는 상호 독립적으로 진행돼야 하고 어느 한쪽에 다른 한쪽을 이유로 지연해선 안 된다는 게 국제 기준”이라며 “사조위 사고조사 결과는 형사 책임 판단을 위한 자료가 아님에도 이를 전제로 삼는 건 국제기준에 부합하지 않는다”고 지적했다. 같은 당 이연희 의원은 “특검도 수사기간이 90일이다. 그런데 경찰이 1년이 지나도록 결과조차 못 내는 걸 누가 납득하겠나”라고 비판했다. 경찰 출신인 서천호 국민의힘 의원도 “가장 핵심적인 내용은 둔덕이 왜 설치됐고 왜 콘크리트로 설치됐으며 방치됐냐는 것”이라며 “그런데 (수사) 주요인물 안에 그 부분이 대폭 빠져있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of Land, Infrastructure and Transport Kim Yun-deok, who attended the hearing, said, "I think it is a wrongful incident to the point where, as the Minister, I have nothing to say about the fact that regulations (related to the embankment) could have been improved several times but were not properly addressed," and added, "I sincerely apologize to the bereaved families, and I will do my utmost to examine regulations not only regarding the embankment issue but across all aviation facility safety and establish measures so that things can proceed properly." (이날 청문회에 나온 김윤덕 국토부 장관은 “여러 차례에 걸쳐서 (둔덕 관련) 규정을 개선할 수 있었음에도 제대로 되지 못한 점에 대해 장관으로서 할말이 없을 정도로 잘못된 일이라고 생각한다”며 “유가족께 진심으로 사과드리고, 둔덕 문제 뿐 아니라 항공시설 안전 전반에 걸쳐서 규정 등을 살펴보고 대책을 세워서 제대로 진행될 수 있도록 최선의 노력을 다하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Min-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신민정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shin@hani.co.kr"&gt;shin@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241147.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690670116759_20260122503061.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:06:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>5,000 Points Ridden on Debt... Warning Bells Sound Over 'KRW 29 Trillion in Credit Transactions' (빚으로 올라탄 오천피…‘신용거래 29조’ 과열 경고음)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241156.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/488/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503211.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;코스피 지수가 장중 사상 처음으로 5019.54를 기록한 22일 서울 중구 우리은행 본점 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 코스피 지수 5000선 돌파를 축하하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI enters the '5,000-point' era, the scale of individual investors' 'debt-fueled investing' (investing using borrowed money) has surpassed KRW 29 trillion, hitting a record high. This is interpreted as a result of increased chase buying driven by anxiety over potentially missing out on the upward trend. (코스피가 ‘오천피’(코스피 5000) 시대를 맞은 가운데 개인투자자들의 ‘빚투’(빚내서 투자) 규모가 29조원을 넘어 사상 최대치를 기록했다. 상승 흐름에서 소외될 수 있다는 불안 심리에 추격 매수가 늘어난 결과로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Korea Financial Investment Association on the 22nd, the outstanding balance of credit transaction loans stood at KRW 29.0821 trillion as of the 21st. This increased further in just one day after it first exceeded KRW 29 trillion, recording KRW 29.0586 trillion the previous day. The outstanding balance of credit transaction loans represents the amount investors have not yet repaid after borrowing funds from securities firms to buy stocks, serving as a key indicator to gauge the scale of individual investors' debt-fueled investing. (22일 금융투자협회에 따르면, 지난 21일 기준 신용거래융자 잔고는 29조821억원으로 집계됐다. 전날 29조586억원을 기록하며 사상 처음으로 29조원을 넘어선 데 이어 하루 만에 더 늘어났다. 신용거래융자 잔고는 투자자가 증권사에서 자금을 빌려 주식을 매수한 뒤 아직 상환하지 않은 금액으로, 개인투자자의 빚투 규모를 가늠할 수 있는 대표 지표다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just six months ago, in August of last year, the outstanding balance of credit transaction loans was around KRW 21 trillion. However, it has steadily increased amid the stock market boom. It recorded KRW 24.8 trillion on October 27 last year, when the KOSPI first surpassed 4,000 points historically, and first exceeded KRW 27 trillion on December 5. Subsequently, it broke through KRW 28 trillion on the 8th of this month, just over a month later, and then surpassed KRW 29 trillion in just over 10 days. As expectations grew for the KOSPI to break through 5,000 points, individual investors actively jumped into investing by taking on debt. (6개월 전인 지난해 8월만 해도 신용거래융자 잔고는 21조원대 수준이었지만, 증시 호황 속에 꾸준히 불어났다. 코스피가 사상 처음 4000을 돌파한 지난해 10월27일 24조8천억원을 기록했고, 12월5일에는 처음 27조원을 넘어섰다. 이후 1개월여 만인 이달 8일 28조원을 돌파한 데 이어, 불과 10여일 만에 29조원을 넘긴 것이다. 코스피 5000 돌파에 대한 기대감이 커지면서 개인투자자들의 빚을 내어 적극적으로 투자에 뛰어든 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, debt-fueled investing has been concentrated in large-cap stocks that led the KOSPI's rise. As of the 20th of this month, SK Hynix and Samsung Electronics saw their credit balances increase by KRW 325.1 billion and KRW 138.6 billion, respectively, compared to the previous month, showing the highest growth rates. The total credit balance stands at approximately KRW 1.8584 trillion for Samsung Electronics and KRW 1.3069 trillion for SK Hynix. Hyundai Motor, which recently showed strong performance and rose to third place in market capitalization, also saw its credit balance increase to KRW 407.9 billion, growing by KRW 124 billion just this month. (특히 코스피 상승을 이끈 대형주에 빚투가 집중됐다. 이달 20일까지 에스케이하이닉스와 삼성전자의 신용잔고는 전월에 견줘 각각 3251억원, 1386억원 순증하며 가장 높은 증가세를 보였다. 전체 신용잔액 규모는 삼성전자가 1조8584억원, 에스케이하이닉스가 1조3069억원 수준이다. 최근 강세를 보이며 시가총액 3위로 올라선 현대차도 신용잔고가 4079억원으로, 이달 들어서만 1240억원 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, voices of concern are growing. This is because credit buying can lead to forced liquidation if stock prices fall beyond a certain level. Particularly in a situation where the index has surged sharply in a short period, if the KOSPI enters a correction phase, a large volume of forced liquidation could pour out all at once, potentially widening the decline and amplifying investor losses. (이에 따라 우려의 목소리도 커지고 있다. 신용매수는 주가가 일정 수준 이상 하락하면 반대매매(강제 청산)로 이어질 수 있기 때문이다. 특히 단기간에 지수가 급등한 상황이어서, 코스피가 조정 국면에 접어들 경우 대규모 반대매매 물량이 한꺼번에 쏟아지며 하락 폭을 키우고 투자자 손실을 확대시키는 리스크로 작용할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Lee Hyo-seop of the Capital Market Institute stated, "In a situation where the scale of credit transactions has become excessively large, if stock prices plummet sharply, credit volumes could be liquidated all at once through forced selling, triggering additional stock price declines." He added, "Even if stock prices do not rise again in the short term or move sideways, high interest burdens could occur, significantly expanding investor losses." (이효섭 자본시장연구원 박사는 “신용거래 규모가 과도하게 커진 상황에서 주가가 급락할 경우, 신용 물량이 반대매매로 한꺼번에 청산되면서 추가적인 주가 하락을 불러올 수 있다”며 “주가가 단기간에 다시 오르지 않거나 횡보할 경우에도 높은 이자 부담이 발생해 투자자 손실이 크게 확대될 수 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ahn Tae-ho &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (안태호 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:eco@hani.co.kr"&gt;eco@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241156.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/488/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503211.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:05:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>While the KOSPI is in a Bull Market, the Real Economy is Chilly... 'K-Shaped Growth' Deepens (‘코스피 불장’인데 실물 경제는 찬바람…‘K자형 성장’ 심화)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241161.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503276.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 아래에 5000 돌파 당시 사용했던 꽃종이가 떨어져 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean economy shrank in the fourth quarter of last year, barely achieving an annual growth rate of '1%'. While the KOSPI broke through 5,000 during trading and asset markets are experiencing a historic rally, the real economy actually posted its most sluggish performance in five years since the COVID-19 pandemic. Although growth at the potential rate level is expected this year, the shadow of 'K-shaped growth'—characterized by slow domestic demand recovery and increasing dependence on semiconductors and exports—is projected to deepen. (우리나라 경제가 지난해 4분기 역성장하며 연간 ‘1% 성장률’에 턱걸이했다. 코스피가 장중 5000을 돌파하며 자산 시장이 역사적 랠리를 펼치고 있지만, 정작 실물 경제는 코로나 팬데믹 이후 5년 만에 가장 저조한 성적을 낸 것이다. 올해는 잠재성장률 수준이 예상되지만 내수 회복세는 더디고 반도체와 수출 의존도는 높아지는 ‘케이(K)자 성장’의 그림자는 짙어질 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Bank of Korea announced on the 22nd that the real GDP growth rate for the fourth quarter of last year (quarter-on-quarter, preliminary) was -0.3%. The quarterly growth rate contracted in the first quarter of last year, rebounded in the second quarter (0.7%), rose sharply in the third quarter (1.3%), and then contracted again in the fourth quarter. The fourth-quarter growth rate is 0.5 percentage points lower than the BOK's forecast (0.2%). It is the lowest level in three years since the fourth quarter of 2022 (-0.4%). (  한국은행은 지난해 4분기 실질 국내총생산(GDP) 성장률(전분기 대비·속보치)이 -0.3%로 집계됐다고 22일 밝혔다. 분기 성장률은 작년 1분기 역성장했다가 2분기 반등(0.7%)해 3분기에는 큰 폭 상승(1.3%)했는데 4분기 다시 역성장했다. 4분기 성장률은 한은 예상(0.2%)보다 0.5%포인트나 낮은 것이다. 2022년 4분기(-0.4%) 이후 3년 만에 최저치다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The annual growth rate for last year barely reached 1.0%. It narrowly hit 1% through rounding to two decimal places (0.97%). The government and the BOK explained the reason for the fourth-quarter contraction as "base effects from the high growth in the third quarter and the impact of the construction investment slump." They explained that a technical adjustment appeared due to base effects from the largest quarterly growth in 15 quarters in the third quarter of last year (1.3%, annualized 5.4%). For the entire second half of last year (0.5%), it is said to be at the potential growth rate level (0.4~0.5%). (  작년 한 해 연간 성장률은 1.0%에 턱걸이했다. 소수점 둘째자리 반올림(0.97%)으로 가까스로 1%를 맞췄다. 정부와 한은은 4분기 역성장 이유를 “3분기 높은 성장률에 따른 기저효과와 건설투자 침체 영향”이라고 밝혔다. 지난해 3분기 15분기 만에 최대 폭 성장(1.3%, 연환산 5.4%)한 기저효과로 기술적 조정이 나타났다는 설명이다. 작년 하반기 전체(0.5%)로는 잠재성장률 수준(0.4~0.5%)이라는 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They also offered the assessment that it wasn't that bad if construction investment was excluded. Construction investment decreased by nearly 10% last year, dragging down the annual growth rate by 1.4 percentage points. Excluding construction investment, the annual growth rate is calculated to reach 2.4%. Construction investment has declined for nine consecutive quarters due to factors such as rising raw material prices. (건설투자를 빼면 그리 나쁘지 않았다는 평가도 내놨다. 건설투자는 지난해 10% 가까이 감소해 연간 성장률을 1.4%포인트나 끌어내렸다. 건설투자를 제외하면 연간 성장률이 2.4%에 이른다는 계산이 나온다. 건설투자는 원자재 가격 상승 등의 영향으로 9분기 연속 감소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering the recovery trend in private consumption and the increase in exports since the second half of last year, the growth rate this year is expected to be higher than last year. The BOK forecasts 1.8%, and the government forecasts 2.0%. These are figures set higher than the initial forecasts. The BOK predicted, "This year's government budget has increased by 3.5% compared to last year, so the contribution of government expenditure to growth will be higher than last year (0.5 percentage points), and the constraint on growth from construction investment will decrease significantly." (  지난해 하반기 이후 민간소비 회복세와 수출 증가세를 감안할 때 올해 성장률은 작년보다 높아질 전망이다. 한은은 1.8%, 정부는 2.0%를 예상한다. 애초 전망치보다 높여 잡은 수치다. 한은은 “올해 정부 예산이 작년보다 3.5% 늘어 정부 지출의 성장 기여도가 작년(0.5%포인트) 보다 높아지고 건설투자의 성장률 제약은 상당 폭 줄어들 것”이라고 전망했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BOK estimates Korea's potential growth rate to be 'below 2%' (1.8~2.0%). The growth rate forecasts for this year and next (1.8%, 1.9%) are projected to remain at the potential growth rate level. They also fall significantly short of the global economic growth forecasts for this year and next (2.9%, 3.1%). This is why concerns are arising that the Korean economy may have fallen into a long-term low-growth trend. (한은은 우리나라 잠재성장률이 ‘2%를 밑도는 수준’(1.8~2.0%)이라고 추산한다. 올해와 내년 성장률 전망(1.8%, 1.9%)은 잠재성장률 수준에 머물 것이란 전망이다. 올해와 내년 세계경제 성장률 전망(2.9%, 3.1%)에도 크게 미치지 못한다. 우리 경제가 장기 저성장 기조에 빠져든 게 아니냐는 우려가 나오는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Particularly concerning is the 'quality of growth'. What drove growth last year was semiconductors. The contribution of semiconductor exports to last year's growth rate (1%) is estimated at 0.9 percentage points. This means the increase in value-added in the semiconductor sector accounted for 90% of the entire economic growth. This year as well, semiconductors remain the variable affecting the rise and fall of the growth rate. The BOK anticipated "expansion of semiconductor factory facilities and increased investment related to artificial intelligence." (  특히 우려되는 것은 ‘성장의 질’이다. 지난해 성장을 이끈 건 반도체였다. 지난해 성장률(1%)에서 반도체 수출 기여도는 0.9%포인트로 추산된다. 반도체 부문의 부가가치 증가가 전체 경제 성장의 90%를 차지한 셈이다. 올해도 성장률 등락의 변수는 여전히 반도체다. 한은은 “반도체 공장 증설과 인공지능 관련 투자 확대”를 예상했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the semiconductor super cycle, the greater the numerical improvement, the more inevitable the concentration phenomenon becomes. As of the end of last year, semiconductors and automobiles accounted for over 30% of exports, with semiconductors alone responsible for a quarter of total exports. On the other hand, the construction industry, which has a significant impact on domestic demand such as employment and consumption, and traditional manufacturing sectors like petrochemicals, steel, and machinery, are struggling to find a turning point. According to BOK estimates, excluding the information technology (IT) sector, this year's growth forecast (1.8%) drops to 1.4%. BOK Governor Lee Chang-yong recently warned, "The recovery gap between sectors is large, so there will be a significant discrepancy with the perceived economic conditions," and "A K-shaped recovery can hardly be seen as sustainable and complete." (  반도체 슈퍼 사이클 덕분에 수치상 개선 폭이 커질수록 쏠림 현상은 더 심해질 수 밖에 없다. 지난해 말 기준 반도체와 자동차가 차지하는 수출 비중은 30%를 넘어섰고, 반도체가 전체 수출의 4분의 1을 담당했다. 반면, 고용과 소비 등 내수 영향이 큰 건설업과 석유화학·철강·기계 등 전통 제조업은 좀처럼 반전의 계기를 찾지 못하고 있다. 한은 추산을 보면, 정보기술(IT) 부문을 제외하면 올해 성장률 전망(1.8%)은 1.4%로 떨어진다. 이창용 한은 총재는 최근 “부문간 회복 격차가 커 체감 경기와는 괴리가 클 것”이라며 “케이자형 회복은 결코 지속 가능하고 완전한 회복으로 보기 어렵다”고 경고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hoe-seung &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  김회승 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:honesty@hani.co.kr"&gt;honesty@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241161.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/900/600/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503276.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:05:16 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>