<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:11:17 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>"Insufficient Document Submission" "Mafia-Style Retaliatory Politics"... The Stalemate and Blame Game Over 'Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing' (“자료제출 미비” “조폭식 보복정치”…‘이혜훈 청문회’ 무산 공방)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240569.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Insufficient Document Submission" "Mafia-Style Retaliatory Politics"... The Stalemate and Blame Game Over 'Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing' (“자료제출 미비” “조폭식 보복정치”…‘이혜훈 청문회’ 무산 공방)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/428/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503408.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 19일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열릴 예정인 인사청문회를 앞두고 대기하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, did not take place on the 19th as scheduled. This is because the People Power Party, which holds the authority to place the hearing on the agenda, refused to do so. The ruling and opposition parties have entered discussions regarding the future hearing schedule but are facing difficulties in reaching an agreement. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회가 예정됐던 19일 열리지 못했다. 청문회 안건 상정 권한을 가진 국민의힘 쪽이 상정을 거부했기 때문이다. 여야는 향후 청문회 일정에 대한 논의에 나섰지만 협의에 난항을 겪고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Eui-ja, a member of the People Power Party and chairperson of the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, convened a plenary meeting around 10 a.m. that day and stated, "No agreement has been reached between the floor leaders of the two parties. As the committee chairperson, I cannot place the agenda item related to (nominee Lee's) hearing." This follows Chairperson Im's announcement on the 16th of her intent to refuse to hold the hearing, citing the nominee's 'insufficient document submission,' which she acted upon by refusing to place the hearing on the agenda. The Democratic Party of Korea, which had considered holding a unilateral hearing, had to watch as the hearing was canceled without even being placed on the agenda. Nominee Lee, who had stayed at the National Assembly since morning to attend the hearing, waited in another space without even being able to enter the meeting room. (국민의힘 소속 임이자 국회 재정경제기획위원회(재경위) 위원장은 이날 오전 10시께 전체회의를 개의하면서 “양당 간사 간 협의가 이루어지지 않았다. 위원장으로서 (이 후보자) 청문회 관련 안건을 상정할 수 없다”고 밝혔다. 지난 16일 이 후보자의 ‘자료 제출 미비’를 이유로 청문회 개최 거부 의사를 밝힌 임 위원장이 이날 실제로 청문회 안건 상정을 거부한 것이다. 단독 청문회 개최를 검토했던 더불어민주당은 이날 청문회 안건이 상정조차 되지 않으면서 청문회가 무산되는 걸 지켜봐야 했다. 청문회 참석을 위해 아침부터 국회에 머물던 이 후보자는 회의장에 가 보지도 못한 채 다른 공간에서 대기했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Strategy and Finance Committee that day, a dispute between the ruling and opposition parties continued for about an hour and a half but adjourned without a conclusion. The opposition party's floor leader, People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, argued, "We requested 2,187 documents (from nominee Lee's side), but only 15% were submitted. This is a very low figure even compared to other confirmation hearings," claiming that the hearing cannot be held until the nominee's side sufficiently submits documents. In contrast, the ruling party's floor leader, Democratic Party lawmaker Jeong Tae-ho, countered, "We can start the hearing first and directly request any additional necessary documents from the nominee," and added, "Not even allowing the nominee to sit (at the hearing) and talking about adjusting the schedule can only be seen as a lack of will to hold a normal hearing." (이날 재경위에서 여야 간 공방이 한시간 반가량 이어졌지만 결론 없이 정회했다. 야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원은 “(이 후보자 쪽에) 자료를 2187건 요청했는데 15%만 제출했다. 다른 인사청문회와 비교해도 매우 낮은 수치”라며 이 후보자 쪽이 충분히 자료를 제출하기 전에는 청문회를 열 수 없다고 주장했다. 반면 여당 간사인 정태호 민주당 의원은 “일단 청문회를 시작하고 더 필요한 자료는 후보에게 직접 요구할 수 있다”며 “후보조차도 (청문회에) 앉히지 않고 일정 조정을 거론하는 건, 정상적으로 청문회를 할 의지가 없는 것으로 볼 수밖에 없다”고 반박했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties shifted the blame for the hearing's cancellation onto each other. People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok claimed that day, "Nominee Lee is breaking promises and completely boycotting the document submission requested by the National Assembly. On the contrary, she is threatening to request investigations into opposition lawmakers who raise issues." Democratic Party floor leader Han Byung-do said, "The People Power Party is attacking this nominee as if a mafia organization is trying to kill and retaliate against a member who left their organization." (여야는 청문회가 무산된 책임을 서로에게 떠넘겼다. 송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 이날 “이 후보자가 약속을 어기고 국회가 요구한 자료 제출을 아예 보이콧하고 있다. 도리어 문제 제기하는 야당 국회의원을 수사 의뢰하겠다고 협박하고 있다”고 주장했다. 한병도 민주당 원내대표는 “국민의힘은 조직폭력배가 자기들 조직에서 이탈한 조직원을 어떻게든 죽이고 보복하듯 이 후보자를 공격하고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The floor leaders of the ruling and opposition parties discussed the hearing schedule again but showed differences of opinion. Ruling party floor leader Jeong Tae-ho told The Hankyoreh, "(A unilateral hearing) is not appropriate. Even if it is an option, it doesn't look good to the public," and added, "I proposed (to the People Power Party) to hold (the hearing) even tomorrow (the 20th)." However, People Power Party chief spokesperson Park Sung-hoon argued, "Even if the documents are submitted today (the 19th), it will take at least two days to analyze them and prepare questioning materials," insisting on holding the hearing on the 21st. (여야 간사는 청문회 일정을 다시 논의했지만 이견을 보였다. 여당 간사인 정태호 의원은 한겨레에 “(단독 청문회는) 적절하지 않다. 선택지에 (단독 청문회가) 있어도 국민들이 보기에 모습이 좋지 않다”며 “내일(20일)이라도 (청문회를) 하자고 (국민의힘에) 제안했다”고 말했다. 그러나 박성훈 국민의힘 수석대변인은 “오늘(19일) 자료가 제출된다고 해도 이를 분석하고 질의 자료를 만들기까지 최소 이틀은 필요하다”며 21일 청문회를 개최하자고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the ruling and opposition parties have differing opinions on coordinating the hearing schedule, Strategy and Finance Committee Chairperson Im Eui-ja has repeatedly stated, "I believe the hearing must be held," raising the possibility of a dramatic agreement between the parties on a date. However, some within the People Power Party hold the view that even if the hearing becomes dysfunctional, if President Lee Jae-myung forcefully appoints the nominee without a hearing, the political burden would be significant and not disadvantageous to the People Power Party. (여야가 청문회 일정 조율에 이견을 보이고 있지만, 임이자 재경위원장이 “반드시 청문회를 열어야 한다는 생각”이라고 거듭 밝히고 있어, 여야가 청문회 개최 일정에 극적으로 합의할 수 있다. 다만 국민의힘 일각에서는 청문회가 파행되더라도 이재명 대통령이 청문회 없이 이 후보자 임명을 강행할 경우 정치적 부담이 커 국민의힘에 불리하지 않을 거라는 시선도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That day, nominee Lee refuted the People Power Party's claim of insufficient document submission. Nominee Lee, who waited at the National Assembly all day, left the Assembly in the afternoon and said, "All necessary documents have been submitted," and "I am waiting for an opportunity to explain at the hearing."&lt;br/&gt;Leaving the National Assembly that night, when asked by reporters, 'Does your position that holding the hearing comes before resignation still stand?', she also said, "Shouldn't the public know? Wouldn't the public also want to clarify all these suspicions?" (이날 이 후보자는 자료 제출이 미비하다는 국민의힘 쪽 주장을 반박했다. 하루 종일 국회에서 대기하던 이 후보자는 이날 오후 국회를 나가며 “필요한 자료는 다 제출했다”며 “청문회에서 소명할 기회를 기다리고 있다”고 말했다.&lt;br/&gt;그는 이날 밤 국회를 떠나며 ‘사퇴보다 청문회 진행이 먼저라는 입장이 여전하냐’는 기자들의 질문에 ”국민들께서 아셔야 되지 않겠냐. 국민들도 이 모든 의혹을 시시비비를 가리고 싶지 않겠냐”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Hae-jeong and Go Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240569.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/428/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503408.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee, smiling, asks "Are you perhaps anti-Myung?"... Jeong Cheong-rae says "Pro-Myung, pro-Cheong" (이 대통령, 웃으며 “혹시 반명입니까?”…정청래 “친명·친청”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240577.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee, smiling, asks "Are you perhaps anti-Myung?"... Jeong Cheong-rae says "Pro-Myung, pro-Cheong" (이 대통령, 웃으며 “혹시 반명입니까?”…정청래 “친명·친청”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/472/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 19일 청와대에서 열린 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리와의 공동언론발표에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Are you perhaps anti-Myung (anti-Lee Jae-myung)?" (“혹시 반명(반이재명)이십니까?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a dinner meeting with the new leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea on the evening of the 19th, President Lee Jae-myung smiled and said this to Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae. He was making a joke, recalling the talk of a 'Myung-Cheong (Lee Jae-myung vs. Jeong Cheong-rae) showdown' that emerged during the recent by-election for Supreme Council members. Leader Jeong immediately retorted, "We are all pro-Myung (pro-Lee Jae-myung) and pro-Cheong (pro-Cheong Wa Dae [Blue House])." Park Soo-hyun, the Democratic Party's chief spokesperson, relayed that "President Lee burst into hearty laughter." (이재명 대통령은 19일 저녁 더불어민주당 신임 지도부와의 만찬 회동에서 정청래 민주당 대표를 향해 웃으며 이렇게 말했다. 최근 치러진 최고위원 보궐선거 과정에서 ‘명-청(이재명-정청래) 대결’ 구도란 말들이 나온 걸 상기시키며 농담을 건넨 것이다. 정 대표는 곧장 “우리는 모두 친명(친이재명)이고 친청(친청와대)입니다”라고 응수했고, “이 대통령은 파안대소했다”고 박수현 민주당 수석대변인은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dinner meeting that day was held to celebrate the launch of the Democratic Party's new leadership following the by-elections for floor leader and Supreme Council members on the 11th, which saw Han Byung-do elected as floor leader and Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Seong-yun, and Moon Jeong-bok elected as Supreme Council members. President Lee reportedly said, "I wanted to meet the Democratic Party leadership, now complete with the election of Supreme Council members," and added, "I wish to frequently hear from you, who are breathing together with the people on the ground, about public sentiment and stories of the world that I may not yet fully grasp." (이날 만찬 회동은 지난 11일 원내대표·최고위원 보궐선거를 통해 한병도 원내대표와 강득구·이성윤·문정복 최고위원 등이 선출되며 민주당 지도부가 새롭게 출범한 것을 기념해 이뤄졌다. 이 대통령은 “최고위원 선출로 완전체가 된 민주당 지도부를 뵙고 싶었다”며 “제가 미처 잘 모를 수도 있는 민심과 세상 이야기를 현장에서 국민과 함께 호흡하고 있는 여러분을 통해 자주 듣고자 한다”고 말했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the dinner meeting, which lasted for 2 hours and 40 minutes starting at 6 PM at the Cheong Wa Dae main building, President Lee and the Democratic Party leadership reportedly discussed responses to rapid changes in the international situation, the successful promotion of administrative integration, and broadly gathering opinions on follow-up legislation for prosecution reform. Regarding this, Chief Spokesperson Park relayed, "They pledged to become a Democratic Party that firmly supports the President so that 2026 becomes a year where President Lee's state management philosophy takes firm root and yields abundant achievements through integration and leap forward." (청와대 본관에서 저녁 6시부터 2시간40분 동안 진행된 이날 만찬 회동에서 이 대통령과 민주당 지도부는 급격한 국제정세 변화에 대한 대응과 행정통합의 성공적 추진, 검찰개혁 후속 입법에 대한 폭넓은 의견 수렴 등을 했다고 한다. 박 수석대변인은 이와 관련해 “이 대통령의 국정철학이 굳게 뿌리내리고 통합과 도약으로 풍성한 성과를 거두는 2026년이 되도록 대통령님을 튼튼히 뒷받침하는 민주당이 되겠다고 다짐했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, Floor Leader Han said, "Upon examining the legislative situation after taking office as floor leader, based on the 20-month mark since the opening of the National Assembly, the 22nd National Assembly's bill passage rate is 20.2%, the lowest compared to the 21st Assembly's 24.5% and the 20th Assembly's 29.2%, so I feel apologetic and concerned for the people." He added, "There are 184 bills related to the Lee Jae-myung administration's state affairs tasks that need to be swiftly promoted, of which only 37 have currently passed the National Assembly. We will mobilize all our capabilities going forward to focus on processing legislation and strive to firmly support the Lee Jae-myung administration's state affairs tasks." (한 원내대표는 이 자리에서 “원내대표 취임 후 입법 상황을 점검해보니, 개원 후 20개월 지점을 기준으로 보면, 22대 국회 입법 통과율이 20.2%로 21대 국회의 24.5%, 20대 국회의 29.2%에 비해 최저를 기록하고 있어 국민께 죄송하고 걱정이 앞선다”며 “이재명 정부의 국정과제와 관련하여 신속 추진되어야 할 입법이 184건인데 그 중 37건만이 현재 국회를 통과하고 있어 앞으로 모든 역량을 동원하여 입법 처리에 집중함으로써 이재명 정부의 국정과제를 튼튼하게 뒷받침하도록 노력하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party leadership used the dinner that day to emphasize the image of harmony between the party and the administration. In particular, Leader Jeong reportedly mentioned President Lee's time as Democratic Party leader, saying, "When I think about how, even while undergoing that difficult investigation and trial, he never neglected his party duties as leader for even a moment, I feel I am far too lacking as a leader," and "I always vow to redouble my efforts for the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration." He continued, "As this is still a period where a different level of seriousness remains, we will perform the party's role well, uniting firmly around the President to create a great Republic of Korea." Leader Jeong's demeanor was seen as lowering his posture considerably, conscious of controversies like the 'Myung-Cheong showdown' that President Lee had joked about. (민주당 지도부는 이날 만찬을 통해 당·청이 화합하는 면모를 강조했다. 특히 정 대표는 이 대통령의 민주당 대표 시절을 언급하며 “그 힘든 수사와 재판을 받으면서도 대표로서 당무에 한치도 소홀함이 없었던 것을 생각하면 저는 대표로서 부족함이 너무 많다는 생각을 하게 된다”며 “이재명 정부의 성공을 위해 분골쇄신 더 노력해야겠다고 늘 다짐한다”고 말했다고 한다. 그러면서 “지금도 다른 차원의 엄중함이 여전히 자리 잡고 있는 시기이므로 대통령님을 중심으로 똘똘 뭉쳐 위대한 대한민국을 만들기 위해 당의 역할을 잘 해나가겠다”고 말했다. 정 대표의 이런 모습은, 이 대통령이 농담 소재로 얘기했던 ‘명-청대결’ 논란 등을 의식해 한껏 몸을 낮춘 것으로 비쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, a leadership official commented on President Lee's 'anti-Cheong?' joke, saying, "95% of it was a joke to lighten the mood, but it seemed like about 5% was mixed with sincerity." Regarding this, he relayed, "President Lee said, 'Lately they talk about anti-Myung, Myung-Cheong, isn't that an attempt to divide us?' and 'Shouldn't we correct such things?'" The intent was to say there is no conflict between the party and the administration. He also added, "President Lee even went as far as to say, laughing, 'I'd rather it be anti-Cheong (anti-Jeong Cheong-rae), I don't know about pro-Cheong.'" (지도부 관계자는 이와 관련해 이 대통령의 ‘반청이냐’는 농담과 관련해 “95%는 분위기를 좋게 하려는 농담이었지만, 한 5%정도는 진담도 섞여있는 것 같더라”고 말했다. 그는 이와 관련해 “이 대통령이 ‘요즘 반명 명-청 하는데, 그건 우리를 갈라치기하려는 것 아니냐’며 ‘이런 건 바로 잡아야 되는 거 아니냐’고 했다”고 전했다. 당·청 간 갈등은 없다는 취지로 얘기했다는 것이다. 그러면서 “이 대통령이 ‘차라리 반청(반정청래), 친청이면 모르겠다’ 이렇게까지 말씀하며 웃으셨다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240577.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/472/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong Wa Dae: "Too early to discuss Lee Hye-hoon's appointment"... Likely to wait for ruling and opposition party negotiations (청와대 “이혜훈 임명 논하긴 일러”…여야 협의 지켜볼 듯)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240578.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cheong Wa Dae: "Too early to discuss Lee Hye-hoon's appointment"... Likely to wait for ruling and opposition party negotiations (청와대 “이혜훈 임명 논하긴 일러”…여야 협의 지켜볼 듯)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/849/588/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503506.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 19일 청와대 본관에서 열린 한-이탈리아 공식 오찬에서 인사말을 하고 있다. 청와대사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the cancellation of the confirmation hearing for Planning and Budget Minister nominee Lee Hye-hoon on the 19th due to a boycott by opposition party committee members, Cheong Wa Dae stated, "It is still too early to discuss whether to appoint her," indicating it would wait and see the negotiations between the ruling and opposition parties. (19일 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회가 야당 청문위원들의 보이콧으로 무산된 뒤 청와대는 “임명 여부를 논하기 아직 이르다”며 여야 협상을 지켜보겠다는 입장을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a phone call with The Hankyoreh that day, a Cheong Wa Dae official said, "Since the nominee herself has not gone through the process of directly explaining the suspicions or seeking public understanding, we cannot immediately say 'because the hearing was dysfunctional, we will appoint or not appoint this nominee.'" The official added, "What is important is for the nominee herself to explain the suspicions to the public." The official further stated, "We will watch the process as the National Assembly discusses how to handle the hearing that could not be held today." (청와대 관계자는 이날 한겨레와 한 통화에서 “이 후보자가 직접 의혹을 해명하거나 국민의 이해를 요구하는 절차를 거치지 않았는데, 당장 ‘청문회가 파행했으니 이 후보자를 임명하겠다, 안 하겠다’고 할 수는 없다”며 “중요한 것은 이 후보자 본인이 국민에게 의혹을 해명하는 것”이라고 말했다. 이 관계자는 “오늘 열지 못한 청문회를 어떻게 할 것인지 국회에서 논의되는 과정을 지켜보겠다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the opposition party continues to refuse to hold the confirmation hearing, Cheong Wa Dae could request the National Assembly to resubmit the report on the hearing progress. If the hearing still does not take place, it would then have to choose whether to proceed with the appointment or withdraw it. However, the mood within Cheong Wa Dae is that there is currently not a strong reason to withdraw the appointment. This is because the suspicions or criticisms raised against the nominee are not considered fatal flaws significant enough to warrant withdrawing the nomination. The Cheong Wa Dae official said, "If the raised suspicions had enough destructive power to bring down the nominee, the opposition party would have no reason to boycott the hearing," adding, "Doesn't it mean that the opposition party also believes that if they set up the stage of a hearing, it would be difficult for the nominee to explain the suspicions or for them to make a big issue out of them?" (청와대로선 야당이 계속 인사청문회 개최를 거부할 경우 국회에 인사청문 경과보고서 송부를 다시 요청할 수 있고, 그래도 청문회가 안 열리면 임명을 강행할지 철회할지 선택해야 한다. 청와대는 다만 현재로선 임명을 철회할 이유는 크지 않다는 분위기다. 이 후보자를 향해 제기된 의혹이나 비판이 후보 지명을 철회할 만큼 결정적 흠결은 아니라는 것이다. 청와대 관계자는 “제기된 의혹이 후보자를 낙마시킬 만큼 파괴력이 큰 것이라면, 야당이 청문회를 보이콧할 이유도 없다”며 “야당도 청문회라는 판을 깔아주면 의혹들을 후보자가 해명하거나 크게 문제삼기 어려울 것으로 본다는 뜻 아니겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the fact that recent various opinion polls show public support for appointing this nominee languishing in the mid-10% range is also a considerable burden for Cheong Wa Dae. Cheong Wa Dae appears likely to closely monitor what impact the opposition party's refusal to hold the hearing will have on public opinion surrounding this nominee. (다만 최근 여러 여론조사에서 이 후보자 임명에 찬성하는 여론이 10%대 중반으로 저조하게 나오는 것은 청와대에도 적잖은 부담이다. 청와대는 야당의 청문회 거부가 이 후보자를 둘러싼 여론에 어떤 영향을 미칠지도 면밀히 지켜볼 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Koh Kyung-joo, Koh Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240578.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/849/588/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503506.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi, Who Held On, Finally Leaves the Party... Evaluations of "Too Little, Too Late" and "Leaving a Heavy Burden" (버티던 김병기, 결국 당 떠나…“만시지탄” “큰 부담 남겨” 평가)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240579.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kim Byeong-gi, Who Held On, Finally Leaves the Party... Evaluations of "Too Little, Too Late" and "Leaving a Heavy Burden" (버티던 김병기, 결국 당 떠나…“만시지탄” “큰 부담 남겨” 평가)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/501/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503509.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 김병기 의원이 19일 국회 소통관에서 윤리심판원 제명 결정에 대한 재심 청구를 하지 않겠다는 뜻을 밝힌 기자회견을 마친 뒤 엘리베이터를 타기 위해 기다리고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is interpreted that Representative Kim Byeong-gi of the Democratic Party of Korea, who had held firm with the stance that 'he would rather be expelled than leave the party on his own,' changed his initial position on the 19th, giving up a retrial and voluntarily leaving the party, judging that the critical public opinion was growing fiercer by the day and that he was becoming a political burden to the party and his fellow lawmakers. The reason is that if he continued to refuse to leave and faced expulsion through a vote at the general meeting of lawmakers, he would risk being branded as having prioritized his personal safety over burdening the party, and would likely find himself in a position where he could not expect help from the party or lawmakers during any future investigation or trial. (‘제명을 당할지언정 스스로 당을 떠나지는 않겠다’며 버티던 김병기 더불어민주당 의원이 애초 입장을 바꿔 19일 재심을 포기하고 자진 탈당한 것은 비판 여론이 나날이 거세지면서, 당과 동료 의원들에게도 정치적 부담이 되고 있다는 판단에 따른 것으로 풀이된다. 탈당을 거부하다가 의원총회 투표로 제명이 결정될 경우, 사적 안위를 앞세워 당에 부담을 안겼다는 오명과 함께 추후 수사나 재판을 받는 과정에서 당과 의원들의 도움을 기대하기 힘든 처지에 직면할 수 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim's declaration of leaving the party comes just one week after the party's Ethics Tribunal decided on expulsion on the 12th. His sudden change of stance is attributed to accumulated dissatisfaction over controversies involving his aides' abuse of power, suspicions of receiving and covering up nomination funds, and suspicions of his spouse's personal use of a district council corporate card, which have led to a simultaneous decline in the approval ratings of President Lee Jae-myung and the party. (김 의원이 탈당을 선언한 건, 지난 12일 당 윤리심판원이 제명 처분을 의결한 지 일주일 만이다. 그가 돌연 입장을 바꾼 건, 보좌진 갑질 논란과 공천헌금 수수 및 무마 의혹, 배우자의 구의회 법인카드 사적 유용 의혹 등에 따른 불만이 누적되며 이재명 대통령과 당 지지율 동반 하락으로 이어지고 있는 데 따른 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, in a Real Meter opinion poll released that day, President Lee's positive evaluation of state affairs fell 3.7 percentage points from the previous week to 53.1%, and the Democratic Party's approval rating fell 5.3 percentage points to 42.5%. Within the party, voices urging Representative Kim to 'put the party first and personal matters second by leaving the party' were growing louder. (실제로 이날 발표된 리얼미터 여론조사에서 이 대통령의 국정수행 긍정평가는 지난주보다 3.7%포인트 내린 53.1%로 집계됐고, 민주당 지지율은 5.3%포인트 하락한 42.5%로 집계됐다. 당 안에선 김 의원을 향해 ‘탈당을 통해 선당후사하라’는 목소리가 고조되는 상황이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, he stated, "I will not apply for a retrial (against the Ethics Tribunal's expulsion decision) and will leave (the party)," but he initially demanded that 'the expulsion be concluded solely by a decision of the Supreme Council, without a vote at the general meeting of lawmakers.' This appeared to be an attempt to avoid the formality of leaving the party, which could be seen as admitting to the suspicions, while also conveying his desire to avoid a situation where lawmakers would be divided for and against regarding his fate. (그는 이날 “(윤리심판원의 제명 결정에) 재심 신청을 하지 않고 (당을) 떠나겠다”면서도, 애초 ‘의원총회 표결 없이 최고위원회 의결만으로 제명을 매듭지어달라’고 요구했다. 의혹을 인정하는 것처럼 보일 수도 있는 탈당이란 형식을 피하면서, 동시에 자신의 거취를 두고 의원들이 찬반양론으로 맞서는 모습만은 피하고 싶다는 뜻을 전달하기 위한 것으로 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that 'an expulsion decision without a general meeting of lawmakers' is impossible under the current Political Parties Act and the Democratic Party's party constitution and regulations. The leadership explained to Representative Kim's side that 'it is legally difficult to make an expulsion decision without a general meeting of lawmakers' and conveyed a request that 'voluntary withdrawal would be better,' which Representative Kim ultimately accepted. (문제는 ‘의원총회 없는 제명 결정’은 현행 정당법과 민주당 당헌·당규상 불가능하다는 점이다. 지도부는 김 의원 쪽에 ‘의원총회 없이 제명 결정을 내리는 건 법적으로 어렵다’는 설명을 전하며 ‘자진 탈당이 좋겠다’는 요청을 전달했고, 결국 김 의원은 이를 수용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Representative Kim leaving the party during the disciplinary process, the Democratic Party can now resolve the issue of his status without going through a separate decision-making procedure. Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae, meeting with reporters at the National Assembly, stated, "According to the party constitution and regulations, in principle, a person who leaves the party during disciplinary action cannot rejoin the party for five years (from the time of leaving)," but added, "If, after leaving the party, (they go through investigation and trial and) receive a disposition of no charges, they can explain themselves to the party and seek reinstatement." (김 의원이 징계 도중 탈당을 하게 되면서 민주당은 별도의 의결 절차를 거치지 않고 김 의원의 거취 문제를 매듭지을 수 있게 됐다. 조승래 사무총장은 국회에서 기자들을 만나 “당헌·당규에 따라 징계 중 탈당한 사람에 대해서도 (탈당으로부터) 5년간 복당을 할 수 없는 것이 원칙”이라면서도 “만약 탈당 뒤 (수사와 재판 과정을 거쳐) 무혐의 처분을 받는다면 당에 소명하고 구제받을 수 있을 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmakers showed reactions of 'relief that Representative Kim made the decision, even if belatedly.' Representative Park Ji-won of the Democratic Party, who had strongly demanded Representative Kim's voluntary withdrawal, left a post on Facebook saying, "I express gratitude for the spirit of sacrificing oneself for the public good and putting the party first." However, one metropolitan-area second-term lawmaker commented, "While it's fortunate that lawmakers don't have to make a decision at the general meeting, it's a case of too little, too late," adding, "He thought of himself for too long instead of the party. He placed too heavy a burden on the party." (민주당 의원들은 ‘김 의원이 이제라도 결단해 다행’이라는 반응을 보였다. 김 의원의 자진 탈당을 강하게 요구해온 박지원 민주당 의원은 페이스북에 “살신성인 선당후사 애당심에 감사를 표한다”는 글을 남겼다. 다만 한 수도권 재선 의원은 “의총에서 의원들이 결단하지 않아도 되게 된 점은 다행스러운 일이나, 만시지탄”이라며 “당보다 자기 자신을 생각한 시간이 너무 길었다. 당에 너무 큰 부담을 줬다”고 평했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party downplayed the significance, calling it a 'sham withdrawal,' and urged him to resign his parliamentary seat and called for a special prosecutor investigation. Park Seong-hoon, the PPP's chief spokesperson, issued a commentary that day, stating, "The shallow trick of trying to cover up this situation by dismissing it as personal corruption by Representatives Kim Byeong-gi and Kang Seon-woo must stop," and "Pretending to leave the party cannot be the end of responsibility." Floor leader spokesperson Choi Soo-jin also said, "We strongly urge Representative Kim's immediate resignation from his parliamentary seat and the Democratic Party's acceptance of a special prosecutor (investigation into nomination funds)." (국민의힘은 ‘꼼수 탈당’이라고 의미를 깎아내린 뒤 의원직 사퇴와 특검 조사를 촉구했다. 박성훈 국민의힘 수석대변인은 이날 논평을 내어 “이번 사태를 김병기 의원과 강선우 의원의 개인 비리로 치부해 덮으려는 얄팍한 꼼수는 멈춰야 한다”며 “당을 떠나는 흉내가 책임의 끝이 될 수 없다”고 했다. 최수진 원내수석대변인도 “김 의원의 즉각적인 의원직 사퇴와 함께 더불어민주당의 (공천헌금) 특검 수용을 강력히 촉구한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Choi Hayan and Jang Narae &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최하얀 기민도 장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240579.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/501/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503509.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italian Prime Minister, a 'K-pop Enthusiast' Daughter, Visits South Korea Holding a BLACKPINK Lightstick (‘K팝 열성팬’ 딸과 블랙핑크 응원봉 들고 방한한 이탈리아 총리)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240580.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Italian Prime Minister, a 'K-pop Enthusiast' Daughter, Visits South Korea Holding a BLACKPINK Lightstick (‘K팝 열성팬’ 딸과 블랙핑크 응원봉 들고 방한한 이탈리아 총리)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/496/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503512.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령과 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 19일 청와대에서 열린 공식 오찬에서 건배하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung and Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni held a summit on the 19th, confirming their shared commitment to achieving the complete denuclearization of the Korean Peninsula and agreeing to join forces for peace and stability in the Indo-Pacific region as well. The Italian Prime Minister's visit to South Korea is the first in 19 years, marking the first foreign dignitary to be received by President Lee since his return to the Blue House and the first visit by a European leader since the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration. (이재명 대통령과 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리는 19일 정상회담을 열어 한반도의 완전한 비핵화 실현에 대한 공통된 의지를 확인하고, 인도·태평양 지역의 평화와 안정을 위해서도 힘을 모으기로 했다. 이탈리아 총리의 방한은 19년 만으로, 이 대통령이 청와대로 복귀한 뒤 처음 맞는 외빈이자 이재명 정부 출범 이후 첫 유럽 정상의 방한이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following their summit at the Blue House on the 19th, President Lee and Prime Minister Meloni issued a joint press statement containing these points. President Lee stated at the event, "South Korea and Italy will go beyond easing tensions on the Korean Peninsula to jointly uphold the value of world peace." Prime Minister Meloni emphasized the importance of security cooperation once again, saying, "Whether viewed from the perspective of European security or from the Indo-Pacific region, the war in Ukraine is extremely dangerous." (이 대통령과 멜로니 총리는 19일 청와대에서 정상회담을 마친 뒤 이런 내용이 담긴 공동언론발표문을 발표했다. 이 대통령은 이 자리에서 “한국과 이탈리아는 한반도 긴장 완화를 넘어 세계 평화의 가치를 함께 수호할 것”이라고 말했다. 멜로니 총리는 “유럽의 안전이라는 측면에서나 인도·태평양 지역의 시각에서 보거나 우크라이나 전쟁은 매우 위험하다”며 안보 협력의 중요성을 다시 한번 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also conveyed at the event, "The two countries have agreed to further develop their relationship to a future-oriented level befitting the title of 'Strategic Partnership.'" To this end, they plan to broaden the horizon of cooperation in advanced industries such as artificial intelligence (AI) and aerospace, while continuing complementary cooperation in the defense industry sector. (이 대통령은 또 이 자리에서 “양국이 ‘전략적 동반자 관계’라는 명칭에 맞춰 미래지향적 수준으로 관계를 더 발전시키기로 했다”고 전했다. 이를 위해 인공지능(AI)과 우주항공 등 첨단산업으로 협력의 지평을 넓히는 한편, 방위산업 분야에서도 상호 보완적인 협력을 이어간다는 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The joint press statement also specified that they will strengthen joint efforts to develop critical mineral supply chains through multilateral dialogue frameworks like the Mineral Security Partnership (MSP), for which South Korea currently holds the chairmanship. The two leaders also took the opportunity of the day's meeting to sign three Memoranda of Understanding (MOUs) covering △semiconductor industry cooperation △civil protection cooperation △and the protection of cultural heritage and landscapes. (공동언론발표문에는 한국이 현재 의장직을 맡은 광물안보파트너십(MSP)과 같은 다자간 대화체를 통해 핵심 광물 공급망 개발을 위한 공동 노력을 강화한다는 점도 명시됐다. 두 정상은 이날 회담을 계기로 △반도체 산업 협력 △시민보호 협력 △문화유산 및 경관 보호 등을 위한 3건의 양해각서(MOU)를 체결하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee requested special attention to the safety of the Korean delegation and citizens visiting Italy for the Winter Olympics to be held there next month. (이 대통령은 다음달 이탈리아에서 열리는 겨울올림픽을 계기로 현지를 방문할 한국 대표단과 국민의 안전에 각별한 관심을 요청했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this day, Prime Minister Meloni drew attention by being accompanied by her daughter Ginevra, known to be an avid K-pop fan. Although Ginevra did not participate in the official schedule, footage released on Prime Minister Meloni's official YouTube account showed her disembarking from the official aircraft the previous day holding BLACKPINK's lightstick, which has pink hammer-shaped ends on both sides. Lightsticks are 'goods' used by K-pop fans at concerts or events, symbolizing K-pop fan club culture. (이날 멜로니 총리는 케이(K)팝 열성팬으로 알려진 딸 지네브라와 동행해 눈낄을 끌었다. 지네브라는 공식 일정엔 함께하지 않았지만, 전날 분홍색 망치 모양이 양 옆으로 달린 블랙핑크의 응원봉을 손에 든 채 전용기에서 내린 모습이 멜로니 총리 공식 유튜브 계정을 통해 공개됐다. 응원봉은 케이팝 팬들이 콘서트나 행사장에서 사용하는 ‘굿즈’로, 케이팝 팬클럽 문화를 상징한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee and Prime Minister Meloni also engaged in a lengthy conversation about K-pop during the summit. When President Lee mentioned during the expanded meeting, "Recently, the popularity of K-culture has been rising in Italy as well, leading to an increase in Italian citizens visiting South Korea," Prime Minister Meloni burst into laughter. Later, during a luncheon between the two leaders, Prime Minister Meloni said, "I think there were very smart choices and strategies behind the success of K-culture," adding, "It can be said to be a strategy that subtly blends the extremely global with the extremely national." (이 대통령과 멜로니 총리는 이날 정상회담에서도 케이팝에 대한 대화를 오랜 시간 나눴다. 이 대통령이 확대 회담에서 “최근에는 이탈리아에서도 케이컬처의 인기가 높아져서 한국을 찾는 이탈리아 국민들이 늘어나고 있다”고 말하자, 멜로니 총리는 웃음을 크게 터트렸다. 이후 양국 정상 간 오찬에서 멜로니 총리는 “케이컬처의 성공 뒤에는 굉장히 똑똑한 선택과 전략이 있었다고 생각한다”며 “그것은 바로 지극히 세계적인 것과 지극히 국가적인 것을 오묘하게 섞은 전략이라고 할 수 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240580.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/496/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503512.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Kim Byeong-wook Resigns to Run for Seongnam Mayor Election (김병욱 정무비서관, 성남시장 선거 출마 위해 사직)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240581.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Kim Byeong-wook Resigns to Run for Seongnam Mayor Election (김병욱 정무비서관, 성남시장 선거 출마 위해 사직)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/486/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503516.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김병욱 정무비서관이 19일 청와대 기자회견장에서 사직 의사를 밝히고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Byeong-wook, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs at the Presidential Office, resigned on the 19th after finishing his duties, in order to run in the June 3 local elections. (김병욱 청와대 정무비서관이 6·3 지방선거 출마를 위해 19일 근무를 끝으로 사직했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim announced his resignation during a briefing at the Presidential Office's Chunchugwan press center, stating, "I have worked hard over the past seven months for the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration." (김 비서관은 이날 청와대 춘추관 브리핑에서 “지난 7개월 간 이재명 정부의 성공을 위해서 열심히 달려왔다”며 사직 소식을 알렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim said, "I take pride in having worked to establish a close relationship between the ruling party and the Presidential Office and to facilitate smooth communication with the opposition parties," adding, "I have always worked with the conviction that the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration is essential for the development of South Korea, and I will continue to work hard in a truly enviable South Korea." (김 비서관은 “당·청 간 긴밀한 관계 정립을 확립하고, 야당과의 원활한 소통을 위해 나름대로 힘 써왔다고 자부한다”며 “이재명 정부의 성공이 대한민국 발전에 필연적 요소임을 항상 새기며 일해왔으며, 앞으로도 전 세계가 부러워하는 진짜 대한민국에서 열심히 일하도록 하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim, who served as a two-term National Assembly member representing Seongnam, Gyeonggi Province in the 20th and 21st sessions, is known to be running as a candidate for mayor of Seongnam in the upcoming June local elections. He concluded his duties as Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs after attending a dinner with President Lee Jae-myung and the ruling party leadership today. The appointment of his successor is expected to be announced soon. (경기 성남을 지역구에서 20·21대 재선 국회의원을 지낸 김 비서관은 오는 6월 지방선거에서 성남시장 후보에 출마할 것으로 알려졌다. 김 비서관은 이날 이재명 대통령과 여당 지도부 만찬 일정을 끝으로 정무비서관 업무를 마무리했다. 후임 정무비서관 인선은 조만간 발표될 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to Secretary Kim, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho expressed his intention to resign to run for governor of Gangwon Province. The Presidential Office appointed former Democratic Party lawmaker Hong Ik-pyo as his successor the previous day. Secretary Hong is scheduled to begin his handover of duties starting with a dinner with the Democratic Party leadership today and officially start his term on the 20th. (김 비서관에 앞서 우상호 정무수석이 강원도지사 출마를 위해 사의를 표한 바 있다. 청와대는 전날 우 전 수석의 후임으로 홍익표 전 민주당 의원을 임명했다. 홍 수석은 이날 민주당 지도부 만찬을 시작으로 업무를 인수인계 받고 오는 20일부터 공식 임기를 시작할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240581.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/486/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119503516.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>One Year into Trump's Second Term: South Korea's Diplomacy with the U.S. Put to the 'Crisis Management Test' (트럼프 2기 1년, 한국 대미외교 ‘위기관리 시험대’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240585.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;One Year into Trump's Second Term: South Korea's Diplomacy with the U.S. Put to the 'Crisis Management Test' (트럼프 2기 1년, 한국 대미외교 ‘위기관리 시험대’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500066.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령과 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 지난해 10월25일 경주에서 정상회담을 하기 전 선물 증정 행사에서 악수하고 있다. 이 대통령은 트럼프 대통령에게 경주 금관 모형과 훈장을 주었다. 경주/로이터 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
President Trump's return to the White House coincided with a period when South Korea was plunged into chaos due to an illegal state of emergency. As South Korean far-right forces colluded with Trump's supporters, the MAGA crowd, to spread conspiracy theories and justify Yoon Suk-yeol's martial law, South Korea's political crisis deepened. ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lee Jae-myung administration, which began in June 2024, faced an oncoming tsunami of President Trump's unilateral America First policy, pressure on allies, tariff wars, and attacks by some Trump supporters claiming 'election fraud'. Just two and a half hours before the summit meeting with President Lee Jae-myung was set to begin on August 25th, U.S. President Donald Trump posted a message saying, "It looks like a situation of purges or revolution is happening in South Korea." Right up until the meeting, the U.S. Departments of Commerce, State, and Defense presented our government with high-stakes investment, security, and economic demands, pressuring that the summit would be canceled if they were not met. Trump, claiming allies had been 'ripping off' America, treated the Korea-U.S. Free Trade Agreement (K-FTA) like a scrap of paper and used the threat of a 25% tariff bomb as leverage to pressure South Korea into making massive investments, significantly increasing defense cost-sharing, and purchasing American weapons on a large scale. (트럼프 대통령의 백악관 귀환은 한국이 불법 비상계엄으로 혼란에 빠져 있던 시기와 맞물렸다. 한국 극우세력이 트럼프 대통령의 지지자들인 마가(MAGA) 세력과 결탁해 음모론을 퍼뜨리며 윤석열의 계엄을 정당화하려 하면서, 한국의 정치 위기는 더 깊어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, through the August White House summit and the October Gyeongju summit, President Lee Jae-myung and the South Korean government managed the precarious situation by combining resistance and negotiation against Trump's excessive demands, creating a 'reversal'. After arduous negotiations, the 'Joint Fact Sheet' (joint statement) from the Korea-U.S. summit announced on November 14th scaled down the U.S.-bound investment Trump pressured for with the tariff bomb to $200 billion in cash investment (with an annual limit of $20 billion) and $150 billion in shipbuilding cooperation (MASGA) investment, while lowering the automobile tariff to 15%. 'Korea-U.S. Alliance Modernization' focused more on increasing defense spending than on adjusting the role of U.S. Forces Korea, agreeing to raise defense spending to 3.5% of GDP and spend $25 billion on purchasing American weapons by 2030. By traditional diplomatic standards, these are disappointing and concerning outcomes, but they are the result of a necessary compromise reflecting the stark reality of a 'transactional alliance' in the Trump era. President Lee Jae-myung's success in securing President Trump's public support during the two rounds of talks for South Korea's pursuit of nuclear-powered submarines and for uranium enrichment/spent nuclear fuel reprocessing, and including it in the fact sheet, is a significant achievement for South Korea. How to turn this 'promise' into reality going forward is also the biggest challenge for Korea-U.S. relations. Whether the North Korea-U.S. dialogue will resume around President Trump's planned visit to China in April, and whether the coordination between South Korea and the U.S.—which divided roles as 'peacemaker and pacemaker'—will proceed properly are also key to the future of the Korean Peninsula. (  2024년 6월 출범한 이재명 정부 앞에는 트럼프 대통령의 일방적인 미국 우선주의와 동맹 압박, 관세전쟁, 일부 트럼프 지지자들의 ‘부정선거’ 공격 등이 쓰나미처럼 몰려오고 있었다. 8월25일 이재명 대통령과의 정상회담이 시작되기 불과 2시간30분 전, 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령은 “한국에서 숙청 또는 혁명이 일어나는 상황 같다”는 글을 올렸다. 회담 직전까지 미국 상무부와 국무부, 국방부는 우리 정부를 향해 수위 높은 투자·안보·경제 청구서를 내밀면서 이를 들어주지 않으면 정상회담을 취소하겠다고까지 압박했다. 트럼프는 동맹국이 미국을 ‘뜯어먹어온’ 존재라면서, 한미 자유무역협정(FTA)을 휴짓조각 취급하고 25% 관세 폭탄을 지렛대로 한국이 거액의 투자, 방위비 대폭 증액, 미국 무기 대규모 구입에 나설 것을 압박했다.  )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Trump emphasizes rebuilding U.S. manufacturing through expanded South Korean investment in the U.S., but the reality is chaotic. Last September, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) arrested about 450 people, including 317 Koreans, working at the construction site of a Hyundai Motor Group-LG Energy Solution joint battery factory in Georgia, chaining them with shackles, which sent shockwaves and heightened anxiety regarding South Korean investment in the U.S. (  하지만, 8월 백악관 정상회담과 10월 경주 정상회담을 통해 이재명 대통령과 한국 정부는 트럼프의 과도한 요구에 대해 버티기와 협상을 병행하면서, ‘반전’을 만들어내면서 위태로운 상황을 관리해왔다. 힘겨운 협상 끝에 11월14일 발표된 한미 정상회담 ‘조인트 팩트시트(공동 발표자료)’는 트럼프가 관세 폭탄으로 압박한 대미 투자를 현금 투자 2000억달러(연간 200억달러 한도), 조선업 협력(MASGA) 투자 1500억 달러로 하고, 자동차 관세를 15%로 낮췄다.  ‘한-미 동맹 현대화’는 주한미군의 역할 조정보다는 국방비 인상에 초점을 맞춰, 국내총생산(GDP)의 3.5%까지 국방비를 증액하고 2030년까지 미국산 무기 구매에 250억 달러를 지출하기로 했다.  기존의 외교 기준으로 보면 아쉽고 우려스러운 내용이지만, 트럼프 시대 ‘거래형 동맹’의 적나라한 현실을 반영한  고육지책의 결과다. 이재명 대통령이 2차례의 담판을 통해 한국의 핵추진 잠수함 건조와 우라늄 농축·사용후핵연료 재처리에 대해 트럼프 대통령의 공개적 지지를 받아내고 팩트시트에 담아낸 것은 한국에는 중요한 성과이자, 앞으로 이 ‘약속’을 어떻게 현실로 만들어나갈지는 한미관계의 가장 큰 숙제이기도 하다. 오는 4월로 예정된 트럼프 대통령의 방중을 계기로 북미 대화가 재개될지, ‘피스메이커, 페이스메이커’로 역할 분담을 한 한미간 조율이 제대로 진행될지도 한반도 미래의 관건이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new year began with the Trump administration's invasion of Venezuela. Having lost its soft power, ability to maintain alliances, and economic/industrial superiority, Trump's America is blatantly racing down the path of predatory imperialism and militarism, maximizing the use of its remaining sole strength—military power—to expand the scale of its plunder. President Trump withdraws from UN organizations and loudly declares, "International law is unnecessary." (  트럼프 대통령은 한국의 대미투자 확대를 통한 미국 제조업 재건을 강조하지만, 현실은 어지럽다. 지난해 9월에는 미 이민세관단속국(ICE)이 조지아주 현대차그룹-LG에너지솔루션 합작 배터리 공장 건설 현장에서 일하던 한국인 317명 등 450여명을 쇠사슬로 묶어 체포하면서, 한국 대미 투자에 충격과 불안을 키웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, President Lee has presented 'self-reliance' and 'strategic autonomy' as guiding principles. The aim is to keep the Korea-U.S. alliance at the center, advance South Korea-Japan cooperation, but also seek maximum cooperation with China in possible areas to find a path to peace on the Korean Peninsula. (  새해는 트럼프 행정부의 베네수엘라 침공으로 시작됐다. 소프트파워와 동맹 유지 능력, 경제·산업의 우위를 상실한 트럼프의 미국은 남아 있는 유일한 힘인 군사력을 최대로 이용해 약탈의 규모를 키우며 약탈적 제국주의·군국주의의 길로 노골적으로 질주한다. 트럼프 대통령은 유엔 기구를 탈퇴하고 “국제법은 필요하지 않다”고 큰소리친다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (  이에 대해 이 대통령은 ‘자강’과 ‘전략적 자율성’을 좌표로 제시했다. 한-미동맹을 중심에 두고 한·일 협력을 진전시키지만, 중국과도 가능한 분야에서 최대한 협력하면서 한반도 평화의 길을 찾아나가려는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240585.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500066.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[View Briefing] Speed of Investigation into Shincheonji-Church-State Collusion ([뷰리핑] 신천지 정교유착 수사 속도)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240597.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[View Briefing] Speed of Investigation into Shincheonji-Church-State Collusion ([뷰리핑] 신천지 정교유착 수사 속도)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500537.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host: Kwon Tae-ho, Editorial Office Director, The Hankyoreh. Guests: Ha Eo-young, The Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter; Kim Hanna, Lawyer; Kim Wan, Team Leader, The Hankyoreh21 Reporting Team 2. (진행: 권태호 한겨레 논설위원실장. 출연: 하어영 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 김한나 변호사, 김완 한겨레21 취재2팀 팀장)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suspect in 'North Korea Infiltration Drone' Case, Received Money from Defense Intelligence Agency for Activities / Joint Investigation Headquarters Speeds Up Investigation into Shincheonji-Church-State Collusion / 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing' on Multiple Allegations Stalls / Kim Byeong-gi, After Abandoning Retrial, Voluntarily Leaves Party..."Didn't Want to Be a Burden" / Will It Ease Tensions on the Korean Peninsula?...Push for 'No-Fly Zone' as Buffer. Please tune in for today's (January 20) View Briefing. (‘북 침투 무인기’ 용의자, 정보사 돈 받아 활동 정황 / 합수본, 신천지 정교유착 수사 속도 / 무더기 의혹 ‘이혜훈 청문회’ 파행 / 김병기, 재심 포기 이어 자진 탈당…“부담 주기 싫다” / 한반도 갈등 완화할까…‘비행금지구역’ 완충 추진. 오늘(01월 20일) 뷰리핑 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240597.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500537.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's hearing fails, shifting blame... "Submit the documents," "If time runs out, appointment proceeds" (이혜훈 청문회 불발 책임도 떠넘기기…“자료 내놔라” “시간 넘기면 임명”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240602.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon's hearing fails, shifting blame... "Submit the documents," "If time runs out, appointment proceeds" (이혜훈 청문회 불발 책임도 떠넘기기…“자료 내놔라” “시간 넘기면 임명”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688691481513_20260120500669.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 19일 국회에서 열릴 예정인 인사청문회를 앞두고 대기하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It appears unlikely that the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, will be held on the 20th as well. The People Power Party, which boycotted the hearing the previous day citing insufficient document submission, is maintaining its stance that "document submission must come first" today as well. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회가 20일에도 열리기 쉽지 않을 것으로 보인다. 전날 자료 제출 미비를 이유로 인사청문회를 보이콧했던 국민의힘은 이날도 “자료 제출이 먼저”라는 입장만 고수하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-young, a People Power Party lawmaker and the opposition party's secretary on the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, posted on Facebook today, writing, "Whether the confirmation hearing resumes is determined by document submission." In a phone call with The Hankyoreh, Rep. Park also emphasized, "Not a single piece of (the additional documents requested yesterday afternoon) has arrived by 8 a.m. this morning," adding, "If the documents don't arrive, (the hearing today) cannot proceed." (국회 재정경제기획위원회 야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원은 이날 페이스북에 글을 올려 “인사청문회 재개 여부는 자료제출이 결정한다”고 적었다. 박 의원은 한겨레와의 통화에서도 “오늘 아침 8시까지 (어제 오후 요청한 추가 자료가) 한 건도 자료가 안 왔다”며 “자료가 안 오면 (오늘도 청문회는) 못 한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a YTN radio interview today, he stressed, "Looking at the 75% of content that the nominee's side claims to have submitted, a significant portion consists of responses stating they cannot be submitted due to lack of consent for personal information disclosure," and "We cannot consider these as responses." (그는 이날 와이티엔(YTN) 라디오 인터뷰에서 “이 후보자 측에서 (제출했다고) 주장하는 75%의 내용을 보면 상당수가 개인정보 제공을 동의하지 않아 제출할 수 없다고 제출한 답변”이라며 “저희는 이것을 답변이라고 볼 수 없다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Park urged the nominee to voluntarily step down. He said, "I think it is disrespectful to the appointing authority for a person with many suspicions to hold on until the end," adding, "It would help public sentiment if the Blue House makes a quick decision or the nominee makes a quick decision themselves." (박 의원은 이에 이 후보자의 자진 사퇴를 촉구했다. 그는 “의혹이 많은 사람이 끝까지 버티는 것은 임명권자에 대한 예의도 아니라고 생각한다”며 “청와대가 빨리 결단하거나 본인이 빨리 결단하는 것이 국민 정서에도 도움이 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling party plans to continue negotiations until the deadline for adopting the hearing report. The ruling party's secretary, Jeong Tae-ho of the Democratic Party of Korea, told The Hankyoreh, "Since the People Power Party is not changing its position of not holding the hearing as it did yesterday, (it likely) won't be held (today either)," and "The 21st is the deadline (for adopting the hearing report). If (the hearing cannot be held), the President has no choice but to appoint (the nominee) as is or request (the hearing) again." (여당은 청문보고서 채택 시한까지 협의를 이어가겠다는 방침이다. 여당 간사인 정태호 더불어민주당 의원은 한겨레에 “국민의힘이 어제와 같이 청문회 열지 않겠다는 입장을 바꾸지 않고 있어 (이날도) 못 열린다”며 “21일이 (청문보고서 채택) 시한인데 (청문회가 열리지 못하면) 대통령이 그대로 임명하거나 재요청하는 방법밖엔 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240602.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688691481513_20260120500669.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Compensate Residents for Military Noise Damage More Broadly"... 8 New Airfields and Firing Ranges Designated for Compensation (“군 소음 피해 주민 더 넓게 보상”…비행장·사격장 보상 8곳 신규 지정)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240605.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Compensate Residents for Military Noise Damage More Broadly"... 8 New Airfields and Firing Ranges Designated for Compensation (“군 소음 피해 주민 더 넓게 보상”…비행장·사격장 보상 8곳 신규 지정)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/452/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500723.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이두희 국방부 차관(오른쪽 첫 번째)이 20일 서울 국회 의원회관에서 열린 군용비행장 및 군 사격장 소음피해대책 관련 당정 협의에서 인사말을 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea and the government have decided to newly designate 8 areas as noise control zones for residents near military airfields and firing ranges, and expand the designation of the existing 69 areas to broaden the compensation coverage area. (더불어민주당과 정부가 군용 비행장과 군 사격장 주면 주민을 위해 소음대책 지역 8곳을 신규 지정하고 기존 69곳은 확대 지정해 보상 대상 면적을 넓히기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Bu Seung-chan, the ruling party secretary of the National Assembly's National Defense Committee, announced that the party and government held a 'Party-Government Council on Military Noise Damage Countermeasures' at the National Assembly on the 20th and finalized the 'Second Basic Plan for Noise Prevention and Compensation in Noise Control Zones' containing these details. (당정은 20일 국회에서 ‘군 소음 피해 대책 당정 협의회’를 열어 이런 내용이 담긴 ‘2차 소음대책지역 소음방지 및 소음 보상에 관한 기본계획’을 확정했다고 국회 국방위원회 여당 간사인 부승찬 의원이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The newly designated areas include the Meoleun-ri firing range in Paju, Gyeonggi Province, the Machajin firing range in Goseong, Gangwon Province, and the Typhoon Scientific Training Ground in Yeoncheon County, Gyeonggi Province, totaling 48.3㎢. The new areas were determined through noise impact assessments. With the designation of the new areas, approximately 770 residents are expected to receive compensation. (신규 지정된 지역은 경기 파주 멀은리 사격장, 강원 고성 마차진 사격장, 경기 연천군 태풍과학화 훈련장 등으로 총 48.3㎢다. 신규 지역은 소음 영향도 조사를 통해 결정됐다. 신규 지역 지정에 따라 주민 약 770명이 보상받을 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The existing noise control zones will be expanded by approximately 5.3㎢ through expanded designation. Approximately 6,900 residents will be newly included as compensation recipients through this measure. (기존 소음대책 지역은 확대 지정을 통해 약 5.3㎢가 늘어난다. 이렇게 새로 포함되는 보상 대상 주민은 약 6900명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party and government also decided to continue reviewing measures to change the evaluation unit for military aircraft noise and establish compensation standards considering realistic conditions. (당정은 군용 항공기 소음 평가 단위를 변경하고 현실 여건을 고려해 보상 기준을 세우는 방안도 지속해서 검토하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the party-government council were Vice Defense Minister Lee Doo-hee, Policy Committee Chairperson Han Jeong-ae, Senior Vice Policy Committee Chairperson Choi Ki-sang, Senior Vice Floor Leader Kim Han-gyu, Rep. Kim Byeong-ju, and Rep. Hwang Myeong-seon. (이날 당정협의회에는 이두희 국방부 차관과 한정애 정책위의장, 최기상 정책위 수석부의장, 김한규 원내정책수석부대표, 김병주 의원, 황명선 의원 등이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Policy Committee Chairperson Han said, "We will pursue regulatory reforms to expand compensation for damage areas under the Military Noise Compensation Act going forward." (한 정책위의장은 “앞으로 군소음 보상법에 따른 피해지역 보상 확대를 위한 규제개혁을 추진해 나가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240605.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/452/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500723.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un visits factory, dismisses vice premier on the spot: "Does a goat pull a cart?" (공장 방문한 김정은, 현장서 부총리 해임 “염소가 달구지 끕니까”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240606.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Kim Jong Un visits factory, dismisses vice premier on the spot: "Does a goat pull a cart?" (공장 방문한 김정은, 현장서 부총리 해임 “염소가 달구지 끕니까”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/731/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500822.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장은 19일 함경남도 룡성기계연합기업소 1단계 개건 현대화 대상 준공식에 참석해 “공장 현대화 사업 준공식에 참석해 ‘무책임·무능·보신주의’ 등을 문제삼아 담당 부총리를 현장에서 해임했다고 20일 노동신문이 보도했다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, attended the completion ceremony for a factory modernization project and dismissed the responsible vice premier on the spot, citing issues such as 'irresponsibility, incompetence, and self-preservationism'. (김정은 북한 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장이 공장 현대화 사업 준공식에 참석해 ‘무책임·무능·보신주의’ 등을 문제삼아 담당 부총리를 현장에서 해임했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the completion ceremony for the first-stage reconstruction and modernization project at the Ryongsong Machine Complex in South Hamgyong Province on the 19th, General Secretary Kim criticized that "the plan for modernizing the production process was absurdly drafted" and that "by ignoring the requirements of the technical assignment document, which is a legal document, during the construction process and allowing production facilities to be irrationally arranged, the modernization has completely derailed from its original track," Rodong Sinmun reported on the 20th. (김 총비서는 19일 함경남도 룡성기계연합기업소 1단계 개건 현대화 대상 준공식에 참석해 “생산공정 현대화 방안이 황당하게 작성”돼 “공사 과정에서 법적 문건인 기술과제서의 요구를 무시하고 생산설비들이 불합리하게 배치되는 것을 방치한 결과 현대화가 본도(본 궤도)에서 완전히 탈선하게 됐다”고 비판했다고 20일 노동신문이 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the fact that "modernization was proceeding haphazardly and as a mere facade," General Secretary Kim stated that when a "group of modernization experts from the munitions industry sector" was brought in for review, "over 60 problems requiring correction were raised." He further criticized this, saying, "I see this as a concentrated expression of the chronic bad habits in Cabinet work and a clear example that reveals the true state of economic guidance officials who are unfaithful and incompetent in their assigned responsibilities." (김 총비서는 “현대화가 마구잡이식으로, 눈속임으로 진행”되고 있는 것과 관련해 “군수공업 부문의 현대화 전문가 그루빠(그룹)”을 투입해 검토해보니 “바로잡아야 할 문제가 60여건이나 제기됐다”고 밝혔다. 이어 “나는 이것을 내각 사업의 고질적 버릇의 집약적인 표현이고 맡은 소관에 불충실하고 무능한 경제지도 일군들의 실상을 그대로 드러낸 명백한 실례”라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Secretary Kim said that "the then-Premier and the current vice premier in charge of the machine-building industry did their work carelessly," and particularly questioned the "conscience and basic sense of responsibility" of the vice premier of the Cabinet. The 'then-Premier' pointed out by General Secretary Kim is Kim Tok Hun, and the 'current vice premier in charge of the machine-building industry' is Yang Sung Ho. (김 총비서는 “당시 내각총리와 현재 기계공업 담당 부총리는 일을 되는대로 해먹었다”고 하고는, 특히 내각부총리의 “양심과 초보적인 책임의식”을 문제삼았다. 김 총비서가 지목한 ‘당시 내각총리’는 김덕훈, ‘현재 기계공업 담당 부총리’는 양승호다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Targeting Vice Premier Yang, General Secretary Kim said, "We do not consider him to have acted against the Party. He was originally a person who could only be that way," and evaluated it as "like harnessing a goat to a cart, an accidental mistake." He then stated, "Does an ox pull a cart or does a goat pull a cart? I hereby dismiss Comrade Vice Premier from his post at this very site." Rodong Sinmun reported that "Comrade Kim Jong Un dismissed Yang Sung Ho, Vice Premier of the Cabinet, on the spot." (김 총비서는 양 부총리를 겨냥해 “우리는 그가 반당을 했다고는 보지 않는다. 원래 그 모양 그 꼴밖에 안 되는 사람”이라며 “염소에게 달구지를 메워놓았던 격, 우발적인 실수”라고 평가했다. 그러곤 “황소가 달구지를 끌지 염소가 달구지를 끕니까”라며 “나는 오늘 이 자리에서 부총리 동무를 해임시킨다”라고 밝혔다. 노동신문은 “김정은 동지께서는 현지에서 양승호 내각부총리를 해임하시었다”라고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vice Premier Yang, who was dismissed on the spot, is a high-ranking economic official who rose through positions such as manager of the Taean Heavy Machine Complex and Minister of Machine-Building Industry to become a candidate member of the Political Bureau of the Party Central Committee. Former Premier Kim, who was criticized along with Vice Premier Yang by General Secretary Kim, has had no reports of public activities since the 13th Plenary Meeting of the 8th Central Committee of the Workers' Party held last December, making it uncertain whether he retains his position as the Party Central Committee Secretary in charge of the economy. (현지 해임된 양 부총리는 대안중기계연합기업소 지배인, 기계공업상 등을 거쳐 노동당 중앙위 정치국 후보위원에 오른 경제 분야 고위 관료다. 양 부총리와 함께 김 총비서의 비판을 받은 김 전 총리는 지난해 12월 열린 노동당 중앙위 8기 13차 전원회의 이후 공개활동 보도가 없어 당중앙위 경제 담당 비서 자리를 유지하고 있는지 불확실하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Secretary Kim's dismissal of Vice Premier Yang and criticism of former Premier Kim are interpreted as discipline aimed at accumulating justification for a large-scale personnel reshuffle, including generational change, ahead of the 9th Party Congress. In fact, General Secretary Kim stated that "there is a major systemic problem in the appointment of cadres" or "there are many problems in the current ranks of administrative cadres," and that "responsible cadres in the policy guidance sector should also feel due remorse." He then emphasized, "The most important thing in the comprehensive development of socialism we aspire to is preparing people, and the foremost among them is building our ranks of guidance officials into solid and competent revolutionary talents." In particular, General Secretary Kim stressed, "Breaking with the practice of placing expectations on people who have been too long accustomed to defeatism, irresponsibility, and passivity becomes a new start for future pioneering and development." This is seen as a preview that there will be a large-scale generational personnel reshuffle at the 9th Party Congress. (김 총비서의 양 부총리 해임과 김 전 총리 비판은 노동당 9차 대회에서 세대교체를 포함한 대대적인 인적 개편을 염두에 둔 명분 축적용 기강 잡기로 풀이된다. 실제 김 총비서는 “간부 등용에서 지금 체계상 큰 문제가 있다”거나 “지금 행정 간부 대열에 문제가 많다”며 “정책지도 부문의 책임간부들도 마땅히 가책을 받아야 한다”라고 밝혔다. 이어 “우리가 지향하는 사회주의의 전면적 발전에서 첫째로 중요한 것이 사람들 준비시키는 것이며 그 첫째중의 첫째는 우리의 지도일군 대열을 견실하고 수준있는 혁명인재로 꾸리는 것”이라고 강조했다. 특히 김 총비서는 “패배주의와 무책임성, 비적극성에 너무도 오래동안 습관된 사람들에게 기대를 걸어온 관행과의 결별은 앞으로의 개척과 발전을 위한 새로운 출발로 된다”고 강조했다. 노동당 9차 대회에서 대대적인 세대교체성 인사가 있으리라는 예고인 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;General Secretary Kim said, "Only if Ryongsong stands up can other machine factories stand up, and only if the country's machine manufacturing industry rises can our entire national economy rise," and added, "We must take the lessons and experiences awakened by the transformation of the Ryongsong Machine Complex as a valuable stepping stone for a new change and rapid leap forward in the entire people's economy." The Ryongsong Machine Complex is a representative factory in the machine-building industry, referred to as the 'mother factory' in North Korea. (김 총비서는 “룡성이 일어서야 다른 기계공장들도 일어설 수 있고 나라의 기계제작공업이 들고 일어나야 우리 국가경제 전반이 일떠설 수 있다”며 “룡성기계연합기업소의 변천이 깨우치는 경험과 교훈을 인민경제전반의 새로운 변화와 급속한 도약을 위한 귀중한 발판으로 삼아야 한다”고 말했다. 룡성기계연합기업소는 북한에서 ‘어머니 공장’으로 불리는 기계공업 분야의 대표 공장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Je-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240606.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/731/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120500822.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Byung-do: "Testimony Emerges that 50,000 Shincheonji Members Joined the People Power Party... Will They Still Refuse a Special Prosecutor Investigation?" (한병도 “5만 신천지 교인 국힘 입당 증언 나와…이래도 특검 안 할 건가”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240610.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Han Byung-do: "Testimony Emerges that 50,000 Shincheonji Members Joined the People Power Party... Will They Still Refuse a Special Prosecutor Investigation?" (한병도 “5만 신천지 교인 국힘 입당 증언 나와…이래도 특검 안 할 건가”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688711209048_20260120500926.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한병도 더불어민주당 원내대표가 20일 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 발언하고 있다. 김경호 선임기자 jijae@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, Han Byung-do, the floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, stated, "Media reports have emerged that &lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/society/society_general/1240383.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Shincheonji systematically enrolled its followers into the People Power Party&lt;/a&gt;," and asked, "(Will the People Power Party) still refuse a special prosecutor investigation into Shincheonji even after this?" (한병도 더불어민주당 원내대표가 20일 “&lt;a class="linkstyle-u" href="/arti/society/society_general/1240383.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;신천지가 신도들을 조직적으로 국민의힘에 입당&lt;/a&gt;시켰다는 언론 보도가 나왔다”며 “(국민의힘은) 이래도 신천지 특검을 거부하겠느냐”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a floor leaders' meeting held at the National Assembly that day, Floor Leader Han said, "It is said that (Shincheonji) not only threatened members that they would go to hell if they failed to meet their membership enrollment quotas but also subjected them to disciplinary actions like 'duck walking'," and added, "Under the operation name so-called 'Pilates', a former (Shincheonji) executive has given specific testimony that at least 50,000 believers have joined the People Power Party over the past five years." He continued, "Previously, the Kim Geon-hee special prosecutor investigation also revealed allegations of the Unification Church's illegal interference in the People Power Party's leadership election." (한 원내대표는 이날 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 “(신천지가) 당원 입당 할당량을 채우지 못하면 지옥에 간다는 협박도 모자라 오리걸음 같은 기합도 시켰다고 한다”며 “이른바 필라테스라는 작전명 아래 최근 5년간 최소 5만여명 교인이 국민의힘에 입당했다는 전직 (신천지) 간부의 구체적인 증언까지 나왔다”고 했다. 이어 “앞서서는 통일교가 국민의힘 당대표 경선에 불법 개입한 혐의도 김건희 특검이 밝힌 바 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Han said, "The People Power Party issued a press release yesterday (the 19th) and announced that the number of party members who have paid dues has exceeded 1 million," and added, "The public is skeptical whether the People Power Party's 1 million members are not a tower built upon collusion between the church and state with the Unification Church and Shincheonji." (한 원내대표는 “국민의힘은 어제(19일) 보도자료를 내고 당비 납부 당원이 100만명을 넘었다고 발표했다”며 “국민의힘 당원 100만명이 통일교, 신천지와의 정교 유착으로 쌓아 올린 탑이 아닌지 국민들은 의구심을 갖고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then stated, "The Democratic Party's position remains consistent," and said, "Let's conduct a special prosecutor investigation into both the Unification Church and Shincheonji." He continued, "We must use this opportunity to clear away all suspicions of collusion between the church and state," and demanded, "We urge the People Power Party. If you have nothing to hide, immediately accept a special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church and Shincheonji." (그러면서 “민주당 입장은 한결 같다”며 “통일교와 신천지 함께 특검하자”고 했다. 이어 “이참에 정교 유착 의혹을 모두 털어내야 한다”며 “국민의 힘에 요구한다. 떳떳하다면 당장 통일교·신천지 특검을 수용하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party and the People Power Party have held several negotiations regarding a special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church and Shincheonji, but they have failed to find common ground, as the Democratic Party insists on a comprehensive special prosecutor investigation covering both the Unification Church and Shincheonji, while the People Power Party advocates for separate investigations. (민주당과 국민의힘은 통일교·신천지 특검과 관련해 수차례 협상을 진행하고 있지만, 민주당은 통일교와 신천지를 묶은 종합 특검을, 국민의힘은 별도의 특검을 주장하면서 합의점을 찾지 못하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240610.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688711209048_20260120500926.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Eon-seok Says "New Chief of Staff for Political Affairs, Please Visit Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site"... Struggling to Find a 'Reason to Stop the Hunger Strike' (송언석 “새 정무수석, 장동혁 단식장 와달라”…‘단식 중단’ 명분 찾기 안간힘)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240612.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Song Eon-seok Says "New Chief of Staff for Political Affairs, Please Visit Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site"... Struggling to Find a 'Reason to Stop the Hunger Strike' (송언석 “새 정무수석, 장동혁 단식장 와달라”…‘단식 중단’ 명분 찾기 안간힘)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688712802273_20260120500953.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;송언석 국민의힘 원내대표가 20일 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 발언하고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Song Eon-seok, the floor leader of the People Power Party, has asked Hong Ik-pyo, the new Chief of Staff for Political Affairs at the Presidential Office, to visit the site of party leader Jang Dong-hyeok's hunger strike. This is essentially a request for a 'reason to stop the hunger strike'. (송언석 국민의힘 원내대표가 홍익표 신임 청와대 정무수석에게 장동혁 대표 단식장을 방문해달라고 했다. 사실상 ‘단식 중단’ 명분을 달라는 요청이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a party meeting held at the National Assembly on the 20th, Floor Leader Song said, "I offer my congratulations to the new Chief of Staff for Political Affairs, Hong Ik-pyo," and added, "I hope the new Chief of Staff seriously recognizes the life-threatening hunger strike struggle of the main opposition party leader, who is urging the passage of the dual special prosecutor laws. For the ruling and opposition parties to move towards a cooperative relationship for people's livelihoods, a strong shift in the Presidential Office's stance must come first." He continued, "As Chief of Staff Hong is known to be a reasonable person, we expect him to play a positive role with the opposition party. His first action after appointment should be to visit the site of Leader Jang's hunger strike sit-in," and said, "After that, he should return to the Presidential Office and recommend to President Lee the acceptance of the dual special prosecutor laws and the withdrawal of the nominee for the Prosecutor General." This is effectively asking Chief of Staff Hong to visit Leader Jang, whose hunger strike has no end in sight, and provide a reason for him to stop. (송 원내대표는 20일 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 “홍익표 신임 정무수석에게 축하한다는 말씀을 드린다”며 “신임 수석은 쌍특검법을 촉구하는 제1야당 당대표의 목숨 건 단식투쟁을 심각하게 인식 바란다. 여야가 민생 협치 관계로 나아가려면 청와대의 강력한 기조 전환이 선행돼야 한다”고 했다. 이어 “홍 수석은 합리적인 분으로 정평이 난 분인 만큼 야당과 긍정적인 역할을 기대한다. 홍 수석의 임명 후 첫 행보는 장 대표 단식 농성장 방문이어야 할 것”이라며 “이후 청와대로 돌아가 이 대통령에게 쌍특검 수용과 이 후보자 지명 철회를 건의해야 할 것”이라고 했다. 출구가 보이지 않는 장 대표의 단식에 홍 수석이 찾아와 중단할 명분을 달라고 청한 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the former Chief of Staff for Political Affairs, Woo Sang-ho, who stepped down, he expressed resentful feelings, saying, "It's hard to call it normal for a former Chief of Staff for Political Affairs to submit his resignation and leave to run in an election while completely ignoring and turning a blind eye to the opposition party leader's hunger strike. How can someone who failed to fulfill even the basic responsibilities of a Chief of Staff for Political Affairs take responsibility for Gangwon Province's administration?" Floor Leader Song criticized, "When the mindset of those assisting the President is only at this level, it's inevitable that relations between the ruling and opposition parties under the Lee Jae-myung administration will head towards extreme deadlock." (물러난 우상호 정무수석을 향해서는 “야당 대표 단식을 나 몰라라 외면하면서 자기 선거 출마하겠다고 사표 내고 나가는 전임 정무수석은 정상이라고 하기 어렵다. 정무수석으로서 기본적인 자기 책임도 다하지 못하는 사람이 어떻게 강원 도정을 책임질 수 있겠나”라며 원망스런 감정을 드러냈다. 송 원내대표는 “대통령을 보좌하는 사람들 마인드가 이런 수준밖에 되지 않으니 이재명 정부에는 여야 관계가 극단적인 경색으로 갈 수밖에 없는 것”이라고 힐난했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jeon Gwang-joon &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240612.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688712802273_20260120500953.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Joon-pyo says, "They said they'd give 1.5 billion if given the nomination"... Park Ji-won says, "For conservatives, there's an extra zero or two" (홍준표 “공천 주면 15억 주겠다더라”…박지원 “보수는 0 한둘 더 붙어”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240617.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hong Joon-pyo says, "They said they'd give 1.5 billion if given the nomination"... Park Ji-won says, "For conservatives, there's an extra zero or two" (홍준표 “공천 주면 15억 주겠다더라”…박지원 “보수는 0 한둘 더 붙어”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/955/573/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501129.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;홍준표 전 대구시장과 박지원 더불어민주당 의원. 페이스북 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid independent lawmaker Kang Seon-woo's appearance at the police on the 20th over allegations of receiving a 100 million won nomination contribution, attention is drawn to the nomination contribution anecdotes shared by political veterans from both ruling and opposition parties, including former Daegu Mayor Hong Joon-pyo, formerly of the People Power Party, and Democratic Party lawmaker Park Ji-won. (공천헌금 1억원 수수 의혹이 제기된 강선우 무소속 의원이 20일 경찰에 출석한 가운데, 국민의힘 소속이었던 홍준표 전 대구시장과 박지원 더불어민주당 의원 등 여야 정치원로들의 공천헌금 경험담이 눈길을 끈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor Hong stated on Facebook on the 18th, "I first learned about the so-called 'nomination contribution' in April 2004 when I was serving on the nomination screening committee for the general election," adding, "A senior lawmaker from TK (Daegu-Gyeongbuk) came to me and proposed that if I helped him get renominated, he would give 1.5 billion won. I told him I understood, went to the nomination screening committee that same day, reported the fact to the committee members, and that day, that senior was cut off, and a newcomer was decided for the nomination." (홍 전 시장은 지난 18일 페이스북에서 “‘공천헌금’이라는 것을 처음 안 것이 2004년 4월 총선 공천심사위원을 할 때였다”며 “티케이(TK·대구경북) 중진 의원이 찾아와서 자기를 재공천해 주면 15억원을 주겠다고 제의하길래 알았다고 하고 그날 바로 공천심사위원회에 가서 그 사실을 공심위원들에게 고하고 그날 그 선배는 컷오프하고 신인 공천을 결정했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor Hong also said, "During the local elections in April 2006, a former senior official from the Seoul Metropolitan Government came to me, asking to be nominated for Dongdaemun District Chief in Seoul and offered 1 billion won. I was utterly shocked," and stated that he nominated someone else instead. Former Mayor Hong added, "Even back then, it was an open secret that a metropolitan council seat cost 100 million won and a basic-level council seat cost 50 million won. Seeing the case of Seoul Council member Kim Kyeong now, over 20 years later, it seems nomination contributions haven't gone down." (홍 전 시장은 “2006년 4월 지방선거 때는 서울시 간부 공무원 출신이 찾아와서 (서울) 동대문구청장을 공천해달라고 하면서 10억원을 제시하길래 깜짝 놀랐다”며 이에 다른 사람을 공천했다고도 했다. 홍 전 시장은 “그 당시에도 광역의원은 1억원, 기초의원은 5000만원이라는 게 공공연한 비밀이었는데 20여년이 지난 지금도 김경 시의원 사례를 보니 공천헌금은 오르지 않았나 보다”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Park also stated that such incidents were "commonplace" in the past. (박 의원도 과거 그런 일이 “비일비재했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appearing on MBC's News Today on the 20th, Lawmaker Park said, "In the past, as former Mayor Hong mentioned, such talk of nomination (contributions) was commonplace." When asked by the host if he had actually seen or heard of such things around him, Lawmaker Park replied, "I saw it a lot and was involved a lot." (박 의원은 20일 문화방송(MBC) 뉴스투데이에 출연해 “과거에는 홍 전 시장이 얘기한 대로 그런 공천(헌금) 언급이 비일비재했다”고 말했다. 박 의원은 ‘실제 주변에서 보거나 들은 게 있었냐’는 진행자의 질문에 “많이 봤고 많이 관계가 있었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Park said, "However, as former Mayor Hong said, for conservatives, isn't there an extra zero or two?" adding, "(For conservatives) it's in the range of 1 billion, 2 billion won, but in the Democratic Party, our progressive camp, they're making a fuss over just tens of millions of won." However, when asked if he could definitively say there are no nomination contributions now, Lawmaker Park added, "I believe so." (박 의원은 “그렇지만, 홍 전 시장이 말한 대로 보수는 영(0)이 하나씩, 둘씩 더 있지 않냐”며 “(보수는) 10억원대, 20억원대 그렇지만 민주당, 우리 진보세력에는 기천만원 가지고 이렇게 시끄럽다”고 말했다. 박 의원은 그러나 ‘지금은 공천헌금이 없다고 확실하게 말할 수 있냐’는 질문에 “저는 그렇게 본다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Kang, who was summoned that day, is suspected of receiving a 100 million won nomination contribution from Seoul Council member Kim Kyeong ahead of the 2022 local elections. This became known last month when a recording was belatedly made public, featuring independent lawmaker Kim Byeong-gi, who was the secretary of the Democratic Party's Seoul mayoral nomination management committee at the time, and Lawmaker Kang, who was a committee member. Lawmaker Kim, who is under suspicion of condoning the nomination contribution, resigned as the Democratic Party's floor leader and left the party the day before. (이날 소환된 강 의원은 2022년 지방선거를 앞두고 김경 서울시의원으로부터 공천헌금 1억원을 받은 혐의를 받는다. 이는 당시 민주당 서울시장 공천관리위원회 간사였던 김병기 무소속 의원과 공관위원이었던 강 의원의 녹취가 지난달 뒤늦게 공개되며 알려졌다. 공천헌금을 묵인한 의혹 등을 받는 김 의원은 민주당 원내대표직을 사퇴한 데 이어 전날 민주당에서 탈당했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Kyung-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240617.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/955/573/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501129.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "We Went Through Great Difficulty to Bring Lee Hye-hoon On Board, Wouldn't a Hearing Be Necessary?" (이 대통령 “이혜훈, 어렵게 모셨는데 인사청문회는 필요하지 않겠나”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240619.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "We Went Through Great Difficulty to Bring Lee Hye-hoon On Board, Wouldn't a Hearing Be Necessary?" (이 대통령 “이혜훈, 어렵게 모셨는데 인사청문회는 필요하지 않겠나”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0120/1617688733248803.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 20일 청와대 본관에서 열린 국무회의에서 모두발언을 하고 있다. 청와대사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that President Lee Jae-myung commented on the disruption of the confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, saying, "We went through great difficulty to bring her on board, wouldn't a hearing be necessary?" (이재명 대통령이 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회 파행에 대해 “어렵게 모시고 왔는데 인사청문회까지는 필요하지 않겠느냐”고 말한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, a Cheong Wa Dae (Blue House) official stated that President Lee made these remarks during a dinner meeting with the leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea held at Cheong Wa Dae the previous day. The official added, "It was a principled statement, suggesting that going through the hearing process and procedures would allow us to gauge public reaction." (20일 청와대 관계자는 전날 청와대에서 열린 더불어민주당 지도부와의 만찬 자리에서 이 대통령이 이렇게 말했다고 밝혔다. 그는 “청문회 과정과 절차를 거쳐야 국민 반응을 볼 수 있지 않겠냐는 원칙적 말씀이었다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The previous day, the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee held a plenary session to open the confirmation hearing for the nominee, but the hearing was disrupted and failed to proceed due to reasons including insufficient submission of required documents. (전날 국회 재정경제기획위원회는 이 후보자의 인사청문회를 열기 위해 전체회의를 열었으나 자료 제출 미비 등을 이유로 청문회를 열지 못하고 파행했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheong Wa Dae has maintained its position that it will provide the nominee with an opportunity to directly address suspicions against her through the hearing, observe the public's response accordingly, and then decide on the appointment. If the hearing cannot proceed normally due to opposition from the minority party, Cheong Wa Dae is expected to request the National Assembly to resubmit a report on the progress of the confirmation hearing, rather than forcefully proceeding with the appointment. (청와대는 청문회를 통해 이 후보자가 직접 본인의 의혹을 해명할 수 있도록 기회를 주고, 그에 따른 국민 반응을 지켜본 뒤 임명 여부를 결정하겠다는 입장을 밝혀왔다. 만약 야당의 거부로 청문회가 정상적으로 진행되지 못할 경우, 청와대는 이 후보자 임명을 강행하는 대신 국회에 인사청문회 경과보고서 재송부를 요청할 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Koh Kyung-joo &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240619.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0120/1617688733248803.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoo Seung-min meets fasting Jang Dong-hyeok... On rumors of running for Gyeonggi governor, says "It is not appropriate" (‘단식’ 장동혁 만난 유승민…경기지사 출마설엔 “적절치 않아”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240623.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Yoo Seung-min meets fasting Jang Dong-hyeok... On rumors of running for Gyeonggi governor, says "It is not appropriate" (‘단식’ 장동혁 만난 유승민…경기지사 출마설엔 “적절치 않아”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501208.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당에 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 엿새째 단식 농성 중인 국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 20일 국회 로텐더홀 단식 농성장을 찾은 유승민 전 의원과 대화하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former People Power Party lawmaker Yoo Seung-min visited People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok on the 20th to encourage him on his sixth day of a hunger strike. (유승민 전 국민의힘 의원이 20일 단식 농성 6일째인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 격려차 방문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After meeting with Leader Jang, who is on a hunger strike at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall, former lawmaker Yoo met with reporters and said, "I heard that Leader Jang is having a very hard time, and I was worried, so I came (to the hunger strike site)." He added, "I hope he can end his fast quickly and that he does not harm his health." Leader Jang is continuing his fast for the sixth day today, demanding the ruling party accept a special investigation into the Unification Church and nomination bribes. (유 전 의원은 이날 국회 로텐더홀에서 단식 농성 중인 장 대표를 만난 뒤 기자들과 만나 “장 대표께서 많이 힘들어한다는 얘기를 듣고 걱정돼서 (단식 농성장에) 왔다”며 “빨리 단식을 끝낼 수 있게 되면 좋겠고 건강을 해치지 않았으면 좋겠다”고 말했다. 장 대표는 여당에 통일교·공천헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 이날로 엿새째 단식을 이어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time former lawmaker Yoo has met with Leader Jang since he took office. He has strongly criticized the party multiple times, saying it is on a "path to ruin" and a "path to extinction," for denying the December 3 rebellion incident and opposing the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol. (유 전 의원이 장 대표를 만난 건 장 대표 취임 이후 처음이다. 그는 12·3 내란 사태 이후 국민의힘이 이를 부정하고 윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵에 반대하는 태도를 보이고 있는 것을 비판하며 당이 “망하는 길” “소멸 테크”로 가고 있다고 여러 차례 강하게 비판한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that former lawmaker Yoo visited Leader Jang in this situation, there is talk that he may be seeking reconciliation with the party ahead of the June 3 local elections. Regarding this, when asked by reporters about the possibility of running for Gyeonggi governor, he said, "As I said, I am not considering it at all," and "It is not appropriate to discuss such matters today." (유 전 의원이 이런 상황에서 장 대표를 찾자, 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 당과 화해에 나선 것이 아니냐는 얘기가 나왔다. 그는 이와 관련해 경기도지사 출마 가능성을 묻는 기자들의 질문에 “말씀드린 대로 전혀 생각하고 있지 않다”며 “그런 말씀을 오늘 드리는 건 적절치 않다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Yoo emphasized, "The most sincere thing our party must do now is to rebuild conservatism by gaining the trust and support of the people," and added, "Even if we have different thoughts on some issues, we must find solutions that can transform us into a conservatism the people can trust." He continued, "Only by restoring the people's trust and support can we stand as an alternative that can stop the current administration's misgovernment and recklessness and give hope to the people." (유 전 의원은 그러면서 “지금 우리 당이 가장 성실하게 해야 할 일은 국민의 신뢰와 지지를 받아 보수를 재건하는 것”이라며 “일부 문제에 있어 생각이 달라도 국민이 신뢰할 수 있는 보수로 거듭날 수 있는 해결책을 찾아야 한다”고 강조했다. 이어 “우리가 국민의 신뢰와 지지를 회복해야 정권의 실정과 폭주를 막아내고 국민께 희망을 드릴 수 있는 대안으로서 설 수 있다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also said, "I told the leader to get checked properly so as not to harm his health and not to be stubborn. I hope he does not harm his health and returns to play a central role in the party well." (그는 또 “대표께서 건강을 해치지 않도록 잘 점검하고 고집부리지 말라고 말씀드렸다. 건강 해치지 않고 다시 당의 중심으로 역할 잘 해주셨으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about his views on the internal party strife sparked by the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon, former lawmaker Yoo said, "We may have different thoughts and may disagree on some issues," and added, "Even if our methods or expressions have been different so far, a far more important issue is whether the party can gain the people's trust and support." (유 전 의원은 한동훈 전 대표 제명 사태로 불거진 당 내홍 사태에 대한 견해를 묻자 “서로 생각이 다르고 일부 문제에 생각이 다를 수 있다”며 “그동안 방식이나 표현이 달랐다고 하더라도 훨씬 더 중요한 문제는 당이 국민 신뢰와 지지받을 수 있느냐”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240623.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501208.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Drone Infiltration, Firing a Gun at North Korea... How Could Civilians Even Imagine Such a Thing?" (이 대통령 “무인기 침투, 북한에 총 쏜 것…민간인이 이런 상상 할 수 있나”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240628.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Drone Infiltration, Firing a Gun at North Korea... How Could Civilians Even Imagine Such a Thing?" (이 대통령 “무인기 침투, 북한에 총 쏜 것…민간인이 이런 상상 할 수 있나”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688741049852_20260120501253.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 19일 청와대 본관에서 열린 한-이탈리아 공식오찬에서 인사말을 하고 있다. 김태형 기자 xogud555@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung, regarding civilians sending drones to North Korea, stated, "We must conduct a thorough investigation and impose strict sanctions to prevent such acts from happening again." (이재명 대통령이 민간인이 북한에 무인기를 날려 보낸 것과 관련해 “철저하게 수사해 다시는 이런 짓을 못하게 엄중하게 제재해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a cabinet meeting on the 20th, President Lee said, "It is unthinkable for civilians to infiltrate drones into North Korean territory for illegal purposes," adding, "I am suspicious of how civilians could even imagine such a thing." He continued, "We need to investigate, but there is also speculation that state agencies are involved. It's essentially like firing a gun at North Korea on a whim; I don't understand how they could be so bold." Two civilians, suspected of manufacturing and sending drones to North Korea, were found to have worked at the presidential office during the Yoon Suk-yeol administration. Furthermore, suspicions have been raised that they received support from the military intelligence agency, the Defense Intelligence Command, prompting military authorities to verify the facts. (이 대통령은 20일 국무회의에서 “불법적 목적으로 민간인이 북한 지역에 무인기를 침투시키는 것은 있을 수 없는 일”이라며 “어떻게 민간인이 이런 상상을 할 수 있는지 의심스럽다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “수사를 해봐야겠지만 국가기관이 연관돼 있다는 설도 있다”며 “멋대로 북한에 총을 쏜 거나 마찬가진데, 이걸 어떻게 과감하게 할 수 있는지 이해가 안 간다”고 말했다. 무인기를 제작하고, 북한에 보낸 혐의를 받는 민간인 2명은 윤석열 정부 대통령실에서 근무한 것으로 드러났다. 또 이들이 군 정보기관인 국군정보사령부(정보사)의 지원을 받았다는 의혹이 제기돼 군 당국이 사실 확인에 나섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also addressed the Ministry of National Defense, saying, "Given the development of our defense capabilities, can't we detect drones going back and forth (to the North)? It's said (the graduate student in question) sent drones to North Korea three times; how is it that they couldn't be detected at guard posts? This suggests there's a hole somewhere." (이 대통령은 또 국방부를 향해 “국방 역량이 발전된 상황에서 무인기가 (북으로) 왔다갔다 하는 걸 체크 못 하느냐. (해당 대학원생이 북한으로 무인기를) 세 번 보냈다는데 어떻게 경계 근무하는 데서 체크도 못 하냐”며 “뭔가 구멍이 났다는 얘기”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Defense Minister An Kyung-baek said, "We are checking with local air defense radar, and we are investigating even if only a faint dot appears." (이에 안규백 국방부 장관은 “국지방공 레이더로 체크하는데, 미세한 점만 보인다고 해서 조사를 하는 중”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "It's said we tracked some during the North Korean drone infiltration, but there is a suspicious aspect that we couldn't track the ones going to North Korea. If necessary, we should improve our equipment." He added, "If unnecessary tensions rise and a confrontational atmosphere is created between the two Koreas due to such incidents, it will negatively impact the economy as well. I hope we manage this well so that trust between the two Koreas is not broken and hostile sentiments are not reignited. I also hope the investigative agencies conduct a swift investigation to ensure such incidents do not happen again." (이 대통령은 “북한 무인기 침투 때도 일부는 추적했다고 하는데, (왜) 북한으로 간 건 추적 못 하느냐 의심받는 측면이 있다”며 “필요하면 장비개선을 하든지 해야 한다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “이런 걸로 불필요하게 긴장 고조되고, 남북 간 대결 분위기가 조성되면 경제에도 악영향을 미친다”며 “남북 사이에 이런 신뢰가 깨지지 않게 적대 감정이 재고되지 않게 잘 관리하길 바란다. 수사기관도 신속 조사해 다시는 이런 일이 생기지 않으면 좋겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240628.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688741049852_20260120501253.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Please Come to Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site"... People Power Party 'Pleading' to the Blue House and Democratic Party (“장동혁 단식농성장 와달라”…청와대·민주당에 ‘읍소’하는 국힘)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240633.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Please Come to Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site"... People Power Party 'Pleading' to the Blue House and Democratic Party (“장동혁 단식농성장 와달라”…청와대·민주당에 ‘읍소’하는 국힘)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501329.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;엿새째 단식 농성 중인 국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 20일 국회 로텐더홀 단식 농성장에 마련한 텐트에서 일어나고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"It's the sixth day of the hunger strike. The Democratic Party hasn't budged an inch." (Jang Dong-hyeok, People Power Party leader), "The first move of the Blue House's Senior Secretary for Political Affairs should be a visit to the hunger strike site." (Song Eon-seok, People Power Party floor leader) "It's right for the President to at least send the Senior Secretary for Political Affairs to console and show concern." (Kang Myeong-gu, People Power Party lawmaker) (“단식 엿새째. 민주당은 미동도 없다.”(장동혁 국민의힘 대표), “청와대 정무수석 첫 행보는 단식농성장 방문이어야 한다.”(송언석 국민의힘 원내대표) “대통령이 정무수석이라도 보내서 위로하고 걱정을 하는 게 맞다.”(강명구 국민의힘 의원))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere is shifting from criticism of the ruling camp to 'pleading'. The point is why the Blue House and the ruling party are showing no response while the leader of the main opposition party is on his sixth day of a hunger strike. (여권에 대한 비판이 ‘읍소’로 바뀌는 분위기다. 제1 야당 대표가 엿새째 단식 중인데 청와대와 여당이 왜 아무런 반응을 보이지 않느냐는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on a hunger strike demanding a special investigation into the Unification Church and nomination bribes, posted a handwritten message on Facebook on the 20th. He wrote that the fact the Democratic Party is not reacting while he is on his sixth day of fasting is "an admission that there is corruption significant enough to shake the administration." While he showed resolve by stating "The people's special investigation has already begun," it can also be interpreted as revealing his frustration over the Democratic Party's lack of response. (통일교·공천헌금 특검 수사를 주장하며 단식 중인 장동혁 대표는 20일 페이스북에 손글씨 메시지를 올렸다. 자신이 6일째 단식을 하는데 더불어민주당이 아무 반응을 하지 않는 것은 “정권이 흔들릴 정도의 부패가 있다는 것을 자백하는 것”이라는 내용이다. “국민의 특검은 이미 시작됐다”며 결기를 드러냈지만, 해석하기에 따라서는 민주당 무반응에 대한 답답한 속내가 읽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the hunger strike started abruptly without an exit strategy, the People Power Party leadership has also begun emphasizing political propriety. They are calling for Hong Ik-pyo, the newly appointed Senior Secretary for Political Affairs to the President who began his term that day, to visit Leader Jang while making courtesy calls at the National Assembly. Floor leader Song Eon-seok said at a party meeting held that morning, "I hope the new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs seriously recognizes the life-risking hunger strike struggle of the main opposition party leader. I look forward to meeting Senior Secretary Hong at the hunger strike site." He added rare praise, saying, "As he is known to be a reasonable person, we expect him to play a positive role in communication with the opposition party." (출구 전략 없이 덜컥 시작한 단식에 국민의힘 지도부도 정치적 도의를 강조하기 시작했다. 때마침 이날 임기를 시작한 신임 홍익표 대통령실 정무수석이 국회를 돌며 인사를 할 때 장 대표를 찾아가 달라는 것이다. 송언석 원내대표는 이날 아침 열린 원내대책회의에서 “신임 정무수석은 제1 야당 대표의 목숨을 건 단식 투쟁을 심각하게 인식하기 바란다. 홍 수석을 단식농성장에서 만날 수 있게 되길 기대한다”고 했다. “평소 합리적인 분으로 정평이 나 있는 만큼 야당과의 소통에도 긍정적 역할을 기대한다”는 근래 보기 힘든 칭찬도 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Kang Myeong-gu, appearing on Channel A radio's 'Political Signal' that day, assessed that "the entire opposition camp is uniting" around Leader Jang's hunger strike, but also directed remarks at Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae, saying, "It's right to be concerned out of human decency and to come (to the hunger strike site) to console and encourage." He also said to President Lee Jae-myung, "It's right to at least send the Senior Secretary for Political Affairs." Lawmaker Kang said, "Not even President's Special Advisor for Political Affairs Cho Jung-sik has visited once. He hasn't even offered words of consolation. This is unprecedented in our political history. It's not too late even now. Please come directly, listen to the opposition leader, and convey it to President Lee Jae-myung." Lawmaker Kang served as the Presidential Secretary for State Planning at the Yoon Suk Yeol presidential office in September 2023, when President Lee Jae-myung, then Democratic Party leader, was on a 24-day hunger strike. (강명구 의원은 이날 채널에이(A) 라디오 ‘정치시그널’에 출연해 장 대표의 단식을 계기로 “야권 전체가 결집하고 있다”고 평가하면서도, 정청래 더불어민주당 대표를 향해 “인간적 도리로 걱정하고, (단식농성장에) 와서 위로하고 격려를 하는 게 맞다”고 했다. 이재명 대통령을 향해서도 “정무수석이라도 보내는 게 맞다”고 했다. 강 의원은 “조정식 대통령 정무특보도 한 번 찾아오지도 않는다. 위로의 말을 건네지도 않는다. 우리 정치 역사에 없었던 일이다. 지금이라도 늦지 않았다. 직접 와서 야당 대표 얘기를 듣고 이재명 대통령에게 전달해달라”고 했다. 강 의원은 이재명 대통령이 민주당 대표로 24일간 단식을 했을 때인 2023년 9월 윤석열 대통령실에서 국정기획비서관을 지냈다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Leader Jang's health condition deteriorates rapidly, the possibility of suspending the hunger strike in the near future is being raised. Within the People Power Party, there is some self-assessment that there has been a degree of success, such as rallying party strength divided by the Han Dong-hoon expulsion incident and uniting the opposition camp ahead of local elections. However, there is also much cold criticism that there has never been a case where public interest in a main opposition leader's hunger strike was as low as this time. The fact that the hunger strike began right after Han Dong-hoon's expulsion is also a reason for the cold criticism labeling it a 'hunger strike for internal party consumption'. (장 대표의 건강 상태가 급격히 나빠지면서, 조만간 단식농성 중단 가능성도 제기된다. 국민의힘에서는 한동훈 제명 사태로 갈라진 당력을 모으고, 지방선거를 대비한 야권이 결집하는 등 일정 정도 성과가 있다는 자평도 나온다. 다만 제1 야당 대표의 단식농성에 대한 여론의 관심이 이번처럼 적은 사례는 없었다는 박한 평가도 많다. 단식 돌입 시점이 한동훈 제명 직후라는 점도 ‘당 내부용 단식’이라는 싸늘한 비판을 사는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, some within the People Power Party had also requested that former leader Han Dong-hoon, who was expelled over the party member bulletin board incident, visit Leader Jang's hunger strike site. The political calculation was that even if the party member bulletin board incident could be temporarily papered over through a scene of the two joining hands, it would provide a justification to stop the hunger strike, which has found no exit. (앞서 국민의힘 일부에서는 당원게시판 사태로 제명 결정이 내려진 한동훈 전 대표에게 장 대표 단식농성장을 찾아가 달라는 주문을 하기도 했다. 두 사람이 손을 잡는 장면을 통해 당원게시판 사태를 일단 봉합만 할 수 있어도, 출구를 찾지 못하는 단식을 중단할 명분이 된다는 정치적 계산이 깔렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240633.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501329.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's Another Reproach: "Unconditionally Taking the Prosecution's Side on Specific Cases... Public Broadcasters and General Programming Channels Must Maintain Neutrality" [Video] (이 대통령 또 핀잔 “특정 사안 무조건 검찰 편…종편 중립성 지켜야” [영상])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240643.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/836/502/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688763815523_20260120501512.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 20일 청와대 본관에서 열린 국무회의에서 모두발언을 하고 있다. 청와대사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, President Lee Jae-myung said, "In specific cases, (some media) unconditionally take the prosecution's side," adding that areas receiving (licensing) privileges, such as public broadcasters or general programming channels (GPCs), "must maintain neutrality and public interest." (이재명 대통령이 20일 “특정 사안의 경우 무조건 검찰 편을 든다”며 공중파나 종합편성채널(종편) 등 “(허가) 특혜를 받는 영역은 중립성과 공익성을 지켜야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a cabinet meeting that day, President Lee said, "I won't name names, but for example, when a court issues a not guilty verdict or dismisses a case, saying the prosecution's indictment was unreasonably wrong, it is common to respect the court's ruling and criticize the (prosecution's) indictment as being excessive. However, in specific cases, (some) unconditionally take the prosecution's side." He continued, "While one can criticize that the court was wrong and the prosecution's indictment was correct," he added, "the nuance that the court was wrong and the prosecution was right seems to occur only in political cases. Isn't there a problem with neutrality or public interest?" (이 대통령은 이날 국무회의에서 “어디라고 말을 안 하겠는데, 예를 들어 법원이 (검찰의) 무리한 잘못된 기소라고 무죄를 내리거나 공소기각하면 보통은 법원 판결을 존중하고, (검찰) 기소가 무리했다고 비판하는데, 특정 사안의 경우 무조건 검찰 편을 든다”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “(검찰의) 기소가 잘됐는데, 법원이 잘못했다고 비판을 할 수 있다”면서도 “법원이 잘못했다, 검찰이 잘했다는 뉘앙스는 꼭 정치적 사건에서만 그렇다. 중립성이나 공익성에 문제가 없냐”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This appears to be pointing out problems with the reporting stance of some media outlets regarding recent events such as the abandonment of an appeal in the 'Daejang-dong development corruption' case and the partial appeal in the 'West Sea official shooting' case. Previously, on the 7th, President Lee had also said, "When a court rules that the prosecution's indictment was wrong, we typically criticize the prosecution for wrongful indictment. But strangely, when Lee Jae-myung or the Democratic Party is involved, (some) defend the prosecution, saying the court's judgment was wrong." (이는 최근 ‘대장동 개발 비리’ 사건 항소 포기와 ‘서해 공무원 피격’ 사건 부분 항소 등과 관련한 일부 언론의 보도 태도를 문제 삼는 것으로 보인다. 앞서 이 대통령은 지난 7일에도 “검찰의 기소가 잘못됐다고 법원이 판결하면 우리는 통상적으로는 잘못 기소한 검찰을 비판하면서, 희한하게 이재명이나 민주당이 관계되면 법원 판단이 잘못됐다고 검찰을 두둔한다”고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That day, Kim Jong-cheol, Chairman of the Korea Communications Commission (KCC), said, "The Broadcasting Act stipulates public responsibility obligations," but added, "There are limitations for the state to uniformly judge aspects related to the direction of the press, such as neutrality. Regarding content regulation, in the case of broadcasting, there is a private independent organization called the Deliberation Committee." President Lee emphasized, "It is natural to conduct reviews as neutrally as possible, but we must have a sense of awareness about these issues." (이날 김종철 방송미디어통신위원회(방미통위) 위원장은 “방송법에는 공적 책임 의무가 있다”면서도 “언론의 방향에 대한 부분은 국가가 중립성 이런 부분을 일률적으로 판단하는데 제약이 있다. 내용 규제 관련해선 방송의 경우 심의위원회라는 민간 독립기구를 두고 있다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 “어떻게 심사할지는 최대한 중립적으로 하는 건 당연한데, 이런 데 대한 문제 의식을 가져야 한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a KCC work report last month on the 12th, President Lee mentioned the bias of general programming channels, saying, "There are quite a few cases where one wonders if it's broadcasting or a biased YouTube channel." (이 대통령은 지난달 12일 방미통위 업무보고에서 종편의 편향성을 언급하며 “방송인지, 편파 유튜브인지 그런 의심이 되는 경우가 꽤 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240643.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/836/502/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688763815523_20260120501512.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoon Suk-yeol's Hastily Established Drone Command Mobilized for Rebellion... Defense Ministry Advisory Committee 'Recommends Abolition' (윤석열이 급조해 내란 동원한 드론사령부…국방부 자문위 ‘폐지 권고’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240646.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/305/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501555.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2023년 9월1일 오후 경기도 포천시 옛 6군단 인근 15항공단 군 비행장에서 열린 드론작전사령부창설식에서 참석자들이 기념 촬영을 하고 있다. 합동참모본부 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Future Strategy Subcommittee of the Defense Ministry's 'Civil-Military Joint Special Advisory Committee for Overcoming Rebellion and Designing Future Defense' has recommended to the Defense Minister a plan to abolish the Drone Operations Command (Drone Command) established during the Yoon Suk-yeol administration. (국방부 ‘내란극복·미래국방 설계를 위한 민관군 합동 특별자문위원회’ 미래전략 분과위원회(미래전략 분과위)가 윤석열 정부 때 만들어진 드론작전사령부(드론사)를 폐지하는 방안을 국방부 장관에게 권고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Future Strategy Subcommittee concluded discussions on advisory proposals for military structural reorganization through ten meetings held from September to December last year and announced the activity results containing these contents on the 20th. (미래전략 분과위는 지난해 9~12월 10차례 회의를 통해 군 구조 개편 자문안에 대한 논의를 마무리하고 20일 이런 내용이 담긴 활동 결과를 발표했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding command and unit structure reorganization, the subcommittee recommended abolishing the Drone Command organization, considering inefficiencies due to functional overlap with each military service, and comprehensively promoting drone combat development plans. This follows criticism that after the Drone Command was established (in September 2023) following North Korean UAV intrusions into the capital region airspace in 2022, deploying drones used by existing frontline combat units to the Drone Command, which was created to conduct strategic-level activities, led to overlaps in equipment and missions with existing units. (분과위는 지휘·부대구조 개편과 관련해 드론사는 각 군과의 기능 중복에 따른 비효율 등을 고려하여 조직을 폐지하고 드론 전투발전 방안을 통합적으로 추진할 것을 권고했다. 2022년 북한 무인기의 수도권 영공 침범 이후 드론사를 창설(2023년 9월)했는데, 전략 수준의 활동을 하겠다고 만든 드론사에 기존 일선 전투부대에서 사용하는 드론을 배치하면서 기존 부대와 장비·임무가 겹친다는 지적이 나온 데 따른 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the Drone Command's launch, issues such as airspace control problems and the dualization of missions between the Drone Command and various units raised inefficiencies and redundancies rather than advantages of integrated operation. Although these problems were raised within the military during the Drone Command's preparation stage, the Yoon Suk-yeol administration hastily established it. This Drone Command was mobilized for a Pyongyang drone infiltration operation in October 2024 with the purpose of creating a pretext for declaring a state of emergency. (드론사 출범 이후 공역 통제의 문제, 드론사와 각급 부대로 임무의 이원화 등 통합 운용의 장점보다는 중북의 비효율성이 제기됐다. 이런 문제들은 드론사 창설 준비 단계에서 군 내부에서 제기됐지만 윤석열 정부는 서둘러 드론사를 창설했다. 이렇게 창설된 드론사는 2024년 10월 비상계엄 선포 명문을 만들 목적으로 평양 무인기 침투 작전에 동원됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The subcommittee also recommended that the Strategic Command re-establish its role and mission as a unit ensuring strategic autonomy. Even before its establishment, the Strategic Command faced criticism as an 'unnecessary addition' due to command system confusion with the Joint Chiefs of Staff and mission overlap with major units of each service, but the Yoon Suk-yeol administration pushed ahead with its creation, citing the need to counter the North Korean nuclear threat. (분과위는 또 전략사령부(전략사)는 전략적 자율성을 보장하는 부대로서 역할과 임무를 재정립하라고 권고했다. 전략사는 창설 이전부터 합동참모본부와의 지휘체계 혼선, 각군 주요 부대와의 임무 중복 등으로 ‘옥상옥‘이란 지적을 받았지만 윤석열 정부는 북핵 위협에 맞서야 한다며 창설을 강행했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, to prepare for the transfer of wartime operational control (OPCON) and enhance the unity of the command structure and the completeness of wartime/peacetime operational command, it proposed establishing a Joint Operations Command. It suggested adjusting the Joint Chiefs of Staff to transfer operational functions to the Joint Operations Command and take on responsibilities for strategic situation assessment, military strategy formulation, and military force building. Considering the space security situation and future warfare aspects, it also recommended the necessity of establishing a Space Command. (아울러 전시작전통제권 전환에 대비해 지휘구조 단일화와 전·평시 작전 지휘의 완결성 제고를 위해 합동작전사령부를 창설하며, 합동참모본부는 작전 기능을 합동작전사령부에 이양하고 전략상황 평가와 군사전략 수립, 군사력 건설을 담당하는 임무를 맡도록 조정안을 제시했다. 우주 안보 상황과 미래전 양상을 고려해 우주사령부 창설의 필요성도 권고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding personnel structure reorganization, it proposed a direction to simultaneously ensure the stability and professionalism of combat power through the organic combination of officers, specialist soldiers, and civilian personnel. For utilizing civilian resources, it stated it is desirable to start by utilizing defense civilian personnel like public servants and private companies in non-combat fields such as cooking, transportation, facilities, and administration, and gradually expand to some combat support areas. (인력구조 개편과 관련해서는 간부·전문병·민간인력의 유기적인 결합을 통해 전투력의 안전성과 전문성을 동시에 확보할 수 있는 방향을 제시했다. 민간자원 활용은 우선 취사·수송·시설·행정 등 비전투 분야에 군무원 등 국방 민간인력과 민간기업을 활용하는 것을 시작으로, 일부 전투지원 영역까지 확대해 나가는 것이 바람직하다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Considering the population in the 2040s for troop supply and the personnel demands required by the reorganized military structure, the subcommittee proposed a total defense manpower level of 500,000, including 350,000 active-duty troops and 150,000 civilian defense personnel such as public servants and specialist reservists. (분과위는 2040년대 인구를 고려한 병력 공급과 개편된 군 구조에 요구되는 병력 수요를 고려해 상비병력 35만명, 군무원과 전문예비군 등 민간 국방인력 15만명을 포함해 총 50만명 규모의 국방인력 수준을 제시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The activity results of the Constitutional Values Establishment Subcommittee of the Civil-Military Joint Special Advisory Committee were also made public on this day. The Constitutional Values Subcommittee discussed five agenda items: revising laws related to establishing constitutional values within the military, improving related laws/systems to prevent illegal martial law, operational plans for civilian control in the military, strengthening education for protecting constitutional values, and plans to establish an independent and fair military judicial system. (민관군 합동 특별자문 위원회 헌법가치 정착 분과위원회(헌법가치 분과위) 활동 결과도 이날 공개됐다. 헌법가치 정착 분과위는 군 내 헌법가치 정착과 관련한 법령 개정, 불법계엄 방지를 위한 관련 법령·제도 개선, 군에서의 문민통제 운영방안, 헌법가치 수호를 위한 교육 강화, 독립적이고 공정한 군 사법체계 구축방안 등 5가지 안건을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding establishing constitutional values within the military, it reviewed the necessity of amending the 'Basic Act on Military Service'. Specifically, it recommended explicitly stipulating the right to refuse illegal orders while providing specific criteria so that subjects of the law can judge what constitutes an illegal order, and establishing immunity provisions to ensure those who refuse illegal orders are not punished under the Military Criminal Act for crimes like insubordination. (군 내 헌법가치 정착과 관련해 ‘군인복무기본법’ 개정 필요성을 검토했다. 구체적으로 위법한 명령에 대한 거부권을 명시함과 동시에 수범자(법령, 법규범을 적용받는 대상)가 위법한 명령이 무엇인지 판단할 수 있도록 구체적 기준을 제시하고, 위법한 명령을 거부한 자는 군형법상 항명죄 등으로 처벌받지 않게끔 면책 규정을 두도록 권고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding strengthening education for protecting constitutional values, it suggested restructuring much of the military's internal education based on constitutional values to expand constitutional education opportunities, implementing participatory education rather than rote learning, and significantly strengthening education for field-grade/senior officers and commanders. It particularly recommended newly establishing a clause obligating commanders to swear an oath to protect and abide by the Constitution upon assuming command. (헌법가치 수호를 위한 교육 강화와 관련해서는 다수의 군 내 교육을 헌법가치를 기준으로 구조조정해 헌법교육 기회를 확대하고, 주입식 교육이 아닌 참여형 교육을 실시하며, 영관급·장성급 장교와 지휘관에 대한 교육을 대폭 강화하라고 제언했다. 특히 지휘관 취임 시 헌법을 수호하고 준수한다는 내용을 선서하도록 의무를 지우는 조항을 신설하도록 권고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding operational plans for civilian control in the military, it proposed establishing the concept of 'control by the people' instead of 'civilian control', meaning that in a democratic republic where the people are sovereign, elected power should be able to control the military according to law and procedures. (군에서의 문민통제 운영 방안과 관련해서는 국민이 주권자인 민주공화국이라면 선출된 권력이 법과 절차에 따라 군을 통제할 수 있어야 한다는 의미에서 문민통제 대신 ‘국민의 통제’ 개념을 정립할 것을 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kwon Hyuk-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:nura@hani.co.kr"&gt;nura@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (권혁철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nura@hani.co.kr"&gt;nura@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240646.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/305/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501555.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:14:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Let's Elevate the Level"... President Lee Says "Korea-China Preservation Agreement Needed" for Shanghai Provisional Government Building (“격 올리자”…이 대통령, 상하이 임정 청사에 “한-중 보전협약 필요”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240648.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501579.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 20th that relying solely on China's goodwill regarding "the Provisional Government building or independence heritage sites in China, which are truly precious assets as government cultural heritage, is problematic," and that a Korea-China preservation agreement is necessary. (이재명 대통령이 20일 중국에 있는 “임시정부 청사나 독립 유적지는 정부 문화유산으로 정말 소중한 자산인데 (중국의) 호의에만 기대는 건 문제가 있다”며 한중 간 보전 협약이 필요하다고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a State Council meeting that day, President Lee stated, "Among the anti-Japanese movement sites in China, this is the most symbolic location," and added, "Shouldn't the Ministry of Foreign Affairs establish a preservation agreement or understanding between Korea and China?" He continued, "Didn't China previously not agree to a comprehensive survey of anti-Japanese heritage sites? We need to create a system to make this official and elevate the level to ensure sustainability." (이 대통령은 이날 국무회의에서 “중국에 있는 항일운동 장소 중 여기가 제일 상징적 장소”라며 “외교부가 한중 간 보전 협약이나 양해를 해놔야 하지 않겠느냐”고 말했다. 이어 이 대통령은 “중국은 항일 유적지 전수조사도 이전엔 동의 안 한 거 아니냐”며 “공식적으로 할 수 있게 제도를 만들고 지속성이 있도록 격을 올려야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during the Korea-China summit on the 5th of last month, the two countries agreed to strengthen the protection of independence historical sites within China and solidify the historical foundation for friendly sentiments between the peoples of both nations, marking the 100th anniversary of the Shanghai Provisional Government building this year. President Lee's remarks that day were intended to emphasize that regarding the protection of independence historical sites, rather than relying solely on China's goodwill, it should be institutionalized through agreements and other means. (앞서 지난 5일 한-중 정상회담을 통해 양국은 올해 상해 임시정부 청사 100주년을 맞아 중국 내 독립사적지 보호를 강화하고, 양 국민 간 우호 정서에 역사적 기반을 굳건히 하기로 한 바 있다. 이 대통령의 이날 발언은 독립사적지 보호와 관련해 중국의 선의에만 기댈 게 아니라 협약 등을 통해 이를 제도화해야 한다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240648.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120501579.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:14:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Second Comprehensive Special Prosecution Bill Passes Cabinet Meeting... 'Roh Sang-won's Notebook' to Be Re-examined (2차 종합특검법 국무회의 통과…‘노상원 수첩’ 다시 캔다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240672.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0120/6117688856591074.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 청와대통신사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second comprehensive special prosecution bill, aimed at investigating unresolved aspects and new suspicions related to the three major special prosecutions (sedition, Kim Keon-hee, and Corporal Chae), passed the Cabinet meeting on the 20th. This comes just four days after it passed the plenary session of the National Assembly, led by the ruling party, on the 16th. (3대 특검(내란·김건희·채 상병 특검)의 미진한 부분과 새로운 의혹을 수사하기 위한 2차 종합특검법이 20일 국무회의를 통과했다. 지난 16일 여당 주도로 국회 본회의를 통과한 지 나흘 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Cabinet meeting presided over by President Lee Jae-myung at the Blue House that day, the government deliberated and decided on five bills for promulgation including the second comprehensive special prosecution bill, nine legislative bills, 13 presidential decrees, and three general agenda items. (정부는 이날 이재명 대통령 주재로 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 2차 종합특검법을 포함한 법률공포안 5건과 법률안 9건, 대통령령안 13건, 일반안건 3건 등을 심의·의결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investigation targets of the second comprehensive special prosecution bill consist of a total of 17 items, including suspicions related to 'Roh Sang-won's notebook' that were not covered in the previous three major special prosecutions. It will also investigate allegations of sedition and foreign exchange/military rebellion by former President Yoon Suk-yeol, as well as various suspicions of election and power interference surrounding the former president and his wife. (2차 종합특검법의 수사 대상은 앞서 3대 특검에서 다루지 못했던 ‘노상원 수첩’ 관련 의혹 등 총 17가지다. 윤석열 전 대통령의 내란 및 외환·군사 반란 혐의와 윤 전 대통령 부부를 둘러싼 각종 선거·권력 개입 의혹 등도 수사한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investigation period is up to 170 days, including a 20-day preparation period, with a maximum investigation personnel of 251. Accordingly, the special prosecution political situation is expected to continue until the local elections in June. (수사 기간은 수사 준비 20일을 포함해 최장 170일이며, 수사 인력은 최대 251명이다. 이에 따라 6월 지방선거 때까지 특검 정국이 이어질 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also decided that day was the bill for promulgation of the revised law concerning the investigation of aviation and railway accidents, which elevates the Aviation and Railway Accident Investigation Board from under the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport to under the Prime Minister. This revision was made in response to criticism that when the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport could be a party involved in an accident, having an institution under its jurisdiction conduct the investigation could not guarantee independence and objectivity. (또 이날 항공철도사고조사위원회를 국토교통부 소속에서 국무총리 소속으로 격상한 항공철도사고조사에 관한 법률 개정안 공포안도 의결됐다. 해당 법안은 국토부가 사고 이해 당사자일 수 있는 상황에서 국토부 소속 기관이 조사를 맡으면 독립성과 객관성을 담보할 수 없다는 지적이 제기되면서 개정됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An agenda item containing regulations related to the establishment and operation of the Basic Society Committee was also deliberated. The Basic Society Committee, a presidential advisory committee, aims to realize a 'basic society' that guarantees a basic life for all people, enabling stable living and diverse opportunities. It will serve as a policy control tower, overseeing, coordinating, and supporting related policies being promoted by various ministries. (아울러 기본사회위원회의 설치·운영 관련 규정을 담은 안건도 심의됐다. 대통령 소속 자문위원회인 기본사회위원회는 모든 사람에게 기본적인 삶을 보장해 안정적인 생활과 다양한 기회를 누리도록 하는 ‘기본사회’ 실현을 목표로, 여러 부처에서 추진 중인 관련 정책을 총괄·조정·지원하는 정책 콘트롤타워 역할을 하게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240672.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0120/6117688856591074.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:13:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party's Kim Min-soo says, "'Han Dong-hoon party incident,' open verification... If it's manipulation, I will resign from Supreme Council membership" (국힘 김민수 “‘한동훈 당게 사건’, 공개검증을…조작이면 최고위원직 사퇴”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240679.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/638/383/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688870509728_20260120502192.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김민수 국민의힘 최고위원이 2025년 10월 국회 최고위원회의에서 발언하고 있다. 국민의힘TV 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Min-soo, a Supreme Council member of the People Power Party, said on the 20th, "If the investigation results of the People Power Party's internal audit committee (the so-called party member bulletin board incident) are manipulated, I will resign from my Supreme Council membership." He also asked, "(Former leader Han Dong-hoon, who raised the suspicion of manipulation) what will he stake?" (김민수 국민의힘 최고위원이 20일 “국민의힘 당무감사위원회의 (이른바 당원게시판 사건) 조사 결과가 조작이라면 최고위원직에서 사퇴하겠다”고 말했다. 그는 “(조작 의혹을 제기한) 한동훈 전 대표는 무엇을 걸겠느냐”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim appeared on a YouTube channel that day and said, "Former leader Han Dong-hoon is making remarks to the effect that our party's internal audit committee's investigation process is entirely fabricated and is demanding an apology," adding, "He now judges that our opposition party's internal audit committee's investigation and the ethics committee's decision are fabricated and that our party has engaged in such acts again." (김 최고위원은 이날 한 유튜브 채널에 나와 “한동훈 전 대표가 우리 당무감사위원회 조사 과정이 전체 조작이라는 취지의 발언을 하며 사과라고 하고 있다”며 “지금 우리 야당 당무감사위원회의 조사가, 윤리위원회의 결정이 조작이라고 하면서 또다시 우리 당에 해당행위를 한 것이라고 판단한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, former leader Han, on the 18th, apologized for the first time regarding the so-called party member bulletin board incident involving his family, while maintaining his existing position that "the disciplinary action against me is clear manipulation and political retaliation." (앞서 한 전 대표는 지난 18일 자신의 가족이 얽힌 이른바 당원게시판 사건과 관련해 처음으로 사과하면서도 “저에 대한 징계는 명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라는 기존 입장을 고수했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim continued, "If former leader Han Dong-hoon truly believes it is a manipulated investigation or manipulated results, I hope he will boldly undergo open verification before the public," and added, "A 10-day period for raising objections was given, so I hope he fully raises objections during that time. If he cannot do so, I hope he refrains from making remarks that disparage or belittle the party." (김 최고위원은 이어 “만약 한동훈 전 대표가 진정으로 조작 수사, 조작 결과라고 생각하면 당당하게 국민 앞에 공개 검증받길 바란다”며 “10일 간 이의제기 시간이 주어졌으므로 그 시간 동안 충분히 이의제기하길 바란다. 만약 그러지 못할 것이라면 당을 폄훼하거나 비하하는 발언을 삼가길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party's internal audit committee concluded at the end of last month that former leader Han's family was essentially involved in the party member bulletin board incident, and based on this investigation result, the party's central ethics committee decided on the 14th to 'expel' former leader Han. Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who must finalize the disciplinary decision, gave former leader Han a deadline to raise objections instead of immediately putting it to a vote at the Supreme Council meeting on the 15th. (당 당무감사위는 지난달 말 당원 게시판 사건과 관련해 사실상 한 전 대표 가족이 연루됐다고 결론 내렸고, 이 조사 결과를 받아든 당 중앙윤리위원회는 지난 14일 한 전 대표에 대해 ‘제명’을 결정했다. 징계를 최종 의결해야 하는 장동혁 대표는 지난 15일 곧바로 최고위원회에서 의결하는 대신 한 전 대표에게 이의 제기 기한을 준 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240679.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/638/383/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688870509728_20260120502192.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:13:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[News Dive] Shincheonji, Circumstances of '50,000 Party Members for People Power Party' ([뉴스 다이브] 신천지, ‘국힘에 5만 당원’ 정황)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240691.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120502542.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Featuring: Attorney Yang Ji-yeol, Current Affairs Commentator Park Young-sik, Broadcaster Oh Yun-hye, Attorney Shin In-gyu, Hankyoreh Editorial Chief Kwon Tae-ho; Host: Ko Hyun-joon. Shincheonji's 'Pilates' Operation... Circumstances of Mobilizing 50,000 Organized Party Members for People Power Party / Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Loses Both Justification and Persuasiveness / Na Kyung-won Ignores Court Ruling... Strongly Argues "Yoon Suk Yeol Investigation by Corruption Investigation Office is Illegal" / The Day After Death Penalty Sought for Yoon, Han Deok-su's 'Peaceful Daily Life' Outside Court / Han Deok-su's First Trial Sentencing for 'Aiding Rebellion' on 21st... Second After Yoon Suk Yeol / 'North Korea Infiltration Drone' Graduate Student, Behind the Scenes Military Intelligence Agency? / Democratic Party Hearing Debate Over Special Investigation and Prosecution Reform Bill. Please tune in for today's (January 20) News Dive. (출연: 양지열 변호사, 박영식 시사평론가, 오윤혜 방송인, 신인규 변호사, 권태호 한겨레 논설실장, 진행: 고현준. 신천지 ‘필라테스’ 작전... 국힘 당원 5만명 조직 동원 정황 / 명분도 설득력도 잃은 장동혁의 단식 / 나경원, 법원 판결 무시... “공수처 윤석열 수사는 위법” 강변 / 윤 사형 구형 다음 날, 법정 밖 한덕수의 ‘평온한 일상’ / ‘내란 방조’ 한덕수 21일 1심 선고... 윤석열 이어 두 번째 / ‘북 침투 무인기’ 대학원생 배후에 군 정보기관? / 중수청·공소청법 놓고 민주당 공청회 논쟁. 오늘 (1월 20일) 뉴스 다이브 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240691.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120502542.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:13:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dr. Kim Yu-geun, Who Provided 'Free Medical Care for Low-Income Americans,' Passes Away (‘미 저소득층 무료 진료’ 김유근 박사 별세)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/diplomacy/1240701.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/350/325/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120502894.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김유근 박사&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dr. Kim Yu-geun, who provided free medical care for uninsured low-income individuals for a long time in Knoxville, Tennessee, USA, passed away on the 16th (local time), according to announcements from the Knoxville Korean Association and others on the 18th. He was 81 years old. (미국 테네시주 녹스빌에서 오랜 기간 무보험 저소득층을 위해 무료 진료를 해온 김유근 박사가 지난 16일(현지시각) 별세했다고 녹스빌 한인회 등이 18일 전했다. 향년 81.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A graduate of Yonsei University College of Medicine who immigrated to the United States in 1961, the late Dr. Kim established the 'American Free Medical Clinic' in Knoxville in 1993 and dedicated himself to volunteer work. This free clinic expanded to four locations, benefiting over 70,000 low-income individuals without medical insurance. (연세대 의대를 나와 1961년 도미한 고인은 1993년 녹스빌에 ‘미국 무료 의료 진료소&amp;#x27;를 개설하고 자원봉사에 뛰어들었다. 이 무료 진료소는 4개로 늘었으며 의료보험이 없는 저소득층 7만여명이 혜택을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knoxville Mayor Indya Kincannon commemorated him, stating, "Dr. Kim's legacy of helping uninsured Tennessee residents receive treatment will endure for generations to come." (인디아 킨캐넌 녹스빌 시장은 “무보험 테네시 주민들이 치료받을 수 있도록 도운 김 박사의 유산은 앞으로 세대를 넘어 이어질 것”이라고 추모했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yonhap News, Reporter Kang Seong-man (연합뉴스, 강성만 기자)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/diplomacy/1240701.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/350/325/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120502894.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:13:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoo Si-min on President Lee's 'Nomination of Lee Hye-hoon': "Perhaps he became a bit lax while engrossed in other matters" (유시민 “이 대통령 ‘이혜훈 지명’, 다른 일 몰두하다 좀 느슨해진 것 아닌가”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240707.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688925496002_20260120503006.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;유튜브 ‘박주민티브이(TV)’ 영상 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Roh Moo-hyun Foundation Chairman Yoo Si-min commented on President Lee Jae-myung's nomination of Lee Hye-hoon as Minister of Planning and Budget, saying, "Perhaps (President Lee) became a bit lax while being too engrossed in other matters." (유시민 전 노무현재단 이사장이 이재명 대통령의 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 지명을 두고 “(이 대통령이) 너무 다른 일들에 몰두하다 보니까 좀 느슨해졌던 것이 아닌가”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former chairman made these remarks in a conversation video with Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Park Ju-min, which was released on YouTube on the 20th. (유 전 이사장은 20일 박주민 더불어민주당 의원이 유튜브에 공개한 두 사람의 대담 영상에서 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Chairman Yoo said, "It seems President Lee is doing well, and the Democratic Party's original tendencies are resurfacing. Supporting the Democratic Party has always required a lot of effort." (유 전 이사장은 “이 대통령은 잘하고 계신 것 같고 민주당은 원래 그런 모습이 있는 게 또 나오고 있다. 원래 민주당을 지지하려면 손이 많이 간다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "President Lee and I discussed this a lot during the election period. Originally, the politician Lee Jae-myung is not someone who makes you think, 'What should I do for that person?' but rather has a side that makes you support him by thinking, 'Maybe I can benefit from that person.'" He added, "That strength has been building even greater expectations during the six months since his presidential inauguration." (유 전 이사장은 이어 “이 대통령과 내가 선거 기간에 그런 얘기를 많이 했는데, 원래 이재명이라는 정치인은 ‘내가 저 사람을 위해 뭘 해줘야겠는데?’라는 마음이 들게 하는 사람이 아니고 ‘저 사람 덕을 내가 좀 볼 수 있을지도 몰라’ 이렇게 해서 지지하게 만드는 면이 있다”며 “그런 장점이 지금 대통령 취임하고 반년이 지나는 동안 그런 기대를 더 크게 만들고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Chairman Yoo stated, "However, regarding the nomination of Lee Hye-hoon or the pre-announcement of legislation for prosecutorial reform, I think perhaps the president became a bit lax in his political judgment while being too engrossed in other matters." (유 전 이사장은 “그런데 이혜훈씨 지명이나 검찰 개혁안 입법 예고한 거나 이런 거는 이제 대통령이 정치적인 판단 면에서 너무 다른 일들에 몰두하다 보니까 내 생각에는 좀 느슨해졌던 것이 아닌가 그런 생각이 든다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "From the outside, we cannot fully know why it happened or how the decision-making process went in the Lee Hye-hoon case or the pre-announcement process for prosecutorial reform legislation," but added, "It is clear that this decision-making method was somewhat different from how the president has operated until now." Former Chairman Yoo emphasized, "Then it's time for a review." (유 전 이사장은 “왜 그렇게 됐는지를 이혜훈씨 건이나 검찰개혁 입법 예고 과정(에서) 어떻게 의사 결정이 그렇게 이뤄졌는지 밖에선 다 알 수 없는데”라면서도 “그 의사 결정 방식이 지금까지 대통령이 해왔던 거하곤 좀 다른 방식이었단 건 분명하다”고 말했다. 유 전 이사장은 “그럼 점검을 해볼 때”라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Chairman Yoo also commented on independent lawmakers Kim Byeong-gi and Kang Seon-woo, who left the Democratic Party over suspicions of receiving nomination funds. (유 전 이사장은 공천헌금 수수 의혹 등으로 민주당에서 탈당한 김병기, 강선우 무소속 의원에 대해서도 입을 열었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Chairman Yoo said, "What is revealed in the cases of lawmakers Kim Byeong-gi and Kang Seon-woo is the dark side that has existed since the past," and added, "If such things were rampant in the past, I see them as only partially existing now." (유 전 이사장은 “김병기 의원 사건이나 강선우 의원 사건에서 드러나는 것은 과거부터 있어왔던 그 어두운 면이 드러나는 것”이라며 “예전에는 그런 게 만연했다면 지금은 일부 좀 있는 걸로 본다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "It's not that something non-existent is emerging; it's that something that originally existed was hidden in the past but is now being exposed," and added, "We should look for any institutional loopholes that keep creating such incidents, and if there are problems with the system, we should fix them and move forward that way." (그는 “없는 게 나오는 게 아니고 원래 있는 게 예전엔 다 감춰졌지만 지금은 노출되는 것”이라며 “계속 이런 일들을 만들어내는 제도적 허점이 있는지를 찾아보고 시스템에 어떤 문제가 있으면 그것도 고쳐나가고 그렇게 해나가면 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Chairman Yoo added, "It seems the Democratic Party does not have such a major problem," and "Although there are still many points that need to be fixed, they do not appear to be the culture of the entire party or to that extent." (유 전 이사장은 “민주당은 그렇게 큰 문제는 없는 것 같다”며 “고쳐야 될 점이 여전히 많이 남아있긴 한데 그것이 당 전체의 문화라든가 이렇게까지 보이지 않는다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, regarding the confirmation hearing for this nominee becoming dysfunctional, President Lee was reported to have said, "We went through difficulty to bring them in, so isn't proceeding with the confirmation hearing necessary?" A Cheong Wa Dae official stated on this day that President Lee made these remarks during a dinner with the Democratic Party leadership held at Cheong Wa Dae the previous day. (한편, 이 대통령은 이 후보자 인사청문회가 파행되는 데 대해 “어렵게 모시고 왔는데 인사청문회까지는 필요하지 않겠느냐”고 말한 것으로 알려졌다. 청와대 관계자는 이 대통령이 전날 청와대에서 열린 민주당 지도부와의 만찬 자리에서 이렇게 말했다고 이날 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Gyeong-hwa &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:freehwa@hani.co.kr"&gt;freehwa@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240707.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0120/53_17688925496002_20260120503006.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:12:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] No special pardon for Lunar New Year either... "President Lee's firm stance that pardon power should not be abused" ([단독] 설 특별사면도 없다…“이 대통령, 사면권 남용 안 된단 입장 확고”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240714.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/469/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503088.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed on the 20th that President Lee Jae-myung is not considering a special pardon for this Lunar New Year. (이재명 대통령이 이번 설날 특별사면을 검토하지 않고 있는 것으로 20일 확인됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Cheong Wa Dae official said on that day, "A minimum of one month is needed to carry out a special pardon, but a Lunar New Year special pardon is not being considered at all at present." A special pardon follows a procedure where the Ministry of Justice's Pardon Review Committee examines a list of candidates, the Minister of Justice submits it to the President, and after deliberation by the State Council, the President makes the final decision and announcement. Typically, this process takes about a month. A government official also stated, "If a Lunar New Year pardon were to be carried out, the outline should be emerging by now, but there is no preparation whatsoever." (청와대 관계자는 이날 “특별사면을 하려면 최소 한 달은 필요하지만, 현재 설날 특별사면은 전혀 검토되고 있지 않다”고 말했다. 특별사면은 법무부 사면심사위원회가 대상자 명단을 심사한 뒤 법무부 장관이 대통령에게 상신하고, 국무회의 심의를 거쳐 대통령이 최종 결정·공표하는 절차를 밟는다. 통상 이 과정에는 한달가량이 소요된다. 정부 관계자도 “설 사면을 단행하려면 지금쯤 윤곽이 나와야 하는데, 준비가 전혀 없다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Typically, if the year-end 'Christmas special pardon,' also called the New Year special pardon, is not implemented, there have been many cases where a Lunar New Year special pardon is carried out instead. However, this time, it appears neither will be implemented. Former President Yoon Suk-yeol carried out a New Year special pardon in December 2022, his first year in office, and at the end of 2023, he skipped the New Year special pardon and instead implemented a Lunar New Year special pardon in February 2024. (통상적으로 연말에 ‘성탄절 특사’로 불리는 신년 특별사면을 시행하지 않을 경우 설날 특별사면을 하는 사례가 많았지만, 이번에는 모두 시행하지 않는 셈이다. 윤석열 전 대통령은 2022년 12월 임기 첫해 신년 특별사면을 단행했고, 2023년 말에는 신년 특별사면을 건너뛴 대신 2024년 2월 설날 특별사면을 실시한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that President Lee has maintained a cautious stance on additional pardons since granting a special pardon to over 830,000 people, including former Justice Party leader Cho Kuk and his wife, on the occasion of the 80th anniversary of Liberation Day last August 15th. A Cheong Wa Dae official said, "President Lee's stance that 'the pardon power should not be abused' is firm." When former President Yoon granted a special pardon to former Presidential Chief of Staff Kim Ki-choon and former Defense Minister Kim Kwan-jin in February 2024, President Lee also remarked at the time, "If you pardon someone as soon as a guilty verdict is confirmed, what's the point of having a judicial system?" and "There's no difference from a monarchy if the President arbitrarily decides guilt or innocence and whether to carry out sentences." (이 대통령은 지난해 80주년 8·15 광복절을 맞아 조국 전 조국혁신당 대표 부부를 포함해 83만여명을 특별사면한 이후 추가 사면에는 신중한 입장을 유지하고 있는 것으로 전해졌다. 청와대 관계자는 “이 대통령은 ‘사면권은 남용해서는 안 된다’는 입장이 확고하다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 2024년 2월 윤 전 대통령이 김기춘 전 대통령비서실장과 김관진 전 국방부 장관을 특별사면했을 때도 “유죄가 확정되자마자 사면하면 사법제도가 왜 필요하냐”며 “유·무죄 판단과 형 집행 여부를 대통령이 임의로 결정하는 것은 군주국가와 다를 바 없다”고 말한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240714.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/469/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503088.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:12:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Also Invited South Korea... 'Membership Fee $1 Billion' Gaza Peace Committee (트럼프, 한국도 초청했다…‘가입비 10억 달러’ 가자 평화위원회)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240718.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503205.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난 14일 백악관에서 트럼프 대통령이 로이터 통신과 인터뷰하고 있다. 워싱턴/로이터 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been confirmed that U.S. President Donald Trump has invited South Korea to participate in the 'Gaza Peace Committee' he is leading. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 한국에도 자신이 주도하는 ‘가자지구 평화위원회’에 참여해달라며 초청한 것으로 확인됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated on the 20th that it had received an invitation to the Peace Committee from the United States and is reviewing whether to participate. A ministry official said, "We received the invitation recently, and we will likely be able to decide (on participation) after comprehensively reviewing which countries are participating, among other factors," adding, "We will need to take time to review it." (외교부는 20일 미국으로부터 평화위원회 초청을 받고, 참여할지 검토 중이라고 밝혔다. 외교부 당국자는 “최근에 초청받았고 어떤 국가들이 참여할지 등을 종합적으로 봐야 (참여 여부를) 판단할 수 있을듯하다”며 “시간을 가지고 검토해 나가야 할 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Trump previously announced the establishment of the Peace Committee as a key organization for the second phase of his 'peace plan' aimed at ending the war in Gaza. Foreign media reported that President Trump is expected to serve as the lifelong chairman of this body. So far, it is reported that invitations have been sent to over 60 countries, including South Korea, France, Germany, Australia, Canada, the European Union (EU), Egypt, Turkey, Israel, Russia, and Belarus. (트럼프 대통령은 앞서 가자지구 전쟁 종식을 목표로 하는 ‘평화 구상’ 2단계의 핵심 기구로 평화위원회 창설을 발표했다. 외신들은 트럼프 대통령이 이 기구의 종신 의장을 맡을 예정이라고 보도했다. 지금까지 한국을 포함해 프랑스, 독일, 오스트레일리아(호주), 캐나다, 유럽연합(EU), 이집트, 튀르키예, 이스라엘, 러시아, 벨라루스 등 60여개국이 초청장 발송국에 포함된 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversy is arising that the 'Peace Committee' proposed by President Trump under the pretext of ending and managing the Gaza war is, in fact, being pushed forward with the intention of replacing the United Nations. The Financial Times (FT) reported on the 17th (local time) that the draft charter for the establishment of the Peace Committee, which was initially known as the supreme decision-making body to govern the region until Gaza's reconstruction is completed, includes content to expand its role from resolving the Gaza conflict to mediating other regional conflicts, indicating it is being promoted with the intent to replace the UN. (트럼프 대통령이 가자지구 전쟁 종식과 관리를 명분으로 내건 ‘평화위원회&amp;#x27;가 사실상 유엔을 대체하려는 의도에서 추친되고 있다는 논란이 일고 있다. 파이낸셜타임스(FT)는 17일(현지시간) 당초 가자지구 재건이 마무리될 때까지 이 지역을 통치할 최고 의사결정 기구로 알려졌던 평화위원회의의 설립 헌장 초안에 가자 분쟁 해결을 시작으로 다른 지역 분쟁 중재까지 역할을 확대할 것이라는 내용이 담겨 있어, 유엔을 대체하겠다는 의도에서 추진되고 있다고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After French President Emmanuel Macron effectively refused to participate in the Peace Committee, U.S. President Trump, in a meeting with reporters on the 19th, threatened to impose a 200% tariff on French wine and champagne if President Macron does not participate. (에마뉘엘 마크롱 프랑스 대통령이 평화위원회 참여를 사실상 거부하자, 트럼프 미국 대통령은 19일 기자들과 만난 자리에서 마크롱 대통령이 참여하지 않으면 프랑스산 와인과 샴페인에 200% 관세를 부과하겠다고 위협하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240718.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503205.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:11:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Hyun to visit Türkiye and Belgium from 21st to 24th... Likely to discuss Greenland issue (조현, 21~24일 튀르키예·벨기에 방문…그린란드 문제도 논의할 듯)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240723.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503271.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;조현 외교부 장관이 20일 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 이재명 대통령의 질문에 답하고 있다. 청와대사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Cho Hyun will visit Türkiye and Belgium from the 21st to the 24th. (조현 외교부 장관이 21~24일 튀르키예와 벨기에를 방문한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced on the 20th that Minister Cho will visit Türkiye on the 21st, hold talks with Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan, and review follow-up measures regarding nuclear power plants, defense industry, bio-technology, infrastructure, and other matters discussed during the Korea-Türkiye summit last November. (조 장관은 21일 튀르키예를 방문해 하칸 피단 외교장관과 회담을 하고, 지난해 11월 한-튀르키예 정상회담에서 다뤄진 원전·방산·바이오·인프라 등에 대해 후속 조치를 점검한다고 외교부가 20일 발표했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following his visit to Türkiye, Minister Cho will visit Belgium on the 22nd to hold the second Korea-European Union Foreign Ministers' Strategic Dialogue with EU High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy Kaja Kallas. (조 장관은 튀르키예 방문에 이어 22일에는 벨기에를 방문해 카야 칼라스 유럽연합(EU) 외교안보 고위대표와 제2차 한-유럽연합 외교장관 전략대화를 개최한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This strategic dialogue is the second of its kind, following the first one held in Seoul in November 2024. As U.S. President Donald Trump's recent attempt to acquire Greenland has emerged as a top priority for the European Union and its impact on the international situation is significant, it is expected that this issue will also be discussed during the strategic dialogue. In a regular briefing that day, Deputy Spokesperson Lee Moon-bae explained, "We plan to discuss the overall Korea-EU relationship, including high-level exchanges, and also exchange views on major regional situations such as the Korean Peninsula and Ukraine." (이번 전략대화는 2024년 11월 서울에서 열린 제1차 대화에 이어 두번째 열리는 것이다. 최근 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 그린란드 소유 시도가 유럽연합의 최고 현안으로 떠오른데다 국제 정세에 미치는 파장도 크기 때문에, 전략대화에서는 이 문제도 논의될 것으로 예상된다. 이문배 외교부 부대변인은 이날 정례브리핑에서 “고위급 교류를 포함한 한-유럽연합 관계 전반을 논의하고 한반도와 우크라이나 등 주요 지역 정세에 대해서도 의견을 교환할 예정”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, Minister Cho is also scheduled to meet with Belgian Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Employment, Economy, and Agriculture David Clarinval. At this meeting, plans to strengthen cooperation in various fields such as economy and culture, including high-level exchanges between the two countries to commemorate the 125th anniversary of diplomatic relations this year, are expected to be discussed. (조 장관은 오는 23일엔 다비드 클라린발 벨기에 부총리 겸 고용·경제·농업 장관과도 면담할 예정이다. 이 자리에서는 올해 수교 125주년을 기념하기 위해 양국 간 고위급 교류를 비롯해 경제·문화 등 다양한 분야의 협력 강화 방안이 논의할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240723.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503271.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:11:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea-China Foreign Ministers' Meeting to be Held in Q1... Additional Discussions on 'Hallyu Ban' and West Sea Structures (한·중 외교장관 회담 1분기 추진…한한령·서해 구조물 등 추가 협의)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240735.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503411.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난해 9월17일 중국 베이징에서 조현 외교장관과 왕이 중국 외교부장 겸 중앙외사판공실 주임이 회담하고 있다. 외교부 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs is pursuing a South Korea-China foreign ministers' meeting within the first quarter (January-March). (외교부가 중국과 1분기(1~3월) 중 한·중 외교장관 회담을 추진한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Cho Hyun-dong said at a cabinet meeting on the morning of the 20th, "We are trying to hold a (South Korea-China foreign) ministers' meeting once again in the first quarter." This was in response to President Lee Jae-myung's inquiry about the progress level of cultural exchange and cooperation with China. Foreign Ministry Deputy Spokesperson Lee Moon-bae said at the regular briefing that day that "topics covering the overall bilateral relationship will be discussed" at the South Korea-China foreign ministers' meeting. (조현 외교부 장관은 20일 오전 국무회의에서 “1분기에 (한중 외교)장관 회담을 다시 한 번 하려고 하고 있다”고 말했다. 이재명 대통령이 중국과의 문화 분야 교류 협력 진척 수준을 물은 데 대한 답변이다. 이문배 외교부 부대변인은 이날 정례브리핑에서 한중 외교장관 회담에서 “양국 관계 전반에 대한 주제들이 논의될 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the cabinet meeting, President Lee instructed to discuss with the Chinese side a kind of preservation agreement between the South Korean and Chinese governments regarding independence movement sites in China, and Minister Cho replied that he would do so. (이 대통령은 국무회의에서 중국 내 독립운동 유적지에 대한 한중 정부 간 일종의 보전 협약을 중국 측과 협의해보라고 지시했고, 조 장관은 그렇게 하겠다고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the South Korea-China foreign ministers' meeting is held this time, follow-up discussions from the South Korea-China summit earlier this month are expected to take place. These include ways to promote cultural exchange, including the easing of China's 'Hallyu Ban' (restrictions on Korean culture), discussions related to independence movement sites in China, and the implementation of agreements between the leaders regarding China's structures in the West Sea. Deputy Spokesperson Lee explained, "Typically, foreign ministers' meetings do not discuss only specific issues but topics covering the overall bilateral relationship." (이번에 한중 외교장관 회담이 열리면 중국의 ‘한한령’(한국문화 제한 조치) 완화를 비롯한 문화 교류 방안과 중국내 독립운동 유적지 관련 협의를 비롯해 중국의 서해 구조물 관련 정상 간 합의 사항 이행 문제 등 이달 초 한중 정상회담의 후속 협의가 이뤄질 것으로 보인다. 이 부대변인은 “통상 외교장관회담에서는 특정 이슈만을 논의하는 것이 아니라 양국 관계 전반에 대한 주제들이 논의될 것”이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Cho and Wang Yi, Director of the Chinese Communist Party Central Committee Foreign Affairs Commission Office and Minister of Foreign Affairs, held a foreign ministers' meeting in China last September. Whether the upcoming meeting will be held in China or Seoul is also a point of interest. (조 장관과 왕이 중국공산당 중앙외사판공실 주임 겸 외교부장(장관)은 지난해 9월 중국에서 외교장관 회담을 한 바 있다. 이번에 회담이 중국과 서울 중 어디에서 열릴지도 관심 사안이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240735.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0120/20260120503411.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:11:17 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>