<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:36:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>As KOSPI Breaks 5,000, Democratic Party Says "Dreams Come True... Let's Open the 7,000 Era" (코스피 5천 돌파에 민주 “꿈은 이루어진다…7000 시대 열자”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241075.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;As KOSPI Breaks 5,000, Democratic Party Says "Dreams Come True... Let's Open the 7,000 Era" (코스피 5천 돌파에 민주 “꿈은 이루어진다…7000 시대 열자”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/467/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501223.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한병도 더불어민주당 원내대표(가운데)가 22일 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 정책조정회의에서 발언하고 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI broke 5,000 for the first time ever during trading on the 22nd, the Democratic Party of Korea poured out a unified welcome. (코스피가 22일 장중 사상 처음으로 5000을 돌파하자 더불어민주당에서는 일제히 환영이 쏟아졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party leader Chung Cheong-rae wrote on Facebook that day, "At this very moment, celebrating the composite stock price index at 5,014! The dream of the KOSPI 5,000 era comes true," adding, "For the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and an era of national happiness, let's go together." (정청래 대표는 이날 페이스북에 “지금 이시각, 종합주가 지수 5,014 경축! 코스피 5천시대의 꿈은 이루어진다”며 “이재명 정부의 성공, 국민행복 시대를 위하여 함께 갑시다”라고 적었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor leader Han Byung-do also stated at a policy coordination meeting held at the National Assembly that day, "KOSPI 5,000 is clear evidence that after the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration, South Korea is moving beyond normalization towards a great transformation and leap forward," and said, "Achieving KOSPI 5,000 is not the end. We will continue to create shareholder-friendly systems and open the KOSPI 6,000 and 7,000 eras together with the people." (한병도 원내대표도 이날 국회에서 열린 정책조정회의에서 “코스피 5000은 이재명 정부가 출범한 뒤 대한민국이 정상화를 넘어 대전환과 대도약으로 나아가고 있다는 방증”이라며 “코스피 5000 달성으로 끝이 아니다. 앞으로도 주주친화적 제도를 만들어 코스피 6000, 7000 시대를 국민들과 함께 열어가겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Oh Ki-hyung, who chairs the party's internal KOSPI5000 Special Committee, also posted a short message on Facebook saying, "Finally, KOSPI 5,000!" That day, Rep. Oh and other members of the special committee were invited by President Lee to have lunch together at the presidential office. (당내 기구인 코스피5000 특별위원회 위원장을 맡고 있는 오기형 의원도 페이스북에 “드디어 코스피 5000!”이라는 짧은 글을 올렸다. 이날 오 의원을 비롯한 5000특위 소속 의원들은 이 대통령 초청으로 청와대에서 오찬을 함께 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Deputy Floor Leader for Communication Jeon Yong-ki also said on Facebook, "Through breaking KOSPI 5,000, the Lee Jae-myung administration has set a milestone for the transformation of the capital market where corporate performance is fairly evaluated and capital stays within the country," and added, "The Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party will work harder to ensure the Korean economy moves forward unshakably through a virtuous cycle structure of industry, technology, and capital." (전용기 원내소통수석부대표도 페이스북에 “이재명 정부는 코스피 5천 돌파를 통해 기업의 성과가 정당하게 평가받고, 자본이 국내에 머무는 자본시장 전환의 이정표를 세웠다”며 “산업과 기술, 자본이 선순환하는 구조를 통해 대한민국 경제가 흔들림없이 앞으로 나아가도록 이재명 정부와 민주당이 더 노력하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241075.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/467/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501223.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk Responds to Chung Cheong-rae's Merger Proposal, Says "Will Decide According to the People's Will" (조국, 정청래 합당 제안에 “국민 뜻 따라 결정”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241076.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cho Kuk Responds to Chung Cheong-rae's Merger Proposal, Says "Will Decide According to the People's Will" (조국, 정청래 합당 제안에 “국민 뜻 따라 결정”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/634/476/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501249.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;=조국 조국혁신당 대표가 22일 전북 전주시 전북도당 당사에서 현장 최고위원회의를 주재하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, stated on the 22nd regarding the merger proposal from Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, that "we will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and will." (조국 조국혁신당 대표가 22일 정청래 더불어민주당 대표의 합당 제안에 대해 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Cho made these remarks at the Jeonbuk Field Supreme Council meeting held at the Innovation Party's Jeonbuk Special Self-Governing Province Party office. He said, "Yesterday (the 21st) in the late afternoon, I met with Leader Chung and received the details of today's (merger proposal) announcement. It was sudden, but as the weight of the proposal is by no means light, I have carefully considered it together with the Supreme Council members." (조 대표는 이날 혁신당 전북특별자치도당 당사에서 열린 전북 현장 최고위원회의에서 “어제(21일) 늦은 오후 정 대표님을 만나 오늘의 (합당 제안) 발표 내용을 전달받았다. 갑작스럽지만 제안의 무게가 결코 가볍지 않기에 최고위원분들과 함께 숙고했다”며 이렇게 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Cho stated, "The Innovation Party fully agrees with the goals mentioned by Leader Chung: the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the re-creation of political power. At the same time, we are independently pursuing progressive future tasks that the Democratic Party does not address, such as political reform and constitutional amendment, realizing a socially advanced nation, and legislating the public concept of land." He added, "We will listen to the voices of the people and party members on what the best path is to achieve both of these era-defining tasks. To this end, I have instructed for the prompt convening of a general assembly of lawmakers and a party affairs committee meeting." (조 대표는 “혁신당은 정 대표가 언급한 이재명 정부의 성공과 정권 재창출이라는 목표에 전적으로 동의한다. 동시에 정치 개혁과 개헌, 사회권 선진국 실현, 토지공개념 입법화 등 민주당이 말하지 않는 진보적 미래 과제를 독자적으로 추구하고 있다”며 “이러한 두 시대적 과제를 모두 실현하는 최선의 길이 무엇인지 국민과 당원의 목소리를 경청하겠다. 이를 위해 의원총회와 당무위원회의 조속한 개최를 지시했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Leader Cho emphasized, "The Innovation Party will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and will, and we will report the results to the people as they emerge. In that process, I will fulfill my responsibility as the party leader." (&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;이어 조 대표는&lt;strong&gt; “&lt;/strong&gt;혁신당은 국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정할 것이고, 그 결과가 나오는 대로 국민께 보고를 올리겠다. 그 과정에서 당 대표로서 책임을 다하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Hansol sol@hani.co.kr (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241076.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/634/476/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501249.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Despite Jang Dong-hyuk's Hunger Strike, 'Approval Rating ↓'... 53% of People Power Party Supporters Say "Expelling Han Dong-hoon Was the Right Thing" (장동혁 단식에도 ‘지지율 ↓’…국힘 지지층 53%는 “한동훈 제명 잘한 일”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241084.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Despite Jang Dong-hyuk's Hunger Strike, 'Approval Rating ↓'... 53% of People Power Party Supporters Say "Expelling Han Dong-hoon Was the Right Thing" (장동혁 단식에도 ‘지지율 ↓’…국힘 지지층 53%는 “한동훈 제명 잘한 일”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민의힘 장동혁 대표, 한동훈(오른쪽) 전 대표. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, the eighth day of People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike, a public opinion poll result showed that the People Power Party's approval rating had actually declined. Regarding the disciplinary expulsion of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon, more people said it was 'the right decision'. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식농성이 8일째로 접어든 22일, 국민의힘 지지율이 오히려 하락했다는 여론조사 결과가 나왔다. 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표의 제명 처분에 대해서는 ‘잘한 결정’이라는 의견이 더 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Embrain Public, K-Stat Research, Korea Research, and Hankook Research released the results of their regular national indicator survey conducted from the 19th to the 21st on 1,001 eligible voters nationwide (margin of error ±3.1%p at a 95% confidence level, response rate 20.2%, telephone interviews via virtual mobile numbers). (엠브레인퍼블릭·케이스탯리서치·코리아리서치·한국리서치는 19∼21일 전국 유권자 1001명을 대상으로 실시한 정례 전국지표조사(표본오차 95% 신뢰수준에 ±3.1%포인트·응답률 20.2%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화면접) 결과를 22일 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party support rates were as follows: Democratic Party of Korea 40%, People Power Party 20%, Cho Kuk Innovation Party and Reform New Party 3% each, and Progressive Party 1%. In the survey two weeks prior, the Democratic Party was at 39% and the People Power Party at 23%. The gap was even larger among centrist voters, who will decide the outcome of the June 3 local elections. The Democratic Party's support among centrists was 41%, while the People Power Party's support remained at only 13%. (정당 지지도는 더불어민주당 40%, 국민의힘 20%, 조국혁신당·개혁신당 각 3%, 진보당 1% 순이었다. 2주 전 조사 때는 민주당 39%, 국민의힘 23%였다. 6·3 지방선거 승패를 가를 중도층에서는 격차가 더 컸다. 중도층의 민주당 지지율은 41%였지만, 국민의힘 지지율은 13%에 그쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the People Power Party Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon, holding him responsible for the party bulletin board incident, 43% said it was 'the right decision', 38% said it was 'the wrong decision', and 19% said they didn't know or did not respond. What was particularly notable was that while many supporters of the ruling bloc said it was 'the wrong decision', over half of People Power Party supporters themselves said it was 'the right decision'. Among People Power Party supporters, 53% said it was 'the right decision' and 39% said it was 'the wrong decision'. Among Democratic Party supporters, 'the right decision' (43%) and 'the wrong decision' (41%) were similar, while among Cho Kuk Innovation Party supporters, 50% said it was 'the wrong decision' and 30% said it was 'the right decision'. (국민의힘 윤리위원회가 당원게시판 사태에 책임을 물어 한동훈 전 대표를 제명하기로 결정한 것에 대해서는 ‘잘한 결정’ 43%, ‘잘못한 결정’ 38%, 모름·무응답 19%였다. 특히 눈에 띄는 것은 여권 지지층에서는 ‘잘못한 결정’이라는 의견이 많은 반면, 정작 국민의힘 지지층에서는 ‘잘한 결정’이라는 응답이 절반이 넘었다는 점이다. 국민의힘 지지층은 ‘잘한 결정’ 53%, ‘잘못한 결정’ 39%였다. 민주당 지지층에서는 ‘잘한 결정’(43%), ‘잘못한 결정’(41%)이 비슷했고, 조국혁신당 지지층에서는 ‘잘못한 결정’ 50%, ‘잘한 결정’ 30%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241084.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690490109394_20260122501504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Park Geun-hye says "Please stop fasting"... Jang Dong-hyeok says "I will do so" (박근혜 “단식 멈춰달라”…장동혁 “그렇게 하겠다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241091.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Park Geun-hye says "Please stop fasting"... Jang Dong-hyeok says "I will do so" (박근혜 “단식 멈춰달라”…장동혁 “그렇게 하겠다”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690497028839_20260122501571.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;박근혜 전 대통령이 22일 쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검)을 요구하며 8일째 단식을 이어가는 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식 현장을 방문해 대화를 나누고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park Geun-hye visited People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who was on the eighth day of his hunger strike on the 22nd, and asked him to stop fasting. Leader Jang replied, "I will do so." (박근혜 전 대통령이 22일 8일째 단식하는 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 찾아 단식 중단을 요구했다. 장 대표는 “그렇게 하겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park entered the National Assembly's Rotten Hall, where Leader Jang was fasting, around 11:20 AM that day. Floor Leader Song Eon-seok and lawmaker Yoo Young-ha greeted former President Park in front of the National Assembly's main building. When former President Park appeared at the protest site, Leader Jang, who had been lying inside a tent, was helped up and sat on a chair. (박 전 대통령은 이날 오전 11시20분께 장 대표가 단식을 하고 있는 국회 로텐더홀에 들어섰다. 송언석 원내대표와 유영하 의원이 국회 본관 앞에서 박 전 대통령을 맞았다. 박 전 대통령이 농성장에 모습을 드러내자 텐트 안에 누워있던 장 대표는 부축을 받아 일어나 의자에 앉았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park said to Leader Jang, "Some might criticize that this is a fruitless fast because the government and ruling party did not accept the special prosecutor investigation you demanded, but that is absolutely not the case," adding, "The public will recognize your sincerity for risking your life to fight for what you believed was right as a politician." She then emphasized, "For the future, I hope you will stop fasting today and recover your health," and "I hope you will promise here today that you will now stop fasting." In response, Leader Jang replied, "I will do so." (박 전 대통령은 장 대표에게 “장 대표가 요구한 특검을 정부·여당이 받아주지 않아서 ‘아무것도 얻지 못한 단식이 아니냐’고 비난할 수도 있겠지만 절대 그렇지 않다”며 “정치인으로서 옳다고 생각한 것에 대해 목숨을 건 투쟁을 한 것에 대해 국민들께서 대표님의 진정성을 인정할 것”이라고 말했다. 이어 “훗날을 위해 오늘 단식을 이제 멈추시고 건강을 회복하셨으면 한다”며 “오늘 이 자리에서 이제 단식을 그만두겠다, 이렇게 약속을 해주셨으면 합니다”고 강조했다. 이에 장 대표는 “그렇게 하겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park then said, "Thank you. I understand you will stop today," and added, "If you recover your health quickly, we will meet again someday." (이에 박 전 대통령은 “고맙다. 오늘 멈추시는 것으로 알겠다”며 “앞으로 건강을 빨리 회복을 하시면 다시 만날 날이 있을 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After exchanging greetings with former President Park, Leader Jang returned to the tent. A party leader's side official said, "Leader Jang is deeply contemplating (stopping the fast)." (장 대표는 박 전 대통령과 인사를 나눈 뒤 다시 텐트로 돌아갔다. 당 대표 쪽 관계자는 “장 대표가 (단식 중단을) 고심하고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was former President Park's first time entering the National Assembly's main building since the impeachment motion was passed in the National Assembly in December 2016. (박 전 대통령이 국회 본청에 들어온 것은 2016년 12월 국회에서 탄핵 소추안이 가결된 이후 처음이다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241091.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690497028839_20260122501571.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong Wa Dae: "73 Scam Suspects Arrested in Cambodia to Be Repatriated to Korea Tomorrow" (청와대 “캄보디아서 검거 스캠 피의자 73명 내일 국내 송환”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241092.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cheong Wa Dae: "73 Scam Suspects Arrested in Cambodia to Be Repatriated to Korea Tomorrow" (청와대 “캄보디아서 검거 스캠 피의자 73명 내일 국내 송환”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/453/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501581.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;강유정 청와대 대변인이 22일 청와대 춘추관에서 캄보디아 스캠 조직 피의자 송환 관련 브리핑을 마친 뒤 취재진 질문을 받고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government will repatriate 73 Korean suspects arrested in Cambodia to Korea via Incheon International Airport on the 23rd, using a chartered flight. This repatriation is the largest in scale for a single incident to date. (정부가 캄보디아에서 검거한 한국인 피의자 73명을 전세기에 태워 23일 인천국제공항을 통해 국내로 송환한다. 이번 송환 규모는 단일 사건 기준으로 역대 최대다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheong Wa Dae Spokesperson Kang Yu-jeong announced during a briefing on the 22nd, "Following President Lee Jae-myung's instructions, the Transnational Crime Special Response Task Force (TF) will forcibly repatriate 73 Korean nationals suspected of defrauding approximately 48.6 billion won from 869 of our citizens, operating out of Cambodia, tomorrow morning." The chartered flight carrying the suspects is scheduled to depart Incheon International Airport at 8:45 PM today and arrive back at Incheon Airport at 9:10 AM the following day. (강유정 청와대 대변인은 22일 브리핑을 통해 “이재명 대통령의 지시로 구성된 초국가범죄 특별대응 티에프(TF)는 내일 오전 캄보디아를 거점으로 우리 국민 869명에게 약 486억원을 편취한 한국 국적 피의자 73명을 강제 송환한다”고 밝혔다. 피의자들을 태울 전용기는 이날 오후 8시45분 인천국제공항을 출발해, 이튿날 오전 9시10분 인천공항에 다시 도착할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Kang assessed, "This domestic repatriation of criminal suspects is the largest in scale to date and is the result of a long-term investigation by the dispatched Korea Task Force, the National Intelligence Service, and local police in Cambodia." The investigation team identified seven scam compounds and arrested 51 members of a scam organization in the southwestern port city of Sihanoukville, Cambodia last December, 15 members of a scam organization in the Thai border city of Poipet, and 26 members of a scam organization in the eastern highland region of Mondulkiri. (강 대변인은 “이번 범죄 피의자 국내 송환은 역대 최대 규모로 캄보디아 현지에 파견된 코리아 전담반, 국가정보원, 현지경찰 등 수사팀이 장기간 추적 끝에 거둔 성과”라고 평가했다. 수사팀은 스캠단지 7곳을 확인해 지난해 12월 캄보디아 남서부 항구도시 시하누크빌 스캠조직 51명, 태국 접경 도시 포이펫 스캠조직 15명, 동부 고원지역 몬둘키리 스캠조직 26명을 검거했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The targets of this repatriation also include a romance scam couple fraud ring that had not been repatriated to Korea last October. They are suspected of defrauding approximately 12 billion won from 104 Korean citizens by impersonating fictional characters and using deepfake technology. It has been determined that they used organized evasion strategies, such as altering their appearance through plastic surgery, to avoid pursuit by domestic judicial authorities. (이번 송환 대상에는 지난해 10월 국내로 송환되지 못했던 로맨스 스캠 부부 사기단도 포함됐다. 이들은 가상 인물로 위장하고 딥페이크 기술을 활용하는 수법으로 우리 국민 104명에게 약 120억원 상당의 금액을 편취한 혐의를 받고 있다. 이들은 국내 사법당국의 추적을 피하기 위해 성형수술로 외모를 바꾸는 등 조직적인 도피 전략을 사용해온 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also included in this repatriation are fugitive criminals who committed sex crimes against minors in Korea before fleeing to Cambodia and participating in local scam crimes. The repatriation group also includes the mastermind of a fraud organization that impersonated investment experts to defraud approximately 19.4 billion won from young adults starting their careers and retirees, as well as members who committed inhumane crimes by holding victims detained in scam compounds hostage to threaten their families in Korea and extort money and valuables. (이와 함께 미성년자를 대상으로 성범죄를 저지른 뒤 캄보디아로 도주해 현지 스캠 범죄에 가담한 도피 사범도 이번 송환 대상에 포함됐다. 투자 전문가를 사칭해 사회 초년생과 은퇴자를 상대로 약 194억원을 편취한 사기 조직의 총책, 스캠 단지에 감금된 피해자를 인질 삼아 국내에 있는 가족을 협박하고 금품을 갈취한 반인륜적 범죄를 저지른 조직원들도 함께 송환된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Kang explained, "The government judged that leaving major criminals who have caused immense damage to our citizens abroad could send the wrong signal of effectively condoning their flight and that there is a risk of recidivism, so we have proceeded swiftly with the repatriation process." (강 대변인은 “정부는 우리 국민에게 막대한 피해를 준 중대 범죄자들을 해외에 방치하면 범죄자의 도피를 사실상 묵인한다는 잘못된 신호를 줄 수 있고, 재범 우려도 있다고 판단해 송환 절차를 신속하게 진행해 왔다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, all the repatriated suspects have arrest warrants issued against them. Upon arrival in Korea, they will be immediately handed over to investigative authorities for investigation and then processed according to judicial procedures. Furthermore, the government plans to thoroughly pursue the assets the suspects have hidden overseas and actively proceed with the recovery of criminal proceeds. (한편, 송환되는 피의자는 전원 체포영장이 발부된 상태로 국내 도착 즉시 수사기관에 인계돼 수사를 거친 뒤 사법 절차에 따라 처리될 예정이다. 또한 정부는 피의자들이 해외에 은닉한 재산에 대해서도 끝까지 추적해 범죄수익 환수를 본격적으로 추진한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241092.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/453/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501581.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>57% See Democratic Party's Nomination Fund Suspicion as a 'Structural Problem'... 30% as 'Individual Misconduct' (민주당 공천헌금 의혹 ‘구조적 문제’ 57%…‘개인 일탈’ 30%)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241095.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;57% See Democratic Party's Nomination Fund Suspicion as a 'Structural Problem'... 30% as 'Individual Misconduct' (민주당 공천헌금 의혹 ‘구조적 문제’ 57%…‘개인 일탈’ 30%)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/463/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501616.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2022년 지방선거를 앞두고 김경 서울시의원이 공천 대가로 건넨 1억원을 수수한 혐의를 받는 무소속 강선우 의원이 20일 서울 마포구 서울경찰청 공공범죄수사대로 출석하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the nomination fund suspicion, the Democratic Party of Korea defines it as 'individual misconduct' and is not accepting the People Power Party's demand for a special prosecutor investigation. Public opinion showed that the view of it being a 'structural problem' was nearly twice as common as the view of it being 'individual misconduct'. (공천헌금 의혹에 대해 더불어민주당은 ‘개인 일탈’로 규정하고 국민의힘의 특검수사 요구를 받아들이지 않고 있다. 여론은 ‘구조적 문제’라는 의견이 ‘개인적 일탈’이라는 의견보다 2배 가까이 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Embrain Public, K-Stat Research, Korea Research, and Hankook Research released the results of their regular national indicator survey on the 22nd. The survey was conducted from the 19th to the 21st on 1,001 eligible voters nationwide (margin of error ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level, response rate 20.2%, telephone interviews using virtual mobile numbers). (엠브레인퍼블릭·케이스탯리서치·코리아리서치·한국리서치는 19∼21일 전국 유권자 1001명을 대상으로 실시한 정례 전국지표조사(표본오차 95% 신뢰수준에 ±3.1%포인트·응답률 20.2%, 휴대전화 가상번호 전화면접) 결과를 22일 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about their perception of the Democratic Party's nomination fund suspicion, 57% responded they see it as a 'structural problem of the nomination system,' while 30% responded they see it as 'individual misconduct by some figures.' 13% answered don't know/no response. This shows a significant gap between the Democratic Party leadership's judgment of it as 'Kang Sun-woo and Kim Kyeong's individual misconduct' and the voters' perception. Even among Democratic Party supporters, opinions were similarly divided, with 47% seeing it as a 'structural problem' and 44% as 'individual misconduct.' (민주당 공천헌금 의혹에 대한 인식을 물었다. ‘공천 시스템의 구조적 문제로 본다’는 응답이 57%, ‘일부 인사의 개인적 일탈로 본다’는 응답은 30%였다. 모름·무응답은 13%였다. ‘강선우-김경 개인 일탈’이라는 민주당 지도부 판단과 유권자 인식 사이에 괴리가 큰 것이다. 민주당 지지층에서도 ‘구조적 문제’ 47%, ‘개인적 일탈’ 44%로 평가가 비슷하게 갈렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the evaluation of President Lee Jae-myung's state administration, 59% said he is 'doing well,' and 31% said he is 'doing poorly.' Compared to the survey two weeks prior, positive responses decreased by 2 percentage points, and negative responses increased by the same amount. (이재명 대통령 국정운영에 대한 평가는 ‘잘하고 있다’ 59%, ‘잘못하고 있다’ 31%였다. 2주 전 조사에 견줘 긍정 응답은 2%포인트 줄었고, 부정 응답은 그만큼 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the nature of the June 3 local elections, 47% said 'the ruling party should be empowered for stable state affairs,' 40% said 'the opposition party should be empowered to check the government,' and 13% answered don't know/no response. (6·3 지방선거 성격을 두고는 ‘국정안정을 위해 여당에 힘을 실어줘야 한다’ 47%, ‘정부 견제 위해 야당에 힘을 실어줘야 한다’ 40%, 모름·무응답 13%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241095.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/463/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501616.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Professor Park Han-sik, 'Bridge of Peace on the Korean Peninsula,' Passes Away... Mediated Carter-Kim Il Sung Meeting (‘한반도 평화의 다리’ 박한식 교수 별세…카터-김일성 회동 중재)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241096.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Professor Park Han-sik, 'Bridge of Peace on the Korean Peninsula,' Passes Away... Mediated Carter-Kim Il Sung Meeting (‘한반도 평화의 다리’ 박한식 교수 별세…카터-김일성 회동 중재)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501623.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;생전의 박한식 교수가 한겨레와 인터뷰 하고 있다. 김보근 기자&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Han-sik, an emeritus professor at the University of Georgia (UGA) in the United States, who worked for over half a century as a scholar and peace activist for peace on the Korean Peninsula and the world, passed away on the 20th (local time) in Augusta, Georgia, USA, his family announced on the 21st. He was 87 years old. (학자이자 평화운동가로서 반세기 넘게 한반도와 세계 평화를 위해 노력했던 박한식 미국 조지아대(UGA) 명예교수가 20일(현지시간) 미국 조지아주 오거스타에서 별세했다고 가족들이 21일 밝혔다. 향년 87.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Park was born in 1939 in Harbin, China, and settled in Daegu via Pyongyang during the chaotic period immediately after liberation. He introduced himself as having been 'obsessed with peace' from experiencing the horrors of war and the pain of displacement during his childhood. After experiencing the Korean War and the April 19 Revolution, he graduated from Seoul National University's Department of Political Science and, carrying his father's dying wish to 'not return until reunification,' left for the United States to study in 1965. (박 교수는 1939년 중국 하얼빈에서 태어나 해방 직후 혼란기에 평양을 거쳐 대구에 정착했다. 그는 어린 시절 경험을 통해 전쟁의 참상과 유랑의 고통을 체감하며 ‘평화에 미쳤다’고 자신을 소개했다. 한국전쟁과 4·19혁명을 경험하고 서울대 정치학과를 졸업한 그는 ‘통일될 때까지 돌아오지 말라’는 부친의 유지를 가슴에 안고 1965년 미국 유학을 떠났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He dedicated his life to researching peace on the Korean Peninsula and improving inter-Korean relations. From 1970, centered around the University of Georgia's Department of International Relations and the Global Institute for International Affairs (GLOBIS), he taught peace to thousands of young people for 45 years, worked to realize that peace in reality, and pioneered 'peace studies.' Since first setting foot in Pyongyang in 1981 with fellow Korean-American scholars, he traveled back and forth over 50 times, researching the realities of North Korean society through direct observation and striving to build a 'bridge of peace' between North and South. (그는 한반도 평화 연구와 남북관계 개선을 위해 평생을 바쳤다. 1970년부터 조지아대학 국제관계학과와 국제문제연구소(GLOBIS)를 중심으로 45년간 수천명의 청년들에게 평화를 가르치고, 그 평화를 현실에서 구현하기 위해 노력하며 ‘평화학’을 일궜다. 1981년 재미 학자들과 함께 평양 땅을 처음 밟은 이래 50여 차례 오가며 직접 관찰한 북한 사회의 실상을 연구하고 남북 사이에 ‘평화의 다리’를 놓으려 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1994, when the crisis of war on the Korean Peninsula loomed over the North Korean nuclear issue, he arranged former U.S. President Jimmy Carter's visit to North Korea, facilitating a meeting with then-Chairman Kim Il Sung and creating a dramatic turning point. In 2009, he promoted former U.S. President Bill Clinton's visit to North Korea, leading to the release of American journalists detained there at the time and creating an opportunity for a shift in North Korea-U.S. relations. When official government communication channels were closed, he promoted Track II talks between South Korea, North Korea, and the U.S., and facilitated mutual exchanges between North Korean and U.S. agricultural delegations with the goal of alleviating famine in North Korea. (북핵 문제를 둘러싸고 한반도 전쟁 위기가 감돌던 1994년 지미 카터 전 미국 대통령의 방북을 주선해 당시 김일성 주석과의 만남을 성사시켜 극적인 반전의 계기를 만들어냈다. 2009년에는 빌 클린턴 전 미국 대통령의 방북을 추진해 당시 북한에 억류돼 있던 미국 기자들의 석방을 이끌어내 북-미 관계 변화의 기회를 마련했다. 정부 간 소통 창구가 닫힌 상황에서 남·북·미 간 트랙II 회담을 추진하고, 북한의 기아 완화를 목적으로 북한과 미국 농업대표단의 상호 교류를 성사시켰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 1980, he visited his hometown of Heilongjiang Province, China, annually, recording and broadcasting the stories of separated families. For these multifaceted contributions, Park Han-sik received the Gandhi-King-Ikeda Peace Award in 2010, often called the preliminary Nobel Peace Prize. On that occasion, he appealed that 'unless we change the security paradigm that has dominated us for the past several centuries into a peace paradigm, humanity will not see the dawn of the 22nd century.' In 2015, he was invited to a TED conference, where he emphasized that the concept of peace is not a state without war, but a state of recognizing and accepting difference and diversity. (1980년부터 고향인 중국 헤이룽장성을 매년 방문해 직접 녹화한 이산 가족들의 사연을 방송에 내보냈다. 이러한 다방면의 공헌으로 박한식은 2010년 예비 노벨평화상이라 일컬어지는 간디·킹·이케다 평화상을 받았다. 그는 이 자리에서 ‘지난 수 세기 우리를 지배해온 안보 패러다임을 평화 패러다임으로 변화시키지 못하면 인류에게 22세기의 도래는 없을 것’이라고 호소했다. 2015년엔 테드(TED) 콘퍼런스에 초청돼 평화의 개념은 전쟁이 없는 상태가 아니라 다름과 다양성을 인정하고 수용하는 상태라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After retiring from his professorship at the University of Georgia in 2015, the late professor dedicated himself to lectures and writing, stating he would do his best until his last moment to explore solutions to inter-Korean conflict, South-South conflict, and North Korea-U.S. conflict, and to open the path to true peace and Korean reunification. (2015년 조지아대 교수직에서 퇴임한 고인은 남북갈등·남남갈등·북미갈등의 해법을 탐색하면서 진정한 평화와 한반도 통일의 길을 여는 데 여생의 마지막 순간까지 최선을 다하겠다며, 강연과 저술에 전념했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From March 2019 to December 2020, Professor Park serialized the story of his journey biweekly in *The Hankyoreh*, and these writings were published as 'Obsessed with Peace - The Memoirs of Park Han-sik' (Samin). In 2021, he received the 23rd Hankyoreh Unification Culture Award. (박 교수는 2019년 3월부터 2020년 12월까지 격주로 자신이 걸어온 길을 ‘한겨레’에 연재했고, 이 글들은 ‘평화에 미치다-박한식 회고록’(삼인)으로 출간됐다. 2021년에는 23회 한겨레통일문화상을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his memoirs, he stated that the reason for a scholar's existence is to academically explain the most painful problems of reality in our time and to consistently guide the way to solve those problems. He also revealed the following about the path he walked and his hopes: (그는 회고록에서 학자의 존재 이유는 우리 시대의 가장 고통스러운 현실의 문제를 학문적으로 설명하는 것, 그래서 그 문제를 해결할 수 있는 길을 꾸준히 안내하는 것에 있다고 했다. 또 자신이 걸어온 길과 소망에 대해 다음과 같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"For me, the problem to solve was the inter-Korean issue, and I believed that presenting the ideal form of a society capable of resolving the division and military tension between North and South, and designing and planning that society, was my role and duty as a scholar, and I devoted my life to it. (...) Since the Korean War, both Korea and North Korea have become prisoners of system competition and the security paradigm, demonizing each other, and a divided system where even dialogue and exchange, let alone reunification, are severed continues to this day. I hope to experience in my lifetime the thrill and joy of true peace and reunification between Korea and North Korea, but if that is difficult in terms of time, I hope to at least see the solid cornerstone of peace and reunification being laid." (“나에게 있어 해결해야 할 문제는 남북문제였고, 남북 분단과 군사적 긴장을 해결할 수 있는 이상적인 사회의 모습을 제시하고 그 사회를 도안하고 설계하는 것이 학자인 나의 역할이자 책무라고 믿으며 평생을 애면글면해왔다. (...) 한국전쟁 이후, 한국과 조선 모두 체제 경쟁과 안보 패러다임의 포로가 되어 서로를 악마화하면서 통일은커녕 대화와 교류도 단절된 분단체제가 지금도 지속되고 있다. 내 살아 생전에 한국과 조선의 진정한 평화와 통일의 감격과 환희를 누려볼 수 있기를 소망하지만, 그것이 시간적으로 어렵다면 평화와 통일의 단단한 초석이 놓이는 것만이라도 볼 수 있기를 바라본다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The current situation on the Korean Peninsula and in the world is far from his hopes, but for that very reason, the importance of the peace he yearned for has grown even greater. (지금 한반도와 세계의 상황은 그의 소망과 너무나 멀어져 있지만, 그래서 그가 염원했던 평화의 중요성은 더욱 커졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Park Min-hee &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박민희 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:minggu@hani.co.kr"&gt;minggu@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241096.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/426/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122501623.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike at Park Geun-hye's Request… "To Wage a Bigger Fight" (박근혜 요구에 장동혁 단식 중단…“더 큰 싸움 하려고”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241100.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike at Park Geun-hye's Request… "To Wage a Bigger Fight" (박근혜 요구에 장동혁 단식 중단…“더 큰 싸움 하려고”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/664/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2717690614296657.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;박근혜 전 대통령이 22일 국회 로텐더홀 단식 농성장에서 통일교·공천헌금 &amp;#x27;&amp;#x27;쌍특검&amp;#x27;&amp;#x27; 수용을 요구하며 여드레째 단식 중인 국민의힘 장동혁 대표를 방문해 인사하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, ended his 8-day hunger strike on the 22nd, stating, "I am ending the hunger strike today to wage a longer and bigger fight." (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 22일 “좀 더 길고 큰 싸움을 위해서 오늘 단식을 중단한다”며 8일간의 단식 투쟁을 끝냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Concluding his hunger strike at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall around 11:55 AM, Representative Jang said, "These eight days were spent with our 106 lawmakers, party chapter chairpersons, fellow party members, and the people. I thank everyone who stood with me. I will not forget the support you have shown." (장 대표는 이날 오전 11시55분께 국회 로텐더홀에서 진행하던 단식을 마무리하며 “106명의 우리 의원님들, 당협위원장님들, 당원동지들, 국민과 함께한 8일이었다. 함께해주신 모든 분께 감사드린다. 그 응원하는 마음을 잊지 않겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang stated, "I am ending the hunger strike today to wage a longer and bigger fight," adding, "However, the people's lament against the corrupt Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party of Korea's tyranny will flare up like a wildfire from today." He concluded by saying, "The true fast begins today. I will stop here." Representative Jang was transported to a hospital in a wheelchair. (장 대표는 “좀 더 길고 큰 싸움을 위해서 오늘 단식을 중단한다”며 “그러나 부패한 이재명 정권과 더불어민주당의 폭정을 향한 국민의 탄식은 오늘부터 들불처럼 타오를 것이다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “진정한 단식은 오늘부터가 시작이다. 여기까지 하겠다”며 말을 끝냈다. 장 대표는 휠체어를 탄 채 병원으로 이송됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, former President Park Geun-hye visited Representative Jang around 11:20 AM and requested he end his hunger strike. Representative Jang replied, "I will do so," leading to the conclusion of the hunger strike. (앞서 박근혜 전 대통령이 이날 오전 11시20분께 장 대표를 찾아 단식 중단을 요구했고, 장 대표가 “그렇게 하겠다”고 답하면서 단식투쟁이 마무리됐다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was reported that Representative Jang's health deteriorated rapidly on the 8th day of his hunger strike. He had planned to preside over the party's Supreme Council meeting at 9 AM but was unable to even sit due to health issues. Representative Jang had continued his fast despite being urged to go to the hospital the previous day. (단식 8일 차인 이날 장 대표의 건강은 급격히 악화한 것으로 전해졌다. 당장 대표는 이날 오전 9시 당 최고위원회의를 주재하려고 했으나 건강상 문제로 착석조차 하지 못했다. 장 대표는 전날 병원 이송 권유에도 거부하며 단식을 이어왔다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, Floor Leader Song Eon-seok announced through a notice to the press corps, "We will inherit the spirit of Representative Jang's life-risking hunger strike and wage a strong fight to introduce the dual special prosecutor laws." (이에 따라 송언석 원내대표는 이날 출입기자단 공지를 통해 “장 대표의 목숨 건 단식 투쟁의 뜻을 이어받아 쌍특검법 도입을 위한 강력한 투쟁을 전개해 나가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Representative Jang began his hunger strike at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall on the 15th, demanding the passage of the dual special prosecutor laws (Unification Church and nomination bribery special prosecutor laws). Within the People Power Party, demands such as "The first action of the Blue House Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs should be to visit the hunger strike site" (Floor Leader Song Eon-seok) and "It is right for the President to send even the Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs to console and show concern" (Vice Chairman for Organization Kang Myeong-gu) continued. However, the Democratic Party of Korea leadership, including newly appointed Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo, who had visited the Democratic Party leadership the previous day, did not visit Representative Jang's hunger strike site even once. (앞서 장 대표는 지난 15일 쌍특검법(통일교·공천헌금 특검법)을 요구하며 국회 로텐더홀에서 단식 투쟁에 돌입한 바 있다. 국민의힘에서는 “청와대 정무수석 첫 행보는 단식농성장 방문이어야 한다.”(송언석 원내대표) “대통령이 정무수석이라도 보내서 위로하고 걱정을 하는 게 맞다.”(강명구 조직부총장) 등 요구가 잇따랐으나, 전날 더불어민주당 지도부를 예방했던 홍익표 신임 정무수석을 비롯한 더불어민주당 지도부는 장 대표 단식 농성장을 한번도 방문하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241100.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/664/imgdb/original/2026/0122/2717690614296657.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Integration of Democratic and Innovation Parties is President Lee's Long-Held View"...Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, Reveals (“민주-혁신 양당 통합은 이 대통령 지론”…홍익표 정무수석 밝혀)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241113.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Integration of Democratic and Innovation Parties is President Lee's Long-Held View"...Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, Reveals (“민주-혁신 양당 통합은 이 대통령 지론”…홍익표 정무수석 밝혀)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690595890747_20260122502176.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs, stated regarding Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae's proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party that "I received a call from Representative Chung beforehand." (홍익표 청와대 정무수석이 더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 것과 관련해 “사전에 정 대표에게 연락을 받았다”고 22일 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters at the Chunchugwan of the Presidential Office this day, Senior Secretary Hong said, "The integration of the two parties and political integration have long been President Lee Jae-myung's established view," adding, "Since Representative Chung raised this issue and Representative Cho Kuk also said he would gather opinions within his party, we will watch how the discussions between the two parties proceed." (홍 수석은 이날 청와대 춘추관에서 기자들과 만나 “양당 통합과 정치적 통합은 평소 이재명 대통령의 지론이었다”며 “이 문제에 대해 정 대표가 제기했고, 조국 대표도 당내 의견을 수렴한다고 했으니까 양당 간 논의가 잘 진행되길 지켜보겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the day, Representative Chung Cheong-rae proposed a merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party ahead of the June 3 local elections, and Representative Cho Kuk stated, "We will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and intentions." (앞서 이날 오전 정청래 대표는 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 조국혁신당을 향해 합당을 제안했고, 조국 대표는 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정할 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241113.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690595890747_20260122502176.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party on Democratic-Innovation Integration Talks: "Not a Dream Team but a Doomed Team... A Diversionary Tactic for Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi" (민주·혁신 통합 논의에 국힘 “원팀 아닌 망팀…강선우·김병기 물타기”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241123.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502428.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안하고 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party criticized Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae on the 22nd for proposing a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party before the local elections, stating, "The Democratic Party is treating the local elections solely as a tool for extending its power." The Reform Party downplayed the significance, saying, "They are the same Chinese restaurant, so merging is right." (국민의힘은 22일 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 조국혁신당에 지방선거 전 합당을 제안한 데 대해 “민주당이 지방선거를 권력 연장의 도구로만 취급하고 있다”고 비판했다. 개혁신당은 “같은 중국집이니 합치는 게 맞다”고 의미를 축소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a commentary released that day, People Power Party spokesperson Ham In-kyung argued, "To the public's eyes, it looks like a 'big, broken-down bus' speeding along is extending a hand to the 'do-as-I-say-not-as-I-do' Cho Kuk Party (Innovation Party), saying, 'Don't drool over a few spots in the local elections, come ride our bus.'" He emphasized, "The problem is an accident," adding, "A broken-down bus is dangerous even driving alone; if the idea is to increase its size, the damage from an accident will be borne entirely by the people." (함인경 국민의힘 대변인은 이날 논평을 내어 “고장 난 채 질주하는 ‘덩치 큰 버스’가 내로남불 조국당(혁신당)에 ‘지방선거 몇몇 군데 침 흘리지 말고 우리 버스에 탑승하라’고 손을 내미는 장면으로 국민 눈에는 보인다”고 주장했다. 그는 “문제는 사고”라며 “고장 난 버스는 혼자 달려도 위험한데, 덩치까지 키우겠다는 발상이라면 사고 피해는 고스란히 국민이 떠안게 된다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Ham continued, "If the two parties merge to contest the local elections, it won't be a dream team but a doomed team. It will merely be seat coalition politics, covering each other's faults with size and pushing through with numbers to evade responsibility," and stated, "The local elections are not a playground for the ruling party to expand its power." (함 대변인은 이어 “두 당이 합쳐 지방선거를 치른다면 원팀이 아니라 망팀이다. 서로의 과오를 덩치로 덮고, 책임을 회피하기 위해 숫자로 밀어붙이는 의석 연합 정치가 될 뿐”이라며 “지방선거는 여당의 권력 확장 놀이터가 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party spokesperson Jo Yong-sul also issued a commentary, sharpening his criticism: "In the serious situation where Representative Jang Dong-hyuk's life-risking hunger strike has entered its eighth day, Representative Jeong came out with an absurd merger proposal. This is nothing but a blatant diversionary tactic to cover up various illegal suspicions surrounding lawmakers Kim Byeong-gi and Kang Seon-woo and suspicions of Unification Church involvement within the Democratic Party, and an expression of political ambition to strengthen his own position within the party." (조용술 국민의힘 대변인도 논평을 내어 “장동혁 대표의 목숨을 건 단식이 8일째 이어지는 엄중한 상황에서 정 대표가 황당한 합당 제안을 내놨다”며 “김병기·강선우 의원을 둘러싼 각종 불법 의혹과 민주당 내 통일교 연루 의혹을 덮기 위한 노골적인 물타기이자, 자신의 당내 입지를 강화하려는 정치적 야욕의 발로에 불과하다”고 날을 세웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok met with reporters after the party's Supreme Council meeting at the National Assembly this morning and said, "We shouldn't do politics like running the same Chinese restaurant with two separate phones." He added, "While there is a clear difference in stance regarding martial law between the Reform Party and the People Power Party, the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party are clearly the same Chinese restaurant." (이준석 개혁신당 대표는 이날 오전 국회에서 열린 당 최고위원회가 끝난 뒤 기자들과 만나 “같은 중국집인데 전화기 두 대 놓고 하는 식으로 정치하면 안 된다”며 “개혁신당과 국민의힘의 경우 계엄에 대한 입장에 선명한 차이가 있는데, 민주당과 혁신당은 분명히 같은 중국집”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee said, "When we previously proposed to the Innovation Party to work together on the special prosecution (related to the Unification Church suspicions), the Innovation Party effectively expressed refusal, likely leading the public to perceive it as a party wanting to be the 'Democratic Party's second team.'" He added, "If that's the case, then merging is actually the right thing to do." (이 대표는 “지난번에 (통일교 의혹) 특검 관련해서 혁신당 측에 같이 하자는 제안을 했을 때, 혁신당이 사실상 거부 의사를 밝히면서 국민에게 ‘민주당 이중대’가 되고 싶어 하는 당으로 인식됐을 것”이라며 “그렇다면 사실은 합치는 게 맞다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party Secretary-General Lee Dong-hoon posted on Facebook that day, writing, "In the end, the Innovation Party's final destination was the Democratic Party. It has essentially confessed to being a 'Democratic Party outer unit' that had no reason to exist from the start." He continued, "Now the choice is clear. The Reform Party will become a solid alternative protecting people's lives as a distinct third party that does not mix with injustice." (이동훈 개혁신당 사무총장은 이날 페이스북에 글을 올려 “결국 혁신당의 종착지는 민주당이었다. 처음부터 존재 이유가 없었던 ‘민주당 외곽부대’임을 스스로 고백한 꼴”이라며 “이제 선택지는 명확하다. 개혁신당은 불의와 섞이지 않는 선명한 제3당으로서 국민의 삶을 지키는 굳건한 대안이 되겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241123.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502428.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Na Kyung-won, Who Mocked 'KOSPI 5,000'... "Lee Jae-myung's Empty Promise" Recalled (‘코스피 5천’ 비웃던 나경원…“이재명 허황된 공약” 재소환)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241125.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Na Kyung-won, Who Mocked 'KOSPI 5,000'... "Lee Jae-myung's Empty Promise" Recalled (‘코스피 5천’ 비웃던 나경원…“이재명 허황된 공약” 재소환)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/905/543/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502443.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;나경원 국민의힘 의원. 유튜브 방송 ‘매불쇼’ 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the era of 'KOSPI 5,000', a key presidential campaign pledge of President Lee Jae-myung, became a reality on the 22nd, past remarks by opposition figures who confidently declared the pledge impossible are being re-examined. (22일 이재명 대통령의 대선 공약이었던 ‘코스피 5000’ 시대가 현실화하면서, 공약 달성이 불가능하다고 호언장담했던 야권 인사들의 과거 발언이 재조명되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI broke through 5,000 for the first time in its 46-year history during intraday trading, reactions from the ruling and opposition parties were sharply divided. The Democratic Party of Korea welcomed the news in a commentary issued in the name of spokesperson Moon Geum-ju, calling it "the result of the accumulation of consistent policy direction to correct the structural limitations the Korean economy had been facing." In contrast, the People Power Party did not issue any particular statement. Within the Democratic Party, celebratory posts from the leadership and party members continued. (이날 코스피가 개장 46년 만에 장중 사상 처음으로 5000을 돌파하자 여야 반응은 극명히 엇갈렸다. 더불어민주당은 이날 문금주 원내대변인 명의 논평에서 “한국 경제가 안고 있던 구조적 한계를 바로잡기 위한 일관된 정책 기조가 축적된 결과”라며 반색했다. 반면 국민의힘은 별다른 입장을 내놓지 않았다. 민주당 안에선 지도부를 비롯해 소속 의원들의 자축 글도 이어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP's silence appears related to its previously skeptical stance towards KOSPI 5,000. Last October, PPP leader Jang Dong-hyuk attended the 'PPP Committee for Enhancing Stock and Digital Asset Value Appointment Ceremony and First Plenary Meeting' held at the National Assembly and stated, "The Lee Jae-myung administration is shouting 'KOSPI 5,000' with its mouth, but let me be clear. The Lee Jae-myung administration, held captive by the Korean Confederation of Trade Unions, can absolutely never achieve KOSPI 5,000." He added, "Even now, it is only pushing legislation that goes in the opposite direction of KOSPI 5,000." The PPP had predicted that the Commercial Act revision bill and the so-called "yellow envelope law" (amendments to Articles 2 and 3 of the Trade Union and Labor Relations Adjustment Act), which the party opposed as an "economic insurrection law," would become obstacles to the stock index's rise. (국민의힘의 침묵은 코스피 5000에 회의적이었던 그간의 태도와 무관치 않아 보인다. 장동혁 대표는 지난해 10월 국회에서 열린 ‘국민의힘 주식 및 디지털자산 밸류업 특위 임명장 수여식 및 1차 전체회의’에 참석해 “이재명 정부는 입으로 코스피 5000을 외치고 있지만 단호하게 말씀드린다. 민주노총에 사로잡힌 이재명 정부는 절대 코스피 5000을 달성할 수 없다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “지금도 계속해서 코스피 5000과 거꾸로 가는 입법들만 밀어붙이고 있다”고 덧붙였다. 국민의힘이 “경제내란법”이라며 반대한 상법 개정안과 노란봉투법(노동조합 및 노동관계조정법 2·3조 개정안)이 주가지수 상승의 걸림돌이 될 것으로 내다본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even last April, when then-presidential candidate Lee Jae-myung announced policies to revitalize the stock market and stated he would "resolve the Korea Discount and usher in the era of a stock index of 5,000," the PPP dismissed it as "empty talk." (지난해 4월 이 대통령이 대선후보이던 시절 주식시장 활성화 정책을 발표하면서 “코리아 디스카운트를 해소해 주가지수 5000 시대를 열겠다”고 밝혔을 때도, 국민의힘은 “허황된 얘기”라고 일축했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Moon-soo, former Minister of Employment and Labor and the PPP's presidential candidate at the time, pointed out in a May last year meeting of the party's Central Election Committee held at the Korea Exchange, while criticizing the Democratic Party's push for the yellow envelope law and the Serious Accidents Punishment Act, "It doesn't make sense for someone who is worsening the most fundamental aspects to say they will raise stocks to 5,000." (국민의힘 대선후보였던 김문수 전 고용노동부 장관은 지난해 5월 한국거래소에서 열린 중앙선거대책위원회 회의에서 민주당이 추진한 노란봉투법과 중대재해처벌법 등을 비판하면서 “기본적인 부분을 가장 악화시키는 사람이 주식을 5000까지 올리겠다는 건 말이 앞뒤가 안 맞는다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Na Kyung-won, who was a co-chair of the election committee, also said, "Recently, candidate Lee Jae-myung, with his anti-market, anti-corporate DNA, is shouting the empty slogan of a 'KOSPI 5,000 era.' It's like a mirage," adding, "Lee Jae-myung's KOSPI 5,000 is a castle built on sand." Rep. Na stated, "Stock indices don't rise with slogans. It's only possible through the hard-earned value growth of companies, a solid economic foundation, and the accumulation of market trust," and also said, "Candidate Lee Jae-myung's promise of KOSPI 5,000 is like saying he will build a fancy two- or three-story house while skipping the foundation work." (공동선대위원장이었던 나경원 의원도 “최근 반시장, 반기업 디엔에이(DNA) 이재명 후보가 코스피 5000시대라는 허황된 구호를 외치고 있다. 마치 신기루 같다”며 “이재명식 코스피 5000은 모래 위의 성”이라고 말했다. 나 의원은 “주가지수는 구호로 오르지 않는다. 기업의 피땀 어린 가치 성장, 튼튼한 경제 기초 체력, 그리고 시장의 신뢰가 쌓여야 가능하다”며 “이재명 후보의 코스피 5000 약속은 마치 기초공사는 생략한 채 화려한 2층, 3층 집을 올리겠다는 말과 같다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a presidential candidate TV debate held a month later, similarly cynical responses continued: "Isn't it too much to say it will go to 5,000?" (former Minister Kim) and "I think they are taking it too lightly" (Lee Jun-seok, then the presidential candidate for the Reformist Party). At the time, the KOSPI was in the 2,000 range, so they viewed it as unachievable. (한 달 뒤 열린 대선후보 티브이(TV) 토론회에서도 “5000까지 가겠다고 말하는 건 너무 심한 것 아니냐”(김 전 장관), “너무 가볍게 생각하는 거 아닌가 한다”(이준석 당시 개혁신당 대선후보) 같은 냉소적인 반응이 이어졌다. 당시 코스피는 2000대였던 만큼, 실현 가능성이 없다고 본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even when the KOSPI rose after the new administration took office, the opposition downplayed it as a "new business bump." Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reformist Party, said at a Supreme Council meeting held at the National Assembly last August, "The person who ultimately loses the most by trading stocks is precisely the one who made money initially through luck. It's often called 'beginner's luck' or a 'new business bump'," adding, "When people make money luckily at the beginning, they get excited. They mistakenly think they are Warren Buffett. Then, eventually, they run wild like a car with its brakes off and fail spectacularly." (새 정부 취임 뒤 코스피가 상승세를 탔을 때도 야당은 “개업빨”이라며 평가절하했다. 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 지난해 8월 국회에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “주식하다가 결국 가장 크게 망하는 사람은 바로 처음 운으로 돈을 번 사람이다. 흔히 ‘신참자의 운&amp;#x27;, ‘개업빨&amp;#x27;이라고 한다”며 “초반에 운 좋게 돈을 벌면 사람은 흥분한다. 마치 내가 워런 버핏이라도 된 듯 착각한다. 그러다 결국 브레이크 풀린 차처럼 폭주하다가 크게 망하는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee also said, "I hope the current Lee Jae-myung administration does not become such a 'new business bump' government. It should not mistake the release of the structural pressure of the martial law-like political situation for its own competence and run wild," and asked, "How far must the KOSPI fall for them to come to their senses?" (이 대표는 “저는 지금 이재명 정권이 그런 개업빨 정부가 되지 않길 바란다. 계엄 정국이라는 구조적 눌림목이 풀린 것을 자기 실력으로 착각하고 폭주하면 안 된다”며 “코스피가 어디까지 빠져야 정신을 차릴 것인가”라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241125.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/905/543/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502443.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[News Dive] KOSPI Breaches '5000' Mark 7 Months After Government Inauguration ([뉴스 다이브] 정부 출범 7개월 만에 코스피 ‘5000’ 돌파)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241127.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[News Dive] KOSPI Breaches '5000' Mark 7 Months After Government Inauguration ([뉴스 다이브] 정부 출범 7개월 만에 코스피 ‘5000’ 돌파)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502477.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Featuring: Political Correspondent Jang Yun-seon, Lawyer Jang Yun-mi, Hankyoreh21 Team 2 Leader Kim Wan, Host: Ko Hyun-joon. KOSPI breaches '5000' mark 7 months after government inauguration... "A new milestone" / "A high-stakes showdown with North Korea? The economy is ruined..." President Lee's blunt press conference / Han Deok-su sentenced to 23 years for involvement in coup attempt, accomplices also expected to face heavy sentences / 'Anger at Governor Lee Jae-myung' Lee Man-hee's audio recording released... even mentions Yoon Suk-yeol / Even soccer tournaments... connecting links of 'collusion between politics and religion' involving Shincheonji and the Unification Church / Jeong Cheong-rae proposes merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, "Let's hold local elections together" / Jang Dong-hyeok ends hunger strike "For a bigger fight...". Please tune in for today's (January 22nd) News Dive. (출연: 장윤선 정치전문기자, 장윤미 변호사, 김완 한겨레21 취재2팀 팀장, 진행: 고현준. 정부 출범 7개월 만에 코스피 ‘5000’ 돌파...“새 이정표” / “북한과 고자세로 한판? 경제 망해...”이 대통령의 직설 회견 / 한덕수 친위쿠데타 가담 징역 23년, 공범들도 줄줄이 중형 전망 / ‘이재명 지사에 분노’ 이만희 육성 공개...윤석열 언급까지 / 축구대회까지...신천지·통일교 ‘정교유착’ 연결고리 / 정청래, 조국혁신당에 “지선 같이 치르자” 합당 제안 / 장동혁 단식 중단 “더 큰 싸움 위해...”. 오늘 (1월 22일) 뉴스 다이브 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241127.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502477.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Promotion Council Holds In-Person Meeting After 4 Years... Discusses 'Import of North Korean Food Products' (남북교류추진협, 4년 만에 대면 회의…‘북한산 식품 반입’ 등 논의)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1241128.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Promotion Council Holds In-Person Meeting After 4 Years... Discusses 'Import of North Korean Food Products' (남북교류추진협, 4년 만에 대면 회의…‘북한산 식품 반입’ 등 논의)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502573.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정동영 통일부 장관이 22일 서울 종로구 정부서울청사에서 열린 제340차 남북교류협력추진협의회를 주재하고 있다. 연합뉴&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government held an in-person meeting of the Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Promotion Council (IECPC) on the 22nd for the first time in four years. This is an expression of strong will to normalize inter-Korean exchange and cooperation and develop it into an improvement in inter-Korean relations. During the previous Yoon Suk Yeol administration, not a single in-person meeting was held. (정부는 22일 남북교류협력추진협의회(교추협) 대면 회의를 4년 만에 열었다. 남북교류협력을 정상화해 남북관계 개선으로 발전시키겠다는 강력한 의지의 표현이다. 전임 윤석열 정부 기간엔 대면 회의가 한 차례도 열리지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Unification announced that the government held the 340th in-person meeting of the IECPC at the main building of the Government Complex Seoul, presided over by Minister of Unification Jung Dong-young, and decided to allocate 17.1 billion won from the Inter-Korean Cooperation Fund to seven inter-Korean exchange and cooperation projects, including the 'Joint North-South Compilation Project for the Great Dictionary of the Korean People's Language'. It is reported that the meeting also discussed a draft notification on 'Procedures for Inspecting the Import of North Korean Food Products'. (정부는 이날 정부서울청사 본관에서 정동영 통일부 장관 주재로 제340차 교추협 대면 회의를 열어 ‘겨레말큰사전 남북공동편찬사업’ 등 7건의 남북교류협력 관련 사업에 남북협력기금 171억원을 지원하기로 의결했다고 통일부가 밝혔다. 이날 회의에선 ‘북한산 식품의 반입 검사 절차 등에 관한 고시’ 제정안도 논의됐다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Jung, who serves as the ex officio chairman of the IECPC, stated, "It has been exactly four years since the last in-person IECPC meeting," and added, "The Lee Jae-myung administration's strong will is to rebuild a house on the ruins of inter-Korean relations. This occasion is to reaffirm that will once again." The last in-person IECPC meeting was held on February 10, 2022, during the final year of the Moon Jae-in administration, presided over by then Minister of Unification Lee In-young, making this the first in four years. Although IECPC meetings were held several times during the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, they were all conducted as written meetings, not in-person ones. Regarding the significance of holding an in-person IECPC meeting after four years, the Ministry of Unification stated it "holds meaning in normalizing the role of the government-civilian cooperation body for inter-governmental consultation and cooperation on inter-Korean exchange and cooperation." (교추협 당연직 위원장인 정 장관은 “교추협 대면 회의가 꼭 4년 만”이라며 “남북관계 폐허 위에 다시 집을 짓겠다는 것이 이재명 정부의 강력한 의지다. 그 의지를 다시 한번 밝히는 자리”라고 밝혔다. 교추협 대면 회의는 문재인 정부 마지막 해인 2022년 2월10일 이인영 당시 통일부 장관 주재로 열린 뒤 4년 만이다. 윤석열 정부 시기에도 교추협 회의가 여러 차례 열렸으나 모두 대면 회의가 아닌 서면 회의로 갈음했다. 통일부는 교추협을 4년 만에 대면회의로 연 사실과 관련해 “남북 교류협력에 관한 정부 간 협의 및 민관협력 기구의 역할을 정상화했다는 데 의의가 있다”고 의미를 담았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, Minister Jung recalled the policy to promote the 'Seoul-Beijing High-Speed Railway Construction' project included in the presidential work report on December 19 last year, stating, "We must lift the curtain of hostility and confrontation and reopen all roads and railways leading to the continent, and the Lee Jae-myung administration is fully prepared for this." He further emphasized, "We must reopen the roads to Mount Kumgang and Kaesong, and open new roads to Wonsan-Kalma and Mount Paektu-Samjiyon." He then stressed, "The surest path to creating peace is inter-Korean exchange," and added, "Through reciprocal, multilateral, and groundbreaking cooperation concepts, we will definitely find a path to resume inter-Korean exchange." (정 장관은 회의에서 지난해 12월19일 대통령 업무보고에 담긴 ‘서울∼베이징 고속철 건설’ 사업 추진 방침 등을 환기하며 “적대와 대결의 장막을 걷어내고 대륙으로 가는 모든 도로 철도를 다시 열어야 하고, 이를 위한 이재명 정부의 준비는 모두 돼 있다”고 밝혔다. 이어 “금강산과 개성으로 가는 길을 다시 열어야 하고, 원산갈마와 백두산 삼지연으로 가는 길을 새로 열어야 한다”고 거듭 강조했다. 그러곤 “평화를 만드는 가장 확실한 길은 남북 간 교류”라며 “호혜적이고 다자적인, 획기적인 협력 구상을 통해 남북 교류재개의 길을 반드시 찾아갈 것”이라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, the following items for 2026 Inter-Korean Cooperation Fund support were reviewed and approved: △Commissioned projects of the Association for Supporting Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation (4.75 billion won) △Joint North-South Compilation Project for the Great Dictionary of the Korean People's Language (2.607 billion won) △Projects related to the Joint North-South Excavation Survey of Manwoldae in Kaesong (845 million won) △Inter-Korean Separated Family Gene Testing Project (612 million won) △Operating expenses for the Korean Peninsula Unification Future Center (5.192 billion won) △Integrated management and operation of Panmunjom tours (2.209 billion won) △Expenses for the Kaesong Industrial Complex Support Foundation (Liquidation Entity) (847 million won). All seven approved items are ongoing projects that have been carried out previously. (이날 회의에선 2026년도 남북협력기금 지원 안건으로 △남북교류협력지원협회 위탁사업(47억5천만원) △겨레말큰사전 남북공동편찬사업(26억700만원) △개성만월대 남북공동발굴조사 관련 사업(8억4500만원) △남북 이산가족 유전자검사사업(6억1200만원), △한반도통일미래센터 운영 경비(51억9200만원) △판문점 견학 통합 관리 운영(22억900만원) △개성공업지구지원재단(청산법인) 경비(8억4700만원)를 심의·의결했다. 의결된 7건 모두 전부터 해오던 계속 사업이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The draft notification on 'Procedures for Inspecting the Import of North Korean Food Products' reviewed that day contains measures to relax the documentation required for import declaration and on-site inspection requirements, considering the severed state of inter-Korean relations, while strengthening safety inspections. As on-site inspections in North Korea are impossible when safety issues arise with imported food products, a compromise was made to conduct safety inspections for each import. (이날 심의한 ‘북한산 식품의 반입 검사 절차 등에 관한 고시’ 제정안은 남북관계 단절의 상황을 고려해 수입신고에 필요한 서류와 현지실사 요건을 완화하면서도 안전검사는 강화하는 내용이다. 수입 식품에 안전 문제가 불거졌을 때 북한산은 현지실사를 할 수 없기에 수입 때마다 안전검사를 하는 식으로 절충한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Jung said, "Moving forward, in the direction of private sector leadership with government support, we will carry out legal and institutional improvements to restore the ecosystem of inter-Korean exchange and cooperation," and added, "Starting today, let's revitalize the IECPC (in-person meetings) and pool the wisdom of the government and private sector to find a path for peaceful coexistence and inter-Korean peaceful exchange." (정 장관은 “앞으로 민간이 주도하고 정부가 지원하는 방향에서 남북교류협력 생태계의 회복을 위한 법적 제도적 정비를 하겠다”며 “오늘을 시작으로 교추협(대면회의)을 활성화해 정부와 민간이 함께 지혜를 모아 평화공존과 남북평화교류의 길을 찾아나가자”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The IECPC is a government-civilian consultative body established under the 'Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Act' within the Ministry of Unification. It reviews and decides on matters such as whether to provide cooperation fund support for inter-Korean exchange and cooperation projects undertaken by the government and private sector. It is composed of 25 members in total, with the Minister of Unification serving as chairman, including government members at the vice-ministerial level from relevant ministries such as the National Security Office, Office for Government Policy Coordination, Ministry of Economy and Finance, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Ministry of Justice, and Ministry of Unification, along with civilian members. (교추협은 ‘남북교류협력에 관한 법률’에 따라 통일부에 설치된 민관협의체로 정부와 민간의 남북 교류협력 사업에 협력기금 지원 여부 등을 심의·의결한다. 통일부 장관이 위원장을 맡고 국가안보실·국무조정실·재정경제부·외교부·법무부·통일부 등 관련 부처 차관급 정부위원과 민간위원 등 모두 25명으로 이뤄져 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Je-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1241128.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/415/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502573.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "If reforms cling to justification and increase chaos, it's not reform"... Likely referring to prosecution reform (이 대통령 “명분 매달려 혼란 가중하면 개혁 아냐”…검찰개혁 언급한 듯)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241131.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "If reforms cling to justification and increase chaos, it's not reform"... Likely referring to prosecution reform (이 대통령 “명분 매달려 혼란 가중하면 개혁 아냐”…검찰개혁 언급한 듯)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/788/452/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502747.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령과 강훈식 비서실장이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관회의 참석을 위해 회의실로 향하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said, "If any reform measure, far from improving the people's lives, clings to justification and grand causes and increases suffering and chaos, that is not reform." (이재명 대통령이 “국민 삶을 개선하기는커녕 어떤 개혁 조치가 명분과 대의에 매달려 고통과 혼란을 가중한다면 그건 개혁이 아니다”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks while presiding over a meeting of senior secretaries at the Blue House on the afternoon of the 22nd, stating, "The sole purpose of governing on behalf of the sovereign people, first and foremost, is to tangibly improve the lives and livelihoods of the people." (이 대통령은 22일 오후 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관회의에서 “주권자를 대리해서 국정 운영을 하는 것은 첫째도 둘째도 오로지 국민의 삶, 민생을 실질적으로 개선하기 위한 것”이라며 이렇게 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reform measures mentioned by President Lee are interpreted to include prosecution reform. At a New Year's press conference held the previous day at the Blue House's state guesthouse, President Lee also said, "The core of prosecution reform is not to strip the prosecution of its power. It is the means and process," adding, "The true ultimate goal is the relief of the people's rights." (이 대통령이 언급한 개혁 조치는 검찰개혁을 포함한 것으로 해석된다. 이 대통령은 전날 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서도 “검찰개혁의 핵심은 검찰의 권력을 빼앗는 게 아니다. 수단과 과정”이라며 “진짜 최종 목표는 국민의 권리 구제”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "The success or failure of the 'Five Great Transitions,' which are core state goals, also depends on what kind of changes and to what extent 50 million citizens can feel in their daily lives," adding, "The same goes for reform tasks." At the New Year's press conference held the previous day, President Lee presented five major transitions: △region-led growth, △inclusive growth sharing opportunities and failures, △sustainable growth based on safety, △attractive growth led by culture, and △stable growth underpinned by peace. (이 대통령은 “핵심 국정 목표인 ‘5대 대전환’의 성패도 5천만 국민이 실생활에서 어떤 변화를 얼마만큼 체감할 수 있느냐에 달려 있다”며 “개혁과제도 마찬가지”라고 말했다. 이 대통령은 전날 열린 신년 기자회견에서 △지방 주도 성장 △기회·과실 나누는 모두의 성장 △안전 기반한 지속가능한 성장 △문화가 이끄는 매력적인 성장 △평화가 뒷받침하는 안정적 성장 등 5가지 대전환을 제시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Based on firm will and clear direction, we must carefully judge and meticulously examine from a practical and effective perspective which direction helps protect the people's human rights and guarantee their substantive rights," adding, "Changing the paradigm of growth and pushing for reforms are ultimately all for the people, by the people, and done by the people." (이 대통령은 “확고한 의지와 명확한 방향성을 바탕으로 어느 방향이 국민의 인권 보호와 실질적인 권리 보장에 도움이 되는지를 실용적인 관점에서, 실효적인 관점에서 신중하게 판단하고 꼼꼼하게 봐야 한다”며 “성장의 패러다임을 바꾸는 일도, 개혁을 추진하는 일도 결국 모두 국민을 위한 것이고 국민에 의한 것이고, 국민이 하는 일”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also called for a faster pace in state affairs management. President Lee said, "I ask that you pick up the pace a bit more than now," adding, "The time we have to work is also limited, and as time passes, our driving force diminishes." He then emphasized, "Only by reforming what can be reformed as soon as possible can there be changes that the people can feel." (이 대통령은 또 속도감 있는 국정운영 추진을 주문했다. 이 대통령은 “지금보다 좀 더 속도를 내 주시길 부탁한다”며 “우리가 일할 수 있는 시간도 제한적이고 시간이 지날수록 추진 동력도 떨어진다”고 말했다. 이어 “하루라도 빨리 개혁 가능한 조치는 개혁을 해놔야 국민이 체감하는 변화도 있을수 있다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee urged, "I feel time is truly precious. Please cooperate well so that the National Assembly legislation can also pick up speed, and encourage government ministries and agencies, who are already working hard, to move faster and produce visible results early." (이 대통령은 “시간이 참으로 아깝단 생각이 든다. 국회 입법도 속도를 낼수 있도록 협력을 잘 해주고, 정부 부처·청들도 지금 열심히 하고 있지만 더 속도를 내서 가시적인 성과를 조기에 낼 수 있게 독려해 달라”고 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241131.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/788/452/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122502747.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea Considers Joining 'Trump Gaza Peace Council' with 1.5 Trillion Won Membership Fee... UK, France, China Say "No" (한국, 회비 1.5조원 ‘트럼프 가자 평화위’ 가입하나…영·프·중은 “노”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241173.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503418.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난해 8월25일(현지시각) 미국 워싱턴 백악관에서 열린 한미 정상회담에 앞서 방명록 서명을 준비하며 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 안내를 받고 있다. 워싱턴/연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, a Ministry of Foreign Affairs official stated that South Korea is "at the stage of reviewing the charter" of the new multilateral organization 'Gaza Peace Council' being promoted by U.S. President Donald Trump, regarding whether the country will join. (도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 추진하는 새로운 다자 기구인 ‘가자 평화위원회’에 한국이 가입할지를 두고, 외교부 관계자가 “평화위 헌장 내용을 검토하는 단계”라고 22일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters that day, the Foreign Ministry official said, "We will decide after reviewing how the Peace Council can contribute to peace and security in the Gaza Strip, and what contributions we can make if we participate." The Foreign Ministry had initially confirmed on the 20th that South Korea had also received an invitation to the Peace Council and stated it was "under review," and this statement provided more specific details of the review. The Foreign Ministry official added, "We are also trying to understand the responses of countries with similar (participation or non-participation) stances." (외교부 관계자는 이날 기자들을 만나 “평화위원회가 (가자지구) 평화와 안전에 어떻게 기여할 수 있는지, 또 (한국이) 참여할 경우 우리가 어떤 기여를 할 수 있는지 등을 검토 후 결정 내릴 것”이라고 밝혔다. 외교부는 지난 20일 한국도 평화위 초청을 받았다고 처음 확인한 뒤 “검토 중”이란 입장을 밝혔는데, 보다 구체적인 검토 내용을 밝힌 것이다. 외교부 관계자는 “(참여 또는 불참) 입장이 유사한 국가와 (해당 국가의) 대응을 파악하려고 노력 중”이라고도 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that the draft charter of the Peace Council sent by the U.S. government does not contain separate membership fee regulations and states that expenses will be covered through voluntary contributions from each country. It is said that a contribution of $1 billion (1.5 trillion won) exempts a member country from the three-year term limit. President Trump plans to hold a charter signing ceremony locally on this day, the second day of his participation in the Davos Forum in Switzerland. (미국 정부가 보낸 평화위 헌장 초안에는 가입비 규정이 따로 없고, 각국의 자발적 기여를 통해 경비를 충당한다는 내용이 담긴 것으로 전해졌다. 10억달러(1조5000억원)를 기여하면 회원국 3년 임기 제한도 받지 않는다고 한다. 트럼프 대통령은 스위스 다보스포럼 참석 이틀째인 이날, 현지에서 평화위 헌장 서명식을 열 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Trump announced plans to establish a Peace Council for the purpose of ending the war and reconstruction in the Gaza Strip on the 15th. The U.S. government has sent invitations to join the Peace Council to 60 countries, including the European Union, France, the United Kingdom, Japan, China, and Russia. Ultimately, there is a prevailing observation that through this organization, President Trump aims to create an international conflict resolution body to replace the United Nations (UN). Immediately, U.S. allies and UN Security Council permanent members France and the United Kingdom have expressed their opposition to joining the Peace Council. China also expressed a negative stance, saying it will "uphold the principle of a UN-centered international order." Japan, like South Korea, is at the stage of reviewing whether to participate. (트럼프 대통령은 지난 15일 가자지구 종전과 재건 목적의 평화위원회 창설 계획을 밝혔다. 미국 정부는 유럽연합과 프랑스, 영국, 일본, 중국, 러시아 등 60개국에 평화위 가입 초청장을 보낸 상태다. 궁극적으론 이 기구를 통해 트럼프 대통령이 유엔(UN)을 대체할 분쟁 해결 국제기구를 만들 것이란 관측이 우세하다. 당장 미국의 동맹이자 유엔 상임이사국인 프랑스와 영국은 평화위 가입 반대 의사를 밝혔다. 중국도 “유엔 중심의 국제 질서 원칙을 수호할 것”이라며 부정적인 입장을 내비쳤다. 일본은 우리와 마찬가지로 참가 여부를 검토하는 단계다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of now, about 20 countries have decided to participate in the Peace Council, including Israel, Hungary, Belarus, Argentina, and Vietnam. Major Muslim countries Saudi Arabia, Türkiye, Egypt, Jordan, Indonesia, Pakistan, Qatar, and the United Arab Emirates (UAE) formalized their membership in the Peace Council on the 21st. President Trump said on this day that Russian President Vladimir Putin had also decided to participate in the Peace Council, but President Putin has stated he is still reviewing the matter. (현시점 평화위 참여를 결정한 나라는 이스라엘과 헝가리, 벨라루스, 아르헨티나, 베트남 등 20여개국이다. 주요 무슬림 국가인 사우디아라비아와 튀르키예, 이집트, 요르단, 인도네시아, 파키스탄, 카타르, 아랍에미리트(UAE)는 21일 평화위 가입을 공식화했다. 트럼프 대통령은 이날 블라디미르 푸틴 러시아 대통령도 평화위 참여를 결정했다고 말했지만, 푸틴 대통령은 아직 검토 중이란 입장을 냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241173.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503418.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:42:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Impeached Park Geun-hye as an exit strategy?"... Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike ends as a 'show' (“탄핵 박근혜가 출구전략이라니”…‘쇼’로 끝난 장동혁의 단식)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241186.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690718730118_20260122503499.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검&amp;#x27; 수용을 요구하며 여드레째 단식 농성 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표(왼쪽)가 22일 국회 로텐더홀 단식 농성장을 찾은 박근혜 전 대통령과 악수하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was none other than former President Park Geun-hye who ended the hunger strike by People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, which had no end in sight. Inside and outside political circles, there are criticisms pointing out that the appearance of him obediently ending his hunger strike at the urging of a former president who was impeached for the state affairs interference scandal and expelled from the party is "bizarre." (출구가 보이지 않던 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식을 끝낸 건 다름 아닌 박근혜 전 대통령이었다. 정치권 안팎에서는 국정농단 사건으로 탄핵당하고 당에서도 제명당한 전직 대통령의 권유에 순순히 단식을 종결한 모양새가 “해괴하다”는 지적이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the morning of the 22nd, there seemed to be no end in sight for the hunger strike by PPP leader Jang, which had entered its eighth day. From the sixth day of the fast, his blood oxygen saturation plummeted, and his health condition, requiring him to wear an oxygen concentrator, led to diagnoses that morning such as "cardiac arrest could occur at any time" and "medically at the limit of human endurance" (according to PPP lawmaker Seo Myeong-ok, a former doctor). Calls from inside and outside the party for him to stop the hunger strike poured in, but Leader Jang refused to be hospitalized, stubbornly maintaining his stance that "I will be buried here." (22일 오전까지도 여드레째를 맞은 장 대표의 단식 중단은 기약이 없는 것처럼 보였다. 단식 엿새째부터 산소포화도가 급격히 낮아져 산소발생기를 착용한 장 대표의 건강 상태는 이날 오전 “언제든 심정지 가능성이 있다”, “의학적으로 인간의 한계”(의사 출신 서명옥 국민의힘 의원)라는 진단이 나올 정도였다. 당 안팎에선 단식 중단을 요구하는 목소리가 빗발쳤으나, 장 대표는 “나는 여기에 묻힐 것”이라는 입장을 굽히지 않은 채 병원 이송을 완강히 거부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the party leader's consciousness fading to the point where he could not even preside over Supreme Council meetings, a somber mood hung over the leadership. Presiding over the Supreme Council meeting in Jang's stead that day, floor leader Song Eon-seok said, "I cannot contain my sorrow at the sight of Leader Jang, whose health has deteriorated extremely, and I cannot contain my anger at the Democratic Party of Korea's two-faced DNA." (당 대표가 의식이 혼미해 최고위원 주관조차 못 하는 상황에, 지도부 안에선 침울함이 감돌았다. 장 대표를 대신해 이날 최고위를 주재한 송언석 원내대표는 “건강이 극도로 악화된 장 대표의 모습에 비통함을 금할 수 없고, 더불어민주당의 인면수심 디엔에이(DNA)에 분노를 금할 수가 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Park's visit to the hunger strike site took place abruptly amid this situation. Appearing at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall, where the hunger strike site was located, around 11:20 a.m. that day, former President Park said, "For the future, I hope you will stop the hunger strike today and recover your health," adding, "I hope you will promise here today that you will now stop the hunger strike." Leader Jang replied, "I will do so." About 30 minutes later, Leader Jang announced he would end the hunger strike and was transported to a hospital. (박 전 대통령의 단식 농성장 방문은 이런 상황 속에서 전격적으로 이뤄졌다. 이날 오전 11시20분께 단식 농성장이 있는 국회 로텐더홀에 모습을 드러낸 박 전 대통령은 “훗날을 위해 오늘 단식을 이제 멈추시고 건강을 회복하셨으면 한다”며 “오늘 이 자리에서 이제 단식을 그만두겠다, 이렇게 약속을 해주셨으면 합니다”고 말했다. 장 대표는 “그렇게 하겠다”고 답했다. 장 대표는 이로부터 30여분 뒤 단식을 중단하겠다고 밝히고 병원으로 이송됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Critical reactions emerged from inside and outside political circles. This is because it created the appearance of pulling a former president, who lost the presidency in 2017 due to the state affairs interference scandal and was even stripped of party membership, back into the center of politics. Former President Park, whose 22-year sentence for bribery and abuse of power was finalized, served 4 years and 9 months in prison before being pardoned and having her rights restored by former President Moon Jae-in in 2021, and has since kept her distance from political circles. Her visit to the hunger strike site that day was also her first visit to the National Assembly since her impeachment. (정치권 안팎에선 비판적인 반응이 나왔다. 국정농단 사건으로 2017년 대통령직을 상실해 당적까지 박탈된 전직 대통령을 다시금 중앙정치로 끌어들인 모양새가 됐기 때문이다. 박 전 대통령은 뇌물과 직권남용 혐의로 22년형이 확정돼 4년9개월간 복역하다가 2021년 문재인 전 대통령에 의해 사면·복권된 뒤 정치권과 거리를 둬왔다. 이날 단식 농성장 방문도 탄핵 뒤 처음으로 국회를 찾은 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Shin Jang-sik of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party posted on Facebook that day, criticizing, "It's a bizarre scene. The exit for the rose hunger strike is Park Geun-hye?" He added, "PPP's tearful Jang Dong-hyuk, crying while visiting impeached No. 2 Yoon Suk Yeol, and sobbing while ending his hunger strike on the orders of impeached No. 1 Park Geun-hye. The PPP's class is such that you need to be impeached to move the party leader." (신장식 조국혁신당 의원은 이날 페이스북에 글을 올려 “기괴한 장면이다. 장미 단식의 출구가 박근혜라니”라며 “탄핵 2호 윤석열을 면회하며 울고, 탄핵 1호 박근혜의 지시로 단식을 풀며 울먹이는 국민의힘 눈물 장동혁 선생. 탄핵 정도는 당해줘야 당대표를 움직일 수 있는 국힘 클라스(클래스)”라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seo Yong-joo, head of the Mac Political and Social Research Institute, also pointed out in an interview with MBC's 'News Outside' that day, "When you see a leadership that supports an impeached president and a president indicted for rebellion and facing the death penalty meeting to devise an exit strategy for a hunger strike and shaking hands, you wonder where the hope for conservatism is," adding, "It gives an image of an 'impeachment party'." Director Seo added that the two "trivialized a desperate means of struggle." (서용주 맥 정치사회연구소장도 이날 문화방송(MBC) ‘뉴스외전’과 인터뷰에서 “탄핵당한 대통령과, 내란범으로 사형을 구형받은 대통령을 지지하는 지도부가 만나 단식의 출구전략을 짜고 손잡는 모습을 보면 보수의 희망은 어디 있는가 (생각이 든다)”며 “탄핵당이라는 이미지를 준다”고 지적했다. 서 소장은 두 사람이 “절체절명의 투쟁 수단을 희화화했다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawyer Shin In-gyu also appeared on the YouTube show 'Mae Bul Show' that day and pointed out, "Park Geun-hye is a state affairs interference criminal. Politically, she is nothing," adding, "From Leader Jang Dong-hyuk's perspective, it's a bizarre method where he puts on a show to gain TK (Daegu-Gyeongbuk) public sentiment while also finding a way out of the hunger strike." (신인규 변호사도 이날 유튜브 방송 ‘매불쇼’에 출연해 “박근혜는 국정농단범이다. 정치적으로 아무것도 아니”라며 “장동혁 대표 입장에서 티케이(TK·대구경북) 민심을 얻는 쇼를 하면서도, 단식도 빠져나오는 건데, 해괴한 방식”이라고 꼬집었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241186.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690718730118_20260122503499.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:41:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"President Lee Instructs Visit to Jang Dong-hyeok"... Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo Meets with Song Eon-seok (“이 대통령, 장동혁 병문안 지시”…홍익표 정무수석, 송언석 만나)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241187.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690718652031_20260122503501.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;홍익표(오른쪽) 신임 청와대 정무수석과 송언석 국민의힘 원내대표가 22일 국회에서 만나 악수하고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs at the Blue House, has expressed his intention to visit Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, who has stopped his hunger strike and been hospitalized. However, regarding Jang's demand for a 'dual special prosecutor' investigation, he stated it is "a matter for the ruling and opposition parties to agree upon." (홍익표 청와대 정무수석이 단식농성을 중단하고 병원에 입원한 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 병문안하겠다는 뜻을 밝혔다. 다만 장 대표가 요구했던 ‘쌍특검’ 수용에 대해서는 “여야가 합의할 사안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the afternoon of the 22nd, Secretary Hong met with People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok at the National Assembly and said, "Representative Jang has been transferred to the hospital, and I hope for his swift recovery. The President also instructed that a visit to the hospital be made as soon as possible." Earlier that morning, after former President Park Geun-hye, who visited the National Assembly, urged him to "stop the hunger strike," Representative Jang immediately accepted and was admitted to the hospital. (홍 수석은 22일 오후 국회에서 송언석 국민의힘 원내대표를 만나 “장 대표가 병원으로 이송됐는데, 쾌유했으면 한다. 대통령께서도 빠른 시일 내에 병원에 방문하라고 말씀하셨다”고 했다. 앞서 이날 오전 장 대표는 국회를 찾은 박근혜 전 대통령이 “단식을 중단해달라”고 하자, 바로 이를 수용하고 병원에 입원했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The previous day, Secretary Hong had visited the National Assembly for personnel matters and met with the leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea, but did not step into the hunger strike site set up by Representative Jang in the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall. Regarding this, Secretary Hong apologized to Floor Leader Song, saying, "Yesterday, due to a complicated schedule at the National Assembly, I had no choice but to leave. Since the scheduled visit today was to the People Power Party, I had planned to visit Representative Jang's hunger strike site." (홍 수석은 전날 인사차 국회를 방문해 더불어민주당 지도부를 만났지만, 국회 로텐더홀에 차려진 장 대표 단식농성장에는 걸음을 하지 않았다. 이에 홍 수석은 송 원내대표에게 “어제는 국회에 복잡한 일정이 있어서 불가피하게 그냥 갔다. 예정된 일정이 국민의힘 방문이라서 오늘 장 대표 단식 현장 방문을 계획하고 있었다”고 양해를 구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the acceptance of the special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church and nomination bribes, which Representative Jang demanded during his hunger strike, he stated it is not a matter for the Blue House to intervene in. Secretary Hong said, "We take seriously the various claims made by the People Power Party, including Representative Jang," but added, "Fundamentally, matters related to special prosecutors or various parliamentary investigations should be well discussed between the ruling and opposition parties in the National Assembly." The previous day, President Lee had expressed the same position during his New Year's press conference. (장 대표가 단식농성을 하며 요구했던 통일교·공천헌금 특검 수용에 대해서는 청와대가 관여할 일이 아니라고 했다. 홍 수석은 “장 대표를 포함해 국민의힘이 주장하는 여러 주장을 무겁게 받아들인다”면서도 “기본적으로 특검이나 여러 국정조사 관련 내용들은 국회에서 여야가 잘 협의했으면 좋겠다고 생각한다”고 했다. 전날 이 대통령은 신년 기자회견에서 같은 입장을 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Hong passed the ball to the ruling and opposition parties while emphasizing that related investigations are already underway. "Revealing the truth and holding legal responsibility are natural measures in a democratic government. Currently, under the President's instructions, related investigations are proceeding rapidly, even before any special prosecutor appointment," he said. (홍 수석은 여야에 공을 넘기면서 관련 수사가 이미 진행되고 있다는 점을 강조했다. “진실을 밝히고 법적 책임을 지우는 것은 민주적인 정부에서 당연한 조치다. 현재 대통령 지시에 따라서 특검 이전에라도 관련 수사가 빠르게 진행되고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song said, "(Representative Jang's hunger strike) was a desperate struggle that went beyond simply appointing a special prosecutor; it was about the need for political reform or a nomination revolution to uproot the deep-seated dark money in politics. I ask the Senior Secretary for Political Affairs to proactively review this at the Blue House." (송 원내대표는 “(장 대표의 단식은) 단순히 특검을 임명하자는 차원을 넘어 정치권의 뿌리 깊은 검은돈 뿌리 뽑기를 위한 정치혁신 또는 공천혁명을 해야 하지 않겠냐는 처절한 몸부림이었다고 생각한다. 청와대에서 전향적으로 검토해주시길 정무수석께 당부드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241187.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690718652031_20260122503501.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:41:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NIS to Designate Lee Jae-myung's Attacker as a 'Terror Risk Person' (국정원, 이재명 습격범 ‘테러 위험인물’로 지정한다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241205.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503643.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령(당시 더불어민주당 대표)가 2024년 1월2일 부산 가덕도 신공항 부지를 둘러보던 중 왼쪽 목 부위에 습격을 당해 피를 흘린 채 쓰러져 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Service (NIS) has decided to form a task force (TF) regarding the 'Lee Jae-myung Gadeokdo Assault Incident' and designate the perpetrator as a 'terror risk person.' This is a follow-up measure after the government officially designated the incident as 'terrorism.' (국가정보원이 ‘이재명 가덕도 피습 사건’ 관련 태스크포스(TF)를 꾸리고, 가해자를 ‘테러 위험인물’로 지정하기로 했다. 정부가 해당 사건을 ‘테러’로 공식 지정한 데 따른 후속 조치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a press release on the 22nd, the NIS announced that it formed the 'Gadeokdo Terror Incident Designation Follow-up Measures Task Force' (headed by First Deputy Director Lee Dong-soo) on that day, designated the perpetrator of the incident, Mr. Kim (69), as a 'terror risk person' under the Counter-Terrorism Act, and stated it would meticulously re-examine the specific charges. The NIS stated, "As the National Investigation Headquarters of the police has launched a reinvestigation into the Gadeokdo terror incident, we plan to support relevant information upon request from the investigative agency and back a swift investigation." (국정원은 22일 보도자료를 내어 이날 ‘가덕도 테러 사건 지정 후속조치 태스크포스’(팀장 이동수 1차장)를 꾸리고, 해당 사건 가해자 김아무개(69)씨를 테러방지법상 ‘테러 위험인물’로 지정한 뒤 구체적인 혐의를 면밀히 재확인 하겠다고 밝혔다. 국정원은 “경찰 국가수사본부가 가덕도 테러 사건 재수사에 나선 만큼, 수사기관 요청 시 관련 정보를 지원하고 신속한 수사를 뒷받침할 예정”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also added that it will participate in the 'Counter-Terrorism Work Innovation Task Force' under the Prime Minister's Office's Counter-Terrorism Center, which is scheduled to be launched on the 26th, and "has decided to make multi-faceted efforts, such as improving response systems including the terror crisis management standard manual and ensuring rapid response in case of similar incidents." (또 오는 26일 발족 예정인 국무총리실 산하 대테러센터의 ‘대테러업무 혁신 태스크포스’에 참여해 “테러 위기관리 표준매뉴얼 등 대응 체계를 정비하고 유사 사건 발생 시 신속 대응 등 다각도의 노력을 기울여나가기로 했다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'Lee Jae-myung Gadeokdo Assault Incident' occurred on January 2, 2024. At the time, then-leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, President Lee, was stabbed in the left neck with a weapon wielded by Mr. Kim while inspecting the site for the new Busan Gadeokdo Airport. The government's National Counter-Terrorism Committee officially designated this incident as terrorism on the 20th. This is the first government-level terrorism designation since the enactment of the Counter-Terrorism Act in 2016. (‘이재명 가덕도 피습 사건’은 2024년 1월2일 일어났다. 당시 더불어민주당 대표였던 이 대통령은 부산 가덕도 신공항 부지를 둘러보던 중 김씨가 휘두른 흉기에 왼쪽 목을 찔렸다. 정부 국가테러대책위원회는 지난 20일 이 사건을 테러로 공식 지정했다. 2016년 테러방지법 제정 뒤 정부 차원의 첫 테러 지정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241205.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/427/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503643.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:41:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing to Be Held on the 23rd... Allegations Including Children's Illegal Study Abroad to Be Examined (이혜훈 청문회 23일 열린다…자녀 불법유학 의혹 등 검증)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241223.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/929/580/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503735.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 22일 서울 중구 예금보험공사에 마련된 인사청문회 준비 사무실로 출근하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, will be held on the 23rd. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 인사청문회가 23일 열린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee announced that it will hold a plenary meeting at 10 a.m. on the 23rd to conduct the nominee's confirmation hearing. This follows the nominee's side submitting an additional 87 documents requested by the People Power Party this morning, after the hearing scheduled for the 19th was canceled due to issues with insufficient document submission. Park Soo-young, the opposition party's secretary on the committee and a People Power Party lawmaker, stated, "The documents are still insufficient, but we will proceed with the hearing to inform the public of the nominee's unethical behavior." (22일 국회 재정경제기획위원회(재경위)는, 23일 오전 10시 전체회의를 열어 이 후보자 인사청문회를 연다고 밝혔다. 지난 19일 인사청문회가 자료 부실 제출 문제로 무산됐다가, 이날 오전 이 후보자 쪽에서 국민의힘이 요구한 87건의 자료를 추가로 제출한 데 따른 것이다. 재경위 야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원은 “자료는 여전히 부실하지만 일단 청문회를 열어 후보자의 부도덕성을 알리겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party plans to focus intensely during the hearing on issues sensitive to public sentiment, including allegations of 'verbal abuse and power abuse towards aides,' as well as the fraudulent subscription for a lottery apartment worth around 9 billion won. Lawmaker Park Soo-min also raised suspicions that the nominee violated the Elementary and Secondary Education Act by sending her eldest and second sons, who were elementary school students at the time, to study in the U.S. between 2002 and 2004. Study abroad is only recognized for elementary and middle school students if both parents are abroad and the child's accompanying departure is unavoidable. Given the nominee's political activities and her spouse's travel records, it is believed there is a possibility the law was violated. (국민의힘은 이 후보자 청문회에서 국민 정서에 민감한 ‘보좌진에 대한 폭언·갑질’ 논란을 비롯해 90억원대 로또 아파트 부정 청약에 대해 집중적으로 따져 묻겠다는 방침이다. 박수민 의원은 또 이날 이 후보자가 2002~2004년 초등학생이던 장남과 차남을 미국으로 유학 보내면서 초·중등교육법을 위반했다는 의혹을 제기했다. 부모가 모두 출국해 초·중학생 자녀가 불가피하게 동반 출국할 경우에만 유학으로 인정되는데, 이 후보자의 정치 활동과 배우자의 출국 기록을 볼 때 법을 위반했을 가능성이 있다고 본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling party and the presidential office also stated they will approach the verification without prejudging the hearing's outcome. A presidential office official said, "The public's reaction is important, isn't it?" and added, "If the nominee fails to provide a proper explanation during the hearing, wouldn't the appointment be difficult?" (여당과 청와대 쪽에서도 청문회 결과를 예단하지 않고 검증에 임하겠다는 입장이다. 청와대 관계자는 “국민 반응이 중요하지 않겠느냐”며 “청문회에서 잘 해명하지 못하면 (임명이) 어렵지 않겠느냐”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Hae-jeong, Choi Ha-yan, and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김해정 최하얀 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241223.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/929/580/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503735.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:40:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae Proposes "Let's Merge Parties" to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party... 'Integration of the Ruling Camp' Gains Momentum Ahead of Local Elections (정청래, 조국당에 “합당하자”…지방선거 전 ‘여권 통합’ 본격화)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241224.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/646/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503739.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안하고 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, proposed a 'party-to-party merger' to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party on the 22nd. The Innovation Party decided to hold a general meeting of lawmakers and a party affairs committee to gather opinions on whether to merge with the Democratic Party. With the local elections just over four months away, this sudden move for realignment initiated by the Democratic Party is drawing attention to whether political camp consolidation will fully materialize. (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 조국혁신당에 ‘당대당 통합’을 제안했다. 혁신당은 의원총회와 당무위원회를 열어 민주당과의 합당 여부에 대한 의견을 모아 나가기로 했다. 지방선거를 4개월 남짓 앞두고 돌출한 민주당발 여권 재편 움직임으로, 정치권의 진영 결집이 본격화할지 주목된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an emergency press conference on the 22nd, Representative Chung made a surprise proposal, stating, "I propose to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party," and "Let's merge with us." Representative Chung said, "The success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and victory in the local elections are the spirit of the times," adding, "I believe the spirit of the times pursued by the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party is not different. Therefore, there is no reason to hold the June 3 local elections separately." He continued, "Based on the spirit of the times, the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party should run as one team for the common goal of the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration." (정 대표는 22일 긴급 기자회견을 열어 “조국혁신당에 제안한다”며 “우리와 합칩시다”라고 깜짝 제안을 했다. 정 대표는 “이재명 정부의 성공, 지방선거의 승리가 시대정신”이라며 “민주당과 혁신당이 추구하는 시대정신이 다르지 않다고 생각한다. 따라서 6·3 지방선거를 따로 치를 이유가 없다”고 밝혔다. 그러면서 “민주당과 혁신당은 시대정신에 입각해, 이재명 정부 성공이라는 공동 목표를 위해 원팀으로 뛰어야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Innovation Party, responded at an on-site Supreme Council meeting held in Jeonju, North Jeolla Province, saying, "I met with Representative Chung late yesterday afternoon and was informed of today's (merger proposal) announcement," and "We will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the hearts and will of the people." Representative Cho stated, "We will listen to the voices of the people and party members on what is the best path to achieve both of (the Innovation Party's) two tasks: 'the goal of the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the renewal of the administration' and 'progressive future tasks that the Democratic Party does not mention, such as political reform, constitutional amendment, and becoming an advanced nation in social rights.'" The Innovation Party decided to hold a general meeting of lawmakers on the 24th and a party affairs committee on the 26th to gather internal opinions on the merger. (조국 혁신당 대표는 전북 전주에서 연 현장 최고위원회의에서 “어제 늦은 오후 정 대표를 만나 오늘의 (합당 제안) 발표 내용을 전달받았다”며 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정하겠다”고 답했다. 조 대표는 “이재명 정부의 성공과 정권 재창출이라는 목표”와 “정치개혁, 개헌, 사회권 선진국 등 민주당이 말하지 않는 진보적 미래 과제”라는 “(혁신당의) 두 과제를 모두 실현하는 최선의 길이 무엇인지 국민과 당원의 목소리를 경청하겠다”고 했다. 혁신당은 오는 24일 의원총회와 26일 당무위원회를 열어 합당 여부에 대한 당내 의견을 수렴하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The presidential office welcomed the merger discussions. Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs, met with reporters at the Chunchugwan of the presidential office and said, "The integration of the two parties and political integration have long been President Lee Jae-myung's consistent position," adding, "We received prior notice from Representative Chung (about the intention to propose a merger to the Innovation Party)." (청와대는 합당 논의를 반겼다. 홍익표 정무수석은 이날 청와대 춘추관에서 기자들과 만나 “양당 통합과 정치적 통합은 평소 이재명 대통령의 지론이었다”며 “사전에 정 대표로부터 (혁신당에 합당을 제안하겠다는) 연락을 받았다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung's sudden proposal of a merger today appears to be intended to conclude the integration issue with the Innovation Party early, thereby avoiding the political energy drain that would come from party-to-party alliances or candidate unification negotiations during the election period, and to firmly secure political initiative in the first half of the Lee Jae-myung administration's term through a landslide victory in the local elections. (정 대표가 이날 전격적으로 합당을 제안한 것은 혁신당과의 통합 문제를 조기에 마무리지음으로써 선거 시기 당대당 연대나 후보 단일화 협상으로 정치적 에너지가 소모되는 것을 피하고, 지방선거 압승으로 이재명 정부 임기 전반기에 정국 주도권을 확실히 쥐고 가겠다는 의도로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the merger discussions with the Innovation Party get on track, there is a high possibility that other minor parties within the broader ruling camp, such as the Basic Income Party and the Social Democratic Party (each with one seat), may join the integration talks. This could also trigger a trend of integration within the conservative opposition camp to unite against a consolidated ruling camp ahead of the local elections. Jang Dong-hyuk, leader of the People Power Party, and Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, are narrowing their distance by showing cooperative moves in discussions targeting the Democratic Party with a 'double special prosecutor' (special prosecutors for the Unification Church and nomination funds). (혁신당과의 합당 논의가 궤도에 오를 경우 기본소득당·사회민주당(각 1석) 등 범여권 소수 정당들이 통합 논의에 합류하고, 지방선거를 앞두고 뭉치는 여권에 대항하기 위한 보수 야권의 통합 흐름을 촉발할 가능성도 크다. 장동혁 국민의힘 대표와 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 민주당을 겨냥한 ‘쌍특검’(통일교·공천헌금 특검) 논의에서 공조 움직임을 보이며 거리를 좁혀가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A variable is the backlash within the Democratic Party. Supreme Council members classified as the 'anti-Chung Cheong-rae faction'—Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu—expressed opposition on the same day, saying, "There was absolutely no discussion process within the leadership," and "We cannot erase suspicions that this is groundwork considering the party leader's re-election." Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun said, "The leader's proposal falls within the realm of political judgment and political decision," adding, "In the future, procedures such as discussions and votes among all party members and a party convention will be followed." (변수는 민주당 내 반발이다. ‘반정청래계’로 분류되는 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 이날 “지도부 논의 과정이 전혀 없었다” “당대표 연임을 염두에 둔 포석이라는 의구심을 지울 수 없다”며 반발했다. 박수현 수석대변인은 “대표의 제안은 정무적 판단과 정치적 결단의 영역”이라며 “앞으로 전 당원 토론과 투표, 전당대회 등의 절차를 거치게 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol and Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241224.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/646/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503739.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:40:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike Without Gaining Dual Special Prosecutions; Opinions Divided on Conservative Consolidation (장동혁, 쌍특검 소득 없이 단식 중단…보수 결집도 의견분분)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241227.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/896/658/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503753.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;8일째 단식을 이어오던 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 22일 오전 서울 여의도 국회 중앙홀에서 단식을 중단한 뒤 병원으로 이동하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hunger strike by Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, came to an end after seven days. Unable to find an exit strategy amid the government and ruling party's firm stance of not accepting the 'dual special prosecutions' related to the Unification Church and nomination funds, he made a face-saving move by accepting former President Park Geun-hye's recommendation to stop fasting. While Jang's side is attributing significance to visits to his hunger strike tent by figures who have been critical of the party, calling it the 'prelude to conservative consolidation,' both inside and outside the party, there are also comments that all Jang gained from this hunger strike was the 'isolation of Han Dong-hoon.' (장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식이 7일 만에 막을 내렸다. 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’을 수용할 수 없다는 정부·여당의 완강한 입장 속에 출구전략을 찾지 못하다가, 박근혜 전 대통령의 단식 중단 권유를 받아들이며 체면치레한 모습이다. 장 대표 쪽에선 그동안 당에 비판적인 목소리를 내왔던 이들이 단식 농성 텐트를 찾아온 것을 두고 ‘보수 결집의 서막’이라는 의미를 부여하고 있지만, 당 안팎에선 장 대표가 이번 단식을 통해 얻은 건 ‘한동훈 고립’뿐이란 말도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Jang announced the end of his hunger strike, stating it was "for a longer and bigger fight," and was transported to a hospital. The move was framed as accepting the recommendation from former President Park, a party elder, who visited Jang that morning and urged him to stop fasting, saying, "The public will recognize the sincerity of a politician who risked his life for what he believed was right." On his way to the hospital, Jang posted on Facebook, "I end my hunger strike today, but the public's lament towards corrupt power will ignite like wildfire from today." (장 대표는 22일 “좀 더 길고 큰 싸움”을 위한 것이라며 단식 중단을 선언하고, 병원으로 이송됐다. 당의 원로인 박 전 대통령이 이날 오전 장 대표를 찾아 “정치인으로서 옳다고 생각한 것에 대해 목숨을 건 투쟁을 한 것에 대해서는 국민들께서 진정성을 인정할 것”이라며 단식 중단을 권유한 것을 받아들이는 형식이었다. 장 대표는 병원으로 이송되는 길에 “나는 오늘 단식을 끝내지만 부패한 권력을 향한 국민의 탄식은 오늘부터 들불처럼 타오를 것”이라는 글을 페이스북에 올렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with floor leader Song Eon-seok that day, Hong Ik-pyo, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs, said, "I hope Representative Jang recovers quickly," adding, "The President also said he should visit the hospital soon." However, regarding the People Power Party's demand for 'acceptance of the dual special prosecutions,' he reiterated that it remains a matter requiring "bipartisan agreement." (이날 송언석 원내대표를 만난 홍익표 청와대 정무수석은 “장 대표가 쾌유했으면 한다”며 “대통령께서도 빠른 시일 내에 병원에 방문하라고 말씀하셨다”고 했다. 하지만 국민의힘의 ‘쌍특검 수용’ 요구에는 여전히 “여야 합의” 사안이라고 선을 그었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the People Power Party, although they failed to achieve the goal of 'introducing the dual special prosecutions,' there is self-assessment that "by showing conservatives uniting through the sacrifice of a hunger strike, a foundation for integration has been laid" (a senior lawmaker). They attribute meaning to the fact that two former presidents from the party (Lee Myung-bak and Park Geun-hye) recently lent support to Jang, and figures who have maintained an 'uncomfortable relationship' with the party, such as Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reformist Party, former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min, and former Minister of Employment and Labor Kim Moon-soo, have also visited. (국민의힘 쪽에선 비록 ‘쌍특검 도입’이라는 목표 달성에는 실패했지만, “단식이라는 희생을 통해 보수가 뭉치는 모습을 보여 통합할 수 있는 발판을 마련했다”(중진 의원)는 자평이 나온다. 최근 당 출신 전직 두 대통령(이명박·박근혜)이 장 대표에게 힘을 실어준데다, 그동안 당과 ‘불편한 관계’를 이어온 이준석 개혁신당 대표와 유승민 전 의원, 김문수 전 노동부 장관 등의 발길이 이어진 데 의미를 부여한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Lee Jun-seok continues to draw a line, stating that 'there will be no electoral alliance unless the People Power Party breaks with the pro-Yoon forces.' Moreover, in a public opinion poll released that day by Embrain Public, K-Stat Research, Korea Research, and Hankook Research (referenced from the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission website), the party's approval rating actually dropped further (23% → 20%) after Jang's hunger strike. Notably, among moderates, the party's approval rating fell to 13%. (하지만 이준석 대표는 여전히 국민의힘을 향해 ‘윤 어게인 세력과 단절하지 않는 한 선거 연대는 없다’고 선을 긋고 있다. 게다가 이날 발표된 엠브레인퍼블릭·케이스탯리서치·코리아리서치·한국리서치의 여론조사(중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집 참조)에선, 장 대표 단식 이후 당 지지율이 오히려 더 하락(23→20%)했다. 특히 중도층에선 당 지지율이 13%까지 빠졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, there are remarks questioning what was gained other than isolating former leader Han Dong-hoon, who did not visit Jang's hunger strike tent despite requests from inside and outside the party, labeling him a 'cold-hearted person.' Some point out that this may rather provide justification for the disciplinary expulsion of former leader Han and become a factor exacerbating future intra-party conflicts. (결과적으로 당 안팎의 요청에도 장 대표 단식 텐트를 찾지 않은 한동훈 전 대표를 ‘매정한 사람’으로 고립시킨 것 외에 얻은 게 뭐냐는 얘기가 나온다. 오히려 이것이 한 전 대표 제명 징계를 정당화할 명분이 되며 향후 당내 갈등을 더 부추기는 요인이 될 것이란 지적도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A second-term lawmaker from the Yeongnam region said, "The visit by critical figures (like former lawmaker Yoo, etc.) to the hunger strike site was merely a matter of minimal courtesy; it's difficult to evaluate it as having achieved a substantial 'chemical consolidation,'" adding, "As long as Representative Jang does not change his course (focusing only on hardline supporters), the divided situation within the party will remain unchanged." (영남권의 한 재선 의원은 “(유 전 의원 등) 비판 세력이 단식 농성장을 찾아온 건 최소한의 예의 차원일 뿐, 실질적인 ‘화학적 결집’까지 이뤘다고 평가하기는 어렵다”며 “장 대표가 (강성 지지층만 바라보는) 노선을 바꾸지 않는 한 갈라진 당내 상황은 그대로일 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241227.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/896/658/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503753.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:39:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Ending Communication with the Blue House, Jeong Cheong-rae Pulls Out the 'Party Merger' Card for the Local Elections (청와대와 교감 끝낸 정청래, 지방선거 카드로 ‘합당’ 꺼냈다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241229.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/826/550/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503759.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안하고 있다. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is widespread speculation that Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae's proposal on the 22nd for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party was either in response to a request from the Blue House or, at the very least, the result of prior coordination. This is because a 'party-to-party merger' with a '12-seat parliamentary party' is a politically significant event that exceeds the discretionary authority of the leader of the '163-seat ruling party'. The fact that a merger with the Innovation Party also increases political uncertainty for Leader Jeong himself, who has been gradually strengthening his control within the party through the introduction of a 'one-member-one-vote system', further fuels this speculation. (22일 조국혁신당을 향한 정청래 더불어민주당 대표의 합당 제안은 청와대의 요구에 따른 것이거나 최소한 사전 조율을 거친 결과물이라는 것이란 관측이 많다. ‘12석 원내정당’과의 ‘당 대 당 통합’은 ‘163석 집권여당’의 대표가 가진 재량권의 범위를 넘어선 정치적 중대사이기 때문이다. ‘1인1표제’ 도입을 통해 당내 장악력을 차근차근 높여가던 정 대표 개인에게도 혁신당과의 통합은 정치적 불확실성을 키우는 요인이란 점도 이런 관측에 힘을 더한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following Leader Jeong's press conference proposing the merger, the Blue House stated that day that "the merger of the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party is President Lee Jae-myung's long-held position" (Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs). Senior Secretary Hong also conveyed that he had received prior notice of the press conference contents from Leader Jeong and said, "We will watch (hoping) that discussions between the two parties proceed well." ( 이날 청와대는 정 대표의 합당 제안 기자회견 뒤 “민주당과 혁신당의 합당은 이재명 대통령의 지론”(홍익표 정무수석)이라는 입장을 내놨다. 홍 수석은 정 대표로부터 회견 내용을 사전에 연락받았다고 전하며 “양당 간 논의가 잘 진행되기를 (바라며) 지켜보겠다”는 말도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Political circles are noting Senior Secretary Hong's wish for the merger discussions between the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party to proceed 'well'. A member of the Democratic Party leadership said, "It is very meaningful that the Blue House sent a message wishing for the discussions to progress well toward a merger, rather than drawing a line saying that political realignment is a matter for the party to discuss." Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Young-jin, known as part of the 'original Lee Jae-myung faction', said in a phone call that day, "A merger with the Innovation Party is the right direction in terms of securing victory in the local elections and, furthermore, laying the foundation for building a pool of candidates for the next presidential election," adding, "I support Leader Jeong's decision to choose the right direction for (the camp) as a whole." ( 정치권에선 홍 수석이 민주당과 혁신당의 통합 논의가 ‘잘’ 진행되길 바란다고 한 것에 주목한다. 민주당 지도부 관계자는 “청와대가 정계 개편은 당에서 논의할 일이라고 선을 그은 것이 아니라, 논의가 합당 쪽으로 잘 진척되길 바란다는 취지의 메시지를 낸 것에 많은 의미가 담겨 있는 것”이라고 말했다. ‘원조 이재명계’로 불리는 김영진 민주당 의원은 이날 통화에서 “혁신당과의 합당은 지방선거 승리, 더 나아가 차기 대선 후보군을 만들어가는 기반 다지기란 차원에서 맞는 방향”이라며 “(진영) 모두를 위해 맞는 방향을 선택한 정 대표의 결단을 지지한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, it is viewed that Leader Jeong, who is aiming for the next presidential candidate position following his re-election as party leader, proposed 'merging' to potential rival Leader Cho Kuk because he judged that producing a good result in the June 3 local elections is the top priority. A metropolitan-area second-term lawmaker said, "For Leader Jeong, merging with the Innovation Party means taking the risk of bringing a competitor into the household," adding, "Nevertheless, the reason he made the decision is probably that he saw if he showed a passive attitude toward the merger and the local election results were unsatisfactory, even his re-election as party leader could become difficult." ( 당내에선 대표직 연임에 이어 차기 대선 후보 자리를 노리는 정 대표가 잠재적 경쟁자인 조국 대표에게 ‘합치자’는 제안을 한 것은 일단 6·3 지방선거에서 좋은 결과를 내는 것이 급선무라는 판단을 했기 때문이라고 본다. 한 수도권 재선 의원은 “정 대표에게 혁신당과의 합당은 경쟁자를 집안에 들이는 위험을 감수하는 것”이라며 “그럼에도 결단을 한 것은 합당에 소극적인 태도를 보였다가 지방선거 결과가 만족스럽지 못할 경우 당대표 재선도 어려워질 수 있다고 본 것 아니겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the merger proposal that day, strong backlash arose not only among lawmakers but also among party members. The general sentiment was that 'Leader Jeong made this decision unilaterally for personal ambition without prior discussion.' Some party members also intensively sent protest calls and text messages to pro-leadership lawmakers that day. Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo cited this, saying, "I think it would be better to hold a national party convention and ask all members directly, and even ask about the party leader's staying or leaving." As the controversy grew, Leader Jeong posted on Facebook, "I made the proposal today, and of course there will be a procedure to ask the members' will. The Democratic Party is a party where members are sovereign." ( 이날 합당 제안 뒤 의원들은 물론 당원들 사이에서도 큰 반발이 일었다. ‘사전 논의 없이 정 대표가 개인 욕심으로 독단적으로 결정한 것 아니냐’는 취지가 대부분이었다. 일부 당원들은 이날 당권파 의원들에게 집중적으로 항의 전화·문자메시지를 보내기도 했다. 이언주 최고위원은 이를 들어 “차라리 전당원대회를 열어서 전당원들에게 직접 다 물어보고, 당대표의 진퇴도 묻는 게 맞다고 생각한다”고 말했다. 논란이 거세지자 정 대표는 페이스북에 “저는 오늘 제안을 한 것이고, 당연히 당원들의 뜻을 묻는 절차가 있다. 민주당은 당원주권정당”이라는 글을 남겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, the prevailing view is that considering the symbolic effect of 'pan-progressive camp integration', the backlash will subside over time. A multi-term lawmaker from the Honam region said, "Right now, there is backlash saying Leader Jeong acted without sufficient discussion within the party, but there is an aspect where prior discussion is difficult when pushing for something like a merger. I believe discussions will soon gain speed because Leader Cho Kuk also sees that merging is good for expanding his personal political options." ( 당 안에선 ‘범여권 통합’이라는 상징적 효과를 고려할 때, 시간이 지나면 반발이 사그라들 것이라는 게 중론이다. 한 호남권 다선 의원은 “지금은 정 대표가 당내에서 충분한 논의 없이 일을 벌였다며 반발하지만, 합당 같은 일을 추진할 때는 사전 논의가 어려운 측면이 있다. 조국 대표도 합당을 하는 것이 개인의 정치적 선택지를 넓혀나가는 데 좋기 때문에 논의에도 곧 속도가 붙을 것으로 본다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party explained that there had been sufficient communication with Leader Cho even before announcing the merger proposal. The previous afternoon, "not only was Leader Cho given prior notice of the merger proposal press conference, but we have communicated several times (regarding the merger) since Leader Cho returned to politics (after the pardon)" (Park Soo-hyun, Chief Spokesperson). ( 민주당은 합당 제안 발표 전 조 대표와도 충분한 교감이 있었다고 설명한다. 전날 오후 “조 대표에게 합당 제안 회견을 미리 알린 것은 물론, “조 대표가 (사면 뒤) 정치에 복귀한 시점부터 여러 차례 (합당을 두고) 교감했다”(박수현 수석대변인)는 것이다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Choi Ha-yan, Kim Chae-woon, and Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (최하얀 김채운 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:chy@hani.co.kr"&gt;chy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241229.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/826/550/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503759.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:39:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Jo Bok Innovation Party's Sense of Crisis Over Independent Survival... Choosing a New Breakthrough to Minimize Risk (조국혁신당 독자생존 위기감…리스크 최소화 새 돌파구 선택)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241230.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/966/580/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690786796143_20260122503767.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;조국 조국혁신당 대표가 22일 전북 전주시 전북도당 당사에서 현장 최고위원회의를 주재하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'response' by Jo Bok, leader of the Jo Bok Innovation Party, to the 'party merger' proposal from Jeong Cheong-rae, leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, stating he would "proceed to gather opinions within the party," is interpreted as a choice to minimize the risks the Innovation Party would shoulder ahead of the upcoming June local elections. Although it positioned itself as 'to the left of the Democratic Party,' being trapped by the limitations of having a small number of seats and unable to break free from a 3-4% approval rating, the judgment that 'independent survival is difficult' had become predominant both inside and outside the Innovation Party. (조국 조국혁신당 대표가 정청래 더불어민주당 대표의 ‘합당’ 제안에 “당내 의견 수렴에 나서겠다”고 ‘화답’한 것은 오는 6월 지방선거 전에 혁신당이 짊어지게 될 리스크를 최소화하려는 선택으로 풀이된다. ‘민주당의 왼쪽’을 자처했지만 소수 의석의 한계에 갇혀 지지율이 3~4%에서 벗어나지 못하자 혁신당 안팎에선 ‘독자생존이 어렵다’는 판단이 우세해지던 상황이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a field Supreme Council meeting held in Jeonju, Jeollabuk-do on the 22nd, Leader Jo said regarding Leader Jeong's merger proposal, "The Innovation Party fully agrees with the goals mentioned by Leader Jeong: the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the re-creation of political power." Although the Innovation Party has only been founded for 1 year and 10 months, instead of flatly rejecting the merger, it left the possibility open by stating it would "listen to the voices of the people and party members." (조 대표는 22일 전북 전주에서 연 현장 최고위원회의에서 정 대표의 합당 제안에 “혁신당은 정 대표가 언급한 이재명 정부의 성공과 정권 재창출이라는 목표에 전적으로 동의한다”고 말했다. 혁신당이 창당한 지 1년10개월밖에 되지 않았지만, 단박에 합당을 거절하는 대신 “국민과 당원의 목소리를 경청하겠다”며 가능성을 열어둔 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussions on the merger are gaining rapid momentum. A key official from the Innovation Party stated, "We will proceed quickly through the Supreme Council, the Assembly of Members of the National Assembly (on the 24th), and the Party Affairs Committee (on the 26th) to somewhat set a basic direction and clearly state our position, whether 'for' or 'against'." After going through this process, all that remains is a 'vote by all party members'. (합당 논의는 급물살을 타는 분위기다. 혁신당 핵심 관계자는 “최고위와 의원총회(24일), 당무위원회(26일)까지 빠르게 진행해서 기본 방향을 좀 잡고 ‘가’든 ‘부’든 입장을 분명히 밝힐 것”이라고 밝혔다. 이 절차를 거치면 남은 건 ‘전 당원 투표’뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even before Leader Jeong's merger proposal today, the prevailing view in political circles was that a merger between the two parties was only a matter of timing—'before or after the local elections'. The Innovation Party's situation was particularly urgent. For lawmakers who had previously been affiliated with the Democratic Party or had planned to run as Democratic Party candidates, merging with the Democratic Party before the 2028 general election and running in the general election under 'ballot number 1' was the best option for seeking 're-election'. The same was true for Leader Jo Bok. To meet the aspirations of his supporters who want him to become the next president, it was difficult to find a realistic alternative other than running in the presidential election as the candidate of the largest party. Ultimately, from the Innovation Party's perspective, the situation had come down to a 'political judgment' of whether to secure a foothold in the Honam region through the local elections to increase its negotiating stake and then merge, or to hasten the merger before the local elections to reduce political burden. (이날 정 대표의 합당 제안이 있기 전부터 정치권에서 두 당의 합당은 ‘지방선거 전이냐 후냐’라는 시기의 문제일 뿐이란 전망이 우세했다. 특히 혁신당의 처지가 다급했다. 과거 민주당에 적을 뒀거나 민주당 소속으로 출마를 도모했던 이력이 있는 의원들로선, 2028년 총선 전 민주당과 합당해 ‘기호 1번’을 달고 총선에 나가는 게 ‘재선’을 향한 최상의 선택지였다. 조국 대표도 마찬가지였다. 그가 차기 대통령이 되길 바라는 지지층 열망에 부응하려면, 제1당의 후보로 대선에 나서는 것 외에 현실적 대안을 찾기 어려웠기 때문이다. 결국 혁신당 입장에선 지방선거를 통해 호남 교두보를 확보해 협상 지분을 늘린 뒤 합당하느냐, 지방선거 전에 합당을 서둘러 정치적 부담을 줄이느냐는 ‘정무적 판단’만 남은 상황이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, upon being elected leader last November, Leader Jo had emphasized 'self-reliance theory', stating, "Under the name of the Jo Bok Innovation Party, which is not the name of any other party, we will change the Republic of Korea." An early local election planning team was also formed, with the goal of raising the party's approval rating to the 10% range by this spring. However, due to the limitations of having a small number of seats (12), the party's message failed to gain prominence, and with issues like sexual violence within the party surfacing, the party's approval rating remained stuck at 3-4%, putting it in a position where it could not refuse the Democratic Party's merger proposal. (애초 조 대표는 지난해 11월 대표에 당선되며 “어느 정당의 이름도 아닌 조국혁신당이라는 이름을 걸고 대한민국을 바꾸겠다”며 ‘자강론’에 힘을 실어왔다. 지방선거기획단도 조기에 꾸리고 올해 봄까지 당 지지율 10%대로 올리겠다는 목표도 내걸었다. 하지만 소수 의석(12석)의 한계 탓에 당이 내세우는 메시지가 부각되지 않고, 당내 성폭력 문제 등까지 불거지면서 당 지지율은 줄곧 3∼4%에 머무르면서 민주당의 합당 제안을 거부할 수 없는 처지가 됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241230.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/966/580/imgdb/child/2026/0122/53_17690786796143_20260122503767.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:38:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On the Day KOSPI Hit 5,000... Democrats Tighten the Reins on the 3rd Commercial Act Revision Mandating Treasury Stock Cancellation (오천피 찍은 날…민주, 자사주 소각 의무화 3차 상법개정 ‘고삐’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241231.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503769.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 당내 기구인 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’ 소속 의원들이 22일 청와대 초청 오찬을 한 뒤 국회 소통관에서 브리핑을 하고 있다. 왼쪽부터 박홍배·이강일·오기형·정준호 의원. 오기형 의원 페이스북 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, the day the KOSPI index surpassed 5,000 for the first time in history, lawmakers from the Democratic Party of Korea's 'KOSPI 5,000 Special Committee' (5,000 Special Committee) had lunch with President Lee Jae-myung and agreed to "promptly pursue the 3rd revision of the Commercial Act." (코스피 지수가 사상 처음 5000을 돌파한 22일, 더불어민주당 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’(오천특위) 의원들은 이재명 대통령과 오찬을 하며 “3차 상법 개정을 신속히 추진”하기로 뜻을 모았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the lunch at the Blue House, to which he was invited by President Lee, Committee Chairman and lawmaker Oh Ki-hyung met with reporters at the National Assembly. He stated, "There was an assessment that (the KOSPI surpassing 5,000) is the result of consistent policy efforts, including forming a task force for capital market revitalization and pushing for Commercial Act revisions, which President Lee Jae-myung has focused on since his time as party leader." He added, "We shared the view that the party and the Blue House must continuously make efforts for institutional reforms to strengthen the fundamental health of the capital market." (이날 이 대통령 초청으로 청와대를 방문한 오천특위 위원장 오기형 의원은 오찬 뒤 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “(코스피 5000 돌파는) 자본시장 활성화 티에프(TF) 구성, 상법 개정 추진 등 이재명 대통령이 당대표 시절부터 공을 들여온 일관된 정책 의지의 결과물이라는 평가가 있었다”며 “당과 청와대가 자본시장의 기초 체력을 강화하기 위한 제도 개혁의 노력을 지속적으로 해야 한다는 데 공감을 가졌다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the '3rd Commercial Act revision' in particular, Rep. Oh said, "We shared the view that it should no longer be delayed," and "We agreed to communicate and persuade (the party and the administration) together." The Democratic Party previously passed the 1st Commercial Act revision last year, expanding the fiduciary duty of directors to shareholders, followed by the 2nd revision mandating cumulative voting. Now, it is pushing for the 3rd revision, which mandates the cancellation of treasury stock. It requires companies to cancel newly acquired treasury shares within one year, and grants an additional grace period of six months, for a total of 1.5 years, to cancel existing treasury shares. (오 의원은 특히 ‘3차 상법 개정’과 관련해 “더 이상 미루면 안 된다는 공감을 가졌다”며 “(당·청이) 함께 소통하고 설득해나가기로 했다”고 말했다. 민주당은 지난해 이사의 충실 의무 대상을 주주로 확대하는 1차 상법 개정을 했고, 집중투표제를 의무화하는 2차 상법 개정에 이어, 자사주 소각 의무화를 담은 3차 상법 개정을 추진하고 있다. 기업이 신규 취득한 자사주를 1년 내 소각하도록 하고, 기존에 보유한 자사주는 유예 기간 6개월을 더해 1년6개월 안에 소각하도록 한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Oh also conveyed that during the lunch, discussions were held on institutional improvements regarding the so-called 'stock price suppression prevention law' (a partial amendment to the Inheritance and Gift Tax Act) aimed at preventing listed companies facing inheritance from intentionally lowering their stock prices for tax avoidance, as well as on the issue of 'dual listing' where a listed parent company spins off and lists a profitable subsidiary. (이날 오찬에서는 상속을 앞둔 상장기업이 상속세 절세를 위해 의도적으로 주가를 낮추는 것을 막기 위한 이른바 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’(상속세 및 증여세법 일부개정법률안)과 상장된 모회사가 수익성 높은 자회사를 분할 상장하는 ‘중복 상장’ 문제에 대한 제도 개선 논의도 이뤄졌다고 오 의원은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol, Ko Kyung-joo &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241231.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503769.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:38:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee on Prosecution Reform Controversy: "Reform is Not About Clinging to Justification and Increasing Confusion" (이 대통령, 검찰개혁 논란에 “명분에 매달려 혼란 가중시키는 건 개혁 아냐”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241232.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/371/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503772.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 22일 청와대에서 열린 수석보좌관 회의에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, President Lee Jae-myung said, "If a reform measure, by clinging only to justification and the greater cause, increases suffering and confusion, it cannot be called reform." This statement is interpreted as expressing his position that prosecution reform should not be solely fixated on the grand justification of stripping the prosecution of its power, amid ongoing debates within the ruling party over issues such as retaining the prosecution's supplementary investigation rights. (이재명 대통령이 22일 “개혁 조치가 명분과 대의에만 매달려 고통과 혼란을 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다. 여권 내에서 검찰의 보완수사권 존치 등을 놓고 갑론을박이 이어지는 것과 관련해, 검찰개혁이 검찰의 권력 박탈이라는 대의명분에만 매몰돼서는 안 된다는 입장을 밝힌 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks while outlining the direction of state affairs and commending the hard work of his senior secretaries during a meeting he presided over at the Blue House that day. President Lee said, "You have done well so far, but I ask you to pick up the pace a bit more from now on," adding, "Operating state affairs on behalf of the sovereign people must be, first and foremost, for the practical improvement of people's lives and livelihoods." He continued, "We must carefully judge from a practical and effective perspective which measures help protect people's human rights and guarantee their substantive rights, and meticulously check them," stating, "If any reform measure, far from improving people's lives, only increases suffering and confusion by clinging to justification and the greater cause, it cannot be called reform." (이 대통령의 이런 발언은 이날 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 수석들의 노고를 치하하며 국정 운영의 방향을 밝히는 과정에서 나왔다. 이 대통령은 “지금까지도 잘해주셨는데 지금보다는 조금 더 속도를 내주시길 부탁한다”며 “주권자를 대리해 국정을 운영하는 것은 첫째도 둘째도 국민 삶, 민생의 실질적인 개선을 위한 것이어야 한다”고 말했다. 그는 이어 “어떤 방안이 국민 인권을 보호하고 실질적인 권리 보장에 도움이 되는지를 실용적인 관점에서, 실효적 관점에서 신중히 판단하고 꼼꼼하게 챙겨 봐야 한다”며 “국민 삶을 개선하기는커녕 어떤 개혁 조치가 명분과 대의에 매달려서 고통과 혼란만 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's remarks appear to reiterate the principles of prosecution reform he mentioned during his New Year's press conference the previous day. The day before, President Lee stated, "The core of prosecution reform is not about taking away the prosecution's power, but about providing remedies for people's rights," and mentioned that the controversial prosecution's supplementary investigation rights are "exceptionally necessary in some cases." This signifies that we should not face a situation where people's rights are harmed due to an obsession solely with the grand justification of stripping the prosecution of its investigative authority. In a press conference marking one month in office last July, President Lee also questioned the complete and unconditional deprivation of the prosecution's investigative rights, saying, "Can the police handle all (investigations)? There is debate over how to solve the issue of police overexpansion." (이 대통령의 발언은 전날 신년 기자회견에서 언급한 검찰개혁의 원칙을 거듭 강조한 것으로 보인다. 이 대통령은 전날 “검찰개혁의 핵심은 검찰 권력을 빼앗는 게 아니라 국민의 권리 구제”라며 논란이 되고 있는 검사의 보완수사권이 “예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”고 밝힌 바 있다. 검사의 수사 권한을 뺏는 대의명분에만 집착하다가, 국민의 권리가 피해받는 상황을 맞아서는 안 된다는 뜻을 밝힌 것이다. 이 대통령은 지난해 7월 취임 한달 기자회견에서도 “(수사권을) 경찰이 다 감당할 수 있느냐. 경찰 비대화는 어떻게 해결할 것이냐는 논쟁이 있다”며 검사의 수사권을 예외 없이 완전히 박탈하는 데 대해 의문을 제기한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's clarification of the meaning that "people's rights come first" within a day appears to also contain the intention of clearly sorting out the differences in opinion within the ruling party. During the Democratic Party of Korea's policy general meeting of lawmakers held that morning, opinions advocating for exceptionally recognizing the prosecution's supplementary investigation rights increased compared to before, but opinions centered on hardliners still emerged calling for the complete deprivation of those rights. A Blue House official said, "President Lee's position is that reform tasks should be viewed from the standpoint of the sovereign people; it is not right to legislate from a stance of fighting the prosecution or intending to fight the prosecution," adding, "Granting exceptional supplementary investigation rights is a necessary system from the people's perspective, so he means we should discuss it from this viewpoint." (이 대통령이 하루 만에 ‘국민 권리가 우선한다’는 뜻을 밝힌 것은 여권 내부의 입장 차이를 분명하게 정리하려는 의도도 담긴 것으로 보인다. 이날 오전 열린 더불어민주당 정책 의원총회에서 검사의 보완수사권을 예외적으로 인정해야 한다는 의견이 전보다 늘었지만, 여전히 강경파를 중심으로 검사의 보완수사권을 완전히 박탈해야 한다는 의견이 나왔다. 한 청와대 관계자는 “이 대통령의 입장은 개혁과제를 주권자인 국민 입장에서 바라봐야지, 검찰하고 싸웠거나, 검찰과 싸우려는 입장에서 입법을 하는 것은 맞지 않다는 취지”라며 “예외적인 보완수사권 부여는 국민들 입장에서 필요한 제도인 만큼 이 관점에서 토론을 해보자는 뜻”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's attitude of prioritizing 'people's rights' serves as a basic guideline not only for prosecution reform but for state affairs as a whole. The previous day, regarding sensitive issues such as new nuclear power plant construction and the North Korean nuclear problem, President Lee expressed his thoughts based on pragmatism, stating, "We must keep options open and judge," and "Will North Korea give up its nukes? We must approach it pragmatically." (‘국민 권리’를 앞세우는 이 대통령의 태도는 검찰개혁뿐만 아니라 국정 전반에 대한 기본적인 지침이기도 하다. 이 대통령은 전날 신규 원전 건설과 북핵 문제 등 민감한 사안에 대해 “열어놓고 판단해야 한다”, “북한이 핵을 포기하겠나. 실용적으로 접근해야 한다” 등 실용주의를 바탕으로 한 자신의 생각을 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241232.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/371/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503772.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:38:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Within the Ruling Party, "Exceptional Need for Prosecutors' Supplementary Investigation Rights"... A 'Reversal' Following President Lee's Remarks (여당 내부 “보완수사권 예외적 필요”…이 대통령 한마디에 ‘반전’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241233.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503774.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 국회의원들이 22일 국회에서 열린 중대범죄수사청·공소청 설치법 관련 정책 의원총회 회의장에 들어서고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day after President Lee Jae-myung stated that prosecutors' rights to conduct supplementary investigations should exceptionally be guaranteed, various voices within the ruling party, which had been suppressed by the 'hardline prosecution reform faction', erupted. Various opinions also emerged regarding the scope of investigation for the Major Crime Investigation Bureau (MCIB), which has been expanded to nine categories. (이재명 대통령이 예외적으로 검사의 보완수사권을 보장해야 한다고 밝힌 다음날, 여당에서는 그동안 ‘검찰 개혁 강경파’에 억눌려 있었던 다양한 목소리가 분출했다. 9가지로 확대된 중대범죄수사청(중수청)의 수사 범위를 두고도 여러 의견이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea held a policy general meeting of lawmakers at the National Assembly on the 22nd regarding the bills to establish the MCIB and the Public Prosecution Service. A noticeable change compared to previous meetings was the prevalence of opinions that prosecutors' rights to conduct supplementary investigations should exceptionally be permitted. Lawmaker Park Gyun-taek, a former prosecutor, said, 'If we do not even recognize prosecutors' exceptional and conditional supplementary investigations, it will be difficult to protect defendants or victims appealing their innocence.' Lawmaker Hong Ki-won reportedly also said, "Didn't the President cite examples like situations where the statute of limitations for prosecution is imminent? He spoke specifically, reasonably, and well." (더불어민주당은 22일 국회에서 중수청·공소청 설치 법안 관련 정책 의원총회를 열었다. 이전 총회와 비교해 눈에 띄는 변화는 검사의 보완수사권을 예외적으로 허용해야 한다는 의견이 많았다는 점이다. 검사 출신 박균택 의원은 ‘검사의 예외적·조건부 보완수사조차 인정하지 않으면 억울함을 호소하는 피의자나 피해자를 보호하기 힘들다’고 말했고, 홍기원 의원도 “대통령께서 공소시효 만료가 코앞으로 다가온 상황 등을 예로 들지 않았나. 구체적으로 합당하게 잘 얘기하셨다”고 말했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Han-gyu, the party's chief deputy floor leader for policy, met with reporters after the meeting and explained, "(Unlike usual) there were many opinions in favor of the government's proposal. Many people used the President's remarks (yesterday) as a basis for their own arguments." Regarding this, Lawmaker Hong Ki-won said, "Until now, it was difficult to raise objections to the so-called hardline lawmakers' arguments. Yesterday, the President opened the floodgates first, creating an atmosphere where we can speak freely." President Lee mentioned the necessity of retaining prosecutors' supplementary investigation rights at a New Year's press conference the previous day, stating there are "cases where it is exceptionally necessary." (김한규 원내정책수석부대표는 의총 뒤 취재진을 만나 “(평소와 달리) 정부안에 대한 찬성 의견이 많았다. 본인들의 주장에 (어제) 대통령의 발언을 근거로 삼는 분들이 많았다”고 설명했다. 이에 대해 홍기원 의원은 “그동안 소위 강성 의원들의 주장에 이의를 제기하기 어려운 상황이었다. 어제 대통령이 먼저 물꼬를 트면서 자유롭게 말할 수 있는 분위기가 됐다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 전날 신년 기자회견에서 검사 보완수사권이 “예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”며 존치 필요성을 언급한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Various opinions were also presented regarding the MCIB's investigative scope. According to the government bill, the MCIB's investigative targets are '9 major crimes' (corruption, economic crimes, public official crimes, election crimes, defense industry crimes, major disasters, drugs, national crimes such as insurrection, and cyber crimes). Within the ruling party, opinions centered around hardliners had previously dominated, arguing that the investigative scope 'must be unconditionally reduced.' However, on this day, Chief Deputy Floor Leader Kim explained that opinions varied from "limiting targets to corruption and economic crimes" to "keeping it at nine but restricting the scope through enforcement decrees." (중수청의 수사 범위를 놓고도 다양한 의견이 나왔다. 정부 법안상 중수청의 수사 대상은 ‘9개 중대범죄’(부패, 경제, 공직자, 선거, 방위사업, 대형참사, 마약, 내란 등 국가범죄, 사이버 범죄)이다. 여당에서는 그동안 강경파를 중심으로 수사 범위를 ‘무조건 줄여야 한다’는 의견이 주를 이뤘지만 이날은 수사 대상을 “부패·경제 범죄로 제한해야 한다는 의견부터, 9개로 하되 시행령으로 범위를 제한해야 한다는 의견까지 다양했다”는 게 김 수석부대표의 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The legislative notice period for the MCIB/Public Prosecution Service bills lasts until the 26th of this month. The Democratic Party plans to "try to meet the legislative notice timeline as much as possible, but without being bound by the deadline, we will gather various opinions within the party." Once opinions are consolidated, it is expected that the government will submit a revised bill around early to mid-February after party-government consultations. (중수청·공소청 법안의 입법예고 기간은 오는 26일까지다. 민주당은 “입법예고 시점을 가능하면 맞추되, 기한에 구애받지 않고 다양한 당내 의견을 수렴하겠다”는 계획이다. 의견이 모이면 당정 협의를 거쳐 2월 초·중순께 정부가 수정안을 다시 낼 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Chae-woon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241233.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503774.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:37:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Those who harm our citizens will face ruin"... Largest repatriation of Cambodia scam organization members (이 대통령 “우리 국민 가해하면 패가망신”…캄보디아 조직원 최대 송환)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241234.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/296/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503777.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;청와대는 캄보디아 스캠 조직 한국 국적 피의자 73명을 22일 강제송환한다고 밝혔다. 사진은 검거 모습. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government is repatriating 73 Korean suspects, who were arrested for operating in scam organizations in Cambodia, to South Korea on a chartered plane on the 23rd. This is the largest single-case repatriation in history. President Lee Jae-myung instructed, "Make it clear that those who harm Korean citizens will face ruin, whether domestically or internationally." (정부가 캄보디아 스캠 조직에서 활동하다 검거된 한국인 피의자 73명을 전세기에 태워 23일 국내로 송환한다. 송환 규모는 단일 사건 기준으로 역대 최대다. 이재명 대통령은 “대한민국 국민을 가해하면 국내든 국외든 패가망신한다는 점을 확실하게 보여달라”고 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kang Yu-jeong, the presidential spokesperson, announced at a briefing on the 22nd, "Following President Lee's directive, the Special Task Force (TF) on Transnational Crime will forcibly repatriate 73 Korean suspects on the morning of the 23rd. They are accused of defrauding approximately 48.6 billion won from 869 of our citizens, operating from bases in Cambodia." The chartered plane carrying the suspects departed from Incheon International Airport in the afternoon of the same day. ( 강유정 청와대 대변인은 22일 브리핑을 통해 “이 대통령의 지시로 구성된 초국가범죄 특별대응 티에프(TF)가 캄보디아를 거점으로 우리 국민 869명에게 약 486억원을 편취한 한국 국적 피의자 73명을 23일 오전 강제 송환한다”고 밝혔다. 피의자들을 태울 전용기는 이날 오후 인천국제공항을 출발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Kang assessed, "This repatriation of crime suspects is the largest in scale to date. It is the result of a long-term investigation by a team dispatched to Cambodia, including a dedicated Korea unit, the National Intelligence Service, and local police." The investigation team identified seven scam compounds and, after a prolonged pursuit, arrested 92 individuals last December in the southwestern port city of Sihanoukville (51 people), the Thai border city of Poipet (15 people), and the eastern highland region of Mondulkiri (26 people) in Cambodia. They decided to repatriate 73 of them. ( 강 대변인은 “이번 범죄 피의자 국내 송환은 역대 최대 규모로 캄보디아 현지에 파견된 코리아 전담반, 국가정보원, 현지 경찰 등 수사팀이 장기간 추적 끝에 거둔 성과”라고 평가했다. 수사팀은 스캠 단지 7곳을 확인한 뒤 지난해 12월 캄보디아 남서부 항구도시 시아누크빌(51명)과 타이 접경 도시 포이페트(15명), 동부 고원 지역 몬둘키리(26명)에서 92명을 검거한 뒤 이 가운데 73명을 송환하기로 한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The repatriation targets include a romance scam couple who could not be repatriated last October. They are suspected of using deepfake technology while posing as fictional characters to defraud approximately 12 billion won from 104 Korean citizens. Also included are fugitive criminals who fled to Cambodia after committing sex crimes against minors and then participated in local scam operations. The ringleader of a fraud organization, who posed as an investment expert to defraud around 19.4 billion won from young adults starting their careers and retirees, and members who committed inhumane crimes by holding victims confined in scam compounds hostage to threaten their families in Korea and extort money and valuables are also being repatriated. ( 이번 송환 대상에는 지난해 10월 국내로 송환되지 못한 로맨스 스캠 부부 사기단도 포함됐다. 이들은 가상 인물로 위장한 뒤 딥페이크 기술을 활용해 우리 국민 104명에게 약 120억원 상당을 뜯어낸 혐의를 받고 있다. 미성년자를 대상으로 성범죄를 저지른 뒤 캄보디아로 도주해 현지 스캠 범죄에 가담한 도피 사범도 이번 송환 대상에 포함됐다. 투자 전문가를 사칭해 사회 초년생과 은퇴자를 상대로 약 194억원을 뜯어낸 사기 조직의 총책, 스캠 단지에 감금된 피해자를 인질 삼아 국내에 있는 가족을 협박하고 금품을 갈취한 반인륜적 범죄를 저지른 조직원들도 함께 송환된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee mentioned the repatriation of these crime organization members at a meeting of senior secretaries presided over at the presidential office in the afternoon. He stated, "Such transnational crimes are extremely malicious and threatening, not only destroying citizens' lives but also undermining the foundation of trust in the community and even causing diplomatic disputes. We must pursue them to the end and completely eradicate their roots." He then instructed the Office of the Senior Secretary for Civil Affairs, which oversees the TF, saying, "Make it clear that committing crimes against Korean citizens will result in greater losses, not profits. Based on cooperation with foreign governments, do your utmost to recover every last penny of the criminal proceeds so that the damages suffered by our citizens can be restored." ( 이 대통령은 이날 오후 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 이번 범죄조직원 송환을 거론하며 “이러한 초국가범죄는 국민의 삶을 파괴할 뿐만 아니라 공동체의 신뢰 기반을 훼손하고 외교 분쟁까지도 야기하는 아주 악질적이고 위협적인 범죄다. 끝까지 추적해 그 뿌리를 완전히 뽑아야 하겠다”고 했다. 그러면서 티에프를 총괄하는 민정수석실에 “대한민국 국민을 상대로 범죄 행위를 하면 이익은커녕 더 큰 손해를 본다는 점을 확실하게 보여달라. 외국 정부와의 공조를 바탕으로 범죄수익을 한푼도 빠짐없이 환수해 국민 피해가 회복될 수 있도록 최선을 다해달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shin Hyeong-cheol &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (신형철 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:newiron@hani.co.kr"&gt;newiron@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1241234.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/296/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503777.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:37:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party Calls for 'Election Alliance' Amid Ruling Bloc Merger Moves, While Reform Party Draws a Line (여권발 합당 움직임 속 ‘선거연대’ 외치는 국힘, 선긋는 개혁신당)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241235.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/397/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503779.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이준석 개혁신당 대표가 지난 21일 서울 여의도 국회 중앙홀에서 단식투쟁 일주일째를 맞은 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 농성장을 찾아 대화를 하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the People Power Party and the Reform Party are downplaying the significance of the ruling bloc's merger moves that surfaced on the 22nd, calling them "an attempt to cover up mistakes with sheer size" and "the same Chinese restaurant," while closely monitoring the impact of the ruling camp's consolidation. Within the People Power Party, voices are emerging that they should accelerate efforts for an election alliance to counter the large ruling party, especially since the push for a 'double special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds has opened the door for cooperation with the Reform Party. However, the Reform Party is signaling a line should be drawn, mentioning the remaining 'Yoon Again' faction within the People Power Party. (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 22일 터져 나온 여권발 합당 움직임에 “과오를 덩치로 덮으려는 것”, “같은 중국집”이라고 의미를 폄하하면서도 여권 결집의 파장을 예의주시하는 분위기다. 당 안에선 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 추진으로 개혁신당과의 공조에 물꼬를 튼 만큼, 거대 여당에 맞서기 위한 선거 연대에 속도를 내야 한다는 말들이 나온다. 하지만 개혁신당은 국민의힘에 남아 있는 ‘윤 어게인’ 세력을 언급하며 선을 긋는 분위기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ham In-kyung, spokesperson for the People Power Party, criticized in a commentary released that day, "If the two parties merge and contest the local elections, it would not be a united team but a losing team. It would merely be seat-based coalition politics, covering up each other's mistakes with size and evading responsibility by pushing through with numbers," adding, "They are treating the local elections solely as a tool for extending power." Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, also said after the party's Supreme Council meeting that morning, "The Democratic Party and the Innovation Party are clearly the same Chinese restaurant. Politics shouldn't be conducted like having two phones on the table." This was a dismissal and minimization of the meaning of the merger proposal between the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party put forward by Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae that day, framing it as a "tool for extending power" and essentially a merger between the same party. (함인경 국민의힘 대변인은 이날 논평을 내어 “두 당이 합쳐 지방선거를 치른다면 원팀이 아니라 망팀이다. 서로의 과오를 덩치로 덮고, 책임을 회피하기 위해 숫자로 밀어붙이는 의석 연합 정치가 될 뿐”이라며 “지방선거를 권력 연장의 도구로만 취급하고 있다”고 비판했다. 이준석 개혁신당 대표도 이날 오전 당 최고위원회의 뒤 “민주당과 혁신당은 분명히 같은 중국집이다. 전화기 두 대 놓고 하는 식으로 정치를 하면 안 된다”고 말했다. 이날 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 내놓은 조국혁신당과의 합당 제안의 의미를 “권력 연장의 도구”이자 사실상 같은 당끼리의 합당으로 폄하하고 축소한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the People Power Party, there are voices saying that to counter the ruling bloc's unification moves, they must accelerate 'conservative integration'. A second-term lawmaker said, "Representative Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike brought former President Park Geun-hye and former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min together, showing a vision of conservative integration. This should be used as an opportunity to lead to an alliance with the Reform Party." Another first-term lawmaker said, "If a merger with the Reform Party is difficult, we should at least pursue a realistic election alliance." Yet another second-term lawmaker said, "President Lee Jae-myung's recruitment of conservative figures and the merger of the two parties could be signals of a political realignment, but the party doesn't seem to be giving it much thought," adding, "Given that the Reform Party is also drawing a line at an 'election alliance', I'm worried the People Power Party might become isolated like a Galapagos party." (국민의힘 안에선 여권 통합 움직임에 맞서기 위해서라도 ‘보수통합’에 박차를 가해야 한다는 얘기가 나온다. 한 재선 의원은 “장동혁 대표의 단식으로 박근혜 전 대통령과 유승민 전 의원까지 한자리에 모여 보수 통합의 모습을 보여준 것을 계기로 개혁신당과의 연대까지 이끌어내야 한다”고 말했다. 또 다른 초선 의원은 “개혁신당과의 합당이 쉽지 않다면, 현실적인 선거 연대라도 해야 한다”고 말했다. 또다른 재선 의원은 “이재명 대통령의 보수 인사 영입, 두 당의 합당 등이 정계 개편 시작의 신호일 수 있는데 당은 별다른 고민이 없는 모습”이라며 “개혁신당도 ‘선거 연대’에는 선을 긋는 상황이라 국민의힘만 갈라파고스 정당처럼 고립될까 걱정”이라고 말했다.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;개혁신당은 일단 선거 연대 필요성에 공감하지 않는 분위기다. 이준석 대표는 이날 당 최고위에서 국민의힘을 겨냥해 “명백한 내란을 계몽령이라는 궤변으로 국민을 우롱하는 이른바 윤 어게인 세력이 숨 쉬고 있다”며 “보수 진영이 궤멸의 늪에서 빠져나오려면 윤석열과 검찰주의자들과 철저히 단절해야 한다”고 지적했다. 개혁신당 관계자는 “조국혁신당이 사라지면 선명한 제3당으로서 우리 입지를 더욱 다질 수 있다”며 “우리로서 최악의 선택은 국민의힘과 연대했는데, 선거에서 지는 것 아니겠나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform Party, for now, does not seem to share the sense of necessity for an election alliance. Leader Lee Jun-seok pointed out at the party's Supreme Council meeting that day, targeting the People Power Party, "The so-called 'Yoon Again' faction, which deceives the people by calling a clear insurrection an 'enlightenment decree', is still breathing within it," and stated, "For the conservative camp to escape the swamp of collapse, it must thoroughly sever ties with Yoon Suk-yeol and the prosecutorial supremacists." A Reform Party official said, "If the Cho Kuk Innovation Party disappears, we can further solidify our position as a clear third party," adding, "For us, the worst choice would be to ally with the People Power Party and then lose the election, wouldn't it?" (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;, 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241235.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/397/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503779.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:36:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok Ends Hunger Strike with Park Geun-hye's Help... So What About Han Dong-hoon? [Gongdeok Pocha] (박근혜 도움으로 단식 끝낸 장동혁…그래서 한동훈은요? [공덕포차])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241243.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503860.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae made a surprise proposal for a merger to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, saying, "Let's join us." In response, Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, replied, "We will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and will." Regarding the merger proposal, Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs, stated, "I was contacted in advance by leader Chung," and added, "The integration of the two parties and political integration have long been President Lee Jae-myung's established position." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 22일 조국혁신당에 “우리와 합치자”며 합당을 전격 제안했습니다. 이에 조국 조국혁신당 대표는 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정하겠다”고 답했는데요. 홍익표 청와대 정무수석은 정 대표의 합당 제안에 대해 “사전에 정 대표에게 연락을 받았다”며 “양당 통합과 정치적 통합은 평소 이재명 대통령의 지론이었다”고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that morning, former President Park Geun-hye visited People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who had been continuing a hunger strike for eight days, and requested he stop. In response, leader Jang stated, "I am stopping the hunger strike today for a longer and bigger fight." (이날 오전 박근혜 전 대통령이 8일 간 단식을 이어온 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 찾아 단식 중단을 요청했는데요. 이에 장 대표는 “좀 더 길고 큰 싸움을 위해서 오늘 단식을 중단한다”고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What decision will leader Jang, who has ended his hunger strike, make regarding the expulsion of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon? Will the Democratic Party and the Innovation Party ultimately merge? What explanations will candidate Lee Hye-hoon, whose confirmation hearing as Minister of Planning and Finance is scheduled for the 23rd, provide regarding the suspicions raised against her so far? Let's find out on &amp;lt;Gongdeok Pocha&amp;gt;. Check out the video! (단식을 중단한 장 대표는 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표에 대한 제명을 두고 어떤 결정을 내릴까요? 민주당과 혁신당은 결국 합당을 하게 될까요? 23일 열릴 예정인 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회에서 이 후보자는 그동안 제기된 의혹들에 대해 어떤 해명을 내놓을까요? &amp;lt;공덕포차&amp;gt;에서 알아봅니다. 영상으로 확인하시죠!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Production Team&lt;br/&gt;Executive Producer: Lee Kyung-joo &lt;br/&gt;Writer: Park Yeon-shin&lt;br/&gt;Host: Song Chae-kyeonghwa&lt;br/&gt;Cast: Jang Seong-cheol, Kim Jun-il &lt;br/&gt;Title: Moon Seok-jin &lt;br/&gt;Technical Director: Park Seong-young &lt;br/&gt;Camera: Jang Seung-ho&lt;br/&gt;Subtitles/Graphics Design: Jung Hyun-sun&lt;br/&gt;Administration: Kim Geun-young&lt;br/&gt;Directors: Jung Joo-yong, Lee Gyu-ho, Jang Ji-nam&lt;br/&gt;Production: Hankyoreh TV (제작진&lt;br/&gt;책임 프로듀서 : 이경주 &lt;br/&gt;작가 : 박연신&lt;br/&gt;진행 : 송채경화&lt;br/&gt;출연 : 장성철 김준일 &lt;br/&gt;타이틀 : 문석진 &lt;br/&gt;기술 : 박성영 &lt;br/&gt;카메라 : 장승호&lt;br/&gt;자막그래픽디자인 : 정현선&lt;br/&gt;행정 : 김근영&lt;br/&gt;연출 : 정주용 이규호 장지남&lt;br/&gt;제작 : 한겨레TV)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Song Chae-kyeonghwa &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (송채경화 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:khsong@hani.co.kr"&gt;khsong@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241243.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503860.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:36:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Mentions LS Group's Dual Listing, Calling It a "Cause of the Korea Discount" (이 대통령, LS 중복상장 언급하며 “코리아 디스카운트 원인”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241245.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503949.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 당내 기구인 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’ 소속 의원들이 22일 청와대 초청 오찬을 한 뒤 국회 소통관에서 브리핑을 하고 있다. 왼쪽부터 박홍배·이강일·오기형·정준호 의원. 오기형 의원 페이스북 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed that on the 22nd, the day the KOSPI index surpassed 5,000 for the first time in history, President Lee Jae-myung met with lawmakers from the Democratic Party of Korea's 'KOSPI 5,000 Special Committee' (Ocheon Committee) and mentioned the controversy surrounding LS Group's 'dual listing,' urging continued efforts for institutional improvements to protect minority shareholders' rights. At the meeting, President Lee discussed additional legislative matters, including the swift passage of the third revision to the Commercial Act, to solidify the KOSPI 5,000 era. (이재명 대통령이 코스피 지수가 사상 처음 5000을 돌파한 22일 더불어민주당 ‘코스피 5000 특별위원회’(오천특위) 의원들과 만나 엘에스(LS)그룹의 ‘중복상장’을 둘러싼 논란을 언급하며 소액주주 권리 보호를 위한 제도적 개선 노력을 계속할 것을 당부한 것으로 확인됐다. 이 대통령은 이 자리에서 코스피 5000 시대 안착을 위해 3차 상법 개정안의 조속한 통과 등 추가 입법 사안을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A participating lawmaker relayed that during a luncheon with the Ocheon Committee members that day, when a participant mentioned a news report titled "Don't buy stocks with an 'L' in their name," President Lee said, in essence, "Such dual listing issues become a cause of the Korea Discount," and urged, "Let's ensure we do not neglect institutional efforts (to protect minority shareholders)." (이 대통령은 이날 오천특위 의원들과 한 오찬 자리에서 “‘엘’(L)자가 들어간 주식은 안 사”라는 제목의 언론 보도를 한 참석자가 언급하자, “그런 중복상장 문제가 코리아 디스카운트의 원인이 된다”며 “(소액주주 보호를 위한) 제도적 노력에 소홀이 없도록 하자”는 취지로 말했다고 한 참석 의원이 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article President Lee referred to covered the issue of LS Group's dual listing. LS Group recently pursued the listing of its unlisted great-grandchild company, Essex Solutions. Furthermore, it is known that LS's core unlisted companies, such as LS MnM and LS Cable &amp; System, are also considering going public. However, if the parent company and an unlisted great-grandchild company are listed simultaneously, problems arise, such as the dilution of the parent company's minority shareholders' equity value and a reduction in benefits for the great-grandchild company's shareholders. (이 대통령이 언급한 기사는 엘에스그룹 중복상장 문제를 다룬 것이다. 엘에스 그룹은 최근 비상장 증손회사인 에식스솔루션즈의 상장을 추진했다. 그뿐만 아니라 엘에스엠엔엠(MnM), 엘에스전선 등 엘에스의 핵심 비상장사들도 상장을 검토하고 있는 것으로 알려졌다. 하지만 모회사와 비상장 증손회사가 동시에 상장되면 모회사 소액주주의 지분 가치가 희석되고 증손회사 주주들의 이익도 줄어드는 문제가 발생한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Oh Ki-hyung, chairman of the Ocheon Committee, later met with reporters and stated, "We discussed the need to be proactive in institutional improvements to resolve corporate dual listing issues." Additionally, during the luncheon, a consensus was formed that the third revision to the Commercial Act, which mandates companies to cancel their treasury shares, "should not be delayed any further." Discussions on institutional improvements also took place regarding the so-called 'stock price suppression prevention law' (a partial amendment to the Inheritance and Gift Tax Act) aimed at preventing listed companies facing inheritance from intentionally lowering their stock prices for inheritance tax reduction purposes. (오천특위 위원장인 오기형 의원은 이후 기자들을 만나 “기업 중복상장 문제를 해결하기 위한 제도 개선에 적극적이어야 한다는 얘기를 나눴다”고 전했다. 아울러 이날 오찬에서는 기업의 자기 주식을 의무적으로 소각하게 하는 내용을 담은 3차 상법 개정안과 관련해 “더 이상 미루면 안 된다”는 공감대가 형성됐고, 상속을 앞둔 상장기업이 상속세 절세를 위해 의도적으로 주가를 낮추는 것을 막기 위한 이른바 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’(상속세 및 증여세법 일부개정법률안)에 대한 제도 개선 논의도 이뤄졌다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol, Choi Ha-yan &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 최하얀 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1241245.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/766/510/imgdb/original/2026/0122/20260122503949.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:36:08 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>