<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 경제 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/economy/</link><description>Hankyoreh Economy bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Won-Dollar Exchange Rate Widens Decline in Night Trading to Around 1,465 Won... Reflecting Expectations for Ukraine War End (원-달러, 야간거래서 낙폭 확대 1465원…우크라 종전 기대감 반영)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241271.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Won-Dollar Exchange Rate Widens Decline in Night Trading to Around 1,465 Won... Reflecting Expectations for Ukraine War End (원-달러, 야간거래서 낙폭 확대 1465원…우크라 종전 기대감 반영)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691260622222_20260123500274.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;22일 오후 서울 중구 하나은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 원-달러 환율이 표시돼 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The won-dollar exchange rate widened its decline in night trading, closing around 1,465 won. (원-달러 환율이 야간 거래에서 낙폭을 확대하며 1465원 부근에서 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At 2 a.m. on the 23rd, the won-dollar exchange rate concluded night trading at 1,464.50 won, down 5.40 won from the previous day's closing price (1,469.9 won at 3:30 p.m.) in the Seoul foreign exchange market's daytime session. The won-dollar rate, which started around 1,468 won in the New York session, faced downward pressure influenced by a strong euro. Expectations for an end to the Ukraine war, including news that the US, Russia, and Ukraine will soon hold a trilateral meeting, drove euro strength, which in turn triggered 'dollar weakness and won strength.' US President Donald Trump, after meeting with Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelenskyy for about an hour, said, "I think it was good. The war must end." The US, Russia, and Ukraine announced they will hold trilateral talks in the United Arab Emirates (UAE) on the 23rd. (23일 새벽 2시 원-달러 환율은 야간거래에서 전날 서울 외환시장 주간거래 종가(1469.9원, 오후 3시 30분) 대비 5.40원 하락한 1464.50원에 거래를 마쳤다. 뉴욕장에 1468원 안팎으로 시작한 원-달러 환율은 유로 강세 영향을 받으며 하방 압력을 받았다. 미국과 러시아, 우크라이나가 조만간 3자 회동을 여는 등 우크라이나 전쟁 종전 기대감이 유로 강세를 끌어냈고, 이에 따라 ‘달러 약세-원화 강세’가 촉발됐다. 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령은 이날 볼로디미르 젤렌스키 우크라이나 대통령과 1시간가량 회동한 뒤 ”좋았다고 생각한다. 전쟁은 끝나야 한다”고 말했다. 미국과 러시아, 우크라이나는 오는 23일 아랍에미리트(UAE)에서 3자 회담을 한다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the euro faced upward pressure from the expectations for war's end, the Dollar Index (DXY), which reflects the dollar's value against a basket of six major currencies, fell sharply during the session to 98.315. Consequently, the won-dollar exchange rate also dropped to the 1,464 won range. (종전 기대감에 유로가 강세 압력을 받으면서 주요 6개 통화에 대한 달러 가치를 반영하는 달러인덱스(DXY)는 장중 98.315까지 크게 떨어졌다. 이에 따라 원-달러 환율도 1464원대로 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241271.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691260622222_20260123500274.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Coupang says "U.S. investors' 'Notice of Intent to Submit to International Investment Dispute Arbitration' is unrelated to us" (쿠팡 “미 투자사 ‘국제투자분쟁 중재의향서’ 제출, 우리와 무관”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241287.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Coupang says "U.S. investors' 'Notice of Intent to Submit to International Investment Dispute Arbitration' is unrelated to us" (쿠팡 “미 투자사 ‘국제투자분쟁 중재의향서’ 제출, 우리와 무관”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691307736567_20260123500827.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난해 12월 서울 시내 한 주차장에 주차된 쿠팡 배송 차량. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the submission of a Notice of Intent to Submit to International Investment Dispute Arbitration (ISDS) to the Korean government by Coupang's U.S. investors, who claim they suffered damages due to the Korean government and National Assembly's all-out pressure, including a fact-finding investigation, following Coupang's personal data leak incident, Coupang stated that it is "unrelated to the company's position." (쿠팡의 미국 투자사들이 쿠팡 개인정보 유출 사고 이후 한국 정부와 국회의 진상조사 등 전방위 압박으로 손해를 입었다며 한국 정부에 국제투자분쟁(ISDS) 중재의향서를 제출한 일과 관련해 쿠팡이 “당사 입장과 무관하다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coupang released a statement on the 23rd, saying, "The submission of the Notice of Intent to Submit to International Investment Dispute Arbitration by U.S. investors is unrelated to the company's position. Coupang is faithfully responding to all government investigation requests." (쿠팡은 23일 입장문을 내어 “미국 투자사의 국제투자분쟁 중재의향서 제출은 당사의 입장과는 무관하다. 쿠팡은 모든 정부 조사 요청에 성실히 임하고 있다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 22nd, the Ministry of Justice announced that U.S.-nationality shareholders of the U.S. company Coupang, such as Greenoaks and Altimeter, had submitted a Notice of Intent to Submit to International Investment Dispute Arbitration to the Korean government based on the Korea-U.S. Free Trade Agreement (FTA). It is reported that the claimants, including Greenoaks, argue that the Korean government's all-out pressure on Coupang following the personal data leak incident constitutes a violation of the Korea-U.S. FTA agreement, resulting in billions of dollars in damages. As Coupang's investors take legal action against the Korean government, the possibility of the dispute escalating into a trade conflict between the Korean and U.S. governments has also been raised. (앞서 법무부는 미국 쿠팡사의 주주인 미국 국적의 그린옥스(Greenoaks)와 알티미터(Altimeter) 등이 한-미 자유무역협정(FTA·에프티에이)에 근거해 국제투자분쟁 중재의향서를 대한민국 정부에 제출했다고 지난 22일 밝힌 바 있다. 그린옥스 등 청구인들은 개인정보 유출 사태 이후 쿠팡을 향한 한국 정부의 전방위적인 압박이 한-미 에프티에이 협정 위반에 해당하며, 이로 인해 수십억달러의 손해가 발생했다고 주장한 것으로 전해졌다. 쿠팡 투자사들이 한국 정부를 상대로 법적 행동에 나서면서, 한-미 정부 간 무역 갈등으로 확대될 가능성도 제기된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Reuters reported that Greenoaks and Altimeter have also filed a complaint with the U.S. Trade Representative (USTR), claiming that Korea's response to the Coupang incident was "discriminatory" and requesting that the Korean government be investigated and trade protection measures be imposed. (한편 그린옥스와 알티미터는 쿠팡 사태에 대한 한국의 대응이 “차별적”이라며 한국 정부를 조사하고 통상 보호 조처를 부과해달라고 미국 무역대표부(USTR)에도 제소했다고 로이터가 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241287.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691307736567_20260123500827.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In the AI Era, Re-examining 'Collaboration and Education'... Kookmin University Hosts International Design Award (AI 시대, ‘협업과 교육’을 다시 묻다… 국민대, 국제 디자인 어워드 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241294.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;In the AI Era, Re-examining 'Collaboration and Education'... Kookmin University Hosts International Design Award (AI 시대, ‘협업과 교육’을 다시 묻다… 국민대, 국제 디자인 어워드 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/654/749/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3617691323220298.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민대-중국상하이공과대 MOU 체결 사진 (정승렬 총장과 Lou Yongqi 총장).국민대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Design is not just the final product, but the very process of thinking, collaborating, and questioning that precedes it. The DBEW AWARD aims to reveal to the world the 'power of that process'."&lt;br/&gt;Kookmin University (President Seungryeol Jeong), a leader in design education in South Korea, is partnering with the world-renowned industrial design association ADI (ASSOCIAZIONE DESING INDUSTRIALE, Director Andrea Cancellato) to host an international-scale design award, 'DBEW AWARD 2026'.&lt;br/&gt;President Seungryeol Jeong of Kookmin University stated, "In the AI era, the role of education in nurturing human thought and collaboration has become even more important," adding, "We expect the DBEW AWARD to establish itself as a global platform where design educators and students from around the world can design the future together."&lt;br/&gt;Unlike existing design awards, the DBEW AWARD does not focus solely on finished results. Its most distinctive feature is that it highlights designs born as outcomes of creative education and officially recognizes the collaborative process between educators and students itself as a creative achievement. As the world's first design award to evaluate and award the leadership and mentoring capabilities of creative educators, the DBEW AWARD is expected to set a new standard for design education.&lt;br/&gt;True to its name, it aims to place emphasis on fostering convergent design across various fields—such as technology and design, humanities and design—by discovering and awarding educators who nurture talent and their students, who pursue harmonious designs where Eastern and Western values coexist based on outstanding creativity.&lt;br/&gt;The judging process will be conducted in two stages by a multidisciplinary panel of judges, ranging from globally renowned practitioners in design, architecture, and curation to leading academics in education. The panel includes experts from around the world such as Paola Antonelli, Senior Curator and Director of Research &amp; Development in the Department of Architecture and Design at MoMA; John Thackara, a pioneer in sustainability discourse; Stefano Giovannoni, who established a design language connecting industrial design and marketing; Daniel Libeskind, known for architectural work that transcends East-West boundaries; Korean representative architect Byungsoo Cho; and President Lou Yongqi of Shanghai Polytechnic University in China.&lt;br/&gt;Architect Byungsoo Cho emphasized, "The attitude of embracing fresh ideas through the collaborative model of student and professor is at the core of the DBEW AWARD," stating, "Rather than dividing East and West dichotomously, the point of contemplating how they can interact and present a new vision is what differentiates it from other awards, making the process of breaking down disciplinary boundaries and exchanging ideas more important than anything."&lt;br/&gt;The message the DBEW AWARD sends to the global design community is also clear. President Lou Yongqi of Shanghai Polytechnic University, who is participating as a judge, said, "While many design awards already exist, awards focusing on the co-creation of educators and students are very rare," adding, "By placing the value of human collaboration and education at the forefront in the age of artificial intelligence, the DBEW AWARD will suggest a new direction."&lt;br/&gt;The DBEW AWARD's judging criteria consist of six categories: originality, innovation, relevance to theme, aesthetic completeness, sustainability &amp; social responsibility, and expressiveness. President Lou Yongqi stated, "How these six criteria are creatively combined and expressed is of utmost importance," explaining, "This is deeply connected to the designer's experience, cultural context, and 'tacit knowledge' that is not easily quantifiable."&lt;br/&gt;Any undergraduate or graduate student in design or an emerging designer within two years of graduation can participate, and it proceeds with students and educators forming teams to enter. Educators participate solely in a mentoring role, and works must have been produced within the last two years. Submission categories are Space &amp; Architectural Design, Product &amp; Fashion Design, and Visual, Communication &amp; Service Design (AI, digital media, branding, services, etc.).&lt;br/&gt;Professor Kyungran Choi of Kookmin University (Director of the Institute of Oriental Culture &amp; Design), who is the chairperson of the 1st DBEW Award operating committee, describes the DBEW Award not as a simple result-oriented design competition, but as an international design contest that evaluates the entire process where creative educational processes lead to outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;She added that global design opinion leaders, resonating with this distinctiveness and the timeliness of the theme 'Sustainable Design Beyond East and West', have actively participated as judges.&lt;br/&gt;Submissions will be accepted until March 15, 2026, with final results announced on March 25, 2026. The total prize money is $25,000. The award ceremony and forum will be held at the ADI Design Museum during Milan Design Week on April 21, 2026, followed by an exhibition at Seoul DDP during Seoul Design Week in October 2026. Detailed information about DBEW AWARD 2026 can be found on the official website (dbewaward.com). (“디자인은 완성된 결과물 이전에, 사고하고 협업하며 질문을 던지는 과정 그 자체입니다. DBEW AWARD는 바로 그 ‘과정의 힘’을 세상에 드러내고자 합니다.”&lt;br/&gt;대한민국 디자인 교육을 선도해 온 국민대학교(총장 정승렬)가 세계적인 산업 디자인 협회 ADI(ASSOCIAZIONE DESING INDUSTRURIALE, 관장 안드레아 칸첼라토)와 손잡고 국제적 규모의 디자인 AWARD ‘DBEW AWARD 2026’를 개최한다.&lt;br/&gt;국민대 정승렬 총장은 “AI 시대에서 인간의 사고와 협업을 키우는 교육의 역할은 더욱 중요해진다”며 “DBEW AWARD가 전 세계 디자인 교육자와 학생들이 미래를 함께 설계하는 글로벌 플랫폼으로 자리 잡기를 기대한다”고 전했다. &lt;br/&gt;DBEW AWARD는 기존의 디자인 어워드와 달리 완성된 결과물에만 초점을 맞추지 않는다. 창의적인 교육의 결과로서 탄생한 디자인을 조명하며, 교육자와 학생 간의 협업 과정 자체를 하나의 창의적 성취로 공식 인정한다는 점이 가장 큰 특징이다. DBEW AWARD는 창의적인 교육자의 지도력과 멘토링 역량을 평가·시상하는 세계 최초의 디자인 어워드로서, 디자인 교육의 새로운 기준을 제시할 것으로 기대를 모으고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;그 명칭처럼 뛰어난 창의력을 바탕으로 동서양 가치가 공존하는 조화로운 디자인을 지향하는 인재와 그 학생들을 육성하는 교수자를 발굴하여 시상함으로써, 기술과 디자인 · 인문과 디자인 등 다양한 분야의 융합적 디자인의 육성에 방점을 찍을 계획이다.  &lt;br/&gt;심사는 세계적으로 주목받는 디자인·건축·큐레이션 분야의 실무 전문가부터 교육계 석학까지 다학제적인 전문가로 구성된 심사위원단이 1, 2차 단계를 거쳐 진행한다. MoMA 디자인 부문 수석 큐레이터이자 연구개발 책임자인 파올라 안토넬리(Paola Antonelli), 지속가능성 담론을 이끌어온 존 타카르(John Thackara), 산업디자인과 마케팅을 연결한 디자인 언어를 확립한 스테파노 지오반노니(Stefano Giovannoni), 동서양의 경계를 넘는 건축 작업으로 알려진 다니엘 리베스킨트(Daniel Libeskind), 한국을 대표하는 건축가 조병수, 중국 상하이 공과대학교 Lou Yongqi 총장 등 세계 각지의 전문가들로 구성됐다. &lt;br/&gt;조병수 건축가는 “학생과 교수의 협력 모델을 통해 신선한 아이디어를 수용하려는 태도가 DBEW AWARD의 핵심”이라며 “동서양을 이분법적으로 나누기보다 어떻게 상호 작용하며 새로운 비전을 제시할 수 있을지를 고민하는 지점이 다른 시상과의 차별점이기 때문에 분야의 경계를 허물고 교류하는 과정이 무엇보다 중요하다”고 강조했다. &lt;br/&gt;DBEW AWARD가 세계 디자인계에 전달하는 메시지도 명확하다. 심사위원으로 참여하는 중국 상하이 공과대학교 Lou Yongqi 총장은 “이미 많은 디자인 어워드가 존재하지만, 교육자와 학생의 공동 창작에 초점을 둔 상은 매우 드물다”며 “인공지능 시대에 인간의 협업과 교육의 가치를 전면에 내세운다는 점에서, DBEW AWARD는 새로운 방향을 제시할 것”이라고 말했다.&lt;br/&gt;DBEW AWARD의 심사기준은 독창성, 혁신성, 주제 적합성, 미적 완성도, 지속가능성 및 사회적 책임, 표현력 등 총 6가지이다. Lou Yongqi 총장은 “이 6가지 기준이 어떻게 창의적으로 결합하는지 표현하는 것이 무엇보다 중요하다”며 “이는 디자이너의 경험과 문화적 맥락, 그리고 쉽게 수치화할 수 없는 ‘암묵적 지식’과 깊이 연결되어 있다”고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;디자인 관련 학부생 및 대학원생 또는 졸업 후 2년 이내의 신진 디자이너라면 누구나 참여할 수 있으며 학생과 교육자가 팀을 이루어 참여하는 방식으로 진행된다. 교육자는 멘토링 역할로만 참여하며, 작품은 최근 2년 이내 제작된 결과물이어야 한다. 공모 분야는 공간·건축 디자인, 프로덕트·패션 디자인, 시각·커뮤니케이션·서비스 디자인(AI, 디지털 미디어, 브랜딩, 서비스 등)이다. &lt;br/&gt;제1회 DBEW Award 운영위원장인 국민대학교 최경란 교수(동양문화디자인연구소 소장)는 DBEW Award를 단순한 결과 중심의 디자인 공모가 아닌, 교육의 창의적 과정이 성과물로 이어지는 전 과정을 평가하는 국제 디자인 공모전으로 설명한다.&lt;br/&gt;그는 이러한 차별성과 ‘동양과 서양을 넘어서는 지속가능한 디자인’이라는 주제에 시대의 중요성에 공감한 세계적인 디자인 오피니언 리더들이 심사위원으로 적극 참여하게 되었다고 덧붙였다.  &lt;br/&gt;공모 접수는 오는 2026년 3월 15일까지 진행되며, 최종 결과는 2026년 3월 25일 발표된다. 총상금은 2만5천 달러 규모다. 시상식과 포럼은 2026년 4월 21일 밀라노 디자인 위크 기간 동안 ADI 디자인 뮤지엄에서 개최되며, 이후 2026년 10월 서울 디자인 위크 기간 동안 서울 DDP에서 전시로 이어질 예정이다. DBEW AWARD 2026에 대한 자세한 내용은 공식 홈페이지(dbewaward.com)를 통해 확인할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Kookmin University (* 자료제공 :  국민대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241294.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/654/749/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3617691323220298.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon, embroiled in 'abuse of power' controversy, says "I reflect on my immature words and actions"... also apologizes for involvement in insurrection (‘갑질’ 논란 이혜훈 “성숙하지 못한 언행 반성”…내란동조 사과도)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241295.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, embroiled in 'abuse of power' controversy, says "I reflect on my immature words and actions"... also apologizes for involvement in insurrection (‘갑질’ 논란 이혜훈 “성숙하지 못한 언행 반성”…내란동조 사과도)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/678/imgdb/original/2026/0123/7917691358294932.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에 출석해 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, said regarding the controversy over verbal abuse and abuse of power towards her aides, "I sincerely apologize to all those who were hurt due to my immature words and actions." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 보좌진에 대한 폭언·갑질 논란과 관련해 “저의 성숙하지 못한 언행 때문에 상처받은 모든 분들께 진심으로 사과드린다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During her opening statement at the National Assembly confirmation hearing on the 23rd, the nominee said, "Living as a one-eyed person obsessed with proving myself only through policy tenacity and results, I failed to properly see the wounds I inflicted on precious colleagues who worked with me. I deeply reflect on this." (이 후보자는 23일 국회 인사청문회 모두발언에서 “정책에 대한 집념과 결과로만 증명하겠다는 성과에 매몰된 외눈박이로 살아오면서 저와 함께했던 소중한 동료들에게 상처를 드린 점을 제대로 보지 못했다. 뼈저리게 반성한다”며 이렇게 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee stated, "Since being nominated as the candidate for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, there have been many criticisms pointing out my shortcomings," and added, "I am sorry for causing concern to the respected citizens. I am also sorry to the members of the confirmation hearing committee and to the President who nominated me as a ministerial candidate." (이 후보자는 “기획예산처 장관 후보자에 지명된 이후 저의 부족함에 대한 여러 지적이 있었다”며 “존경하는 국민들께 심려를 끼쳐 송구하다. 청문위원 여러분, 그리고 저를 장관 후보자로 지명하신 대통령님께도 송구하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She also apologized for her actions related to the December 12th insurrection. The nominee said, "I apologize once again for having taken a position of flawed judgment from which it is difficult to avoid criticism of having sympathized with the insurrection," and added, "I will not make any excuses. The responsibility lies solely with me." She further stated, "I clearly acknowledge that failing to immediately admit my mistake and spending a full year in hesitation and silence, in other words, this belated apology itself, is another wrongdoing." (그는 12·3 내란과 관련한 행보에 대해서도 사과했다. 이 후보자는 “내란에 동조했다는 비판을 피하기 어려운 잘못된 판단의 자리에 서 있었음을 다시 한 번 사과드린다”며 “어떠한 변명도 하지 않겠다. 책임은 오롯이 저에게 있다”고 말했다. 그는 “잘못을 즉시 인정하지 못하고 무려 1년이라는 시간을 망설임과 침묵 속에서 흘려보냈다는 사실, 즉 이 늦은 사과 자체가 또 하나의 잘못임을 분명히 인정한다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee said, "If I am given the opportunity to contribute even a small part to the success of the people-sovereign government with the experience and expertise in fiscal policy I have accumulated over my lifetime, I will understand the people's command to repay my past wrongs with the weight of state affairs and devote all my energy," and added, "I stand here with the mindset that I will participate, even if it means being stoned, in opening a new path for the Republic of Korea, which is currently unable to take a single step forward due to being shackled by partisan politics." (이 후보자는 “제가 평생 쌓아온 재정정책의 경험과 전문성으로 국민주권정부의 성공에 단 한 부분이라도 기여할 기회를 주신다면, 저의 과오를 국정의 무게로 갚으라는 국민의 명령으로 알고 사력을 다하겠다”며 “진영정치에 발목 잡혀 한 걸음도 앞으로 나아가지 못하는 지금의 대한민국에 새로운 길을 여는 일에는 돌을 맞더라도 동참하겠다는 심정으로 이 자리에 서게 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee emphasized, "To boost the potential growth rate and alleviate polarization and K-shaped recovery, an active role for fiscal policy is necessary, so attention and focus on the productivity and sustainability of public finance are more important than ever," and stated, "I am prepared to produce results in eliminating redundancies and plugging leaks. My consistent principle is to pursue 'smart fiscal management' that maximizes budget efficiency through fiscal operations based on data and performance analysis, while faithfully fulfilling its role when fiscal support is needed." (이 후보자는 “잠재성장률을 반등시키고 양극화와 K자형 회복을 완화하기 위해서는 재정의 적극적인 역할이 필요하기에 재정의 생산성과 지속가능성에 대한 주의와 관심 또한 그 어느 때보다 중요하다”며 “중복은 걷어내고 누수는 막아내는 일에 성과를 낼 준비가 돼 있다. 재정이 필요한 시점에 제 역할을 충실히 하면서도 데이터와 성과 분석에 기반한 재정 운영을 통해 예산의 효율성을 극대화하는 ‘똑똑한 재정’을 하자는 것이 저의 일관된 지론”이라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She said, "I consider the mission of transforming the budget into a means to realize the national vision, a tool to adjust policy priorities, and a performance-centered management instrument as my final calling, and I will pour all my capabilities into four tasks." These are: △Establishing a mid-to-long-term national development strategy for future generations △Establishing a sustainable growth foundation through simultaneous achievement of growth and welfare △Leading fiscal innovation and concentrating fiscal investment in AI, advanced strategic industries, etc. △Ensuring substantive public participation in the entire process of national budget formulation, execution, and settlement. (그는 “예산을 국가 비전을 실현하는 수단으로, 정책 우선순위를 조정하는 도구로, 성과 중심의 관리 수단으로 전환하는 임무를 저의 마지막 소명으로 알고 네 가지 과업에 저의 모든 역량을 쏟아붓겠다”고 말했다. △미래 세대를 위한 중장기 국가발전 전략 수립 △성장과 복지의 동시 달성을 통해 지속가능한 성장 기반 확립 △재정 혁신 선도 및 인공지능·첨단 전략산업 등에 재정 집중 투입 △국가 예산 편성·집행·결산 전 과정에 실질적인 국민 참여 보장 등이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the nominee's opening statement, Committee Chairwoman Lim Yi-ja pointed out, "'One-eyed person' is a derogatory term, do you not intend to revise it?" In response, the nominee replied, "I'm sorry. I didn't think of that. I will revise it." (임이자 재정경제위원장은 이 후보자의 모두발언 중 “‘외눈박이’는 낮잡은 말인데 수정할 생각 없느냐”고 지적했다. 이에 이 후보자는 “죄송하다. 생각 못 했다. 수정하겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241295.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/678/imgdb/original/2026/0123/7917691358294932.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sookmyung Women's University and Moncler Group Collaborate to Foster Female Talent in Fashion... Joint Operation of Field Training and Internships (숙명여대, 몽클레르그룹과 패션 분야 여성인재 양성 협력… 현장실습·인턴십 공동 운영)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241302.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sookmyung Women's University and Moncler Group Collaborate to Foster Female Talent in Fashion... Joint Operation of Field Training and Internships (숙명여대, 몽클레르그룹과 패션 분야 여성인재 양성 협력… 현장실습·인턴십 공동 운영)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/2117691339250975.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;1월 21일(수) 서울 용산구 숙명여대 행정관에서 열린 업무협약식에서 문시연 숙명여대 총장(오른쪽)이 이용택 몽클레르그룹 대표와 기념촬영을 하고 있다. (숙명여자대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University is joining hands with the global fashion brand Moncler Group to foster the next generation of female talent to lead the fashion and retail sectors. As the first Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) for Sookmyung Women's University, which marks its 120th founding anniversary this year, this strategic collaboration with a global company is expected to broaden the scope of industry-academia cooperation and significantly enhance students' practical capabilities. (숙명여대가 글로벌 패션 브랜드 몽클레르그룹과 손잡고 패션·리테일 분야를 이끌 차세대 여성인재 양성에 나선다. 올해 창학 120주년을 맞은 숙명여대의 첫 업무협약(MOU)으로, 글로벌 기업과의 전략적 협력을 통해 산학협력의 외연을 넓히고 학생들의 실무 역량을 한층 강화할 것으로 기대된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University (President Si-yeon Moon) held a signing ceremony for an MOU to promote industry-academia cooperation and recruitment linkage with Moncler Group Korea on Wednesday, January 21st, at the university's administration building in Yongsan-gu, Seoul. Attendees included Sookmyung Women's University President Si-yeon Moon, Moncler Group Representative Yong-taek Lee, along with Sookmyung's Vice President Kyung-woo Wi, External Cooperation Director Hyung-jin Lee, Career Development Director Seo-hee Son (Director of the University Job Plus Center), and College of Human Ecology Dean Young-sun Kim (Professor of the Department of Clothing and Textiles). (숙명여자대학교(총장 문시연)는 1월 21일(수) 서울 용산구 숙명여대 행정관에서 몽클레르그룹코리아와 산학협력 및 채용연계 활성화를 위한 업무협약식을 개최했다. 협약식에는 문시연 숙명여대 총장, 이용택 몽클레르그룹 대표를 비롯해 숙명여대 위경우 부총장, 이형진 대외협력처장, 손서희 경력개발처장(대학일자리플러스센터장), 김영선 생활과학대학장(의류학과 교수) 등이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This agreement was established to expand students' practical experience and strengthen their employment capabilities, linking with the Ministry of Employment and Labor support project currently operated by Sookmyung Women's University's University Job Plus Center. (이번 협약은 숙명여대 대학일자리플러스센터가 운영 중인 고용노동부 지원사업과 연계해 학생들의 실무 경험을 확대하고 취업 역량을 강화하기 위해 마련됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through this agreement, both parties will pursue the following: △Operation of field training and internship programs in the fashion and retail sectors △Establishment of industry-linked extracurricular programs △Holding of recruitment information sessions △Collaboration on sustainable fashion research and eco-friendly material development. Seo-hee Son, Director of Sookmyung Women's University's University Job Plus Center, stated, "We plan to expand partnerships with excellent companies to broadly provide students with field experience and employment opportunities." (양측은 이번 협약을 계기로 △패션·리테일 분야 현장실습 및 인턴십 프로그램 운영 △산학연계형 비교과 프로그램 개설 △채용설명회 개최 △지속가능 패션 연구 및 친환경 소재 개발협력 등을 추진한다. 손서희 숙명여대 대학일자리플러스센터장은 &amp;quot;앞으로 우수 기업과의 파트너십을 확대해 학생들에게 현장 경험과 취업 기회를 폭넓게 제공하겠다&amp;quot;고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University and Moncler Korea have been consistently running the student-participation field training internship program 'MONCareer' jointly since 2022. Sookmyung's University Job Plus Center plans to actively strengthen practical-based partnerships with excellent companies going forward to enhance students' employment capabilities. (숙명여대와 몽클레르코리아는 2022년부터 현장실습 인턴십 프로그램 ‘MONCareer’을 공동 운영하며 학생 참여형 프로그램을 꾸준히 이어왔다. 숙명여대 대학일자리플러스센터는 앞으로도 우수 기업과 실무 기반의 파트너십을 강화해 학생들의 취업 역량 향상에 적극적으로 나설 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moncler Group Representative Yong-taek Lee said, "We find it very meaningful that through continuous industry-academia cooperation with Sookmyung Women's University, we can discover the creative talent needed for the fashion retail industry and nurture the future generation together." (이용택 몽클레르그룹 대표는 &amp;quot;숙명여자대학교와의 지속적인 산학협력을 통해 패션 리테일 산업에 필요한 창의적 인재를 발굴하고, 미래세대를 함께 육성할 수 있어 매우 뜻깊게 생각한다&amp;quot;고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University President Si-yeon Moon said, "Through this MOU, we expect to strengthen ties with a global fashion brand and help students develop the capabilities required in the industrial field." (문시연 숙명여대 총장은 &amp;quot;이번 MOU를 통해 글로벌 패션 브랜드와 연결고리를 강화하고, 학생들이 산업현장에서 요구하는 역량을 키울 수 있기를 기대한다&amp;quot;고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the global luxury fashion brand Moncler transitioned to the Moncler Group structure after acquiring Stone Island in 2020. Currently, Moncler Korea and Stone Island Korea, under Moncler Group Korea, operate distribution networks centered around major domestic department stores and flagship stores. (한편, 글로벌 럭셔리 패션 브랜드 몽클레르는 2020년 스톤아일랜드를 인수하며 몽클레르그룹 체제로 전환했으며, 현재 몽클레르그룹코리아 산하의 몽클레르코리아와 스톤아일랜드코리아는 국내 주요 백화점과 플래그십 스토어를 중심으로 유통망을 운영하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241302.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/2117691339250975.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon and Chun Ha-ram bring up a memorandum; "I did not write it" (이혜훈, 천하람이 꺼낸 비망록에 “내가 쓴 것 아니다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241303.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon and Chun Ha-ram bring up a memorandum; "I did not write it" (이혜훈, 천하람이 꺼낸 비망록에 “내가 쓴 것 아니다”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에 출석해 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, a nominee for the Minister of Planning and Budget, denied allegations regarding the authenticity of a memorandum, stating, "I did not write it." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 비망록 진위 의혹에 대해 “제가 작성하지 않았다”고 부인했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee on the 23rd, the nominee drew a line on the controversy over the memorandum's authenticity, saying, "I do not create such things (memorandums) as Hangeul files." He explained, "Based on various schedules that all office staff share, it appears someone mixed their own conjectures and various rumors, in my view." This implies that someone plausibly fabricated it using his actual schedules and rumors. When asked, "Are you aware that you could be punished for perjury?" he replied, "Yes." (이 후보자는 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 “한글 파일로 이런 것(비망록)을 만들지 않는다”며 진위 논란에 선을 그었다. 그는 “사무실 직원들은 다 공유하는 여러 일정을 기반으로 누군가가 제가 보기에는 본인의 짐작과 여러가지 소문을 버무린 것으로 보인다”고 설명했다. 자신의 실제 일정과 소문 등으로 개연성 있게 누군가 꾸며낸 것이라는 취지다. ‘위증하시면 처벌받는다는 것 알고 있냐’는 물음엔 “그렇다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'memorandum' claimed by Chun Ha-ram, a member of the Reform Party, to have been written by the nominee is known to contain details such as circumstances of covering up suspicions of the nominee's own receipt of money and valuables in 2017, reliance on shamans and religion, creation of a list of lawmakers to be defeated, and prayers for their defeat. (천하람 개혁신당 의원이 이 후보자가 작성했다고 주장한 ‘비망록’에는 2017년 이 후보자 본인의 금품수수 의혹에 대한 무마 정황, 무속인과 종교에 의지하는 내용, 낙선 의원 명단 작성과 낙선 기도 등이 담겨있는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Rep. Chun, who obtained the memorandum, asked, "Can the memorandum be disclosed to the public?" the nominee responded, "Regarding the misunderstandings and suspicions arising from something I did not write, it is very difficult to agree," and added, "I would like to mention the various damages I suffer if it is fully disclosed. I have already suffered considerable damage. Even though I did not write it, wouldn't it appear in the media under the name 'Lee Hye-hoon's memorandum'?" (해당 비망록을 입수한 천 의원이 ‘비망록을 국민에 공개해도 되느냐’고 묻자 “제가 작성하지도 않은 것으로 인해 오해와 의혹을 받는 부분에 대해선 굉장히 동의하기가 어렵다”며 “다 공개할 때 제가 받는 여러 피해에 대해 말씀드리고 싶다. 이미 상당의 피해를 받았다. 제가 작성하지 않은 것인데 ‘이혜훈 비망록’이라는 이름으로 언론에 나가지 않겠는가”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241303.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sogang University Graduate School of Economics Signs Business Agreement with Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters and Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul (서강대학교 경제대학원, (사)한국산업단지경영자연합회서울, 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부와 업무협약 체결)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241304.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sogang University Graduate School of Economics Signs Business Agreement with Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters and Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul (서강대학교 경제대학원, (사)한국산업단지경영자연합회서울, 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부와 업무협약 체결)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0123/7317691345425705.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(왼쪽부터) 김경수 KIBA서울 회장, 서강대 경제대학원 박정수 원장, 박종배 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부장. (서강대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sogang University Graduate School of Economics, the Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters, and the Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul (KIBA) signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) on Tuesday, January 20, for 'Fostering Opinion Leaders and Building an ESG Ecosystem'. (서강대학교 경제대학원과 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부, 그리고 (사)한국산업단지경영자연합회 서울(KIBA)이 지난 1월 20일(화) ‘OPINION LEADER 육성 및 ESG 생태계 구축을 위한 업무 협약(MOU)’을 체결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The signing ceremony, held at the Sogang Economics Reception Hall in the Gaepoert Nam Duck-Woo Economics Building at Sogang University, was attended by key officials from both organizations. Attendees included Dean Park Jeong-soo and Vice Dean Kim Jin-won of the Graduate School of Economics, Professor Lee Kang-oh (Director of OLP), Professor Joo Ha-yeon (Chair of the Department of Economics), Vice Director Son Seong-bin of the Jiam Nam Duck-Woo Economic Research Institute, Professor Lee Seong-won (Chair of the Graduate Department of Economics); from the Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters, Director Park Jong-bae, Team Leader Yoon Eun-sik of the Corporate Support Team, and Assistant Manager Na Yu-bin; from the Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul, Chairman Kim Gyeong-su, Standing Vice Chairman Choi Chang-seok, Vice Chairman Kim Hee-jeong, Director Joo Young-hye, Deputy Manager Jeong Jeong-mi; and Director Yoon Joong-sik of Daeshin Economic Research Institute. (서강대학교 게페르트 남덕우 경제관 서강경제 리셉션홀에서 진행된 협약식에는 박정수 경제대학원 원장, 김진원 부원장, 이강오 OLP 주임교수, 주하연 경제학과장, 손성빈 지암남덕우경제연구원 부원장, 이성원 대학원 경제학과 주임교수, 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부 박종배 본부장, 윤은식 기업지원팀장, 나유빈 대리, (사)한국사업단지경영자연합회서울 김경수 회장, 최창석 상근부회장, 김희정 부회장, 주영혜 이사, 정정미 차장, 대신경제연구소 윤중식 이사를 비롯한 양 기관의 주요 관계자들이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul is an economic organization established to promote the rights and interests and foster mutual development of business operators in industrial complexes. Its vision is to enhance corporate competitiveness through field-centered cooperative networks and practical industry-academia-research linkages. It promotes the co-growth of industrial complexes through cooperation among member companies and connections with external institutions. ((사)한국산업단지경영자연합회서울은 산업단지 입주기업 경영자들의 권익 증진과 공동 발전을 목적으로 설립된 경제단체로, 현장 중심의 협력 네트워크와 실질적인 산학연 연계를 통해 기업 경쟁력을 높이는 것을 비전으로 하고 있다. 회원사 간 협력과 외부 기관과의 연계를 통해 산업단지의 동반 성장을 도모하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters is a public institution established for the systematic management of industrial complexes and the strengthening of corporate competitiveness. Its core vision is technological innovation and talent cultivation based on industry-academia-research collaboration. It aims for the sustainable growth of Seoul's industrial complexes and the creation of a future industrial ecosystem by linking companies, universities, and research institutions. (한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부는 산업단지의 체계적인 관리와 기업 경쟁력 강화를 목적으로 설립된 공공기관으로, 산학연 협력을 기반으로 한 기술 혁신과 인재 양성을 핵심 비전으로 삼고 있다. 기업·대학·연구기관 간 연계를 통해 서울 산업단지의 지속가능한 성장과 미래 산업 생태계 조성을 지향하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through this agreement, each institution has promised to cooperate mutually by establishing an interlinked system for ▲educational cooperation to foster Opinion Leaders and ▲mutually enhancing shared interests for building an ESG ecosystem based on industrial complexes. (본 협약을 통해 각 기관은 상호 간의 연계 체계를 구축하여 ▲Opinion Leader 육성을 위한 교육협력 ▲산업단지 기반의 ESG 생태계 조성을 위한 상호 공동의 이익 증진 등에 대해서 상호 협력하기로 약속했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Jeong-soo, Dean of Sogang University Graduate School of Economics, stated, "This tripartite business agreement involving Sogang University Graduate School of Economics, the Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters, and the Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul is the first of its kind and a very meaningful occasion." He added, "While ESG faces various short-term difficulties, it is an important direction our society must firmly establish in the long term," and expressed his hope that "this agreement will become the starting point for sustainable industry-academia cooperation." (박정수 서강대학교 경제대학원 원장은 “서강대학교 경제대학원, 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부, 한국산업단지경영자연합회 서울이 함께하는 3자 간 업무협약은 처음으로, 매우 뜻깊은 자리”라고 전했다. 이어 “ESG는 단기적으로는 여러 어려움이 있지만, 우리 사회가 장기적으로 반드시 정착시켜 나가야 할 중요한 지향점”이라며 “이번 협약이 지속가능한 산학협력의 출발점이 되길 기대한다”라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Jong-bae, Director of the Korea Industrial Complex Corporation Seoul Regional Headquarters, said, "The Seoul Digital National Industrial Complex (G-Valley) is a representative national industrial complex, sensitive to industrial trend changes, with about 17,000 companies and 150,000 workers active within it. The Corporation plays a role in supporting these industrial complex companies to smoothly adapt to the changing business environment." He added, "I hope that through this agreement, the linkage between the university and the industrial complex will be further strengthened." (박종배 한국산업단지공단 서울지역본부장은 “서울디지털국가산업단지(G밸리)는 약 1만7천 개 기업과 15만 명의 근로자가 활동하는, 산업 트렌드 변화에 민감한 대표적인 국가산업단지인데, 공단은 이러한 산업단지 기업들이 변화하는 경영 환경에 원활히 적응할 수 있도록 지원하는 역할을 맡고 있다”라며 “이번 협약을 계기로 대학과 산업단지 간 연계가 더욱 강화되기를 기대한다”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Gyeong-su, Chairman of the Korea Industrial Complex Business Association Seoul (KIBA), conveyed, "About 60% of companies within industrial complexes are small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). While they recognize the necessity of ESG, the reality is they don't know how to implement it." He continued, "We aim to address the funding and manpower issues most needed by SMEs through ESG-based financial linkages and industry-academia linked talent cultivation," and expressed his hope that "this MOU will not remain a formality but will lead to a practical cooperation model that SMEs can actually rely on." (김경수 한국산업단지경영자연합회 서울(KIBA) 회장은 “산업단지 내 기업의 약 60%가 중소기업으로, ESG의 필요성은 공감하지만 어떻게 실행해야 할지 모르는 것이 현실”이라고 전했다. 이어 “중소기업이 가장 필요로 하는 자금과 인력 문제를 ESG 기반 금융 연계와 산학 연계 인재 양성으로 해결해 나가고자 한다”라며 “이번 MOU가 형식에 그치지 않고, 중소기업이 실제로 기댈 수 있는 실천적 협력 모델로 이어지길 기대한다”라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241304.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/533/imgdb/original/2026/0123/7317691345425705.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hanyang University ERICA Startup Education Center and Haedong Science and Culture Foundation Successfully Hold '2025 Haedong Startup DCI Results Sharing and Networking' Event (한양대 ERICA 창업교육센터-해동과학문화재단, ‘2025 해동창업 DCI 성과공유 및 네트워킹’성황리 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241305.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hanyang University ERICA Startup Education Center and Haedong Science and Culture Foundation Successfully Hold '2025 Haedong Startup DCI Results Sharing and Networking' Event (한양대 ERICA 창업교육센터-해동과학문화재단, ‘2025 해동창업 DCI 성과공유 및 네트워킹’성황리 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/525/imgdb/original/2026/0123/2017691348678451.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2025 해동창업 DCI 성과공유 및 네트워킹 사진.한양대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanyang University's ERICA Startup Education Center (Director Kim Ji-hwan) announced that it successfully held the '2025 Haedong Startup DCI Results Sharing and Networking' event on the 21st at the Haedong Boost-up Room on campus.&lt;br/&gt;This event was organized to share the entrepreneurial achievements of the second cohort of 'Haedong Startup DCI' students, who were discovered and nurtured at Hanyang University ERICA over the past year, and to strengthen networking. The event was attended by a total of 80 participants, including Haedong Science and Culture Foundation Chairman Kim Young-jae and Vice Chairman Park Seong-han, Hanyang University ERICA Vice President Baek Dong-hyun, Vice President for Industry-Academia Cooperation Lee Ki-hyung, Head of the Industry-Academia Cooperation Division Ryu Jong-seok, Startup Education Center Director Kim Ji-hwan, and other stakeholders of the Haedong Startup DCI program (hereinafter referred to as Haedong DCI).&lt;br/&gt;Haedong DCI is a customized three-stage startup support program consisting of Dreamer (startup discovery), Challenger (startup nurturing), and Innovator (startup advancement). Since 2019, the Haedong Science and Culture Foundation has donated a cumulative total of 770 million KRW to Hanyang University ERICA by 2025, providing full-fledged support for the activation of student technology startups.&lt;br/&gt;A total of 254 teams participated in the 2025 Haedong DCI second cohort, of which 36 teams were finally selected and received startup grants. These teams recorded approximately 12 billion KRW in sales during 2025, created 28 new jobs, attracted investments totaling 110 million KRW across 2 cases, secured 41 intellectual property rights, and achieved significant results including selection for numerous internal and external projects and signing MOUs.&lt;br/&gt;Lee Ki-hyung, Vice President for Industry-Academia Cooperation at Hanyang University ERICA, stated, "We will strengthen cooperation with the Haedong Science and Culture Foundation and spare no support so that student entrepreneurs can continuously grow into excellent technology entrepreneurs."&lt;br/&gt;Kim Young-jae, Chairman of the Haedong Science and Culture Foundation, expressed, "I was deeply moved to see Haedong Startup DCI establish itself as a sustainable startup platform and a cradle for future technological innovation," adding, "I will continue to support the passionate challenges of students."&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the event also featured an 'INNOVATOR Awards Ceremony' for teams that achieved outstanding results in the startup advancement stage, further enhancing the meaning of sharing achievements. (한양대학교 ERICA 창업교육센터(센터장 김지환)는 지난 21일 교내 해동부스트업룸에서 ‘2025 해동창업 DCI 성과공유 및 네트워킹’ 행사를 성황리에 개최했다고 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;이번 행사는 지난 1년간 한양대 ERICA에서 발굴·육성한 ‘해동창업 DCI’ 2기 학생들의 창업 성과를 공유하고 네트워킹을 강화하기 위해 마련됐다. 행사에는 해동과학문화재단 김영재 이사장과 박성한 부이사장, 한양대 ERICA 백동현 부총장, 이기형 산학협력부총장, 류종석 산학협력부단장, 김지환 창업교육센터장을 비롯해 해동창업 DCI 프로그램(이하 해동 DCI) 관계자 등 총 80명이 참석했다.&lt;br/&gt;해동 DCI는 Dreamer(창업 발굴), Challenger(창업 육성), Innovator(창업 고도화)로 이어지는 3단계 맞춤형 창업 지원 프로그램이다. 해동과학문화재단은 2019년부터 2025년까지 누적 7억 7천만 원을 한양대 ERICA에 기부하며 학생 기술창업 활성화를 전폭적으로 지원해오고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;2025년 해동 DCI 2기에는 총 254개 팀이 참여했으며, 이 중 36개 팀이 최종 선발돼 창업 지원금을 받았다. 해당 팀들은 2025년 한 해 동안 약 120억 원의 매출을 기록했으며, 신규 고용 28명 창출, 총 2건·1억 1천만 원 규모의 투자 유치, 41건의 지식재산권 확보, 다수의 교내외 사업 선정 및 MOU 체결 등 의미 있는 성과를 거뒀다.&lt;br/&gt;이기형 한양대 ERICA 산학협력부총장은 “학생 창업자들이 지속적으로 우수한 기술 창업가로 거듭날 수 있도록 해동과학문화재단과 협력을 강화하고 지원을 아끼지 않겠다”라고 전했다. &lt;br/&gt;김영재 해동과학문화재단 이사장은 “해동창업 DCI가 지속가능한 창업 플랫폼이자 미래 기술혁신의 산실로 자리 잡은 모습에 깊은 감동을 느꼈다”며 “앞으로도 학생들의 열정적인 도전을 응원하겠다”고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;한편, 이날 행사에서는 창업 고도화 단계에서 우수한 성과를 거둔 팀을 대상으로 ‘INNOVATOR 시상식’도 함께 진행돼 성과 공유의 의미를 더했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Hanyang University (* 자료제공 :  한양대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241305.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/525/imgdb/original/2026/0123/2017691348678451.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'From AI to Smart Mobility' Soongsil University GTEP Promotes K-Technological Prowess at CES 2026, Targeting Overseas Buyers ('AI부터 스마트 모빌리티까지' 숭실대 GTEP, CES 2026서 K-기술력 전파하며 해외 바이어 공략)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241306.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'From AI to Smart Mobility' Soongsil University GTEP Promotes K-Technological Prowess at CES 2026, Targeting Overseas Buyers ('AI부터 스마트 모빌리티까지' 숭실대 GTEP, CES 2026서 K-기술력 전파하며 해외 바이어 공략)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8917691349659969.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;(왼쪽부터) GTEP 소속 정수빈, 김윤원, 김채연, 어윤성, 이예인 학생이 세계 최대 규모의 IT·가전 전시회 ‘CES 2026’에 참가했다. (숭실대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Soongsil University's Regional Specialized Young Trade Expert Training Project Group (hereafter GTEP, Director Jo Seung-ho) announced its participation in the world's largest IT and home appliance exhibition, 'CES 2026 (Consumer Electronics Show)', held in Las Vegas, USA. (숭실대학교 지역특화청년무역전문가양성사업단(이하 GTEP, 단장 조승호)은 미국 라스베이거스에서 열린 세계 최대 IT·가전 전시회 ‘CES 2026(Consumer Electronics Show)’에 참가했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Five GTEP-affiliated students participated in this exhibition: Kim Yun-won (Business Administration, 4th year) and Kim Chae-yeon, Jeong Su-bin, Eo Yun-seong, and Lee Ye-in (all Global Commerce, 4th year). They were responsible for booth operation, buyer consultations, and product demonstrations for four partner companies: DKLAB Co., Ltd., LBS TECH Co., Ltd., Awesome Lab Co., Ltd., and Rubit Co., Ltd. (이번 전시회에는 김윤원(경영학부 4학년)과 김채연·정수빈·어윤성·이예인(이상 글로벌통상학과 4학년) 등 GTEP 소속 학생 5명이 참여해 ㈜DKLAB, ㈜LBS TECH, ㈜어썸랩, ㈜루빗 등 4개 협력기업의 부스 운영과 바이어 상담, 제품 시연을 담당했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DKLAB Co., Ltd. showcased 'Base on Board', a baseball board game incorporating digital technology. The product won the CES Innovation Award in both 2025 and 2026. Students Kim Yun-won and Jeong Su-bin explained the game's structure and core technology to visitors and conducted demonstrations at the DKLAB booth. Student Jeong Su-bin said, "I was able to directly perform technology-centered product explanations and communication at a global exhibition site, enhancing my practical capabilities." (㈜DKLAB은 디지털 기술을 접목한 야구 보드게임 ‘Base on Board’를 선보였으며, 해당 제품은 2025년에 이어 2026년에도 CES 혁신상을 수상했다. 김윤원, 정수빈 학생은 ㈜DKLAB 부스에서 방문객을 대상으로 게임의 구조와 핵심 기술을 설명하고 시연을 진행했다. 정수빈 학생은 “글로벌 전시회 현장에서 기술 중심의 제품 설명과 커뮤니케이션을 직접 수행하며 실무 역량을 키울 수 있었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LBS TECH Co., Ltd. won the CES 2026 Best of Innovation Award with its smart mobility solution 'MaaS-Bridge', based on pedestrian environment data. Student Lee Ye-in was in charge of explaining the solution's functions and use cases to overseas visitors and buyers at the booth and handling consultations. Student Lee Ye-in stated, "I was able to directly confirm the high interest of the overseas market in mobility services that consider the transportation vulnerable." (㈜LBS TECH는 보행환경 데이터 기반 스마트 모빌리티 솔루션 ‘MaaS-Bridge(마스브릿지)’로 CES 2026 최고 혁신상(Best of Innovation)을 수상했다. 이예인 학생은 해당 부스에서 해외 참관객과 바이어를 대상으로 솔루션의 기능과 활용 사례를 설명하고 상담을 맡았다. 이예인 학생은 “교통약자를 고려한 모빌리티 서비스에 대한 해외 시장의 높은 관심을 현장에서 직접 확인할 수 있었다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Awesome Lab Co., Ltd. presented an eco-friendly boiler system applying water electrolysis technology. Student Kim Chae-yeon participated in booth operation, introducing the technical features and environmental friendliness to overseas visitors and buyers. Student Kim Chae-yeon said, "It was an experience that allowed me to feel the global demand and market potential for next-generation energy technology." (㈜어썸랩은 수전해 방식을 적용한 친환경 보일러 시스템을 선보였다. 김채연 학생은 부스 운영에 참여해 해외 관람객과 바이어를 대상으로 기술 특징과 친환경성을 소개했다. 김채연 학생은 “차세대 에너지 기술에 대한 글로벌 수요와 시장 가능성을 체감할 수 있는 경험이었다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rubit Co., Ltd. unveiled 'loody', a generative AI-based real-time conversational AI companion platform. Student Eo Yun-seong was in charge of demonstrating the avatar creation and conversation functions, helping visitors understand the product. Student Eo Yun-seong said, "I could vividly feel at the site how AI technology can bring changes to everyday communication methods." (㈜루빗은 생성형 인공지능(AI) 기반 실시간 대화형 AI 동반자 플랫폼 ‘loody’를 공개했다. 어윤성 학생은 아바타 생성과 대화 기능 시연을 맡아 참관객들의 이해를 도왔다. 어윤성 학생은 “AI 기술이 일상 속 소통 방식에 어떤 변화를 가져올 수 있는지 현장에서 생생히 느낄 수 있었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the GTEP project is a trade expert training program operated by the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy and the Korea International Trade Association in collaboration with 20 universities nationwide. Soongsil University's GTEP project group is uniquely operated as the only Europe-specialized project group in the country. Alongside theoretical education, students conduct field-centered trade practices such as exhibition marketing, import-export operations, and handling overseas buyers. (한편 GTEP 사업단은 산업통상자원부와 한국무역협회가 전국 20개 대학과 함께 운영하는 무역 전문인력 양성 사업으로, 숭실대 GTEP 사업단은 전국에서 유일한 유럽지역 특화 사업단으로 운영되고 있다. 학생들은 이론 교육과 함께 전시회 마케팅, 수출입 실무, 해외 바이어 응대 등 현장 중심의 무역 실습을 수행하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241306.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8917691349659969.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sangji University Finishes as Runner-up in the 22nd 1st and 2nd Year University Football Tournament (상지대, 제22회 1‧2학년 대학축구대회 준우승)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241309.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sangji University Finishes as Runner-up in the 22nd 1st and 2nd Year University Football Tournament (상지대, 제22회 1‧2학년 대학축구대회 준우승)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/673/imgdb/original/2026/0123/5717691351424343.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;상지대, 제22회 1‧2학년 대학축구대회 준우승 (상지대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Sangji University football team finished as runner-up in the '22nd 1st and 2nd Year University Football Tournament in the Sports Hub City of Gimcheon', hosted by the Korea University Football Federation (President Park Han-dong). (상지대 축구부가 한국대학축구연맹(회장 박한동)이 주최한 ‘스포츠 중심도시 김천 제22회 1·2학년 대학축구대회’에서 준우승을 차지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sangji University concluded the tournament with a 3-4 loss to Chung-Ang University in the final held at the main stadium of Gimcheon University in North Gyeongsang Province on the 22nd. Sangji, who led 2-0 in the first half, unfortunately conceded a comeback after a close second half. (상지대는 22일 경북 김천대 대운동장에서 열린 결승전에서 중앙대와 맞붙어 3-4로 패하며 대회를 마무리했다. 전반을 2-0으로 앞선 상지대는 후반 접전 끝에 아쉽게 역전을 허용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sangji University advanced to the semifinals after defeating Yeungnam University 2-1 in the round of 16, and then beating Songho University 5-4 in a penalty shootout following a 2-2 draw in the quarterfinals. (상지대는 16강전에서 영남대를 2-1로 꺾은 데 이어, 8강전에서는 송호대와 2-2로 비긴 뒤 승부차기에서 5-4로 승리하며 준결승에 진출했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the semifinals, they secured their spot in the final by defeating Yongin University 3-1 in a penalty shootout after a 1-1 draw. Hwang Tae-hwan scored the equalizing goal at that time, and Lee Sang-min, Lee Tae-hyun, and Choi Tae-rim were successful in the penalty shootout. (4강전에서는 용인대와 1-1로 맞선 뒤 승부차기에서 3-1로 승리하며 결승을 확정했다. 당시 황태환이 동점골을 기록했으며, 승부차기에서는 이상민, 이태현, 최태림이 성공했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the final, Sangji University took the lead with No Yoon-jun's opening goal in the 2nd minute of the first half, and added another goal when No Yoon-jun finished Hwang Tae-hwan's cross in the 7th minute. Choi Tae-rim scored in the 37th minute of the second half. (결승전에서 상지대는 전반 2분 노윤준의 선제골로 앞서 나갔고, 전반 7분 황태환의 크로스를 노윤준이 마무리하며 추가골을 기록했다. 후반 37분에는 최태림이 득점에 성공했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this tournament result, Sangji University recorded its fourth overall runner-up finish, following those in 2009, 2022, and 2024. (상지대는 이번 대회에서 2009년, 2022년, 2024년에 이어 통산 네 번째 준우승을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the awards ceremony held after the tournament, player Kim Dong-geon received the Outstanding Player Award, player Hwang Tae-hwan received the Assist Award, and player No Yoon-jun received the Young Player Award. Furthermore, coach Nam Young-yeol and coach Hwang In-hyeok received the Outstanding Leader Award. (대회 종료 후 열린 시상식에서는 김동건 선수가 우수선수상을, 황태환 선수가 도움상을 수상했으며, 노윤준 선수는 영플레이어상을 받았다. 또한 남영열 감독과 황인혁 코치는 우수 지도자상을 수상했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241309.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/673/imgdb/original/2026/0123/5717691351424343.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Fluctuates Around 5,000 Mark in Early Trading on Individual Investor Buying (코스피, 개인 ‘사자’에 장 초반 5000선 오르락내리락)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241310.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSPI Fluctuates Around 5,000 Mark in Early Trading on Individual Investor Buying (코스피, 개인 ‘사자’에 장 초반 5000선 오르락내리락)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/510/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501192.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 오전 서울 중구 우리은행 딜링룸에서 딜러들이 업무를 보고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, the KOSPI recovered the 5,000 mark in early trading on individual investor buying and is now fluctuating around that level in a tug-of-war. (코스피가 23일 개인의 매수세에 장 초반 5000선을 회복한 뒤, 5000선 주변에서 엎치락뒤치락하며 공방하는 양상이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of 11:05 AM, the KOSPI was up 11.29 points (0.23%) from the previous day to 4,963.55. The index started the day at 4,984.08, up 31.55 points (0.64%) from the previous day, and extended its gains to reach an intraday high of 5,021.13. Although the KOSPI touched the 5,000 mark for the first time ever during trading the previous day before paring gains to close in the 4,950 range, it recovered the 5,000 mark again today and is now fluctuating. (이날 오전11시5분 기준 코스피는 전날보다 11.29(0.23%) 오른 4963.55다. 지수는 전날보다 31.55(0.64%) 오른 4984.08로 출발해 상승폭을 키우며 장중 5021.13까지 올랐다. 전날 코스피는 장중 사상 처음 5000선을 ‘터치’한 뒤 오름폭을 줄여 4950대에서 마감했으나, 이날 다시 5000선을 회복한 뒤 오르락내리락하는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the KOSPI market, individual investors are net buyers of 112.9 billion won, pulling the index higher. In contrast, foreign and institutional investors are showing net selling positions of 80.8 billion won and 15.2 billion won, respectively. In the KOSPI 200 futures market, foreigners are also showing a net selling position of 63.2 billion won. Overnight, the New York stock market continued its upward trend as the three major indices rose, with improved investor sentiment continuing due to President Trump's withdrawal of tariffs on Europe. The decision by the US, Ukraine, and Russia to hold their first trilateral talks for ending the war also improved stock market sentiment. (유가증권시장에서 개인이 1129억원 순매수하며 지수를 끌어 올리고 있다. 반면 외국인과 기관은 각각 808억원, 152억원 매도 우위를 보이고 있다. 외국인은 코스피200 선물시장에서도 632억원 ‘팔자’를 나타내고 있다. 간밤 뉴욕증시는 트럼프 대통령의 유럽에 대한 관세 철회로 개선된 투자심리가 이어지며 3대 지수가 상승세를 지속했다. 미국과 우크라이나, 러시아가 처음으로 종전을 위한 3자 회담을 갖기로 결정한 점도 증시 투자심리를 개선했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Han Ji-young, a researcher at Kiwoom Securities, said, "Today, the domestic stock market will see a fierce battle around the 5,000 mark," adding, "There tends to be psychological resistance at every 1,000-point interval for the index, and it is also key to watch how much Intel, which is currently plummeting in after-hours trading in the US market, will hold back domestic semiconductor stocks." (한지영 키움증권 연구원은 “오늘 국내 증시는 5000선에서 공방전이 치열할 것”이라며 “지수 1000포인트마다 심리적인 저항 구간이 발생하는 경향이 있고, 미국 장에서 현재 시간 외 거래에서 급락 중인 인텔이 국내 반도체주의 발목을 얼마나 붙잡을지도 관건”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the KOSDAQ index was up 9.81 points (1.01%) from the previous day to 980.16. (같은 시각 코스닥지수는 전날보다 9.81(1.01%) 오른 980.16이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Cho Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241310.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/510/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501192.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sookmyung Women's University's University Job Plus Center Rated 'Excellent' for 10 Consecutive Years in Performance Evaluation... The Only University in the Metropolitan Area (숙명여대, 대학일자리플러스센터 성과평가 10년 연속 '우수'… 수도권 대학 유일)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241312.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sookmyung Women's University's University Job Plus Center Rated 'Excellent' for 10 Consecutive Years in Performance Evaluation... The Only University in the Metropolitan Area (숙명여대, 대학일자리플러스센터 성과평가 10년 연속 '우수'… 수도권 대학 유일)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/927/623/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8317691356133549.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;숙명여자대학교 대학일자리플러스센터가 2025년 9월 15일(월)부터 이틀간 교내 눈꽃광장홀에서 개최한 &amp;#x27;용산-숙명 취·창업 페스타&amp;#x27; (숙명여자대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University (President Si-yeon Moon) announced that its University Job Plus Center received the highest grade of 'Excellent' in the '2025 University Youth Employment Service Performance Evaluation' conducted by the Ministry of Employment and Labor. (숙명여자대학교(총장 문시연) 대학일자리플러스센터가 고용노동부 주관 &amp;#x27;2025년 대학청년고용서비스 성과평가&amp;#x27;에서 최고 등급인 &amp;#x27;우수&amp;#x27;를 획득했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this evaluation, Sookmyung Women's University achieved the distinction of being the only university in the metropolitan area to receive an 'Excellent' rating for ten consecutive years. It also secured the incentive of having its University Job Plus Center project period extended by one more year. (이번 평가로 숙명여대는 수도권 대학 중 유일하게 10년 연속 우수 평가를 받는 성과를 거뒀다. 대학일자리플러스센터 사업 기간이 1년 더 연장되는 인센티브도 확보했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The University Job Plus Center is a project operated by the Ministry of Employment and Labor to strengthen major-specific career guidance from the lower grades and provide comprehensive employment support services through universities. (대학일자리플러스센터는 저학년부터 전공별 진로지도를 강화하고, 대학을 통해 종합적인 취업지원 서비스를 제공하기 위해 고용노동부가 운영하는 사업이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sookmyung Women's University has organically operated the 'University Job Plus Center' project and the 'Customized Employment Service for Current Students' project, providing step-by-step tailored services from career planning for lower-grade students to practical job preparation for upper-grade students. This systematic system is evaluated as having contributed to enhancing the employment competitiveness of not only its students but also local youth. (숙명여대는 &amp;#x27;대학일자리플러스센터&amp;#x27; 사업과 &amp;#x27;재학생 맞춤형 고용서비스&amp;#x27; 사업을 유기적으로 운영하며, 저학년의 진로 설계부터 고학년의 실전 취업 준비까지 단계별 맞춤 서비스를 제공해 왔다. 이같은 체계적 시스템은 재학생은 물론 지역청년들의 취업 경쟁력 제고에도 기여했다는 평가를 받고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year, in particular, the university newly secured the Ministry of Employment and Labor's 'Graduate Specialized Program', further expanding its support scope. It is leading the effort to eliminate blind spots in employment support by providing professional counseling, job training, and customized matching for unemployed graduates facing difficulties in job seeking. (특히 지난해에는 고용노동부의 &amp;#x27;졸업생 특화프로그램&amp;#x27;을 신규 수주하며 지원 범위를 더욱 확장했다. 구직에 어려움을 겪는 미취업 졸업생을 대상으로 전문 상담, 직무 교육, 맞춤형 매칭 등을 제공하며 취업지원 사각지대 해소에 앞장서고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seo-hee Son, Head of the Career Development Center at Sookmyung Women's University (Director of the University Job Plus Center), stated, "The achievement of being the only university in the metropolitan area to receive an 'Excellent' rating for ten consecutive years is proof of Sookmyung Women's University's systematic employment support capabilities," and added, "We will strengthen our role as a platform, in connection with government support projects, so that Sookmyung members and local youth can continue their career development stably throughout their entire life cycle." (손서희 숙명여대 경력개발처장(대학일자리플러스센터장)은 &amp;quot;수도권 유일 10년 연속 우수 평가라는 성과는 숙명여대의 체계적인 취업지원 역량을 입증한 결과&amp;quot;라며 &amp;quot;앞으로도 정부 지원사업과 연계해 숙명인과 지역청년들이 전 생애 주기에 걸쳐 안정적으로 경력개발을 이어갈 수 있도록 플랫폼 역할을 강화하겠다&amp;quot;고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241312.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/927/623/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8317691356133549.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sogang University Holds Donation Ceremony for Student Creative Research Center Building Fund by Chairman Choi Kwon-wook of Anda Asset Management (서강대학교, 최권욱 ㈜안다자산운용 회장학생창의연구관 건립기금 전달식 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241313.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Sogang University Holds Donation Ceremony for Student Creative Research Center Building Fund by Chairman Choi Kwon-wook of Anda Asset Management (서강대학교, 최권욱 ㈜안다자산운용 회장학생창의연구관 건립기금 전달식 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/6317691359859543.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;발전기금을 전달하는 최권욱 ㈜안다자산운용 회장 (서강대학교 제공)&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sogang University (President Shim Jong-hyeok) held a donation ceremony for the Student Creative Research Center (AI IMPACT COMPLEX) building fund by Chairman Choi Kwon-wook (German Language '79) of Anda Asset Management Co., Ltd. on Tuesday, January 20th, at 11:30 AM in the President's Office on the 2nd floor of the Main Hall. The event was attended by Chairman Choi Kwon-wook, President Shim Jong-hyeok, Vice President for External Affairs Song Tae-kyung, and Director of External Affairs Lee Sang-geun, among others, who graced the occasion. (서강대학교(총장 심종혁)은 지난 1월 20일(화) 오전 11시 30분, 본관 2층 총장실에서 최권욱(독문79) ㈜안다자산운용 회장의 학생창의연구관(AI IMPACT COMPLEX) 건립기금 전달식을 개최했다. 이날 행사에는 최권욱 회장을 비롯해 심종혁 총장, 송태경 대외부총장, 이상근 대외교류처장 등이 참석해 자리를 빛냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Choi Kwon-wook, who entered Sogang University's Department of German Language and Literature in 1979, currently serves as the Chairman of Anda Asset Management Co., Ltd. Chairman Choi has consistently demonstrated his affection for his alma mater through donations, including contributing 100 million won in September 2023 for the Student Creative Research Center (AI IMPACT COMPLEX) building fund. Furthermore, on December 22nd of last year, he made an additional donation of 200 million won for the same purpose, extending his warm generosity to foster well-rounded individuals with knowledge, virtue, and physical health and to improve the research environment for junior students. (최권욱 회장은 서강대학교 독어독문학과 79학번으로, 현재 ㈜안다자산운용의 회장으로 재직 중이다. 최 회장은 2023년 9월, 학생창의연구관(AI IMPACT COMPLEX) 건립기금으로 1억 원을 기부하는 등 모교를 향한 애정을 꾸준히 실천해왔다. 또한 지난 12월 22일에는 같은 목적의 기금으로 2억 원을 추가로 기부하며, 지덕체를 겸비한 인재 양성과 후배들의 연구 환경 개선을 위한 따뜻한 나눔을 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Choi Kwon-wook stated, "I have always hoped that future talents from my alma mater would grow to be more creative and challenging," adding, "I hope that Sogang University juniors will become talents leading the AI era in an even better environment and achieve their respective dreams." (최권욱 회장은 “모교의 미래 인재들이 더욱 창의적이고 도전적으로 성장했으면 좋겠다는 생각이 항상 있었다”라며 “서강대학교 후배들이 더욱 좋은 환경에서 AI 시대를 선도하는 인재가 되어 저마다의 꿈을 이뤄냈으면 좋겠다”라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, President Shim Jong-hyeok expressed his gratitude, saying, "I sincerely thank Chairman Choi Kwon-wook for his donation to the Student Creative Research Center building fund, following his contribution in 2023," and added, "This donation has provided great strength for future talents to fully demonstrate their capabilities in the Student Creative Research Center, which is a space for creation and entrepreneurship leading the AI era, a space to grow as leaders by nurturing social skills and character, and a healthy physical space supporting knowledge and virtue." (이에 심종혁 총장은 “지난 2023년에 이어 학생창의연구관 건립기금으로 또 한 번 기부를 해주신 최권욱 회장님께 진심으로 감사드린다”라며, “AI 시대를 이끄는 창작과 창업의 공간, 사회성과 인격을 키워 리더로 성장하는 공간, 지와 덕을 뒷받침하는 건강한 체력 공간인 학생창의연구관에서 미래 인재들이 역량을 마음껏 펼치기 위해 큰 힘이 되었다”라고 감사의 뜻을 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Sogang University's Student Creative Research Center (AI IMPACT COMPLEX) is a core infrastructure of Sogang aimed at breaking away from the existing framework of university education, accommodating changes in the times and industrial environment, and transitioning to research and inquiry-centered education, with a target opening in 2028. It is a space where Sogang's future talents can engage in research, inquiry, and practice regardless of their major, growing into leading talents who drive the rapidly changing industrial environment and well-rounded individuals with balanced knowledge, virtue, and physical health. (한편, 서강대학교 학생창의연구관(AI IMPACT COMPLEX)은 2028년 개관을 목표로 하는 기존 대학 교육의 틀에서 벗어나 시대적, 산업적 환경 변화를 수용하고 연구와 탐구 중심 교육으로 전환하기 위한 서강의 핵심 인프라이다. 서강의 미래 인재들이 전공 구분 없이 연구와 탐구, 실습을 하며 빠르게 변화하는 산업 환경을 이끌어가는 선도적 인재, 지덕체를 고루 갖춘 인재로 성장할 수 있는 공간이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an information article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241313.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/6317691359859543.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>USTR Representative Meets with Trade Minister Again After 9 Days, “Stable Management of Trade Relations” (USTR 대표 9일 만에 또 만난 통상본부장 “통상 관계 안정적 관리”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241315.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;USTR Representative Meets with Trade Minister Again After 9 Days, “Stable Management of Trade Relations” (USTR 대표 9일 만에 또 만난 통상본부장 “통상 관계 안정적 관리”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/447/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501291.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;여한구 산업통상부 통상교섭본부장이 지난 13일 워싱턴에서 제이미슨 그리어 미국무역대표부(USTR) 대표를 만나고 있다. 산업부 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy announced on the 23rd that Yeo Han-koo, the Minister for Trade, who is attending the World Economic Forum Annual Meeting in Davos, Switzerland, met with Jayme White, the Deputy United States Trade Representative (USTR), on the 22nd (local time) to discuss trade issues. (산업통상부는 스위스 다보스에서 열리는 세계경제포럼 연차총회에 참석한 여한구 통상교섭본부장이 22일(현지시각) 제이미슨 그리어 미국무역대표부(USTR) 대표를 만나 통상 현안을 논의했다고 23일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ministry stated that Minister Yeo "exchanged opinions on Korea-U.S. trade issues and agreed to maintain close communication to manage Korea-U.S. trade relations stably." Previously, Minister Yeo had visited the United States to address U.S. concerns regarding Korea's digital sector legislation and also met with Deputy USTR White on the 13th. (산업부는 여 본부장이 “한·미 간 통상 현안에 대해 의견을 교환하고, 한·미 통상 관계를 안정적으로 관리하기 위한 소통을 긴밀히 해나가기로 했다”고 전했다. 앞서 여 본부장은 한국의 디지털 분야 입법에 대한 미국 쪽 문제 제기에 대응하기 위한 목적 등으로 방미해 지난 13일에도 그리어 대표를 만난 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the ministry did not specify the detailed areas or content of the discussions, it is presumed that discussions continued on bilateral trade issues such as Korea's digital regulatory legislation. Some within the U.S. government and Congress have been protesting, arguing that the strengthened obligations under Korea's revised Network Act to regulate the distribution of "false or manipulated information" impose burdens on U.S. companies like Google and infringe on freedom of expression. It is also believed that the Korea-U.S. trade chiefs discussed the semiconductor tariff issue, recently highlighted by U.S. Commerce Secretary Gina Raimondo's warning of potential 100% tariffs if factories are not built in the U.S. (산업부는 구체적 논의 분야나 내용을 설명하지는 않았지만, 양국 통상 현안인 한국의 디지털 규제 입법 등에 대한 논의를 이어갔을 것으로 보인다. 미국 정부와 의회 일각에서는 한국의 개정 정보통망법에 따른 ‘허위조작정보’ 유통 단속 의무 강화가 구글 등 미국 기업들에 부담을 지우고 표현의 자유를 침해한다며 반발하고 있다. 한·미 통상 수장들은 최근 하워드 러트닉 상무장관이 미국에 공장을 짓지 않으면 100%를 물리겠다고 경고한 반도체 관세 문제도 논의했을 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it appears they also exchanged views on the Coupang data leak incident, which was discussed in recent meetings as well. The ministry had previously explained that during his visit to the U.S. last week, amid complaints from the U.S. Congress and others that the Korean government's investigation into Coupang was a "witch hunt," Minister Yeo clarified to Deputy USTR White and members of Congress that the investigation was being conducted by relevant Korean agencies in accordance with the law. The ministry added that Minister Yeo clearly explained that "it is inappropriate to interpret this issue as expanding into a diplomatic or trade matter between Korea and the U.S." (이와 함께 최근 면담에서도 논의한 쿠팡 정보 유출 사건을 두고도 의견을 주고받았을 것으로 보인다. 산업부는 지난주 미국 의회 등에서 쿠팡에 대한 한국 정부의 조사가 “마녀사냥”이라는 불만을 표출하는 가운데 방미한 여 본부장이 한국의 관련 기관이 법령에 따라 진행하는 조사라는 점을 그리어 대표와 의원들에게 설명했다고 밝힌 바 있다. 산업부는 여 본부장이 이 문제를 두고 “한·미 간 외교·통상 현안으로 확대해석하는 것은 부적절하다는 점을 명확히 설명했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Coupang incident is emerging as a potential intergovernmental issue, as U.S. investment firms Greenoaks and Altimeter submitted a petition to the USTR claiming losses due to excessive investigations by the Korean government and sent a notice of intent to initiate international investment dispute arbitration to the Korean government. The USTR must decide within 45 days whether to initiate an investigation into the petition from the two investment firms, which invested in Coupang and claim losses due to the Korean government's investigation, requesting responses such as imposing tariffs or restricting Korean services in the U.S. (하지만 미국 투자회사 그린옥스와 알티미터가 한국 정부의 과도한 조사로 손해를 입었다며 미국무역대표부에 청원을 제출하고 한국 정부에는 국제투자분쟁 중재 착수 의향서를 보내면서 쿠팡 사건은 정부 간 문제로 비화할 가능성도 떠오르고 있다. 미국무역대표부는 쿠팡에 투자했다가 한국 정부의 조사 탓에 손해를 봤다고 주장하는 두 투자회사가 관세 부과나 한국 쪽의 미국 내 서비스 제한 등으로 대응해달라고 청원한 건에 대해 45일 안에 조사 개시 여부를 결정해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By Lee Bon-young, Reporter &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이본영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:ebon@hani.co.kr"&gt;ebon@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241315.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/701/447/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501291.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Heavy Capital Gains Tax on Multiple Homeowners to Start from May 10th... Without Strengthening Holding Taxes, Risk of 'Property Lock-up' (다주택 양도세 중과 5월10일부터…보유세 강화 않으면 ‘매물 잠금’ 가능성)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241318.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Heavy Capital Gains Tax on Multiple Homeowners to Start from May 10th... Without Strengthening Holding Taxes, Risk of 'Property Lock-up' (다주택 양도세 중과 5월10일부터…보유세 강화 않으면 ‘매물 잠금’ 가능성)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/562/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3217691413140511.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 21일 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년기자회견에서 취재진 질문에 답하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung has ruled out the possibility of extending the 'suspension of the heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners', which is set to end this May. This marks the President himself putting an end to the market's mixed outlook regarding whether the suspension of the heavy capital gains tax would be extended. With the implementation of the heavy tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners approaching, market attention is focused on how many 'tax-saving properties' from multiple homeowners will be released into the market. (이재명 대통령이 오는 5월 종료되는 ‘다주택자 양도소득세 중과 유예’의 연장 가능성을 일축했다. 그동안 양도세 중과 유예 연장 여부를 둘러싼 시장의 엇갈린 전망에 이 대통령이 직접 종지부를 찍은 것이다. 다주택자 양도세 중과 시행을 앞두고 다주택자들의 ‘절세 매물’이 시장에 얼마나 풀릴지를 두고 시장의 관심이 쏠리고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, President Lee stated on X (formerly Twitter) regarding the suspension of the heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners, which is set to automatically end on May 9th, that "we are not considering an extension at all." The 'heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners', first introduced by the Moon Jae-in administration in 2021, refers to the heavy tax rate applied to multiple homeowners in adjustment target areas. The Yoon Suk Yeol administration, upon its launch in May 2022, has suspended it for one year each time, so it has never actually been implemented. (이 대통령은 23일 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 오는 5월9일 자동 종료를 앞둔 다주택자 양도소득세 중과 유예에 대해 “연장을 전혀 고려하지 않고 있다”고 밝혔다. 2021년 문재인 정부에서 처음 도입된 ‘다주택자 양도세 중과’는 조정대상지역 다주택자에게 적용되는 중과세율을 말한다. 윤석열 정부는 2022년 5월 출범과 동시에 이를 해마다 1년씩 유예해 실제로 시행된 적은 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's latest statement is interpreted as a signal to 'dispose of owned multiple homes before May 9th this year.' This is because, following the previous October 15th measures, all of Seoul and 12 areas in Gyeonggi were designated as adjustment target areas, meaning multiple homeowners in regulated areas must sell their owned properties before May 9th to avoid the heavy capital gains tax. If the suspension of the heavy capital gains tax ends starting May 10th, an additional tax rate of 20 percentage points for two-homeowners and 30 percentage points for three or more homeowners will be applied on top of the basic capital gains tax rate (6-45%). The long-term holding special deduction will also be unavailable. (이 대통령의 이번 발언은 ‘올해 5월9일 전에 보유 다주택을 정리하라’는 신호로 해석된다. 앞선 10·15 대책으로 서울 전역과 경기 12개 지역이 조정대상지역으로 묶이면서 규제지역 다주택자들은 5월9일 이전에 보유 매물을 팔아야만 양도세 중과를 피할 수 있기 때문이다. 당장 5월10일부터 양도세 중과 유예가 종료되면 양도세 기본세율(6∼45%)에 2주택자는 20%포인트, 3주택자 이상은 30%포인트의 가산세율이 붙게 된다. 장기보유특별공제도 받을 수 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the market is skeptical about whether the heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners will actually lead to a release of multiple-home properties. While there may be a short-term increase in some properties, analysis suggests that in the long term, a significant number of multiple homeowners will choose to hold out or transfer via gift, potentially causing a 'property lock-up' phenomenon instead. Woo Byung-tak, a senior expert at Shinhan Premier Passfinder, said, "If the policy goal is price stabilization through property release, the market needs to be given confidence that the heavy capital gains tax will continue," adding, "Currently, the heavy capital gains tax is stipulated by enforcement decree; at the very least, action such as upgrading it to law is necessary." (다만, 실제로 다주택자 양도세 중과로 다주택 매물이 풀릴 수 있을지에 대해 시장은 회의적 시선을 보내고 있다. 단기적으로 일부 매물 증가가 나타날 순 있어도, 장기적으로는 상당수 다주택자가 버티기나 증여를 선택해 도리어 ‘매물 잠금’ 현상을 부를 것이란 분석이다. 우병탁 신한프리미어 패스파인더 전문위원은 “매물 출회를 통한 가격 안정화가 정책 목표라면 양도세 중과가 계속 이어질 것이라는 확신을 시장에 줘야 한다”며 “현재 양도세 중과는 시행령으로 정하고 있는데 적어도 이를 법률로 상향시키는 정도의 액션은 필요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tight timeframe is also a problem. Park Won-gap, Chief Real Estate Expert at KB Kookmin Bank, said, "All adjustment target areas are also designated as land transaction permit zones, and the permit process alone takes two weeks, with the Lunar New Year holiday in February," adding, "Considering that a transaction typically takes 2-3 months, the timing is tight." Moreover, in land transaction permit zones, a two-year actual residence obligation arises when buying and selling a home, making it difficult to complete transactions themselves. (촉박한 시간도 문제다. 박원갑 케이비(KB)국민은행 부동산수석전문위원은 “조정대상지역이 모두 토지거래허가구역으로 함께 묶여 있는데, 허가 절차에만 2주가 들고 2월에는 설 연휴도 있다”며 “보통 거래에 2∼3개월이 소요되는 점을 감안하면 시기적으로 촉박한 상황”이라고 말했다. 더구나 토지거래허가구역에서는 주택을 매매할 때 2년 실거주 의무가 발생하기 때문에, 거래 성사 자체도 쉽지 않다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Experts point out that to prevent property lock-up, the burden of holding taxes must also be increased following the heavy capital gains tax. This is because the capital gains tax is only levied when a home is sold, so it has limitations in drawing out properties. Chae Sang-wook, CEO of Connected Ground, said, "If transaction costs are increased while holding costs are not, properties will inevitably be locked up," adding, "In addition to increasing the transfer burden for multiple homeowners, the burden of holding homes must also be increased by strengthening holding taxes for multiple-home properties to come onto the market." (전문가들은 양도세 중과에 이어 보유세 부담을 함께 늘려야만 매물 잠금을 막을 수 있다고 지적한다. 양도세는 주택을 팔지 않으면 물지 않는 세금이기 때문에 매물을 끌어내는 데에는 한계가 있는 탓이다. 채상욱 커넥티드그라운드 대표는 “거래 비용을 늘리면서 보유 비용을 늘리지 않는다면 매물은 잠길 수밖에 없다”며 “다주택자들의 양도 부담을 늘리는 것에 더해 보유세 강화로 주택 보유 부담을 함께 늘려야 다주택자 매물이 시장에 나올 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Ji-hye &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이지혜 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:godot@hani.co.kr"&gt;godot@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241318.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/562/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3217691413140511.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon, Suspected of False Subscription by 'Feigning Unmarried Status' for Eldest Son, Says "Determined It Was Difficult to Maintain the Marriage" (이혜훈, 장남 ‘위장 미혼’ 부정청약 의혹에 “혼인 유지 어렵다 판단”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241321.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, Suspected of False Subscription by 'Feigning Unmarried Status' for Eldest Son, Says "Determined It Was Difficult to Maintain the Marriage" (이혜훈, 장남 ‘위장 미혼’ 부정청약 의혹에 “혼인 유지 어렵다 판단”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3517691427541932.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 의원 질의에 답하며 물을 마시고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the suspicion that Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, falsely increased the number of dependents by pretending her married eldest son was unmarried and then won a subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Banpo-dong, Seoul, she stated, "After my eldest son's marriage, the relationship broke down, and we determined it was difficult to maintain the marital union." This implies that they did not register the marriage due to a marital crisis immediately after the wedding ceremony. When asked about her intention to return the apartment, the nominee said, "I will follow the results of the investigation." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 혼인한 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 부양가족 수를 늘린 뒤 서울 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹에 대해 “장남이 결혼 이후 관계가 깨져 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단했다”고 말했다. 결혼식 직후 파경 위기를 겪어 혼인신고를 하지 않았다는 취지다. 이 후보자는 해당 아파트를 반환할 의향을 묻는 말에는 “수사 결과에 따르겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee personnel hearing on the 23rd, the nominee began addressing the 'false subscription' suspicion by saying, "At the time, my eldest son had no choice but to continue living with us." She explained, "In December 2023, my eldest son prepared a newlywed home, but problems arose immediately after the wedding ceremony," adding, "The relationship between the two had broken down and reached its worst point. At the time, we determined it was difficult to maintain the marital union." She further stated, "In truth, I earnestly hoped I wouldn't have to discuss this publicly, but given how things have unfolded, it seems I have no choice but to share our family's story." (이 후보자는 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회 인사청문회에 출석해 ‘부정 청약’ 의혹에 대해 “당시 장남은 저희와 함께 계속 있을 수밖에 없는 상황이었다”고 운을 뗐다. 그는 “2023년 12월 장남은 신혼집을 마련했지만, 혼례를 올리고 곧바로 문제가 생겼다”며 “두 사람의 관계가 깨어진 상황으로, 최악으로 치달았다. 당시에는 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단했다”고 말했다. 이어 “사실은 제가 이런 이야기를 공개적으로 하게 되지 않기를 간절히 바랐는데, 일이 이렇게 된 이상 저희 가족 이야기를 할 수밖에 없는 상황인 것 같다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked by Representative Jin Sung-joon of the Democratic Party of Korea, "Did the relationship between your eldest son and his wife recover after a year and a half?" the nominee effectively acknowledged it by responding, "Both they themselves and many people made efforts." (이 후보자는 “장남 부부 사이가 1년 반 만에 다시 회복된 것인가”라는 진성준 더불어민주당 의원의 물음에 “(장남 부부)본인들도, 많은 사람들도 노력했다”며 사실상 인정하는 취지로 답했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Representative Jin also asked, "Are you willing to give up the (relevant) home?" the nominee replied, "I will follow the results of the investigative authorities." Representative Jin pointed out, "According to subscription rules, only unmarried children are recognized as dependents, but in fact, they had a wedding ceremony. Even if they were in discord, the subscription was applied for by taking advantage of the fact that the son's family registration was still under the nominee's household," adding, "I believe it is clearly illegal and the home should be given up." (이 후보자는 또한 진 의원이 “(해당)집을 내놓을 용의가 있는가”라고 묻자 “수사기관의 결과에 따라 따르겠다”고 답했다. 진 의원은 “청약 규칙상 미혼인 자녀만 부양가족으로 인정되는데, 사실상 혼인을 올렸다. 불화 상태라고 해도 (장남의) 주민등록이 여전히 후보자 집안으로 돼 있는 것을 이용해서 청약을 신청한 것”이라며 “명백하게 불법으로 집을 내놓아야 한다고 생각한다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yun-ju &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241321.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3517691427541932.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon: "With Four Consecutive Quarters of 0% Growth, Proactive Fiscal Policy is Needed Now... It's Different from the Past" (이혜훈 “4분기 연속 0%대 성장, 지금은 적극적 재정 필요…과거와 달라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241322.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon: "With Four Consecutive Quarters of 0% Growth, Proactive Fiscal Policy is Needed Now... It's Different from the Past" (이혜훈 “4분기 연속 0%대 성장, 지금은 적극적 재정 필요…과거와 달라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691389069067_20260123501380.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 재정경제기획위원회의 인사청문회에서 의원 질의에 답하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, stated on the 23rd, "In a situation where we are experiencing four consecutive quarters of 0% growth, proactive fiscal policy is more necessary than anything else." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 “4분기 연속으로 0%대 성장을 하고 있는 상황에서는 적극적 재정이 무엇보다 필요하다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee gave this response at a confirmation hearing held by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee when asked about her stance on current fiscal policy, adding that "prices are also stable in the 2% range." (이 후보자는 이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회 인사청문회에서 현재 재정정책에 대한 입장을 묻는 말에 “물가도 2%대로 안정적”이라며 이처럼 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding lawmakers' comments that she 'positively evaluated sound fiscal policy during the Yoon Suk Yeol administration,' she explained, "My stance on fiscal policy is no different now than it was then," adding, "The criteria for deciding between expansion or austerity must comprehensively consider economic variables such as economic conditions, fiscal balance, monetary policy, and prices." She continued, "During the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, the growth rate was enjoying the 2% range, but instead, prices were very high at 5.1%. In that situation, austerity was appropriate." (그는 ‘윤석열 정부 당시 건전 재정에 대해 긍정적으로 평가했다’는 의원들 지적에 대해서는 “재정정책에 대한 입장은 그때나 지금이나 다름이 없다”며 “확장이냐 긴축이냐 결정하는 기준은 경제 여건과 재정수지, 통화정책, 물가 등 경제 변수를 종합 고려해야 하기 때문”이라고 설명했다. 이어 “윤석열 정부 때에는 성장률이 2%대를 구가하고 있었고 대신 물가는 5.1%로 굉장히 높았다. 그런 상황에서는 긴축이 적절했다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She reiterated, "What has changed is the economic situation, not my principles." This emphasis on the changed economic situation addresses criticism that the nominee, known as a fiscal conservative who had not previously advocated for proactive fiscal policy, may have shifted her stance upon being nominated as a minister in the new government. (그는 “경제 상황이 그때와 지금 달라진 것이지 저의 원칙이 달라진 것은 아니다”라고 거듭 말했다. 재정 보수론자로 그동안 적극적 재정을 옹호하지 않던 이 후보자가 새 정부 장관 후보자로 지명되자 입장을 선회한 것이 아니냐는 지적에 대해 경제 상황 변화를 강조한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241322.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0123/53_17691389069067_20260123501380.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Homeplus to Close Jamsil and Incheon Sungui Stores... Will KDB Step in with Loans? (홈플러스, 잠실·인천숭의점도 영업종료…산은, 대출 나설까)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241343.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Homeplus to Close Jamsil and Incheon Sungui Stores... Will KDB Step in with Loans? (홈플러스, 잠실·인천숭의점도 영업종료…산은, 대출 나설까)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501764.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울시내 한 홈플러스 매장. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus, which is undergoing corporate rehabilitation procedures and has been sequentially deciding to close stores, has decided to also end operations at its Jamsil store in Seoul and its Incheon Sungui store. As a consensus has formed that government-level cooperation is necessary to resolve the Homeplus situation, attention is focused on whether the Korea Development Bank (KDB) will accept the emergency operating funds (DIP loan) requested by Homeplus. (기업회생 절차를 밟으며 순차적으로 지점 영업종료를 결정하고 있는 홈플러스가 서울 잠실점·인천숭의점 영업도 종료하기로 했다. 홈플러스 사태 해결을 위해 정부 차원의 협력이 필요하다는 공감대가 형성된 가운데, 홈플러스가 요청한 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출을 한국산업은행이 수용할지에 관심이 쏠린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Homeplus official said on the 23rd, "We have decided to close the Jamsil and Incheon Sungui stores due to the expiration of their contract periods. These two stores have been chronically unprofitable, and we expect improvements in cash flow and business viability from their closure." The specific closure schedule has not been decided. (홈플러스 관계자는 23일 “계약 기간 만료로 잠실점·인천숭의점 영업을 종료하기로 했다. 두 곳은 장기적자 점포여서 영업종료에 따른 현금흐름과 사업성 개선을 기대하고 있다”고 말했다. 구체적인 종료 일정은 결정되지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From last month until recently, Homeplus has decided to close a total of 17 stores. These include stores in Gyesan, Siheung, Ansan Gojan, Cheonan Sinbang, Dongchon, Gayang, Jangnim, Ilsan, Woncheon, Ulsan Buk-gu, Munhwa, Busan Gamman, Ulsan Nam-gu, Jeonju Wansan, Hwaseong Dongtan, Cheonan, and Jochiwon. With the inclusion of the Jamsil and Incheon Sungui stores this time, the number of stores confirmed for closure has increased to 19. (홈플러스는 지난달부터 최근까지 모두 17개 점포의 영업종료를 결정했다. 계산·시흥·안산고잔·천안신방·동촌·가양·장림·일산·원천·울산북구·문화점·부산감만점·울산남구점·전주완산점·화성동탄점·천안점·조치원점 등이다. 이번에 잠실점·인천숭의점이 포함되면서 영업종료가 확정된 점포는 모두 19곳으로 늘어났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus, which was unable to pay its employees' January salaries due to financial difficulties, stated on the 22nd that "emergency operating funds (DIP loan) are necessary for business normalization." Homeplus has requested an emergency operating funds (DIP) loan of 100 billion won each from its major shareholder MBK Partners, its largest creditor Meritz Financial Group, and the policy financial institution KDB. Currently, only MBK Partners has indicated it will respond to this request, while Meritz Securities and KDB have not stated their positions. (자금난으로 임직원의 1월 급여를 지급하지 못한 홈플러스 쪽은 “경영 정상화를 위해 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출이 필요하다”는 입장을 지난 22일 밝힌 바 있다. 홈플러스는 주주사인 엠비케이(MBK)파트너스와 최대 채권자인 메리츠금융그룹, 정책금융기관인 산업은행에 각 1천억원씩 부담하는 긴급운영자금(DIP) 대출을 요청한 상태다. 현재 엠비케이파트너스만 이런 요청에 응하겠다는 뜻을 밝혔고, 메리츠증권과 산업은행은 입장을 밝히지 않고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Homeplus CEO Jo Joo-yeon appealed at an emergency forum on Homeplus held at the National Assembly on the 21st, saying, "Please allow us to operate stably until we can prevent the imminent payment default situation and the effects of the rehabilitation plan become visible," and added, "As Homeplus is in a difficult situation, we have no choice but to plead with Meritz Securities, which represents the creditors, and the policy financial institution KDB to participate (in the emergency operating funds loan), and we ask for your understanding." (조주연 홈플러스 대표는 지난 21일 국회에서 열린 홈플러스 긴급 좌담회에서 “눈앞에 닥친 지급 불능 사태를 막고 회생안 효과가 가시화될 때까지 안정적으로 운영할 수 있게 해달라”며 “어려운 상황인 홈플러스로서는 채권자들의 대표 격인 메리츠증권과 정책금융기관인 산업은행에 (긴급운영자금 대출에) 참가해 주실 것을 간청드릴 수밖에 없는 점 양해를 부탁드린다”고 호소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241343.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/460/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123501764.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cyber University of Foreign Studies Holds "5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program" (사이버한국외국어대학교, “제5회 사이버한국외대-니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램” 진행)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241351.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies Holds "5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program" (사이버한국외국어대학교, “제5회 사이버한국외대-니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램” 진행)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/394/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691479093591.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;사이버한국외국어대학교 전경.사이버한국외대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cyber University of Foreign Studies (Acting President Kim Byeong-cheol) held the '5th CUFS-Niigata Prefectural University Online Exchange Program' with Japan's Niigata Prefectural University on Saturday, January 17th.&lt;br/&gt;This exchange program between CUFS and Niigata Prefectural University is the fifth event in the Korea-Japan online exchange that began in 2022, operated in a format where students from both universities meet online and communicate in Korean. This program saw participation from 15 CUFS undergraduate and graduate students and 22 students majoring in Korean language in the Faculty of International and Regional Studies at Niigata Prefectural University. CUFS students completed pre-program training before participating, finishing their preparations with anticipation and excitement. During the actual program, they actively exchanged opinions on daily life, interests, careers, and more using Korean as the medium.&lt;br/&gt;CUFS participating students, who broadened their mutual understanding even through a non-face-to-face environment, unanimously shared their impressions, stating, "Despite the online setting, conversations filled with laughter and empathy continued," and "We experienced that the exchange with Niigata Prefectural University students was built on focus and sincerity towards each other, more than physical distance." Niigata Prefectural University also highly praised the educational outcomes of the exchange program. Professor Kim Sae-rang of Niigata Prefectural University said, "It was a time, as a Korean language educator, that I felt great reward, confirming students actively communicating in Korean without fear of 'making mistakes' and building confidence in language learning."&lt;br/&gt;Regarding this, Professor Park Ki-seon of the CUFS Korean Language Department, who conducted the program, added, "It became an opportunity for students learning Korean and prospective teachers wanting to teach Korean to communicate freely, understand each other's cultures, and advance towards their respective goals," and "I hope the cooperation between the two universities continues to expand such exchange programs." CUFS plans to continue striving for the international spread of Korean language education and providing learner-centered, practical educational experiences through various exchange programs with overseas universities.&lt;br/&gt;The CUFS Korean Language Department aims to be a 'Hub for Global Korean Language Education,' cultivating Korean language and Korean culture professionals equipped with both theory and practice. Based on differentiated Korean language education know-how, it operates a 'Korean Language Education' major for training Korean language teachers who teach Korean as a foreign language and Korean culture, and a 'Korean Language' major where foreign learners can systematically learn Korean language and Korean culture.&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, Cyber University of Foreign Studies is recruiting new and transfer students for the first semester of the 2026 academic year from Wednesday, January 28th to Thursday, February 12th. It selects students across 10 departments: ▲English Department ▲Chinese Department ▲Japanese Department ▲Korean Language Department ▲Spanish Department ▲Vietnamese &amp; Indonesian Department ▲Business Administration Department ▲Industrial Safety &amp; Housing Management Department ▲Counseling Psychology Department ▲K-Beauty Department. Anyone with a high school diploma or higher qualification can apply. Detailed information can be found on the university's Admissions Support Center website (go.cufs.ac.kr), and individual admissions counseling is also available via phone (02-2173-2580), KakaoTalk (cufs), or email (ipsi@cufs.ac.kr). (사이버한국외국어대학교(총장직무대행 김병철)는 1월 17일(토) 일본 니가타현립대학과 함께 ‘제5회 사이버한국외대–니가타현립대학 온라인 교류 프로그램’을 진행했다.&lt;br/&gt;사이버한국외국어대학교와 니가타현립대학의 교류 프로그램은 2022년 시작된 한‧일 온라인 교류의 다섯 번째 행사로, 양교 학생들이 온라인으로 만나 한국어로 소통하는 방식으로 운영됐다. 이번 프로그램에는 사이버한국외대 학부 및 대학원생 15명과 니가타현립대학 국제지역학부 한국어전공 재학생 22명이 참가했다. 사이버한국외대 학생들은 프로그램 참여에 앞서 사전 교육을 이수하여 기대와 설렘을 가지고 교류 준비를 마쳤으며, 실제 프로그램에서는 한국어를 매개로 일상과 관심사, 진로 등에 대해 활발한 의견을 나눴다. &lt;br/&gt;비대면 환경을 통해서도 상호에 대한 이해를 넓혔다는 사이버한국외대의 참가 학생들은 “온라인이라는 환경에도 불구하고 웃음과 공감이 오가는 대화가 이어졌다”며 “니가타현립대학 학생들과의 교류는 물리적 거리보다 서로를 향한 집중과 진심으로 이어진다는 것을 경험할 수 있었다”고 입을 모아 소감을 전했다. 니가타현립대학 측에서도 교류 프로그램의 교육적 성과를 높이 평가했다. 니가타현립대학 김세랑 교수는 “학생들이 ‘틀림’을 두려워하지 않고 적극적으로 한국어로 소통하며 언어 학습에 대한 자신감을 키우는 모습을 확인한, 한국어 교육자로서 큰 보람을 느끼는 시간”이었다고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;이에 프로그램을 진행한 사이버한국외국어대학교 한국어학부 박기선 교수는 “한국어를 배우는 학생들과, 한국어를 가르치고자 하는 예비 교원들이 자유롭게 소통하며 서로의 문화를 이해하고 각자의 목표를 향해 나아가는 계기가 됐다”며 “이러한 교류 프로그램의 확대를 위해 양교의 협력이 지속되기를 바란다”고 덧붙였다. 사이버한국외대는 앞으로도 해외 대학과의 다양한 교류 프로그램을 통해 한국어 교육의 국제적 확산과 학습자 중심의 실질적인 교육 경험 제공에 힘쓸 계획이다.&lt;br/&gt;사이버한국외대 한국어학부는 ‘세계 한국어교육의 허브’를 목표로 이론과 실제를 겸비한 한국어와 한국 문화 전문 인력을 양성하고 있다. 차별화된 한국어교육 노하우를 바탕으로 외국어로서의 한국어와 한국 문화를 가르치는 한국어 교원을 양성하는 ‘한국어교육’ 전공과, 외국인 학습자가 체계적으로 한국어와 한국 문화를 배울 수 있는 ‘한국어’ 전공을 운영한다.&lt;br/&gt;한편 사이버한국외국어대학교는 1월 28일(수)부터 2월 12일(목)까지 2026학년도 1학기 신·편입생을 모집한다. ▲영어학부 ▲중국어학부 ▲일본어학부 ▲한국어학부 ▲스페인어학부 ▲베트남·인도네시아학부 ▲경영학부 ▲산업안전·주택관리학부 ▲상담심리학부 ▲K뷰티학부 등 10개 학부에서 학생을 선발하며, 고등학교 졸업 이상 학력의 소유자라면 누구나 지원할 수 있다. 자세한 내용은 대학 입학지원센터(go.cufs.ac.kr)에서 확인하면 되며, 전화(02-2173-2580)나 카카오톡(cufs), 이메일(ipsi@cufs.ac.kr)을 통해 개별 입학 상담도 가능하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Cyber University of Foreign Studies (* 자료제공 :  사이버한국외국어대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241351.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/394/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691479093591.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul National University of Science and Technology's University Job Plus Center Receives Top 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Ministry of Employment and Labor Evaluation (서울과학기술대학교 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 고용노동부 평가 최고 등급‘우수’획득)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241353.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Seoul National University of Science and Technology's University Job Plus Center Receives Top 'Excellent' Grade in 2025 Ministry of Employment and Labor Evaluation (서울과학기술대학교 대학일자리플러스센터, 2025년 고용노동부 평가 최고 등급‘우수’획득)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/311/232/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3917691482555027.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대학일자리플러스센터 홍보포스터 전경.서울과기대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;□ The University Job Plus Center at Seoul National University of Science and Technology (President Kim Dong-hwan, hereinafter referred to as SeoulTech) has received the highest grade of 'Excellent' in the 2025 University Job Plus Center project performance evaluation conducted by the Ministry of Employment and Labor and the Korea Employment Information Service. &lt;br/&gt;□ SeoulTech has been operating the University Job Plus Center project since 2021, marking its fifth year this year. It is currently running both the University Job Plus Center (hub-type) and the Customized Employment Service Project for enrolled students. Through these, it operates career counseling, employment support programs, and recruitment connection services for enrolled students, graduates, and local youth.&lt;br/&gt;□ Kim Byeong-il, Head of the SeoulTech Employment and Career Headquarters (Director of the University Job Plus Center), stated, "Starting from this achievement of the 'Excellent' grade, we will actively expand career and employment support services tailored to industrial changes and youth demands to help students fully utilize their capabilities in society." (□ 서울과학기술대학교(총장 김동환, 이하 서울과기대) 대학일자리플러스센터는 고용노동부와 한국고용정보원이 주관한 2025년 대학일자리플러스센터 사업 성과 평가에서 최고 등급인‘우수’를 획득했다. &lt;br/&gt;□ 서울과기대는 2021년부터 대학일자리플러스센터 사업을 시작해 올해로 5년째 사업을 운영중이며, 현재 대학일자리플러스센터(거점형)와 재학생 맞춤형 고용서비스 사업을 함께 수행하고 있다. 이를 통해 재학생·졸업생·지역 청년을 대상으로 진로상담, 취업지원 프로그램, 채용 연계 서비스 등을 운영하고 있다.&lt;br/&gt;□ 김병일 서울과기대 취업진로본부장(대학일자리플러스센터장)은“이번‘우수’등급 획득을 기점으로“앞으로도 산업 변화와 청년 수요에 맞춘 진로·취업지원서비스를 확대해 학생들이 자신의 역량을 사회에서 충분히 발휘할 수 있도록 적극 지원하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul National University of Science and Technology (* 자료제공 :  서울과학기술대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241353.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/311/232/imgdb/original/2026/0123/3917691482555027.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul Women's University Holds AX Vision Declaration Ceremony, Aiming to Become a "University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People" (서울여대, “사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학으로…” AX 비전 선포식 개최)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241354.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Seoul Women's University Holds AX Vision Declaration Ceremony, Aiming to Become a "University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People" (서울여대, “사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학으로…” AX 비전 선포식 개최)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8417691486855201.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;서울여대 AX 비전 선포 퍼모먼스 참여자(왼쪽부터) 서울여대 김경원 대학원장, 염지원 총학생회 비상대책위원장, 이윤선 총장, 학교법인 정의학원 김경진 이사장, 이귀운 총동문회장, 박남춘 기획처장, 조현미 노동조합 지부장).서울여대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seoul Women's University (President Lee Yun-sun) has declared its 'AX (AI Transformation) Vision,' redefining the university's fundamental role and educational values in the face of the AI era, and has embarked on full-fledged steps to leap forward as a center for future education.&lt;br/&gt;On Thursday, January 22nd, at 1:30 PM, Seoul Women's University held the 'Seoul Women's University AX Vision Declaration Ceremony' at the International Conference Hall of the 50th Anniversary Memorial Building, with about 200 attendees including key guests, faculty, and students filling the venue. This event was prepared to publicly announce Seoul Women's University's unique AX educational vision, which proactively responds to the innovation and changes created by the AI era to enhance educational quality and strengthen unwavering human dignity even in the technological age.&lt;br/&gt;■ 'A University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People'... Embodying a Human-Centered Technology Philosophy&lt;br/&gt;On this day, Seoul Women's University announced its AX vision with the slogans 'AI to Learn, Human to Share (AI that aids human growth, Humans that connect communities)' and 'A University Leading Social Innovation with Technology for People,' containing the aspirations of a new AX-leading university.&lt;br/&gt;President Lee Yun-sun, who presented the vision declaration, stated, 'The faster technology develops, the more universities must question whether the direction of development is correct,' emphasizing that in the AI era, Seoul Women's University's language is about speaking of people, direction, and responsibility amidst an age of speed and efficiency. Introducing the university's educational philosophy that has always placed the value of 'us' at the center as much as the value of 'me,' she declared, "Based on the philosophy that AI is not a tool to replace humans but a technology to aid human growth, and that humans are not beings who possess that growth alone but beings who share it with the community, we will establish education for the AI era."&lt;br/&gt;The AX vision presented by Seoul Women's University is planned to operate centered on seven major principles: ▲Human Values First ▲Social Innovation Orientation ▲Participation and Experience Focus ▲Convergence and Collaborative Education ▲Strengthening Women's Leadership and Inclusivity ▲Research•Education•Administration Linkage ▲AI Education Based on Global Cooperation.&lt;br/&gt;■ 'AI to Learn, Human to Share' Specific AX Promotion Strategy and University Innovation Roadmap Revealed&lt;br/&gt;Following this, Planning Director Park Nam-chun announced the specific 'AX Promotion Strategy.' Seoul Women's University announced its specific strategies and roadmap, including: advancing a data-based personalized learning support system; establishing a President-direct AX control tower; innovating the academic structure to lead AI convergence education; data-centric intelligent administrative innovation; building an AI convergence curriculum and hyper-connected liberal arts convergence AX system that transcends major boundaries; establishing a Future Advanced Research Institute for human-centered AI education; and AX education for instructors. Director Park expressed the aspiration, "Seoul Women's University will carry out innovation across all areas, from internal administrative systems to teaching methods, to set a new standard for universities in the AI era."&lt;br/&gt;■ Keynote Speech by President Yum Jae-ho of Taejae University ... "A University Where Humans and AI Coexist, the Power to Question is Key"&lt;br/&gt;In the second part of the event, a conference sharing insights from AI and education experts continued. President Yum Jae-ho of Taejae University gave a keynote speech on the theme.&lt;br/&gt;President Yum stated, "In an era where AI takes over the role of delivering knowledge, universities must become spaces that cultivate students' 'ability to question' and 'the work of joyfully mastering skills,'" and evaluated that the human-centered AX vision declared by Seoul Women's University will be an important answer for the future university model.&lt;br/&gt;■ In-Depth Discussion with AI Experts from Academia and Industry&lt;br/&gt;In the roundtable that proceeded as the final session, moderated by Seoul Women's University's Industry-Academic Research Director Han Won-sik, participants including Professor Hong Helen of the Software Convergence Department, Director Kim Myung-joo of the AI Safety Research Institute (Professor, School of Intelligent Information Security), and Director Kim Ji-seop of Lutein Technologies exchanged opinions on strategies for how the AX vision presented by Seoul Women's University can be implemented in actual education and research fields, and on the values universities must uphold amidst rapid technological advancement. Director Kim Myung-joo noted, "Coincidentally, it is the first day the 'Framework Act on Artificial Intelligence' takes effect in Korea, the world's first, making it even more meaningful to discuss human-centered AX. While AX is an inevitable global trend, it has a dual nature. Therefore, at universities nurturing the next generation of talent, efforts to actively respond to the shadowy side of AX and cultivate it into human-centered, sustainable technology are absolutely necessary," urging Seoul Women's University's leading role.&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the event featured congratulatory speeches from Chairman Kim Kyung-jin of the Jeongui Academy School Foundation, National Assembly Speaker Woo Won-shik, Nowon District Mayor Oh Seung-rok, Seoul Metropolitan Council Members Oh Geum-ran and Seo Jun-oh, CEO Lee Yong-kwan of Bluepoint, and President Yoon Do-young of Kwangwoon University. A large number of local university presidents, government and political figures, and industry and academia representatives attended to celebrate Seoul Women's University's new vision. Starting from this vision declaration, Seoul Women's University plans to play a pivotal role in presenting the direction for a human-centered AI era and continue the university's growth. (서울여자대학교(총장 이윤선)가 AI 시대를 직면한 대학의 근본적인 역할과 교육 가치를 재정의하는 ‘AX(AI Transformation) 비전’을 선포하고, 미래 교육의 중심지로 도약하기 위한 본격적인 행보에 나섰다.&lt;br/&gt;서울여자대학교는 1월 22일(목) 오후 1시 30분, 서울여대 50주년 기념관 국제회의실에서 주요 내외빈과 교직원, 학생 등 200여 명이 자리를 가득 메운 가운데 ‘서울여자대학교 AX 비전 선포식’을 개최했다. 이 행사는 AI 시대가 만들어내는 혁신과 변화에 능동적으로 대응해 교육의 질을 높이고, 기술 시대에도 흔들리지 않는 인간 존엄성을 강화하는 서울여대만의 독창적인 AX 교육 비전을 대내외에 공포하기 위해 마련되었다.&lt;br/&gt;■ ‘사람을 향한 기술로 사회 혁신을 이끄는 대학’... 인간 중심의 기술 철학 담아&lt;br/&gt;서울여대는 이날 새로운 AX 선도대학의 포부를 담은 슬로건으로 ‘AI to Learn, Human to Share(인간의 성장을 돕는 AI, 공동체를 잇는 인간)’, 그리고 ‘사람을 향한 기술로 사회혁신을 이끄는 대학’을 AX 비전으로 발표했다.&lt;br/&gt;비전 선포 발표자로 나선 이윤선 총장은 ‘기술의 발전 속도가 빠를수록, 대학은 발전의 방향이 맞는지 질문해야 한다’고 말하며, AI 시대에 서울여대의 언어는 속도와 효율의 시대 한가운데서 다시 사람과 방향, 그리고 책임을 말하는 것이라고 강조했다. 또한 ‘나’의 가치만큼 ‘우리’의 가치를 중심에 두어 온 서울여대의 교육 철학을 소개하면서 “AI는 인간을 대체하기 위한 도구가 아니라 인간의 성장을 돕기 위한 기술이고, 인간은 그 성장을 혼자 소유하는 존재가 아니라 공동체와 나누는 존재여야한다는 철학을 기반에 두고 AI 시대의 교육을 세우겠다”고 선언했다.&lt;br/&gt;서울여대가 제시한 AX 비전은 ▲인간 가치 우선 ▲사회 혁신 지향 ▲참여와 경험 중심 ▲융합과 협력 교육 ▲여성 리더십과 포용성 강화 ▲연구•교육•행정 연동 ▲글로벌 협력 기반의 AI교육 7대 원칙을 중심으로 운영될 예정이다.&lt;br/&gt;■ ‘AI to Learn, Human to Share’ 구체적인 AX 추진 전략 및 대학 혁신 로드맵 공개&lt;br/&gt;이어 박남춘 기획처장은 구체적인 ‘AX 추진 전략’을 발표했다. 서울여대는 데이터 기반의 개인화된 학습 지원 시스템을 고도화하고, 총장 직속 AX 컨트롤 타워 설치, AI 융합교육을 선도하는 학사구조로의 혁신, 데이터 중심의 지능형 행정 혁신, 전공의 경계를 넘나드는 AI 융합 커리큘럼과 초연결형 교양 융합 AX 체계 구축, 인간 중심 AI 교육을 위한 미래첨단연구원 설립, 교수자를 위한 AX 교육 등 서울여자대학교의 구체적인 전략과 로드맵을 발표했다. 박 처장은 “서울여대는 학내 행정 시스템부터 교수법까지 전 영역에 걸쳐 혁신을 단행해 AI 시대 대학의 새로운 표준을 만들겠다”는 포부를 밝혔다.&lt;br/&gt;■ 염재호 태재대 총장 기조 강연 ... “인간과 AI가 공존하는 대학, 질문하는 힘이 핵심”&lt;br/&gt;행사 2부에서는 AI와 교육 전문가들의 통찰을 공유하는 컨퍼런스가 이어졌다. 기조 강연 자로 나선 태재대학교 염재호 총장은 를 주제로 발표를 진행했다.&lt;br/&gt;염 총장은 “AI가 지식을 전달하는 역할을 대신하게 되는 시대에 대학은 학생들에게 ‘질문하는 능력’과 ‘즐겁게 숙련하는 일’을 길러주는 공간이 되어야 한다”며, 서울여대가 선포한 인간 중심의 AX 비전이 미래 대학 모델의 중요한 해답이 될 것이라고 평가했다.&lt;br/&gt;■ 학계와 산업계 AI 전문가들과의 깊이 있는 토론&lt;br/&gt;마지막 순서로 진행된 라운드테이블에서는 서울여대 한원식 산학연구처장의 진행 아래 홍헬렌 소프트웨어융합학과 교수, 김명주 AI안전연구소장(지능정보보호학부 교수), 김지섭 뤼튼테크놀로지스 이사 등이 참여해 서울여대가 제시한 AX 비전이 실제 교육과 연구 현장에서 어떻게 구현될 수 있는지에 대한 전략과, 급격한 기술 발전 속에서 대학이 지켜야 할 가치가 무엇인지에 대해 의견을 교환했다. 김명주 소장은 “마침 한국에서 ‘인공지능기본법’이 세계 최초로 시행되는 첫날, 인간 중심의 AX를 논할 수 있어 더욱 뜻깊다. AX는 피할 수 없는 세계의 흐름이지만, 양면성이 있으므로, 다음 세대 인재를 기르는 대학에서 AX의 그늘진 면에 적극적으로 대응하며 인간중심의 지속 가능한 기술로 가꿔가는 노력이 반드시 필요하다” 라며 서울여대의 선도적인 역할을 당부했다.&lt;br/&gt;한편, 이날 행사에는 김경진 학교법인 정의학원 이사장을 비롯해 우원식 국회의장과 오승록 노원구청장, 오금란·서준오 서울시의원, 이용관 블루포인트 대표, 윤도영 광운대학교 총장이 축사를 전하고, 지역 대학 총장과 정·관계, 산업계·학계 관계자들이 대거 참석해 서울여자대학교의 새로운 비전을 축하했다. 서울여대는 이번 비전 선포를 기점으로, 인간 중심의 AI 시대의 방향을 제시하는 중추적인 역할을 수행하며 대학의 성장을 이어갈 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Seoul Women's University (* 자료제공 :  서울여자대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational article provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241354.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/471/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8417691486855201.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hanyang University Launches Physician-Scientist Training Unit... Cultivating Full-Cycle Convergence-Type Talents (한양대, 의사과학자 양성사업단 발족…전주기적 융합형 인재 양성)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241359.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hanyang University Launches Physician-Scientist Training Unit... Cultivating Full-Cycle Convergence-Type Talents (한양대, 의사과학자 양성사업단 발족…전주기적 융합형 인재 양성)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0123/2917691491616775.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;[한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단 설립기념 사진]제1의학관 3층 의과대학 행정팀 내 사업단 현판 앞에서 설립 기념 촬영을 진행했다. 사진 왼쪽부터 의과대학 한호철 차장, 엄유진 교수, 박훈기 학장, 김영서 사업단장, 김인아 의예과장, 이제연 교수.한양대 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hanyang University College of Medicine announced that, having been selected for the Ministry of Health and Welfare's 'Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Project' in the latter half of 2025, it has established the Hanyang University Physician-Scientist Training Unit under the Future Talent Development Group and is formally embarking on cultivating full-cycle convergence-type physician-scientists. Professor Kim Young-seo from the Department of Neurology at the College of Medicine will serve as the inaugural unit director.&lt;br/&gt;The newly launched unit aims to systematically cultivate medical students into physician-scientists. It plans to nurture talents who will lead in the fields of convergence medicine and biomedical sciences through education and research that integrate medicine, engineering, and natural sciences. In particular, it plans to jointly provide convergence medicine education to students from the College of Engineering and Interdisciplinary Programs, allowing students early exposure to collaborative medical research environments.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, it will operate a convergence-type physician-scientist graduate program for various clinical specialty graduate students even after graduation from medical school. Moving away from the existing consortium format, it will be operated solely by Hanyang University starting in 2026. The plan is to actively support research capacity enhancement by providing participating graduate students with research funds of 20 million won per person.&lt;br/&gt;Hanyang University is currently operating various educational and practical programs for physician-scientist training throughout the entire medical education cycle. Medical students complete required courses related to convergence medicine such as data science, biomedical engineering, and life sciences, and can also electively take convergence medicine-related courses offered by the College of Engineering and Interdisciplinary Programs. Alongside this, the curriculum will be continuously expanded through various programs such as Medical Science Camps, Basic Medicine Practice Camps, and dispatch to overseas basic medicine education programs.&lt;br/&gt;Unit Director Kim Young-seo stated, "The cultivation of physician-scientists perfectly aligns with Hanyang University's founding philosophy of 'Love in Deed and Truth' and the educational purpose of the College of Medicine, which is to cultivate professional medical personnel who, while actively pursuing self-development, utilize creative research to apply specialized medical knowledge practically and practice love for the local community, the nation, and ultimately, human society." He added, "This opening ceremony is an important first step in establishing a physician-scientist training ecosystem, and we expect talents who will play a leading role in the development of the national biomedical field to be cultivated going forward."&lt;br/&gt;Park Hun-ki, Dean of Hanyang University College of Medicine, said, "We expect the excellent professors from Hanyang University's basic and clinical medicine departments to act as capable mentors through their high interest and affection for students." He added, "We will actively support students so they can be nurtured into physician-scientists who can lead the future by strengthening programs to allow for more convergence medicine education choices in line with the 6-year curriculum reform."&lt;br/&gt;Meanwhile, the Hanyang University Physician-Scientist Training Unit, with support from the Ministry of Health and Welfare, plans to operate the following programs: ▲Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Undergraduate Program (Responsible: Prof. Kim Young-seo, Dept. of Neurology, College of Medicine) ▲Convergence-Type Physician-Scientist Training Graduate Program (Responsible: Prof. Kim Bong-young, Dept. of Infectious Diseases, College of Medicine) ▲Postdoctoral Research Growth Support Program (Responsible: Prof. Sung Yoon-kyung, Dept. of Rheumatology, College of Medicine). An operating committee, with participation from the College of Medicine, College of Engineering, Interdisciplinary Programs, and Hanyang University Medical Center, will promote educational programs, academic camps, and research achievement exchanges. Furthermore, plans are in place to continuously expand the educational foundation through future collaboration with global medical schools. (한양대학교 의과대학은 2025년 하반기 보건복지부 ‘융합형 의사과학자 양성 사업’에 선정됨에 따라 미래인재양성단 산하에 한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단을 설립하고, 전주기적 융합형 의사과학자 양성에 본격적으로 나선다고 밝혔다. 초대 사업단장은 의과대학 신경과 김영서 교수가 맡았다.&lt;br/&gt;이번에 발족한 사업단은 의과대학 학생을 의사과학자(Physician-Scientist)로 체계적으로 육성하는 것을 목표로, 의학과 공학, 자연과학을 융합한 교육과 연구를 통해 융합의학 및 의생명과학 분야를 선도할 인재를 양성할 계획이다. 특히 공과대학과 인터칼리지 학생들에게도 융합의학 교육을 공동으로 제공해, 학생들이 조기에 의학 협동연구 환경에 노출될 수 있도록 할 예정이다.&lt;br/&gt;또한 의과대학 졸업 이후에도 다양한 임상 전공의 대학원생을 대상으로 한 융합형 의사과학자 대학원 과정을 운영한다. 기존 컨소시엄 형태에서 벗어나 2026년부터는 한양대학교 단독으로 운영하며, 참여 대학원생에게는 개인당 2천만 원 규모의 연구비를 지원해 연구 역량 강화를 적극적으로 뒷받침할 계획이다.&lt;br/&gt;한양대학교는 현재 의학교육 전주기에 걸쳐 의사과학자 양성을 위한 다양한 교육과 실습을 운영하고 있다. 의과대학 학생들은 데이터사이언스, 의공학, 생명과학 등 융합의학 관련 필수과목을 이수하며, 공과대학과 인터칼리지에서 개설된 융합의학 관련 교과목도 선택 수강할 수 있다. 이와 함께 메디컬 사이언스 캠프, 기초의학 실습 캠프, 해외 기초의학 교육과정 파견 등 다양한 프로그램을 통해 교육과정을 지속적으로 확대해 나갈 예정이다. &lt;br/&gt;김영서 사업단장은 “의사과학자 양성은 사랑의 실천이라는 한양대학교의 건학이념과 능동적으로 자개개발을 추구하면서 창의적인 연구로 의학전문지식을 실용화하고 지역사회와 국가, 나아가 인류사회에 사랑을 실천하는 전문의료인을 양성한다는 한양대학교 의과대학의 교육목적과 정확히 부합한다”며 “이번 개소식은 의사과학자 양성 생태계를 구축하기 위한 중요한 첫 출발로 앞으로 국가 바이오메디컬 분야 발전에 선도적인 역할을 할 인재들이 양성될 것으로 기대한다”고 말했다. &lt;br/&gt;박훈기 한양대학교 의과대학장은 “한양대학교의 우수한 기초의학교실과 임상의학교실 교수들이 높은 학생에 대한 관심과 사랑을 통해 유능한 멘토로 활동할 것으로 기대한다”며 “6년제 학제 개편에 보다 많은 융합의학 교육을 선택할 수 있도록 프로그램을 보강해서 학생들이 미래를 선도할 수 있는 의사과학자로 육성될 수 있도록 적극 지원하겠다” 고 밝혔다. &lt;br/&gt;한편, 한양대학교 의사과학자 양성사업단은 보건복지부의 지원을 받아 ▲융합형 의사과학자 양성 학부과정(책임자: 의과대학 신경과 김영서 교수) ▲융합형 의사과학자 양성 대학원과정(책임자: 의과대학 감염내과학교실 김봉영 교수) ▲박사후 연구성장지원 과정(책임자: 의과대학 류마티스내과학교실 성윤경 교수)을 운영할 예정이다. 운영위원회는 의과대학을 비롯해 공과대학, 인터칼리지, 한양대학교 의료원이 함께 참여해 교육 프로그램과 학술 캠프, 연구성과 교류회를 추진하며, 향후 글로벌 의과대학과의 협력을 통해 교육 기반을 지속적으로 확대해 나갈 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Information provided by: Hanyang University (* 자료제공 :  한양대학교)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;This article is an informational piece provided by the university and may differ from the views of The Hankyoreh.&gt; (&amp;lt;이 기사는 대학이 제공한 정보기사로, 한겨레의 의견과 다를 수 있습니다&amp;gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/biznews/1241359.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/700/467/imgdb/resize/test/original/2026/0123/2917691491616775.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Closes in the 4990s, Fails to Settle Above '5,000-pi'... KOSDAQ Approaches 'Cheon-sdaq' (코스피, 4990대 마감 ‘오천피’ 안착 실패…코스닥은 ‘천스닥’ 눈앞)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241371.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSPI Closes in the 4990s, Fails to Settle Above '5,000-pi'... KOSDAQ Approaches 'Cheon-sdaq' (코스피, 4990대 마감 ‘오천피’ 안착 실패…코스닥은 ‘천스닥’ 눈앞)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502344.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;23일 서울 중구 우리은행 본점 딜링룸 현황판에 코스피 지수 등이 표시되고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, the KOSPI recovered the 5,000-point level in early trading but reduced its gains to close in the 4990s. It failed to settle above '5,000-pi' on a closing basis for the second consecutive day. Meanwhile, the KOSDAQ index surged over 2%, closing in on 'Cheon-sdaq' (KOSDAQ 1,000). (코스피가 23일 장 초반 5000선을 회복한 뒤 오름폭을 줄여 4990대에서 장을 마쳤다. 전날에 이어 종가 기준 ‘오천피’ 안착에는 실패했다. 반면 코스닥지수는 2% 넘게 급등해 ’천스닥’(코스닥 1000)에 바짝 다가섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSPI closed at 4,990.07, up 37.54 points (0.76%) from the previous day. It once again set a new all-time closing high, surpassing the record set the day before. It opened at 4,984.08, up 31.55 points (0.64%), and expanded its gains to reach an intraday high of 5,021.13, setting a new all-time intraday record. However, the gains were trimmed later as profit-taking selling emerged. (  이날 코스피는 전날보다 37.54(0.76%) 오른 4990.07에 장을 마쳤다. 전날 기록한 종가 기준 최고치를 재차 경신했다. 전날보다 31.55(0.64%) 오른 4984.08로 출발해 상승폭을 키워 한 때 5021.13까지 올라 장중 기준 사상 최고치를 경신했다. 이후 차익 실현 매물이 출회되면서 상승폭은 축소됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the opening of the 'KOSPI 5,000 era', securities stocks surged sharply, with Mirae Asset Securities rising 16.58% on the day. (  ‘코스피 5000 시대’가 열리자 이날 미래에셋증권이 16.58% 오르는 등 증권주들이 급등했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The KOSDAQ index closed at 993.93, up 23.58 points (2.43%) from the previous day, marking its highest level in over four years since January 7, 2022 (995.16). Analysts suggest that expectations for the institutionalization of stablecoins stimulated investor sentiment in the KOSDAQ market. Kakao Pay, classified as a stablecoin-themed stock, hit the upper price limit on the day. (  코스닥지수는 전날보다 23.58(2.43%) 오른 993.93에 장을 마치며 2022년 1월 7일(995.16) 이후 4년여 만에 최고치를 기록했다. 이날 코스닥은 스테이블코인 제도화에 대한 기대감이 투자심리를 자극한 것으로 분석된다. 스테이블코인 테마주로 분류돼온 카카오페이는 이날 상한가를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Seoul foreign exchange market, the won-dollar exchange rate closed at 1,465.8 won at the end of daytime trading (3:30 PM), down 4.1 won from the previous day's closing rate. (  이날 서울 외환시장에서 원-달러 환율은 주간거래 종가(오후 3시 30분) 기준으로 전날 주간거래 종가보다 4.1원 내린 1465.8원을 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Jo Kyewan &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 조계완 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyewan@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyewan@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241371.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/574/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502344.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hyundai Motor's Labor-Management Conflict Over 'Atlas' Deployment... A Déjà Vu from 30 Years Ago (‘아틀라스’ 현장 배치 두고 현대차 노사갈등…30여년 전 데자뷔)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241381.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hyundai Motor's Labor-Management Conflict Over 'Atlas' Deployment... A Déjà Vu from 30 Years Ago (‘아틀라스’ 현장 배치 두고 현대차 노사갈등…30여년 전 데자뷔)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502504.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;현대자동차그룹의 휴머노이드 로봇 아틀라스. 현대차 제공&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A rift has erupted over Hyundai Motor Group's announcement that it will deploy the humanoid robot 'Atlas' on production lines. The Hyundai Motor labor union is pushing back, stating that "not a single robot can enter the production site without agreement," with the situation poised to escalate into a full-blown labor-management conflict. With the company's stance of reducing costs and increasing production efficiency pitted against the union's demand for job security, it's a pattern of similar debates that repeats with each technological transition. (인간형(휴머노이드) 로봇 ‘아틀라스’를 생산 현장에 투입하겠다는 현대차그룹의 발표를 두고 파열음이 터져 나오고 있다. 현대차 노조가 “합의 없이는 단 한 대의 로봇도 (생산) 현장에 들어 올 수 없다”고 반발하면서, 노사 갈등으로까지 번질 기세다. 비용 절감과 생산 효율을 높이려는 회사쪽과 고용 안정을 요구하는 노조쪽 입장이 맞서면서, 기술 혁신 과도기마다 비슷한 논쟁이 되풀이되는 모습이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Metal Workers' Union Hyundai Motor Branch stated in its newsletter on the 22nd, "The introduction of new technology (robot automation) is a one-way street without labor-management agreement," adding, "It is absolutely unacceptable, and mass production and deployment of robots into production sites is expected to cause employment shock." It further noted, "After the initial purchase cost, robots only incur maintenance fees, making them a good pretext for capitalists seeking long-term profit maximization," and concluded, "From the workers' perspective, this is not a welcome situation." (전국금속노조 현대차지부는 지난 22일 소식지를 내어 “신기술 도입(로봇 자동화)은 노사 합의 없는 일방통행”이라며 “절대 용납할 수 없고 (로봇을) 대량 양산해 생산 현장에 투입할 시 고용충격이 예상된다”고 했다. 이어 “로봇은 초기 구입비 이후 유지비만 발생하므로 장기적으로 이익 극대화를 노리는 자본가에 좋은 명분이 된다”며 “노동자 입장에선 반갑지 않은 상황”이라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The robot the union is taking issue with is Atlas. It is a humanoid robot developed by Boston Dynamics, a robotics company acquired by Hyundai Motor Group, and was first unveiled earlier this month at CES 2026, the world's largest consumer electronics and IT trade show held in Las Vegas, USA. At CES, Hyundai Motor Group announced that it would deploy Atlas starting in 2028 at its Hyundai Motor Group Metaplant America (HMGMA) in Georgia, USA, and gradually apply it to manufacturing sites. (노조 쪽이 문제 삼은 로봇은 아틀라스다. 현대차그룹이 인수한 로보틱스 기업 보스턴다이나믹스가 개발한 휴머노이드 로봇으로 이달 초 미국 라스베이거스에서 열린 세계 최대 가전·정보통신(IT) 전시회 ‘시이에스(CES) 2026’에서 처음 공개됐다. 현대차그룹은 아틀라스를 2028년부터 미국 조지아주에 있는 현대차그룹 메타플랜트 아메리카(HMGMA)에 투입하고, 제조 현장에 단계적으로 적용하겠다고 시이에스에서 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the plan is to deploy it in various parts assembly processes by 2030 and subsequently expand its application scope to more complex processes like repetitive tasks and handling heavy objects. The company explained that Atlas can learn most tasks within a day and autonomously handle a variety of high-intensity labor, from delicate work to tasks requiring lifting objects weighing up to 50 kilograms over 2 meters. Hyundai Motor Group also announced plans to establish a system capable of mass-producing 30,000 robots annually by 2028 and to mass-produce Atlas. (구체적으로 2030년까지 각종 부품 조립 공정에 배치하고 이후 반복 작업, 중량물 취급 등 더욱 복잡한 공정으로 적용 범위를 확대할 계획이다. 회사는 아틀라스가 대부분의 작업을 하루 안에 학습할 수 있고 섬세한 작업부터 최대 50킬로그램(kg)의 물건을 2미터(m)가 넘게 들어올려야 하는 작업까지 다양한 고강도 노동을 자율적으로 처리할 수 있다고 설명했다. 현대차그룹은 2028년까지 연간 3만대의 로봇을 양산할 수 있는 시스템을 구축하고, 아틀라스를 대량 생산하겠다는 계획도 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The company explains this move by saying it will "make the work environment safer for employees and accelerate smart factory innovation." However, as it is a general-purpose robot developed with the goal of real-world manufacturing site application, if its use expands across the group's global production bases, there is a high possibility that humans will be replaced by robots in some processes. This is why the union has taken a firm stance, stating, "We cannot accept even a single unit without labor-management agreement." (회사 쪽은 이를 두고 “근로자의 작업환경을 더욱 안전하게 하고 스마트 팩토리 혁신을 가속화할 것”이라고 설명한다. 하지만 실제 제조 현장 적용을 목표로 개발된 범용 로봇인 만큼 그룹 글로벌 생산거점 전반으로 확대 적용될 경우 일부 공정에서 사람이 로봇으로 대체될 가능성이 크다. 노조 쪽에서 “노사 합의 없이는 단 한 대도 받아들일 수 없다”며 강경한 반대 입장을 내놓은 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is not the first conflict between a company and a union over new technology. A similar conflict arose in the early 1990s when factory automation began in earnest in Korean industrial sites. A Hankyoreh report from January 15, 1991, highlighted the 'light' and 'shadow' of factory automation. In an article titled "Worker alienation obscured by the 'light' of productivity increase - Factory automation in full swing," The Hankyoreh wrote that as the introduction of informatization and computer technology progressed rapidly, the reorganization of factory production lines accelerated. While this brought the 'light' of machines taking over 'difficult, tedious, and dirty work,' it also cast the 'shadow' of worker alienation. (신기술을 둘러싼 기업-노조 간 갈등은 이번이 처음이 아니다. 1990년대 초 한국 산업 현장에서 공장 자동화가 본격화할 때에도 비슷한 갈등 국면이 빚어졌다. 1991년 1월15일치 한겨레 보도는 공장 자동화에 따른 ‘빛’과 ‘그늘’을 짚었다. 한겨레는 “생산성 증대 ‘빛’에 가린 노동자 소외-본격화되는 공장자동화”란 제목의 기사에서 정보화·컴퓨터 기술 도입이 빠르게 진행되면서 공장의 생산라인 개편이 가속화했고 이에 따라 ‘힘들고 지루하고 더러운 작업’을 기계가 대신해주는 ‘빛’이 생겼지만, 동시에 노동자 소외라는 ‘그림자’를 드리운다고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the recurring labor-management conflicts due to technological innovation, experts have repeatedly emphasized the importance of tripartite consultation (labor, management, government). In its 2017 report 'Tasks and Response Strategies for Labor-Management Relations in the 4th Industrial Revolution,' the Korea Labor Institute stated, "Concerns and fears about jobs observed in industries like automotive are issues that require policy intervention, not a wait-and-see approach," and described that "it is important for labor and management from key industries to directly participate in and cooperate, compromise, and discuss within government or social institutions and organizations." (기술혁신에 따라 반복되는 노사 갈등과 관련해, 전문가들은 노사정 협의의 중요성을 여러 차례 강조해왔다. 한국노동연구원은 2017년 발표한 ‘4차 산업혁명의 노사관계 차원 과제와 대응전략’에서 “자동차 산업 등에서 관찰되는 일자리 우려와 공포는 관망이 아니라 정책적으로 관여해야 할 이슈”라며 “정부나 사회적 기구, 조직에 주요 산업의 노사가 직접 참여해서 협력하고 타협, 논의하는 것이 중요하다”고 서술했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Professor Lee Byung-hoon of Chung-Ang University (Department of Sociology) wrote in his 2018 paper 'The 4th Industrial Revolution and Labor-Management Relations: Focusing on Labor-Management Conflict Issues and Western Unions' Response Strategies,' "With the widespread replacement of human labor by AI and robots through digital technological innovation, referred to as the 4th Industrial Revolution, there are concerns that the future of labor will result in a very unfortunate 'dystopia.'" However, he also noted, "The ripple effects of digital technology can vary significantly depending on the strategic choices of labor and management and their mutual response processes." He added, "As shown by the cases of German unions, an approach that devises union policy formation strategies and proactively prepares for the disruptive damage caused by digital technological innovation through social dialogue among labor, management, and government to minimize labor-management conflict is desirable." (앞서 이병훈 중앙대 교수(사회학과)는 2018년 발간한 ‘4차 산업혁명과 노사관계 : 노사갈등 이슈와 서구 노조들의 대응전략을 중심으로’ 논문에서 “4차 산업혁명으로 일컬어지는 디지털 기술혁신을 통해 인공지능과 로봇 등에 의한 인력 대체가 광범위하게 전개되면서 노동의 미래는 매우 불행한 ‘디스토피아’로 귀결될 것으로 우려되고 있다”면서도 “노사의 전략적 선택과 상호 간의 대응과정을 통해 디지털 기술의 파급효과는 상당히 달라질 수 있다”고 썼다. 그러면서 “독일 노조들의 사례가 보여주듯 노조의 정책 형성 전략을 강구, 노사정 간의 사회적 대화를 통해 디지털 기술혁신으로 인한 파괴적 피해를 선제적으로 대비하고 노사갈등을 최소화하려는 접근이 바람직하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the research, when Volkswagen announced 'Strategy 2025' in 2016, with production process digitalization as a core element, labor and management concluded a 'Future Pact,' reaching an agreement to address job reductions. Key elements of the labor-management agreement included a ban on layoffs for operational reasons, utilization of part-time systems for older workers, and retraining/reassignment. (해당 연구에 따르면 폭스바겐이 2016년 생산공정 디지털화 등을 핵심 내용으로 한 ‘전략 2025’를 발표했을 때, 노사는 ‘미래 협약’을 맺고 일자리 감소에 대응하는 노사합의를 이뤄냈다. 경영상 해고 금지와 고령자 파트타임 제도 활용, 재교육·전환 배치 등이 대표적인 노사합의 내용이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agreement between Germany's IG Metall union and aircraft manufacturer Airbus is also noteworthy. Previously, in 2017, IG Metall and Airbus agreed to implement production tasks using a cobot (collaborative robot) method at the Hamburg site. This is not about robots replacing workers, but about introducing wearable robots so that workers and robots become 'partners,' interlinked and cooperating with each other. Furthermore, to maintain employment for surplus personnel resulting from this, an agreement was reached on reducing working hours, natural attrition, and job retraining. (독일 금속산별노조와 항공기 제조사인 에어버스의 노사 합의도 눈에 띄는 대목이다. 앞서 독일 금속산별노조는 2017년 에어버스와 함부르크 사업장에서 코봇(cobot·협동로봇) 방식으로 생산작업을 수행하는 것에 합의했다. 로봇이 작업자를 대체하는 것이 아니라, 사람이 착용할 수 있는 로봇을 도입해 노동자와 로봇이 ‘짝’이 되어 상호 연계해 협동하는 방식이다. 또한 이에 따른 잉여 인력의 고용 유지를 위해 근로 시간 단축과 자연퇴직 및 직무 재훈련에 대한 노사 합의도 이뤄냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Yoo Ha-young &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (유하영 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yhy@hani.co.kr"&gt;yhy@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241381.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/450/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502504.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Naver 'Strengthens C-Level' and Kakao 'Reduces Control Tower'... Why the Divergent Organizational Restructurings? (네이버 ‘C레벨 강화’·카카오 ‘컨트롤타워 축소’…엇갈린 조직개편 왜?)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241384.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Naver 'Strengthens C-Level' and Kakao 'Reduces Control Tower'... Why the Divergent Organizational Restructurings? (네이버 ‘C레벨 강화’·카카오 ‘컨트롤타워 축소’…엇갈린 조직개편 왜?)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/789/461/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502548.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;생성형 인공지능(AI) ‘제미나이’(Gemini)에 “네이버와 카카오의 기업 이미지(CI)를 반영해 이 기사에 어울리는 이미지를 생성해주세요”라는 지시어를 입력해 생성한 이미지.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naver and Kakao are embarking on establishing new management systems to open the door to the '20 trillion won revenue era' through organizational restructurings in opposite directions, effective December 1st. Naver is significantly strengthening its C-level (Chief-level) executive system to drive integration between businesses and enhance AI competitiveness, while Kakao is downsizing its group control tower and shifting to a management structure focused on swift decision-making and execution. (네이버와 카카오가 다음달 1일 상반된 방향의 조직개편을 통해 ‘매출 20조원 시대’ 문을 여는 새 경영 체제 구축에 나선다. 네이버는 최고경영진(C레벨) 체계를 대폭 강화해 사업 간 통합과 인공지능(AI) 경쟁력 고도화를 추진하는 반면, 카카오는 그룹 컨트롤타워를 축소하며 빠른 의사결정과 실행력 중심의 경영 구조로 전환한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kakao announced on the 23rd that it will reorganize its group control tower, the CA (Corporate Alignment) Council, from the existing structure of '4 committees, 2 heads, 1 office' to a '3 divisions, 4 managers' structure. The intent is to increase flexibility by reducing the organizational scale and slimming down the structure. (카카오는 그룹 컨트롤타워인 시에이(CA)협의체를 기존 ‘4개 위원회·2개 총괄·1개 단’ 체제에서 ‘3개 실·4개 담당’ 구조로 개편한다고 23일 밝혔다. 조직 규모를 줄여 구조를 슬림화하는 대신, 유연성을 높이겠다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This restructuring is interpreted as readjusting the role of the CA Council, which was launched to exert centralized control over affiliated companies after founder and Future Initiative Center head Kim Beom-soo became embroiled in allegations of stock price manipulation involving SM Entertainment in 2023. Having largely completed structural adjustments, such as drastically reducing the number of affiliates from 174 (as of the end of Q3 2021) to 94 (as of the end of last year), Kakao's strategy is now to increase decision-making speed and execution power to match a growth phase. Accordingly, organizations previously under the CA Council responsible for risk management—ESG (Environmental, Social, and Governance), public relations, government relations, and compliance—will be transferred to Kakao's headquarters. The CA Council will then focus on supporting the company's mid-to-long-term investment, finance, and HR strategies, centered around the newly established Group Investment Strategy Division, Group Finance Strategy Division, and Group HR Strategy Division. (이번 개편은 2023년 김범수 창업자 겸 미래이니셔티브센터장이 에스엠(SM)엔터테인먼트 주가 시세 조종 의혹에 휩싸인 뒤, 각 계열사에 대한 중앙집권적 통제를 위해 출범한 시에이협의체의 역할을 재조정하는 차원으로 해석된다. 카카오는 2021년 3분기 말 기준 174개에 달했던 계열사 수를 94개(지난해 말 기준)로 대폭 줄이는 등 구조조정 작업을 마무리한 만큼, 이제는 성장 국면에 맞춰 의사결정 속도와 실행력을 높이겠다는 전략이다. 이에 따라 기존에 시에이협의체에서 리스크 관리를 담당해 온 이에스지(ESG, 환경·사회·지배구조), 홍보, 대관, 준법경영 조직은 카카오 본사로 이관되고, 시에이협의체는 신설된 그룹투자전략실·그룹재무전략실·그룹인사전략실을 중심으로 회사의 중장기 투자·재무·인사 전략을 지원하는 데 집중한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Naver also announced a full-scale leadership reorganization on the 20th by newly appointing three C-level executives: Chief Data &amp; Content Officer (CDO), Chief Responsibility Officer (CRO), and Chief Human Resources Officer (CHRO). This expands the C-suite from the previous three-member system—CEO Choi Soo-yeon, COO Kim Beom-jun, and CFO Kim Hee-cheol—to a total of six members. This is the largest in Naver's corporate history. (앞서 네이버도 지난 20일 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자(CDO), 최고책임경영책임자(CRO), 최고인사책임자(CHRO) 등 3명의 시레벨 임원을 새로 선임하며 리더십 체계를 전면 개편했다. 이로써 기존 최수연 최고경영자(CEO), 김범준 최고운영책임자(COO), 김희철 최고재무책임자(CFO) 등 3명 체제였던 최고경영진은 모두 6명으로 늘었다. 이는 네이버 창사 이래 최대 규모다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naver's strategy is to establish focal points for each major area to maximize integrated synergy as the company's scale and business domains rapidly expand. In particular, the Chief Data &amp; Content Officer will be responsible for integrating user data and content accumulated across Naver to implement 'AI assistants' (AI agents) across all services. Consequently, some organizations within the existing CEO's direct 'specialized units' related to search and user-generated content (UGC) will be incorporated under the Chief Data &amp; Content Officer. The Chief Responsibility Officer will oversee policy and risk management amidst rapidly changing external environments, and the Chief Human Resources Officer will lead mid-to-long-term HR strategies for domestic and international business expansion and strengthen organizational competitiveness in the AI era. A Naver official explained, "As the organizational scale grows and the pace of technological change accelerates, the need to concentrate the company's capabilities through focal points for each major area has increased." (네이버는 회사 규모와 사업 영역이 빠르게 확장되는 상황에서, 부문별 구심점을 세워 통합 시너지를 극대화하겠다는 전략이다. 특히 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자는 네이버 전반에 축적된 사용자 데이터와 콘텐츠를 융합해 전 서비스에 ‘인공지능 비서’(AI 에이전트)를 구현하는 역할을 맡는다. 이에 따라 기존 최고경영자 직속 ‘전문조직’ 가운데 검색, 사용자 제작 콘텐츠(UGC) 관련 일부 조직은 최고데이터·콘텐츠책임자 산하로 편입된다. 최고책임경영책임자는 급변하는 대외 환경 변화 속 정책·리스크 관리를 총괄하고, 최고인사책임자는 국내외 사업 확장에 따른 중장기 인사 전략과 인공지능 시대의 조직 경쟁력 강화를 주도한다. 네이버 관계자는 “조직 규모가 커지고 기술 변화 속도가 빨라지면서 부문별 구심점을 통해 회사 역량을 집중할 필요성이 커졌다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An industry insider said, "While Naver is strengthening its C-suite following the return of Chairman Lee Hae-jin to the board, amid an aggressive business expansion process including M&amp;A, Kakao is promoting an organizational restructuring towards an execution-centric system as it needs to secure new growth engines after concluding over two years of legal risks and management renewal efforts." (업계 한 관계자는 “네이버는 이해진 이사회 의장 복귀 뒤 공격적인 인수·합병(M&amp;amp;A) 등 사업 확장 과정에서 최고경영진 강화하는 반면, 카카오는 2년 넘게 이어진 사법 리스크와 경영 쇄신 작업을 끝내고 새 성장 동력을 확보해야 하는 만큼 실행 중심 체제로 조직 개편을 추진하는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, according to consensus (market forecasts) from financial information provider FnGuide on this day, Kakao is estimated to have recorded revenues of 8.0875 trillion won last year, and Naver 12.1022 trillion won, with the combined annual revenue of the two companies expected to surpass 20 trillion won for the first time ever. (한편, 이날 금융정보업체 에프엔가이드의 컨센서스(시장 전망치)에 따르면, 카카오는 지난해 매출 8조875억원, 네이버는 12조1022억원을 기록할 것으로 추정돼 두 회사 연간 매출 합계가 사상 첫 20조원을 돌파할 것으로 전망된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Sun Dam &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (선담은 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sun@hani.co.kr"&gt;sun@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/it/1241384.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/789/461/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502548.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI 5000 Era... "If Capital Market Reform Slows, Could Fall Back to 3500" (코스피 5000 시대…“자본시장 개혁 늦추면 3500으로 회귀할 수도”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241401.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;KOSPI 5000 Era... "If Capital Market Reform Slows, Could Fall Back to 3500" (코스피 5000 시대…“자본시장 개혁 늦추면 3500으로 회귀할 수도”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502665.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한국기업거버넌스포럼이 23일 서울 종로구 프레스센터에서 개최한 ‘코스피 5000시대 지속가능한 코리아 프리미엄을 위한 긴급 좌담회’에서 참석자들이 토론을 하고 있다.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the KOSPI temporarily broke above the 5000 mark on the 22nd, a point was raised that to prevent the Korean stock market from falling back to 3500 and to continue its rise towards 7000, the pace of capital market reform must not be slowed. (코스피가 지난 22일 장중 한때 5000선을 돌파한 가운데 한국 증시가 3500으로 다시 떨어지지 않고 7000을 향해 계속 상승하려면 자본시장 개혁의 고삐를 늦춰서는 안된다는 지적이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the 'Emergency Symposium for a Sustainable Korea Premium in the KOSPI 5000 Era' held by the Korea Corporate Governance Forum on the 23rd at the Korea Press Center in Jongno-gu, Seoul, Forum Chairman Lee Nam-woo stated in his presentation, "The KOSPI breaking 5000 is due to expectations for corporate governance improvement following the 1st and 2nd revisions of the Commercial Act, and strong performance by semiconductor and automobile companies." He added, "However, semiconductor companies' operating profits cannot remain strong forever. Considering that stock prices typically peak 6-12 months ahead of corporate earnings, there is a high risk of stock prices falling around the end of this year or early next year." He emphasized, "The KOSPI is currently at a crossroads, either falling back to 3500 or rising further to 7000. To increase the downside rigidity of stock prices, we must not slow down but must continue capital market reform." (한국기업거버넌스포럼이 23일 서울 종로구 한국프레스센터에서 개최한 ‘코스피 5000시대 지속가능한 코리아 프리미엄을 위한 긴급 좌담회’에서 이남우 포럼 회장은 발제를 통해 “코스피 5000 돌파는 1·2차 상법 개정에 따른 기업지배구조 개선에 대한 기대감과, 반도체·자동차 기업들의 실적 호조 때문”이라며 “하지만 반도체 기업의 영업이익이 계속 좋을 수는 없고, 통상 주가의 고점이 기업 이익보다 6~12개월 앞서 반영되는 선행성을 감안하면, 올해 말이나 내년초에는 주가가 하락할 리스크가 높다”고 진단했다. 그는 “코스피는 현재 3500으로 다시 떨어지거나 7000까지 더욱 상승하는 갈림길에 있다”며 “주가의 하방 경직성을 높이려면 자본시장 개혁의 고삐를 늦춰서는 안되고 지속해야 한다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Lee Nam-woo pointed out, "Last April, we proposed seven capital market reform tasks to the new government. Over the past eight months, the ruling party and government have implemented the introduction of directors' duty of loyalty to shareholders, the introduction of separate taxation for dividend income and tax rate reduction, and the mandatory cumulative voting system. However, the introduction of a discovery system (evidence disclosure system) to activate relief for minority shareholders, mandatory share buybacks, the principle of prohibiting subsidiary listings and protecting parent company shareholders in exceptional cases, fair value assessment during mergers between listed affiliates, and the mandatory announcement and implementation of value-up plans for all listed companies have not yet been achieved." He emphasized, "While the ruling party is pushing for mandatory share buybacks through the 3rd Commercial Act revision, recognizing two exceptions—management purposes like new technology introduction and financial structure improvement, and free contributions to employee stock ownership associations—raises significant concerns about potential abuse by companies." He also stressed, "A 'stock price suppression prevention law' is also needed to prevent owner-managers from artificially keeping stock prices low to reduce inheritance taxes." (이남우 회장은 “지난해 4월 새정부에 7가지의 자본시장 개혁과제를 제언했는데, 정부여당이 지난 8개월 동안 이사의 주주 충실 의무 도입, 배당소득 분리과세 도입과 세율인하, 집중투표제 의무화를 시행했지만, 아직 (소액주주 피해구제 활성화를 위한) 디스커버리제도(증거개시제도) 도입, 자사주 소각 의무화, 자회사 상장의 원칙 금지와 예외시 모회사 주주 보호, 상장 계열사 간 합병 때 공정가치로 평가, 모든 상장사에 밸류업계획 발표 및 실천 의무화는 아직 이뤄지지 않았다”고 지적했다. 그는 “(정부여당이 3차 상법 개정으로) 자사주 소각 의무화를 추진하면서 신기술 도입과 재무구조의 개선 등 경영상 목적과, 우리사주조합 등에 무상출연 등 2가지를 예외로 인정하려는 것은 기업들이 악용할 우려가 크다”며 “(오너 경영진이) 상속세를 낮추기 위해 주가를 인위적으로 낮게 유지하는 것을 방지하는 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’도 필요하다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding exchange rate defense measures, Chairman Lee Nam-woo said, "The exchange rate is a relative price and has a large psychological component. International investors have a very high wall of distrust, feeling they have been deceived by the Korean government and companies over the past 30 years. To overcome this, we need a direct approach: strongly and persistently continuing capital market and corporate governance reforms to firmly establish the perception that Korea is an advanced country that protects investors." He added, "Once this perception takes root, domestic investors will also increase their investment in the Korean stock market instead of the U.S. market." (이남우 회장은 환율 방어 대책과 관련 “환율은 상대가격이고 심리적 요소가 크다”며 “국제 투자자들은 지난 30년간 한국 정부 및 기업에 속아왔다는 불신의 벽이 매우 높은데, 이를 극복하려면 자본시장과 기업지배구조 개혁을 강력히 지속해서 한국이 투자자 보호가 되는 선진국가라는 인식을 확실히 심어주는 정공법이 필요하다”고 말했다. 그는 “이런 인식이 자리잡으면 국내 투자자도 미국 증시 대신 한국 증시에 투자를 늘릴 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on the 22nd, the ruling party and members of the Democratic Party of Korea's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee met with President Lee Jae-myung at the Presidential Office. They agreed not to be satisfied with achieving KOSPI 5000 and to continue reform efforts, including the 3rd Commercial Act revision for mandatory share buybacks. (한편 정부여당은 지난 22일 이재명 대통령과 더불어민주당의 코스피5000 특별위원회 소속 의원들이 청와대에서 만나 코스피 5000 달성에 만족하지 않고, 자사주 소각 의무화를 위한 3차 상법개정 등 개혁 노력을 지속하기로 뜻을 같이했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the symposium, Oh Ki-hyung, Chairman of the Democratic Party's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee, gave a congratulatory speech. The discussion was joined by Choi Jun-cheol, CEO of VIP Asset Management; Chun Jun-beom, Attorney at Law, CEO of Wiseforest; Lee Chang-hwan, CEO of Align Partners; Shim Hye-seop, Attorney at Law; and Kim Hyung-kyun, Head of Department at Cha Partners Asset Management. (이날 좌담회에서는 오기형 더불어민주당 코스피5000 특별위원장이 축사를 하고, 토론에 최준철 브이아이피(VIP)자산운용 대표, 천준범 와이즈포레스트 대표 변호사, 이창환 얼라인파트너스 대표, 심혜섭 변호사, 김형균 차파트너스자산운용 본부장이 참여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article and photos · Senior Reporter Kwak Jeong-su, Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (글·사진 ·곽정수 한겨레경제사회연구원 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:jskwak@hani.co.kr"&gt;jskwak@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241401.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/728/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502665.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Korean Air passenger plane malfunctions after landing at Jeju Airport...runway closed for 20 minutes (대한항공 여객기, 제주공항 착륙 후 고장…활주로 20분간 폐쇄)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241404.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Korean Air passenger plane malfunctions after landing at Jeju Airport...runway closed for 20 minutes (대한항공 여객기, 제주공항 착륙 후 고장…활주로 20분간 폐쇄)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/860/516/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502686.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;대한항공 누리집 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Operations at Jeju International Airport's runway were suspended for about 20 minutes due to a malfunction on a Korean Air passenger plane. (대한항공 여객기 고장으로 제주국제공항 활주로 운영이 약 20분간 중단되는 일이 발생했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Korean Air stated on the 23rd, "Flight KE1105, which departed from Gimpo International Airport at 12:40 PM and arrived at Jeju Airport at 1:55 PM today, experienced a hydraulic system abnormality during the landing preparation phase and occupied the runway for approximately 20 minutes." (대한항공은 23일 “이날 오후 12시40분 김포국제공항에서 출발해 오후 1시55분 제주공항에 도착하는 KE1105편 여객기가 착륙 준비 단계에서 유압계통 이상이 생겨 약 20분간 활주로를 점유했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The passenger plane landed normally on the Jeju Airport runway. However, it came to a stop on the 'taxiway'—the area for moving from the runway to the apron—after a hydraulic system warning light illuminated, rendering it unable to move under its own power. As the plane was towed away by a towing tractor (tow car), runway operations were suspended from 2:00 PM to 2:20 PM, a period of 20 minutes. (여객기는 제주공항 활주로에 정상적으로 착륙했지만, 유압계통에 이상 메시지가 점등되면서 활주로에서 계류장으로 이동하는 공간인 ‘유도로’에 멈춰 섰다. 자력으로 이동하지 못하는 여객기를 견인차량인 토잉 트랙터(토잉카)로 끌어 이동시키면서 활주로 운영이 이날 오후 2시부터 2시20분까지 20분간 중단됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 278 passengers on the affected flight disembarked safely. However, the temporary suspension of runway use caused subsequent delays for aircraft using Jeju Airport. A Korean Air official said, "The aircraft in question is currently under inspection." (사고 여객기에 탑승한 승객 278명은 안전하게 내렸으나, 활주로 사용이 일시적으로 중단되면서 제주공항을 이용하는 항공기들이 잇따라 지연됐다. 대한항공 관계자는 “해당 여객기는 현재 점검 중”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Joo-bin &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이주빈 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yes@hani.co.kr"&gt;yes@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241404.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/860/516/imgdb/original/2026/0123/20260123502686.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon, when asked "Are you willing to give up the apartment acquired through fraudulent subscription?" replies "Yes" "Yes" "Yes" (이혜훈, “부정청약 아파트 포기할 뜻 있나” 묻자 “네” “네” “네”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241412.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, when asked "Are you willing to give up the apartment acquired through fraudulent subscription?" replies "Yes" "Yes" "Yes" (이혜훈, “부정청약 아파트 포기할 뜻 있나” 묻자 “네” “네” “네”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 서울 여의도 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에 출석해 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, ruling and opposition party lawmakers intensely criticized the nominee over suspicions of 'fraudulent subscription' for an apartment. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회에서 여야 의원들은 이 후보자의 아파트 ‘부정 청약’ 의혹을 집중적으로 질타했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the hearing on the 23rd, when Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Jung Il-young said, "You must be prepared to admit it was wrong, accept any punishment, and if necessary, give up this apartment. Only with that level of resolve do I believe you are qualified to be the first Minister of Planning and Budget of the Lee Jae-myung administration," the nominee replied, "Yes, I understand." The nominee is suspected of having falsely presented her married eldest son as single to increase the number of dependents, thereby winning the subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul. (이 후보자는 23일 인사청문회에서 정일영 더불어민주당 의원이 “잘못됐다, 어떤 처벌이라도 받겠다, 필요하면 이 아파트를 내가 포기하겠다, 이 정도 각오는 가지셔야 이재명 정부의 초대 기획예산처 장관의 자격이 있는 것으로 본다”고 말하자 “네, 알겠습니다”라고 했다. 이 후보자는 결혼식을 올린 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 부양가족 수를 늘린 뒤 서울 서초구 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹을 받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Rep. Jung subsequently asked, "Do you have such an intention?" Nominee Lee only nodded her head. Rep. Jung then said, "No, please answer. No one will know if you just nod. It needs to be on the official record." He pressed again, asking, "Do you (have the intention to give up the apartment) or not?" This time, the nominee simply replied, "Yes." When Rep. Jung said, "What does 'yes' mean? Continue," the nominee engaged in a tense exchange, saying, "Yes, I do." (이어 정 의원이 “그런 용의가 있으신 것이냐”고 묻자, 이 후보자는 고개만 끄덕였다. 이에 정 의원은 “아니, 대답을 하세요. 고개 끄덕끄덕하시면 누가 압니까. 속기록에 남겨야지”라고 말했다. 그러면서 “(아파트를 포기할 용의가) 있으신 거예요, 없으신 거예요”라고 재차 질의하자, 이 후보자는 이번에는 “네”라고만 답했다. 정 의원이 “네가 뭐예요, 계속”이라고 하자 이 후보자는 “네, 있다고요”라며 신경전을 벌였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that morning, in response to Democratic Party lawmaker Jin Sung-jun's question, "Are you willing to give up the (said) house?" the nominee had answered, "I will follow the results of the investigative authorities." (이 후보자는 앞서 이날 오전 “(해당)집을 내놓을 용의가 있는가”라는 진성준 민주당 의원의 질문에는 “수사기관의 결과에 따르겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the fraudulent subscription suspicions that day, the nominee began by saying, "To be honest, I earnestly hoped I wouldn't have to talk about this publicly, but since things have come to this, it seems I have no choice but to talk about my family's situation." She said, "In December 2023, my eldest son prepared a newlywed home (in Yongsan, Seoul), but right after the wedding ceremony, problems arose," adding, "The relationship between the two broke down, reaching the worst point. At the time, it was judged difficult to maintain the marriage." She continued, "At that time, my eldest son had no choice but to continue living with us." Her remarks were intended to convey that while her son, who had held a wedding ceremony, did not move out to the Yongsan newlywed home, it was not a fabricated change of residence aimed at gaining subscription points. (이 후보자는 이날 부정 청약 의혹에 대해 “사실은 제가 이런 이야기를 공개적으로 하게 되지 않기를 간절히 바랐는데, 일이 이렇게 된 이상 저희 가족 이야기를 할 수밖에 없는 상황인 것 같다”고 운을 뗐다. 그는 “2023년 12월 장남은 (서울 용산에) 신혼집을 마련했지만, 혼례를 올리고 곧바로 문제가 생겼다”며 “두 사람의 관계가 깨어진 상황으로, 최악으로 치달았다. 당시에는 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단했다”고 말했다. 이어 “당시 장남은 저희와 함께 계속 있을 수밖에 없는 상황이었다”고 덧붙였다. 결혼식을 올린 장남이 용산 신혼집으로 분가하지 않았을 뿐, 청약 가점을 노린 위장 전입이 아니란 취지의 발언이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked by Rep. Jin Sung-jun, "Did the relationship between the eldest son and his wife recover after a year and a half?" the nominee effectively affirmed it by saying, "The (son and his wife) themselves, and many people, made efforts." (이 후보자는 “장남 부부 사이가 1년 반 만에 다시 회복된 것인가”라는 진성준 의원의 물음에 “(장남 부부)본인들도, 많은 사람도 노력했다”며 이를 사실상 긍정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While explaining the related suspicions, the nominee did not disclose a specific diagnosis but did reveal that her son had developed an illness. When Democratic Party lawmaker Lee So-young pointed out, "For 1 year and 5 months after marriage, the registered addresses of the eldest son and his wife did not overlap at all," the nominee explained during her clarification, "My son developed an illness during that period and is still receiving treatment." The nominee said, "As the relationship reached a breaking point, (my son) fell into an extremely worst situation due to mental pressure and stress, which led to the onset of the illness, and he is still receiving treatment." The nominee showed tears during her answer. (이 후보자는 관련 의혹을 해명하는 과정에서 구체적인 병명을 밝히진 않았지만 장남의 발병 사실을 공개하기도 했다. 이 후보자는 이소영 민주당 의원이 “장남 부부가 결혼 이후 1년5개월간 주민등록상 주소가 전혀 겹치지 않았다”고 지적하자 이를 해명하는 과정에서 “아들이 그 시기에 발병해서 지금까지 치료받고 있다”고 말했다. 이 후보자는 “관계가 파경이 되면서 (장남이) 정신적인 압박과 스트레스 등으로 굉장히 최악의 상황으로 치달아서 발병했고, 지금까지 치료를 받고 있다”고 말했다. 이 후보자는 답변 도중 눈물을 보이기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Yoon-joo &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김윤주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:kyj@hani.co.kr"&gt;kyj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241412.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/1717691358292945.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling and Opposition Parties Unite in Criticism: "Lee Hye-hoon's Eldest Son's University Admission Process and Apartment Application Were Inappropriate" (여야, 한목소리로 “이혜훈 장남 입학 경위·아파트 청약 부적절”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241419.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Ruling and Opposition Parties Unite in Criticism: "Lee Hye-hoon's Eldest Son's University Admission Process and Apartment Application Were Inappropriate" (여야, 한목소리로 “이혜훈 장남 입학 경위·아파트 청약 부적절”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691676463439.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 인사청문회에서 발언하고 있다. 공동취재사진&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the confirmation hearing for Minister of Economy and Finance nominee Lee Hye-hoon, which opened after much delay, questions from ruling and opposition party lawmakers focused on the circumstances of the nominee's eldest son's admission to Yonsei University and suspicions of improper apartment subscription. Typically, at ministerial confirmation hearings, the ruling party defends against opposition attacks and focuses on policy questions, but at this hearing, not only opposition lawmakers but also ruling party members sharpened their knives for scrutiny. (진통끝에 열린 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회에서는 이 후보자 장남의 연세대 입학 경위와 아파트 부정 청약 의혹에 대한 여야 의원들의 질의가 집중됐다. 통상 국무위원 인사청문회에서 여당은 야당의 공격을 방어하고 정책질의에 집중하는 모습을 보이지만, 이번 청문회에서는 야당뿐만 아니라 여당 의원들도 검증의 날을 세웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both ruling and opposition parties raised issues at the nominee's confirmation hearing held on the 23rd by the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee regarding the circumstances of her eldest son's admission to Yonsei University in 2010. The controversy began with nominee Lee's explanation that "my eldest son was admitted (to Yonsei University at the time) not through the multi-child household track, but through the 'National Prestige Enhancer' track." Nominee Lee stated, "My father-in-law (former Minister of Home Affairs Kim Tae-ho) received the Order of Civil Merit (Cheongjo Geunjeong Medal) in recognition of his various public service achievements during his lifelong career as a public official, which qualified him (for the track)." Although nominee Lee stated in a written response submitted to the National Assembly prior to the hearing that "my eldest son was admitted to Yonsei University through the multi-child household track," it was revealed that there was no multi-child household track in the 2010 academic year when her son was admitted, sparking controversy over improper admission. (여야는 23일 국회 재정경제기획위원회에서 열린 이 후보자 인사청문회에서 후보자 장남의 2010년 연세대 입학 경위를 문제 삼았다. 논란의 발단은 “장남이 다자녀 전형이 아니라, 국위선양자 전형으로 (당시 연세대에) 입학했다”는 이 후보자 해명이었다. 이 후보자는 “시부(김태호 전 내무부 장관)께서 공무원으로 평생 봉직한 여러 공적을 인정받아 청조근정훈장을 받으셨기 때문에 (전형) 자격 요건이 됐다”고 했다. 이 후보자는 인사청문회에 앞서 국회에 낸 답변서에서 “장남이 다자녀가구 전형으로 연세대에 입학했다”고 밝혔지만, 이 후보자 장남이 입학한 2010학년도에는 다자녀전형이 없었던 것으로 드러나 부정입학 논란이 불거진 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, People Power Party lawmaker Choi Eun-seok said, "Can we say that (nominee Lee's) eldest son's grandfather enhanced our nation's prestige by serving as Minister of Home Affairs and receiving a medal?" adding, "Through this, the nominee is essentially confessing to improper admission." The nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho, is a former four-term lawmaker who received the Order of Civil Merit. (이에 최은석 국민의힘 의원은 “(이 후보자)장남의 할아버지가 내무부 장관을 해서 훈장을 받은 게 우리나라의 국위를 선양했다고 할 수 있는가”라며 “이런 걸 통해 부정 입학을 했다는 걸 후보자가 그대로 자백하고 있는 것”이라고 말했다. 이 후보자의 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관은 4선 의원 출신으로 청조근정훈장을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To Rep. Choi's point, nominee Lee retorted, "It's not a regulation I created, but a regulation the school created." Rep. Choi continued raising suspicions, stating, "At the time, the nominee's husband was the head of the Academic Affairs Office at Yonsei University," and "It appears nominee Lee Hye-hoon's eldest son seized a spot meant for a social contributor." (최 의원의 지적에 이 후보자는 “제가 만든 규정이 아니고 학교가 만든 규정”이라고 반박했다. 최 의원은 “당시 후보자 남편은 연세대 교무부처장”이라며 “사회 기여자 자리를 이혜훈 후보자의 장남이 강탈한 것”이라고 의혹 제기를 이어갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party lawmaker also joined in. Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Ahn Do-gul pointed out problems with the eldest son's university admission process, stating, "Article 11, Clause 3 of the Constitution stipulates that decorations, medals, and other honors are effective only for the recipients and do not grant any privileges." (여당 의원도 가세했다. 안도걸 더불어민주당 의원은 “헌법 제11조 3항은 훈장 등의 영전은 이를 받은 자에게만 효력이 있고 어떠한 특권도 이에 따르지 아니한다고 규정하고 있다”며 장남의 대학 입학 과정에 문제가 있다고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When nominee Lee later got a chance to explain, she again specifically mentioned her son's admission issue. She said, "The school conducts a comprehensive evaluation mainly based on the CSAT (college entrance exam), school records, then various English scores, written exams, and oral interviews," and added, "In my son's case, he was an outstanding student academically; for English tests like TOEFL, SAT, and AP (Advanced Placement) exams taken in advance for U.S. college courses, he submitted scores all at the highest level (grade 5)." She continued, "If this student received a GPA of 3.85 after entering the school, I believe that is sufficient proof," and said, "As the (Planning and Finance Committee) Chairman (Im I-jae) mentioned earlier, the school no longer has any materials as the document retention period has passed. We are in a truly frustrating situation wondering how to clear this false accusation." (이 후보자는 이후 해명 기회를 얻자 다시 구체적으로 장남의 입학 문제를 언급했다. 그는 “주로 수능, 내신, 그 다음에 영어 각종 성적, 그리고 필기시험, 구술시험으로 학교에서 종합평가를 한다”며 “장남의 경우에 성적 우수자이고, 영어시험의 경우에는 토플, 에스에이티(SAT), 그다음에 에이피(AP)라고 미국 대학 과목을 먼저 시험 보는 것들이 있는데 다 5등급을 받아서 냈다”고 했다. 이어 “이 학생이 학교에 들어가서 3.85 학점을 받았으면 저는 그걸로 충분히 입증됐다고 본다”며 “아까 (임이자 재경경제기획위원회) 위원장님이 말씀하신 것처럼 학교는 자료 폐기 보존 기간이 지나서 아무 자료를 가지고 있지 않다는데, 저희는 어떻게 이 누명을 벗어야 될지 정말 답답한 상황”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Suspected improper subscription' was also put under scrutiny. Nominee Lee faces suspicions that she falsely represented her married eldest son as single to increase the number of dependents, leading to his winning a subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul. Regarding these suspicions, nominee Lee explained, "At the time, the relationship between the two (son and his wife) had deteriorated to the worst point," and "At the time, we thought it would be difficult for them to maintain their marriage." (‘부정 청약’도 도마 위에 올랐다. 이 후보자는 결혼식을 올린 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 부양가족 수를 늘린 뒤, 서울 서초구 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹을 받는다. 이런 의혹과 관련해 이 후보자는 “당시 두 사람(아들 부부)의 관계가 최악으로 치달았다”며 “당시 저희는 (아들 부부가) 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 생각했다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominee Lee shed tears while responding to related suspicions. When Democratic Party lawmaker Lee So-young pointed out that "the addresses on the resident registrations of the eldest son and his wife did not overlap at all for 1 year and 5 months after their marriage," nominee Lee, while explaining this, said, "My son fell ill during that period and has been receiving treatment ever since." She added, "As the relationship reached a breaking point, (my eldest son) fell into a very worst state due to mental pressure and stress, which led to his illness, and he has been receiving treatment until now." Nominee Lee shed tears as she continued this story. (이 후보자는 관련 의혹에 대해 답변하는 과정에 눈물을 보이기도 했다. 그는 이소영 민주당 의원이 “장남 부부가 결혼 이후 1년5개월간 주민등록상 주소가 전혀 겹치지 않았다”고 지적하자, 이를 해명하는 과정에서 “아들이 그 시기에 발병해서 지금까지 치료받고 있다”고 말했다. 이어 “관계가 파경이 되면서 (장남이) 정신적인 압박과 스트레스 등으로 굉장히 최악의 상황으로 치달아서 발병했고, 지금까지 치료를 받고 있다”고 덧붙였다. 이 후보자는 이런 이야기를 이어가며 눈물을 흘렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On that day, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport stated regarding the suspicions of improper subscription surrounding nominee Lee that if the related suspicions are true, there is a possibility of improper subscription. Jeong Su-ho, head of the Housing Finance Division at the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, who attended the hearing as a witness, responded to a question from Reform Party lawmaker Cheon Ha-ram, who asked, "Even in the case of a common-law marriage that broke down, shouldn't it be treated the same as divorce and not counted as a dependent?", by saying, "If the suspicions raised by the National Assembly or the media are true, there is a possibility of improper subscription." (이날 국토교통부는 이 후보자를 둘러싼 부정 청약 의혹을 두고, 관련 의혹이 사실이라면 부정 청약 소지가 있다고 밝혔다. 청문회에 증인으로 출석한 정수호 국토부 주택기금과장은 “사실혼 관계였다가 파탄 난 경우도 (이혼과) 동일하게 부양가족으로 넣으면 안 되는 것 아닌가”라는 천하람 개혁신당 의원 질의에 “국회나 언론에서 제기되는 의혹이 사실이면, 부정 청약 소지가 있다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the authenticity of the so-called 'memorandum' containing content such as wishes for other lawmakers to lose elections, nominee Lee denied it, saying, "I did not write it. I do not create such things (memorandums) as HWP (Hangul Word Processor) files." Nominee Lee also said, "It seems someone mixed their own guesses and rumors based on various schedules shared by our office staff," and added, "(The author) seems to be someone from our office nearby who is well aware of my every move." (이 후보자는 다른 의원에 대한 낙선 기도 등의 내용이 담긴 이른바 ‘비망록’의 진위를 놓고선 “제가 작성하지 않았다. 한글 파일로 이런 것(비망록)을 만들지 않는다”며 부인했다. 이 후보자는 “사무실 직원들이 공유하는 여러 일정을 기반으로 누군가가 본인의 짐작과 소문을 버무린 것으로 보인다”며 “(작성자는) 저의 일거수일투족을 잘 아는 지근거리에 있는 우리 사무실 직원인 것 같다”고 말하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Park Su-ji &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (박수지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:suji@hani.co.kr"&gt;suji@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/economy_general/1241419.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/647/imgdb/original/2026/0123/8017691676463439.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For KOSPI to Leap Beyond 5000... 'Fire on One's Feet' is Substantializing the Stewardship Code (코스피 5000 넘어 도약하려면…스튜어드십 코드 내실화 ‘발등의 불’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241425.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;For KOSPI to Leap Beyond 5000... 'Fire on One's Feet' is Substantializing the Stewardship Code (코스피 5000 넘어 도약하려면…스튜어드십 코드 내실화 ‘발등의 불’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0124/53_17692114886627_20260124500134.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;1월 23일 국회 의원회관에서 ‘스튜어드십코드 실효성 제고를 위한 내실화 방안 모색 토론회’ 가 열려 참석자들이 오기형 더불어민주당 코스피 5000 특위 위원장의 인사말을 듣고 있다.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a point being made that for the KOSPI 5000 point not to become just a 'turning point' that is briefly touched and then recedes, a transparent and fair corporate governance structure must be established. As one of the methods, the reorganization of the 'Lee Jae-myung administration version Stewardship Code', which includes strengthening the responsible investment of pension funds, building a cooperation platform among institutional investors, and improving laws and systems, has emerged as a key task. (코스피 5000 포인트가 한번 갔다 오는 ‘반환점’이 되지 않으려면 투명하고 공정한 기업지배구조가 자리 잡아야 한다는 지적이 나온다. 그 방안의 하나로 연기금의 책임투자 강화와 기관투자자 간 협력플랫폼 구축, 법·제도 정비를 포함한 ‘이재명 정부판 스튜어드십 코드’ 재정비가 핵심 과제로 떠올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Stewardship Code refers to the rules where institutions that invest others' money, such as pension/funds and asset management companies, promise to "protect the interests of the people who invested by responsibly and actively monitoring and participating in companies like a steward." Korea's Stewardship Code has been criticized for remaining a formal operation without a single revision even as it approaches 10 years since its introduction. (스튜어드십 코드는 남의 돈을 맡아 투자하는 연·기금, 자산운용사 같은 기관들이 “집사처럼 책임 있게, 적극적으로 기업을 감시·참여해서 투자한 사람들의 이익을 지키자”고 약속한 규칙을 말한다. 국내 스튜어드십 코드는 도입된 지 10년을 앞두고도 개정 한 번 없이 형식적 운영에 머물렀다는 비판을 받아왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A discussion forum on the topic of 'Substantialization Measures to Enhance the Effectiveness of the Stewardship Code' was held on the morning of the 23rd at the National Assembly Members' Office Building. Co-hosted by the Democratic Party of Korea's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee and Representative Kim Yun, the forum was attended by the Financial Services Commission, the National Pension Service, asset management companies, and civic groups to examine the actual implementation status of the code and discuss revision directions for more effective operation, an implementation monitoring system, and measures to strengthen the role of pension funds. (23일 오전 국회의원회관에서 ‘스튜어드십 코드 실효성 제고를 위한 내실화 방안’을 주제로 한 토론회가 열렸다. 더불어민주당 코스피 5000 특별 위원회와 김윤 의원이 공동주최한 토론회는 금융위원회, 국민연금, 자산운용사, 시민단체 등이 참여해 코드 이행 실태를 점검하고, 더 효과적으로 작동하기 위한 개정 방향과 이행점검 체계, 연기금 역할 강화 방안을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, Hwang Hyun-young, a research fellow at the Capital Market Research Institute, defined the Stewardship Code as "a code of conduct that encourages institutional investors to go beyond simply holding shares and engage in the long-term value creation of the companies they invest in," stating it is "a key tool for improving governance, expanding shareholder interests, and developing the capital market by having institutional investors with professional knowledge and resources play an active role." (황현영 자본시장 연구원 연구위원은 발제에서 “스튜어드십 코드는 기관투자자가 단순 주식 보유를 넘어 투자대상 회사의 장기 가치 형성에 관여하도록 하는 행동지침”이라며 “전문지식과 자원을 가진 기관투자자가 적극적 역할을 함으로써 지배구조 개선과 주주 이익 확대, 자본시장 발전을 위한 핵심 수단”이라고 정의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, since the system's introduction in 2016, the shareholder activities of private institutional investors participating in the code have seemingly become more active. The rate of voting against regular shareholder meeting agenda items increased from around 1% in 2014 to 4.59% in 2024, and the opposition rate of code-participating institutions was found to be more than three times higher than that of non-participating institutions. The National Pension Service also saw significant increases in its rate of voting against and the number of shareholder engagement activities such as letters and meetings with companies after participating in the code. (실제 2016년 제도 도입 이후 코드 참여 민간 기관투자자의 주주활동은 외견상 활발해졌다. 정기주총 안건에 대한 반대 의결권 행사 비율이 2014년 1%대에서 2024년에는 4.59%까지 늘었고 코드 참여기관의 반대율은 미참여 기관보다 3배 이상 높은 것으로 나타났다. 국민연금 역시 코드 참여 이후 반대의결권 행사 비율과 기업과의 서신·면담 등 주주 관여활동 건수가 많이 증가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, its effectiveness is lacking in reporting, disclosure, and execution. Only about 10 institutions on average annually regularly publish Stewardship implementation reports, and for insurers, banks, and securities firms excluding pension funds and asset management companies, no cases of report publication have been confirmed. In particular, private equity fund managers, investment advisory firms, and service institutions do not even have a website related to the Stewardship Code. (하지만 보고·공시·실행 면에서는 실효성이 떨어진다. 스튜어드십 이행 보고서를 정기적으로 발간하는 기관은 연간 평균 10여건에 불과하고, 연기금과 자산운용사를 제외한 보험사·은행·증권사는 보고서 발간 사례가 확인되지 않는다. 특히 사모펀드 운용사, 투자자문사, 서비스 기관 등은 스튜어드십 코드 관련한 홈페이지조차 없는 실정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Voting rights disclosure is also poor. According to a Financial Supervisory Service inspection in August 2024, 96.7% of the inspected asset management companies filled the reasons for exercising or not exercising voting rights with formal phrases like "no infringement of shareholder rights," and many companies did not properly state even the agenda name, proposal type, or relationship with the target corporation. Over 40% of management companies also disclosed only basic policies at the legal level for internal guidelines related to voting rights exercise and did not disclose detailed guidelines for each agenda item. (의결권 공시도 부실하다. 2024년 8월 금융감독원 점검에 따르면, 점검 대상 자산운용사의 96.7%가 의결권 행사·불행사 사유를 “주주권 침해 없음” 등 형식적인 문구로 채웠고, 안건명·의안 유형·대상 법인과의 관계조차 제대로 적지 않은 회사가 다수였다. 의결권 행사 관련 내부 지침도 법령 수준의 기본정책만 공시하고 안건별 세부 지침을 공개하지 않은 운용사도 40%가 넘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Hwang pointed out that there are almost no incentives to be gained even by faithfully implementing the code, while the costs for personnel, research, and legal review are significant. He assessed that ultimately, within a structure where the market cannot distinguish between code implementation and non-implementation, "the 'rational indifference' of institutional investors is solidifying." (황 연구위원은 코드를 충실히 이행해도 얻을 수 있는 인센티브는 거의 없는데, 인력·리서치·법률 검토 비용은 상당하다고 지적했다. 결국 코드 이행과 비이행을 시장이 구분하지 못하는 구조 속에서 “기관 투자자의 ‘합리적 무관심’이 굳어지고 있다”고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the forum, a suggestion was made to first 'establish a management system premised on substantial implementation from the registration stage.' It is a proposal to abolish the current system where about 50 institutions remain only in a 'planned participation' status and to allow registration only for institutions that submit specific implementation plans approved by their boards, etc. (토론회에서는 우선 ‘등록 단계부터 실질 이행을 전제로 한 관리체계’를 구축하자는 제언이 나왔다. 현재 50여개 기관이 ‘참여 예정’ 상태로만 남아있는 제도는 폐지하고, 이사회 승인 등을 거친 구체적 이행계획을 제출한 기관만 등록을 허용하자는 제안이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After code participation, opinions were presented that package-type management including regular implementation checks, disclosure, and sanctions is necessary. That is, △integrating and disclosing participating institutions' implementation reports and inspection results so investors can compare at a glance, △giving incentives to excellent implementers in the selection of entrusted managers and fee calculation by pension funds, etc., and △considering measures to exclude institutions that persistently fail to implement despite improvement requests from the list of participating institutions. (코드 참여 이후에는 정기적 이행점검과 공시, 제재까지 포함하는 패키지형 관리가 필요하다는 의견이 제시됐다. 즉 △ 참여기관의 이행보고서와 점검결과를 통합 공시해 투자자가 한눈에 비교할 수 있게 하고 △ 이행 우수 기관은 연기금 등의 위탁운용사 선정과 수수료 산정에서 인센티브를 부여하며 △개선 요구에도 미이행이 지속하는 기관은 참여기관 명단에서 제외하는 방안까지 검토해야 한다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, revision directions were suggested to expand the scope of the Stewardship Code beyond listed stocks to bonds, real estate, infrastructure, etc., and to explicitly include ESG and sustainability factors. In particular, opinions were raised to re-establish 'engagement activities' such as dialogue with companies, sending letters, public letters, shareholder proposals, and lawsuits as a core axis beyond simply voting for or against shareholder meeting agendas, and to include detailed procedures, escalation stages, and termination criteria for engagement activities in the code and guidelines. (아울러 스튜어드십 코드의 적용 범위를 상장주식 외에 채권·부동산·인프라 등으로 확대하고, 이에스지(ESG)·지속가능성 요소를 명시적으로 포함하자는 개정방향도 제시됐다. 특히 주주총회 안건 찬반을 넘어 기업과의 대화·서신 발송·공개서한·주주제안·소송 등 ‘관여활동’(engagement)을 핵심축으로 재정립하고, 관여활동 절차·격상 단계·종료 기준을 코드와 지침에 상세히 담자는 의견도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Seung-hee, a research fellow at the Economic Reform Institute, argued that "the current 'comply or explain' method uniformly applied to the seven principles should be improved to enhance effectiveness by making principles mandatory and allowing exception explanations only for some detailed guidance." (이승희 경제개혁연대 연구위원은 “현행 7대 원칙에 일괄 적용된 ‘준수 또는 설명’ 방식을 개선해, 원칙은 의무 준수, 세부 안내지침 일부에만 예외 설명을 허용하는 방식으로 실효성을 높여야 한다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussants unanimously called for strengthening the role of pension funds, especially the National Pension Service. The case of Japan's Government Pension Investment Fund (GPIF) expanding the proportion of stewardship activities in its evaluation of entrusted managers and entrusting funds to activist funds to promote engagement activities was cited as a representative benchmark. In entrusted manager management, the National Pension Service gives a 2-point bonus in selection if an institution participates in the code and prepares guidelines, but the structure of evaluating the quality and performance of actual engagement activities and reflecting them in the entrusted scale or fees is still insufficient. In contrast, Japan's GPIF includes stewardship activities as a separate item in its selection/evaluation criteria for entrusted managers, checking in detail ESG integration status, engagement methods, and voting principles. (토론자들은 한목소리로 연기금, 특히 국민연금의 역할 강화를 주문했다. 일본 국민연금(GPIF)이 위탁운용사 평가에 스튜어드십 활동 비중을 확대하고, 행동주의 펀드에도 자금을 맡겨 관여 활동을 촉진한 사례가 대표적 베치마크로 거론됐다. 위탁운용사 관리에서도 국민연금은 코드에 참여해 지침만 마련해도 선정 시 2점 가점을 부여하지만, 실제 관여 활동의 질·성과를 평가해 위탁규모나 수수료에 반영하는 구조는 아직 미흡하다. 이에 비해 일본 국민연금은 위탁사 선정·평가 기준에 스튜어드십 활동을 별도 항목으로 포함해, 이에스지 통합 여부·관여활동 방식·의결권 행사 원칙 등을 상세히 점검한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Dong-seop, head of the Fiduciary Responsibility Department at the National Pension Service Fund Management Headquarters, introduced that they are conducting fiduciary responsibility activities such as dialogue with companies, focusing on six key management issues including dividend policy, executive compensation, and legal violations. He said, "Dialogue with companies is based on the principle of confidentiality, so most of it is not disclosed externally," and did not agree with the assessment that the National Pension Service has "passively conducted fiduciary responsibility activities." However, he acknowledged that there are not a few unresolved issues, such as △the opacity of capital allocation plans after dividends, △the refusal to specifically disclose executive compensation policies, and △passive compensation and recurrence prevention measures in incidents involving controlling shareholders. (이동섭 국민연금공단 기금운용본부 수탁자책임실장은 배당정책, 임원 보수, 법령위반 등 6대 중점관리 사안을 중심으로 기업과의 대화 등 수탁자책임 활동을 수행하고 있다고 소개했다. 그는 “기업과의 대화는 비공개를 원칙으로 해서 대부분 외부에 공개되지 않았다”며 국민연금이 수탁자책임활동을 “소극적으로 행해 왔다는 평가에 동의하지 않는다”고 말했다. 하지만 그는 △배당 이후 잔여 자본배치 계획의 불투명성 △경영진 보수정책의 구체적 공개 거부 △ 지배주주가 연루된 사건에서의 소극적 손해배상·재발방지 조치 등 해결되지 않는 과제가 적지 않다고 인정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Lee Seung-hee emphasized that "the National Pension Service should strengthen the engagement activities it directly performs, such as selecting engagement targets," and "it is necessary to utilize the expertise activist funds have in corporate governance improvement by also entrusting funds to activist funds." (이승희 연구위원은 “국민연금이 관여활동 대상 선정 등 직접 수행하는 관여활동을 강화해야 한다”며 “행동주의 펀드에도 자금을 위탁해 기업지배구조 개선에서 행동주의 펀드가 가진 전문성을 활용”할 필요가 있다고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Legal and institutional risks were also pointed out as obstacles hindering the active exercise of shareholder rights. It is pointed out that the current large shareholding reporting system (5% rule) and proxy solicitation regulations under the Capital Markets Act vaguely define concepts like 'management participation' and 'joint holding,' making it difficult for institutions to engage in lawsuits, shareholder proposals, or joint actions. (법·제도 리스크 역시 적극적인 주주권 행사를 가로막는 장애물로 지목됐다. 현행 자본시장법상 주식 등 대량보유 보고 제도(5%룰) 와 의결권 대리행사 권유 규정이 ‘경영 참여’와 ‘공동보유’ 개념을 모호하게 정의하고 있어, 기관들이 소송·주주제안·연대 행동에 나서기 어렵게 만든다는 지적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Fellow Hwang said, "Uncertainty exists where even a request to appoint one outside director or jointly raising an issue about a merger that damages shareholder value could be interpreted as management participation." He added, "As violations can lead to fines, criminal penalties, and even restrictions on voting rights, it becomes an obstacle to active shareholder rights exercise." He stated, "These two systems were introduced in the early days of the capital market and do not consider the current level of capital market development and active shareholder activities," and "It is difficult to find a country (on Earth) with a system designed like this." (황 연구위원은 “사외이사 한 명 선임 요구나 주주가치를 훼손하는 합병에 대한 공동문제제기까지 경영 참여로 해석될 수 있는 불확실성이 존재한다.”라며 “위반 시 과징금·형사처벌·심지어 의결권 제한까지 가능해 적극적 주주권 행사에 장애가 된다”고 말했다. 그는 “두 제도는 자본시장 초창기 도입된 제도로 현재와 같은 자본시장 발전과 적극적 주주활동을 고려하지 못하고 있다”며 “이렇게 제도가 설계된 나라는 (지구 위에서) 찾기 어렵다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Seung-hee, research fellow at the Economic Reform Institute, introduced overseas cases, saying, "The UK effectively excludes joint voting rights exercise limited to specific shareholder meeting proposals from large holding disclosure obligations to ensure cooperative engagement activities, and Japan also revised its Financial Instruments and Exchange Act in 2024 to broadly recognize exceptions for joint engagement activities among financial institutions." He said, "Korea should also revise the 5% rule enforcement decree and legal interpretation books to exclude general governance improvement demands, dividend policy improvement demands, etc., which are not aimed at seizing management control, from rapid reporting requirements, allowing management companies and pension funds to actively negotiate with companies." (이승희 경제개혁연대 연구위원은 해외 사례를 들며 “영국은 특정 주주총회 의안에 한정된 공동 의결권 행사를 대량보유 공시의무에서 사실상 제외해 협력적 관여활동을 보장하고, 일본도 2024년 금융상품 거래법을 개정해 금융기관 간 공동 관여활동에 폭넓은 예외를 인정했다”고 소개했다. 그는 “한국도 5%룰 시행령과 법령해석집을 개정해, 경영권 장악 목적이 아닌 일반적인 지배구조 개선, 배당정책 개선 요구 등은 신속신고 대상에서 제외해 운용사와 연기금이 적극적으로 기업과 교섭하게 해야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his opening remarks, Representative Oh Ki-hyung (Chairman of the Democratic Party's KOSPI 5000 Committee) said, "Japan has revised its Stewardship Code three times since its introduction in 2014, but Korea has not touched it once since introduction," and "We must revise the code to induce more long-term investment rather than short-term trading and move towards a structure where shareholders can share in the company's innovation performance." (오기형 의원(민주당 코스피 5000 위원장)은 인삿말에서 “일본은 2014년 도입 이후 세차례나 스튜어드십 코드를 개정했지만 한국은 도입 이후 단 한번도 손질하지 않았다”며 “코드를 개정해 단타투자가 아니라 좀더 장기적 투자를 유도하고 주주들이 기업의 혁신 성과를 공유할 수 있는 구조로 가야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim Yun (Democratic Party of Korea) also emphasized, "The Stewardship Code must now move beyond the stage of asking about participation to asking about the quality of implementation." He said, "As the National Pension Service manages over 1,400 trillion won of the people's retirement assets, it is time to meticulously design an implementation check and evaluation/feedback structure so that its fiduciary responsibility activities do not stop at formality but lead to changes in corporate behavior." (김윤 의원(더불어민주당)도 “스튜어드십 코드는 이제 참여여부가 아니라 이행의 질을 묻는 단계로 넘어가야 한다”고 강조했다. 그는 “국민연금이 1400조원이 넘는 국민의 노후 자산을 운용하는 만큼, 그 수탁자책임 활동이 형식에 그치지 않고 기업 행동 변화를 이끌도록 이행점검과 평가·환류 구조를 정교하게 설계”할 때라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article and photo by Lee Bong-hyun, Research Fellow at The Hankyoreh Economic &amp; Social Research Institute &lt;a href="mailto:bhlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;bhlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (글·사진 이봉현 한겨레경제사회연구원 연구위원 &lt;a href="mailto:bhlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;bhlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/economy/finance/1241425.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0124/53_17692114886627_20260124500134.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:35:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>