<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>전체기사 : 정치 : 뉴스 : 한겨레 뉴스 - 인터넷한겨레 (Bilingual Full Text)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/rss/politics/</link><description>Hankyoreh Politics bilingual full-text RSS</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:18:09 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Choo Mi-ae says, "Death penalty for a poor youth, Yoon Suk-yeol gets a 5-year 'half-price sale'... The scales of justice are tilted" (추미애 “빈민 청년 사형, 윤석열은 5년 ‘반값 세일’…균형추 기울어”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240262.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Choo Mi-ae says, "Death penalty for a poor youth, Yoon Suk-yeol gets a 5-year 'half-price sale'... The scales of justice are tilted" (추미애 “빈민 청년 사형, 윤석열은 5년 ‘반값 세일’…균형추 기울어”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/474/imgdb/original/2026/0117/20260117500417.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;추미애 국회 법사위원장이 지난해 9월29일 국회 소통관에서 하남시 지역 현안 관련 지역주민들의 기자회견장을 보고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 17th, Representative Choo Mi-ae of the Democratic Party of Korea criticized the sentencing of former President Yoon Suk-yeol, who was indicted on charges of obstructing arrest, to five years in prison in the first trial, stating, "I lament the insensitivity of the judiciary, which shows extreme favor to Yoon Suk-yeol, the ringleader of a rebellion who tried to collapse the state," and that "the scales of justice have tilted too far." Earlier, on the 16th, the Seoul Central District Court's Criminal Division 35 (presiding judge Baek Dae-hyun) sentenced former President Yoon to five years in prison for the charge of mobilizing Presidential Security Service personnel to obstruct the execution of an arrest warrant by the Corruption Investigation Office for High-ranking Officials, stating it was "an act of essentially privatizing public servants loyal to the Republic of Korea for personal safety and private gain." (추미애 더불어민주당 의원이 체포 방해 혐의로 기소된 윤석열 전 대통령이 1심에서 징역 5년을 선고받은 것을 두고 “국가를 무너뜨리려 한 내란 우두머리 윤석열에 대해 극진한 호의를 베푸는 사법부의 무감각을 개탄한다”며 “정의의 균형추가 너무 기울었다”고 17일 비판했다. 앞서 16일 서울중앙지법 형사35부(재판장 백대현)는 윤 전 대통령이 대통령경호처 직원들을 동원해 공수처의 체포영장 집행을 방해한 혐의에 대해 “일신의 안위와 사적 이익을 위해 대한민국에 충성하는 공무원을 사실상 사병화한 행위”라며 징역 5년을 선고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a post on Facebook that day, Rep. Choo criticized the judiciary by comparing the sentencing of former President Yoon to the 1980 case of the executed 'Mudeungsan Tarzan,' Park Heung-sook. She recounted the details of the case involving Park Heung-sook, widely known as Mudeungsan Tarzan, stating, "A young man who passed the middle school entrance exam at the top of his class but had to give up attending school due to poverty, passed the high school equivalency exam, worked as a factory laborer while dreaming of preparing for the judicial exam to become a prosecutor, was executed on Christmas Eve in December 1980." Rep. Choo wrote, "Eviction notices were regularly delivered to the urban poor on the slopes of Gwangju's Mudeungsan during the cold winter, treating them like dogs, and then demolition crews stormed in. They destroyed houses and even set them on fire, burning the life-saving money hidden in the ceiling and the seeds for sowing, leaving people with nowhere to go. (Mudeungsan Tarzan Park Heung-sook), enraged, ended up killing four demolition crew members." (추 의원은 이날 페이스북에 올린 글에서 윤 전 대통령 선고와 1980년 사형된 ‘무등산 타잔’ 박흥숙씨 사건을 견주며 사법부를 비판했다. 그는 “중학교를 수석 합격하고도 가난으로 학교를 다닐 수 없어 포기하고 검정고시에 합격하고 공장노동자로 전전하다가 사법고시를 준비해 검사가 되기로 꿈꾸었던 한 청년이 1980년 12월의 크리스마스이브에 사형됐다”며 무등산 타잔으로 잘 알려진 박흥숙씨 사건의 내막을 전했다. 추 의원은 “광주 무등산 비탈의 도시 빈민에게 추운 겨울에 집 비우라고 꼬박꼬박 계고장이 날라오고 개 취급을 당하던 중 철거반원이 들이닥쳤다. 집을 부수고 불까지 질러, 오갈 데도 없는 사람들이 천장에 꽂아둔 목숨과도 같은 돈과 파종 씨앗까지 다 태워버리니 (무등산 타잔 박흥숙씨가) 격분한 나머지 철거반원 네 명을 해치고 죽인 것”이라고 적었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She then meticulously listed the charges against 'defendant Yoon Suk-yeol.' Rep. Choo wrote, "Prosecutor Yoon Suk-yeol, who passed the bar exam on his ninth attempt, highly praised dictators Syngman Rhee and Chun Doo-hwan, and after seizing power, he dreamt of emergency powers, and on December 3, 2024, mobilized armed forces to stage a rebellion, leading to his impeachment by the National Assembly within two weeks. However, he holed up in the official residence, refused an arrest warrant issued by the court, used the Presidential Security Service as his private army, ordering armed responses by saying 'show them the guns,' 'can't we shoot,' and even suggested intimidating with missiles." She further reflected, "He had senior security service officials erect barbed wire and use water cannons to block access to the residence, pitting state agencies that should enforce and uphold the law against each other, creating a dangerous situation. A tragedy leading to mass casualties could have occurred." (이어 그는 ‘피고인 윤석열’의 죄목을 조목조목 따졌다. 추 의원은 “9수의 사시 합격 검사 윤석열은 독재자 이승만과 전두환을 높이 평가하다가 권력을 잡고 호시탐탐 비상대권을 꿈꾸던 중 2024년 12월3일 무장 군을 동원해 내란을 일으키고 2주 만에 국회 탄핵을 당했다. 그러나 그는 관저에서 버티면서 법원이 발부한 체포영장을 거부하고 경호처를 사병으로 부리며 ‘총을 보여줘라’, ‘쏠 수는 없나’라고 하며 무력 대응을 지시하고 심지어 미사일로 겁을 주라고도 했다”고 적었다. 이어 “경호처 간부들로 하여금 철조망을 두르고 살수차로 관저 접근을 차단하려 하는 등 법을 집행하고 지켜야 하는 국가 기관끼리 대립하게 해 위험하게 만들었다. 하마터면 대량 살상으로 이어지는 참극이 발생할 수 있었다”고 돌아봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Choo stated, "Yet, he received a feather-light sentence on the grounds of being a first-time offender and his age. For the poor youth who was treated like a dog and abandoned by the state, the state even deprived him of his life," juxtaposing the judiciary's judgment on Park Heung-sook and former President Yoon. Rep. Choo lamented, "(The court) imposed the death penalty on a young first-time offender who never got to unfold his dreams, while for the cunning self-proclaimed fool who became president and acted on vain desires, it handed down a 'half-price sale' sentence, a discount on the special prosecutor's indictment recommendation." (추 의원은 “그런데도 그는 초범과 나이를 이유로 깃털처럼 가벼운 형을 받았다. 국가로부터 개 취급당하며 버림받았던 빈민 청년에 대해서는 그 생명마저도 국가가 박탈했다”며 박흥숙씨와 윤 전 대통령에 대한 사법부의 판단을 나란히 세웠다. 추 의원은 “(법원이) 꿈을 펼쳐보지도 못한 청년 초범에는 사형을, 대통령이 돼 헛된 욕망을 부린, 노회한 자칭 바보는 특검의 에누리 구형에다가 반값 세일 선고형을 내렸다”고 개탄했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Eom Ji-won &lt;a href="mailto:umkija@hani.co.kr"&gt;umkija@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (엄지원 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:umkija@hani.co.kr"&gt;umkija@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240262.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/474/imgdb/original/2026/0117/20260117500417.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination for Sale"... People Power Party Spokesperson's Remarks Pour 'Cold Water' on Jang Dong-hyuk and Lee Jun-seok's Cooperation (“개혁신당 40억 공천팔이”…국힘 대변인, 장동혁·이준석 공조에 ‘찬물’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/assembly/1240265.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination for Sale"... People Power Party Spokesperson's Remarks Pour 'Cold Water' on Jang Dong-hyuk and Lee Jun-seok's Cooperation (“개혁신당 40억 공천팔이”…국힘 대변인, 장동혁·이준석 공조에 ‘찬물’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/360/imgdb/original/2026/0117/20260117500467.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국민의힘 장동혁 대표와 개혁신당 이준석 대표가 13일 국회 국민의힘 당대표 회의실에서 만나 악수하고 있다. 김경호 선임기자 jijae@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the People Power Party and the Reform Party have begun cooperating on matters such as introducing a special counsel investigation into allegations surrounding the ruling party's acceptance of Unification Church and nomination funds, a sharp war of nerves has already erupted due to a People Power Party spokesperson's remarks about the "Reform Party's 4 billion won nomination for sale." (국민의힘과 개혁신당이 여당의 통일교·공천헌금 수수 의혹에 대한 쌍특검 도입 등으로 공조에 나섰지만, 국민의힘 대변인의 ‘개혁신당 40억원 공천팔이’ 발언으로 벌써부터 날선 신경전을 벌이고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeong Yi-han, spokesperson for the Reform Party, criticized the remarks in a commentary on the 17th, stating, "This is a serious juncture where the leadership of both parties should be pooling their strength to push through the special counsel investigations into the Unification Church and the money-for-nomination allegations involving lawmakers Kang Sun-woo and Kim Byeong-gi." He added, "In such a situation, the People Power Party spokesperson's attack on the opposing party with baseless slander is an irresponsible act that undermines the very trust needed for cooperation." This criticism came in response to People Power Party spokesperson Lee Jae-neung's appearance on a YouTube broadcast on the 16th, where he said, "The Reform Party is currently selling nominations for 4 billion won. All 4,000 (candidates) are victims," and added, "Since they won't get elected anyway, making them run the full course is just exploiting them, which is pitiful." (정이한 개혁신당 대변인은 17일 논평을 내어 “지금은 양당 지도부가 통일교 특검과 강선우·김병기 의원의 돈 공천 특검 관철을 위해 힘을 모으는 엄중한 국면”이라며 “이런 상황에서 국민의힘 대변인이 근거 없는 비방으로 상대 정당을 공격한 것은 공조의 신뢰를 스스로 허무는 무책임한 행동”이라고 비판했다. 앞서 16일 이재능 국민의힘 대변인이 유튜브 방송에 출연해 “개혁신당이 지금 40억원 공천팔이를 하고 있다. (출마할) 4000명이 다 피해자”라며 “어차피 당선이 안 되는 건데 완주시킨다는 건 그들이 이용당하는 꼴밖에 안 되니 불쌍하더라”고 말한 데 대한 비판이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The "4 billion won nomination for sale" appears to refer to the estimated election costs assuming the Reform Party fields 4,000 candidates in the June 3 local elections. Previously, Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok had pledged to make it possible to run for local elections, for basic-level councilor positions, with campaign funds as low as 990,000 won. Spokesperson Jeong urged the People Power Party leadership, "Will you stand by while a spokesperson's remarks, made without even verifying basic facts, are shaking the framework of cooperative governance?" and called for measures such as spokesperson Lee Jae-neung's resignation. (‘40억원 공천팔이’는 6·3 지방선거에서 개혁신당이 4000명의 출마자를 낼 경우를 가정한 선거비용을 가리킨 것으로 보인다. 앞서 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 지방선거 출마 시 기초의원 기준으로 99만원으로도 선거 운동이 가능하게 하겠다고 공약한 바 있다. 정 대변인은 국민의힘 지도부를 향해 “기초적 사실관계조차 확인하지 않은 대변인의 발언이 협치의 틀을 흔들고 있는데 이를 방치할 것이냐”며 이재능 대변인의 사퇴 등을 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, spokesperson Lee promptly posted an apology to address the conflict. In a post on Facebook that afternoon, he stated, "In a recent broadcast, I used incorrect expressions regarding the Reform Party's nomination process, such as '4 billion won nomination sale,' '4,000 victims,' and 'exploiting/threatening youth.' Those remarks were excessive expressions stemming from my own misunderstanding, and all my related statements were wrong." He then apologized, saying, "As a spokesperson for a public party, I should have been more cautious without sufficiently verifying the facts." (이에 이 대변인은 바로 사과문을 올려 갈등 봉합에 나섰다. 이 대변인은 이날 오후 페이스북에 글을 올려 “저는 최근 방송에서 개혁신당의 공천 과정과 관련해 ‘40억 공천판매’, ‘4천명의 피해자’, ‘청년을 이용한 협박’이라는 잘못된 표현을 사용한 바 있다. 해당 발언은 저의 잘못된 이해에서 비롯된 과도한 표현이었으며, 관련한 저의 ‘모든 발언’은 틀렸다”고 밝혔다. 이어 그는 “사실관계를 충분히 확인하지 않은 상태에서 공당의 대변인으로서 보다 신중했어야 했다”며 사과했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Eom Ji-won &lt;a href="mailto:umkija@hani.co.kr"&gt;umkija@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (엄지원 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:umkija@hani.co.kr"&gt;umkija@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/assembly/1240265.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/360/imgdb/original/2026/0117/20260117500467.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Subtracting Lee Jun-seok, Subtracting Han Dong-hoon, Subtracting Oh Se-hoon... The End of Subtraction Politics is the 'Yoon Again Party' (이준석 빼고 한동훈 빼고 오세훈 빼고…뺄셈 정치 결말은 ‘윤 어게인 당’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240274.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Subtracting Lee Jun-seok, Subtracting Han Dong-hoon, Subtracting Oh Se-hoon... The End of Subtraction Politics is the 'Yoon Again Party' (이준석 빼고 한동훈 빼고 오세훈 빼고…뺄셈 정치 결말은 ‘윤 어게인 당’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686942554542_5417686942407536.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;2차 종합특검법 처리에 반대해 단식중인 국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 1월17일 국회에서 단식을 이어가던 중 손을 머리에 올리고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, there were unusually many major news stories. There was a summit between President Lee Jae-myung and Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi. In the trial of former President Yoon Suk-yeol for leading an insurrection, the death penalty was sought. In the first trial for obstruction of arrest, a five-year prison sentence was handed down. The ruling party also had many negative issues, such as the election of Han Byung-do as the Democratic Party's floor leader, the expulsion of former floor leader Kim Byung-ki, and the controversy over candidate for Planning and Budget Minister Lee Hye-hoon, but they were hardly newsworthy enough to present a business card. (지난주에는 유난히 큰 뉴스가 많았습니다. 이재명 대통령과 다카이치 사나에 일본 총리의 정상회담이 열렸습니다. 윤석열 전 대통령 내란 우두머리 재판에서 사형이 구형됐습니다. 체포 방해 1심 재판에서 징역 5년이 선고됐습니다. 민주당 한병도 원내대표 선출, 김병기 전 원내대표 제명, 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 논란 등 여권 발 악재도 많았지만 뉴스라고 명함을 내밀 수 없을 지경이었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a mega news story that made all these other news stories look shabby. It was the news that the People Power Party's Central Ethics Committee decided in the early hours of the 14th to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon. Democratic Party lawmaker Lee Ki-heon posted this on Facebook on the morning of the 14th. (이 모든 뉴스를 모두 초라하게 만들어버린 초대형 뉴스가 있었습니다. 국민의힘 중앙윤리위원회가 14일 새벽 한동훈 전 대표 제명을 결정했다는 소식이었습니다. 이기헌 민주당 의원이 14일 아침 페이스북에 이런 글을 올렸습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"I went to bed late last night after hearing about the death penalty being sought for Yoon Suk-yeol, and when I woke up in the morning, Han Dong-hoon's political life was over." (“늦은 저녁 윤석열의 사형 구형을 듣고 잠자리에 들었는데 아침에 일어나 보니 한동훈의 정치 생명이 끝났다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was also shocked. The expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon was somewhat predictable. However, I never expected it to be decided and announced so abruptly, right after the death penalty was sought for former President Yoon Suk-yeol, and in the middle of the night. I strongly suspect that Central Ethics Committee Chairman Yoon Min-woo rushed out the expulsion decision to dilute the negative news for the People Power Party, which was the death penalty being sought for former President Yoon Suk-yeol. (저도 깜짝 놀랐습니다. 한동훈 전 대표 제명은 어느 정도 예측된 일이었습니다. 하지만 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형 직후에, 그것도 한밤중에 전격적으로 결정해서 발표하리라고는 전혀 예상하지 못했습니다. 윤민우 중앙윤리위원장이 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형이라는 국민의힘 악재를 희석하기 위해서 제명 결정을 서둘러 내놓은 것 같다는 의심이 강하게 듭니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The media also seemed quite surprised. All newspapers simultaneously published editorials criticizing the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon. I'll introduce only a few. (언론도 상당히 놀란 것 같습니다. 모든 신문이 일제히 한동훈 전 대표 제명을 비판하는 사설을 실었습니다. 일부만 소개하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Late-night decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon, a further plummeting People Power Party" (Munhwa) (“심야에 한동훈 전 대표 제명 의결, 더 추락하는 국민의힘”(문화))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Han Dong-hoon's late-night expulsion... The PPP's 'subtraction politics' is nothing but a long silence" (Seoul) (“한동훈 심야 제명…국힘 ‘뺄셈 정치’ 유구무언일 뿐”(서울))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The PPP's expulsion of Han Dong-hoon is self-harm and subtraction politics that is hard to accept" (Segye) (“국힘 한동훈 제명, 납득 어려운 자해·뺄셈 정치다”(세계))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Expelling Han Dong-hoon late at night, calling it 'terror' and 'mafia,' is not normal" (Chosun) (“심야에 ‘테러’ ‘마피아’라며 한동훈 제명, 정상 아니다”(조선))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The subtraction politics of the conservative opposition revealed by the Han Dong-hoon expulsion incident" (JoongAng) (“한동훈 제명 사태로 드러난 보수 야당의 뺄셈 정치”(중앙))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have rarely seen a case where all newspapers simultaneously criticized an internal party matter in editorials like this. The media seems to perceive this incident not as a crisis for the People Power Party, but as a crisis for the entire conservative camp and for South Korean democracy. (정당 내부 사안에 대해 이처럼 모든 신문이 일제히 사설로 비판하는 경우를 저는 거의 보지 못했습니다. 언론은 이번 사태를 국민의힘의 위기가 아니라 보수 세력 전체의 위기, 대한민국 민주주의의 위기로 인식하는 것 같습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps frightened by the media's strong criticism? Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok on the 15th suspended the resolution on the expulsion motion for former leader Han Dong-hoon and suddenly began a hunger strike. The stated reason for the hunger strike was to publicize the unfairness of the 'second comprehensive special prosecutor' being pushed by the Democratic Party. However, in reality, it seems the purpose was to divert attention from the controversy over former leader Han Dong-hoon's expulsion to an external issue. Lawmaker Bae Hyeon-jin urged him to stop the hunger strike on the 17th, saying, "A solitary hunger strike, started without even gathering party consensus, avoiding the correct answer of withdrawing the disciplinary action, will only invite ridicule from Lee Jae-myung and the Democratic Party. There is nothing to gain from the party's leader starving to death at this point." (언론의 강한 비판에 겁을 먹었을까요? 장동혁 대표는 15일 한동훈 전 대표 제명안 의결을 보류하고 갑자기 단식을 시작했습니다. 민주당이 추진하는 ‘2차 종합특검’의 부당함을 알리겠다는 것이 단식의 명분이었습니다. 그러나 사실은 한동훈 전 대표 제명 논란에 쏠리는 시선을 외부로 돌리려는 목적인 것 같습니다. 배현진 의원은 17일 “징계 철회라는 정답을 피해 가려 당내 동의도 모으지 못한 채 시작한 홀로 단식은 이재명과 민주당의 조소만 살뿐이다. 우리 당의 가장이 굶어 죽어 얻을 것이 아무것도 없는 시점이다”라며 단식 중단을 촉구했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chosun Ilbo published an editorial in its January 16th edition titled "Whatever the PPP's new party name is, isn't its essence the 'Yoon Again Party'?" The title was so intense that I checked which newspaper it was again and read the content. (조선일보는 1월16일 치 신문에 “국힘 새 당명 뭐로 하든 본질은 ‘윤 어게인 당’ 아닌가”라는 제목의 사설을 실었습니다. 제목이 하도 강렬해서 어느 신문인지 다시 한 번 확인하고 내용을 읽었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Currently, Leader Jang is surrounded by people from former President Yoon Suk-yeol's side. He appointed a person who opposed the impeachment of former President Yoon as an appointed Supreme Council member, and entrusted the party communication committee chairmanship to a Supreme Council member who defended martial law as the 'Gwacheon Landing Operation.' Former President Yoon's speech secretary is the party's message office head, and a person who claimed 'On December 3rd, we awoke' was appointed as media spokesperson. The party ethics committee chairman who disciplined former leader Han is the person who claimed that 'Gae-ddal's love for Lee Jae-myung is linked to jealousy of Kim Keon-hee.' There is also widespread talk that Leader Jang is captured by YouTubers advocating 'Yoon Again.' (“지금 장 대표는 윤석열 전 대통령 측 사람들에 둘러싸여 있다. 윤 전 대통령 탄핵에 반대했던 인사를 지명직 최고위원에 앉히고, 계엄을 ‘과천 상륙작전’이라며 옹호한 최고위원에게 당 소통위원장을 맡겼다. 윤 전 대통령의 연설문 담당 비서관은 당 메시지실장으로, ‘12월3일 우리는 깨어났다’고 주장한 사람은 미디어 대변인에 기용했다. 한 전 대표를 징계한 당 윤리위원장은 ‘개딸의 이재명 사랑은 김건희 여사에 대한 질투와 연동되어 있다’고 주장했던 사람이다. 장 대표가 ‘윤 어게인’을 주장하는 유튜버들에 포획돼 있다는 얘기도 파다하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the leader's surroundings, the party seems not like the People Power Party but like a 'Yoon Again' gathering. The PPP is said to be soliciting a new party name. Whatever they change the party name to, its essence will be the 'Yoon Again Party.' If they think the public won't know this essence, they are mistaken." (대표 주변을 보면 당이 국민의힘이 아니라 ‘윤 어게인’ 모임처럼 보인다. 국힘이 새 당명을 공모한다고 한다. 당명을 무엇으로 바꾸든 그 본질은 ‘윤 어게인 당’일 것이다. 이 본질을 국민이 모를 것으로 생각한다면 오산이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do you think? I believe the Chosun Ilbo editorial is 100% correct. Although the Chosun Ilbo published an editorial in its January 17th edition titled "Han Dong-hoon also bears significant responsibility for the decline and degeneration of the main opposition party," it is certainly much more critical of Leader Jang Dong-hyeok. (어떻습니까? 저는 조선일보 사설이 100% 옳다고 생각합니다. 조선일보는 17일 치에 “제1야당 몰락과 변질엔 한동훈 책임도 크다”라는 제목의 사설을 실었지만, 장동혁 대표에게 훨씬 더 비판적인 것은 확실합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But why on earth is Leader Jang Dong-hyeok acting like this? Last week, citing the words of a senior People Power Party lawmaker from behind the political scenes, I analyzed that "the fear of being unable to get down after climbing onto the back of the tiger that is the hardcore 'Yoon Again' supporters has seized Leader Jang Dong-hyeok." I analyzed that the PPP's hardcore supporters do not read newspapers, are addicted to fake news produced by far-right YouTubers, and are turning their backs on the formula for conservative party election victory, which is expansion to the center. (그런데 장동혁 대표는 도대체 왜 이러는 걸까요? 저는 지난주 정치 막전막후에서 국민의힘 중진 의원의 말을 인용해 “윤 어게인 강성 지지층이라는 호랑이 등에 올라타서 내려오지 못하고 있는 공포감이 장동혁 대표를 사로잡고 있다”고 분석했습니다. 국민의힘 강성 지지층은 신문을 읽지 않고 극우 유튜버들이 생산하는 가짜 뉴스에 중독돼 중도 확장이라는 보수 정당 선거 승리 공식을 외면하고 있다고 분석했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A People Power Party supporter sent me a protest email about my article. The expression was somewhat intense and rough, but summarizing it, the content was roughly this: (어느 국민의힘 지지자가 제 기사에 항의하는 이메일을 보내왔습니다. 표현이 좀 격하고 거칠지만 정리하면 대략 이런 내용입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"During Hwang Kyo-ahn's leadership, the conservative media (JoongAng, Chosun, DongA) kept harping on about the center. We succumbed to that and accepted the entire Bareunmirae Party. We suffered a crushing defeat in the election. When Han Dong-hoon was emergency committee chairman, he said he would capture the center and massively recruited lawmakers ousted from the Democratic Party. The hardcore supporters rebelled and didn't go to the polls, leading to another crushing defeat." (“황교안 대표 때 조중동에서 중도 타령을 해댔다. 거기에 굴복해서 바른미래당을 다 받아줬다. 선거에서 참패했다. 한동훈 비대위원장 때 중도를 잡는다고 민주당에서 밀려난 의원들을 대거 영입했다. 이에 반발한 집토끼들이 투표장에 나가지 않아서 또 참패했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Traitors must be driven out. Leftist figures should not be recruited. Just as the Democratic Party changed to pure-blooded pro-Moon, the People Power Party must also change. We should not accept all sorts of riffraff under the guise of the center. Even if Leader Jang Dong-hyeok loses the local elections, we will make him leader again." (“배신자는 쫓아내야 한다. 좌파 인사는 영입하면 안 된다. 민주당이 순혈 친명으로 바뀐 것처럼 국민의힘도 바뀌어야 한다. 중도랍시고 어중이떠중이 받아들이면 안 된다. 장동혁 대표가 설사 지방선거에서 져도 우리가 다시 대표로 만들 것이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Through this person's writing, I understood a bit more clearly why the PPP's hardcore supporters dislike former leader Han Dong-hoon so much and blindly support Leader Jang Dong-hyeok. (어떻습니까? 저는 이분의 글을 통해서 국민의힘 강성 지지층이 왜 한동훈 전 대표를 그렇게 싫어하고 장동혁 대표를 맹목적으로 지지하는지 조금 더 명확하게 알게 됐습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Far-right YouTuber Go Seong-guk recently said, "Opportunists, after Han Dong-hoon, next is Oh Se-hoon," arguing that Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon should be driven out of the People Power Party. Mr. Go's argument accurately represents the sentiment of the PPP's hardcore supporters. (극우 유튜버 고성국 씨가 최근 “기회주의자들, 한동훈 다음은 오세훈”이라며 오세훈 서울시장을 국민의힘에서 쫓아내야 한다고 했습니다. 고성국 씨의 주장은 국민의힘 강성 지지층의 정서를 정확히 대변하는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the PPP's hardcore supporters, there are quite a few who say, "Na Kyung-won should run for Seoul Mayor. Oh Se-hoon is not acceptable. If Oh Se-hoon and Jeong Won-o face off, I'd rather vote for Jeong Won-o." Regarding the Gyeonggi Governor race, the argument is spreading that "Even if it means losing to the Democratic Party, Ahn Cheol-soo is not acceptable." It's the 'Oh Se-hoon unacceptable theory' and the 'Ahn Cheol-soo unacceptable theory.' (국민의힘 강성 지지자 중에는 “서울시장은 나경원이 출마해야 한다. 오세훈은 안 된다. 오세훈과 정원오가 붙으면 차라리 정원오를 찍겠다”는 사람들이 꽤 있습니다. 경기지사도 “민주당에 지는 한이 있어도 안철수는 안 된다”는 주장이 퍼지고 있습니다. ‘오세훈 불가론’, ‘안철수 불가론’입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Isn't it strange? Why do the PPP's hardcore supporters hate Han Dong-hoon, Oh Se-hoon, and Ahn Cheol-soo more than President Lee Jae-myung and the Democratic Party? What is the reason for falling into irrational thinking and extreme sentiment? (신기하지요? 국민의힘 강성 지지층은 왜 이재명 대통령과 민주당보다 한동훈 오세훈 안철수를 더 미워할까요? 비상식적 사고와 극단적 정서에 빠진 이유가 뭘까요?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, humans are inherently like that. The PPP's hardcore supporters are not aliens. Let's examine them one by one. (사실은 인간이 본래 그렇습니다. 국민의힘 강성 지지자들은 외계인이 아닙니다. 하나씩 따져보겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, hatred. Hatred is humanity's most primitive emotion. Humans have never existed as individuals with free will. Belonging to a tribe and group is what defines humans. Feeling hatred and fear towards other tribes is human nature. (첫째, 증오입니다. 증오는 인간의 가장 원초적 감정입니다. 인간은 자유 의지를 가진 개인으로 존재한 적이 없었습니다. 부족과 집단에 속한 것이 인간입니다. 다른 부족에는 증오와 공포를 느끼는 것이 인간의 본성입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, jealousy. Humans can endure losing to someone who belongs to a completely different side, but find it difficult to endure losing to a competitor within the same side. This is why civil wars within the same country or ethnic group are much more brutal than wars with other countries or ethnic groups. (둘째, 질투입니다. 인간은 아예 다른 편에 속한 사람에게 지는 것은 견딜 수 있어도, 같은 편 안의 경쟁자에게 지는 것은 견디기 어렵습니다. 다른 나라나 민족과의 전쟁보다 같은 국가와 민족 안에서 벌어지는 내전이 훨씬 더 잔혹한 이유입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third, projection. In psychology, projection refers to a defense mechanism where one attributes one's own unacceptable feelings, thoughts, or attitudes to others. The PPP's hardcore supporters, while disliking Han Dong-hoon themselves, are projecting that Han Dong-hoon dislikes them. (셋째, 투사입니다. 투사는 심리학에서 자신의 받아들일 수 없는 감정·생각·태도를 다른 사람에게 전가하는 방어기제를 의미합니다. 국민의힘 강성 지지층은 자신들이 한동훈을 싫어하면서 한동훈이 자신들을 싫어한다고 뒤집어씌우고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To escape these primitive human instincts of hatred, jealousy, and projection, the PPP leadership, including Leader Jang Dong-hyeok, needs persuasive leadership to make the hardcore supporters understand the necessity of expanding to the center. However, it seems difficult to expect such leadership from the PPP leadership. Because they are not leaders, but followers who simply go along with the will of the hardcore supporters. (이처럼 인간의 원초적 본능인 증오·질투·투사에서 벗어나기 위해서는 장동혁 대표를 비롯한 국민의힘 지도부가 강성 지지층에 중도 확장의 필요성을 이해시키는 설득의 리더십이 필요합니다. 그러나 국민의힘 지도부에 그런 리더십을 기대하기는 어려울 것 같습니다. 그들은 리더들이 아니라 강성 지지층의 뜻을 그냥 따라가는 팔로워들이기 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phenomenon now occurring in the People Power Party has also appeared in the Democratic Party. After losing the 2022 presidential election, the hardcore supporters of candidate Lee Jae-myung blamed former Prime Minister Lee Nak-yeon and non-Lee Jae-myung faction politicians for the election defeat. The so-called watermelon debate. The watermelon debate led to the 'non-pro-Moon candidate massacre' nomination controversy in the 2024 general election, leaving significant scars on the Democratic Party. (지금 국민의힘에서 벌어지는 현상은 민주당에서도 나타난 일이 있습니다. 2022년 대선에서 패배한 뒤 이재명 후보를 지지하는 강성 지지층은 대선 패배의 책임을 이낙연 전 국무총리와 비 이재명계 정치인들에게 돌렸습니다. 이른바 수박 논쟁입니다. 수박 논쟁은 2024년 총선에서 ‘비명횡사’ 공천 논란으로 이어졌고 민주당에 적잖은 상처를 남겼습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This subtraction politics in the People Power Party also seems likely to grow increasingly intense within the conservative camp and the PPP, eventually leading to nomination turmoil for the June 3 local elections. The peak will be the Seoul Mayor primary. What if, as the hardcore supporters hope, lawmaker Na Kyung-won defeats Mayor Oh Se-hoon and advances to the main election? I'll leave it to your imagination. (국민의힘의 이번 뺄셈 정치도 보수 세력과 국민의힘 안에서 점점 더 격렬해지다가 결국 6·3 지방선거 공천 파동으로 이어질 가능성이 커 보입니다. 정점은 서울시장 후보 경선이 될 것입니다. 만약 강성 지지층의 희망대로 나경원 의원이 오세훈 시장을 누르고 본선에 나가면 어떻게 될까요? 여러분의 상상에 맡기겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 2024 general election, despite the Democratic Party's nomination conflicts, President Yoon Suk-yeol caused bigger incidents like 'green onion prices' and 'fleeing ambassador,' presenting victory to the Democratic Party. In the 2026 local elections, will President Lee Jae-myung cause a major scandal to help the People Power Party? That doesn't seem likely. (2024년 총선에서 민주당 공천 갈등에도 불구하고 윤석열 대통령은 ‘대파 가격’ ‘도주 대사’ 등 더 큰 사건을 일으켜서 민주당에 승리를 헌납했습니다. 2026년 지방선거에서는 이재명 대통령이 큰 사고를 쳐서 국민의힘을 도와줄까요? 그럴 것 같지 않습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude. The People Power Party won the 2022 presidential election with addition politics, recruiting then-Prosecutor General Yoon Suk-yeol from the Moon Jae-in administration and bringing in Kim Jong-in and Ahn Cheol-soo. However, after the election, President Yoon Suk-yeol dropped Yoo Seung-min in the Gyeonggi Governor primary, drove out leader Lee Jun-seok, and even declared a state of emergency to try to remove leader Han Dong-hoon. (마무리하겠습니다. 국민의힘은 문재인 정부 검찰총장이었던 윤석열 검사를 후보로 영입하고 김종인, 안철수를 끌어들이는 덧셈 정치로 2022년 대선을 이겼습니다. 그런데 윤석열 대통령은 대선 이후 경기지사 후보 경선에서 유승민을 떨어뜨렸고, 이준석 대표를 쫓아냈습니다. 한동훈 대표를 제거하려고 비상계엄까지 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, the 'Yoon Again' forces united around Leader Jang Dong-hyeok are trying to drive out Han Dong-hoon, drive out Oh Se-hoon, and drive out Ahn Cheol-soo. Where is the final destination of this endless subtraction politics? (이제 장동혁 대표를 중심으로 뭉친 ‘윤 어게인’ 세력은 한동훈을 쫓아내고 오세훈을 쫓아내고 안철수를 쫓아내려 하고 있습니다. 끝없는 뺄셈 정치의 종착역은 어디일까요?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the end, will only the 'Yoon Again' forces remain in the People Power Party, and will the entire conservative camp head down the path of decline? How much possibility remains for the People Power Party to turn back to center expansion and a grand conservative alliance? What do you think? (결국 국민의힘에는 ‘윤 어게인’ 세력만 남고, 보수 세력 전체가 몰락의 길로 가는 것은 아닐까요? 국민의힘이 중도 확장과 보수 대연합으로 돌아설 가능성이 얼마나 남아 있을까요? 여러분은 어떻게 생각하십니까?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Political Correspondent &lt;a href="mailto:shy99@hani.co.kr"&gt;shy99@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (정치부 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:shy99@hani.co.kr"&gt;shy99@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240274.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686942554542_5417686942407536.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoo Byung-ho's 'Tiger Faction' Still Strong at Board of Audit and Inspection... Limits to Reform, Internal Harmony Remains Distant (유병호의 ‘타이거파’ 건재한 감사원…쇄신은 한계, 내부 화합은 멀기만)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240280.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Yoo Byung-ho's 'Tiger Faction' Still Strong at Board of Audit and Inspection... Limits to Reform, Internal Harmony Remains Distant (유병호의 ‘타이거파’ 건재한 감사원…쇄신은 한계, 내부 화합은 멀기만)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/723/434/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686968719867_20260118500465.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;유병호 감사위원(가운데)이 2일 서울 종로구 감사원에서 열린 김호철 신임 감사원장(오른쪽) 취임식에서 인사를 마친 뒤 돌아서고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Ho-cheol, who was inaugurated as the new Chairman of the Board of Audit and Inspection (BAI) on the 2nd, has been emphasizing "settlement-type harmony." His goal is to resolve the past of the BAI, which was torn apart by factional politics under the system of former Secretary-General Yoo Byung-ho (now a standing commissioner), and to integrate the divided organization. However, there remains an assessment that personnel reform regarding those who led political and targeted audits during the previous administration and benefited from personnel appointments as a result has been insufficient. (지난 2일 취임한 김호철 감사원장은 “청산형 화합”을 강조하고 있다. 유병호 전 사무총장(현 감사위원) 체제에서 파벌 정치로 찢긴 감사원의 과거를 청산하고 분열됐던 내부를 통합하겠다는 것이다. 하지만 지난 정부 시절 정치·표적감사에 앞장서고, 그로 인해 인사 혜택을 본 이들에 대한 인적쇄신은 미진하다는 평가가 여전히 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Hankyoreh's comprehensive reporting on the 18th, Chairman Kim Ho-cheol, during a New Year's special lecture for BAI employees on the 7th, stated, "We will pursue settlement-type harmony. Harmony without settling the past is a falsehood, and settlement without harmony is violence." He also revealed a firm will to address factional politics within the BAI, saying, "Factions are not to be eliminated, but to be resolved." (18일 한겨레 취재를 종합하면, 김호철 원장은 지난 7일 감사원 직원들을 상대로 신년 특강을 하면서 “청산형 화합을 하겠다. 과거에 대한 청산 없이 화합을 하겠다는 것도 허구고, 화합하지 않고 청산만 하겠다는 것도 폭력이다”라고 말했다. 또 “파벌은 제거하는 것이 아니라 해소하는 것”이라며 감사원 내 파벌 정치에 대해 단호한 대처 의지를 드러냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;BAI Shouts "Reform"... Regarding Presidential Office Relocation Audit, Concludes "It Was Not a Lenient Audit" (“쇄신” 외친 감사원…관저 이전 “봐주기 감사 아니었다”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="color:#333333"&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span style="color:#333333"&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI's reform efforts did not begin after Chairman Kim's inauguration. After new Secretary-General Jung Sang-woo took office last September, the BAI established an 'Operational Reform Task Force (TF).' The TF identified illegal and improper acts, such as filing complaints against seven individuals, including Commissioner Yoo Byung-ho and former BAI Chairman Choi Jae-hae, on charges of leaking military secrets related to audits of the West Sea public official killing incident and the inadequate verification of North Korean GP (Guard Post) incapacitation. Commissioner Yoo was additionally accused of abuse of audit and personnel authority. A BAI auditor, Mr. G, assessed, "There is an aspect that by addressing the issues once before the new chairman took office, it helped reduce the burden on the organization for a fresh start." (감사원이 쇄신 노력이 김 원장 취임 뒤에 시작된 건 아니다. 지난해 9월 정상우 신임 사무총장이 취임한 뒤 감사원은 ‘운영 쇄신 티에프(TF)’를 만들었다. 티에프는 유병호 위원과 최재해 전 감사원장 등 7명을 서해 공무원 피살 사건 감사와 북한 지피(GP·감시초소) 불능화 부실검증 관련 감사에 대한 군사기밀 누설 혐의로 고발하는 등 위법·부당 행위를 확인했다. 유 위원은 감찰·인사권 남용으로도 추가 고발됐다. 감사관 ㄱ씨는 “새 원장 취임 전 문제를 한번 짚고 감으로써 조직의 새 출발 부담을 덜어준 측면이 있다”고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the limitations of the TF were clear. A BAI auditor, Mr. N, said, "The TF was supposed to uncover the abuses of power during Commissioner Yoo's tenure as Secretary-General, but among its members were quite a few auditors who were part of or close to the 'Tiger Faction.' It's questionable whether they could have conducted a proper investigation." For their part, Commissioner Yoo and Standing Commissioner Kim Young-shin resisted the TF's activities and refused to cooperate with the investigation at all. Instead, they submitted rebuttals to the TF's findings through the BAI's internal bulletin board and the media. (그러나 티에프의 한계는 뚜렷했다. 감사관 ㄴ씨는 “티에프는 유 위원의 사무총장 시절 전횡을 밝혀야 하는데, 구성원 중에 ‘타이거파’이거나 거기에 가까운 감사관들이 꽤 섞여 있었다. 이들이 제대로 조사를 할 수 있었을지 의문이 든다”고 했다. 유 위원이나 김영신 감사위원 등은 그들대로 티에프 활동에 반발해 조사에 일절 응하지 않았다. 대신 감사원 내부 게시판과 언론을 통해 티에프 조사 결과에 반박자료를 냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the statistical audit (suspicions of real estate statistics manipulation during the Moon Jae-in administration) examined by the TF, although circumstances suggesting the BAI conducted coercive audits are emerging in the trial of the statistics manipulation case, the TF was unable to hold the auditors at the time accountable, citing reasons such as "some subjects refused interviews." The TF also examined whether the department responsible for auditing the relocation process of President Yoon Suk Yeol's office conducted a lenient audit favoring the administration, but it was confirmed that it concluded "it was not a lenient audit." The BAI released the results of the presidential office relocation audit in September 2024, after about two years, but it failed to uncover the illegality of the relocation or whether First Lady Kim Keon-hee was involved, leading to criticism that it was a lenient audit. The responsible auditors became subjects of investigation by the special counsel team investigating Kim Keon-hee. (티에프가 점검했던 통계감사(문재인 정부 시절 부동산 통계 조작 의혹)의 경우, 통계 조작 사건 재판에서 감사원이 강압 감사를 했던 정황들이 나오고 있지만, 티에프는 “일부 대상자들이 면담을 거부했다”는 등의 이유로 당시 감사관들의 책임을 묻지 못했다. 티에프는 윤석열 대통령실의 관저 이전 과정을 감사했던 담당 부서가 정권 봐주기식 감사를 한 건 아닌지도 살폈지만, “봐주기 감사는 아니었다”는 결론을 내린 것으로도 확인됐다. 감사원은 지난 2024년 9월, 2년여만에 관저 이전 감사 결과를 내놨지만 관저 이전의 불법성과 김건희 여사의 개입 여부 등은 밝혀내지 못해 봐주기 감사를 했다는 비판을 받았고, 담당 감사관들은 김건희 특검팀의 수사 대상이 됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Who is Responsible for the Abuse of Personnel and Audit Authority Wielded by the Yoo Byung-ho Faction? (유병호 사단 휘두른 인사·감찰권 남용 책임은 누가?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Distrust regarding the BAI's will for personnel reform also persists. Criticisms have consistently been raised that Commissioner Yoo used the Personnel and Audit Department to build a factional lineup and disadvantaged auditors who opposed him through excessive audits and heavy disciplinary actions. However, because the auditors and personnel department staff who carried out the audit and personnel measures at the time were also members of the TF, there were significant concerns about the fairness of the investigation. (감사원의 인적 쇄신 의지에 대한 불신도 여전하다. 유 위원이 인사·감찰과를 앞세워 파벌 줄 세우기를 하고, 자신에 반대하는 감사관들은 과잉 감찰과 중징계 등으로 불이익을 준다는 비판은 꾸준히 나왔다. 그러나 당시 감찰 및 인사 조처를 취한 감찰관과 인사 부서 직원도 티에프에 소속돼 있었기 때문에, 조사의 공정성에 우려가 컸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although 55 out of 90 anonymous opinions sent by employees to the TF (60%) were about personnel and audit operations, the TF publicly disclosed only 6 cases as problematic. Apart from Commissioner Yoo, the TF did not hold any personnel or audit staff accountable. A BAI auditor, Mr. D, said, "Regarding this issue, only Commissioner Yoo was accused (of abuse of authority). As for the head of the Personnel and Audit Department, who is suspected of coercively auditing employees and unfairly submitting disciplinary proposals under Commissioner Yoo at the time, I understand the TF investigation hardly took place." (직원들이 티에프에 보낸 익명 의견 90건 중 60%인 55건이 인사·감찰 운영에 관한 것이었지만, 티에프가 문제 사례로 공개한 건 6건에 불과했다. 유 위원 외에 티에프가 책임을 물은 감찰·인사 담당 직원은 없었다. 감사관 ㄷ씨는 “이 문제로 유 위원만 (직권남용으로) 고발했을 뿐, 당시 유 위원 아래에서 직원들을 강압적으로 감찰하고 부당하게 징계안을 올린 것으로 의심받는 인사·감찰과장에 대해선 티에프 조사가 거의 이뤄지지 않은 것으로 안다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;No remedial measures have yet been taken for Auditor Lee So-and-so, who was dismissed after raising suspicions that Commissioner Yoo, during the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, tried to suppress an audit at the request of the presidential office. In 2023, Auditor Lee, who was in charge of auditing the development of a returned US military base site in Uijeongbu, Gyeonggi Province, identified that Uijeongbu City converted the returned US military site into private apartment land, sold it to the private sector at a low price, and improperly exempted 42.3 billion won in public interest contribution fees, and submitted an opinion requesting an investigation. (윤석열 정부 때 유 위원이 대통령실 청탁을 받고 감사를 무마하려고 했다는 의혹을 제기했다가 해임된 이아무개 감사관에 대해선 여전히 구제조치가 나오지 않고 있다. 2023년 경기 의정부시 미군기지 반환 부지 개발 감사를 맡았던 이 감사관은 의정부시가 미군 반환 부지를 민간 아파트 부지로 전환해 민간에 헐값에 매각하고, 공익환원금 423억원도 부당면제해 준 사실을 파악해 수사요청 의견을 올렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, this case resulted only in a simple warning request for two public officials at the BAI's Audit Committee meeting. Instead, the BAI conducted two audits against Auditor Lee, alleging he conducted coercive audits against Uijeongbu City, and imposed the heavy disciplinary action of dismissal. It is said that the bureau chief who ignored Auditor Lee's investigation request opinion at the time was recently promoted to a high-ranking position. (하지만 이 사건은 감사위원회의에서 공무원 2명에게 단순주의 요구를 주는 데 그쳤다. 대신 감사원은 이 감사관이 의정부시를 상대로 강압 감사를 했다며 두 차례 감찰을 벌여 해임이란 중징계를 내렸다. 당시 이 감사관의 수사요청 의견을 묵살한 담당 국장은 최근 고위직으로 승진했다고 한다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The TF, which re-examined the BAI's measures at the time, only pointed out that the audit department that audited Auditor Lee reached a conclusion of coercive audit based solely on the statements of the auditees without cross-verification and cited this as grounds for discipline. It viewed the discipline against Auditor Lee itself as having no problem. Auditor Lee has filed an appeal with the Appeals Commission against the dismissal decision. (당시 감사원 조치 내용을 다시 들여다본 티에프는 이 감사관을 감찰했던 감찰부서가 교차 검증 없이 피감사자들 진술만을 토대로 강압 감사 결론을 내리고 이를 징계 사유로 적었다는 부분만 문제 삼았다. 이 감사관 징계 자체엔 문제가 없다고 본 것이다. 이 감사관은 해임 결정에 불복해 소청심사위원회에 소청을 제기한 상태다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"We Wanted Truth-Finding and Clear Rewards/Punishments..." Internal Harmony a Long Road (“진상규명, 신상필벌 바랐는데….” 내부 화합 먼 길)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former auditor Jeon Hee-jung, who was dismissed at the end of 2024 after being investigated by the BAI's audit department and the prosecution on charges of leaking audit materials, also filed a petition with the TF, but the TF viewed the disciplinary process as having no problem. Former auditor Jeon was identified as the leaker of audit materials for the Sky72 case, for which former BAI Chairman Choi Jae-hae had instructed 'no further action,' and the audit team requested an investigation, but the prosecution decided not to indict due to insufficient evidence. Nevertheless, the BAI conducted a second audit, asserting that former auditor Jeon did leak the materials without authorization, gathered new disciplinary grounds, and dismissed her. (감사자료 유출 혐의로 감사원 감찰과 검찰 수사를 받고 지난 2024년 말 해임된 전희정 전 감사관도 티에프에 진정을 냈지만 티에프는 징계 과정에 문제가 없다고 봤다. 전 전 감사관은 최재해 전 감사원장이 ‘불문’을 지시한 스카이72 사건 감사 자료 유출자로 지목돼 감찰팀이 수사 의뢰를 했지만 검찰은 증거 불충분으로 무혐의 처분을 했다. 그럼에도 감사원은 전 전 감사관이 무단으로 자료를 유출한 것이 맞다며 2차 감찰을 벌이고, 새 징계사유를 모아 전 전 감사관을 해임했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former auditor Jeon claimed, "There were many procedural issues during the audit process, such as forensic analysis without the party's consent. I hoped the TF would correct even the issues of authority abuse and procedural violations by the audit office, but it wasn't accepted." On the other hand, a BAI official stated, "Apart from the leak, former auditor Jeon had many misconduct issues, making heavy discipline unavoidable." (전 전 감사관은 “감찰 과정에서 당사자 동의 없는 포렌식이 이뤄지는 등 절차 문제도 많았다. 감찰관실의 권한 남용과 절차 위반 문제라도 티에프가 바로잡아주길 원했지만, 받아들여지지 않은 것”이라고 주장했다. 반면 감사원 관계자는 “유출 건 외에도 전 전 감사관의 비위 사항이 많아 중징계가 불가피했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A BAI auditor, Mr. R, said, "I heard some Tiger Faction auditors recently say, 'Let's see in 5 years (when the administration changes).' I hoped the truth about what those who actively collaborated with former Secretary-General Yoo to conduct improper audits or audited employees would be uncovered, and that there would be clear rewards and punishments. If things are passed over like this, I wonder what message it sends to the organization." (감사관 ㄹ씨는 “최근 타이거파 감사관 일부는 ‘5년 뒤 (정권이 바뀌면) 보자’는 이야길 한다고 들었다”며 “유 전 총장에게 적극적으로 부역해 부당 감사를 했거나 직원들을 감찰했던 이들이 어떤 일을 했는지 진상을 규명하고, 신상필벌이 되길 바랐는데, 이런 식으로 넘어간다면 조직에 어떤 메시지를 줄 수 있을지 의문”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the BAI stated, "To identify responsibility for those who abused personnel and audit authority during the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, we have assigned TF participating employees to the audit office," expressing additional willingness to respond. (이에 대해 감사원은 “윤석열 정부 당시 인사·감찰권 남용 관련자에 대한 책임규명 등을 위해 티에프 참여 직원들을 감찰관실에 배치했다”며 추가적인 대응 의지를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240280.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/723/434/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686968719867_20260118500465.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Everyone but us with the South, and hmph'... North Korea's reasoned 'snub of Xi Jinping' (‘우리 빼고 남쪽이랑, 흥칫뿡’… 북한의 이유 있는 ‘시진핑 홀대’)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240281.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;'Everyone but us with the South, and hmph'... North Korea's reasoned 'snub of Xi Jinping' (‘우리 빼고 남쪽이랑, 흥칫뿡’… 북한의 이유 있는 ‘시진핑 홀대’)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/562/337/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686980248441_20260118500537.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;지난해 9월 4일 김정은 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장과 시진핑 중국공산당 중앙위 총서기 겸 국가주석이 베이징 인민대회당에서 정상회담에 앞서 악수를 하며 기념촬영을 하고 있다. 이 회담은 김 위원장의 중국 전승절 80돌 경축행사 참석 계기에 이뤄졌다. 조선중앙통신 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, the Rodong Sinmun reported, without detailing the contents, that Kim Jong Un, General Secretary of the Workers' Party of Korea and Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, sent a 'New Year's greeting card' to Xi Jinping, General Secretary of the Communist Party of China Central Committee and President of the state, and his wife. (김정은 조선노동당 총비서 겸 국무위원장이 시진핑 중국공산당 중앙위 총서기 겸 국가주석 부부한테 ‘새해 연하장’을 보냈다고 18일 노동신문이 내용 소개 없이 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the headline "Respected Comrade Kim Jong Un Sends New Year's Cards to Party and State Leaders and Figures of Various Countries," the Rodong Sinmun reported that Chairman Kim sent "New Year's cards on the occasion of the 2026 New Year" to, among others, President Xi and his wife, the General Secretary of the Communist Party of Vietnam Central Committee, and the President of Vietnam. (노동신문은 이날 “경애하는 김정은 동지께서 여러 나라 당 및 국가수반들과 인사들에게 년하장을 보내시였다”라는 제목을 달아 김 위원장이 시 주석 부부를 포함해 베트남공산당 중앙위 총비서, 베트남 주석 등한테 “2026년 새해에 즈음하여 연하장”을 보냈다고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This reporting format is the same as that used by the Rodong Sinmun on January 1st when it reported the fact that President Xi and his wife had sent a 'New Year's greeting card' to Chairman Kim. Although the page placement appears slightly different—page 5 on the 1st and page 2 this time—it is essentially the same level of reporting format. On the 1st, the newspaper covered news such as Chairman Kim attending and giving a speech at the 'New Year's Celebration Performance' held at the May 1st Stadium in Pyongyang, and sending 'New Year's congratulatory messages' to the Russian-dispatched People's Army and Heo Jong-man, Chairman of the Central Standing Committee of the General Association of Korean Residents in Japan, across pages 1 to 4, and placed the news about the greeting card from President Xi and his wife on page 5. It is rare for the Rodong Sinmun to report on the exchange of letters, such as New Year's cards, between Chairman Kim and President Xi without detailing their contents. (이는 시 주석 부부가 김 위원장한테 ‘새해 연하장’을 보낸 사실을 전한 지난 1일 노동신문의 보도 형식과 같다. 1일엔 5면에, 이번엔 2면에 실려 지면 배치가 조금 달라 보이지만 사실상 동일한 위상의 보도 형식이다. 지난 1일치엔 김 위원장이 평양 5·1경기장에서 진행된 ‘새해경축공연’에 참석해 연설을 한 소식, 러시아 파병 인민군과 재일본조선인총연합회 중앙상임위 허종만한테 ‘새해 축하 전문’을 보낸 소식 등을 1∼4면에 펼치고 5면에 시 주석 부부의 연하장 소식을 전했기 때문이다. 노동신문이 김 위원장과 시 주석의 연하장 등 편지 교환 사실을 내용 소개 없이 보도하는 건 전례가 드문 일이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comparing the Rodong Sinmun's reporting on the exchange of 'New Year's greeting cards' between Chairman Kim and President Xi and his wife with its reporting on the exchange of 'New Year's congratulatory messages' between Chairman Kim and Russian President Vladimir Putin allows for speculation on its 'political implications.' On December 25th, the Rodong Sinmun reported that in the 'New Year's congratulatory message' President Putin sent to Chairman Kim on December 18th last year, he characterized North Korea-Russia relations as "invincible friendship and militant comradeship, friendly and allied relations." On December 27th last year, it featured as its front-page lead article that Chairman Kim, addressing President Putin as "my most respected friend," sent a 'New Year's congratulatory message' defining North Korea-Russia relations as "the most genuine alliance sharing life and death, joy and sorrow, having shed blood together in the same trench." (김 위원장과 시 주석 부부의 ‘새해 연하장’ 교환 관련 노동신문 보도를 김 위원장과 블라디미르 푸틴 러시아 대통령의 ‘새해 축전’ 교환 보도와 비교하면 그 ‘정치적 함의’를 추정할 수 있다. 노동신문은 푸틴 대통령이 지난해 12월 18일 김 위원장한테 보낸 ‘새해 축전’에서 북러 관계를 “불패의 친선과 전투적 우의, 친선적이며 동맹적인 관계”라고 규정했다고 12월 25일치로 보도했다. 지난해 12월 27일엔 김 위원장이 푸틴 대통령을 ”가장 친애하는 당신”이라 부르며 북러관계를 “한전호에서 피를 나누며 생사고락을 함께하는 가장 진실한 동맹”이라 규정한 ‘새해 축전’을 보냈다고 1면 머리기사로 다뤘다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In light of these circumstances, the Rodong Sinmun's reporting format and content regarding the exchange of 'New Year's greeting cards' between Chairman Kim and President Xi and his wife could be seen as an 'intentional snub.' This is even more so considering that North Korea-China relations have historically been described with phrases like 'lips and teeth' (meaning closely interdependent) and "friends and comrades sharing destiny." It appears to be an expression of 'dissatisfaction' with China's continued implementation, in one way or another, of UN Security Council sanctions resolutions against North Korea, and with President Xi inviting South Korean President Lee Jae-myung to Beijing for summit diplomacy from the beginning of the year. (이런 사정에 비춰 보면 김 위원장과 시 주석 부부 사이의 ‘새해 연하장’ 교환과 관련한 노동신문의 보도 형식과 내용은 ‘의도된 홀대’로 비칠 여지가 있다. 북중 관계가 역사적으로 입술이 없으면 이가 시리다는 뜻의 ‘순망치한’, “운명을 함께하는 친구·동지” 등으로 불려온 사실에 비춰 더욱 그렇다. 중국이 유엔 안전보장이사회의 대북 제재 결의를 어떤 식으로든 계속 이행하고 있는데다, 시 주석이 이재명 대통령을 베이징으로 초청해 연초부터 정상외교를 한 사실 등에 대한 ‘불만’ 표현으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Reporter Lee Je-hoon &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이제훈 선임기자 &lt;a href="mailto:nomad@hani.co.kr"&gt;nomad@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/defense/1240281.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/562/337/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686980248441_20260118500537.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Joon-pyo: "Han Dong-hoon prevented martial law? Narcissists should just disappear." (홍준표 “한동훈이 계엄 막았다고? 나르시시스트는 그만 사라져라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240283.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hong Joon-pyo: "Han Dong-hoon prevented martial law? Narcissists should just disappear." (홍준표 “한동훈이 계엄 막았다고? 나르시시스트는 그만 사라져라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686983599544_20260118500572.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;홍준표 후보가 2025년 4월29일 서울 여의도 국민의힘 당사에서 열린 제21대 대통령 후보자 국민의힘 3차 경선 진출자 발표 행사에서 탈락 발표가 난 후 퇴장하고 있다. 국회사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Daegu Mayor Hong Joon-pyo criticized former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon, calling him "a presence that should no longer exist in Korean politics." (홍준표 전 대구시장이 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표를 두고 “더 이상 한국 정치판에 있어서는 안 될 존재”라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a post on Facebook on the 17th, former Mayor Hong claimed, "He was a political prosecutor, like Yoon Suk Yeol, who, after the impeachment of Park Geun-hye, devastated the Korean conservative camp in a fleeting moment of glory. Thanks to Yoon Suk Yeol's consideration, he rose meteorically to become Minister of Justice and conducted the investigation into Lee Jae-myung, but didn't he fail?" (홍 전 시장은 17일 페이스북에 올린 글에서 “그는 윤석열과 같이 박근혜 탄핵 후 한국 보수 진영을 궤멸시킨 화양연화 정치검사였고, 윤석열의 배려로 벼락출세해 법무부 장관을 하면서 이재명 수사를 했으나 망하지 않았느냐”며 이같이 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Mayor Hong continued, "Then, again thanks to Yoon Suk Yeol's consideration, he became the (People Power Party) emergency committee chairman, monopolized nominations, engaged only in self-promotion, and led the party to a crushing defeat in the general election. After becoming party leader, he bickered and clashed with Yoon's faction, causing nothing but discord, which led to the emergency martial law situation and devastated the conservative camp." (홍 전 시장은 이어 “또다시 윤석열의 배려로 (국민의힘) 비대위원장을 하면서 공천을 농단하고 자기선전만 하다가 총선에 참패했고 당대표가 된 후 윤통과 깐죽거리며 반목만 일삼다가 비상계엄을 초래하고 보수 진영을 궤멸시켰다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "It was not Han Dong-hoon who prevented the emergency martial law, but the then-opposition Democratic Party of Korea and the people." Former leader Han, when declaring his candidacy for the 21st presidential election last April, had said, "I, Han Dong-hoon, who said I would head to the National Assembly first and stand with the people first to prevent martial law, unlike Lee Jae-myung, who was so scared he hid in the woods, must stand up," among other statements, repeatedly emphasizing his role in preventing the December 3 emergency martial law. (그러면서 “비상계엄을 막은 것은 한동훈이 아니고 당시 야당이었던 더불어민주당과 국민들”이라고 덧붙였다. 한 전 대표는 지난해 4월 제21대 대통령 선거 출마를 선언하면서 “겁이 나서 숲에 숨은 이재명 대표보다 제일 먼저 국회로 향하고, 제일 먼저 국민과 함께 계엄을 막겠다고 한 저, 한동훈이 맞서야 한다”고 말하는 등 여러 차례 12·3 비상계엄 저지에 있어서 자신의 역할을 강조해 온 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, former Mayor Hong said, "Does the very person who caused the emergency martial law situation still have business causing trouble in that party with a handful of followers?" and added, "A narcissist, obsessed only with superficial politics with such a lack of foresight that he can't see even an inch ahead, should just disappear now." (마지막으로 홍 전 시장은 “비상계엄을 초래한 장본인이 한 줌도 안 되는 종물들 데리고 아직도 그 당에서 분탕 칠 일이 남았냐”며 “한 치 앞도 내다보지 못하는 그런 식견으로 겉치레 정치에만 몰두하는 나르시(시)스트는 이제 그만 사라지거라”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the People Power Party's Ethics Committee decided on the 14th to expel former leader Han, stating, "The post on the party member bulletin board appears to have been written by former leader Han." People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk stated on the 15th, "We will grant former leader Han an opportunity for a retrial and a proper chance to explain himself, and the Supreme Council will not decide on the disciplinary action during the retrial period to allow the process to conclude properly," postponing the vote on the disciplinary motion. (한편, 국민의힘 윤리위원회는 지난 14일 “당원게시판 글은 한 전 대표가 작성한 것으로 보인다”며 한 전 대표 제명 결정을 내린 바 있다. 장동혁 국민의힘 대표는 15일 “한 전 대표에게 재심 기회를 부여하고 제대로 된 소명 기회를 부여받아 절차가 마무리되도록 재심 기간 최고위에서 (징계를) 결정하지 않겠다”며 징계안 의결을 연기한 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Lee Yoo-jin &lt;a href="mailto:yjlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;yjlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (이유진 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yjlee@hani.co.kr"&gt;yjlee@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240283.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17686983599544_20260118500572.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Na Kyung-won, who 'ate honey'... Shouted "Yoon's arrest is illegal," but remains silent on 5-year prison sentence (‘꿀 먹은’ 나경원…“윤 체포는 불법” 샤우팅 하더니 징역 5년엔 침묵)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240289.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Na Kyung-won, who 'ate honey'... Shouted "Yoon's arrest is illegal," but remains silent on 5-year prison sentence (‘꿀 먹은’ 나경원…“윤 체포는 불법” 샤우팅 하더니 징역 5년엔 침묵)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/561/imgdb/child/2026/0118/17687045666884_20260118500740.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;나경원 의원을 비롯한 국민의힘 의원들이 지난해 1월6일 오후 서울 용산구 대통령 관저 앞에서 입장발표를 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid a court ruling that former President Yoon Suk-yeol obstructed the execution of an arrest warrant by the Corruption Investigation Office for High-ranking Officials (CIO) by giving illegal instructions to the Presidential Security Service to avoid investigation into a rebellion case, criticism has been raised that People Power Party lawmakers, who gathered in front of the presidential residence claiming the CIO's arrest warrant was 'illegal,' must bear political and legal responsibility. (윤석열 전 대통령이 고위공직자범죄수사처(공수처) 체포영장 집행을 방해한 건 내란 사건 수사를 피하기 위해 대통령경호처에 위법한 지시를 한 것이라는 법원 판단이 나온 가운데, 공수처 체포영장이 ‘불법’이라며 대통령 관저 앞에 집결했던 국민의힘 의원들은 정치적·법적 책임을 져야 한다는 비판이 제기됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, the Seoul Central District Court Criminal Division 35 (Presiding Judge Baek Dae-hyun) sentenced former President Yoon to five years in prison on charges including obstructing the execution of the CIO's arrest warrant last January. The court did not accept any of former President Yoon's claims that the CIO's application for and execution of the arrest warrant, and the Seoul Western District Court's issuance of the warrant, were all illegal because the CIO lacked investigative authority for the crime of rebellion. (지난 16일 서울중앙지법 형사35부(재판장 백대현)는 지난해 1월 공수처의 체포영장 집행을 방해한 혐의 등으로 윤 전 대통령에게 징역 5년을 선고했다. 내란죄 수사 권한이 없는 공수처의 체포영장 청구 및 집행, 서울서부지법의 영장 발부는 모두 위법이라는 윤 전 대통령 쪽 주장은 하나도 받아들이지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court ruled that there was no problem with the CIO expanding its investigation from the crime of abuse of authority to the related crime of rebellion, and that the CIO's application for a warrant to the Western District Court instead of the Central District Court did not constitute a violation of jurisdiction. The court rebuked former President Yoon, stating, "He abused his influence as president to obstruct the execution of the warrant, which was for his personal safety and effectively privatized the Presidential Security Service." (법원은 공수처가 직권남용죄로 수사를 개시한 뒤 관련 범죄인 내란죄로 수사를 확장한 것에 문제가 없으며, 공수처가 서울중앙지법이 아닌 서부지법에 영장을 청구한 것도 관할 위반에 해당하지 않는다고 판단했다. 법원은 윤 전 대통령을 향해 “대통령으로 영향력을 남용해 영장 집행을 저지했는데, 이는 일신의 안위를 위한 것이며 대통령경호처를 사실상 사병화한 것”이라고 질타했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the court's sentencing, the political spotlight turned to the People Power Party. This is because the People Power Party had amplified and reproduced former President Yoon's sophistry that the CIO's investigation was 'illegal.' When the CIO arrested former President Yoon on its second attempt on January 15 last year, the People Power Party filed a complaint against CIO chief Oh Dong-woon, claiming the execution of the arrest warrant was "illegal." Kwon Young-se, then the party's emergency committee chairman, argued, "The arrest of the president is a tragic trio created by the CIO, which lacks investigative authority, the Seoul Western District Court, which issued an arrest warrant with a high likelihood of illegality, and the police colluding with the Democratic Party of Korea." (법원 선고 뒤 정치권의 시선은 국민의힘으로 쏠렸다. 국민의힘이 공수처 수사가 ‘불법’이라는 윤 전 대통령의 궤변을 확대재생산 해왔기 때문이다. 국민의힘은 지난해 1월15일 공수처가 두 번째 시도 만에 윤 전 대통령을 체포하자, 체포영장 집행은 “불법”이라며 오동운 공수처장을 고발한 바 있다. 권영세 당시 국민의힘 비상대책위원장은 “대통령 체포는 수사권이 없는 공수처와 위법 소지가 다분한 체포영장을 발부한 서울서부지법, 더불어민주당과 내통한 경찰이 만든 비극의 삼중주”라고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the legitimacy of the CIO's arrest warrant execution being verified through four different judges across two warrant issuances by the Western District Court, one dismissal of an objection, and the Seoul Central District Court's dismissal of a warrant validity review, they merely echoed former President Yoon's claims. (두 차례에 걸친 서부지법의 체포영장 발부, 한 차례의 이의신청 기각, 서울중앙지법의 체포적부심 기각까지 각기 다른 4명의 판사를 통해 공수처 체포영장 집행의 정당성이 입증됐음에도, 윤 전 대통령 쪽 주장에 동조하기만 한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 40 People Power Party lawmakers also gathered in front of the presidential residence in Hannam-dong, Yongsan-gu, Seoul, to block the execution of the CIO's arrest warrant. Lawmakers including Na Kyung-won, Yoon Sang-hyun, Park Dae-chul, Lee Sang-hwi, Kang Myung-gu, Jo Bae-sook, Cho Ji-yeon, Lee Man-hee, Sung Il-jong, Lee Cheol-gyu, Jung Hee-yong, Kim Jung-jae, Jung Jeom-sik, Kwon Young-jin, Lee Jong-wook, Kang Seung-kyu, Park Sung-min, Koo Ja-geun, Yoo Sang-bum, Jang Dong-hyuk, and Kim Wi-sang, along with about 30 others including non-assembly district party chapter chairmen, flocked to the residence during the second arrest warrant execution attempt. Previously, when the CIO attempted to execute the first arrest warrant, over 40 people gathered. (국민의힘 의원 40여명은 공수처의 체포영장 집행을 막으려 서울 용산구 한남동 대통령 관저 앞에 집결하기도 했다. 나경원·윤상현·박대출·이상휘·강명구·조배숙·조지연·이만희·성일종·이철규·정희용·김정재·정점식·권영진·이종욱·강승규·박성민·구자근·유상범·장동혁·김위상 의원 등과 원외 당협위원장 등 30여명이 2차 체포영장 집행 당시 관저 앞에 몰려갔고, 그에 앞서 공수처가 1차 체포영장을 집행하려 할 때는 40명 넘게 모이기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In particular, Representative Na Kyung-won is one of the figures who actively participated in obstructing the warrant execution, vehemently arguing that the lawfully issued arrest warrant was 'illegal.' At a protest denouncing the second arrest warrant execution in front of the presidential residence on January 15 last year, Rep. Na made the absurd claim, "Even if it's a murderer caught in the act, the law must be alive. Exerting unreasonable and illegal physical force against the incumbent president, who is only suspended from duties, is a setback for the rule of law in South Korea." (특히 나경원 의원은 법원이 적법하게 발부한 체포영장을 ‘불법’이라고 강변하며 영장 집행 저지에 적극적으로 나섰던 인물 가운데 하나다. 나 의원은 지난해 1월15일 대통령 관저 앞에서 열린 2차 체포영장 집행 규탄 시위에서 “아무리 살인범 현행범이라고 해도 법이 살아 있어야 되는 것이다. 직무만 정지되어 있지 현행 대통령에게 무리하고 불법적인 물리력을 행사하는 것은 대한민국 법치주의를 후퇴시키는 것”이라는 황당한 주장을 폈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, she also stated she would propose a bill to abolish the CIO, saying, "The Democratic Party's CIO, which led the illegal investigation and illegal detention atrocities against the president, and the illegal investigation office, the CIO, should be abolished." (이후 “대통령에 대한 불법수사와 불법구금 만행을 주도한 민주당의 하명수사처, 불법수사처 공수처는 마땅히 폐지돼야 한다”며 공수처 해체법을 발의하겠다고 밝히기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the first-instance verdict revealed all these claims to be 'sophistry,' neither the People Power Party nor the individual lawmakers who gathered in front of the residence had issued any particular statement as of the 18th, the third day after the sentencing. Park Sung-hoon, the People Power Party's chief spokesperson, met with reporters at the National Assembly on the 16th and only said, "The People Power Party's position is that we have no special stance on the trial result," and "We respect the judiciary's judgment." (1심 선고가 나오면서 이런 주장들은 모두 ‘궤변’으로 드러났지만, 국민의힘과 관저 앞에 모였던 개별 의원들은 선고 사흘째인 18일까지도 별다른 입장을 내지 않고 있다. 박성훈 국민의힘 수석대변인은 16일 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “재판 결과에 대해 특별한 입장이 없다는 게 국민의힘의 입장”이라며 “사법부의 판단을 존중한다”고만 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea, in a commentary issued in the name of spokesperson Baek Seung-ah on the 17th, urged, "The 45-member 'Yoon Suk-yeol bulletproof lawmakers' group of the People Power Party, who systematically obstructed the arrest of rebellion ringleader Yoon Suk-yeol and undermined the rule of law, must immediately apologize to the people and take political and legal responsibility." (더불어민주당은 17일 백승아 원내대변인 명의 논평에서 “내란수괴 윤석열의 체포를 조직적으로 방해하며 법치를 훼손한 국민의힘 소속 45명의 ‘윤석열 방탄 의원단’은 국민 앞에 즉각 사죄하고 정치적·법적 책임을 져야 한다”고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Shim Woo-sam &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (심우삼 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wu32@hani.co.kr"&gt;wu32@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240289.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/561/imgdb/child/2026/0118/17687045666884_20260118500740.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon says "It's fabrication and retaliation, but I am sorry"... First apology over party member bulletin board incident (한동훈 “조작·보복이지만 송구”…당원게시판 사건 첫 사과)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240299.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Han Dong-hoon says "It's fabrication and retaliation, but I am sorry"... First apology over party member bulletin board incident (한동훈 “조작·보복이지만 송구”…당원게시판 사건 첫 사과)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/324/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118500986.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표 페이스북 영상 갈무리&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon said regarding the growing intra-party conflict surrounding the party member bulletin board controversy, "It is fabrication and retaliation, but I am sorry." (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 18일 당원게시판 논란을 둘러싸고 당내 갈등이 커지는 데 대해 “조작·보복이지만 송구스럽다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a video posted on Facebook that day, the former leader said, "The disciplinary action against me is clear fabrication and political retaliation," but added, "Regarding the situation reaching this point, and regarding causing concern to the public and party members, as a responsible politician who led the party, I feel sorry." This is the first time the former leader, who received an expulsion decision from the party's ethics committee on the 13th, has expressed an apology regarding the party member bulletin board incident. (한 전 대표는 이날 페이스북에 영상을 올려 “나에 대한 징계는 명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라면서도 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것에 대해서, 국민과 당원 여러분께 걱정 끼쳐드린 데 대해서 당을 이끌었던 책임있던 정치인으로서 송구한 마음”이라고 했다. 지난 13일 당 윤리위원회로부터 제명 처분을 받은 한 전 대표가 당원게시판 사건과 관련해 사과의 뜻을 밝힌 것은 이번이 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former leader emphasized, "Seeing such a scene of political retaliation unfold ahead of a crucial election to overcome the state of emergency and control the runaway Democratic Party administration, I am deeply worried that many people will turn their hearts away from our party," and added, "They may be able to strip me of my party membership through political retaliation using party power, but they cannot strip away the spirit and future of our party that I love." (한 전 대표는 “계엄을 극복하고 민주당 정권 폭주를 제어할 중대한 선거를 앞두고 이런 정치 보복의 장면이 펼쳐지는 것 보고 우리 당에 대한 마음 거두는 분들이 많아질거 같아서 걱정이 크다”며 “당권으로 정치보복해서 저의 당적을 박탈할 순 있어도, 제가 사랑하는 우리 당 정신과 미래는 박탈할 수 없다”고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Jang Ye-chan, Vice President of the Yeouido Research Institute, who is pro-Yoon Suk Yeol, sarcastically remarked, "It's the worst excuse for an apology disguised as a complaint in history," adding, "Public opinion is unfavorable, so he pretends to apologize, but doesn't want to admit wrongdoing; it's truly a golden child-like appearance." (이에 대해 친윤석열계 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장은 “역대 최악의 사과를 빙자한 투정문”이라며 “여론이 불리하니 사과하는 척은 해야겠고, 잘못을 인정하기는 싫고, 그야말로 금쪽이 같은 모습”이라고 비꼬았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240299.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/324/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118500986.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Park Soo-hyun: "Is the one-person-one-vote system for Jeong Cheong-rae's re-election? It's an insult to party members." (박수현 “1인1표제가 정청래 연임용? 당원에 대한 모독”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240300.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Park Soo-hyun: "Is the one-person-one-vote system for Jeong Cheong-rae's re-election? It's an insult to party members." (박수현 “1인1표제가 정청래 연임용? 당원에 대한 모독”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/638/391/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118501014.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;박수현 더불어민주당 수석대변인이 18일 국회에서 현안 관련 기자간담회를 하고 잇다. 김경호 선임기자 jijae@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-hyun, the chief spokesperson for the Democratic Party of Korea, stated regarding the 'one-person-one-vote system for delegates and regular party members' being promoted by party leader Jeong Cheong-rae that "it is not being pursued with the leader's re-election in mind." (박수현 더불어민주당 수석대변인이 정청래 대표가 추진하는 ‘대의원-권리당원 1인1표제’와 관련해 “대표의 연임을 염두에 두고 추진하고 있지 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press briefing at the National Assembly today, when asked about the party's differing views on the 'one-person-one-vote system,' Chief Spokesperson Park retorted, "Isn't the core question whether one-person-one-vote is the Democratic Party's spirit of the times, or a stepping stone for Jeong Cheong-rae's re-election?" He added, "From Leader Jeong, I have never heard even the syllable 'ㅇ' (the first letter of '연임' - re-election), let alone the word '연' (yeon)." He continued, "Leader Jeong's consistent position is, 'I have never worked with a specific position as a goal. I give my all to today's work today, and tomorrow's work tomorrow.'" He further stated, "Even making a hundred concessions, Leader Jeong has absolutely not been promoting the one-person-one-vote system with re-election in mind so far, nor has he mentioned re-election to anyone." (박 수석대변인은 이날 국회 기자간담회에서 ‘1인 1표제’를 둘러싼 당내 이견에 대한 입장을 묻는 질문에 “1인1표가 민주당의 시대 정신인가, 아니면 정청래 대표의 연임 포석인가 이것이 핵심 질문 아닌가”라고 반문하며 “정 대표로부터 ‘연임’의 ‘연’자는커녕 ‘이응’자마저도 들어본 적 없다”고 했다. 그러면서 “정 대표의 일관된 입장은 ‘어떤 자리를 목표로 정해놓고 일한 적 없다. 오늘은 오늘의 일에 사력을 다하고 내일은 내일의 일에 사력을 다한다’는 것”이라며 “백번 양보하더라도 정 대표는 적어도 지금까지는 연임을 염두에 두고 1인1표제를 추진하고 있거나, 누구에게도 연임을 언급한 바가 절대 없다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park also refuted the view that the one-person-one-vote system is advantageous to Leader Jeong. He said, "Who can guarantee that just because Leader Jeong led in the regular party member vote at the last national convention, he will do so in the future?" He added, "The assumption that regular party members will unconditionally support Leader Jeong without question is a disparagement of regular party members and an insult to party members, treating the party's will as Leader Jeong's personal property." (박 수석대변인은 1인1표제가 정 대표에게 유리하다는 시각에 대해서도 반박하고 나섰다. 박 수석대변인은 “지난 전당대회에서 정 대표가 권리당원 투표에서 앞섰다고 해서 앞으로도 그럴 거라는 보장을 누가할 수 있는가”라며 “권리당원이 묻지도 따지지도 않고 무조건 정 대표를 지지할 거란 가정은 권리당원에 대한 폄훼이자, 당심을 정 대표의 개인 종속물로 취급하는 당원에 대한 모독”이라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He showed discomfort targeting party figures who exaggerate conflicts within the leadership. He said, "At the non-public Supreme Council meeting on the 16th, the one-person-one-vote party constitution amendment was unanimously approved, although one or two members expressed their opinions to create a better amendment. However, it is very inappropriate for someone to speak to the media with a different intention, making it seem as if there were disagreements on a unanimously approved matter." He added, "At a time when we are passing through a golden time for the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration, words and actions that could be seen as a power struggle should be restrained." He also said, "Some are pressuring, saying that to keep the one-person-one-vote promise, the leader should declare he won't seek re-election or that it shouldn't be applied in this party leadership election, but this is an act that ignores even the basic principles of democracy." (지도부내 갈등을 과장하는 당내 인사들을 겨냥해선 불편한 기색을 내비쳤다. 그는 “16일 최고위 비공개회의에서 1인1표 당헌개정은 만장일치로 의결됐으나 한 두 분의 더 좋은 개정안을 만들기 위한 의사 개진이 있었다. 그런데 만장일치로 의결된 사안을 이견이 있었던 것처럼 언론에 다른 말씀을 어떤 의도를 가지고 하는 건 매우 부적절하다”며 “이재명 정부 성공을 위한 골든타임을 지나는 시기에 자칫 당권투쟁으로 보일 수 있는 언행과 행동은 자제돼야 한다”고 했다. 또 “1인1표 약속을 지키려면 대표 연임 포기를 선언하라거나 이번 당 대표 선거에서는 적용하지 말아야 한다고 윽박지르기도 하는데, 이는 민주주의의 기본 원리마저 무시하는 처사”라고도 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on his fourth day of a hunger strike demanding the Democratic Party accept a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds, Park said, "It's like trying to stop something that could be stopped with a hoe by bringing out a plow; it's very regrettable. I hope he takes good care of his health." He added, "Separately from that, the life-risking hunger strike by the leader of the main opposition party should be for a greater public interest of the people. I still cannot understand whether issues related to the Unification Church and Shincheonji are subjects for a life-risking hunger strike." (민주당에 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 나흘째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표에 대해선 “호미로 막을 수 있는 것을 쟁기를 들고 막겠다고 나선 격이라 매우 안타깝다. 건강을 잘 챙기시길 기원한다”고 했다. 그러면서 “그와 별개로 제1야당 대표의 목숨을 건 단식은 좀 더 큰 국민의 공익을 위해서 이뤄져야지, 통일교와 신천지에 관한 사안들이 목숨을 건 단식 대상인가 여전히 이해할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Go Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240300.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/638/391/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118501014.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Successive U.S. Semiconductor Pressure, Blue House Emphasizes Principle of "Not Being at a Disadvantage Compared to Taiwan" (연이은 미 반도체 겁박, 청와대 “대만보다 불리하지 않게” 원칙 강조)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240303.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Successive U.S. Semiconductor Pressure, Blue House Emphasizes Principle of "Not Being at a Disadvantage Compared to Taiwan" (연이은 미 반도체 겁박, 청와대 “대만보다 불리하지 않게” 원칙 강조)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/624/375/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687116458033_20260118501098.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 미국의 그린란드 확보에 협조하지 않는 국가에 관세를 부과할 수 있다고 경고했다. 로이터 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, regarding the Trump administration's semiconductor proclamation, the Blue House stated, "As stipulated in the Korea-U.S. Joint Fact Sheet, we will proceed with consultations to minimize the impact on our companies based on the 'principle of non-disadvantageous treatment.'" (청와대가 18일 미 트럼프 행정부의 반도체 포고령과 관련해 “한미 조인트 팩트시트에 명시된 대로 ‘불리하지 않은 대우 원칙’에 따라 우리 기업에 미치는 영향이 최소화될 수 있도록 협의해나갈 것”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Blue House official said on that day, "Last year's Korea-U.S. Joint Fact Sheet specified the future application of 'conditions no less favorable than those for major countries' regarding semiconductor tariffs. Based on this principle, we plan to closely analyze the U.S.-Taiwan agreement, communicate with the industry, and engage in consultations with the U.S. side." (청와대 관계자는 이날 “지난해 한미 조인트 팩트시트에서 반도체 관세 관련 추후 ‘주요국 대비 불리하지 않은 조건’ 적용을 명시한 바 있다. 이 원칙에 기반해 미국-대만 간 합의사항을 면밀히 분석하고 업계와 소통하며 미국 측과 협의에 나갈 예정”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 14th (local time), U.S. President Donald Trump signed a proclamation imposing a 25% tariff on semiconductors imported into the U.S. and then re-exported to other countries. However, as our government agreed in the Korea-U.S. Joint Fact Sheet to 'provide conditions no less favorable than those to be provided in future agreements covering semiconductor trade volumes exceeding Korea's semiconductor trade volume,' the plan is to secure an agreement at the level achieved by competitor Taiwan. 'Conditions to be provided in future agreements' refers to the semiconductor tariff rate to be determined between the U.S. and Taiwan. (앞서 지난 14일(현지시각) 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령은 미국으로 수입됐다가 다른 나라로 재수출되는 반도체에 대해 25%의 관세를 부과하는 내용의 포고문에 서명했다. 다만 우리 정부는 한미 조인트 팩트시트에 ‘한국의 반도체 교역규모 이상의 반도체 교역을 대상으로 하는 미래 합의에서 제공될 조건보다 불리하지 않은 조건을 부여하고자 한다’고 합의한 만큼 경쟁국인 대만이 관철한 수준의 합의를 끌어낸다는 계획이다. ‘미래 합의에서 제공될 조건’은 미국과 대만 사이에 정해질 반도체 관세율을 의미한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 15th, the U.S. announced a trade agreement with Taiwan, stating that for Taiwanese companies establishing new semiconductor production capacity in the U.S., tariffs would be exempted for imports up to 2.5 times the production capacity during the construction period of the facility. (미국은 15일 대만과 무역합의를 통해 미국에 반도체 생산능력을 신설하는 대만 기업의 경우 해당 시설의 건설이 진행되는 동안에는 생산능력의 2.5배 수입분까지 관세를 면제하는 합의문을 발표한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240303.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/624/375/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687116458033_20260118501098.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Ik-pyo appointed as new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs at the Blue House... Woo Sang-ho intends to run for Gangwon Governor (청와대 새 정무수석에 홍익표…우상호는 강원지사 출마 뜻)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240307.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Hong Ik-pyo appointed as new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs at the Blue House... Woo Sang-ho intends to run for Gangwon Governor (청와대 새 정무수석에 홍익표…우상호는 강원지사 출마 뜻)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/553/imgdb/original/2024/0418/20240418501081.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;홍익표 더불어민주당 원내대표가 2024년 4월18일 국회에서 열린 정책조정회의에서 발언을 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Hong Ik-pyo has been appointed as the successor to Senior Secretary for Political Affairs Woo Sang-ho. Ahead of the June 3 local elections, a series of resignations from the Blue House staff, starting with Senior Secretary Woo, is expected to follow. (우상호 정무수석의 후임으로 홍익표 전 더불어민주당 의원이 임명됐다. 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 우 수석을 시작으로 청와대 참모진의 줄 사표가 이어질 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Gyu-yeon, Senior Presidential Secretary for Public Communication, emphasized during a briefing at the Blue House on the 18th, "As Senior Secretary Woo expressed his resignation for personal reasons, the new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs who will join is former lawmaker Hong," adding, "Former lawmaker Hong has a rational and amicable disposition and has consistently practiced collaborative politics." The term of the new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, Hong, begins on the 20th. Former lawmaker Hong, a three-term lawmaker, has served as the Democratic Party's floor leader, policy committee chair, and chief spokesperson. (이규연 청와대 홍보수석은 18일 청와대에서 브리핑을 통해 “우 수석이 개인적인 이유로 사의를 표명함에 따라 새롭게 합류하게 될 정무수석은 홍 전 의원”이라며 “홍 전 의원은 합리적이고 원만한 성품으로 협업 정치를 지속적으로 실천해온 분”이라고 강조했다. 홍 신임 정무수석의 임기는 오는 20일부터다. 홍 전 의원은 3선 의원 출신으로 민주당 원내대표와 정책위의장, 수석대변인 등을 지냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Secretary Woo, who expressed his resignation, will run for Gangwon Governor in the upcoming June 3 local elections. Spokesperson Kim Nam-joon is highly likely to run in the by-election for the Incheon Gyeyang constituency, which was President Lee Jae-myung's former district. Lee Seon-ho, former head of the Ulsan City Party Committee and currently in the Autonomous Development Secretariat, and Jin Seok-beom, senior administrative officer in the Health and Welfare Secretary's Office, are expected to run for Mayor of Ulsan and Mayor of Hwaseong, Gyeonggi Province, respectively. Kim Gwang, an administrative officer in the Autonomous Development Secretariat, may run for Mayor of Gyeyang District, Incheon; Seo Jeong-wan, an administrative officer in the Autonomous Development Secretariat, for Mayor of Hanam, Gyeonggi Province; and Sung Jun-hoo, an administrative officer in the National Integration Secretariat, for County Governor of Imsil, North Jeolla Province. (사의를 표한 우 수석은 이번 6·3 지방선거에서 강원지사에 출마한다. 김남준 대변인은 이재명 대통령의 지역구였던 인천 계양을 국회의원 보궐선거에 출마할 가능성이 크다. 울산시당위원장을 지낸 이선호 자치발전비서과 진석범 보건복지비서관실 선임행정관은 각각 울산시장과 경기 화성시장에 나설 것으로 보인다. 김광 자치발전비서관실 행정관은 인천 계양구청장에, 서정완 자치발전비서관실 행정관은 경기 하남시장에, 성준후 국민통합비서관실 행정관은 전북 임실군수에 도전할 가능성이 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The greatest attention is on whether Chief of Staff Kang Hun-sik and Policy Chief Kim Yong-beom will run. While Chief Kang is being mentioned for a run in the Chungcheong region and Chief Kim in the Honam region, the prevailing view is that they will remain at the Blue House for now. (최대 관심은 강훈식 비서실장과 김용범 정책실장의 출마 여부다. 강 실장은 충청, 김 실장은 호남 출마가 거론되지만, 아직은 청와대에 남을 것이라는 전망이 우세하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240307.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/553/imgdb/original/2024/0418/20240418501081.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>23 Years Ago, a 'Senior Party Leader's' Hunger Strike Secured a Special Counsel Act... Why is Jang Dong-hyeok Fighting Han Dong-hoon? (23년 전 ‘선배 당대표’ 단식은 특검법 따냈는데…장동혁은 왜 한동훈과 싸울까)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240329.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;23 Years Ago, a 'Senior Party Leader's' Hunger Strike Secured a Special Counsel Act... Why is Jang Dong-hyeok Fighting Han Dong-hoon? (23년 전 ‘선배 당대표’ 단식은 특검법 따냈는데…장동혁은 왜 한동훈과 싸울까)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/394/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118501626.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;18일 더불어민주당에 통일교·공천헌금 쌍특검 수용을 요구하며 국회 로텐더홀에서 나흘째 단식 투쟁을 이어가고 있는 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 의료진의 진찰을 받고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'last breakfast' was abalone porridge. He picked up his spoon and chopsticks but left more than half the bowl. There had been a doctor's advice to reduce food intake before starting the hunger strike. There was also advice that, due to gastritis, suddenly fasting could twist his stomach. So, for the first three days of the fast, he decided to drink rice water. That's why rumors spread among the public that the white broth he was drinking was bear soup. (‘최후의 조찬’은 전복죽이었다. 수저를 들었지만 반 그릇 이상 남겼다. 단식에 들어가기 전 음식량을 줄여야 한다는 의사 충고가 있었다. 위염이 있어 갑자기 굶으면 위가 뒤틀릴 수 있다는 조언도 있었다. 그래서 단식 초반 사흘은 쌀뜨물을 먹기로 했다. 항간에 그가 마시는 허연 국물을 두고 곰국이라는 소문이 퍼진 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2003, Choi Byeong-ryeol, then the leader of the Grand National Party (Hannaradang), began a hunger strike protest in response to President Roh Moo-hyun's exercise of his veto against a special counsel bill investigating corruption among the president's close aides. It was a time when the Grand National Party was cornered by the illegal presidential campaign funds scandal (the "Cha Ttaegi" incident). The political purpose of the hunger strike was clear, but whether it would achieve its goal was uncertain. A prolonged hunger strike was anticipated, and his age of 65 was a burden. Despite mockery calling it a 'health fast' rather than a 'save-the-nation fast,' he diligently carried out his 'pre-fast buildup.' Secretary-General Lee Jae-oh joined in a solidarity fast. (2003년 11월26일 최병렬 당시 한나라당 대표가 노무현 대통령의 측근 비리 특검법 거부권 행사에 반발해 단식농성에 들어갔다. 한나라당 불법 대선자금 사건(차떼기 사건)으로 궁지에 몰리던 때였다. 단식농성의 정치적 목적은 분명했고, 목적 달성 여부는 불분명했다. 단식농성 장기화가 예상됐고, 65살이라는 나이는 부담이었다. ‘구국 단식’이 아닌 ‘건강 단식’이라는 조롱에도 ‘단식 전 빌드업’을 착실하게 했다. 이재오 사무총장은 동조 단식을 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crisis came unexpectedly. An oblivious party lawmaker came for a visit of encouragement and started talking about the bosintang (dog meat soup) he had eaten for dinner. The Democratic Labor Party criticized the main opposition leader's hunger strike for ignoring urgent livelihood issues as a 'hunger strike tantrum' and tried to deliver jajangmyeon (black bean noodles). Police guarding the entrance of the Grand National Party headquarters in Yeouido, Seoul, the site of the hunger strike, attempted to confiscate the delivery container, and the bowl of jajangmyeon overturned, rolling in front of the party headquarters along with pickled radish. The labor sector defined the main opposition leader's hunger strike as an 'illegal strike.' (위기는 예기치 않게 찾아온다. 눈치 없는 소속 의원이 격려 방문을 와서는 저녁에 먹은 보신탕 얘기를 했다. 민주노동당은 민생현안을 도외시한 거대야당 대표의 단식농성을 ‘단식투정’이라고 비난하며 짜장면을 전달하려 했다. 단식농성장인 서울 여의도 한나라당 당사 입구를 지키고 있던 경찰이 철가방을 탈취하려 했고, 짜장면 그릇이 엎어지며 단무지와 함께 당사 앞을 굴렀다. 노동계는 거대야당 대표의 단식농성을 ‘불법파업’으로 규정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although he starved, he was able to secure his weakened leadership within the party and satiate his political hunger. Over a thousand people visited to encourage him during his six-day fast. Not only the party mainstream but also the younger faction, which had opposed 'Choi-tler's extreme struggle,' said, 'We must gather strength for our leader.' Former President Kim Young-sam, who held the record for the longest hunger strike by a politician at the time (23 days), visited Representative Choi on the 8th day of his fast. "I also fasted for 23 days, but it's certain that if you starve, you die." Former President Kim advised him to stop the fast, leaving behind his famous remark, "If you starve, you die." (밥은 굶었지만 허약했던 당내 리더십을 확보하며 정치적 허기를 채울 수 있었다. 단식 중인 그를 엿새 만에 1천여명이 찾아 격려했다. 당내 주류는 물론, ‘최틀러 극한투쟁’에 반대하던 소장파까지 ‘대표에게 힘을 모아줘야 한다’고 했다. 당시 정치인 최장 단식 기록(23일)을 갖고 있던 김영삼 전 대통령이 단식농성 8일째를 맞은 최 대표를 찾았다. “나도 23일간 단식해봤지만, 굶으면 죽는 것이 확실하다.” 김 전 대통령은 단식 중단을 권하며 그 유명한 ‘굵으면 죽는다’는 말을 남겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 9th day of his fast, Representative Choi also wrote a 'Letter to President Roh Moo-hyun' published in the Hankyoreh newspaper. He said, "I want to meet the President one-on-one, open my heart, and have a discussion." The Grand National Party, the Democratic Party, and the United Liberal Democrats cooperated to re-vote on the special counsel bill for corruption among close aides. Representative Choi's fast ended after ten days. Hospitalized at Seoul National University Hospital, he could only return to party duties six days later, despite his pre-fast buildup. The special counsel investigation, which began as President Roh Moo-hyun promulgated the re-voted bill, ended in futility. All major suspicions pointed out by the Grand National Party were concluded to be untrue. (최 대표는 단식 9일째 한겨레 지면을 통해 ‘노무현 대통령에게 보내는 편지’를 쓰기도 했다. “대통령과 일 대 일로 만나서 흉금을 터놓고 토론하고 싶다”고 했다. 한나라당·민주당·자민련이 공조해 측근 비리 특검법을 재의결했다. 최 대표 단식은 열흘 만에 끝났다. 서울대병원에 입원한 그는, 단식 빌드업에도 불구하고 엿새 뒤에야 당무에 복귀할 수 있었다. 재의결된 법안을 노무현 대통령이 공포하며 시작한 특검 수사는 허망했다. 한나라당이 지목한 주요 의혹은 모두 사실이 아닌 것으로 결론 났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House is unresponsive... Han Dong-hoon: "It's fabrication and retaliation, but..." (청와대는 무반응…한동훈 “조작·보복이지만”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok's decision to go on a hunger strike was suddenly made after 2 PM on the 15th. He stated it was a hunger strike urging the ruling party and the President to introduce a dual special counsel (Unification Church/ nomination bribery special counsel) targeting the Democratic Party of Korea. Not only the ruling party but also many within the People Power Party viewed it as 'sudden and out of the blue.' It was criticized as a 'fasting event' to break through the rapidly deteriorating public opinion and leadership crisis inside and outside the party following the decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표 단식은 15일 오후 2시 넘어 갑자기 결정됐다. 여당과 대통령을 향해 더불어민주당을 수사 대상으로 하는 쌍특검(통일교·공천헌금 특검) 도입을 촉구하는 단식이라고 했다. 여당은 물론 국민의힘 내부에서도 ‘뜬금없다’는 시각이 많았다. 한동훈 전 대표 제명 결정으로 급격히 나빠진 당 안팎 여론과 리더십 위기를 돌파하려는 ‘공복 이벤트’라는 비판이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;23 years ago, Representative Choi Byeong-ryeol's hunger strike was an attempt to create a 'opposition leader vs. president' one-on-one confrontation. Strangely, Representative Jang's hunger strike has only made the 'Jang Dong-hyeok vs. Han Dong-hoon' confrontation clear. It's a sight of a sitting party leader fighting a former party leader. This is why analyses are emerging that it is a political act of self-harm by an opposition leader ahead of local elections. (23년 전 최병렬 대표의 단식은 ‘야당대표 대 대통령’ 일 대 일 구도를 만들려는 시도였다. 장 대표의 단식은 기이하게도 ‘장동혁 대 한동훈’ 구도만 선명해졌다. 현직 당대표가 전직 당대표와 싸우는 꼴이다. 지방선거를 앞두고 야당대표의 정치적 자해 행위라는 분석이 나오는 이유다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, the fourth day of Representative Jang's fast, the Democratic Party of Korea expressed the position that "it's regrettable why he is doing this." Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun pointed out at a press briefing, citing examples of hunger strikes by former Presidents Kim Young-sam and Moon Jae-in, and President Lee Jae-myung during their time as opposition politicians, that "a life-risking hunger strike by the leader of the main opposition party should be undertaken as a means to significantly shift the course of history or as a last resort." (장 대표 단식 나흘째인 18일, 더불어민주당은 ‘왜 저러는지 안타깝다’는 입장을 냈다. 박수현 수석대변인은 기자간담회에서 김영삼·문재인 전 대통령, 이재명 대통령의 야당 정치인 시절 단식 사례를 거론하며 “제1야당 대표의 목숨 건 단식은 역사의 물줄기를 크게 전환하거나 최후의 수단으로 이뤄져야 한다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House has no official response. Although it was a pre-scheduled event before the hunger strike began, President Lee invited the leadership of the ruling party and five opposition parties for a luncheon meeting on the 16th. It was an event Representative Jang did not attend. They took a commemorative photo shouting "Fighting, Republic of Korea!" The People Power Party revealed its uncomfortable feelings, saying, "Now is not the time for a leisurely 'lunch show'," and proposed a bilateral meeting between President Lee and the People Power Party leadership. There is also a possibility that newly appointed Blue House Senior Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo, who begins his duties on the 20th, may visit Representative Jang's hunger strike site during his 'courtesy visit' to the National Assembly on that day. Secretary Hong said that day, "As a bridge connecting the Blue House and the political arena, I will open my ears wide, move diligently, do my best to convey various opinions without addition or subtraction, and forge them into a united force." (청와대는 공식 반응이 없다. 단식 돌입 전 미리 잡힌 일정이긴 하지만, 이 대통령은 지난 16일 여당과 야5당 지도부를 초청해 오찬 회동을 했다. 장 대표는 불참한 행사였다. “대한민국 파이팅”을 외치며 기념사진을 찍었다. 국민의힘은 “지금 한가한 ‘오찬 쇼’를 할 때가 아니다”라고 불편한 속내를 드러내며, 이 대통령과 국민의힘의 지도부 양자 회담을 제안했다. 18일 새로 임명된 홍익표 청와대 정무수석이 업무를 시작하는 20일 ‘인사차’ 국회를 방문하며 장 대표의 단식농성장을 찾을 가능성도 있다. 홍 수석은 이날 “청와대와 정치권을 잇는 가교로서 귀를 크게 열고, 부지런히 움직여 다양한 의견들을 가감 없이 전달하고 하나 된 힘으로 만들어가는 데 최선을 다하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one who reacted to Representative Jang's hunger strike was former leader Han Dong-hoon. After a period of inactivity on Facebook following his expulsion, he said on the 18th, "The disciplinary action against me is a clear fabrication and political retaliation, but... I feel apologetic to the public and party members that the situation has come to this point." Within the People Power Party, there are calls for former leader Han to provide an explanation and apology regarding the party bulletin board incident first, in order to mend the self-destructive clash between the former and current party leaders. It appears he has chosen a rhetoric of making a comprehensive apology for the current party situation, lumping things together, likely viewing that a specific explanation and apology could become a self-inflicted wound, politically and legally tripping him up. (장 대표의 단식에 반응한 것은 한동훈 전 대표였다. 제명 처분 이후 한동안 페이스북을 끊었던 그는, 18일 “저에 대한 징계는 명백한 조작이자 정치보복”이라면서도 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것에 대해 국민과 당원께 송구한 마음”이라고 했다. 국민의힘 내부에서는 전·현직 당대표의 자해적인 충돌을 봉합하기 위해 우선 당원게시판 사건에 대한 한 전 대표의 소명과 사과를 요구하고 있다. 구체적 해명과 사과가 자칫 정치적·법적으로 발목을 잡는 자충수가 될 수 있다고 보고, 현재의 당내 상황에 대한 포괄적 사과로 뭉뚱그리는 화법을 선택한 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another Attempt to Secure Leadership with a Record-Breaking Fast? (이번에도 최장 기록으로 리더십 확보 시도?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not known what Representative Jang's last meal was before his fast. However, by the end of last year, Representative Jang had already lost 7kg. A fast started without physical preparation places a great strain on the body. Not only is the justification weak, but it also cannot be sustained for long. Being taken to the hospital after fasting for about a week in an awkward state yields no gains. (장 대표의 단식 전 마지막 식사가 무엇이었는지는 알려진 바 없다. 다만 지난 연말 장 대표는 이미 몸무게가 7㎏ 빠진 상태였다. 몸만들기 없이 바로 시작한 단식은 몸에 무리가 크다. 명분도 약하지만 오래 할 수도 없다. 일주일 정도 단식을 하다 병원에 실려 가는 어정쩡한 모습으로는 얻는 것도 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some in political circles also view Representative Jang as being sensitive to 'political records.' At the end of last year, Representative Jang conducted a 24-hour filibuster opposing the bill to establish a special court for insurrection cases. The fact that it was highlighted as a 'record-long in the National Assembly' brought evaluations from inside and outside the party that it showed the opposition leader's resolve, and it had the effect of temporarily easing the leadership crisis. (정치권 일각에서는 장 대표가 ‘정치적 기록’에 민감하다는 시각도 있다. 장 대표는 지난 연말 내란전담재판부법에 반대하며 24시간 필리버스터를 했다. ‘국회 최장 기록’이라는 점이 부각되며 야당 대표의 결기를 보여줬다는 당 안팎 평가와 함께, 리더십 위기를 잠시 진화하는 효과가 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, this time, setting a record is not expected to be easy. The longest hunger strike records among politicians are held by progressive party figures. The longest record is 30 days. In 2011, Roh Hoe-chan and Shim Sang-jeong, standing advisors of the New Progressive Party, conducted a month-long hunger strike demanding the withdrawal of layoffs at Hanjin Heavy Industries. The record within the National Assembly is held by lawmaker Kang Gi-gap of the Democratic Labor Party. In 2005, he fasted for 29 days in opposition to the ratification motion for the rice tariffization delay agreement. Although he was transferred to the hospital midway, he resumed fasting. It is said Lawmaker Kang maintained his physical condition through meditation and abdominal breathing. (다만 이번에는 기록 세우기가 쉽지 않을 전망이다. 정치인 최장 단식 기록은 진보정당 인사들이 가지고 있다. 최장 기록은 30일이다. 2011년 노회찬·심상정 진보신당 상임고문이 한진중공업 정리해고 철회를 요구하며 한 달간 단식농성을 했다. 원내 기록은 강기갑 민주노동당 의원이 갖고 있다. 2005년 쌀 관세화 유예협상 비준동의안에 반대하며 29일간 단식했다. 중간에 병원에 이송되기도 했지만, 다시 단식에 나섰다. 강 의원은 명상과 복식호흡으로 몸 상태를 유지했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Kim Nam-il &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (김남일 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:namfic@hani.co.kr"&gt;namfic@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240329.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/394/imgdb/original/2026/0118/20260118501626.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party to Boycott Tomorrow's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing'... Clash Inevitable as They Insist on Chair's Authority (국힘, 내일 ‘이혜훈 청문회’ 불참…사회권 고수에 충돌 불가피)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240373.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;People Power Party to Boycott Tomorrow's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing'... Clash Inevitable as They Insist on Chair's Authority (국힘, 내일 ‘이혜훈 청문회’ 불참…사회권 고수에 충돌 불가피)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687341530997_20260118502028.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 박수영 간사(가운데) 등 의원들이 18일 국회 소통관에서 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회 거부를 밝히고 있다. 왼쪽부터 박대출, 박수영, 최은석 의원. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, one day before the confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, the People Power Party (PPP) declared a boycott of the hearing. While the Democratic Party of Korea (DPK) stated it is willing to hold the hearing alone if the PPP does not participate, the PPP indicated it will not simply stand by if a unilateral hearing is held, making clashes and disruption seem inevitable. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회를 하루 앞둔 18일 국민의힘이 청문회 보이콧을 선언했다. 더불어민주당은 국민의힘이 불참한다면 단독 개최도 불사한다는 방침이지만, 국민의힘이 단독 청문회를 순순히 지켜보지만은 않겠다는 입장이어서 충돌과 파행이 불가피해 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP lawmakers belonging to the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee held a press conference at the National Assembly Communication Center, stating, "This nominee should be sitting in an interrogation room at an investigative agency, not in a National Assembly hearing room," and "We completely refuse to hold a confirmation hearing for a lawbreaker." The PPP also cited the nominee's failure to submit additional requested materials, citing personal information, as grounds for refusing the hearing. (국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들은 이날 국회 소통관에서 기자회견을 열어 “이 후보자는 국회 청문회장이 아니라, 수사기관 피의자 자리에 앉아야 할 사람”이라며 “범법행위자에 대한 인사청문회를 전면 거부한다”고 밝혔다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 개인정보 등을 이유로 추가 요구 자료를 제출하지 않고 있다는 것도 청문회 거부의 명분으로 삼았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;DPK lawmakers on the Planning and Finance Committee issued a statement saying, "The PPP Planning and Finance Committee members' refusal to hold a confirmation hearing for this nominee is tantamount to the National Assembly abandoning its own authority and responsibility," and "The nominee's side has been continuously striving to submit the key materials requested by the PPP by today." The DPK believes that with PPP lawmakers boycotting the hearing, the justification for holding it unilaterally is satisfied. (재정경제기획위 소속 민주당 의원들은 이날 성명을 내어 “국민의힘 소속 재경위원들이 이 후보자에 대한 인사청문회를 거부하는 것은, 국회 스스로 권한과 책임을 포기하는 것”이라며 “후보자 측은 오늘까지 국민의힘이 요구한 주요 자료를 제출하기 위해 지속적으로 노력하고 있다”고 했다. 민주당은 국민의힘 의원들이 청문회를 보이콧한 만큼 단독 개최의 명분은 충족됐다고 보는 분위기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, even if the PPP boycotts, the hearing on the 19th is unlikely to proceed smoothly. This is because the PPP maintains that, separate from its committee members' non-participation, it will not relinquish the chair's authority to preside over the meeting. PPP floor leader Song Eon-seok met with reporters at the National Assembly and said, "It is a misjudgment to talk about (the ruling party) taking over the chair's authority just because (PPP member and Planning and Finance Committee Chairman Lim) is refusing to hold the hearing." (하지만 국민의힘이 청문회를 보이콧하더라도 19일 청문회가 순탄하게 진행되기는 어려울 것으로 보인다. 국민의힘이 소속 재경위원들의 청문회 불참과 별개로 상임위원장의 사회권은 넘길 수 없다는 입장을 고수하고 있기 대문이다. 송언석 원내대표는 이날 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “(국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장이) 청문회를 거부하는 게 아니기 때문에 (여당에서) 사회권을 가져갈 수 있다고 운운하는 것은 잘못된 판단”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DPK stated, "If Chairman Lim does not exercise his chair's authority, transferring it to the secretary of the largest negotiating group (Rep. Jeong Tae-ho) is the procedure under the National Assembly Act." According to the National Assembly Act, if a standing committee chairman refuses or avoids convening or proceeding with a meeting, the secretary of the majority party can act on behalf of the chairman. However, if Chairman Lim does not hand over the gavel and instead sits in the chairman's seat to delay the proceedings, the DPK lacks a clear method to force the issue. (민주당은 “임 위원장이 사회권을 행사하지 않으면 제1당 교섭단체 간사(정태호 의원)에게 사회권을 넘기는 것이 국회법상 절차”라고 했다. 국회법상 상임위원장이 개회 또는 의사진행을 거부·기피하면 다수당의 간사가 위원장 직무를 대행할 수 있다는 것이다. 하지만 임 위원장이 의사봉을 넘기지 않고 위원장석에 앉아 회의 진행을 지연시킬 경우 민주당으로선 강행할 방법이 마땅치 않다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at this hearing, the nominee must face verification of suspicions, including allegations that she fraudulently applied for a high-priced apartment in Seoul's Seocho District worth over 4 billion won by postponing her eldest son's marriage registration and address change to increase the number of dependents. Other suspicions include that her spouse purchased land in the Yeongjong Island area about a year before the opening of Incheon International Airport and sold it to the Korea Land and Housing Corporation six years later, reaping profits in the range of 2 billion won; that her husband, an expert in the field, was listed as a co-author on her eldest son's doctoral dissertation, a so-called 'dad chance' suspicion; and suspicions of power abuse by her aides. (한편 이 후보자는 장남의 혼인 신고와 주소 이전을 미뤄 부양가족을 늘리는 방식으로 서울 서초구 고가 아파트를 부정 청약해 40억원 넘는 이득을 취했다는 의혹 등을 이번 청문회에서 검증받아야 하는 상황이다. 배우자가 인천국제공항 개항 1년여 전 영종도 일대 토지를 매입하고 6년 뒤 한국토지공사에 매각해 20억원대의 차익을 남겼다는 의혹, 장남이 쓴 박사 논문에 해당 분야 전문가인 아버지가 공동 저자로 이름을 올린 ‘아빠 찬스’ 의혹, 보좌진 갑질 의혹도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party and the presidential office maintain that they will decide on the nominee's appointment after observing the hearing verification and the resulting public opinion. In a briefing, Lee Gyu-yeon, Senior Presidential Secretary for Public Communication, responded to a question about whether the presidential office's stance has changed given the PPP's boycott, saying, "There is absolutely no change in our stance." (당·청은 청문회 검증과 이에 따른 여론을 지켜보며 이 후보자의 임명 여부를 판단한다는 입장을 유지하고 있다. 이규연 청와대 홍보소통수석은 이날 브리핑에서 국민의힘이 청문회 보이콧을 한 상황에서 청와대 입장 변화가 있느냐는 질문에 “입장에는 전혀 변함이 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Kim Min-do, Jang Na-rae, and Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 장나래 고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240373.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687341530997_20260118502028.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Daejeon-Chungnam, Gwangju-Jeonnam Administrative Integration Picks Up Speed... Shaking Up Local Election Landscape (대전·충남, 광주·전남 행정통합 속도전에…지방선거 판 흔들)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240379.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Daejeon-Chungnam, Gwangju-Jeonnam Administrative Integration Picks Up Speed... Shaking Up Local Election Landscape (대전·충남, 광주·전남 행정통합 속도전에…지방선거 판 흔들)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687454364703_20260118502146.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김민석 국무총리가 16일 서울 종로구 정부서울청사에서 행정통합 인센티브와 관련해 브리핑을 하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the government is finalizing support plans worth tens of trillions of won for the administrative integration of Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam, the political sphere has found it inevitable to establish strategies for the June 3 local elections based on the premise of administrative integration, just in case. With the election landscape in regions where the first integrated local government heads could be elected becoming volatile, the concerns of potential candidates and central parties are deepening. (정부가 수십조원에 이르는 대전·충남, 광주·전남 행정통합 지원 방안 등을 구체화하면서, 정치권에서는 만일을 대비해 행정통합을 전제로 한 6·3 지방선거 전략 수립이 불가피해졌다. 첫 통합단체장 선출 가능성이 생긴 지역의 선거 판도가 출렁이면서 출마 후보군과 중앙당의 고민이 깊어지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Daejeon-Chungnam, which the Democratic Party of Korea aims to recapture, Democratic Party lawmakers Jang Jong-tae (Daejeon Seo-gap) and Jang Cheol-min (Daejeon Dong-gu) have already declared their candidacy for the integrated mayor position. Additionally, lawmakers Park Beom-kye (Daejeon Seo-eul) and Cho Seung-rae (Daejeon Yuseong-gap), along with lawmakers Moon Jin-seok (Chungnam Cheonan-gap) and Park Soo-hyun (Chungnam Gongju·Buyeo·Cheongyang), who were initially mentioned as potential candidates for Chungnam governor, are now being mentioned as part of the candidate pool for the integrated mayor position. In the region, former Chungnam Governor Yang Seung-jo and former Daejeon Mayor Heo Tae-jeong are also mentioned as possible candidates. (더불어민주당이 탈환을 노리는 대전·충남에서는 민주당 장종태(대전 서갑)·장철민(대전 동구) 의원이 이미 통합시장 출마를 선언한 상태다. 여기에 박범계(대전 서을)·조승래(대전 유성갑) 의원, 애초 충남도지사 출마가 거론되던 문진석(충남 천안갑)·박수현(충남 공주·부여·청양) 의원이 통합시장 출마 후보군으로 이름이 오르내리고 있다. 지역에서는 양승조 전 충남지사, 허태정 전 대전시장도 출마 가능 인사로 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the People Power Party, incumbent Governor Kim Tae-heum of Chungnam and incumbent Mayor Lee Jang-woo of Daejeon, who have the advantage of being incumbents, are strong contenders for re-election. However, Governor Kim recently hinted that he would not run if the integration is successfully realized. (국민의힘에서는 현역 프리미엄이 있는 김태흠 충남지사와 이장우 대전시장의 재도전이 유력하다. 다만 김 지사는 최근 통합이 성사되면 불출마하겠다는 뜻을 내비친 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Gwangju-Jeonnam, where the Democratic Party primary result is often seen as tantamount to election, the situation is even more turbulent. While the re-election bids of Gwangju Mayor Kang Ki-jeong and former Jeonnam Governor Kim Young-rok are anticipated, in Gwangju, lawmakers Min Hyung-bae (Gwangsan-eul) and Jeong Jun-ho (Buk-gap), former lawmaker Lee Byung-hoon (Chief Vice-Chairman of the Democratic Party's Honam Development Special Committee), and Moon In, the head of Buk-gu District Office, are categorized as potential candidates. In Jeonnam, lawmakers Shin Jeong-hoon (Naju·Hwasun), Lee Gae-ho (Damyang·Hampyeong·Yeonggwang·Jangseong), and Joo Cheol-hyun (Yeosu-gap) are mentioned. (민주당 경선 결과가 곧 당선으로 받아들여지는 광주·전남은 판세가 더 요동친다. 강기정 광주시장과 김영록 전남지사의 재도전이 점쳐지는 가운데, 광주에서는 민형배(광산을)·정준호(북갑) 의원, 이병훈 전 의원(민주당 호남발전특위 수석부위원장), 문인 북구청장 등이 출마 후보군으로 분류된다. 전남에서는 신정훈(나주·화순)·이개호(담양·함평·영광·장성)·주철현(여수갑) 의원이 언급된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The biggest variable shaking up the election landscape is whether Blue House officials will run. In the case of Daejeon-Chungnam, the possibility of Blue House Chief of Staff Kang Hun-sik, whose hometown is Asan, Chungnam, running is being discussed. He served three terms in Asan-eul, Chungnam. A political figure from the region said on the 18th, "If Chief Kang runs, the election scale could expand, and a box office effect is also expected. However, we need to wait and see a bit more how the nomination method for the integrated local government head will be finalized." Rumors about Blue House Policy Chief Kim Yong-beom, who was born in Muan, Jeonnam and attended high school in Gwangju, running in Gwangju-Jeonnam also persist. Public officials wishing to run in the local elections must resign by March 5th (90 days before the election date). (선거 판도를 흔들 최대 변수는 청와대 인사의 출마 여부다. 대전·충남의 경우 충남 아산이 고향인 강훈식 청와대 비서실장의 출마 가능성이 거론된다. 충남 아산을에서 3선을 했다. 이 지역 정치권 인사는 18일 “강 실장이 출마한다면 선거판이 커지고 흥행 효과도 기대할 수 있다. 다만 통합단체장 공천 방식이 어떻게 정리될지 좀 더 지켜봐야 한다”고 했다. 전남 무안에서 태어나 광주에서 고등학교를 나온 김용범 청와대 정책실장의 광주·전남 출마설도 잦아들지 않고 있다. 지방선거에 출마하려는 공무원은 오는 3월5일까지(선거일 기준 90일 전) 사퇴해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol, Jang Na-rae, Seo Young-ji &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 장나래 서영지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240379.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/384/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687454364703_20260118502146.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"To Extend Chung Cheong-rae's Term" "Refrain from Remarks Seen as Leadership Struggles"... Tensions Over 'One Member, One Vote' Party Charter Revision (“정청래 연임용” “당권투쟁 언행 말라”…‘1인1표’ 당헌개정 신경전)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240380.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;"To Extend Chung Cheong-rae's Term" "Refrain from Remarks Seen as Leadership Struggles"... Tensions Over 'One Member, One Vote' Party Charter Revision (“정청래 연임용” “당권투쟁 언행 말라”…‘1인1표’ 당헌개정 신경전)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687457267371_20260118502148.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;더불어민주당 박수현 수석대변인이 18일 국회에서 현안 관련 기자간담회를 열고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea will submit a party charter revision bill, which includes the 'one member, one vote system for rights-holding party members and delegates', to its Party Affairs Committee on the 19th. This comes about a month and a half after a party charter revision bill with the same content was voted down in the Central Committee. As some within the party pointed out that this is 'for extending Representative Chung Cheong-rae's term', Representative Chung's side expressed displeasure, saying, "Refrain from remarks that could be seen as a leadership struggle." (더불어민주당이 ‘권리당원-대의원 1인1표제’가 포함된 당헌 개정안을 19일 당무위원회에 올린다. 같은 내용의 당헌 개정안이 중앙위원회에서 부결된 지 약 한달 반 만이다. 이를 두고 당 일각에서 ‘정청래 대표 연임용’이라는 지적이 나오자, 정 대표 쪽은 “당권 투쟁으로 보일 수 있는 언행을 자제하라”며 불쾌감을 드러냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding reports of internal disagreements over the 'one member, one vote system', Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun said at a press briefing at the National Assembly on the 18th, "Isn't the core question whether one member, one vote is the Democratic Party's zeitgeist, or whether it is a stepping stone for Representative Chung Cheong-rae's re-election?" He added, "The assumption that if the one member, one vote system is implemented, rights-holding party members will unconditionally support Representative Chung without question or scrutiny is a disparagement of rights-holding party members." He further stated, "If (such arguments) go a bit further, it might reach a point where one could be criticized for electioneering and have nothing to say in defense," and emphasized, "Remarks that could be seen as a leadership struggle should be refrained from." (박수현 수석대변인은 18일 국회 기자간담회에서 ‘1인1표제’를 둘러싼 당내 이견이 있다는 보도와 관련해 “1인1표가 민주당의 시대정신인가, 아니면 정청래 대표의 연임 포석인가가 질문의 핵심 아닌가”라며 “(1인1표가 되면) 권리당원은 묻지도 따지지도 않고 무조건 정 대표를 지지할 거란 가정은 권리당원에 대한 폄훼”라고 했다. 그러면서 “(이런 주장에서) 조금 더 나가면 해당행위라고 비난받아도 할 말이 없는 상황이 될지 모르겠다”며 “당권 투쟁으로 보일 수 있는 언행은 자제돼야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inside and outside the party, there is suspicion that Representative Chung, who won overwhelmingly in the rights-holding party member vote but lost in the delegate vote at the August 2nd national convention last year, is pushing for the one member, one vote party charter revision for his re-election. It is also known that during the non-public Supreme Council meeting on the 16th, which deliberated on the charter revision bill, Supreme Council members Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Eon-joo, and Hwang Myeong-seon, who are part of the 'anti-Chung Cheong-rae faction', raised similar concerns. Supreme Council member Kang raised the issue on his Facebook that day, asking, "How will the current leadership resolve concerns about conflicts of interest that some party members may have regarding the current leadership making decisions and then immediately applying the results to the current leadership?" Supreme Council member Kang is a close associate of Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who is speculated to run for the next party leadership. (당 안팎에선 지난해 8·2 전당대회 때 권리당원 투표에서 압승했으나 대의원 투표에서 뒤진 정 대표가 연임을 위해 1인1표제 당헌 개정을 추진한다고 의심한다. 당헌 개정안을 의결한 16일 최고위원회 비공개회의에서도 ‘반정청래계’인 강득구·이언주·황명선 최고위원이 비슷한 우려를 제기한 것으로 알려졌다. 강 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에 “현 지도부에서 결정하고, 그 결과를 곧바로 현 지도부에 적용하는 것에 대해 일부 당원들이 가질 수 있는 이해충돌 우려를 어떻게 해소할 것이냐”고 문제제기를 했다. 강 최고위원은 차기 당대표 출마가 점쳐지는 김민석 국무총리의 측근이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one member, one vote party charter revision bill will go through the Party Affairs Committee on the 19th and an opinion survey of rights-holding party members from the 22nd to the 24th, before being put to a vote in the Central Committee on the 2nd and 3rd of next month. The one member, one vote system received a 72% approval rate in the Central Committee vote on December 5th last year, but was voted down as it fell short of the quorum requirement of a majority of registered members (299). Unlike during the Central Committee meeting last month, the Democratic Party plans to encourage Central Committee members to participate in the vote this time. A party official said, "Even lawmakers seem to be refraining because they are burdened by being seen as engaging in a power struggle, so the likelihood of passage appears high." (1인1표 당헌 개정안은 19일 당무위원회와 22~24일 권리당원 여론조사를 거쳐 다음달 2~3일 중앙위원회 투표에 부쳐진다. 1인1표제는 지난해 12월5일 중앙위 표결에서 72%의 찬성률을 기록했지만, 의결 기준인 재적 과반(299명)에 미달해 부결된 바 있다. 민주당은 지난달 중앙위 때와 달리 이번에는 중앙위원들의 투표 참여를 독려한다는 방침이다. 당 관계자는 “의원들도 권력다툼으로 비치는 게 부담스러워 자제하는 분위기라 통과 가능성이 높아 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ki Min-do &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (기민도 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:key@hani.co.kr"&gt;key@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240380.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687457267371_20260118502148.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Provide support so substantial that you'll regret it if administrative integration doesn't happen before the local elections" (이 대통령 “‘지방선거 전 행정통합’ 안 하면 후회할 만큼 지원해라”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240381.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee: "Provide support so substantial that you'll regret it if administrative integration doesn't happen before the local elections" (이 대통령 “‘지방선거 전 행정통합’ 안 하면 후회할 만큼 지원해라”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687458272205_20260118502150.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 지난 16일 청와대 상춘재에서 열린 정당 지도부 초청 오찬에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been confirmed that the government's presentation on the 16th of a groundbreaking incentive plan to provide up to 40 trillion won over four years to the special cities of Daejeon-South Chungcheong and Gwangju-South Jeolla, which would be created through administrative integration, was based on President Lee Jae-myung's instruction that "we must provide support on such a scale that we would deeply regret it if integration doesn't happen this time." (정부가 지난 16일 행정통합으로 생길 대전·충남, 광주·전남 특별시에 4년간 최대 40조원을 지원하는 파격적 인센티브를 제시한 데는 “이번에 통합하지 않으면 두고두고 후회할 만큼 지원해야 한다”는 이재명 대통령의 지시가 있었던 것으로 확인됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party official told The Hankyoreh on the 18th, "President Lee recently instructed (the relevant ministries) that 'if administrative integration doesn't happen before this year's local elections, it will become even more difficult in the future. If we don't integrate this time, we must provide large-scale support to the extent that we will deeply regret it for a long time.' Accordingly, the Ministry of Economy and Finance prepared and brought forward this extraordinary plan," the official said. Attendees also relayed that during a luncheon meeting with lawmakers from Gwangju and South Jeolla on the 9th, President Lee said, "Will there be anyone who can provide support as generously as I can for (administrative integration)? We must create a turning point for integration even if it means overexerting ourselves." The integration of metropolitan governments is also part of President Lee's regional development pledge, summarized as '5 Megaregions, 3 Special Autonomous Provinces' during the last presidential election. It is a plan to reorganize the country into 5 megaregions (Capital Region, Central Region, Daegu-Gyeongbuk Region, Honam Region, Southeast Region) and 3 special autonomous provinces (Jeju, North Jeolla, Gangwon) to pursue balanced development. (여권 관계자는 18일 한겨레에 “이 대통령이 최근 ‘올해 지방선거 전에 행정통합을 하지 않으면 앞으로는 더 어려워진다. 이번에 통합하지 않으면 두고두고 후회할 만큼 대규모로 지원해야 한다’고 (소관 부처에) 지시했다”며 “이에 따라 기획예산처가 파격적인 안을 짜서 가져왔다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 지난 9일 광주·전남 의원들과 한 오찬 간담회에서도 “나처럼 (행정통합에) 통 크게 지원할 수 있는 사람이 있겠나. 무리를 해서라도 통합의 전기를 만들어야 한다”고 말했다고 참석자들이 전했다. 광역자치단체 통합은 지난 대선 당시 ‘5극3특’으로 요약되는 이 대통령의 지역발전 공약이기도 하다. 전국을 5개 초광역권(수도권·중부권·대경권·호남권·동남권)과 3개 특별자치도(제주·전북·강원)로 재편해 균형 발전을 꾀한다는 구상이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also a political calculation underlying the recent drive for administrative integration. This is because having the ruling party in government, which holds policy decision-making power, take the lead in setting the agenda on a mega-issue like 'city/province integration' is advantageous for securing election initiative. In fact, the ruling party atmosphere is that now is the most opportune time to play the administrative integration card. Recent opinion polls also show that support for administrative integration is high not only in Gwangju and South Jeolla, the Democratic Party's stronghold, but also in Daejeon and South Chungcheong, a key battleground in the central region. A ruling party official said, "It allows us to preempt a core election issue without putting a significant burden on the President's approval rating, and if we win the election, it can strengthen our initiative in state affairs." The Democratic Party aims to propose bills related to administrative integration and complete their passage in the plenary session next month. (최근의 행정통합 드라이브에는 정치적 셈법도 깔려 있다. ‘시·도 통합’이라는 초대형 이슈는 정책 결정권을 쥔 정부 여당이 선도적으로 의제화하는 게 선거 주도권을 확보하는 데도 유리하기 때문이다. 실제 여권은 지금이 행정통합 카드를 꺼내기에 가장 적기라고 보는 분위기다. 최근 여론조사에서도 행정통합에 찬성하는 응답은 더불어민주당 텃밭인 광주·전남뿐 아니라, 중부권 승부처인 대전·충남에서도 높게 나타났다. 여권 관계자는 “대통령 지지율에 큰 부담을 주지 않으면서 선거판 핵심 이슈를 선점할 수 있고, 선거에서 승리할 경우엔 국정 운영의 주도권을 강화할 수 있다”고 했다. 민주당은 행정통합 관련 법안을 발의해, 다음달 본회의 처리까지 마치는 게 목표다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party is protesting, calling it a "hasty integration for elections." Spokesperson Ham In-kyung said in a commentary that day, "Although Prime Minister Kim Min-seok presented the administrative integration incentive, the method for securing that enormous budget was left blank as 'to be determined later,'" adding, "The People Power Party supports integration but firmly opposes hasty integration." (국민의힘은 ‘선거용 졸속 통합’이라며 반발하고 있다. 함인경 대변인은 이날 논평을 내어 “김민석 총리가 행정통합 인센티브를 내놨지만 정작 그 막대한 재원 마련 방식은 ‘추후’라고 비워두었다”며 “국민의힘은 통합에 찬성하지만, 졸속 통합에는 단호히 반대한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Seo Young-ji, Go Han-sol, Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (서영지 고한솔 장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:yj@hani.co.kr"&gt;yj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240381.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687458272205_20260118502150.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon's Strange Apology, Jang Dong-hyeok Still on Hunger Strike... Where is the People Power Party's Internal Strife Headed? (한동훈은 이상한 사과, 장동혁은 아직도 단식중…국힘 내분, 어디로)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240382.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Han Dong-hoon's Strange Apology, Jang Dong-hyeok Still on Hunger Strike... Where is the People Power Party's Internal Strife Headed? (한동훈은 이상한 사과, 장동혁은 아직도 단식중…국힘 내분, 어디로)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687460593199_20260118502152.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 18일 국회 본관 중앙홀에서 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하는 단식 투쟁을 4일째 이어가고 있다. 김경호 선임기자 jijae@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon apologized for the first time regarding the recent intraparty conflict triggered by the party's ethics committee's decision to expel him. However, without mentioning the party member bulletin board incident that served as the grounds for the expulsion, he repeated his existing claim that the disciplinary action was political retaliation, leading to criticism from the party mainstream that the apology "lacks sincerity." (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 18일 자신에 대한 당 윤리위원회의 제명 결정으로 촉발된 최근의 당내 갈등과 관련해 처음으로 사과했다. 하지만 제명의 명분이 된 당원게시판 사태에 대한 언급 없이 징계가 정치 보복이라는 기존 주장을 반복해 당 주류에선 ‘사과의 진정성이 없다’는 지적이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a 2-minute, 5-second video posted on Facebook that morning, former leader Han stated, "The disciplinary action against me is a clear fabrication and political retaliation," but also expressed, "As a responsible politician who led the party, I feel deeply sorry for causing concern to the public and party members regarding the situation reaching this point." While it was the first apology message issued since the party member bulletin board controversy, there was no mention regarding the allegations about his family posting on the bulletin board. (한 전 대표는 이날 오전 페이스북에 올린 2분5초 분량의 영상에서 “나에 대한 징계는 명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라면서도 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것에 대해서, 국민과 당원 여러분께 걱정을 끼쳐드린 데 대해서 당을 이끌었던 책임 있던 정치인으로서 송구한 마음”이라고 밝혔다. 당원게시판 논란 뒤 처음으로 낸 사과 메시지였지만, 가족의 당원게시판 게시글 작성 의혹과 관련한 언급은 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reason former leader Han suddenly posted the apology video today appears to be that he found it difficult to ignore demands within the party urging him to 'show efforts to resolve the conflict rather than just unconditionally opposing.' After the party leadership decided on the 15th to suspend the disciplinary resolution, offering former leader Han a chance to request a review, opinions poured out during a subsequent general meeting of lawmakers that a political solution was needed where Representative Jang Dong-hyeok would withdraw the expulsion measure, premised on an apology from former leader Han. (한 전 대표가 이날 갑자기 사과 영상을 올린 데는 한 전 대표를 향해 ‘무조건 반발만 할 게 아니라, 갈등을 풀려고 노력하는 모습을 보여줘야 한다’는 당내 요구를 외면하기 어려웠기 때문으로 보인다. 당 지도부가 지난 15일 한 전 대표에게 재심 청구 기회를 주겠다며 징계 의결 보류를 결정한 뒤 열린 의원총회에서는 한 전 대표의 사과를 전제로 장동혁 대표가 제명 조치를 철회하는 정치적 해법이 필요하다는 의견이 쏟아졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pro-Han Dong-hoon faction seems to perceive that the ball has now been passed to Representative Jang Dong-hyeok through former leader Han's message. Lawmaker Park Jeong-hoon said on Facebook that day, "I thank former leader Han for showing courage. I hope this decision becomes a foundation for normalizing the party." However, the party's power faction sharpened their knives, calling it an 'insincere apology.' Jang Ye-chan, Vice President of the Yeouido Research Institute, wrote on Facebook, "It's the worst disguised apology in history, a tantrum from the golden child of Seocho-dong," adding, "There's not a single important detail about what was wrong or to what extent it is acknowledged." Floor Leader Song Eon-seok, meeting with reporters, said, "We need to once again consider how many people are receiving the content of the apology." (친한동훈계는 한 전 대표의 메시지로 공이 장동혁 대표에게 넘어갔다고 판단하는 분위기다. 박정훈 의원은 이날 페이스북에 “용기를 내준 한 전 대표에게 감사드린다. 이 결단이 당을 정상화하는 데 밑거름이 되길 바란다”고 했다. 하지만 당권파는 ‘진정성 없는 사과’라고 날을 세웠다. 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장은 페이스북에 “역대 최악의 사과를 빙자한 서초동 금쪽이 투정문”이라며 “무엇을 잘못했는지, 어디까지 인정하는지 중요한 내용은 하나도 없다”고 했다. 송언석 원내대표는 기자들과 만나 “사과 내용에 대해 많은 분들이 어떻게 받아들이고 있는지 다시 한번 생각해봐야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang Dong-hyeok, who entered a hunger strike on the 15th demanding the ruling party accept a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds, said on the fourth day of his fast, "My body and mind are suffering, but I will protect freedom and the rule of law to the end." While voices within the party suggest considering an 'exit strategy' given the hunger strike was entered without preparation, the problem is the 'justification.' As of that day, neither the Blue House nor the Democratic Party of Korea had shown any response to Representative Jang's demand for the twin special prosecutor investigation, which he raised upon starting the hunger strike. (지난 15일 여당에 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 단식 투쟁에 들어간 장동혁 대표는 단식 나흘째인 이날 “몸도 마음도 힘들지만 자유와 법치를 끝까지 지켜내겠다”고 했다. 당내에선 준비 없이 돌입한 단식인 만큼 ‘출구 전략’을 고민해야 한다는 목소리도 나오지만, 문제는 ‘명분’이다. 청와대와 더불어민주당은 이날까지도 장 대표가 단식에 나서며 내건 쌍특검 요구에 대해 아무런 반응을 보이지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240382.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0118/53_17687460593199_20260118502152.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's Approval Rating at 53%... "Impact of Ruling Party Nomination Bribery Allegations" [Realmeter] (이 대통령 지지율 53%…“여권 공천헌금 의혹 영향” [리얼미터])</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240392.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;President Lee's Approval Rating at 53%... "Impact of Ruling Party Nomination Bribery Allegations" [Realmeter] (이 대통령 지지율 53%…“여권 공천헌금 의혹 영향” [리얼미터])&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/621/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500176.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령이 16일 청와대에서 열린 아소 다로 전 일본 총리와의 면담에서 발언하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung's approval rating for state affairs has recorded 53.1%, turning to a decline after three weeks. (이재명 대통령의 국정수행 지지도가 53.1%를 기록해 3주 만에 하락세로 돌아섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a survey (margin of error ±2 percentage points at a 95% confidence level) of 2,516 voters aged 18 and over nationwide, conducted via wireless (100%) automated response from the 12th to the 16th by Realmeter at the request of the Energy Economy Newspaper on the 19th, the positive assessment of President Lee's state affairs performance was tallied at 53.1%, down 3.7 percentage points from the previous week. (19일 리얼미터가 에너지경제신문 의뢰로 지난 12∼16일 전국 18살 이상 유권자 2516명을 대상으로 실시한 무선(100%) 자동응답 방식의 조사(표본오차 95% 신뢰수준에 ±2%포인트)를 보면, 이 대통령의 국정수행 긍정 평가는 지난주보다 3.7%포인트 내린 53.1%로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The negative assessment was surveyed at 42.2%, up 4.4 percentage points from the previous week. The gap between positive and negative assessments narrowed from 19 percentage points last week to 10.9 percentage points. (부정평가는 지난주보다 4.4%포인트 오른 42.2%로 조사됐다. 긍·부정 격차는 지난주 19%포인트에서 10.9%포인트로 좁혀졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter analyzed, "On a daily indicator basis, a clear downward trend was observed in the latter half of the week," and stated, "Despite economic and diplomatic achievements such as the KOSPI surpassing 4800 and the Korea-Japan summit, the approval rating showed a decline as controversies over morality overlapped, including the exposure of disagreements between the party and the government regarding the government's prosecution reform bills (Major Crime Investigation Bureau/Public Prosecution Service Act) and allegations of nomination bribery involving ruling party figures." (리얼미터 쪽은 “일간 지표상으로 주 후반 뚜렷한 하락세를 보였다”며 “코스피 4800 돌파와 한-일 정상회담 등 경제·외교 성과가 있었는데도, 정부의 검찰개혁안(중수청·공소청법)을 둘러싼 당정 간 이견 노출과 여권 인사들의 공천헌금 의혹 등 도덕성 논란이 겹치며 지지율이 하락세를 보였다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at the daily indicator trend, the positive assessment for state affairs performance started at 53.6% on the 13th and rebounded to 55.3% (negative 40.7%) on the 14th, but fell for two consecutive days to 52.9% (negative 42.2%) on the 15th and 51.7% (negative 42.8%) on the 16th. (일간 지표 흐름을 보면 국정수행 긍정 평가는 지난 13일 53.6%로 시작해 14일 55.3%(부정 40.7%)로 반등했지만, 15일 52.9%(부정 42.2%), 16일 51.7%(부정 42.8%)로 이틀 연속 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Positive assessments declined in all regions and age groups, with Daegu/North Gyeongsang Province (positive 48%) showing the largest drop of 8 percentage points. Incheon/Gyeonggi Province (54.6%) fell by 4.5 percentage points, Seoul (49.5%) by 3.3 percentage points, Busan/Ulsan/South Gyeongsang Province (47.6%) by 2.7 percentage points, Daejeon/Sejong/Chungcheong Province (54.0%) by 2.3 percentage points, and Gwangju/Jeolla Province (74.6%) by 1.7 percentage points each. (모든 지역과 연령대에서 긍정 평가가 하락했고, 특히 대구·경북(긍정 48%)에서 8%포인트 하락해 가장 큰 하락 폭을 보였다. 인천·경기(54.6%)는 4.5%포인트, 서울(49.5%) 3.3%포인트, 부산·울산·경남(47.6%) 2.7%포인트, 대전·세종·충청(54.0%) 2.3%포인트, 광주·전라(74.6%)는 1.7%포인트 각각 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By age group, those in their 20s (33.5%) showed the largest decline, dropping by 10.2 percentage points. Those aged 70 and above were at 49.9% (down 5.2 percentage points), those in their 60s at 55.2% (down 2.8 percentage points), those in their 50s at 65.7% (down 2.3 percentage points), and those in their 40s at 65.4% (down 2.2 percentage points). (연령별로는 20대(33.5%)에서 10.2%포인트 하락해, 하락 폭이 가장 컸다. 70대 이상 49.9%(5.2%포인트↓), 60대 55.2%(2.8%포인트↓), 50대 65.7%(2.3%포인트↓), 40대 65.4%(2.2%포인트↓) 등이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in a party support survey (margin of error ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level) conducted on 1,004 voters aged 18 and over nationwide from the 15th to the 16th, the Democratic Party of Korea was tallied at 42.5%, down 5.3 percentage points from the previous week. The People Power Party recorded 37%, up 3.5 percentage points. As the Democratic Party turned to a decline after four weeks and the People Power Party rose after four weeks, the gap between the two parties (5.5 percentage points) narrowed to within the margin of error for the first time in about four months since the fourth week of September last year. (또 지난 15∼16일 전국 18살 이상 유권자 1004명을 대상으로 이뤄진 정당 지지도 조사(표본오차 95% 신뢰수준에 ±3.1%포인트)에서 더불어민주당은 지난주보다 5.3%포인트 하락한 42.5%로 집계됐다. 국민의힘은 3.5%포인트 오른 37%를 기록했다. 더불어민주당이 4주 만에 하락세로 돌아서고, 국민의힘이 4주 만에 상승하면서 양당 간 격차(5.5%포인트)가 지난해 9월4주차 이후 4개월여 만에 오차범위 안으로 좁혀졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter analyzed, "It is judged that the Democratic Party's decline widened due to the overlap of heightened morality controversies following the full-scale investigation into the nomination bribery allegations involving lawmakers Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi, and intra-party conflict due to criticism from hardliners within the party regarding the Major Crime Investigation Bureau/Public Prosecution Service Act." Regarding the People Power Party, it explained, "It appears that the rebound in support was led by the rallying of traditional support bases such as Daegu/North Gyeongsang Province (up 15.3 percentage points) and conservatives (up 2.9 percentage points) amid controversies over the special prosecutor's demand for the death penalty for former President Yoon Seok-youl and the expulsion of Han Dong-hoon." (리얼미터는 “민주당은 강선우·김병기 의원 공천헌금 의혹 수사 본격화로 도덕성 논란이 커진 데다, 중대범죄수사청·공소청법을 둘러싼 당내 강경파 비판으로 당정 갈등이 겹치며 하락 폭을 키운 것으로 판단된다”고 분석했다. 국민의힘에 대해서는 “특검의 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형과 한동훈 제명 논란으로 대구·경북(15.3%포인트↑)과 보수층(2.9%포인트↑) 등 전통 지지층이 결집하며 지지율 반등을 이끈 것으로 보인다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the Reform Party was at 3.3%, the Fatherland Innovation Party at 2.5%, the Progressive Party at 1.7%, and non-partisans at 11.5%. (이어 개혁신당 3.3%, 조국혁신당 2.5%, 진보당 1.7%, 무당층은 11.5% 등 차례였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 누리집을 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240392.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/621/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500176.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[View Briefing] Drone Suspect Worked at President Yoon's Office ([뷰리핑] 무인기 용의자, 윤 대통령실 근무)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240396.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;[View Briefing] Drone Suspect Worked at President Yoon's Office ([뷰리핑] 무인기 용의자, 윤 대통령실 근무)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500388.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Host: Kwon Tae-ho, Editorial Department Director, The Hankyoreh. Guests: Ha Eo-young, The Hankyoreh Politics Team Reporter, Kang Soo-young, Attorney. (진행: 권태호 한겨레 논설위원실장. 출연: 하어영 한겨레 정치팀 기자, 강수영 변호사)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Drone suspect confesses... turns out he worked at President Yoon's office / 'Dual special counsel hunger strike' Jang Dong-hyeok's unreasonable move... no exit strategy in sight / Shincheonji, after building permit falls through, orders "Join the People Power Party"? / People Power Party boycott declared... a dysfunctional Lee Hye-hoon confirmation hearing / 'One person, one vote system' controversy... will Chung Cheong-rae succeed this time? / The speechless People Power Party... what is the meaning of Yoon's "5-year prison sentence"? Please tune in for today's (January 19) View Briefing. (무인기 용의자 자백…알고 보니 윤 대통령실 근무 / ‘쌍특검 단식’ 무리수 장동혁…출구 전략 안 보인다 / 신천지, 건물 허가 무산 직후 “국힘 당원 가입” 지시? / 국민의힘 보이콧 선언…파행의 이혜훈 청문회 / ‘1인 1표제’ 논란…정청래 이번엔 성공? / 말 못하는 국민의힘…윤 ‘징역 5년 선고’ 의미는? 오늘(01월 19일) 뷰리핑 많은 시청바랍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240396.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/546/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500388.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Eon-seok: "Lee Hye-hoon's confirmation hearing is pointless... Arrogant thinking that 'we must hold the hearing anyway'" (송언석 “하나마나 한 이혜훈 청문회…‘청문회 해봐야 된다’ 오만한 발상”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240403.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Song Eon-seok: "Lee Hye-hoon's confirmation hearing is pointless... Arrogant thinking that 'we must hold the hearing anyway'" (송언석 “하나마나 한 이혜훈 청문회…‘청문회 해봐야 된다’ 오만한 발상”)&lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/540/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500684.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;단식 5일째인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 19일 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 국민의힘 최고위원회의에 참석하고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Song Eon-seok, the floor leader of the People Power Party, said on the 19th regarding the scheduled confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, "It will be a pointless, bland hearing that only increases public stress." (송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 19일 예정된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회에 대해 “하나마나 한 맹탕 청문회이자, 국민 스트레스만 키우는 청문회가 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Supreme Council meeting held in the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall, where party leader Jang Dong-hyeok is conducting a hunger strike, Floor Leader Song said, "It is crystal clear that this nominee's hearing will degenerate into a venue for evasive statements regarding all sorts of power abuse, abusive language, speculation, and illegal acts." He added, "I once again urge President Lee Jae-myung to stop being stubborn and withdraw the nomination (of this candidate)." (  송 원내대표는 이날 장동혁 대표가 단식 투쟁 중인 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “이 후보자 청문회는 온갖 갑질, 막말, 투기, 불법 행위에 대한 면피성 발언의 장으로 전락할 것이 명약관화하다”며 “이재명 대통령은 더이상 고집 부리지 말고 (이 후보자를) 지명철회하길 다시 한번 촉구한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He stated, "An innumerable amount of disqualifying reasons have already been revealed," and added, "The thinking that 'we must hold the hearing anyway because the president nominated her' is extremely arrogant." He emphasized, "Nominee Lee Hye-hoon is not a subject for verification but a subject for investigation." (  그는 “이미 헤아릴 수 없을 만큼 많은 결격 사유가 드러났다”며 “대통령이 지명했으니 청문회는 해봐야 한다는 것은 매우 오만한 발상”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “이혜훈 후보자는 검증 대상이 아니라 수사 대상”이라고 강조했다. )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song also repeatedly urged the ruling party to accept the 'dual special prosecutor probes' into the Unification Church and nomination contributions. He said, "It is heartbreaking to see Leader Jang Dong-hyeok's complexion worsening and his health deteriorating day by day," and asked, "How desperate must the opposition leader be to stop eating and go on a hunger strike?" He stated, "Accepting the dual special probes is the starting point for shifting the state administration's direction," and urged, "I call on President Lee Jae-myung to immediately engage in a summit meeting with Leader Jang for state administration focused on people's livelihoods and the economy." (  송 원내대표는 또 여당에 통일교·공천헌금 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 거듭 요청했다. 그는 “장동혁 대표가 하루게 다르게 안색이 나빠지고 건강이 악화하는 모습을 보는 것이 너무 마음이 아프다”며 “야당 대표가 오죽했으면 곡기를 끊고 단식하겠냐”고 했다. 그는 “쌍특검 수용은 국정기조 전환의 출발점”이라며 “이재명 대통령은 장 대표와 민생 경제 중심의 국정 운영을 위한 영수 회담에 즉각 나서길 촉구한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who entered the 5th day of his hunger strike, said at the meeting, "I am appealing to the people with my life on the line. It is difficult," and "I am gradually reaching my limit." He then concluded his brief remarks by saying, "But if we stop here, there is no future for the Republic of Korea," and "For the future of the Republic of Korea, I ask the people to join forces with us." (  단식 5일 차에 접어든 장동혁 대표는 이날 회의에서 “목숨 걸고 국민께 호소드리고 있다. 힘이 든다”며 “점차 한계가 오고 있다”고 했다. 그러면서 “하지만 여기서 멈춘다면 대한민국에 미래는 없다”며 “대한민국의 미래를 위해 국민 여러분께서 함께 힘을 보태달라”고 짧게 발언을 마쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Na-rae &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; Reporter Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; ( 장나래 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:wing@hani.co.kr"&gt;wing@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240403.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/800/540/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500684.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kwang-han, Supreme Council Member Appointed by Jang Dong-hyuk, Says "Han Dong-hoon's Apology is Crocodile Tears" (장동혁이 임명한 조광한 최고위원 “한동훈 사과는 악어의 눈물”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240408.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/363/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500797.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;단식 5일째인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 19일 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 국민의힘 최고위원회의에서 발언하고 있다. 가장 오른쪽에 조광한 최고위원이 앉아있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kwang-han, a Supreme Council member appointed by People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, criticized the apology issued by former PPP leader Han Dong-hoon regarding the previous day's party member bulletin board incident, calling it "insincere wordplay." (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 임명한 조광한 지명직 최고위원이 전날 당원 게시판 사건과 관련해 나온 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표 사과를 두고 “진정성 없는 말장난”이라고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a Supreme Council meeting held on the 19th in the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall, where Leader Jang's hunger strike is taking place, Supreme Council Member Cho said, "I will say a word about former leader Han's insincere wordplay," adding, "The moment I heard the words of apology yesterday, I thought of crocodile tears. It's a term referring to fake tears or hypocritical actions, or a concise expression for such behavior." (조 최고위원은 19일 장 대표 단식이 진행되는 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “한 전 대표의 진정성 없는 말장난에 대해 한말씀하겠다”며 “어제 사과한다는 말을 접하는 순간 악어의 눈물이 떠올랐다. 거짓 눈물 또는 위선적 행위를 이르는 말 또는 그런 행위를 압축적으로 표현한 말”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Politics must be done with heart. We must no longer deceive the world with cunning minds, sweet talk, clever words, and feigned expressions. Especially in these already difficult times, we must stop hurting our fellow citizens." Supreme Council Member Cho was appointed by Leader Jang on the 8th to the position of appointed Supreme Council member, which had been vacant since last August. (그는 이어 “정치는 가슴으로 해야 한다. 영악한 머리를 앞세워 교언영색, 교묘한 말과 꾸민 얼굴 빛으로 더이상 세상을 속여서는 안 된다. 그렇지 않아도 세상사가 너무 힘든 요즘, 동료 시민들을 이제 그만 아프게 해야 한다”고도 했다. 조 최고위원은 지난 8일 장 대표에 의해 지난 8월 이후 공석이었던 지명직 최고위원 자리에 임명된 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This day marks the fifth day of Leader Jang's hunger strike, which he began to oppose the second comprehensive special prosecutor bill and to urge the introduction of a special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds. Prior to Supreme Council Member Cho's remarks, Supreme Council Member Yang Hyang-ja mentioned Leader Jang's hunger strike and former leader Han's apology, saying, "Let's unite as one." (이날은 2차 종합특검법 반대 및 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 도입을 촉구하며 장 대표가 단식에 돌입한 지 닷새째되는 날이다. 조 최고위원의 발언에 앞서 양향자 최고위원은 장 대표의 단식과 한 전 대표의 사과를 언급하며 “하나로 단결하자”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council Member Yang said, "Unfortunately, PPP supporters are divided into two," adding, "Can't we accept Leader Jang's intention for the hunger strike as it is and trust the sincerity of former leader Han's apology?" While expressing regret over the content of former leader Han's apology, she also said, "Let's end the conflict with a warm embrace and achieve victory through unity." (양 최고위원은 “안타깝게도 국민의힘 지지자들은 둘로 나뉘어있다”며 “장 대표가 단식하는 의도를 있는 그대로 받아주고 한 대표가 사과하는 진심 그대로를 좀 믿어줄 순 없나”라고 했다. 그는 한 전 대표의 사과 내용이 아쉽다면서도 “서로를 보듬는 따듯한 품으로 갈등을 끝내고 단결로 승리하자”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, in a video posted on Facebook the day before, former leader Han stated, "The disciplinary action against me is clear manipulation and political retaliation," but also said, "Regarding the situation having come to this point, and for causing concern to the public and party members, as a responsible politician who led the party, I feel deeply sorry." (앞서 한 전 대표는 전날 페이스북에 올린 영상에서 “나에 대한 징계는 명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라면서도 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것에 대해서, 국민과 당원 여러분께 걱정을 끼쳐드린 데 대해서 당을 이끌었던 책임있는 정치인으로서 송구한 마음”이라고 한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jeon Gwang-jun &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240408.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/363/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119500797.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi: "I will leave the Democratic Party without applying for a reconsideration of the expulsion" (김병기 “제명 재심 신청 않고 민주당 떠나겠다”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240410.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0119/53_17687865370852_5417687862504998.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김병기 전 더불어민주당 원내대표가 19일 국회 소통관에서 기자회견을 마친 뒤 엘리베이터에 타고 있다. 윤운식 선임기자 yws@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Representative Kim Byeong-gi of the Democratic Party of Korea stated, "I have not yet received the official decision document from the Ethics Tribunal, but I will not apply for reconsideration and will leave (the Democratic Party of Korea)." (김병기 더불어민주당 의원이 19일 “아직까지 윤리심판원의 결정원을 통보받지 못했지만 재심 신청을 하지 않고 (더불어민주당을) 떠나겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press conference held at the National Assembly this morning, he said, "Until now, I have stated that even if I were to be expelled, I would not choose to leave the party on my own. That position remains the same now. This is because I am confident that I can provide a clear explanation through the police investigation." However, he added, "If my presence causes disagreements within the party or places even the slightest burden on my colleagues, I believe I should fully bear that burden and leave." (그는 이날 오전 국회에서 기자회견을 열어 “그동안 저는 제명을 당하더라도 스스로 당을 떠나는 선택을 하지 않겠다고 말해왔다. 그 입장은 지금도 같다. 경찰 수사를 통해 확실하게 해명할 자신이 있기 때문”이라면서도 “저로 인해서 당 안에 이견이 생기고 동료들에게 조금이라도 마음의 짐이 된다면 그 부담 만큼은 제가 온전히 짊어지고 가야한다고 생각했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim had previously received a decision of expulsion from the Democratic Party of Korea's Ethics Tribunal due to various allegations of misconduct, including suspicions related to nomination donations and staff abuse. Regarding this, he stated, "I request that the Supreme Council consider a method to conclude (the disciplinary action) without me applying for reconsideration," and added, "I do not wish to impose even the slightest mental burden on senior, fellow, or junior lawmakers by going through the process of ratification at the general assembly of lawmakers." (김 의원은 공천 헌금·보좌진 갑질 등 각종 비위 의혹으로 더불어민주당 윤리심판원에서 제명 처분 결정을 받은 바 있다. 그는 이와 관련해 “제가 재심 신청하지 않는 상태에서 최고위원회에서 (징계를) 종결하는 방안을 검토해달라”며 ”굳이 의원총회 추인을 거치며 선배·동료·후배 의원들에게 조금이라도 마음의 부담을 지우고 싶지 않다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Hansol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240410.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/child/2026/0119/53_17687865370852_5417687862504998.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Outrageous" "Self-serving rule revision"... Open dispute within Democratic Party over 'one-member-one-vote system' (“기가 차” “셀프 룰 개정”…민주 ‘1인1표제’ 공개 설전)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240414.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/resize/test/child/2026/0119/53_17687869997085_20260119501000.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 19일 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 발언하고 있다. 왼쪽부터 강득구·이언주 최고위원, 가장 오른쪽은 한병도 원내대표. 김영원 기자 forever@hani.co.kr&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some members of the Democratic Party of Korea's leadership publicly demanded on the 19th that the application timing of the "one-member-one-vote system" be postponed until after the national convention. This open dispute erupted just one day after a warning was issued that actions linking the one-member-one-vote system to the party leadership race could soon constitute "prohibited conduct," a controversy sparked by the side of Representative Chung Cheong-rae. (더불어민주당 지도부 일부 최고위원이 19일 “1인1표제 적용 시점을 전당대회 뒤로 하라”고 공개 요구했다. 정청래 대표 쪽에서 1인1표제를 당권 경쟁과 연결 지어 논란을 촉발하는 것에 대해 “조금만 더 가면 해당 행위”라고 경고한 지 하루만에 공개적으로 설전이 벌어진 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Hwang Myeong-seon stated at the Supreme Council meeting held at the National Assembly this morning, "What was contained in last month's rejection (of the one-member-one-vote system) was agreement in principle (on the system) but a meaning to eliminate room for misunderstanding." She added, "If the parties revising the election rules are immediately elected under those very rules, it is difficult to avoid criticism of it being a self-serving rule revision. No matter how correct the content is, if problems arise in the process, legitimacy and trust are damaged." (황명선 최고위원은 이날 오전 국회에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “지난달 (1인1표제) 부결에 담긴 건 (1인1표제) 원칙에는 동의하지만 오해의 소지를 없애라는 의미”라며 “선거 룰 개정 당사자들이 곧바로 그 규칙에 따라 선출되면 셀프 룰 개정이라는 비판을 피하기 어렵다. 내용이 아무리 옳더라도 과정에서 문제가 발생하면 정당성이나 신뢰가 손상된다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Hwang further demanded, "We should introduce the one-member-one-vote system this time, but amend the party constitution and rules so that the application timing is after the next national convention," and "During the opinion-gathering process, we should ask party members for their opinions on the application timing and procedure, and the party should publicly organize that conclusion." Given the controversy that Representative Chung's push to reintroduce the one-member-one-vote system is groundwork for his own re-election as party leader, the intent is to avoid suspicion by having the rule apply from the next leadership term. (황 최고위원은 이어 “이번에 1인1표제를 도입하되 적용 시점은 다음 전당대회 이후로 당헌·당규를 개정하면 된다”며 “의견 수렴 과정에서 당원들에게 적용 시점과 절차에 대한 의견을 묻고 그 결론을 당이 공개적으로 정리해야 한다”고 요구했다. 정 대표의 1인1표제 재추진이 자신의 당대표 연임을 위한 포석이란 논란이 제기되는 만큼, 의심을 피하기 위해 차기 지도부부터 룰 적용을 받도록 하자는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to Supreme Council member Hwang's argument, Supreme Council member Moon Jeong-bok countered, "Saying it should be applied from the next leadership term is creating another frame, creating another problem." Supreme Council member Moon retorted, "Bringing this up for postponement or making it an issue now for other secondary reasons is an act of betraying the promise the Democratic Party has made to party members so far," and "It is absolutely not desirable to make another proposal now that the party affairs committee meeting is being held today to begin the procedure for gathering party member opinion." (황 최고위원의 이런 주장에 문정복 최고위원은 “차기 지도부부터 (1인1표제를) 적용해야 된다, 이런 건 또 다른 프레임을 만드는 일이자, 또 다른 문제를 만드는 일”이라고 반발했다. 문 최고위원은 “이제 와서 다른 부차적인 이유로 이를 다시 보류하거나 문제 삼는 건 그동안 당원들에게 얘기했던 민주당의 약속을 저버리는 행위”라며 “오늘 당무위원회의가 열려 당원 여론 수렴 절차에 들어가는데 또 다른 제안하는 건 결코 바람직하지 않다”고 맞받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticism also emerged at the Supreme Council meeting regarding Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun's 'prohibited conduct' remarks from the previous day. At a press briefing the day before, Chief Spokesperson Park had publicly warned that an opinion from within the Supreme Council to link the reintroduction of the one-member-one-vote system with the issue of Representative Chung's re-election was "just a step away from prohibited conduct" and that "words and actions that could be seen as a party leadership struggle should be restrained." (이날 최고위원회에선 박수현 수석대변인의 전날 ‘해당 행위’ 발언에 대한 비판도 나왔다. 박 수석대변인은 전날 기자간담회에서 1인1표제를 재추진할 때 정 대표의 연임 문제도 함께 묻자는 의견이 최고위에서 나온 데 대해 “조금만 더 가면 해당 행위” “당권 투쟁으로 보일 수 있는 언행은 자제돼야 한다”라고 공개 경고한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo said, "As you saw today, there seems to be very active discussion among Supreme Council members on how to properly implement party member sovereignty. I think this is the face of democracy," and added, "To speak of 'prohibited conduct' regarding such discussion and 'muzzle' people is betraying the spirit of democracy." (이언주 최고위원은 “오늘 보셨다시피 최고위원 간에도 당원주권주의를 어떻게 잘 구현할지 토론이 굉장히 활발한 듯하다. 이게 민주주의의 모습이라 생각한다”며 “이런 토론에 대해 해당행위 운운하며 ‘입틀막’하는 건 민주주의 정신을 저버리는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kang Deuk-gu also met with reporters after the Supreme Council meeting and said, "How is this prohibited conduct?" He stated, "I don't know the background of why Chief Spokesperson Park called it prohibited conduct," and added, "Does this mean Supreme Council members cannot properly say anything even in a closed-door meeting? Is this the face of the Democratic Party? It's truly outrageous." (강득구 최고위원도 이날 최고위원회의를 마친 뒤 기자들을 만나 “이게 (어떻게) 해당 행위인가”라고 했다. 그는 “박 수석대변인이 해당 행위라 한 배경이 뭔지 (모르겠다)”라며 “최고위원이 비공개회의 때 어떤 말도 제대로 할 수 없다는 것 아닌가. 이게 민주당의 모습인가. 참 기가 찬다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kang demanded an apology from Chief Spokesperson Park, saying, "(If there is no apology) I will state my position at the open Supreme Council meeting this coming Wednesday (the 21st)." (강 최고위원은 박 수석대변인의 사과를 요구하며 “(사과하지 않으면) 오는 수요일(21일)에 제 입장을 공개 최고위원회의 때 밝히겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the party constitutional amendment for one-member-one-vote will go through the party affairs committee on the 19th, an opinion survey of eligible party members from the 22nd to the 24th, and then be put to a vote at the Central Committee meeting on the 2nd or 3rd of next month. The one-member-one-vote system received a 72% approval rate in the Central Committee vote on December 5th last year, but was rejected as it fell short of the quorum for passage, which is a majority of registered members (299). (한편, 1인1표 당헌 개정안은 19일 당무위원회와 22~24일 권리당원 여론조사를 거쳐 다음 달 2~3일 중앙위원회 투표에 부쳐진다. 1인1표제는 지난해 12월5일 중앙위 표결에서 72%의 찬성률을 기록했지만, 의결 기준인 재적 과반(299명)에 미달해 부결된 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Hansol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Chaewoon &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김채운 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:cwk@hani.co.kr"&gt;cwk@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240414.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/970/582/imgdb/resize/test/child/2026/0119/53_17687869997085_20260119501000.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:20:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ministry of Unification Recruits University Students Who Are North Korean Defectors or Their Children for U.S. Study Program (통일부, 미국 연수 참가할 탈북민·자녀 대학생 모집)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240428.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/710/426/imgdb/child/2026/0119/53_17687904418073_9617687903890365.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;정부서울청사 통일부 간판 아래로 직원들이 오가고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Unification announced on the 19th that it is recruiting four university students who are North Korean defectors or children of defectors to participate in the 2026 'Korea-U.S. University Student Exchange (WEST·Work, English Study, Travel)' program by the 27th. Based on an intergovernmental work agreement, this program, run by the Ministry of Education's National Institute for International Education, provides young people with a 10 to 12-month opportunity for an internship, language study, and travel in the United States. (통일부는 2026년도 &amp;#x27;한·미 대학생연수(WEST·Work, English Study, Travel)&amp;#x27; 프로그램에 참가할 북한이탈주민이나 탈북민의 자녀인 대학생 4명을 27일까지 모집한다고 19일 밝혔다. 정부 간 업무협약을 바탕으로 교육부 국립국제교육원이 청년들에게 미국에서 10∼12개월에 걸쳐 인턴십과 어학연수, 여행 기회를 제공하는 프로그램이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean defectors or their children who hold Republic of Korea nationality and are either current domestic university students or graduated from university after August of last year are eligible to apply. Applications can be submitted in person or by mail. (대한민국 국적을 소지한 탈북민이나 그들의 자녀로서 국내 대학생 및 작년 8월 이후 대학 졸업자면 신청할 수 있다. 지원은 방문 또는 우편으로 하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240428.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/710/426/imgdb/child/2026/0119/53_17687904418073_9617687903890365.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:20:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Sector MZ Generation Unwilling to Become Junior Managers or Executives... "Promotion? No Thanks" (공공기관 MZ, 초급간부·임원되기 싫다…“승진 NO”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240431.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/480/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501376.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지뱅크&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;An audit by the Board of Audit and Inspection (BAI) has revealed that the phenomenon of public institution employees avoiding promotions, not only to junior management positions but also to executive roles, is becoming increasingly severe. (공공기관 직원들이 초급간부는 물론 임원 승진도 기피하는 현상이 심각해지고 있다는 감사원 감사 결과가 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the audit results on the 'State of Human Resource Management in Public Institutions' released by the BAI on the 18th, in a survey of 5,471 personnel (535 senior/mid-level managers, 1,195 junior managers, 3,741 staff) from 35 institutions, 57.1% (3,122 respondents) answered affirmatively when asked if there was a phenomenon of avoiding promotion to junior management. Particularly, in seven public institutions (Korea Western Power, KEPCO KPS, Korea South-East Power, Korea Electric Power Corporation, Korea Southern Power, Korea Midland Power, Korea Hydro &amp; Nuclear Power), less than 30% of respondents expressed an intention to be promoted to junior management. (감사원이 18일 발표한 ‘공공기관 인력운용 실태’ 감사 결과를 보면, 35개 기관 소속 5471명(고위·중간 간부 535명, 초급간부 1195명, 직원 3741명)을 대상으로 실시한 설문조사에서 초급간부 승진 기피 현상이 발생하고 있느냐는 질문에 57.1%(3122명)가 그렇다고 답변했다. 특히 7개 공공기관(한국서부발전, 한전케이피에스, 한국남동발전, 한국전력공사, 한국남부발전, 한국중부발전, 한국수력원자력)의 경우, 초급간부 승진 의사가 있다고 밝힌 응답자는 30% 이하였다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI stated, "The phenomenon of avoiding promotions is a global trend of the times, emerging alongside the rise of the MZ generation," adding, "(In Korea as well) this phenomenon is appearing not only in the private sector but also in the public domain." (감사원은 “승진 기피 현상은 엠제트(MZ) 세대의 등장과 함께 전 세계에서 나타나는 시대적 흐름”이라며 “(한국에서도) 이런 현상은 민간기업 뿐 아니라 공공 영역에서도 나타나고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was found that the competition rates for promotion exams are continuously declining at 12 institutions, including Korea Electric Power Corporation, which operate a junior management promotion exam system. For example, at KEPCO KPS, a power facility maintenance specialist public corporation, while 168 people (6.3% of the 2,673 eligible candidates) took the exam in 2010, 16 years ago, in 2024, only 8 people (0.7% of 1,110 eligible candidates) took it. (초급간부 승진시험 제도를 운영하는 한국전력 등 12개 기관의 시험 경쟁률은 지속적으로 하락하고 있는 것으로 나타났다. 전력 설비 정비 전문 공기업 한전케이피에스(KPS)의 경우, 16년 전인 2010년엔 승진시험 응시 가능 인원(2673명)의 6.3%인 168명이 시험을 봤지만, 2024년엔 응시 가능 인원 1110명 중 0.7%인 8명만 응시한 것으로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reasons for not wanting promotion were varied. Work responsibility increases, but authority over subordinates is weak, and financial compensation is insufficient. For junior managers in public institutions located in provincial areas, relocation is also not easy. Looking at the case of Korea Hydro &amp; Nuclear Power, from 2020 to 2024, 331 junior managers concurrently held positions in other departments for an average of 136 days (up to a maximum of 1,186 days), experiencing excessive workload burdens. (승진을 원치 않는 이유는 다양했다. 업무 책임은 커지지만 하급자에 대한 통제 권한은 약하고, 금전적 보상은 미흡하다. 지방에 있는 공공기관 초급간부는 거주지 이동도 쉽지 않다. 한국수자력원자력의 사례를 보면, 2020∼2024년 초급간부 331명이 평균 136일(최대 1186일) 동안 다른 부서를 겸임하는 등 과중한 업무 부담을 겪었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A similar phenomenon is occurring in executive promotions as well. According to a BAI survey of 447 standing directors and grade 1 employees working at 35 institutions, 44.1% of respondents from 31 institutions, including the Korea Racing Authority, acknowledged the existence of a phenomenon of avoiding executive promotion. When asked about the reasons, the most common response, given by 151 people, was concern over potential 'wage reversal' where compensation could actually decrease due to factors like management evaluation performance. This was followed by concerns about non-guaranteed retirement age and a sharp increase in workload. (임원 승진에서도 비슷한 현상이 발생하고 있다. 감사원이 35개 기관에 재직 중인 상임이사와 1급 직원 447명에게 설문조사한 결과, 한국마사회 등 31개 기관 응답자의 44.1%는 임원 승진 기피 현상이 존재한다고 인정했다. 원인을 묻는 물음엔 경영평가 성과 등으로 오히려 보수가 낮아지는 ‘임금역전’이 발생할 수 있다는 우려에 답한 대상자가 151명으로 가장 많았다. 보장되지 않는 정년, 업무량 급증도 뒤를 이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI also pointed out flaws in the public institution wage peak system. The wage peak system was introduced in 2016 with the purpose of guaranteeing the retirement age for older workers while reducing their wages after a certain age and using the saved labor costs for new hires. The problem is that when wage peak system participants are assigned to different duties than their original ones, their work performance declines. According to a BAI survey and interview with 132 department heads whose departments included wage peak system participants, 93 department heads of participants assigned to separate, different duties responded that the actual working hours of those department members were "less than 5 hours per week." Examining the assignment of tasks to 122 wage peak system participants with separate duties, the vast majority, 92.6%, were found not to have received specific tasks. (감사원은 공공기관 임금피크 제도의 허점도 지적했다. 임금피크제는 2016년 고령 근로자의 정년을 보장하되 일정 연령 이후 임금을 깎아 절감된 인건비를 신규채용에 활용한다는 취지로 도입됐다. 문제는 임금피크제 대상자 중 기존직무가 아닌 다른 직무를 맡게 됐을 때 업무 실적이 낮아진다는 것이다. 감사원이 임금피크제 대상자가 소속된 부서의 부서장 132명을 상대로 설문·면담 조사를 해 본 결과, 기존과 다른 별도 직무를 맡은 임금피크제 대상자의 부서장 93명은 해당 부서원의 실질적 업무시간이 “주 5시간 미만”에 불과하다고 응답했다. 별도 직무를 하는 임금피크제 대상자 122명에 대한 과제부여 실태를 봤을 땐 대다수인 92.6%가 구체적인 과제를 받지 못한 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240431.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/480/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501376.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:20:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Public institutions exploit 'exception clauses' in mandatory hiring... Regional talent hiring rate stalls at 17% (공공기관, 의무채용 ‘예외규정’ 꼼수…지역인재 채용률 17% 그쳐)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240434.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/878/621/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501382.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;게티이미지뱅크 코리아&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been revealed that public institutions excessively apply 'exception clauses' of the mandatory hiring system, resulting in a regional talent hiring rate that falls short of the mandatory 30% ratio. (공공기관들이 의무채용 제도의 ‘예외 규정’을 과다하게 적용해 지역인재 채용률이 의무 비율인 30%에 미치지 못하는 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the key audit results of 'Public Institution Workforce Management Status' released on the 19th, the Board of Audit and Inspection stated that public institutions frequently apply mandatory hiring exception clauses, reducing the number of candidates subject to mandatory hiring. As of 2023, the actual regional talent hiring rate compared to the total new hiring quota across eight regions, including Gangwon, Chungcheong, and Jeonbuk, was 17.7%, failing to meet the mandatory hiring ratio of 30%. (감사원은 19일 공개한 ‘공공기관 인력운용 실태’ 주요 감사결과에서 공공기관이 의무채용 예외 규정을 빈번하게 적용해 의무채용 대상자 수가 줄어들고 있다고 밝혔다. 2023년 기준 강원과 충청, 전북 등 8개 권역의 신규채용 총정원 대비 실제 지역인재 채용률은 17.7%로, 의무채용비율 30%에 미치지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Government public institutions relocated to local areas must hire a certain percentage of high school or university graduates from the non-capital region where their headquarters are located when hiring new employees, based on the 'Special Act on the Creation and Development of Innovation Cities'. The target scale for mandatory regional talent hiring increased from 18% in 2018 to 30% in 2022. However, exceptions to regional talent hiring are allowed in situations such as when the annual hiring number is five or fewer, or when hiring individuals requiring expertise like a doctoral degree. (지방에 이전한 정부 공공기관은 ‘혁신도시 조성 및 발전에 관한 특별법’에 근거해 새 직원 채용시 본사가 있는 비수도권 지역 고교·대학 졸업자를 일정 비율 채용해야 한다. 지역인재 의무채용 규모 목표치는 2018년 18%에서 2022년 30%로 증가했다. 다만 연간 채용인원이 5명 이하이거나, 박사 학위 취득 조건 등 전문성이 요구되는 사람을 채용해야 하는 상황 등에는 지역인재 채용에 예외를 두고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the effectiveness of the mandatory hiring system is low due to institutions excessively utilizing these exception clauses. For example, when hiring 'five or fewer people annually' by examination field, the mandatory regional talent hiring ratio does not need to be applied. Nine institutions, including the Korea Gas Technology Corporation, applied this clause in 98 out of 136 recruitment exams held between 2018 and 2024, thus avoiding mandatory hiring. (문제는 이러한 예외규정을 과도하게 활용하는 기관들 탓에 의무채용 제도 실효성이 낮다는 것이다. 가령, 시험 분야별로 ‘연간 5명 이하’를 채용할 때는 지역인재 의무채용 비율을 적용하지 않아도 되는데, 한국가스기술공사 등 9개 기관이 2018∼2024년 치른 채용시험 136회 중 98회에 이 규정을 적용해 의무채용을 하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Audit and Inspection also revealed that the total new hiring quota for 127 public institutions operating the regional talent hiring system was 11,476 people. Among these, 8,356 people were hired by applying the system's exception clauses, accounting for 72.8% of the total. This means that approximately 7 out of 10 hires were made by applying exception clauses that exempt them from hiring regional talent. (감사원은 또 지역인재 채용 제도를 운영하는 127개 공공기관의 전체 신규채용 정원이 1만1476명이었는데, 이 가운데 지역인재 제도 예외규정을 적용해 채용한 인원이 8356명으로, 전체의 72.8%를 차지한다고 밝혔다. 10명 중 7명꼴로 지역인재를 채용하지 않아도 되는 예외규정을 적용해 채용을 했다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Audit and Inspection also pointed out the potential for 'reverse discrimination' that the regional talent hiring system could create. By operating the regional talent hiring target system alongside the previously used regional quota system, applicants from other regions may actually be disadvantaged. The Board of Audit and Inspection suggested abolishing the hiring point system and quota system as an improvement measure. (감사원은 지역인재 채용 제도가 낳을 수 있는 ‘역차별’ 가능성도 지적했다. 지역인재 채용 목표제와 그 이전에 운용하던 지역 할당제 등을 함께 운용하면서, 다른 지역 출신 지원자가 오히려 불이익을 받을 수 있다는 것이다. 감사원은 채용 가점제와 할당제를 폐지하는 안을 개선 방안으로 제시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also pointed out that a concentration phenomenon, where a large number of hires come from specific universities like regional hub national universities located in the area, may occur, potentially lowering the efficiency of personnel management. To mitigate hiring concentration, the Board of Audit and Inspection proposed considering measures to broaden the talent pool, such as expanding the recruitment region scope to wider areas (e.g., Chungcheong region, Gyeongsang region) or expanding the definition of regional talent to include job seekers who graduated from high school in the region but attended university elsewhere. (또 해당 지역에 소재한 지방거점 국립대학교 등 특정 대학 출신이 대거 채용되는 쏠림 현상이 발생해 인사 운영의 효율성의 낮아질 수 있다고도 지적했다. 감사원은 채용 쏠림 완화를 위해 전형 지역 범위를 광역화(충청권역, 경상권역 등)하거나, 지역인재 대상을 해당 고교 졸업 이후 다른 지역에서 대학을 졸업한 구직자로 확대하는 등 인력풀을 넓히는 방안을 검토할 것을 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jang Ye-ji &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (장예지 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:penj@hani.co.kr"&gt;penj@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240434.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/878/621/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501382.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:19:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee and Prime Minister Meloni Hold Summit... Strengthen Semiconductor and Security Cooperation (이 대통령-멜로니 총리 정상회담…반도체·안보 협력 강화한다)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240439.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/430/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501465.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이재명 대통령과 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 19일 청와대에서 열린 확대회담에서 악수하고 있다. 청와대사진기자단&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung and Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni held a summit on the 19th, agreeing to expand cooperation in economic and security fields and to strengthen the exchange of views and cooperation on major regional and global issues. (이재명 대통령과 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 19일 정상회담을 열어 경제 및 안보 분야 협력을 확대하고, 주요 지역 및 글로벌 현안에 대한 의견 교환 및 협력을 강화하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After concluding the summit, the two countries stated in a joint press release, "The two leaders met in Seoul and expressed their will to further strengthen the ongoing cooperation at both bilateral and multilateral levels to actively contribute to maintaining world peace and security and to respond to global challenges." (양국은 이날 정상회담을 마친 뒤 공동언론 발표문을 통해 “두 정상은 서울에서 만나 세계 평화와 안보 유지에 적극적으로 기여하고, 글로벌 도전 과제에 대응하기 위해 양자 차원 및 다자 무대에서 지속하고 있는 협력을 더욱 강화하고자 하는 의지를 표명했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the occasion of this summit, the two countries signed three Memoranda of Understanding (MOUs) covering △civil protection, △protection of cultural heritage and landscapes, and △semiconductor industry cooperation. They agreed to enhance the protection capabilities of their citizens by promoting cooperation in disaster management and civil protection, and to cooperate on policy formulation, data management, and excavation research for the preservation and protection of cultural heritage and landscapes. In the semiconductor industry, they will also promote business cooperation, including in advanced fields such as artificial intelligence (AI), and work to activate information sharing and networking to strengthen supply chains. (양국은 이번 정상회담을 계기로 △시민보호 △문화유산 및 경관 보호 △반도체 산업 협력 등 3건의 양해각서를 체결했다. 재난관리 및 시민보호 분야의 협력 증진을 통해 양국 국민의 보호 역량을 강화하고, 문화유산 및 경관 보전·보호에 대해서도 정책수립, 데이터 관리나 발굴 연구 등에 협력하기로 했다. 반도체 산업에서도 인공지능(AI) 등 첨단 분야를 포함해 비즈니스 협력을 추진하고, 공급망 강화를 위한 정보 공유 및 네트워킹 활성화에 나선다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the economy, trade, and investment in particular, the two countries shared the outcomes of the Korea-Italy Business Forum jointly held in Seoul last September. Furthermore, based on this, they agreed to further strengthen and expand bilateral cooperation and to promote trade and investment in third-country markets. They also agreed to work together on developing critical mineral supply chains through multilateral initiatives such as the Minerals Security Partnership (MSP), for which Korea currently holds the chairmanship. (특히 경제, 교역 및 투자 분야에 대해, 양국은 지난해 9월 서울에서 공동 개최한 한-이탈리아 비즈니스 포럼의 성과를 공유했다. 또 이를 바탕으로 양자협력을 더욱 강화·확대하며 제3국 시장에서의 교역·투자를 증진시키기로 했다. 한국이 현재 의장직을 맡은 광물안보파트너십(MPS)과 같은 다자간 이니셔티브를 통해 핵심 광물 공급망 개발 역시 함께 노력하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two leaders also reaffirmed their will to achieve the complete denuclearization of the Korean Peninsula and realize permanent peace and stability. They agreed to cooperate closely on multilateral stages, including the G20, and to work together to strengthen the partnership between Korea and the G7. (두 정상은 한반도의 완전한 비핵화와 항구적 평화 및 안정 실현에 대한 의지도 재확인했다. 이들은 주요 20개국(G20)을 비롯한 다자무대에서 긴밀히 협력하고, 한국과 주요7개국(G7) 간 파트너십 강화를 위해서도 함께 노력하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the two countries agreed to promptly hold the next strategic dialogue and to prepare a five-year action plan for 2026–2030. Prime Minister Meloni reiterated her hope that President Lee would accept the invitation from Italian President Sergio Mattarella and make a state visit to Italy within this year. (회담이 끝난 뒤 양국은 차기 전략대화를 조속히 개최하고, 2026∼2030년 5년 간 액션플랜을 마련하기로 했다. 멜로니 총리는 이 대통령이 올해 중으로 세르지오 마타렐라 이탈리아 대통령의 초청을 수락하고 이탈리아를 국빈 방문할 수 있기를 기대한다고 거듭 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two leaders' schedule on the day began with a small-group meeting around 10:40 AM, followed by an expanded meeting and a joint press announcement. Afterwards, the two leaders held a luncheon meeting for about an hour and thirty minutes. (양국 정상은 이날 오전 10시40분께 소인수회담을 시작으로 확대회담, 공동언론발표 등의 일정을 소화했다. 이후 양 정상은 1시간30여분 간 오찬 회동을 갖는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Gyeong-ju &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고경주 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:goh@hani.co.kr"&gt;goh@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/bluehouse/1240439.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/430/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501465.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:19:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing Suspended Before It Could Even Start... Ruling and Opposition Parties Clash Over 'Inadequate Submitted Materials' (이혜훈 청문회 시작도 못하고 정회…여야 ‘제출 자료 부실’ 공방)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240440.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/761/507/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501472.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;19일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 재정경제기획위원회 전체회의에 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 좌석이 비어 있다. 이날 재정기획위에서는 이혜훈 후보자 인사청문회가 열리기로 예정돼 있었지만, 청문 자료 제출을 둘러싼 여야 갈등으로 전체회의는 개회한 채 인사청문회 상정이 되지 않아 청문회가 열리지 못하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties clashed fiercely on the 19th over whether to hold the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget. The National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, which had scheduled the hearing for Lee that day, suspended its session after a dispute between People Power Party lawmakers, who argued that "the submitted materials are inadequate," and Democratic Party of Korea lawmakers, who argued that "the hearing should be held first for verification." The committee's floor leaders from both parties agreed to hold additional discussions regarding whether to proceed with the hearing. (여야가 19일 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회 개최 여부를 두고 거세게 충돌했다. 국회 재정경제위원회는 이혜훈 후보자 인사청문회를 예정한 이날 “제출 자료가 부실하다”는 국민의힘 의원들과 “청문회는 일단 열고 검증해보자”는 더불어민주당 의원들의 공방 끝에 정회했고, 양당 간사는 인사청문회 개최 여부와 관련해 추가 협의를 이어가기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Eui-ja, the People Power Party lawmaker who chairs the Strategy and Finance Committee, said during the committee's plenary session that day, "The two floor leaders (DPK's Jeong Tae-ho and PPP's Park Soo-young) will soon have lunch. I ask them to use this time to discuss how to proceed with the confirmation hearing." Chairman Im added, "Once the floor leaders conclude their discussion, we will resume the session." (국민의힘 소속 임이자 국회 재정경제위원회 위원장은 이날 국회 재정경제위 전체회의에서 “양당 (민주당) 정태호 간사와 (국민의힘) 박수영 간사가 곧 오찬을 할 텐데 이 시간을 활용해 인사청문회를 어떻게 진행할지 협의를 해달라”고 했다. 임 위원장은 “간사가 협의해오면 (회의를 속개)하는 것으로 하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Im stated, "It is the chairperson's view that the hearing must be held," but also said, "Even after accommodating (the DPK's request to) move the hearing date to the 19th, I urged (the nominee) to sincerely submit the required materials. However, as many suspicions have arisen, opinions are divided on the hearing's effectiveness. We need to discuss whether to proceed with the hearing today or change the schedule." (임 위원장은 “반드시 청문회를 열어야 한다는 게 위원장의 생각”이라면서도 “(민주당 주장대로 청문회 일정을) 19일로 당겨주면서도 반드시 자료 제출에 성실히 임해달라고 했는데 여러 가지 의혹들이 많이 나와 (청문회) 실효성에 대한 의견이 분분하다. 오늘 청문회를 계속 진행해야 되는 것인지, 아니면 일정 변경을 해야 하는지 (논의가 필요하다)”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Im declared the plenary session suspended around 11:32 AM. Subsequently, the floor leaders from both parties began their discussions. (임 위원장은 오전 11시32분께 전체회의 정회를 선언했다. 이후 여야 간사는 협의에 들어갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally scheduled for that day, the Strategy and Finance Committee's plenary session saw intense clashes throughout the morning between the PPP, which boycotted the hearing citing inadequate material submissions, and the DPK, which insisted the hearing should still be held. As the hearing agenda item was not presented, nominee Lee did not attend the committee meeting room. (애초 이 후보자 청문회가 예정돼있던 이날 국회 재경위 전체회의는 오전 내내 부실한 자료 제출을 이유로 청문회를 보이콧한 국민의힘과 그래도 청문회는 열자는 민주당이 거센 공방을 벌였다. 청문회 안건이 상정되지 못해 이 후보자는 국회 재경위 회의장에 출석하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opposition floor leader Park Soo-young (PPP) stated, "They promised to submit materials by 5 PM on the 15th, and trusting that promise, we agreed to hold the hearing on the 19th. However, the interim materials submitted are severely lacking. Out of 2,187 requested items, only 15% were submitted. This is a very low figure even compared to other confirmation hearings." He added, "Proper materials are needed for a proper hearing." Chun Ha-ram, a lawmaker from the Reform Party, also said, "If the nominee consistently maintains an attitude of protecting (the One Pentas high-priced apartment in Seocho-gu, which is under suspicion of fraudulent subscription) rather than focusing on the ministerial position, then she is not qualified to undergo a confirmation hearing." (야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원은 “15일 오후 5시까지 자료를 제출하겠다고 약속해 그걸 믿고 인사청문회를 19일로 진행하기로 한 건데, 중간 자료가 굉장히 부족하다. 2187건을 요청했는데 15%만 제출했다. 다른 인사청문회와 비교해도 매우 낮은 수치”라며 “제대로 된 청문회를 하려면 제대로 된 자료가 필요하다”고 했다. 천하람 개혁신당 의원도 “이 후보자가 장관직이 아니라 (부정 청약 의혹이 있는 서초구 고가 아파트) 원펜타스를 지키겠다는 태도로 일관하고 있다면 청문회를 받을 자격이 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ruling party floor leader Jeong Tae-ho (DPK) said, "We can start the hearing first and directly request any additional materials needed from the nominee. However, not even seating the nominee and discussing schedule adjustments seems to indicate a lack of will to hold a normal hearing." He added, "This is us abandoning our duty to verify the nominee on behalf of the people." Lawmaker Lee So-young also said, "What are we doing amongst ourselves without even starting the hearing properly and without the nominee present?" She suggested, "The opposition floor leader can compile the materials essential for verification and request their submission. If even those are not submitted faithfully, it would not be too late to then judge whether to proceed." (여당 간사인 정태호 의원은 “일단 청문회를 시작하고 더 필요한 자료는 후보에게 직접 요구할 수 있는데 후보조차도 (청문회에) 앉히지 않고 일정 조정을 거론하는 건 정상적으로 청문회를 할 의지가 없는 것으로 보인다”며 “국민을 대신해 후보를 검증해야 할 우리의 책무를 스스로 저버리는 것”이라고 했다. 이소영 의원도 “(청문회를 제대로) 시작도 하기 전에 후보자도 없는 상황에서 우리끼리 뭐 하는 건가”라며 “검증에 꼭 필요한 자료를 야당 간사가 취합해 (다시) 제출을 요구하고 그마저도 충실히 제출되지 않으면 다시 한 번 진행 여부를 판단해도 늦지 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporters Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; and Kim Hae-jeong &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; 김해정 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sea@hani.co.kr"&gt;sea@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240440.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/761/507/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501472.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:18:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party's Kim Jong-hyuk, Facing 'Party Membership Suspension Crisis', Says "Will File for Recusal of Ethics Committee Chairman" (‘당원권 정지 위기’ 국힘 김종혁 “윤리위원장 기피신청할 것”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240441.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501507.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;김종혁 전 국민의힘 최고위원이 19일 서울 여의도 국민의힘 중앙당사에서 열린 윤리위원회에 출석한 뒤 취재진과 인터뷰하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong-hyuk, the People Power Party's Goyang City Byeong district party committee chairman, who is facing the crisis of a heavy disciplinary action of a two-year party membership suspension, stated he will file for the recusal of party Central Ethics Committee Chairman Yoon Min-woo. The reason is that Chairman Yoon has shown prejudice against the person under investigation by comparing him to the mafia, among other things. (당원권 정지 2년의 중징계 위기에 처한 김종혁 국민의힘 고양시병 당협위원장이 윤민우 당 중앙윤리위원장에 대한 기피신청을 하겠다고 했다. 윤 위원장이 자신을 마피아에 비유하는 등 피조사자에 대한 예단을 드러냈다는 이유에서다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After completing the Ethics Committee's explanation procedure held at the People Power Party headquarters in Yeouido, Seoul on the morning of the 19th, Chairman Kim met with reporters and said, "I intend to file for the recusal of the Ethics Committee chairman who already holds clear prejudice against the person under investigation. Although the atmosphere seems such that it won't be accepted, that is for them to decide." (김 위원장은 19일 오전 서울 여의도 국민의힘 당사에서 열린 윤리위 소명 절차를 마친 뒤 기자들을 만나 “이미 피조사자에 대한 명백한 예단을 가진 윤리위원장에 대해 기피신청을 내려고 한다. 받아들여지지 않을 것 같은 분위기지만 그건 그쪽에서 결정하는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Kim cited the content of the Ethics Committee's decision document from the 14th regarding the expulsion of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon as grounds for recusal. In the decision document, which compared Chairman Kim to 'mafia' and 'terrorist', he stated, "Ethics Committee Chairman Yoon Min-woo holds the prejudice that I have committed illegal acts." It is said that Chairman Yoon told Chairman Kim to send the recusal application via email by 0:00 on the 20th. (김 위원장은 지난 14일 윤리위의 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표의 제명 결정문 내용을 기피 사유로 들었다. 결정문에서 김 위원장을 ‘마피아’ ‘테러리스트’에 비유하는 등 “윤민우 윤리위원장이 저에 대한 범법 행위를 했다는 예단을 가졌다”는 것이다. 윤 위원장은 김 위원장에게 20일 0시까지 기피신청을 이메일로 보내달라고 말했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the People Power Party's regulations, a person subject to disciplinary review may, in writing, explain the facts and apply for the recusal of a committee member if there is a member among the ethics committee members who is likely to make a significantly unfair decision. In such a case, the committee must decide on the recusal without delay through a committee resolution, and a recused member cannot participate in the deliberation of the relevant case. (국민의힘 당규를 보면, 징계심의 대상자는 윤리위원 중 현저히 불공정한 의결을 할 우려가 있는 위원이 있는 때, 그 사실을 서면으로 소명하고 위원 기피를 신청할 수 있다고 돼 있다. 이 경우 지체 없이 위원회 의결로 기피 여부가 결정돼야 하며, 기피당한 위원은 당해 안건 심의에 참여할 수 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, the People Power Party's Party Affairs Audit Committee (Chairman Lee Ho-seon) requested the Ethics Committee to impose a two-year party membership suspension on Chairman Kim. It is reported that during the approximately one-hour Ethics Committee explanation procedure held that day, Chairman Kim actively explained his position regarding the disciplinary reasons determined by the Party Affairs Audit Committee. Regarding the disciplinary reason of 'mocking former President Yoon Suk-yeol's religious activities', he said, "I cannot understand (why the ethics committee members) are acting as legal representatives for former President Yoon, who is not even a party member." Regarding the disciplinary reason of 'defaming People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk', he reportedly responded, "Criticizing the party leader becoming subject to an audit undermines democratic principles." Regarding the inclusion of 'criticism of Shincheonji' as a disciplinary reason, he reportedly answered, "I do not understand the party's attitude of protecting Shincheonji." (지난달 국민의힘 당무감사위원회(위원장 이호선)는 김 위원장에게 당원권 정지 2년을 내려달라고 윤리위에 요청했다. 김 위원장은 이날 1시간가량 진행된 윤리위 소명 절차에서 당무감사위가 판단한 자신의 징계 사유에 대해 적극적으로 소명했다고 한다. ‘윤석열 전 대통령의 종교적 행위를 조롱했다’는 징계 사유에 대해서는 “(윤리위원들이) 당원도 아닌 윤 전 대통령의 소송대리인 역할을 하는지 이해할 수 없다”고 했고, ‘장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 모독했다’는 징계 사유에 관해서는 “당대표를 비판한 것이 감사 대상이 되는 것은 민주주의 원칙 훼손”이라고 답했다고 한다. ‘신천지 비판’이 징계 사유에 포함된 것에 대서는 “당이 신천지를 비호하는 태도가 이해 안 된다”고 답했다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Jeon Gwang-joon &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (전광준 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:light@hani.co.kr"&gt;light@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240441.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/640/537/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501507.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:18:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon: "Submitted all available materials... Opposition's claims are exaggerated" (이혜훈 “확보할 수 있는 자료는 다 제출…야당 주장은 과장”)</title><link>https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240446.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/631/444/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501643.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 19일 서울 여의도 국회에서 열릴 예정인 인사청문회를 앞두고 대기하고 있다. 연합뉴스&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, stated on the 19th, ahead of the National Assembly confirmation hearing, regarding the controversy over 'insufficient document submission,' that "all materials we have or could obtain have been submitted." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자는 19일 국회 인사청문회를 앞두고 ‘자료 제출 미비’ 논란이 일고 있는 데 대해 “갖고 있거나 확보할 수 있는 자료는 모두 제출했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters at the National Assembly that day, the nominee responded to a question about 'the People Power Party claiming only 15% of the requested materials were submitted' by saying, "The opposition's claim is exaggerated," and that "about 75% was submitted." The nominee added, "I am waiting for the opportunity to explain in detail before the public once the hearing is held." (이 후보자는 이날 국회에서 취재진을 만나 ‘국민의힘이 요구한 자료의 15%만 제출됐다고 주장하고 있다’는 취재진의 질문에 “야당의 주장은 과장”이라며 “75% 정도 제출했다”고 말했다. 이 후보자는 “청문회가 열려 국민들 앞에 소상히 소명할 수 있는 기회를 갖기를 기다리고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He explained, "We submitted all the materials (I could provide), and among the materials that related agencies should provide, some were already past their retention period, and they even requested items from 30-40 years ago, so there were many cases where the state agencies did not possess the relevant materials and thus could not submit them." He further emphasized, "Nevertheless, we searched for any additional materials we could possibly submit and submitted everything by 3 PM on Sunday." (그는 “(제가 낼 수 있는) 자료를 다 냈고, 관계기관들이 내야 하는 자료 가운데는 이미 자료 보존 기간이 지난 것도 있고 심지어 30~40년 전 것을 달라고 하시니 국가기관이 해당 자료를 보유하고 있지 않아 제출하지 못하는 경우가 많았다”고 설명했다. 이어 “그럼에도 불구하고 저희들이 조금이라도 더 낼 수 있는 자료들이 있는지 찾아서 일요일 오후3시에 다 제출했다”고 거듭 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding some lawmakers raising the issue that '(the materials) were submitted in the middle of the night,' he countered, saying, "There is a record showing they were submitted at 3 PM." Additionally, he noted, "Listening to the lawmakers, there were many cases where they requested materials already submitted again," and added, "We will search and provide them. We are continuously looking to see if there is anything more we can submit." (또 일부 의원들이 ‘(자료가) 한밤중에 제출됐다’고 문제를 제기한 데 대해서도 “(오후) 3시에 제출했다는 자료가 모두 남아 있다”고 반박했다. 아울러 “의원님들 말씀을 들어보니 이미 제출한 자료를 다시 요구하는 경우도 많았다”며 “더 찾아서 드리겠다. 혹시 더 낼 수 있는 게 있는지 계속 찾고 있다”고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee did not express a clear position regarding calls from within and outside the political sphere for him to voluntarily resign. (이 후보자는 정치권 안팎에서 자진 사퇴를 요구하는 데 대해선 이렇다 할 입장을 밝히지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that morning, a plenary meeting of the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee was held, but the agenda item for this nominee's confirmation hearing was not presented. With the People Power Party claiming 'inadequate document submission' and Democratic Party lawmakers calling the demands 'excessive,' opinions clashed, and the morning meeting was adjourned around 11:32 AM. The nominee waited at the National Assembly, unable to attend the committee meeting room while the dispute was ongoing. (앞서 이날 오전 국회 재정경제기획위원회 전체회의가 열렸지만 이 후보자 인사청문회 건은 상정되지 못했다. ‘자료 부실 제출’을 주장하는 국민의힘과 ‘지나친 요구’라는 민주당 의원들의 의견이 맞서며, 이날 오전 회의는 11시32분께 정회했다. 이 후보자는 공방이 이뤄지는 동안 국회 재경위 회의장에 출석하지 못하고 국회에서 대기했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reporter Ko Han-sol &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt; (고한솔 기자 &lt;a href="mailto:sol@hani.co.kr"&gt;sol@hani.co.kr&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.hani.co.kr/arti/politics/politics_general/1240446.html</guid><enclosure url="https://flexible.img.hani.co.kr/flexible/normal/631/444/imgdb/original/2026/0119/20260119501643.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:18:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>