<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Education Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Education articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:33:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Daniel Walker Howe, Historian of Antebellum America, Dies at 88</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/obituaries/daniel-walker-howe-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/11/multimedia/11howe-UCLA-jbpk/11howe-UCLA-jbpk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Walker Howe, an American historian who sought to dethrone President Andrew Jackson as the singular defining figure of his era of American history, arguing instead for the central importance of technological advance, the women’s rights movement and the long-defunct Whig Party, died on Dec. 25 at his home in Sherman Oaks, Calif. He was 88.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His death was confirmed by the University of California, Los Angeles, where Professor Howe taught American history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Howe was known above all for a landmark book, published in 2007 and awarded the Pulitzer Prize in history the following year. By this time, he had already retired into emeritus status at the two universities where he taught, UCLA and Oxford. He had never before tried to write history for a nonspecialist audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His book’s title elegantly embedded several arguments at once: “What Hath God Wrought: The Transformation of America, 1815-1848.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening phrase, a line from the Old Testament, was used at a ceremony in Washington by Samuel F.B. Morse as the first official message sent by telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Howe argued that this invention, part of a “communications revolution,” brought about a more dramatic change in society than even the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The America of 1815, he said in a C-SPAN lecture, was tantamount to a “third-world country,” with most families living in isolated farmsteads, producing their own food and clothes, ruled by changes in the weather and unable to afford any goods sent from far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life was subject to “the tyranny of distance,” Professor Howe argued. He emphasized that the War of 1812 was both caused and ended by poor communication. Americans declared war because of policies that the British had actually reversed two days earlier — not in time for the news to travel across the ocean. And the final battle, a bloody one in New Orleans, occurred two weeks after a peace treaty was signed in Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of the telegraph, a prominent New Orleans journal commented, “scarcely anything now will appear to be impossible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovations around the same time in printing, and the wide proliferation of railway travel, amounted to a new commercial order. The price of a mattress dropped from $50 to $5 — leading a whole nation to sleep better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These changes also reshaped popular morality and culture. Journalism so flourished that the No. 1 item delivered by the Postal Service was not letters but newspapers, Professor Howe wrote. Fringe political movements, like abolitionism and women’s suffrage — both inspired by rising Christian religiosity — got a hearing (however incredulously) across the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of progressivism’s core texts, Harriet Beecher Stowe’s “Uncle Tom’s Cabin,” became “the blockbuster of the century,” Professor Howe said in his lecture. That, in turn, was part of the rise of the novel as a literary form. In his book, he observed that John Marshall, chief justice of the United States for much of the era covered by his book, was a fan of Jane Austen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Howe’s book ended with a chapter called “A Vision of the Future” about the Seneca Falls Convention of 1848 on the rights of women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I wanted to highlight that which had first surprised me, but then convinced me, the principle that material improvement in society fostered moral improvement,” Professor Howe said in an interview with the National Book Critics Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a long review in The New Yorker, the historian Jill Lepore celebrated Professor Howe’s “great success” in “chronicling changes of all sorts, from rates of childhood mortality to the gross national product, from the frequency of bathing to the firepower of cannons.” In Foreign Affairs, Walter Russell Mead wrote that “What Hath God Wrought” was “a book that every student of American history and politics should read.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of its apparently universal acclaim, Professor Howe’s book sought to upend consensus in several respects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Esteemed historians of the period — particularly Arthur M. Schlesinger Jr., Charles Grier Sellers and Sean Wilentz — had considered it “the Age of Jackson,” crediting the president with embodying America’s democratic spirit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, Professor Howe’s book replaced a book making just such an argument by Professor Sellers, a historian at Berkeley, as part of the Oxford History of the United States, a long-running series originally begun by C. Vann Woodward and Richard Hofstadter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Sellers’s book, “The Market Revolution: Jacksonian America, 1815-1846” (1991), was rejected for the list. That book claimed that the major event of the period was the establishment of “capitalist hegemony over economy, politics, and culture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Sellers depicted Americans as shifting from a modest, agrarian society governed by “enduring human values of family, trust, cooperation, love, and equality” into a market society dominated by competition, oriented toward trade with strangers and plagued by social alienation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Professor Sellers, Jackson expressed a popular revolt against the increasing power of financial interests, as exemplified by his opposition to paper money and a national bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Howe portrayed America’s economic transformation in less dour terms and instead saw society’s traumas in Jackson’s own policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jackson’s policy of kicking Native Americans out of lands that they had been guaranteed by treaty, leading to the exodus known as the Trail of Tears, set a precedent for “geographical expansion and white supremacy that would be invoked in years to come by advocates of America’s imperial ‘manifest destiny,’” Professor Howe wrote. He also emphasized Jackson’s youth as a slave trader and his continuing support of slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the long run, the United States would head toward greater equality among the races and the sexes, along with a more activist federal government — leading Professor Howe to characterize the Whigs as “the party of America’s future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He went so far as to dedicate his book “to the memory of John Quincy Adams,” a Whig and the loser to Jackson in the 1828 presidential election. Adams, Professor Howe wrote, “envisioned the American republic as the culmination of the history of human progress.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Gething Walker Howe was born in Ogden, Utah, on Jan. 10, 1937. He grew up in Denver. His father, Maurice, was a journalist who lost his job during the Depression and found jobs with the federal government. His mother was Lucie (Walker) Howe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Howe went on a long train journey to attend college at Harvard, where in 1959 he received a bachelor’s degree in history and literature. He earned a master’s degree at Oxford and a Ph.D. in history from Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He married Sandra Shumway, a Radcliffe graduate studying at Oxford at the same time as he, in 1961. They had three children, Christopher, Rebecca and Stephen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family’s church, Saint Alban’s Episcopal in Los Angeles, said that Professor Howe was survived by his wife, children and grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years after “What Hath God Wrought” came out, many on the left described it as an unexpected guide to modern America, including the political commentators Ta-Nehisi Coates and John Ganz as well as Jake Auchincloss, a Democratic member of the House of Representatives from Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It discusses how Andrew Jackson built the Democratic Party in 1828 as a Christian nationalist anti-elitist party — if that sounds familiar to people — and then how the Whigs came to contest him and ultimately won in the 1840 election,” Representative Auchincloss told The New York Times last year. “And I find that template to be informative for the political era we’re living in now.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/obituaries/daniel-walker-howe-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:32:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>If You Can’t Teach Plato in a Philosophy Class, What Can You Teach?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/opinion/plato-texas-academic-freedom.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/opinion/12Lukianoff-image/12Lukianoff-image-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Peterson, a Texas A&amp;M University philosophy professor, was presented last week with a choice straight out of a dystopian novel. To bring his class in line with a prohibition on course materials that “advocate race or gender ideology,” he could either censor the part of his course that included readings from Plato or he could teach a different class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case illustrates the extent to which campus censorship has run amok in Texas: If some of Plato’s texts can’t be taught in a college philosophy course, what, exactly, can be taught?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bill passed last spring by the Texas Legislature undercut faculty control on public university campuses and clamped down on what can be taught, the First Amendment be damned. Last fall, the Texas A&amp;M University system separately introduced policy changes aimed at purging woke curriculums. Under these measures, administrators have conducted a sweeping review of course materials, aiming to root out officially disapproved ideas about race and gender that professors may impart to their students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Peterson submitted the materials for his course on contemporary moral issues to a university administrator as part of one such review — which he accurately described as “mandatory censorship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a philosophy class that explores how classical ethical concepts apply to contemporary social problems. It includes discussions on the ethics of war, the death penalty and abortion. And to the apparent alarm of university leadership, it includes discussions related to race and gender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Peterson was told he could “mitigate” his course content to “remove the modules on race ideology and gender ideology, and the Plato readings that may include these.” Those readings included a portion of Plato’s “Symposium,” a classic of Western philosophy. In one of its most famous passages, Plato offers a haunting, beautiful idea: that we are incomplete creatures, wandering the world in search of our other halves, and that love can make us whole — even, in a sense, bring us closer to the divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To cut that material from a class because it might set off alarms about “gender ideology” would only further politicize the classroom. It is importing today’s culture war into the ancient agora — turning the modern academy into a parody of its ancient namesake, a place where discussion is replaced by prior restraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas A&amp;M seems to have concluded that the safest way to handle the ideas contained in a classic text is to bury them. This is no way to run an institution of higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University administrators and state lawmakers are saying, in effect, that academic freedom won’t protect you if you teach ideas they don’t like. Never mind that decades ago, the Supreme Court described classrooms as the very embodiment of the “marketplace of ideas”: “Our nation is deeply committed to safeguarding academic freedom, which is of transcendent value to all of us, and not merely to the teachers concerned. That freedom is therefore a special concern of the First Amendment, which does not tolerate laws that cast a pall of orthodoxy over the classroom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas A&amp;M leadership seems to want, instead, to ensure that faculty members push the state’s preferred orthodoxy. It’s part of a broader effort in Texas and beyond to limit academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2024 The Chronicle of Higher Education reported that administrators at the University of North Texas College of Education had made over 200 changes to graduate and undergraduate courses, including to the syllabuses, course names and descriptions. Last fall, the larger University of North Texas system began a review of faculty syllabuses, and the University of Houston system said it was conducting a similar review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the Texas Tech University System, which has more than 60,000 students, a Dec. 1 memo warned faculty members not to “promote or otherwise inculcate” certain specific viewpoints about race and sex in the classroom. These include concepts like “One race or sex is inherently superior to another”; “An individual, by virtue of race or sex, is inherently racist, sexist or oppressive”; and “Meritocracy or a strong work ethic are racist, sexist or constructs of oppression.” The point isn’t that these concepts should just be accepted or go unchallenged, it’s that challenging them through a robust give-and-take is what universities are for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language in the memo echoes a law in Florida known as the Stop WOKE Act, which my organization, the Foundation for Individual Rights and Expression has been litigating against since 2022. A federal judge described Florida’s law restricting instruction in college classrooms as “positively dystopian,” recognizing that the First Amendment protects classroom instruction. Unfettered, Texas is following Florida’s unconstitutional example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas’s authoritarianism does not end at the classroom door, either. Last September, my organization sued to stop a brazenly unconstitutional Texas law banning all “expressive activities” on campus between 10 p.m. and 8 a.m. — a measure clearly aimed at campus protest. The law doesn’t even try to hide its targeting of “speech or expressive conduct protected by the First Amendment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, the president of West Texas A&amp;M University, Walter Wendler, canceled a drag show on campus, claiming that the show would be demeaning and offensive to women. He admitted that even though “the law of the land appears to require” that he allow the “artistic expression” to go forward, he was still shutting it down. (My organization is suing to allow the drag show to proceed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Amendment advocates often warn about a slippery slope. Once censorship starts at the margins, core freedoms are next. In Texas, university administrators and state commissars are skipping the slope and going straight for the trap door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the form below to share your thoughts on this or any other piece published in The New York Times in the past seven days. For your letter to be considered for publication, it should be 150 to 250 words and include your first and last names. If your submission is selected, an editor will contact you to review any necessary edits before publication. Most published letters will appear in both the online and print editions. Your submission must be exclusive to The New York Times. We do not publish open letters or third-party letters. Click  here for more information about the selection process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greg Lukianoff is an author, with Nadine Strossen, of “The War on Words: 10 Arguments Against Free Speech — and Why They Fail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times is committed to publishing a diversity of letters to the editor. We’d like to hear what you think about this or any of our articles. Here are some tips. And here’s our email: letters@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the New York Times Opinion section on Facebook, Instagram, TikTok, Bluesky, WhatsApp and Threads.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/opinion/plato-texas-academic-freedom.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:38:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaders of Historians’ Group Veto Resolutions Critical of Israel</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/arts/american-historical-association-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12CUL-HISTORIANS-GAZA-kfhg/12CUL-HISTORIANS-GAZA-kfhg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leadership of the American Historical Association has vetoed two resolutions criticizing Israel’s actions in Gaza that were approved by a member vote over the weekend, saying they lay outside the group’s mission and would pose risks to the organization and the historical profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first resolution criticized what it characterized as intentional “scholasticide” in Gaza, where most of the educational system, including all 12 universities, has been damaged or destroyed. The second condemned ongoing attacks on academic freedom at American universities, including the silencing of protest against “the U.S.-sponsored genocide perpetrated by Israel in Gaza.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both resolutions passed with nearly 80 percent support from the almost 500 members who attended the vote, held on Saturday during the group’s annual conference in Chicago. But on Sunday the 16 voting members of the executive council voted not to pass them on to the full membership of roughly 14,000 for final consideration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As worded the two resolutions fall outside the scope of the American Historical Association’s chartered mission,” the council said in a statement. “Approving them on behalf of the entire association would present institutional risk and have long-term implications for the discipline and the organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The association, an independent nonprofit organization, is the largest group of professional historians in the country. It was chartered by Congress in 1889, with the mission of pursuing “the promotion of historical studies, the collection and preservation of historical manuscripts” and “kindred purposes in the interest of American history and of history in America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the group has been a prominent critic of laws restricting teaching on race, gender and other controversial subjects. It has also strongly criticized President Trump’s efforts to promote what he calls “patriotic” history emphasizing a positive story of national greatness, including his continuing campaign against the Smithsonian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as with many universities and cultural organizations, the war in Gaza has opened up deep internal rifts. Those fissures have become only more complex as the Trump administration has cited pro-Palestinian activism and campus antisemitism as a central justification for its pressure campaign against higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the council vetoed a similar “scholasticide” resolution after a member vote supporting it. In a statement at the time, the council said it “deplores any intentional destruction of Palestinian educational institutions, libraries, universities and archives in Gaza,” without taking a position on whether the damage had been intentional or who was responsible for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The resolution’s charge of “scholasticide” rests on an April 2024 statement by United Nations experts, which said that the damage or destruction of 80 percent of Gaza’s schools, including all 12 of its universities, stemmed from “patterns of attacks” by Israel. The Israeli government has disputed that report, blaming destruction of Gaza’s schools on the “exploitation of civilian structures for terror purposes” by Hamas.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, the council announced that it would not allow a revised version of the “scholasticide” resolution along with a new one on academic freedom, to be presented for a vote at all. This weekend’s vote came after the resolutions were reintroduced at the meeting itself, as allowed under procedural rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supporters of the resolutions, which were sponsored by the group Historians for Peace and Democracy, were dismayed that the council vetoed a member-approved resolution for a second time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Margaret Power, a retired professor at the Illinois Institute for Technology, said the executive council’s action reflected an “anti-Palestinian bias among leadership” and a lack of respect for members’ democratic wishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they had any hesitation of which way to go, they should have sent it to the full membership, so the entire membership could express its opinion,” she said. “That’s how a democratic organization operates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of the resolutions have also accused the organization of a double standard, noting that within days of the Russian invasion of Ukraine in 2022, the group’s leadership had issued a statement condemning it as “an unprovoked act of military aggression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sarah Weicksel, the executive director of the historical association, said that the statement about Ukraine was broader, and focused on what it called the “distorted and tendentious misreading of history” that the Russian President Vladimir Putin invoked to justify it. The “scholasticide” resolution, by contrast, commits the group to unspecified actions to support the rebuilding of Gaza’s educational system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the academic freedom resolution, Weicksel said the concern lay with the reference to “the U.S.-sponsored Israeli genocide in Gaza.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue, she said, wasn’t the accuracy or inaccuracy of the genocide charge, which is a matter of intense debate among scholars, legal experts and human rights advocates, but that it is “a political statement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The resolution includes phrasing that requires the A.H.A. to take a political stance, and that would be problematic in terms of mission and in terms of the fiduciary responsibility to the organization to ensure its continued nonprofit status,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opponents of the resolutions have noted that many individual scholars have spoken out strongly against Israel’s actions in Gaza, including accusing it of genocide, and the group should defend their speech rights without itself endorsing any one point of view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have also argued that the resolutions would damage the group’s reputation at a moment when the profession is already facing attacks from the political right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“History is under assault right now,” Natalia Mehlman Petrzela, a professor at the New School, said by phone Sunday after the vote. “Pushing the pre-eminent organization of historians to take an overtly political stance only serves to divide the organization and also to jeopardize its reputation as a place for nonpartisan historical inquiry.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions around the resolutions were present throughout the four-day conference, where nearly 3,000 scholars gathered for some 200 panels on both historical topics and current challenges to the profession, like the cratering academic job market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program included nearly a dozen sessions relating to Gaza and broader Palestinian history, where some panelists issued denunciations of the historical association, including charges that it was complicit in genocide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the vote, the group’s outgoing president, Benjamin Vinson, a former president of Howard University, said the question before the council wasn’t whether the situation in Gaza “warrants moral concern.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It plainly does,” he said, noting that the association had begun forming a committee to advise on how to aid Palestinian historians. (Three invited members withdrew from the committee last month, after the council said it would not allow a vote on the resolutions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue, Vinson said, was whether the group should adopt “binding institutional positions on active geopolitical conflicts that would set enduring precedent,” particularly on matters where membership holds “deeply divergent views.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “scholasticide” measure was passed with 282 votes for, 76 against, and two abstentions. The academic freedom resolution passed 245 in favor, 62 against, with one abstention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The academic freedom resolution was developed in coordination with members of the Modern Language Association, the country’s largest scholarly association in the humanities. Over the weekend, it was approved by that group’s delegate assembly, by a vote of 61 in favor, 52 against. That resolution will now pass to a vote by the group’s roughly 20,000 members, where it must receive a majority that also totals at least 10 percent of membership.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/arts/american-historical-association-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:46:22 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>