<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:33:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Deposed Shah’s Son Hopes Trump Will Put Iran Regime ‘Down for Good’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/world/europe/iran-protests-shah-son-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/11/multimedia/11trump-news-iran-shah-son-ktlz/11trump-news-iran-shah-son-ktlz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reza Pahlavi, the son of Iran’s deposed shah and a figure of Iran’s opposition in exile, said he supported U.S. intervention to support a mass protest movement against Iran’s theocratic rulers and issued a direct plea to President Trump to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mass protesters have been emboldened by Mr. Trump’s warnings that he could strike the Iranian government if peaceful protesters were killed, Mr. Pahlavi said in an interview on the Fox News program “Sunday Morning Futures.” Several Iranian rights groups on Sunday said the death toll, after two weeks of protests, had reached the hundreds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Addressing Mr. Trump directly, Mr. Pahlavi said: “They know that you’re not going to throw them under the bus, as has happened before. This is why they are empowered — by the hope that you have their back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in Tehran in 1960 and once Iran’s crown prince, Mr. Pahlavi has lived in exile since the 1979 revolution that ousted his father, Shah Mohammed Reza Pahlavi, and ushered in the rule of the Islamic Republic, which is currently headed by Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked directly during the interview by Maria Bartiromo whether he wanted U.S. forces to “take out Khamenei,” Mr. Pahlavi said “the people of Iran have responded and reacted positively to a promise of intervention.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added, “We need to cut the snake’s head off for good so it can no longer be a threat to Iranian interests, to American interests, to regional interests. And the only solution is to make sure this regime goes down for good and the Iranian people can liberate themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pahlavi, 65, has long been a divisive figure among Iran’s opposition, many of whom disdained the idea of restoring a monarchy that Iranians ousted because of its repressive rule. But he appears to have gained a base of support inside Iran in recent years, according to some analysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plunge in the value of Iran’s currency on Dec. 28 incited the current protests, which quickly grew into broader calls for the ouster of Mr. Khamenei. Many protesters have also begun voicing support for the Pahlavis, with chants of “long live the shah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Pahlavi and members of several activist groups issued calls for mass protests, helping accelerate the movement. Huge crowds have taken to the streets of large metropolises and marginalized rural provinces alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the U.S. operation to capture Venezuela’s president, Nicolás Maduro, Mr. Trump has indicated several times that he was considering striking Iran’s leadership. Several U.S. officials told The New York Times on Saturday that the president had been briefed on options for military strikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether Iranians will be further emboldened by Mr. Pahlavi’s calls for U.S. intervention remains to be seen. When Israel launched a 12-day war on Iran over the summer, briefly joined by U.S. warplanes, many Iranians expressed disdain for foreign intervention and did not turn against the government.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/world/europe/iran-protests-shah-son-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:28:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Grass-Fed Beef Really Better for the Climate?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/climate/climate-emissions-grassfed-beef.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/climate/00cli-askclimate-beef/00cli-askclimate-beef-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether making a spaghetti Bolognese or getting ready to grill some steaks, Americans buying beef might find themselves wondering if they should spend a few dollars more per pound for the grass-fed option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image of cows grazing in a pasture is certainly picturesque. And, at first glance, it may seem like a more humane and planet-friendly alternative to factory-farmed beef.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the environmental effects of food are often complex. So, we asked the experts: Is grass-fed beef better for the climate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly a quarter of all global greenhouse gasses come from food production, and beef accounts for the single biggest share. It generates 8 times the emissions of pork, per kilogram of food, and 100 times the emissions of protein-rich vegetables like peas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big reason is that cows, regardless of what they’re raised for, produce methane. In fact, they have it coming out of both ends day and night. And, while methane disappears faster than carbon dioxide, it’s about 80 times as potent as a greenhouse gas during its first 20 years in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s true that grass-fed beef raises fewer animal welfare and pollution concerns than industrial feedlots, which cram thousands of cows into small spaces where they tend to kick up a lot of air pollution. Their manure and feed are also a big source nitrogen runoff that can create dead zones in aquatic ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Peter Smith, a professor at the University of Aberdeen in Scotland who focuses on climate change and agriculture, said people often conflate climate with other environmental and animal welfare issues. “All these things get rolled in together,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big thing in climate terms is how long the cows are around belching and tooting methane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, most cows begin life on a pasture. At six months, those headed for industrial production move to feedlots to be “finished” on high-calorie grain. By about 18 months, they reach market weight and are slaughtered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grass-fed cows, by contrast, can take up to three years to reach market weight. And all that extra time means more methane. “There’s a whole bunch of reasons you might prefer grass-fed beef,” Dr. Smith said. But in terms of climate-warming emissions, “it actually comes out no better — in fact, a little worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few decades, and as recently as 2024, industry-funded studies have suggested that grazing cattle can offset their methane emissions by stimulating grass regrowth and recycling nutrients through manure. Some research found that this helps to mitigate climate change by locking away planet-warming carbon in the soil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Ron Milo, an environmental scientist at the Weizmann Institute of Science, an Israeli research center, and Gidon Eshel, a professor at Bard College in upstate New York who studies the environmental impact of agriculture, put these claims to the test by calculating the footprint of beef operations in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their analysis was complex, but it boiled down to one question: Grazing can store carbon in the soil, but does that outweigh the methane that cows produce?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We wanted to see exactly how the numbers add up,” Dr. Eshel said. “The bottom line answer is that they mostly don’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their study, published in March, found that even the most efficient grass-fed beef operations create at least 10 percent more emissions than U.S. industrial beef per kilogram of protein. After taking soil sequestration into account, most grass-fed options ended up no better than industrial ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These results didn’t surprise Dr. Smith, who was not affiliated with the study. Soil has a carbon saturation limit, he said, and the benefits vanish after about a decade. Offsetting methane emissions from cattle is “simply unfeasible” for most of the planet, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grass-fed beef also uses more land than industrial beef. “Land is not free,” said Paul Behrens, a food system scientist at the University of Oxford. “The question is, what else could we be using it for?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, meat and dairy production use 80 percent of agricultural land, much of which is better suited to other crops for human consumption, Dr. Behrens said, or could store more carbon if left to grow wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the experts all agreed that eating any kind of beef comes with climate baggage, making a difference doesn’t have to mean giving up beef entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The bulk of food-related emissions comes from a relatively small number of people eating quite a lot of meat,” said Tara Garnett, director of Table, a nonprofit group that studies food systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2023 study found that just 12 percent of the population accounts for half the beef eaten in America on any given day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The biggest benefit to the climate,” Dr. Garnett said, is not going to come from trying to increase the number of vegans. “It’s going to come from the majority of people cutting back on their meat consumption.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re going to eat meat, think about what matters most to you,” she said. But whether you focus on animal welfare, air pollution or greenhouse gas emissions, she said, “there isn’t an answer that sounds like, ‘Eat as much meat as you like.’”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/climate/climate-emissions-grassfed-beef.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:54:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Europe and China Take Step to Resolve Dispute on Electric Vehicles</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/europe-china-electric-vehicles-tariffs-volkswagen.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12biz-eu-china-ev1-wbqt/12biz-eu-china-ev1-wbqt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission and China’s Ministry of Commerce announced on Monday guidance that could lead to the removal of tariffs on some electric vehicles imported from China, notably Volkswagen's Cupra Tavascan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission, the executive arm of the European Union, said it was setting up a procedure for automakers to volunteer limits on the number of electric vehicles they ship from China to Europe. The automakers would also set minimum prices for which they would sell these cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automakers that do limit the number of imported electric vehicles and pledge price floors could be exempt from the anti-subsidy tariffs of up to 35 percent that the European Commission imposed in late 2024 on electric cars from China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have said from the start, as the European Commission, as the investigative authority in this case, that we’re willing to look at alternatives to the anti-subsidy duties we put in place,” said Olof Gill, a spokesman for the European Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The framework announced on Monday came as Europe was looking to develop more trade ties with regions other than the United States in response to President Trump’s wide-ranging tariffs and other initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But European leaders face a quandary. The United States is the only country in recent years that has been willing to run extremely large trade deficits, which has made the American market enticing for European exporters. China has severely limited purchases from Europe through a wide-ranging program of domestic production to replace imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any arrangement for automakers to avoid paying the tariffs on E.V. shipments to Europe may not take effect quickly. Each automaker’s plan would have to be approved separately not only by the European Commission but also by member countries of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new procedure comes after Volkswagen broke ranks this winter with the Chinese car industry by volunteering to limit shipments to Europe of its Cupra electric cars from its factory in Hefei, China, and to set an undisclosed minimum price for the Cupras when they arrived in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exchange, Volkswagen asked the European Commission to stop collecting its 20.7 percent anti-subsidy tariff on the Cupra. The commission’s move on Monday sets a procedure for reviewing such requests by automakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve issued this guidance because, in December, the first meaningful offer on a price undertaking came,” Mr. Gill, the commission’s spokesman, said. “We’ve taken the decision to issue this more detailed additional guidance in the event that other offers will come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s Ministry of Commerce has contended that automakers with factories in China should negotiate as a bloc with the European Commission, and should not submit their own offers. If automakers make separate proposals, they might compete against each other over concessions to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese ministry took a different stance late last year when seeking its own concessions from foreign producers. The ministry demanded that brandy producers in Europe each submit their own offers to set price limits on their sales to China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European trade officials have been wary of accepting deals that allow automakers to set high minimum prices for their electric cars. That could allow automakers to fix prices and pocket the profits from limited sales in Europe instead of paying tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission reached a similar deal in 2013 for Chinese solar panel manufacturers to set high minimum prices in the European market in exchange for avoiding tariffs. The Chinese solar industry reaped large profits from these high prices and invested the money in new factories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helped the Chinese industry become so dominant that most solar manufacturers in Europe have had to close or severely curtail operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting from Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/europe-china-electric-vehicles-tariffs-volkswagen.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:02:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela Frees 24 More Political Prisoners, Rights Group Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-political-prisoners-freed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12VENEZUELA-PRISONER-RELEASE-bzcg/12VENEZUELA-PRISONER-RELEASE-bzcg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s leading human rights organization said on Monday that at least 24 political prisoners had been released from prison in the early morning, bringing the total freed in recent days to at least 41.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number could soon rise: Just after 6 a.m. local time, Gonzalo Himiob, a leader of Foro Penal, the rights group, said on social media that even more prisoners might have been freed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The releases, which began on Thursday, represent the most visible gesture of change for the interim Venezuelan government. On Jan. 3, American soldiers raided the country and captured President Nicolás Maduro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s interim government has promised to free an “important number” of detainees. Rights groups estimate that between 800 and 900 political prisoners are incarcerated in Venezuela, many under harsh conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the people released on Monday were Italian citizens, Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni of Italy said on Facebook. Some of those who have been released in recent days are prominent members of the Venezuelan opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rocío San Miguel, who was released on Thursday, had been investigating the authoritarian government. Enrique Márquez, a former presidential candidate who had demanded voting records from the disputed 2024 election, was also freed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of these prisoners were charged with incitement of hate, terrorism or conspiring to overthrow the government for simply exercising basic political rights, rights groups say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The releases have offered some optimism for a more democratic future in Venezuela, but they come as the interim government has intensified a crackdown on other citizens, interrogating people and searching their phones for signs of support for Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-political-prisoners-freed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:01:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Archaeologists Find Large Roman Villa Under Deer Park in Wales</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/archaeologists-roman-villa-park-wales.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-uk-roman-villa-02-ktqw/12int-uk-roman-villa-02-ktqw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its Iron Age hill fort, medieval abbey ruins and 19th-century castle, Margam Country Park in Wales offers plenty of history for its regular stream of visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the most spectacular relic of all appears to lie around three feet below ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists announced on Monday that they had detected the outline of the largest stand-alone Roman villa structure to be uncovered in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appears to be particularly well preserved because it lies beneath a deer park that was never disturbed by cultivation or construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discovery was made using geophysical surveys, which use high-resolution magnetometry and ground radar data to detect objects below the surface. Although excavation has yet to begin, Alexander Langlands, an associate professor at Swansea University who is leading the project, describes the discovery as the “Pompeii of Port Talbot” — referring to one of the world’s most famous archaeological sites and to a nearby Welsh town that is famous for its steelworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like being a 12-year-old all over again,” he said, recalling his first sight of the images. “I was really, really excited.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More structures are likely to be buried nearby, Dr. Langlands said in a phone interview, including a possible Roman bathhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surveys show that the villa occupied an enclosure spanning roughly 43 meters by 55 meters, or 141 feet by 180 feet. Its fortified structure suggests that it was equipped for defense against aggressors from the east and west. That was often necessary in the unstable years toward the end of the Roman occupation of Britain, which began in A.D. 43 and lasted until the fifth century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time, the Romans conquered most of Wales despite resistance from Indigenous tribes. Most Roman remains that have been excavated in Wales are from military fortifications or marching camps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes the discovery of a villa — of a size and scale that would not seem out of place in the center of Roman England — particularly significant, Dr. Langlands said. It could show that Wales was not a “kind of liminal borderland” region, he added, but “just as Roman as anywhere else we’ve got in the heartlands of the province of Britannia.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geophysical surveys revealed a substantial aisled building southeast of the main villa. This is believed to have been either a large agricultural storage facility or a structure dating from the later history of the site, possibly a meeting hall for post-Roman leaders and their followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The surveys went exceptionally well,” said Christian Bird, the technical director of TerraDat UK, the company that undertook the survey of around 30 to 40 hectares of land. In a statement, he added that the “data are remarkably clear, identifying and mapping in 3-D the villa structure, surrounding ditches and wider layout of the site.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More precise information about when the villa was built and how it was used will likely be revealed only through excavation, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of particular interest to researchers is whether the settlement collapsed in the late fourth century, alongside some other Roman villas around that time, or whether it continued into the fifth century, perhaps becoming a center of Christianity. That could connect the history of Margam Park to its medieval development as a place of Christian worship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its Bronze and Iron Age relics, the park can trace its origins to prehistoric times, but the area also includes the ruins of an abbey that was founded in the middle of the 12th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Henry VIII dissolved the country’s monasteries, a succession of different structures were built on the site, including Margam Castle in the early 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The archaeological project that uncovered the Roman villa was a collaboration between Swansea University’s Center for Heritage Research and Training, Neath Port Talbot Council, which owns Margam Country Park, and Margam Abbey Church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether and when excavation can begin is unclear and, in the first instance, Dr. Langlands hopes the survey area can be extended to reveal more of what lies beneath the Welsh landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the time being, the villa is destined to remain undisturbed as it has for centuries. Because of the risk to the site from rogue metal detectors searching for artifacts, its precise location is being kept secret.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/archaeologists-roman-villa-park-wales.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:39:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Global Cost of Futzing With the Fed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/federal-reserve-global-costs-iran-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/07/25/multimedia/13int-theworld-fed-powell-promo/25db-trump-powell-zbgq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, President Trump has been trying to pressure the Federal Reserve, the U.S. central bank, into cutting interest rates. Yesterday, my colleagues revealed that he has made his most aggressive move yet: Prosecutors have opened a criminal investigation against the chairman of the Fed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insulating central banks from politicians has long been considered sound economic policy. That conventional wisdom has been challenged since the financial crisis. But one thing is clear: If Trump succeeds in gaining control over the Fed, it won’t just affect Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has called the Federal Reserve chair Jerome Powell a “clown,” a “dummy,” a “major loser” and a “bad head of the Fed.” He has gone after him on social media, saying Powell and his colleagues “should be ashamed.” He sent him a handwritten note accusing him of costing the United States “a fortune” and demanding that he cut interest rates “by a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we learned that Trump’s campaign against Powell has escalated further: Federal prosecutors have begun investigating Powell for his role in overseeing the renovation work being done on the Fed’s headquarters. The criminal investigation is being overseen by a longtime Trump ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump told NBC News that the investigation didn’t have anything to do with interest rates. Powell sees it differently. The investigation, he said in a rare video statement (below), is about whether “monetary policy will be directed by political pressure or intimidation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the dispute is the question of whether the Fed, which sets interest rates, should be governed by technocrats whose main objective is to maximize employment and keep inflation under control; or whether it should, as Trump has argued, be controlled by politicians with a mix of objectives — among them winning elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who wins that fight matters not just for Americans but for everyone else, too. As my colleague Eshe Nelson wrote last year, the Fed is “the most important and influential central bank in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top dollar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. dollar has a special role in the global economy. So when the Fed changes interest rates, the ripple effects are felt far beyond U.S. borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some countries like Panama and El Salvador have replaced their own currency with the dollar. Others, like Saudi Arabia, have pegged the value of their currencies to it. And most global commodities, like oil and gold, are denominated in dollars. So are U.S. stocks and Treasuries, which feature prominently in the portfolios of governments and private investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this all possible? Stability. Investors and governments trust that the value of the dollar won’t be too volatile, rising or falling solely on the whims of politicians seeking to win over voters at election time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Fed’s importance goes beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke to Leah Downey, a lecturer at King’s College London and author of “Our Money,” a book about monetary policy, who explained that the Fed had effectively become “the lender of last resort to the world.” During times of turmoil, like the subprime mortgage crisis and the Covid-19 pandemic, the Fed stepped in to supply dollars to other central banks to make sure that global markets don’t break down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing faith&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why markets have reacted badly every time Trump has threatened the Fed’s independence — not just in the United States but worldwide. Stocks, the dollar and U.S. government bonds wobbled on the morning after news broke of Powell’s criminal investigation. The price of gold, a haven when investors are anxious, set a fresh record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed also sets the standard for how central banks operate around the globe. A Federal Reserve controlled by the White House could undermine the idea of central bank independence elsewhere, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept of central bank independence has been sacrosanct for decades. The idea is that politicians can’t always be trusted with monetary policy, because the temptation of lowering interest rates right before an election is too great. That can cause long-term damage by increasing inflation down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many instances when central banks have become subject to political meddling and the outcome wasn’t good, Eshe told me. Turkey is perhaps the clearest recent example. President Recep Tayyip Erdogan pressured the central bank for years to cut interest rates, even as the country’s currency plummeted; inflation now sits at a punishing 30 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, some academics, Downey included, have begun to wonder whether the structure of the Federal Reserve — and its connections to private financial institutions — make it overly focused on very low inflation at the expense of things that might be a higher priority for many Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a softer version of bringing politics into monetary policy — say, a system of periodic reviews of the central bank, or adding to its objectives — may not be welcomed by the rest of the world because of the volatility it might introduce. It could threaten the special status of the dollar, which might create its own consequences: The U.S. may not be able to borrow and spend as freely. But some economists argue that the potential benefits might be worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has, in a way, touched on an important discussion. But not even the fiercest advocates for a more accountable central bank think it’s a good idea to threaten Powell with prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than two months ago, Israel and Hamas signed a cease-fire agreement that offered Palestinians in Gaza a hope of respite after a punishing two-year Israeli bombardment that left much of their enclave in ruins. Yet the destruction has continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel has demolished more than 2,500 buildings in Gaza since the cease-fire began, a New York Times analysis of satellite imagery has found. While most of these structures are in Israeli-controlled areas, dozens lie beyond the agreed-upon boundary for Israeli forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli officials say the demolitions are part of efforts to “demilitarize” Gaza, destroying tunnels and booby-trapped homes. But Palestinians in Gaza argue that Israel has been flattening entire neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is absolute destruction,” said one former Israeli military commander who led forces in Gaza in the 1990s. “It’s not selective destruction. It’s everything.” Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran said it was prepared for war but also ready to negotiate, after Trump threatened military strikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s government released at least 24 more political prisoners, bringing the total to at least 41.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain began an investigation into the social media platform X, over its artificially generated sexual images of women and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The E.U. gave automakers a workaround for electric vehicles made in China, forgoing stiff tariffs if they limit imports and set minimum prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nigerian author Chimamanda Ngozi Adichie accused a Lagos hospital of negligence in the death of her 21-month-old son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Swiss court ordered an owner of a bar that caught fire on New Year’s Day to be placed in pretrial detention for at least three months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Xabi Alonso was sacked as head coach of Real Madrid, replaced by the club’s reserve team coach, Alvaro Arbeloa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basketball: The French phenom Victor Wembanyama can jump-kick a basketball out of the net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A growing number of U.S. citizens are joining the military in an attempt to protect their immigrant families from deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little-known government program called Parole in Place protects undocumented parents and spouses of service members from deportation, and gives them a streamlined pathway to a green card. That benefit has become a powerful incentive and recruiting tool amid ongoing immigration raids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Greg Jaffe spent over a week shadowing Sgt. First Class Rosa Cortez, a top recruiter for the Oregon National Guard, who is herself the daughter of Mexican immigrants. “Emotions are everywhere for me,” she said of her work. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— New research shows that dogs have advanced word-learning skills: They can learn the names of new toys by listening in on the conversations of their owners. Some dogs, especially Border collies, have memorized the names of hundreds of toys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At an adult football league in suburban Dallas, enrollment starts with a weigh-in. “Sorry, you’re not fat enough,” one coach told some newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The league was founded in Britain in 2014 as an answer to weight-loss programs that primarily attracted women. It has expanded to the U.S., with more than a dozen leagues in New York, Florida and Texas. Games are reserved for hefty players lured by competitive football and heavy doses of self-deprecating humor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its cheeky team names (Fat Man United, Totten-Ham and Cheese) and playful ethos, Man v Fat might be dismissed as a gag. But participants say they are serious about getting in shape. “You have no idea how much faster we are now,” one player said. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boost: Try seven expert-backed tips to improve your gut health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen: Virginia Evans discusses the success of her debut novel, “The Correspondent,” which became one of last year’s sleeper hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch: Check out these five new international movies that are streaming now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kelewele is a popular Ghanaian dish of ripe plantains, marinated in a blend of ginger, garlic, selim seeds and cayenne, and then fried and served as a side dish or a snack. This version is made in the oven, and the result is a parade of flavors and textures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these ski slopes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cortina d’Ampezzo, Italy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Queenstown, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nagano Alps, Japan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Moritz, Switzerland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/federal-reserve-global-costs-iran-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:23:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Explores Diplomacy With Iran While Weighing Strikes, Officials Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-iran-options-diplomacy-strikes.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/10/multimedia/12dc-diplo-iran-gwzm/10int-iran-streets-gwzm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is exploring options for diplomacy with Iran even as he weighs whether to attack the country to try to deter its leaders from killing more protesters, U.S. officials said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon is presenting a wider range of strike options to Mr. Trump than previously reported. Possible targets include Iran’s nuclear program, going beyond the U.S. airstrikes that battered it in June, and ballistic missile sites, a U.S. official said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the narrower options, a cyberattack or a strike against Iran’s domestic security apparatus, which is using lethal force against protesters, are more likely, the official said. Any attack is at least several days away, and could prompt a vigorous retaliation from Iran, the official said. Mr. Trump is scheduled to be briefed on options on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House press secretary, Karoline Leavitt, said that airstrikes were “one of the many, many options that are on the table,” but that “diplomacy is always the first option for the president.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What you’re hearing publicly from the Iranian regime is quite different from the messages the administration is receiving privately,” she added, “and I think the president has an interest in exploring those messages.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That suggested that the private missives the administration has received were less fiery than the Iranian government’s bellicose public messages about the United States since Mr. Trump’s initial threats of a new attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump told reporters on Sunday night that it appeared that Iran had crossed his red line, after he said this month that he would come to the aid of protesters if the Iranian government used lethal force against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There seems to be some people killed who weren’t supposed to be killed,” he said. “These are violent — you can call them leaders, I don’t know if they’re leaders. I guess they rule with violence. But we’re looking at it very seriously; the military’s looking at it. And there’s a couple options.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday afternoon, Mr. Trump issued a new threat, saying in a social media post that the United States would impose a tariff of 25 percent on “any and all business” done with the United States by countries that are also engaged in commerce with Iran. It is unclear how or whether this would be enacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India, Turkey and Middle Eastern nations could be affected, as well as China, which is the biggest buyer of Iranian oil. But Mr. Trump and China’s leader, Xi Jinping, agreed to a truce last fall in their trade war, and the American president has aimed to keep relations stable in order to ensure a planned April summit with Mr. Xi in Beijing stays on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government has managed to cut internet service across the country, keeping it in an information blackout. Ms. Leavitt said Mr. Trump had asked Elon Musk, a conservative billionaire ally in the technology industry, to see if his company SpaceX can get internet service to Iranian citizens through the Starlink satellite network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Iranian officials appeared to temper some of their anti-American rhetoric of recent days by saying they were ready to talk with the Trump administration again. “We are not looking for war, but we are prepared for war — even more prepared than the previous war,” Abbas Araghchi, the foreign minister, told a conference of foreign ambassadors in the capital, Tehran, broadcast by state television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He appeared to be referring to the 12-day war with Israel in June, during which the United States joined Israel to bomb Iran’s nuclear facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are also ready for negotiations, but negotiations that are fair, with equal rights and mutual respect,” Mr. Araghchi added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran also said on Monday that communication channels were open between Mr. Araghchi and Steve Witkoff, a top envoy for Mr. Trump who led U.S.-Iran talks last spring. “Iran has never left the negotiating table, but it will not engage in one-sided negotiations,” Esmail Baghaei, a foreign ministry spokesman, said at a news conference on Monday. Mr. Witkoff did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some American officials think Iran is trying to delay a U.S. attack rather than aiming to sincerely engage in diplomacy, two officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not clear on what topics the Iranian government was willing to negotiate with the United States. The two nations held talks last spring over Iran’s nuclear program, which the country’s leaders say is for civilian use. American and Israeli officials, however, fear it could be used to make nuclear warheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Obama administration had negotiated an agreement to limit the program, but Mr. Trump withdrew from the pact in his first term. Iran then increased its uranium enrichment, bringing the material closer to weapons-grade, though as of June the country’s leaders had not made a decision to pursue nuclear weapons, according to U.S. intelligence assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks between the Trump administration and Iran ended with the U.S. strikes on the country’s nuclear sites in June. Iranian officials made some overtures after that, but American officials did not engage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s new diplomatic outreach comes at what might be the greatest moment of crisis the government has faced in years, more so than even during the 12-day war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, and his allies are trying to quell mass protests that have spread across the country. They began in late December over dissatisfaction with the economy and a currency crisis, but in reality are the result of years of discontent with the government. The protesters are calling for expansive changes to the government, and while top officials have acknowledged the need to address problems, they are intent on not giving up power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iranian security forces armed with tear gas rifles and long guns have fired into crowds, and videos of gunfire and people yelling have circulated widely, according to an analysis of the videos by The New York Times. The forces have killed scores of Iranian civilians and injured many more, according to estimates from human rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Iran is dangling talks and deals to dissuade Trump from using military force against them,” said Karim Sadjadpour, a senior fellow at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace who studies Iran and its foreign policy. “It’s not clear what they would be offering as concessions given the destruction of much of their nuclear program and regional proxies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vali Nasr, a scholar of Iran at Johns Hopkins University, said that the Iranian government was taking a pragmatic approach and not just trying to buy time, but that it had less leverage now in negotiations because its nuclear program has been at a standstill since the June war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Iran’s objective is they don’t want any war with the United States, and they want the United States to prevent Israel from attacking Iran,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli officials have been stressing the dangers of Iran’s ballistic missile program, but Mr. Nasr said the top commanders of the Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps, the major power center in Iran’s military, would be reluctant to allow Iranian diplomats to negotiate over that. There is a view in Tehran that Iran’s ballistic missiles are the country’s most important form of deterrence, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has threatened since Jan. 2 that he would attack Iran if the government killed protesters. “We are locked and loaded and ready to go,” he wrote that day in a social media post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear what, if any, legal justifications under U.S. law and international law the Trump administration would cite for such an attack. Two days after ordering the June 21 attack on Iranian nuclear sites, Mr. Trump sent a letter to Congress that said the action was done to advance a “vital” national interest and to defend an ally, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump was recently briefed by the Pentagon on options for a new strike on Iran, The Times reported on Saturday. The strike could take aim at targets in Tehran, including ones associated with domestic security forces that U.S. officials deem to be responsible for attacks on protesters, including the state-backed Basij militia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.S. strike would be aimed at sending a message to the ayatollah about killing protesters and not intended to lead to a direct overthrow of the government, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State Marco Rubio and other aides have been keeping Mr. Trump apprised of the protests, and he has also been tracking news coverage about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellie Geranmayeh, the deputy head of the Middle East and North Africa program at the European Council on Foreign Relations, said in an interview on Friday that there had been signs late in the week that the Iranian government could be having security agencies hold back on unleashing their most repressive actions in order to avoid giving Mr. Trump a rationale to attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Islamic Republic of Iran is now facing an unprecedented bottom-up pressure, as well as a top-down pressure,” she said. “Usually they’ve only had to confront one or the other. And they are masters at survival, by the way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the security agencies intensified their crackdown over the weekend, leading to what Ms. Geranmayeh said on Monday was a “very bleak turn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intensifying violence has fueled more vocal threats against Iran from Mr. Trump, even as he has denounced protesters in the United States who criticize his policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president has shown he’s unafraid to use military options if and when he deems necessary,” Ms. Leavitt said on Monday, “and nobody knows that better than Iran.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katrin Bennhold and Sanam Mahoozi contributed reporting from London, and Aurelien Breeden from Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/trump-iran-options-diplomacy-strikes.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:42:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Attacked Boat With Aircraft That Looked Like a Civilian Plane</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/us-boat-attacks-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-secret-plane-fljt/12dc-secret-plane-fljt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon used a secret aircraft painted to look like a civilian plane in its first attack on a boat that the Trump administration said was smuggling drugs, killing 11 people last September, according to officials briefed on the matter. The aircraft also carried its munitions inside the fuselage, rather than visibly under its wings, they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nonmilitary appearance is significant, according to legal specialists, because the administration has argued its lethal boat attacks are lawful — not murders — because President Trump “determined” the United States is in an armed conflict with drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the laws of armed conflict prohibit combatants from feigning civilian status to fool adversaries into dropping their guard, then attacking and killing them. That is a war crime called “perfidy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retired Maj. Gen. Steven J. Lepper, a former deputy judge advocate general for the United States Air Force, said that if the aircraft had been painted in a way that disguised its military nature and got close enough for the people on the boat to see it — tricking them into failing to realize they should take evasive action or surrender to survive — that was a war crime under armed-conflict standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Shielding your identity is an element of perfidy,” he said. “If the aircraft flying above is not identifiable as a combatant aircraft, it should not be engaged in combatant activity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aircraft swooped in low enough for the people aboard the boat to see it, according to officials who have seen or been briefed on surveillance video from the attack. The boat had turned back toward Venezuela, apparently after seeing the plane, before the first strike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two survivors of the initial attack later appeared to wave at the aircraft after clambering aboard an overturned piece of the hull, before the military killed them in a follow-up strike that also sank the wreckage. It is not clear whether the initial survivors knew that the explosion on their vessel had been caused by a missile attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military has since switched to using recognizably military aircraft for boat strikes, including MQ-9 Reaper drones, although it is not clear whether those aircraft got low enough to be seen. In a boat attack in October, two survivors of an initial strike swam away from the wreckage and so avoided being killed by a follow-up strike on the remnants of their vessel. The military rescued them and returned them to their home countries, Colombia and Ecuador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. military manuals about the law of war discuss perfidy at length, saying it includes when a combatant feigns civilian status so the adversary “neglects to take precautions which are otherwise necessary.” A U.S. Navy handbook says lawful combatants at sea use offensive force “within the bounds of military honor, particularly without resort to perfidy,” and stresses that commanders have a “duty” to “distinguish their own forces from the civilian population.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions about perfidy have arisen in closed-door briefings of Congress by military leaders, according to people familiar with the matter, but have not been publicly discussed because the aircraft is classified. The public debate has focused on a follow-up strike that killed the two initial survivors, despite a war-law prohibition on targeting the shipwrecked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The press office for the U.S. Special Operations Command, whose leader, Adm. Frank M. Bradley, ran the operation on Sept. 2, declined to comment on the nature of the aircraft used in the attack. But the Pentagon insisted in a statement that its arsenal has undergone legal review for compliance with the laws of armed conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The U.S. military utilizes a wide array of standard and nonstandard aircraft depending on mission requirements,” Kingsley Wilson, the Pentagon press secretary, said in response to questions from The New York Times. “Prior to the fielding and employment of each aircraft, they go through a rigorous procurement process to ensure compliance with domestic law, department policies and regulations, and applicable international standards, including the law of armed conflict.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not clear what the aircraft was. While multiple officials confirmed that it was not painted in a classic military style, they declined to specify exactly what it looked like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amateur plane-spotting enthusiasts posted pictures on Reddit in early September of what appeared to be one of the military’s modified 737s, painted white with a blue stripe and with no military markings, at the St. Croix airport in the U.S. Virgin Islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the specific aircraft at issue, three people familiar with the matter acknowledged that it was not painted in the usual military gray and lacked military markings. But they said its transponder was transmitting a military tail number, meaning broadcasting or “squawking” its military identity via radio signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several law-of-war experts said that would not make the use of such an aircraft lawful in these circumstances since the people on the boat probably lacked equipment to pick up the signal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the legal specialists who said the use of a military transponder signal would not solve a perfidy problem was Todd Huntley, a retired Navy captain who formerly deployed with the Joint Special Operations Command as a judge advocate general, or JAG, and directed the Navy’s national security law division.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Captain Huntley said he could think of legitimate uses for such an aircraft that would make it lawful to have in the arsenal for other contexts, including a hostage rescue scenario in which munitions might be needed for self-defense but were not intended for launching offensive attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration kept planning for the boat attacks operation closely held, excluding many military lawyers and operational experts who would normally be involved. Moreover, Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth has sought to undercut the role of military lawyers as an internal check, including by firing the top service JAGs in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military operates several aircraft that are built on civilian airframes — including modified Boeing 737s and Cessna turboprops — and can launch munitions from internal weapons bays without visible external armaments. Such aircraft are usually painted gray and have military markings, but military and plane-spotting websites show that a few are painted white and have minimal markings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military has killed at least 123 people in 35 attacks on boats, including the Sept. 2 strike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A broad range of specialists in laws governing the use of force have said the orders by Mr. Trump and Mr. Hegseth to attack the boats have been illegal and the killings have been murders. The military is not allowed to target civilians who pose no imminent threat, even if they are suspected of crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration has argued that the strikes are lawful and the people on the boats are “combatants” because Mr. Trump decided the situation was a so-called noninternational armed conflict — meaning a war against a nonstate actor — between the United States and a secret list of 24 criminal gangs and drug cartels he has deemed terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legitimacy of that claim is widely disputed. Still, it has put attention on ways particular attacks might have violated the laws of war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like General Lepper and Captain Huntley, Geoffrey Corn, a retired lieutenant colonel JAG officer who was the Army’s senior adviser for law-of-war issues, said he does not believe that the Sept. 2 attack took place in an armed conflict. He is now a law professor at Texas Tech University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he noted that the United States considers perfidy to be a crime in noninternational armed conflicts: It charged a Guantánamo detainee before a military commission with that offense over Al Qaeda’s 2000 attack on the U.S.S. Cole, in which militants in a small boat floated a hidden bomb up to the side of the warship while waving in a friendly manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Corn said an assessment of whether the Sept. 2 attack counted as perfidy would turn on whether the military was trying to make the people on the boat think the aircraft was civilian to “get the jump” on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The critical question is whether there is a credible alternative reason for using an unmarked aircraft to conduct the attack other than exploiting apparent civilian status to gain some tactical advantage,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/us/politics/us-boat-attacks-law.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:44:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Owner of Swiss Bar Where 40 Died Is Ordered to Jail as a Flight Risk</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/switzerland-fire-bar-owner-detention.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-switzerland-court-order-detention-tmhl/12int-switzerland-court-order-detention-tmhl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Swiss court on Monday ordered one of the two owners of a bar that caught fire during a New Year’s celebration to be placed in pretrial detention for at least three months, according to a court statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owners, Jacques and Jessica Moretti, are under investigation over whether negligence played a role in the fire at Le Constellation bar in Crans-Montana, a popular ski town in the French-speaking part of Switzerland. The fire killed 40 people, most of them teenagers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators have said they believe the fire was started by sparklers but have not elaborated. Videos and witnesses have suggested that pyrotechnics placed on bottles of alcohol ignited the foam-covered ceiling of the bar’s basement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators interrogated the Morettis, a married couple who are both French citizens, on Friday in the nearby town of Sion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court, which under Swiss law had 48 hours to make a decision, approved a prosecutor’s request to place Mr. Moretti in pretrial detention “for an initial period of three months due to the risk of flight.” The court said that it could lift the detention order if other means were found to eliminate the flight risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It added that it was “not a question of punishing the defendant, who is presumed innocent until a possible conviction becomes final.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike her husband, Ms. Moretti was let go after questioning. The couple’s lawyers said in a statement that the decision would allow Mr. Moretti, “once the conditions are met, to regain his freedom.” The statement said that the couple would not “evade this legal process, which they will face together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sébastien Fanti, a lawyer for three Swiss citizens injured in the fire, said that he and his clients were “not entirely satisfied” with the court’s decision to detain only Mr. Moretti. “This morning, the father of a child who was burned alive said to me, ‘He died as if in war, so now it’s war,’” Mr. Fanti said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the victims and their relatives have also asked investigators to look into the role of town officials. In a news conference last week, Nicolas Féraud, the mayor of Crans-Montana, acknowledged that the local authorities had not carried out yearly safety inspections between 2020 and 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/switzerland-fire-bar-owner-detention.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 06:57:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World Court Hears Groundbreaking Genocide Case Against Myanmar</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/asia/myanmar-icj-rohingya.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-icj-myanmar-1-jqch/12int-icj-myanmar-1-jqch-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The charge that Myanmar committed genocide against the Rohingya Muslims went before the World Court on Monday for three weeks of argument and testimony, in the first case of its kind, with implications for other genocide cases like the one pending against Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gambia, a West African country thousands of miles from Myanmar, in Southeast Asia, filed the suit in 2019. The International Court of Justice, in The Hague, allowed the case to proceed on the premise that international law gives countries a mandate to act against genocide anywhere in the world, even if they are not affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same basis, the International Court of Justice, an arm of the United Nations, later allowed the 2023 genocide charge by South Africa against Israel, which is still at an early stage. Israel has rejected the charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myanmar launched a military campaign against the Rohingya minority, primarily in western Rakhine state, in 2016, after alleging insurgent attacks on border posts. U.N. officials and human rights groups have called it a coordinated, scorched-earth campaign to remove the Rohingya — killing, wounding and raping untold numbers of people, razing villages and forcing about a million people to flee the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myanmar’s government denies committing genocide or “ethnic cleansing,” which legal experts say can be considered a form of genocide. It called the campaign “clearance operations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dawda A. Jallow, the attorney general and justice minister of Gambia, said in his opening remarks to the 15-judge court that Myanmar’s military rulers had turned the lives of the Rohingya “into a nightmare subjecting them to the most horrific violence and destruction one could imagine.” He said his country was prompted to file its case, under an international treaty known as the Genocide Convention, because of its own experiences with a military regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Myanmar merely asserts that the motive of its operations was counterterrorism,’’ Philippe Sands, a member of Gambia’s legal team, told the court, but the scale and systematic nature of the campaign went far beyond any military goal, he said. “The only reasonable conclusion is that Myanmar acted in this case with genocidal intent.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another lawyer on that team, Paul Reichler, cited extensive witness testimony, primarily from 2017, including 54 instances of houses being locked and set ablaze with families inside. Witnesses recounted women and girls being gang raped and some times mutilated, he said, and children being wrenched from their mothers’ arms and thrown into fires. Satellite images showed dozens of villages burned to the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rohingya are related to the people of Bangladesh, and many also claim descent from Arab traders; they have lived in what is now Myanmar for generations, even centuries. They are a small, mostly Muslim minority in a country that is overwhelmingly Buddhist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myanmar’s government has called them illegal immigrants and denies them citizenship. It long denied the existence of a distinct Rohingya ethnicity, calling them Bengali.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language Myanmar used at the height of the campaign, Mr. Reichler said, supports the genocide charge. Citing a U.N.-backed investigation, he said the government called the Rohingya an “impure and subhuman race” from abroad whose population growth “threatened to supplant the pure-blooded local race.’’ He quoted one official as announcing that Myanmar “would soon solve the Bengali problem.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘’It was the state itself that generated the atrocities,’’ he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its 80-year history, the nearest the World Court has come to holding a nation responsible for genocide was in 2007, in a case brought against Serbia by Bosnia. In that case, the judges ruled that the 1995 Srebrenica massacre in Bosnia was an act of genocide, and that Serbia had failed in its duty to prevent the atrocity. But a divided court did not find Serbia guilty of the slaughter, itself, though it was committed by Bosnian Serb forces that worked closely with Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the court, which rules on disputes between nations, has no independent power to enforce its decisions, they carry legal and moral weight, and international lawyers say the Myanmar case will be closely watched for possible repercussions in other genocide claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jallow made an unusual gesture on Monday, asking a group of Rohingya people in the courtroom to stand and be seen by the judges and the audience of diplomats and lawyers gathered in the great hall of the Peace Palace in The Hague. Some are expected to testify in the coming weeks, but those sessions will be closed to the public and the press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a million Rohingya people now live in overcrowded camps in Bangladesh, in dire conditions. Relief workers say the refugees’ plight has worsened since Washington cut its substantial aid contributions last year.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/asia/myanmar-icj-rohingya.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:28:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hints of Political Amnesty Stoke Hope and Frustration in Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-political-prisoners-amnesty.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12venezuela-imprisoned-gcwq/12venezuela-imprisoned-gcwq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Venezuela’s interim government announced last week that it would start freeing political prisoners, Ramón Guanipa Linares, a college psychology student, immediately packed a bag and flew from his hometown in western Venezuela to the capital, Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On arrival, he went straight to a prison where his father Juan Pablo Guanipa, a prominent opposition politician, has been detained for the past eight months for challenging President Nicolás Maduro’s rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I wanted to be the first to hug my father,” Mr. Guanipa Linares, 28, said in a phone interview from his home in Maracaibo, Venezuela’s second largest city. “But they had no information about his liberation or anything like that. They were just rumors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guanipa Linares, like most Venezuelans, has been trying to understand his country’s political course since the U.S. captured Mr. Maduro and helped install his vice president, Delcy Rodríguez, as the country’s interim leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her unexpected alliance with the United States has raised cautious hopes that Venezuela could become less repressive, if not democratic. On Thursday, Ms. Rodriguez’s brother and congressional speaker, Jorge Rodríguez, announced that the government would be freeing an “important number” of political prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump raised expectations further on Saturday, announcing on social media that “Venezuela has started the process, in a BIG WAY, of releasing their political prisoners.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the slow pace of the ensuing liberations has raised questions in Venezuela over Ms. Rodríguez’s ultimate intentions, as well as her ability to impose her will on the more extreme factions of her government that control the various security agencies and their prisons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning, Venezuela’s government announced that it had released 116 prisoners “in recent hours.” But rights groups that monitor political prisoners in the country have counted only 41 releases since Mr. Maduro’s downfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 800 political prisoners remained behind bars as of Sunday, according to a count by Foro Penal, one of the rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday night, relatives of political prisoners held a night vigil outside the secret police’s notorious El Helicoide prison in Caracas, a move that underscored both the growing impatience with the government’s foot-dragging and a cautious sense of hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the final years of Mr. Maduro’s rule, security forces would have dispersed such a protest within minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guanipa Linares has since returned home, where he has been trying to make sense of his country’s new power dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“From what we understand, there was a plan to free all these political prisoners, but something has happened midway,” he said. “So we are just trying to raise our voices and maintain the pressure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Juan Pablo Guanipa, is arguably the most prominent politician who remains in detention in Venezuela. A former congressman from a centrist opposition party, he ran successfully for governor of Venezuela’s oil rich Zulia state in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Maduro’s government dismissed him from office for refusing to swear allegiance to a legislative body that the president had created, in violation of Venezuelan law, to bypass the opposition-controlled congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Mr. Guanipa ran to be the presidential candidate for the main opposition alliance for the election to be held the following year. After coming second in the primary, he threw his support behind the winning candidate, Maria Corina Machado, who won the Nobel Peace Prize in 2025 for her pro-democracy campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposition alliance won those presidential elections in a landslide, voting machine tallies show, but was prevented from taking power by Mr. Maduro, who declared himself the winner and then unleashed a new wave of repression against opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guanipa and Ms. Machado were among the few prominent opposition leaders who chose to remain in Venezuela as repression deepened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, security forces raided his hiding place, breaking down the door of his room at 2 a.m. and dragging him off to prison, according to Mr. Guanipa Linares, his son. Like many other political prisoners, he has been charged with terrorism and treason, but never convicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guanipa Linares said he has seen his father once since, and has had no telephone contact with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following his father’s detention, Mr. Guanipa Linares said he had to take on the role of looking after his four younger brothers and sisters, while raising his 8-year-old daughter as a divorced single parent and campaigning for his father’s release. His mother died in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said his father “didn’t want to flee the country and become another exiled politician in Spain or the U.S.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In his own words,” Mr. Guanipa Linares added, “he wanted to fight the good fight.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-political-prisoners-amnesty.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:08:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s India Envoy Offers Hope Amid a Strained Relationship</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/asia/india-us-ambassador-sergio-gor.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-india-US-ghmv/12int-india-US-ghmv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergio Gor, a close ally of President Trump, began his role as the United States ambassador to India on Monday, promising to help resolve differences that have badly strained ties between the two nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Real friends can disagree, but always resolve their differences in the end,” Mr. Gor said in a speech to hundreds of embassy staff members, emphasizing Mr. Trump’s “great friendship" with Prime Minister Narendra Modi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such sentiments may have rung hollow to Indian officials, who in recent months have been trying to rebuild the bilateral relationship after a series of blows by Mr. Trump that has left them confused about American objectives. Mr. Modi, who enjoyed a close bond with Mr. Trump during the U.S. president’s first term, has been left reeling from punishingly high tariffs and constant public jabs from Mr. Trump and his aides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s diplomats have struggled to find a working relationship with the new U.S. administration and negotiations over a bilateral trade deal that could bring New Delhi some relief have carried on without a resolution in sight. The tensions threaten to unravel two decades of painstaking diplomatic work across Democratic and Republican administrations to bring a skeptical India closer to the United States, in part as a counterweight to an aggressive China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an upbeat speech, his first since arriving in New Delhi, Mr. Gor said the trade negotiations were continuing and that the two sides were expected to have another meeting on Tuesday. He said India would be invited to join Pax Silica, a U.S. initiative to build supply chains for artificial intelligence and other advanced technology, and described the countries’ ties as “the most consequential global partnership of this century.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gor, 39, previously served as Mr. Trump’s head of presidential personnel appointments. Before that, he helped lead a publishing venture that produced Mr. Trump’s books. Mr. Trump has described him as a “great friend who has been at my side for many years” — a bond that Mr. Gor emphasized on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His closeness to Mr. Trump could help New Delhi troubleshoot the relationship at a time when it is struggling to get its message to the president’s inner circle. But Mr. Gor also comes with complications that have made Indian officials cautious: He has an additional role as a special envoy to South and Central Asia, which includes India’s rival Pakistan. In the minds of many in New Delhi, it couples the countries together when Indian officials had worked hard to shed such an association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was how Mr. Trump treated India and Pakistan as equals following a brief military conflict between the two countries last spring that amplified his disagreements with Mr. Modi. Mr. Trump announced that he had pressured the two sides into a cease-fire, an assertion he has repeated many times since. His declaration hurt Mr. Modi’s image as a strongman and cast doubt on the Indian leader’s role in driving the terms of the conflict and its resolution. As Indian officials worked to contain the damage, Mr. Trump grew sour with India for downplaying his role at time when he was campaigning for a Nobel Peace Prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the most severe damage of the downturn in relations has been economic. President Trump has singled out India for its purchases of Russian oil, slapping it with an additional 25 percent penalty tariff, doubling India’s overall tariff rate to 50 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India’s economic growth has withstood the impact of the tariffs better than some had feared, in part because the fees did not apply to two of India’s highest value goods — pharmaceuticals and electronics — or to the professional services that India-based back offices provide to U.S.-headquartered companies. But smaller industries reliant on exports to the U.S., such as textiles, jewelry, and carpets, have been feeling the pinch, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of the pressure, India began reducing its imports of Russian oil last year, to levels in December that Kpler, a company that tracks global trade, described as a three-year low. While Indian officials are seeking to remove the penalty tariff, the signs from Washington have been conflicting. Senator Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina, recently said Mr. Trump supported legislation that could slap 500 percent tariffs on countries that bought Russian oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For the Indian system, the egregious 25 percent tariff is the touchstone,” said Ashok Malik, the India chair at the Asia Group, a Washington-based advisory firm, and a former adviser to the Indian government. “If that goes, we can say that we are back in repair mode.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gor’s address, before a large group of members of the news media, veered from the convention that new envoys officially present their credentials to a country’s leader before such a public engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had handpicked a musical playlist, which included “The Phantom of the Opera” and the James Brown-Luciano Pavarotti duet “It’s a Man’s World.” Before Mr. Gor arrived, one U.S. official led a rehearsal of how attendees should welcome the envoy in front of the cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Act like Elvis just walked into the building,” the official told them. “We need some cheers!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alex Travelli contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/asia/india-us-ambassador-sergio-gor.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:56:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Investigates Elon Musk’s X Over Grok’s Sexualized A.I. Images</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/grok-ai-images-x-elon-musk-uk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12UK-GROK-kzvc/12UK-GROK-kzvc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;British authorities on Monday announced an investigation into X, the social media platform owned by Elon Musk, over the spread of artificially generated sexual images of women and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcom, the British regulator with oversight of online platforms, said it had started a formal inquiry to consider whether X had violated a law that aims to stop the spread in Britain of “priority” illegal content, including nonconsensual intimate images and child sexual abuse material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sexually explicit images generated by Grok, Mr. Musk’s artificial intelligence chatbot, have flooded X in recent weeks. In response to simple user prompts on X, the chatbot automatically created and publicly posted manipulated photos of real people, including children, in skimpy clothing and in sexually provocative situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many women who have been subjects of the Grok-generated sexualized images have reacted with horror and called on Mr. Musk to remove features that allow such activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcom said in a statement that “platforms must protect people in the U.K. from content that’s illegal in the U.K., and we won’t hesitate to investigate where we suspect companies are failing in their duties, especially where there’s a risk of harm to children.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regulator did not set a firm timeline for the investigation but said it was a matter of the “highest priority.” X could face fines up to 18 million pounds ($24 million), or 10 percent of its worldwide revenue, whichever is higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If X is found to have broken the law and refuses to comply with Ofcom’s requests for action, the regulator has the power, if necessary, to seek a court order that would prevent payment providers and advertisers from working with X. It could also, in cases where a court finds “significant harm” to individuals, require internet service providers to block access to the platform altogether inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ofcom said it had been in communication with xAI, the parent company that controls X and Grok, to understand the steps it is taking to protect users in Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, X reacted to the growing outrage over the images by announcing that only paying customers would be able to use Grok’s image-making tool. A spokesman for Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain said the change was “insulting” to victims of misogyny and sexual violence. It “simply turns an A.I. feature that allows the creation of unlawful images into a premium service,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Musk has claimed the controversy over the images is a pretext for governments to attack “free speech.” He recently posted an A.I.-generated image of British Prime Minister Keir Starmer in a bikini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why is the U.K. government so fascist?” Mr. Musk wrote on X on Jan. 10. He has also boasted that the controversy has led to more downloads of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Musk and X could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Musk’s social media platform has seen its business deteriorate in Britain. Last week, the company disclosed that annual revenue in 2024 fell 58 percent to 28.9 million pounds, while gross profit slumped to £1.1 million, from £13.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company attributed the slide to a drop in advertising sales because businesses have “concerns about brand safety, reputation and/or content moderation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, Indonesia and Malaysia became the first two countries to ban Grok, blocking access to the application in their countries. Authorities in the European Union, France, Brazil and elsewhere have also said they are reviewing X over the spread of sexual images of people without their consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing uproar risks creating wider geopolitical tension. President Trump and other administration officials have defended Mr. Musk against other attempts in Europe to regulate X, calling it an attack on free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/europe/grok-ai-images-x-elon-musk-uk.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 13:25:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia’s Fearsome Arsenal Fizzled in Venezuela. Here’s Why.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-russian-weapons-fail.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-venezuela-russia-tjqg/12int-venezuela-russia-tjqg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s advanced, Russian-made air defense systems were not even hooked up to radar when U.S. helicopters swooped in to snatch President Nicolás Maduro, American officials say, rendering Venezuelan airspace surprisingly unprotected long before the Pentagon launched its attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vaunted, Russian-made S-300 and Buk-M2 air defense systems were supposed to be a potent symbol of the close ties between Venezuela and Russia, two rivals of the United States. Their alliance appeared to give Russia a growing foothold in the Western Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With great fanfare, Venezuela announced it was buying the air defenses from Russia in 2009 amid tensions with Washington. Venezuela’s leftist president at the time, Hugo Chávez, heralded the weapons as a deterrent to American aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Venezuela was unable to maintain and operate the S-300 — one of the world’s most advanced antiaircraft systems — as well as the Buk defense systems, leaving its airspace vulnerable when the Pentagon launched Operation Absolute Resolve to capture Mr. Maduro, four current and former American officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, an analysis by The New York Times of photos, videos and satellite imagery found that some air defense components were still in storage, rather than operational, at the time of the attack. Taken together, the evidence suggests that, despite months of warnings, Venezuela was not ready for the American invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, the Venezuelan military’s incompetence appears to have played a big role in the U.S. success. Venezuela’s much-touted antiaircraft systems were essentially not connected when U.S. forces entered the skies over Venezuela’s capital, and they may not have been working for years, former officials and analysts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“After years of corruption, poor logistics and sanctions, all those things would have certainly degraded the readiness of Venezuela’s air defense systems,” said Richard de la Torre, a former C.I.A. station chief in Venezuela who now runs Tower Strategy, a Washington-based lobbying firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia shared in the failure, officials and experts said, because Russian trainers and technicians would have had to ensure the system was fully operational and help keep it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Russia’s own war demands in Ukraine may have limited its ability to sustain those systems in Venezuela, to make sure they were fully integrated,” Mr. de la Torre said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, two former American officials argued that Russia may have quietly allowed the military equipment it sold Venezuela to fall into disrepair, to avoid greater conflict with Washington. If the Venezuelan military had shot down an American aircraft, they said, the blowback on Russia could have been significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Chávez bought the air defense systems from Russia, they were part of a spending spree worth billions of dollars that was supposed to remake Venezuela’s military, filling its arsenal with Su-30 fighters jets, T-72 tanks and thousands of shoulder-launched surface-to-air missile systems known as Manpads. Before then, Venezuela had largely relied on U.S. military hardware, but as hostilities grew, Washington banned the sale of arms to the South American country in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With these rockets it’s going to be very difficult for foreign planes to come and bomb us,” Mr. Chávez said in 2009, after the deal to buy the Russian air defense systems was announced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Venezuela struggled to maintain the Russian equipment, often running out of spare parts and the technical know-how to service the military hardware or operate it, said the four current and former senior U.S. officials, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to share sensitive intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Seems those Russian air defenses didn’t quite work so well, did they?” The U.S. defense secretary, Pete Hegseth, said just days after the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ouster of Mr. Maduro and the Venezuelan government’s new, if uneasy, partnership with the United States is a blow to Russian influence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past 15 years, Moscow had steadily rebuilt its presence in Latin America after the collapse of the Soviet Union, increasing its arms sales to the region and forging new alliances, especially with Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that alliance may not have been as ironclad as Russia and Venezuela portrayed. Moscow had signaled to Washington that it would give the Americans unfettered influence in Venezuela in return for a free hand in Ukraine, according to Fiona Hill, who ran Russian and European affairs on the National Security Council during the first Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a news conference in November, the Russian foreign minister, Sergey V. Lavrov, was asked if Moscow would deploy more weapons to Venezuela to shore up its defenses in the way it has to neighboring Belarus, one of Russia’s closest allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lavrov made it clear that Venezuela, so far from Russian soil, was not as central to Russia. “It would be inaccurate to juxtapose our partnership with Venezuela with our union with the Republic of Belarus,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia and Venezuela signed a strategic partnership agreement in May, when Mr. Maduro visited Moscow, to expand ties, including defense cooperation. But it did not commit either country to collective defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think, coming out of this crisis, Russian prestige is going to be quite tarnished,” said Brian Naranjo, who was deputy chief of mission at the U.S. Embassy in Caracas from 2014 to 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They didn’t show up when Venezuela needed it,” he said. “They’ve been revealed to be a paper tiger.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Venezuelan military appeared to be taken by surprise by the U.S. operation, despite months of threats from Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An assessment by The Times of photos and videos posted to social media, along with satellite imagery, shows that the U.S. military primarily targeted locations where Venezuela had deployed or stored Buk air defense systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one location, storage units containing components of the Buk missile system were destroyed by U.S. aircraft before they were even deployed, indicating that the Venezuelan military was unprepared for the invasion that unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Locations of strikes based on analysis of photos, videos and satellite imagery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Leanne Abraham and Christiaan Triebert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In La Guaira, a coastal city that buffers Caracas, several videos posted online showed a large explosion at warehouses in the port. Days later, the local governor, José Alejandro Terán, posted a video on his Facebook page of him touring the damaged warehouses. He said they had been used to store medicine for kidney patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage also showed the burned-out remains of a Buk missile launcher, along with what appeared to be missile or missile debris scattered between two warehouses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few miles away, in Catia La Mar, loud explosions were also reported during the night of the attack. Mr. Terán later visited the site and posted videos from the area, as did other social media users. The footage showed bombed-out warehouses containing several components of a Buk system, including launchers and a command vehicle, suggesting the air defense vehicles had been in storage, instead of being operational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At La Carlota Air Base, videos recorded during the attack show explosions across the military airfield and smoke billowing into the air. Hours later, after daybreak, footage — including video broadcast by Venezuela’s state-run television network — showed the smoldering remains of a Buk missile launcher system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At another airport, in the coastal town of Higuerote, footage posted online captured a nighttime explosion as a separate fire burned nearby. Video from the aftermath showed a destroyed Buk missile launcher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Venezuelan armed forces were practically unprepared for the U.S. attack,” said Yaser Trujillo, a military analyst in Venezuela. “Their troops were not dispersed, the detection radar was not activated, deployed or operational. It was a chain of errors that allowed the United States to operate with ease, facing a very low threat from the Venezuelan air defense system.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s Manpads also failed to make much of an appearance to defend the country’s airspace against U.S. aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, Mr. Maduro boasted about Venezuela’s arsenal of SA-24 Manpads, claiming they had been deployed in key positions to defend the country, ready for a U.S. attack. Venezuela’s bulk purchase of Russian Manpads in 2017 had long concerned American officials, given their ability to shoot down aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any military force in the world knows the power of the Igla-S, and Venezuela has no less than 5,000,” Mr. Maduro said at the time, using another name for the SA-24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several videos, however, showed the same moment in which what appeared to be a Manpads was fired during the operation only to come under intense counterfire from U.S. aircraft. Two American officials familiar with the operation suggested that the heavy response from the U.S. military may have created a disincentive for other Venezuelan troops to fire their Manpads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long the fragile peace with the United States will hold remains to be seen. Washington is threatening to use its naval forces massed in the Caribbean if Caracas does not heed its demands, including opening up oil fields to U.S. companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State Marco Rubio is also pressuring the interim Venezuelan government to expel foreign advisers from Russia, Cuba, Iran and China, in a bid to assert Washington’s dominance over the country and the region more widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after Mr. Maduro’s capture, the State Department published a photo of a glowering President Trump with the caption “this is our hemisphere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“On many levels, what the Russians were trying to do was just to piss us off just by being in Venezuela,” said Mr. Naranjo, the former U.S. diplomat. “There’s a desire on Russia’s part to demonstrate that they still have strategic reach around the globe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, he said, Putin’s ability “to come into our backyard and annoy us doesn’t go to the point of actually confronting us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Sonne contributed reporting from Berlin. Video production by Jamie Leventhal and McKinnon de Kuyper.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/americas/venezuela-russian-weapons-fail.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 05:45:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Prepared for War but Ready to Negotiate, Foreign Minister Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/middleeast/iran-protests-trump-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12int-iran-protests-01-fgjp/12int-iran-protests-01-fgjp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian foreign minister said on Monday that the country was prepared for war but was also ready to negotiate, after President Trump hinted at possible U.S. military action to stop a deadly crackdown by Iran’s authorities against antigovernment protests in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not looking for war, but we are prepared for war — even more prepared than the previous war,” Abbas Araghchi, the foreign minister, told a conference of foreign ambassadors in Tehran, the capital, that was broadcast by state television. He appeared to be referring to the 12-day war with Israel this past June, which the United States joined to bomb Iran’s nuclear facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are also ready for negotiations, but negotiations that are fair, with equal rights and mutual respect,” Mr. Araghchi added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran also said on Monday that communication channels were open between Mr. Aragchi and Steve Witkoff, Mr. Trump’s envoy to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Iran has never left the negotiating table, but it will not engage in one-sided negotiations,” Esmail Baghaei, a spokesman for Iran’s foreign ministry, said at a news conference on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signaling from the Iranian authorities that they were open to diplomacy with the United States came after Mr. Trump hinted on Sunday that he might act militarily to curb the Iranian government’s repression of widespread demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran has been roiled in recent weeks by protests that were sparked by economic hardship but that have snowballed into a serious challenge to the rule of its authoritarian government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump was briefed in recent days on new options for military strikes in Iran but had not made a final decision, according to multiple U.S. officials familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are looking at it very seriously, the military is looking at it, and we’re looking at some very strong options,” Mr. Trump told reporters on Air Force One, without providing details. He added: “I’m getting an hourly report, and we’re going to make a determination.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump later said that “the leaders of Iran” had called him on Saturday and that they wanted to negotiate, although it was unclear to whom he was referring and what ground negotiations would cover. Talks on Iran’s nuclear program have stalled in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think they are tired of being beat up by the United States,” Mr. Trump said, adding that “a meeting is being set up, but we may have to act because of what’s happening.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, human rights groups monitoring the uprisings in Iran began reporting a sharp rise in the death toll as accounts of a violent repression broke through a communications blackout imposed by the Iranian authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Oslo-based Iran Human Rights group raised its toll for the protests to 192, while the Human Rights Activists News Agency, based in Washington, said it had confirmed the deaths of nearly 500 protesters and almost 50 security personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos published on Iranian social media channels Sunday and verified by The New York Times showed dozens of what appeared to be black body bags, lined up on the ground or on stretchers outside the Forensic Diagnostic and Laboratory Center in Kahrizak, a city on the outskirts of Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had repeatedly threatened lethal action against the Iranian government if it killed protesters. Asked on Sunday whether Iran’s leaders had crossed a red line, Mr. Trump replied: “It looks like it. There seems to be some people killed who weren’t supposed to be killed.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/world/middleeast/iran-protests-trump-us.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:44:53 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>