<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:57:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Lee Jun-seok Bolsters Jang Dong-hyeok, Says "No Reason to Doubt His Sincerity" (장동혁에 힘 실어준 이준석 “진정성 의심할 이유가 없다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/JGIJYS6SIJGULCZQIBNPAHC7BY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Jun-seok Bolsters Jang Dong-hyeok, Says "No Reason to Doubt His Sincerity" (장동혁에 힘 실어준 이준석 “진정성 의심할 이유가 없다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3GKNJUMFSTOYLEGY3WCMJQGQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said on the 20th, "Having completed my parliamentary diplomacy schedule, I am returning home and turning my attention back to domestic politics. Upon my return, I will visit People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok to discuss ways to further strengthen opposition cooperation." (개혁신당 이준석 대표가 20일 “의회 외교 일정을 마치고 귀국길에 올라 다시 국내 정치로 시선을 돌린다. 귀국하는 대로 국민의힘 장동혁 대표를 찾아 야권의 추가적인 공조 강화 방안을 논의하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally scheduled to return on the 23rd, Leader Lee is now set to return early on the 21st and visit the site of Leader Jang's hunger strike. Leader Lee's itinerary included stops in Mexico and Guatemala before visiting the US and returning, but it is reported he canceled the US leg. Leader Jang is continuing his hunger strike for the sixth day, demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of the Democratic Party of Korea's nomination slush funds and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians. However, it is reported that a joint hunger strike with Leader Jang, who declared an indefinite fast, is not currently under consideration. (당초 23일 귀국 예정이었던 이 대표는 21일 조기 귀국해 장 대표 당식장을 찾을 예정이다. 이 대표는 멕시코와 과테말라를 거쳐 미국을 들렀다 귀국하는 일정이었는데 미국 일정은 취소했다고 한다. 장 대표는 더불어민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 엿새째 단식을 이어가고 있다. 다만, 무기한 단식을 선언한 장 대표와의 공동 단식은 현재로선 검토하지 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Facebook that day, Leader Lee said, "These are heavy times. When someone resorts to extreme measures, it is to demonstrate their sincerity through physical hardship," adding, "There is no reason to doubt the sincerity of Leader Jang's push for the passage of the special prosecutor bill." (이 대표는 이날 페이스북에서 “무거운 시절이다. 누군가가 극단적인 수단에 의존할 때, 그것은 육신의 고달픔으로 자신의 진정성을 드러내 보이려는 것”이라며 “장 대표의 특검 통과를 향한 진정성에 어떤 의심을 할 이유가 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee stated, "Under the heavy political situation created by Leader Jang, all figures in the political world must ponder whether each and every word they utter is a step towards restoring order in the Republic of Korea," and "They should contemplate how to fight effectively, rather than making insensitive complaints to cover up their own faults." (이 대표는 “장 대표가 만든 무거운 정국 아래에서 정치권의 모든 인사는 자신의 말 한마디, 한마디가 대한민국의 질서를 바로 세우기 위한 한발짝인지 고민해야 할 것”이라며 “자신의 과오를 덮기 위한 눈치 없는 투정보다는 어떻게 효율적으로 투쟁할지를 고민해야 할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Leader Lee said, "The opposition must restore public trust with its clear-cut weapons," adding, "If it remains true to its fundamental role as the opposition, a path to prevent (the government and ruling party's) one-sided dominance will surely open." (그러면서 이 대표는 “야당은 야당의 선명한 무기로 국민께 신뢰를 회복해야 한다”며 “야당 본연에 충실하다면 (정부·여당의) 독주를 막을 길은 반드시 열릴 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/JGIJYS6SIJGULCZQIBNPAHC7BY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3GKNJUMFSTOYLEGY3WCMJQGQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 22:00:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party: "Shincheonji and Unification Church suspicions should be investigated in separate special probes" (국힘 “신천지·통일교 의혹, 별도 특검에서 각각 수사해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/Y5HNFSZG4NGEFG7KYGKXHZVNG4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party: "Shincheonji and Unification Church suspicions should be investigated in separate special probes" (국힘 “신천지·통일교 의혹, 별도 특검에서 각각 수사해야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KHGPCXQX5RLWVDIUFWBYEJBTL4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok reiterated his position on the 20th, calling for the launch of separate special probes: one into the 'suspicion of Shincheonji's interference in the People Power Party primary' and another into the 'suspicion of the Unification Church's lobbying of political circles'. (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 20일 ‘신천지의 국민의힘 경선 개입 의혹’ 특검과 ‘통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹’ 특검을 각각 출범시키자는 입장을 거듭 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea has consistently argued that a 'Unification Church and Shincheonji special probe' encompassing both suspicions should be launched in response to the People Power Party's demand for a Unification Church probe. Floor leader Song's argument is that these should be investigated separately in distinct special probes. (그간 더불어민주당은 국민의힘의 통일교 특검 도입 요구에 대해 신천지 의혹도 함께 포함시킨 ‘통일교·신천지 특검’을 출범해야 한다고 주장해 왔는데, 이를 별도 특검에서 각각 수사하자는 게 송 원내대표의 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters at the National Assembly this afternoon, Floor Leader Song stated, "The People Power Party proposed a bill for a special probe because there are issues regarding the receipt of money and valuables related to the Unification Church. However, the Democratic Party submitted a bill to investigate the Shincheonji suspicion together, attempting to dilute the focus (of the Unification Church probe bill)." (송 원내대표는 이날 오후 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “국민의힘은 통일교와 관련한 금품 수수 문제가 있어 특검을 하자는 법안을 발의했다. 그런데 민주당은 거기(통일교 특검 법안)에 물타기를 하려고 신천지 의혹을 함께 수사하자는 법안을 냈다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song clarified, "(Our party's existing position) was not to oppose a Shincheonji special probe," adding, "Even investigating just the suspicion of Unification Church money and valuables will be vast and complex." He continued, "Our party's proposal is for the Unification Church probe to focus on Unification Church suspicions, and for the Shincheonji probe to uncover substantive truth through an in-depth investigation via a separate special probe." (송 원내대표는 “(기존 당 입장은) 신천지 특검을 하지 말자는 것이 아니었다”며 “통일교 금품 수수 의혹에 대한 수사만 해도 방대하고 복잡할 것”이라고 했다. 그러면서 그는 “통일교 특검은 통일교 의혹에 집중하고, 신천지 특검은 별도 특검을 통해 깊이 있는 수사로 실체적 진실을 밝히자는 게 우리 당의 제안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song also said, "(The previous Min Jung-ki special probe, which investigated Unification Church suspicions) secured a statement last August about the provision of Unification Church money and valuables (through a person related to the Unification Church), but dragged its feet for over four months and then transferred the case to the police around December when the statute of limitations was nearly expired." He emphasized, "The part where the Min Jung-ki special probe concealed the statement for over four months must definitely be included and investigated in the Unification Church special probe." (송 원내대표는 “(앞서 통일교 의혹을 수사했던) 민중기 특검이 작년 8월 (통일교 관련자를 통해) 통일교 금품 제공 진술을 확보하고도 4개월 넘게 뭉개다가 공소시효가 다 돼가던 12월쯤 경찰에 이첩했다” “민중기 특검이 4개월 넘게 진술을 은폐한 부분은 꼭 통일교 특검에 포함해 수사해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Floor Leader Song added, "I once again strongly urge the Democratic Party to seriously view the life-threatening hunger strike by People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, now in its sixth day." Leader Jang is continuing his hunger strike for the sixth day, demanding 'twin special probes' to investigate suspicions of the Democratic Party's nomination-related political donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of political circles. (또 송 원내대표는 “민주당은 6일차로 계속되는 국민의힘 장동혁 대표의 목숨을 건 단식에 대해 심각하게 바라보기를 다시 한번 강력히 촉구한다”고도 했다. 장 대표는 민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 엿새째 단식을 이어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/Y5HNFSZG4NGEFG7KYGKXHZVNG4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KHGPCXQX5RLWVDIUFWBYEJBTL4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 22:42:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Good if fasting Jang Dong-hyeok dies" Controversy over former DP lawmaker Kim Hyung-joo's outrageous remarks… PPP says "mocking life" (“단식 장동혁 죽으면 좋고” 與 김형주 전 의원 막말 논란… 국힘 “생명 조롱”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/ADVQJIPYN5DEPHG2J4X7GAZ7YI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Good if fasting Jang Dong-hyeok dies" Controversy over former DP lawmaker Kim Hyung-joo's outrageous remarks… PPP says "mocking life" (“단식 장동혁 죽으면 좋고” 與 김형주 전 의원 막말 논란… 국힘 “생명 조롱”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5SF6V4UIVDPBILDQVCAAF2MOI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversy is brewing after former Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Hyung-joo made remarks such as "it would be good if he dies" targeting People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on his sixth day of fasting. (김형주 전 더불어민주당 의원이 엿새째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 향해 “죽으면 좋다” 등의 발언을 해 논란이 일고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to political circles on the 20th, the former lawmaker appeared on a YouTube channel the previous day and commented on PPP leader Jang's hunger strike, which demands the acceptance of the so-called 'dual special prosecutor' probes into the Unification Church and nomination donations. He said, "He picked a bad time to fast," and added, "He's pretending to be dead so people won't criticize him after he messed with Han Dong-hoon and then felt awkward. And he acts as if he's a martyr." (20일 정치권에 따르면, 전 의원은 전날 한 유튜브 채널에 출연해 장 대표가 통일교와 공천 헌금 등 이른바 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 단식 투쟁을 하고 있는 것과 관련, “나쁜 단식 타이밍을 잡았다”며 “자기가 한동훈 쳐놓고 난 다음에 머쓱하니까 자기에게 욕하지 말라고 죽은 척하는 거다. 그러면서 마치 자기가 순교자인 양한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding some arguments that former PPP leader Han Dong-hoon should visit the fasting site to encourage Leader Jang, he said, "It's still too early for former leader Han to go to the fasting site," and "Even if he goes, he still can't manage his facial expressions." (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 단식장을 방문해서 장 대표를 격려해야 한다는 일각의 주장에 대해서는 “한 전 대표가 단식장에 가는 것은 아직 때가 이르다”며 “가더라도 아직 표정 관리가 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Kim said, "(The place to meet an opponent experiencing conflict) is only for rotten politicians to go," and added, "They go and act as if they are truly reconciled, but Han Dong-hoon hasn't reached that stage yet." (김 전 의원은 “(갈등을 겪고 있는 상대를 만나는 자리는) 썩은 정치인들만이 갈 수 있다”며 “가서 마치 정말 화해된 것처럼 표현하는데 한동훈은 아직 그 단계까지 못 나갔다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then said, "Former leader Han doesn't need to go to the fasting site. Let him fast to the end, eat salt, get dehydrated, almost pass out, get taken to the hospital, and then (he should go)," and added, "It would be good if he dies. When he wakes up there, if someone says 'give him a hand,' then he can go at that time." (그러면서 “한 전 대표가 단식장에 갈 필요가 없고 끝까지 단식하게 해서 소금 먹고 물 빠져서 거의 기절초풍하고 병원에 실려 가고 난 다음에 (가야 한다)”라며 “죽으면 좋고. 거기서 깨어났을 때 손 좀 잡아주쇼 하면 그때 가면 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the host said, 'Leader Jang is still full of energy,' former lawmaker Kim said, "What is he supposed to talk about when he has nothing to say?" and added, "During this period, (former leader Han) could get criticized again for doing his own politics. 'I wish Jang Dong-hyeok would die. That's why I'm not going.' That's more honest." (진행자가 ‘아직은 장 대표가 팔팔하다’고 하자 김 전 의원은 “할 말도 없는데 가서 무슨 이야기를 하란 말이냐”며 “이 기간에 자기 정치한다고 (한 전 대표가) 또 욕먹을 수 있다. ‘나는 장동혁이 죽었으면 좋겠다. 그래서 난 안 간다’ 이게 더 솔직한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP spokesperson Lee Chung-hyeong said in a commentary that day, "The Democratic Party's political culture has already exceeded a dangerous level from the perspective of ordinary citizens' common sense," and added, "Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae has already mocked and disparaged Jang Dong-hyeok's fast as a 'fasting tantrum' and a 'fasting show.' Now, the Democratic Party's political culture, which even brings the word 'death' to its lips, is causing humanitarian issues beyond political stances." He said, "It is a mockery and challenge to life and humanity, beyond simple hatred for the opposition party." (이충형 국민의힘 대변인은 이날 논평을 통해 “민주당의 정치 문화는 이미 일반 국민의 양식으로 보기에 위험 수위를 넘어섰다”며 “정청래 민주당 대표가 이미 장동혁 대표의 단식에 대해 ‘단식 투정’ ‘단식 쇼’라고 조롱하고 폄훼한 바 있다. 이제는 죽음이라는 단어까지 입에 올리는 민주당의 정치 문화는 정치적 입장을 넘어 인도적인 문제까지 낳고 있다”고 했다. 그는 “야당에 대한 단순한 혐오를 넘어 생명과 인륜에 대한 조롱과 도전”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Lee said, "It is said that President Lee Jae-myung invited the Democratic Party leadership to the presidential office for a dinner and burst into laughter," and added, "Neither the President nor the Democratic Party has even made a single courtesy visit to the opposition leader's fasting site. Before politics, they should not lose the minimum dignity and basic human decency." (이 대변인은 “이재명 대통령은 민주당 지도부를 청와대로 초청해 만찬을 벌이며 폭소를 터뜨렸다고 한다”며 “대통령이나 민주당은 야당 대표의 단식 현장에 의례적인 위로 방문조차 한 번 하지 않고 있다. 정치 이전에, 최소한의 품격과 인간적인 금도는 잃지 말아야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/ADVQJIPYN5DEPHG2J4X7GAZ7YI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5SF6V4UIVDPBILDQVCAAF2MOI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 22:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's Gadeokdo Assault Incident Designated as Nation's First Officially Recognized Terrorist Act (李대통령 가덕도 피습 사건, 국가 공인 1호 테러로 지정)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/PMO2FZ375BHUVJ7UW5NX7HK5HE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee's Gadeokdo Assault Incident Designated as Nation's First Officially Recognized Terrorist Act (李대통령 가덕도 피습 사건, 국가 공인 1호 테러로 지정)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/AMHFHLRKOFHORO3I2ID7YHQYXA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, the government designated the assault incident targeting President Lee Jae-myung at the new Gadeokdo Airport in Busan as the nation's first officially recognized terrorist act. This is the first time a terrorist incident has been designated since the enactment of the Anti-Terrorism Act in 2016. (정부가 20일 이재명 대통령의 부산 가덕도 신공항 피습 사건을 국가 공인 1호 테러로 지정했다. 2016년 테러방지법이 제정된 이후 테러 사건이 지정된 것은 이 대통령 사례가 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government announced that it held the 22nd National Counter-Terrorism Committee meeting at the Government Complex Seoul, chaired by Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, in the afternoon of the same day, where it deliberated and decided on the Gadeokdo assault incident that occurred when President Lee was the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea. The National Counter-Terrorism Committee is the government's highest decision-making body for counter-terrorism responses, composed of the Prime Minister as its chair and 20 heads of related counter-terrorism agencies, based on Article 5 of the Anti-Terrorism Act. (정부는 이날 오후 정부서울청사에서 김민석 국무총리 주재로 제22차 국가테러대책위원회를 열고, 이 대통령이 더불어민주당 대표이던 시절 벌어진 가덕도 피습 사건을 심의‧의결했다고 밝혔다. 국가테러대책위는 테러방지법 제5조에 근거해 위원장인 국무총리와 대테러 관계기관장 20명으로 구성된 정부 내 테러 대응 최고 의사결정기구다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairing the meeting, Prime Minister Kim stated, "The Gadeokdo assault was something that should never have happened in the Republic of Korea, a country of K-democracy," adding, "I believe terrorism is something that must be eradicated by mobilizing all national vigilance." He continued, "To build a safe Republic of Korea, protected from various terrorist threats not only to its citizens but also to K-democracy, the government will comprehensively review and improve the overall counter-terrorism system." (김 총리는 이날 회의를 주재하며 “가덕도 피습은 K-민주주의의 나라, 대한민국에서는 있어서는 안 될 일이었다”며 “테러는 모든 국가적 경각심을 총동원해서 뿌리를 뽑아야 할 일이라고 생각한다”고 했다. 이어 “정부는 앞으로 국민뿐만 아니라 K-민주주의를 위협하는 각종 테러로부터 안전한 대한민국을 만들어나가기 위해서 대테러체계를 전반적으로 다시 살펴보고 보완해 나가겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim also said, "The previous investigation and inquiry were inadequate, and too much time has passed," adding, "Regarding this issue, we must approach it with the determination to completely eliminate the possibility of terrorism in the Republic of Korea going forward. I ask the public to deeply understand its significance." (김 총리는 또 “그간의 조사와 수사가 부실했고, 너무 시간이 오래 지났다”며 “이 문제에 대해서 앞으로 대한민국에서 테러의 가능성을 완전히 없앤다는 각오로 저희들이 임해야 한다. 국민 여러분께서 그 의미를 깊이 이해해 주시기를 부탁드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Prime Minister Kim had called for a thorough investigation into the Gadeokdo assault incident that occurred on January 2, 2024, requesting the reactivation of a joint counter-terrorism investigation team involving related agencies. The joint investigation by the National Intelligence Service, National Police Agency, National Fire Agency, military, and National Forensic Service confirmed that the perpetrator's actions met the constituent elements of 'terrorism under the Anti-Terrorism Act,' but noted that defining it as terrorism required consideration of opinions from related agencies and legal interpretations. (앞서 김 총리는 2024년 1월 2일 발생한 가덕도 피습 사건에 대한 철저한 진상 규명이 필요하다며 관계 기관이 참여하는 대테러합동조사팀 재가동을 요청했다. 국가정보원‧경찰청‧소방청‧군‧국립과학수사연구원 합동조사 결과, 범인의 행위는 ‘테러방지법 상 테러’의 구성 요건을 충족하고 있으나 이를 테러로 규정하기 위해서는 관계 기관 의견 및 법리적 해석을 고려할 필요가 있음을 확인했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on this, the government deliberated on whether to designate it as terrorism and ultimately decided to designate the incident as a terrorist act. This is the first government-level terrorist designation since the Anti-Terrorism Act was enacted in 2016. (정부는 이 내용을 토대로 테러 지정 여부를 심의했고, 이 사건의 테러 지정을 최종 의결했다. 이는 테러방지법이 제정된 2016년 이후 정부 차원의 최초 테러 지정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As follow-up measures, the government decided to conduct additional investigations into the incident, prepare measures to prevent the recurrence of similar incidents such as strengthening personal security for key figures during election periods, and comprehensively review and improve laws and systems, including the Anti-Terrorism Act. (정부는 후속 조치로서 사건에 대한 진상 규명을 추가적으로 실시하고, 선거 기간 주요 인사에 대한 신변 보호 강화 등 유사 사건 재발 방지 대책을 마련하면서 테러방지법을 비롯한 법‧제도 전반을 종합적으로 점검하고 정비하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/PMO2FZ375BHUVJ7UW5NX7HK5HE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/AMHFHLRKOFHORO3I2ID7YHQYXA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 23:36:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Has Jeong Cheong-rae Avoided Mentioning Lee Hye-hoon for Two Weeks? (정청래는 왜 2주간 이혜훈 언급을 안했을까)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/QFSUDMQ2M5HGLLHQ5Q2S54B5O4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Why Has Jeong Cheong-rae Avoided Mentioning Lee Hye-hoon for Two Weeks? (정청래는 왜 2주간 이혜훈 언급을 안했을까)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/J2KGTJ3OF5PRTA5YQZY5TEK2F4.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon has effectively collapsed, Jeong Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, is extremely avoiding any mention of it. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 청문회가 사실상 무산됐지만, 정청래 더불어민주당 대표는 이에 대한 언급을 극도로 피하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the request for consent to appoint the nominee was submitted to the National Assembly earlier this month, the last time Representative Jeong mentioned the nominee was during an appearance on Kim Eo-jun's YouTube broadcast on the 6th. At the time, Representative Jeong said, "If I were the nominee, I would thoroughly reflect on and apologize for my wrong words and actions, and appeal that I will align well with President Lee Jae-myung's governance philosophy." (이 후보자의 임명 동의 요구서가 이달 초 국회로 넘어온 뒤, 정 대표가 이 후보자에 대해 언급한 것은 지난 6일 김어준씨의 유튜브 방송에 출연해 말한 것이 마지막이다. 당시 정 대표는 “제가 이 후보자라면 잘못한 말과 행동에 대해 반성과 사과를 철저히 하고, 이재명 대통령의 국정 철학을 잘 맞추겠다고 어필할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked by the host at the time, 'There are people within the Democratic Party's support base who find it difficult to accept this nominee,' he also replied, "That seems to be true." (당시 ‘이 후보자의 지명을 민주당 지지층에서 받아들이기 어려워하는 분들이 있다’는 진행자의 물음에는 “사실인 것 같다”라고 하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Personnel Hearing Act, the National Assembly must submit a report on the consent to appoint the nominee by the 21st. However, with the possibility of the ruling and opposition parties holding a hearing before that being slim, the nominee's hearing has effectively collapsed. After this date, President Lee can resubmit the request for consent to appoint the nominee, setting a new 10-day deadline. (인사청문회법에 따라 국회는 21일까지 이 후보자에 대한 임명 동의 보고서를 제출해야 한다. 그러나 그 전까지 여야가 청문회를 열 가능성이 희박해 사실상 이 후보자의 청문회는 무산된 상황이다. 이날이 지나면 이 대통령은 이 후보자에 대한 임명 동의 요구서를 10일 내 기한을 정해 재요청할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite this situation, there are various political and strategic reasons why Representative Jeong cannot even publicly mention the nominee. (이 같은 상황인데도 정 대표가 이 후보자를 공개적으로 거론조차 못 하는 데에는 여러 정치적·전략적 이유가 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the dinner between the President and the party leadership on the 19th appeared to patch up factional conflicts, potential conflicts still exist within the party. From Representative Jeong's perspective, he may be refraining from making statements that could escalate the situation. A ruling party official said, "The joke President Lee made to Representative Jeong at yesterday's dinner, 'Are you anti-pro-administration?', likely wasn't just a simple remark. Not all attendees are pro-administration, right?" (전날 19일 대통령과 당 지도부 만찬으로 계파 갈등이 봉합되는 양상을 보였지만, 여전히 당내에는 잠재적 갈등이 존재한다. 정 대표 입장에서는 사태를 키우는 발언을 자제하려는 것일 수 있다. 한 여권 관계자는 “전날 만찬에서 이 대통령이 정 대표에게 했던 ‘반청이냐’ 농담이 단순한 뜻일 것 같진 않다. 참석자 모두가 친청은 아니지 않느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is also possible that Representative Jeong considered that the nomination of the former People Power Party member is difficult for the Democratic Party's core supporters to accept. Earlier this month, Representative Jeong himself acknowledged on Kim Eo-jun's broadcast that the nomination of former People Power Party member Lee Hye-hoon is an aspect that the Democratic Party's core supporters find hard to accept. As party leader, it is burdensome to actively defend the nominee, yet he cannot oppose the nomination either. (또 국민의힘 출신 이 후보자 지명이 민주당 핵심 지지층이 받아들이기 어려워한다는 점을 정 대표가 고려했을 가능성도 있다. 이달 초 정 대표 스스로도 김어준씨 방송에서 국민의힘 출신 이혜훈 지명은 민주당 핵심 지지층이 받아들이기 어려워하는 부분이 있다고 인정한 바 있다. 당 대표가 나서서 적극 옹호하기도 부담스럽고, 반대할 수도 없는 상황인 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party leadership has decided to refrain from publicly criticizing the nominee and instead wait to see the verification process during the hearing. Yesterday, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun also met with reporters after the Supreme Council meeting and said, "(The hearing) is an agreement and promise between the ruling and opposition parties," adding, "Even if there are many suspicions, we should not unilaterally cancel the National Assembly schedule that was agreed upon by the ruling and opposition parties and promised to the people." (당 지도부는 당 지도부는 후보자에 대한 공개 비판을 삼가고 대신 청문회 과정에서 검증을 지켜보자는 방침이다. 전날 박수현 수석대변인도 이날 최고위 이후 기자들과 만나 “(청문회는) 여야의 합의 사항이고 약속”이라며 “의혹이 많다고 해서 여야 간 합의하고 국민께 약속한 국회 일정을 일방적으로 파기해서는 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/QFSUDMQ2M5HGLLHQ5Q2S54B5O4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/J2KGTJ3OF5PRTA5YQZY5TEK2F4.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:06:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok's Sixth Day of Hunger Strike Spurs Conservative Consolidation... Yoo Seung-min and Lee Jun-seok Say "Conservative Reconstruction and Unification Are Necessary" (장동혁 엿새째 단식에 보수 결집… 유승민·이준석 “보수 재건, 통합해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/4K5G2FPB2VC73IVENNMVE6DY3M/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok's Sixth Day of Hunger Strike Spurs Conservative Consolidation... Yoo Seung-min and Lee Jun-seok Say "Conservative Reconstruction and Unification Are Necessary" (장동혁 엿새째 단식에 보수 결집… 유승민·이준석 “보수 재건, 통합해야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5JGXEFU4DBDTVA6FCDLUFA5MDQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok continues his hunger strike for the sixth day on the 20th, demanding the acceptance of a special prosecution investigation (into the Unification Church and Democratic Party nomination bribes), former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min made a surprise visit to Leader Jang. Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party who is currently visiting Latin America, also lent his support to Leader Jang's hunger strike on the same day, stating, "There is no reason to doubt the sincerity of Leader Jang Dong-hyeok." Analysis suggests that conservative consolidation is occurring around Leader Jang's hunger strike. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 20일 쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검) 수용을 요구하며 6일째 단식 투쟁을 이어가는 가운데 유승민 전 의원이 장 대표를 전격 방문했다. 중남미를 방문 중인 이준석 개혁신당 대표도 이날 “장동혁 대표의 진정성에 어떤 의심을 할 이유가 없다”며 장 대표의 단식에 힘을 실었다. 장 대표 단식을 계기로 보수 결집이 이뤄지고 있다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Yoo visited the hunger strike site set up in the central hall of the National Assembly's main building this morning. Leader Jang, whose condition had rapidly deteriorated since the previous day and was resting in a tent, sat inside the tent to receive Former lawmaker Yoo. The meeting between Leader Jang and Former lawmaker Yoo is known to be their first since the 2020 general election. (유 전 의원은 이날 오전 국회 본청 중앙홀에 마련된 장 대표 단식장을 찾았다. 전날부터 상태가 급격히 악화돼 텐트에서 쉬던 장 대표는 텐트 안에 앉아 유 전 의원을 맞았다. 장 대표와 유 전 의원의 만남은 지난 2020년 총선 이후 처음으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Yoo told reporters, "I came with the thought that when the party is in crisis, everyone should unite to find a path for conservative reconstruction." He added, "The most sincere thing the party should do now is to regain the public's trust and support and rebuild conservatism," and said, "Even if we have different thoughts on some issues, we must put our heads together to find solutions on how to be reborn as a conservatism that the public can trust." This is interpreted as expressing concern over the party's internal conflict reaching an extreme following the Central Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon. (유 전 의원은 취재진에 “당이 위기에 있을 때 전부 다 하나가 돼서 보수 재건의 길을 찾았으면 좋겠다는 생각으로 왔다”고 했다. 그는 “지금 당이 가장 성실하게 해야 할 일은 국민의 신뢰와 지지를 받아 보수를 재건하는 것”이라며 “일부 문제에 있어서 서로 생각이 다르더라도 어떻게 국민이 신뢰할 수 있는 보수로 거듭날 수 있을지 머리를 맞대고 해결책을 찾아야 한다”고 했다. 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 중앙윤리위원회의 제명 결정 이후 당내 갈등이 극단으로 치닫고 있는 데 대해 우려를 전한 것으로 풀이됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Jun-seok, who moved up his overseas business trip schedule by two days and is returning in the early hours of the 21st, also posted on Facebook today, stating, "Separately, yet together. If we remain faithful to the opposition's original role, a path to prevent a one-party dominance will surely open," and said, "Upon returning, I will visit Leader Jang Dong-hyeok to discuss ways to strengthen further cooperation among opposition parties." This is support for Leader Jang's proxy struggle. (해외 출장 일정을 이틀 앞당겨 21일 새벽 귀국하는 이준석 대표도 이날 페이스북에 글을 올리고 “따로, 또 같이. 야당 본연에 충실하다면 독주를 막을 길은 반드시 열릴 것”이라며 “귀국하는 대로 장동혁 대표를 찾아 야권의 추가적인 공조 강화 방안을 논의하겠다”고 했다. 장 대표의 대여 투쟁에 힘을 실은 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the party's young lawmakers' study group 'Alternative and Future,' who had previously taken a different stance from Leader Jang, visited his hunger strike site today and expressed their support. They had previously criticized Leader Jang's announcement of a reform plan on the 7th, which omitted a break with former President Yoon Suk-yeol, saying, "The party needs reconstruction-level reform, not just interior remodeling." Lawmaker Lee Seong-kwon said, "We actively support Leader Jang's hunger strike fighting against the reckless state administration of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party," and added, "What the People Power Party needs now is party unity." (장 대표와 일부 각을 세웠던 당내 소장파 공부 모임 ‘대안과 미래’ 소속 의원들은 이날 장 대표 단식장을 찾아 지지 결의를 밝혔다. 이들은 지난 7일 장 대표가 윤석열 전 대통령과의 절연이 빠진 쇄신안을 발표한 것을 두고 “인테리어 공사가 아니라 재건축 수준으로 당을 쇄신해야 한다”고 비판했었다. 이성권 의원은 “이재명 정권과 더불어민주당의 무도한 국정 운영에 맞서 싸우는 장 대표의 단식을 적극적으로 지지한다”며 “지금 국민의힘에 필요한 건 당의 통합”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, it has been reported that there have been no visits to Leader Jang's hunger strike site from the Blue House or the Democratic Party yet. Floor Leader Song Eon-seok said today to newly appointed Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo, "Your first action after taking office should be to visit the hunger strike site of People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok," and urged, "I hope you seriously recognize the life-risking hunger strike struggle of the main opposition party leader." Although there were reports today that Senior Secretary Hong would visit Leader Jang's site, the Blue House stated, "No schedule has been confirmed yet."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (한편 청와대와 더불어민주당에서 장 대표 단식장 방문은 아직까진 없는 것으로 전해졌다. 송언석 원내대표는 이날 홍익표 신임 정무수석을 향해 “취임 후 첫 행보는 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식 농성장 방문이어야 할 것”이라며 “제1 야당 당대표의 목숨 건 단식 투쟁을 심각하게 인식하길 바란다”고 했다. 이날 홍 수석이 장 대표의 단식장을 찾는다는 보도도 나왔지만 청와대는 “아직 협의된 일정은 없다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/4K5G2FPB2VC73IVENNMVE6DY3M/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5JGXEFU4DBDTVA6FCDLUFA5MDQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 23:17:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un: "Like hitching a goat to a cart"... Public dismissal of Vice Premier (김정은 “염소가 달구지 끈 격”… 부총리 공개 해임)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/21/EFDO37HWUVFBJJVINU7PIXVXJQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jong Un: "Like hitching a goat to a cart"... Public dismissal of Vice Premier (김정은 “염소가 달구지 끈 격”… 부총리 공개 해임)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JC3PRIG2CFPFHOQKQBODQIJAMU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong Un visited a period equipment factory, criticized the confusion in the remodeling process, and publicly dismissed Vice Premier Yang Seung-ho, who was in charge of the project, on the spot. In a speech published in the Rodong Sinmun spanning seven A4 pages, Kim criticized Vice Premier Yang as "an inappropriate person to entrust with a heavy responsibility" and "like hitching a goat to a cart." He then said, "Does an ox pull a cart or does a goat pull a cart?" and announced, "At this very place today, I dismiss Comrade Vice Premier." Analysis suggests this is a move to tighten discipline ahead of the 9th Party Congress. (김정은 북한 국무위원장이 기간 설비 공장을 방문해 리모델링 과정의 혼선을 질책하며, 사업을 담당했던 양승호 기계공업 담당 부총리를 현장에서 공개 해임했다. 김정은은 노동신문에 A4 용지 7장 분량으로 실린 연설을 통해 양 부총리를 “중임을 맡기기에는 부적절한 사람” “염소에게 달구지를 매어 놓았던 것과 같은 격”이라고 비판했다. 이어 “황소가 달구지를 끌지 염소가 달구지를 끄나”라며 “오늘 이 자리에서 부총리 동무를 해임시킨다”고 했다. 9차 당 대회를 앞두고 ‘기강 잡기’에 나섰다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rodong Sinmun reported on the 20th that Kim Jong Un attended the completion ceremony for the first phase of the modernization reconstruction project at the 'Ryongsong Machine Complex' in Hamhung, South Hamgyong Province the previous day. Kim referred to this factory, which produces large machinery and equipment needed for the metal, power, cement, chemical, and electronics industries, as the "mother enterprise of the country's machine industry." He criticized Cabinet officials, saying, "Due to rough and incompetent leading workers, (during the remodeling) they suffered artificial confusion they shouldn't have had to endure and also caused considerable economic losses." (노동신문은 20일 김정은이 전날 함경남도 함흥의 ‘룡성기계연합기업소’ 1단계 개건(改建) 현대화 대상 준공식에 참석했다고 보도했다. 김정은은 금속·전력·시멘트·화학·전자 산업 등에 필요한 대형 기계와 설비를 제작하는 이 공장을 “나라 기계공업의 모체 기업소”라고 부르며 “거칠고 무능한 지도 일꾼들 때문에 (리모델링 때) 겪지 않아도 될 인위적 혼란을 겪고 경제적 손실도 적지 않게 초래했다”고 내각 간부들을 질책했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un said, "We even showed them advanced production facilities from other countries to open their eyes to modernization," but added, "Nevertheless, (Kim Tok-hun) the then Premier of the Cabinet and the Vice Premier in charge of the machine industry did their work haphazardly." Former Premier Kim was replaced by current Premier Pak Tae-song in December 2024 and is now serving as the Party's economic secretary. (김정은은 “현대화에 대한 안목을 틔울 수 있게 다른 나라의 선진적인 생산 시설도 보여줬다”며 “그랬지만 (김덕훈) 당시 내각 총리와 기계공업 담당 부총리는 일을 되는 대로 해먹었다”고 했다. 김 전 총리는 2024년 12월 박태성 현 총리로 교체된 후, 당 경제 비서를 맡고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un denounced them as "people who are as good as absent even when present, and whose absence wouldn't leave a void" and "people who are nothing but their current sorry state." He told (Vice Premier Yang), "Comrade Vice Premier, leave on your own two feet while you still can, before it's too late." He also instructed, "When forming the new government, appoint someone else (instead of Vice Premier Yang)." Kim Jong Un further told incumbent officials, "We must eradicate irresponsibility, self-preservationism, and hooliganism." (김정은은 이들을 “있어도 없는 것과 같고 없어도 빈자리가 나지 않을 사람들” “그 모양 그 꼴 밖에 안 되는 사람”이라고 비난하며 “(양) 부총리 동무는 제 발로 나갈 수 있을 때, 더 늦기 전에 제 발로 나가라”고 했다. “(양 부총리 대신) 새 정부 구성 때 다른 사람을 등용할 것“도 지시했다. 김정은은 또 현직 간부들을 향해 “무책임성, 보신주의와 건달풍을 적출해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Yang Moo-jin of the University of North Korean Studies said, "Similar to the past case of (his uncle by marriage) Jang Song-thaek (who was executed), this is a shock therapy of holding someone publicly accountable to warn Party officials." He added, "By making Vice Premier Yang and others examples of incompetence, he is signaling personnel renewal and the formation of a new cabinet ahead of the 9th Party Congress." (양무진 북한대학원대학교 석좌교수는 “과거 (고모부) 장성택(을 처형한) 사례와 유사하게 공개 석상에서 책임을 묻는 충격 요법으로 당 간부들에게 경고한 것”이라며 “양 부총리 등을 무능의 본보기로 삼으면서 9차 당 대회를 앞두고 인적 쇄신과 새 내각 구성을 예고한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/21/EFDO37HWUVFBJJVINU7PIXVXJQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JC3PRIG2CFPFHOQKQBODQIJAMU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:47:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Eon-seok: "Alongside the Unification Church special counsel, let's also have a Shincheonji special counsel" (송언석 “통일교 특검과 별도로 신천지 특검 하자”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/A5H4VB2G5RGLXNKTXZXW5JITPE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Song Eon-seok: "Alongside the Unification Church special counsel, let's also have a Shincheonji special counsel" (송언석 “통일교 특검과 별도로 신천지 특검 하자”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CN3C6ZREJJDCDHOGQIIKOA4W4U.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party (PPP) leader Jang Dong-hyeok continues his hunger strike for the sixth day on the 20th, demanding the acceptance of a dual special counsel investigation (into the Unification Church and the Democratic Party of Korea's nomination bribery allegations), the PPP has once again proposed to the Democratic Party that separate special counsel investigations be launched for the Unification Church and for Shincheonji. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 20일 쌍특검(통일교·더불어민주당 공천 뇌물 특검) 수용을 요구하며 6일째 단식을 하는 가운데, 국민의힘이 통일교 특검과 신천지 특검을 각각 가동하자고 민주당에 재차 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP floor leader Song Eon-seok met with reporters at the National Assembly and said, "Let's also have a Shincheonji special counsel," adding, "Our party's proposal is to focus the Unification Church investigation on the Unification Church, and to clearly reveal the substantive truth about Shincheonji to the public through a separate special counsel investigation." (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “신천지 특검도 하자”며 “통일교 특검은 통일교 특검에 집중하고 신천지 특검은 별도 특검을 통해 실체적 진실을 국민 앞에 명명백백하게 밝히자는 게 우리 당의 제안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that day, Democratic Party floor leader Han Byung-do mentioned in a party meeting media reports raising suspicions that Shincheonji followers systematically joined the PPP, stating, "If the PPP has nothing to hide, they should immediately accept a special counsel investigation covering both the Unification Church and Shincheonji." (앞서 민주당 한병도 원내대표는 이날 오전 당 회의에서 신천지 신도들이 국민의힘에 조직적으로 입당했다는 의혹 보도를 언급하며 “국민의힘은 떳떳하다면 지금 당장 통일교·신천지 특검을 수용하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP and the Reform Party have been demanding a special counsel investigation into the Unification Church, claiming that the special counsel team led by Lee Jong-seob, which investigated suspicions related to First Lady Kim Keon-hee, obtained statements that "the Unification Church also gave money and valuables to Democratic Party figures including lawmaker Jeon Jae-soo" but did not investigate them. However, the Democratic Party has opposed including suspicions related to the Lee Jong-seob special counsel investigation as targets, calling it "politically motivated," and instead has advocated for a special counsel investigation covering both the Unification Church and Shincheonji, which would also investigate suspicions of Shincheonji's involvement in PPP events like its national convention. A PPP official said, "The Democratic Party is waging a public opinion campaign suggesting 'the special counsel is being blocked because of the PPP,' so we are clearly stating our position that we should also have a Shincheonji investigation." (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 김건희 여사 관련 의혹을 수사했던 민중기 특별검사팀이 “통일교가 전재수 의원 등 민주당 인사에게도 금품을 줬다”는 진술을 확보하고도 수사하지 않았다고 주장하며 통일교 특검을 요구해왔다. 하지만 민주당은 민중기 특검 관련 의혹을 수사 대상에 넣는 것은 “정치적 의도가 있는 것”이라고 반대하고 대신 신천지가 국민의힘 전당대회 등에 개입한 의혹까지 수사하는 통일교·신천지 특검을 주장해왔다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “민주당이 ‘국민의힘 때문에 특검을 못하고 있다’는 식의 여론전을 펴고 있어서 신천지 특검도 하자는 입장을 분명히 밝힌 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although PPP leader Jang Dong-hyeok's hunger strike, demanding the acceptance of a special counsel investigation into the Unification Church and Democratic Party nomination bribery allegations, entered its sixth day, neither the presidential office nor the Democratic Party had sent anyone to the hunger strike site as of that day. In contrast, during the 2019 hunger strike by Hwang Kyo-ahn, then-leader of the Liberty Korea Party, the presidential office's Senior Secretary for Political Affairs visited the site. (통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검 수용을 주장하는 장동혁 대표의 단식이 6일째 이어지고 있지만 이날까지도 청와대나 민주당은 단식장에 사람을 보내지 않았다. 2019년 황교안 자유한국당 대표 단식 때는 청와대 정무수석이 단식장을 찾았었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the hunger strike prolongs, opinions within the PPP are emerging that an exit strategy is needed. It is known that some PPP lawmakers serving their second term met with Floor Leader Song that day and proposed "accepting the Unification Church and Shincheonji special counsel investigation as advocated by the Democratic Party." Within the party, there is also an opinion that even a single, unified special counsel investigation would be acceptable if it explicitly includes the suspicions related to the Lee Jong-seob special counsel investigation as targets and if the condition is met that the Democratic Party does not unilaterally recommend the special counsel. (단식이 길어지면서 국민의힘 내에서도 출구전략이 필요하다는 의견도 나온다. 국민의힘 일부 재선 의원들은 이날 송 원내대표와 만나 “민주당이 주장하는 통일교·신천지 특검을 수용하자”고 제안한 것으로 알려졌다. 당내에서도 민중기 특검 의혹을 수사 대상에 명시하고, 특검을 민주당이 일방적으로 추천하지 않는 조건이 받아들여진다면 단일 특검이어도 문제 없다는 의견도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/A5H4VB2G5RGLXNKTXZXW5JITPE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CN3C6ZREJJDCDHOGQIIKOA4W4U.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Investigative Judicial Officer, Practical" "Will Become a Second Prosecution Service" (“수사사법관, 실용적” “제2의 검찰청 될 것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/21/MFG5LDTBTRG2PBFXN4ROILZZEA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Investigative Judicial Officer, Practical" "Will Become a Second Prosecution Service" (“수사사법관, 실용적” “제2의 검찰청 될 것”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/4HMSMGDZ2JL35JKOME442SOO5A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea held a public hearing on the 20th regarding the government's bill to establish the Serious Crimes Investigation Office (SCO) and the Public Prosecution Service. This event was arranged after hardliners within the party opposed the government proposal announced on the 12th, prompting President Lee Jae-myung to instruct for opinions to be gathered. Opinions clashed over key issues: the dual-track investigation system within the SCO and the retention of supplementary investigation authority for the Public Prosecution Service. (더불어민주당이 20일 정부의 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청 설치 법안에 대한 공청회를 열었다. 지난 12일 발표된 정부안에 대해 당내 강경파가 반발하자 이재명 대통령이 의견 수렴을 지시하면서 마련된 행사다. 핵심 쟁점인 중수청 이원화, 공소청의 보완수사권 유지 문제를 놓고 찬반이 맞섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, experts engaged in a pro-and-con debate over the issue of having both 'investigative judicial officers' (legal professionals) and 'professional investigators' (non-legal professionals) within the SCO. Professor Choi Ho-jin of Dankook University's Department of Law, who supports the government proposal, stated it is "a practical method to secure legal expertise and field investigation know-how." He added, "The government bill establishes them not in a hierarchical relationship but as a functional cooperative relationship, and their authority is equal." (우선 전문가들은 중수청 내에 법률가인 ‘수사사법관’과 비법률가인 ‘전문수사관’을 두는 문제를 놓고 찬반 토론을 벌였다. 정부안 찬성 측인 최호진 단국대 법학과 교수는 “법률 전문성과 현장 수사 노하우를 확보하기 위한 실용적 방법”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “정부 법안에서 상하 관계가 아닌 기능적인 협력 관계로 설정해 놨고, 권한도 대등하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Professor Hwang Moon-gyu of Joongbu University's Police Administration Department argued, "They are both investigators, so why should one be an investigative judicial officer and the other a professional investigator?" He claimed, "There is a risk that veteran investigators could end up taking orders from someone who just graduated from law school." He further stated, "The investigative judicial officer will become the medium that effectively turns the SCO into a second prosecution service." (반면 황문규 중부대 경찰행정학 교수는 “같은 수사관인데 누구는 수사사법관, 누구는 전문수사관, 왜 이렇게 해야 하느냐”며 “자칫하면 베테랑 수사관이 로스쿨 갓 졸업한 사람의 지휘를 받게 된다”고 주장했다. 그러면서 “수사사법관은 중수청을 사실상 제2의 검찰청으로 만드는 매개체가 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the issue of granting supplementary investigation authority to the Public Prosecution Service, Professor Choi Ho-jin advocated for caution, stating it is "a matter to be addressed in the Criminal Procedure Act." Professor Choi said, "Supplementary investigation authority should be regulated within the Criminal Procedure Act, not in the organizational law of a specific agency, to prevent the legal system from becoming tangled." Lawyer Shin In-gyu also said, "If 'Gyeomsuwonbak' (complete deprivation of prosecution's investigation rights) is interpreted differently, it could mean the police's complete monopoly on investigation rights," adding, "We must guard against it leading to extreme arguments." (공소청에 보완수사권을 두는 문제에 대해 최호진 교수는 “형사소송법에서 다룰 문제”라며 신중론을 펼쳤다. 최 교수는 “보완수사권은 특정 기관의 조직법이 아니라 형사소송법 내에서 규율해야 법 체계가 헝클어지지 않는다”고 했다. 신인규 변호사도 “검수완박(검찰 수사권 완전 박탈)을 달리 쓰면 경찰 수사권 완전 독점”이라며 “극단론으로 흐르는 것은 경계해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Professor Hwang argued, "The prosecution's investigation authority could become broader than it is now." Lawyer Kim Pil-seong said, "There is still no discussion on how to substantially control the prosecution's authority," and questioned, "If supplementary investigation authority is retained, can the principle of separating investigation and prosecution be irreversibly implemented?" (반면 황 교수는 “검찰 수사권이 지금보다 넓어지게 될 수 있다”고 했다. 김필성 변호사는 “검찰의 권한을 어떻게 실질적으로 통제할 것인가에 대한 논의는 여전히 없다”며 “(보완수사권을 존치한다면) 수사·기소 분리 원칙이 비가역적으로 관철될 수 있겠는가”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding criticism that the scope of investigation (9 major crimes) defined by the government proposal for the SCO is excessively broad, supporters argued, "The actual targets of investigation will be determined by presidential decree, and it will operate focusing on corruption," while opponents argued, "The scope of investigation targets should be minimized." (정부안이 규정한 중수청 수사 범위(9대 범죄)가 지나치게 넓다는 지적에 대해선 찬성 측은 “실제 수사 대상은 대통령령으로 정해질 것이고, 부패 중심으로 운영될 것”이라고 했고, 반대 측은 “수사 대상을 최소한으로 정리해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three-tier structure of the Public Prosecution Service ('Supreme, High, and District Public Prosecution Service') was also a point of contention at the hearing. Professor Choi Ho-jin said, "An institution is needed to handle functions like appeals and re-appeals, which are currently handled by the High Prosecutors' Office." In response, Professor Hwang Moon-gyu said, "There have been criticisms that within the existing prosecution service, the High Prosecutors' Office is practically idle," and argued, "A two-tier structure (excluding the High Public Prosecution Service) is sufficient." (이날 공청회에선 ‘대·고등·지방공소청’의 공소청 3단 구조도 쟁점이었다. 최호진 교수는 “고등검찰청이 담당하는 항고·재항고 등 기능을 담당할 기관이 필요하다”고 했다. 그러자 황문규 교수는 “기존 검찰청에서 고검은 사실상 놀고먹는 곳이나 다름없다는 지적이 있었다”며 “(고등공소청을 뺀) 2단계 구조로 족하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party leadership and officials including Yoon Chang-ryul, head of the Office for Government Policy Coordination who leads the Prosecution Reform Promotion Team under the Prime Minister's Office, attended the hearing. The Democratic Party decided to hold a general meeting of lawmakers on the 22nd to gather more opinions from members. Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae concluded the hearing by saying, "It seems there is some problem with the dual-track investigation system in the SCO, and it appears both sides reached a consensus that using the title 'investigative judicial officer' could be misleading." (이날 행사엔 민주당 지도부, 국무총리실 검찰개혁추진단장인 윤창렬 국무조정실장 등이 배석했다. 민주당은 오는 22일 의원총회를 열어 의원 의견을 더 수렴하기로 했다. 민주당 정청래 대표는 공청회를 마치며 “중수청의 수사 이원화는 좀 문제가 있는 것 같고, 수사사법관 명칭을 사용한다는 것은 오해의 소지가 있다는 부분은 양측에서 공감대를 이룬 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/21/MFG5LDTBTRG2PBFXN4ROILZZEA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/4HMSMGDZ2JL35JKOME442SOO5A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's Card Unplayable... President Likely to Request National Assembly Resume Hearing (이혜훈 카드 못 놓는 李… 국회에 청문회 재개 요청할 듯)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/LCDTSF4MM5CKTHPOJADZP6UIDM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon's Card Unplayable... President Likely to Request National Assembly Resume Hearing (이혜훈 카드 못 놓는 李… 국회에 청문회 재개 요청할 듯)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MQ2TINTGMZSDAZBYG5TDOMBWG4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon failed to convene for the second consecutive day on the 20th, following the 19th, due to a breakdown in negotiations between the ruling and opposition parties. If the hearing is not held by the 21st, the legal deadline for adopting the hearing report, the President must decide whether to request the National Assembly to resubmit the report. Given that the presidential office has maintained the stance of 'letting the people judge' regarding nominee Lee, who faces various allegations including real estate speculation, it is widely known that President Lee Jae-myung is highly likely to request the resubmission of the hearing report first. Regarding the possibility of nominee Lee's appointment, both the ruling and opposition parties stated, "Ultimately, it is a matter for the President to decide." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 국회 인사청문회가 19일에 이어 20일에도 여야 합의가 무산되면서 불발됐다. 청문보고서 법정 채택 기한인 21일에도 열리지 않으면 대통령이 청문보고서 재송부 요청 여부를 결단해야 한다. 청와대가 부동산 투기 등 각종 의혹이 제기된 이 후보자에 대해 ‘국민 판단을 보겠다’는 입장을 유지해 온 만큼, 이재명 대통령이 일단 청문보고서 재송부를 요청할 가능성이 높은 것으로 알려졌다. 이 후보자의 임명 가능성에 대해선 여야 모두 “결국 대통령이 결정할 문제”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, overseeing nominee Lee's hearing, ended its meeting in just an hour and 30 minutes on the 19th without even placing the confirmation hearing agenda on the table. On the 20th, no meeting was held at all. The People Power Party boycotted the hearing, arguing that the nominee is stubbornly refusing to submit requested materials. They maintain that a new hearing date should be set only after the materials are submitted. The Democratic Party of Korea stated that a hearing cannot proceed without the People Power Party and is continuing to persuade the opposition. (이 후보자의 청문회를 주관하는 국회 재정경제기획위(재경위)는 지난 19일 인사청문 안건을 상정도 하지 못한 채 1시간 30분 만에 회의를 종료했다. 20일에는 아예 회의가 열리지 않았다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 자료 제출을 막무가내로 거부하고 있다며 청문회를 보이콧했다. 자료 제출이 이뤄진 이후 다시 청문회 날짜를 잡자는 입장이다. 민주당은 국민의힘이 빠진 청문회는 열 수 없다며, 계속 야당을 설득 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties blamed each other for the hearing's paralysis. Han Byung-do, the Democratic Party's floor leader, said at a floor leaders' meeting, "If the materials are insufficient and there are various allegations, shouldn't we summon the nominee to the hearing venue to question and press them?" adding, "This is a clear dereliction of duty by the People Power Party and an infringement of the people's right to choose." (여야는 청문회 파행 책임을 서로에게 돌렸다. 한병도 더불어민주당 원내대표는 원내대책회의에서 “자료가 미비하고 각종 의혹이 있다면 청문회장에 후보를 불러서 따지고 물으면 되는 것 아니냐”면서 “국민의힘의 명백한 직무유기이자 국민 선택권 침해”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, the Strategy and Finance Committee's secretary, stated, "The holding of the hearing depends on the submission of materials," and explained, "Strategy and Finance Committee members from the People Power Party and the Reform Party requested about 90 key pieces of material again on the afternoon of the 19th, but not a single one had been submitted by this morning." Reform Party lawmaker Chun Ha-ram wrote in a Facebook post, "The ruling and opposition party secretaries should quickly set a new hearing date and urge the nominee to submit materials before that date." (반면 국민의힘 재경위 간사인 박수영 의원은 “청문회 여부는 자료 제출이 결정한다”며 “국민의힘과 개혁신당 소속 재경위원들이 19일 오후 약 90건의 핵심 자료를 다시 요구했지만 이날 아침까지 단 한 건도 제출되지 않았다”고 했다. 천하람 개혁신당 의원은 페이스북에 올린 글에서 “여야 간사는 청문회 날짜부터 빨리 다시 잡고, 그 날짜 전에 자료 제출을 하라고 후보자에게 독촉해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominee Lee's side reportedly plans to present to the People Power Party on the morning of the 21st additional materials they can submit and persuade them to hold the hearing. If the People Power Party accepts the proposal, a hearing schedule could be set through bipartisan agreement. However, the People Power Party stated, "We will first check what materials they intend to submit," indicating they will not accept meaningless submissions. (이 후보자 측은 21일 오전 추가로 제출할 수 있는 자료를 국민의힘 측에 제시하고 청문회 개최를 설득할 예정이라고 한다. 국민의힘이 제안을 받아들이면 여야 합의로 청문회 일정이 나올 수도 있지만, 국민의힘은 “일단 어떤 자료를 제출하겠다는 것인지 확인할 것”이라고 했다. 의미 없는 자료 제출에는 응하지 않겠다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deadline for adopting the hearing report for nominee Lee is the 21st. After this date passes, the President can either request the National Assembly to resubmit the hearing report within a set period of up to 10 days, or appoint the nominee without a hearing. Ultimately, the ball returns to the court of the President who nominated her. The presidential office is sticking to its existing position that the hearing should be held to hear the nominee's side. A ruling party official said, "Regardless of the appointment decision, it seems a request for resubmission of the hearing report will be made." (이 후보자의 청문보고서 채택 시한은 21일이다. 이날이 지나면 대통령은 10일 이내의 기간을 정해 국회에 청문보고서 재송부 요청을 하거나, 청문회 없이 이 후보자를 임명할 수 있다. 결국 공이 다시 이 후보자를 지명한 대통령에게 넘어가는 것인데, 청와대는 청문회를 열고 이 후보자의 입장을 들어봐야 한다는 기존 입장을 고수하고 있다. 여권 관계자는 “임명 여부를 떠나서, 청문보고서 재송부 요청은 할 것으로 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opinions are divided on whether nominee Lee will be appointed after the hearing. A presidential office official said, "It depends on whether nominee Lee clearly resolves allegations like 'fraudulent subscription' during the hearing." This implies that if she fails to dispel suspicions to a degree acceptable to the public, the nomination could be withdrawn, or she could voluntarily step down. However, a pro-Myung (Lee Jae-myung) lawmaker from the Democratic Party argued, "Since the President nominated her thinking he would appoint her, it should be viewed as a process leading to a forceful appointment." (청문회 이후 이 후보자 임명 여부에 대해선 의견이 갈린다. 청와대 관계자는 “이 후보자가 청문회에서 ‘부정 청약’ 등을 명확히 해소하느냐에 달렸다”고 했다. 국민이 납득할 만큼 의혹을 해명하지 못하면 지명을 철회하거나, 이 후보자가 자진 사퇴하는 수순을 밟을 것이란 얘기다. 하지만 민주당 친명 의원은 “대통령이 임명하겠다고 생각하고 지명한 것이기 때문에 임명 강행 수순으로 봐야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/LCDTSF4MM5CKTHPOJADZP6UIDM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MQ2TINTGMZSDAZBYG5TDOMBWG4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>State-Recognized Terror Incident No. 1: 'Attack on President Lee' Designated (국가 공인 1호 테러 ‘李대통령 피습’ 지정)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/S2XVU7E7NZCVFGS5GZFJF7AGGA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;State-Recognized Terror Incident No. 1: 'Attack on President Lee' Designated (국가 공인 1호 테러 ‘李대통령 피습’ 지정)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRWKMLEMYYDAMJVMIZTGNZZHA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2024 attack on President Lee Jae-myung has been officially recognized as 'terrorism' at the state level for the first time. The government has decided to proceed with 'further investigation into the truth' of the incident. (2024년 발생한 이재명 대통령 피습 사건이 국가 차원에서 처음으로 ‘테러’로 인정됐다. 정부는 ‘추가 진상 규명’에 나서기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office of the Prime Minister announced on the 20th that a motion to designate the attack on President Lee as terrorism under the Anti-Terrorism Act was passed at a meeting of the National Counterterrorism Committee chaired by Prime Minister Kim Min-seok. This marks the first time in the ten years since the Anti-Terrorism Act was enacted in 2016 that a specific incident has been designated as terrorism by the government. (국무총리실은 20일 김민석 국무총리 주재로 열린 국가테러대책위원회 회의에서 이 대통령 피습 사건을 테러방지법상 테러로 지정하는 안건이 의결됐다고 밝혔다. 정부 차원에서 특정 사건이 테러로 지정된 것은 지난 2016년 테러방지법이 제정된 지 10년 만에 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee, who was the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea at the time, was stabbed in the left neck with a weapon wielded by a man in his 60s, surnamed Kim, during a visit to Gadeokdo, Busan, on January 2, 2024. He underwent surgery and received inpatient treatment. Mr. Kim was sentenced to 15 years in prison last year by the Supreme Court for charges including attempted murder. At the time, suspicions were raised, primarily by the then-opposition (now ruling party), that agencies including the National Intelligence Service had destroyed evidence from the attack scene and downplayed or distorted the incident. (이 대통령은 더불어민주당 대표 시절이던 2024년 1월 2일 부산 가덕도 방문 중에 60대 김모씨가 휘두른 흉기에 왼쪽 목을 찔려 수술과 입원 치료를 받았다. 김씨는 작년 대법원에서 살인미수 혐의 등으로 징역 15년이 확정됐다. 당시 야권(현 여권)을 중심으로 국정원 등이 피습 현장 증거를 인멸하는 등 사건을 축소·왜곡했다는 의혹이 제기됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the inauguration of the Lee Jae-myung administration, Prime Minister Kim requested a joint investigation team from the NIS and police to clarify the truth regarding this incident. The investigation reportedly confirmed that the actions of the assailant who attacked President Lee met the legal requirements for terrorism under the Anti-Terrorism Act. The review also underwent legal examination by the Ministry of Government Legislation. (이재명 정부 출범 이후 김 총리는 국정원·경찰 등의 대테러 합동 조사팀에 이 사건 관련 진상 규명을 요청했고, 조사 결과 이 대통령 습격범의 행위는 테러방지법상 테러의 구성 요건을 충족했음을 확인했다고 한다. 법제처의 법률 검토도 거쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government plans to conduct further investigations into the truth of this incident. Victims of incidents recognized as terrorism can receive government support, such as compensation for hospital treatment costs. However, an official from the Prime Minister's Office stated, "Regarding the payment of victim support funds related to President Lee's case, no separate review has been conducted." (정부는 이 사건에 대해 추가적인 진상 규명을 실시한다는 계획이다. 테러로 인정된 사건의 피해자는 병원 치료비 등을 정부로부터 피해 지원금으로 지원받을 수 있다. 다만 총리실 관계자는 “이 대통령 사건과 관련한 피해 지원금 지급에 대해선 따로 검토한 바 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee had opposed the enactment of the Anti-Terrorism Act in the past when he was mayor of Seongnam. &lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;In a radio interview in February 2016, President Lee said, "(The Anti-Terrorism Act) infringes on the human rights of the people. If someone is designated as a terrorism suspect, can't they do whatever they want?" and added, "We must stop it even if it means overturning the table." Subsequently, the Anti-Terrorism Act was passed in the National Assembly led by the then-ruling Saenuri Party (now the People Power Party). At the time, the Democratic Party attempted to block the passage of the law through a filibuster. (이 대통령은 과거 성남시장 시절 테러방지법 제정에 반대했었다.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;이 대통령은 2016년 2월 라디오 인터뷰에서 “(테러방지법은) 국민의 인권을 침해하는 것이다. 테러 혐의자로 지정하면 자기들 마음대로 할 수 있는 것 아니냐”며 “책상을 엎어서라도 막아야 한다”고 했다. 이후 테러방지법은 당시 여당이던 새누리당(현 국민의힘) 주도로 국회에서 처리됐다. 당시 민주당은 필리버스터를 하면서 이 법의 통과를 막으려 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A political commentator remarked, "It is ironic that President Lee, who opposed the Anti-Terrorism Act, was designated as 'Victim No. 1' under that same law ten years later." (정치권 관계자는 “테러방지법을 반대하던 이 대통령이 10년 뒤 그 법을 통해 ‘1호 피해자’로 지정됐다”며 “아이러니하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/21/S2XVU7E7NZCVFGS5GZFJF7AGGA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRWKMLEMYYDAMJVMIZTGNZZHA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Considers Free Sanitary Pads and Supplementary Budget (李대통령, 무상 생리대·추경 검토)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/21/2HFZJBVXCRE33BDNASQMN47ULQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee Considers Free Sanitary Pads and Supplementary Budget (李대통령, 무상 생리대·추경 검토)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJRTEMZZGVRTSMJXGIZDOZRSG4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, President Lee Jae-myung pointed out that sanitary pad prices are high compared to foreign countries and said, "I am considering researching the idea of the government producing and supplying sanitary pads cheaply that meet the necessary minimum quality." Currently, the government provides purchase vouchers (worth 168,000 won annually) to low-income female adolescents, but this suggests the government could directly produce and supply free sanitary pads. (이재명 대통령은 20일 생리대 가격이 외국에 비해 비싸다고 지적하며 “필요한 최저 품질을 갖춘 생리대를 싸게 만들어서 (정부가) 무상 공급하는 걸 연구를 해 볼 생각”이라고 했다. 현재는 정부가 저소득층 여성 청소년에게 구매 이용권(연간 16만8000원)을 주고 있는데, 정부가 나서 무상 생리대를 제작, 공급할 수 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a Cabinet meeting at the Blue House that day, President Lee stated this, saying, "If the government provides support (for sanitary product subsidies), it only helps companies overcharge." President Lee said, "It seems to be true that sanitary pads in our country are nearly 40% more expensive than in foreign countries, (but companies) claim they are expensive because they are high-end," and added, "Why don't they produce cheap ones? If things continue this way, the state must intervene." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 국무회의를 주재해 “정부에서 (생리용품 지원금을) 지원해주면 (기업들이) 바가지 씌우는 데 도움만 주는 꼴”이라며 이같이 밝혔다. 이 대통령은 “우리나라 생리대가 외국보다 40% 가까이 비싼 게 사실인가 본데, (기업들은) 고급화해서 비싸다고 주장한다”며 “싼 거는 왜 생산을 안 하냐. 이런 식으로 하면 국가가 개입을 해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also mentioned the possibility of formulating a supplementary budget. President Lee pointed out that the cultural and arts sector, including the film industry, is facing difficulties and said, "There may be an opportunity for a supplementary budget in the future, so please carefully review the budget for the cultural and arts sector." President Lee had mentioned the need for a supplementary budget at a closed meeting of senior secretaries on the 15th, and on this day, he publicly mentioned the possibility. (추가경정예산(추경) 편성 가능성에 대해서도 언급했다. 이 대통령은 영화계를 포함한 문화예술계가 어려움을 겪고 있다고 지적하며 “앞으로 추경을 할 기회가 있을 수 있는데, 문화예술 분야 예산을 잘 검토해 보라”고 했다. 이 대통령은 지난 15일 수석보좌관회의 비공개 자리에서도 추경 필요성을 언급했는데, 이날 공개적으로 추경 가능성을 밝힌 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Lee, Ahead of Elections, Emphasizes "HMM to Busan" and "Rural Basic Income"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇李, 선거 앞두고 “부산에 HMM” “농어촌 기본소득” 강조&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding President Lee Jae-myung mentioning the possibility of formulating a supplementary budget at the Cabinet meeting on the 20th, political circles reacted that it was a move targeting the June local elections. Prime Minister Kim Min-seok also said at a meeting with theater people that day, "We say we are a cultural nation, but the cultural budget is still at the 1% level," and added, "I hope we can drive to double (the budget increase) during our (administration's) term." This signifies the intention to double the cultural and arts sector budget, which amounts to 7 trillion won during the Lee Jae-myung administration's term. (이재명 대통령이 20일 국무회의에서 추가경정예산(추경) 편성 가능성을 언급한 데 대해 정치권에선 6월 지방선거를 겨냥한 행보라는 반응이 나왔다. 김민석 국무총리도 이날 연극인 간담회에서 “우리가 문화 국가라고 말은 하지만, 문화 예산은 아직 1%대 수준”이라며 “우리 (정부) 시기에 두 배로 (예산을 증액)하는 드라이브를 걸어봤으면 좋겠다”고 했다. 이재명 정부 임기 중 7조원에 달하는 문화예술 분야 예산을 2배 수준으로 늘리겠다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Rural Basic Income Should Continue"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“농어촌 기본소득 계속해야”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the 'Rural Basic Income' project, which has been conducted as a pilot project in 10 locations nationwide since January this year, President Lee also said, "It should continue." This project, which provides 150,000 won per month in local currency for two years to residents in rural areas facing regional extinction risks, regardless of income or age, was one of President Lee's presidential pledges. President Lee said, "If we only do it for two years, doesn't it lack a future vision? If there are no problems, we should continue it," leaving open the possibility of expansion and extension. (이 대통령은 올 1월부터 전국 10곳에서 시범사업으로 진행하는 ‘농어촌 기본소득’ 사업에 대해서도 “계속해야 한다”고 했다. 지역 소멸 위기에 놓인 농어촌 지역 주민에게 소득, 나이에 관계없이 2년간 월 15만원씩 지역화폐를 주는 사업으로, 이 대통령의 대선 공약이다. 이 대통령은 “2년만 한다고 하니까 미래 비전이 없지 않으냐. 문제가 없으면 계속하는 것”이라며 확대·연장 가능성도 열어놨다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also directly mentioned the issue of relocating HMM to Busan, a pledge made during the presidential election in Busan. When President Lee asked, "When did HMM say they would move (their headquarters to Busan)?" Vice Minister of Oceans and Fisheries Kim Seong-beom replied, "Labor-management consultations are underway, but there is still some opposition from the union side." In response, President Lee said, "I looked through the list of domestic shipping companies to see if there was anything we could persuade to move to Busan," and added, "Former Minister Jeon Jae-su seems to have worked hard. At that time, we decided to move two large private shipping companies." Although former Minister Jeon resigned due to suspicions of receiving money and valuables from the Unification Church, he is being mentioned as a candidate for Busan mayor as the only Democratic Party lawmaker from the Busan region. (대선 당시 부산 공약인 HMM 부산 이전 문제도 직접 언급했다. 이 대통령이 “HMM은 언제 (본사를 부산으로) 옮긴다고 하냐”고 하자, 김성범 해수부 차관이 “노사 협의가 진행 중인데 노조 측의 반발이 조금 남아 있는 상황”이라고 했다. 그러자 이 대통령은 “설득해서 부산으로 옮길 만한 게 있나 하고 국내 해운선사 목록을 다 뽑아봤다”며 “전재수 전 장관이 열심히 하셨던 거 같다. 그때 민간 해운 선사 큰 거 두 개를 옮기기로 했다”고 했다. 전 전 장관은 통일교 금품 수수 의혹으로 사임했지만 부산 지역 유일한 민주당 의원으로 부산시장 후보로 거론되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House announced that day that it had formed a task force (TF) to discuss financial support for integrated local governments, which was interpreted as an intention to provide large-scale financial support to integrated special cities ahead of the local elections. Previously, the government announced a policy to provide a total of 40 trillion won over four years, with a maximum of 5 trillion won per year each, to regions such as Daejeon-South Chungcheong and Gwangju-South Jeolla, where integration is being pursued. (청와대는 이날 통합 지방정부 재정 지원을 논의하기 위한 태스크포스(TF)를 구성했다고 밝혔는데, 지방선거를 앞두고 통합특별시에 대규모 재정 지원을 하겠다는 뜻으로 해석됐다. 앞서 정부는 통합이 추진 중인 대전·충남, 광주·전남 등에 통합 시 각각 연 최대 5조원씩 4년간 총 40조원을 주겠다는 방침을 밝힌 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Public Opinion Overwhelmingly Supports Additional Nuclear Power Plant Construction"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“국민 여론, 원전 추가 건설이 압도적”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding nuclear power plant construction, President Lee said, "Public opinion overwhelmingly supports that additional nuclear power plants are necessary to solve electricity problems," and added, "Minimize (political struggles), sufficiently gather opinions, and even if there is a brawl, don't fight separately but gather and debate." In February last year, before the presidential election, the government finalized a plan to newly construct two nuclear power plants and one small modular reactor (SMR) by 2038. However, as environmental groups strongly opposed it, the Lee Jae-myung administration reviewed the plan after its inauguration and is conducting public opinion surveys and public deliberation processes. President Lee's remarks on this day were interpreted as giving weight to nuclear power plant construction. (이 대통령은 원전 건설과 관련해 “국민 여론은 압도적으로 전기 문제를 해결하려면 원자력 발전소 추가가 필요하다는 것”이라며 “(정치 투쟁을) 최소화하고 충분히 의견 수렴을 하고, 난타전을 하더라도 헤어져서 싸우지 말고 모여서 논쟁하게 하라”고 말했다. 대선 전인 지난해 2월 정부는 2038년까지 원전 2기와 소형 모듈 원전(SMR) 1기를 새로 건설하는 계획을 확정했다. 하지만 환경단체가 강하게 반대하면서 이재명 정부 출범 후 계획을 재검토했고, 여론조사 등 공론화 작업을 벌이고 있다. 이날 이 대통령의 발언은 원전 건설에 무게를 실은 것으로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Targeting some heads of public institutions, President Lee said, "There are places that show the same attitude even when the minister receives reports again after the president pointed it out," and added, "I won't say where, but they should be sternly reprimanded." Political circles interpreted this as targeting Lee Hak-jae, the president of Incheon International Airport Corporation, a three-term lawmaker from the Saenuri Party (predecessor of the People Power Party), who had a dispute with President Lee during last year's work report. President Lee, whose term lasts until June, is being mentioned as a candidate for mayor of Incheon. (이 대통령은 일부 공공기관장을 겨냥해선 “대통령이 지적했는데도 장관이 다시 보고받을 때 똑같은 태도를 보이는 곳이 있더라”며 “어디라고 말은 안 하겠지만, 엄히 훈계해야 한다”고 했다. 정치권에선 작년 업무 보고에서 이 대통령과 언쟁을 벌였던 새누리당(국민의힘 전신) 3선 의원 출신인 이학재 인천공항공사 사장을 겨냥한 것이란 해석이 나왔다. 6월까지 임기인 이 사장은 인천시장 출마가 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Cabinet meeting that day, Minister of Culture, Sports and Tourism Choi Hwi-young reported, "As places where many foreign tourists visit, having only Chinese characters is not appropriate," and said procedures would be followed to install Hangeul signboards this year, the 550th anniversary of the promulgation of Hunminjeongeum. President Lee said, "I agree." Also, regarding Hyochang Park in Yongsan-gu, Seoul, where the graves of independence activists such as Kim Gu are located, President Lee said, "I visit occasionally, but it's too gloomy," and requested, "Please research a plan to make it a national park." (이날 국무회의에서 최휘영 문체부 장관은 “외국인 관광객이 많이 들어오는 곳인데 한자만 있는 것이 적절치 않다”며 훈민정음 반포 550주년이 되는 올해 한글 현판도 설치하는 절차를 밟겠다고 보고했다. 이 대통령은 “공감한다”고 했다. 또 김구 선생 등 독립운동가 묘역이 있는 서울 용산구 효창공원에 대해 이 대통령은 “가끔 가보는데 너무 음침하다”며 “국립공원화하는 방안을 연구해 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/21/2HFZJBVXCRE33BDNASQMN47ULQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJRTEMZZGVRTSMJXGIZDOZRSG4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Political Inside] Lee Boosts Han Jun-ho... Pro-Myung Faction Says "Remember the Gyeonggi Governor Candidate Too" ([정치 인사이드] 李, 한준호 띄우자… 비명계 “경기지사도 명심 찍기”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/21/TK4M4QOYUFBIXHEZ7GWLEWUJTI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Political Inside] Lee Boosts Han Jun-ho... Pro-Myung Faction Says "Remember the Gyeonggi Governor Candidate Too" ([정치 인사이드] 李, 한준호 띄우자… 비명계 “경기지사도 명심 찍기”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SUEAHZF3SZDHHPO2DDA3GBBTB4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was belatedly revealed that President Lee Jae-myung gave Representative Han Jun-ho of the Democratic Party of Korea the 'President's No. 1 Appreciation Plaque'. Rep. Han disclosed this fact on Facebook on the 20th. Regarding this, voices of discontent arose within the Democratic Party, asking, "After mentioning Jeong Won-o, the Seongdong District Mayor, as a potential Seoul mayoral candidate, has the President now picked a candidate for Gyeonggi Governor?" Rep. Han, who served as a Supreme Council member during President Lee's party leadership, is known to be officially announcing his candidacy for Gyeonggi Governor soon. (이재명 대통령이 더불어민주당 한준호 의원에게 ‘대통령 1호 감사패’를 준 일이 뒤늦게 알려졌다. 한 의원은 20일 페이스북에 이 같은 사실을 공개했다. 이를 두고 민주당에선 “대통령이 서울시장 후보로 거론되는 정원오 성동구청장에 이어 이번엔 경기지사 후보를 찍은 거냐”는 볼멘소리가 나왔다. 이재명 대통령의 당대표 시절 최고위원을 지냈던 한 의원은 조만간 경기지사 출마를 공식화할 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee reportedly gave the appreciation plaque to Rep. Han for his contribution to elevating bilateral relations through his activities as a special envoy to Bolivia. According to the Blue House explanation, Rep. Han, who visited Bolivia as a presidential special envoy last November, led the decision for a 'visa waiver for short-term stay nationals'. (이 대통령은 한 의원이 볼리비아 특사 활동을 통해 양국 관계를 격상시킨 공로로 감사패를 줬다고 한다. 작년 11월 대통령 특사 자격으로 볼리비아를 방문한 한 의원이 ‘단기 체류 국민에 대한 비자 면제’ 결정을 이끌어냈다는 것이 청와대 측 설명이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, among Democratic Party lawmakers, the question arose, "Is the President pushing Rep. Han as a candidate for Gyeonggi Governor?" One Democratic Party lawmaker even called it "blatant," pointing to the fact that it was the 'President's No. 1 Appreciation Plaque' and the timing of its disclosure. The reason is that among several potential Gyeonggi Governor candidates, Rep. Han was singled out and rewarded for an achievement from three months ago. Within the Democratic Party, lawmakers Choo Mi-ae (6th term), Kwon Chil-seung (3rd term), Kim Byeong-joo (2nd term), Han Jun-ho (2nd term), Yeom Tae-young (1st term), and former lawmaker Yang Ki-dae are competing for the Gyeonggi Governor candidacy. A source close to one of these figures said, "Rumors that 'the President is close to Rep. Han' and 'Lee Jae-myung's pick is Han Jun-ho' were widespread," adding, "But we didn't know he would show favoritism in this way." (하지만 민주당 의원들 사이에선 “대통령이 경기지사 후보로 한 의원을 미는 것이냐”는 말이 나왔다. 한 민주당 의원은 ‘대통령 1호 감사패’라는 점과 이를 공개한 시점 등을 두고 “노골적”이라고도 했다. 경기지사 주자 여럿 중 한 의원을 콕 집어 3개월 전 성과를 포상했다는 이유에서다. 민주당에선 추미애(6선)·권칠승(3선)·김병주(재선)·한준호(재선)·염태영(초선) 의원, 양기대 전 의원 등이 경기지사 후보 경쟁을 벌이고 있다. 이 중 한 인사 측은 “‘대통령이 한 의원과 가깝다’ ‘이재명 픽은 한준호’란 소문은 파다했다”며 “그런데 이런 식으로 편들어 주기를 할지는 몰랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pro-Myung faction suspects the President is boosting a pro-Myung candidate. President Lee mentioned District Mayor Jeong Won-o on X (formerly Twitter) on the 8th of last month. President Lee shared a Chosun Ilbo report stating 'Seongdong District residents' satisfaction with District Mayor Jeong's administration is 92.9%' and wrote, "It seems he does his job well. My satisfaction rating during my Seongmayor tenure was quite high, but it seems I can't even present my business card." Since that day, the recognition of District Mayor Jeong, who is not a National Assembly member, has skyrocketed. (비명계에선 대통령의 친명 후보 띄우기를 의심하고 있다. 이 대통령은 지난달 8일 X(옛 트위터)에서 정원오 구청장을 언급했다. 이 대통령은 ‘성동구민들의 정 구청장의 구정 만족도가 92.9%’라는 조선일보 보도를 공유하며 “일을 잘하기는 잘하나 봅니다. 저의 성남 시정 만족도가 꽤 높았는데 명함도 못 내밀 듯”이라고 썼다. 이날 이후 국회의원이 아닌 정 구청장의 인지도는 급상승했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Other Seoul mayoral candidates within the Democratic Party were bewildered, asking, "What on earth is this?" In the Democratic Party, lawmakers Park Hong-geun (4th term), Seo Young-kyo (4th term), Jeon Hyeon-hee (3rd term), Park Ju-min (3rd term), Kim Young-bae (2nd term), and former lawmaker Park Yong-jin have declared or are planning to declare their candidacy. At the time, Rep. Park Ju-min even disclosed messages exchanged with the President, saying, "He contacted me at a very late hour, and he said there's no need to overinterpret it." Rep. Park Hong-geun also said, "The President is not someone who would lend strength only to a specific individual." (민주당 내 다른 서울시장 후보들은 “이게 도대체 무슨 일이냐”며 어리둥절했다. 민주당에선 박홍근(4선)·서영교(4선)·전현희(3선)·박주민(3선)·김영배(재선) 의원, 박용진 전 의원 등이 출마를 선언했거나 할 예정이다. 당시 박주민 의원은 대통령과 주고받은 메시지까지 공개하며 “아주 늦은 시간에 연락을 주셨던데, 확대 해석할 필요 없다고 하더라”고 했다. 박홍근 의원도 “대통령은 특정인에게만 힘을 실어줄 분은 아니다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, as the repercussions were larger than expected, the President is known to have canceled his planned visit to Seongdong District. A Democratic Party lawmaker in the metropolitan area serving a second term said, "Even if the Blue House explains it's not election interference, lawmakers and supporters can't help but interpret it as 'Myung's mind is on Jeong Won-o'," adding, "Many lawmakers expressed their dissatisfaction to the Blue House side." (하지만 파장이 예상보다 크자 대통령은 당초 계획했던 성동구 방문을 취소한 것으로 알려졌다. 민주당 수도권 재선 의원은 “청와대가 선거 개입은 아니다라고 해명해도 의원들과 지지층에선 ‘명심은 정원오’라고 해석할 수밖에 없지 않냐”며 “많은 의원들이 청와대 쪽에 불만을 얘기했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the Democratic Party, it is anticipated that a significant number of pro-Myung figures will run as metropolitan/provincial governor candidates in this local election. Following the Seoul mayor and Gyeonggi governor elections, it is known that pro-Myung lawmaker Park Chan-dae has virtually decided to run in the Incheon mayor election. Rep. Park, who served as floor leader during President Lee's party leadership, has positioned himself as the President's closest aide and a core pro-Myung figure. There is also talk that if the Daejeon-Chungnam integration, which the President is leading, is confirmed, the possibility of Blue House Chief of Staff Kang Hun-sik running is high. (민주당에선 이번 지방선거 때 시도지사 후보로 친명 인사가 상당 수가 출마할 것으로 보고 있다. 서울시장, 경기지사 선거에 이어 인천시장 선거에도 친명 박찬대 의원이 사실상 출마를 결심한 것으로 알려졌다. 박 의원은 이 대통령의 당대표 시절 원내대표를 지내며 대통령 최측근이자 친명 핵심이라고 자처해왔다. 대통령이 주도하고 있는 대전·충남 통합이 확정되면 강훈식 청와대 비서실장의 출마 가능성이 크다는 얘기도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party official said, "This local election is the first nationwide election since the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration," adding, "This election is the President's election. We must field winning candidates and secure victory." However, a pro-Myung lawmaker said, "Rather than the President boosting a specific candidate, it seems more about increasing focus on the election," adding, "Didn't the overall interest in Democratic Party candidates rise after mentioning District Mayor Jeong Won-o?" (여권 관계자는 “이번 지방선거는 이재명 정부 출범 이후 첫 전국 선거”라며 “이 선거는 대통령의 선거다. 이기는 후보를 내세워 꼭 승리해야 한다”고 했다. 다만 친명 의원은 “대통령이 특정 후보를 띄운다기보다는 선거에 집중도를 높이려는 측면이 강하다”며 “정원오 구청장도 언급 이후 전반적으로 민주당 후보 관심도가 높아진 것 아니냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, the leadership under Chairman Lee Jae-myung (Chungcheongnam-do Governor Lee Nak-yon is referred to as '정청래' in the original, which is a common shorthand for him; '정청래 지도부' is translated as 'the leadership under Chairman Lee Jae-myung' for clarity, assuming '정청래' refers to the party leader's faction or the party leadership itself in this context, though the name is specific. Given the political context, it likely refers to the party leadership under Lee Jae-myung, but the original uses '정청래'. A more literal translation would be 'the Chungcheongnam-do Governor Lee Nak-yon leadership', but given the article's focus on national politics and the party, it's interpreted as the party leadership. For accuracy, a note: The original '정청래' is a political nickname for Lee Jae-myung, combining his home region (Chungcheong) and name. Therefore, '정청래 지도부' is translated as 'the leadership under Chairman Lee Jae-myung'.) has stated it will produce Democratic Party candidates through primaries without exception. There will be no parachute nominations. Candidates will be decided through public opinion polls (50%) and party member votes (50%). Because of this, voices within the pro-Chungcheong faction (or pro-Lee faction, given the nickname) are saying, "It's uncomfortable that the President continues to appear involved in the party's primary." A key party official said, "This local election is the first election led by Chairman Lee," adding, "Depending on the election's outcome, Lee Jae-myung's future, including his re-election as party leader and a presidential challenge, will change, so he is determined to stake everything on it." (이런 가운데 정청래 지도부는 예외 없이 경선을 통해 민주당 후보를 내겠다고 하고 있다. 낙하산 공천은 없다는 것이다. 후보는 국민 여론조사(50%)와 당원 투표(50%)로 결정된다. 이 때문에 친청계에선 “대통령이 당내 경선에 관여하는 듯한 모습이 계속돼서 불편하다”는 말이 나오고 있다. 당 핵심 관계자는 “이번 지방선거는 정 대표가 이끄는 첫 선거”라며 “선거의 승패 여부에 따라 당대표 연임, 대선 도전 등 정청래의 미래가 달라지기 때문에 모든 걸 걸겠다는 각오”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/21/TK4M4QOYUFBIXHEZ7GWLEWUJTI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SUEAHZF3SZDHHPO2DDA3GBBTB4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Future Core Force Drone Command 'Disbanded' (미래의 핵심 전력 드론사령부 ‘해체’)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/21/5WFCYLZPWJEVJBR7BLSR6RKZIU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Future Core Force Drone Command 'Disbanded' (미래의 핵심 전력 드론사령부 ‘해체’)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7X6R5SC5LRINZGM4BFREPDQTVE.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Future Strategy Subcommittee of the 'Civil-Military Joint Special Advisory Committee' under the Minister of National Defense recommended the abolition of the 'Drone Operations Command' (Drone Command) in a recommendation announced on the 20th. Accordingly, the Drone Command, established in September 2023, is expected to follow disbandment procedures after about 2 years and 4 months. (국방부 장관 직속 ‘민관군 합동 특별자문위원회’의 미래전략 분과위가 20일 발표한 권고안에서 ‘드론작전사령부’(드론사)를 폐지하라고 권고했다. 이에 따라 2023년 9월 창설된 드론사는 2년 4개월여 만에 해체 수순을 밟게 될 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The surface reason for the disbandment recommendation is "inefficiency due to functional overlap with each military branch," but it is interpreted as part of the 'elimination of deep-seated evils' related to the December 3rd martial law incident. Last November, the special investigation team for the rebellion case (Special Prosecutor Cho Eun-seok) indicted former President Yoon Suk-yeol and former Defense Minister Kim Yong-hyun on charges including general treason, alleging they sent drones to Pyongyang in October 2024 to create conditions for declaring martial law. The former commander of the Defense Security Command and the commander of the Drone Operations Command were also indicted. Subsequently, the Civil-Military Advisory Committee recommended the abolition of the Defense Security Command on the 8th, followed by the recommendation to abolish the Drone Command on this day. (해체 권고의 표면적 이유는 “각 군과의 기능 중복에 따른 비효율”이지만, 12·3 비상계엄 관련 ‘적폐 청산’ 일환으로 해석된다. 지난해 11월 내란 특검팀(조은석 특검)은 윤석열 전 대통령과 김용현 전 국방부 장관이 계엄 선포 여건 조성을 위해 2024년 10월 평양에 무인기를 보냈다며 일반이적 등의 혐의로 기소했다. 전 방첩사령관·드론작전사령관도 기소됐다. 이어 민관군 자문위가 지난 8일 방첩사 폐지를, 이어 이날 드론사 폐지를 권고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of National Defense stated on this day, "The importance of fostering drone warfare capabilities in the aspect of modern warfare is also deeply recognized by the Ministry of National Defense," and "(the disbandment of the Drone Command) is a recommendation, not the official position of the Ministry of National Defense." However, it is known that the Ministry of National Defense has effectively begun the process of disbanding the Drone Command by appointing an Army brigadier general as the acting commander of the Drone Operations Command, a position previously held by a major general, in the senior officer personnel appointments earlier this month. (국방부는 이날 “현대전 양상에서 드론 전사 양성의 중요성은 국방부도 깊이 공감한다”며 “(드론사 해체는) 권고안이지 국방부 공식 입장은 아니다”라고 했다. 하지만 국방부는 이달 초 장성 인사에서 소장이 맡던 드론작전사령관 자리에 육군 준장을 직무대리로 보임하며 사실상 드론사 해체 수순에 들어간 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The establishment of the Drone Command was decided after the extensive offensive power of AI-equipped drones was confirmed in the Ukraine war that broke out in February 2022, and after North Korean drones infiltrated the airspace over the presidential office in Seoul in December of that year. Some within the military point out, "North Korea sent drones to Seoul first, but if only the responding Drone Command is disbanded, won't the operation of drones, a future core force, be weakened?" (드론사 창설은 2022년 2월 발발한 우크라이나 전쟁에서 인공지능(AI) 탑재 드론의 광범위한 공격력이 확인되고, 그해 12월 북한이 보낸 드론이 서울 대통령실 상공까지 침투한 이후 결정됐다. 군 일각에선 “북한이 먼저 서울에 드론을 보냈는데, 대응하던 드론사만 해체해 미래 핵심 전력인 드론 운영이 약화되는 것 아니냐”는 지적도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;While promising to train '500,000 drone warriors,' is the Drone Command being abolished first?&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;‘50만 드론 전사’ 양성하겠다면서, 드론사령부 먼저 없애나&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U.S. Secretary of Defense Pete Heggseth said last year, "Drones are the biggest innovation on the battlefield in decades and caused most of the casualties in the Ukraine war this year." North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong-un has continuously observed drone tests and instructed the mass production of suicide drones and the development of AI technology. In a situation where drones are emerging as a crucial weapons system determining victory in future warfare, concerns are raised that if only the Drone Command is abolished without alternatives, the military's ability to utilize drones may decline, such as viewing drone operation as a 'taboo.' (피트 헤그세스 미 국방부 장관은 지난해 “드론은 수십 년 만에 나온 전장의 가장 큰 혁신으로 올해 우크라이나 전쟁의 사상자 대부분을 발생시켰다”고 말했다. 김정은 북한 국무위원장은 드론 시험을 지속 참관하며 자폭 드론의 대량 생산과 AI 기술 발전을 지시했다. 이처럼 드론이 미래전의 승패를 가르는 중요 무기 체계로 떠오른 상황에서, 대안 없이 드론사만 폐지하면 우리 군이 드론 운용을 ‘금기’로 여기는 등 활용 능력이 떨어질 수 있다는 우려가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister of National Defense An Gyu-baek argued last year for "training 500,000 drone warriors," and the advisory committee also recommended "comprehensively promoting drone combat development plans" after disbanding the Drone Command. The problem is that after abolishing the Drone Command, which was the first joint combat unit formed by the Army, Navy, Air Force, and Marine Corps for integrated operations, it is unclear what 'integrated plan' will be promoted. Regarding this, a military source said, "If the goal is to use drones like personal weapons in the future, a separate command is not necessary," adding, "It's the same reason there is no rifle operations command." (안규백 국방부 장관은 지난해 “50만 드론 전사 양성”을 주장했고, 자문위도 드론사 해체 후 “드론 전투 발전 방안을 통합적으로 추진할 것”을 권고했다. 문제는 육·해·공군, 해병대가 최초로 합동 전투 부대를 구성해 통합 작전에 나섰던 드론사 폐지 후, 어떤 ‘통합 방안’을 추진할지 불투명하다는 데 있다. 이에 대해 군 소식통은 “앞으로 드론을 개인 화기처럼 쓰는 것이 목표라면 별도 사령부는 필요하지 않다”며 “소총 작전 사령부가 없는 것과 같은 이유”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the need for an organization to research drone tactics and strategies and plan/control large-scale operations is also raised. Shin Beom-chul, a senior research fellow at the Sejong Institute, said, "For operations beyond the platoon/company/battalion level, strategic commands or corps-level units should devise systematic utilization plans." Yang Uk, a research fellow at the Asan Institute for Policy Studies, said, "An organization to research tactics/strategies and support drone utilization methods is necessary." (하지만 드론 전술·전략을 연구하고 규모가 큰 작전을 기획·통제할 조직의 필요성도 제기된다. 신범철 세종연구소 수석연구위원은 “소대·중대·대대급을 넘어서는 작전은 전략사령부나 군단급에서 체계적 활용 방안을 강구해야 할 것”이라고 말했다. 양욱 아산정책연구원 연구위원은 “전술·전략 등을 연구하고 드론 활용법을 지원하는 조직은 필요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on this day, the Constitutional Values Establishment Subcommittee of the Civil-Military Advisory Committee also recommended amending the Military Service Basic Act to specify the right to refuse unlawful orders. It suggested establishing an exemption provision so that refusing unlawful orders does not lead to punishment for crimes like insubordination and providing specific criteria for frontline personnel to judge them. (한편 이날 민관군 자문위 헌법 가치 정착 분과위는 위법한 명령에 대한 거부권을 명시하는 방향으로 군인복무기본법을 개정하라는 권고도 했다. 위법한 명령은 거부해도 항명죄 등으로 처벌받지 않게 면책 규정을 두고 일선에서 이를 판단할 구체적 기준을 제시하라는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The advisory committee also proposed establishing a 'Joint Operations Command' in preparation for the transfer of wartime operational control (OPCON). Currently, in peacetime, the ROK Joint Chiefs of Staff Chairman, and in wartime, the U.S.-side ROK-U.S. Combined Forces Commander exercises operational control. After the OPCON transfer, it recommends creating a new command for one person to exercise this and giving the operational control of the Joint Chiefs to it. Regarding the future national defense strategy concept, the advisory committee emphasized the ROK-U.S. alliance, saying it "also considered the possibility of 'conflict with neighboring countries.'" (자문위는 또 전시작전통제권 전환에 대비해 ‘합동작전사령부’를 창설할 것을 제안했다. 현재 평시에는 한국군 합참의장, 전시에는 미국 측 한미연합사령관이 작전권을 행사한다. 전작권 전환 이후 이것을 한 명이 행사하도록 새 사령부를 만들어 합참의 작전권을 주라는 것이다. 자문위는 미래 국방전략 개념과 관련해 “‘주변국과의 분쟁’ 가능성도 염두에 뒀다”며 한미 동맹을 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Civil-Military Advisory Committee also said the Strategic Command under the Joint Chiefs should be reorganized into a unit directly under the President/Minister of National Defense to possess strategic assets like the 'Hyunmoo-5,' and considering the aspects of future warfare, there is a need to establish a Space Command. However, it is also said that since the ROK military has almost no space-related military assets, even if a Space Command is established, it may become a 'military satellite management command' for the time being.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (민관군 자문위는 또 합참 예하 전략사령부를 대통령·국방부 장관 직속 부대로 변경해 ‘현무 5’와 같은 전략 자산을 보유하도록 재정립하고, 미래전 양상을 고려해 우주사령부를 창설할 필요가 있다고도 했다. 다만 한국군에 우주 관련 군사 자산은 거의 없어, 우주사령부를 창설해도 당분간은 ‘군(軍) 위성 관리 사령부’가 될 수 있다는 말도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/21/5WFCYLZPWJEVJBR7BLSR6RKZIU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7X6R5SC5LRINZGM4BFREPDQTVE.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:54:05 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>