<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:57:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>'Godfather of the Student Movement' Lee Hae-chan in Critical Condition... Flurry of Cheong Wa Dae Special Advisors and Ruling Party Lawmakers Head to Vietnam (‘운동권 대부’ 이해찬 위독…청와대 특보·與 의원들 대거 베트남行)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/DDZL5RGQEBDT5DKDZTFJOCRSMM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;'Godfather of the Student Movement' Lee Hae-chan in Critical Condition... Flurry of Cheong Wa Dae Special Advisors and Ruling Party Lawmakers Head to Vietnam (‘운동권 대부’ 이해찬 위독…청와대 특보·與 의원들 대거 베트남行)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EUQH3VGGSRN6VIGTE2XHX2TIWM.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hae-chan, Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council and former three-term leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, fell critically ill and was hospitalized in Vietnam on the 23rd while on a business trip. On the 24th, Democratic Party lawmakers departed South Korea for Vietnam. (더불어민주당 3대 당 대표를 지낸 이해찬 민주평화통일자문회의 수석부의장이 베트남 출장 중인 23일 위독 상태에 빠져 현지 병원에 입원하자 24일 민주당 의원들이 한국을 출국해 베트남으로 향했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Jung-sik, Special Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, urgently dispatched by President Lee Jae-myung, also arrived at Tam Anh General Hospital in Ho Chi Minh City, where the Senior Vice Chairman is hospitalized, on the afternoon of the 24th (local time). Without making any special remarks, Special Advisor Cho immediately went up to the intensive care unit where Senior Vice Chairman Lee is being treated. Democratic Party lawmakers Kim Tae-nyeon, Lee Hae-sik, Lee Jae-jeong, and Choi Min-hee also arrived at the hospital in the morning and visited the ICU. (이재명 대통령이 현지에 급파한 조정식 정무특별보좌관도 24일 오후(현지 시각) 이 수석부의장이 입원한 호찌민 시내 떰아인 종합병원에 도착했다. 조 특보는 특별한 발언 없이 곧바로 이 수석부의장이 입원 중인 중환자실로 올라갔다. 민주당 김태년·이해식·이재정·최민희 의원도 이날 오전 병원에 도착해 중환자실을 찾았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters, lawmaker Kim said of Senior Vice Chairman Lee, "He has lived his life doing great and significant work for the democratization, democracy, prosperity of the Republic of Korea, and for the lives of our people," adding, "It would be too empty for him to leave like this; I hope he miraculously gets back up." (김 의원은 취재진을 만나 이 수석부의장이 “대한민국의 민주화, 민주주의, 번영, 우리 국민의 삶을 챙기기 위해 평생을 살면서 크고 중대한 일을 해왔다”며 “이렇게 가시기에는 너무 허망하니 기적처럼 반드시 다시 일어나셨으면 좋겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also said, "They say he's a bit better than yesterday, but I'm not sure how meaningful that improvement is," and "(Regarding decisions like returning home) we need to discuss it a bit." The previous evening, lawmaker Kim Hyun also visited the Senior Vice Chairman in Vietnam. Most of these lawmakers are classified as close to the Senior Vice Chairman, part of the 'Lee Hae-chan faction'. It is known that Choi Young-sam, South Korean Ambassador to Vietnam, and staff from the Consulate General in Ho Chi Minh City and other diplomatic missions also gathered at the hospital to support the situation on the ground. (또 “어제보다는 조금 나아졌다고는 하는 데 얼마나 의미 있는 호전인지는 잘 모르겠다”며 “(귀국 결정 등은) 논의를 조금 해봐야 한다”고 했다. 전날 저녁 김현 의원도 현지에 와서 이 수석부의장을 문병했다. 이들 의원은 대부분 이 수석부의장과 가까운 ‘이해찬계’로 분류된다. 최영삼 주베트남 한국대사와 호찌민총영사관 등 공관 직원들도 병원에 모여 현장 상황을 지원하는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Senior Vice Chairman Lee developed symptoms of weakened breathing while on a business trip to Ho Chi Minh City to attend a Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council meeting on the 23rd. He received CPR and was transferred to the emergency room. Subsequently, he was diagnosed with a myocardial infarction, underwent stent placement, and is receiving ECMO (Extracorporeal Membrane Oxygenation) treatment. According to the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council and others, the Senior Vice Chairman's breathing and complexion have somewhat stabilized compared to the previous day, but he remains in critical condition, still unconscious. (앞서 이 수석부의장은 23일 민주평통 회의 참석을 위한 호찌민 출장 도중 호흡이 약해지는 증상이 나타나 심폐소생술을 받으며 응급실로 이송됐다. 이후 심근경색 진단을 받고 스텐트 시술에 이어 에크모(ECMO·체외막산소공급장치) 치료를 받고 있다. 민주평통 등에 따르면 이 수석부의장은 전날보다는 호흡, 혈색 등이 다소 안정됐으나, 여전히 의식이 돌아오지 않는 위중한 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmakers prayed for the Senior Vice Chairman's swift recovery on this day. Party leader Chung Cheong-rae stated on Facebook, "I spoke with lawmaker Kim Hyun who is in Vietnam," and "He says Senior Vice Chairman Lee is currently in critical condition. I pray with all my heart for his swift recovery." Lawmaker Kim Kyo-heung also said on Facebook, "My heart is very heavy," and "He still has much work to do. I pray he recovers fully and returns." (민주당 의원들은 이날 이 수석부의장의 조속한 회복을 기원했다. 정청래 대표는 페이스북에 “베트남 현지에 있는 김현 의원과 통화했다”며 “이 수석부의장이 현재 위중한 상태라고 한다. 조속한 회복을 온 마음을 모아 빈다”고 밝혔다. 김교흥 의원도 페이스북에서 “마음이 매우 착잡하다”며 “아직 하실 일이 많다. 반드시 쾌차해서 돌아오기를 기도한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Seo Young-kyo said, "I hear Senior Vice Chairman Lee is regaining stability after surgery," adding, "That's fortunate, and I respect him." Lawmaker Seo Young-seok said, "I earnestly wish for the swift recovery of former party leader Lee Hae-chan, a great elder of our party." (서영교 의원은 “이 수석부의장이 수술 후 안정을 되찾고 있다고 한다”며 “다행이고 존경한다”고 했다. 서영석 의원은 “당의 큰 어른이신 이해찬 전 대표의 빠른 쾌유를 간절히 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A seven-term lawmaker who served as Democratic Party leader and Prime Minister, and is a leading senior figure within the party, Senior Vice Chairman Lee was appointed Senior Vice Chairman of the Democratic Peaceful Unification Advisory Council last October. Born in Cheongyang, South Chungcheong Province in 1952, he entered Seoul National University's Department of Sociology and became a first-generation student activist, plunging into the student movement following the October Yushin in 1972. As the 'Godfather of the Student Movement,' he has served as a spiritual pillar for the progressive camp. (7선 의원 출신으로 민주당 대표 및 국무총리까지 지낸 당내 대표 원로인 이 수석부의장은 작년 10월 민주평통 수석부의장으로 임명됐다. 1952년 충남 청양에서 태어난 그는 서울대 사회학과에 입학해 1972년 10월 유신을 계기로 학생운동에 투신한 1세대 운동권이다. ‘운동권 대부’로서 진보 진영에서 정신적 지주 역할을 해왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/DDZL5RGQEBDT5DKDZTFJOCRSMM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EUQH3VGGSRN6VIGTE2XHX2TIWM.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 04:04:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Koreans Only Think of Japan as an Object to Enjoy and Consume" (“한국인은 일본을 즐기고, 소비하는 대상으로만 생각한다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/25/6XKUFYXONJDLJKQQX73NOZSHTY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Koreans Only Think of Japan as an Object to Enjoy and Consume" (“한국인은 일본을 즐기고, 소비하는 대상으로만 생각한다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NH4RPX6L6FDI7I7HHYBWGD634E.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, a short post appeared on the Facebook of a Japanese diplomat I have known for a long time. "My report is late. Last November, I concluded 42 and a half years of service at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. It was a great fortune to have been able to meet and learn from many people in various places, and to introduce Japan and engage in negotiations. I am deeply grateful for the irreplaceable days in South Korea, China, the United States, Geneva, Dubai, Micronesia, and Bulgaria." (얼마 전 오래전부터 알고 지낸 일본 외교관의 페이스북에 짧은 글이 올라왔습니다. “보고가 늦었습니다. 작년 11월 42년 반의 외무성 근무를 마쳤습니다. 각지에서 많은 분을 만나고 배우고 일본을 알리고 교섭할 수 있었던 것은 큰 행운이었습니다. 한국, 중국, 미국, 제네바, 두바이, 미크로네시아, 불가리아와 둘도 없는 나날들에 크게 감사드립니다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The author of this post is Ambassador Michigami Hisashi, who retired after serving as Japan's Ambassador to Bulgaria. It was no coincidence that he mentioned South Korea first among the many countries where he served. It is because he served the longest in South Korea during his diplomatic career and developed special relationships with Koreans. (이 글을 쓴 이는 주불가리아 일본 대사를 마지막으로 은퇴한 미치가미 히사시(道上尚史) 대사. 그가 자신이 근무한 여러 나라 가운데 가장 먼저 한국을 언급한 것은 우연이 아닙니다. 그의 외교관 인생에서 한국에 가장 오래 근무하며 한국인들과 각별한 관계를 가져왔기 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;A 'Korean School' Member Who Studied at Seoul National University in the 1980s&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;1980년대 서울대 유학한 ‘코리안 스쿨’ &lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A graduate of the University of Tokyo's Faculty of Law, he became a diplomat in 1983 and studied in the Department of Diplomacy at Seoul National University in 1985. Later, he served at the Japanese Embassy in South Korea as First Secretary/Counselor from 1998 to 2000, and as Director of the Cultural Center/Minister-Counselor from 2011 to 2014. He was appointed Consul General in Busan in 2017, and in 2019, he served as Secretary-General of the Trilateral Cooperation Secretariat (TCS) among Korea, China, and Japan, working in Seoul. Including his studies at Seoul National University, he has lived in South Korea five times for over 10 years, observing Korea's changes for more than 40 years. Therefore, his retirement marks the departure of the most senior pro-Korean diplomat among the 'Korean School' within Japan's Ministry of Foreign Affairs. (도쿄대 법학부 출신인 그는 1983년 외교관이 된 후 1985년 서울대 외교학과에 유학했습니다. 이후 주한 일본 대사관에서 1998~2000년 1등 서기관·참사관으로, 2011~2014년에는 문화원장·총괄공사로 근무했습니다. 2017년 부산 총영사로 부임했고, 2019년에는 한·중·일 3국협력사무국(TCS) 사무총장을 맡아 서울에서 근무했습니다. 서울대 유학을 합치면 한국에서만 5차례, 10년 넘게 살면서 40년 넘게 한국의 변화를 지켜봐 왔습니다. 그렇기에 그의 은퇴는 일본 외무성 내 ‘코리안 스쿨’ 중에서 최고참 지한파 외교관의 퇴장이라고 할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I first met him in 2000 when he was serving as the Political Section Chief at the embassy as First Secretary. (제가 그를 처음 만난 것은 2000년, 그가 1등서기관으로 대사관 정무과장을 맡고 있을 때였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since starting as a political reporter for the Chosun Ilbo in 1999, I have met numerous Japanese diplomats, but he stands out in my memory for a reason. He is a contemporary of former Vice-Minister Mori Takeo and former Ambassador to South Korea Aiboshi Koichi, but evaluations of him inside and outside the Foreign Ministry are mixed. I have also met people who criticize him, saying he is "not like a Japanese diplomat." Ambassador Michigami is a diplomat with a strong personality to that extent, and he did not hesitate to offer straightforward advice to Korean society. In that he has maintained relatively good relationships with Koreans and offered advice beneficial to Korea, he contrasts with former Ambassador to South Korea Muto Masatoshi, who authored the book 'Lucky Not to Be Born Korean'. (1999년부터 조선일보 정치부 기자로 일하면서 수많은 일본 외교관을 만났지만, 유독 그가 기억에 남는 이유가 있습니다. 그는 모리 다케오(森健良) 전 차관, 아이보시 고이치(相星孝一)전 주한 일본대사와 동기인데 외무성 안팎에서의 평가가 엇갈립니다. “일본 외교관답지 않다”며 그를 비판하는 이들을 만나기도 했습니다. 미치가미 대사는 그만큼 개성이 강한 외교관인데, 한국 사회를 향해 직설적인 충고를 마다하지 않았습니다. 그가 한국인들과의 관계를 비교적 잘 유지하면서 한국에 도움이 되는 얘기를 해 왔다는 점에서 ‘한국인으로 태어나지 않아 다행이다(韓國人に生まれなくてよかった)’라는 책을 낸 무토 마사토시(武藤正敏) 전 주한 일본 대사와는 비교됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;"More Necessary Than Praise Is Uncomfortable Advice"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;“칭찬보다 필요한 것은 불편한 충고”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The preface of his 2016 book 'Japan and China, Which Only Koreans Don't Know' begins with the title 'Proposals for Korea's Future'. He says: "It is easy to heap praise, saying Korea is a wonderful country. But I think such praise has little meaning. So, I wrote frankly from the opposite direction instead." (그가 2016년 펴낸 ‘한국인만 모르는 일본과 중국’의 서문은 ‘한국의 미래를 위한 제언’이라는 제목으로 시작합니다. 그는 이렇게 말합니다. “한국은 멋진 나라라고 칭찬을 늘어놓기는 쉽다. 하지만 그런 칭찬은 큰 의미가 없다고 생각한다. 그래서 나는 오히려 반대 방향에서 솔직하게 썼다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even reading it now, ten years later, his critical awareness remains valid. He stated, "Whether Korea properly understands its neighboring countries, China and Japan, without being swept away by the atmosphere, determines Korea's national interest and future," adding, "Frankly speaking, it seems present-day Korea does not properly grasp not only Japan but also China." (10년이 지난 지금 읽어봐도 그의 문제의식은 여전히 유효합니다. “한국이 공기에 휩쓸리지 않고 인접국인 중국과 일본을 제대로 이해하는가의 여부가 한국의 국익과 미래를 좌우한다”며 “지금의 한국은 냉정히 말해 일본은 물론 중국도 제대로 파악하지 못하고 있는 것 같다”고 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His advice regarding Korea's perception of history reflects Japan's position but is worth heeding. "From the perspective of common sense in the international community, 'history' and 'national memory' are in tension, and correct history exists only at the point where simple national memory is overcome." This passage criticizes the atmosphere in Korean society, which, by being overly absorbed in the issue of Japanese colonial rule, labels future-oriented Korea-Japan cooperation as 'pro-Japanese'. (한국의 과거사 인식에 대한 그의 충고는 일본의 입장을 반영한 것이지만 새겨들을 만합니다. “국제사회의 상식으로 보면 ‘역사’와 ‘민족의 기억’은 긴장 관계에 있으며, 단순한 민족의 기억을 극복한 지점에 비로소 올바른 역사가 있다.” 한국 사회가 일제 식민지 문제에만 몰두해 미래 지향적 한일 협력을 ‘친일’로 몰아가는 분위기를 비판한 대목입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;'Dangerous Optimism' Published in Bungeishunju&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;문예춘추에 실린 ‘위험한 낙관론’&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ambassador Michigami expressed concern that as Korea's economic power rose to a level similar to Japan's, it was leading to a disregard for Japan. I remember an article he wrote for the November 2019 issue of 'Bungeishunju' during my time as a Tokyo correspondent. Its title was 'The True Nature of the Dangerous Optimism Sweeping Korea'. He wrote this article based on his experiences while serving as Consul General in Busan before taking up his post as Secretary-General of the Trilateral Cooperation Secretariat in Seoul. (미치가미 대사는 한국의 경제력이 일본과 비슷한 수준으로 올라서면서 일본을 경시하는 것을 우려했습니다. 제가 도쿄 특파원 시절인 2019년 그가 ‘문예춘추’ 11월호에 썼던 기고문을 기억합니다. 그 제목은 ‘한국을 뒤덮은 위험한 낙관론의 정체’. 그는 한중일 3국 협력 사무국 사무총장으로 서울에 부임하기 전에 부산 총영사로 재직하며 겪은 경험을 토대로 이 글을 썼습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He calmly describes tensions experienced by the consulate general due to issues like the Statue of Peace and the statue of forced labor victims, and even an incident in July 2019 where students reading materials in the consulate general's library suddenly went out to the courtyard to hold a brief anti-Japan protest. He points out the Moon Jae-in administration's politicization of anti-Japan sentiment, stating, "The very atmosphere of trying to study Japan is disappearing in Korean society." He wrote, "(For Koreans) Japan has now become merely an object for tourism and food," and "The trend of seriously researching and learning about Japanese industry, technology, law, administration, academia, and fashion as in the past has greatly diminished." (소녀상과 징용 노동자상 문제로 총영사관이 겪었던 긴장, 2019년 7월 총영사관 도서실에서 자료를 열람하던 학생들이 갑자기 마당으로 나와 짧은 반일 시위를 벌였던 일까지, 현장에서 느낀 일들을 담담하게 서술합니다. 그리고 그는 문재인 정부의 반일 정치화를 지적하며 “한국 사회에서 일본을 공부하려는 분위기 자체가 사라지고 있다”고 지적했습니다. “(한국인들에게) 일본은 이제 관광과 음식의 대상이 돼버렸다”며 “과거처럼 산업·기술·법률·행정·학문·패션을 진지하게 연구하며 배우려는 흐름은 크게 줄었다”고 썼습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also said this at meetings with Koreans: "There are people who say, 'I like sushi, I go to izakayas, I've traveled to Japan a lot, my children are studying Japanese, so I know Japan well. Our generation is not anti-Japanese.' But enjoying and consuming something and diplomacy toward Japan are separate issues." This was a criticism of Korean society for thinking of Japan only as an object of consumption. While those conducting in-depth research on Japan have noticeably decreased, the fact that the number of Korean visitors to Japan last year reached 9,459,600, approaching 10 million, shows his point was not wrong. (그는 한국인들과의 모임에서 이런 말도 했습니다. “‘나는 스시가 좋다, 이자카야에 간다, 일본 여행도 많이 가 봤다, 자식들이 일본어 공부한다, 그러니까 일본을 잘 안다. 우리 세대는 반일이 아니다’라고 말씀하시는 분들이 있어요. 하지만 즐기고 소비하는 것과 일본에 대한 외교는 별개 문제입니다.” 일본을 소비의 대상으로만 생각하는 한국 사회를 비판한 겁니다. 일본을 심층 연구하는 이들은 눈에 띄게 줄어드는데, 지난해 방일 한국인 여행객 수가 945만 9600명으로 1000만명에 육박한 것은 그의 지적이 틀리지 않았음을 보여줍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The 'Benkyokai' That Studies Korea Even on Holidays&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;휴일에도 한국 공부하는 ‘벤쿄카이’&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;His criticism struck me as very painful. It felt like a flaw in Korean society had been exposed. At that time, seen from Tokyo, unlike in Korea, Japanese society saw a noticeable increase in efforts to study Korea after the October 2018 South Korean Supreme Court ruling on forced labor compensation and the Abe cabinet's economic measures targeting Korea in July 2019. (저에게는 그의 비판이 매우 아프게 다가왔습니다. 한국 사회의 치부를 들킨 것 같은 생각이 들었습니다. 당시 도쿄에서 보니 한국과는 달리 일본 사회에서는 2018년 10월 한국 대법원의 징용 배상 판결과 2019년 7월 아베 내각의 한국을 겨냥한 경제 조치 이후, 한국을 공부하려는 움직임이 눈에 띄게 늘어났습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around that time, I was invited to a 'benkyokai' (study meeting) of Japanese intellectuals deeply interested in Korea-Japan relations. It was held on a Saturday, a day off, so I attended with a light heart but soon had to straighten my posture. When the presenter gave a comparative analysis of the two countries, saying, "While Japan values promises, Korea values justice," the about 20 attendees took diligent notes. (그즈음 한일 관계에 관심이 많은 일본 지식인들의 벤쿄카이(勉強会·공부 모임)에 초대받았을 때의 일입니다. 휴무(休務)인 토요일에 열린 모임이라 가벼운 마음으로 참석했다가 금세 자세를 가다듬어야 했습니다. 발표자가 “일본은 약속을 중시하는 반면 한국은 정의가 중요하다”며 양국을 비교 분석하자 20여 명의 참석자는 열심히 메모했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Their posture of listening intently, ears perked up to analyses of the Moon Jae-in administration and Korean society, even felt tense. One attendee even asked me, "What does 'nan-nan gatto' (South-South conflict) mean?" (문재인 정권과 한국 사회에 대한 분석에 귀를 쫑긋 세우고 경청하는 모습엔 긴장감마저 느껴졌습니다. 한 참석자는 “난난갓토(남남갈등·南南葛藤)가 무슨 뜻이냐”고 제게 물어보기도 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the Mainichi Shimbun, a partner newspaper of the Chosun Ilbo, a special in-house lecture was held by a mid-career journalist who had been dispatched as a Seoul correspondent. It was a benkyokai for reporters and staff, as many were curious about who President Moon Jae-in was and what Korea's ruling forces were like. (조선일보 제휴사인 마이니치 신문에서는 서울 특파원으로 파견됐던 중견 기자의 사내 특강이 열렸습니다. 문재인 대통령은 누구인지, 한국의 집권 세력은 어떤 이들인지에 대해 궁금해하는 이들이 많아 기자들과 직원들을 상대로 벤쿄카이를 연 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even a private commercial broadcaster, not NHK, aired a two-hour special on Korea-Japan relations during prime weekend time. Articles related to Korea consistently appeared in Japanese weekly and monthly magazines, leading to the side effect of connecting to provocative 'Kenkan' (anti-Korea) articles. (NHK도 아닌 민영 상업 방송이 주말 황금 시간대에 한일 관계를 2시간 동안 다룬 기획을 방영하기도 했습니다. 일본의 주간지, 월간지에는 한국 관련 기사가 빠지지 않고 등장하면서 자극적인 혐한(嫌韓) 기사로 연결되는 부작용도 나왔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Korea Must Deal with Japan with a Long-Term Strategy&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;한국은 장기 전략 갖고 일본 다뤄야&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Korean correspondents in Tokyo often received requests to explain Korea's current situation whenever they met Japanese people. Thanks to that, for a while, I frequently had to explain the meaning of 'sekihi seisan' (settling past wrongs), which was unfamiliar in Japan. (도쿄의 한국 특파원들은 일본인들을 만날 때마다 한국의 현 상황을 설명해 달라는 요청을 많이 받았습니다. 그 덕분에 한동안 일본에서는 생소한 ‘세키헤이세산(적폐청산·積弊淸算)’의 뜻을 자주 설명해줘야 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I once gave a special lecture to about ten Japanese university students invited by the Japan-Korea Exchange Foundation. Concluding the lecture, I said, "If you have any questions, please send me an email." I then received specific questions from three of them about Korean lawmakers' interest in Japan, Korean youth's political participation, etc., and replied. Japanese society seemed to show an atmosphere of wanting to study Korea rather than getting agitated over the forced labor ruling, while in Korea, it seemed more energy was poured into criticizing Japan and severing contact with it, which was regrettable. (일한교류기금 초청으로 일본의 대학생 10여 명을 대상으로 특강을 한 적이 있습니다. 특강을 마치면서 “궁금한 것이 있으면 이메일을 보내 달라”고 했습니다. 그랬더니 세 명에게서 한국 국회의원의 일본에 대한 관심, 한국 젊은이들의 정치 참여 등에 대해 구체적인 질문을 받아 답장해줬습니다. 일본 사회는 징용 배상 판결에 흥분하기보다는 한국을 공부하려는 분위기가 엿보이는데, 한국에서는 일본을 비난하고 일본과의 접촉을 끊는 데 더 많은 에너지를 쏟는 것처럼 보여 안타까웠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the contrasting situations of the two countries in mind, Ambassador Michigami has pointed out that Korea shows no sign of making efforts to meticulously study and manage Japan at the national level. Japan is one of the key variables in Korea's diplomacy, security, and economy, yet Korea only repeats immediate reactions and backlash without a long-term strategy. His frank advice is uncomfortable but remains a warning that must be heeded. Next time we meet, instead of his harsh words, I would like to hear him say, "Japan should be nervous about Korean society's studious attitude." (미치가미 대사는 양국의 대비되는 모습을 염두에 두고, 한국이 국가 차원에서 일본을 치밀하게 연구하고 관리하려는 노력이 보이지 않는 점을 지적해 왔습니다. 일본은 한국의 외교·안보·경제에서 핵심 변수 중 하나인데, 장기 전략 없이 즉각적인 반응과 반발만 반복하고 있다는 것입니다. 그의 솔직한 충고는 불편하지만, 새겨들어야 할 경고로 남아 있습니다. 다시 만날 때는 그의 쓴소리 대신 “한국 사회의 공부하는 모습에 일본이 긴장해야겠다”는 말을 듣고 싶습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; ()&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/25/6XKUFYXONJDLJKQQX73NOZSHTY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NH4RPX6L6FDI7I7HHYBWGD634E.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Moo-sung: "Korean Politics Was Ruined by the Racket of Nominations" (김무성 “한국 정치는 공천 장사가 망쳤다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/25/56KHR2YHNVGDFJWENSLG3WHYTE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Moo-sung: "Korean Politics Was Ruined by the Racket of Nominations" (김무성 “한국 정치는 공천 장사가 망쳤다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVRTIZBUMNTGINJXMJSGKMRUHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The core of the controversy surrounding Democratic Party of Korea lawmakers Kang Sun-woo and Kim Byeong-gi is simple. It's that they held the power to nominate candidates for local councilors and heads of local governments in their districts and engaged in selling positions. The political culture of secretly deciding candidates behind closed doors under the pretext of 'strategic nominations' has resurfaced. There is a figure who foresaw this kind of thing long ago. It's former Saenuri Party leader Kim Moo-sung (74), who throughout his political journey considered 'bottom-up nominations' his lifelong goal. (더불어민주당 강선우·김병기 의원을 둘러싼 논란의 핵심은 간단하다. 지역구 지방의원과 자치단체장 공천권을 쥐고 매관매직을 했다는 것이다. 전략공천이라는 명분으로 밀실에서 후보자를 결정하던 정치문화가 다시 수면 위로 떠올랐다. 오래전부터 이 같은 일을 예견한 인물이 있다. 정치 여정 내내 ‘상향식 공천’을 숙원으로 여겼던 김무성(74) 전 새누리당 대표다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although former leader Kim was considered a representative figure of factional politics like the pro-Lee and pro-Park factions during his active career, he also pushed for revisions to election laws, such as fully open national primaries and 'safe number' opinion polls. The unprecedented 'State Seal Scandal' also arose from opposition to government and ruling party interference in nominations. Meeting with Weekly Chosun, he raised his voice, saying, "What ruins Korean politics is precisely this racket of nominations," and he did not hold back his blunt criticism regarding recent political issues. Regarding the People Power Party maintaining a hardline stance, he said, "If things continue like this, they will suffer a crushing defeat in the local elections," and he also expressed without hesitation his opinion that the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon was excessive. We met him on January 20th at the Chosun News Press conference room in Sangam-dong, Seoul. (김 전 대표는 현역 시절 친이·친박 등 계파 정치의 대표격 인물로 여겨지기도 했지만, 완전국민경선과 안심번호 여론조사 등 선거법 개정을 추진하기도 했다. 희대의 ‘옥새 파동’도 정부·여당의 공천 개입에 반발해 생긴 사건이다. 주간조선과 만나 “한국 정치를 망치는 것이 바로 이 공천 장사”라고 목소리를 높인 그는 최근 정치 현안에도 쓴소리를 아끼지 않았다. 국민의힘이 강경 노선을 유지하는 데 대해 “이대로면 지방선거에서 참패할 것”이라며, 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명 처분은 과하다는 의견도 스스럼없이 냈다. 그를 지난 1월 20일 서울 상암동 조선뉴스프레스 회의실에서 만났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;"Bottom-up nominations since my first term"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;“초선 때부터 상향식 공천”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- The public is in an uproar over Kang Sun-woo and Kim Byeong-gi.&lt;/b&gt; "I've received many interview requests but have declined them all. The reason I agreed to this interview is because you specifically asked to 'talk about nominations.' In the world we live in, corruption is inevitable, especially where there is power. That's why there are checks and balances on power, like the separation of powers. However, South Korea is the country with the strongest presidential power among presidential systems. When such strong power exercises nomination rights, corruption is inevitable. The president may not directly receive money, but as great power descends, those in the middle take money. That's our politics." (&lt;b&gt;- 세간이 강선우와 김병기로 시끄러운데. &lt;/b&gt;“여러 취재 요청이 들어오지만 일절 하지 않았다. 인터뷰에 응한 이유는 당신이 ‘공천 이야기를 해달라’고 콕 집었기 때문이다. 사람 사는 세상에 부정은 있기 마련인데 특히 권력이 있는 곳에는 필연적이다. 그래서 삼권분립처럼 권력을 견제하는 장치가 있는 것인데, 우리나라는 대통령제 국가 중 대통령의 힘이 제일 센 나라다. 이렇게 강한 권력이 공천권을 행사하니 부정이 있을 수밖에 없다. 대통령이 직접 돈을 받지야 않겠지만, 큰 권력이 내려오면서 중간에 있는 자들이 돈을 받는다. 그게 우리 정치다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You served six terms in Busan alone, so you must see 'what they do' clearly.&lt;/b&gt; "It's obvious. Local elections are the rice bowls of National Assembly members. Since my first term, I've done all nominations bottom-up. I have nothing else to boast about, but this one thing I can be proud of." (&lt;b&gt;- 부산에서만 6선을 했는데, ‘하는 짓’들이 훤히 보이겠다. &lt;/b&gt;“뻔하지. 지방선거는 국회의원들의 밥그릇이다. 나는 초선 때부터 전부 상향식 공천을 했다. 나는 다른 건 자랑할 게 없지만, 이것 하나만은 자랑할 수 있다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- How did you do it?&lt;/b&gt; "I made them all conduct opinion polls. I gathered all the candidates by region and chaired the meeting, saying, 'I won't designate anyone. Agree to decide by opinion poll. Otherwise, I won't give you a chance.' Doesn't conducting an opinion poll cost money? After reaching an agreement to split the cost N-ways, I nominated based on the results. That's why there's been no noise until now. Of course, there were people who brought money. Once, someone came with a trunk full of 10,000-won bills, asking to be made district mayor. He said he'd leave the car keys and told me to handle it. I said, 'If you don't take it back, I'll report you,' and sent him away." (&lt;b&gt;- 어떻게 했나. &lt;/b&gt;“다 여론조사를 돌리게 했다. 출마자들을 지역별로 모두 모아 내가 회의를 주재해서, ‘나는 지명하지 않는다. 여론조사로 결정하자고 합의하라. 아니면 기회를 주지 않겠다’고 했다. 여론조사를 하면 돈이 들어가지 않나. 그 돈을 N분의1로 내자는 합의를 낸 뒤 결과에 따라 공천했다. 그러니까 여태 아무 잡음이 없잖나. 물론 돈 싸들고 오는 사람도 있었다. 한번은 구청장 시켜달라고 트렁크에 1만원짜리를 가득 싣고 오더라. 차 열쇠를 놓고 갈 테니 알아서 하라고. 내가 ‘도로 안 가져가면 고발하겠다’고 해서 보냈다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- There are also opinion poll operators like Myeong Tae-gyun. There must be side effects.&lt;/b&gt; "That's an excuse from those who oppose bottom-up nominations to make money. No system in the world is perfect. It's a matter of probability. In the past, they voted with delegates. When a few hundred electors vote, you only need to buy half of them to get elected, right? So, you need to broaden the scope. That's the open primary." (&lt;b&gt;- 명태균 같은 여론조사 업자도 있다. 부작용이 없지 않을 텐데. &lt;/b&gt;“그건 상향식 공천을 반대해서 돈 벌겠다는 놈들의 핑계다. 세상에 무슨 제도든 완벽하진 않다. 가능성의 문제지. 과거에는 대의원 투표를 했다. 몇백 명에 불과한 선거인단이 투표하면, 그 절반만 매수하면 당선되는 것 아닌가. 그러니 범위를 넓혀야지. 그게 오픈 프라이머리고.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Do you still see that as the answer?&lt;/b&gt; "Nominations are about finding who is most competitive in that region. Then shouldn't you ask the voters?" (&lt;b&gt;- 지금도 그게 해답이라고 보나. &lt;/b&gt;“공천이란 그 지역에서 누가 가장 경쟁력이 있는지 찾는 거다. 그럼 유권자에게 물어봐야 하는 것 아닌가.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- In 2015, when you were party leader, you partially implemented bottom-up nominations.&lt;/b&gt; "During the party leader election, my slogan was to take the nomination power from the powerful and return it to the people. I was elected because of that, so shouldn't I keep the promise? I set the primary rules with a 50% party member, 50% public opinion poll ratio. Responsible party members 20%, general party members 30%, direct voting by a national electoral college 30%, opinion poll 20%." (&lt;b&gt;- 2015년 당 대표 당시 상향식 공천을 일부는 관철했다. &lt;/b&gt;“당 대표 선거 때 공천권을 권력자로부터 빼앗아 국민에게 돌려드리겠다는 게 내 슬로건이었다. 그것 때문에 당선됐으니 약속을 지켜야 할 것 아닌가. 당원 50%, 국민 50% 비율 여론조사로 경선 룰을 정했다. 책임당원 20%, 일반당원 30%, 국민 선거인단 직접 투표 30%, 여론조사 20%.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- There was strong opposition.&lt;/b&gt; "The pro-Park faction rushed at me with tremendous insults. Saying Kim Moo-sung is doing this to create his own party. When the opposition party and I agreed to change the election law and introduce safe numbers, President Park, through her chief of public relations, vilified me, saying, 'He goes around doing things like that.'" (&lt;b&gt;- 반발이 컸다. &lt;/b&gt;“친박들이 나한테 엄청난 모욕을 하며 달려들었다. 김무성이 자기 당 만들려고 이런다고. 박 대통령은 야당과 내가 선거법을 바꿔 안심번호를 도입하기로 합의하자 홍보수석을 통해 ‘그런 거나 하고 다닌다’고 나를 매도했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;"I never benefited from nominations"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;“공천으로 덕 본 일 없다”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After becoming the Saenuri Party leader in July 2015, former leader Kim argued that the ruling and opposition parties should hold open national primary-style nominations for the general election on the same day. However, an agreement with the opposition party (New Politics Alliance for Democracy) fell through, and most importantly, the Blue House opposed it. Eventually, former leader Kim stepped back to 'safe number opinion poll nominations,' but the Blue House did not relinquish its will to exercise nomination power. After her impeachment, President Park was found guilty of election law violations for this nomination interference. (김 전 대표는 2015년 7월 새누리당 대표가 된 이후 여야가 총선 공천을 개방형 국민경선 형태로 같은 날에 하자고 주장했었다. 그러나 야당(새정치민주연합)과 합의도 불발됐고, 무엇보다 청와대가 반대했다. 결국 김 전 대표는 ‘안심번호 여론조사 공천’으로 물러섰지만, 청와대는 공천권을 행사하려는 의지를 놓지 않았다. 박 대통령은 파면 뒤 이때의 공천 개입으로 선거법 유죄를 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- What was the opposition party's reaction?&lt;/b&gt; "During Chuseok in 2015, I met Moon Jae-in (then leader of the New Politics Alliance for Democracy) who came down to Busan. We agreed to change the election law and introduce safe numbers. The concept of safe number opinion polls, where phone numbers are kept private, was created for the first time. However, since Moon Jae-in's own pledge when becoming party leader was open primaries, I asked him to accept that too. But he said, 'There are about 30% of people in our party that we need to weed out, so we can't.'" (&lt;b&gt;- 야당의 반응은 어땠나.&lt;/b&gt; “2015년 추석 때 부산에 내려간 문재인(당시 새정치민주연합 대표)과 만났다. 선거법을 바꿔 안심번호를 도입하기로 합의했다. 전화번호가 비공개되는 안심번호 여론조사라는 개념이 처음 만들어진 거다. 그런데 문재인 본인도 당 대표가 될 때 공약이 오픈 프라이머리였으니, 내가 그것도 받아달라고 했다. 그런데 그가 하는 말이 ‘우리 당에는 한 30% 정도 쳐내야 하는 사람들이 있어서 안 된다’는 거다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- President Moon said that?&lt;/b&gt; "Yes. This was slightly before Chuseok. There was a Blue House meeting I arranged (March 17, 2015, three-way meeting between Park Geun-hye, Moon Jae-in, and Kim Moo-sung). After the meeting, when making the announcement, I called Representative Moon aside for a talk, and he said that. Does that make sense? Who weeds out whom? By what right?" (&lt;b&gt;- 문 대통령이? &lt;/b&gt;“그렇다. 이건 추석보다 약간 앞의 일이다. 내가 주선한 청와대 회담(2015년 3월 17일, 박근혜·문재인·김무성 3자 회담)이 있었거든. 회담이 끝나고 발표문을 만들 때 문 대표를 불러 구석에서 이야기를 했더니 그러더라. 그게 말이 되는 소리인가. 누가 누구를 쳐내나. 무슨 자격으로.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Eventually, the Blue House tapped Representative Lee Han-gu as the nomination management committee chairman.&lt;/b&gt; "During the collective leadership period, only Representative Kim Eul-dong sided with me. The pro-Park supreme council members pressured me, so I had no choice but to approve Lee Han-gu. Then his first statement was, 'The party leader may not even get a nomination.' The nomination turmoil started that day. The very act of discussing who gets a nomination or not was against the principle from the start." (&lt;b&gt;- 결국 청와대는 이한구 의원을 공천관리위원장으로 찍었다. &lt;/b&gt;“집단지도체제 시절, 내 편을 들어주는 건 김을동 의원뿐이었다. 친박 일색 최고위원들이 재촉하기에 어쩔 수 없이 이한구를 의결했다. 그랬더니 첫 일성이 ‘당 대표도 공천 주지 않을 수도 있다’는 거다. 공천 파동은 그날로 시작된 거다. 공천을 누굴 주니 마니 하는 것부터 취지에 안 맞는 것이었다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Rumors also circulated about the existence of a blacklist.&lt;/b&gt; "It's all true. Someone from the Blue House came saying, 'I obtained a blacklist of 42 people for nominations.' Saying, 'These XXs, (even though the people on the list did well by the president) they are bad people.' The late Representative Jeong Doo-un was on the list. I sat him down in the main assembly hall and said, 'They made this over there, but I'll block it, so don't worry.' But Representative Jeong spilled it to the press, and I took all the blame. However, I had to protect the person who gave me the information, so I kept my mouth shut." (&lt;b&gt;- 살생부의 존재도 나돌았다. &lt;/b&gt;“다 사실이다. 청와대의 누군가 ‘공천 살생부 42명 명단을 입수했다’며 왔다. ‘이 XX들, (명단에 있는 사람들이 대통령한테 잘했는데) 나쁜 놈들입니다’라면서. 명단에 고(故) 정두언 의원이 있더라. 본회의장에서 앉혀 놓고 ‘저쪽에서 이런 걸 만들었는데, 내가 막을 테니 걱정 마라’고 했다. 그런데 정 의원이 이를 언론에 터뜨리며 내가 다 뒤집어썼다. 하지만 내게 정보 준 사람을 보호해야 하니 입을 다물었지.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- How did the Blue House demand nomination rights?&lt;/b&gt; "The Blue House said, 'Shouldn't Halmae (Park Geun-hye) use her power stably after retirement?' and asked for the nomination rights for Daegu and North Gyeongsang Province. When I said no, they asked for at least Daegu. Does it make sense for a retiring president to exercise nomination rights?" (&lt;b&gt;- 청와대에서 공천권을 어떻게 요구했나. &lt;/b&gt;“청와대에서 ‘할매(박근혜)가 퇴임 이후에 안정적으로 힘을 써야 안 되겠습니까?’ 하면서 대구·경북 공천권을 달라더라. 안 된다고 했더니 대구만이라도 달라더라. 퇴임하는 대통령이 공천권을 행사한다는 게 말이 되는 소린가?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- The president is in a position to bear sole responsibility for state affairs; realistically, can they not be involved in nominations?&lt;/b&gt; "Our constitution is liberal democracy; is it democracy for the president to intervene in nominations?" (&lt;b&gt;- 대통령은 국정 운영에 대한 책임을 혼자 지는 입장인데, 현실적으로 공천에 관여하지 않을 수 있나.&lt;/b&gt; “우리 헌법이 자유민주주의인데, 대통령이 공천에 개입하는 게 민주주의인가?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You also receive evaluations of being a main player in factional politics.&lt;/b&gt; "I never created a faction. Have you ever heard of a 'Mudae faction'? If you do the right thing, everyone follows; why should I only take a few with me?" (&lt;b&gt;- 계파 정치의 장본인이라는 평도 듣는데. &lt;/b&gt;“나는 계파를 만든 일이 없다. ‘무대계’라는 이름 들어본 적 있나? 옳은 일을 하면 다 따라오게 돼 있는데, 왜 일부만 데리고 가야 하나?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Haven't you ever benefited from nominations?&lt;/b&gt; "No one has suffered from nominations like I have. I failed to get nominations twice, during both the Lee Myung-bak and Park Geun-hye administrations. During former President Lee's time, there was a 'pro-Park massacre,' but I was elected by causing a pro-Park independent wind. Next, when Park Geun-hye became emergency committee chairperson, there was a 'pro-Lee massacre.' I considered running with 35 seats but refrained due to concerns about right-wing division. And then they put me in charge of presidential election command." (&lt;b&gt;- 공천에서 덕 본 일이 없나. &lt;/b&gt;“나처럼 공천으로 고생한 사람이 없다. 이명박·박근혜 정부 두 번 다 공천을 못 받았다. 이 전 대통령 때는 ‘친박 학살’이 있었지만 친박 무소속 돌풍을 일으켜 당선됐다. 그다음 박근혜가 비상대책위원장이 되니 또 ‘친이 학살’을 했다. 35석을 데리고 나오려다 우파 분열을 우려해 불출마했다. 그래놓고 대선 지휘를 맡기더라.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Have you ever influenced nominations?&lt;/b&gt; "I have never influenced nominations for even one person close to me. Even now, I'm criticized for having no loyalty. I never created a 'mess.'" (&lt;b&gt;- 공천에 영향을 준 적도 없나. &lt;/b&gt;“나는 가까운 사람들 한 명도 공천에 영향을 미친 적이 없다. 지금까지도 의리가 없다고 욕을 먹는다. 나는 ‘개판’ 만든 일 없다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You were elected by moving districts in the first by-election of the new government.&lt;/b&gt; "I didn't get it for free. On the evening of former President Park's inauguration day, they told me to come to a party for foreign guests. When leaving, I was the last to greet the president. Holding hands for a handshake, I said this: 'I'm going down to Yeongdo tonight. I won't ask for a nomination. Give me a primary. Otherwise, I won't stay quiet.' When I went down to Yeongdo, all the existing preliminary candidates gave up." (&lt;b&gt;- 새 정부 첫 보궐선거에서 지역구를 옮겨 당선됐는데. &lt;/b&gt;“공짜로 얻은 게 아니다. 박 전 대통령 취임식 날 저녁 외빈들을 위한 파티에 오라더라. 퇴장할 때 내가 마지막으로 대통령과 인사했다. 손잡고 악수하면서 이랬다. ‘나 오늘 밤에 영도 내려갑니다. 공천 달라는 말 안 하겠습니다. 경선을 붙여주시오. 안 그러면 가만히 있지 않겠습니다’ 내가 영도에 내려가니 기존 예비후보들이 모두 포기했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Still, you were once classified as 'pro-Lee' or 'pro-Park.'&lt;/b&gt; "The media gave those names. In 2008, I failed to get a nomination from President Lee Myung-bak and was elected as an independent. When I returned to the party, they told me to become a political affairs minister to handle the candlelight protest situation. I refused. Not long after, they told me to become floor leader. I did that. Isn't it a comedy? He didn't give me a nomination, then gave me a minister position and floor leader position. During President Park Geun-hye's time, as party leader, to appoint balanced personnel, I made a person the president favored into a spokesperson. Then the Blue House called that person a 'traitor' and eliminated them in the next nomination. They're ridiculous people. That's why they fail." (&lt;b&gt;- 그래도 한때 ‘친이’나 ‘친박’으로 분류됐다. &lt;/b&gt;“언론에서 이름을 붙인 거다. 2008년 이명박 대통령으로부터 공천 못 받아 무소속 당선됐다. 복당했더니 촛불정국 수습할 정무장관을 하라고 하더라. 안 했다. 얼마 안 있다가는 원내대표를 하라더라. 그건 했다. 코미디 아닌가? 자기가 공천 안 주더니 장관도 주고 원내대표도 주고. 박근혜 대통령 때는 대표로서 탕평 인사를 하려고 대통령이 귀여워하는 인물을 대변인을 시켰다. 그랬더니 청와대가 ‘배신자’라며 그 사람을 다음 공천에서 탈락시켰다. 웃기는 사람들이다. 그러니까 망하지.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Why did you have such a bad relationship with former President Park?&lt;/b&gt; "If you judge the contributions to Park Geun-hye's election, I am number one, with no second, third, fourth, or fifth. Still, I didn't grovel. Elders born in 1937-1938 acted towards Park Geun-hye, who was about five or six years younger, as if she were President Park Chung-hee. I didn't bow my head. As a political comrade, I helped make her president; why should I do that? However, Park Geun-hye is a polite person, and I am a straightforward Gyeongsang Province person. Once, in front of others, I said 'thorny,' and then people around her slandered me, saying Kim Moo-sung always goes around like that. She fell for that and became wary of me, so I left without regret. The decisive moment was clashing over the Sejong City issue in 2009." (&lt;b&gt;- 박 전 대통령과는 왜 그리 안 좋았나. &lt;/b&gt;“박근혜 당선의 공과로 따지면 나는 2, 3, 4, 5등도 없는 1등이다. 그래도 굽신거리지 않았다. 1937~1938년생 선배들이 열대여섯 살 밑의 박근혜에게 박정희 대하듯이 하더라. 나는 고개 안 숙였다. 정치적 동지로서 대통령 만들어줬는데 왜 그래야 하나. 다만 박근혜는 예의 바른 사람이고, 나는 직선적인 경상도 사람이다. 내가 다른 사람 앞에서 한번 ‘가시나’라고 했더니, 김무성이 맨날 그러고 다닌다고 주변에서 모함을 하더라. 거기에 넘어가 나를 경계하니 미련 없이 그냥 떠나버린 거지. 2009년 세종시 문제로 부딪친 게 결정적이었고.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;"Recruitment proposal? Not a single phone call"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;“영입 제안? 전화 한 통 없었다”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- How should a large ruling party be checked?&lt;/b&gt; "If we lost the election because we were wrong, we should acknowledge that we are a minority opposition party and compromise. Out of 10 bad bills, we should remove at least 3. But they just insist on 'all or nothing' and walk out. Then all 10 get passed." (&lt;b&gt;- 거대 여당을 어떻게 견제해야 하나. &lt;/b&gt;“우리가 잘못해서 선거에 졌으면 우리가 소수 야당이란 걸 인정하고 타협해야 한다. 10개의 악법 중에 3개라도 빼야지. 그런데 ‘올 오어 낫싱(all or nothing)’으로 주장만 하고 퇴장하지 않나. 그럼 10개가 통과되는 거다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You strongly opposed the National Assembly Advancement Act.&lt;/b&gt; "On the contrary, compromise was possible when there was no Advancement Act; now, only the principle of majority rule is applied completely. In the past, there was such a thing as legislative tyranny, wasn't there? Now, bad bills are just getting passed. Majority rule is also democracy, but consensus democracy is a higher level." (&lt;b&gt;- 국회선진화법을 강하게 반대했었다. &lt;/b&gt;“오히려 선진화법이 없을 땐 타협이 가능했는데, 지금은 완전히 다수결의 원칙만 적용된다. 예전엔 입법 횡포라는 게 없지 않았나. 지금은 악법이 막 통과되고 있다. 다수결도 민주주의지만 합의 민주주의가 한 단계 높은 차원이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- How did you lead compromise before the Advancement Act?&lt;/b&gt; "I was the ruling party floor leader. You have to save the face of the opposition party. Isn't that what politics is? I saved all of Park Ji-won's (then floor leader) face. President Lee Myung-bak called and said, 'Aren't you getting beaten up?' but I said we were getting all the practical benefits, so not to worry. Since I took care of what needed to be taken care of, the president later praised me highly. Also, former President Lee was someone who would call frequently to have a drink of makgeolli. We met often and talked. Former President Park didn't meet me..." (&lt;b&gt;- 선진화법 이전엔 어떻게 타협을 이끌었나. &lt;/b&gt;“나는 여당 원내대표였다. 야당의 체면을 살려줘야지. 정치라는 게 그런 거 아닌가? 박지원(당시 원내대표)의 체면을 내가 다 살려줬다. 이명박 대통령이 전화해 ‘판판이 당하는 거 아니냐’고 했지만, 실리를 다 취하고 있으니 걱정 말라고 했다. 챙길 걸 챙기니 나중에는 대통령이 극찬하더라. 또 이 전 대통령은 수시로 전화해서 막걸리 한잔하자던 사람이다. 자주 만나서 대화를 했다. 박 전 대통령은 안 만나줬고….”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You also met with opposition lawmakers over makgeolli.&lt;/b&gt; "That's right. A prime example is dramatically reaching an agreement to pass the Korea-EU FTA (Free Trade Agreement). It wouldn't have happened without me. If this hadn't happened, the Korea-US FTA wouldn't have happened either." (&lt;b&gt;- 야당 의원들하고도 막걸리로 만났다. &lt;/b&gt;“그렇지. 대표적인 게 한·EU FTA(자유무역협정)를 극적으로 합의 통과시킨 거다. 내가 아니면 안 됐다. 이게 안 되면 한·미 FTA도 안 되는 거였다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Speaking of which, Representative Park Ji-won recently opposed the story that 'the Blue House is also recruiting Kim Moo-sung.' Haven't you ever received an offer to join the cabinet?&lt;/b&gt; "Shouldn't they at least make one phone call to me (about that kind of thing)?" (&lt;b&gt;- 얘기가 나와서 말인데, 박지원 의원은 최근 ‘청와대가 김무성도 영입한다’는 이야기에 반대한다더라. 입각 제의를 받은 적 없나. &lt;/b&gt;“그런 건 나한테 전화 한 통화라도 놓고(하고) 해야 할 것 아니냐고.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Not even once?&lt;/b&gt; "They don't dare make that kind of call to me." (&lt;b&gt;- 한 번도 없었나. &lt;/b&gt;“나한테는 그런 전화 할 엄두를 못 낸다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Your evaluation of President Yoon Suk-yeol?&lt;/b&gt; "From the perspective of 'doing politics,' I view him positively. Leftist policies are a big mistake. The most important thing in running a country is economic growth. The Yellow Envelope Act, revisions to the Commercial Act, etc., are regressing the economy. It's also wrong to pass legislation that damages the spirit of the separation of powers and infringes on the judiciary. He won't be able to continue like this. It's a path of self-destruction that history will prove." (&lt;b&gt;- 이재명 대통령에 대한 평가는. &lt;/b&gt;“‘정치를 한다’는 측면에서는 좋게 본다. 좌파 정책은 큰 잘못이다. 국가 운영에 제일 중요한 게 경제 성장이다. 노란봉투법, 상법 개정 등은 경제를 퇴보시키는 것이다. 삼권분립 정신을 훼손시키고 사법부를 침해하는 입법을 하는 것도 잘못됐다. 그대로 못 갈 것이다. 역사가 증명하는 자멸의 길이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- What do you mean by 'doing politics'?&lt;/b&gt; "Because he keeps trying to have dialogue. (However) The president also became president riding on the Gyeonggi Eastern Union and the Korean Confederation of Trade Unions, so can he not be mindful of them? We need to watch a bit more. He is a person who came this far with a philosophy of survival. Shuttle diplomacy? The term isn't good, but it's correct. Since we are a small-to-medium country sandwiched between great powers, to survive, we have to be mindful of both sides. We have to go that way with pragmatism." (&lt;b&gt;- 정치를 한다는 게 무슨 뜻인가. &lt;/b&gt;“대화를 자꾸 하려고 하니까. (다만) 대통령도 지금 경기동부연합하고 민주노총에 업혀 대통령이 됐는데, 그 눈치를 안 볼 수 있나. 우리가 좀 더 지켜봐야지. 그는 생존 철학으로 여기까지 온 사람이다. 셰셰 외교? 용어는 안 좋지만 맞는 말이다. 우리가 강대국 사이에 끼어 있는 중소국이니, 살려면 양쪽 눈치를 다 봐야 한다. 그렇게 실용주의로 가야 한다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;"Han Dong-hoon's expulsion is wrong... a path to defeat even while knowing it"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;“한동훈 제명은 잘못… 알면서도 지는 길”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- The People Power Party's local election planning team set 'party sentiment 70%' as the basic framework.&lt;/b&gt; "Isn't a basketball game 5 on 5? But before a basketball game, does it make sense to say let's play 7 on 3? It's the same when electing a party leader. Breaking away from Yoon Suk-yeol is public sentiment, right? But the people who said they wouldn't do that (Jang Dong-hyeok, Kim Moon-soo) came in first and second in the last leadership election, right? Wasn't that created in an 8 to 2 structure? Do the people like a party controlled by the far-right?" (&lt;b&gt;- 국민의힘 지방선거 기획단이 ‘당심 70%’를 기본 틀로 삼았는데. “&lt;/b&gt;농구 경기가 5 대 5 아닌가. 근데 농구 경기를 앞두고 7 대 3으로 하자는 게 말이 되나. 당 대표를 뽑을 때도 마찬가지다. 윤석열과 절연하는 게 민심이잖나. 근데 그러지 않겠다는 사람들(장동혁, 김문수)이 지난 대표 선거에서 1등, 2등 했잖나. 그게 8 대 2 구도로 만들어진 것 아닌가. 극우가 장악한 당을 국민들이 좋아하나?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- How did you reconcile conflicts within the party during your active career?&lt;/b&gt; "Politics is originally noisy. Preventing people from speaking is political oppression. A living party is one where opponents can vigorously criticize. You have to leave that be; if you prevent it, they'll do it outside. Even if you listen to everything and are insulted, you endure it, respond with a smile and no answer, laugh and move on. Then you persuade them. After they finish cursing, that person feels relieved. If you persuade them then, they are ready to agree. Politics is about compromising. But what's this about expelling Han Dong-hoon? Does this make sense?" (&lt;b&gt;- 현역 시절 당내 갈등은 어떻게 융합했나. &lt;/b&gt;“원래 시끄러운 게 정치다. 말을 못하게 하면 정치 탄압이다. 반대파들이 막 신나게 비판을 할 수 있어야 살아있는 정당이다. 그걸 놔둬야지, 못하게 하면 밖에 나가서 한다니까. 다 듣고 모욕을 줘도 참고, 소이부답(笑而不答)으로 웃고 넘어가는 거다. 그다음에 설득을 하는 거다. 욕해놓고 나면 그 사람은 속 시원하거든. 그때 설득하면 응하게 돼 있다. 타협해서 하는 게 정치다. 그런데 무슨 한동훈 제명? 이게 말이 되는 소린가?”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- Do you think former leader Han's expulsion was wrong?&lt;/b&gt; "It's not something that warrants expulsion, is it? Former leader Han claimed he did nothing wrong, so it should be clarified." (&lt;b&gt;- 한 전 대표 제명이 잘못됐다고 보나. &lt;/b&gt;“제명까지 할 일이 아니잖나. 한 전 대표는 잘못이 없다고 주장을 했으니 밝혀야지.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- The People Power Party is changing its name again. How should it reform?&lt;/b&gt; "It must practice party democracy. Now, expelling former leader Han and placing radical people on the ethics committee... It's already undemocratic. I am not someone who intends to defend former leader Han. Also, ideology is important for a party, but in the AI era, using the existing left-right concept as is is out of sync with the times. We should have taken 'centrist pragmatism' first, but this president preempted it. The party's future lies in going that route. It must change to a bottom-up nomination system." (&lt;b&gt;- 국민의힘이 당명을 또 바꾼다. 어떻게 쇄신해야 하나. &lt;/b&gt;“정당 민주주의를 실천해야 한다. 지금 한 전 대표를 제명시키고 윤리위원회에 과격한 사람들을 갖다 놓고… 벌써 비민주적이다. 나는 한 전 대표를 두둔할 생각이 없는 사람이다. 또 정당은 이념이 중요한데, AI 시대에 기존의 좌우 개념을 그대로 쓰는 것은 시대에 안 맞는다. ‘중도 실용주의’를 우리가 먼저 가져갔어야 하는데 이 대통령이 선점해버렸다. 당 노선을 그렇게 가야 미래가 있다. 상향식 공천 제도로 바꿔야 하고.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- The word former President Lee Myung-bak often used was 'pragmatism.'&lt;/b&gt; "That's right. Former President Lee Myung-bak did well. We must create a pragmatic line suitable for the AI era as an ideology." (&lt;b&gt;- 예전 이명박 전 대통령이 즐겨 쓰던 단어가 ‘실용’인데. &lt;/b&gt;“그렇다. 이명박 전 대통령이 잘했었다. AI 시대에 맞는 실용주의 노선을 이념으로 만들어야 한다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;- You announced a run for the 2024 general election but withdrew.&lt;/b&gt; "At the time, rumors circulated that our party's nominations were all arranged by Lee Cheol-gyu and Jang Je-won. If this happened, we would (&lt;b&gt;- 2024년 총선에 출마했다 철회했는데. &lt;/b&gt;“당시 우리 당 공천은 이철규와 장제원이 다 짜 놓은 것이라는 얘기가 돌았다. 이러면 또 총선을 지는 거였다. 이걸 깨야 되겠다고 생각해 출마선언을 한 것이다. 하루에 인터뷰만 10개씩 하면서 어필을 하니, 윤 전 대통령이 생각을 바꿔 ‘상향식 공천으로 몇몇 지역은 전환하자’고 했다더라. 그런데 정작 나는 컷오프시킨다길래 내 출마는 접었다.”)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/25/56KHR2YHNVGDFJWENSLG3WHYTE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVRTIZBUMNTGINJXMJSGKMRUHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Parental Chance Plus Grandparental Chance?...'Yoon Suk-yeol + Cho Kuk + Kang Sun-woo' Combined into an All-Time Great Anger Provoker (“부모 찬스에 조부 찬스까지?...‘윤석열+조국+강선우’ 합친 역대급 분노 유발자)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/25/WYMDJ7M63FHCTHOOMCDC6GWCNY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Parental Chance Plus Grandparental Chance?...'Yoon Suk-yeol + Cho Kuk + Kang Sun-woo' Combined into an All-Time Great Anger Provoker (“부모 찬스에 조부 찬스까지?...‘윤석열+조국+강선우’ 합친 역대급 분노 유발자)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G43GCODDHEYWMNRUME4DKNJYGQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon was different from other public official nominee hearings. Typically, in confirmation hearings, when the opposition party raises various suspicions and launches attacks, the ruling party shields and defends the nominee. However, in this nominee's hearing, not only the opposition party but also the ruling party stepped forward, posing pointed questions and pouring out critical remarks towards the nominee. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사 청문회는 다른 공직 후보자 청문회와 달랐습니다. 야당이 각종 의혹을 제기하며 공세를 펴면 여당이 후보자를 감싸며 엄호해 주는 것이 통상적인 인사 청문회의 모습입니다. 그런데 이 후보자 청문회에선 야당뿐 아니라 여당까지 나서서 이 후보자에게 송곳 질문을 던지고 질책성 발언을 쏟아냈습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is likely because the various suspicions surrounding this nominee were judged to be at a level difficult to comprehend by common sense and serious. The nominee used an absurd method called 'pretending to be unmarried' to apply for and win a lottery for a high-end apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu. Her eldest son was embroiled in the 'parental chance' controversy. He entered Yonsei University through the 'social contributor' track and is suspected of having his name listed as an author on a paper co-authored with his father to use it for employment. The nominee frequently verbally abused her aides. Although she apologized for the high-handedness controversy during the hearing, the controversy has not subsided. (이 후보자를 둘러싼 각종 의혹이 상식적으로 납득하기 힘들고 심각한 수준이라고 판단했기 때문일 것입니다. 이 후보자는 ‘위장 미혼’이라는 황당한 방법으로 서초구 반포동 고급 아파트를 청약받았습니다. 그의 장남은 ‘부모 찬스’ 논란에 휩싸였습니다. ‘사회기여자’ 전형으로 연세대에 입학했고, 부친과 같은 논문에 저자로 이름을 올려 취업에 활용했다는 의혹을 받고 있습니다. 이 후보자는 보좌진들에게 수시로 폭언을 했습니다. 청문회에서 갑질 논란에 대해 사과했지만 논란은 수그러들지 않고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are also significant doubts within the ruling party regarding her attendance at a rally opposing the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol, questioning if it's a case of 'Yoon Again'. Add to that admissions irregularities and parental chance reminiscent of former Justice Minister Cho Kuk, controversies over special favors and rule-breaking, and high-handed behavior that rivals lawmaker Kang Sun-woo, leading to an assessment that she encompasses all kinds of suspicions. Within the ruling party, there's talk of her being an all-time great 'suspicion comprehensive set' combining 'Yoon Suk-yeol, Cho Kuk, and Kang Sun-woo'. She is described as a 'national dislike' and an 'anger provoker' possessing all the elements the public dislikes. (윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵에 반대하는 집회에 참석한 것을 두고 ‘윤 어게인’ 아니냐는 여권 내부의 의구심도 큽니다. 여기에 조국 전 법무장관을 연상시키는 입시 비리와 부모 찬스, 반칙 특혜 논란과 내로남불, 강선우 의원 뺨치는 갑질 행태까지, 온갖 의혹을 총망라했다는 평가가 나옵니다. 여권 내부에선 ‘윤석열·조국·강선우’를 합쳐 놓은 역대급 ‘의혹 종합 세트’라는 말이 나옵니다. 국민이 싫어하는 모든 요소를 갖춘 ‘국민 비호감’이자 ‘분노 유발자’라는 겁니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, during this nominee's hearing, there were no new suspicions or decisive blows. However, the nominee's unconvincing explanations only poured fuel on the controversy. In particular, the explanations regarding 'pretending to be unmarried' and the 'social contributor admissions' track are drawing reactions that they only fueled public anger. (23일 이 후보자 청문회에서 새로운 의혹이나 결정적 한 방은 없었습니다. 하지만 이 후보자의 석연치 않은 해명이 오히려 논란에 기름을 부었습니다. 특히 ‘위장 미혼’과 ‘사회 기여자 입시’에 대한 해명은 국민들 화만 돋웠다는 반응입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's husband applied for and won the lottery for the 'Raemian One Pentas' apartment in Banpo, Seocho-gu, Seoul. However, in this process, they received application points by pretending their eldest son, who even held a wedding ceremony in 2024, was unmarried. The nominee stated, "Immediately after my son got married, the couple's relationship deteriorated to the worst, making it difficult to maintain the marriage, so (for two years) they did not register the marriage." She also said, "I never thought it was an improper application." (이 후보자의 남편은 서울 서초구 반포 ‘래미안 원펜타스’ 아파트에 청약해 당첨됐습니다. 하지만 이 과정에서 2024년 결혼식까지 올린 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 속여 청약 가점을 받았습니다. 이 후보자는 “아들이 결혼한 직후 부부 관계가 최악으로 치달아 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단해 (2년간) 혼인 신고를 안 했다”고 했습니다. “부정 청약을 했다는 생각은 전혀 없다”고도 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the couple registered their marriage after winning the apartment and are still living well together. The daughter-in-law, who had moved into the newlywed home prepared in Yongsan in February 2024, suddenly moved out of that house around the time of the nominee's family's apartment application. And the nominee's entire family collectively moved into that house. This was to increase their application points. Later, after winning the One Pentas apartment, the nominee's family moved out of the Yongsan house and into One Pentas, and the daughter-in-law moved back into the Yongsan house. After the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport's apartment inspection results came out, the eldest son moved to Yongsan and registered the marriage. It was a meticulously planned series of moves in and out, like a scripted play. This is why the nominee's explanation that the son's couple was essentially on the verge of breakup lacks persuasiveness. (하지만 두 사람은 아파트 당첨 이후 혼인 신고를 했고 현재까지 잘 살고 있습니다. 2024년 2월 용산에 마련한 신혼집에 전입했던 며느리는 이 후보자 측의 청약 신청을 전후해 그 집에서 갑자기 전출했습니다. 그리고 이 후보자 가족이 모두 그 집으로 집단 전입했습니다. 청약 가점을 높이려 한 것입니다. 이후 원펜타스 아파트에 당첨되자 이 후보자 가족은 용산 집에서 전출해 원펜타스로 전입했고, 며느리가 다시 용산 집으로 전입했습니다. 국토부의 아파트 점검 결과가 나온 이후 장남은 용산으로 전입하고 혼인신고를 했습니다. 짜인 각본처럼 치밀하게 전입·전출을 한 것입니다. 아들 부부가 사실상 파경 상태였다는 이 후보자의 해명이 설득력을 갖지 못하는 이유입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairwoman Lee Mi-ja of the Planning and Finance Committee predicted the day before the hearing, "(The nominee) will make excuses that her son and his wife had a bad relationship." This prediction was spot on. People Power Party lawmakers said, "Isn't the daughter-in-law the best filial daughter-in-law, who not only didn't have a breakup but even delayed marriage registration and moved in and out to help?" (임이자 재정경제기획위원장은 청문회 하루 전날 “(이 후보자가) 아들 부부 사이가 안 좋아서 그랬다고 변명할 것”이라고 예측했습니다. 이는 정확하게 적중했습니다. 국민의힘 의원들은 “며느리가 파경은커녕 혼인 신고도 늦추며 전입·전출까지 해준 최고의 효부 아니냐”고 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's explanation regarding her son's admission to Yonsei University is also hard to accept. Initially, the nominee said her eldest son entered through the 'multi-child track', then changed her story to say he went through the 'social contributor' track, which is for students from families of independence activists, national meritorious persons, or those who enhanced national prestige. She claimed he qualified because his grandfather, a former minister, received a medal. (아들의 연세대 입학에 대한 이 후보자의 해명도 납득하기 힘듭니다. 애초 이 후보자는 장남이 ‘다자녀 전형’으로 입학했다고 했다가 ‘독립유공자·국가유공자·국위선양자 가족을 둔 학생이 지원할 수 있는 ‘사회기여자’ 전형을 거쳤다고 말을 바꿨습니다. 장관을 지낸 시아버지가 훈장을 받았기 때문에 자격 요건이 됐다는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the opposition party criticized, "Didn't he receive special favors because the nominee's husband was a professor at Yonsei University?" and "Why should a grandson enter university because his grandfather was a minister and received a medal?" They questioned if it was a case of using not only 'parental chance' but also 'grandparental chance' for preferential admission. (하지만 야당은 “이 후보자 남편이 연세대 교수로 재직하고 있어서 특혜를 받은 것 아니냐” “할아버지가 장관 지내고 훈장 받았다고 왜 손자가 대학에 입학하느냐”고 비판했습니다. ‘부모 찬스’에 ‘조부 찬스’까지 써서 특혜 입학한 것 아니냐는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Suspicions were also raised that the eldest son used 'dad's chance' in his employment process. This is because the second author on a paper the eldest son submitted to an academic journal in 2020 was the nominee's husband. The eldest son submitted this paper when applying for a job at a state-run research institute. (장남이 취업 과정에서도 ‘아빠 찬스’를 썼다는 의혹도 제기됐습니다. 장남이 2020년 학회지에 투고한 논문의 2저자가 이 후보자 남편이었기 때문입니다. 장남은 국책연구원에 취업할 때 이 논문을 제출했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the controversy over verbal abuse and high-handed behavior towards aides, the nominee bowed her head and said, "I deeply reflect on this" and "I apologize to all those hurt by my immature words and actions." However, a former council member who exposed the high-handedness appeared as a witness and said, "I felt it was disgusting." The nominee also said she reflects on her attendance at last year's rally opposing the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol. But hardline Democratic Party members protested, saying, "Someone who opposed impeachment and aligned with forces of rebellion should not be appointed as a minister." (이 후보자는 보좌관에 대한 폭언과 갑질 논란에 대해선 “뼈저리게 반성한다” “성숙하지 못한 언행 때문에 상처받은 모든 분들께 사과드린다”고 고개를 숙였습니다. 하지만 갑질을 폭로했던 구의원은 참고인으로 나와 “가증스럽다는 느낌을 받았다”고 했습니다. 이 후보자는 작년 윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵 반대 집회에 참석한 것에 대해서도 반성한다고 했습니다. 하지만 민주당 강성 당원들은 “탄핵에 반대하며 내란 세력과 코드를 맞췄던 사람을 장관에 임명해선 안 된다”고 반발했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are observations that the suspicions related to this nominee are on par with those surrounding former Justice Minister Cho Kuk, who was considered the strongest ever. It's said that parental chance, rule-breaking, special favors, and hypocrisy are identical. It's also said that compared to lawmaker Kang Sun-woo, who caused national anger during last year's ministerial nominee confirmation hearing, the types and number of suspicions are more than double. The types of suspicions related to this nominee are about 10, and media reports number 119. For lawmaker Kang Sun-woo, the types of suspicions were 5, and related reports numbered 47. It's 'Kang Sun-woo times two'. (이 후보자 관련 의혹이 역대 최강이었던 조국 전 법무장관에 필적할 수준이라는 지적이 나옵니다. 부모 찬스와 반칙, 특혜, 내로남불이 판박이라는 겁니다. 작년 장관 후보자 인사청문회에서 국민적 분노를 일으켰던 강선우 의원에 비해서도 의혹의 종류와 숫자가 2배 이상이라고 합니다. 이 후보자 관련 의혹의 종류가 10여 가지이고 언론 보도는 119회에 달했습니다. 강선우 의원 의혹의 종류는 5가지, 관련 보도 건수는 47회였습니다. ‘강선우 따블’인 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the hearing ended, public opinion is worsening further. The atmosphere within the ruling party is also chilly. This is because the nominee showed an attitude of trying to merely evade the immediate crisis with explanations beyond common sense and evasive answers. Parties across the opposition spectrum are also uniformly critical. The Cho Kuk Innovation Party and the Progressive Party said, "It gives the common people a deep sense of loss, and there's nothing she has properly explained." (청문회가 끝난 후 여론은 더 악화되고 있습니다. 여권 분위기도 싸늘합니다. 이 후보자가 상식 밖 해명과 얼버무리는 답변으로 눈 앞의 위기만 모면하려는 태도를 보였기 때문입니다. 범여권 정당들도 비판 일색입니다. 조국혁신당·진보당은 “서민들에게 깊은 상실감을 안기고, 무엇 하나 제대로 해명한 게 없다”고 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This critical atmosphere is because this nominee possesses all four elements most disliked by the public and party members. (이런 비판적 분위기는 이 후보자가 국민과 당원들이 가장 싫어하는 네 가지 요소를 모두 갖췄기 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Combining these four elements results in Yoon Suk-yeol, Cho Kuk, and Kang Sun-woo overlapping simultaneously. She is an all-time great anger provoker equipped with all elements of national dislike. That's why even the ruling party cannot defend her. Democratic Party lawmakers are signaling that the presidential office should judge for itself. (네 가지를 합치면 윤석열과 조국, 강선우가 한꺼번에 오버랩됩니다. 국민 비호감 요소를 모두 갖춘 역대급 분노 유발자인 셈입니다. 이러니 여당도 엄호하지 못하는 것입니다. 민주당 의원들은 청와대에서 알아서 판단하라는 기류입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung, who sought a reversal opportunity in the confirmation hearing, appears to be in a dilemma. Whenever various suspicions poured out, President Lee said, "We must give the nominee a chance to explain" and "Let's watch the hearing." However, it's becoming a situation where using the hearing as a shield is increasingly difficult. (인사 청문회에서 반전의 계기를 찾으려 했던 이재명 대통령은 고민에 빠진 듯합니다. 각종 의혹이 쏟아질 때마다 이 대통령은 “이 후보자가 해명할 기회를 줘야 한다” “청문회를 지켜보자”고 했습니다. 그런데 더 이상 청문회를 방패막이로 쓰기 힘든 상황이 돼가고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For President Lee, this nominee was a symbol of national unity personnel and a two-birds-with-one-stone card that could shake the People Power Party. This is also why he painstakingly pushed through to the hearing. As president, he likely inwardly thought that if the nominee properly explained and somewhat dispelled the controversy, he could appoint her. (이 대통령에게 이 후보자는 국민 통합 인사의 상징이자 국민의힘을 흔들 수 있는 일석이조의 카드였습니다. 청문회까지 힘들게 끌고 온 것도 이 때문인데요. 대통령으로선 내심 이 후보자가 제대로 해명해서 논란을 어느 정도 불식시켜주면 임명할 수도 있다는 생각이었을 겁니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, not only the opposition party but also the Democratic Party and the broader opposition spectrum are uniformly negative. For President Lee, opposition from within the ruling party and his support base is more burdensome than opposition from the opposition party. It is said that among presidential office staff, there are many opinions that voluntary resignation or withdrawal of the nomination is inevitable. President Lee will agonize over the weekend. However, it doesn't seem easy to forcefully proceed with the appointment. (그런데 야당은 물론이고 민주당과 범여권도 부정적 평가 일색입니다. 이 대통령으로선 야당의 반대보다 여권 내부, 지지층의 비토가 더 부담스러운 일입니다. 청와대 참모진 사이에서도 자진 사퇴나 지명 철회가 불가피한 것 아니냐는 의견이 많다고 합니다. 이 대통령은 주말 사이 고심할 것입니다. 하지만 임명 강행을 하기가 쉽지는 않아 보입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/25/WYMDJ7M63FHCTHOOMCDC6GWCNY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G43GCODDHEYWMNRUME4DKNJYGQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Korea, a Substantial No. 3 AI Nation" (李 대통령 “韓, 명실상부 AI 3위 국가”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/OX42K3LDAVCPRB6QTKVF6BAGNI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBRDEOBZMMYTEZBRGU3GMMLDME.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung stated that Korea has risen to become a top-three nation in the field of artificial intelligence (AI). (이재명 대통령은 한국이 인공지능(AI) 분야에서 세계 3위권으로 올라섰다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his social networking service (SNS), President Lee wrote, "They say if you can't avoid it, enjoy it," and added, "Korea has now established itself as a substantial No. 3 nation in the AI field." He continued, "Thanks to Korea's National Sovereign AI Initiative, several Korean AI labs possessing cutting-edge AI have emerged," stating, "The key driver of this growth is the 'National Sovereign AI Initiative,' a nationwide competition supported by the Korean government." (이 대통령은 자신의 사회관계망서비스(SNS)에 “피할 수 없다면 즐기라고 했다”며 “한국은 이제 AI 분야에서 명실상부한 3위 국가로 자리매김했다”고 썼다. 이어 “한국의 국가 소버린 AI 이니셔티브에 힘입어 최첨단 수준의 AI를 보유한 여러 한국 AI 연구소가 등장했다”며 “이러한 성장세의 핵심 동력은 한국 정부가 지원하는 전국 규모의 경진 대회인 ‘국가 소버린 AI 이니셔티브’”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sovereign AI refers to the capability and system for a specific nation to independently create and operate AI according to its own laws, values, and security requirements. It is a concept encompassing not only hardware, such as data center construction, but also software. (소버린 AI는 특정 국가가 자국의 법과 가치, 안보 요구에 따라 스스로 AI를 만들고 운영하는 역량과 체계를 뜻한다. 데이터센터 구축 같은 하드웨어는 물론 소프트웨어까지 포괄하는 개념이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also shared a post from the overseas AI research institution 'Artificial Analysis.' The post stated, "Korea has now become a clear world No. 3 in the AI field," and "Several Korean AI labs with near-frontier intelligence have emerged, powered by Korea's 'National Sovereign AI Initiative.'" (이 대통령은 해외 AI 연구 기관 ‘아티피셜 애널리시스(Artificial Analysis)’의 게시물을 올리기도 했다. 해당 게시물에는 “한국은 이제 AI 분야에서 확실한 세계 3위 국가가 됐다”며 “한국의 ‘국가 소버린 AI 이니셔티브’를 동력으로 최전선에 가까운 지능을 가진 여러 한국 AI 랩이 등장했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artificial Analysis cited the 'National Sovereign AI Initiative' as a key factor in this outcome. It noted that Korea, with its high semiconductor technology competitiveness, is one of the few countries capable of implementing its own AI services based on a unique language infrastructure (Hangul). (아티피셜 애널리시스는 이 같은 결과의 핵심 요인으로 ‘국가 소버린 AI 이니셔티브’를 꼽았다. 반도체 기술 경쟁력이 높은 한국은 고유 언어 인프라(한글)를 바탕으로 자체 AI 서비스를 구현할 수 있는 몇 안 되는 나라로 꼽은 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/OX42K3LDAVCPRB6QTKVF6BAGNI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBRDEOBZMMYTEZBRGU3GMMLDME.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:27:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee "It's regrettable that the KOSPI has become a political theme" (이 대통령 “정치테마 된 코스피, 안타깝다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/Z263S4TJXNDDBDO34DRIA3JGZM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HAYTGZRTGMZDIZLDMFRGGMZUHA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung shared an article on the night of the 24th about the sharply divided outlook for the KOSPI market depending on political leanings, saying, "On one hand, it's also regrettable." (이재명 대통령은 24일 밤 코스피 시장 전망이 정치 성향에 따라 극명하게 갈린다는 내용의 기사를 공유하며 “한편으로 안타깝기도 하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Introducing an article titled 'The KOSPI, a political theme: will it rise or fall?' on X (formerly Twitter), President Lee said, "It's an interesting analysis in many aspects, such as stock holdings, domestic and international investment tendencies, and future economic forecasts." He added, "I hope we can overcome small differences, pool our strength together to get through this crisis, and move toward a future of shared prosperity." (이 대통령은 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 ‘정치 테마가 된 코스피, 오를까 떨어질까’라는 제목의 기사를 소개하며 “주식 보유 상황, 국내외 투자 성향, 향후 경제 예측 등 여러 면에서 재미있는 분석”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “작은 차이를 넘어 모두 힘을 모아 함께 이 위기를 넘어 공동 번영의 미래를 향해 나아가면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article covers how, as the KOSPI recently broke through the 5,000-point mark, political leanings are influencing economic sentiment. It cited public opinion poll results showing that while progressives are optimistic about stock price prospects over the next year, conservatives hold a predominantly pessimistic view, and preferences for domestic versus international stocks also show clear differences depending on supported political parties. (해당 기사는 코스피가 최근 5000포인트를 돌파한 가운데 정치 성향이 경제 심리에 영향을 미치고 있다는 내용을 담고 있다. 향후 1년간 주가 전망에 대해 진보층은 낙관적인 반면 보수층은 비관적인 시각이 우세했으며, 지지 정당에 따라 국내외 주식 선호도도 뚜렷한 차이를 보인다는 여론조사 결과가 인용됐다)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/Z263S4TJXNDDBDO34DRIA3JGZM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HAYTGZRTGMZDIZLDMFRGGMZUHA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:44:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Emphasizes "Independent Defense is the Fundamental of Fundamentals" in Response to U.S. Defense Strategy Stressing ROK Responsibility (李 대통령, 韓 책임 강조한 美 국방전략에 “자주국방, 기본중 기본”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/K7QHD5MYHBDEPKMTHT3XEQBB5A/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/P3MVKDY7L74TY6MJCYPTWNUJCY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 24th, President Lee Jae-myung responded to the mention in the new National Defense Strategy (NDS) of the Donald Trump administration that "the ROK has the capability to bear primary responsibility for deterrence against North Korea," stating, "Amid an unstable international situation, independent defense is the fundamental of fundamentals." (이재명 대통령이 24일 도널드 트럼프 미국 행정부가 새 국방 전략(NDS)에서 ‘한국이 대북 억제에 대해 주된 책임을 질 능력이 있다’고 언급한 것에 대해 “불안정한 국제 정세 속에 자주 국방은 기본 중의 기본”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee posted an article on X (formerly Twitter) analyzing the new NDS of the Trump administration, which is oriented towards strengthening South Korea's responsibility for its own defense, and wrote the above. President Lee further stated, "It is unthinkable that the Republic of Korea, which spends 1.4 times North Korea's GDP on defense and possesses the world's fifth-largest military force, cannot defend itself," adding, "Firm independent defense and peace on the Korean Peninsula enable sustained economic growth." This is a point he has emphasized multiple times since his presidential candidacy. (이 대통령은 이날 엑스(X·옛 트위터)에 한국의 자국 방어 책임을 강화하는 방향의 트럼프 행정부의 새 NDS 내용을 분석한 기사를 올리고 이같이 적었다. 이 대통령은 이어 “북한 국내총생산(GDP)의 1.4배나 국방비를 지출하며 세계 5위 군사력을 가진 대한민국이 스스로 방어하지 못한다는 것은 있을 수 없는 일”이라며 “확고한 자주국방과 한반도 평화가 지속적인 경제성장을 가능하게 한다”고 했다. 이는 대선 후보 시절부터 여러 차례 강조한 말이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this NDS, the Trump administration stated, "The ROK has the capability to bear primary responsibility for deterrence against North Korea while receiving critical but more limited U.S. support." It also said, "This rebalancing of responsibility aligns with U.S. interests in updating the posture of U.S. forces on the Korean Peninsula." The implication is that South Korea should invest more capabilities than before in building conventional deterrence against North Korea and preventing North Korean provocations. (트럼프 행정부는 이번 NDS에서 “한국은 매우 중요하면서도 더 제한적인 미국의 지원(critical but more limited US support)을 받으며 대북 억제에서 주된 책임을 질 능력이 있다”고 했다. 또 “(대북 억제) 책임에서 이런 균형 조정은 한반도에서 미군의 태세를 업데이트하는 데 미국의 이익과 부합한다”고 했다. 한국이 대북 재래식 억지력 구축과 북한의 도발 방지 등에 지금까지보다 더 많은 역량을 투입해야 한다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lee Jae-myung administration is currently pursuing the transfer of wartime operational control (OPCON). Accordingly, there are forecasts that efforts to modernize U.S. Forces Korea capabilities will gain momentum. The ROK and the U.S. have discussed this direction of 'role adjustment' in the 'Joint Fact Sheet' containing the results of last November's tariff and security negotiations and last month's joint press statement from the Nuclear Consultative Group (NCG). (이재명 정부는 현재 전시작전통제권 환수를 추진하고 있다. 이에 따라 주한 미군 전력 첨단화 등에도 탄력이 붙을 것이라는 전망이 나온다. 한미 양국은 지난해 11월 관세·안보 협상 결과를 담은 ‘조인트 팩트시트’(공동 설명 자료) 및 지난달 핵협의그룹(NCG) 공동 언론 성명에서 이 같은 방향의 ‘역할 조정’을 협의한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/K7QHD5MYHBDEPKMTHT3XEQBB5A/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/P3MVKDY7L74TY6MJCYPTWNUJCY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:36:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party's Cho Seung-rae: "Cho Kuk Innovation Party's DNA will blend well within the Democratic Party... Now is the right time for merger" (與 조승래 “민주당에 조국혁신당 DNA 잘 섞일 것…지금이 합당 적기”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/25/TSAIJYE3NZDYRBAF7MJ2BOC7YA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/C5FQH3KQCVOKVFTV3YISBDEZCU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea stated on the 25th, "We will proceed with the procedures for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party," adding, "We will proceed according to the party constitution and regulations." (더불어민주당은 25일 “조국혁신당과 합당을 위한 절차를 진행하겠다”며 “당헌·당규가 정한 바에 따라 진행할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae announced this at a press briefing today, saying, "It involves discussions and voting by party members, and the procedures for a national convention or a central committee resolution as stipulated by the Political Parties Act." Secretary-General Cho stated, "The 17 city and provincial party chapters and various levels will commence discussions among party members regarding whether to merge and the procedures." (민주당 조승래 사무총장은 이날 기자간담회에서 “당원들의 토론과 투표, 그리고 정당법이 정한 전당대회 혹은 중앙위 의결 절차를 거치게 돼 있다”며 이같이 밝혔다. 조 사무총장은 “17개 시·도당과 각급 단위에서 합당 여부, 절차에 대해 당원 토론에 착수할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary-General Cho said, "A 'dual resolution' is required: a vote for or against by eligible party members, and if a favorable opinion is confirmed there, the next step is a resolution by the central committee or a delegates' national convention." He added, "The same procedure was followed during the merger with the Open Democratic Party in 2021." He noted, "If there are significant reasons, it can be done through a central committee resolution instead of a national convention." (조 사무총장은 “권리당원 찬반 투표, 거기서 찬성 여론이 확인되면 다음 절차로 중앙위 혹은 대의원 전당대회 의결을 하는 ‘이중 의결’이 필요하다”며 “2021년 열린민주당과 합당 때도 같은 절차를 거쳐 진행했다”고 했다. 그는 “상당한 이유가 있으면 전당대회가 아닌 중앙위 의결로 할 수 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary-General Cho stated, "Representative Chung Cheong-rae judged that now is the right time (for the merger)," and "considering the local election schedule, it was judged that discussions must happen now to proceed with the local election schedule together." Regarding the deadline, he said, "It should be settled within a month or two at the latest. The integration with the Open Democratic Party also took about 50 days," but added, "Since the other party is involved, it's not a matter for us to unilaterally set a timetable." (조 사무총장은 “지금이 (합당의) 적기라고 정청래 대표가 판단했다”며 “지방선거 일정상 지금 논의해야 지방선거 스케줄을 함께 치러나갈 수 있다고 판단한 것”이라고 했다. 그는 데드라인에 대해선 “늦어도 한두 달 이내에는 정리해야 하지 않을까. 열린민주당과 통합도 50여 일 걸렸다”면서도 “상대가 있는 것이기 때문에 우리가 일방적으로 시간표를 제시할 문제는 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary-General Cho addressed the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, saying, "Since they have stated 'we have the intention to merge and will proceed with internal procedures,' it would be good to proceed with greater courage." He continued, "The DNA of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party will also blend well within the large organism that is the Democratic Party." (조 사무총장은 조국혁신당을 향해 “합당에 대해 ‘합당할 의사가 있고 내부 절차를 진행하겠다’고 한 만큼, 더 큰 용기를 갖고 진행하면 좋을 듯하다”고 했다. 그러면서 “민주당이란 큰 생명체 내에 조국혁신당의 DNA도 잘 섞이게 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, met with reporters after a general meeting of lawmakers the previous day and said, "Under no circumstances should the vision, values, and political DNA of politician Cho Kuk and the Innovation Party disappear." He stated, "We will discuss and decide based on the principle that the Innovation Party's independent, political DNA must not only be preserved but also expanded." (조국혁신당 조국 대표는 전날 의원총회를 마치고 기자들과 만나 “어떤 경우에도 정치인 조국과 혁신당의 비전과 가치, 정치적 DNA가 사라져서는 안 된다”고 했다. 그는 “혁신당의 독자적, 정치적 DNA가 보존돼야 함은 물론이고 확대돼야 한다는 원칙에 기초해 논의하고 결정할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Secretary-General Cho said, "The 70-year history of the Democratic Party is inscribed with the DNA of numerous political forces," and "Our Democratic Party's identity has been formed through that multitude of DNA, and that is the history of the Democratic Party." (이에 대해 조 사무총장은 “민주당의 70년 역사에는 수많은 정치 세력의 DNA가 새겨져 있다”며 “그 많은 DNA를 통해 우리 민주당의 정체성이 형성돼 있고, 그게 민주당의 역사”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the issue of shares between the two parties upon merger, Secretary-General Cho said, "As internal procedures progress, a practical consultation framework for each party should be established," and "Typically, it proceeds with about 2+2, involving the secretary-general and one other person from each side. I don't think discussions about shares can occur during that process." He stated, "The topic is how we can pool our strength for the complete liquidation of past wrongs and victory in the local elections, not dividing shares; such discussions cannot happen." (조 사무총장은 합당 시 양당의 지분 문제에 대해선 “내부적으로 절차가 진행되면서 각 당의 실무 협의 틀이 만들어져야 할 것”이라며 “통상 사무총장과 1인 정도 해서 2+2 정도로 진행되는데, 그 과정에서 지분 논의는 있을 수 없다고 생각한다”고 했다. 그는 “어떻게 하면 내란의 완전한 청산과 지방선거 승리를 위해 우리가 어떻게 힘을 모을지가 주제인 것이지, 지분을 나누고 그런 논의는 있을 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the party name upon merger, Secretary-General Cho said, "Naturally, wouldn't we hold the view that the party name 'Democratic Party of Korea' should be maintained?" (조 사무총장은 합당 시 당명에 대해선 “우리는 당연히 ‘더불어민주당’ 당명이 유지돼야 한다는 생각을 갖고 있지 않겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/25/TSAIJYE3NZDYRBAF7MJ2BOC7YA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/C5FQH3KQCVOKVFTV3YISBDEZCU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:05:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "No Extension for Deferral of Heavy Capital Gains Tax on Multiple Homeowners... No Market Can Beat the Government" (李 대통령 “다주택 양도세 중과 유예, 연장 안해… 정부 이기는 시장 없다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/5G4Q24ITWBEKXAJ6BPJXK4NH2A/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI2GGMLBGAYDOZRWMMYWGZTGGQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 25th, President Lee Jae-myung stated on his SNS, "The scheduled end of the deferral of the heavy capital gains tax for multiple homeowners on May 9, 2026, is already set," adding, "If you were expecting a legal revision for re-extension, you were mistaken." He also said, "No government can beat the market, but no market can beat the government either." (이재명 대통령은 25일 자신의 SNS를 통해 “다주택자 양도세 중과 유예의 2026년 5월 9일 종료는 이미 정해진 것”이라며 “재연장 법 개정을 기대했다면 오산”이라고 밝혔다. “시장을 이기는 정부도 없지만 정부를 이기는 시장도 없다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "The Republic of Korea is returning to being a predictable, normal society," and "Unfair benefits arising from abnormality must be eliminated, no matter how difficult." Specifically targeting the phenomenon of multiple homeowners withholding properties from the market, he said, "Abnormal holding out should not be profitable," and "The benefit of holding out should not be greater than the cost of holding out." (이 대통령은 “대한민국은 예측 가능한 정상 사회로 복귀 중”이라며 “비정상으로 인한 불공정한 혜택은 힘들더라도 반드시 없애야 한다”고 했다. 특히 다주택자들의 매물 잠김 현상을 겨냥해 “비정상적인 버티기가 이익이 되어서는 안 된다”며 “버티는 이익이 버티는 비용보다 크게 해서는 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee likened real estate market reform to "major surgery for a serious illness." He said, "There will be much pain and resistance in escaping the 'Republic of Unearned Real Estate Income' that was heading towards a lost 30 years, but if it is necessary and useful, we must not avoid it," adding, "If we endure the pain for a while, we will become healthier and earn money better." (이 대통령은 부동산 시장 개혁을 ‘큰 병의 수술’에 비유했다. 그는 “잃어버린 30년을 향해 치닫는 부동산 불로소득 공화국을 탈출하는 데 고통과 저항은 많겠지만, 필요하고 유용한 일이라면 피하지 말아야 한다”며 “잠시 아픔을 견디면 더 건강하고 돈도 더 잘 벌 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also mentioned the recently completed revision of the Commercial Act. He asked rhetorically, "Regarding the Commercial Act revision for normalization, businesses and the country resisted as if it would ruin them, but after the revision, haven't both businesses and the national society improved?" This is interpreted as his intention to break through head-on, defining the resistance in the real estate market as a backlash from vested interests. (이 대통령은 최근 완료된 상법 개정을 언급하기도 했다. 그는 “정상화를 위한 상법 개정을 두고 기업과 나라가 망할 듯 호들갑 떨며 저항했지만, 막상 개정하고 나니 기업과 국가 사회 모두가 좋아지지 않았느냐”고 반문했다. 부동산 시장의 저항 역시 기득권의 반발로 규정하며 정면 돌파하겠다는 뜻으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, President Lee also partially acknowledged the government's responsibility for past policy confusion. He added, "The government is also at fault for making people believe in repeated deferrals over the past four years," and "We will discuss at the State Council meeting granting the tax deferral for contracts made until May 9, 2026." This is interpreted as opening an 'exit' to minimize confusion on the ground due to sudden policy changes. The real estate industry and political circles view President Lee's latest remarks as essentially a final pressure to 'induce property listings'. (다만, 이 대통령은 그간의 정책 혼선에 대한 정부의 책임도 일부 인정했다. 그는 “지난 4년간 유예 반복을 믿게 한 정부 잘못도 있다”며 “2026년 5월 9일까지 계약한 것에 대해서는 중과세 유예를 해주도록 국무회의에서 논의해 보겠다”고 덧붙였다. 이는 급격한 정책 변화로 인한 현장의 혼란을 최소화하기 위한 ‘출구’를 열어준 것으로 해석된다. 부동산 업계와 정치권에서는 이 대통령의 이번 발언이 사실상 ‘매물 유도’를 위한 마지막 압박이라고 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/25/5G4Q24ITWBEKXAJ6BPJXK4NH2A/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI2GGMLBGAYDOZRWMMYWGZTGGQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 02:21:14 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>