<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:11:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Regarding the Controversy over Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion... People Power Party's Shin Dong-wook Proposes 'Supreme Council Public Verification' (한동훈 제명 논란에… 국힘 신동욱 ‘최고위 공개 검증’ 제안)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/5AXEGDDVU5FBPBWDYMCRKCZHOY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Regarding the Controversy over Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion... People Power Party's Shin Dong-wook Proposes 'Supreme Council Public Verification' (한동훈 제명 논란에… 국힘 신동욱 ‘최고위 공개 검증’ 제안)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/AT3HCZFZIFOUZDDGAQ54ZET3FU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shin Dong-wook, a member of the People Power Party's Supreme Council, proposed on the 17th a public verification at the Supreme Council level regarding the party's Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon in relation to the 'party member bulletin board incident'. (국민의힘 신동욱 최고위원은 17일 당 윤리위원회가 ‘당원 게시판 사건’과 관련해 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명 결정을 한 것을 두고 최고위원회 차원의 공개 검증을 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Shin stated on Facebook that day, "I propose a public verification involving all Supreme Council members to bring closure to the party member bulletin board controversy." He said, "The controversy has dragged on for too long. It's already entering its third year by count," and added, "Our party might be stuck on this issue, unable to move forward even a single step. We must end it now." (신 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에 “당원게시판 논란 종식을 위한 최고위원 전원 공개 검증을 제안한다”고 밝혔다. 그는 “논란이 너무 길어지고 있다. 햇수로 벌써 3년째에 접어 들었다”며 “우리 당은 어쩌면 지금 이 문제에 발목 잡혀 한 발도 전진하지 못하고 있는지도 모르겠다. 이제 끝내야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Shin said, "On the 15th, the Supreme Council postponed the disciplinary decision. It opened an opportunity for reconsideration, but (former leader Han) has not yet responded," and "If a decision is made in this state, the discord will only grow." He continued, "I believe this issue should not be resolved by letting emotions take the lead." (신 최고위원은 “지난 15일 최고위가 징계 의결을 보류했다. 재심 기회를 열었지만 (한 전 대표가) 아직 응하지 않고 있다”며 “이 상태로 의결이 되면 분란이 더 커진다”고 했다. 이어 “이 문제는 감정을 앞세워 해결할 문제가 아니라고 본다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Shin stated, "As a final solution, I propose a public verification involving all elected Supreme Council members," and "If even this fails, then this matter will ultimately have to have its facts determined within the realm of an investigation." Furthermore, Supreme Council member Shin said, "Objective and thorough verification is essential to avoid leaving any lingering resentment," and "For this, consent for the use of personal information of former leader Han and his family should also be obtained." (신 최고위원은 “마지막 해법으로 선출직 최고위원 전원이 참가하는 공개 검증을 제안한다”며 “이마저도 무산된다면 이 문제는 결국 수사의 영역에서 사실관계가 확정될수 밖에 없을 것”이라고 했다. 그러면서 신 최고위원은 “뒤끝을 남기지 않도록 객관적이고 철저한 검증이 필수적”이라며 “이를 위해 한 전 대표와 가족들의 개인정보 이용 동의도 있어야 할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The members of the People Power Party's Supreme Council include Shin Dong-wook, Kim Min-su, Kim Jae-won, Yang Hyang-ja, and Woo Jae-jun. (국민의힘 최고위원으론 신동욱·김민수·김재원·양향자·우재준 등이 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/5AXEGDDVU5FBPBWDYMCRKCZHOY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/AT3HCZFZIFOUZDDGAQ54ZET3FU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:27:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un at Large Youth Event: "The March of Succession Must Continue"... Praises Troops Dispatched to Russia (김정은, 대규모 청년행사서 “계승의 보무 계속돼야”... 러 파병軍 치하)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/K5QO6G7QXRCZVACCCNOJL7U2PE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jong Un at Large Youth Event: "The March of Succession Must Continue"... Praises Troops Dispatched to Russia (김정은, 대규모 청년행사서 “계승의 보무 계속돼야”... 러 파병軍 치하)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MUYWEOBQMZSTAYTCMEYTGZLFGA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong Un, ahead of the major political event, the 9th Congress of the Workers' Party, held a large-scale youth event and stated, "The revolutionary cause, carried on through generations, imposes a resolute and significant mission on the Youth League and the youth, and the march of succession passed down year after year must continue." (김정은 북한 국무위원장이 최대 정치 이벤트인 노동당 9차 대회를 앞두고 대규모 청년 행사를 열어 “대를 이어 수행되는 혁명 위업은 청년동맹과 청년들에게 의연 중대한 사명을 부여하고 있으며 년년이 이어온 계승의 보무는 계속되어야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea's Korean Central News Agency reported on the 17th that Kim Jong Un made these remarks in a speech at a commemorative meeting for the 80th anniversary of the founding of the Socialist Patriotic Youth League (hereinafter referred to as the Youth League) held at the Kim Il Sung Stadium in Pyongyang the previous day. Kim Jong Un emphasized the 'succession of the revolutionary cause.' (김정은은 전날 평양 김일성경기장에서 열린 사회주의애국청년동맹(이하 청년동맹) 창립 80주년 기념대회 연설에서 이같이 말했다고 북한 조선중앙통신이 17일 보도했다. 김정은이 ‘혁명 위업의 계승’을 강조한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un said, "The seductive winds aiming to corrupt the new generations have never ceased," but "the red flag held aloft by the youth has not faded in the flow of time and the snow and rain of history, and has fluttered higher and more fiercely in the pure and thorough succession." (김정은은 “새 세대들의 변질을 노리는 유혹의 바람”이 멎은 적 없었지만 “청년들이 추켜든 붉은 기는 세월의 흐름과 역사의 눈비 속에 바래지 않았고 순결하고 철저한 계승 속에서 더 높이, 더 거세차게 휘날려 왔다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un stated, "Looking around the world today, it is none other than youths of the same age as our comrades who are at the center of unprecedented bloodshed and tragedy," and added, "Youths soaked in extreme human hatred, the poison of money worship, corruption, and pessimism are causing serious social problems everywhere and giving rise to the heartbreaking tragedy of bloodshed and discord." (김정은은 “오늘의 세계를 둘러보면 일찍이 있어본 적 없는 유혈참극의 중심에 다름 아닌 동무들과 같은 연령기의 청년들이 있다”며 “극도의 인간 증오와 황금 만능의 독소, 타락과 염세에 물젖은 청년들이 곳곳에서 심각한 사회적 문제들을 일으키고 유혈과 불화의 가슴아픈 비극을 산생시키고 있는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Kim Jong Un said, "The fact that we have reliable and steadfast young revolutionaries who hold the title of successor as the honor of their youth, overcome trials together with their own party and their own country, and train and perfect themselves is something worthy of boasting to the world." (그러면서 김정은은 “우리에게 계승자의 명함을 청춘의 영예로 간직하고 자기 당, 자기 조국과 시련을 함께 이겨내며 자신들을 스스로 단련하고 완성해 나가는 미덥고 끌끌한 젊은 혁명가들이 있다는 것은 세상에 내놓고 자랑할 만한 일”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Kim Jong Un praised the Russian-dispatched soldiers attending the commemorative meeting, calling it "something only the youth of Korea (North Korea) can do." Seemingly conscious of external criticism regarding the troop dispatch, he said, "The world still does not understand that world." (또 김정은은 기념대회에 참석한 러시아 파병 군인들을 가리켜 “조선(북한)의 청년들만이 할 수 있는 일”이라며 치하했다. 파병에 대한 외부 비판을 의식한 듯 “세상은 아직 그 세계를 이해하지 못한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un awarded the Youth League the Kim Jong Il Order, the 'country's highest order,' and took commemorative photos with event participants. The Korean Central News Agency also reported that he met with youths who had achieved feats in the 'main frontlines of national defense and socialist construction.' (김정은은 청년동맹에 ‘국가 최고훈장’인 김정일훈장을 수여하고 행사 참가자들과 기념사진을 찍었다. 또 ‘조국 보위와 사회주의 건설의 주요 전구’에서 위훈을 세운 청년들을 만났다고 조선중앙통신은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/K5QO6G7QXRCZVACCCNOJL7U2PE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MUYWEOBQMZSTAYTCMEYTGZLFGA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:56:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bae Hyun-jin Urges Jang Dong-hyeok to End Hunger Strike, Saying "This Is Not the Time"... First 'Stop the Hunger Strike' Call from People Power Party (배현진, 장동혁 단식에 “이럴 때 아니다”... 국힘 첫 ‘단식 중단’ 촉구)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/2SOAFG6GZVH43PITPICRDNWQ7M/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Bae Hyun-jin Urges Jang Dong-hyeok to End Hunger Strike, Saying "This Is Not the Time"... First 'Stop the Hunger Strike' Call from People Power Party (배현진, 장동혁 단식에 “이럴 때 아니다”... 국힘 첫 ‘단식 중단’ 촉구)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FJYSIJI5L5KSLPS2MW77NC6674.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party lawmaker Bae Hyun-jin stated on the 17th, "I urge Representative Jang Dong-hyeok to stop his hunger strike." Representative Jang began his hunger strike at the National Assembly on the 15th, demanding the acceptance of a 'dual special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of campaign funds involving the Democratic Party of Korea and suspicions of lobbying by the Unification Church in the political sphere. This is the first time a People Power Party lawmaker has publicly called for Representative Jang to end his hunger strike. (국민의힘 배현진 의원은 17일 “장동혁 대표의 단식 중단을 촉구한다”고 했다. 장 대표는 지난 15일 더불어민주당 공천 헌금 의혹과 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 국회에서 단식을 시작했다. 국민의힘 의원 가운데 장 대표 단식 중단을 공개적으로 촉구한 건 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post that day, Representative Bae said, "A solitary hunger strike, started without even gathering internal party agreement while avoiding the correct answer of withdrawing the disciplinary action, only invites ridicule from Lee Jae-myung (the President) and the Democratic Party." Representative Bae claims that Representative Jang's hunger strike is related to former Representative Han Dong-hoon, who received a decision of expulsion in connection with the 'party member bulletin board' incident. Representative Bae added, "Representative Jang must resolve the expulsion incident, which has caused great shock inside and outside the party, as soon as possible and gather the party's full strength." (배 의원은 이날 페이스북에 “징계 철회라는 정답을 피해가려 당내 동의도 모으지 못한 채 시작한 홀로 단식은 이재명(대통령)과 민주당의 조소만 살 뿐”이라고 했다. 장 대표의 단식이 ‘당원 게시판’ 사건과 관련해 제명 결정을 받은 한동훈 전 대표와 관련이 있다는 게 배 의원 주장이다. 그러면서 배 의원은 “장 대표는 당 내외에 큰 충격을 준 제명 사태를 하루 빨리 수습하고 당의 총력을 모아야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Bae stated, "At this time, when every moment is precious until the June (local) elections, the hearts of (prospective local election) candidates are burning with anxiety," and added, "Not only will we lose the health of our leader, but the futures, livelihoods of thousands of our candidates, and the party's survival will also be shattered." (배 의원은 “6월 (지방)선거까지 매일 매순간이 소중한 이 때, (지방선거 출마 예정) 후보들의 마음이 타들어가고 있다”며 “대표의 건강만 잃고 끝나는 것이 아니라 수천 명 우리 후보들의 미래와 생계, 당의 생존도 박살난다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continuing, she strongly requested, "End the hunger strike, return to work, rectify the abnormal disciplinary situation that was put into drive, and heal the divided party," saying, "There is nothing to gain from the head of our party starving to death. This is not the time for this." (그러면서 “단식을 풀고 일터로 돌아와 드라이브 걸었던 비정상적 징계 사태를 정돈하고 분열된 당을 수습해주길 강력히 요청한다”면서 “우리 당의 가장이 굶어 죽어 얻을 것이 아무것도 없는 시점이다. 이럴 때가 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 16th, Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae, at a party Supreme Council meeting, said to Representative Jang, "This is a hunger strike show where you are throwing a tantrum without even the slightest reflection before the people and history," and added, "I hope you will stop the hunger strike and cooperate with the historical trend of liquidating the rebellion." (앞서 정청래 민주당 대표는 지난 16일 당 최고위원회의에서 장 대표를 향해 “국민과 역사 앞에 최소한의 반성도 없이 몽니를 부리고 있는 단식쇼”라며 “단식을 중단하시고 시대적 흐름인 내란 청산에 협조해 주시기를 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/2SOAFG6GZVH43PITPICRDNWQ7M/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FJYSIJI5L5KSLPS2MW77NC6674.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:06:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party Spokesperson Apologizes After Backlash Over "Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination Sales, They'll Lose Anyway" Remarks (국힘 대변인 “개혁신당 40억 공천팔이, 어차피 낙선”... 반발 일자 사과)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/UKZFRDMJ3NGQNMDXE4LWRTNJBM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party Spokesperson Apologizes After Backlash Over "Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination Sales, They'll Lose Anyway" Remarks (국힘 대변인 “개혁신당 40억 공천팔이, 어차피 낙선”... 반발 일자 사과)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUMO7TZYLNKY5DTMOHOMIZLG54.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the June 3 local elections, a spokesperson for the People Power Party (PPP) claimed the Reform Party was "selling nominations," prompting a backlash from the Reform Party and leading to an immediate apology. In response, Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said, "I thank them for the courage to acknowledge and correct the mistake." (6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 국민의힘 소속 대변인이 개혁신당을 향해 “공천 팔이를 하고 있다”며 했다가, 개혁신당이 반발하자 즉각 사과했다. 이에 개혁신당 이준석 대표는 “실수를 인정하고 정정한 용기에 감사하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP and the Reform Party have recently been cooperating, jointly demanding a 'dual special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of Democratic Party nomination donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians. The conflict arose as a sign of potential discord, which both sides have now moved to mend. (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 최근 더불어민주당 공천 헌금 의혹과 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하면서 공조에 나섰는데, 갈등이 생길 조짐을 보이자 양측이 이를 봉합한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, PPP media spokesperson Lee Jae-neung appeared on a YouTube broadcast and said, "The Reform Party is currently selling nominations for 4 billion won. All 4,000 (candidates running for the Reform Party) are victims," adding, "Since they won't get elected anyway, making them run through to the end only results in them being used, so it's pitiful." (국민의힘 이재능 미디어대변인은 지난 16일 한 유튜브 방송에 출연해 “개혁신당이 지금 40억원 공천팔이를 하고 있다. (개혁신당 후보자로 출마할) 4000명이 다 피해자”라며 “어차피 당선이 안 되는 건데 완주시킨다는 건 그들이 이용당하는 꼴밖에 안 되니까 불쌍하더라”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok announced that for the June 3 local elections, he would reduce the election costs for running for basic-level council positions (city/county/district), which typically cost hundreds of millions or tens of millions of won, to 990,000 won. The spokesperson's remarks implied that if 4,000 Reform Party candidates run, the party would collect 4 billion won in election costs, but they would lose the elections. (앞서 개혁신당 이준석 대표는 6·3 지방선거에서 시·군·구 등 기초의원 출마를 위해 수백, 수천만 원이 드는 선거 비용을 99만원으로 줄이겠다고 밝혔다. 이 대변인의 발언은 이에 따라 4000명의 개혁신당 후보자가 출마할 경우 개혁신당이 40억원의 선거 비용을 거두지만 선거에선 낙선하게 될 것이라는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, Reform Party spokesperson Jeong Yi-han said in a commentary on the 17th, "This is a serious juncture where the leadership of both parties is pooling their strength to push through the special prosecutor investigations into the Unification Church and the money-for-nominations allegations involving Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi," adding, "In such a situation, the PPP spokesperson's attack on an opposing party with baseless slander is an irresponsible act that undermines the trust in cooperation itself." (이에 대해 개혁신당 정이한 대변인은 17일 논평에서 “지금은 양당 지도부가 통일교 특검과 강선우·김병기 돈 공천 특검 관철을 위해 힘을 모으는 엄중한 국면”이라며 “이런 상황에서 국민의힘 대변인이 근거 없는 비방으로 상대 정당을 공격한 것은 공조의 신뢰를 스스로 허무는 무책임한 행동”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Jeong asked, "We ask the PPP leadership: Will they stand by while the spokesperson's remarks, made without even checking basic facts, shake the framework of cooperative governance?" and urged spokesperson Lee Jae-neung to resign, among other actions. (정 대변인은 “국민의힘 지도부에 묻는다. 기초적 사실관계조차 확인하지 않은 대변인의 발언이 협치의 틀을 흔들고 있는데, 이를 방치할 것이냐”며 이재능 대변인의 사퇴 등을 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, spokesperson Lee apologized on Facebook that day, stating, "The remarks stemmed from my incorrect understanding and were excessive expressions; all my related statements were wrong." He added, "I once again offer my apologies to the Reform Party, its candidates, and all related parties." (이에 이 대변인은 이날 페이스북에 “해당 발언은 저의 잘못된 이해에서 비롯된 과도한 표현이었으며 관련한 저의 모든 발언은 틀렸다”고 사과했다. 그는 “개혁신당과 출마자, 그리고 관계자 여러분께 다시 한 번 사과의 말씀을 드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, leader Lee Jun-seok accepted the apology on Facebook, saying, "I will regard this incident as a mistake made out of habit." He added, "While individuals can express their opinions in any way, I hope they do not escalate to attacks based on false information." (그러자 이준석 대표는 페이스북에서 “이번 일은 관성에 따른 실수 정도로 받아들이겠다”며 사과를 받아들였다. 이 대표는 “개인의 의견이야 어떤 식으로든 표현할 수 있으나 그것이 허위사실에 의한 공격에 이르지 않았으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/UKZFRDMJ3NGQNMDXE4LWRTNJBM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUMO7TZYLNKY5DTMOHOMIZLG54.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 23:48:13 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>