<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 01:15:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jung Cheong-rae's "We are pro-Chung" remark causes a momentary silence... Laughter only blooms after hearing "pro-Cheongwadae" (정청래, 李에 “우린 친청” 발언 순간 정적… “친청와대” 듣고서야 웃음꽃)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/MKE73YQKB5BGVCZQTZIKJAVEYA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jung Cheong-rae's "We are pro-Chung" remark causes a momentary silence... Laughter only blooms after hearing "pro-Cheongwadae" (정청래, 李에 “우린 친청” 발언 순간 정적… “친청와대” 듣고서야 웃음꽃)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/E3Z3VVR4QJEQNPEEUKQQ3PVMTU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung's question to Democratic Party of Korea leader Jung Cheong-rae at a Cheongwadae dinner on the 19th, asking "Are you perhaps anti-Myeong (anti-Lee Jae-myung)?" has become a topic of discussion. The Democratic Party explained in an official briefing that "the President made a 'joke' that caused uproarious laughter." They also stated that when Leader Jung replied to President Lee, saying "We are all pro-Myeong, pro-Chung," the President broke into a broad smile. (이재명 대통령이 지난 19일 청와대 만찬에서 정청래 더불어민주당 대표에게 “혹시 반명(반이재명)이십니까”라고 물은 일이 화제다. 민주당은 공식 브리핑에서 “대통령이 ‘농담’을 던져 폭소를 자아냈다”고 설명했다. 정 대표가 이 대통령에게 “우리 모두가 친명, 친청입니다”라고 답했고, 대통령은 파안대소했다고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, one dinner attendee said, "When Leader Jung said 'pro-Chung,' there was a momentary silence, as if people had misunderstood the meaning." Leader Jung was referring to the abbreviation for 'pro-Lee Jae-myung, pro-Cheongwadae,' but it was interpreted as meaning 'pro-Lee Jae-myung, pro-Jung Cheong-rae.' Leader Jung immediately clarified that 'pro-Chung' meant "pro-Cheongwadae," and the atmosphere reportedly became warm and friendly. Another attendee also said, "It seems most people thought he meant pro-Jung Cheong-rae and were momentarily taken aback." (하지만 한 만찬 참석자는 “정 대표가 친청이라고 말하는 순간 그 말을 다른 뜻으로 알아들었는지 잠깐 정적이 흘렀다”고 했다. 정 대표가 언급한 건 ‘친이재명, 친청와대’의 줄임말이었는데, ‘친이재명, 친정청래’의 뜻으로 받아들여졌다는 뜻이다. 정 대표는 즉각 친청의 뜻을 “친청와대”라고 풀어 말했고 분위기가 화기애애해졌다고 한다. 다른 참석자도 “대부분 친정청래라고 하는 줄 알고 잠시 당황했던 듯하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An uncomfortable atmosphere between the party and Cheongwadae has been noticeable since Leader Jung Cheong-rae's election as party leader, surrounding various policy issues. And it has escalated into a Myeong-Chung conflict. Each time, the party and Cheongwadae have glossed over the situation by saying, "We are one team." However, within the ruling camp, there are comments that "even a single word like 'pro-Chung' is bound to be sensitive given the current party-Cheongwadae relationship." The party and Cheongwadae are also engaged in a power struggle over the current administration's prosecution reform plan. (당청 간 불편한 분위기는 정청래 대표의 당대표 선출 이후 각종 정책 현안을 둘러싸고 감지됐다. 그리고 명청 갈등으로 비화됐다. 그때마다 당청은 “우리는 원팀”이라며 상황을 넘겼다. 하지만 여권 내에선 “‘친청’ 한마디로도 예민할 수밖에 없는 게 지금의 당청 관계”라는 말이 나온다. 당청은 현재 정부의 검찰 개편안을 놓고도 기싸움을 벌이고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-hyun, the Democratic Party's chief spokesperson appointed by Leader Jung, said on a radio program that day, "In the President's remark 'Are you anti-Myeong?', there was a mix of 95% considerate joke and 5% sincerity," adding, "I think about 5% was genuine." Rep. Han Min-soo, Leader Jung's chief of staff, also said on radio, "The pro-Myeong vs. pro-Chung frame is something that sows discord and divides Cheongwadae and the party." (정 대표가 임명한 박수현 민주당 수석대변인은 이날 라디오에서 “대통령의 ‘반명이십니까’란 말에는 95% 배려의 농담과 5% 진담이 함께 섞여 있다”며 “한 5%는 진심이었던 것 같다”고 했다. 정 대표 비서실장인 한민수 의원도 라디오에서 “친명 대 친청 프레임은 청와대와 당을 이간질하고 갈라치는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are predictions that conflicts in the party-Cheongwadae relationship may intensify again ahead of the August party leadership election following the June local elections. Leader Jung is known to be challenging for re-election as party leader after leading the party to victory in the local elections. Among potential candidates for party leader, pro-Myeong faction figure Prime Minister Kim Min-seok is also mentioned. Because of this, some say the next party leadership struggle has already begun. Therefore, regarding the 'one member, one vote system for delegates and rights-holding party members' championed by Leader Jung, the pro-Myeong faction is calling it "for Jung Cheong-rae's re-election" and urging that its handling be postponed until after the party leadership election. However, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun stated, "One member, one vote is simply a promise to party members," and dismissed the idea of a next party leadership struggle as "nonsense." (당청 관계는 6월 지방선거 이후 오는 8월 당대표 선거를 앞두고 다시 갈등이 증폭될 수도 있다는 말이 나온다. 정 대표는 지방선거를 승리로 이끈 뒤 당대표 연임에 도전할 것으로 알려졌다. 당대표 후보로는 친명계 김민석 국무총리도 거론된다. 이 때문에 차기 당권 투쟁이 벌써 시작됐다는 말도 나온다. 그래서 정 대표가 주도하는 ‘대의원·권리당원 1인 1표제’를 두고 친명계는 “정청래 연임용”이라며 당대표 선거 이후로 처리를 미루자고 하고 있다. 하지만 박수현 수석대변인은 “1인 1표는 당원과의 약속일 뿐”이라며 “차기 당권 투쟁은 말도 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/MKE73YQKB5BGVCZQTZIKJAVEYA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/E3Z3VVR4QJEQNPEEUKQQ3PVMTU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party Launches Late Investigation into Jang Kyung-tae and Choi Min-hee Controversies (장경태·최민희 논란 민주당, 뒤늦게 조사)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/GBBXAMRYLJESNOJPSYXBJRCGHE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Democratic Party Launches Late Investigation into Jang Kyung-tae and Choi Min-hee Controversies (장경태·최민희 논란 민주당, 뒤늦게 조사)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ethics Tribunal of the Democratic Party of Korea has initiated an ex officio investigation into the allegations of sexual harassment against lawmaker Jang Kyung-tae and the controversy surrounding lawmaker Choi Min-hee's daughter's wedding. There had been criticism within the party that the leadership under Chairman Chung Cheong-rae was responding passively to these two issues. Now, the independent Ethics Tribunal has launched a separate investigation. (더불어민주당 윤리심판원이 장경태 의원 성추행 의혹과 최민희 의원의 딸 결혼식 논란에 대해 직권조사에 나섰다. 그동안 두 사안에 대해 당 일각에선 “정청래 지도부가 소극적으로 대응하는 것 아니냐”고 문제를 제기했는데, 독립 기관인 윤리심판원이 별도로 조사에 나선 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Han Dong-soo, the head of the Democratic Party's Ethics Tribunal, stated in an MBC radio interview on the 21st, "I have issued an order for an ex officio investigation into the two cases: lawmaker Jang's sexual misconduct incident and the allegations concerning congratulatory money for lawmaker Choi's wedding." According to the party's regulations, the head of the Ethics Tribunal can order an investigation by the tribunal when it is determined that a party member has engaged in actions harmful to the party. Chairman Han said, "(Regarding the Jang case,) the Ethics Inspection Team and the Ethics Tribunal are investigating, and the police are also conducting an investigation," adding, "Investigations and disciplinary actions are separate. The standards of proof or principles are somewhat different." This was interpreted to mean that disciplinary action is possible even while an investigation is ongoing. (한동수 민주당 윤리심판원장은 21일 MBC라디오 인터뷰에서 “장 의원의 성 비위 사건과 최 의원의 결혼식 축의금 의혹, 두 사안에 대해 직권조사 명령을 발령했다”고 밝혔다. 민주당 당규에 따르면 윤리심판원장은 당원의 해당(害黨) 행위가 있었다고 판단할 때 윤리심판원에 조사를 명령할 수 있다. 한 원장은 “(장 의원 사건을) 윤리감찰단과 윤리심판원이 조사하고 있고, 경찰도 수사하고 있다”며 “수사와 징계는 별개다. 각각의 증명의 정도나 원리는 좀 달리한다”고 했다. 수사 중이라도 징계가 가능하다는 뜻으로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Jang is under police investigation after being reported in November last year on suspicion of sexually harassing an intoxicated woman at a gathering in October 2024. Lawmaker Jang has completely denied the allegations and has filed a counter-complaint against the accuser for false accusation. Democratic Party Chairman Chung Cheong-rae instructed the party's Ethics Inspection Team to investigate when the allegations were reported in the media in November last year, but the results of that investigation have not yet been released. Lawmaker Choi, who chairs the National Assembly's Science, ICT, Broadcasting, and Communications Committee, is under police investigation for the controversy surrounding receiving congratulatory money from audited organizations, among others, for her daughter's wedding held at the National Assembly during the parliamentary audit period in October last year. Chairman Chung has not taken any specific measures regarding this matter. Regarding the Ethics Tribunal's investigation, Lawmaker Jang has not issued a statement, while Lawmaker Choi expressed regret, saying, "I question whether this matter warrants an ex officio investigation." (장 의원은 2024년 10월 한 술자리에서 만취한 여성을 성추행한 혐의로 작년 11월 고소당해 경찰 수사를 받고 있다. 장 의원은 혐의를 전면 부인하면서 고소인을 무고 혐의로 맞고소했다. 정청래 민주당 대표는 이 의혹이 언론에 보도된 작년 11월 당 윤리감찰단에 조사를 지시했으나, 조사 결과는 아직 나오지 않은 상태다. 국회 과학기술정보방송통신위원장인 최 의원은 국정감사 기간인 작년 10월 국회에서 딸 결혼식을 치르며 피감기관 등에서 축의금을 받았다는 논란에 대해 경찰 수사를 받고 있다. 정 대표는 이에 대해선 별다른 조치를 내리지 않았다. 윤리심판원 조사에 대해 장 의원은 입장을 내지 않았고 최 의원은 “이 사안이 직권 조사까지 할 사안인지 의문이 있다”며 유감을 표했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, there has been dissatisfaction, with some questioning why the Ethics Tribunal recently imposed the highest level of discipline, including expulsion, on lawmakers Kim Byeong-gi and Kang Seon-woo, who left the party over allegations of receiving nomination-related donations, while delaying disciplinary action against the previously controversial lawmakers Jang and Choi. One Democratic Party lawmaker said, "Even after leaving the party, lawmaker Kang was expelled to prevent him from rejoining," adding, "It's hard to shake off the suspicion that other lawmakers are being given leniency because they are seen as pro-Chung Cheong-rae faction members." (당 일각에선 최근 윤리심판원이 공천 헌금 수수 의혹 등으로 탈당한 김병기·강선우 의원에 대해선 제명 등 최고 수위의 징계를 하면서도 앞서 논란이 됐던 장·최 의원에 대해선 징계를 미루는 것이냐는 불만이 나왔었다. 한 민주당 의원은 “강 의원은 탈당 후에도 제명해 복당도 못하게 해놨다”며 “다른 의원들은 친정청래계라 봐주기한다는 의심을 지울 수가 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/GBBXAMRYLJESNOJPSYXBJRCGHE/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Jun-seok Visits Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site, Urges Him to "Play the Role of Commander" (장동혁 단식장 달려간 이준석 “지휘관 역할해달라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/5POOFUK2WVGJJMGPQ5PRYPJILQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Jun-seok Visits Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site, Urges Him to "Play the Role of Commander" (장동혁 단식장 달려간 이준석 “지휘관 역할해달라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DS7UW4JVRRJRXHSYBDIWH2KXQY.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party (PPP) leader Jang Dong-hyeok continues his hunger strike for the seventh day on the 21st, demanding a dual special counsel investigation (into the Unification Church and Democratic Party of Korea nomination bribery allegations), Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok visited the hunger strike site and stated, "We will prepare a joint struggle plan and fight together." Lawmakers who have clashed with Leader Jang by demanding a severance of ties with former President Yoon Suk Yeol also expressed their support for his hunger strike. Meanwhile, newly appointed Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo visited the National Assembly to meet with the Democratic Party leadership but did not visit the hunger strike site located just tens of meters away. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 21일 쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검)을 요구하며 7일째 단식을 이어가는 가운데 개혁신당 이준석 대표가 단식 현장을 찾아 “공동 투쟁 방안을 마련해 함께하겠다”고 했다. 윤석열 전 대통령과의 절연을 요구하며 장 대표와 갈등을 빚은 의원들도 장 대표 단식을 지지하는 입장을 밝혔다. 홍익표 신임 청와대 정무수석은 이날 국회를 찾아 민주당 지도부를 만났지만 수십 m 거리의 단식장을 찾지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok, who returned from a business trip to South America in the early hours of the morning, visited Leader Jang's hunger strike site in the National Assembly's Central Hall at 9 a.m. Leader Jang, wearing a medical oxygen concentrator in his nose, greeted Leader Lee inside a tent. Leader Lee said, "Who is there now who does not believe in your resolve?" and added, "To strengthen bipartisan cooperation, you must play the role of commander." Leader Lee returned two days earlier than scheduled after Leader Jang began his hunger strike. Leader Jang stated, "I was able to decide to go on this hunger strike because of the courage shown by Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram, who stepped up as the first filibuster speaker (against the second comprehensive special counsel bill) and did her best." (남미 출장에서 이날 새벽 귀국한 이준석 대표는 오전 9시 국회 중앙홀에 있는 장 대표 단식장을 찾았다. 장 대표는 코에 의료용 산소 발생기를 착용한 채 텐트 안에서 이 대표를 맞았다. 이 대표는 “지금 대표님의 결기를 믿지 못하는 사람이 어디 있느냐”며 “양당 공조를 강화하기 위해서는 대표님이 지휘관으로서 역할을 해주셔야 한다”고 했다. 이 대표는 장 대표가 단식을 시작하자 예정보다 이틀 앞당겨 귀국했다. 장 대표는 “제가 단식 결정을 할 수 있던 건 개혁신당 천하람 원내대표께서 (2차 종합 특검 반대) 필리버스터 1번 주자로 나서서 최선을 다해주시는 그 용기가 있었기 때문”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is known that the PPP and the Reform Party are reviewing joint public opinion campaigns regarding the necessity of introducing the dual special counsel. An opposition party official said, "If the Jang-Seok alliance is activated with the dual special counsel as the link, Leader Jang could gain the justification of expanding his external reach and also explore cooperation in the local elections. However, if the PPP becomes too closely aligned with its hardcore supporters, the alliance will be difficult." (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 쌍특검 도입 필요성에 대한 공동 여론전 등을 검토하는 것으로 알려졌다. 야권 관계자는 “쌍특검을 고리로 장·석 연대가 가동되면 장 대표도 외연 확장이라는 명분을 얻고 지방선거에서 협력도 타진해 볼 수 있다”며 “다만 국민의힘이 강성 지지층에 지나치게 밀착할 경우 연대가 어려울 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a media interview on the same day, PPP lawmaker Lee Seong-kwon, the secretary of the party's reform-minded faction 'Alternative and Future,' stated, "When an external enemy appears, internal fights should stop and we should unite," expressing active support for Leader Jang's hunger strike. Members of 'Alternative and Future' have been at odds with Leader Jang, demanding a severance of ties with former President Yoon and the withdrawal of the ethics committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon. (국민의힘 내 개혁 성향 의원 모임인 ‘대안과 미래’ 간사인 이성권 의원은 이날 한 언론 인터뷰에서 “외부에서 적이 들어오면 내부 싸움을 멈추고 힘을 합쳐야 한다”며 장 대표의 단식을 적극적으로 지지한다는 입장을 밝혔다. 대안과 미래 소속 의원들은 윤 전 대통령과의 절연, 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 윤리위원회의 제명 결정 철회 등을 요구하며 장 대표와 각을 세워왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Minister of Employment and Labor Kim Moon-soo, who competed against Leader Jang in the party leadership election last August, also visited the hunger strike site. The previous day, former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min visited to console Leader Jang, emphasizing, "Even if our thoughts differ, now is the time to put our heads together to find solutions on how to be reborn as a conservatism that the people can trust." (작년 8월 당대표 선거 당시 장 대표와 경쟁했던 김문수 전 고용노동부 장관도 단식 현장을 찾았다. 전날에는 유승민 전 의원이 방문해 장 대표를 위로하고 “생각이 다르더라도 국민이 신뢰할 수 있는 보수로 어떻게 거듭날 수 있는가에 대해 머리를 맞대고 해결책을 찾아야 할 때”라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Seok-yeon, Chairman of the Presidential Committee on National Cohesion, was the first among ruling camp figures to visit Leader Jang's hunger strike site on this day. Chairman Lee requested the hunger strike be stopped, saying, "I don't know how politics has come to this point," and added, "It is the minimum courtesy for the Presidential Chief of Staff or the Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs to check on Leader Jang and deliver a message." Chairman Lee, who is evaluated as a moderate conservative figure, served as a co-chair of the election committee for Lee Jae-myung's presidential campaign and was later appointed as the chairman of the presidential committee. (이석연 국민통합위원장은 이날 여권 인사 가운데 처음으로 장 대표 단식장을 찾았다. 이 위원장은 단식 중단을 요청하고 “어쩌다 정치가 여기까지 왔는지 (모르겠다)”라며 “대통령 실장이나 정무수석은 장 대표를 살펴보고 메시지를 전달하는 게 최소한의 예의”라고 했다. 중도 보수 인사로 평가됐던 이 위원장은 지난 대선 이재명 캠프에서 공동선대위원장을 맡은 뒤 대통령 직속 국민통합위원회 위원장에 임명됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, newly appointed Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo visited the National Assembly to pay a courtesy call on Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae. However, he did not stop by Leader Jang's hunger strike site, located about 20 meters from the National Assembly entrance. PPP chief spokesperson Park Sung-hoon said, "This scene reveals the arrogant perception of the government and the Democratic Party, which view the opposition as an enemy." As Senior Secretary Hong announced he would pay a courtesy call on PPP floor leader Song Eon-seok on the 22nd, the possibility of him visiting Leader Jang's hunger strike site on the same day was mentioned. (비슷한 시각 홍익표 신임 청와대 정무수석은 국회를 찾아 정청래 더불어민주당 대표를 예방했다. 다만 국회 출입구에서 20여 m 떨어진 장 대표 단식장엔 들르지 않았다. 박성훈 국민의힘 수석대변인은 “야당을 적으로 인식하는 정부와 민주당의 오만한 인식이 드러난 장면”이라고 했다. 홍 수석은 22일에는 송언석 국민의힘 원내대표를 예방한다고 밝혀 같은 날 장 대표의 단식 현장을 찾을 가능성이 거론됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Leader Jang's health deteriorated on the seventh day of his hunger strike, the PPP held an emergency general meeting of lawmakers and urged Leader Jang to stop his hunger strike in the name of all party lawmakers. Some senior lawmakers visited Leader Jang to dissuade him from continuing. At the request of lawmakers, a 119 ambulance team was dispatched to the National Assembly with a stretcher, but Leader Jang refused to go to the hospital until the end. On this day, Leader Jang posted on Facebook, "I will be buried here, and the Democratic Party will be buried by public sentiment."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (7일째 단식으로 장 대표 건강이 악화하자 국민의힘은 긴급 의원총회를 열고 의원 전원 명의로 장 대표에게 단식 중단을 촉구했다. 일부 중진 의원은 장 대표를 찾아 단식을 만류했다. 의원들 요청에 따라 119 구급대가 들것을 들고 국회로 출동했지만 장 대표는 끝까지 병원행을 거부했다. 장 대표는 이날 페이스북에 “나는 여기서 묻히고, 민주당은 민심(民心)에 묻힐 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/5POOFUK2WVGJJMGPQ5PRYPJILQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DS7UW4JVRRJRXHSYBDIWH2KXQY.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardliners Calling for Abolition of Supplementary Investigation Authority, President Says "There Are Times When It Is Exceptionally Necessary" (보완 수사권 폐지 외치는 강경파에 “예외적으로 필요할 때 있다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/MP6CLZQDYJCODFVO37DH2QLWEM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Hardliners Calling for Abolition of Supplementary Investigation Authority, President Says "There Are Times When It Is Exceptionally Necessary" (보완 수사권 폐지 외치는 강경파에 “예외적으로 필요할 때 있다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CAA7AAT4VJNUHJOWMCVV4WD42M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the issue of granting supplementary investigation authority to the newly established Public Prosecution Service, President Lee Jae-myung said on the 21st, "I think it's right not to conduct supplementary investigations," but added, "However, there are exceptionally necessary cases." Recently, while announcing the bill to establish the Public Prosecution Service, the government did not provide specific mention regarding supplementary investigation authority. However, hardline lawmakers and strong supporters of the Democratic Party of Korea strongly protested, saying, "The government's proposal essentially intends to retain supplementary investigation authority," and demanding, "Abolish supplementary investigation authority immediately." The President's remarks were an explanation of the need for exceptional permission in response to this. (이재명 대통령은 21일 신설되는 공소청 검사에게 보완 수사권을 부여하는 문제와 관련해 “저는 보완 수사를 안 하는 게 맞다고 생각한다”며 “그러나 예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”고 말했다. 최근 정부는 공소청 신설 법안을 발표하면서 보완 수사권에 대한 구체적 언급은 하지 않았다. 하지만 더불어민주당 강경파 의원과 강성 지지층이 “정부안은 사실상 보완 수사권을 남겨두겠다는 것”이라며 “당장 보완 수사권을 폐지하라”고 강하게 반발했다. 이에 대해 대통령이 예외적 허용 필요성을 설명한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the New Year's press conference that day, President Lee said, "When a case is transferred (from the police to the prosecution) with only two days left before the statute of limitations expires, if supplementary investigations are completely prohibited even for simple verification, sending it back to the police and having it return would take up the remaining two days." He added, "After blocking the possibility of abuse and establishing safety measures, allowing such things is actually a reform for efficiently handling state affairs." (이 대통령은 이날 신년 기자회견에서 “공소시효가 이틀밖에 안 남았는데 (경찰에서 검찰로 사건이) 송치가 됐을 때, 간단히 확인할 게 있어도 보완 수사가 전면 금지돼 있으면 (사건을) 다시 경찰로 보내고 돌아오는 데 이틀이 끝나버린다”며 “남용의 가능성을 봉쇄하고 안전장치를 만든 다음에 그런 것 정도는 허용해 주는 게 실제로 국가 업무를 효율적으로 처리하는 개혁”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "The core of prosecution reform is not taking power away from the prosecution, but protecting citizens' rights and human rights," and questioned, "If we do it in a way that completely strips prosecutors of all their power, how will responsibility be assigned later?" (이 대통령은 “검찰개혁의 핵심은 검찰에서 권력을 빼앗는 게 아니고, 국민의 권리 구제와 인권 보호”라며 “검사의 모든 권력을 완전히 빼앗는 방식으로 해 놓으면 나중에 책임은 어떻게 질 것이냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the Democratic Party hardliners opposing the government's proposal, President Lee said, "We should understand those who act emotionally," and added, "Because the prosecution has committed so many wrongs, hasn't it become a witch? Anything they do is disliked." He also said, "(I) have been most victimized by the prosecution. There are about 20 cases where I was indicted alone," and mentioned, "The Daejang-dong case was also something prosecutors colluded in." However, he continued, "There are over 2,000 prosecutors, how many of them are the ones who did such bad things?" and said, "The rest are people who protect citizens' human rights so that no one is wronged and punish the bad guys." (다만 정부안에 반발하는 민주당 강경파에 대해 이 대통령은 “감정적으로 하는 분도 이해해 줘야 한다”며 “검찰이 하도 저지른 업보가 많아서 마녀가 된 것 아니냐, 뭐든지 미운 것”이라고 했다. 또 “(내가) 검찰에 가장 많이 당했다. 기소된 것만 한 20건”이라며 “대장동도 검사들이 한패로 해 먹은 것”이라고 했다. 그러면서도 “2000명 넘는 검사가 있는데 이런 나쁜 짓 한 검사가 몇 명이나 될까”라며 “나머지는 억울한 사람 없게 국민 인권을 보호하고 나쁜 놈 처벌한 사람들”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said that no conclusion has been reached regarding supplementary investigation authority and suggested, "We have time, so let's discuss it sufficiently." This means discussing until October, when the Supreme Prosecutors' Office closes and the Serious Crimes Investigation Office and the Public Prosecution Service, responsible for investigation and prosecution respectively, are newly established. He also said, "Some are concluding as if the government intends to grant supplementary investigation authority, and some are saying, 'Lee Jae-myung has betrayed us, withdraw support.'" (이 대통령은 보완 수사권에 대해 결론이 나지 않았다며 “시간이 있으니 충분히 논의하자”고 했다. 오는 10월 검찰청은 문을 닫고 수사와 기소를 각각 담당하는 중대범죄수사청과 공소청이 신설되는데 그때까지 논의하자는 얘기다. 또 “마치 정부는 보완 수사권을 주려는 것처럼 단정하고 일부는 ‘이재명이가 배신했어, 지지 철회’ 이러고 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/MP6CLZQDYJCODFVO37DH2QLWEM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CAA7AAT4VJNUHJOWMCVV4WD42M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Blue House is responsible for verifying Lee Hye-hoon... "How would we know if they engaged in power abuse?" (靑에 이혜훈 검증 책임 있는데… “우리가 갑질 어떻게 아느냐”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/TIYV5EUOW5G2FCWEDG2Y3YHYGE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The Blue House is responsible for verifying Lee Hye-hoon... "How would we know if they engaged in power abuse?" (靑에 이혜훈 검증 책임 있는데… “우리가 갑질 어떻게 아느냐”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, who faces various allegations including real estate speculation and power abuse by aides, President Lee Jae-myung said on the 21st, "It does seem there are problems," but added, "This is a person who received nominations from that side (the People Power Party) five times, was elected as a lawmaker three times, and no issues were raised before." The President spoke with the intent that the nominee should be given an opportunity to explain herself at a National Assembly confirmation hearing. Subsequently, the ruling and opposition parties tentatively agreed to hold a hearing on the 23rd, provided the nominee submits materials related to the various allegations demanded by the opposition party. (이재명 대통령은 21일 부동산 투기, 보좌진 갑질 등 각종 의혹이 제기된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대해 “문제가 있어 보이기는 한다”면서도 “그쪽(국민의힘) 진영에서 공천을 5번 받고 3번이나 국회의원에 당선되고 아무런 문제가 제기되지 않았던 분”이라고 했다. 이 대통령은 이 후보자가 국회 인사청문회를 통해 소명할 기회를 줘야 한다는 취지로 말했고, 이후 여야는 오는 23일 청문회를 열기로 잠정 합의했다. 이 후보자가 야당이 요구하는 각종 의혹과 관련한 자료를 제출하면 열겠다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the press conference that day, President Lee said, "I haven't yet decided what to do about nominee Lee Hye-hoon." Previously, the National Assembly failed to hold a hearing for this nominee due to a breakdown in inter-party agreement. The President said, "I wanted to have an opportunity to hear her story publicly and listen to the public's judgment after seeing the hearing process, but it was blocked, which is regrettable." He continued, "I don't easily believe even stories from very close people," adding, "Shouldn't we also hear the person's own explanation regarding that? That is fair." (이 대통령은 이날 기자회견에서 “이혜훈 후보자에 대해 어떻게 할지 아직 결정을 못 했다”고 했다. 앞서 국회는 여야 합의가 무산돼 이 후보자 청문회를 열지 못했다. 이 대통령은 “본인 이야기를 공개적으로 들어볼 기회를 갖고, 청문회 과정을 본 국민 판단을 들어보고 싶었는데 봉쇄돼 아쉽다”고 했다. 이어 “저는 아주 가까운 사람 얘기도 잘 안 믿는다”며 “거기에 대해 본인의 해명도 들어봐야 하는 것 아니냐. 그게 공정하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding criticism that the Blue House's verification was insufficient, the President said, "There are problems, and ultimately it is lacking," but also stated, "How would we know whether that person engaged in power abuse towards their aide or not?" Then, addressing the People Power Party, he said, "They attack using information only they know among themselves, as if punishing a traitor like in the movie 'The Godfather'," adding, "For us, it's difficult to know." The responsibility for verifying nominees lies with the Blue House. In particular, the core allegation against this nominee—the suspicion of fraudulent subscription for an apartment in Seoul's Banpo-dong One Pentas through her eldest son's feigned unmarried status—is an area that could have been sufficiently verified. However, the President did not mention this. (이 대통령은 청와대의 검증이 미흡했다는 지적에 대해서는 “문제가 있고, 결론적으로 부족하다”면서도 “그분이 보좌관에게 갑질했는지 안 했는지 우리가 어떻게 아느냐”라고 했다. 그러면서 국민의힘을 향해 “자기들끼리만 알고 있는 정보를 갖고 마치 (영화) ‘대부’에 나오는 배신자 처단하듯 공격한다”며 “우리로서는 알기 어렵다”고 했다. 후보자 검증 책임은 청와대에 있다. 특히 이 후보자의 핵심 의혹인 장남의 위장 미혼을 통한 서울 반포동 원펜타스 아파트 부정 청약 의혹은 충분히 검증 가능한 부분이다. 하지만 대통령은 이에 대해선 언급하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this nominee, appointed as part of a unity personnel move, President Lee said, "In the economic field, conservative values are also an important aspect, so I tried this with the thought of listening to different voices and working together," adding, "I didn't know we would encounter such fierce resistance." He also said, "If necessary, we use bows, swords, and spears; we can't just be told to 'only use swords,' can we?" Furthermore, he stated, "Please tolerate the necessity of such personnel to some extent," and "Although we divided sides and fought, the fight is over, so we must take the path of unity."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령은 통합 인사로 지명한 이 후보자에 대해 “경제 분야는 보수적 가치가 중요한 부분도 있으니 다른 목소리도 듣고 함께하자는 생각에 시도해본 것”이라며 “이렇게 극렬하게 저항에 부딪힐 줄은 몰랐다”고 했다. “필요하면 활도 쓰고 칼도 쓰고 창도 쓰고 그러는 것이지, 모두 ‘칼만 쓰라’ 이렇게 할 수는 없지 않나”고도 했다. 그러면서 “이런 인사의 필요성을 일부 용인해달라”며 “편을 갈라 싸우긴 했지만 싸움이 끝났으니 통합의 길로 가야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/TIYV5EUOW5G2FCWEDG2Y3YHYGE/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Exchange Rate Expected to Be Around 1,400 Won in a Month or Two... No Special Measures" (“환율 한두달 뒤 1400원 전후 될 것… 특별 대책은 없어”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/KCRKKNI475A2FI3D7W2CEJBUP4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Exchange Rate Expected to Be Around 1,400 Won in a Month or Two... No Special Measures" (“환율 한두달 뒤 1400원 전후 될 것… 특별 대책은 없어”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/R3RO27W76BJUDPWTFPCZAH6ACA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;At his New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee Jae-myung, regarding the recent surge in the exchange rate, stated, "It is a difficult situation to restore it to normal with Korea's policies alone," but also said, "The foreign exchange authorities predict that the exchange rate (of the won against the dollar) will fall to around the 1,400 won level soon." Regarding real estate tax policies, he said, "Taxes are not a means of regulation," but also added, "If problems arise, tax measures must also be mobilized." The market reacted, saying, "The President's message is complex and somewhat confusing." (이재명 대통령은 21일 신년 기자회견에서 최근 치솟는 환율과 관련해 “대한민국만의 정책으로 원상 회복은 어려운 상황”이라면서도 “외환 당국은 (달러 대비 원화) 환율이 조만간 1400원 선으로 내려온다고 예측한다”고 했다. 부동산 세제와 관련해서는 “세금은 규제의 수단이 아니다”라면서도 “문제가 되면 세제도 동원해야 한다”고 했다. 시장에서는 “이 대통령의 메시지가 복합적이라 다소 혼란스럽다”는 반응이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Exchange Rate Expected to Be Around 1,400 Won in a Month or Two"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“환율, 한두 달 뒤 1400원 전후 될 것”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about exchange rate countermeasures that day, President Lee said, "If there were special measures, we would have already taken them," and "Since it is not a phenomenon unique to Korea, it is a difficult situation to reverse with Korea's policies alone." He then added, "According to the authorities, it is predicted that it will fall to around 1,400 won in about a month or two." This was interpreted as being optimistic about dollar supply and demand because exports are doing well. Following the President's remarks, the exchange rate fell to the late 1,460 won range during the day before closing at 1,471.3 won. (이날 이 대통령은 ‘환율 대책이 있느냐’는 질문에 “특별한 대책이 있으면 이미 했을 것”이라며 “대한민국만의 독특한 현상은 아니어서 대한민국만의 정책만으로 되돌리기는 어려운 상황”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “당국에 의하면 한두 달 정도 지나면 1400원 전후로 떨어질 거라고 예측한다”고 했다. 수출이 잘되고 있기 때문에 달러 수급을 낙관하는 것으로 해석됐다. 이 대통령 언급에 환율은 장중 한때 1460원대 후반까지 떨어졌다가 1471.3원으로 마감했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also said, "If we were to exactly match Japan's standard, the exchange rate should be 1,600 won, but compared to the yen-dollar linkage, we are still holding up well." However, there were criticisms that directly comparing the yen, a quasi-key currency, with the won, a non-key currency, is unreasonable. The United States has a 'standing currency swap' agreement with Japan, allowing it to borrow dollars whenever necessary. (이 대통령은 또 “일본 기준을 그대로 맞추면 (환율이) 1600원이 돼야 하지만 엔·달러 연동에 비하면 그래도 잘 견디는 편”이라고 했다. 하지만 준기축통화인 엔화와 비기축통화인 원화를 직접 비교하는 것은 무리라는 지적이 나온다. 미국은 일본과는 필요할 때 언제든 달러를 빌려 쓸 수 있는 ‘상설 통화 스와프’를 체결하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"If Real Estate Crosses the Line, Tax Measures Will Be Mobilized"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“부동산, 선 넘으면 세제 수단 동원”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding real estate tax policies, President Lee said, "It is not desirable to repurpose taxes as a means of regulation," and "There is constant talk in the market about property holding taxes, but it is politically incorrect and places an unfair burden on our citizens." He continued, "There are rumors about strengthening property holding taxes only for properties exceeding 5 billion won, but as of now, we are not deeply considering implementing real estate policies through tax measures." (부동산 세제와 관련해 이 대통령은 “세금을 이걸 규제의 수단으로 전용하는 건 바람직하지 않다”며 “시중에 보유세 얘기를 자꾸 하는데, 정치적으로 옳지 않고 우리 국민에게 부당한 부담을 준다”고 했다. 이어 “50억원 넘는 데만 보유세를 (강화)한다는 소문이 있으나, 지금으로서는 세제를 통해 부동산 정책을 하는 것은 깊이 고려하고 있지 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, President Lee also said, "If a necessary situation arises, there is no reason not to use them just because they are not desirable," and "If the line is crossed and it becomes a social problem, tax measures must also be mobilized." He added, "Speculative demand of buying and hoarding multiple houses is not desirable and requires regulation," which was interpreted as meaning that taxes targeting multiple homeowners could be further strengthened. However, since the Moon Jae-in administration, most multiple homeowners have reduced their number of houses and switched to a 'solid single house.' The market is on high alert over whether the government's real estate regulations will target 'solid single homeowners'. (이 대통령은 그러면서도 “필요한 상황이 됐는데 바람직하지 않다는 이유만으로 쓰지 않을 이유는 없다”며 “선을 벗어나 사회적 문제가 되는 단계라면 세제 수단도 동원해야 한다”고 했다. 또 “집을 여러 채 사 모으는 투기 수요는 바람직하지 않으며 규제가 필요하다”고 했는데 다주택자를 겨냥한 세금은 더 강화할 수 있다는 취지로 해석된다. 다만 문재인 정부 이후 대부분의 다주택자가 주택 수를 정리하고 ‘똘똘한 한 채’로 갈아탔다. 시장은 정부의 부동산 규제가 ‘똘똘한 1주택’으로 향할지 촉각을 곤두세우고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "The Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport will soon announce realistic supply expansion measures," and "We intend to present realistic figures. Not at the planning level, but based on 'permits, approvals, and groundbreaking standards.'" (이 대통령은 “곧 국토교통부에서 현실적인 공급 확대 방안을 발표할 것”이라며 “현실적인 수치를 제시하려고 한다. 계획 수준이 아니라 ‘인·허가와 착공 기준으로 (발표할 것)’”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Stock Investment Should Be Done Wisely on One's Own"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“주식 투자 알아서 잘해야”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "There are baseless rumors spreading that the government intends to arbitrarily use retirement pensions to defend the foreign exchange market," and "It is not only impossible but also unnecessary, and we have absolutely no intention of doing so." He added, "If the parties involved don't want it, it can't be done." The ruling Democratic Party of Korea had earlier this month stated that it is proceeding with a project to pool retirement pensions into a fund. Currently, retirement pensions are managed through individual contracts between subscribers and financial institutions, and the idea is to pool them for fund-based management. (이 대통령은 “퇴직연금을 정부에서 외환시장을 방어하려고 마음대로 쓰려고 그런다 이런 헛소문이 퍼지고 있다”며 “가능하지도 않을 뿐 아니라 그렇게 할 필요도 없고 그렇게 할 의사도 전혀 없다”고 했다. 이어 “당사자가 싫으면 못하는 것”이라고도 했다. 여당인 더불어민주당은 이달 초 퇴직연금 기금화 용역을 진행 중이라고 밝힌 바 있다. 현재 퇴직연금은 가입자가 개별 금융기관과 계약해 운용하는데, 이를 모아 기금으로 운용하자는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also said that day that he would not force the pooling into a fund, but added, "The return on retirement pensions is around 1%. They are not being managed well, so should we just leave them as is?" and "Pooling into a fund is one of the alternatives that can be considered." (이 대통령도 이날 기금화를 강제하지 않을 것이라 하면서도 “퇴직연금의 수익률이 1% 수준이다. 운영이 잘 안 되는데 방치할 것인가”라며 “기금화도 생각할 수 있는 대안 중 하나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding recent stock market trends, he said, "Looking at the U.S. market last night (20th) or the international situation, it should have plummeted, but in reality, it didn't fall much," and "This means there are quite a few buyers waiting on the sidelines." He then said, "Stock investment is something each person must do wisely on their own. No one will take responsibility for it." (최근 증시 동향에 대해서는 “어젯밤(20일) 미국 장이나 국제 정세를 보면 대폭락했어야 했는데 실제로는 많이 안 떨어졌다”며 “대기 매수자가 상당히 있다는 의미”라고 했다. 그러면서 “주식 투자는 각자가 알아서 잘해야 한다. 아무도 책임져주지 않는다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Supplementary Budget, Won't Be in the Trillions or Tens of Trillions"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“추경, 몇 조원씩 하진 않을 것”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the claim raised by Democratic Party lawmakers from the Honam region about 'relocating the Yongin Semiconductor Cluster,' he said, "It's not something that can be moved just because the government says to move it," but added, "It's not something to be decided politically, but persuasion or inducement is possible." Regarding administrative integration, he said it is "a symbolic starting point for 'regional-led growth' and a national survival strategy that must be made successful." President Lee also said, "If regional integration is achieved, up to 5 trillion won annually can be supported, and if integration is achieved within my term, up to about 20 trillion won can be supported." (민주당 호남 의원들이 제기했던 ‘용인 반도체 클러스터 이전’ 주장과 관련해서는 “정부가 옮기라고 옮겨지나”라면서도 “정치적으로 결정할 일은 아니고, 다만 설득이나 유도는 할 수 있다”고 했다. 행정 통합에 대해선 “‘지방 주도 성장’의 상징적 출발점이자 반드시 성공시켜야 할 국가의 생존 전략”이라고 했다. 이 대통령은 “광역 통합을 하면 연간 최대 5조원까지, 제 임기 내에 통합하면 최대 20조원 정도를 지원할 수 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding new nuclear power plant construction, he said, "I think the nuclear power issue has become too politicized," and "If necessary, we can review (new nuclear power plants), including safety issues." Regarding a supplementary budget, he said, "When I said that if there is an opportunity for a supplementary budget, support for the culture and arts sectors should be increased a bit, rumors spread that we are doing a supplementary budget," and "It's not about issuing deficit bonds worth trillions or tens of trillions of won." (신규 원전 건설과 관련해서는 “원전 문제가 너무 정치 의제화됐다고 생각한다”며 “필요하면 안전성 문제를 포함해 (신규 원전을) 검토할 수 있다”고 했다. 추경에 대해서는 “추경의 기회가 있다면 문화·예술 분야 지원을 좀 늘려야겠다고 했더니 추경을 한다고 소문이 났다”며 “몇 조원, 몇십 조원씩 적자 국채를 발행해서 하는 것은 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/KCRKKNI475A2FI3D7W2CEJBUP4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/R3RO27W76BJUDPWTFPCZAH6ACA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Will North Korea Give Up Its Nukes?" Lee's First Mention of Nuclear Disarmament Negotiations (“북한이 핵을 포기하겠나” 李, 핵 군축 협상 첫 언급)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/RNCLEAGYWNDBBBL4GDXEHFG2BE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Will North Korea Give Up Its Nukes?" Lee's First Mention of Nuclear Disarmament Negotiations (“북한이 핵을 포기하겠나” 李, 핵 군축 협상 첫 언급)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRSJEYAIREETNT4LF5AUMKGVA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;At his New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee Jae-myung, regarding the North Korean nuclear issue, said, "Denuclearization should happen, and while that is the most ideal, will North Korea give up its nukes?" He added, "Let's start with the most realistic first step, which is freeze negotiations, and then proceed with nuclear disarmament, disarmament negotiations." He continued, "Let's aim for denuclearization in the long run," and stated, "If their regime security is guaranteed and the (nuclear) management costs become too high, wouldn't they (North Korea) possibly get rid of (their nukes)?" (이재명 대통령은 21일 신년 기자회견에서 북핵 문제와 관련해 “비핵화를 해야 하는데 (그것이) 가장 이상적이기는 하지만 북한이 핵을 포기하겠나”라며 “1단계로 가장 현실적인 중단 협상을 하고 그다음 핵 군축, 군축 협상하자”고 말했다. 이어 “길게는 비핵화를 향해 가자”며 “체제 보장이 확실하고 (핵) 관리 비용이 많이 들면 (북이 핵을) 없앨 수도 있지 않을까”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the first time since taking office that President Lee has clearly stated, "Let's have 'disarmament negotiations'." Nuclear disarmament negotiations have traditionally been conducted between recognized nuclear powers like the US and Russia. Shin Kak-soo, former Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs, commented, "Starting to mention disarmament could also be interpreted as a de facto acknowledgment of their nuclear possession." (이 대통령이 ‘군축 협상’을 하자고 명확히 말한 것은 취임 후 처음이다. 핵 군축 협상은 미·러 등 공인된 핵보유국 간에 이뤄져 왔다. 신각수 전 외교부 차관은 “군축을 언급하기 시작하면 핵 보유를 사실상 인정했다는 해석도 가능하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The press conference lasted 173 minutes, nearly double the scheduled 90 minutes. While President Lee mentioned a 'nuclear-free Korean Peninsula' in his opening remarks, when questioned about his North Korea strategy, he brought up 'disarmament negotiations,' saying, "(Denuclearization) is an ideal, but the result of ignoring reality while dreaming of that ideal is that nuclear weapons continue to increase." (이날 회견은 예정된 90분보다 두 배쯤 늘어난 173분간 진행됐다. 이 대통령은 모두 발언에서 ‘핵 없는 한반도’를 언급했지만 대북 전략에 대한 질문이 나오자 “(비핵화란) 이상을 꿈꾸면서 현실을 외면한 결과, 핵무기가 계속 늘어나고 있다”며 ‘군축 협상’을 거론했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his opening remarks under the theme 'Great Transformation for Growth,' President Lee stated, "We will completely reallocate the government's resources and capabilities to redraw the growth map," proposing "local-led growth" through wide-area integration and "growth for all" centered on startups to share opportunities and fruits. However, he mentioned, "We will take care of specific policies," without providing detailed plans. (이 대통령은 ‘성장을 위한 대전환’이란 주제의 모두 발언에서 “정부가 지닌 자원과 역량을 완전히 재배치해 성장 지도를 다시 그리겠다”며 광역 통합을 통한 “지방 주도 성장”, 스타트업 중심으로 기회와 과실을 나누는 “모두의 성장” 등을 제시했다. 다만 세부안 없이 “구체적 정책을 챙겨 나가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "There are even churches preaching that 'Lee Jae-myung must die for the country to live'," adding, "I think (some Protestants) might naturally engage in such rhetoric." (이 대통령은 “‘이재명이 죽어야 나라가 산다’고 설교하는 교회도 있다”며 “(일부 개신교도) 자연스럽게 수사하게 되지 않을까 싶다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding granting 'supplementary investigation authority' to the prosecution service after abolishing the Supreme Prosecutors' Office, he said, "I think it's right not to conduct supplementary investigations. However, there are exceptional cases where it's necessary," and added, "Allowing that much is a reform for efficient handling of state affairs." (검찰청 폐지 후 공소청에 ‘보완수사권’을 주는 데 대해서는 “보완 수사를 안 하는 게 맞다고 생각한다. 그러나 예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”며 “그런 거 정도는 해주는 게 국가 업무를 효율적으로 처리하는 개혁”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Should we take a hardline stance and have a showdown with North Korea? That would ruin the economy."&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“고자세로 북한과 한판 떠야 하나, 그러면 경제 망하는 거다”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung, who proposed a North Korean nuclear solution of 'freeze → reduction → denuclearization' last August, changed the expression to 'stop → disarmament → denuclearization' in a September TIME interview. At the time, a presidential office official said, "It doesn't seem he meant any particular significance by saying 'disarmament'." This can be seen as being mindful of the criticism that 'nuclear disarmament' could effectively mean condoning North Korea's nuclear program. (지난해 8월 ‘동결(freeze)→축소(reduction)→비핵화’의 북핵 해법을 제시한 이재명 대통령은 9월 타임 인터뷰에서 ‘중단(stop)→군축(disarmament)→비핵화’로 표현을 바꿨다. 당시 대통령실 관계자는 “어떤 의미를 담아 ‘군축’이라고 말한 것 같지는 않다”고 했다. ‘핵 군축’은 사실상 북핵 용인이 될 수 있다는 지적을 의식했다고 볼 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 21st, President Lee also suggested having disarmament negotiations, asking, "Does that mean giving up on denuclearization? There are various opinions." He then said, "Let's approach this pragmatically," and "We must do what the other side can accept." Kim Jong Un, Chairman of North Korea's State Affairs Commission, said last year, "Denuclearization is absolutely impossible." (이 대통령도 21일 군축 협상을 하자며 “그러면 비핵화를 포기하는 거냐. 여러 얘기들이 있다”고 했다. 이어 “실용적으로 접근하자” “상대가 받아들일 수 있는 것을 해야 한다”고 말했다. 김정은 북한 국무위원장은 지난해 “비핵화는 절대로 있을 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Park Won-gon of Ewha Womans University said, "It seems (he) used the (disarmament) expression to cross the threshold (of dialogue) since North Korea says it can't engage in denuclearization talks." Former Vice Minister Shin Kak-soo expressed concern, saying, "Even if it's difficult, we must stick to the goal of denuclearization to have a 'card' to use in US-North Korea negotiations; if we throw it away first, the game doesn't work." (박원곤 이화여대 교수는 “북한이 비핵화 협상은 못 하겠다니 (대화의) 문턱을 넘으려고 (군축) 표현을 쓴 것 같다”고 했다. 신각수 전 차관은 “어려워도 비핵화 목표를 고수해야 미북 협상 때 우리가 쓸 ‘카드’가 생기는데 먼저 던지면 게임이 안 된다”고 우려했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding 'unification,' President Lee said, "In the current situation, it's fortunate if we avoid war, let alone talk about unification." Kim Jong Un also said last year, "Unification is absolutely unnecessary." (‘통일’에 대해 이 대통령은 “지금 통일은커녕 전쟁만 안 나도 다행인 상황”이라고 말했다. 김정은은 지난해 “결단코 통일은 불필요하다”고도 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding North Korea recently raising the 'unmanned aerial vehicle' issue, President Lee said, "It's like being startled by a pot lid after being scared by an eel; (their) distrust (toward the South) has reached its peak," adding, "This is not siding with North Korea. It's about seeing things from their perspective." Responding to criticism that the government's response is 'low-key,' he said, "Then should we take a hardline stance and have a showdown? With North Korea? That's foolish," and added, "That would ruin the economy." (최근 북한이 ‘무인기’ 문제를 제기한 데 대해 이 대통령은 “자라 보고 놀란 가슴 솥뚜껑 보고도 놀란다고 (대남) 불신이 극에 달해 있는 것”이라며 “북한 편드는 것이 아니다. 역지사지하는 것”이라고 했다. 정부의 대처가 ‘저자세’란 비판에 대해서는 “그러면 고자세로 한판 떠야 하나. 북한하고? 바보같이”라며 “그러면 경제 망하는 거다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee emphasized the importance of the US role, saying, "President Trump is a somewhat unique person, but that style seems helpful for dialogue with Chairman Kim Jong Un." However, regarding tariff threats, he emphasized 'strategic autonomy,' stating, "We must not be either 'entrapped' or 'abandoned' (by the alliance)." On South Korea-Japan relations, he said, "While I am not satisfied with the existing agreements on comfort women and forced labor, overturning state-to-state agreements just because administrations changed creates problems for international trust." (이 대통령은 미국의 역할이 중요하다며 “트럼프 대통령이 약간 독특한 분이긴 한데 그런 스타일이 김정은 위원장과 대화에 도움이 되는 것 같다”고 했다. 다만 관세 위협과 관련해서는 ‘전략적 자율성’을 강조하며 “(동맹에) ‘연루’도 ‘방기’도 되면 안 된다”고 했다. 한일 관계에 대해서는 “위안부, 강제징용에 대한 기존 합의가 마음에 들지는 않는데 국가 간 합의를 정권 바뀌었다고 뒤집으면 국제적 신뢰에 문제가 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Chinese President Xi Jinping, he said, "He is humane and better at jokes than I thought," and added, "(During the meeting on the 5th) I also gained confidence that we can manage elements of conflict well." He also said about Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi, whom he met on the 13th, "I would like to host her in Andong once within a short time." (시진핑 중국 국가주석에 대해서는 “인간적이고 생각보다 농담도 잘한다”며 “(지난 5일 회담에서) 갈등 요소도 잘 관리할 수 있을 거라는 확신도 들었다”고 했다. 또 지난 13일 회담한 다카이치 사나에 일본 총리를 “빠른 시간 안에 안동에서 한 번 모시고 싶다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/RNCLEAGYWNDBBBL4GDXEHFG2BE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRSJEYAIREETNT4LF5AUMKGVA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoon Suk-yeol's First Guilty Verdict... Is the 'Sedition = Abuse of Authority' Logic Logically Perfect? (윤석열 첫 유죄…‘내란=직권남용’ 논리적으로 완벽한가?)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/national/court_law/2026/01/22/6KQELLABSJFJLBXP2CPJIY7LQI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Yoon Suk-yeol's First Guilty Verdict... Is the 'Sedition = Abuse of Authority' Logic Logically Perfect? (윤석열 첫 유죄…‘내란=직권남용’ 논리적으로 완벽한가?)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JAFPHSQRO5AFLB63CAC3366B5I.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, the Seoul Central District Court sentenced former President Yoon Suk-yeol to five years in prison on charges including obstruction of the execution of an arrest warrant by the Corruption Investigation Office for High-ranking Officials (CIO). (서울중앙지방법원은 지난 16일, 고위공직자범죄수사처(공수처)의 체포영장 집행을 방해한 혐의 등으로 윤석열 전 대통령에게 징역 5년을 선고했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This case is a trial concerning the execution process of an arrest warrant that took place at the presidential residence in Hannam-dong, Seoul, in January of last year. At the time, the CIO attempted to execute an arrest warrant issued by the Seoul Western District Court, and the Presidential Security Service physically blocked it. The prosecution and the court judged that this blocking action was not a legitimate duty at the level of security protection, but constituted 'instigation' by former President Yoon, who mobilized security service personnel to prevent the execution of the warrant. (이번 사건은 작년 1월 서울 한남동 대통령 관저에서 벌어진 체포영장 집행 과정을 다루는 재판입니다. 당시 공수처는 서울서부지방법원에서 발부받은 체포영장을 집행하려 했고, 대통령경호처는 이를 물리적으로 저지했습니다. 검찰과 법원은 이 저지 행위가 경호 차원 정당한 직무가 아니라, 윤 전 대통령이 경호처 인력을 동원해 영장 집행을 막도록 한 ‘교사(敎唆)’에 해당한다고 판단했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This case was not simply a matter of "whether a former president broke the law." Questions concerning the very foundation of constitutional order and criminal procedure were simultaneously raised. (이 사건은 단순히 “전직 대통령이 법을 어겼는가”의 문제가 아니었습니다. 헌정 질서와 형사 절차의 근간에 관한 질문들이 동시에 제기됐습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will calmly examine the key issues to see whether the court's reasoning contained in the verdict (213 pages) sufficiently answered these questions. (판결문(213쪽)에 담긴 법원의 판단이 이런 의문들에 충분히 답했는지를 주요 쟁점을 차분히 따져보겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The crime of obstruction of official duties presupposes that the official duty is lawful. In other words, if the CIO did not have the authority to investigate the crime of sedition, then the execution of the arrest warrant based on that would be unlawful, and the act of resisting it would not constitute a crime. This is the premise from which this case originates. (공무집행방해죄는 공무가 적법할 것을 전제로 합니다. 즉, 공수처가 내란죄를 수사할 권한이 없다면, 그에 기초한 체포영장 집행은 위법이고, 이에 저항한 행위도 범죄가 성립하지 않습니다. 이 사건의 출발점이 되는 전제입니다)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The CIO Act enumerates the targets of CIO investigation as 'high-ranking public official crimes' such as bribery, abuse of authority, and violations of the Political Funds Act. Sedition is not explicitly listed here. Regarding this, the CIO has argued as follows. (공수처법은 공수처 수사 대상을 뇌물죄, 직권남용죄, 정치자금법 위반 등 ‘고위공직자 범죄’로 열거하고 있습니다. 여기에 내란죄는 명시돼 있지 않습니다. 이에 대해 공수처는 이렇게 주장해 왔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court sided with the CIO, stating that "the CIO Act does not prohibit the investigation of separate cases, and the crime of being a ringleader of sedition falls under a 'related crime' of abuse of authority." The verdict viewed the crimes of sedition and abuse of authority as crimes derived from the same factual circumstances. Both crimes were listed together on the arrest warrant. "The suspect (former President Yoon), in conspiracy with Kim Yong-hyun, Park An-su, and Yeo In-hyeong, etc., with the purpose of excluding state power or disrupting the national constitution, incited a riot and abused his authority to make police officers belonging to the National Assembly Police Guard and martial law troops perform duties they were not obligated to do." (법원은 “공수처법은 별건 수사를 금지하고 있지 아니하고, 내란우두머리 범죄는 직권남용의 ‘관련 범죄’에 해당한다”면서 공수처의 손을 들어줬습니다. 판결문은 내란죄와 직권남용죄가 동일한 사실관계에서 파생된 범죄라고 봤습니다. 체포영장에도 두 범죄가 함께 기재돼 있었습니다. “피의자(윤 전 대통령)는 김용현, 박안수, 여인형 등과 공모하여 국가 권력을 배제하거나 국헌을 문란하게 할 목적으로 폭동을 일으키고 직권을 남용하여 경찰 국회경비대 소속 경찰관들과 계엄군들에게 의무 없는 일을 하게 하였다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, legal questions remain. (그러나 법리적 의문이 남습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If crimes with such an overwhelming difference in penalty can be subsumed under the reason of being 'related crimes,' the very purpose of the CIO Act limiting its investigative targets becomes meaningless. Even at the time, there was criticism calling it "an interpretation where the tail swallows the body," but the verdict addressed this issue in a mere four pages. Furthermore, following the court's logic that 'the factual circumstances are the same,' controversy could arise as to whether indicting the same factual circumstances as both sedition and abuse of authority constitutes double jeopardy. It is regrettable that the court does not seem to have sufficiently answered such questions. (이처럼 형량 차이가 압도적인 범죄를 ‘관련 범죄’라는 이유로 포섭할 수 있다면, 공수처법이 굳이 수사 대상을 한정한 취지가 무색해집니다. 당시에도 “꼬리가 몸통을 삼키는 해석”이라는 비판이 나왔지만, 판결문은 이 문제를 불과 네 쪽 분량으로 처리했습니다. 또 ‘사실관계가 동일하다’는 법원 논리에 따르면 같은 사실관계를 내란죄와 직권남용으로 기소하면 이중 기소가 아니냐는 논란도 생길 수 있습니다. 이런 문제에 대해 법원이 충분히 답하지 않은 듯해 아쉽습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Yoon's side argued that the actions of the security service were legitimate security acts to prevent an illegal arrest. The underlying logic is simple. (윤 전 대통령 측은 경호처의 행동이 불법 체포를 막기 위한 정당한 경호 행위라고 주장했습니다. 전제가 되는 논리는 간단합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Yoon's side took issue with the fact that the CIO obtained the warrant from the Seoul Western District Court, not the Seoul Central District Court. (윤 전 대통령 측은 공수처가 서울중앙지법이 아닌 서울서부지법에서 영장을 발부받은 점을 문제 삼았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Article 26 of the CIO Act stipulates that for crimes over which a CIO prosecutor does not have the authority to prosecute, the case must be transferred to the Seoul Central District Prosecutors' Office. Based on this, they argued that the Central District Court has exclusive jurisdiction. This led to controversy, the so-called 'warrant shopping' allegation, questioning whether the CIO chose a court where obtaining a warrant would be easier. (공수처법 26조는 공수처 검사가 공소 제기 권한이 없는 범죄에 대해서는 사건을 서울중앙지검으로 송부하도록 규정하고 있습니다. 이를 근거로 중앙지법이 전속 관할이라는 주장입니다. 이는 공수처가 영장 발부가 수월한 법원을 고른 것 아니냐는 이른바 ‘영장 쇼핑’ 논란으로 이어졌습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court did not accept this argument either. (법원은 이 주장도 받아들이지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Therefore, it judged that there was no violation of jurisdiction and that the warrant was lawful. (따라서 관할 위반은 없고, 영장은 적법하다고 판단했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The arrest warrant from the Seoul Western District Court in January of last year contained a phrase stating that "Articles 110 and 111 of the Criminal Procedure Act do not apply." (작년 1월 서울서부지법 체포영장에는 “형사소송법 110조·111조는 적용되지 않는다”는 문구가 기재돼 있었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Articles 110 and 111 are provisions stipulating that search and seizure cannot be conducted in places requiring military or official secrets without the consent of the person in charge. The presidential residence has hitherto been perceived as effectively being protected by these provisions. However, this warrant included a phrase 'excluding application.' There was controversy not only because it was unprecedented, but also over whether the warrant undermined the intent of the law. Former President Yoon's side also argued that the warrant was unlawful on these grounds. (110조·111조는 군사상·공무상 비밀을 요하는 장소에 대해 책임자의 승낙 없이 압수·수색할 수 없도록 한 조항입니다. 대통령 관저는 그간 사실상 이 조항의 보호 대상처럼 인식돼 왔습니다. 그런데 이번 영장에는 ‘적용 제외’ 문구를 적었습니다. 전례가 없을 뿐 아니라 영장이 법의 취지를 훼손한 게 아니냐는 논란도 있었습니다. 윤 전 대통령 측도 이 같은 사유를 들어 영장이 위법하다고 주장했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court viewed this phrase as not being problematic. (법원은 이 문구가 문제 되지 않는다고 봤습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the logic is that the warrant was lawful, and the act of obstructing it was obstruction of official duties that went beyond the scope of security protection. However, if it was a 'non-beneficial entry' whose inclusion had no effect, there is no explanation as to why that unprecedented phrase was explicitly written. While stating it had no legal effect, it was a key phrase that caused conflict between the security service and the investigative agency at the scene at the time, yet the court is not providing a clear interpretation of it. (결론적으로 영장은 적법하고, 이를 방해한 행위는 경호 범위를 벗어난 공무집행방해라는 논리입니다. 그러나 기재해도 효과가 없는 ‘무익적 기재사항’이라면, 왜 굳이 전례 없이 그 문구를 적시했는지 설명은 없습니다. 법적 효력이 없다면서도, 당시 현장에서는 경호처와 수사기관 간 충돌을 유발한 핵심 문구였는데 법원은 이를 명확하게 해석해주지 않고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court concluded overall that there were no legal defects in the issuance and execution process of the arrest warrant in January of last year. And it judged that former President Yoon's act of mobilizing security service personnel to block the warrant execution was a privatized abuse of authority. (법원은 전반적으로 작년 1월 체포영장 발부·집행 과정에 법적 하자는 없었다고 결론 내렸습니다. 그리고 윤 전 대통령이 경호처 인력을 동원해 영장 집행을 막은 행위는 사병화된 직권남용이라고 판단했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this verdict is finalized (이 판결이 확정되면)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, questions that clearly remain also exist. (그러나 여전히 남는 질문도 분명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some in the legal community raise the question: "As long as the validity of the Western District Court's warrant could not be denied, wasn't an acquittal judgment by the Central District Court structurally impossible?" (법조계 일각에서는“서부지법 영장의 효력을 부정할 수 없는 이상, 중앙지법의 무죄 판단은 구조적으로 불가능했던 것 아니냐”는 문제 제기도 나옵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Separate from the moral assessment of former President Yoon as an individual, this leaves behind an important legal task: how to set standards for future investigations of high-ranking public officials and the warrant system. This is why it is necessary to await the judgment of the higher court. (이는 윤 전 대통령 개인에 대한 도덕적 평가와는 별개로, 향후 고위공직자 수사와 영장 제도의 기준을 어떻게 설정할 것인가라는 중요한 법리적 과제를 남깁니다. 상급심의 판단을 지켜볼 필요가 있는 이유입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/national/court_law/2026/01/22/6KQELLABSJFJLBXP2CPJIY7LQI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JAFPHSQRO5AFLB63CAC3366B5I.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Story of a Businessman Who Went to the Heritage Foundation and Ripped Up a $10,000 Check (한 기업인이 헤리티지재단에 가 1만 달러 수표를 찢은 사연)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/22/HR5HAYXBWZH3HD2PQNEVCTD3RY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The Story of a Businessman Who Went to the Heritage Foundation and Ripped Up a $10,000 Check (한 기업인이 헤리티지재단에 가 1만 달러 수표를 찢은 사연)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 1984, Heritage Foundation President Edwin Feulner emphasized a short but practical principle to his staff: "Don't pre-judge who the enemy is." (1984년 가을, 헤리티지재단 회장 에드윈 퓰너는 임직원들에게 짧지만 실무적인 원칙 하나를 강조했다. “적이 누구인지 미리 단정하지 마라.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statement wasn't about ideological flexibility. It was closer to meaning that one should look at the 'pathway of ideas' before political camps. Policies don't move along party or ideological lines. They move towards those who have explanatory power and the ability to propose alternatives for specific issues. Feulner defined the think tank's mission not as 'rallying allies,' but as preparing the logic that policymakers would have no choice but to select. (이 말은 이념적 유연성을 말하는 게 아니었다. 정치적 진영 구분보다 ‘아이디어의 이동 경로’를 먼저 보라는 뜻에 가까웠다. 정책은 정당이나 이념 진영을 따라 움직이지 않는다. 특정 문제에 대한 설명력과 대안 제시 능력을 가진 쪽으로 이동한다. 퓰너는 싱크탱크 임무를 ‘아군을 규합하는 일’이 아니라, 정책 결정자가 선택할 수밖에 없는 논리를 준비하는 일로 규정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A prime example of this principle in action was the progressive-leaning black columnist William Raspberry. He wrote a column arguing that the minimum wage actually reduced employment opportunities for young black people. (이 원칙이 실제로 작동한 대표 사례가 진보 성향 흑인 칼럼니스트 윌리엄 래스베리였다. 그는 최저임금제가 흑인 청년층의 고용 기회를 오히려 줄인다는 칼럼을 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This claim was not a simple difference of opinion. At the time, raising the minimum wage was a policy symbol close to 'justice' within the American progressive camp. Criticizing it was seen as an act of turning one's back on the socially disadvantaged. Raspberry's argument essentially shook the internal logic of that position. (이 주장은 단순한 이견이 아니었다. 당시 미국 진보 진영에서 최저임금 인상은 ‘정의’에 가까운 정책 상징이었다. 이를 비판하는 건 곧 사회적 약자를 외면하는 행위로 여겨졌다. 래스베리의 주장은 그 내부 논리를 뒤흔드는 셈이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was precisely the point the Heritage Foundation had long been raising. (헤리티지가 오래전부터 제기해 온 논점도 바로 여기에 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A macro-level explanation is added here. When employment becomes rigid, corporate cost structures worsen, leading to reduced profits. When profits fall, investment and employment shrink, and ultimately tax revenue also decreases. When tax revenue shrinks, the welfare expenditures the government must bear also come under pressure. Heritage's fundamental concern was that 'policies created with good intentions can have counterproductive effects on the overall system.' (여기에 거시적 설명이 덧붙는다. 고용이 경직되면 기업의 비용 구조가 악화되고, 이는 이윤 감소로 이어진다. 이윤이 줄면 투자와 고용이 위축되고, 결국 세수도 감소한다. 세수가 줄어들면 정부가 감당해야 할 복지 지출 역시 압박을 받는다. ‘선의로 만든 정책이 전체 시스템에서는 역효과를 낼 수 있다’는 게 헤리티지의 기본 문제의식이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heritage did not simply argue 'let's eliminate regulations.' It proposed a dual structure: expanding labor market flexibility while returning those who fall out of the market back into it. (헤리티지는 단순히 ‘규제를 없애자’고 주장하지 않았다. 노동시장 유연성을 확대하되, 그로 인해 탈락하는 사람들을 다시 시장으로 돌려보내는 이중 구조를 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This model was strategic because, unlike the 'small government' slogan, it did not completely deny the role of government. The government was positioned not as directly intervening in the market, but as a 'rear support' helping individuals who have fallen out of the market to re-enter. (이 모델은 ‘작은 정부’ 구호와 달리, 정부의 역할을 완전히 부정하지 않는다는 점에서 전략적이었다. 정부는 시장에 직접 개입하기보다, 시장에서 탈락한 개인이 다시 진입할 수 있도록 돕는 ‘후방 지원자’로 위치 지워진다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was also the point that led Raspberry to change his mind. He encountered data through the writings of conservative black economist Walter Williams showing that the minimum wage increased black youth unemployment, and he was logically persuaded. Heritage did not directly persuade Raspberry. Instead, it circulated materials around him that he would inevitably find persuasive. It was an exercise of think tank-style influence. (래스베리가 생각을 바꾸게 된 계기도 이 지점이었다. 그는 보수 성향 흑인 경제학자 월터 윌리엄스의 글을 통해 최저임금이 흑인 청년 실업률을 높인다는 데이터를 접했고, 논리적으로 설득됐다. 헤리티지는 직접 래스베리를 설득하지 않았다. 대신 그가 설득당할 수밖에 없는 자료를 주변에 흘려보냈다. 싱크탱크식 영향력 행사였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feulner emphasized to his staff not to judge the media ideologically. He believed that while it was undeniable that mainstream American media had a progressive lean, the moment one defined them as the enemy, policy influence would be blocked. (퓰너는 임직원들에게 언론을 이념적으로 평가하지 말라고 강조했다. 미국 주류 언론이 진보 성향이라는 사실은 부정할 수 없지만, 그렇다고 이를 적으로 규정하는 순간 정책 영향력은 차단된다고 봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A case he frequently mentioned was ABC's reporting on privatization. In a roughly five-minute report, ABC covered the advantages of privatizing state-owned enterprises relatively balancedly. This was a line of argument Heritage had consistently advocated. (그가 자주 언급한 사례가 ABC 방송의 민영화 보도였다. ABC는 약 5분 분량 리포트에서 공기업 민영화의 장점을 비교적 균형 있게 다뤘다. 이는 헤리티지가 꾸준히 주장해온 논지였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key source for this report was Steve Hanke, then Heritage's senior research fellow. He was a figure who had explained the logic of privatization in a structure journalists could understand, not just in short interview soundbites. Media reporting doesn't change overnight. It becomes possible when long-accumulated explanation and trust build up. (이 보도의 핵심 취재원은 헤리티지의 수석연구원이던 스티브 행크였다. 그는 짧은 인터뷰용 발언이 아니라, 기자들이 이해할 수 있는 구조로 민영화 논리를 설명해온 인물이었다. 언론 보도는 하루아침에 바뀌지 않는다. 장기간 축적된 설명과 신뢰가 쌓일 때 가능해진다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The point of contact Feulner particularly valued was speechwriters. He saw the speech secretaries for the president, senators, representatives, and governors as the "first gatekeepers of policy." (퓰너가 특히 중시한 접점은 연설문 작성자들이었다. 그는 대통령, 상·하원 의원, 주지사의 연설 비서관을 “정책의 첫 관문”으로 봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most policies go through this process. (정책은 대부분 이런 과정을 거친다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this process, speech secretaries look for logic suppliers. Feulner believed Heritage should become precisely that supplier. Because a single sentence that makes it into a speech can later be replicated into dozens of bills and policy reports. (연설 비서관은 이 과정에서 논리 공급자를 찾는다. 퓰너는 헤리티지가 바로 그 공급자가 되어야 한다고 봤다. 연설문에 들어간 문장 하나는 이후 수십 개 법안과 정책 보고서로 복제될 수 있기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What Feulner repeatedly emphasized was the report. Op-eds are highly volatile, but reports cited in policy documents last a long time. (퓰너가 반복해서 강조한 것은 보고서였다. 언론 기고는 휘발성이 강하지만, 정책 문서에 인용된 보고서는 오래 남는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Heritage publishes a human rights report, the Republican leadership distributes it to its members. The members refer to the report during the bill review process, and the report gets cited in official minutes and policy materials. The moment it enters congressional documents, that idea becomes official language. (헤리티지가 인권 보고서를 발간하면, 공화당 지도부가 이를 소속 의원들에게 배포한다. 의원들은 법안 검토 과정에서 해당 보고서를 참조하고, 보고서는 공식 회의록과 정책 자료에 인용된다. 의회 문서에 들어간 순간, 그 아이디어는 공식 언어가 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is also why Feulner recalled that "officials from Nicaragua's Sandinista regime or the Soviet government read Heritage reports." Once a human rights report begins to function as a standard document in international diplomacy, even the criticized parties cannot ignore it. (퓰너가 “니카라과 산디니스타 정권이나 소련 정부 관계자들이 헤리티지 보고서를 읽었다”고 회고한 이유도 여기에 있다. 인권 보고서가 국제 외교의 기준 문서로 기능하기 시작하면, 비판받는 당사자들조차 이를 무시할 수 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feulner did not confine Heritage's policy philosophy solely to domestic American reform. The principles of the free market and individual freedom strengthen the U.S. economy, and the strengthened U.S. market attracts foreign companies. When these companies return to their home countries and demand the same systems, the policy philosophy spreads across borders. (퓰너는 헤리티지의 정책 철학을 미국 내부 개혁에만 가두지 않았다. 자유시장과 개인의 자유라는 원칙은 미국 경제를 강화하고, 강해진 미국 시장은 외국 기업을 끌어들인다. 이 기업들이 다시 본국으로 돌아가 같은 제도를 요구하면, 정책 철학은 국경을 넘어 확산된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Asian Studies Center, established in 1984, was a result of this vision. In South Korea, Samsung and Hyundai participated as major sponsors. As the two companies grew and the Korean-style market economy took root, there is no shortage of research mentioning the influence of the policy discourse provided by Heritage. (1984년 설립된 아시안 스터디 센터는 이런 구상의 결과였다. 한국에서는 삼성과 현대가 주요 후원자로 참여했다. 두 기업의 성장과 함께 한국식 시장경제가 정착하는 과정에서, 헤리티지가 제공한 정책 담론의 영향력을 언급하는 연구도 적지 않다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the UN's Third World Conference on Women held in Nairobi, Kenya in 1985, Heritage utilized another strategic asset. The Reagan administration requested Heritage's cooperation to help conservative-leaning organizations participate. However, official NGO status was required. (1985년 케냐 나이로비에서 열린 유엔 제3차 세계여성대회에서 헤리티지는 또 다른 전략적 자산을 활용했다. 레이건 행정부는 보수 성향 단체들의 참여를 돕기 위해 헤리티지에 협조를 요청했다. 단, 공식 NGO 자격이 필요했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heritage had already secured NGO status in 1982. This qualification, which had little significance in U.S. domestic politics, served as a pass guaranteeing a political voice on the international stage. (헤리티지는 이미 1982년에 NGO 지위를 확보해 두고 있었다. 미국 국내 정치에서는 큰 의미가 없었던 이 자격은, 국제 무대에서는 정치적 발언권을 보장하는 통행증 역할을 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The six principles Feulner outlined boil down to one message. Ideas exert power not at a prepared moment, but when an event occurs. Therefore, the role of a think tank is not to create 'policy for immediate use,' but to prepare policy packages that can be called upon at any time. (퓰너가 정리한 여섯 가지 원칙은 하나의 메시지로 귀결된다. 아이디어는 준비된 순간이 아니라, 사건이 터졌을 때 힘을 발휘한다. 따라서 싱크탱크의 역할은 ‘지금 쓰일 정책’을 만드는 것이 아니라, 언제든 호출될 수 있는 정책 패키지를 준비하는 일이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Heritage Foundation expanded its financial base at a relatively rapid pace after its launch. As of 1979, 87 U.S. corporations sponsored the foundation, with an annual budget reaching $3.7 million. This was an increase of about one-third compared to the previous year. Compared to 1976, the year before Feulner took office, it had grown fourfold in just three years. (헤리티지 재단은 출범 이후 비교적 빠른 속도로 재정 기반을 확대했다. 1979년 기준으로 미국 내 87개 기업이 재단을 후원했고, 연간 예산은 370만달러에 달했다. 이는 전년 대비 약 3분의 1이 늘어난 규모였다. 퓰너가 취임하기 전인 1976년과 비교하면 불과 3년 만에 네 배로 커진 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This figure was not merely a growth indicator. In the Washington think tank ecosystem, financial scale directly translates to voice. Sufficient budget is needed to stably hire research personnel and operate long-term research projects, not one-off commentaries. Feulner perceived financial expansion as "the minimum condition for securing policy autonomy." (이 수치는 단순한 성장 지표가 아니었다. 워싱턴 싱크탱크 생태계에서 재정 규모는 곧 발언권을 의미한다. 충분한 예산이 있어야 연구 인력을 안정적으로 고용할 수 있고, 단발성 논평이 아닌 장기 연구 프로젝트를 운영할 수 있다. 퓰너는 재정 확대를 “정책 자율성을 확보하기 위한 최소 조건”으로 인식했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Feulner made one principle clear: corporate money must not be allowed to silence the foundation. This principle actually came at a great cost. (그러나 퓰너는 한 가지 원칙을 분명히 했다. 기업의 돈이 재단의 입을 막게 해서는 안 된다는 것이었다. 이 원칙은 실제로 큰 대가를 치르게 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heritage consistently supported free trade and promoting competition. This position directly clashed with the U.S. steel and textile industries, which were under restructuring pressure in the 1980s. These companies, demanding protectionism and government support, opposed Heritage's policy line, and some publicly ceased sponsorship. An anecdote from that time is symbolic: a businessman ripped up a $10,000 check in front of Feulner as a protest. This was not simply an emotional fight; it was closer to pressure saying, "Change your policy in exchange for the sponsorship." Feulner did not yield. He believed that the moment a think tank adjusts its position according to stakeholder demands, its credibility as a policy designer collapses. (헤리티지는 자유무역과 경쟁 촉진을 일관되게 지지했다. 이는 1980년대 들어 구조조정 압박에 시달리던 미국 철강·섬유 업계와 정면으로 충돌하는 입장이었다. 보호무역과 정부 지원을 요구하던 이 기업들은 헤리티지의 정책 노선에 반발했고, 일부는 공개적으로 후원을 중단했다. 당시 한 기업인이 항의의 뜻으로 퓰너 앞에서 1만달러짜리 수표를 찢어버렸다는 일화는 상징적이다. 이는 단순한 감정 싸움이 아니라, “후원금의 대가로 정책을 바꾸라”는 압박에 가까웠다. 퓰너는 이에 굴복하지 않았다. 싱크탱크가 이해관계자의 요구에 따라 입장을 조정하는 순간, 정책 설계자로서 신뢰는 무너진다고 봤기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite such conflicts, Heritage's finances actually grew even more after the Reagan administration took office. The foundation's income increased from $5.3 million in 1980 to $7.1 million in 1981, and the number of full-time staff reached 87. (이런 갈등에도 불구하고, 레이건 행정부 출범 이후 헤리티지의 재정이 오히려 더 성장했다. 재단 수입은 1980년 530만달러에서 1981년 710만달러로 늘었고, 정규 직원 수도 87명에 달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This shows that Heritage did not rely simply on 'corporate sponsorship.' Individual donors, small-to-medium sponsors, and conservative-leaning citizen networks formed important pillars of its finances, creating a structure not swayed by the interests of specific industries. Consequently, Heritage secured the financial leeway to maintain its independence even as it grew closer to the ruling power. (이는 헤리티지가 단순히 ‘기업 후원금’에 의존하지 않았음을 보여준다. 개인 기부자, 중소 후원자, 보수 성향 시민 네트워크가 재정의 중요한 축을 형성하면서, 특정 산업의 이해에 휘둘리지 않는 구조를 만들었다. 결과적으로 헤리티지는 집권 세력과 가까워질수록 오히려 독립성을 유지할 수 있는 재정적 여유를 확보하게 됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the Reagan era, Heritage was often called the 'think tank of the ruling conservatives.' However, internally, it did not define itself as the administration's propaganda organization. Feulner repeatedly emphasized that &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;"just because an administration is conservative doesn't mean all its policies are automatically right."&lt;/mark&gt; (레이건 시대, 헤리티지는 흔히 ‘집권 보수의 싱크탱크’로 불렸다. 그러나 내부적으로는 스스로를 정권의 홍보 조직으로 규정하지 않았다. 퓰너는 &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;“정권이 보수적이라고 해서 모든 정책이 자동으로 옳은 건 아니다”&lt;/mark&gt;라는 점을 반복해서 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, Heritage publicly criticized when some personnel appointed by the Reagan administration pushed policies based on political calculations or personal judgment without understanding core conservative values. It believed that remaining silent for being in the same camp was not the role of a think tank. (실제로 헤리티지는 레이건 행정부에 기용된 일부 인사들이 보수의 핵심 가치에 대한 이해 없이, 정치적 계산이나 개인적 판단에 따라 정책을 밀어붙일 경우 공개적으로 비판했다. 같은 진영이라는 이유로 침묵하는 것은 싱크탱크의 역할이 아니라고 본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point, Feulner defined reform as follows: Reform is not a slogan, but the work of actually changing institutions and regulations. The judgment was that if one shouts for small government in words but doesn't actually touch the regulatory structure, that is not reform but merely a slogan.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대목에서 퓰너는 개혁을 이렇게 정의했다. 개혁은 구호가 아니라 제도와 규제를 실제로 바꾸는 작업이다. 말로는 작은 정부를 외치면서, 정작 규제 구조를 손대지 않는다면 그것은 개혁이 아니라 슬로건에 불과하다는 판단이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/22/HR5HAYXBWZH3HD2PQNEVCTD3RY/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Religious Intervention in Politics is an Act of Rebellion; Shouldn't Protestants Also Be Investigated?" (“종교의 정치 개입은 반란 행위, 개신교도 수사해야하지 않겠나”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/22/SRBXLLKHTFCQRFUFIVYQLYU4KY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Religious Intervention in Politics is an Act of Rebellion; Shouldn't Protestants Also Be Investigated?" (“종교의 정치 개입은 반란 행위, 개신교도 수사해야하지 않겠나”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6HHZCDG67RJTXD4FTTEYJRRK4E.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 21st regarding religious groups' intervention in politics, "It is akin to an act of rebellion, pointing guns at the people," and "must be eradicated at its roots." He also stated that suspicions surrounding the Unification Church and Shincheonji should be thoroughly investigated, and regarding 'some Protestant groups,' he added, "Shouldn't it be natural to investigate them as well?" (이재명 대통령은 21일 종교 단체의 정치 개입과 관련해 “국민을 향해 총구를 겨누는 반란 행위와 같다”며 “반드시 뿌리 뽑아야 한다”고 했다. 또 통일교·신천지 의혹을 철저히 수사해야 한다면서 ‘일부 개신교’에 대해서도 “자연스럽게 수사해야 되지 않을까 싶다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the New Year's press conference that day, in response to an MBC reporter's question that "the People Power Party's stance on the special counsel investigation into the Unification Church and Shincheonji seems inconsistent, and there is criticism that it's a delaying tactic," President Lee said, "I get the feeling that they don't really want to do it internally but are only saying so outwardly." He further predicted that the ruling and opposition parties would clash over the scope of the investigation and the method of recommending the special counsel, saying, "(An agreement on the special counsel bill) probably won't happen." He explained that this is also why he had instructed the prosecution and police to conduct investigations. (이 대통령은 이날 신년 기자회견에서 “통일교·신천지 특검에 대해 국민의힘의 행보가 오락가락하고, 지연 작전 아니냐는 비판이 나온다”는 MBC 기자의 질문에 대해 “속으로는 안 하고 싶은데 겉으로만 (도입하자) 말하는 게 아닐까라는 생각이 든다”고 했다. 이어 수사 대상, 특검 추천 방식을 놓고 여야가 대립하리라 전망하면서 “(특검법 합의가) 아마 안 될 것”이라고 했다. 자신이 검찰과 경찰에 수사를 지시한 것도 그 때문이라는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the People Power Party and the Reform Party demanded a special counsel investigation into the Unification Church, claiming that the special investigation team for the Min Jung-ki case had obtained statements that the Unification Church also gave money and valuables to figures from the Democratic Party of Korea, including lawmaker Jeon Jae-soo, but did not investigate. The Democratic Party argued for a special counsel investigation into both the Unification Church and Shincheonji, citing reports that Shincheonji followers had systematically joined the People Power Party. However, regarding suspicions of the special investigation into Min Jung-ki involving a ruling party figure, they took the stance that it "has political motives" and cannot be included in the investigation scope. (앞서 국민의힘과 개혁신당은 민중기 특별검사팀이 통일교가 전재수 의원 등 더불어민주당 인사에게도 금품을 줬다는 진술을 확보하고도 수사하지 않았다며 통일교 특검을 요구했다. 민주당은 신천지 교도가 국민의힘에 조직적으로 입당했다는 보도를 근거로 통일교·신천지 특검을 하자고 주장했다. 하지만 여당 인사가 연루된 민중기 특검 의혹에 대해선 “정치적 의도가 있다”며 수사 대상에 못 넣는다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also said that day, "We can't just railroad or unilaterally push through a special counsel investigation, can we?" People Power Party lawmaker Na Kyung-won responded, "All special counsel bills so far have been unilaterally pushed through by the Democratic Party, so these words are inconsistent," and added, "The People Power Party holds the position of accepting a Shincheonji special counsel as well; the President is distorting the opposition party's stance." (이 대통령은 이날 “특검을 날치기, 일방 처리할 수도 없지 않습니까”라고도 했다. 국민의힘 나경원 의원은 “지금까지 모든 특검법을 민주당 주도로 일방 처리했는데 앞뒤가 안 맞는 말”이라며 “국민의힘은 신천지 특검도 수용한다는 입장인데, 대통령이 야당의 입장을 왜곡하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee spent a considerable amount of time during the press conference criticizing the issue of religious groups' intervention in politics. He said, "It seems Shincheonji started (political intervention) a long time ago, and the Unification Church also seems to have intervened a lot," and "Protestants haven't done it systematically well, but recently, cases have emerged where they are openly doing it systematically." He continued, "There are even churches that repeatedly preach during sermons that 'Lee Jae-myung must be killed for the country to survive,'" and stated, "If religious beliefs and political preferences become combined, it is a path to the country's ruin." (이 대통령은 기자회견에서 상당 시간을 할애해 종교 단체의 정치 개입 문제를 비판했다. 이 대통령은 “신천지는 오래전부터 (정치 개입을) 시작했다는 것 같고, 통일교도 많이 개입한 것 같다”며 “개신교는 조직적으로 잘 하지는 않았는데 최근에는 아예 대놓고 조직적으로 하는 경우가 생겨나고 있다”고 했다. 그러면서 “설교 시간에 ‘이재명을 죽여야 나라가 산다’고 반복적으로 설교하는 교회도 있다”며 “종교적 신념과 정치적 선호가 결합해 버리면 나라가 망하는 길”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also hinted at the possibility of expanding investigations into religious groups. President Lee said, "Originally, there have been various controversies and claims that some Protestant groups should also be investigated," and "They are being left alone for now, but shouldn't it be natural to investigate them?" While he did not mention specific allegations, political circles interpreted this as targeting Protestant groups leading anti-President Lee protests. (종교 단체에 대한 수사 확대 가능성도 시사했다. 이 대통령은 “원래 일부 개신교도 수사해야 되는 거 아니냐는 여러 가지 논란, 주장들이 있었다”며 “지금은 놔두고 있는데 자연스럽게 수사해야 되지 않을까 싶다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 구체적인 혐의에 대해 언급하지는 않았으나, 정치권에선 이 대통령 비판 시위를 주도하는 개신교 단체를 겨냥한 것이라는 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Cheong Wa Dae (Blue House) official stated, "He clarified that acts by far-right forces disguising themselves as religion to intervene in politics should be sanctioned according to law and principles." However, legal circles pointed out that the President's remarks are seen as practically suggesting an investigation direction. A Protestant community official said, "While politics and religion should be separated, the President's remarks could be seen as politics interfering in religion instead, so a cautious approach is needed." (청와대 관계자는 “극우 세력이 종교로 둔갑해 정치에 개입하는 행위는 법과 원칙에 따라 제재돼야 한다는 점을 밝힌 것”이라고 했다. 하지만 법조계에선 이 대통령의 발언이 사실상 수사 방향을 제시한 것으로 보인다는 지적도 나온다. 한 개신교계 관계자는 “정치와 종교는 분리해야 하지만 이 대통령의 발언은 거꾸로 정치가 종교에 관여하는 것으로 보일 수 있는 만큼 신중한 접근이 필요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the possibility that the 2nd Comprehensive Special Counsel Act (Special Counsel Act for Investigating the Truth of Acts of Rebellion/Foreign Interference and State Affairs Manipulation by Yoon Suk-yeol and Kim Keon-hee), passed by the National Assembly led by the Democratic Party, could affect the June local elections, President Lee said, "It doesn't seem likely to be significant." He stated, "We will conduct strict investigations according to principles regardless of friend or foe, and uncover the truth to strictly hold those responsible, so there likely won't be a big difference (between whether it's a special counsel, police, or prosecution conducting the investigation)." (민주당 주도로 국회를 통과한 2차 종합 특검법(윤석열·김건희에 의한 내란·외환 및 국정농단 행위의 진상규명을 위한 특검법)이 6월 지방선거에 영향을 미칠 가능성에 대해 이 대통령은 “크지는 않을 것 같다”고 했다. 그는 “피아(彼我)를 가리지 않고 원칙대로 엄정하게 수사할 건 하고, 진상을 가려서 책임을 엄정하게 물어야 하기 때문에 특검, 경찰, 검찰 (중 누가 수사를 하는지는) 큰 차이는 없을 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 2nd Comprehensive Special Counsel, which passed through the Cabinet meeting on the 20th, will operate for up to 170 days, overlapping with the local election period. Since local governments could also become investigation targets regarding acts of collaboration under martial law, the opposition party is concerned it is a 'special counsel for the local elections.' The special counsel will be appointed by President Lee from among candidates recommended by the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, respectively. (지난 20일 국무회의까지 통과한 2차 종합 특검은 최장 170일간 운영돼 지방선거 기간과 겹친다. 계엄 동조 행위와 관련해 지방자치단체도 수사 대상이 될 수 있어 야당에선 ‘지방선거용 특검’이라고 우려하고 있다. 특별검사는 민주당과 조국혁신당이 각각 추천한 후보 가운데 1명을 이 대통령이 임명한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the meeting with People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk requested by the People Power Party, President Lee said, "Right now, dialogue between the ruling and opposition parties seems to be the priority," and "If I engage in direct dealings with individual parties, what would happen to the ruling-opposition relationship or the National Assembly in Yeouido?" He indicated he has no intention of accepting it immediately. (국민의힘이 요구한 장동혁 대표와의 회담에 대해 이 대통령은 “지금은 여야 간 대화가 우선인 것 같다“며 “제가 개별 정당과 직거래를 하면 여야 관계나 여의도 국회는 어떻게 되겠느냐”고 했다. 당장은 응할 생각이 없다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/22/SRBXLLKHTFCQRFUFIVYQLYU4KY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6HHZCDG67RJTXD4FTTEYJRRK4E.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>He picked a 'conservative killer,' but it turned out to be self-destruction?... The background of how the 'Lee Hye-hoon card' became a blunder. (‘보수 킬러’ 뽑았는데 알고보니 자폭?… ‘이혜훈 카드’가 악수가 된 배경)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/premium/2026/01/22/YUOLCVTCIBEOTMA3PYATFA63DM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;He picked a 'conservative killer,' but it turned out to be self-destruction?... The background of how the 'Lee Hye-hoon card' became a blunder. (‘보수 킬러’ 뽑았는데 알고보니 자폭?… ‘이혜훈 카드’가 악수가 된 배경)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z2IH6PVH3JAWBB2TJLQ3VSBXDQ.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon is on the brink of collapse due to opposition from the opposition party. The surface-level reason is the nominee's failure to submit required documents. However, the fundamental reasons are the continuously raised allegations of misconduct against the nominee and the framing of her as a traitor. The People Power Party is demanding the nominee's withdrawal and continuing to boycott the hearing. Negative voices are also erupting within the ruling bloc regarding this nominee's appointment. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회가 야당의 반대로 무산 위기에 처해 있습니다. 이 후보자의 자료 미제출이 표면적 이유입니다. 하지만 근본적인 이유는 끊임없이 제기되는 이 후보자 비위 의혹과 배신자 프레임입니다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자 사퇴를 요구하며 청문회를 계속 보이콧하고 있습니다. 여권 내부에서도 이 후보자 임명에 대해 부정적 목소리가 분출하고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, President Lee Jae-myung has not given up on his will to appoint this nominee. Even at the New Year's press conference on the 21st, he said, "We must hear the nominee's explanation at the hearing." But even if she gets a chance to explain at the hearing, the possibility of changing the negative public opinion about her seems slim. Why is the President so fixated on this nominee? (하지만 이재명 대통령은 이 후보자 임명 의지를 버리지 않고 있습니다. 21일 신년 기자회견에서도 “청문회에서 이 후보자의 해명을 들어봐야 한다”고 말했습니다. 하지만 청문회에서 해명 기회를 갖는다고 해도 이 후보자에 대한 부정적 여론이 바뀔 가능성은 별로 없어 보입니다. 이 대통령은 왜 이 후보자에게 이처럼 집착하는 걸까요.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling bloc, there is an observation that "the arrow of a one-hit kill that President Lee shot at the People Power Party was precisely nominee Lee Hye-hoon." It is said that this nominee was the President's trump 'divide and rule' card to strike at the conservatives' weak spot and shake their foundation. However, that sniper arrow missed its target due to unexpected allegations of misconduct. The interpretation is that he cannot easily discard this nominee due to regret over the failed gamble and a lingering attachment to somehow revive that card. (여권 내부에선 “이 대통령이 국민의힘을 향해 쏜 일격필살의 화살이 바로 이혜훈 후보자였기 때문”이라는 관측이 나옵니다. 이 후보자는 보수의 급소를 찌르고 기반을 흔들기 위한 이 대통령의 회심의 ‘이이제이(以夷制夷)’ 카드였다고 합니다. 그런데 그 저격용 화살이 예기치 못한 비위 의혹 때문에 과녁을 빗나가 버린 겁니다. 승부수가 빗나간 데 대한 아쉬움, 그 카드를 어떻게든 되살려 보려는 미련 때문에 이 후보자를 쉽사리 버리지 못하고 있다는 해석입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the core of the ruling bloc, there is talk that "if the card President Lee chose to snipe the PPP was not Lee Hye-hoon, a 'department store of misconduct allegations,' but another conservative figure with relatively less controversy, like former lawmaker Kim Sung-sik, the PPP would have been in a considerable dilemma." The idea is that the PPP would have faced a contradictory situation where they could neither easily support nor simply oppose the appointment. However, with the flood of misconduct allegations against this nominee, the opposition party seized an opportunity to counterattack the President. (여권 핵심부에선 “만일 이 대통령이 국힘을 저격하기 위해 선택한 카드가 ‘비위 의혹 백화점’인 이혜훈이 아니라 상대적으로 논란이 적은 김성식 전 의원 같은 다른 보수 인사였다면 국민의힘이 상당히 곤혹스러웠을 것”이라는 말이 나옵니다. 국민의힘이 후보자 임명에 찬성할 수도 없고 반대만 하기도 힘든 자가당착의 상황을 맞았을 거란 얘기입니다. 그런데 이 후보자의 비위 의혹이 쏟아지면서 야당이 이 대통령에게 반격할 기회를 잡았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Kim Sung-sik was appointed this time, alongside nominee Lee Hye-hoon, as the Vice Chairman of the Presidential National Economic Advisory Council, a ministerial-level position. There were even rumors that he was initially considered for a ministerial post. If former lawmaker Kim had been nominated as a ministerial candidate, it's highly likely that the same misconduct controversies as with this nominee would not have occurred. (김성식 전 의원은 이번에 이혜훈 후보자와 함께 장관급인 대통령 직속 국민경제자문회의 부의장에 임명됐습니다. 당초 김 전 의원에게 장관 자리를 제안하려 했다는 소문도 없지 않습니다. 만일 김 전 의원이 장관 후보자에 지명됐다면 이 후보자와 같은 비위 논란은 일어나지 않았을 가능성이 큽니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hearing for this nominee has not been held for several days. Legally, the deadline for holding it has passed. The opposition party boycotting the hearing itself is unusual. The general practice is to hold the hearing, subject the nominee to sharp scrutiny, and then oppose the appointment. This is because the hearing is 'the opposition party's time' where they can lay out their mat and raise their voices. But this time is different. (이 후보자 청문회는 며칠째 열리지 못하고 있습니다. 법적으론 개최 기한이 지났습니다. 야당이 청문회 자체를 보이콧하는 것은 이례적인 일입니다. 청문회를 열어 후보자를 칼날 검증한 뒤 임명에 반대하는 것이 일반적 관례입니다. 청문회는 야당이 멍석을 깔고 목소리를 높일 수 있는 ‘야당의 시간’이기 때문입니다. 그런데 이번에는 다릅니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party judged that if they readily opened the hearing, they could get caught in the President's strategy. The thinking is that since the President will do as he pleases anyway, there's no need to play a supporting role or grant absolution. Opening a hearing doesn't mean only the opposition party speaks. The ruling party holds far more seats. While they could dig into the allegations, covering fire could also scatter attention and dilute the suspicions. (국민의힘은 선선히 청문회를 열어주면 이 대통령 전략에 말려들 수 있다고 봤습니다. 어차피 대통령 마음대로 할 텐데 공연히 들러리 서거나 면죄부 줄 필요가 없다는 것입니다. 청문회를 열면 야당만 발언하는 게 아닙니다. 여당 숫자가 훨씬 많습니다. 의혹을 파헤칠 수도 있지만 엄호 사격으로 시선이 흩어지고 의혹이 희석될 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;Furthermore, it seems they weren't sure they had an additional, definitive blow to surely take down this nominee.&lt;/mark&gt; By continuously delaying the hearing, the opposition party could induce internal strife within the ruling bloc as negative voices grow. It could also embarrass the Blue House, which was hoping for a reversal opportunity at the hearing. (&lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;또 이 후보자를 확실하게 날릴 추가 한 방도 확실치 않았던 것 같습니다.&lt;/mark&gt; 야당이 청문회를 계속 미루면 여권 내 부정적 목소리가 커지면서 자중지란을 유도할 수 있습니다. 청문회에서 반전 기회를 잡으려던 청와대를 곤혹스럽게 만들 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling party's attitude of ignoring the opposition also seems to have had an effect. While party leader Jang Dong-hyuk was on a hunger strike, no one from the ruling bloc visited him until the 20th. They also gave no response to the PPP's demand for a special investigation into the Unification Church/Kim Byeong-gi incident. (야당을 무시하는 여당의 태도도 영향을 준 듯합니다. 장동혁 대표가 단식 중인데 20일까지 여권 인사들이 아무도 찾아오지 않았습니다. 국힘이 요구하는 통일교·김병기 사건 특검에 대해 아무런 답도 하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the problem is the appearance of the opposition party itself kicking away the National Assembly's hearing procedure and opportunity for pointed verification. There are even concerns that this could rather provide grounds for a forced appointment. Therefore, the hearing is still a live card. (하지만 야당이 국회의 청문 절차와 송곳 검증 기회를 스스로 걷어차는 모양새가 문제입니다. 오히려 임명 강행 명분을 줄 수 있다는 우려도 나옵니다. 그래서 청문회는 여전히 살아 있는 카드입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trigger is the return request for the hearing report. President Lee is highly likely to request its return on the 22nd. If that happens, the People Power Party has a high probability of making an abrupt turn towards holding the hearing. Since the President can force the appointment whether the hearing is held or not, the thinking is that it's better to hold the hearing and question the nominee's misconduct allegations and the Blue House's verification failure. It's a scene of the ruling and opposition parties engaging in a push-and-pull while calculating the pros and cons of the hearing. (계기는 청문보고서 재송부입니다. 이 대통령은 22일 재송부를 요청할 가능성이 높습니다. 그러면 국민의힘은 청문회 개최로 급선회할 공산이 큽니다. 청문회를 열든 안 열든 대통령이 임명 강행할 수 있기 때문에 청문회를 열어서 이 후보자 비위 의혹과 청와대의 검증 실패를 따지는 게 낫다는 겁니다. 여야가 청문회 손익계산서를 두드리며 밀당을 하는 모습입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reasons for President Lee's fixation on the Lee Hye-hoon hearing can be summarized into three points. (이 대통령이 이혜훈 청문회에 집착하는 이유는 세 가지로 정리할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem is that opposition voices are also loud within the ruling bloc. Within the Democratic Party, voices of concern are emerging, saying "Lee Hye-hoon's misconduct allegations are serious" and "public opinion is too unfavorable." There is also considerable discontent, asking "Why save a troublesome stone that rolled in while discarding our own Kim Byeong-gi?" and "Why should we cover up a conservative figure's irregularities?" Even within the Blue House, it's said there are many opinions that "forcing the appointment is difficult." (문제는 여권 내부에서도 반대 목소리가 크다는 것입니다. 민주당에선 “이혜훈 비위 의혹이 심각하다” “여론이 너무 안 좋다”는 우려의 목소리가 나옵니다. “우리 편인 김병기는 버리면서 굴러온 미운 돌은 살려주느냐” “보수 인사 비리를 왜 감싸야 하느냐”는 불만도 적잖습니다. 청와대 내부에서도 “임명 강행은 곤란하다”는 의견이 많다고 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere in the Blue House is that they are more worried about opposition within the ruling party and backlash from hardcore supporters than from the opposition party. While they can ignore and move past the PPP's opposition without major damage, if the ruling party internally rebels, it could shake the President's leadership itself. Already in a situation where control over the party has weakened due to the 'Myeong-Chung conflict' with leader Chung Cheong-rae, forcibly pushing through a nominee opposed by hardcore supporters carries too much risk. (청와대는 야당보다 여당 내부의 반대, 강성 지지층의 반발을 더 걱정하는 분위기입니다. 국민의힘의 반대는 무시하고 넘어가도 큰 타격이 없지만, 여당 내부가 반발하면 이 대통령의 리더십까지 흔들릴 수 있기 때문입니다. 안 그래도 정청래 대표와의 ‘명청 갈등’으로 여당에 대한 통제력이 약해진 상황에서 강성 지지층이 반대하는 인사를 억지로 밀어붙이다가는 위험 부담이 너무 커집니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The President, seemingly aware of this, said, "I didn't expect to face such resistance," and "I hope some will be understanding." He also said, "Let's find a path we can all take together." The President strongly believes the nominee should be given a chance to explain at the hearing. Therefore, even among the Democratic Party's core, including leader Chung Cheong-rae, there is a mood to wait and see until the hearing. (이 대통령은 이를 의식한 듯 “이런 저항에 부딪힐 줄 몰랐다”며 “일부 용인은 해주시길 바란다”고 말했습니다. “모두가 함께 갈 수 있는 길을 찾아보자”고도 했습니다. 이 대통령은 청문회에서 해명 기회는 줘야 한다는 생각이 강합니다. 그래서 정청래 대표를 비롯한 민주당 핵심부도 청문회까지는 일단 기다려 보자는 기류입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a situation where the opposition is fiercely opposed and negative sentiment within the ruling bloc is likely to grow, what decision will the President make? For now, he is expected to request the return of the hearing report. After that, there are three options. (야권이 결사 반대하고 여권에서도 부정적 기류가 커질 가능성이 큰 상황에서 이 대통령은 어떤 결정을 내릴까요. 일단 청문 보고서 재송부를 요청할 것으로 보이는데요. 그 이후엔 세 가지 선택지가 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first is withdrawal of the nomination, and the second is voluntary resignation. &lt;mark class="hl_blue"&gt;Considering the President's style or political gains and losses, the observation is that voluntary resignation is the most likely possibility.&lt;/mark&gt; However, it's a variable whether this nominee, who has shown strong will for the ministerial post, will accept it, and whether the President will easily give up on her. The third is forcing the appointment. With both ruling and opposition parties opposed and public opinion unfavorable, will this President, sensitive to approval ratings and public opinion, really throw a reckless gamble? Considering trends in public opinion and the mood of internal backlash within the ruling bloc, it's not an easy choice. (첫째는 지명 철회이고, 둘째는 자진 사퇴입니다. &lt;mark class="hl_blue"&gt;이 대통령 스타일이나 정치적 손익으로 보면 자진 사퇴 가능성이 가장 크다는 관측입니다.&lt;/mark&gt; 하지만 장관직에 강한 의지를 보여온 이 후보자가 받아들일지, 이 대통령이 쉽게 이 후보자를 포기할지가 변수입니다. 셋째는 임명 강행인데요. 여야 모두가 반대하고 국민 여론도 나쁜데 지지율과 여론에 민감한 이 대통령이 과연 무리한 승부수를 던질까요. 여론 동향이나 여권 내부 반발 기류 등을 감안할 때 쉽지 않은 선택입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/premium/2026/01/22/YUOLCVTCIBEOTMA3PYATFA63DM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z2IH6PVH3JAWBB2TJLQ3VSBXDQ.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling and Opposition Parties Agree to Hold Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing on the 23rd (여야, 이혜훈 인사청문회 23일 개최 합의)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/HD23IMZOXZHRHNJBB2FAYNJEGU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6X3L2T7Y2BK3XIRESFOXPKTGEM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties have agreed to hold the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, on the 23rd. (여야가 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회를 23일 열기로 합의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Representative Jeong Tae-ho, the Democratic Party's secretary on the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, stated, "We have finally agreed with People Power Party Secretary Park Su-young to hold the confirmation hearing on the 23rd." (국회 재정경제기획위원회 민주당 간사인 정태호 의원은 22일 “국민의힘 박수영 간사와 23일 인사청문회를 하기로 최종 합의했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally, the nominee's hearing was scheduled for the 19th of this month but was not held as the opposition party protested, citing insufficient submission of materials by the nominee. (당초 이 후보자 청문회는 이달 19일 개최 예정이었으나 야당이 후보자 자료 제출이 미흡하다고 반발하면서 열리지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling party had been persistently persuading for the hearing to be held, arguing that the nominee should be given an opportunity to explain. Furthermore, the nominee's side provided explanations to the opposition party regarding the material submissions, and as the opposition party partially accepted these, the atmosphere shifted. (여당은 이 후보자가 소명할 기회를 줘야 한다며 청문회 개최를 계속 설득해왔다. 또 이 후보자 측이 자료 제출에 관해 야당에 설명에 나섰고, 야당에서 이를 일부 수용하면서 기류가 바뀌었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the People Power Party maintains the position that it will make a final decision on whether to hold the hearing after reviewing the materials submitted by the nominee's side this morning. (다만 국민의힘은 이날 오전 이 후보자 측이 제출하는 자료를 보고 청문회 개최 여부를 최종 판단한다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/HD23IMZOXZHRHNJBB2FAYNJEGU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6X3L2T7Y2BK3XIRESFOXPKTGEM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:31:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Regarding the 'Beloved Kang Hoon-sik' Candidacy Rumors... Lee Says "That's Creepy, I Love My Ex-Wife" (‘사랑하는 강훈식’ 출마설에… 李 “징그럽다, 전 아내를 사랑해”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/21/DB2WFYGDRFBKNEP7HRGGMSGSFI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Regarding the 'Beloved Kang Hoon-sik' Candidacy Rumors... Lee Says "That's Creepy, I Love My Ex-Wife" (‘사랑하는 강훈식’ 출마설에… 李 “징그럽다, 전 아내를 사랑해”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 21st, President Lee Jae-myung commented on the rumors of Chief of Staff Kang Hoon-sik running in the local elections, stating, "I cannot tell someone what political choices to make," and adding, "It's completely unpredictable. I don't know." (이재명 대통령은 21일 강훈식 대통령비서실장의 지방선거 출마설에 대해 “어떤 사람이 어떤 정치적 선택을 하는가 하는 것은 제가 이래라 저래라 할 수 없다”며 “전혀 예측 불능이다. 알 수 없다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a New Year's press conference held at the Cheong Wa Dae (Blue House) State Guest House, a reporter asked, "Some describe the relationship between the President and Chief of Staff Kang as a 'mutually loving relationship.' Can you send off your beloved Chief Kang for the local elections?" Chief Kang has been mentioned as a potential candidate for the integrated metropolitan government head position, linked to the push for administrative integration in Daejeon and South Chungcheong Province. (이날 청와대 영빈관에서 열린 신년 기자회견에서 한 기자는 “일각에서는 대통령과 강훈식 비서실장 사이를 ‘서로 사랑하는 사이’라고 표현하기도 한다. 사랑하는 강 실장을 지선 출마를 위해 떠나보내실 수 있겠나”고 물었다. 강 실장은 대전·충남 행정통합 추진과 맞물려 통합광역단체장 차출론이 거론되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, President Lee laughed and replied, "I love my (ex-)wife." Chief Kang, who was also present, laughed and shook his head at the surrounding staff. (이에 이 대통령은 “저는 제 아내를 사랑한다”고 웃으며 답했다. 자리에 함께 있던 강 실장도 웃으며 주변 참모진들에게 고개를 젓기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "They say politics is like a living frog; you never know where it will jump. It's impossible to predict how the situation will unfold," and added, "For my part, I will work hard in the role I have now. I expect our staff to also do their best in their roles until the very last moment." (이 대통령은 “정치는 살아있는 개구리처럼 어디로 뛸지 알 수 없다고 하더라. 상황은 어떻게 될지 알 수 없다”며 “저로서는 지금 제가 맡은 역할을 열심히 할 거다. 우리 참모들도 자기 역할을 마지막 순간까지 최선을 다해 주시기를 기대한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, looking at Chief Kang, he joked, "But when did we become a loving relationship? Ugh, that's creepy," and said, "I love everyone." Chief Kang also waved his hand, saying, "No, that's not it." (이어 강 실장을 바라보며 “그런데 언제 사랑하는 사이로 됐나. 어휴 징그럽다”라며 “모두를 사랑한다”고 농담을 건넸다. 강 실장도 “아닙니다”라며 손을 저었다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/21/DB2WFYGDRFBKNEP7HRGGMSGSFI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:40:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Breaking News] Jeong Cheong-rae Proposes Sudden Merger with Cho Kuk Innovation Party... "Let's Contest the Local Elections Together" ([속보] 정청래, 조국혁신당에 전격 합당 제안… “지방선거 함께 치르자”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/PLMPFDEZBRDKZKMHG5SXMXBIUA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJQTOYZRGA4TKNJZMQZTGZJQMM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae made a sudden proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party on the 22nd. Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, is expected to announce his position on the matter soon. (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 22일 조국혁신당에 합당을 전격 제안했다. 조국혁신당 조국 대표는 곧 이에 대한 입장을 밝힐 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jeong held an emergency press conference today and stated, "I propose to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. Let's merge with us." (정 대표는 이날 긴급 기자회견을 열어 “조국혁신당에 제안한다. 우리와 합치자”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jeong said, "At the time of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party's founding, I mentioned 'separately yet together'," and added, "We contested the 22nd general election separately and the 21st presidential election together. The Democratic Party shouted 'Judgment on the Yoon Suk Yeol dictatorship regime' and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party shouted 'Three years is too long'." He continued, "We opposed the Yoon Suk Yeol regime together. We have overcome the December 3 emergency martial law rebellion together. We contested the presidential election for the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration together." (정 대표는 “저는 조국혁신당 창당 당시 ‘따로 또 같이’를 말했다”며 “22대 총선을 따로 치렀고 21대 대선을 같이 치렀다. 민주당은 ‘윤석열 독재 정권 심판’을 외쳤고 조국혁신당은 ‘3년은 너무 길다’를 외쳤다”고 했다. 이어 “우리는 같이 윤석열 정권을 반대했다. 우리는 12·3 비상계엄 내란을 같이 극복해 왔다. 우리는 이재명 정부 출범을 위한 대선을 같이 치렀다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jeong then said, "I hope we can contest this June 3 local election together as well. The success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and victory in the local elections are the politics of the times," and added, "I don't think the spirit of the times pursued by the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party is different. Therefore, there is no reason to contest the June 3 local elections separately." (정 대표는 그러면서 “이번 6·3 지방선거도 같이 치렀으면 좋겠다. 이재명 정부의 성공, 지방선거의 승리가 시대의 정치”라며 “민주당과 조국혁신당이 추구하는 시대정신이 다르지 않다고 생각한다. 따라서 6·3 지방선거를 따로 치를 이유가 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jeong stated, "The Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party should now run together as one team based on the spirit of the times for the common goal of the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration, not separately," and expressed, "I hope a working-level table will be established promptly for negotiations between the two parties." (정 대표는 “민주당과 조국혁신당이 이제 따로가 아니라 같이 시대정신에 입각해 이재명 정부 성공이라는 공동 목표를 위해 원팀으로 같이 뛰어야 한다”며 “두 당의 협상을 위해 조속히 실무 테이블이 만들어지기를 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/PLMPFDEZBRDKZKMHG5SXMXBIUA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJQTOYZRGA4TKNJZMQZTGZJQMM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:54:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Army Special Forces Conduct Snow and Cold Endurance Training on Daegwallyeong at Perceived Minus 30 Degrees Celsius (육군 특전사, 체감 영하 30도 대관령에서 설한지 훈련)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/22/53H5ZNKPSBD47JYYIKKE7RSXVQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NOPMMXEWIFMFHHQIMFJCGNJQ2U.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Army announced on the 22nd that its special warfare units are conducting 'Snow and Cold Endurance Training' in the Hwangbyeongsan area of Daegwallyeong, Gangwon Province, amidst extreme cold with perceived temperatures around minus 30 degrees Celsius. (육군 특수전 부대가 체감 영하 30도 안팎의 혹한 속 강원도 대관령 황병산 일대에서 ‘설한지 극복 훈련’을 실시하고 있다고 육군이 22일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Army, units under the Special Warfare Command are sequentially conducting the 11-night, 12-day Snow and Cold Endurance Training until next month. The training includes infiltration into enemy rear areas, hideout activities, special reconnaissance and aerial firepower guidance, strike operations, evasion and escape, and tactical ski maneuvers. The training takes place in the rugged mountainous terrain of Gangwon Province, at an altitude of 1,407 meters, amid a cold wave with perceived temperatures of minus 30 degrees Celsius. An Army official stated, "'Snow and Cold Endurance Training' is conducted annually during the peak of the cold season, and realism is enhanced by utilizing veteran Special Forces members as opposing forces during day and night training." (육군에 따르면 특수전사령부 예하 부대들은 다음 달까지 순차적으로 11박 12일 기간의 설한지 극복 훈련을 하고 있다. 훈련은 적 후방 지역 침투, 은거지 활동, 특수 정찰 및 항공 화력 유도, 타격 작전, 도피 및 탈출, 전술 스키 기동 등이 이뤄진다. 훈련은 강원도 해발 1407m의 험준한 산악 지형과 체감 온도 영하 30도의 한파 속에서 이뤄진다. 육군 관계자는 “‘설한지 극복 훈련’은 매년 추위가 최고조에 이르는 시기에 진행하고, 주야간 훈련 간 베테랑 특전대원들을 대항군으로 운용해 실전성을 강화한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the day, Special Forces members constructed hideouts using snow and natural materials, and at night, they prepared for operations in dugout shelters made by digging into snow and earth. (특전대원들은 주간에는 눈과 자연물을 이용해 은거지를 구축하고, 야간에는 눈과 흙을 파서 만든 잠적호에서 작전을 준비했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During special reconnaissance and aerial firepower guidance training, they utilized surveillance equipment to identify key targets and provided coordinates to higher command to guide aerial firepower. (특수정찰 및 항공 화력 유도 훈련에서는 감시장비를 활용해 핵심 표적을 식별하고 상급 부대에 좌표를 제공해 항공 화력을 유도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They also mastered special operational procedures reflecting recent battlefield conditions, such as using small unmanned aerial vehicles (drones), a core weapon in modern warfare, to identify enemy hideouts and guard posts, and confirming enemy positions before conducting night strike operations. (현대전의 핵심 무기인 소형 무인기(드론)를 활용해 적 은거지 및 경계 초소를 식별하고 야간 타격 작전 수행 전 적 위치를 확인하는 등 최근 전장 상황을 반영한 특수 작전 절차도 숙달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the training, Special Forces members moved along a 20-kilometer escape route for 12 hours while carrying military packs weighing up to 40 kg. Concurrently conducting tactical ski training, they deployed and changed formations as a team to evade enemy fire. (훈련 중 특전대원들은 40㎏에 달하는 군장을 휴대한 채 12시간 동안 20㎞에 달하는 탈출로를 이동했다. 전술 스키 훈련을 병행, 팀 단위로 대형을 전개하고 변경하며 적의 사격을 회피했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lieutenant Colonel Park Gi-geun, commander of the Mujeok Taepung (Invincible Typhoon) Battalion, expressed his resolve, stating, "Despite the extreme cold weather, the passion of the Special Forces members made the training ground hotter than anywhere else," and "As the world's best, irreplaceable Special Forces, we will devote ourselves to mission accomplishment." (무적태풍대대 대대장 박기근 중령은 “혹한의 기상임에도 특전대원들의 열정으로 훈련장의 열기는 그 어느 곳보다 뜨거웠다”며 “세계 최고 대체 불가 특전사로서 임무 완수에 매진하겠다”고 각오를 다졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/22/53H5ZNKPSBD47JYYIKKE7RSXVQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NOPMMXEWIFMFHHQIMFJCGNJQ2U.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:57:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>