<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:56:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>People Power Party Spokesperson Apologizes After Backlash Over "Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination Sales, They'll Lose Anyway" Remarks (국힘 대변인 “개혁신당 40억 공천팔이, 어차피 낙선”... 반발 일자 사과)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/UKZFRDMJ3NGQNMDXE4LWRTNJBM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party Spokesperson Apologizes After Backlash Over "Reform Party's 4 Billion Won Nomination Sales, They'll Lose Anyway" Remarks (국힘 대변인 “개혁신당 40억 공천팔이, 어차피 낙선”... 반발 일자 사과)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUMO7TZYLNKY5DTMOHOMIZLG54.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the June 3 local elections, a spokesperson for the People Power Party (PPP) claimed the Reform Party was "selling nominations," prompting a backlash from the Reform Party and leading to an immediate apology. In response, Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said, "I thank them for the courage to acknowledge and correct the mistake." (6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 국민의힘 소속 대변인이 개혁신당을 향해 “공천 팔이를 하고 있다”며 했다가, 개혁신당이 반발하자 즉각 사과했다. 이에 개혁신당 이준석 대표는 “실수를 인정하고 정정한 용기에 감사하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP and the Reform Party have recently been cooperating, jointly demanding a 'dual special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of Democratic Party nomination donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians. The conflict arose as a sign of potential discord, which both sides have now moved to mend. (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 최근 더불어민주당 공천 헌금 의혹과 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하면서 공조에 나섰는데, 갈등이 생길 조짐을 보이자 양측이 이를 봉합한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, PPP media spokesperson Lee Jae-neung appeared on a YouTube broadcast and said, "The Reform Party is currently selling nominations for 4 billion won. All 4,000 (candidates running for the Reform Party) are victims," adding, "Since they won't get elected anyway, making them run through to the end only results in them being used, so it's pitiful." (국민의힘 이재능 미디어대변인은 지난 16일 한 유튜브 방송에 출연해 “개혁신당이 지금 40억원 공천팔이를 하고 있다. (개혁신당 후보자로 출마할) 4000명이 다 피해자”라며 “어차피 당선이 안 되는 건데 완주시킨다는 건 그들이 이용당하는 꼴밖에 안 되니까 불쌍하더라”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok announced that for the June 3 local elections, he would reduce the election costs for running for basic-level council positions (city/county/district), which typically cost hundreds of millions or tens of millions of won, to 990,000 won. The spokesperson's remarks implied that if 4,000 Reform Party candidates run, the party would collect 4 billion won in election costs, but they would lose the elections. (앞서 개혁신당 이준석 대표는 6·3 지방선거에서 시·군·구 등 기초의원 출마를 위해 수백, 수천만 원이 드는 선거 비용을 99만원으로 줄이겠다고 밝혔다. 이 대변인의 발언은 이에 따라 4000명의 개혁신당 후보자가 출마할 경우 개혁신당이 40억원의 선거 비용을 거두지만 선거에선 낙선하게 될 것이라는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, Reform Party spokesperson Jeong Yi-han said in a commentary on the 17th, "This is a serious juncture where the leadership of both parties is pooling their strength to push through the special prosecutor investigations into the Unification Church and the money-for-nominations allegations involving Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi," adding, "In such a situation, the PPP spokesperson's attack on an opposing party with baseless slander is an irresponsible act that undermines the trust in cooperation itself." (이에 대해 개혁신당 정이한 대변인은 17일 논평에서 “지금은 양당 지도부가 통일교 특검과 강선우·김병기 돈 공천 특검 관철을 위해 힘을 모으는 엄중한 국면”이라며 “이런 상황에서 국민의힘 대변인이 근거 없는 비방으로 상대 정당을 공격한 것은 공조의 신뢰를 스스로 허무는 무책임한 행동”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Jeong asked, "We ask the PPP leadership: Will they stand by while the spokesperson's remarks, made without even checking basic facts, shake the framework of cooperative governance?" and urged spokesperson Lee Jae-neung to resign, among other actions. (정 대변인은 “국민의힘 지도부에 묻는다. 기초적 사실관계조차 확인하지 않은 대변인의 발언이 협치의 틀을 흔들고 있는데, 이를 방치할 것이냐”며 이재능 대변인의 사퇴 등을 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, spokesperson Lee apologized on Facebook that day, stating, "The remarks stemmed from my incorrect understanding and were excessive expressions; all my related statements were wrong." He added, "I once again offer my apologies to the Reform Party, its candidates, and all related parties." (이에 이 대변인은 이날 페이스북에 “해당 발언은 저의 잘못된 이해에서 비롯된 과도한 표현이었으며 관련한 저의 모든 발언은 틀렸다”고 사과했다. 그는 “개혁신당과 출마자, 그리고 관계자 여러분께 다시 한 번 사과의 말씀을 드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, leader Lee Jun-seok accepted the apology on Facebook, saying, "I will regard this incident as a mistake made out of habit." He added, "While individuals can express their opinions in any way, I hope they do not escalate to attacks based on false information." (그러자 이준석 대표는 페이스북에서 “이번 일은 관성에 따른 실수 정도로 받아들이겠다”며 사과를 받아들였다. 이 대표는 “개인의 의견이야 어떤 식으로든 표현할 수 있으나 그것이 허위사실에 의한 공격에 이르지 않았으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/UKZFRDMJ3NGQNMDXE4LWRTNJBM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUMO7TZYLNKY5DTMOHOMIZLG54.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 23:48:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Jung Cheong-rae Party' vs. 'Jang Dong-hyuk Party'... Two leaders obsessed only with party control (‘정청래당’ 대 ‘장동혁당’...당권에만 혈안인 두 대표)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/premium/2026/01/18/UMFUCPRQQBCUHHJPLQSCZCZ75Y/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UMZYTHRG25K37LPMFBW53WGB2M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyuk, the leader of the People Power Party, is continuously making strategic moves to strengthen his grip on the party. After pulling out the extreme card of expelling former leader Han Dong-hoon, he has now brought up the issue of changing the party's name. As internal and external backlash grew fierce, he temporarily suspended the expulsion motion and immediately launched a hunger strike against the ruling party. This is interpreted as a strategic step to turn the People Power Party into the 'Jang Dong-hyuk Party'. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 연일 당권 강화를 위한 전략적 승부수를 띄우고 있습니다. 한동훈 전 대표 제명이라는 초강경 카드를 꺼내 든 데 이어 당명 개정도 들고나왔습니다. 당 안팎의 반발이 거세지자 제명안을 잠시 유보시키더니 곧바로 대여(對與) 단식 투쟁에 들어갔습니다. 국민의힘을 ‘장동혁당(黨)’으로 만들기 위한 전략적 수순이라는 해석이 나옵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang's attack on former leader Han is seen as a move to garner support from hardcore pro-Yoon party members and eliminate a potential rival for party control. The sudden hunger strike is also interpreted more as a move to quell criticism of the expulsion and lay the groundwork for internal unity within the party, rather than as a genuine struggle against the Lee Jae-myung administration. Jang's side believes that by leveraging the party's aversion to former leader Han and his control over candidate nominations for local elections, they can sufficiently control the backlash from inside and outside the party. (장 대표의 한 전 대표 공격은 친윤 성향 강성 당원의 지지를 이끌어내고 잠재적 당권 경쟁자를 제거하기 위한 것으로 비칩니다. 갑작스러운 단식 투쟁도 이재명 정부에 대한 투쟁 성격보다는 제명 비판 여론을 잠재우고 내부 결집을 위한 당내용 포석으로 해석됩니다. 장 대표 측은 한 전 대표에 대한 당내 거부감과 지방선거 공천권 등을 활용하면 당 안팎의 반발은 충분히 제어할 수 있다고 여기고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the party's internal reaction to Leader Jang's series of extreme moves is critical. Already facing significant public criticism for failing to break away from 'Yoon Again', the move to expel former leader Han appears to be pouring fuel on the fire of internal party conflict. The chronically stagnant party approval ratings and anxiety over defeat in the local elections are also risk factors. If an anti-Jang Dong-hyuk coalition emerges or the coalition with Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reformist Party, breaks down, Jang's plans could be shaken from their very foundation. (하지만 장 대표의 잇단 초강수에 대해 당내 반응은 비판적입니다. 안 그래도 ‘윤 어게인’과 결별하지 못하는 데 대한 비판 여론이 큰 상황에서 한 전 대표 제명 조치는 당 내 갈등에 기름을 부은 모양새입니다. 만성 정체된 당 지지율과 지방선거 패배 불안감도 위험 요소입니다. 반(反)장동혁 연대가 뜨거나 이준석 개혁신당 대표와의 야권 연대가 깨진다면 장 대표의 구상은 뿌리부터 흔들릴 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling party, the 'Myeong·Cheong Conflict' (referring to conflict between pro-Lee Jae-myung and pro-Jung Cheong-rae factions) sparked by Jung Cheong-rae is reigniting. This is because Leader Jung, backed by hardcore party members and hardline lawmakers, has openly opposed the government's bill to establish a Major Crimes Investigation Agency. Leader Jung has also decided to re-push for a 'one-member, one-vote' system to strengthen the votes of hardcore party members. This system, which grants one vote each to delegates and party members, is seen as a card for Leader Jung's re-election and a strategic move to create a 'Jung Cheong-rae Party'. However, the pro-Myeong (pro-Lee Jae-myung) core faction is unlikely to just sit back and watch. The key lies in how President Lee Jae-myung will respond. (여권에선 정청래발(發) ‘명·청 갈등’이 재점화하고 있습니다. 강성 당원과 강경파 의원들을 등에 업은 정 대표가 정부의 중대범죄수사청 설치 법안에 노골적으로 반기를 들었기 때문입니다. 정 대표는 강성 당원 표를 강화하는 ‘1인 1표제’도 재추진하기로 했습니다. 대의원과 당원에게 똑같이 1인 1표를 주는 이 제도는 정 대표의 연임을 위한 카드이자 정청래당(黨)을 만들기 위한 전략적 승부수로 여겨집니다. 하지만 친명 핵심부가 이를 두고만 보고 있지는 않을 것입니다. 이재명 대통령이 어떻게 대응할지가 관건입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang's call for a special investigation into the Unification Church and Kim Byeong-gi and his subsequent hunger strike came just two days after the move to expel former leader Han. Although he fronted it as a struggle against the Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party, interpretations suggest it is a move to strengthen his party control. Leader Jang also said he would push for a change in the party name. This means changing the signboard from former President Yoon Suk-yeol's 'People Power Party' to Jang Dong-hyuk's political party. (장 대표가 통일교·김병기 특검을 촉구하며 단식에 들어간 것은 한 전 대표 제명 조치가 나온 지 이틀 만입니다. 이재명 정부와 민주당을 향한 투쟁을 앞세웠지만, 당권 강화용 승부수라는 해석이 나옵니다. 장 대표는 당명 변경도 추진하겠다고 했습니다. 윤석열 전 대통령의 ‘국민의힘’에서 장동혁의 정당으로 간판을 바꾸겠다는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day before, as internal backlash and criticism against the motion to expel Han Dong-hoon grew, Leader Jang postponed the expulsion by ten days, saying he would give former leader Han a chance for reconsideration. This is evaluated as a stalling tactic or a move to defuse criticism. Simultaneously, he began his hunger strike. The stated purpose is to block the ruling party's push for a second comprehensive special investigation and to push through the special investigation into the Unification Church and Kim Byeong-gi. However, many assessments suggest the real intention is to soothe the backlash against the expulsion and strengthen internal unity and control—a move for internal consumption. It's difficult to raise critical voices against a party leader on a hunger strike against the ruling party using internal party issues as a reason. (장 대표는 전날 한동훈 제명안에 대해 당내 반발과 비판이 커지자 한 전 대표에게 재심 기회를 주겠다며 제명을 열흘 뒤로 늦췄습니다. 비판 여론을 무마하기 위한 시간 끌기나 김 빼기 작전이라는 평가입니다. 그와 동시에 시작한 것이 단식 투쟁입니다. 여당의 2차 종합 특검 처리를 막고 통일교·김병기 특검을 관철하겠다는 취지입니다. 하지만 진짜 속내는 제명 반발을 누그러뜨리고 내부 결속과 지배력을 강화하기 위한 대내용이라는 평가가 많습니다. 대여 단식 투쟁을 하는 당대표에게 당내 문제를 이유로 비판 목소리를 높이기는 힘들기 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some also mention that it reminds them of former leader Hwang Kyo-ahn's hunger strike in the past. Former leader Hwang went on a hunger strike in 2020 before the general election to oppose the handling of the Anti-Corruption Investigation Office Act. At that time, former leader Hwang's leadership was shaky due to internal party conflict. However, he failed to block the passage of the Act and it ended without significant results. Four months later, the opposition party suffered a defeat, winning only 103 seats in the general election. (과거 황교안 전 대표의 단식 투쟁을 연상시킨다는 얘기도 나옵니다. 황 전 대표는 2020년 총선 전 공수처법 처리에 반대하는 단식을 했습니다. 당시 황 전 대표는 당내 갈등으로 리더십이 흔들리는 상황이었습니다. 하지만 공수처법 처리를 막지 못했고 큰 성과 없이 끝났습니다. 4개월 후 총선에서 야당은 103석으로 패배했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the push to expel Han Dong-hoon, there is strong criticism inside and outside the party that "it's just internal strife causing self-inflicted harm." They question why, ahead of an election, instead of uniting forces, they are attacking a former leader who is part of the same family. They say that with this, it will be difficult to win the election, and Leader Jang's leadership could also be damaged. (한동훈 제명 추진에 대해 당 안팎에선 “집안 싸움으로 자중지란만 일어났다”는 비판이 큽니다. 왜 선거를 앞두고 힘을 합치기는커녕 한 식구인 전직 대표를 쳐내느냐는 것입니다. 이래서는 선거에서 이기기 힘들고, 장 대표의 리더십도 타격을 받을 수 있다고 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Leader Jang's calculation appears different. He seems to judge that even if it's noisy now, by ousting potential rival former leader Han this time, his party control will become solid and internal unity will increase. He seems to believe internal backlash can be sufficiently blocked. First, &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;hardcore party members have a strong aversion to former leader Han Dong-hoon&lt;/mark&gt;. The psychology of influential party figures wanting to check former leader Han is also considerable. There isn't much sympathy or support for former leader Han. Therefore, they judge that even if they push out former leader Han through expulsion, the backlash won't be as big as one might think. (하지만 장 대표의 계산은 달라 보입니다. 당장은 시끄러워도 잠재적 경쟁자인 한 전 대표를 이번에 쳐내야 당권이 확고해지고 내부 결속력도 커진다는 판단입니다. 내부 반발은 충분히 막을 수 있다고 여기는 듯합니다. 첫째는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;한동훈 전 대표에 대한 강성 당원들의 거부감&lt;/mark&gt;이 큽니다. 당내 유력 인사들의 한 전 대표 견제 심리도 상당합니다. 한 전 대표 우군이나 동정론이 많지 않다는 겁니다. 따라서 한 전 대표를 제명으로 밀어내도 생각만큼 반발이 크지 않을 거라고 판단하고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;former leader Han doesn't have many means to resist&lt;/mark&gt;. Former leader Han has already said he has no plans to apply for reconsideration. This is because even if he requests reconsideration, it's highly likely the ethics committee would again vote for expulsion. He could apply for a court injunction, but there's no guarantee it would be granted. If it's dismissed, it could actually provide justification for the expulsion measure. Even if he leaves the party, the assessment is that there aren't many incumbent district lawmakers who would follow him, and his ability to found a new party isn't great. (둘째는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;한 전 대표가 반발할 수단이 별로 없다&lt;/mark&gt;는 것입니다. 한 전 대표는 이미 재심 신청할 계획이 없다고 했습니다. 재심을 청구해도 윤리위가 다시 제명을 의결할 가능성이 크기 때문입니다. 법원에 가처분 신청을 할 수는 있지만, 인용된다는 보장은 없습니다. 기각되면 오히려 제명 조치에 면죄부를 줄 수 있습니다. 탈당을 해도 따라나갈 현역 지역구 의원이 별로 없고 창당 여력도 크지 않다는 평가입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third is &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;the nomination authority held by Leader Jang&lt;/mark&gt;. Since he holds the nomination authority, it's difficult for incumbent lawmakers or local government heads, many of whom are from the Yeongnam region, to strongly oppose him. In reality, many Yeongnam lawmakers are taking a wait-and-see approach. Yeongnam region local government heads are also not raising loud voices of opposition. They are watching Leader Jang's demeanor. Leader Jang seems to judge that if he pushes forward with determination like this, internal opposition will gradually weaken and the current system will be further strengthened. (셋째는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;장 대표가 가진 공천권&lt;/mark&gt;입니다. 공천권을 쥐고 있는 만큼 영남이 다수인 현역 의원이나 단체장들이 강하게 반발하기 힘들다는 겁니다. 실제로 영남 의원들은 관망파가 많습니다. 영남권 단체장들도 반발 목소리를 크게 내지 못하고 있습니다. 장 대표 눈치를 보고 있는 겁니다. 장 대표는 이대로 뚝심 있게 밀고 나가면 내부 반발은 점차 약해지고, 현 체제가 더 강화될 거라고 판단한 듯합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, contrary to the expectations of Leader Jang's side, there are also not a few pessimistic outlooks. Reorganizing into a 'Jang Dong-hyuk Party' is difficult. Even if it happens, there's no guarantee of winning elections and achieving success. (하지만 장 대표 측의 기대와 달리 비관적 전망도 적지 않습니다. ‘장동혁당’으로 재편하는 것은 어려운 일입니다. 설사 그렇게 된다고 해도 선거에서 이겨 성공한다는 보장은 없습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since Leader Jang took office, the People Power Party's approval ratings have been chronically stagnant. Depending on the poll, they are stuck in a range from the low 20s to the mid 30s. In a poll released after the decision to expel Han Dong-hoon, the party's approval rating actually fell. This suggests public evaluation isn't very good. In Daegu and Gyeongbuk, the PPP's approval rating also fell below 40%. This means even in its stronghold of Yeongnam, victory in the local elections cannot be guaranteed. (장 대표 취임 이후 국민의힘 지지율은 만성 정체 상태입니다. 여론조사에 따라 20%대 초반에서 30%대 중반까지 박스권에 갇혀 있습니다. 한동훈 제명 의결 후 발표된 조사에선 당 지지율이 오히려 떨어졌습니다. 국민의 평가가 그리 좋지 못하다는 얘기입니다. 대구·경북에서도 국힘 지지율은 40% 이하로 떨어졌습니다. 텃밭인 영남에서도 지방선거 승리를 장담할 수 없다는 얘기입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The election anxiety among candidates for local government heads and council members is growing increasingly. Already, centrist voters are leaving due to the failure to break away from 'Yoon Again', and with the self-inflicted harm of the Han Dong-hoon expulsion, even the traditional conservative base is falling away. There is a great sense of crisis that even with internal harmony and external coalitions, election victory is difficult due to the aftermath of the impeachment, and if the party splits, it will be hard to avoid a crushing election defeat. (단체장과 지방의원 후보자들의 선거 불안감은 갈수록 커지고 있습니다. 안 그래도 ‘윤 어게인’과 결별하지 못해 중도층이 이반하는 상황에서 한동훈 제명 자중지란에 전통적 보수층까지 떨어져 나가고 있다는 것입니다. 당내 화합과 외부 연대를 해도 탄핵 여파 때문에 선거 승리가 쉽지 않은데 당이 분열된다면 선거 참패를 피하기 어렵다는 위기감이 큽니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If internal conflict intensifies, an 'anti-Jang Dong-hyuk coalition' could emerge. If 'disadvantages in nominations' are given to local government heads who oppose Leader Jang's line, influential local government heads and former leader Han Dong-hoon could join forces and launch a united struggle. Scenarios of a joint response from some metropolitan city and provincial governors, including Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon, are already emerging. (당내 갈등이 극심해지면 ‘반(反)장동혁 연대’가 뜰 수도 있습니다. 장 대표 노선에 반대하는 단체장들에게 ‘공천 불이익’을 줄 경우 유력 단체장과 한동훈 전 대표가 힘을 합쳐 연대 투쟁에 나설 수 있다는 겁니다. 벌써 오세훈 서울시장 등 일부 시도지사들의 공동 대응 시나리오가 나오기도 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The coalition with Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reformist Party, could also break down. The Reformist Party says it supports Leader Jang's hunger strike but does not mean it will form an election coalition. If this happens, the 'Jang Dong-hyuk Party' concept will be shaken from its roots. (이준석 개혁신당 대표와의 야권 연대도 깨질 수 있습니다. 개혁신당은 장 대표의 단식은 지지하지만 선거 연대까지 하겠다는 것은 아니라고 합니다. 이렇게 되면 ‘장동혁당’ 구상은 뿌리부터 흔들릴 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For incumbent lawmakers, local government heads, and other candidates, the most important thing is receiving the nomination and being elected. They are loyal to a party leader who gives them the nomination and leads them to election victory, but if the leader fails to demonstrate the ability to get them elected, they will turn away. As the election approaches, if party approval ratings fall and the possibility of election becomes slim, candidates will panic. They may rebel against the party leader or start looking for a new leader. (현역 의원과 단체장 등 출마 후보자들에게 가장 중요한 건 공천을 받아 선거에서 당선되는 것입니다. 자신에게 공천을 주고 선거 승리를 이끄는 당대표에겐 충성하지만 당선시킬 능력을 보여주지 못하면 외면하게 됩니다. 선거가 임박했는데 당 지지율이 떨어지고 당선 가능성도 희박해지면 후보자들은 패닉에 빠집니다. 당대표에게 반기를 들거나 새 리더를 찾아 나설 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Politics is frightening. If elections become uncertain, leadership also becomes shaky. Politics that only looks at hardcore supporters may be effective in internal struggles, but in the main election, it is more likely to be poison. No matter how much you hold party control, if you lose the election, it's useless. The party itself could disappear. (정치는 무섭습니다. 선거가 불안해지면 리더십도 흔들립니다. 강성 지지층만 바라보는 정치는 내부 투쟁엔 효과적이지만 본선에선 오히려 독이 될 가능성이 큽니다. 아무리 당권을 잡아도 선거에서 지면 소용이 없습니다. 당 자체가 사라질 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jung Cheong-rae said regarding the government's Major Crimes Investigation Agency bill, "I will tear it apart and fix it." This means the ruling party leader will overturn a bill that the presidential office has accepted. The government's proposal involves a dual structure with a prosecutor serving as the investigative judicial officer and professional investigators as the working-level staff. The possibility of maintaining supplementary investigation authority is also high. The presidential office and the government believe this is a rational and realistic plan. However, Leader Jung views it as a harmful revision that revives prosecutorial power. (정청래 대표는 정부의 중수청 법안에 대해 “뜯어 고치겠다”고 했습니다. 청와대도 수용한 법안을 여당 대표가 뒤집겠다는 것입니다. 정부안은 검사가 맡는 수사사법관과 실무진인 전문수사관으로 이원화시키는 내용입니다. 보완수사권도 유지될 가능성이 큽니다. 청와대와 정부는 이것이 합리적이고 현실적인 안이라고 생각합니다. 하지만 정 대표는 검찰 권력을 되살리는 개악이라고 여깁니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jung also says he will re-push for a one-member, one-vote system to strengthen party members' voting rights. The one-member, one-vote system was rejected at the central committee a month ago due to controversy that it was for Leader Jung's re-election. Re-pushing for this is seen as a move to secure the backing of hardcore party member votes and seek re-election in the party leadership election this August. It is also read as a will to firmly seize the initiative in the relationship between the party and the government (Cheong Wa Dae). (정 대표는 당원 투표권을 강화하는 1인 1표 제도도 재추진하겠다고 합니다. 1인 1표제는 정 대표 재선용이라는 논란 때문에 한 달 전 중앙위에서 부결됐는데요. 이걸 재추진하는 건 강성 당원 표를 등에 업고 올 8월 당대표 선거에서 연임하겠다는 뜻입니다. 또 당청 관계에서 정 대표가 확실하게 주도권을 쥐겠다는 의지로도 읽힙니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until now, conflicts with the presidential office have been significant due to the legislative solo runs of Leader Jung and the ruling party's hardliners. The pro-Myeong (pro-Lee) camp criticized Leader Jung for pursuing his own politics. There were also strong suspicions that he was trying to change the 'Lee Jae-myung Party' into the 'Jung Cheong-rae Party'. With this attempt to overturn the Major Crimes Investigation Agency bill, the 'Myeong·Cheong Conflict', which had subsided, is reigniting. There is talk that Leader Jung's second offensive has begun. (그동안 정 대표와 여당 강경파의 입법 독주로 청와대와 갈등이 컸습니다. 친명 진영에선 정 대표가 자기 정치를 한다고 비판했습니다. ‘이재명당’을 ‘정청래당’으로 바꾸려는 것 아니냐는 의구심도 컸습니다. 이번 중수청 법안 뒤집기 시도로 잦아들던 ‘명·청 갈등’이 재점화하는 분위기입니다. 정 대표의 2차 진격이 시작됐다는 얘기가 나옵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Leader Jung's actions, the presidential office and the pro-Myeong camp are not hiding their displeasure. They question how the leader of the ruling party can so openly voice opposition and try to overturn a bill being pushed by the presidential office. However, the pro-Cheong hardliners are in a mood to push through according to their will. (정 대표의 이 같은 행보에 대해 청와대와 친명 진영은 불쾌감을 감추지 못하고 있습니다. 집권 여당 대표가 어떻게 청와대가 추진하는 법안에 노골적으로 반대 목소리를 내고 뒤집을 수 있느냐는 겁니다. 하지만 친청 강경파는 자기들 뜻대로 밀어붙이려는 기류입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Major Crimes Investigation Agency bill is opposed not only by hardcore party members but also by a considerable number of Democratic Party lawmakers. Leader Jung seems to judge that he has the advantage in terms of numbers or the battle of legitimacy. Although the one-member, one-vote system was rejected a month ago, those in favor far outnumbered those opposed. It was rejected only because the quorum wasn't met; the prevailing trend is for the one-member, one-vote system. The recent victory of the pro-Cheong faction over the pro-Myeong faction by a 2-to-1 margin in the Supreme Council election also had an impact. Leader Jung seems to have gained confidence that he can win even against the pro-Myeong camp. (중수청 법안은 강성 당원뿐 아니라 민주당 의원 상당수가 반대하고 있습니다. 정 대표는 숫자나 명분 싸움에서 유리하다고 판단하는 것 같습니다. 1인1표제도 한달 전 부결되긴 했지만 찬성이 반대보다 월등히 많았습니다. 정족수가 안 돼 부결됐을 뿐 대세는 1인1표제라는 겁니다. 최근 최고위원 선거에서 친청파가 2대 1로 친명파에 승리를 거둔 것도 영향을 미쳤습니다. 정 대표는 친명 진영과 붙어도 이길 수 있다는 자신감을 갖게 된 듯합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the problem is how President Lee Jae-myung will view this Leader Jung. It has only been 7 months since President Lee took office. The president's approval rating is also over 60%. For a ruling party leader to so openly confront a president in the early stages of his term is unprecedented. If the president and the ruling party leader clash, it could also negatively impact elections. It would also cause major disruption to Leader Jung's re-election. (하지만 이재명 대통령이 이런 정 대표를 어떻게 생각할지가 문제입니다. 지금은 이 대통령이 취임한 지 7개월밖에 되지 않았습니다. 대통령 지지율도 60%를 넘습니다. 이런 취임 초 대통령에게 여당 대표가 노골적으로 맞서는 것은 전례가 없는 일입니다. 대통령과 여당 대표가 맞서면 선거에도 악영향을 줄 수 있습니다. 정 대표 연임에도 큰 차질이 생깁니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The success or failure of the two depends on the results of the local elections. The side that loses in the local elections will face fierce pressure to resign. There is virtually no party leader who can hold on after losing an election. If the Democratic Party loses in the Seoul and Busan elections, Leader Jung's position will be shaken and his re-election will become difficult. Conversely, if they win the election, the Jung Cheong-rae system will be greatly strengthened. The path to a 'Jung Cheong-rae Party' might truly open. (두 사람의 성패는 지방선거 결과에 달렸습니다. 지방선거에서 지는 쪽은 거센 사퇴 압박을 받을 겁니다. 선거에 지고도 버틸 수 있는 당대표는 사실상 없습니다. 만일 민주당이 서울·부산 선거에서 지면 정 대표 입지는 흔들리고 연임도 힘들어질 겁니다. 반대로 선거에 이기면 정청래 체제가 대폭 강화될 겁니다. 그야말로 ‘정청래당’으로 가는 길이 열릴지도 모릅니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the People Power Party loses, Leader Jang will suffer a fatal blow. Those around Leader Jang argue that "even if we lose the election to some extent, the current system can be maintained." They believe that even if they lose the election, as long as they maintain party control, a path to the presidential election remains open. However, if they lose the election, the problem isn't just the leadership position. A political reorganization tsunami that sweeps everything away will come crashing down. The party itself could disappear. (국민의힘이 지면 장 대표는 치명타를 입게 됩니다. 장 대표 주변에선 “선거에서 웬만큼 져도 현 체제가 유지될 수 있다”는 주장을 합니다. 선거에 져도 당권만 유지하면 대선까지 길이 열릴 수 있다는 겁니다. 하지만 선거에 지면 대표직이 문제가 아닙니다. 모든 것을 휩쓰는 정계 개편 쓰나미가 밀어닥칠 겁니다. 당이 사라질 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/premium/2026/01/18/UMFUCPRQQBCUHHJPLQSCZCZ75Y/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UMZYTHRG25K37LPMFBW53WGB2M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>