<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 20:31:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi, Who Said He Would Accept Expulsion, Voluntarily Leaves Democratic Party (제명 따르겠다던 김병기, 민주당 자진 탈당)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/AIHPNCAF3VB7JPPGFJBDONCAJ4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Byeong-gi, Who Said He Would Accept Expulsion, Voluntarily Leaves Democratic Party (제명 따르겠다던 김병기, 민주당 자진 탈당)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VRSNPY2JGJC2BABUGD7P7EYAIE.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that former floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, Kim Byeong-gi, submitted a letter of resignation to the party's Seoul chapter on the 19th. (김병기 전 더불어민주당 원내대표가 19일 민주당 서울시당에 탈당계를 제출한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This comes just seven days after he received an 'expulsion' ruling from the party's Ethics Tribunal on the 12th over various allegations, including receiving nomination-related donations. (그가 지난 12일 민주당 윤리심판원에서 공천 헌금 수수 등 각종 의혹으로 ‘제명’ 처분을 받은 지 7일 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that day, former floor leader Kim held a press conference at the National Assembly Communication Center and stated, "I have not yet received the official decision document from the Ethics Tribunal, but I will leave without applying for a retrial." (앞서 김 전 원내대표는 이날 국회 소통관에서 기자회견을 열고 “아직까지 윤리심판원의 결정문을 통보받지 못했지만 재심을 신청하지 않고 떠나겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the press conference, he also drew a line at voluntary resignation, saying, "I have said that even if I am expelled, I will not choose to leave the party on my own. That position remains the same." However, he appears to have reversed his stance afterward.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (그는 또 기자회견에서 “제명당하더라도 스스로 당을 떠나는 선택은 하지 않겠다고 말해왔다. 그 입장은 지금도 같다”며 자진 탈당에 선을 그었다. 그러나 이후 입장을 선회한 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/AIHPNCAF3VB7JPPGFJBDONCAJ4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VRSNPY2JGJC2BABUGD7P7EYAIE.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:01:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Seong-gyu, Progressive Party Chief Spokesperson, Runs for Gyeonggi Governor... "Will Appoint a Vice Governor for Labor" (홍성규 진보당 수석대변인, 경기도지사 출마…“노동부지사 임명”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/G3YQD4IHWZBG5HYZKDE5QA45SQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Hong Seong-gyu, Progressive Party Chief Spokesperson, Runs for Gyeonggi Governor... "Will Appoint a Vice Governor for Labor" (홍성규 진보당 수석대변인, 경기도지사 출마…“노동부지사 임명”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4TQMTDGQ4DKMZWME3DQOBTGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Seong-gyu, the Progressive Party's chief spokesperson, held a press conference at the Gyeonggi Provincial Council briefing room on the 19th and declared his candidacy for governor of Gyeonggi Province in the June 3 local elections. (홍성규 진보당 수석대변인은 19일 경기도의회 브리핑룸에서 기자회견을 열어 6·3 지방선거 경기도지사 출마를 선언했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Hong stated, "The four years under Governor Kim Dong-yeon of the Democratic Party of Korea were a period of 'regression and chaos.' Governor Kim never once met with the Korean Confederation of Trade Unions throughout his term, and while claiming to be a climate governor, he did not let go of the scam that is the Gyeonggi International Airport," adding, "A decisive break from the past four years is the start of a new Gyeonggi Province." (홍 수석대변인은 “김동연 더불어민주당 경기도지사의 4년은 ‘퇴행과 혼란’이었다. 김 지사는 임기 내내 단 한 번도 민주노총을 만나지 않았고 기후도지사를 자처하면서 경기국제공항이라는 사기극을 놓지 않았다”며 “지난 4년과 단호히 결별하는 것이 새로운 경기도의 시작”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He pledged, "Respect for labor is the solid foundation of the new Gyeonggi provincial administration, irreplaceable by anything else. I will appoint a 'Vice Governor for Labor' to be part of the provincial administration from start to finish," and "As fundamental solutions to the pressing issues of waste and care, I will establish a 'Gyeonggi-type circular economy model' and a 'tailored public care system.'" (그는 “노동 존중은 무엇과도 대체할 수 없는 새로운 경기도정의 단단한 근간으로 ‘노동부지사’를 임명해 도정의 처음부터 끝까지 함께 하겠다”며 “당면 과제인 쓰레기 문제와 돌봄에 대한 근본 해법으로 경기도형 순환경제모델과 맞춤형 공공돌봄체계’를 구축하겠다”고 공약했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the Progressive Party elected Chief Spokesperson Hong as its candidate for Gyeonggi governor through a vote of all eligible party members from September 26 to 30 last year. (앞서 진보당은 지난해 9월 26~30일 권리당원 총투표를 통해 홍 수석대변인을 경기도지사 후보로 선출했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Hong had previously run as the Gyeonggi governor candidate for the People's Party, the predecessor of the Progressive Party, in the 7th local elections eight years ago in 2018. (홍 수석대변인은 8년 전인 2018년 제7회 지방선거에서 진보당의 전신인 민중당 경기도지사 후보로 출마한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/G3YQD4IHWZBG5HYZKDE5QA45SQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4TQMTDGQ4DKMZWME3DQOBTGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 22:22:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young's Requested 'Gift' of Transferring the Institute for National Unification to the Ministry Faces Inevitable Delays (정동영이 ‘선물’로 달라던 통일연구원의 통일부 이관 차질 불가피)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W4LKCKOIK5F45KMWHWLGN26FJA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young's Requested 'Gift' of Transferring the Institute for National Unification to the Ministry Faces Inevitable Delays (정동영이 ‘선물’로 달라던 통일연구원의 통일부 이관 차질 불가피)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3TGOLFHA3TIMRRGJSWKMJZHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transfer of the Institute for National Unification to the Ministry of Unification, which Minister Jeong Dong-young had requested from President Lee Jae-myung as a 'gift,' has been halted. (정동영 통일부 장관이 이재명 대통령에게 ‘선물’로 달라고 요청했던 통일연구원의 통일부 이관 작업이 중단됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 17th, the Ministry of Unification announced on its website, "We are withdrawing the legislative notice for the Institute for National Unification Act (draft) as additional consultations with related agencies are necessary." This came just three days after the ministry had issued the legislative notice for a bill to transfer the state-funded research institute, the Institute for National Unification, under its jurisdiction. (통일부는 지난 17일 홈페이지에 “통일연구원법(안) 입법예고 관련 관계기관과 추가적인 협의가 필요함에 따라 이를 철회한다”고 공지했다. 국책연구기관인 통일연구원을 통일부 산하로 이관하는 내용의 법안을 입법예고한 지 사흘 만에 거둬들인 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 14th, the Ministry of Unification had issued a legislative notice for the 'Draft Act on the Institute for National Unification,' stating its intention to change the affiliation of the Institute for National Unification, which is currently supported and managed by the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences under the Office for Government Policy Coordination, to "under the Ministry of Unification." As reasons for the legislative notice, the ministry cited that "research outcomes in the unification and security fields have a significant impact on inter-Korean relations and national security" and the "need for organic linkage between policy and research." (통일부는 지난 14일 ‘통일연구원법 제정안’을 입법 예고하고 현재 국무조정실 산하 경제인문사회연구회가 지원·관리하는 통일연구원을 “통일부 산하로 변경하고자 한다”고 했었다. 통일부는 입법예고 사유로 “통일·안보 분야 연구 결과가 남북 관계와 국가 안보에 미치는 영향이 심대하다”는 점과 “정책과 연구의 유기적 연계 필요성”을 들었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during a presidential briefing on December 19 last year, Minister Jeong Dong-young said, "I request... that the Institute for National Unification be transferred to the Ministry of Unification... I ask the President to give us one gift," and President Lee instructed Prime Minister Kim Min-seok on the spot to discuss the matter. Minister Jeong stated, "The Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of National Defense, and the National Intelligence Service all have think tanks, but the Ministry of Unification does not," adding, "During the IMF (International Monetary Fund foreign exchange crisis), (affiliated institutions) were merged or abolished; powerful ministries kept theirs, but the Ministry of Unification, lacking power, saw the Institute for National Unification separated." (앞서 정동영 장관은 지난해 12월 19일 대통령 업무보고에서 “통일연구원을 통일부로 이관해 주십사 하는…, 대통령님께서 선물을 하나 주십사 하는 부탁을 드립니다”라고 했고 이 대통령은 그 자리에서 김민석 국무총리에게 관련 논의를 할 것을 지시했다. 정 장관은 “외교부와 국방부, 국가정보원은 모두 싱크탱크가 있지만 통일부는 없다”며 “IMF(국제통화기금 외환 위기) 때 (산하 기관들이) 통폐합됐는데 힘 있는 부처는 다 남았고 통일부가 힘이 없어서 통일연구원이 분리됐다”고 했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personnel at the Institute for National Unification reportedly only learned of Minister Jeong's proposal to transfer the institute to the ministry after watching the live televised presidential briefing. One researcher said, "There was absolutely no prior consultation with the Ministry of Unification regarding the transfer of the institute before the presidential briefing," and "we were extremely embarrassed by the Minister's remarks during the live broadcast, asking for the institute as a 'gift.'" It is reported that the institute later conveyed its negative stance on the transfer to the Ministry of Unification during a briefing to Prime Minister Kim Min-seok by the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences on the 9th, but the Ministry of Unification proceeded with the legislative notice anyway, and during this process, proper prior consultations were not adequately conducted with the council or the Office for Government Policy Coordination, to which the institute belongs. (통일연구원 소속 인사들은 정 장관의 연구원의 통일부 이관 건의를 TV로 생중계된 대통령 업무보고를 보고서야 알았다고 한다. 한 연구원은 “대통령 업무보고 전 연구원의 통일부 이관에 대해 통일부와 사전에 협의한 게 전혀 없었다”며 “생중계된 방송에서 연구원을 ‘선물’로 달라는 장관의 발언에 굉장히 당혹스러웠다”고 했다. 연구원은 이후 지난 9일 김민석 국무총리에 대한 경제인문사회연구회(경인사연) 업무보고에서 연구원의 통일부 이관에 대해 부정적 입장을 전달했으나 통일부는 입법예고를 강행했고 이 과정에서 연구원이 속한 경인사연, 국조실과도 사전 협의가 제대로 이뤄지지 않았다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Institute for National Unification was initially established under the Ministry of Unification in 1991 and was transferred under the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences in 1999 following the enactment of relevant legislation. This was based on the Kim Dae-jung administration's plan to guarantee independent research for state-funded research institutes, following the judgment that such institutes had failed to foresee the IMF economic crisis and take preemptive measures. An official from the Institute for National Unification stated, "If the institute were to come under a ministry, there is a high risk that the minimum autonomy and independence in research required for a state-funded research institute would be compromised, which is why the dominant stance within the institute was negative towards the transfer to the Ministry of Unification." (통일연구원은 1991년 설립 초기 통일부 산하에서 1999년 관련 법 제정에 따라 경인사연 산하로 이관됐다. 국책 연구기관이 IMF 경제 위기를 예견하지 못하고 사전 대응에 실패했다는 판단에 국책 연구기관들의 독립적 연구를 보장하겠다는 김대중 정부의 구상에 따른 것이었다. 통일연구원의 한 관계자는 “연구원이 부처 산하로 들어가게 되면 국책 연구기관에 요구되는 최소한의 연구의 자율성과 독립성이 훼손될 위험이 크기 때문에 연구원의 통일부 이관에 부정적 입장이 지배적이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W4LKCKOIK5F45KMWHWLGN26FJA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3TGOLFHA3TIMRRGJSWKMJZHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:31:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Jun-seok to Visit Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site Immediately Upon Early Return on the 21st (이준석, 21일 조기 귀국하자마자 장동혁 단식장 찾는다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ZEPLWIWMPVFYRBFJ2PM455PAW4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Jun-seok to Visit Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site Immediately Upon Early Return on the 21st (이준석, 21일 조기 귀국하자마자 장동혁 단식장 찾는다)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WPBM63BRWRPBLGPLAKNP3S3C4Q.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, continues his hunger strike for the fifth day, demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of Democratic Party of Korea nomination donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians, Lee Jun-seok, the leader of the Reform Party, will return early on the 21st and immediately visit Jang's hunger strike site. However, it is reported that a joint hunger strike with Jang, who declared an indefinite hunger strike, is not currently under consideration. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 더불어민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 닷새째 단식을 이어가는 가운데 이준석 개혁신당 대표가 21일 조기 귀국해 곧바로 장 대표 단식장을 찾는다. 다만 무기한 단식을 선언한 장 대표와의 공동 단식은 현재로선 검토하지 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform Party announced on the 19th that Lee, who was originally scheduled to return on the 23rd, will return early on the 21st to cooperate on issues like the twin special prosecutor. Lee's itinerary involved returning via Mexico and Guatemala after visiting the United States, but it is said he canceled his U.S. schedule. Lee told this newspaper, "I plan to go directly from the airport to the National Assembly Rotunda Hall, the site of Jang's hunger strike, immediately after returning early in the morning on the 21st." A Reform Party official stated, "The cooperation between the two parties for the twin special prosecutor was originally proposed by Lee," adding, "This is to show support for Jang, who is on a hunger strike for the twin special prosecutor." (개혁신당은 19일 당초 23일 귀국 예정이었던 이 대표가 21일 조기 귀국해 쌍특검 등에 대해 공조할 예정이라고 밝혔다. 이 대표는 멕시코와 과테말라를 거쳐 미국을 들렀다 귀국하는 일정이었는데 미국 일정은 취소했다고 한다. 이 대표는 이날 본지에 “21일 새벽 귀국 직후 공항에서 곧바로 장 대표의 국회 로텐더홀 단식 현장을 찾을 예정”이라고 밝혔다. 개혁신당 관계자는 “당초 쌍특검을 위한 양 당의 공조는 이 대표가 먼저 제안했던 것”이라며 “쌍특검을 위해 단식하는 장 대표에게 힘을 실어주는 차원”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Reform Party is drawing a line at joining the hunger strike. Cheon Ha-ram, the party's floor leader, met with reporters and said, "Doing everything exactly the same is not necessarily the right answer," adding, "Last week, while Jang began his hunger strike, the Reform Party conducted a filibuster. Although our methods were different, we made cooperative efforts to strongly appeal to the public about the necessity of the twin special prosecutor." He further stated, "We plan to persuade the public about the necessity of the twin special prosecutor in various ways." A party official said, "Since Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won also began a hunger strike starting today, we believe it would not be helpful for Lee to join and sit with them." (다만 개혁신당은 동조 단식에는 선을 긋고 있다. 천하람 원내대표는 이날 기자들과 만나 “모든 걸 똑같이 하는 것만이 정답은 아닐 것”이라며 “지난주 장 대표는 단식에 들어가고 개혁신당은 필리버스터를 하는 형태로 서로 모습은 다르지만 국민들께 쌍특검의 필요성을 강하게 어필하기 위한 공조 노력을 했다”고 했다. 그러면서 “다양한 형태로 국민들께 쌍특검 필요성을 설득할 예정”이라고 말했다. 당 관계자는 “이날부터 김재원 최고위원이 함께 단식을 시작한 만큼 이 대표가 함께 앉는 그림이 도움이 되진 않는다고 보고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, after a meeting between leaders Jang and Lee on the 13th, the two parties began full-fledged so-called 'special prosecutor cooperation.' Subsequently, when Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram began an unlimited debate on the 15th to oppose the second comprehensive special prosecutor bill pushed by the Democratic Party, Jang started his hunger strike at the Rotunda Hall. Jang, who is facing internal party backlash over the push to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon, is reportedly viewing solidarity with the Reform Party as an escape route. (앞서 지난 13일 장·이 대표가 회동한 뒤 두 당은 이른바 ‘특검 공조’를 본격화했다. 이후 장 대표는 개혁신당 천하람 원내대표가 15일 민주당이 추진하는 2차 종합 특검법 반대를 위한 무제한 토론을 시작하자 로텐더홀에서 단식을 시작했다. 장 대표는 한동훈 전 대표 제명 추진을 두고 당내 반발에 직면한 상황에서 개혁신당과의 연대를 탈출구로 보고 있는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ZEPLWIWMPVFYRBFJ2PM455PAW4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WPBM63BRWRPBLGPLAKNP3S3C4Q.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:35:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Representative Visits U.S... Shared Understanding on 'Prompt Consultations' (한미 원자력협력 대표 미국 방문... ‘조속한 협의’ 공감)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/HVWAX4JHJVBEFHDBH2XWR5DCIU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Representative Visits U.S... Shared Understanding on 'Prompt Consultations' (한미 원자력협력 대표 미국 방문... ‘조속한 협의’ 공감)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUH7SFDPFFPAFG3C5NEWLQKLOE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Gap-su, the head of the South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Pan-Government Consultative Body (TF) tasked with negotiating with the United States to expand rights for uranium enrichment and spent nuclear fuel reprocessing, visited Washington D.C. last week to meet with U.S. officials and coordinate the negotiation schedule. (우라늄 농축 및 사용후핵연료 재처리 권한 확대를 미국과 협상할 ‘한미 원자력 협력 범정부협의체(TF)’의 임갑수 대표가 지난주 미국 워싱턴DC를 방문해 미 당국자들과 만나 협상 일정 등을 조율했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced that Representative Im visited the U.S. for two days on the 15th and 16th, meeting with U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Arms Control and Nonproliferation Christopher Ye and Deputy Administrator of the National Nuclear Security Administration Matthew Napoli. (19일 외교부는 임 대표가 지난 15~16일 양일간 방미해 미 국무부 군비통제·비확산국 크리스토퍼 여 차관보, 매튜 나폴리 핵안보청 부청장 등을 만났다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated, "Representative Im held introductory meetings with key figures and exchanged views on the overall plan for future cooperation to secure our commercial and peaceful enrichment and reprocessing capabilities." (외교부는 “임 대표가 주요 인사들과 상견례 차 면담을 갖고, 우리의 상업적·평화적 농축·재처리 역량 확보를 위한 향후 협력 추진 전반에 대해 의견을 교환했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs further stated, "It was agreed that a U.S. working-level delegation will visit South Korea as soon as possible for follow-up consultations to promptly implement the agreement between the two leaders contained in the joint fact sheet from the South Korea-U.S. summit." (외교부는 또 “한미 정상회담 공동 설명 자료(조인트 팩트 시트)에 담긴 양국 정상 간 합의를 조속히 이행하기 위한 후속 협의를 위해 가급적 빠른 시일 내에 미 실무 대표단이 방한하기로 했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, working-level negotiations between South Korea and the U.S. are expected to commence in Seoul in the near future. However, who the U.S. representative will be has not yet been disclosed. (이에 따라 조만간 서울에서 한미 양측의 실무 협상이 개시될 것으로 보인다. 다만 미국 측 대표가 누가 될지는 아직 공개되지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, National Security Advisor Wi Sung-lak visited the U.S. last month and met with Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Secretary of Energy Chris Wright. After the meetings, he stated, "It was agreed that a U.S. working-level delegation will visit South Korea at the earliest possible time early next year to begin full-fledged (specific) consultations on each security issue included in the two countries' joint fact sheet." (앞서 위성락 국가안보실장은 지난달 미국을 방문해 마코 루비오 국무장관, 크리스 라이트 에너지부 장관 등과 면담한 뒤 “내년 초 가능한 이른 시기에 미 측 실무 대표단이 방한, 양국의 조인트 팩트시트에 포함된 안보 사안별로 (구체적인) 본격 협의를 갖기로 했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The South Korean side's 'South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Pan-Government Consultative Body' held its first meeting on the 9th at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs building in Seoul. The government plans to use the consultative body to detail how to address the expansion of enrichment and reprocessing rights—whether through a full revision or partial amendment of the existing South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Agreement—and then enter into negotiations with the United States. (우리 측 ‘한미 원자력 협력 범정부협의체’는 지난 9일 서울 외교부 청사에서 첫 회의를 열었다. 정부는 협의체를 통해 농축·재처리 권한 확대를 기존 한미 원자력협력 협정의 전면 개정 내지 일부 수정 등 어떤 방식으로 풀어낼지를 구체화한 뒤 미국과 협상에 나설 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/HVWAX4JHJVBEFHDBH2XWR5DCIU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUH7SFDPFFPAFG3C5NEWLQKLOE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 23:16:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Regarding the Ilta Instructor·Teacher Exam Question Backdoor Deal... Kang Ho-sik Says "Education Authorities Should Apologize" (일타강사·교사 문제 뒷거래에... 강훈식 “교육 당국 사과해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/DH5N2JB3JJEUZKEFBDDUDA3IMI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Regarding the Ilta Instructor·Teacher Exam Question Backdoor Deal... Kang Ho-sik Says "Education Authorities Should Apologize" (일타강사·교사 문제 뒷거래에... 강훈식 “교육 당국 사과해야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Presidential Chief of Staff Kang Ho-sik stated regarding the 'exam question trading' incident involving school teachers and private education instructors, "A sincere reflection and apology at the level of the education authorities is necessary for the sense of betrayal and helplessness the students must have felt." Presiding over a senior secretary meeting at the Blue House that day, Chief of Staff Kang emphasized, "The starting point of a fair Republic of Korea is managing the college entrance system without foul play." (강훈식 대통령 비서실장은 19일 학교 교사들과 사교육 강사들의 ‘시험 문항 거래’ 사건과 관련해 “학생들이 느꼈을 허탈감과 무력감에 대해 교육 당국 차원의 진정성 있는 성찰과 사과가 필요하다”고 밝혔다. 강 실장은 이날 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 “공정한 대한민국의 출발점은 반칙 없는 입시제도 관리”라며 이같이 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "Recently, cases that fundamentally undermine the fairness of the college entrance system, such as illegal trading and leaking of exam questions across the educational field, have been revealed one after another, seriously damaging public trust," adding, "This is a significant issue that infringes upon the entire education system and social order, going beyond simple individual misconduct." Furthermore, he instructed, "The Ministry of Education and national education offices must thoroughly inspect whether there are any additional foul plays in the overall management of the college entrance system and school records, and report any areas requiring system improvement." (그는 “최근 교육 현장 전반에서 불법적인 시험문제 거래와 유출 등 입시제도의 공정성을 근본적으로 훼손한 사례들이 잇따라 드러나며 국민적 신뢰를 심각하게 무너뜨렸다”며 “이는 단순한 개인 비리를 넘어 교육제도 전반과 사회질서를 침해하는 중대한 문제”라고 했다. 아울러 “교육부와 전국 교육청에서 입시제도와 학교 내신 관리 전반에 추가적인 반칙은 없는지 철저히 점검하고 제도 개선이 필요한 사항을 보고하라”고 지시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Chief of Staff Kang pointed out, "As the global popularity of K-beauty and K-food increases, the distribution of counterfeit products cleverly imitating Korean brands is spreading overseas," and "Beyond our companies suffering damage, this threatens the health and safety of overseas consumers and can damage the overall trust in Korean products." He then ordered, "The counterfeit Korean goods problem has limitations if addressed only by individual companies' responses," and instructed, "Relevant ministries such as the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and the Korean Intellectual Property Office should cooperate to conduct a comprehensive inspection of the current system operation status and, if necessary, promptly prepare and report on measures such as legal revisions and budget support." (이어 강 실장은 “K-뷰티와 K-푸드 등의 세계적 인기가 높아지면서 한국 브랜드를 교묘하게 위조한 가짜 상품 유통이 해외에서 확산하고 있다”며 “우리 기업이 피해를 보는 것을 넘어 해외 소비자의 건강과 안전을 위협하고 한국 상품 전반의 신뢰를 훼손할 수 있다”고 지적했다. 그러면서 “가짜 한국 상품 문제는 개별 기업의 대응만으로는 한계가 있다”며 “산업통상부, 외교부, 지식재산처 등 관계부처가 협력해 제도 운영 현황을 전면 점검하고 필요한 경우 법 개정과 예산 지원 방안 등을 신속히 마련해 보고하라”고 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/DH5N2JB3JJEUZKEFBDDUDA3IMI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 23:37:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party Surpasses 1 Million Paying Members for First Time... "Strengthening Member Rights Since Jang Dong-hyuk's Leadership Began" (국힘, 당원 100만명 첫 돌파... “장동혁 체제 출범 후 당원 권리 강화”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/4SKDXUNYQZF53BVXJLHYCLOVLM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party Surpasses 1 Million Paying Members for First Time... "Strengthening Member Rights Since Jang Dong-hyuk's Leadership Began" (국힘, 당원 100만명 첫 돌파... “장동혁 체제 출범 후 당원 권리 강화”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LFGWJ4O72VMZ5GK4DTF652GV3Q.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party announced on the 19th that the number of members paying party dues has surpassed 1 million for the first time in the party's history, starting this month. (국민의힘은 이달부터 당비를 내는 당원 인원수가 당 사상 최초로 100만명을 돌파했다고 19일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party's organization bureau stated in a press release that day, "As of January 2026, for the first time in the party's history, the number of members paying party dues has exceeded 1 million per month, reaching approximately 1,083,000 as of today." This figure includes not only responsible members, who have voting rights within the party after paying dues for three months or more, but also general members who have paid dues for even one month. (국민의힘 조직국은 이날 보도자료를 내고 “2026년 1월을 기점으로 당 역사상 최초로 당비를 납부하는 당원 수가 월 100만명을 돌파해, 이날 기준 108만3000여 명에 이르는 것으로 확인됐다”고 했다. 이는 3개월 이상 당비를 납부해 당내 투표권을 갖는 책임당원뿐 아니라 한달이라도 당비를 낸 일반 당원까지 포함한 규모다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party explained, "The number of dues-paying members was around 750,000 before the party convention last August, but since the inauguration of the Jang Dong-hyuk leadership system, policies to honor long-term responsible members and strengthen member rights have led to increased membership recruitment." (국민의힘은 “당비 납부 당원은 작년 8월 전당대회 이전에는 75만명수준이었으나, 장동혁 대표 체제 출범 이후 장기 책임당원을 예우하고 당원의 권리를 강화하는 정책이 당원 모집으로 이어졌다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party added, "The 'era of 1 million responsible members' is also expected to be established soon," and stated, "We will actively mobilize the party member organization in the local elections to closely reflect grassroots public sentiment, present practical alternatives to resolving regional issues, and decisively lead the elections to victory." (국민의힘은 “‘100만 책임당원 시대’도 곧 안착할 전망”이라며 “지방선거에서 당원 조직을 적극 가동해 풀뿌리 민심을 촘촘히 반영하고, 지역별 현안 해결에 실질적인 대안을 제시해 선거를 반드시 승리로 이끌겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/4SKDXUNYQZF53BVXJLHYCLOVLM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LFGWJ4O72VMZ5GK4DTF652GV3Q.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 02:09:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Following the Disruption of Lee Hye-hoon's Hearing...People Power Party Announces "All Standing Committee Meetings This Week Suspended" (이혜훈 청문회 파행 이어...국힘 “이번 주 상임위 모두 중단”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/IT5MKGWSH5CKDD7NAKV57SRXKY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Following the Disruption of Lee Hye-hoon's Hearing...People Power Party Announces "All Standing Committee Meetings This Week Suspended" (이혜훈 청문회 파행 이어...국힘 “이번 주 상임위 모두 중단” )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62ZU2375YBKXJD3756JOMUG2VQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the People Power Party announced it would boycott all standing committee meetings scheduled for this week, in a show of support for its leader, Jang Dong-hyuk, who is on the fifth day of a hunger strike demanding the acceptance of special counsel probes into the Unification Church and election nomination bribes. This announcement came after the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for the inaugural Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, scheduled for the same day, was disrupted following a heated argument between the ruling and opposition parties. (국민의힘이 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 중인 장동혁 대표에게 힘을 싣는 차원에서 이번 주 예정된 상임위원회를 모두 보이콧하겠다고 19일 밝혔다. 이 같은 공지는 이날 예정됐던 이혜훈 초대 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회가 여야 간 설전 끝에 파행된 이후 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party's intra-parliamentary administration office stated in a parliamentary notice that day, "Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike struggle for the acceptance of the dual special counsel probes (into the Unification Church and nomination bribes) has entered its fifth day," adding, "Our party will postpone all standing committee schedules planned for this week from this time onward and join forces in supporting Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk's resolute actions." (국민의힘 원내행정국은 이날 원내 공지에서 “쌍특검(통일교·공천 뇌물) 수용을 위한 장동혁 당 대표의 단식 투쟁이 5일째 이어지고 있다“면서 “우리 당은 이 시간 이후 금주 예정된 모든 상임위 일정을 순연하고, 장동혁 당 대표의 결연한 행보에 힘을 모으도록 하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intra-parliamentary administration office also said, "We request that each standing committee suspend its schedule until the hunger strike struggle concludes and join the struggle for the immediate acceptance of the dual special counsel probes by President Lee Jae-myung and the Democratic Party of Korea." (원내행정국은 “각 상임위에서는 단식 투쟁이 종료되는 시점까지 상임위 일정을 중단해주시고, 이재명 대통령과 더불어민주당의 쌍특검 즉각 수용을 위한 투쟁에 함께해 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly had planned to hold the nominee's confirmation hearing that day, but as the ruling and opposition parties argued over the submission of the nominee's documents and whether to change the schedule, the meeting was adjourned without Lee Hye-hoon even being able to attend. The People Power Party maintained that the hearing could not proceed because the nominee had failed to submit a significant portion of the requested documents by the deadline, while the Democratic Party countered that the nominee should be brought in for public verification. Ultimately, People Power Party member and chairman of the Strategy and Finance Committee, Im I-jae, adjourned the meeting, telling the floor leaders of both parties to "go and hold further consultations." (국회는 이날 이 후보자의 인사청문회를 열기로 했지만, 여야가 후보자 자료 제출과 일정 변경 여부를 놓고 설전을 벌이면서 정작 이혜훈 후보자는 참석도 못한 채 회의를 정회했다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 요구된 자료의 상당 부분을 기한 내 제출하지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 열 수 없다는 입장을 고수한 반면, 민주당은 후보자를 출석시켜 공개 검증에 나서야 한다고 맞섰다. 결국 국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장은 여야 간사를 향해 “추가 협의해 오라”며 회의를 정회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/IT5MKGWSH5CKDD7NAKV57SRXKY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62ZU2375YBKXJD3756JOMUG2VQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 22:49:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Installs "South Korea is the Primary Enemy State" Signage at Ideological Education Facility (北 사상교육 시설에 “한국은 제1의 적대국” 게시물 설치)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/RM7XOBEYWZGZJP4KG6ML3KEF6Q/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea Installs "South Korea is the Primary Enemy State" Signage at Ideological Education Facility (北 사상교육 시설에 “한국은 제1의 적대국” 게시물 설치)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/T5IV6XCMHROQNK7QA67BILCZVQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea, which has declared inter-Korean relations as a 'relationship between two hostile states,' has reportedly installed signage stating "South Korea is the primary enemy state" at a 'Class Education Hall,' a space used to instill anti-U.S. and anti-South Korea hostility. (남북관계를 ‘적대적 두 국가 관계’로 선언한 북한이 대미·대남 적개심을 주입하는 공간인 ‘계급교양관’에 “한국은 제1의 적대국”이라는 내용의 게시물을 설치한 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Central News Agency reported on the 19th that participants in an event commemorating the 80th anniversary of the founding of the Socialist Patriotic Youth League (Youth League) visited the Central Class Education Hall in Pyongyang, and included a photo of soldiers listening to an instructor's explanation. (조선중앙통신은 19일 사회주의애국청년동맹(청년동맹) 창립 80주년 기념행사 참가자들이 평양 시내 중앙계급교양관을 참관했다며 군인들이 강사의 설명을 듣는 사진을 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interior view revealed in the photo shows two wall surfaces densely covered with content inciting anti-South Korea hostility. The upper parts of the walls prominently display phrases such as "South Korea is the primary enemy state, the unchanging main enemy," "Our 'system overthrow'," and "confrontation frenzy." Also captured was a display of Article 3 of the South Korean constitution, which states, "The territory of the Republic of Korea shall consist of the Korean Peninsula and its adjacent islands." This appears to be using Article 3 as propaganda to claim that South Korea maintains a hostile policy towards North Korea and aims for absorption unification. (사진에 공개된 내부 모습을 보면 두 개 벽면에 대남 적개심을 부추기는 내용이 빼곡히 설치돼 있다. 벽면 상단에는 각각 “한국은 제1의 적대국, 불변의 주적” “우리의 ‘제도전복’, “대결광기” 등의 문구가 크게 부착됐다. 또 “대한민국의 영토는 한반도와 그 부속도서로 한다”는 내용의 남한 헌법 3조를 게시한 모습도 포착됐다. 한국이 북한에 적대 노선을 유지하고 흡수통일을 노리고 있다는 선전의 근거로 헌법 3조를 활용하고 있는 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a speech at the Supreme People's Assembly last September, Chairman of the State Affairs Commission Kim Jong Un criticized former President Syngman Rhee for promulgating a constitution in July 1948 that included the clause "The territory of the Republic of Korea shall consist of the Korean Peninsula and its adjacent islands," which contained the will for absorption unification, stating it "codified the most hostile innate nature towards our state." In a Supreme People's Assembly speech in January 2024, Kim Jong Un also instructed that it should be stipulated in constitutional clauses to "strengthen educational and indoctrination work to firmly regard the Republic of Korea as the primary enemy state and the unchanging main enemy." (김정은 국무위원장은 지난해 9월 최고인민회의 연설에서 이승만 전 대통령이 1948년 7월 흡수통일 의지가 담긴 ‘대한민국의 영토는 한반도와 그 부속 도서로 한다’는 조문이 포함된 헌법을 공포했다면서 “우리 국가에 가장 적대적인 태생적 본성을 성문화했다”고 비난했었다. 김정은은 2024년 1월 최고인민회의 연설에선 “대한민국을 철두철미 제1의 적대국으로, 불변의 주적으로 확고히 간주하도록 교육교양사업을 강화한다는 것”을 헌법 조문에 명기해야 할 것을 지시하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Central Class Education Hall is a facility for the North Korean authorities' ideological education of residents. It opened in 2016 on the banks of the Pothong River in Pyongyang. It is a space filled with exhibits aimed at fostering hostility towards free democratic countries with different systems from North Korea, such as South Korea, the United States, and Japan. (중앙계급교양관은 북한 당국의 주민들에 대한 사상교육을 위한 곳으로 평양 보통강변에 2016년 개관했다. 한국, 미국, 일본 등 북한과 체제가 다른 자유민주주의 국가들에 대한 적대감을 고취하는 내용의 전시물로 꾸려진 공간이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/RM7XOBEYWZGZJP4KG6ML3KEF6Q/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/T5IV6XCMHROQNK7QA67BILCZVQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:42:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Independence Hall of Korea Board of Trustees Passes Motion Demanding Dismissal of Director Kim Hyung-seok (독립기념관 이사회, 김형석 관장 해임요구안 의결)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/MR45LMOKMJFQFPJGZSWIVFPFDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Independence Hall of Korea Board of Trustees Passes Motion Demanding Dismissal of Director Kim Hyung-seok (독립기념관 이사회, 김형석 관장 해임요구안 의결)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZM46ANT6FZD77FNUVTDOLWY5C4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Trustees of the Independence Hall of Korea passed a motion on the 19th recommending the dismissal of Director Kim Hyung-seok. (독립기념관 이사회가 19일 김형석 독립기념관장 해임 건의안을 가결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 13th, the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs had publicly disclosed 14 alleged irregularities by Director Kim, including the privatization of the Independence Hall, and recommended his dismissal. (앞서 국가보훈부는 지난 13일 김 관장의 독립기념관 사유화 등 14가지 비위 사실을 공개하며 해임을 건의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that the board meeting proceeded with 13 out of the 15 registered members in attendance, excluding members Bae Joon-young (a People Power Party lawmaker) and Park Yi-taek. (이날 이사회는 재적 인원 15명 중 배준영(국민의힘 의원), 박이택 이사 2명을 제외한 13명이 참석한 가운데 진행된 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the 12 members present (excluding Director Kim), 10 voted in favor, leading to the passage of the dismissal recommendation motion. (이 가운데 김형석 관장을 제외한 12명 중 10명이 찬성하면서 해임건의안은 가결됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs plans to submit the request for Director Kim's dismissal to President Lee Jae-myung. (국가보훈부는 김 관장에 대한 해임을 이재명 대통령에게 제청할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the board meeting, Director Kim stated at a press conference, "The audit by the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs, which formed the basis for the dismissal decision, was unjustly conducted with the sole purpose of dismissing the Director of the Independence Hall, disregarding substantive facts," adding, "I cannot agree with the contents of the audit report." (김 관장은 이사회 후 가진 기자간담회에서 “해임 의결의 근거가 된 보훈부 감사는 실체적 사실과 무관하게 독립기념관장의 해임을 목적으로 부당하게 진행됐다”며 “감사결과보고서 내용에 대해 동의할 수 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/MR45LMOKMJFQFPJGZSWIVFPFDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZM46ANT6FZD77FNUVTDOLWY5C4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As the Ruling Party Said, "We'll Remove Him in January"... Board of Trustees Dismisses Independence Hall Director (“1월에 자르겠다” 與 말대로... 독립기념관장 해임한 이사회)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/GO3VDMIPJ5A7LBUH37WIWT5DP4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;As the Ruling Party Said, "We'll Remove Him in January"... Board of Trustees Dismisses Independence Hall Director (“1월에 자르겠다” 與 말대로... 독립기념관장 해임한 이사회)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NJIRNYZIOVNCPJINQLS2YCMEBI.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A motion demanding the dismissal of Independence Hall Director Kim Hyung-suk, who was appointed under the Yoon Suk-yeol administration, was passed by the Independence Hall Board of Trustees on the 19th. Based on this, the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs will recommend dismissal to President Lee Jae-myung, who is expected to approve it. Previously, Democratic Party of Korea floor spokesperson Kim Hyun-jung appeared on MBC Radio last month and stated that after the period for appealing the ministry's special audit of Director Kim ended on the 5th of this month, "he must be dismissed." This follows the steps for a 'dismissal at the beginning of the year' as forewarned by the Democratic Party. (윤석열 정부에서 임명된 김형석 독립기념관장에 대한 해임 요구안이 19일 독립기념관 이사회에서 의결됐다. 국가보훈부가 이를 토대로 이재명 대통령에게 해임 제청을 하고, 이 대통령은 재가할 것으로 예상된다. 앞서 더불어민주당 김현정 원내대변인은 지난달 MBC 라디오에 출연해 김 관장에 대한 보훈부 특정감사의 이의 신청 제기 기간이 끝나는 이달 5일 이후에 “반드시 해임시켜야 한다”고 말했다. 민주당이 예고한 대로 ‘연초 해임’ 수순을 밟고 있는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Director Kim, who took office in early August 2024, has over 18 months remaining in his term, which lasts until August next year. Director Kim held a press conference on this day and said, "I will seek a judgment through administrative procedures on whether there was a 'serious violation' constituting grounds for dismissal of the director." It is reported that Director Kim's side is considering administrative litigation and other measures if the dismissal is finalized. (2024년 8월 초 취임한 김 관장의 임기는 내년 8월까지로 18개월 이상 남았다. 김 관장은 이날 기자회견을 열고 “행정 절차를 통해 관장 해임 사유에 해당하는 ‘중대 위반’이 있었는지 판단을 받아볼 것”이라고 했다. 김 관장 측은 해임이 확정될 경우, 행정소송 등도 검토하고 있는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Independence Hall held an emergency board meeting on this day at the request of six directors, including Democratic Party lawmakers Moon Jin-seok, Kim Yong-man, and Song Ok-ju, and deliberated and passed a dismissal recommendation against Director Kim. Director Kim, who is also the chairman of the board, attended the convened meeting. Passing the dismissal recommendation required a majority vote of 8 out of the 15 registered directors. On this day, 10 out of the 12 directors, excluding Director Kim, voted in favor of the dismissal recommendation. Among the 15 directors of the Independence Hall, three are ex-officio directors: the Director of the Independence Hall, the Chairman of the Korean Liberation Association, and the Director-General in charge at the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs. Four are recommended by the National Assembly Speaker, with three allocated to the Democratic Party and one to the People Power Party. The remaining eight are appointed by the Minister of Patriots and Veterans Affairs. (독립기념관은 더불어민주당 문진석·김용만·송옥주 의원 등 이사 6명의 요청에 따라 이날 긴급 이사회를 열고 김 관장에 대한 해임 건의안을 상정·의결했다. 이사회 의장인 김 관장도 이사회 소집에 응했다. 해임 건의안 의결에는 재적 이사 15명의 과반수인 8명의 찬성이 필요하다. 이날 김 관장을 제외한 이사 12명 중 10명이 해임 건의안에 찬성했다. 독립기념관 이사 15명 중 3명은 독립기념관장과 광복회장, 보훈부 담당 국장 등 당연직 이사다. 4명은 국회의장이 추천하며 그중 3명은 민주당 몫, 1명은 국민의힘 몫이다. 나머지 8명은 보훈부 장관이 임명한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that the board passed the dismissal recommendation based on the results of a special audit on Director Kim released by the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs on the 13th. The ministry stated that Director Kim committed misconduct in 14 areas, including improperly charging usage and parking fees to the ROTC 15th Class Alumni Association he belongs to and a specific church when lending Independence Hall space, and misappropriating operational funds. (이날 이사회는 보훈부가 지난 13일 공개한 김 관장에 대한 특정감사 결과를 토대로 해임 건의안을 의결한 것으로 전해졌다. 보훈부는 김 관장이 자신이 속한 ROTC 15기 동기회와 특정 교회에 사용료·주차료를 제대로 받지 않고 독립기념관 공간을 빌려주고, 업무추진비를 유용하는 등 14가지 분야의 비위를 저질렀다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Director Kim said, "I do not agree with the allegation of misappropriating operational funds for private use, but even if I were to accept the audit report's contents at face value, the 14 violations amount to a recovery of 552,000 won," and added, "Even combining the (discounted) facility usage fees and parking fees (for acquaintances), it's only about 200,000 won." He claims the ministry's audit was "unjustly conducted with the aim of dismissal." (김 관장은 “업무추진비 사적 유용이란 지적에 동의하지도 않지만, 설령 감사보고서 내용을 액면 그대로 인정한다고 해도 14건 위반에 환수액 55만2000원”이라며 “(지인에게 감면해 준) 장소 사용료와 주차료를 모두 합쳐도 20만원에 불과하다”고 말했다. 보훈부 감사가 “해임을 목적으로 부당하게 진행됐다”는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Historian Director Kim, around the time of his appointment, made statements such as, "National integration is only possible by treating both Syngman Rhee and Kim Gu as 'founding fathers'" and "There should not be those unfairly labeled as pro-Japanese collaborators." The Democratic Party and Korean Liberation Association Chairman Lee Jong-chan, among others, criticized Director Kim from the time of his appointment as 'pro-Japanese' and 'New Right' and boycotted the 2024 Liberation Day event. Some Democratic Party lawmakers even proposed a bill to amend the law so that the National Assembly also has the power to pass impeachment motions against the Independence Hall Director. (역사학자인 김 관장은 취임 전후 “이승만과 김구를 모두 ‘건국의 아버지’로 둬야 국민 통합이 가능하다” “억울하게 친일 인사로 매도되는 분들이 있어서도 안 되겠다”는 등의 주장을 했다. 민주당과 이종찬 광복회장 등은 취임 당시부터 김 관장을 ‘친일적’ ‘뉴라이트’라고 비판하며 2024년 광복절 행사에 불참했다. 일부 민주당 의원은 김 관장을 탄핵하기 위해 국회가 독립기념관장에 대해서도 탄핵소추 의결권을 갖도록 하는 법 개정안도 발의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration, Democratic Party lawmakers have obstructed Director Kim's commute to work and joined civic group protests demanding his resignation. When Director Kim said in his speech last year commemorating the 80th anniversary of liberation that "viewing liberation from a world historical perspective, it was a gift obtained through the victory of the Allied Forces," the Democratic Party called it "belittling the independence movement" and demanded his dismissal. The Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs, which began an audit of Director Kim last September, excluded him from last month's presidential briefing on the grounds that he was 'under audit.' During the briefing, President Lee, noticing Director Kim's absence, remarked, "Is he not coming out because he's upset about being under disciplinary review? He just didn't show up." (이재명 정부 출범 후 민주당 의원들은 김 관장의 출근을 저지하고 사퇴를 요구하는 시민단체 시위에 가세했다. 김 관장이 지난해 광복 80주년 기념사에서 “광복을 세계사적 관점에서 보면 연합국의 승리로 얻은 선물”이라고 말하자, 민주당은 “독립운동 비하”라며 파면을 요구했다. 지난해 9월 김 관장에 대한 감사에 착수한 보훈부는 지난달 대통령 업무보고에서도 ‘감사 중’이란 이유로 그를 배제했다. 이 대통령은 업무보고에서 김 관장을 찾다가 자리에 없자 “징계 중이니까 기분 나빠서 못 나오겠다는 건가요. 그냥 안 나왔군요”라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/GO3VDMIPJ5A7LBUH37WIWT5DP4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NJIRNYZIOVNCPJINQLS2YCMEBI.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 02:41:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's joke "Are you perhaps 'anti-Myeong'?" met with Jeong Cheong-rae's reply "We are all pro-Myeong and pro-Cheong (Blue House)" (李 대통령 “혹시 ‘반명’이십니까?” 농담에 정청래 “모두 친명이고 친청”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/BZAIQGFTPZDB5BCCWPJ3CDJZDM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee's joke "Are you perhaps 'anti-Myeong'?" met with Jeong Cheong-rae's reply "We are all pro-Myeong and pro-Cheong (Blue House)" (李 대통령 “혹시 ‘반명’이십니까?” 농담에 정청래 “모두 친명이고 친청”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4GGYZYGE2GENZXHA4TIMRQGY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung held a dinner with the newly reorganized leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea at the Blue House on the 19th. This came eight days after the new leadership took office. (이재명 대통령은 19일 재편된 더불어민주당 지도부와 청와대에서 만찬을 함께했다. 새 지도부 출범 8일 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dinner was attended by party leader Jeong Cheong-rae, along with newly elected floor leader Han Byung-do, Supreme Council members Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Seong-yoon, and Moon Jeong-bok, and all other Supreme Council members. Also present were Policy Committee Chairperson Han Jeong-ae, Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae, and Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun. New Senior Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo was also in attendance. (만찬에는 정청래 대표를 비롯해 지난 11일 새로 선출된 한병도 원내대표, 강득구·이성윤·문정복 최고위원 등과 최고위원 전원이 참석했다. 한정애 정책위의장, 조승래 사무총장, 박수현 수석대변인 등도 배석했다. 홍익표 신임 정무수석도 배석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun of the Democratic Party, President Lee jokingly asked party leader Jeong, who was seated next to him, "Are you perhaps 'anti-Myeong'?" In response, party leader Jeong replied, "We are all pro-Myeong and pro-Cheong (Blue House)," which reportedly made President Lee burst into hearty laughter. (박수현 민주당 수석대변인에 따르면, 이 대통령은 옆자리에 앉은 정 대표를 향해 “혹시 반명(反明)이십니까?”라고 농담을 던졌다. 이에 정 대표는 “우리는 모두 친명이고 친청(청와대)입니다”라고 응수해 이 대통령이 파안대소했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park relayed that President Lee said, "I requested to meet quickly on the occasion of the new leadership's formation," and added, "I intend to frequently hear about public sentiment and the state of the world, which I may not fully grasp, through all of you." (이 대통령은 “새 지도부 결성을 계기로 빨리 뵙자고 청했다”면서 “제가 미처 잘 모를 수도 있는 민심과 세상 이야기를 여러분을 통해 자주 듣고자 한다”고 말했다고 박 수석대변인은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor leader Han Byung-do stated, "Upon reviewing the legislative situation after taking office as floor leader, based on the 20-month mark since the opening of the National Assembly, the 22nd National Assembly's bill passage rate is 20.2%, the lowest compared to the 21st Assembly's 24.5% and the 20th Assembly's 29.2%. I feel sorry and concerned for the people." He continued, "Regarding the Lee Jae-myung administration's state affairs tasks, there are 184 bills that need to be swiftly promoted, of which only 37 have currently passed the National Assembly. We will strive to solidly support the Lee Jae-myung administration's state affairs tasks by mobilizing all capabilities and focusing on processing legislation." (한병도 원내대표는 “원내대표 취임 후 입법 상황을 점검해보니, 개원 후 20개월 지점을 기준으로 보면, 22대 국회 입법 통과율이 20.2%로 21대 국회 24.5%, 20대 국회 29.2%에 비해 최저를 기록하고 있어 국민께 죄송하고 걱정이 앞선다”며 “이재명 정부의 국정 과제와 관련하여 신속히 추진되어야 할 입법이 184건인데 그중 37건만이 현재 국회를 통과하고 있어 앞으로 모든 역량을 동원하여 입법 처리에 집중함으로써 이재명 정부의 국정 과제를 튼튼하게 뒷받침하도록 노력하겠다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party's public affairs bureau reported that the dinner menu consisted of octopus tatsuta salad, flounder and tuna sashimi, grilled sea bream with soy sauce, fried oysters, multigrain rice, and clear Daegu (cod) soup. Supreme Council member Park Ji-won reportedly proposed a toast with Gyeongju Beopju (traditional rice wine) accompanied by the slogan 'Party Member Sovereignty! People's Sovereignty!' (이날 만찬 메뉴는 문어 타다끼 샐러드, 광어와 참치회, 대방어 간장구이, 석화튀김, 잡곡밥과 대구 맑은 탕으로 구성됐다고 당 공보국은 전했다. 박지원 최고위원은 경주 법주를 곁들여 ‘당원주권!, 국민주권!’이라는 구호로 건배를 제의했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, within the Democratic Party, tensions have been brewing between the pro-Myeong faction and the pro-Cheong (Blue House) faction over proposed revisions to the party constitution and rules, such as a one-member-one-vote system, which could influence the dynamics of the party convention scheduled for this August. In political circles, there is talk that President Lee's joke, "Are you perhaps anti-Myeong?" might have been a pointed joke, conscious of the current internal party situation. (최근 민주당 내에선 올 8월 차기 전당대회 판도에 영향을 줄 수 있는 1인 1표제 등 당헌·당규 개정안 등을 놓고 친명계와 친청계 간 신경전을 벌이고 있다. 이에 정치권에선 이날 이 대통령의 “혹시 반명이냐”는 농담도 현 당내 상황을 의식한 ‘뼈 있는 농담’이 아니겠느냐는 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/BZAIQGFTPZDB5BCCWPJ3CDJZDM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4GGYZYGE2GENZXHA4TIMRQGY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 03:44:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italian Prime Minister, Accompanied by Her 'K-Pop Superfan' Daughter, Visits South Korea... Arrives Holding a BLACKPINK Lightstick (‘K팝 열성팬’ 딸과 방한한 이탈리아 총리... 블랙핑크 응원봉 들고 입국)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/ONQQYNUKQ5BLPOT5ULUNQ4DICY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Italian Prime Minister, Accompanied by Her 'K-Pop Superfan' Daughter, Visits South Korea... Arrives Holding a BLACKPINK Lightstick (‘K팝 열성팬’ 딸과 방한한 이탈리아 총리... 블랙핑크 응원봉 들고 입국)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FU7KA2F2DVIGRLEWKMLNGYYFTY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni, who is visiting South Korea for a summit with President Yoon Suk Yeol, drew attention by bringing along her 10-year-old daughter Ginevra, known as a 'K-pop superfan'. Although Ginevra did not appear in the official schedule, she was spotted disembarking from the official aircraft holding a BLACKPINK lightstick. (이재명 대통령과의 정상회담을 위해 한국을 방문 중인 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 ‘K팝 열성팬’으로 알려진 딸 지네브라(10)를 동행해 눈길을 끌었다. 지네브라는 공식 일정엔 등장하지 않았으나, 블랙핑크의 응원봉을 손에 든 채 전용기에서 내린 모습이 포착됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, Prime Minister Meloni's official YouTube account released footage from the previous day showing her and her daughter disembarking from the official aircraft at Seoul Airport and receiving an honor guard review from the Korean side. In Ginevra's hand was a BLACKPINK lightstick with a black handle and pink hammer-shaped ends on both sides. Lightsticks are 'goods' used by K-pop fans at concerts or events, symbolizing K-pop fandom culture. (18일 멜로니 총리의 공식 유튜브 계정엔 전날 서울공항에 도착한 멜로니 총리가 딸과 함께 전용기에서 내려 우리 측 의장대 사열을 받는 모습이 공개됐다. 지네브라의 손에는 검은색 손잡이에 분홍색 망치 모양이 양옆으로 달린 블랙핑크 응원봉이 들려있었다. 응원봉은 K팝 팬들이 콘서트나 행사장에서 사용하는 ‘굿즈’로, K팝 팬클럽 문화를 상징한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Prime Minister Meloni first met President Yoon in New York last September, she introduced her daughter as "the most enthusiastic K-pop fan in the world." She also became a topic of discussion last August when she attended a BLACKPINK concert in Milan, Italy, with her daughter. (멜로니 총리는 작년 9월 뉴욕에서 이 대통령을 처음 만나 자신의 딸이 “전세계에서 가장 열광적인 K팝 팬”이라고 소개했었다. 그는 작년 8월엔 이탈리아 밀라노에서 열린 블랙핑크 콘서트를 딸과 함께 관람해 화제가 되기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Yoon and Prime Minister Meloni also talked extensively about K-pop during their summit on the 19th. When President Yoon mentioned during the expanded meeting that "Recently, the popularity of K-culture has increased in Italy as well, leading to more Italian citizens visiting Korea," Prime Minister Meloni burst into laughter, seemingly reminded of her daughter. (이 대통령과 멜로니 총리는 19일 정상회담에서도 K팝에 대한 대화를 한참 나눴다. 이 대통령이 확대 회담에서 “최근에는 이탈리아에서도 K컬처의 인기가 높아져서 한국을 찾는 이탈리아 국민들이 늘어나고 있다”고 말하자, 멜로니 총리는 딸이 생각난 듯 웃음을 크게 터트렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the official luncheon, President Yoon said, "Hearing that your daughter is an ardent fan of K-pop made me realize anew the power of high-quality culture." Prime Minister Meloni responded, "Behind the success of K-culture, there were very smart choices and strategies," adding, "It is a strategy that masterfully blends the extremely global with the extremely national."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령은 공식 오찬에서 “따님이 K-팝에 열렬한 팬이라는 말씀을 듣고 새삼스럽게 높은 문화의 힘을 실감했다”고 했고, 멜로니 총리는 “K컬처의 성공 뒤에는 굉장히 똑똑한 선택과 전략이 있었다”며 “그것은 바로 지극히 세계적인 것과 지극히 국가적인 것을 오묘하게 섞은 전략”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/ONQQYNUKQ5BLPOT5ULUNQ4DICY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FU7KA2F2DVIGRLEWKMLNGYYFTY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 21:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hearing Fails to Take Place, Lee Hye-hoon Leaves National Assembly Late at Night... Dismisses Possibility of Withdrawal (청문회 불발, 밤 늦게 국회 떠난 이혜훈... 사퇴 가능성 일축)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/P5LYEHPBHRAL3GNOORR4L73VNY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Hearing Fails to Take Place, Lee Hye-hoon Leaves National Assembly Late at Night... Dismisses Possibility of Withdrawal (청문회 불발, 밤 늦게 국회 떠난 이혜훈... 사퇴 가능성 일축)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YVEU37MS6NNX3MXWLIZXYFMEDA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid the failure of the National Assembly's confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, scheduled for the 19th, due to issues such as inadequate submission of hearing materials, the nominee waited within the National Assembly grounds from the morning and left late at night. (19일로 예정됐던 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사 청문회가 인사 청문 자료 부실 제출 등 문제로 불발된 가운데, 이 후보자는 이날 아침부터 국회 경내에서 대기하다가 밤 늦게 국회를 떠났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee dismissed the possibility of voluntarily withdrawing until that evening. She then repeatedly urged for the hearing to be held, stating, "Wouldn't the public want to see the truth and falsehood of all these suspicions clarified?" Controversies raised about the nominee include allegations of her staff's abuse of power and verbal abuse during her time as a lawmaker, her eldest son's alleged fraudulent lottery win for a Gangnam apartment through 'feigned unmarried status', and suspicions of her husband's land speculation in Incheon's Yeongjongdo. (이 후보자는 이날 밤까지 자진 사퇴 가능성을 일축했다. 이어 “국민들이 이 모든 의혹의 시시비비를 가리고 싶어 하지 않겠는가”라며 청문회 개최를 거듭 촉구했다. 이 후보자에 대해선 국회의원 시절 보좌진 갑질·폭언, 장남의 ‘위장 미혼’을 통한 강남 아파트 부정 당첨 논란, 남편의 인천 영종도 땅 투기 의혹 등이 제기돼 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around 9:20 PM, the nominee met with reporters at the National Assembly main building and said, "I was waiting for an opportunity at a hearing to explain everything in detail to the public. However, since the (hearing) committee members have all left work, it seems there would be no effect in waiting any longer, so I am leaving." She then immediately got into a vehicle and departed the National Assembly. (이 후보자는 이날 오후 9시 20분쯤 국회 본관에서 기자들과 만나 “국민 앞에 소상히 설명드릴 수 있는 청문회 기회를 기다리고 있었다. 그런데 (청문)위원들이 다 퇴근해서 더 이상 기다려도 효과가 없을 것 같아서 퇴청한다”며 이같이 말했다. 이어 이 후보자는 곧장 차량을 타고 국회를 떠났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked if she would visit the National Assembly again on the 20th to await the hearing, the nominee replied, "I will watch for an agreement between the floor leaders (of the ruling and opposition parties)." Regarding the submission of additional materials, she said, "(Opposition lawmakers) requested many materials that (I) cannot submit, and they are asking for materials already submitted again, so I am providing the already submitted materials once more." (이 후보자는 오는 20일에도 국회를 찾아 청문회 개최를 기다릴 것이냐는 질문에 “(여야) 간사 간의 합의를 지켜보겠다”고 답했다. 그러면서 이 후보자는 추가 자료 제출 여부에 대해 “(야당 의원들이 제가) 낼 수 없는 자료들을 많이 요청했고, 이미 다 낸 자료를 또 달라고 해서 이미 낸 자료를 또 드리고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee held a plenary meeting at 10 AM to discuss whether to hold the confirmation hearing for the nominee, but could not even place the hearing agenda on the table and adjourned after an hour and a half. The People Power Party and the Reform Party stated that the hearing could not proceed due to the nominee's inadequate material submission. In contrast, the Democratic Party reiterated its position that "the public's judgment must be received." (앞서 국회 재정경제기획위원회는 이날 오전 10시 이 후보자 인사 청문회 개최 여부를 논의하기 위해 전체회의를 열었지만 인사청문 안건을 상정도 못하고 1시간 30분 만에 정회했다. 국민의힘과 개혁신당은 이 후보자의 자료 제출이 부실하다며 청문회를 진행할 수 없다고 했다. 반면 민주당은 “국민 판단은 받아야 한다”는 입장을 되풀이했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, the nominee waited within the National Assembly grounds that day, unable to even enter the meeting room, and returned home. She also had lunch inside the National Assembly with a packed meal. Around 5:50 PM, the nominee met with reporters and said, "I believe it is the National Assembly's role to create an opportunity for verification before the public," adding, "But the National Assembly should reconsider whether it is abandoning and blocking that role itself." (이에 따라 이 후보자는 이날 국회 경내에서 대기하다가 회의장에 들어가지도 못하고 귀가한 것이다. 이날 점심 식사도 국회 안에서 도시락으로 해결했다. 이 후보자는 이날 오후 5시 50분쯤 기자들과 만나 “국민 앞에서 검증하는 기회를 만드는 게 국회 역할이라고 생각한다”며 “그런데 그 역할을 스스로 포기하고 차단하는 건 아닌지 국회가 다시 생각해봐야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/P5LYEHPBHRAL3GNOORR4L73VNY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YVEU37MS6NNX3MXWLIZXYFMEDA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:37:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi Voluntarily Leaves Party One Week After Expulsion Decision (김병기, 제명 결정 일주일만에 자진 탈당)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/ANRQ7EG265D2ZOSJIXDQDBZFHE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Q7Y25E7CN5CSBDX3PBVQBEVONU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Kim Byeong-gi, who was issued an expulsion penalty by the Democratic Party of Korea's Ethics Tribunal over various allegations including nomination-related donations and staff abuse, voluntarily left the Democratic Party on the 19th. He withdrew his previous stance of contesting the decision through a retrial within a week. (공천 헌금, 보좌관 갑질 등 각종 의혹으로 더불어민주당 윤리심판원이 제명 처분을 내린 김병기 의원이 19일 민주당을 자진 탈당했다. 재심으로 다투겠다는 기존 입장은 일주일 만에 철회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press conference held at the National Assembly that day, Lawmaker Kim stated, "I thought that if my actions cause disagreements within the party or place even the slightest burden on my colleagues, I should fully bear that responsibility myself," and announced he would not apply for a retrial. Previously, on the 12th, the Democratic Party's Ethics Tribunal decided on the highest-level penalty of expulsion for Lawmaker Kim, to which he responded by expressing his intent to request a retrial, saying, "The allegations cannot become facts." (김 의원은 이날 국회에서 기자회견을 열고 “저로 인해 당 안에 이견이 생기고 동료들에게 조금이라도 마음에 짐이 된다면 그 부담만큼은 제가 온전히 짊어지고 가야 한다고 생각했다”면서 재심을 신청하지 않겠다고 밝혔다. 앞서 지난 12일 민주당 윤리심판원은 김 의원에 대해 최고 수위 징계인 제명을 결정했고, 김 의원은 “의혹이 사실이 될 수는 없다”면서 재심 청구 의사를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the press conference, Lawmaker Kim said, "I have stated that even if I were to be expelled, I would not choose to leave the party on my own," adding, "If an expulsion penalty is to be imposed, I asked for it to be finalized by a decision of the Supreme Council (instead of a general meeting of lawmakers)." This was to avoid burdening fellow lawmakers by going through a general meeting. (김 의원은 이날 회견에서 “저는 제명당하더라도 스스로 당을 떠나는 선택은 하지 않겠다고 말해왔다”면서 “제명 처분을 한다면 (의원총회 대신) 최고위원회의 결정으로 종결해달라”고 했다. 의원총회를 거치면서 동료 의원들에게 부담을 지우지 않고 싶다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, approximately three hours after the press conference, Lawmaker Kim changed his stance and submitted his resignation from the party. Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae explained, "According to the Political Parties Act, expelling a sitting lawmaker requires the consent of a majority of affiliated lawmakers, making a general meeting mandatory," and added, "This was explained to Lawmaker Kim, which is why he resigned from the party." (그러나 김 의원은 기자회견 3시간여 만에 입장을 바꾸고 탈당계를 제출했다. 조승래 사무총장은 “정당법상 현역 의원을 제명할 때는 소속 의원 과반의 동의가 필요해 의원총회를 반드시 열어야 한다”면서 “이를 김 의원에게 설명했고 그래서 탈당한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After submitting his resignation, Lawmaker Kim posted a message in a group Telegram chatroom for Democratic Party lawmakers, stating, "I will return to greet you all after fully clearing all allegations." Political circles commented, "Amid ongoing investigations and continuous allegations, Lawmaker Kim likely saw no practical benefit in applying for a retrial." (탈당계를 낸 이후 김 의원은 민주당 의원들이 모인 단체 텔레그램방에 “모든 의혹을 온전히 씻어낸 후 다시 돌아와 인사드리겠다”는 글을 올렸다. 정치권에선 “연일 수사와 의혹 제기가 이어지는 상황에서 김 의원도 재심 신청의 실익이 없다고 봤을 것”이란 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party's Ethics Tribunal took post-facto expulsion measures against Lawmaker Kim that day. The decision document specifies the reasons for the penalty, which will be reflected in any future review for party reinstatement. (민주당 윤리심판원은 이날 김 의원에 대해 사후 제명 조치를 했다. 결정문에 징계 사유를 명시해 향후 복당 심사에 반영하겠다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/ANRQ7EG265D2ZOSJIXDQDBZFHE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Q7Y25E7CN5CSBDX3PBVQBEVONU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italian PM Meloni in Korea Takes a Selfie with President Lee's Gifted 'Z Flip' (한국 온 伊 멜로니 총리, 李대통령이 선물한 ‘Z플립’으로 셀카 )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/HH634D3E6RH4JM5HUCCAUMEEIA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6674ELDWJ5FUNNFABI6BU33QLM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung and Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni took a selfie together using a Samsung mobile phone during a luncheon following their summit meeting at the Blue House on the 19th. The Blue House stated, "President Lee surprised Prime Minister Meloni with a 'Galaxy Z Flip 7' in her favorite color, pink." During the summit, the two leaders agreed to cooperate in advanced fields such as artificial intelligence (AI), space, defense, and semiconductors, and to share information related to supply chains, including rare earth elements. This visit marks the first time an Italian Prime Minister has visited Korea for bilateral talks in 19 years, since 2007. (이재명 대통령과 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 19일 청와대에서 정상회담을 마친 뒤 이어진 오찬에서 삼성 휴대전화로 함께 ‘셀카’를 찍고 있다. 청와대는 “이 대통령이 멜로니 총리가 가장 좋아하는 분홍색의 ‘갤럭시 Z플립 7’을 깜짝 선물했다”고 했다. 양 정상은 정상회담에서 인공지능(AI), 우주, 방산, 반도체 등 첨단 분야 협력과 희토류 등 공급망 관련 정보 공유에 합의했다. 이탈리아 총리가 양자 회담차 방한한 것은 2007년 이후 19년 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/HH634D3E6RH4JM5HUCCAUMEEIA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6674ELDWJ5FUNNFABI6BU33QLM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon's Apology Falls Flat... Hardliners in People Power Party Unite (한동훈 사과도 안 먹혀… 뭉치는 국힘 강성파)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/ESZ3G3Q6ZVBLJJJAASOYVSOHNU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GWJJDUEQGZCHXB7BS4PMVNHYE4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party (PPP), continued his hunger strike for the fifth day on the 19th, demanding the acceptance of a special prosecution investigation (into alleged bribery involving the Unification Church and Democratic Party nominations). While the Democratic Party is refusing the special probe, Jang's side believes the hunger strike is uniting the party internally. An encouraging atmosphere is also being felt as poll results showing a rise in the party's approval rating have emerged. Former anti-impeachment figures (who opposed the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol) who had clashed with former leader Han Dong-hoon dismissed his apology that day regarding the 'party member bulletin board' controversy, calling it "insincere." (국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 19일 쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검) 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 투쟁을 이어갔다. 더불어민주당이 특검을 거부하고 있지만, 단식으로 당 내부가 결집하고 있다는 게 장 대표 측 생각이다. 당 지지율이 올랐다는 여론조사 결과가 나오자 고무된 분위기도 감지된다. 한동훈 전 대표와 대립했던 옛 반탄파(윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵 반대) 인사들은 이날 ‘당원 게시판’ 논란에 대한 한 전 대표의 사과를 놓고 “진정성이 없다”고 평가절하했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP held a Supreme Council meeting that morning in front of the hunger strike site set up in the Central Hall of the National Assembly's main building. Leader Jang stated, "I am gradually reaching my limit," and "I am appealing to the public with my life on the line." In the afternoon, he posted a handwritten note on Facebook referencing a rose that bloomed with a broken stem, writing, "Let's grow stronger the more we are broken. Let a flower bloom on our face." (국민의힘은 이날 오전 국회 본청 중앙홀에 마련된 장 대표 단식장 앞에서 최고위원 회의를 열었다. 장 대표는 “점차 한계가 오고 있다”며 “목숨 걸고 국민께 호소드리고 있다”고 했다. 오후엔 페이스북에 줄기가 꺾인 채 꽃을 피운 장미를 언급하며 “꺾을수록 더 강해지자. 얼굴에 꽃을 피우자”는 손글씨를 올렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won began a solidarity hunger strike with Leader Jang that day. Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party who is visiting Latin America, plans to visit Leader Jang's hunger strike site at the National Assembly immediately upon his early morning return on the 21st, having moved his schedule up by two days. However, it is said Leader Lee does not currently plan to join the solidarity hunger strike. (김재원 최고위원은 이날 장 대표와 동조 단식을 시작했다. 중남미를 방문 중인 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 당초 일정을 이틀 앞당겨 21일 새벽 귀국하는 대로 국회에 마련된 장 대표 단식장을 찾을 예정이다. 다만, 이 대표가 동조 단식을 할 계획은 아직 없다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A PPP leadership official said, "Leader Jang's hunger strike is creating an atmosphere of unity for the party and its supporters." The PPP also issued a press release that day stating, "As of the 19th, the number of party members paying dues has been confirmed at approximately 1,093,000," and "Exceeding 1 million is a first in the party's history, and the number of responsible party members is also expected to soon surpass 1 million." According to the PPP, the number of responsible party members (those who have paid dues for over 3 months and have voting rights within the party) was 750,000 just before the national convention in August last year. (국민의힘 지도부 관계자는 “장 대표의 단식이 당과 지지층을 단결시키는 분위기”라고 했다. 국민의힘은 이날 “당비를 납부하는 당원이 19일 기준 109만3000여 명으로 확인됐다”며 “100만명이 넘은 것은 당 역사상 처음으로 책임당원도 곧 100만을 돌파할 것”이라는 보도자료도 냈다. 국민의힘에 따르면 당내 투표권을 가진 책임당원(3개월 이상 당비 납부)은 작년 8월 전당대회 직전 75만명이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang's side also circulated the results of a public opinion poll released that day. In a regular poll conducted via wireless automated response (ARS) on the 15th and 16th and released that day by pollster Realmeter, the PPP's approval rating was 37%, up from the previous week (33.5%). Notably, in the Daegu/North Gyeongsang region, the approval rating rose to 60.6%, an increase of over 15 percentage points from the previous week (45.3%) (for details, refer to the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission website). (장 대표 측은 이날 발표된 여론조사 결과를 돌려보기도 했다. 여론조사 업체 리얼미터가 지난 15~16일 무선 자동 응답(ARS) 방식으로 실시해 이날 발표한 정기 여론 조사에서 국민의힘 지지율은 37%로, 전주(33.5%)보다 상승했다. 특히 대구·경북에서 지지율은 60.6%로 전주(45.3%)보다 15%포인트 이상 올랐다(자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위 홈페이지 참조).)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Figures close to Leader Jang suggested, "Wouldn't Leader Jang's hunger strike and the party ethics committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon (on the 14th) have had an impact?" Inside and outside the party, there were many calls for former leader Han to apologize and for Leader Jang to rescind the expulsion decision. Leader Jang has postponed the Supreme Council's vote on the ethics committee's expulsion decision until the 23rd. Although former leader Han apologized the previous day for the party member bulletin board incident, Supreme Council member Jo Gwang-han, appointed by Leader Jang, said that day it was "insincere wordplay" and "crocodile tears." Some within the PPP observe that, "judging by the current mood among Supreme Council members, they will likely vote to expel former leader Han." (장 대표 측 인사들은 “장 대표 단식과 당 윤리위의 한동훈 전 대표 제명(14일) 결정이 영향을 미치지 않았겠느냐”고 했다. 당 안팎에선 한 전 대표가 사과하고, 장 대표는 제명 결정을 취소하라는 주문이 많았다. 장 대표는 윤리위의 제명 결정에 대한 최고위원회 의결을 오는 23일까지 미룬 상태다. 한 전 대표는 전날 당원 게시판 사건에 대해 사과했지만, 장 대표가 임명한 조광한 최고위원은 이날 “진정성 없는 말장난”이라며 “악어의 눈물”이라고 했다. 국민의힘 일각에서는 “현재 최고위원들 분위기로 볼 때, 한 전 대표 제명을 의결할 것”이라는 관측이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP has decided to suspend National Assembly standing committee schedules until Leader Jang's hunger strike ends. However, within the party, concerns are also being raised that there is no visible exit strategy after the hunger strike. At a meeting of floor leaders from both ruling and opposition parties that day, the Democratic Party also did not accept the demand for a special probe. A senior party lawmaker said, "While Leader Jang's hunger strike may have the effect of rallying hardcore supporters," they questioned "whether there is a reform plan prepared that would enable expanding outreach after the hunger strike." It is reported that some senior PPP lawmakers advised Leader Jang to stop the hunger strike, but he did not respond.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (국민의힘은 장 대표의 단식 투쟁이 종료될 때까지 국회 상임위원회 일정을 중단하기로 했다. 하지만 당내에선 장 대표의 단식 이후 출구 전략이 안 보인다는 우려도 나온다. 이날 여야 원내대표 회동에서도 민주당은 쌍특검 요구를 받아들이지 않았다. 한 중진 의원은 “장 대표의 단식이 강성 지지층을 결집시키는 효과는 있을 것”이라면서도 “단식 이후 외연 확장을 가능하게 하는 개혁 플랜(계획)이 마련돼 있는지는 의문”이라고 했다. 국민의힘 일부 중진 의원이 장 대표에게 단식 중단을 건의했지만 장 대표는 답을 하지 않은 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/ESZ3G3Q6ZVBLJJJAASOYVSOHNU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GWJJDUEQGZCHXB7BS4PMVNHYE4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee to Jeong Cheong-rae: "Are You Perhaps Anti-Myeong?" Jeong: "We Are All Pro-Myeong and Pro-Blue House" (李대통령, 정청래에 “혹시 반명이십니까” 鄭 “친명·친청와대”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/NZ6XDIVZGBAUXDDSOL6P2MJJO4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung invited the newly reorganized leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea to the Blue House for a dinner on the 19th. At this meeting, President Lee reportedly asked Party Leader Jeong Cheong-rae, "Are you perhaps anti-Myeong (anti-Lee Jae-myung)?" to which Leader Jeong replied, "We are all pro-Myeong (pro-Lee Jae-myung) and pro-Cheong (pro-Blue House)." This exchange of pointed jokes comes amid the formation of a 'pro-Myeong vs. pro-Cheong (pro-Jeong Cheong-rae)' confrontation structure within the Democratic Party following recent events like the by-election for Supreme Council members. (이재명 대통령은 19일 새로 재편된 더불어민주당 지도부를 청와대로 초청해 만찬을 함께했다. 이 자리에서 이 대통령은 정청래 대표에게 “혹시 반명(반이재명)이십니까”라고 물었고, 정 대표는 “우리는 모두 친명(친이재명)이고 친청(친청와대)입니다”라고 답했다고 한다. 최근 최고위원 보궐선거 등을 계기로 민주당 내에서 ‘친명 대 친청(친정청래)’ 대결 구도가 형성된 가운데 두 사람이 뼈 있는 농담을 주고받은 것이란 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-hyun, the Democratic Party's chief spokesperson, relayed that President Lee told attendees, "I wanted to meet the Democratic Party leadership, now complete with the election of Supreme Council members," adding, "I had hoped to meet you all frequently on various occasions even under normal circumstances, and I specifically requested this meeting quickly to mark the formation of the new leadership." (이날 이 대통령은 참석자들에게 “최고위원 선출로 완전체가 된 민주당 지도부를 뵙고 싶었다”며 “평소에도 여러 계기에 자주 뵙기를 소망했고, 특히 이번에는 새 지도부 결성을 계기로 빨리 뵙자고 청했다”고 말했다고 박수현 민주당 수석대변인이 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, within the Democratic Party, former Floor Leader Kim Byeong-gi resigned due to various allegations, and three Supreme Council members vacated their positions to run in the June local elections, leading to a by-election on the 11th. Attendees at the dinner included newly appointed Floor Leader Han Byung-do and Supreme Council members Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Seong-yun, and Moon Jeong-bok. (앞서 민주당에서는 김병기 전 원내대표가 각종 의혹으로 사퇴하고, 최고위원 3명이 6월 지방선거 출마를 위해 자리를 내놓으면서 지난 11일 보궐선거가 있었다. 이날 자리에는 신임 한병도 원내대표, 강득구·이성윤·문정복 최고위원 등이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party Leader Jeong Cheong-rae said, "During Lee Jae-myung's tenure as (Democratic Party) leader, we suffered under the oppression of the Yoon Suk-yeol dictatorship and crossed life-and-death lines together," adding, "Thinking about how he never neglected party affairs by even an inch while enduring those difficult investigations and trials makes me feel I am far too lacking as a leader." Attendees reportedly toasted with the slogan "party member sovereignty, people's sovereignty." (정청래 대표는 “이재명 (민주당) 대표 시절 윤석열 독재의 탄압으로 고통을 받으면서 함께 사선을 넘었다”며 “그 힘든 수사와 재판을 받으면서도 대표로서 당무에 한 치도 소홀함이 없었던 것을 생각하면 저는 대표로서 부족함이 너무 많다는 생각을 하게 된다”고 했다. 참석자들은 “당원 주권, 국민 주권” 구호로 건배했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dinner reportedly discussed issues such as whether to maintain the supplementary investigation authority of the Public Prosecution Service. Hardliners within the Democratic Party have been opposing the government's recently proposed bills to establish the Public Prosecution Service and the Serious Crimes Investigation Agency. The Democratic Party is holding a related public hearing on the 20th. (이날 만찬에서는 공소청의 보완 수사권 존치 여부 등이 논의됐다고 한다. 민주당 강경파들은 최근 정부가 내놓은 공소청과 중수청(중대범죄수사청) 설치 법안에 반발하고 있다. 민주당은 20일 관련 공청회를 연다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was reportedly little discussion regarding Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Finance, whose confirmation hearing was canceled that day. One attendee said, "Since the new leadership was just elected not long ago, there was a cautious atmosphere regarding sensitive pending issues." (이날 인사청문회가 무산된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자와 관련한 얘기는 별로 오가지 않았다고 한다. 한 참석자는 “아직 신임 지도부가 선출된 지 얼마 되지 않았기 때문에 민감한 현안에 대해서는 조심하는 분위기가 있었다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the People Power Party criticized the Blue House dinner that evening, saying, "In the face of People Power Party Leader Jang Dong-hyeok's life-threatening hunger strike, is President Lee Jae-myung planning a 'mukbang party' with the ruling party?" President Lee had invited the ruling and opposition party leaderships to the Blue House for a luncheon meeting on the 16th, which the People Power Party did not attend at that time. (한편 국민의힘은 이날 저녁 청와대 만찬에 대해 “죽음을 건 장동혁 (국민의힘) 대표의 단식 앞에서, 이재명 대통령은 여당과 ‘먹방 파티’나 계획하고 있는 거냐”고 비판했다. 이 대통령은 지난 16일 여야 지도부를 청와대로 초청해 오찬 간담회를 가졌는데 당시 국민의힘은 불참했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/NZ6XDIVZGBAUXDDSOL6P2MJJO4/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pro-Moon faction clashes with Jeong Cheong-rae... "One-member-one-vote system is a self-serving revision" (정청래 들이받은 친명… “1인 1표제, 자신 위한 셀프 개정”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/O2WSP7MQUJHNVKWL2G2RVCERFI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/4VZ7BE3BVBEBXATQQEOKMLUO2Y.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The leadership of the Democratic Party of Korea publicly clashed during a meeting on the 19th over the 'one-member-one-vote system for delegates and rights-holding party members' led by party leader Jeong Cheong-rae. A pro-Moon faction Supreme Council member confronted Leader Jeong, asking, "Isn't the one-member-one-vote system a self-serving revision? If not, change it after the August party leadership election." The pro-Moon faction views the renewed push for the one-member-one-vote system, which was previously rejected once, as a move for Leader Jeong's re-election as party leader. Within the party, there are comments that a power struggle between the pro-Moon and pro-Jeong factions over the next party leadership has begun. (더불어민주당 지도부가 정청래 대표가 주도하는 ‘대의원·권리당원 1인 1표제’를 놓고 19일 회의에서 공개 충돌했다. 친명 최고위원이 정 대표 앞에서 “1인 1표는 셀프 개정 아니냐. 그게 아니라면 8월 당대표 선거 이후에 바꾸라”고 한 것이다. 친명계는 한 차례 부결됐던 1인 1표제 재추진을 두고 정 대표의 당대표 연임을 위한 작업이라고 보고 있다. 여권에선 차기 당권을 둘러싼 명·청 싸움이 벌어지는 것이란 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pro-Moon faction Supreme Council member Hwang Myung-sun said at the party meeting that day, "If the parties who revised the election rules are immediately elected under those rules, it is difficult to avoid criticism that it's a self-serving revision," adding, "We can amend the party constitution and rules to introduce the one-member-one-vote system but apply it after the next national convention." This means Leader Jeong should not challenge for re-election in the upcoming August party leadership election, which would be held after the introduction of the one-member-one-vote system. Supreme Council member Hwang also said, "Like the wisdom of ancient scholars who did not adjust their hat strings under a plum tree, a mechanism to preemptively block unnecessary misunderstandings is absolutely necessary." (친명계 황명선 최고위원은 이날 당 회의에서 “선거 룰을 개정한 당사자들이 곧바로 그 규칙에 따라 선출된다면 셀프 개정이라는 비판을 피하기 어렵다”며 “1인 1표제를 도입하되 적용 시점은 다음 전당대회 이후로 하는 것으로 당헌당규를 개정하면 된다”고 했다. 정 대표가 1인 1표제를 도입한 뒤 열리는 오는 8월 당대표 선거에서 연임에 도전해선 안 된다는 것이다. 황 최고위원은 “오얏나무 아래에서 갓끈을 고쳐 매지 않았던 옛 선비의 지혜처럼 불필요한 오해를 사전에 차단하는 장치가 반드시 필요하다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pro-Moon faction also took issue with the statement made the previous day by Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun, who said, "Leader Jeong has never even mentioned the word 're-election.' Such remarks invite misunderstanding." Spokesperson Park is a leadership figure appointed by Leader Jeong. Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo said at the meeting, "It seems questions are being raised about the intention and fairness of implementing the one-member-one-vote system," adding, "However, for some to talk about 'such remarks' and 'gagging' in response to this discussion is abandoning the spirit of democracy." Supreme Council member Kang Deuk-gu also told reporters regarding Chief Spokesperson Park's remarks, "It's completely putting a gag in our mouths." Chief Spokesperson Park expressed his intention to apologize. However, Supreme Council member Kang is known to be holding a press conference on the 20th to criticize Leader Jeong's one-member-one-vote system. (친명계는 박수현 수석대변인이 전날 “정 대표는 연임의 이응(ㅇ)자도 말한 적이 없다. 이런 오해 살 발언은 해당 행위”라고 한 발언도 문제 삼았다. 박 대변인은 정 대표가 임명한 지도부 인사다. 이언주 최고위원은 회의에서 “1인 1표제 시행 의도, 공정성에 대한 의문이 제기되는 것 같다”면서 “그런데 이런 토론에 대해 일각에서 ‘해당 행위’ 운운하며 ‘입 틀막’하는 것은 민주주의 정신을 져버리는 것”이라고 했다. 강득구 최고위원도 기자들과 만나 박 수석대변인 말에 대해 “완전히 재갈을 물리는 것”이라고 했다. 박 수석대변인은 사과의 뜻을 밝혔다. 하지만 강 최고위원은 20일 기자회견을 열어 정 대표의 1인 1표를 비판할 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The pro-Moon faction agrees with the purpose of the one-member-one-vote system but argues that Leader Jeong is using it for his re-election as party leader. In the August party leadership election last year, Leader Jeong lost to rival candidate Rep. Park Chan-dae in the delegate vote but won overwhelmingly in the rights-holding member vote, being elected as party leader. At that time, one delegate vote was equivalent to 17 rights-holding member votes. One pro-Moon lawmaker said, "The one-member-one-vote system aims to abolish delegate votes, which are organizational votes for lawmakers, and elect the party leader through a popularity vote among party members," adding, "If this happens, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who is considered a potential party leadership candidate, will inevitably feel burdened about running." Particularly within the pro-Moon faction, there is a view that there is an intention behind trying to quickly pass the one-member-one-vote system, which was rejected once last month. Last year's one-member-one-vote proposal received many votes in favor during the Central Committee vote but was rejected due to a lack of quorum. A two-term Democratic Party lawmaker said, "It seems Leader Jeong has gained confidence as the leadership majority was filled with the pro-Jeong faction following the recent Supreme Council by-election." (친명계는 1인 1표의 취지에는 동의하지만, 정 대표가 당대표 연임을 위해 이를 이용하고 있다고 주장하고 있다. 정 대표는 작년 8월 당대표 선거에서 경쟁 후보인 박찬대 의원에게 대의원 투표에선 졌지만 권리당원 투표에서 크게 이기며 당대표로 선출됐다. 당시 대의원 1표는 권리당원 17표와 같았다. 한 친명 의원은 “1인 1표는 국회의원 조직표인 대의원 표를 없애고 당원 인기 투표로 당대표를 뽑자는 것”이라며 “이렇게 되면 당대표 후보로 꼽히는 김민석 국무총리도 출마에 부담을 느낄 수밖에 없다”고 했다. 특히 친명계 내부에선 지난달 한 차례 부결됐던 1인 1표제를 빠르게 통과시키려는 것도 의도가 있다고 보고 있다. 작년 1인 1표는 중앙위 투표에서 찬성이 많이 나왔지만 정족수 미달로 부결됐었다. 민주당 재선 의원은 “최근 최고위원 보궐선거로 지도부 과반이 친청계로 채워지면서 정 대표가 자신감을 얻은 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the pro-Jeong faction states that the one-member-one-vote system is the first step toward party member sovereignty and that it is not for Leader Jeong's re-election as party leader. In fact, Leader Jeong reportedly said at a recent closed-door Supreme Council meeting in response to some Supreme Council members' opposition, "The one-member-one-vote system is something President Lee also pursued when he was party leader," and "How do you know if I will run for party leader again?" However, Leader Jeong said nothing regarding the one-member-one-vote system that day. Instead, pro-Jeong faction lawmakers publicly refuted the claims. Supreme Council member Lee Sung-yoon said that day, "For moving toward an era of party member sovereignty, the one-member-one-vote system is a right that is too natural under the constitution and party constitution." Supreme Council member Moon Jeong-bok also said, "In the Supreme Council by-election, 4-5 candidates fully agreed on the one-member-one-vote system for party members," adding, "To say it should be applied from the next leadership creates another frame and problem." (하지만 친청계는 1인 1표는 당원 주권주의를 위한 첫 단계라고 하고 있다. 정 대표의 당대표 연임용도 아니라고 했다. 실제 정 대표는 최근 비공개 최고위에서 일부 최고위원 반발에 “1인 1표제는 이 대통령도 당대표 때 추진했던 것”이라면서 “내가 또 당대표 선거에 나올지 어떻게 아느냐”고 말한 것으로 알려졌다. 다만 정 대표는 이날 1인 1표와 관련해 아무 말도 하지 않았다. 대신 친청계 의원들이 공개 반박에 나섰다. 이성윤 최고위원은 이날 “당원 주권 시대를 향해 나아가기 위해 1인 1표제는 헌법상·당헌상 너무나 당연한 권리”라고 했다. 문정복 최고위원도 “최고위원 보궐선거에서 4~5명의 후보들은 전적으로 당원 1인 1표제에 대해서 찬성을 했다”면서 “차기 지도부부터 이것을 적용해야 한다는 것은 또 다른 프레임과 문제를 만드는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, the Democratic Party held a Party Affairs Committee meeting after the Supreme Council meeting that day and decided to submit the party constitution amendment for the one-member-one-vote system as an agenda item for the Central Committee. Chief Spokesperson Park met with reporters after the meeting and stated, "Out of 79 Party Affairs Committee members, 61 participated in the vote, including 16 on-site attendees, and among them, 2 cast opposing votes in writing." The amendment will be finalized through a Central Committee vote on the 2nd and 3rd of next month after an opinion survey of rights-holding party members from the 22nd to the 24th. A Democratic Party official said, "If the one-member-one-vote system is rejected again this time following last month, it will be a significant blow to Leader Jeong's leadership." (이런 가운데 민주당은 이날 최고위원회의 이후 당무위원회를 열고 1인 1표제 당헌 개정안을 중앙위 안건에 부의하는 건을 의결했다. 박 수석대변인은 회의 후 기자들을 만나 “당무위원 79명 중 현장 참석자 16명을 포함해 61명이 표결에 참여했고, 이 중 2명이 서면으로 반대표를 던졌다”고 밝혔다. 개정안은 오는 22∼24일 권리당원 여론조사를 거쳐 다음 달 2∼3일 중앙위 투표를 통해 확정된다. 민주당 관계자는 “지난달에 이어 이번에도 1인 1표제가 부결되면 정 대표의 리더십에 큰 타격이 될 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/O2WSP7MQUJHNVKWL2G2RVCERFI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/4VZ7BE3BVBEBXATQQEOKMLUO2Y.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Prosecutors Should Not Be Given Supplementary Investigation Authority"... Prime Minister and Minister Oppose Government Proposal Amid Hardliners' Pressure (“검사에 보완수사권 줘선 안돼”… 강경파 등쌀에 총리·장관이 정부안 반대)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/4LVSOGZW5JA23MSUB5LU6O3UKA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/43OCYSDA5BADTB4OQRKRTU5K7E.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Minister of the Interior and Safety Yoon Ho-joong stated, "The newly established Public Prosecution Service should not be given supplementary investigation authority." This is interpreted as Minister Yoon siding with hardliners within the ruling party, who have been opposing the recently announced government bill regarding the Public Prosecution Service and the Major Crime Investigation Agency (MCIA). (윤호중 행정안전부 장관이 19일 “신설되는 공소청의 검사에게 보완 수사권을 줘선 안 된다”고 밝혔다. 최근 정부가 발표한 공소청·중대범죄수사청(중수청)법을 두고 여권 내 강경파가 반발하고 있는 가운데 윤 장관이 강경파 손을 들어준 것으로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with Yonhap News published that day, Minister Yoon said, "Our position is that establishing a right to request supplementary investigations, rather than granting supplementary investigation authority, aligns with the basic principle of separating investigation and prosecution." He added, "If supplementary investigation authority is retained, prosecutors could conduct investigations even within the Public Prosecution Service, so why would they come to the MCIA?" The Minister of the Interior and Safety will oversee and supervise the newly established MCIA. Previously, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok also stated, "The principle is to abolish supplementary investigation authority." Following the Prime Minister, the minister in charge has now also expressed opposition, effectively challenging the government proposal led by the Presidential Office and the Ministry of Justice. (윤 장관은 이날 공개된 연합뉴스 인터뷰에서 “보완 수사권보다는 보완 수사 요구권을 두는 것이 수사·기소 분리의 기본 원칙에 맞다는 입장”이라며 “보완 수사권을 남겨두게 되면 검사가 공소청에서도 수사할 수 있는데, 뭐 하러 중수청에 오겠느냐”고 했다. 행안부 장관은 신설되는 중수청을 지휘·감독하게 된다. 앞서 김민석 국무총리도 “보완수사권은 폐지가 원칙”이라고 했었다. 총리에 이어 주무 장관까지 사실상 청와대와 법무부가 주도해온 정부안에 반대 의견을 낸 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, the government proposal was known to include content that would effectively allow prosecutors in the Public Prosecution Service to have supplementary investigation authority. However, due to strong backlash from hardliners, the government omitted mention of this part when announcing the proposal on the 12th, stating it would be discussed later. Nevertheless, hardline lawmakers from the Democratic Party demanded, "Abolish supplementary investigation authority immediately." Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae said, "The government proposal is a draft," and indicated they would begin amendment procedures. The Democratic Party plans to hold a public hearing on the 20th to discuss the issue of supplementary investigation authority. (당초 정부안에는 사실상 공소청 검사에게 보완 수사권을 허용하는 내용이 담길 것으로 알려졌었다. 하지만 강경파가 크게 반발하면서, 정부는 지난 12일 안을 발표할 때 이 부분에 대해선 추후 논의하겠다며 언급하지 않았다. 그러나 민주당 강경파 의원들은 “당장 보완 수사권을 폐지하라”고 했다. 정청래 민주당 대표는 “정부안은 초안”이라며 수정 절차에 들어가겠다고 했다. 민주당은 20일 공청회를 열고 보완 수사권 문제를 논의할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this process, President Lee Jae-myung instructed regarding supplementary investigation authority and other matters, "The party should deliberate, and the government should gather opinions." A ruling party official said, "The President also did not anticipate the backlash from his supporters," adding, "However, that doesn't mean he is siding with the hardliners. His position is to discuss it further." While the Ministry of Justice has not taken a public stance, a government official stated, "Changing the investigation system should not be dictated by hardliners. If that happens, it will become a patchwork law." In particular, there is reportedly significant dissatisfaction within parts of the government over the Democratic Party moving according to the hardliners' opinions. (이 과정에서 이재명 대통령은 보완 수사권 등에 대해 “당이 숙의하고, 정부가 의견을 수렴하라”고 지시했다. 여권 관계자는 “대통령도 지지층의 반발을 예상하지 못했다”며 “그렇다고 강경파의 손을 들어준 건 아니다. 더 논의해보자는 입장”이라고 했다. 법무부 역시 공개 입장은 내지 않고 있지만, 한 정부 관계자는 “수사 시스템을 바꾸는 일이 강경파 뜻대로 끌려가선 안 된다. 그렇게 되면 누더기법이 될 것”이라고 했다. 특히 정부 일각에선 민주당이 강경파 의견대로 움직이고 있는 것에 대한 불만이 상당하다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, within the Democratic Party, there are voices saying, "The issue of supplementary investigation authority is highly likely to be abolished as the hardliners desire." Attention is now focused on what stance President Lee will take regarding this matter during his New Year's press conference on the 21st. During a press conference last September, President Lee commented on the issue of supplementary investigation authority, saying, "Can the police be trusted? Even if you dislike maggots, would you throw away the entire earthenware jar?" (하지만 민주당 내에선 “보완 수사권 문제는 강경파가 원하는 쪽으로 폐지될 가능성이 높다”는 말이 나온다. 이에 이 대통령이 21일 신년 기자회견에서 이와 관련한 어떤 입장을 밝힐지 주목되고 있다. 작년 9월 회견 때 이 대통령은 보완 수사권 문제와 관련해 “경찰은 믿을 만하냐. 구더기가 싫어도 장독을 없애면 되겠느냐”고 한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/4LVSOGZW5JA23MSUB5LU6O3UKA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/43OCYSDA5BADTB4OQRKRTU5K7E.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Defective Document Submissions Become the 'New Normal' of the Lee Administration... Kim Min-seok 26%, Choi Hwi-young 30% Submission Rates (李정부의 ‘뉴노멀’이 된 부실 자료… 김민석 26%, 최휘영 30% 제출)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/CUW6UFN6YZBLLOAJKTT6QNLNZM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5PVBNWJBFBMJPPZ26DQ4YZUUE.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon was disrupted on the 19th due to incomplete submission of requested documents. The People Power Party protested that day, stating, "This nominee submitted only 15% of the 2,187 items of data requested by the People Power Party," and asking, "Are you telling us to hold a confirmation hearing in the dark?" The nominee requested that the hearing proceed, claiming, "About 75% of the data has been submitted." However, the People Power Party side countered, asking, "Does that include responses stating 'we cannot agree due to personal information reasons'?" and accused, "They are deceiving the public with wordplay." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 청문회가 19일 자료 제출 불성실을 이유로 파행했다. 국민의힘은 이날 “이 후보자는 국민의힘의 자료 요구 2187건 중 15％만 제출했다”며 “깜깜이 청문회를 하라는 것이냐”고 반발했다. 이 후보자는 이날 “자료의 75% 정도를 제출했다”며 청문회를 열어달라고 했다. 하지만 국민의힘 측에선 “‘개인정보를 이유로 동의할 수 없다’고 답변한 것도 제출한 것이냐”며 “말장난으로 국민을 호도하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party believes that even the documents submitted by this nominee are mostly inadequate. In particular, the nominee submitted additional documents at 9 PM the night before the hearing, and even these were reportedly deficient or contained irrelevant materials. A People Power Party official said, "Are they telling us to stay up all night and then hold the hearing?" and added, "It can only be seen as deliberate mischief." For example, regarding the request for documents related to the application for the Seoul Banpo One Pentas apartment, where suspicions arose that the nominee had fraudulently obtained subscription points by falsely listing a married eldest son as an unmarried child, it is said the nominee submitted a family relation certificate and a marriage relation certificate. A People Power Party official stated, "They did not submit the documents directly related to resolving the suspicion." (국민의힘은 이 후보자가 제출한 자료마저도 대부분 부실하다고 보고 있다. 특히 이 후보자는 청문회를 하루 앞둔 밤 9시에 추가로 자료를 냈는데, 이마저도 자료도 부실하거나 엉뚱한 자료가 많다고 했다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “밤새고 청문회를 하라는 것이냐”며 “일부러 장난친 것으로밖에 볼 수 없다”고 했다. 예컨대 이 후보자는 혼인한 장남을 미혼 자녀로 둔갑시켜 부정하게 청약 점수를 얻었다는 의혹이 불거진 서울 반포 원펜타스 아파트 청약 관련 서류 제출 요구에 주민등록 초본과 혼인관계증명서를 제출했다고 한다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “의혹 해소와 직접 관련된 자료는 제출하지 않은 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversy over the submission of inadequate documents by ministerial nominees has continued since the Lee Jae-myung administration began. In June of last year, Prime Minister nominee Kim Min-seok submitted only 26.7% of the data requested by the opposition party as of the day before his hearing. The People Power Party demanded the withdrawal of his nomination, protesting that various suspicions surrounding nominee Kim remained unresolved, but the motion for consent to appoint Prime Minister Kim passed the National Assembly led by the Democratic Party. The President also appointed Prime Minister Kim immediately. In July of last year, Science and ICT Minister nominee Bae Gyeong-hoon submitted only 759 out of 1,288 items (59%) requested by ruling and opposition party committee members as of the day before his hearing. Reasons for non-submission included 'trade secrets' and 'no data in possession.' Unification Minister nominee Chung Dong-young also submitted only 786 out of a total of 1,332 items, a submission rate of 59%. He too drew criticism by submitting a large batch at the last minute. Culture, Sports and Tourism Minister nominee Choi Hwi-young also received criticism even from the Democratic Party as her actual document submission rate stood at only 30%. Gender Equality and Family Minister nominee Kang Seon-woo reportedly did not submit 84 out of 216 items requested by the People Power Party as of the day before her hearing. Her document submission rate was 61%. To prevent such situations, the People Power Party has begun revising related laws under the name of the so-called 'Lee Hye-hoon Prevention Act'. (이재명 정부 들어 장관 후보자의 부실 자료 제출 논란은 계속되고 있다. 작년 6월 김민석 국무총리는 청문회 전날 기준 야당이 요구한 자료의 26.7%만 제출했다. 국민의힘은 김 총리의 각종 의혹이 풀리지 않았다며 지명 철회를 요구하며 반발했지만 김 총리에 대한 임명 동의안은 민주당 주도로 국회를 통과했다. 대통령도 김 총리를 곧바로 임명했다. 작년 7월 배경훈 과학기술부 장관 후보자는 청문회 전날까지 여야 위원들이 요구한 자료 1288건 중 759건(59%)만 제출했다. 미제출 사유는 ‘영업기밀’ ‘보유자료 없음’ 등이었다. 정동영 통일부 장관 후보자도 총 1332건 중 786건만 제출해 제출률이 59%였다. 이마저도 막판에 무더기로 제출해 빈축을 샀다. 최휘영 문화체육부 장관 후보자도 실제 자료 제출률이 30%에 그쳐 민주당으로부터도 질타를 받았다. 강선우 여성가족부 장관 후보자도 청문회 전날까지 국민의힘이 요구한 자료 216건 중 84건에 대해 제출하지 않았다고 한다. 자료 제출률은 61%였다&lt;b&gt;.&lt;/b&gt; 국민의힘은 이 같은 상황을 막기 위해 이른바 ‘이혜훈 방지법’이라는 이름으로 관련법 개정에 착수했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;National Assembly officials explain that while document submission issues surfaced during every hearing in past administrations, they have worsened since the Lee Jae-myung administration began. In political circles, there is talk that "the bad precedent of a prime minister and ministers being appointed without properly submitting documents has created the 'new normal' for confirmation hearings in this administration."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (과거 정부에서도 자료 제출 문제는 청문회 때마다 불거졌지만 이재명 정부 들어 더 심해졌다는 게 국회 관계자들의 설명이다. 정치권에선 “자료 제출을 제대로 하지 않고도 임명된 총리, 장관의 나쁜 선례가 이 정부 청문회의 ‘뉴노멀’을 만들었다”는 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/CUW6UFN6YZBLLOAJKTT6QNLNZM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5PVBNWJBFBMJPPZ26DQ4YZUUE.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Confirmation Hearing for Lee Hye-hoon Fails to Open Amid Onion-like Allegations and Inadequate Documentation (양파 의혹에 자료도 부실… 이혜훈 청문회 무산)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/XDRLVVV7UJB2BN2EKHZXDIDI54/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NT47UGS6PBBGRB3X6QRSODXODM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, failed to even begin on the 19th. The National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee held a plenary session in the morning but could not place the hearing on the agenda, adjourning after just an hour and a half. The People Power Party stated the hearing could not proceed due to the nominee's inadequate submission of requested materials. In contrast, the Democratic Party reiterated its stance that "the public's judgment must be sought." It is rare to find a precedent where a hearing fails to open due to a nominee's non-cooperation and the opposition party's refusal. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 국회 인사청문회가 19일 시작도 못하고 불발됐다. 이날 오전 국회 재정경제기획위원회는 전체회의를 열었지만 인사청문 안건은 상정도 못하고 1시간 30분 만에 정회했다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자의 자료 제출이 부실하다며 청문회를 진행할 수 없다고 했다. 반면 민주당은 이날까지 “국민 판단은 받아야 한다”는 입장을 되풀이했다. 후보자의 비협조와 야당의 거부로 청문회가 열리지 않는 건 전례를 찾기 어렵다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Confirmation Hearing Act, a hearing must be held within 15 days of a nomination being referred to the relevant standing committee, and today was that legal deadline. However, the deadline for the National Assembly to send the hearing report to the government is until the 21st. Lim Lee-ja, the Planning and Finance Committee chairperson from the People Power Party, maintains that the hearing can only be held with an agreement between the ruling and opposition party floor leaders, but there are significant differences between the parties regarding document submission. Chairperson Lim stated, "The ball is now in the court of the Blue House." This was interpreted as meaning that, given the difficulty in holding the hearing, the Blue House should either withdraw this nominee or proceed with the appointment without a National Assembly hearing. (인사청문회법에 따르면 임명동의안이 담당 상임위에 회부되면 15일 안에 청문회를 열어야 하는데, 이날이 법정 시한이었다. 다만 국회가 인사청문경과보고서를 정부로 보내야 하는 시한은 오는 21일까지다. 국민의힘 소속인 임이자 재경위원장은 여야 간사가 합의해야 청문회를 열 수 있다는 입장이지만 자료 제출 등에 대해 여야 간 이견이 큰 상황이다. 임 위원장은 “공은 청와대로 넘어갔다”고 했다. 청문회 개최가 어려운 상황인 만큼 청와대가 이 후보자를 낙마시키든지, 국회 청문회 없이 임명을 강행하라는 취지로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee, unable to enter the meeting room, waited at the National Assembly and returned home around 9:20 PM. Earlier, meeting with reporters, the nominee said, "I believe it is the role of the National Assembly to create an opportunity for verification before the public," adding, "The National Assembly should reconsider whether it is abandoning and blocking that role itself." (이 후보자는 회의장에 들어가지 못한 채 국회에서 대기하다 오후 9시 20분 귀가했다. 이 후보자는 앞서 기자들과 만나 “국민 앞에서 검증하는 기회를 만드는 게 국회 역할이라고 생각한다”며 “그 역할을 스스로 포기하고 차단하는 건 아닌지 국회가 다시 생각해봐야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House maintains its existing position that "the confirmation hearing should be held." It is also understood that there is no alternative candidate to replace this nominee. However, a ruling party official said, "The allegations against this nominee are layered like an onion, leaving even those within the ruling party in a perplexed position," adding, "While we would give the opportunity for explanation through a hearing, it's unclear if they can perform normal duties as a minister if appointed." (청와대는 “인사청문회는 열어야 한다”는 기존 입장을 유지하고 있다. 이 후보자를 대체할 다른 후보자도 없는 것으로 알려졌다. 하지만 한 여권 인사는 “이 후보자의 의혹이 양파처럼 이어져서 여권 내부도 당혹스러운 입장”이라며 “청문회를 통해 소명 기회까진 주겠지만 장관으로 임명돼 정상적인 업무 수행이 가능한지 모르겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Hearing Without Lee Hye-hoon Ends in Failure After 90 Minutes of Shouting... Opposition Says "Ball is with the President"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇이혜훈 없이 청문회, 90분 고성 오가다 불발… 野 “공은 대통령에게”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee held a plenary session at 10 AM today to discuss whether to hold the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination. Lim Lee-ja, the committee chairperson from the People Power Party, declared the session open and stated, "As an agreement between the two parties' floor leaders regarding the hearing has not been reached, as chairperson, I cannot place the hearing-related items on the agenda." (국회 재정경제기획위원회는 이날 오전 10시 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사청문회 개최 여부를 논의하기 위해 전체회의를 열었다. 국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장은 개회 선포와 함께 “청문회와 관련해 양당 간사 협의가 이뤄지지 않았기 때문에 위원장으로서 청문회 관련 안건은 상정할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-young, the People Power Party's floor leader on the committee, said, "(The nominee's) submitted response materials amount to only 15% of the total (requested by the National Assembly)," adding, "The materials submitted by the nominee's side, which consistently stalled, only at 9 PM on the 18th, are also inadequate." In contrast, the Democratic Party countered, insisting on holding the hearing for the verification of public officials and receiving additional materials. Chung Tae-ho, the Democratic Party's floor leader on the committee, said, "I wish they would start the hearing first and then proceed to fill in any deficiencies." (재경위 국민의힘 간사인 박수영 의원은 “(이 후보자가 국회에) 제출한 답변 자료가 전체 (국회 요구 자료)의 15%에 불과하다”며 “버티기로 일관했던 이 후보자 측이 18일 오후 9시가 돼서야 낸 자료도 부실하다”고 했다. 반면 민주당은 공직자 검증 차원에서 청문회를 개최하고 추가 자료를 받자고 맞섰다. 민주당 간사인 정태호 의원은 “우선 청문회를 시작하고 부족한 것은 채워나가도록 진행해줬으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties had been engaged in a week-long standoff over this nominee's hearing issue. The Planning and Finance Committee had decided on the 13th to hold the nominee's hearing, agreeing that if the submission of hearing materials was insufficient by 5 PM on the 15th, the hearing date (the 19th) could be postponed. On the 16th, Chairperson Lim Lee-ja held a press conference, hinting at the possibility of refusing the hearing due to the nominee's failure to submit materials, and the Democratic Party requested the nominee's cooperation in submitting additional materials. However, the opposition party claims the nominee failed to properly submit most materials even until the night of the 18th. (여야는 앞서 이 후보자 청문회 문제로 일주일 간 신경전을 벌였다. 국회 재경위는 지난 13일 이 후보자의 청문회 개최 안건을 의결하면서 15일 오후 5시까지 인사청문 자료 제출이 미흡할 경우 청문회 날짜(19일)를 미룰 수 있다고 합의했었다. 임이자 재경위원장은 16일 기자회견을 열고 이 후보자의 자료 미제출을 이유로 청문회 거부 가능성을 시사했고, 민주당이 이 후보자에게 추가 자료 제출 협조를 요구했다. 하지만 이 후보자는 18일 밤까지도 대부분의 자료를 제대로 내지 않았다는 게 야당 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even today, ruling and opposition party lawmakers, unable to even start the hearing, requested 'remarks on the proceedings' and blamed each other for the disruption. Democratic Party lawmaker Park Hong-keun said, "Why are you running the committee like this?" adding, "There has never been a case so far where a hearing was boycotted on the grounds of insufficient document submission." People Power Party lawmaker Kwon Young-se said, "Even former Prime Minister Han Duck-soo's (hearing) was postponed for a week due to document submission issues." (이날도 여야 의원들은 청문회는 시작도 못한 채 ‘의사 진행 발언’을 신청하며 상대방에게 파행의 책임을 돌렸다. 민주당 박홍근 의원은 “왜 위원회를 이따위로 운영하는가”라며 “자료 제출이 미비하다는 이유로 청문회를 보이콧한 경우는 지금까지 없었다”고 했다. 국민의힘 권영세 의원은 “한덕수 전 국무총리도 자료 제출 사유로 (청문회가) 1주일 연기됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the nominee could not enter the meeting room, ruling and opposition party lawmakers also clashed over the nominee's qualifications. People Power Party lawmaker Choi Eun-seok said, "Numerous allegations have piled up, including suspicions of fraudulent seizure crimes related to a Gangnam apartment collectively purchased by the family, and character assassination of aides, to the point it's hard to list them all." In response, Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Young-jin said, "This is someone who has been in politics with you all for 20 years," adding, "You should reflect on yourselves." When Democratic Party lawmaker Chung Tae-ho said, "(This nominee) is someone the People Power Party nominated three times to become a lawmaker," People Power Party lawmakers retorted, "Are you going to make such a person a minister?" (이 후보자가 회의장에 입장하지 못했지만 여야 의원들은 후보 자질 공방도 벌였다. 국민의힘 최은석 의원이 “가족이 전체적으로 공모한 강남 아파트의 사기적 강탈 범죄 의혹, 보좌진들에 대한 인격 살인 행위 등 일일이 열거하기조차 힘든 많은 의혹들이 누적돼 있다”고 했다. 이에 대해 민주당 김영진 의원은 “여러분들과 정치를 20년간 하신 분”이라며 “스스로 반성하라”고 했다. 민주당 정태호 의원이 “(이 후보자는) 국민의힘에서 세번이나 공천해서 의원으로 만든 분”이라고 하자 국민의힘 의원들은 “그런 사람을 장관으로 만들 것이냐”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party lawmaker Chun Ha-ram said, "The hearing must not become a pardon for a nominee who should have been dropped ten or a hundred times," adding, "It must not be turned into a farce of a hearing where it's just about holding out for one more day." Lawmaker Chun also raised an issue with the nominee's 'request for investigation' remark. Earlier, when lawmaker Chun publicized what he claimed was a 'memorandum' written by the nominee, the nominee said on the 15th, "I want to request an investigation," only to apologize the next day, saying, "I apologize for the excessive expression that came out in the process of expressing my grievance." Cho Kuk Innovation Party lawmaker Cha Gyu-geun said, "The nominee's attitude suggesting they could even file a complaint against the confirmation hearing committee members was very inappropriate and regrettable." (개혁신당 천하람 의원은 “열번 백번 낙마했어야 할 이 후보자에게 면죄부를 주는 청문회가 돼선 안된다”며 “하루만 버티면 된다는 식의 청문회로 희화화돼선 안된다”고 했다. 천 의원은 이 후보자의 ‘수사 의뢰’ 발언도 문제 삼았다. 앞서 천 의원이 이 후보자가 작성했다며 ‘비망록’을 공개하자 이 후보자는 지난 15일 “수사 의뢰하고 싶다”고 했다가 하루 만에 “억울함을 토로하는 과정에서 과한 표현이 나간 점을 사과드린다”고 했다. 조국혁신당 차규근 의원은 “이 후보자가 인사청문위원을 고발할 수도 있다는 태도를 보인 점은 매우 부적절한 태도였고 유감”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As shouting matches between ruling and opposition party lawmakers continued and no agreement on holding the hearing was reached, Planning and Finance Committee Chairperson Lim Lee-ja declared an adjournment around 11:30 AM, stating, "Please have the ruling and opposition party floor leaders discuss whether the hearing should proceed today or if the schedule should be changed." (여야 의원 간 고성 섞인 공방이 오가고 청문회 개최에 합의하지 못하자 임이자 재경위원장은 오전 11시 30분쯤 “청문회를 오늘 진행해야 되는 것인지 아니면 일정 변경을 해서 해야 하는 것인지 여야 간사가 협의해달라”며 정회를 선포했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties held additional negotiations in the afternoon but failed to agree on holding the hearing. Democratic Party lawmaker Chung Tae-ho, meeting with reporters, said, "In my view, the opposition party has no intention of holding it." People Power Party lawmaker Park Sung-hoon said, "The materials haven't come in, and even if they do, we need at least two days to analyze them and prepare questions." (여야는 오후 추가 협상을 벌였지만 청문회 개최에 합의하지 못했다. 민주당 정태호 의원은 기자들과 만나 “제가 볼 땐 야당이 하고 싶어하는 생각이 없다”고 했다. 국민의힘 박성훈 의원은 “자료가 들어오지 않았고, 자료가 와도 분석과 질의 자료를 만들기 위해 이틀은 필요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee, who had been waiting for an agreement between the parties, left the National Assembly around 9:20 PM. Regarding the hearing's failure to open, the nominee said, "I will watch for an agreement between the floor leaders." They added, "Wouldn't the public also want to see the rights and wrongs of all these allegations clarified?" (여야 합의를 기다리던 이 후보자는 오후 9시 20분쯤 국회를 떠났다. 이 후보자는 인사청문회 불발에 “간사 간의 합의를 지켜보겠다”고 했다. 그러면서 “국민들도 이 모든 의혹의 시시비비를 가리고 싶지 않으실까요”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today was the final legal deadline for the nominee's National Assembly confirmation hearing. According to the Confirmation Hearing Act, a hearing must be concluded within 15 days of the nomination being referred to the committee. However, the deadline for the National Assembly to adopt the hearing report is until the 21st. Therefore, if the parties agree, there is also mention of the possibility of holding the hearing on the 20th. (이날은 이 후보자의 국회 인사청문회 법정 시한 마지막 날이었다. 인사청문회법에 따르면 인사청문회는 임명동의안이 위원회에 회부된 날로부터 15일 이내 마치도록 돼 있다. 다만 국회가 인사청문경과보고서를 채택해야 하는 시한은 오는 21일까지다. 그래서 여야가 합의할 경우 20일 인사청문회를 열 가능성도 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the possibility of a hearing on the 20th, Planning and Finance Committee Chairperson Lim Lee-ja told this newspaper, "The ball is in the court of the Blue House." This was interpreted as meaning the situation makes it difficult to hold the hearing. If the hearing is not held, President Lee Jae-myung must either withdraw the nomination of this candidate or appoint them as minister without a confirmation hearing. Even within the ruling party, there are voices saying, "This nominee, with so many allegations, is a ticking time bomb." (20일 청문회 가능성에 대해 임이자 재경위원장은 본지에 “공은 청와대로 넘어갔다”고 했다. 인사청문회 개최가 어려운 상황이라는 뜻으로 해석됐다. 인사청문회가 안 열릴 경우 이재명 대통령은 이 후보자에 대한 지명을 철회하거나, 인사청문회 없이 이 후보자를 장관으로 임명해야 한다. 여당 내에서도 “의혹이 많은 이 후보는 시한폭탄”이라는 이야기가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House is in a state of perplexity. Blue House Spokesperson Kim Nam-joon, on CBS Radio today, responded to the point that there are many allegations related to this nominee by saying, "We are listening seriously to all such criticisms. There is not a single aspect we can take lightly," but added, "However, we believe it is necessary for the person themselves to explain to the public." Spokesperson Kim also said, "We are humbly listening to opinions regarding the Blue House's verification issues as well." (청와대는 곤혹스러워하는 분위기다. 김남준 청와대 대변인은 이날 CBS 라디오에서 이 후보자 관련 의혹이 많다는 지적에 대해 “그런 비판도 다 무겁게 듣고 있다. 어느 것 하나 가볍게 볼 수 없는 부분들”이라면서도 “다만 본인이 국민께 설명해 드리는 게 필요하다고 보고 있다”고 했다. 김 대변인은 “청와대의 검증 문제에 대해서도 겸허하게 의견을 듣고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee is known to have been personally chosen by President Lee. There are also accounts that proper verification was difficult. This implies that ultimately, it will be President Lee who decides whether this nominee is dropped. However, among Blue House staff, there is a growing negative sentiment towards the nominee's appointment, with remarks like, "We didn't know there were this many allegations." (이 후보자는 이 대통령이 직접 선택한 것으로 알려졌다. 검증을 제대로 하기 어려웠다는 이야기도 나온다. 이 후보자 낙마 여부를 결정하는 건 결국 이 대통령이 될 것이라는 의미다. 다만 청와대 참모진 사이에선 “의혹이 이렇게 많은 줄은 몰랐다”며 이 후보자 임명에 부정적 기류가 커지는 분위기다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/XDRLVVV7UJB2BN2EKHZXDIDI54/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NT47UGS6PBBGRB3X6QRSODXODM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The World Changed Overnight with the May 17 Coup (5·17 쿠데타로 하룻밤 사이 세상이 바뀌었다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6JVOBAMFDNCNRMUCG5UFH34VEM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;As 1980 drew to a close, YS looked back on the past year. His house arrest had been ongoing for over seven months. "The world changed overnight with the unexpected coup of May 17 (the incident where the new military regime expanded the state of emergency nationwide). I was placed under house arrest. My indescribably painful days began. I had to overcome myself." (YS는 1980년 한 해가 저물면서 지난 한 해를 돌아봅니다. 가택 연금이 7개월 넘게 지속되고 있었습니다. “뜻하지 않던 5.17의 쿠데타(신군부가 비상계엄을 전국으로 확대 조치했던 사건)로 하룻밤 사이에 세상은 바뀌었다. 나는 연금되었다. 나의 말할 수 없는 고통의 나날은 시작되었다. 나 자신에게 이기는 일을 나는 해내야만 했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although surrounded by police forces, there were occasional moments when people managed to slip through the lax security and enter his home. On December 18, Assemblyman Kim Dong-young and two female university students, after several failed attempts, came to YS's house. He expresses his feelings about the students participating in protests. "When I think of the students' demonstrations, I also have a sense of the sublime. If they are caught demonstrating, it means expulsion and prison. They might even lose their entire lives. Yet, when I think of them fighting for justice, we feel ashamed." (경찰 병력에 둘러싸인 채였지만 경비가 느슨한 순간을 뚫고 집으로 들어오는 이들도 간혹 있었습니다. 12월 18일 김동영 의원을 비롯해 여자 대학생 2명이 몇 차례 실패 끝에 YS 집으로 왔습니다. 시위에 나서는 대학생들에 대한 소감을 피력합니다. “대학생들의 데모를 생각할 때 숭고한 생각도 든다. 그들이 데모하다가 붙들리면 퇴학이며 감옥이다. 어쩌면 자기의 일생을 다 잃는 것이다. 그러나 정의를 위하여 싸우는 그들을 생각할 때 우리들은 부끄러운 일이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;YS brought in another pair of canaries to his home. Following the munjo, parakeets, and society finches, the number increased to eight birds. Recalling an anecdote about how India's former Prime Minister Nehru kept lizards and such when he was in prison in the past, he writes: "I once read in the autobiography of India's former Prime Minister Nehru that before becoming Prime Minister, while in prison, he kept insects or lizards living in the prison on a mountainside because he had to do something. During this house arrest, I will raise birds and live as friends with them." (YS는 집에 카나리아 한 쌍을 더 들였습니다. 문조·잉꼬·십자매에 이어 여덟 마리로 늘었습니다. 인도 네루 총리가 과거 감옥에 있을 때 도마뱀 등을 길렀다는 일화를 떠올리며 적습니다. “인도의 전 네루 수상의 자서전 가운데 수상이 되기 전에 감옥에 있을 때 무엇인가 해야 하기 때문에 산비탈에 있는 감옥 안에 살고 있는 벌레나 도마뱀 등을 길렀다는 것을 읽은 적이 있다. 나는 이 연금 중에 새를 기르며 새와 더불어 벗하며 지내련다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our household's bird family increased by another pair. Today, a pair of 'canaries,' known for singing well among birds, arrived. For someone like me who doesn't know much about birds, a cute, petite pair of orange-colored birds has been added. Altogether, that's four pairs, so eight birds. At first, they didn't sing, which was worrying, but now they sing so much it's almost noisy, as if the birds are competing. Raising birds is not that simple. Even today, I woke up at 6:30 AM, cleaned all the droppings from the four birdcages, laid fresh newspaper, washed the water dishes, changed the water, and gave them feed like millet and perilla seeds, and it took a full 40 minutes. And that's because I had prepared and placed the newspaper sheets to lay under the cages last night, so it took less time. Even as I write this, it's noisy. Since my wife says it smells, I'll have to clean the droppings frequently. It was a book I read 5 or 6 years ago, but I remember reading in the autobiography of India's former Prime Minister Nehru that before becoming Prime Minister, while in prison, he kept insects or 'lizards' living in the prison on a mountainside because he had to do something. During this house arrest, I will raise birds and live as friends with them. (우리집 새 식구가 한 쌍이 더 늘었다. 오늘 새 중에 잘 운다는 ‘카나리야’ 한 쌍이 들어왔다. 새에 대(対)해서 잘 모르는 나로써(*서)는 “오렌지” 색의 아담하고 자그마한 기여운(*귀여운) 새 한 쌍이 늘어났다. 모두 합처(*쳐)서 넷 쌍이니까 여덜(*여덟)마리다. 처음에는 울지 않아서 걱정이더니 이제는 시꺼(*끄)러울 정도(程度)로 새들이 경쟁하는 것처럼 울어댄다. 새를 길런다(*기른다)는 것이 그렇게 간단치 않다. 오늘도 아침 6시(時)30분(分)에 일어나 새 집 넷의 새똥을 다 치우고 새 신문지로 새로 깔아주고 물그릇을 씻고 새물을 바구고(*바꾸고) 조와 들개(*들깨) 등 모이를 주고 나니 40분(分)이나 시간(時間)이 걸였다(*걸렸다). 그것도 어제 밤에 새집 밑에 깔 신문지 종이를 마(*맞)추어서 만들어 났(*놨)기 때문에 시간(時間)이 적게 걸린 것이다. 이 글을 써고(*쓰고) 있는데도 씨꺼(*시끄)럽다. 집 사람이 냄새가 난다고 해서 자주 똥 소제를 하지 않으면 안 되겠다. 5, 6년전(年前)에 읽은 책이지마는 인도(印度)의 전(前) 네루 수상(首相)의 자서전 가운데 수상(首相)이 되기 전(前)에 감옥에 있을 때 무엇인가 해야하기 때문에 산 삣탈(*비탈)에 있는 감옥 안에 살고 있는 벌레나 “도마비암(*도마뱀)” 등(等)을 길렀다는 것을 읽은 적이 있다. 나는 이 연금 중(中)에 새를 길루며(*기르며) 새와 더불어 벗하며 지내련다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night, Assemblyman Kim Dong-young managed to visit stealthily for the first time in a while, and today during the day, Pastor Kim Ha-jin and a female evangelist visited together. We happily talked about various church matters and the current political situation. Also during the day, somehow they managed to get in—two young female students who used to follow me, Na Seon-im and Kim Mi-hye, had tried to come several times but couldn't enter, but today they were able to come in. They came and asked, with their young hearts, how I had been and what I would do going forward. I think they are precious children. When I think of the recent university students' demonstrations, I also have a sense of the sublime. (어제 밤에는 모처럼 숨어서 김동영(金東英) 의원(議員)이 왔더니 오늘 낮에는 김(金)하진 목사(牧使)와 여(女) 전도사(傳道師)가 같이 방문(訪問)했다. 여러가지 교회(敎会) 이야기와 시국(時局) 이야기 등을 즐겁게 이야기했다. 또 낮에는 어떻게들 들어왔는지 전(前)에 나를 따르던 어린 여학생(女學生) 나선임(羅宣任)와 김미혜(金美惠)가 여러 차례 왔다가 못 들어왔는데 오늘 들어 올 수 있어서 들어왔다. 찾아와서 그동안 어떻게 지냈으며 앞으로 어떻게 할 것인가 등(等)을 어린 마음에서나마 물어본다. 귀(貴)여운 아이들이라고 생각한다. 요지음의 대학생(大學生)들의 데모를 생각할 때 숭고한 생각도 든다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If they are caught demonstrating, it means expulsion and prison. They might even lose their entire lives. Yet, when I think of them fighting for justice, we feel ashamed. I also heard from Pastor Kim Ha-jin about the sermon story of Pastor Park from Yeongnak Church. He said, 'When I came down from the North as a refugee, it was to spread the gospel, not to live a dirty life...' (그들이 데모하다가 붓들리면(*붙들리면) 퇴학(退學)이며 감옥이다. 어쩌면 자기(自己)의 일생(一生)을 다 잃는 것이다. 그러나 정의(正義)를 위하여 싸우는 그들을 생각할 때 우리들은 부꺼(*끄)러운 일이다. 영락교회(永樂敎会)의 박(朴) 목사(牧師)의 설교(說敎) 이야기도 김하진 목사(牧師)로부터 들었다. 나가(*내가) 이북에서 피난올 때 복음(福音) 전(傳)하려 내려왔지 더럽게 살아가기 위해서 내려 온 것은 아니다 라고….)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been exactly seven months and two days since I was placed under house arrest. With ten more days passing, the Year of the Gapsin (1980) will also be completely over. How can I define the year 1980? (내가 연금 된지가 만 7개월(個月)하고 이틀이 지났다. 1980년도(年度)도 10일(日)이 지나면 경신(庚申)도 다 지나간다. 80년도(年度) 한 해를 어떻게 규정지울(*을) 수 있을까?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a New Year and spring filled with glorious hope. All citizens were thinking of liberal democracy, recalling the suffering under Park Chung-hee's dictatorial system, and yearning for freedom, peace, and liberal democracy. However, the world changed overnight with the unexpected coup of May 17. I was placed under house arrest. My indescribably painful days began. As I have always thought, I had to overcome myself. I had to get through the 24 hours somehow. (영광(榮光)스러운 희망(希望)에 찬 신년(新年)과 봄이였다. 모든 국민(囗民)이 모두가 자유민주주의(自由民主主義)를 생각하며 박정희(朴正熙)의 독제(*독재) 체제(體制) 아래에서 고통받던 생각을 하며 자유(自由)와 평화(平和) 그리고 자유민주주의(自由民主主義)를 갈구했다. 그러나 뜻하지 않던 5.17의 구테타(*쿠데타)로 하로(*하루)밤 사이에 세상(世上)은 바뀌었다. 나는 연금되었다. 나의 말할 수 없는 고통의 나날은 시작(始作)되었다. 늘 생각해온 것이지만 나 자신(自身)에게 이기는 일은 나는 해내야만 했다. 나는 24시간(時間)을 어떻게던(*든)지 보내야만 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the new year of 1981, I pray to God that true peace and justice are realized for me and our people, and that a democratic society returns. Yesterday, after Seop-kwon's wedding ceremony, Hye-young's mother and Hyeon-cheol returned. This morning, a call came from Seop-kwon and his wife in Jeju Island. I pray they build a happy new life together. (1981년(年)의 새해에는 나와 우리 백성(百姓)에게 참 평화(平和)와 정의(正義)가 구현되며 민주주의(民主主義) 사회(社会)가 돌아오기를 하나님께 기도한다. 어제 섭권(燮權)이 결혼식(結婚式)을 마치고 혜영(惠英) 어머니와 현철(賢哲)이가 돌아왔다. 아침에 제주도(濟州島)에서 섭권(燮權)이와 가기로부터 전화(電話)가 왔다. 행복(幸福)한 새 생활을 꾸미기를 기도한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teacher Kang Nam-seok and Pastor Son Sang-seok have passed away. Both were over 80, so they lived a full life, but both were healthy... The world is turning so strangely that it seems they turned their backs on this chaotic world and went to heaven. How much these two must have waited for a good world, a new world. In spring, these people visited me in good health... Life, in a word, is impermanent. I can only pray for their eternal life. (강남석(姜南錫) 선생(先生) 손상석(孫相錫) 목사(牧師)가 세상(世上)을 떠나셨다. 두분 다 80이 넘었어서 살 만큼은 살았지마는 두 분 다 건강(健康)했는데…. 하도 세상(世上)이 이상하게 돌아가니까 어수선한 세상(世上)을 등지고 하늘나라로 간 것 같다. 이 두 분 다 좋은 세상(世上) 새 세상(世上)을 얼마나 기다렸겠나. 봄에도 나에게 이분들이 건강(健康)한 몸으로 다녀갔는데…. 인생(人生)이란 한마디로 무상(無常)하다. 부디 영생(永生)을 빌 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the new year, I only wish for a happy year, a peaceful year, a just year, a free year, a year where the general public and masses can live well. (새해에는 행복(幸福)한 해, 평화(平和)로운 해, 정의(正義)로운 해, 자유(自由)로운 해, 일반(一般) 국민(囗民) 대중(大衆)이 살기 좋은 해를 맞이하기를 빌 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The snow that began to fall quietly last night covered the whole world in white by morning. The white-covered snow truly blanketed the mountains, houses, trees, and the entire world in white. Going out into the yard early in the morning and walking lightly on the snow, it's not like this chaotic present world. I wish this beautiful white snow would swallow up the painful, unwanted, and unlooked-back-upon Year of the Gapsin (1980). Probably today, people with no work will go out on the streets in countless numbers to see the snow. Especially young people will go out to see the snow; although I cannot go outside to see today's spectacle, more than half the people will likely go out to see the snow. That fellow Hyeon-cheol also got excited by the snowy wind and went out since noon. Hye-suk said she wished for a White Christmas this year, and it seems it will be so. (어제 밤부터 고요히 나리기 시작(始作)한 눈은 아침에는 온 세상을 하얗게 덥었다. 하얗게 덥힌 눈은 그야말로 산(山)과 집과 나무와 모든 온 누리를 하얗게 덥었(*덮었)다. 아침 일찍이 뜰에 나가 뜰에 나가 눈 우이(*위)로 삿풋삿푼(*사뿐사뿐) 걸어(*으)니 마치 어지러운 지금 이 세상(世上) 같이(*같지) 않다. 1980년(年)의 고통스럽고 다시 생각하기 싫고 다시 돌아보기 싫은 경신년(庚申年)을 이 아름다운 하얀 눈이 집어 삼켜 갔으면 한다. 아마 오늘은 일 없는 사람들이 눈 구경하기 위하여 거리에 수(數) 없이 많이 나다닐 것이다. 특(特)(*특히) 젊은 사람들이 눈을 구경하기 위하여 나는 밖에 나기(*가)지 못하니 오늘의 강경(*관경)을 구경하지 못하지마는 반수(半數) 이상(以上)의 사람들은 눈구경하려 다닐 것이다. 현철(賢哲)이란 놈도 눈바람에 신이 나서 낮부터 나갔다. 혜숙(惠淑)이가 금년(今年)은 White Christmas가 되었으면 하더니 그렇게 될 모양이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even the dictator 'Marcos' announced that he will release about 1,400 political prisoners and abolish the military tribunals next January to lift martial law. But in our country, they create all sorts of strange laws, even merging and shutting down media outlets, and now they've made a law to control the media. For whom and why are they strengthening the dictatorship like this... (독제(*재)자(者) “마르코스”도 내년(來年) 정월(正月)에 계엄을 해제하기 위하여 정치(政治)범들을 1400명(名)이나 석방하고 계엄 군법회의(軍法會議)도 폐지한다고 발표(發表)했다. 그런데 우리나라는 온갖 이상한 법(法)을 만들고 심지어 언론(言論)을 통폐합 하더니 이제는 언론(言論)을 통제하는 법(法)까지 만들었다. 어저(*쩌)자고 누구를 위하여 이렇게 독제(*재)를 강화(强化)하는지….)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking far out the window from the inner room, the poor houses covered in white snow on the mountain slopes today, on this snowy day, come sharply into view, and the thought of them suffering in cold and poverty fills my heart completely. I even feel like going to see them and comfort them, and an even more lonely feeling comes over me. I live making friends with loneliness. (안방에서 창밖을 멀리 내다보니 산기슬기(*산기슭)에 하얀 눈에 덥힌(*덮인) 가난한 집들 오늘 눈오는날 더욱이 눈에 싹 들어오며 춥고 가난 속에서 고생한다는 생각이 마음 다 차지 한다. 흘흘(*훌훌) 가보구 싶고 위로해 주고 싶은 생각마저 들며 더욱히(*이) 고독한 생각이 던(*든)다. 고독과 함께 벗을 하며 살아간다)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6JVOBAMFDNCNRMUCG5UFH34VEM/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>