<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:48:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>President Lee to Hold Dinner with Ruling Party Leadership Today... Likely to Discuss 'Controversy over Nominee Lee Hye-hoon' and Other Issues (李대통령, 오늘 여당 지도부와 만찬...‘이혜훈 후보자 논란’ 등 논의할듯)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/18/YD6BTILGKZDMVOQKR5CQKUISAI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee to Hold Dinner with Ruling Party Leadership Today... Likely to Discuss 'Controversy over Nominee Lee Hye-hoon' and Other Issues (李대통령, 오늘 여당 지도부와 만찬...‘이혜훈 후보자 논란’ 등 논의할듯)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LXCBZVRG65AORJ76OMONMKZJHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung will host a dinner meeting at the Blue House on the 19th, inviting the ruling Democratic Party of Korea's leadership, including Chairman Chung Cheong-rae and newly elected floor leader Han Byung-do. (이재명 대통령이 19일 더불어민주당의 정청래 당대표와 한병도 원내대표 등 여당 지도부를 청와대로 초청해 만찬 간담회를 갖는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A Blue House official said on the 18th, "There have been recent changes in the Democratic Party's leadership composition, and this meeting holds significance in reaffirming the relationship between the party and the administration as we enter the new year." (청와대 관계자는 18일 “민주당 지도부 구성에 최근 변화가 있었고, 새해를 맞아 당청 관계를 다시 한 번 다지는 의미가 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party elected Representative Han Byung-do as the new floor leader during a general meeting of lawmakers on the 11th. This was a by-election held after former floor leader Kim Byung-ki resigned amid various allegations of misconduct, including suspicions of power abuse by his aides. (민주당은 지난 11일 의원총회에서 한병도 의원을 신임 원내대표로 선출했다. 김병기 전 원내대표가 보좌진 갑질 의혹 등 각종 비위 의혹으로 사퇴해 치러진 보궐선거였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the same day, Representatives Kang Deuk-gu, Lee Sung-yoon, and Moon Jung-bok were elected as Supreme Council members. They replaced three Supreme Council members who resigned to run in the local elections scheduled for June 3rd. (같은 날 강득구, 이성윤, 문정복 의원은 최고위원으로 선출됐다. 6월 3일 열리는 지방선거 출마를 위해 사퇴한 최고위원 3명의 후임을 뽑은 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the dinner on the 19th, President Lee is expected to urge the completion of reform tasks and cooperation with the People Power Party. (이 대통령은 19일 만찬에서 개혁 과제 완수, 국민의힘과의 협치 등을 당부할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the Democratic Party, disagreements persist over issues such as the operational plan for the Public Prosecution Service and the Major Crime Investigation Bureau, which are to replace the abolished Prosecutors' Office, and granting 'supplementary investigation authority' to the Public Prosecution Service. There have also been claims within the party that the nomination of Lee Hye-hoon as Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination is a "mistaken appointment." Although a confirmation hearing for this nominee is scheduled for the 19th, it is unclear whether it will be held as the opposition party has stated its position to 'boycott the hearing.' Opinions on this matter may be exchanged during the dinner meeting. (민주당은 최근 검찰청을 폐지하고 들어서는 공소청과 중대범죄수사청의 운영 방안 및 공소청에 ‘보완 수사권’을 주는 문제 등을 놓고 당내 이견이 계속되고 있다. 이 대통령이 지명한 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대해 당내에서 “잘못된 인사”라는 주장도 나왔다. 이 후보자에 대한 청문회는 19일로 예정되어 있지만, 야당이 ‘청문회 보이콧’ 입장을 밝힌 상태여서 청문회 개최 여부가 불투명하다. 만찬 간담회에서 이에 대한 의견이 오갈 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/18/YD6BTILGKZDMVOQKR5CQKUISAI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LXCBZVRG65AORJ76OMONMKZJHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 04:51:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Ik-pyo Appointed as New Senior Secretary for Political Affairs... Woo Sang-ho to Run for Gangwon Governor (신임 정무수석에 홍익표… 우상호는 강원지사 도전)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ITJXDOJNAVAEHB4EOZ3GSR5RJU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Hong Ik-pyo Appointed as New Senior Secretary for Political Affairs... Woo Sang-ho to Run for Gangwon Governor (신임 정무수석에 홍익표… 우상호는 강원지사 도전)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OEL34F6FI5D6PGIV7XOBREBZII.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House announced on the 18th that it has appointed former Democratic Party of Korea floor leader Hong Ik-pyo as the new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs. This appointment comes as the current Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, Woo Sang-ho, is stepping down to run in the Gangwon Province gubernatorial election in the June 3 local elections. (청와대는 18일 신임 정무수석에 홍익표 전 더불어민주당 원내대표를 임명했다고 밝혔다. 우상호 정무수석이 6·3 지방선거의 강원도지사 선거에 출마하면서 후임을 임명한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Senior Secretary Hong served three terms (19th, 20th, and 21st National Assembly) as a lawmaker representing Seoul's Seongdong district. In 2023, he worked as the party's floor leader when President Lee Jae-myung was the party leader. He ran in the difficult Seoul Seocho-eul district for the Democratic Party in the 22nd general election but was defeated. By accepting the offer to become Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, he has decided not to run for Seoul Mayor, a position he had been preparing for. (홍 신임 수석은 서울 성동에서 3선(19·20·21대) 국회의원을 했고, 지난 2023년 이재명 대통령이 당대표일 때 당 원내대표로 호흡을 맞췄다. 22대 총선에서 민주당 험지인 서울 서초을 지역에 도전했지만 낙선했다. 정무수석 제안을 수락하면서 그동안 준비해왔던 서울시장 출마는 하지 않기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Senior Secretary Woo stepping down, the resignation of Blue House aides running in the June 3 local elections and National Assembly by-elections is expected to accelerate. The personnel drawing the most attention are senior-level officials such as Chief of Staff Kang Ho-sik, Policy Chief Kim Yong-beom, and Senior Secretary for AI and Future Planning Ha Jeong-woo. Chief of Staff Kang, a former three-term lawmaker from Asan, South Chungcheong Province, is being mentioned as a potential ruling party candidate if the integrated special city of Daejeon and South Chungcheong Province is established. However, many observers note there is inevitably pressure for the Chief of Staff, who leads the Presidential Secretariat, to resign just over seven months after the administration's launch. (우 수석이 그만두면서, 6·3 지방선거 및 국회의원 보궐선거에 출마하는 청와대 참모진의 사퇴도 본격화될 전망이다. 가장 관심을 모으는 인사는 강훈식 비서실장과 김용범 정책실장, 하정우 AI미래기획수석 등 수석급 이상 인사들이다. 충남 아산 3선 의원 출신인 강 실장은 대전·충남 통합특별시가 출범할 경우 여당 후보로 거론된다. 다만 대통령비서실을 이끄는 실장이 정부 출범 7개월여 만에 직을 그만두는 데 대한 부담이 따를 수밖에 없다는 관측이 많다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Policy Chief Kim, who is from South Jeolla Province and attended high school in Gwangju, is being mentioned as a potential candidate for Gwangju Mayor or South Jeolla Province Governor, while Senior Secretary Ha, who is from Busan, is rumored to be considering a run for Busan Mayor. However, a Blue House official stated, "There was talk at one point, but the actual possibility of them running seems very slim." (전남 출신으로 광주에서 고등학교를 나온 김 실장은 광주시장 또는 전남지사, 부산 출신인 하 수석은 부산시장 출마설이 거론된다. 하지만 청와대 관계자는 “한때 얘기가 돌았지만 실제 출마할 가능성은 아주 작아 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the secretary level, Political Affairs Secretary Kim Byeong-wook is coordinating the timing of his resignation to run for Seongnam Mayor. Former lawmaker Go Yong-jin, who was re-elected in Seoul's Nowon district, is a strong candidate to succeed him. Presidential Spokesperson Kim Nam-joon is expected to run in the Incheon Gyeyang-eul district by-election, which was President Lee's former National Assembly constituency. (비서관급에서는 김병욱 정무비서관이 성남시장 출마를 위해 사퇴 시기를 조율 중이다. 후임에는 서울 노원에서 재선을 한 고용진 전 의원이 유력하다. 이 대통령의 국회의원 지역구였던 인천 계양을 지역 보궐선거에는 김남준 청와대 대변인이 출마할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, National Listening Secretary Bae Jin-gyo is being mentioned as a possible candidate for Incheon Mayor, Autonomous Development Secretary Lee Seon-ho for Ulsan Mayor, former Digital Communication Secretary Kim Nam-guk for Ansan Mayor, and National Integration Secretary Heo Eun-ah for Seoul's Yeongdeungpo District Mayor. (이밖에 배진교 국민경청비서관은 인천시장, 이선호 자치발전비서관은 울산시장, 김남국 전 디지털소통비서관은 안산시장, 허은아 국민통합비서관은 서울 영등포구청장 출마 가능성이 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of the administration's launch in June last year, there was talk within the ruling party that 'the Blue House staff would be composed only of people who would not run in elections.' The intention was to minimize the impact of elections for stable state affairs management, but the atmosphere has changed significantly recently. A ruling party official said, "Wouldn't the situation, where President Lee's approval rating is fluctuating around 60% and the ruling party is significantly ahead of the opposition party's support rate, making it seem likely to win the local elections big, have had an influence?" (작년 6월 정부 출범 때만 해도 여권 내에선 ‘청와대 참모진은 선거에 안 나갈 사람으로만 구성하기로 했다’는 말이 나왔다. 안정적 국정 운영을 위해 선거 영향을 최소화한다는 것이었는데, 최근엔 분위기가 많이 변했다. 여권 관계자는 “이 대통령 지지율이 60%를 오르내리고, 여당이 야당 지지율을 크게 앞서면서 지방선거를 크게 이길 것 같은 상황이 영향을 미치지 않았겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ITJXDOJNAVAEHB4EOZ3GSR5RJU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OEL34F6FI5D6PGIV7XOBREBZII.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea reports Xi Jinping's greeting cards with other countries... Putin is on page 1 of the Rodong Sinmun (北, 시진핑 연하장을 타국과 묶어서 보도… 푸틴은 노동신문 1면)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/XIEVGB55VJGEHJOWAFHV3RYE4M/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea reports Xi Jinping's greeting cards with other countries... Putin is on page 1 of the Rodong Sinmun (北, 시진핑 연하장을 타국과 묶어서 보도… 푸틴은 노동신문 1면)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA3TIYLFG5TDEMLFGU2DQMBVMM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean media do not report on the New Year's greeting cards exchanged between Chairman Kim Jong-un and Chinese President Xi Jinping, leading to observations that North Korea-China relations are cold. The contents of the New Year's greeting card that Kim Jong-un exchanged with Russian President Vladimir Putin were introduced in detail by the Rodong Sinmun. (북한 매체들이 김정은 국무위원장과 시진핑 중국 국가주석 간에 오간 신년 연하장을 비중 있게 보도하지 않아, 북중 관계가 냉랭하다는 관측이 나오고 있다. 김정은이 블라디미르 푸틴 러시아 대통령과 주고받은 신년 연하장 내용은 노동신문이 자세히 소개했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rodong Sinmun published an article on page 2 on the 18th stating that Kim Jong-un "sent greeting cards to heads of party and state and officials of various countries." The first thing Kim Jong-un sent greeting cards to was "the President and wife of the People's Republic of China, General Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China," but the real names of Xi Jinping and Peng Liyuan were not mentioned. He also did not introduce China separately, but only mentioned the fact that he sent greeting cards in a line with the heads of state of eight countries, including Vietnam, Singapore, and Tajikistan. North Korean media reported that when President Xi and his wife sent a greeting card to Kim Jong-un on the 1st, they did not introduce the contents separately, but only reported that the "Chinese president and his wife" also sent greeting cards by combining them with other leaders of states. (노동신문은 18일 2면에 김정은이 “여러 나라 당 및 국가 수반들과 인사들에게 연하장을 보냈다”는 기사를 게재했다. 김정은이 연하장을 보낸 대상으로 가장 먼저 “중국공산당 중앙위원회 총서기인 중화인민공화국 주석과 부인”을 언급했지만, 시진핑·펑리위안이란 실명은 거론되지 않았다. 또 중국을 따로 소개하지 않고 베트남, 싱가포르, 타지키스탄 등 8국의 국가 수반과 한 줄에 묶어 연하장을 보냈다는 사실만 언급했다. 북한 매체들은 지난 1일 시 주석 부부가 김정은에게 연하장을 보낸 사실을 전할 때도 그 내용을 별도로 소개하지 않고 다른 국가 정상들과 묶어 ‘중국 주석 부부’도 연하장을 보내왔다고만 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, on the 27th of last month, the Rodong Sinmun published the contents of Putin's greeting card to Kim Jong-un on the front page, and on the 2st of last month, the second page of Kim Jong-un's reply to Putin was published. In his greeting card, Putin expressed his gratitude for North Korea's dispatch of troops to Kursk and said that he was confident that "we will continue to carry out constructive cooperation on regional and international issues (in the future)." Kim Jong-un called Putin "my dear comrade" and said that North Korea and Russia are "the most sincere alliance in which we share life and death in the same trench." (반면 지난달 27일 노동신문은 1면에 푸틴이 김정은에게 보낸 연하장 내용을 비중 있게 실었고, 지난달 31일 2면에는 김정은이 푸틴에게 보낸 답장 내용을 게재했다. 푸틴은 연하장에서 북한의 쿠르스크 파병 등에 사의를 표하며 “(앞으로도) 지역 및 국제 문제들에서 건설적인 협동을 진행하게 되리라고 확신”한다고 했다. 김정은은 푸틴을 “친애하는 나의 동지”로 부르며 북·러는 “한 전호(戰壕)에서 피를 나누며 생사고락을 함께 하는 가장 진실한 동맹 관계”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Kim Yo-yong, vice chairman of the Workers' Party of Korea, said in a speech to South Korea on the 13th, "Even if the ruling party goes abroad to solicit money, the reality of inter-Korean relations will never change." It was interpreted as expressing dissatisfaction with the South Korean side's announcement that President Xi held a summit meeting with President Lee Jae-myung, who was on a state visit to China, on the 5th and discussed "creative measures" for peace on the Korean Peninsula. Lim Eul-chul, a professor at the Institute of Far Eastern Studies at Kyungnam University, said, "North Korea will see China's welcome of the South Korean president, whom it has defined as its 'first main enemy,' as a challenge to its 'sovereign decision.'" (그런 한편 김여정 노동당 부부장은 지난 13일 대남 담화에서 “집권자가 해외에까지 돌아치며 청탁질을 해도 남북 관계의 현실은 절대로 달라질 수 없다”고 했다. 시 주석이 국빈 방중한 이재명 대통령과 지난 5일 정상회담을 하며 한반도 평화를 위한 ‘창의적 방안’ 등을 논의했다는 우리 측 발표에 불만을 드러낸 것으로 풀이됐다. 임을출 경남대 극동문제연구소 교수는 “북한은 자신들이 ‘제1의 주적’으로 규정한 한국 대통령을 중국이 국빈으로 맞이한 것 자체를 ‘주권적 결정’에 대한 도전으로 볼 것”이라며 “시진핑의 연하장을 홀대한 것도 김정은의 대중(對中) 불만이 상당하다는 신호”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/XIEVGB55VJGEHJOWAFHV3RYE4M/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA3TIYLFG5TDEMLFGU2DQMBVMM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party: "Lee Hye-hoon is not a subject for verification, but for investigation" (국힘 “이혜훈, 검증 대상 아닌 수사 대상”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FXKZEQVLDVDJVCUZ4DPO2OX5HI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party: "Lee Hye-hoon is not a subject for verification, but for investigation" (국힘 “이혜훈, 검증 대상 아닌 수사 대상”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KXHPP5KCK5PQFGILZZUVLBNCMY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the People Power Party (PPP) refuses to hold a National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, citing insufficient document submissions, the atmosphere has become uncertain regarding whether the hearing will be held on the 19th. The Democratic Party of Korea (DPK) stated it will consult with the PPP as much as possible to hold the hearing normally. (국민의힘이 자료 제출 미비 등을 이유로 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회를 거부하면서, 19일 청문회 개최 여부가 불투명해진 분위기다. 더불어민주당은 청문회 정상 개최를 위해 국민의힘과 최대한 협의해 본다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP is calling the nominee "not a subject for verification, but for investigation." PPP lawmakers belonging to the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee held a press conference on the 18th, stating they "completely refuse to hold a hearing for nominee Lee, a 'lawbreaker'." PPP member and committee chairperson Lim Lee-ja also said on the 16th that she could not hold the hearing as the nominee had not submitted a significant portion of the documents requested by the opposition party. (국민의힘은 이 후보자에 대해 “검증이 아닌 수사 대상”이라고 하고 있다. 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들은 18일 기자회견을 열어 “‘범법 행위자’ 이 후보자에 대한 청문회를 전면 거부한다”고 했다. 국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장도 지난 16일 이 후보자가 야당이 요구한 청문 자료를 상당 부분 제출하지 않고 있다며 청문회를 못 열겠다고 했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of the 15th, the nominee's document submission rate was known to be slightly over 15%. The nominee's side reportedly refuses to consent to submitting related documents regarding their children's employment, military service, and gift tax payment history, citing 'personal information.' (지난 15일 기준 이 후보자의 자료 제출률은 15% 남짓으로 알려졌다. 이 후보자 측은 자녀들의 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 관련 자료에 대해 ‘개인정보’를 이유로 동의하지 않고 있다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP holds the position that it cannot proceed with the hearing if documents related to the children and proof of full gift tax payment are not submitted. In response, it is known that the nominee informed the National Assembly on the afternoon of the 18th that they "will submit more documents." The PPP maintains that even if the nominee submits additional documents, holding the hearing immediately on the 19th is unreasonable as time is needed for analysis. (국민의힘은 자녀 관련 자료와 증여세 완납증명서 제출이 안 되면 청문회에 임할 수 없다는 입장이다. 그러자 이 후보자는 18일 오후 국회에 “자료를 더 제출하겠다”고 한 것으로 알려졌다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 자료를 추가로 제출하더라도 분석할 시간이 필요한 만큼 당장 19일 청문회 개최는 무리라는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DPK submitted a request to the Strategy and Finance Committee to open the hearing on this day. DPK lawmakers belonging to the committee stated in a declaration today, "Refusing the hearing is the National Assembly abandoning its own authority and responsibility," adding, "The nominee's side is making efforts to submit the key documents requested by the People Power Party." (민주당은 이날 재경위에 청문회 개회 요구서를 냈다. 재경위 소속 민주당 의원들은 이날 성명에서 “청문회 거부는 국회 스스로 권한과 책임을 포기하는 것”이라며 “이 후보자 측은 국민의힘이 요구한 주요 자료를 제출하기 위해 노력하고 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some are mentioning the possibility that if the PPP continues to boycott the hearing, the DPK might hold the hearing alone. According to the National Assembly Act, if a standing committee chairperson refuses to proceed with the agenda, the majority party's secretary can conduct the meeting instead of the chairperson. However, it is reported that if Chairperson Lim does not hand over the authority to preside, disruption is inevitable, and the DPK also views it as realistically difficult to take over the presiding authority. Within the opposition party, there are also demands that the hearing should be held to receive the public's judgment on the nominee, so the possibility of a last-minute hearing cannot be ruled out. A DPK official said, "We plan to continue consultations until the morning of the 19th." (일각에선 국민의힘이 청문회를 계속 보이콧할 경우 민주당이 단독으로 청문회를 열 가능성도 거론된다. 국회법상 상임위원장이 의사 진행을 거부하면 다수당 간사가 위원장 대신 회의를 진행할 수 있다. 그러나 임 위원장이 사회권을 넘기지 않으면 파행이 불가피하고, 민주당도 사회권을 가져오는 것은 현실적으로 어렵다고 보는 것으로 전해졌다. 야당 내에도 이 후보자에 대한 국민 판단을 받아보려면 청문회를 열어야 한다는 요구가 있어 막판 청문회 개최 가능성도 배제할 수는 없다. 민주당 관계자는 “19일 아침까지도 계속 협의할 방침”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FXKZEQVLDVDJVCUZ4DPO2OX5HI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KXHPP5KCK5PQFGILZZUVLBNCMY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon Apologizes, Saying "I Am Sorry for Causing Concern to Party Members" (한동훈 “당원께 걱정 끼쳐 송구” 사과)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FTVQLLOADNFVNEOUQ52W3G2Z3I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Han Dong-hoon Apologizes, Saying "I Am Sorry for Causing Concern to Party Members" (한동훈 “당원께 걱정 끼쳐 송구” 사과)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ML4VNGYNQNOFPGFOY5J6THLU2A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon expressed his feelings regarding the party division related to the 'party member bulletin board' issue, stating, "As a responsible politician who led the party, I feel deeply sorry that the situation has come to this point and for causing concern to the public and party members." This marks his first apology in 14 months since the issue surfaced in November 2024. (국민의힘 한동훈 전 대표가 18일 ‘당원 게시판’ 문제로 인한 당내 분열과 관련해 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것, 국민과 당원께 걱정을 끼친 점에 대해서 당을 이끌었던 책임 있는 정치인으로서 송구한 마음”이라고 했다. 2024년 11월 이 사건이 불거진 지 14개월 만의 첫 사과다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a two-minute video message posted on Facebook, the former leader clarified his stance. However, regarding the party audit committee's investigation into him and the ethics committee's decision to expel him, he stated, "It is a clear fabrication and political retaliation." He further added, "They may be able to strip me of my party membership through political retaliation using party authority, but they cannot strip away the spirit and future of our party, which I love." (페이스북에 게시한 2분짜리 영상 메시지를 통해 이같이 밝힌 한 전 대표는 다만 자신에 대한 당무감사위원회 조사와 윤리위원회 제명 결정에 대해서는 “명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라고 했다. 또 “당권으로 정치 보복을 해서 저의 당적을 박탈할 수는 있어도 제가 사랑하는 우리 당의 정신과 미래는 박탈할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among neutral figures within the party, reactions varied. Some called it a "half-hearted apology," while others urged, "In any case, former leader Han has made a concession, so leader Jang Dong-hyeok should also take a step back for unity." (중립 성향의 당내 인사들 사이에선 “반쪽 사과였다”는 반응과 “어쨌든 한 전 대표가 양보한 셈이니, 장동혁 대표도 한발 물러서서 통합하라”는 주문이 함께 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Han Dong-hoon's Apology Amid Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike... Will It Find an Exit from the Internal Strife?&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;장동혁 단식 중에 나온 한동훈 사과… 내분 출구 찾을까&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ethics committee, officially formed by leader Jang Dong-hyeok on the 8th, held two meetings on the 9th and 13th before deciding on 'Han Dong-hoon's expulsion.' The Jang Dong-hyeok leadership attempted to finalize the expulsion decision on the 15th. However, People Power Party lawmakers, regardless of faction, strongly opposed, saying, "Expulsion is not acceptable." In response, leader Jang stepped back, stating, "I will suspend the decision until the 10-day appeal period." Former leader Han countered, saying, "I have no intention of appealing." (지난 8일 장동혁 대표가 공식 구성한 윤리위는 지난 9일과 13일 두 차례 회의를 가진 뒤 ‘한동훈 제명’ 결정을 내렸다. 장동혁 지도부는 지난 15일 한 전 대표 제명 결정을 ‘최종 의결’하려 했다. 그러나 국민의힘 의원들이 계파를 불문하고 “제명은 안 된다”고 강력 반발했고, 이에 장 대표는 “10일간의 재심 신청 기간까지 결정을 보류하겠다”고 물러섰다. 한 전 대표는 “재심 신청할 생각이 없다”고 맞받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, many lawmakers requested during the general meeting of lawmakers on the 15th that "an apology from former leader Han is also necessary." This opinion began to emerge even from the pro-Han faction. Party elders also called for a grand compromise between the two. It is reported that one elder visited leader Jang's hunger strike site at the National Assembly main building on the night of the 17th and spoke with former leader Han over the phone the same day, urging unity. (다만 의원 다수가 15일 의원 총회에서 “한 전 대표의 사과도 필요하다”고 주문했다. 친한계에서도 이런 의견이 나오기 시작했다. 당 원로들도 두 사람의 대승적 통합을 주문했다. 한 원로는 지난 17일 밤 국회 본청의 장 대표 단식장을 찾았고, 같은 날 한 전 대표와 통화하며 통합을 주문한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, former leader Han had been contemplating a political apology message regarding the recent party member bulletin board issue. Within the pro-Han faction, opinions were divided between "should not apologize" and "should apologize for the responsibility in the party division." Some figures reportedly suggested, "Let's also apologize for the conflicts that occurred during former President Yoon Suk-yeol's term while serving as party leader." However, the prevailing opinion was that "the illegal/unfair investigation and disciplinary decision regarding the party member bulletin board issue are not subjects for apology," and it is understood that former leader Han took this stance today. (이에 한 전 대표는 최근 당원 게시판 문제를 두고 정치적 사과 메시지에 대해 고심해 왔다. 친한계 내부는 “사과를 해서는 안 된다”는 의견과 “당내 분열 부분에 대한 책임은 사과하자”는 의견으로 갈렸다. 일부 인사는 “윤석열 전 대통령 재임 시절 당 대표로서 갈등 국면에 있던 것도 사과하자”고 건의했다고 한다. 다만 “당원 게시판 문제에 대한 불법·부당한 조사, 징계 결정은 사과 대상이 아니다”라는 의견이 우세해, 한 전 대표가 이날 이 같은 입장을 낸 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reactions to former leader Han's apology today among neutral lawmakers and figures were mixed. Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon, after visiting leader Jang's hunger strike site today, told reporters, "It is fortunate that former leader Han mustered the courage to apologize," adding, "It will serve as an opportunity for party unity." A fourth-term lawmaker said, "This is just the beginning. There is now room for gradual, step-by-step reconciliation." Supreme Council member Yang Hyang-ja posted on Facebook today, "Let's gather everyone's wisdom for unity, the future, and victory." However, a second-term lawmaker commented, "It would have been better if it were only a political apology, but mentioning 'political retaliation' and such leaves room for further dispute." (한 전 대표의 이날 사과에 대해 중립 성향 의원들과 인사들 사이에선 복잡한 반응이 나왔다. 오세훈 서울시장은 이날 장 대표 단식장을 찾은 뒤 취재진에 “한 전 대표가 용기를 내서 (사과)해 준 것은 다행”이라며 “당 화합의 계기가 될 것”이라고 했다. 한 4선 의원은 “이제 시작이다. 한 걸음씩 차근차근 화합할 여지가 생긴 것”이라고 했다. 양향자 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에서 “화합과 미래, 승리를 위해 모두의 지혜를 모아가자”고 했다. 다만, 한 재선 의원은 “정치적 사과만 했으면 좋았을 텐데 ‘정치 보복’ 등을 운운해 분란의 여지를 남겼다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Geun-sik, chairman of the Seoul Songpa-gap district party committee, proposed to former leader Han on the 17th, "Let's show magnanimous politics by visiting and supporting leader Jang's hunger strike." A standing advisor also said, "Former leader Han should visit leader Jang's hunger strike site, and leader Jang should show a welcoming attitude." It is said that former leader Han currently has no plans to visit leader Jang's hunger strike site. Former lawmaker Kim Seong-tae said in a phone call, "Whether it's former leader Han or leader Jang, the one who shows courage and makes a decision first will be the winner." (김근식 서울 송파병 당협위원장은 지난 17일 한 전 대표를 향해 “장 대표의 단식을 지지 방문하며 통 큰 정치를 보여주자”고 제안했다. 한 상임고문도 “한 전 대표가 장 대표 단식장을 찾아가고 장 대표는 반기는 모습을 보여주라”고 했다. 한 전 대표는 아직 장 대표 단식장을 찾을 생각이 없다고 한다. 김성태 전 의원은 통화에서 “한 전 대표든 장 대표든 먼저 용기와 결단을 내리는 사람이 승자가 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang, who began his hunger strike on the 15th and entered his fourth day today, did not issue an official statement. When New Future Democratic Party leader Jeon Byeong-heon, who visited him today, said, "I hope you exercise political leadership to declare a truce with former leader Han and pool your strength," leader Jang smiled, said "Yes," and nodded. Floor leader Song Eon-seok said, "Regarding the content (of former leader Han's apology), it seems we need to think again about how many people are receiving it." (지난 15일 단식을 시작해 이날 나흘째를 맞은 장 대표는 공식 입장을 내지 않았다. 장 대표는 이날 자신을 찾은 새미래민주당 전병헌 대표가 “정치력을 발휘해서 한 전 대표와 휴전하고 힘을 모았으면 한다”고 하자, 웃으며 “예”라고 답한 뒤 고개를 끄덕였다. 송언석 원내대표는 “(한 전 대표의 사과) 내용에 대해 많은 분들이 어떻게 받아들이고 있는지 다시 한번 생각해봐야 할 듯하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Figures close to leader Jang criticized, saying, "Is this an apology?" and "Public opinion is unfavorable, so they pretend to apologize, but they don't want to admit wrongdoing." On the other hand, pro-Han lawmakers countered, "Despite the illegal investigation and disciplinary action, former leader Han mustered the courage to apologize." (장 대표 측 인사들은 “이게 사과냐” “여론이 불리하니 사과하는 척은 해야겠고, 잘못을 인정하기는 싫은 모습”이라며 비판했다. 반면 친한계 의원들은 “불법적인 조사와 징계에도 한 전 대표가 용기를 내서 사과한 것”이라고 맞섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some within the party predict that the ethics committee's decision regarding former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyeok, a pro-Han figure, will be one of the watershed moments determining whether the internal conflict can be resolved. Previously, the party audit committee recommended severe disciplinary action of 'two-year suspension of party membership rights' to the ethics committee, citing that former Supreme Council member Kim insulted the party leadership and members in media interviews and other statements. The ethics committee is scheduled to hold a meeting on the 19th to hear former Supreme Council member Kim's explanation. (당 일각에선 친한계인 김종혁 전 최고위원에 대한 윤리위 결정이 당내 갈등 봉합 여부의 분수령 중 하나가 될 것이란 전망이 나온다. 앞서 당무감사위는 김 전 최고위원이 언론 인터뷰 등에서 당 지도부와 당원을 모욕하는 언행을 했다며 ‘당원권 정지 2년’의 중징계를 윤리위에 건의했다. 윤리위는 19일 회의를 열고 김 전 최고위원의 소명을 들을 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FTVQLLOADNFVNEOUQ52W3G2Z3I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ML4VNGYNQNOFPGFOY5J6THLU2A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Ruling Camp's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Calculation'... "A Win-Win Whether She Passes or Falls" (與 ‘이혜훈 청문회 셈법’… “통과든 낙마든 꽃놀이패”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RSGLHRT43ZAQBJJ5ZBSU5UI4MA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The Ruling Camp's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Calculation'... "A Win-Win Whether She Passes or Falls" (與 ‘이혜훈 청문회 셈법’… “통과든 낙마든 꽃놀이패”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HE4DSNJVGYYDCYLBHA3DSMJXHA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, the Presidential Office once again stated regarding the various suspicions surrounding Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, "We expect her to provide answers and explanations that meet the public's expectations through the confirmation hearing." This reaffirmed their existing stance of waiting to see the hearing's outcome. Within the ruling camp, there is talk that "If this conservative nominee passes the hearing, it will be evaluated as President Lee Jae-myung's effort for integration, and even if she fails, it won't be a significant loss for the ruling camp as a whole." (청와대는 18일에도 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 각종 의혹에 대해 “청문회를 통해 국민의 눈높이에 맞는 답변을 하고 해명할 것으로 기대한다”고 했다. 청문회를 지켜보겠다는 기존 입장을 재확인한 것이다. 여권에선 “보수 인사인 이 후보자가 청문회를 통과하면 이재명 대통령의 통합 노력이란 평가가 나올 것이고, 낙마해도 여권 전체에 손해는 아니다”란 말이 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee unprecedentedly nominated former three-term People Power Party lawmaker Lee Hye-hoon as the first Minister of Planning and Budget on the 28th of last month. At the time, the Presidential Office called it "President Lee's personnel choice for integration and pragmatism." Subsequently, as suspicions such as real estate speculation and staff misconduct surrounding the nominee were raised one after another, concerns emerged even within the Democratic Party that "this could become a major negative factor for the ruling camp." Calls for her voluntary resignation also came from the Democratic Party. (이 대통령은 지난달 28일 국민의힘에서 3선 의원을 지낸 이 후보자를 초대 기획예산처 장관 후보자로 파격 발탁했다. 당시 청와대는 “이 대통령의 통합과 실용 인사”라고 했다. 이후 후보자를 둘러싸고 부동산 투기, 보좌진 갑질 등의 의혹이 잇따라 제기되자 민주당 내에서도 “여권에 큰 악재가 될 수 있다”는 우려가 나왔다. 민주당에선 자진 사퇴 요구도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the Presidential Office maintains its position of "waiting to see the hearing" regarding this nominee. An interpretation has emerged that this is because the current controversy is not significantly damaging the approval ratings of the President and the Democratic Party. In various opinion polls, positive evaluations of this personnel appointment are in the 10-20% range. However, President Lee's approval rating has been maintaining around 60%. In a Gallup Korea survey from the 13th to the 15th, it was 58%. Although it fell 2 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week, it was actually 1%p higher than the third week of December, just before the nominee's designation. In a Realmeter survey from the 5th to the 9th, President Lee's approval rating hit 56.8%, its highest point in two months. During the same period, the Democratic Party's approval rating also steadily remained in the low 40% range. Public opinion experts said, "Since the nominee is a conservative figure, the emphasis is on 'the President's personnel choice for integration,' and her personal misconduct seems to be perceived as the fault of the conservative camp." (그런데도 청와대가 이 후보자에 대해 “청문회를 지켜보겠다”고 하고 있다. 이번 논란이 대통령과 민주당 지지율에 별다른 타격을 주지 않고 있기 때문이란 해석이 나온다. 실제 각종 여론조사에서 이 후보자 인사에 대한 긍정 평가는 10~20%대다. 하지만 이 대통령 지지율은 60% 안팎을 유지 중이다. 한국갤럽의 13~15일 조사에선 58%였다. 전주 대비 2%포인트(p) 하락했지만, 이 후보자 지명 직전인 12월 셋째 주와 비교하면 오히려 1%p 높았다. 지난 5~9일 리얼미터 조사에서 이 대통령 지지율은 56.8%로 두 달 만에 최고치를 찍기도 했다. 같은 기간 민주당 지지율도 꾸준히 40%대 초반을 유지했다. 여론조사 전문가들은 “이 후보자가 보수 인사이다 보니 ‘대통령의 통합 인사’에 방점이 찍혔고, 이 후보자 개인 비리는 보수 진영 잘못으로 인식하는 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of this, within the ruling camp, there is talk that the choice between forcefully appointing or letting this nominee fall is a "win-win." If the nominee sufficiently explains the various suspicions during the hearing and is appointed as minister, it can emphasize the image of a 'pragmatic government.' Even if she falls, she would have served her purpose as a symbol of 'conservative division.' One second-term lawmaker said, "Aren't most of the suspicions about this nominee things that happened during her time in the People Power Party?" adding, "On the contrary, the opposition camp is being divided due to President Lee's bold recruitment of talent." A Democratic Party official stated, "(Even if she falls,) just having made this nominee apologize about the martial law incident is a significant achievement for us." (이 때문에 여권에선 이 후보자를 두고 임명 강행이냐, 낙마냐는 선택은 꽃놀이패라는 말이 나온다. 이 후보자가 청문회에서 각종 의혹을 충분히 소명하면 장관으로 임명해 ‘실용 정부’ 이미지를 강조할 수 있고, 낙마하더라도 ‘보수 분열’의 상징으로 쓰임새를 다했다는 것이다. 한 재선 의원은 “이 후보자의 의혹 대부분이 국민의힘 시절 벌어진 일 아니냐”며 “오히려 이 대통령의 과감한 인재 영입으로 야권이 분열하고 있다”고 했다. 한 민주당 관계자는 “(낙마하더라도) 이 후보자가 비상계엄에 대해 사과하게 한 것만으로 우리는 상당한 성과”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RSGLHRT43ZAQBJJ5ZBSU5UI4MA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HE4DSNJVGYYDCYLBHA3DSMJXHA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon Holds Firm Despite Opposition Boycott... Political Circles Say "Her Will for Power is Uncommon" (野 보이콧에도 버티는 이혜훈… 정치권 “권력 의지 남다른 사람”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/B3PLJEM76BAHTA3Y3U7PDQTOUY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon Holds Firm Despite Opposition Boycott... Political Circles Say "Her Will for Power is Uncommon" (野 보이콧에도 버티는 이혜훈… 정치권 “권력 의지 남다른 사람”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBIZ5ZC6SZFCXELBSVLAAYELWM.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the People Power Party declaring it will boycott the National Assembly confirmation hearings, the possibility of holding the hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, scheduled for the 19th, has become uncertain. Demands for her resignation are growing not only from the opposition but also within the ruling party itself. (국민의힘이 국회 인사청문회를 거부하겠다고 하면서 19일 예정된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 청문회 개최 여부가 불투명해졌다. 야당은 물론 여당 내부에서도 이 후보자에 대한 사퇴 요구가 커지고 있는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversies have been raised regarding the nominee, including allegations of abusive language and power abuse by her aides during her time as a lawmaker, the controversy over her eldest son's 'sham single status' to unfairly win a Gangnam apartment lottery, and suspicions of her husband's land speculation in Incheon's Yeongjong Island. (이 후보자에 대해선 국회의원 시절 보좌진 갑질·폭언, 장남의 ‘위장 미혼’을 통한 강남 아파트 부정 당첨 논란, 남편의 인천 영종도 땅 투기 의혹 등이 제기돼 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the nominee's side maintains the position that "there will be no resignation." Political figures familiar with the nominee said on the 18th, "She will not resign voluntarily and will hold out until the end," adding, "You can understand this if you look at the process of how she entered politics and pursued power." (그러나 이 후보자 측은 “사퇴는 없다”는 입장이다. 이 후보자를 잘 아는 정치권 인사들은 18일 “자진 사퇴하지 않고 끝까지 버틸 것”이라며 “이 후보자가 정치에 입문하고 권력을 쫓아간 과정을 보면 안다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An economist by background, the nominee is the eldest daughter-in-law of the late former Minister of Home Affairs Kim Tae-ho, who served four terms as a lawmaker from Ulsan in the 1980s-2000s. It was the daughter-in-law, nominee Lee, not her son Professor Kim Young-se of Yonsei University, who inherited the family business of 'politics'. The nominee maximized the use of that 'legacy'. (경제학자 출신인 이 후보자는 1980~2000년대 울산에서 4선 의원을 지낸 고(故) 김태호 전 내무부 장관의 맏며느리다. 아들인 김영세 연세대 교수가 아닌 며느리인 이 후보자가 가업(家業)인 ‘정치’를 물려받았다. 이 후보자는 그 ‘유산’을 최대한 활용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the hearing, the formation process of the nominee's family wealth, amounting to 17.5 billion won, has also come to light. Apart from assets inflated through real estate like the Yeongjong Island land deal and the Gangnam apartment lottery, a significant portion originated from her mother-in-law. (청문회를 앞두고 175억원대인 이 후보자 가족 재산의 형성 과정도 알려지게 됐다. 영종도 땅 매매, 강남 아파트 당첨 등으로 부동산으로 불린 재산 외에, 상당 부분은 시어머니가 출발점이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"The Daughter-in-law Inherited the Family Business of 'Politics'"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“며느리가 家業인 ‘정치’ 승계”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho, passed away from leukemia in July 2002 during his 16th term as a lawmaker. That same year, the nominee entered the political arena as a policy advisor to Lee Hoi-chang, the Grand National Party's presidential candidate. In a media interview at the time, the nominee stated that her family strongly recommended her 'political entry'. (이 후보자 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관은 2002년 7월 16대 의원 임기 도중 골수암으로 별세했다. 그해 이 후보자는 한나라당 이회창 대통령 후보의 정책 자문역으로 정치권에 입문했다. 이 후보자는 당시 언론 인터뷰에서 가족이 ‘정치 입문’을 강력히 권유했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee served three terms as a lawmaker, all from Seocho Gap district, in the 2004, 2008, and 2016 general elections. In the 2012 general election, she failed to receive the party nomination due to the Grand National Party's 'principle prohibiting a third-term run in one's home turf'. Subsequently, she challenged the Seoul mayoral election in the 2014 local elections but lost in the primary. That year, she also threw her hat in the ring for the Ulsan Nam-eul by-election for the National Assembly but withdrew her nomination application amid criticism from inside and outside the party. (이 후보자는 2004·2008·2016년 총선까지 서초갑에서만 3선 의원을 했다. 2012년 총선 땐 한나라당의 ‘텃밭 3선 출마 금지 원칙’ 때문에 공천을 못 받았다. 그러자 2014년 지방선거에서 서울시장 선거에 도전했다가 경선에서 탈락했다. 그해 울산 남을 국회의원 보궐선거에도 출사표를 냈다가 당 안팎의 비난에 공천 신청을 철회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the impeachment motion against former President Park Geun-hye passed the National Assembly in 2017, the nominee left the Saenuri Party and served as the leader of the Bareun Party. Later, in the 2020 and 2024 general elections, she ran as a candidate for the United Future Party and the People Power Party in Seoul's Dongdaemun and Seoul Jung-Seongdong districts respectively, but lost. In the 2022 local elections, she also challenged the North Chungcheong Province governorship election but was eliminated in the primary. (이 후보자는 2017년 박근혜 전 대통령 탄핵소추안이 국회를 통과하자 새누리당을 탈당해 바른정당 대표를 지냈다. 이후 2020년, 2024년 총선 때 미래통합당과 국민의힘 후보로 서울 동대문을, 서울 중·성동을에 각각 출마했지만 낙선했다. 2022년 지방선거 땐 충북지사 선거에도 도전했다가 경선에서 떨어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the current Democratic Party administration, she has switched camps and been nominated as a minister. A ruling party official said, "An influential politician recommended her to President Lee Jae-myung, and I understand the nominee accepted the offer immediately." An opposition party official stated, "The nominee's will for power was extraordinary, having inherited the family business from her in-laws on behalf of her husband." (이번 민주당 정권에서는 진영을 바꿔 장관 후보자에 올랐다. 여권 관계자는 “유력 정치인이 이재명 대통령에게 추천했고, 이 후보자는 제안을 받자 바로 수락한 걸로 안다”고 했다. 야권 관계자는 “남편을 대신해 시댁의 가업을 이어 받은 이 후보자의 권력 의지는 남달랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Family as a 'Community of Interest', Fails to Submit Documents&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇가족은 ‘이익공동체’, 자료제출 안해&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's family wealth amounts to 17.56952 billion won, most of which was formed through gifts from her mother-in-law or real estate investments. (이 후보자 가족 재산은 175억6952만원인데, 대부분 시어머니로부터 증여를 받거나 부동산 투자를 통해 형성했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, looking at the real estate transaction history, the nominee, at age 28 in 1992 while studying abroad in the US, purchased five commercial buildings in Eungbong-dong, Seongdong-gu, Seoul, in her and her husband's names, realizing a market price profit of about 1 billion won. Also, it was revealed that the nominee's husband purchased miscellaneous land on Incheon's Yeongjong Island in 2000, one year before the opening of Incheon International Airport, and made a profit of over 2 billion won. (먼저 부동산 변동 내역을 보면, 이 후보자는 스물여덟 살이던 1992년 미국 유학 시절에 본인과 남편 명의로 서울 성동구 응봉동 상가 5채를 사들여, 10억여 원의 시세 차익을 실현했다. 또 이 후보자 남편은 인천국제공항 개항 1년 전인 2000년 인천 영종도 잡종지를 매입해 20억원 이상의 차익을 본 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She also won the 'lottery subscription' for an apartment in Seoul's Gangnam area. The nominee's eldest son maintained his status as a household member under his parents without filing a marriage report ('sham single status'), thereby receiving a higher subscription score, and won the subscription for the 'Raemian One Pentas' apartment in Banpo-dong in July 2024. This apartment is currently valued in the 7 billion won range, with a market price profit exceeding 3 billion won. (서울 강남권 아파트 ‘로또 청약’에도 당첨됐다. 이 후보자 장남이 혼인 신고를 하지 않고 이 후보자 부부 아래 세대원을 유지하는 ‘위장 미혼’을 통해 청약 가점을 높게 받은 뒤, 2024년 7월 반포동 ‘래미안 원펜타스’ 아파트 청약에 당첨됐다. 이 아파트는 현재 70억원대이며 시세 차익은 30억원이 넘는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her three sons, in their 20s and 30s, each hold assets ranging from 1.2 to 1.7 billion won, totaling about 4.7 billion won. Most of this was gifted by the nominee's mother-in-law. The mother-in-law gifted 2,400 shares (worth about 3.1 billion won) of KSM, a semiconductor equipment company, to the nominee's three sons in 2016 and 2021, and in May of last year, also gifted a house in a redevelopment planned area in Jeonnong-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul, to the nominee's second son. (20~30대인 세 아들은 각자 12억~17억원씩 47억원 정도를 보유하고 있다. 대부분 이 후보자 시어머니가 증여해 준 것이다. 시어머니는 2016년과 2021년 이 후보자의 세 아들에게 반도체 장비 회사인 KSM의 주식 2400주(31억여 원)를 증여했고, 작년 5월 서울 동대문구 전농동 재개발 예정지 주택도 이 후보자의 차남에게 증여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KSM is a 'family company' operated by the brother of the nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho. The opposition has also raised suspicions that the nominee, during her time as a lawmaker, engaged in preferential legislation supporting specialized parts and materials companies like KSM. However, it was reported that as of the night of the 18th, the nominee's side had not submitted documents related to her sons, such as employment records, military service records, or gift tax payment details. (KSM은 이 후보자 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관의 동생이 운영 중인 ‘가족 회사’다. 야당은 이 후보자가 의원 시절 KSM 같은 부품·소재 전문 기업을 지원하는 특혜성 입법에 나섰다는 의혹도 제기했다. 하지만 이 후보자 측은 18일 밤까지 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 아들들과 관련 자료들은 제출하지 않은 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's mother-in-law is also the founder of a social welfare corporation in Ulsan. According to People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young's office, this social welfare corporation received a total of 56.9 billion won in support from the Ulsan Office of Education from 2016 to 2025 under the title of 'private school financial deficit subsidy'. There are also suspicions that employees of this corporation were mobilized for the nominee's intra-party election campaign in 2010. In 2024, a case of habitual abuse of disabled persons occurred at a social welfare facility operated by this corporation, causing controversy in the Ulsan region. (이 후보자의 시어머니는 울산의 모 사회복지법인 설립자이기도 하다. 국민의힘 박수영 의원실에 따르면, 이 사회복지법인은 2016~2025년 울산교육청에서 ‘사립학교 재정 결함 보조금’ 명목으로 총 569억원을 지원받았다. 이 법인 직원들은 2010년 이 후보자의 당내 선거 운동에 동원됐다는 의혹도 있다. 지난 2024년 이 법인이 운영하는 사회복지시설에서 장애인 상습 학대 사건이 벌어져 울산 지역에서 논란이 일었다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/B3PLJEM76BAHTA3Y3U7PDQTOUY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBIZ5ZC6SZFCXELBSVLAAYELWM.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Breaches 4800, Yet President Lee's Approval Rating Drops to 53%... "Due to Rift Between Party and Government, Bribery Allegations in Nominations" (코스피 4800 돌파에도 李대통령 지지율 하락해 53%…“당정 엇박자·공천 뇌물 논란 탓" )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A public opinion poll released on the 19th showed that President Lee Jae-myung's job approval rating has turned downward for the first time in three weeks, standing at 53.1%. (이재명 대통령의 국정 수행 지지도가 53.1%로 3주 만에 하락세로 돌아섰다는 여론조사 결과가 19일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a survey conducted by Realmeter for the Energy Economy News from the 12th to the 16th, targeting 2,516 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, 53.1% of respondents gave a positive assessment of President Lee's job performance. This is a decrease of 3.7 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week. (리얼미터가 에너지경제신문 의뢰로 지난 12∼16일 전국 18세 이상 2516명을 대상으로 조사한 결과 이 대통령의 국정 수행을 긍정 평가한 응답자는 53.1%로 집계됐다. 지난주보다 3.7%포인트(p) 낮은 수치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negative assessments rose to 42.2%, up 4.4 percentage points from the previous survey. (부정 평가는 42.2%로 지난 조사 대비 4.4%p 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter analyzed, "Despite economic and diplomatic achievements such as the KOSPI breaking through the 4800 mark and the Korea-Japan summit, the approval rating showed a downward trend as controversies over morality overlapped, including the exposure of disagreements between the ruling party and the government regarding the prosecution reform bill and allegations of nomination bribes and illegal election funds (bribery) involving ruling party figures." (리얼미터는 “코스피 4800선 돌파와 한일 정상회담 등 경제·외교 성과가 있었는데도 정부의 검찰 개혁안을 둘러싼 당정 이견 노출과 여권 인사들의 공천 헌금·선거 불법 자금(뇌물) 의혹 등 도덕성 논란이 겹치며 지지율이 하락세를 보였다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a party support survey conducted from the 15th to the 16th of last month, targeting 1,004 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, the Democratic Party of Korea showed a support rate of 42.5%, while the People Power Party showed 37.0%. (지난달 15∼16일 전국 18세 이상 1004명을 대상으로 한 정당 지지도 조사에서는 더불어민주당이 42.5%, 국민의힘은 37.0%의 지지율을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party fell by 5.3 percentage points compared to the previous week, showing a decline for the first time in four weeks, while the People Power Party rose by 3.5 percentage points, showing a rebound for the first time in four weeks. (민주당은 지난주 대비 5.3%p 하락하며 4주 만에 하락세를 보인 반면 국민의힘은 3.5%p 상승하며 4주 만에 반등세를 나타냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform New Party was at 3.3%, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party at 2.5%, and the Progressive Party at 1.7%. The non-partisan group was 11.5%. (개혁신당은 3.3%, 조국혁신당은 2.5%, 진보당은 1.7%로 나타났다. 무당층은 11.5%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter explained, "It is judged that the Democratic Party's decline widened as controversies over morality grew with the full-scale investigation into the nomination bribery allegations involving lawmakers Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi, compounded by intra-party conflict due to criticism from hardliners within the party regarding the Serious Crime Investigation Office (SCIO) and the Public Prosecution Service Act." (리얼미터는 “민주당은 강선우·김병기 의원 공천 헌금 의혹 수사 본격화로 도덕성 논란이 커진 데다 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청법을 둘러싼 당내 강경파의 비판으로 당정 갈등이 겹치며 하락 폭을 키운 것으로 판단된다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the People Power Party, it interpreted, "It appears that the rebound in support was led by the consolidation of traditional supporters, such as those in the Daegu/Gyeongbuk region and conservative groups, due to the special prosecutor's demand for the death penalty for former President Yoon Suk-yeol and the controversy over the expulsion of Han Dong-hoon." (국민의힘에 대해서는 “특검의 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형과 한동훈 제명 논란으로 대구·경북과 보수층 등 전통 지지층이 결집해 지지율 반등을 이끈 것으로 보인다”고 해석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The margin of error for the presidential job approval rating survey is ±2.0 percentage points at a 95% confidence level, and for the party support survey, it is ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level. (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사의 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±2.0%p, 정당 지지도 조사 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±3.1%p다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response rate for the presidential job approval rating survey was 4.5%, and for the party support survey, it was 3.8%. For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사 응답률은 4.5%, 정당 지지도 조사 응답률은 3.8%였다. 자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 홈페이지 참조.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:09:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The 'Jang Dong-hyeok vs. Han Dong-hoon' Conflict Comes at a Staggering Cost... It's Not a Personal Feud but a War Over the Party's Identity (막대한 비용 치를 ‘장동혁·한동훈’ 갈등...개인 싸움 아니라 黨 정체성 전쟁)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/19/DX5GJFRKHRADREMP6DVTA6E3VU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The 'Jang Dong-hyeok vs. Han Dong-hoon' Conflict Comes at a Staggering Cost... It's Not a Personal Feud but a War Over the Party's Identity (막대한 비용 치를 ‘장동혁·한동훈’ 갈등...개인 싸움 아니라 黨 정체성 전쟁)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/V672WGXQFBFCJJ6HR6ZXMSLXXY.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party's internal affairs are engulfed in a whirlwind due to the clash between Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok and former Chairman Han Dong-hoon. This is not merely a personal conflict or a leadership struggle. It is a structural turning point that will determine what kind of party the People Power Party will remain. Big data analysis indicates it is perceived as a critical juncture that will dictate the party's identity, competitiveness in local elections, and even its future survival strategy. (국민의힘 내부는 장동혁 대표와 한동훈 전 대표 충돌로 소용돌이에 휩싸여 있다. 이는 단순한 개인 간 갈등이나 리더십 다툼이 아니다. 국민의힘이 어떤 정당으로 남을 것인가를 가르는 구조적 분기점이다. 당의 정체성과 지방선거 경쟁력, 나아가 향후 생존 전략을 좌우할 중대 국면으로 인식한다는 게 빅 데이터 분석이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a keyword association analysis by SomeTrend (January 1-15, 2026), keywords surrounding Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok were primarily institution and tactics-focused words such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'special prosecution bill', 'proposal', 'promotion', 'strategy', 'operation', 'state administration'&lt;/mark&gt;. (썸트렌드(SomeTrend) 연관어 분석(2026년 1월 1~15일)에서 장동혁 대표를 둘러싼 키워드는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘특검법’, ‘제안’, ‘추진’, ‘전략’, ‘운영’, ‘국정운영’ &lt;/mark&gt;등 제도·전술 중심 단어들이 주를 이룬다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This signifies that Chairman Jang is positioning himself as a "practical leader at the forefront of political struggle." The frequent detection of words like 'special prosecution' and 'promotion' suggests his intention to use the Unified Church special prosecution not as a simple defensive argument but as an offensive tool—a card to shift the political landscape—is gaining traction. (장 대표가 자신을 “정치적 투쟁의 전면에 선 실천형 리더”로 포지셔닝하고 있다는 의미다. ‘특검’, ‘추진’이라는 단어가 많이 포착된 건 통일교 특검을 단순한 방어 논리가 아니라 공격 수단, 즉 정국 전환용 카드로 활용하고자 하는 의도가 먹히고 있다는 의미다..)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, keywords associated with former Chairman Han centered on words evoking conflict and division, such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'condemnation', 'outrage', 'riot', 'criticism', 'conflict', 'National Election Commission', 'Daegu Mayor', 'Jo Eun-seok'&lt;/mark&gt;. The image is more of conflict than unity. (반면 한 전 대표 연관어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘단죄’, ‘격앙’, ‘폭동’, ‘비판’, ‘갈등’, ‘중앙선관위’, ‘대구시장’, ‘조은석’&lt;/mark&gt; 등 충돌과 분열을 연상시키는 단어가 중심이다. 통합 보다는 갈등의 이미지가 강하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this indicates a fundamental clash over the party's direction and strategy. Big data points out that Chairman Jang insists on a 'hardline, rallying-type struggle,' while former Chairman Han does not agree with that struggle. (결국 이는 당의 노선과 전략을 둘러싼 근본적 충돌이 깔려 있다. 장 대표는 ‘강경 결집형 투쟁’을 고집하고, 한 전 대표는 그 투쟁에 동의하지 않고 있는 것으로 빅 데이터는 지적하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Big data sentiment keyword analysis (January 15) shows a similar pattern. The sentiment words appearing alongside 'Jang Dong-hyeok hunger strike' were mostly negative terms like &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'suspicion', 'criticism', 'money/gifts', 'illegal funds', but simultaneously, positive or neutral words like 'defend', 'essential', 'noteworthy' also stand out.&lt;/mark&gt; This suggests that while the hunger strike itself is controversial, there is an atmosphere acknowledging it has a certain justification and sincerity as a political act. (빅데이터 감성 연관어 분석(1월 15일)도 비슷하다. ‘장동혁 단식’과 함께 나타난 감성어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘의혹’, ‘비판’, ‘금품’, ‘불법자금’과 같은 부정어가 다수이지만, 동시에 ‘옹호하다’, ‘필수’, ‘주목되다’라는 긍정 또는 중립적 단어도 눈에 띈다.&lt;/mark&gt; 단식 자체는 논란의 여지가 있지만 정치적 행위로서 일정한 명분과 진정성을 인정하는 분위기가 있다는 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, sentiment words combined with 'Han Dong-hoon expulsion' were largely negative, such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'criticize', 'controversy', 'conflict', 'backlash', 'mutual destruction', 'collapse'&lt;/mark&gt;. This implies that discussions surrounding former Chairman Han are solidifying into a framework of exhausting conflict. (반면 ‘한동훈 제명’과 결합한 감성어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘비판하다’, ‘논란’, ‘갈등’, ‘반발하다’, ‘공멸’, ‘무너지다’ 등 부정적인 단어들이 많다.&lt;/mark&gt; 이는 한 전 대표를 둘러싼 논의가 소모적인 갈등 프레임으로 굳어지고 있다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public opinion perceives Chairman Jang's hunger strike as a "politically meaningful attempt" beyond simply being right or wrong. In contrast, former Chairman Han is still perceived as a "cause of conflict." Although former Chairman Han officially apologized on the 18th regarding the core conflict—the party bulletin board controversy—it remains to be seen if this will change the current trend. (여론은 장 대표 단식에 대해 “옳고 그름”을 넘어서 “정치적으로 의미 있는 시도”로 받아들인다. 반면 한 전 대표는 여전히 “갈등의 원인”으로 인식하고 있다. 18일 한 전 대표가 갈등의 핵심인 당내 게시판 논란에 대해 공식 사과하긴 했지만 이런 흐름을 바꿀 수 있을 지는 두고 봐야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Jang's hunger strike is assessed to have, for now, brought the issues of the Unified Church special prosecution and the investigation into Democratic Party nomination funds to the forefront. The hunger strike politically aims for two effects. (장 대표의 단식은 일단 통일교 특검과 민주당 공천헌금 수사를 전면으로 끌어올리는 효과를 냈다고 조사됐다. 단식은 정치적으로 두 가지 효과를 노린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok's hunger strike will become a decisive turning point in pushing through the Unified Church special prosecution and the investigation into Democratic Party nomination funds is still unknown. &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;However, judging solely from big data trends, it appears to have succeeded to some extent at least in reviving and setting the agenda in motion again.&lt;/mark&gt; (장동혁 대표의 단식이 통일교 특검 관철과 민주당 공천헌금 수사에서 결정적 전환점이 될 수 있을지는 아직 미지수다. &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;다만 빅데이터 흐름만 놓고 보면, 최소한 의제를 다시 살아 움직이게 만드는 데에는 어느 정도 성공한 것으로 보인다.&lt;/mark&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But for this agenda shift to lead to tangible results, strategic follow-up measures at the party level are essential. In the context of local elections, it could create a simple yet powerful framework of "morality vs. corruption." (그러나 이 의제 전환이 실질적 성과로 이어지기 위해서는 당 차원의 전략적 후속 조치가 필수적이다. 지방선거 국면에서 “도덕성 대 부패”라는 단순하면서 강력한 구도를 만들 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussions on expelling former Chairman Han will have complex implications for the local elections and the future of the People Power Party. In the short term, it could simplify the party's message by removing a source of conflict and induce consolidation among hardline supporters. However, big data reveals words like 'backlash' and 'mutual destruction,' meaning it could come at a high price. (한 전 대표 제명 논의는 지방선거와 국민의힘 미래에 복합적인 영향을 미칠 것이다. 단기적으로는 갈등 요인을 제거함으로써 당의 메시지를 단순화하고, 강경 지지층의 결집을 유도할 수 있다. 하지만 빅데이터는 ‘반발’, ‘공멸’이란 단어를 드러낸다. 비싼 대가를 치를 수 있다는 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the mid-to-long term, there is a risk of losing centrist and non-partisan voters. If the expulsion is seen as a mere emotional decision, it could become a fatal weakness in closely contested metropolitan and swing regions during the local elections. (중장기적으로는 중도층과 무당층의 이탈 위험이 존재한다. 제명이 단순한 감정적 결단으로 비친다면, 지방선거에서 수도권과 접전 지역에서 치명적 약점으로 작용할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conflict, hunger strike, and expulsion controversy are highly likely to cause short-term fluctuations in the People Power Party's approval ratings. While the core support base may consolidate, fatigue among centrist voters is also growing. The appearance of sentiment words like 'concern' and 'collapse' in big data well illustrates this dual trend. Local elections cannot be won by consolidation alone. Ultimately, the key is whether the People Power Party can connect this situation to a strategy of "internal cleanup followed by external offensive." (이번 충돌과 단식, 제명 논란은 국민의힘 지지율을 단기적으로 출렁이게 할 가능성이 크다. 핵심 지지층은 결집할 수 있지만, 중도층의 피로감 또한 커지고 있다. 빅데이터 감성어에서 ‘우려’, ‘무너지다’라는 표현이 등장한 것은 이러한 이중적 흐름을 잘 보여준다. 지방선거는 결집만으로 이길 수 있는 선거가 아니다. 결국 국민의힘이 이번 사태를 “내부 정리 후 외부 공세”라는 전략으로 연결할 수 있느냐가 관건이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Jang Dong-hyeok and Han Dong-hoon conflict is forcing a choice upon the People Power Party. To mend the conflict or to clarify its direction through the conflict. Chairman Jang's hunger strike is a risky gamble, but it could also be a final, decisive move. Former Chairman Han's expulsion could also be a signal flare for cleanup or a fuse for division.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (장동혁과 한동훈 충돌은 국민의힘에 선택을 강요하고 있다. 갈등을 봉합할 것인가, 아니면 갈등을 통해 노선을 명확히 할 것인가. 장 대표의 단식은 위험한 도박이지만, 마지막 승부수일 수도 있다. 한 전 대표의 제명 역시 정리의 신호탄이 될 수도, 분열의 도화선이 될 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/19/DX5GJFRKHRADREMP6DVTA6E3VU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/V672WGXQFBFCJJ6HR6ZXMSLXXY.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jae-won Joins Hunger Strike in Solidarity with Jang Dong-hyk on 'Day 5'... Lee Jun-seok to Return Early (김재원, ‘단식 5일차’ 장동혁 옆에서 동조 단식...이준석은 조기 귀국)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyk continues his hunger strike for the fifth day, demanding the Democratic Party of Korea accept a special counsel probe into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won also began a solidarity hunger strike on the 19th. Kim is the first from the opposition camp to join a solidarity hunger strike in support of Leader Jang. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 더불어민주당의 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 농성을 벌이고 있는 가운데, 김재원 최고위원도 19일 동조 단식에 들어갔다. 야권에서 장 대표에 호응해 동조 단식에 나선 것은 김 최고위원이 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim posted on Facebook that day, "I've come to the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall. I begin my hunger strike struggle today." In a Facebook post the previous day, he had stated, "Leader Jang Dong-hyk's hunger strike, confronting the Lee Jae-myung administration with his whole body, continues into its fourth day," and added, "I will also participate in the hunger strike starting tomorrow (19th) at 6 AM at the National Assembly Rotunda Hall." At the time, Kim said, "I had postponed it due to unavoidable schedules until now," and added, "I don't know how long my frail body can endure, but I only hope it provides some comfort to Leader Jang." (김 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에 “국회 로텐더홀에 왔다. 오늘부터 단식 투쟁 시작한다”고 밝혔다. 그는 전날에도 페이스북 글에서 “이재명 정권에 온몸으로 맞서는 장동혁 대표의 단식이 4일째 계속되고 있다”면서 “저도 내일(19일) 오전 6시부터 국회 로텐더홀에서 단식에 참여하겠다”고 했었다. 당시 김 최고위원은 “그간 피치 못할 일정으로 미뤄왔다”며 “부실한 몸으로 얼마 버틸지 모르겠지만 장 대표에게 조금이라도 위안이 되길 바랄 뿐”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, who had been on parliamentary diplomacy activities in Mexico and Guatemala along with National Assembly Deputy Speaker Joo Ho-young, is scheduled to return early on the 21st. Leader Lee plans to cooperate with Leader Jang to urge the Democratic Party to accept the dual special counsel probes. However, it is reported that he is not currently considering a hunger strike. (주호영 국회부의장과 함께 멕시코·과테말라로 의원 외교 활동을 떠났던 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 귀국 일정을 앞당겨 21일 귀국할 예정이다. 이 대표는 장 대표와 공조해 민주당에 쌍특검 수용을 촉구할 방침이다. 다만 현재로선 단식을 고려하지는 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post the previous day, Leader Jang expressed his determination to continue the hunger strike, stating, "Since yesterday, a single rose has been guarding my side," and "It was prepared for death from the moment it came to my side. I must not collapse first." (장 대표는 전날 페이스북 글에서 “어제부터 장미 한 송이가 내 곁을 지키고 있다”면서 “내 곁에 올 때부터 죽기를 각오했다. 내가 먼저 쓰러지면 안 된다”고 단식 의지를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:24:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae: "Jang Dong-hyeok Must End His Groundless Hunger Strike... The People Power Party Should Be Prostrating in Repentance" (정청래 “장동혁, 명분 없는 단식 중단해야...국힘은 석고대죄할 때”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, urged Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party who is on the fifth day of a hunger strike demanding a special investigation into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, saying, "End your groundless hunger strike quickly." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 통일교·공천 헌금 특검을 요구하며 5일째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 향해 19일 “명분 없는 단식을 얼른 중단하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the party's Supreme Council meeting held at the National Assembly that day, Representative Chung stated, "It is not the time for the People Power Party to be on a hunger strike; it is the time for them to be prostrating in repentance." (정 대표는 이날 국회에서 열린 당 최고위원회의에서 “국민의힘은 지금 단식할 때가 아니라 석고대죄할 때”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung said, "Having experienced a 24-day hunger strike myself at Gwanghwamun Square during the Sewol Ferry incident, I know very well how difficult a hunger strike is." He added, "From my experience, the periods from the 3rd to 4th day, the 7th to 8th day, and the 14th to 15th day are particularly tough. Representative Jang, you must be having a very hard time, so please end your groundless hunger strike quickly." He further advised, "Health is the most important thing. Eat and then fight." (정 대표는 “저도 세월호 때 광화문 광장에서 24일간 단식을 해봐서 단식이 얼마나 힘든가를 잘 알고 있다”면서 “제 경험으로는 3일에서 4일 넘어갈 때, 7일에서 8일 넘어갈 때, 14일에서 15일 넘어갈 때가 참 힘들더라. 장 대표님, 많이 힘드실 텐데 명분 없는 단식은 얼른 중단하시라”고 했다. 정 대표는 이어 “건강이 최고”라면서 “밥 먹고 싸우세요”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Representative Chung mentioned, "The law to establish a special tribunal for rebellion cases has already been passed and is awaiting implementation," and stated, "We will also pass judicial reform measures one by one without fail. We will pass legislation on the crime of distorting the law, judicial review petitions, and increasing the number of Supreme Court justices without any setbacks." (한편 정 대표는 “이미 내란재판부 설치법이 통과돼 시행을 앞두고 있다”면서 “사법 개혁도 따박따박 통과시키겠다. 법 왜곡죄, 재판소원, 대법관 증원 등 차질 없이 통과시킬 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the first-instance court's sentencing of former President Yoon Suk-yeol to five years in prison on charges of obstructing an arrest, Representative Chung said, "The outcome of a five-year prison sentence is somewhat disappointing," but added, "However, since you can't be full from the first bite, I evaluate this as our society taking its first step toward restoring democracy and constitutional order." Addressing former President Yoon, Representative Chung said, "An unrepentant, shameless, and ignorant ringleader of rebellion without any reflection or remorse must be permanently isolated from our society." (정 대표는 1심 법원이 윤석열 전 대통령의 체포 방해 혐의에 대해 징역 5년을 선고한 데 대해서는 “징역 5년이라는 결과는 다소 아쉽다”면서도 “무엇이든 첫술에 배부를 수는 없기에 우리 사회가 민주주의와 헌정 질서를 회복하는 첫걸음을 뗀 것이라고 평가한다”고 했다. 정 대표는 윤 전 대통령을 향해서는 “반성과 성찰이 없는 뻔뻔하고 무식한 내란 수괴는 우리 사회에서 영원히 격리시켜야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:41:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>