<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:08:11 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Kim Eo-jun includes Prime Minister Kim in Seoul mayoral election poll... Prime Minister's Office calls it "highly inappropriate" (서울시장 선거 여론조사에 金총리 넣은 김어준… 총리실 “매우 부적절”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/23/LN7GXGT65ZH53CUVISRFXN7HWM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Eo-jun includes Prime Minister Kim in Seoul mayoral election poll... Prime Minister's Office calls it "highly inappropriate" (서울시장 선거 여론조사에 金총리 넣은 김어준… 총리실 “매우 부적절”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5YB27AHZDJPL3HUWHAF7V4TO5M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 23rd, the Office of the Prime Minister stated that it was "highly inappropriate and crossed a line" for broadcaster Kim Eo-jun's polling agency to include Prime Minister Kim Min-seok in a suitability poll for candidates in the June 3 local elections for Seoul mayor. (국무총리실은 23일 방송인 김어준씨의 여론조사 업체가 6·3 지방선거 서울시장 선거 후보 적합도 여론조사에 김민석 국무총리를 포함한 데 대해 “매우 부적절하며 금도를 넘은 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Eo-jun revealed the results of a poll conducted by Yeonjosa-kkot (Poll Flower) from the 19th to the 21st on his YouTube broadcast 'Kim Eo-jun's News Factory, where humility is difficult' this morning. (김어준씨는 이날 오전 자신의 유튜브 방송 ‘김어준의 겸손은 힘들다 뉴스공장’에서 여론조사꽃이 지난 19~21일 시행한 여론조사 결과를 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the survey question asking, 'Who do you think is the most suitable figure as a progressive camp candidate for Seoul mayor?', Prime Minister Kim received 7.3%, following Jeong Won-o, the head of Seoul's Seongdong District Office (20.9%), and Park Joo-min, a member of the Democratic Party of Korea (10.0%). In hypothetical two-way matchups, he led against Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon 48.6% to 32.6%, and against People Power Party lawmaker Na Kyung-won 51.2% to 27.4%. (김 총리는 ‘진보 진영의 서울시장 후보로 가장 적합한 인물은 누구라고 생각하느냐’는 조사 문항에서 정원오 서울 성동구청장(20.9%), 박주민 더불어민주당 의원(10.0%)에 이어 7.3%를 얻었다. 오세훈 서울시장과의 가상 양자 대결에서는 48.6% 대 32.6%, 나경원 국민의힘 의원과의 가상 양자 대결에서는 51.2% 대 27.4%로 앞선 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim said, "(Prime Minister Kim) himself asked not to be included (in the poll), but this is the first local election under this administration, and when you become a politician of Prime Minister Kim's stature, you can't always have things your way," adding, "We cannot rule out the possibility that he might suddenly be nominated (as a Seoul mayoral candidate) at some point." (김씨는 “(김 총리) 본인이 (여론조사에) 넣지 말아 달라 했지만, 정권 첫 번째 지방선거인데 김 총리 정도의 정치인이 되면 본인 뜻대로 못 한다”며 “어느 순간 갑자기 (서울시장 후보로) 차출될 가능성을 배제할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the Prime Minister's Office sent a text message to reporters stating, "We express deep regret regarding some polls that continue to include the Prime Minister despite requests to exclude him from Seoul mayoral election polls." (이에 대해 총리실은 기자들에게 문자 메시지를 보내 “서울시장 선거 여론조사에 총리를 포함시키지 말아 달라는 요청에도 불구하고 계속 포함시키는 일부 조사에 대해 매우 심각한 유감을 표시한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister's Office said, "Continuing to include (Prime Minister Kim) in polls against his will, even though there are other competitive candidates, is highly inappropriate and crosses a line for the polling organization," and "we once again strongly request that the Prime Minister not be included in polls related to the Seoul mayoral election." (총리실은 “이미 경쟁력을 갖는 다른 후보들이 있음에도 (김 총리를) 본인의 의사에 반해 계속 조사에 포함시키는 것은 매우 부적절하며, 조사 기관의 금도를 넘은 것”이라며 “서울시장 관련 조사에 총리를 포함시키지 말 것을 다시 강력히 요청한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 1st of last month, the Prime Minister's Office sent official letters to various media outlets and polling agencies stating, "At this point, it is not appropriate for the Prime Minister to be included in Seoul mayoral election polls," and requested that "Prime Minister Kim be excluded from poll subjects." At the time, the Prime Minister's Office explained that Prime Minister Kim had instructed the sending of these letters. (총리실은 지난달 1일 각 언론사와 여론조사 업체에 공문을 보내 “현 시점에 총리가 서울시장 선거 여론조사에 포함되는 것은 적절치 않다”며 “여론조사 대상에서 김 총리를 제외해 달라”고 했었다. 당시 총리실은 이 공문 발송과 관련해 김 총리의 지시가 있었다고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This poll by Yeonjosa-kkot was conducted over three days from the 19th to the 21st via wireless telephone interviews with 2,008 adults aged 18 and over living in Seoul. The response rate was 9.0%, and the margin of error is ±2.2 percentage points at a 95% confidence level. For details, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission. (여론조사꽃의 이번 조사는 지난 19~21일 사흘간 서울시에 사는 18세 이상 2008명을 대상으로 무선 전화 인터뷰 방식으로 진행됐다. 응답률은 9.0%, 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에서 ±2.2%포인트다. 자세한 사항은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 홈페이지를 참조하면 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/23/LN7GXGT65ZH53CUVISRFXN7HWM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5YB27AHZDJPL3HUWHAF7V4TO5M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:59:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Chung Cheong-rae's Merger Proposal' Sparks Backlash; Several Ruling Party Supreme Council Members Skip Meeting (‘정청래 합당 제안’ 반발 與최고위원들, 최고위 줄줄이 불참)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/3IONLPT4GNAM7AE3WSH7RXYXC4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;'Chung Cheong-rae's Merger Proposal' Sparks Backlash; Several Ruling Party Supreme Council Members Skip Meeting (‘정청래 합당 제안’ 반발 與최고위원들, 최고위 줄줄이 불참)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NM5HCT5VNNLRRPTULP3G6SWSVE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae held a field Supreme Council meeting in Jincheon, North Chungcheong Province on the 23rd, several Supreme Council members were absent from the meeting. (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 23일 충북 진천에서 현장 최고위원회의를 여는 가운데, 최고위원 여러 명이 최고위에 불참했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Chung visited the Jincheon National Training Center in North Chungcheong Province on the 23rd ahead of the Milan-Cortina d'Ampezzo Winter Olympics opening next month on the 7th. However, Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo announced to the press that day, "I will not attend due to personal schedules already arranged before the field Supreme Council meeting." Supreme Council members Kang Deuk-gu and Hwang Myeong-seon were also reported to have not attended, citing schedule conflicts among other reasons. (정 대표는 다음 달 7일부터 열리는 밀라노·코르티나담페초 동계 올림픽을 앞두고 23일 충북 진천선수촌을 찾았다. 그러나 이언주 최고위원은 이날 언론 공지를 통해 “현장 최고위 이전에 이미 잡혀있던 개인 일정 등의 사유로 불참한다”고 했다. 강득구 최고위원과 황명선 최고위원도 일정 등을 이유로 참석하지 않은 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is known that the three Supreme Council members had also expressed concerns about the matter during a closed-door Supreme Council meeting held the previous day, before Leader Chung publicly proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. (세 최고위원은 전날 정 대표가 조국혁신당과의 합당을 공개 제안하기에 앞서 열린 비공개 최고위원회의에서도 해당 사안에 대해 우려를 제기한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Leader Chung held a press conference to propose the merger, Supreme Council member Kang posted on Facebook, "Watching the process of Leader Chung's proposal to merge with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, I felt a deep sense of shame and severe humiliation, thinking, 'Did I become a Supreme Council member for this?', 'What is the role of a Supreme Council member?', 'How did our Democratic Party come to this?'" (정 대표가 합당 제안 기자회견을 연 뒤 강 최고위원은 페이스북에서 “정 대표의 조국혁신당 합당 제안 과정을 바라보며 ‘이러려고 최고위원이 됐나’ ‘최고위원의 역할이 무엇인가’ ‘우리 민주당이 어떻게 이렇게 됐나’라는 깊은 자괴감과 함께 심한 모멸감을 느꼈다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Hwang said, "While advocating for a 'party where members are the masters' and pushing for a one-member-one-vote system, it is a clear self-contradiction to exclude party members from the party's major decision-making processes." (황 최고위원은 “‘당원이 주인인 정당’을 내세워 1인 1표제를 추진하면서, 정작 당의 중대한 의사결정에서 당원을 배제하는 것은 명백한 자기모순”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Lee stated in a broadcast interview, "It is right to hold a national convention to directly ask (about the merger intention) and ask about (Leader Chung Cheong-rae's) resignation or continuation," adding, "I see the situation heading towards asking for a vote of confidence." (이 최고위원은 방송 인터뷰에서 “전당대회를 열어 (합당 의사를) 직접 물어보고 (정청래 대표의) 진퇴를 묻는 것이 맞다”며 “재신임을 묻는 상황으로 가고 있다고 본다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/3IONLPT4GNAM7AE3WSH7RXYXC4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NM5HCT5VNNLRRPTULP3G6SWSVE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:21:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>June 3 Local Election Spending Limits Confirmed... Gyeonggi Governor 4.9 Billion Won, Seoul Mayor 3.7 Billion Won (6·3 지방선거 선거비 한도 확정… 경기지사 49억, 서울시장 37억)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/5ONGXW5K7ZDOHFZF74IWM6GRLA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;June 3 Local Election Spending Limits Confirmed... Gyeonggi Governor 4.9 Billion Won, Seoul Mayor 3.7 Billion Won (6·3 지방선거 선거비 한도 확정… 경기지사 49억, 서울시장 37억)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PJQ2PH72U5NNNC2H7HSDDUAHZI.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spending limit for candidates running for metropolitan city and provincial governors in the June 3 local elections has been set at an average of 1.587 billion won. (6·3 지방선거에서 시도지사 후보들이 쓸 수 있는 선거비 한도가 평균 15억8700만원으로 정해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Election Commission announced on the 23rd the 'election expense limit,' which is the maximum amount candidates in the local elections can spend for their campaigns. The election expense limit varies depending on factors such as the population and the number of towns, townships, and neighborhoods in each electoral district. Due to factors like inflation, the limit has increased by an average of 8.3% compared to the 2022 local elections. (중앙선거관리위원회는 23일 지방선거 후보자들이 선거운동을 위해 쓸 수 있는 비용의 한도액인 ‘선거비용 제한액’을 공고했다. 선거비용 제한액은 각 선거구의 인구수와 읍·면·동수 등에 따라 달라진다. 물가 상승 등으로 2022년 지방선거 때보다 평균 8.3% 늘었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spending limit for metropolitan city and provincial governor candidates averages 1.587 billion won. For a candidate running in Gyeonggi Province, which has the largest population, the limit is 4.945 billion won; for a candidate running for Seoul Mayor, it is 3.721 billion won; and for a candidate running in Sejong City, which has the smallest population, it is 389 million won. (시도지사 후보자의 선거비 한도는 평균 15억8700만원으로, 인구가 가장 많은 경기도에 출마하는 경우 49억4500만원, 서울시장으로 출마하는 경우 37억2100만원, 인구가 가장 적은 세종시에 출마하는 경우 3억8900만원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spending limit for superintendent of education candidates averages 1.586 billion won. For a candidate running in Gyeonggi Province, the limit is 4.945 billion won, and for a candidate in Sejong City, it is 389 million won. (교육감 후보자의 선거비 한도는 평균 15억8600만원으로, 경기도에 출마하는 경우 49억4500만원, 세종시에 출마하는 경우 3억8900만원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The spending limit for candidates running for heads of basic local governments, such as district chiefs, city mayors, and county chiefs, averages 184 million won. A candidate running in Suwon City can spend up to 464 million won, while a candidate in Ulleung County can spend up to 109 million won. (구청장·시장·군수 등 기초자치단체장 선거 후보자의 선거비 한도는 평균 1억8400만원이다. 수원시 출마자는 4억6400만원, 울릉군 출마자는 1억900만원까지 쓸 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For metropolitan and provincial councilor candidates, district candidates can spend an average of 56 million won, while proportional representation candidates can spend an average of 218 million won. For district, city, and county councilor candidates, district candidates have an average limit of 48 million won, and proportional representation candidates have an average limit of 57 million won. (시·도의원 후보자는 지역구 출마자의 경우 평균 5600만원, 비례대표 후보인 경우 평균 2억1800만원까지 쓸 수 있다. 구·시·군의원 후보자는 지역구는 평균 4800만원, 비례대표는 평균 5700만원이 한도다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If a candidate spends election expenses within this limit, they can be fully reimbursed by the state if they are elected or receive 15% or more of the votes. If the vote share is 10% or more but less than 15%, half of the expenses are reimbursed. For election expenses incurred by local council proportional representation candidates, full reimbursement is provided to the candidates on the proportional candidate list only if at least one candidate from that list is elected. (후보자가 이 한도 내에서 쓴 선거비용은 후보자가 당선되거나 15% 이상 득표한 경우 전액을 국가로부터 보전받을 수 있다. 득표율이 10% 이상 15% 미만인 경우에는 절반을 보전받는다. 지방의회 비례대표 후보자들이 쓴 선거비용은 해당 비례 후보 명부에서 당선자가 1명 이상 나온 경우에 한해, 명부에 있는 후보자들이 전액을 보전받는다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/5ONGXW5K7ZDOHFZF74IWM6GRLA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PJQ2PH72U5NNNC2H7HSDDUAHZI.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:24:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee's Approval Rating at 61%... Democratic Party 43%, People Power Party 22% [Gallup Korea] (李 대통령 지지율 61%…민주 43%·국힘 22% [한국갤럽])</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/KSE2KIJT4BDGTIFLZF2MGZF3AE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee's Approval Rating at 61%... Democratic Party 43%, People Power Party 22% [Gallup Korea] (李 대통령 지지율 61%…민주 43%·국힘 22% [한국갤럽])&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSGCODGGYYTIMBUGIYTMNZYGM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A public opinion poll released on the 23rd showed that President Lee Jae-myung's approval rating for state affairs rose by 3 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week, reaching 61%. The approval rating for the Democratic Party of Korea, which proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, increased, while the rating for the People Power Party, whose leader Jang Dong-hyeok was on a hunger strike, declined. (이재명 대통령의 국정 지지율이 전주 대비 3%포인트(p) 상승한 61%를 기록했다는 여론조사 결과가 23일 나왔다. 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 더불어민주당 지지율은 상승했고 장동혁 대표 단식 기간이었던 국민의힘 지지율은 하락했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the job performance evaluation of President Lee, conducted by Gallup Korea from the 20th to the 22nd on 1,000 people nationwide and released today, 61% of respondents answered 'doing well'. The response 'doing poorly' recorded 30%, down 2%p from last week. 'Reserved opinion' was 10%. (한국갤럽이 지난 20~22일 전국 1000명을 대상으로 시행해 이날 공개한 이 대통령의 직무 수행 평가에서 응답자의 61%가 ‘잘하고 있다’고 답했다. ‘잘못하고 있다’는 응답은 지난주보다 2%p 하락한 30%를 기록했다. ‘의견 유보’는 10%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding reasons for positive evaluation, diplomacy was the most common at 27%, followed by economy/livelihood (14%) and communication (8%). This is interpreted as reflecting factors such as the KOSPI breaking the 5000 mark during trading on the 22nd. (긍정 평가 이유로는 외교가 27%로 가장 많았고 경제·민생(14%), 소통(8%) 등이 뒤를 이었다. 22일 장중 5000선을 돌파한 코스피 상황 등이 반영된 것으로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party support ratings were 43% for the Democratic Party of Korea and 22% for the People Power Party. Compared to the previous week, the Democratic Party rose by 2%p and the People Power Party fell by 2%p. Consequently, the gap between the two parties widened to 21%p, the largest since the Jeong Cheong-rae/Jang Dong-hyeok leadership system was established at the end of August. (정당 지지도는 더불어민주당이 43%, 국민의힘이 22%를 각각 기록했다. 전주 대비 민주당은 2%p 상승했고 국민의힘은 2%p 하락했다. 이로써 양당 간 격차는 21%p로 지난 8월 말 정청래·장동혁 체제가 들어선 이후 최대치로 벌어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, regarding the People Power Party's Ethics Committee's decision to expel former party leader Han Dong-hoon, 33% responded it was 'appropriate', 34% said it was 'inappropriate', and 33% reserved their opinion. Among People Power Party supporters, 48% answered 'appropriate' and 35% answered 'inappropriate'. (한편 국민의힘 윤리위원회가 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표를 제명 결정한 데 대해서는 ‘적절하다’는 응답이 33%, ‘적절하지 않다’는 의견이 34%로 나타났다. 의견 유보는 33%였다. 국민의힘 지지층에서는 48%가 ‘적절하다’고 답했고 35%가 ‘부적절하다’고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For detailed information, please refer to the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission website. (자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 홈페이지 참고.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/KSE2KIJT4BDGTIFLZF2MGZF3AE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSGCODGGYYTIMBUGIYTMNZYGM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:52:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae on 'Merger Controversy': "If Passed in Full-Member Vote, We Proceed; If Rejected, We Stop" (정청래, ‘합당 논란’에 “전당원 투표 가결되면 가고 부결되면 멈추는 것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/SI3I64SGT5BHZITUJY3USGPZRA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Chung Cheong-rae on 'Merger Controversy': "If Passed in Full-Member Vote, We Proceed; If Rejected, We Stop" (정청래, ‘합당 논란’에 “전당원 투표 가결되면 가고 부결되면 멈추는 것” )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WOT4FJGOVZPQPLJXGFXQ6MNZFE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chung Cheong-rae, leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, stated on the 23rd regarding the issue of merging with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, "If it passes in a full-member vote, we proceed; if it is rejected, we stop." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표는 23일 조국혁신당과 합당 문제에 대해 “전 당원 투표에서 가결되면 가는 것이고 부결되면 멈추는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During an on-site Supreme Council meeting held at the Jincheon National Training Center in North Chungcheong Province that day, Representative Chung said, "Now that the starting bell has rung, the process and the final destination will all be decided through party members' discussions and according to their will." (정 대표는 이날 충북 진천국가대표선수촌에서 열린 현장 최고위원회의에서 “이제 시작 종이 울렸으니 가는 과정과 최종 종착지는 모두 당원들의 토론과 당원들의 뜻에 따라 결정이 될 것”이라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung held a press conference the previous day and abruptly proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. However, within the party, backlash erupted, criticizing the push for proceeding without sufficient consensus-building. (정 대표는 전날 기자회견을 열어 조국혁신당에 합당을 전격 제안했다. 그러나 당내에선 충분한 의견 수렴 없이 추진한다며 반발이 쏟아져 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung said, "It seems many people were surprised and taken aback by my merger proposal yesterday. I am sorry for not being able to fully share it in advance due to various unavoidable circumstances and physical limitations." (정 대표는 “어제 저의 합당 제안으로 놀라고 당황하신 분들이 많았나 보다. 여러 가지 불가피성과 또 물리적 한계 등으로 사전에 충분히 공유해 드리지 못한 부분에 대해서는 송구스럽다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "However, I made this proposal with an apologetic resolve, thinking that if the party leader did not propose it first, it might be impossible time-wise before the local elections. I believe it is a path we must take. Someone had to cut the tape someday." (정 대표는 “그렇지만 이 부분은 당대표가 먼저 제안을 하지 않고서는 지방선거 전에 시간상 불가능할지도 모르겠다는 생각으로 사과할 각오로 제안을 했다”며 “꼭 가야 할 길이라고 생각한다. 언젠가 누군가는 테이프를 끊어야 하는 일”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung stated, "Now, I hope that through sufficient discussion, party members will wisely resolve this issue with their collective intelligence on what is the better path for winning the local elections and for the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration." (정 대표는 “이제 당원들께서 충분한 토론을 통해서 어떤 것이 지방선거 승리를 위해서, 또 이재명 정부 성공을 위해서 더 나은 길인지 당원들의 집단 지성으로 이 문제를 잘 풀어갔으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/SI3I64SGT5BHZITUJY3USGPZRA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WOT4FJGOVZPQPLJXGFXQ6MNZFE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 17:24:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "No Consideration Whatsoever to Extend Capital Gains Tax Exemption for Multiple Homeowners" (李 대통령 “다주택자 양도세 면제 연장, 전혀 고려 안 해”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/IY3CSOD3AFE3NABWQPLHUGZ4HE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "No Consideration Whatsoever to Extend Capital Gains Tax Exemption for Multiple Homeowners" (李 대통령 “다주택자 양도세 면제 연장, 전혀 고려 안 해”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GAYGMMRUMJSTOZJZHA3TGOBWG4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung stated on the 23rd, "We are not considering extending the capital gains tax exemption for multiple homeowners, which expires on May 9, at all." (이재명 대통령이 23일 “이번 5·9 만기인 다주택자 양도세 면제 연장은 전혀 고려하지 않고 있다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his social media that day, President Lee said, "Even a single home is a single home in its own right. If tax adjustments become unavoidable, wouldn't it be fair to treat non-residential and residential properties differently?" revealing his stance. (이 대통령은 이날 자신의 SNS(소셜미디어)에 “1주택도 1주택 나름, 만약 부득이 세제를 손보게 된다면 비거주용과 거주용은 달리 취급해야 공정하지 않나”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'suspension of the additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners' is a system that does not apply the additional tax rate of 20-30 percentage points, added to the basic rate, when a person owning two or more homes in a regulated area disposes of a property. (‘다주택자 양도세 중과 유예’ 제도는 조정 대상 지역 내 주택을 두 채 이상 보유한 사람이 주택을 처분할 경우 기본 세율에 더해지는 20~30%포인트의 가산 세율을 적용하지 않는 제도다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "Not only for multiple homes, but even a single non-residential home, if it's for investment or speculation rather than residence, it seems odd to reduce taxes just because it was held long-term," adding, "The long-term holding special deduction system ends up blocking supply and encouraging speculation." He further noted, "We are not planning to revise the tax system immediately, but it is a topic that should be discussed." (이 대통령은 “다주택은 물론, 비거주 1주택도 주거용 아닌 투자 투기용이라면 장기 보유했다고 세금 감면은 이상해 보인다”며 “장특공제(장기보유특별공제) 제도가 매물을 막고 투기를 권장하는 꼴”이라고 했다. 이어 “당장 세제를 고칠 건 아니지만, 토론해 봐야 할 주제”라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, at his New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee had already remarked, "Why should we reduce taxes for properties held long-term for speculation or investment, which the owner doesn't even live in?" and "It is strange to provide tax benefits simply because speculative real estate, which is undesirable, has been held for a long time." (이미 이 대통령은 지난 21일 신년 기자회견에서 “자기가 살지도 않으면서 투기용 또는 투자용으로 오랫동안 가지고 있다고 왜 세금을 깎아주느냐”며 “바람직하지 않은 투기용 부동산을 오래 보유했다는 이유로 세제 혜택을 주는 건 이상하다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The long-term holding special deduction is a system that deducts a portion of the capital gains if real estate is held for a certain period or longer. For owners of two or more homes, a deduction rate of 20%, up to a maximum of 30%, applies if the property is held for 10 years or more. The additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners refers to applying an additional tax rate to the capital gains tax for multiple homeowners in regulated areas. An additional rate of 20 percentage points applies to owners of two homes, and 30 percentage points to owners of three or more homes. (장특공제는 부동산 일정 기간 이상 보유 시 양도차익의 일부를 공제해 주는 제도다. 2주택 이상 다주택자는 10년 이상 보유 시 20%, 최대 30%의 공제율이 적용된다. 다주택자 양도세 중과 제도란 조정 대상 지역 내 다주택자의 양도소득세에 가산세율을 적용하는 것이다. 2주택자는 20%포인트, 3주택자는 30%포인트의 가산세율이 적용된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the government's announcement of this year's economic growth strategy, it did not include content about extending the suspension of the additional tax on capital gains for multiple homeowners. (정부의 올해 경제성장 전략 발표에 따르면 다주택자 양도세 중과 유예를 연장하는 내용은 담기지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/IY3CSOD3AFE3NABWQPLHUGZ4HE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GAYGMMRUMJSTOZJZHA3TGOBWG4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 14:33:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Kim Tells U.S. Lawmakers "Absolutely No Discrimination Against Coupang" (金총리, 美 의원들 만나 “쿠팡 차별 전혀 없다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/QWJWJRTAXNBFJHLILOV4AZW2ME/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Prime Minister Kim Tells U.S. Lawmakers "Absolutely No Discrimination Against Coupang" (金총리, 美 의원들 만나 “쿠팡 차별 전혀 없다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5YB27AHZDJPL3HUWHAF7V4TO5M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his visit to the United States, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok told U.S. House members concerned about the Korean government's actions regarding Coupang that "there is absolutely no discrimination against Coupang." (미국을 방문 중인 김민석 국무총리가 쿠팡에 대한 한국 정부의 조치를 우려하는 미 하원 의원들에게 “쿠팡에 대한 차별은 전혀 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Prime Minister's Office, Prime Minister Kim met with eight bipartisan members of the U.S. House of Representatives in Washington, D.C., on the 22nd (local time). Some lawmakers inquired about the Korean government's response to Coupang, and Prime Minister Kim replied, "The Korea-U.S. relationship is one of trust to the extent that there is no need to worry about discriminatory treatment against Coupang." (국무총리실에 따르면, 김 총리는 22일(현지 시각) 미국 워싱턴DC에서 연방 하원 여야 의원 8인과 회동했다. 일부 의원들은 쿠팡에 대한 한국 정부의 대응에 관해 문의했고, 김 총리는 “쿠팡에 대한 차별적인 대우를 걱정하지 않아도 될 만큼 한미 관계는 신뢰 관계에 있다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim cited the incident last September when U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement arrested and detained 317 Korean workers at a Hyundai Motor and LG Energy Solution joint battery factory in Georgia. He explained, "Korea does not consider the 'Georgia incident' as a case of discrimination by the U.S. government because the workers were Korean. Similarly, the measures taken regarding Coupang are not because it is a U.S. company, and we are not discriminating against Coupang at all." (김 총리는 지난해 9월 미 이민세관단속국이 조지아주에 있는 현대차·LG에너지솔루션 합작 배터리 공장에서 일하는 한국인 근로자 317명을 체포·구금했던 사건을 거론하면서 “한국은 ‘조지아 사건’이 한국 노동자이기 때문에 (미국 정부로부터) 차별받은 사건이라고 생각하지 않는다. 마찬가지로 쿠팡도 미국 기업이라는 이유로 취한 조치가 아니며, 쿠팡을 전혀 차별하지 않고 있다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting also discussed cooperation in economic security areas such as supply chains and shipbuilding between Korea and the U.S. Prime Minister Kim said, "Through this visit to the U.S., I hope to further stabilize and sustainably develop the Korea-U.S. relationship, including accelerating the implementation of follow-up measures from the Korea-U.S. customs negotiations." The Prime Minister's Office stated that the lawmakers emphasized the unwavering bipartisan support of the U.S. Congress for the Korea-U.S. alliance and responded, "We hope to strengthen cooperation in various areas, including economic security such as critical mineral supply chains and shipbuilding cooperation, and also expand Korea-U.S.-Japan cooperation." (이 자리에서는 공급망과 조선(造船) 등 한미 간 경제 안보 분야 협력도 거론됐다. 김 총리는 “이번 방미를 통해 한미 관세 협상 후속 조치의 이행을 가속화하는 등 한미 관계를 더욱 안정적이고 지속적으로 발전시켜 나갈 수 있기를 기대한다”고 했다. 총리실은 의원들이 한미 동맹에 대한 미 의회의 흔들림 없는 초당적 지지를 강조했고, “한미 간 핵심 광물 공급망 등 경제 안보와 조선 협력을 포함한 다양한 영역에서 협력을 강화하고 한·미·일 협력 또한 확대해 나가기를 희망한다”고 화답했다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lawmakers told Prime Minister Kim, "We are experiencing the positive effects of Korean companies' investments and contributions in our respective districts on the growth of the Korean community and local economic development," adding, "We hope Korean companies will continue to be interested in and advance into the U.S. market." (의원들은 김 총리에게 “각자의 지역구 내에서 한국 기업의 투자 등 기여가 한인 커뮤니티의 성장과 지역 경제 발전에 미치는 긍정적 효과를 체감하고 있다”며 “앞으로도 한국 기업들이 대미 투자에 관심을 갖고 진출해 주기를 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lawmakers then introduced that Representative Young Kim has proposed the 'Korea Partnership Act,' which would allow U.S. authorities to issue up to 15,000 professional visas annually for Koreans, and the bill is pending in the House. They said, "We will work towards the passage of the bill." (의원들은 이어서 영 김 의원이 한국인을 대상으로 미 당국이 연 최대 1만5000건의 전문직 비자를 발급할 수 있게 하는 ‘한국 동반자법’을 발의해 법안이 하원에 계류 중이라고 소개하고, “법안의 통과를 위해 노력해 나갈 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was attended by Republican Representatives Young Kim, Joe Wilson, Michael Waltz, John Moolenaar, and Ryan Mackenzie, and Democratic Representatives Ami Bera, Marilyn Strickland, and Dave Min. Prime Minister Kim had lunch with some of the lawmakers. (이날 회동에는 공화당 영 김, 조 우리슨, 마이클 바움가트너, 존 물레나, 라이언 매켄지 의원, 민주당 아미 베라, 메릴린 스트릭랜드, 데이브 민 의원이 참여했다. 김 총리는 일부 의원들과 오찬을 함께 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, Prime Minister Kim visited the Korean War Veterans Memorial to lay a wreath and held a discussion on Korean culture with American youth at the Korean Cultural Center in Washington. During the discussion, Prime Minister Kim argued, "The foundation of Korean culture's attention lies in positive and good values like solidarity, affection, and family, which have been somewhat forgotten recently." He also mentioned that during the December 3rd state of emergency, Koreans took to the streets with K-pop light sticks, emphasizing, "Democracy is the foundation of the Korean Wave and an important value explaining its universality." (이후 김 총리는 한국전 참전기념비 공원을 찾아 헌화하고, 워싱턴 한국문화원에서 미 청년들과 함께 한국 문화를 주제로 간담회를 했다. 간담회에서 김 총리는 “한국 문화가 주목받는 근간에는 최근 잊히고 있는 연대, 정, 가족 등 긍정적이고 선한 가치들이 있다”고 주장했다. 또 12·3 비상계엄 당시 한국인들이 K팝 응원봉을 들고 거리로 나왔다면서, “민주주의는 한류의 근간이자 한류의 보편성을 설명하는 중요한 가치”라고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the evening, Prime Minister Kim held a discussion with Korean compatriots in the Washington area. Prime Minister Kim said, "As can be seen from the Prime Minister's visit to the U.S. after 40 years, the importance of the Korea-U.S. relationship is increasing daily," and "The capabilities of the second and third generations of compatriots have greatly contributed to the motherland's leap forward." Prime Minister Kim also stated, "President Lee Jae-myung has great interest in the compatriot community and, after his visit to the U.S., is striving for the development of the compatriot community in Cabinet meetings and work reports." (김 총리는 이날 저녁에는 워싱턴 지역 동포들과 간담회를 했다. 김 총리는 “40년 만에 총리가 미국을 방문한 데서 볼 수 있듯이, 한미관계의 중요성이 날로 높아지고 있다”며 “모국의 도약에 동포 2~3세대의 역량이 큰 도움이 됐다”고 했다. 김 총리는 “이재명 대통령님은 동포 사회에 대한 관심이 지대하고, 미국을 다녀오신 후 국무회의와 업무 보고 등에서 동포 사회 발전을 위해 힘쓰고 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/QWJWJRTAXNBFJHLILOV4AZW2ME/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5YB27AHZDJPL3HUWHAF7V4TO5M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:15:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Three Democratic Party Supreme Council Members Oppose Merger, Say "Chung Cheong-rae's Arbitrary Rule Must End Now" (‘합당 반발’ 與 최고위원 3인 “정청래식 독단 이제 끝나야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/NWVTDDPLN5GRRNMCFZG7JDTE54/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Three Democratic Party Supreme Council Members Oppose Merger, Say "Chung Cheong-rae's Arbitrary Rule Must End Now" (‘합당 반발’ 與 최고위원 3인 “정청래식 독단 이제 끝나야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O3CJXCWSVVA47AJBK7UZPT5O3I.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party Supreme Council members Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu on the 23rd demanded an official apology from leader Chung Cheong-rae, stating, "We demand measures to prevent the recurrence of autocratic party management." (더불어민주당 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 23일 정청래 대표를 향해 “공식 사과하라”며 “독선적 당 운영에 대한 재발 방지 대책을 요구한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They held a press conference at the National Assembly that day, declaring, "Chung Cheong-rae's arbitrary rule must end now." They also demanded, "Immediately disclose the full truth to party members regarding when, with whom, to what extent, and how the merger proposal was discussed." (이들은 이날 국회에서 기자회견을 열고 “정청래식의 독단은 이제 끝나야 한다”며 이같이 밝혔다. 이들은 또 “합당 제안을 언제, 누구랑, 어디까지, 어떻게 논의하였는지 당원들에게 즉각 진상을 공개하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Chung had abruptly proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party the previous day. Facing strong internal backlash, Leader Chung stepped back during the Supreme Council meeting on the 23rd, stating, "It is a path we must take. If it passes in a vote of all party members, we proceed; if it fails, we stop." The Supreme Council meeting was held at the National Athletes' Village in Jincheon, North Chungcheong Province, but Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu did not attend. (정 대표는 전날 조국혁신당에 합당을 전격 제안했다. 정 대표는 당내 반발이 거세자 23일 최고위원회의에서 “꼭 가야 할 길이다. 전 당원 투표에서 가결되면 가는 것이고 부결되면 멈추는 것”이라며 한발 물러섰다. 이날 최고위는 충북 진천 국가대표선수촌에서 열렸는데, 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 불참했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu stated, "We are raising the issue that merger discussions proceeded even without the knowledge of Supreme Council members, and the undemocratic nature of its procedure and process," adding, "We were completely unaware of the merger proposal until 9:30 AM yesterday, just before the Supreme Council meeting." (이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 “최고위원들조차 모르는 사이에 합당 논의가 진행됐다는 점, 그 절차와 과정의 비민주성을 문제 삼는 것”이라며 “우리는 어제 오전 9시 30분 최고위원회의 전까지, 합당 제안 사실을 전혀 알지 못했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They continued, "While the leadership of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party was informed in advance, Democratic Party lawmakers, including Supreme Council members, were notified only 20 minutes before the announcement and learned about it through the media." They also said, "Yesterday's Supreme Council meeting was merely a session to unilaterally notify and receive a decision on a matter already discussed and decided upon with Representative Cho Kuk." (이어 “조국혁신당 지도부는 미리 알고 있었지만, 민주당 최고위원을 포함한 민주당 의원들은 발표 20분 전에 통보받고 언론을 통해 알았다”고 했다. 또 “어제 최고위원회의는 이미 조국 대표와 협의하고 결정된 사안을 일방적으로 통보하고 전달받는 자리였다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They criticized, "While verbally advocating for party member sovereignty, is this the image of a Chung Cheong-rae-style party member sovereign party: deciding the party's fate arbitrarily as the leader wishes and then only giving party members the choice of 'Yes' or 'No'?" They added, "A structure where even elected Supreme Council members cannot voice their opinions, a structure that only forces agreement with the leader's decisions, is not democratic party management. This is a clear overreach and abuse of power by the party leader." (이들은 “말로는 당원 주권을 이야기하지만, 당대표 맘대로 당의 운명을 결정해 놓고 당원들에겐 O, X만 선택하라는 것이 정청래식 당원 주권 정당의 모습이냐”며 “선출된 최고위원들이 의견조차 낼 수 없는 구조, 대표 결정에 동의만 강요하는 구조는 민주적 당 운영이 아니다. 이는 당대표의 명백한 월권이며 직권남용”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding media reports suggesting prior communication between President Lee Jae-myung and Leader Chung Cheong-rae on this matter, Lee Eon-joo, Hwang Myeong-seon, and Kang Deuk-gu claimed, "Our verification shows it is not true," and "It was merely a past mention at a theoretical level; yesterday's announcement was not a matter shared in advance with the presidential office at all." They stated, "Party affairs are the party's responsibility and should be decided by the party," and "A method that creates misunderstanding as if it were the president's will or that the president is involved is never desirable." (이번 사안에 대해 이재명 대통령과 정청래 대표 간에 교감이 있었다는 언론 보도에 대해 이언주·황명선·강득구 최고위원은 “확인 결과 사실이 아니다”라며 “과거 원론적 언급 수준이었을 뿐, 어제 발표는 대통령실과 사전 공유된 사안이 전혀 아니다”라고 주장했다. 이들은 “당무는 당의 책임이고, 당이 결정해야 한다”며 “마치 대통령의 뜻인 것처럼, 대통령이 관여하는 것처럼 오해를 불러일으키는 방식은 결코 바람직하지 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They said, "We can absolutely never become one team in this way," and "We are strongly raising the issue of Leader Chung Cheong-rae's arrogance and undemocratic practices that obstruct grand unity." They further stated, "We are issuing a stern warning regarding Leader Chung's 'selective party member sovereignty'." (이들은 “이 방식으로는 절대로 원팀이 될 수 없다”며 “대통합을 가로막는 정청래 대표의 독선과 비민주성을 강력하게 문제 제기하는 것”이라고 했다. 이어 “정 대표의 ‘선택적 당원 주권’에 대해 엄중히 경고하는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/NWVTDDPLN5GRRNMCFZG7JDTE54/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O3CJXCWSVVA47AJBK7UZPT5O3I.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:25:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing Heated from the Start...10 Repeated Questions on Son's College Admission Suspicions (시작부터 고성 오간 이혜훈 청문회...아들 입시 의혹에 10번 같은 질문)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/6ZVTGKMI6VF7NO3IULPLEBNIME/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing Heated from the Start...10 Repeated Questions on Son's College Admission Suspicions (시작부터 고성 오간 이혜훈 청문회...아들 입시 의혹에 10번 같은 질문)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LWU3EYUL6NJRDD3PQT6AKLP4U4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Minister-nominee Lee Hye-hoon, which began after twists and turns on the 23rd, started with heated exchanges from the outset due to the opposition party's grilling over suspicions surrounding the nominee. (우여곡절 끝에 시작된 이혜훈 장관 후보자에 대한 인사청문회가 열린 23일, 청문회는 이 후보자의 의혹과 관련한 야당의 추궁으로 시작부터 고성이 오갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the hearing, People Power Party lawmaker Choi Eun-seok, a member of the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, raised suspicions about the process through which the nominee's eldest son entered Yonsei University. The suspicions arose after the nominee reversed her statement the previous day, saying her son was admitted through the 'social contributor track' rather than the 'multiple children track'. (국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 최은석 국민의힘 의원은 이날 청문회에서 이 후보자의 장남이 연세대 입학 과정에 대한 의혹을 제기했다. 이 후보자의 장남이 연세대 입학 전형을 ‘다자녀 전형’에서 ‘사회기여자 전형’으로 입학했다고 전날 번복하면서 생긴 의혹이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Choi repeatedly asked the nominee, "What track did (your son) enter through?" and "I'm asking what track he entered through," posing the question five times. He also pointed out, "More lies, the nominee tells lies whenever she opens her mouth." (최 의원은 이날 이 후보자에게 “(아들이) 무슨 전형으로 입학했습니까” “무슨 전형으로 입학했냐니까”라며 5번 되물었다. 최 의원은 이 후보자에게 “또 거짓말, 후보자는 입만 열면 거짓말 한다”고 지적하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the nominee stated, "It was our second son who applied through the multiple children track; we simply had a momentary mix-up between our second and eldest sons." (이 후보자는 답변으로 “다자녀 전형으로 신청을 했던 것은 차남이었는데 차남과 장남을 저희가 잠깐 혼선을 빚었던 것뿐”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also repeated a question about which family member enhanced national prestige a total of ten times. This question pertained to whether a family member qualified as a national prestige enhancer for admission under the social contributor track. Lawmaker Choi pressed intensively, asking, "Are your husband's parents perhaps independence activists?" and "Are you or your husband national meritorious persons?" (또 가족 중 누가 국위선양했냐는 질문도 10차례나 되물었다. 사회기여자 전형으로 입학하기 위해 가족 중 국위선양자에 해당했냐는 물음이다. 최 의원은 “남편의 부모님이 혹시 독립유공자인가” “후보자나 남편이 국가유공자입니까”라고 집중 추궁했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the nominee explained, "My father-in-law received (a medal) in recognition of his lifelong service as a public official, not for his achievements as a politician." (그러자 이 후보자는 “시부께서 정치인으로서의 공적이 아니고 공무원으로 평생 봉직한 공적을 인정받아서 (훈장을) 받았다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/6ZVTGKMI6VF7NO3IULPLEBNIME/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LWU3EYUL6NJRDD3PQT6AKLP4U4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 17:32:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon, Who Submitted Inadequate Materials, Says "I Will Go Even If Stones Are Thrown" (부실 자료 제출 이혜훈 “돌을 맞더라도 가겠다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/3FDWMEEEIVDTHP3DXF64CDYEQQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, Who Submitted Inadequate Materials, Says "I Will Go Even If Stones Are Thrown" (부실 자료 제출 이혜훈 “돌을 맞더라도 가겠다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Q4FL4J7PABKQFMVEQ7Y32OP3CU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, began on the 23rd. She faces various allegations, including 'fraudulent subscription by disguising her eldest son as unmarried' and 'abuse of power by aides'. Previously, the People Power Party had refused to hold the hearing on the 19th, citing the nominee's failure to properly submit requested materials, but the ruling and opposition parties agreed to hold the hearing on this day. (‘장남 위장 미혼 청약’ ‘보좌진 갑질’ 등 각종 의혹이 제기된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 인사청문회가 23일 시작됐다. 앞서 국민의힘은 지난 19일 이 후보자가 요청한 자료를 제대로 제출하지 않았다는 이유로 청문회 개최를 거부했다가, 이날 청문회를 열기로 여야가 합의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In her opening statement, the nominee said, "Since being nominated as the Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, there have been many criticisms regarding my shortcomings," adding, "I am deeply sorry for causing concern to the public. I am also sorry to the President who nominated me." The nominee stated, "First, I sincerely apologize to everyone who was hurt by my immature words and actions," and "Living as a one-eyed person obsessed with achievements, I failed to properly see the hurt I caused to my precious colleagues who worked with me. I deeply reflect on this." (이 후보자는 이날 모두 발언에서 “기획예산처 장관 후보자에 지명된 이후 저의 부족함에 대한 여러 지적이 있었다”며 “국민께 심려를 끼쳐 송구하다. 저를 지명하신 대통령님께도 송구하다”고 했다. 이 후보자는 “우선 저의 성숙치 못한 언행 때문에 상처받은 모든 분들께 진심으로 사과드린다”며 “성과에 매몰된 외눈박이로 살아오면서 저와 함께했던 소중한 동료들에게 상처를 드린 점을 제대로 보지 못했다. 뼈저리게 반성한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee said, "I also apologize once again for having stood in a position of erroneous judgment that is difficult to avoid criticism for sympathizing with rebellion," adding, "I will not make any excuses. The responsibility lies solely with me." (이 후보자는 “또한 내란에 동조했다는 비판을 피하기 어려운 잘못된 판단의 자리에 서 있었음을 다시 한번 사과드린다”며 “어떠한 변명도 하지 않겠다. 책임은 오롯이 저에게 있습다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee said, "The step toward integration, taken in a situation where there is no need for vote-counting as the large ruling party, was read as the President's sincerity toward institutionalizing cooperative governance." She continued, "I stand here with the mindset that I will participate, even if stones are thrown, in opening a new path for South Korea, which is currently unable to take a single step forward due to being shackled by partisan politics." (이 후보자는 “지금 거대 여당으로서 세 불리기 자체가 필요치 않은 상황에서 나온 통합의 발걸음은 협치의 제도화를 향한 대통령님의 진정성으로 읽혔다”고 했다. 그러면서 “진영 정치에 발목 잡혀 한 걸음도 앞으로 나아가지 못하는 지금의 대한민국에 새로운 길을 여는 일에는 돌을 맞더라도 동참하겠다는 심정으로 이 자리에 서게 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to the nominee's opening statement, ruling and opposition party lawmakers on this day demanded the submission of materials related to the subscription for the Raemian One Pentas in Banpo, Seoul. There are allegations that the nominee's eldest son won the subscription by pretending to be unmarried despite being married. The nominee said, "I will submit the relevant materials as much as possible by the afternoon." Regarding the so-called 'Lee Hye-hoon memorandum', the nominee denied it, saying, "I did not write it." (이 후보자 모두 발언에 앞서 여야 의원들은 이날 서울 반포 래미안 원펜타스 청약과 관련한 자료 제출 등을 요구했다. 이 후보자는 장남이 기혼 상태인데도, 미혼 상태로 속여 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹이 있다. 이 후보자는 “오후까지 최대한 관련 자료를 제출하겠다”고 했다. 이 후보자는 이른바 ‘이혜훈 비망록’에 대해선 “제가 쓴 게 아니다”고 부인했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/3FDWMEEEIVDTHP3DXF64CDYEQQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Q4FL4J7PABKQFMVEQ7Y32OP3CU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:41:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Choi Kyung-hwan: "Pension and Labor Reforms, Park Geun-hye Administration's Policies Undervalued" (최경환 “연금·노동 개혁, 박근혜 정부 정책 저평가”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/ZFAQO32VTBCALKEAX2J7Q3PR5Y/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Choi Kyung-hwan: "Pension and Labor Reforms, Park Geun-hye Administration's Policies Undervalued" (최경환 “연금·노동 개혁, 박근혜 정부 정책 저평가”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6LTU6MNCFNEAVHZVR56IRGREU4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Deputy Prime Minister Choi Kyung-hwan, who served as the economic deputy prime minister during the Park Geun-hye administration, will publish a memoir titled 'The Park Geun-hye Administration's Economic Policies - Choinomics' on the 24th. In this memoir, he shares behind-the-scenes stories about economic policies such as the Park administration's 'Four Major Reforms (labor, public sector, education, finance)' and 'real estate policies,' as well as economic diplomacy. (박근혜 정부 시절 경제부총리를 지낸 최경환 전 부총리가 24일 ‘박근혜 정부의 경제 정책-초이노믹스’를 출간한다. 그는 이번 회고록에서 박근혜 정부 ‘4대 개혁(노동·공공·교육·금융)’ ‘부동산 정책’ 같은 경제 정책이나 경제 외교 등에 대한 뒷이야기를 담았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the memoir's preface, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi wrote, "Among all past presidents, is there another figure like 'President Park Geun-hye' whose achievements are buried and only her faults are highlighted in evaluations?" He added, "Despite outstanding economic policy achievements, the reality that she has not received proper historical evaluation due to being overshadowed by the negative image of 'impeachment' was deeply painful." (회고록 서문에서 최 전 부총리는 “역대 대통령 중에서 ‘박근혜 대통령’만큼 공은 묻히고 과(過)만 부각되어 평가받는 인물이 또 있을까”라면서 “뛰어난 경제정책 성과가 있었음에도 ‘탄핵’이라는 부정적 이미지에 가려 제대로 된 역사의 평가를 받지 못하는 현실이 뼈아팠다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Deputy Prime Minister Choi, a four-term lawmaker, served as the Minister of Knowledge Economy during the Lee Myung-bak administration (September 2009 to January 2011). Later, during the Park Geun-hye administration, he worked as the Minister of Strategy and Finance and concurrently as the Deputy Prime Minister for Economic Affairs from July 2014 to January 2016. (4선 의원 출신인 최 부총리는 이명박 정부 시절(2009년 9월~2011년 1월) 지식경제부 장관을 지냈다. 이후 박근혜 정부 시절에서도 2014년 7월~2016년 1월 기획재정부 장관 겸 경제부총리로 일했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Four Major Reforms: "For Youth Jobs and the Economic Future"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇4대 개혁 “청년 일자리, 경제 미래 위한 것”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Deputy Prime Minister Choi designed the direction of the Park Geun-hye administration's economic policies in 2015 as the 'Four Major Reforms.' In the book, he stated about the Four Major Reforms, "A grand compromise among labor, management, and government was achieved for the first time in 17 years, and through public servant pension reform, we achieved results saving 185 trillion won in fiscal expenditure over the next 30 years." (최 전 부총리는 2015년 박근혜 정부 경제 정책 방향을 ‘4대 개혁’으로 설계했다. 그는 책에서 4대 개혁에 대해 “17년 만의 노사정 대타협이 성사됐고, 공무원 연금 개혁을 통해 향후 30년간 185조원의 재정을 절감하는 성과를 거뒀다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also said, "By introducing the wage peak system in public institutions, we significantly increased hiring in 2016 and tightened the reins on debt growth." He added, "This helped raise South Korea's credit rating and provided an opportunity for our country to be evaluated as a global model for structural reform at the G20 summit." (또 “공공기관 임금 피크제를 도입해 2016년에 채용 인원을 크게 늘렸고, 부채 증가에도 고삐를 죄었다”고 했다. 그러면서 “이로 인해 우리나라의 신용 등급을 높일 수 있었고, G20 정상회의에서 우리나라가 구조 개혁의 글로벌 모범 국가로 평가받는 계기도 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Misunderstanding of 'Buy a House with Debt'... Reduced Household Loan Burden for 'House-poor'"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“‘빚내서 집 사라’는 오해… 하우스푸어 가계 대출 부담 줄어” &lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After forming a new economic team in July 2014, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi announced adjustments to economic policy directions, including raising the Loan-to-Value (LTV) ratio to 70% and the Debt-to-Income (DTI) ratio to 60%. The market responded. In October 2014, housing transactions reached 109,000 cases, the highest volume in eight years. In 2015, housing transactions reached about 1.2 million cases, surpassing the 2006 record (1.08 million cases). (최 전 부총리는 2014년 7월 새 경제팀을 꾸린 뒤 경제 정책 방향에 LTV를 70%까지, DTI는 60%까지 조정하는 내용을 담아 발표했다. 시장은 반응했다. 2014년 10월 주택 거래량이 10만9000건으로 8년 만의 최대 거래량이었다. 2015년 주택 거래량은 약 120만건으로 2006년(108만건) 기록을 넘어섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time, there was much criticism that the real estate policy was like saying "buy a house with debt." Regarding this, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi said, "It's natural for housing mortgage loans to increase as new home purchases rise," and added, "As real estate began to be bought and sold, 'house-poor' households—those suffering from excessive debt and relatively high interest rates but unable to sell their homes due to lack of transactions—were able to sell their houses." (당시 부동산 정책에 대해 “빚 내서 집 사라는 것”이란 비판도 많았다. 이에 대해 최 전 부총리는 “신규 주택 구입이 늘면서 주택 담보 대출이 늘어나는 것은 당연한 것”이라며 “부동산이 사고팔리기 시작하자, 과도한 빚과 상대적으로 높은 이자율에 시달리고 있지만 거래가 없어 주택을 팔지 못하던 ‘하우스푸어’ 가구들, 즉 대출을 감당할 수 없는 가구들이 집을 팔 수 있게 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Resuming Korea-Japan Finance Ministers' Meeting with 'Basketball Talk'&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇‘농구 얘기’로 한일 재무장관 회의 재개 &lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The years 2013-2014 were a cooling period in Korea-Japan relations due to issues like the wartime comfort women problem and the Japanese Abe administration's change in constitutional interpretation regarding collective self-defense. The Korea-Japan finance ministers' meeting had also been suspended for over two years since 2012. (2013~2014년은 당시 군 위안부 문제나 일본 아베 정부의 집단적 자위권 헌법 해석 변경 등으로 한일 관계가 냉각기였다. 한·일 재무장관 회의도 2012년 이후 2년 넘게 중단된 상태였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Around that time, in September 2014, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi attended the 'G20 Finance Ministers and Central Bank Governors Meeting' in Cairns, Australia, and approached Japanese Finance Minister Taro Aso during a break. He said, "During the event break, I approached Minister Aso and started the conversation by asking, 'Are you still serving as the basketball association president?'" and explained, "I remembered that I had served as the president of the Korean Women's Basketball Federation and that Aso had served as the president of the Japanese Women's Basketball Federation a few years earlier." Subsequently, the Korea-Japan finance ministers' meeting resumed in May of the following year, 2015. It was an achievement brought about by basketball talk. (최 전 부총리는 그 무렵인 2014년 9월 호주 케언즈에서 열린 ‘G20 재무장관·중앙은행 총재 회의’에 참석해 일본 아소 다로 재무 대신(장관)을 쉬는 시간에 찾아갔다. 그는 “행사 쉬는 시간에 아소 장관에게 다가가 ‘요즘도 농구협회장을 맡고 있느냐’는 말로 대화를 풀어 나갔다”며 “나는 한국여자농구연맹 총재직을 지냈고, 아소도 몇 년 전 일본여자농구연맹 총재를 맡았던 것이 기억났기 때문”이라고 했다. 이후 다음 해인 2015년 5월 한·일 재무장관 회의가 재개됐다. 농구 얘기가 가져온 성과였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Bonding with Chinese Economic Minister in the Smoking Area&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇중국 경제 장관과는 흡연장에서 인연 맺어&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Deputy Prime Minister Choi also formed a connection with Chinese Finance Minister Lou Jiwei at a G20 meeting in 2014. When smoking in the hotel's outdoor smoking area, the only Asians were him and one Chinese person. Former Deputy Prime Minister Choi said, "I encountered this Chinese person so often in the smoking area that I thought to myself, 'He must be as much of a chain smoker as I am,' when our staffer informed me, 'That person is Chinese Finance Minister Lou Jiwei.'" (최 전 부총리는 중국 경제 장관이던 러우지웨이 재정 부장(장관)과도 2014년 G20 회의에서 인연을 맺었다. 호텔 외부 흡연 구역에서 담배를 필 때 동양인은 그와 중국인 한 명뿐이었다. 최 전 부총리는 “이 중국인과 흡연 구역에서 너무 자주 마주치기에 속으로 ‘참 나만큼이나 골초구나’라고 생각했는데, 우리 실무자가 ‘저 사람이 중국 러우지웨이 장관’이라고 알려줬다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterward, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi went to Minister Lou, borrowed a light, and greeted him. He said, "Korea is trying to raise cigarette prices these days, but opposition is fierce, and it's driving me crazy." Minister Lou replied, "That's impressive. In China, that's unimaginable." It is said that he grew closer with Minister Lou, who became a fellow smoking comrade, by frequently meeting at major international conferences. (이후 최 전 부총리는 러우 장관에게 가서 담뱃불을 빌리며 인사를 건넸다. 그는 “한국은 요즘 담배값을 올리려고 하는데, 반대가 심해 정신이 없다”고 하자, 러우 장관은 “대단하다. 중국은 상상도 못할 일”이라고 답했다. 담배 동지가 된 러우 장관과는 주요 국제 회의를 통해 자주 보면서 더욱 가까워졌다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇ "Youth Jobs, Always the Top Priority"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇ “청년 일자리, 언제나 최우선 순위”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this book, former Deputy Prime Minister Choi also shared a story about meeting young people struggling to find jobs at Chungnam National University, saying, "Throughout the meeting, I couldn't help but feel like a sinner," and added, "While working as a politician, creating jobs for the younger generation will always be among the top priorities of what I must do." (최 전 부총리는 이번 책에서 일자리 찾기에 어려움을 겪는 청년들과 충남대에서 만난 얘기도 전하며 “간담회 내내 죄인일 수밖에 없는 심정이었다”며 “내가 정치인으로서 일하는 동안 청년 세대를 위한 일자리 창출은 언제나 내가 해야 할 일 중 최우선 순위에 둘 생각”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/ZFAQO32VTBCALKEAX2J7Q3PR5Y/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6LTU6MNCFNEAVHZVR56IRGREU4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 21:43:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's 'Eldest Son Posing as Unmarried' Subscription Suspicion: "Marital Relationship Worst Right After Wedding" (이혜훈 ‘장남 위장 미혼’ 청약 의혹에 “혼례 직후 부부 관계 최악 상황”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/2XJGNSPFQVB2PCU7XQOABFLYG4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon's 'Eldest Son Posing as Unmarried' Subscription Suspicion: "Marital Relationship Worst Right After Wedding" (이혜훈 ‘장남 위장 미혼’ 청약 의혹에 “혼례 직후 부부 관계 최악 상황”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EUYKMBMDBVF4BCWN6R3FUYYCO4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the suspicion that Minister of Economy and Finance nominee Lee Hye-hoon deceived authorities by falsely claiming her married eldest son was unmarried to increase the number of dependents and win a subscription for a Raemian One Pentas apartment in Seoul's Banpo-dong, she explained, "My eldest son's marital relationship deteriorated to the worst after the wedding," adding, "At the time, I judged it would be difficult to maintain the marriage." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 혼인한 장남을 미혼으로 속인 뒤 부양 가족 수를 늘려 서울 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹에 대해 “장남이 혼례 이후 (부부) 관계가 최악으로 치닫았다”며 “당시엔 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 판단했다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's husband applied for a subscription to Raemian One Pentas' 137A type (exclusive area 137㎡, approximately 54 pyeong) on July 29, 2024. Subsequently, her husband won the subscription lottery that August and paid the full amount of 3.6784 billion won two months later. It is said her husband's subscription points at the time were 74 points. He received full points for the period of being houseless (32 points) and savings account membership period (17 points), with an additional 25 points added for having 4 dependents (the nominee and three sons). (이 후보자 남편은 2024년 7월 29일 래미안 원펜타스의 137A 타입(전용면적 137㎡·약 54평)에 청약을 신청했다. 이후 이 후보자 남편은 그해 8월 청약에 당첨됐고, 2개월 뒤 36억7840만원을 완납했다. 당시 이 후보자 남편의 청약 가점은 74점이었다고 한다. 무주택 기간(32점), 저축 가입 기간(17점)은 모두 만점이었고, 부양 가족 수 4명(이 후보자와 아들 3명) 가점 25점이 더해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among dependents, only unmarried children are recognized, and their registered address on the family relation certificate must also match the parents'. However, the nominee's eldest son had gotten married in December 2023, one year before the subscription application. Two weeks before the wedding, he also signed a jeonse (lump-sum deposit rental) contract for an apartment in Seoul's Yongsan District with a deposit of 730 million won. (부양 가족 중 자녀는 미혼만 인정되며, 주민등록등본상 주소도 부모와 같아야 한다. 그런데 이 후보자 장남은 청약 신청 1년 전인 2023년 12월에 결혼한 상태였다. 결혼 2주 전에는 서울 용산구의 한 아파트를 보증금 7억3000만원에 전세 계약도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this suspicion, Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Kim Young-hwan raised questions during the confirmation hearing that day. The nominee stated, "(My eldest son) had a wedding ceremony in December 2023. Our plan at the time, believing the couple's relationship would be maintained, was to prepare a newlywed home for them." (이 의혹과 관련해 더불어민주당 김영환 의원이 이날 인사 청문회에서 질의했다. 이 후보자는 “(장남이) 2023년 12월에 혼례를 올렸다. 그때 계획은 장남 부부가 (관계 유지가) 될 것으로 알고 신혼집을 마련하는 게 저희 계획이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee said, "The Yongsan house (the newlywed home for the eldest son and his wife) was prepared with each side contributing 50%." She added, "However, after the wedding, (the couple's relationship) deteriorated to the worst. I thought it would be difficult to maintain the marriage," and explained, "(My eldest son) had no choice but to stay with us, and I thought he would come live with us." (이 후보자는 “용산집(장남 부부 신혼집)은 각자 50% 씩 내서 마련했다”고 했다. 이 후보자는 “그런데 혼례 이후로 (장남 부부 관계가) 최악으로 치닫았다. 혼례를 유지하기 어렵다고 생각했다”며 “(장남은) 저희와 있을 수밖에 없었고 저희와 함께 간다고 생각했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Reform Party lawmaker Chun Ha-ram commented on the nominee's daughter-in-law, saying, "The timeline is astonishing." Chun said, "Right up until just before the subscription recruitment announcement, she was left in the Yongsan jeonse house contributed to by the nominee and her father-in-law, and then, astonishingly, she steps aside exactly when the nominee's family needs to register their residence there (at One Pentas)." (이에 대해 개혁신당 천하람 의원은 이 후보자 며느리에 대해 “시간 라인이 기가 막히다”고 했다. 천 의원은 “청약 모집 공고 직전까지는 후보자와 시아버지가 보태준 용산 전셋집에 놔뒀다가 후보자 가족이 거기(원펜타스)에 전입해야 할 시기가 오니까 기가막히게 본인이 빠져준다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chun added, "Looking at this alone, it's not that the daughter-in-law and the eldest son had a bad relationship. She's almost at the level of the world's best filial daughter-in-law. She even got married so her father-in-law and mother-in-law could hit the jackpot lottery subscription, didn't merge her resident registration, waited to report the marriage... isn't she a complete 'filial daughter-in-law'? Is it right to vilify such a filial daughter-in-law before the public?" (천 의원은 “이것만 보면 며느리랑 장남이랑 사이가 안좋았던 게 아니다. 거의 세계 최고의 효부 수준이다. 시아버지 시어머니가 대박 로또 청약을 받을 수 있도록 결혼도 했는데 주민등록도 안 합치고 혼인신고도 기다려주고 완전 ‘효부(孝婦)’ 아니냐. 이런 효부를 국민 보시는데 매도해도 되느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Chun asked, "How did (the eldest son, who works in Sejong) commute to the (Seoul One Pentas) house?", the nominee replied, "He came by bus." Chun stated, "The fact that they still cannot produce the transportation card records alone is an admission that the claim the eldest son and the nominee lived together is a lie." (천 의원은 “(세종에서 근무하는) 장남이 뭘 타고 (서울 원펜타스) 집에 왔느냐”고 묻자, 이 후보자는 “버스 타고 왔다”고 했다. 천 의원은 “교통 카드 내역을 지금까지 못내는 것만 해도 장남과 후보자가 같이 거주했다는 게 거짓말을 했다는 것을 인정하는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/2XJGNSPFQVB2PCU7XQOABFLYG4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EUYKMBMDBVF4BCWN6R3FUYYCO4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 17:29:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Council Member Who Exposed Lee Hye-hoon's Power Abuse Says Hearing Answers Were "Detestable" (이혜훈 갑질 폭로한 구의원, 청문회 답변에 “가증스럽다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/2XICBGTOTZE7DCD2HXVSXEZGJE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Son Ju-ha, a People Power Party council member for Seoul's Jung-gu district who exposed allegations of power abuse by Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, stated on the 23rd that regarding the nominee's answers during the confirmation hearing, "I truly felt they were very detestable." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 갑질 의혹을 폭로한 국민의힘 손주하 서울 중구의원이 이 후보자의 인사청문회 답변에 대해 “정말 가증스럽다는 느낌을 많이 받았다”고 23일 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appearing at the hearing that day as a witness, Council Member Son gave his overall assessment, saying, "There were quite a lot of lies overall." (이날 청문회에 참고인 자격으로 나온 손 구의원은 “전체적으로 거짓말이 좀 많았다”고 인사청문회 총평을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Council Member Son also mentioned the allegation that the nominee forced people to shave their heads in opposition to the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol. Council Member Son said, "It was last winter, and I understand it was the first time in Jung-gu." He also responded to a question during the hearing, which asked, 'Is it true that after the head-shaving event ended, he said, 'Don't you worry about nomination'?' by stating, "I did not attend, but I heard that from a committee member who was present at the time." (또 손 구의원은 이 후보자가 윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵 반대를 위한 삭발을 강요했다는 것에 대해 언급하기도 했다. 손 구의원은 “작년 겨울이었고, 중구에서 최초로 한 걸로 알고 있다”고 했다. 또 청문회에서 ‘삭발식이 끝난 뒤 ‘너희는 공천을 걱정하지 마라’ 이런 말을 했다고 하는데 맞는가’라는 질문에 “제가 참석하지 않았지만 당시 참석했던 위원으로부터 그렇게 들었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the nominee rebutted, "The witness is someone who did not even receive a notice about the head-shaving, was never forced to shave their head, and did not attend the head-shaving event, yet they relayed others' stories in a hearsay format and spoke untruths," adding, "I never forced anyone." (이에 이 후보자는 “참고인은 삭발 연락도 받지 못한 사람이고, 삭발 강요도 당한적이 없고, 삭발 자리에도 오지 않은 분인데 남의 얘기를 전언하는 형식으로 사실이 아닌 얘기를 했다”며 “강요한 적 없다”고 반박했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the allegation of posting a banner supporting insurrection, the nominee answered, "Typically, it is absolutely impossible without the permission of the party district chairperson. Because it costs money and there are complaints about the location, the party district chairperson always reviews and confirms it." (내란을 옹호하는 현수막을 게시했다는 의혹에 대해 이 후보자는 “통상적으로 당협위원장의 허가가 없으면 절대 할 수 없다. 돈이 들어가고, 장소에 대한 민원도 있기 때문에 당협위원장이 항상 검토하고, 확인하게 돼 있다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/2XICBGTOTZE7DCD2HXVSXEZGJE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:33:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>When asked "Are you willing to give up the 9-billion-won apartment?"... Lee Hye-hoon says "Yes" "Yes"... "Yes, I am willing." (“90억 아파트 포기 용의 있나” 묻자... 이혜훈 “네” “네”… “네, 있다고요”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/JQZN4A24OVAIJE6L4LXRBGZAQI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, allegations of improper apartment subscription by the nominee became a major topic. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회에서 이 후보자의 아파트 부정 청약 의혹이 주요 화두로 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee won the subscription for a Banpo-dong Raemian One Pentas apartment by including her married eldest son as a dependent family member, as if he were unmarried. During the hearing on the 23rd, committee members repeatedly questioned the nominee about suspicions that she falsely registered her eldest son as a dependent to win the apartment subscription. (이 후보자는 결혼한 장남을 미혼인 것처럼 부양가족에 포함해 반포동 래미안원펜타스 아파트 청약에 당첨됐다. 청문회 위원들은 23일 청문회에서 이 후보자가 청약 당첨을 위해 거짓으로 부양가족에 장남을 등록했다는 의혹에 대한 질문을 거듭했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Democratic Party lawmaker Jeong Il-young asked, "I will give up this apartment. I believe you must be prepared to do at least this much to be qualified as the first Minister of Planning and Budget under the Lee Jae-myung administration," the nominee replied, "Yes, I understand." (정일영 민주당 의원이 “이 아파트 내가 포기하겠다. 이 정도는 각오를 가지셔야 이재명 정부의 초대 기획예산처 장관의 자격이 저는 있는 걸로 봅니다”라고 묻자 이 후보자는 “예, 알겠습니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Rep. Jeong asked, "So, are you willing to do that?" the nominee only nodded. Rep. Jeong said, "No, please answer. If you just nod, who will know? It needs to be recorded in the stenographic record." When Rep. Jeong asked, "Are you willing (to give it up) or not?" the nominee simply said, "Yes." (정 의원이 “그런 용의가 있으신 거예요?” 묻자 이 후보자는 고개만 끄덕였다. 정 의원이 “아니, 대답을 하세요. 왜 끄덕끄덕하시면 누가 압니까. 속기록에 남겨야지”라고 했다. 정 의원이 “(포가 용의가) 있으신 거예요, 없으신 거예요”라고 하자 이 후보자는 “네”라고만 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Jeong and the nominee engaged in a tense exchange, with phrases like "What does 'yes' mean, continue" and "Yes, I am willing." (정 의원과 이 후보자는 “네가 뭐예요, 계속” “네, 있다고요”라고 신경전을 벌였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Kim Han-kyu said, "It was not the son but the nominee's spouse who listed the son as a dependent," and asked, "Did the nominee not know?" He also stated, "Even if you said 'I'm sorry, I apologize, it was not intentional,' it's questionable whether the public would accept it. If you act like this, how can even the ruling party defend you?" (김한규 의원은 “아들을 부양가족으로 기재한 것은 아들이 아니라 후보자의 배우자”라며 “후보자는 몰랐느냐”고 했다. 또 “‘미안하다, 사죄한다, 의도한 바가 아니다’ 이렇게 얘기해도 국민이 납득할까 말까인데, 이런 식으로 하시면 여당이라도 어떻게 후보자를 옹호해 줍니까”라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/JQZN4A24OVAIJE6L4LXRBGZAQI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:38:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Dong-jin, Architect of 'Real Growth Theory', Named as Blue House Secretary for Growth Economy (靑 성장경제비서관에 ‘진짜성장론’ 설계한 이동진)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/4SJCWNLKWBHKLFV6O3RHXGZEGY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SVMQTYT6H5A75EMHMG4PTLTRJ4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Dong-jin, a policy advisor to the Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Economy and Finance, has been nominated as the Secretary for Growth Economy, the position overseeing the practical implementation of economic policies at the Blue House. This role coordinates the overall practical work of national economic policies within the Blue House and serves as the senior secretary among the secretaries (for growth economy, industrial policy, land and transport, agriculture, forestry and livestock, small and medium-sized ventures, and oceans and fisheries) under the Office of the Senior Secretary for Economic Growth. The vacancy has been filled seven months after the administration's inauguration. (청와대의 경제 정책 실무를 총괄하는 성장경제비서관에 이동진 재정경제부 부총리 정책보좌관이 내정됐다. 청와대에서 국가 경제 정책 실무 전반을 조율하는 자리로, 경제성장수석실 소속 비서관(성장경제, 산업정책, 국토교통, 농림축산, 중소벤처, 해양수산) 중 선임 비서관 역할을 하는 보직이다. 정권 출범 7개월만에 공석을 채웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advisor Lee Dong-jin, formerly a professor at the Department of Economics and Finance at Sangmyung University, was recruited in September last year as a policy advisor to Deputy Prime Minister and Minister Koo Yun-cheol. After the presidential election, he joined the Economic Subcommittee 1 of the Presidential Transition Committee. During the last presidential election, he served as the deputy head of the policy headquarters for the Democratic Party of Korea's election committee and is known as the architect of then-candidate Lee Jae-myung's 'Real Growth Theory'. 'Real Growth' is a concept aimed at leading a great leap forward for the Korean economy and industry through three major strategies: 'technology-driven growth', 'growth for all', and 'fair growth'. (이동진 보좌관은 상명대 경제금융학부 교수를 지내다가 지난해 9월, 구윤철 부총리 장관 정책보좌관으로 영입됐다. 대선 이후 이 보좌관은 국정기획위원회 경제1분과에 합류했다. 지난 대선 때 더불어민주당 선거대책위원회 정책본부 부본부장을 맡으며, 당시 이재명 후보의 ‘진짜 성장론’을 설계한 인물로 알려졌다. ‘진짜 성장’은 ‘기술주도 성장’, ‘모두의 성장’, ‘공정한 성장’ 3대 전략으로 한국 경제 산업의 대도약을 이끈다는 개념이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In media interviews and other occasions, he has presented artificial intelligence (AI) policy as a key economic strategy to overcome Korea's current low-growth phase and has argued that balanced regional development should aim for growth rather than merely distribution. (언론 인터뷰 등에선 현재 한국의 저성장 국면을 타개할 핵심 경제 정책으로 인공지능(AI) 정책을 제시했고, 지역 균형 발전을 분배가 아닌 성장을 목표로 해야 한다는 등의 주장을 하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/4SJCWNLKWBHKLFV6O3RHXGZEGY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SVMQTYT6H5A75EMHMG4PTLTRJ4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:41:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport on Allegations of Lee Hye-hoon's 'Disguised Unmarried Eldest Son' Subscription: "There is Potential for Fraudulent Subscription" (이혜훈 ‘장남 위장 미혼’ 청약 의혹에 국토부 “부정 청약 소지 있다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/PZ4BQMVNZFHJBHQILAWKRLIYOM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU2TMYTBMVSDOYLEME4DQNRWMU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding allegations that Lee Hye-hoon, a nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, increased her subscription points by falsely listing her married eldest son as unmarried, thereby winning a subscription for the Raemian One Pentas apartment in Seoul's Banpo-dong, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport (MOLIT) responded on the 23rd that "there is potential for fraudulent subscription." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 결혼 상태였던 장남을 미혼으로 두고 청약 가점을 높여 서울 반포동 래미안 원펜타스 청약에 당첨된 것과 관련해 국토교통부 측이 “부정 청약 소지가 있다”고 23일 답변했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the nominee's confirmation hearing that day, as a witness, Jeong Su-ho, head of the Housing Finance Division at MOLIT, stated, "If the suspicions raised by the National Assembly or the media are true, it is a fact that there is potential for fraudulent subscription." (이날 이 후보자 인사 청문회의 증인으로 정수호 국토부 주택기금과장은 “국회나 언론 등에서 제기된 의혹들이 사실이라면 부정 청약 소지가 있는 것은 사실”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to a question from Reform Party lawmaker Chun Ha-ram asking, "Is it permissible to include a child in a disguised unmarried situation as a dependent family member during subscription?" Director Jeong replied, "It is not. According to regulations, even if a child is divorced, they cannot be included as a dependent family member." (정 과장은 “위장 미혼 상황에 있는 자녀를 청약시 부양 가족에 넣어도 되느냐”는 개혁신당 천하람 의원의 질문엔 “안 된다. 규정상으로는 (자녀가) 이혼한 경우에도 부양가족으로 넣을 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Director Jeong said, "Typically, it is difficult to detect a disguised unmarried status through documents." However, he added, "Hiding a de facto marital relationship, such as having held a wedding ceremony but not having a marital home, and registering as a dependent family member is indeed fraudulent subscription." He stated, "In cases where a de facto marital relationship has broken down, there is sufficient reason to view it similarly." (정 과장은 “통상 서류상으로는 위장 미혼을 알기 어렵다”고 했다. 그러나 정 과장은 “결혼식을 하고도 신혼집이 없는 등 사실혼 관계를 숨기고 부양 가족으로 등록하는 것은 부정 청약이 맞다”고 했다. 그는 “사실혼 관계 파탄의 경우도 (유사하게) 볼 소지가 충분하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Director Jeong noted, "As MOLIT is not an investigative agency, it does not have the authority to conduct direct investigations," and said, "If the raised suspicions are true, evidence must be confirmed through a police investigation before it can be determined whether it constitutes fraudulent subscription." (다만 정 과장은 “국토부는 수사기관이 아니라서 직접 수사할 권한이 없다”며 “제기된 의혹들이 사실이라면 경찰 수사를 통해 증거가 확인돼야 부정 청약 여부를 확정할 수 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/PZ4BQMVNZFHJBHQILAWKRLIYOM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU2TMYTBMVSDOYLEME4DQNRWMU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:37:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling Party Asks Lee Hye-hoon, Whose 'Sound Finance' Views Changed, "Have You Been Enlightened?" (‘건전 재정’ 생각 바뀐 이혜훈에 與 “계몽되신 거냐” )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/L2DCLON3GJE6HJ6PFP2PCRVOWU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HBRTCMLDHEYWKOBYMNSTQNZWGQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, has been a consistent advocate for conservative economic policies, championing 'sound finance.' However, at her confirmation hearing on the 23rd, she stated her position had completely reversed, saying, "I have deeply contemplated over the past three years of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration." (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자는 ‘건전 재정’을 주장하며 일관되게 보수적인 경제 정책을 찬성해왔던 인물이지만, 23일 인사 청문회에서는 “윤석열 정부 3년 동안 깊은 고민이 있었다”며 입장이 정반대로 바뀌었다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee hearing that day, the nominee said, "The lifelong belief I held regarding sound finance is that what applies in textbooks and what applies in the real world are different. Once changed, such thoughts do not easily revert." (이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회 인사청문회에서 이 후보자는 “평생 건전 재정과 관련해 가지고 있던 생각이, 교과서에서 적용되는 것과 현실 세계에서 적용되는 것은 다르다. 바뀐 생각은 쉽게 돌아가지 않는다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee also stated, "Both the university I attended and the KDI (Korea Development Institute) have strong conservative traditions, so I too emphasized sound finance," but added, "However, observing the past three years of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration has made me reflect a great deal." (또 이 후보자는 “제가 교육받은 대학과 KDI 모두 보수적인 전통이 강한 곳이라 저 역시 건전 재정을 중시했다”면서도 “하지만 윤석열 정부 3년을 지켜보면서 굉장히 많이 돌아보게 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sound finance refers to maintaining fiscal health without excessively increasing debt, a principle long advocated mainly by conservative-leaning economic policymakers. (건전 재정은 빚을 과도하게 늘리지 않고 재정을 유지되게 하는 상태로, 주로 보수 성향의 경제 정책가들이 주장해왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Democratic Party lawmaker Jo Seung-rae remarked, "There's been talk about enlightenment edicts and such; has the nominee been enlightened?" Upon hearing this, the nominee lowered her head, appearing to suppress a smile. (그러자 조승래 민주당 의원은 “계몽령이니 뭐니 얘기가 있었는데, 후보자께서 계몽되신 것이냐”라고 말했다. 이에 이 후보자는 고개를 숙이고 웃음을 참는 모습을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When lawmaker Chung Tae-ho asked, 'Will the People Power Party continue to advocate for fiscal rules?' she explained the reason for her changed perspective, saying, "I lived my whole life believing fiscal soundness was an absolute golden rule," and "It was during the three years of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration, as I engaged with the political sphere, that I gradually opened my eyes to reality and engaged in deep contemplation." (또 정태호 의원이 ‘재정준칙을 계속해서 국민의힘이 주장하지 않겠느냐’라고 묻자, “오랫동안 재정 건전성이 금과옥조인 줄 알고 평생을 살았다”며 “정치의 몸을 잡으면서 조금씩 현실에 눈을 떴고 깊은 고민을 한 것은 윤석열 정부 3년이었다”고 하며 생각이 바뀐 이유를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee also added, "I came to think that when fiscal policy does not align with economic conditions, it can potentially become a disaster." (또 이 후보자는 “재정 정책이 경제 여건과 맞지 않을 때 어떻게 보면 재앙이 될 수 있구나 하는 생각을 했다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, lawmaker Kim Tae-nyeon had asked, "Did you hastily change your stance after being nominated?" The nominee replied, "For the past two years, I have not appeared on broadcasts and have lived keeping my mouth shut," and "During that period, I contemplated deeply and experienced the collapse of what I had believed in my entire life." (앞서 김태년 의원은 “지명받고 나서 급하게 입장을 바꾼 것 아니냐”고 물었는데, 이 후보자는 “지난 2년간 방송에 나가지 않고 입을 다물고 살았다”며”그 기간 동안 많이 고민했고 평생 믿어왔던 것이 무너지는 경험을 했다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/L2DCLON3GJE6HJ6PFP2PCRVOWU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HBRTCMLDHEYWKOBYMNSTQNZWGQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:50:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Mentions "Don't Buy Stocks with 'L'" Report... "Would Such Dual Listings Be Allowed in the U.S.?" (“L 들어간 주식 안 사” 보도 언급한 李 대통령… “미국서 이런 중복상장 허용되겠나”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/SZSEJ2Y5ONHLZI2B7SMZWBFXLE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G5QTEODDMYZGCMZTG43DMMRTME.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung pointed out the issue of LS Group's dual listing during a luncheon on the 22nd with members of the Democratic Party of Korea's special committee for KOSPI 5000. A dual listing refers to a listed parent company spinning off and listing a highly profitable subsidiary. When a profitable subsidiary is separated, the parent company's stock price falls, causing losses to shareholders. President Lee specifically cited the LS Group case as problematic. (이재명 대통령이 22일 더불어민주당 코스피5000 특별위원회 의원들과의 오찬에서 LS그룹의 중복 상장 문제를 지적했다. 중복 상장이란 상장된 모회사가 수익성 높은 자회사를 분할 상장하는 것을 말한다. 수익성이 높은 자회사가 떨어져 나가면 모회사의 주가는 떨어져 주주들이 피해를 보는데, 이 대통령이 LS그룹 사례를 콕 짚어 문제라고 지적한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a Cheong Wa Dae (Blue House) official, during the luncheon, President Lee referred to a media report titled 'Don't Buy Stocks with 'L'' and pointed out, in essence, that such cases still exist. He reportedly also mentioned regarding dual listings, "Would such a thing be allowed in the U.S.?" Members of the special committee reportedly responded, "We also have a proposed amendment that, if dual listing is done the American way, allocates shares of the newly listed company to the parent company's shareholders within a range of over 30%." Representative Oh Ki-hyung, the committee chairman, also held a press conference and stated, "There was discussion on handling it strictly." (청와대 관계자에 따르면 이날 오찬에서 이 대통령은 ‘L 들어간 주식은 안 사’라는 제목의 언론 보도를 두고 ‘아직도 이런 사례가 있다’는 취지로 지적했다고 전했다. “중복 상장에 대해선 ‘미국에선 이런 게 허용이 되겠냐’는 언급도 했다고 한다. 특위 소속 의원들은 “우리도 미국식으로 이중 상장이 되면 그 상장 회사 주식을 모회사의 주주들에게 30% 이상 범위 내에서 배정하는 개정안이 나와 있다”고 답변했다고 한다. 특위 위원장인 오기형 의원도 기자회견을 열고 “엄격하게 처리하자는 논의가 있었다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;LS Group's recent push for a dual listing has been mired in controversy. As LS pursued the listing of its non-listed great-grandchild company, Essex Solutions, the LS Minority Shareholders Alliance submitted a petition to the exchange urging disapproval of the preliminary listing review. In his New Year's press conference the previous day, President Lee also cited spin-off listings as one of the reasons for the undervaluation of the domestic stock market, saying, "They suddenly separate and list it, taking the core part away. It's like I bought a pregnant cow, but the calf's owner is someone else." Previously, when LG Energy Solution was spun off from LG Chem in 2022 and listed on the KOSPI, LG Chem's stock price plummeted. (최근 LS그룹의 중복 상장 추진은 논란에 휩싸였다. LS가 비상장 증손회사인 에식스솔루션즈의 상장을 추진하자 LS소액주주 연대가 거래소에 상장 예비 심사 불승인을 촉구하는 탄원서를 제출했다. 이 대통령은 전날 신년 기자회견에서도 “갑자기 떼서 분리 상장해서 알맹이를 쏙 빼가더라. 내가 송아지 밴 암소를 샀는데 송아지 주인이 남이다”라며 분리 상장을 국내 증시 저평가 이유 중 하나로 거론했다. 앞서 LG에너지솔루션이 2022년 LG화학에서 물적 분할한 뒤 코스피에 상장함에 따라 LG화학 주가가 폭락하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee and the special committee members also agreed on the swift promotion of the 'Third Commercial Act Amendment,' which includes mandatory treasury stock cancellation. Originally scheduled for discussion in the National Assembly's Legislation and Judiciary Committee this week, it failed to proceed amid a standoff between the ruling and opposition parties. Representative Oh stated, "There was a consensus to proceed promptly." (이 대통령과 특위 위원들은 자사주 의무 소각 등을 담은 ‘3차 상법 개정안’의 신속한 추진에도 뜻을 모았다. 당초 이번 주 국회 법제사법위원회에서 논의될 예정이었으나 여야 대치 속에서 불발됐다. 오 의원은 “조속히 하자는 공감이 있었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussion also took place on the 'Stock Price Suppression Prevention Act,' proposed by Representative Lee So-young, a member of the special committee. The content aims to regulate the artificial lowering of listed company stock prices for the purpose of reducing inheritance taxes. Representative Oh conveyed that President Lee also actively agreed with this. (특위 소속 이소영 의원이 대표 발의한 ‘주가 누르기 방지법’에 대한 논의도 이뤄졌다. 상속세 절감을 목적으로 상장사 주가를 인위적으로 낮추는 행위를 규제하는 내용으로, 이 대통령도 적극 공감했다고 오 의원은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/SZSEJ2Y5ONHLZI2B7SMZWBFXLE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G5QTEODDMYZGCMZTG43DMMRTME.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:58:44 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>