<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:47:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Kim Jong Un Observes Multiple Rocket Launcher Test-Firing with Daughter Ju-ae... "Enhancing Nuclear War Deterrence" (김정은, 딸 주애와 방사포 시험 사격 참관… “핵전쟁 억제력 고도화”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/D23E6VOSCRAZJOMNL3SHZ43MUY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jong Un Observes Multiple Rocket Launcher Test-Firing with Daughter Ju-ae... "Enhancing Nuclear War Deterrence" (김정은, 딸 주애와 방사포 시험 사격 참관… “핵전쟁 억제력 고도화”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BCXT5XJSPZOMBBVP3OQ6WADV5M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea's Korean Central News Agency reported on the 28th that Kim Jong Un, Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, observed the test-firing of a new large-caliber multiple rocket launcher (North Korea's term for a multiple launch rocket system). This is presumed to be the ballistic missile launch detected by South Korea's Joint Chiefs of Staff the previous day. (김정은 북한 국무위원장이 신형 대구경 방사포(다연장 로켓포의 북한식 표현)의 시험 발사를 지켜봤다고 북한 조선중앙통신이 28일 보도했다. 전날 한국군 합동참모본부가 포착한 탄도미사일 발사로 추정된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The news agency reported, "The Missile General Bureau conducted a test-firing on the 27th to verify the effectiveness of the renewed large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapon system, into which new technology was introduced." It further stated, "The four rocket shells that were launched struck a sea target 358.5 km away from the launch point." (통신은 “미사일총국은 27일 새로운 기술이 도입된 갱신형 대구경 방사포 무기 체계의 효력 검증을 위한 시험 사격을 진행했다”고 전했다. 이어 “발사된 4발의 방사포탄은 발사점으로부터 358.5㎞ 떨어진 해상 표적을 강타했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un observed the test-firing on-site and expressed satisfaction, stating, "(The new multiple rocket launcher) holds very significant meaning in enhancing the effectiveness of strategic deterrence." (김정은은 시험 발사를 현장에서 지켜보고, “(신형 방사포는) 전략적 억제의 효과성을 제고해 나가는 데서 대단히 중요한 의미를 가진다”며 만족감을 표시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then evaluated the new multiple rocket launcher, saying, "Technical renewals were made to most accurately and effectively utilize the most powerful characteristics of the weapon system, and it has been optimized for special attack purposes," and "All indicators of the weapon system have been improved to maximize attack power." (이어 신형 방사포에 대해 “무기 체계의 가장 위력한 특성을 가장 적중하고 효과적으로 활용하기 위한 기술적 갱신을 했으며, 특수한 공격 사용에 적합화됐다” “무기 체계의 모든 지표가 공격력을 극대화하는 데로 향상됐다”고 평가했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also claimed, "The autonomous precision-guided flight system, which can ignore any external interference, is an important feature demonstrating the superiority of this weapon system," and "No other country will be able to reach such a level of technology for at least the next few years." (또 “외부의 어떤 간섭도 무시할 수 있는 자치 정밀 유도 비행 체계는 이 무기 체계의 우월성을 나타내는 중요 특징”이라며 “최소 가까운 몇 년 안에는 그 어느 나라도 이와 같은 기술에 도달하지 못할 것”이라고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un stated that the purpose of developing this new multiple rocket launcher is "to further enhance nuclear war deterrence," adding, "Building the most reliable attack capability and implementing a deterrence strategy based on it is the unchanging line of our Party (Workers' Party of Korea)'s national defense policy." (김정은은 이런 신형 방사포 개발의 목적이 “핵전쟁 억제력을 더욱 고도화해 나가자는 데 있다”며 “가장 확실한 공격 능력을 구축하고 그에 기초한 억제 전략을 실시하는 것은 우리 당(조선노동당) 국가 방위 정책의 불변한 노선”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un also previewed that at the upcoming 9th Party Congress of the Workers' Party, he would "announce the next-stage plans for further strengthening the country's nuclear war deterrence." (김정은은 곧 열릴 것으로 전망되는 노동당 9차 당대회에서 “나라의 핵전쟁 억제력을 가일층 강화하기 위한 다음 단계의 구상들을 천명하게 될 것”이라고도 예고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un's daughter, Ju-ae, also observed this test-firing alongside him. (김정은의 딸 주애도 이번 시험 사격을 김정은과 함께 지켜봤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;South Korea's Joint Chiefs of Staff announced that a short-range ballistic missile (SRBM) was launched from an area north of Pyongyang around 3:50 PM the previous day. The JCS stated the missile was launched towards the uninhabited island 'Al Island' off the coast of Hwadae County, North Hamgyong Province, and flew approximately 350 km. (한국군 합동참모본부는 전날 오후 3시 50분쯤 평양 북방 일대에서 단거리 탄도미사일(SRBM)을 발사했다고 밝혔다. 합참은 미사일이 함경북도 화대군 앞바다의 무인도 ‘알섬’ 방향으로 발사됐고, 약 350㎞를 비행했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The launch occurred shortly after U.S. Under Secretary of Defense for Policy, Elbridge Colby, concluded his schedule in South Korea and departed for Japan. This marks North Korea's second ballistic missile launch this year, following one on the 4th. The South Korean presidential National Security Office held an emergency security situation review meeting immediately after detecting the North Korean military's launch and stated, "We urge North Korea to immediately cease this launch, which is a provocative act violating UN Security Council resolutions." (미국 엘브리지 콜비 미국 전쟁부(국방부) 정책 담당 차관이 방한 일정을 마치고 일본으로 출국한 직후 발사한 것이다. 북한의 탄도미사일 발사는 지난 4일에 이어 올 들어 두 번째다. 청와대 국가안보실은 북한군의 발사를 포착한 직후 긴급 안보 상황 점검 회의를 열고 “북한의 이번 발사는 유엔 안전보장이사회 결의들을 위반하는 도발 행위로, 이를 즉각 중단할 것을 촉구했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/D23E6VOSCRAZJOMNL3SHZ43MUY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BCXT5XJSPZOMBBVP3OQ6WADV5M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:07:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un with Hands in Pockets... Kim Ju Ae Observes Large-Caliber Multiple Rocket Launcher Test Firing (김정은 옆에서 주머니 손 꽂고... 김주애, 대구경 방사포 시험 사격 참관)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/PH4GBTIRHBALXHMSD2E5GDTF4A/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jong Un with Hands in Pockets... Kim Ju Ae Observes Large-Caliber Multiple Rocket Launcher Test Firing (김정은 옆에서 주머니 손 꽂고... 김주애, 대구경 방사포 시험 사격 참관)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YAGJGNANLNLNFKAXDEYTC7UCXA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea conducted a test firing of a performance-improved large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapon system. (북한이 성능을 개량한 대구경 방사포 무기 체계를 시험 사격했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Central News Agency (KCNA) reported on the 28th that "the Missile General Bureau conducted a test firing on the 27th to verify the effectiveness of the renewed large-caliber multiple rocket launcher weapon system with newly introduced technology." (조선중앙통신은 28일 “미사일 총국은 27일 새로운 기술이 도입된 갱신형 대구경 방사포 무기 체계의 효력 검증을 위한 시험 사격을 진행했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman of the State Affairs Commission Kim Jong Un observed the test launch on-site and expressed satisfaction, stating it "holds very significant meaning in enhancing the effectiveness of strategic deterrence." (김정은 국무위원장은 시험 발사를 현장에서 지켜보고 “전략적 억제의 효과성을 제고해 나가는 데서 대단히 중요한 의미를 가진다”며 만족감을 표시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He further said, "Technical updates have been made to most accurately and effectively utilize the weapon system's most powerful characteristics, making it suitable for special attack purposes," and "all indicators of the weapon system have been improved to maximize attack power." Additionally, he stated, "The self-contained precision-guided flight system, which can ignore any external interference, is a key feature demonstrating the superiority of this weapon system," and "for at least the next few years, no other country will be able to reach this level of technology." (이어 “무기 체계의 가장 위력한 특성을 가장 적중하고 효과적으로 활용하기 위한 기술적 갱신을 하였으며, 따라서 특수한 공격 사용에 적합화됐기 때문”이라며 “무기 체계의 모든 지표가 공격력을 극대화하는 데로 향상됐다”고 했다. 아울러 “외부의 그 어떤 간섭도 무시할 수 있는 자체 정밀유도 비행 체계는 이 무기 체계의 우월성을 나타내는 중요 특징”이라며 “최소한 앞으로 몇 년 안에는 그 어느 나라도 이와 같은 기술에 도달하지 못할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un said, "The purpose of this activity is none other than to further advance our nuclear war deterrence capability," and also described the development of such weapon systems as a "responsible exercise of deterrence" for "self-defense." He added, "Building the most reliable attack capability and implementing a deterrence strategy based on it is the unwavering line of our Party's national defense policy," and "the 9th Congress of the Workers' Party will announce the next-stage plans to further strengthen the country's nuclear war deterrence capability." (김정은은 “해당 활동의 목적은 다른 데 있는 것이 아니라, 분명히 핵전쟁 억제력을 더욱 고도화해 나가자는 데 있다”며 이러한 무기 체계 개발이 ‘자체 방위’를 위한 “억제력의 책임 있는 행사”라고도 했다. 그러면서 “가장 확실한 공격 능력을 구축하고, 그에 기초한 억제 전략을 실시하는 것은 우리 당 국가방위 정책의 불변한 노선”이라며 “노동당 제9차 대회는 나라의 핵전쟁 억제력을 한층 강화하기 위한 다음 단계의 구상들을 천명하게 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, it appears that the upcoming 9th Party Congress, expected to be held soon, will unveil new plans for strengthening defense capabilities, similar to the 8th Party Congress which presented a five-year defense development plan and five major tasks. (이에 따라 조만간 열릴 것으로 보이는 제9차 당대회에서는 국방력 발전 5개년 계획과 5대 과업을 제시한 8차 당대회 때처럼, 국방력 강화를 위한 새로운 계획을 공개할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KCNA released photos from the test firing site, stating, "The four fired multiple rocket shells struck a sea target 358.5 km away from the launch point." (조선중앙통신은 “발사된 4발의 방사포탄은 발사점으로부터 358.5㎞ 떨어진 해상 표적을 강타했다”며 시험 사격 현장 사진을 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this day, Kim Jong Un's daughter, Kim Ju Ae, also observed the test firing. According to the released photos, Kim Ju Ae was seated while Kim Jong Un stood beside her watching the test firing. A scene was also captured where Kim Ju Ae was walking alongside Kim Jong Un in front of a vehicle carrying the large-caliber multiple rocket launcher, with her hands in her coat pockets. North Korean media did not directly mention Kim Ju Ae's accompaniment, but her image was prominently featured in the released photos. (이날 김정은 딸 김주애도 시험 사격을 참관했다. 이날 공개된 사진을 보면, 김주애는 앉아 있고 김정은이 옆에 서서 시험 사격을 지켜본다. 대구경 방사포가 실린 차량 앞에서 김정은과 나란히 걷는 과정에서 김주애가 코트 주머니에 손을 꽂은 장면도 포착됐다. 북한 매체들은 김주애가 동행한 사실을 직접적으로 언급하지 않았으나, 공개된 사진 속엔 김주애 모습이 비중 있게 담겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the Joint Chiefs of Staff announced that they had detected several unidentified ballistic missiles launched from the area north of Pyongyang into the East Sea around 3:50 PM the previous day, and that the detected North Korean missiles flew approximately 350 km. (앞서 합동참모본부는 전날 오후 3시 50분쯤 평양 북방 일대에서 동해상으로 발사된 미상 탄도 미사일 수 발을 포착했다며, 포착된 북한의 미사일이 약 350㎞를 비행했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This ballistic missile launch by North Korea is the first in 23 days since the 4th of this month and the second this year. This launch occurred during the consecutive visits to South Korea and Japan by U.S. Under Secretary of Defense for Policy, Elbridge Colby. (북한의 탄도 미사일 발사는 지난 4일 이후 23일 만이며, 올해 들어 두 번째다. 이번 발사는 엘브리지 콜비 미국 국방부(전쟁부) 정책 담당 차관의 한·일 연쇄 방문 중에 이뤄졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/PH4GBTIRHBALXHMSD2E5GDTF4A/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YAGJGNANLNLNFKAXDEYTC7UCXA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:10:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rep. Han Jun-ho of the Democratic Party: "Proposing Merger Before Local Elections Raises Suspicion of 'Other Intentions' Regarding Chung Cheong-rae" (與 한준호 “지선 전 합당, 정청래 ‘다른 의도’ 있다는 의심 불러와”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/RAN5TLV5XNCNLOUPQ7ACVOISI4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Rep. Han Jun-ho of the Democratic Party: "Proposing Merger Before Local Elections Raises Suspicion of 'Other Intentions' Regarding Chung Cheong-rae" (與 한준호 “지선 전 합당, 정청래 ‘다른 의도’ 있다는 의심 불러와”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OBDXL6YQ4JJTXDTCODPQQNJ3IQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, Rep. Han Jun-ho of the Democratic Party claimed that party leader Chung Cheong-rae's proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party "raises suspicion that there are other intentions." (더불어민주당 한준호 의원은 28일 정청래 대표가 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 것에 대해 “다른 의도가 있다는 의심을 불러온다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Appearing on SBS Radio's 'Kim Tae-hyun's Political Show' this morning, Rep. Han said regarding Leader Chung's surprise proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party on the 22nd, "I am raising the issue that it is too rough in terms of timing, speed, and method." (한 의원은 이날 아침 SBS라디오 ‘김태현의 정치쇼’에 출연해 정 대표가 지난 22일 조국혁신당에 합당을 기습적으로 제안한 데 대해 “저는 시기, 속도, 방법상 너무 거칠다는 문제 제기를 하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han criticized, "To discuss a merger, democratic procedures should be followed, but (Leader Chung) made (the proposal) without having this procedural legitimacy." (한 의원은 “합당 논의를 하기 위해서는 민주적인 절차를 진행해야 하는데, (정 대표는) 이런 절차적 정당성을 갖지 않은 상태에서 (제안을) 했다”고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han also stated, "(A merger) is done when the number of stakeholders is smallest, so it is usually done right before a presidential election," adding, "Discussing a merger at a time (ahead of local elections) when the number of stakeholders is greatest is not appropriate, both in terms of practical benefits and timing." (한 의원은 또 “(합당은) 가장 이해 당사자가 적을 때 하는 것이어서 보통 대선 직전에 한다”며 “(지방선거를 앞둬) 이해 당사자가 가장 많은 시기에 합당을 논의한다는 것은 실리 면에서도 그렇고 시기상으로도 맞지 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han then pointed out, "Why did (he) do it in that way?" and asked, "On the day the KOSPI broke through 5000, ahead of local elections when there are countless stakeholders, why did he go alone, hold a press conference, and make the announcement without even discussing it with the leadership?" (한 의원은 이어서 “왜 그런 방식으로 (합당 제안을) 했느냐”며 “코스피가 5000을 돌파하던 날에, 지방선거를 앞두고 이해 당사자가 수없이 많은 상태에서, 지도부 논의조차도 없이 본인이 혼자 가서 기자회견을 열고 발표를 하느냐”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han argued, "Regardless of (the suspicion of 'other intentions'), the (surprise proposal) act itself invites such suspicion." He added, "Especially if (the merger) proceeds when there are this many stakeholders, it will inevitably raise many suspicions." (한 의원은 그러면서 “(‘다른 의도’가 있다는) 의심을 떠나서, (기습 제안) 행위 자체가 그런 의심을 불러온다”고 주장했다. “특히 이해 당사자가 이렇게 많은 상태에서 (합당을) 진행하게 되면 많은 의혹을 불러일으킬 수밖에 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han mentioned that hundreds of text messages from party members criticizing Leader Chung's merger proposal come in daily, saying, "Some are opposed to the integration itself, and others are raising issues about the procedure." He continued, "(If the merger is put to a vote of all party members) I believe it could pass, but it won't be easy to achieve a high approval rate, and even if it passes, it will cause much controversy." (한 의원은 정 대표의 합당 제안을 비판하는 당원들의 문자메시지가 하루에 수백 통씩 온다며, “통합 자체를 반대하는 분들도 계시고, 절차에 대한 문제를 제기하시는 분들도 계신다”고 했다. 그러면서 “(합당을 전 당원 투표에 부치면) 통과는 될 수 있다고 보지만, 높은 찬성률을 받아 내기가 쉽지 않고, 통과가 되고 나서도 많은 논란을 불러일으킬 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Han argued, "At a time when there are many stakeholders, such important discussions and decisions should be temporarily postponed. It is right to proceed (with the merger) after the local elections, following democratic procedures to persuade and gain understanding from party members and the public." (한 의원은 “이해 당사자가 많은 시기에는 이러한 중요한 논의와 결정은 잠시 보류하고, 지방선거 이후에 민주적 절차를 거쳐서 당원과 국민을 설득하고 이해시킨 다음에 (합당을) 진행하는 것이 맞다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/RAN5TLV5XNCNLOUPQ7ACVOISI4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OBDXL6YQ4JJTXDTCODPQQNJ3IQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:41:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>China Begins Moving Platform in West Sea 'Provisional Measure Zone'... Blue House Welcomes "Meaningful Progress" (中 서해 ‘잠정조치수역’ 플랫폼 이동 착수… 靑 “의미 있는 진전” 환영)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/25MOU6AIOVARPJP7ZWZVBNMSAI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;China Begins Moving Platform in West Sea 'Provisional Measure Zone'... Blue House Welcomes "Meaningful Progress" (中 서해 ‘잠정조치수역’ 플랫폼 이동 착수… 靑 “의미 있는 진전” 환영)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KTWP2HRFEJHCTN4AX4E3VHOFRU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House officially welcomed on the 28th China's decision to move a management platform it had unilaterally installed within the West Sea Provisional Measure Zone (PMZ). (청와대는 중국 정부가 서해 잠정조치수역(PMZ) 내에 일방적으로 설치했던 관리 플랫폼을 이동시키기로 결정한 것에 대해 28일 공식 환영 입장을 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government announced the previous day (26th) that the management platform installed within the Provisional Measure Zone was being moved by a Chinese company based on its own needs. This facility had been a focal point of concerns and criticism regarding maritime rights and interests in the West Sea. The Blue House stated, "Given that this management platform has been a focal point of various concerns, we welcome this measure as meaningful progress." This move is interpreted as China partially accepting our government's persistent protests and requests for consultation. (중국 정부는 전날(26일) 잠정조치수역 내에 설치된 관리 플랫폼을 중국 측 기업이 자체적인 수요에 따라 이동시키고 있다고 발표했다. 해당 플랫폼은 그동안 서해상 해양 권익을 둘러싼 우려와 비판의 중심이 되어왔던 시설물이다. 청와대는 “그간 해당 관리 플랫폼이 여러 우려의 중심이 되어온 만큼, 이번 조치를 의미 있는 진전으로 환영한다”고 했다. 이번 이동은 중국이 우리 정부의 지속적인 항의와 협의 요청을 일정 부분 수용한 결과로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House said, "Our government has continued consultations with China based on its stance opposing the unilateral installation of structures within the Provisional Measure Zone." It added, "While actively safeguarding our maritime rights and interests in the West Sea, the government will continue its efforts to make the West Sea a peaceful sea." (청와대는 “우리 정부는 잠정조치수역 내 일방적인 구조물 설치를 반대한다는 입장 아래 중국과의 협의를 이어왔다”고 했다. 이어 “정부는 서해에서 우리의 해양 권익을 적극 수호하는 가운데, 서해를 평화로운 바다로 만들어나가기 위한 노력을 계속해 나갈 것”이라고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/25MOU6AIOVARPJP7ZWZVBNMSAI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KTWP2HRFEJHCTN4AX4E3VHOFRU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:19:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee's "National Assembly is too slow" remark... Ruling party aims to "process 100 bills on the 29th" (李 “국회 너무 느려” 발언에…與 “29일 법안 100개 처리 목표”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/L6DWJB6CXJGATJYT6BJI7PMHXE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee's "National Assembly is too slow" remark... Ruling party aims to "process 100 bills on the 29th" (李 “국회 너무 느려” 발언에…與 “29일 법안 100개 처리 목표”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O224NILN4NJLNIZAKRXVXWSBW4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea announced on the 29th that it is negotiating with the opposition party with the goal of processing 100 non-controversial bills in the National Assembly plenary session. This comes as the ruling party speeds up bill processing, following President Lee Jae-myung's criticism the previous day that "the National Assembly's legislative process is too slow." (더불어민주당이 29일 국회 본회의에서 비쟁점 법안 100개 처리를 목표로 야당과 협상하고 있다고 밝혔다. 이재명 대통령이 전날 “국회의 입법 과정이 너무 느리다”고 지적한 가운데 여당이 법안 처리에 속도를 내는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-hyun, the Democratic Party's chief spokesperson, revealed this after meeting with reporters following a closed-door Supreme Council meeting at Seoul National University Hospital, where the funeral altar for former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan is located, on the 28th. (박수현 민주당 수석대변인은 28일 이해찬 전 국무총리 빈소가 있는 서울대병원에서 비공개 당 최고위원회의를 마친 뒤 기자들과 만나 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park said, "Currently, discussions are underway to process about 60 bills," and added, "There was talk (in the meeting) that the ruling and opposition parties will put their heads together and strive to increase that number to 100." (박 수석대변인은 “현재 약 60여 법안이 처리되는 걸로 협의 중”이라면서 “이를 100개까지 늘리도록 여야가 머리를 맞대고 노력하겠다는 말이 (회의에서) 있었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park explained, "It is undeniable that the bill processing rate of the 22nd National Assembly is generally sluggish," and added, "Not only were there the President's remarks, but Floor Leader Han Byung-do has also expressed his will to proceed with legislation swiftly and with a sense of urgency since taking office." He continued, "The Democratic Party will complete the processing of so-called reform legislation within February and then devote all its energy to processing livelihood-related bills," and said, "Under this roadmap, we will do our best and engage in sincere dialogue with the opposition party." (박 수석대변인은 “22대 국회의 법안 처리 비율이 전체적으로 부진한 것이 틀림없다”면서 “대통령 말씀도 있었지만, 한병도 원내대표가 취임 이후 (입법을) 속도감 있게 신속히 추진하겠다는 의지를 밝히고 있다”고 설명했다. 이어 “민주당은 2월 중 소위 개혁 입법 처리를 완성하고, 바로 민생 법안 처리에 전력을 다할 것”이라면서 “이런 로드맵 하에 최선의 노력을 다하고, 야당과 성의 있는 대화를 해나가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said at a cabinet meeting the previous day, "The National Assembly is currently too slow, making it impossible to work." President Lee stated, "The problem is, isn't it that we are almost eight months (since the government's inauguration) and even legislation on the government's basic policy direction is only at 20%?" and added, "We cannot keep waiting for that." (이 대통령은 전날 국무회의에서 “지금 국회가 너무 느려서 일을 할 수가 없는 상태”라고 했다. 이 대통령은 “문제는 지금 우리가 (정부 출범) 8개월 다 돼 가는데 소위 정부의 기본적인 정책 방침에 대한 입법조차도 20%밖에 안 된다는 것 아니냐”며 “그걸 계속 기다릴 수는 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Democratic Party's Supreme Council approved the composition plan for the City/Provincial Party Nomination Management Committee (Nomination Committee) on this day. Conscious of recent nomination-related misconduct controversies, the Democratic Party minimized the participation of incumbent lawmakers and regional party chairpersons in the Nomination Committee. Chief Spokesperson Park said, "This City/Provincial Party Nomination Committee was composed objectively and neutrally, focusing on external figures, while almost entirely excluding incumbent lawmakers and regional party chairpersons."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (한편 민주당 최고위는 이날 시도당 공직선거후보자추천관리위원회(공관위) 구성 안건을 의결했다. 민주당은 최근 제기된 공천 비위 논란을 의식해 현역 의원과 지역위원장의 공관위 참여를 최소화했다. 박 수석대변인은 “이번 시도당 공관위는 현역 의원과 지역위원장을 거의 배제하고 외부 인사를 중심으로 객관·중립적으로 구성됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/L6DWJB6CXJGATJYT6BJI7PMHXE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O224NILN4NJLNIZAKRXVXWSBW4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:38:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Growing Tariff Controversy... Opposition: "Not a Hotline but Hot Pants" Ruling Party: "Due to Trump's Uniqueness" (커지는 관세 논란...野 “핫라인 아닌 핫바지” 與 “트럼프 특수성 때문”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/EPFQZVHBGRG2ZIOPG6KWRHK75Q/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Growing Tariff Controversy... Opposition: "Not a Hotline but Hot Pants" Ruling Party: "Due to Trump's Uniqueness" (커지는 관세 논란...野 “핫라인 아닌 핫바지” 與 “트럼프 특수성 때문”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z2X7XIICKBCNBA35ZBHWL3THCE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, the ruling and opposition parties clashed at the National Assembly's Foreign Affairs and Unification Committee over U.S. President Donald Trump's sudden announcement of plans to increase tariffs on South Korea. (여야는 28일 국회 외교통일위에서 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 전격적인 대(對)한국 관세 인상 방침을 놓고 공방을 벌였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As President Trump cited legislative shortcomings as the reason for mentioning the tariff hike, the People Power Party claimed the South Korean government was blindsided and demanded National Assembly ratification for the Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations. (트럼프 대통령이 관세 인상 언급의 이유로 입법 미비를 든 가운데 국민의힘은 한국 정부가 뒤통수를 맞았다며 한미 관세 협상에 대한 국회 비준을 요구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the Democratic Party highlighted that President Trump's diplomatic and trade negotiation style is not typical, emphasizing the need for a united response to strengthen the government's negotiating power with the U.S. (반면 민주당은 트럼프 대통령의 외교·통상 협상 스타일이 일반적이지 않다는 점을 부각하며 정부의 대미 협상력을 높이기 위해서라도 단합된 대응이 필요하다고 강조했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a question-and-answer session on current affairs at the committee, People Power Party lawmaker Song Eon-seok mentioned Prime Minister Kim Min-seok's recent visit to the U.S. and meeting with Vice President JD Vance, criticizing, "Prime Minister Kim promoted that he 'promised faithful implementation of follow-up measures to the tariff negotiations' and that 'communication between South Korea and the U.S. was strengthened through establishing a hotline with Vice President Vance.' The very next day, President Trump announced raising tariffs to 25%, hitting us in the back of the head." (국민의힘 송언석 의원은 외통위 현안 질의에서 김민석 국무총리가 최근 미국을 방문해 JD 밴스 부통령과 만난 것을 거론, “김 총리는 ‘관세 협상 후속 조치의 충실한 이행을 약속했다’, ‘밴스 부통령과 핫라인 구축을 통해서 한미 간 소통이 강화됐다’고 홍보했다”며 “그다음 날 트럼프 대통령이 관세를 25%로 인상한다고 해 뒤통수를 맞았다”고 질타했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Since investing $20 billion annually in the U.S. is not easy due to the structure of the foreign exchange market, we asked for ratification approval, but the government and ruling party opposed it. However, looking at President Trump's materials, it reads as if he is asking why ratification approval wasn't obtained." (이어 “1년에 200억 달러 상당씩 (한국이) 미국에 투자하는 건 외환시장 구조상 쉬운 일이 아니기에 비준 동의를 받으라고 했는데 정부·여당이 반대했다”며 “그런데 트럼프 대통령 자료에 보니 왜 비준 동의를 안 했느냐는 취지로 읽힌다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Ki-hyun, a lawmaker from the same party, also mentioned Prime Minister Kim's visit to the U.S., saying, "You called it a hotline, but it's not a hotline; it's a hot pants line," and asked, "The burden on the people is enormous, so why aren't you submitting the ratification agreement?" (같은 당 김기현 의원도 김 총리의 방미를 언급, “핫라인이라고 하셨는데 핫라인이 아니라 핫바지 라인”이라며 “국민 부담이 엄청 커지는데 왜 비준 동의안을 제출하지 않느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Democratic Party lawmaker Lee Jae-jeong pointed out, "No one would deny Trump's uniqueness. The People Power Party committee members did not oppose (the bill), but they are still talking about ratification now. It feels like they are holding us back in a way that reduces agility regarding South Korea's diplomatic and economic situation." (이에 대응해 민주당 이재정 의원은 “트럼프의 특수성을 부인하시는 분들이 없을 것”이라며 “국민의힘 위원님들이 (법안에) 반대하시지는 않으셨지만, 지금도 비준을 얘기하고 계신다. 한국 외교, 경제 상황에 대한 기민성을 줄이는 방식으로 발목 잡고 있는 것 같이 느껴진다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the 'Korea-U.S. Memorandum of Understanding on Strategic Investment' signed last November, Lee added, "South Korea isn't the only country that signed an MOU in this way. No other country is proceeding with a ratification process for this either." (이 의원은 한미가 작년 11월 체결한 ‘한미 전략적 투자에 관한 양해각서(MOU)’와 관련, “지금 MOU 방식으로 체결한 나라가 우리나라만 있는 건 아니지 않나. 관련해서 비준 절차를 진행하는 나라도 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Ki-won, a lawmaker from the same party, stated, "President Trump is taking actions that deviate from existing diplomatic practices. Acting as if we are at fault every time such a thing happens is very wrong. President Trump will do more in the future. The more this happens, the more important it is for us to respond calmly." (같은 당 홍기원 의원은 “트럼프 대통령이 기존 외교 관행에서 벗어난 조치를 하고 있는데 그런 일이 있을 때마다 우리가 문제가 있는 것인 양 하는 건 굉장히 잘못”이라며 “앞으로 트럼프 대통령은 더 할 것이다. 이럴 때일수록 우리가 차분하게 대응하는 게 중요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, U.S. Trade Representative Jamieson Greer said on the 27th (local time), "Later this week, Korean trade officials will visit here (Washington D.C.), and we will hear directly from them. Korea is an ally, and there is no ill will." (이런 가운데, 미 무역 수장인 제이미슨 그리어 무역대표부(USTR) 대표는 27일(현지 시각) “이번 주 후반 한국의 무역 담당자들이 이곳(워싱턴 DC)을 방문해 그들로부터 직접 (얘기를) 듣게 될 것”이라며 “한국은 동맹이고 반감이 있는 것은 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, he added, "We have a trade agreement with Korea, but they have not fulfilled their promises. They failed to pass the related legislation and only introduced new legislation regarding digital services." (그러면서도 “우리와 한국은 무역 합의를 체결했지만 자신들의 약속을 이행하지 않았다”며 “관련 법안을 통과시키지 못하고, 디지털 서비스에 관한 새 법안을 도입했을 뿐”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greer, a former attorney at a major law firm in Washington D.C., is known to hold a highly critical view of the South Korean government's regulations on U.S. big tech companies. It is reported that during a recent meeting with Yeo Han-koo, head of the Trade Negotiation Division at the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy, he also mentioned Coupang, which the Lee Jae-myung administration is pressuring comprehensively. (워싱턴 DC의 대형 로펌 변호사 출신인 그리어는 우리 정부의 미국 빅테크 기업 규제에 대해 매우 비판적인 인식을 갖고 있는 인물로 알려져 있다. 최근 여한구 산업부 통상교섭본부장과 만난 자리에서도 이재명 정부가 전방위적으로 압박하고 있는 쿠팡과 관련해 언급한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/EPFQZVHBGRG2ZIOPG6KWRHK75Q/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z2X7XIICKBCNBA35ZBHWL3THCE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:15:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] 'Opposition in Name Only' Slotting-In: 80% of Bills in Agenda Coordination Committee Processed on Same Day ([단독]‘무늬만 야당’ 끼워넣기, 안건조정위 안건 80% 당일 처리했다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/EGMNACNZDRFCBA2ORFPNM4N7KA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] 'Opposition in Name Only' Slotting-In: 80% of Bills in Agenda Coordination Committee Processed on Same Day ([단독]‘무늬만 야당’ 끼워넣기, 안건조정위 안건 80% 당일 처리했다)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FDBD6KA3HFISLBRSE2B22T5DII.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed on the 28th that 80% of the bills referred to the Agenda Coordination Committee, a deliberation system stipulated by the National Assembly Advancement Act, in the 22nd National Assembly were passed on the same day. The Agenda Coordination Committee, intended for the ruling and opposition parties to reconcile differences over a maximum of 90 days, is effectively being used like a 'fast track'. In this process, a workaround was employed by assigning members from the Progressive Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, who hold similar positions to the Democratic Party of Korea, to the 'opposition party quota'. The People Power Party protested, stating, "Legislative dictatorship by the majority party has become a reality through slotting in 'opposition in name only'." (22대 국회에서 국회 선진화법에 규정된 숙의(熟議) 제도인 안건조정위원회에 회부된 안건 가운데 80%가 당일 의결된 것으로 28일 확인됐다. 여야가 최대 90일간 이견(異見)을 조정하라는 안건조정위가 사실상 ‘패스트트랙’처럼 활용되고 있는 것이다. 이 과정에서 더불어민주당과 유사한 입장인 진보당·조국현신당 의원을 ‘야당 몫’으로 배치하는 편법이 동원됐다. 국민의힘은 “‘무늬만 야당’ 끼워 넣기로 다수당 입법 독재가 현실화된 것”이라고 반발했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to data submitted by the National Assembly Secretariat to the office of PPP lawmaker Jung Hee-yong, a total of 116 bills have been referred to the Agenda Coordination Committee since the opening of the 22nd National Assembly last September. Among these, 93 bills (80%) were passed immediately on the day they were referred, and the remaining 13 bills (11.2%) were also all processed within a week. Ten bills were not handled by the committee. (국회사무처가 국민의힘 정희용 의원실에 제출한 자료에 따르면, 지난해 9월 개원(開院)한 22대 국회에서 안건조정위에 회부된 안건은 모두 116건이다. 이 가운데 93건(80%)은 안건이 회부된 당일에 곧장 의결됐고, 나머지 13건(11.2%) 또한 일주일 이내에 모두 처리된 것으로 나타났다. 10건의 안건은 안건조정위에서 다루지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Agenda Coordination Committee, introduced through the National Assembly Advancement Act, is a system composed of three members each from the ruling and opposition parties (six total) to reconcile differences for up to 90 days. In the current 22nd National Assembly, all 106 bills passed by the Agenda Coordination Committee had members from the Progressive Party (54 times) or the Cho Kuk Innovation Party (52 times) assigned to the opposition quota. This effectively broke the equal composition (3 vs. 3) stipulated by the National Assembly Advancement Act, creating a '4 pro-ruling bloc vs. 2 opposition bloc' structure, enabling one-sided processing of bills. (국회 선진화법으로 도입된 안건조정위는 여야 3명씩, 모두 6명으로 구성해 최대 90일간 이견을 조정하는 제도다. 이번 22대 국회에서 안건조정위에서 의결한 106건은 모두 야당 몫으로 진보당(54차례) 혹은 조국혁신당(52차례) 의원이 배치됐다. 사실상 국회 선진화법에서 규정한 동수(3 대 3) 구성 비율이 무너지고, ‘범여권 4명 대 야권 2명’ 구도가 되면서 법안 일방처리가 가능해진 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given this situation, since the 21st National Assembly where the Democratic Party held a majority, a phenomenon has emerged where controversial bills are being massively referred to the Agenda Coordination Committee. The number, which was 9 in the 19th Assembly and 73 in the 20th Assembly after the system's introduction, has shown a sharp increase to 302 in the 21st Assembly and 116 in the 22nd Assembly. (사정이 이러니 민주당이 과반 의석을 차지한 21대 국회부터 쟁점 안건이 안건조정위에 대거 몰리는 현상도 나타나고 있다. 제도가 처음 도입된 이후 19대 국회 9건, 20대 국회 73건이었던 것이 21대 국회 302건, 22대 국회 116건으로 급증하는 추세다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the start of the 22nd National Assembly, cases where bills were put to a vote despite objections have also increased significantly. According to National Assembly Secretariat data, bills processed by unilateral vote despite objections in the plenary committee or standing subcommittee numbered 44 in the 18th Assembly, 10 in the 19th, 7 in the 20th, 63 in the 21st, and 282 in the 22nd. The forced closure rate of filibusters, a legitimate procedural delay tactic by the minority to check the majority's dominance, is also rising. Forced closures of filibusters numbered 1 in the 19th Assembly, 2 in the 20th, and 5 in the 21st, but in this 22nd Assembly, the number has already exceeded 20 within just one year of its opening. (22대 국회 들어서는 안건에 이의(異議)가 있음에도 그대로 표결 처리한 사례도 큰 폭으로 늘었다. 국회 사무처 자료를 보면 상위 위원회 혹은 상임위 소위에서 이의가 있는데도 일방 표결로 처리된 안건은 18대 44건, 19대 10건, 20대 7건, 21대 63건, 22대 282건으로 집계됐다. 소수파가 다수파의 독주를 견제하기 위한 합법적 의사 진행 지연 행위인 필리버스터(무제한 토론)의 강제 종료율까지 높아지고 있다. 필리버스터 강제 종료는 19대 국회 1건, 20대 국회 2건, 21대 국회 5건인데 이번 22대 국회는 개원한 지 일 년 만에 벌써 20건 이상을 넘어선 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The opposition party is protesting, stating, "The Democratic Party is blatantly disregarding the spirit of democracy." Lawmaker Jung Hee-yong said, "It's only called the Agenda Coordination Committee in name; it is being abused as a legal means for the majority party to quickly process bills," adding, "The system needs improvement to genuinely protect minority opinions in accordance with the spirit of democracy." (야당은 “민주당이 민주주의 취지를 노골적으로 무시하고 있다”고 반발하고 있다. 정희용 의원은 “이름만 안건조정위원회이지, 다수당이 법안을 신속히 처리하기 위한 합법적 날치기 수단으로 악용되고 있는 것”이라면서 “민주주의 취지에 따라 소수의견을 실질적으로 보호하는 방향으로 제도 개선이 필요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/28/EGMNACNZDRFCBA2ORFPNM4N7KA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FDBD6KA3HFISLBRSE2B22T5DII.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:09:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Oh Se-hoon Urges Jang and Han to "Meet Today if They Think of the Nation and People" Ahead of Expulsion Motion Handling (오세훈, ‘제명안 처리’ 앞둔 張·韓에 “국민 생각한다면 오늘이라도 만나라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/MQZFMMLAPRFH5MWP2FRJXS6AK4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Oh Se-hoon Urges Jang and Han to "Meet Today if They Think of the Nation and People" Ahead of Expulsion Motion Handling (오세훈, ‘제명안 처리’ 앞둔 張·韓에 “국민 생각한다면 오늘이라도 만나라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CV2WAA43ERIUNJCFZBEWEU5EKI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon addressed the internal party conflict surrounding the handling of the expulsion motion against former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon, stating, "If you think of the nation and the people, please meet even today." People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk is scheduled to handle the expulsion motion against former leader Han at the party's Supreme Council meeting as early as the 29th. Mayor Oh's remarks are a call for Leader Jang and former leader Han to meet before that to seek a political solution. (오세훈 서울시장은 28일 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표의 제명안(案) 처리를 둘러싼 당내 갈등에 대해 “나라와 국민을 생각한다면 오늘이라도 만나십시오”라고 했다. 장동혁 국민의힘 대표는 이르면 오는 29일 당 최고위원회의에서 한 전 대표 제명안을 처리할 예정이다. 그전에 장 대표와 한 전 대표가 만나 정치적 해법을 모색하라는 게 오 시장 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh stated this in a Facebook post in the afternoon, saying, "There is still time. I sincerely hope that the two individuals, who have led and are leading the party, will meet even today to have an open-hearted, frank discussion about victory and the future." (오 시장은 이날 오후 페이스북에서 “아직 시간이 있다. 당을 이끌었던, 또 이끌고 계시는 두 분이 오늘이라도 만나 승리와 미래에 대해 열린 마음으로 터놓고 얘기하시기를 진심으로 바란다”며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh said, "If you think of the nation and the people, what could be impossible?" and added, "I earnestly urge you to summon the courage and make a decision to show the people grand politics that seeks a path to unity by setting aside personal interests for a moment, not petty politics of blaming each other—the politics that the people desire." (오 시장은 “나라와 국민을 생각한다면 못 할 것이 무엇이겠나”라며 “서로에게 공을 던지는 작은 정치가 아니라, 각자를 잠시 내려놓고 통합의 길을 찾는 큰 정치, 국민이 바라는 정치를 보여드리기 위해 용기를 내어 결단해 주실 것을 간곡한 마음으로 촉구한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh stated, "Many citizens and party members say that whenever they think of our party, they haven't had a single moment of peace of mind since the impeachment until now," and added, "What is more concerning is the cold, sober voice of public sentiment that says if things continue like this, there will be nothing to expect from the People Power Party in the future." (오 시장은 “많은 국민과 당원들이 우리 당을 생각하면 탄핵 이후 지금까지 한시도 마음 편할 날이 없다고 말씀한다”며 “더 우려되는 것은 이대로 가면 앞으로도 국민의힘에 기대할 것이 없다는 냉정한 민심의 목소리”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "This is not about discussing who is right or wrong, nor is it about taking anyone's side at all," and said, "We have already experienced, not long ago, that forcibly expelling a specific individual like stamping them out and pursuing politics of subtraction is a path where everyone loses." (그러면서 오 시장은 “누구의 잘잘못을 얘기하는 것도 아니며, 누구의 편을 드는 것도 전혀 아니다”라며 “이대로 특정인을 찍어내듯 제명하고, 뺄셈의 정치를 강행하는 것은 모두가 패배하는 길임을 우리는 이미 불과 얼마 전에 경험한 바 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh said, "We must no longer embark on a path of self-defeat," and called it "a sin against the people in the face of attempts by a massive power to seize control of the entire nation." He stated, "How could a party that would hand over the precious administration granted by the people, and still not be satisfied, choosing to split itself, have the face to hope for the people's choice?" (오 시장은 “더 이상 우리 스스로 패배하는 길로 들어서면 안 된다”며 “거대한 권력이 온 나라를 장악하려는 시도 앞에서 국민께 죄를 짓는 일”이라고 했다. 그는 “국민이 주신 소중한 정권까지 내어주고, 그것으로도 모자라 스스로 분열하겠다는 당이 무슨 면목으로 국민의 선택을 바랄 수 있겠는가”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in a statement issued under the name of 'All Seoul Metropolitan City Basic Council Members of the Party,' the People Power Party said, "While the leadership's disgraceful infighting fills the media day after day, the backs of basic council members who must persuade residents in local fields are breaking, and public sentiment is growing cold," and urged, "The leadership must immediately stop the exhausting political strife and power struggles and prepare emergency measures for victory in the June 3 local elections." (또한 국민의힘은 ‘당 서울시 기초의회 의원 일동’ 명의로 낸 입장문에서 “지도부의 볼썽 사나운 이전투구가 연일 언론을 도배하는 동안 지역 현장에서 주민을 설득해야 할 기초의원들의 등은 터지고 민심을 싸늘하게 식어가고 있다”며 “지도부는 소모적 정쟁과 알력 다툼을 즉각 중단하고, 6·3 지방선거 승리를 위한 비상 대책을 마련하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They said, "Return to the spirit of 'party first, personal matters later,' not factional interests, and lend strength to local candidates and the field," and warned, "If the leadership continues to sink into the swamp of internal strife, all responsibility for the upcoming local election defeat will lie solely with the current leadership." (이들은 “계파 이익이 아니라 선당후사의 정신으로 돌아와 지방 후보와 현장에 힘을 실어달라”며 “지도부가 계속 자중지란의 늪에 빠져있다면 다가올 지방선거 패배의 모든 책임은 오롯이 현 지도부에 있을 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/MQZFMMLAPRFH5MWP2FRJXS6AK4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CV2WAA43ERIUNJCFZBEWEU5EKI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:37:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UN Command: "Ruling Party's Proposed DMZ Bill Directly Violates Armistice Agreement" (유엔사 “與 발의 DMZ법안, 정전협정에 정면 위배”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/28/662C5RPLK5FALKQEBMTK3QR6G4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;UN Command: "Ruling Party's Proposed DMZ Bill Directly Violates Armistice Agreement" (유엔사 “與 발의 DMZ법안, 정전협정에 정면 위배”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2EDP5YD57JJOVMX6AUCGDGVWBM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Command stated on the 28th that "the passage of the DMZ law directly violates the Armistice Agreement," regarding the 'Act on the Peaceful Use of the Demilitarized Zone (DMZ)' being promoted by the ruling party. This goes a step further from the UNC's statement last December, which asserted that control over access to the DMZ south of the Military Demarcation Line is the inherent authority of the UNC. It is extremely unusual for the UNC, which is responsible for managing the armistice on the Korean Peninsula during peacetime, to meet with reporters directly to state its position on a specific issue. (유엔군사령부는 여당이 추진하고 있는 ‘비무장지대(DMZ)의 평화적 이용에 관한 법률’과 관련해 “DMZ법 통과는 정전협정 정면 위배”라고 28일 밝혔다. 유엔사는 지난해 12월 성명을 통해 군사분계선 이남 DMZ 출입 통제는 유엔사의 고유 권한이라고 밝혔는데 여기서 한발 더 나아간 것이다. 평시 한반도 정전 관리 업무를 담당하고 있는 유엔사가 특정 현안과 관련해 기자들과 만나 직접 입장을 밝힌 것은 극히 이례적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A UNC official, meeting with reporters at the Dragon Hill Hotel in Yongsan, Seoul, said, "The South Korean government can take back jurisdiction over the southern area of the DMZ based on its sovereignty," but added, "However, legally and logically, if the South Korean government does so, it would directly conflict with the Armistice Agreement." The UNC official also stated regarding the passage of the DMZ law, "That action would have serious consequences." (유엔사 관계자는 이날 서울 용산 드래곤힐호텔에서 기자들과 만나 “한국 정부는 주권에 따라 DMZ 남측 구역에 대한 관할권을 회수할 수 있다(can take back)”면서도 “하지만 법리적·논리적으로 볼 때 한국 정부가 그렇게 한다면 이는 정전협정과 직접적으로 충돌하게 된다”고 했다. 유엔사 관계자는 DMZ법 통과와 관련해 “그 행동에는 중대한 결과가 따를 것”이라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the official said, "From a legal perspective, if the DMZ bill passes, it would be a declaration by the South Korean government that it is no longer subject to the Armistice Agreement," adding, "If this situation occurs, it would undermine the authority of the UNC, which manages and supervises the Armistice Agreement, and cause significant concern not only between South Korea and the UNC but also among other parties." This was interpreted to mean that not only the United States but also UNC member countries and North Korea are concerned about this. (그러면서 “법리적 관점에서 DMZ 법안이 통과되면 한국 정부는 정전협정의 대상이 되지 않겠다는 선언을 하는 것”이라며 “이런 상황이 발생하면 정전협정을 관리·감독하는 유엔사 권한을 저해하고 한국·유엔사뿐 아니라 다른 당사자들 사이에 상당한 우려를 야기하게 될 것”이라고 했다. 미국은 물론 유엔사회원국과 북한 등도 이를 우려한다는 의미로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the inauguration of the Lee Jae-myung administration, lawmakers including Lee Jae-gang and Han Jeong-ae have respectively proposed bills that would allow the South Korean government to approve access to the DMZ for non-military and peaceful purposes, and Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young is also urging its swift passage. (이재명 정부 출범 후 이재강·한정애 의원 등은 비군사적·평화적 목적의 경우 DMZ 출입을 한국 정부가 승인할 수 있도록 하는 법안을 각각 발의했고 정동영 통일부 장관도 조속한 통과를 촉구하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the UNC has stepped forward, arguing that limiting the UNC Commander's access control authority, as claimed by the ruling party, violates the Armistice Agreement. The UNC also stated its position that, in principle, if the law is enacted and civilians enter and exit the DMZ without the UNC Commander's approval, it would constitute a 'violation of the Armistice Agreement.' (이에 대해 유엔사는 여권 주장대로 유엔사령관의 출입 통제권을 제한하는 것은 정전협정 위반이라고 주장하고 나선 것이다. 만약 해당 법이 입법돼 유엔사령관 승인 없이 민간인이 DMZ를 출입하게 될 경우 원칙적으로는 ‘정전협정 위반’이라는 입장도 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UNC official said, "If civilians cross the MDL, it is a violation of the Armistice Agreement," and added, "If we start allowing civilian access to the DMZ without consultation or approval from the UNC, it undermines the very reason for the DMZ's existence as a buffer zone." (유엔사 관계자는 “민간인도 MDL을 월선하면 정전협정을 위반하는 것”이라며 “유엔사와의 협의나 승인 없이 민간인의 DMZ 출입을 허용하기 시작하면 완충 지역이라는 DMZ의 존재 이유를 훼손하는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UNC official stated, "It needs to be made clear," and emphasized, "If an incident occurs within the DMZ and hostilities resume, the person who will be held accountable for the failure is not the President of the Republic of Korea, but the UNC Commander." A military source said, "Looking at recent incidents like the drone situation, from the UNC's perspective, they have no choice but to consider the possibility of South Korean civilians engaging in unexpected actions within the DMZ." (유엔사 관계자는 “분명히 해둘 필요가 있다”며 “만약 DMZ 내에서 사건이 발생해 적대행위가 재개된다면, 실패의 책임을 추궁받을 사람은 대한민국 대통령이 아니고 유엔사령관”이라고 했다. 군 소식통은 “최근 무인기 사태 등을 보면, 유엔사 입장에서는 한국 민간인이 DMZ 내에서 돌발 행위에 나서는 상황도 고려할 수밖에 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The UNC official said, "The UNC is a military organization, not a state, and cannot possess sovereignty," and explained, "The Armistice Agreement does not transfer sovereignty; it grants jurisdiction and control over the southern area of the DMZ." (유엔사 관계자는 “유엔사는 군사 조직이지 국가가 아니고 주권(sovereignty)을 가질 수 없다”며 “정전협정은 (한국의) 주권을 양도하는 것이 아니라, DMZ 남측 구역에 대한 관할권과 통제권을 부여하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the background of the UNC's denial of access to the DMZ for Kim Hyun-jong, the First Deputy Director of the National Security Office, last year, the UNC explained there were practical reasons. According to the UNC, Deputy Director Kim applied to visit Arrowhead Hill within the DMZ in late November last year, but the timing was postponed and the visit location was changed for safety reasons, coinciding with situations such as a Korean military officer being injured in a mine explosion accident. (유엔사가 지난해 김현종 국가안보실 1차장의 DMZ 출입을 불허한 배경에 대해서는 실무적 이유가 있었다고 설명했다. 유엔사에 따르면 김 1차장은 지난해 11월 말 DMZ 내 화살머리 고지 출입을 신청했지만, 마침 한국군 간부가 지뢰 폭발 사고로 부상을 입는 등의 상황 때문에 안전상의 이유로 시점을 연기하고 방문 장소도 변경했다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;UNC Commander Xavier Brunson, appearing on an American podcast last December, said, "What governs our actions is the 'Armistice Agreement,' and we must adhere to the standards specified in it," adding, "We cannot change the way we work while nullifying the legal document that is the Armistice Agreement." The UNC's remarks today were interpreted as an extension of this stance. However, the UNC official stated, "This meeting was not arranged to express concerns about the ruling party's DMZ legislation." (제이비어 브런슨 유엔사령관은 지난해 12월 미국 팟캐스트에 출연해 “우리의 행동을 규정하는 것은 ‘정전협정’이고 정전협정에 명시된 기준을 준수해야 한다”며 “정전협정이라는 법적 문서를 무력화하면서 일하는 방식을 변경하려고 할 수는 없다”고 말했다. 이날 유엔사의 발언도 이 연장선상에서 이뤄진 것으로 해석됐다. 다만 유엔사 관계자는 “여권의 DMZ법 입법에 대한 우려를 밝히기 위해 마련한 자리는 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/28/662C5RPLK5FALKQEBMTK3QR6G4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2EDP5YD57JJOVMX6AUCGDGVWBM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 22:45:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Defector Diplomat Il-gyu Lee: "Kim Jong-un likely felt 'decapitation fear' watching Maduro's ouster" (탈북 외교관 이일규 “김정은, 마두로 축출 보며 ‘참수 공포’ 느꼈을 것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/7W4GS2W2WJHGBAX3QUWKLZG4KM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Defector Diplomat Il-gyu Lee: "Kim Jong-un likely felt 'decapitation fear' watching Maduro's ouster" (탈북 외교관 이일규 “김정은, 마두로 축출 보며 ‘참수 공포’ 느꼈을 것”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O47MX2MQAVEOFG2HSGVSZRV6KE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former North Korean Deputy Ambassador to Cuba, Il-gyu Lee, analyzed that North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong-un likely felt extreme fear upon seeing the military operation to oust Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro. (이일규 전 주쿠바 북한대사관 참사가 김정은 북한 국무위원장이 니콜라스 마두로 베네수엘라 대통령 축출 군사 작전을 보고 극심한 공포를 느꼈을 것이라고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with AFP on the 28th, the former deputy ambassador said, "The swift U.S. operation that took place in Caracas (the capital of Venezuela) likely instilled in Kim Jong-un the fear that he too could be vulnerable," adding, "Kim Jong-un likely felt firsthand that so-called 'decapitation operations' are actually possible." (이 전 참사는 28일 AFP 통신과의 인터뷰에서 “(베네수엘라 수도) 카라카스에서 벌어진 미국의 신속한 작전은 김정은에게 자신도 취약할 수 있다는 공포를 안겼을 것”이라며 “김정은은 이른바 ‘참수 작전’이 실제로 가능하다는 사실을 체감했을 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "There is a high possibility that the North Korean leadership fell into a state of extreme anxiety after Maduro's ouster," and stated, "Kim Jong-un will likely overhaul his security and response systems in preparation for potential attacks against himself." (이어 “마두로 축출 이후 북한 지도부가 극도의 불안 상태에 빠졌을 가능성이 크다”며 “김정은은 자신에 대한 공격 가능성에 대비해 경호와 대응 체계를 전면적으로 재정비할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Deputy Ambassador Il-gyu Lee worked as a political deputy ambassador at the North Korean embassy in Cuba from 2019 to 2023 before defecting and seeking asylum in South Korea in November 2023. He currently works as a senior research fellow at the Institute for National Security Strategy. During his service in Cuba, he was responsible for representing North Korean interests in Latin America based on Cuba-North Korea relations. It is known that he oversaw events and directly met Kim Jong-un when Cuban head of state Miguel Díaz-Canel, Chairman of the Council of State, visited North Korea in 2018. (이일규 전 참사는 2019∼2023년 쿠바 주재 북한대사관에서 정무참사로 일하다 탈북해 2023년 11월 한국으로 망명했다. 현재는 국가안보전략연구원 책임연구위원으로 근무 중이다. 쿠바 근무 당시에는 쿠바와 북한 간 관계를 기반으로 중남미 지역에서 북한의 이익을 대변하는 역할을 맡았다. 2018년 쿠바의 국가 수반급 정상인 미겔 디아스카넬 쿠바 국가평의회 의장이 방북했을 당시 행사를 총괄해 김정은을 직접 대면하기도 한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this interview, the former deputy ambassador also raised his voice regarding two North Korean soldiers captured as prisoners of war in Ukraine, urging the South Korean government to actively step in for their protection. He said, "Their repatriation to North Korea must absolutely not happen," adding, "Surviving itself would be torture to the point where they would feel it's better to die than return." (이 전 참사는 이번 인터뷰에서 우크라이나에 포로로 잡힌 북한군 2명과 관련해 한국 정부가 적극적으로 보호에 나서야 한다고도 목소리를 높였다. 그는 “이들이 북한으로 송환되는 것은 절대 있어서는 안 된다”며 “돌아가느니 차라리 죽는 것이 낫다고 느낄 만큼 살아남는 것 자체가 고문이 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, he said that watching the recent turbulent period in South Korean politics—marked by former President Yoon Suk-yeol's declaration of a state of emergency, impeachment, and the election of President Lee Jae-myung—has deepened his understanding of liberal democracy. The former deputy ambassador stated, "For several months after the president was impeached, the national system functioned well even without a president," and noted, "This is something unimaginable in North Korea, which does not even allow the thought that the supreme leader could be removed according to the will of the people." (아울러 윤석열 전 대통령의 비상계엄 선포와 탄핵, 이재명 대통령 당선으로 이어진 최근 한국 정치의 격동기를 지켜보며 자유민주주의에 대한 인식이 더욱 깊어졌다고도 했다. 이 전 참사는 “대통령이 탄핵당한 이후 수개월간 대통령 없이도 국가 시스템이 잘 작동했다”며 “이는 북한에서는 상상조차 할 수 없는 일로, 최고 지도자가 민중의 뜻에 따라 끌어내려질 수 있다는 생각 자체를 허용하지 않는다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/7W4GS2W2WJHGBAX3QUWKLZG4KM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/O47MX2MQAVEOFG2HSGVSZRV6KE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 23:07:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling and Opposition Parties to Process 90 Non-Controversial Bills Tomorrow... Including National Assembly Act Amendment on 'Filibuster Presiding Authority Transfer' (여야, 내일 비쟁점 법안 90개 처리...‘필버 사회권 이양’ 국회법 포함)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/JWHXHQLFI5GXNJGCRLQNIGVDXQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Ruling and Opposition Parties to Process 90 Non-Controversial Bills Tomorrow... Including National Assembly Act Amendment on 'Filibuster Presiding Authority Transfer' (여야, 내일 비쟁점 법안 90개 처리...‘필버 사회권 이양’ 국회법 포함)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/XGRNJQPUP5F2XJ5MBA6BRT6P6A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties have agreed to process 90 non-controversial livelihood-related bills, including the Special Act on Semiconductors, at the plenary session on the 29th. An amendment to the National Assembly Act, which allows the Assembly Speaker to transfer presiding authority to standing committee chairpersons during a plenary session filibuster, will also be processed by agreement. (여야가 29일 본회의에서 반도체 특별법 등 비쟁점 민생 법안 90건을 합의 처리하기로 했다. 본회의 필리버스터 시 국회의장이 사회권을 상임위원장에 이양할 수 있도록 하는 국회법 개정안도 합의 처리된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Han Byung-do, floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, and Song Eon-seok, floor leader of the People Power Party, reached this agreement during a meeting on the afternoon of the 28th. Floor Leader Song stated, "The agenda items for tomorrow's plenary session will be about 90 non-controversial bills that have been pending in the plenary session after passing through standing committees and the Legislation and Judiciary Committee," adding, "We also agreed to process the National Assembly Act amendment tomorrow." (더불어민주당 한병도 원내대표와 국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 28일 오후 회동을 갖고 이같이 합의했다. 송 원내대표는 “내일 본회의 처리 안건은 그동안 상임위와 법사위를 통과해 본회의에 계류된 비쟁점 법안 중심으로 90건 정도”라면서 “국회법 개정안도 내일 처리하기로 합의했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party had originally planned to submit and process the so-called three major judicial reform bills at the plenary session on the 29th, including the Supreme Court Justice Expansion Act, the Judicial Distortion Crime Act, and the Constitutional Court Appeal Act. However, as it became expected that the processing of other livelihood-related bills would also be delayed due to the People Power Party's unlimited debate (filibuster), the party shifted its stance to 'prioritizing livelihood bills'. Accordingly, bills with relatively little disagreement between the parties, such as the Special Act on Semiconductors which includes content on direct state financial support like subsidies for semiconductor companies, are scheduled to be processed first in the plenary session. (민주당은 당초 29일 본회의에 대법관 증원법, 법 왜곡죄, 재판소원 등 이른바 3대 사법 개혁 법안을 상정·처리할 계획이었다. 그러나 국민의힘의 무제한 토론(필리버스터)으로 다른 민생 법안 처리까지 늦어질 것으로 예상되자 ‘민생 법안 우선 처리’로 기조를 바꿨다. 이에 따라 반도체 기업에 보조금 등 국가가 직접 재정을 지원하는 내용을 담은 반도체 특별법 등 여야 간 이견이 적은 법안들이 먼저 본회의에서 처리될 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party had also initially intended to process a revised Criminal Act on the 29th, which expands the scope of espionage from 'enemy state' to 'foreign country or equivalent organization'. However, it decided not to submit it because the Judicial Distortion Crime Act is bundled with the bill submitted to the plenary session, and the People Power Party could oppose it. (민주당은 당초 간첩죄의 적용 대상을 ‘적국’에서 ‘외국 또는 이에 준하는 단체’로 확대하는 형법 개정안도 29일 처리하려고 했지만, 본회의에 부의된 법에 법 왜곡죄가 묶여 있어 국민의힘이 반대할 수 있다는 이유로 상정하지 않기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties have been at odds since late last year over the processing of various contentious bills, including the Special Prosecutor Act. The processing of various livelihood-related bills has been delayed in the process of the Democratic Party pushing ahead with processing reform bills and the People Power Party countering with filibusters. As Deputy Speaker Joo Ho-young from the People Power Party refused to preside over the filibuster, criticizing the meeting conduct of Speaker Woo Won-shik, the physical burden on Speaker Woo and Deputy Speaker Lee Hak-young from the Democratic Party also increased. (여야는 지난 연말부터 특검법 등 각종 쟁점 법안 처리를 두고 대립해왔다. 민주당이 개혁 법안 처리를 강행하고 국민의힘이 필리버스터로 맞대응하는 과정에서 각종 민생 법안 처리가 늦어졌다. 국민의힘 출신 주호영 부의장이 우원식 국회의장의 회의 진행 방식을 문제 삼으며 필리버스터 사회를 거부하면서 우 의장과 민주당 출신 이학영 부의장의 체력 부담도 커졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the Democratic Party pushed for an amendment to the National Assembly Act to allow the Assembly Speaker to transfer presiding authority not only to Deputy Speakers but also to standing committee chairpersons during a filibuster. The Democratic Party initially tried to include a provision in the amendment that would allow the Assembly Speaker to stop a filibuster if fewer than 60 members are present, but it was excluded due to opposition from the pan-opposition bloc, including the Rebuilding Korea Party. (그러자 민주당은 필리버스터 시 국회의장이 부의장뿐만 아니라 상임위원장에게도 사회권을 이양할 수 있도록 국회법 개정을 추진했다. 민주당은 당초 60명 이상이 재석하지 않으면 국회의장이 필리버스터를 중단할 수 있도록 하는 내용도 개정안에 포함시키려 했지만 조국혁신당 등 범여권 반대로 제외했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/JWHXHQLFI5GXNJGCRLQNIGVDXQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/XGRNJQPUP5F2XJ5MBA6BRT6P6A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 23:48:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Yong-beom: "We will restore KOSDAQ to its original essence" (김용범 “코스닥이 코스닥 다웠던 시절로 되돌리겠다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/VZNMJ22CYVFUBHYUYENLLKJMME/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Yong-beom: "We will restore KOSDAQ to its original essence" (김용범 “코스닥이 코스닥 다웠던 시절로 되돌리겠다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GQ3DGNRSHEZTEMRXMZRDKMRVGM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Policy, stated, "President Lee Jae-myung has directed the Korea Exchange (KRX) to undertake reforms that are central to the capital market," and added, "The Financial Services Commission, the Financial Supervisory Service, and the Exchange have officially begun related discussions." (김용범 청와대 정책실장은 “이재명 대통령이 한국거래소(KRX)가 자본시장의 핵심이 되는 개혁을 지시했다”며 “금융위원회·금융감독원·거래소가 본격적으로 관련 논의를 시작했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a briefing on current affairs held at the Chunchugwan of the Presidential Office on the 28th, Secretary Kim conveyed, "The President gave instructions with the intent of examining the entire system to see if we can make (our country's capital market) the world's best capital market. We are reviewing plans to fundamentally upgrade the system." He particularly noted, "We are contemplating appropriate measures to restore KOSDAQ to its original essence, to the era when KOSDAQ was truly KOSDAQ, meaning its initial status," and added, "Currently, KOSDAQ is quite disappointing compared to KOSPI." (김 실장은 28일 청와대 춘추관에서 열린 현안 브리핑에서 “(우리나라 자본시장을) 세계 최고 자본시장으로 만들 수 없나 하고 제도 전반을 들여다보라는 취지의 지시를 대통령이 했다. 제도를 근본적으로 업그레이드할 방안을 검토하고 있다”며 이같이 전했다. 그는 특히 “코스닥은 당초 코스닥이 코스닥다웠던 시절, 즉 초기 위상으로 되돌릴 수 있도록 걸맞은 방안을 고민 중”이라며 “현재 코스닥은 코스피에 비하면 상당히 아쉽다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Secretary Kim said, "Zombie companies must be promptly cleared out for new companies to enter." He continued, "We will also soon propose creating a startup boom," and stated, "We are developing plans to transform the KOSDAQ market so it can accommodate startups that the government focuses on in various aspects such as innovation, artificial intelligence (AI), and energy." This means that by breaking the structure where companies failing to meet listing maintenance requirements remain for long periods, new enterprises can enter, and the 'exit' path for startups can become robust again. (김 실장은 “좀비 기업들은 바로바로 정리가 되어야 새로운 기업이 들어온다”고 했다. 이어 “곧 창업 붐을 만들자는 제안도 할 것”이라며 “혁신, 인공지능(AI), 에너지 등 여러 측면에서 정부가 주안점을 두는 창업을 담아낼 수 있게 코스닥 시장을 탈바꿈할 만한 방안을 만들고 있다”고 했다. 상장 유지 요건을 채우지 못하는 기업이 장기간 잔류하는 구조를 깨야 신생 기업이 들어오고, 스타트업의 ‘자금 회수(엑시트)’ 경로도 다시 탄탄해질 수 있다는 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He remarked, "Even when major issues arise, the market shows signs of quickly resolving them," and added, "The perception of asset allocation, which had been skewed towards real estate, is being shaken, and a trend of increasing proportion towards securities and stocks is visible." Secretary Kim said, "We will continue the 5000 momentum," and added, "We will use the revision of the Capital Markets Act as an opportunity to advance this market itself." (그는 “대형 이슈가 발생해도 시장이 빠르게 정리되는 모습이 나타났다”면서 “부동산에 쏠렸던 자산 배분 인식이 흔들리고, 유가증권·주식 쪽 비중이 커지는 흐름이 보인다”고 했다. 김 실장은 “5000 모멘텀 이어가겠다”면서 “자본시장법 개정을 이 시장 자체를 선진화할 수 있는 계기로 삼겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/VZNMJ22CYVFUBHYUYENLLKJMME/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GQ3DGNRSHEZTEMRXMZRDKMRVGM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 23:29:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blue House: "Trump's Dissatisfaction 100% Due to Legislative Delays in the National Assembly" (靑 “트럼프 불만, 100% 국회의 입법 지연 때문”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/28/TJ4YXUIUHRBITO7R3FFHK5JZYA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GQ3DGNRSHEZTEMRXMZRDKMRVGM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 28th, the Blue House stated regarding the background of U.S. President Donald Trump's 'tariff increase' remarks, "We assess that the U.S. dissatisfaction is 100% due to legislative delays in the National Assembly." This expresses the complaint that the implementation of the Korea-U.S. agreement is being delayed because the Special Act on Investment in the United States is not being processed swiftly in the National Assembly. (청와대는 28일 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 ‘관세 인상’ 발언 배경에 대해 “미국의 불만은 100% 국회에서의 입법 지연에 있다고 보고 있다”고 밝혔다. 국회에서 대미투자특별법이 신속하게 처리되지 않아 한미 간 합의 이행이 늦어지고 있다는 불만을 표출했다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, Senior Secretary to the President for Policy, said at a briefing that day, "The U.S. also knows that the procedures for the U.S. investment fund can only begin after the law's deliberation is completed in Korea," adding, "It seems the U.S. thinks that process is slower than expected and felt frustrated about it." He continued, "We understand that the U.S. side's expectation to quickly launch the investment project is underlying (in this message from President Trump)." (김용범 청와대 정책실장은 이날 브리핑에서 “한국에서 법이 심의가 끝나야 대미 투자펀드의 절차가 시작된다는 것은 미국도 알고 있다”며 “미국은 그 절차가 기대보다 느리다고 생각한 것 같고, 여기서 답답함을 느낀 것 같다”고 말했다. 그러면서 “투자 프로젝트를 빨리 가동하고 싶은 미국 측의 기대가 (이번 트럼프 대통령의 메시지에) 깔려 있다고 이해하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding speculation that the Korean government's strong response to the Coupang incident and the issue of enacting the Online Platform Act had an influence, Senior Secretary Kim drew a line, saying, "(Trump) actively spoke about the National Assembly, not the Korean government." (김 실장은 쿠팡 사태에 대한 우리 정부의 강경 대응과 온플법 제정 문제가 영향을 미쳤다는 추측에 대해선 “(트럼프가) 한국 정부가 아닌 국회에 대해 적극적으로 말했다”며 선을 그었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He further stated, "We will sufficiently explain to the National Assembly that the special legislation is needed in February," and "We will calmly respond and seek solutions, including explaining in detail to the U.S. that our government and the National Assembly are making such efforts." Additionally, he revealed that they are considering ways to conduct preliminary preparations, such as preliminary reviews of investment projects, even before the special law is passed. (이어 “국회에는 2월에 특별법 입법이 필요하다는 설명을 충분히 하겠다”며 “미국에도 우리 정부와 국회가 이런 노력을 한다는 점을 상세히 설명하는 등 차분히 대응하면서 해결책을 모색하겠다”고 했다. 아울러 특별법이 통과되기 이전이라도 투자 프로젝트에 대한 예비검토를 거치는 등 사전 준비를 할 수 있는 방안을 고민해보겠다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/28/TJ4YXUIUHRBITO7R3FFHK5JZYA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GQ3DGNRSHEZTEMRXMZRDKMRVGM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:19:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheong Wa Dae: "Heavy Capital Gains Tax for Multiple Homeowners Grace Period Ending; Could Be Postponed by One or Two Months" (청와대 “다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 종료, 한두달 연기할수도”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/NG2HZ6GXFRGRHK3SBM3RWCF7A4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Cheong Wa Dae: "Heavy Capital Gains Tax for Multiple Homeowners Grace Period Ending; Could Be Postponed by One or Two Months" (청와대 “다주택자 양도세 중과 유예 종료, 한두달 연기할수도”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Y6ZWZB5WJNDVXMZ4CNIFWXKRVI.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Yong-beom, Senior Presidential Secretary for Policy, stated on the 28th regarding the 'grace period for the heavy capital gains tax on multiple homeowners' ending on May 9, "We are reviewing whether to keep the end date as May 9 or postpone it by one or two months." This move by Cheong Wa Dae comes after concerns arose in the real estate market following President Lee Jae-myung's announcement last week that 'there will be no extension of the grace period.' (김용범 청와대 정책실장은 28일 오는 5월 9일 종료되는 ‘다주택자 양도세 중과 제도 유예’에 대해 “종료 시점을 5월 9일로 할지, 한두 달 뒤로 할지 검토 중”이라고 말했다. 이재명 대통령이 지난주 ‘유예 연장은 없다’고 밝힌 뒤 부동산 시장에서 우려가 나오자, 청와대가 유예 종료 시점 조정에 나선 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Secretary Kim emphasized, "The fundamental premise is ending the grace period," adding, "Even if it is postponed by one or two months, that does not undermine the principle." This implies that even if the grace period is extended beyond the original end date of May 9, it will not be for more than one or two months. (하지만 김 실장은 “대전제는 유예를 종료하는 것”이라며 “한두 달 뒤로 하더라도 그것은 원칙을 훼손하는 건 아니다”라고 했다. 종료 시점인 5월 9일보다 유예가 되더라도 한두 달 이상이 되지는 않을 것이란 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the review of adjusting the grace period end date, Secretary Kim said, "The government also bears some responsibility," explaining, "There were many expectations that it would be extended this time as well, since it had been extended over the past four years." He further added, "We also reflect on whether we should have made the decision (not to extend the grace period) a bit earlier." (김 실장은 유예 종료 시점 조정을 검토하게 된 데 대해 “정부도 약간의 책임이 있다”며 “지난 4년 동안 유예를 연장해 왔으니까 이번에도 연장되겠지 하는 관측이 많았다”고 했다. 이어 “(유예 연장을 하지 않는다는) 결정을 조금 더 일찍 했어야 하지 않느냐는 반성도 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that within Cheong Wa Dae, there is an opinion that it would be appropriate to provide some time flexibility, as even if multiple homeowners decide to sell their properties immediately, it inevitably takes time, for instance, to negotiate with tenants. (청와대 내에서는, 다주택자가 지금 당장 주택 매도에 나선다고 하더라도 세입자와 협의도 해야 하는 등 시간이 걸릴 수밖에 없는 만큼 시간적 여유를 주는 게 맞지 않느냐는 의견이 나온 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In political circles, there is also talk that the review might be considering the local election schedule, as even a one-month postponement from the original May 9 end date would push it past the local elections scheduled for June 3. (정치권에서는 애초 종료 시점인 5월 9일에서 한 달만 늦춰도 6월 3일로 예정된 지방선거 이후로 종료 시점이 늦춰지는 만큼, 지방선거 일정 등을 감안한 검토 아니냐는 말도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/NG2HZ6GXFRGRHK3SBM3RWCF7A4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Y6ZWZB5WJNDVXMZ4CNIFWXKRVI.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 23:56:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Embassy in Korea Holds Event for U.S. 250th Anniversary, "Korea-U.S. Enduring Connection" (주한미국 대사관, 美 건국 250주년 행사 “한미 지속적 연결”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/28/UQ4FTHW4EFDHJHNVBGVBX7JYYA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2EK2VCPLOZMELLPRUSXGFKVLEA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Embassy in Korea held a commemorative event on the 28th to mark the 250th anniversary of the founding of the United States, under the theme of 'the enduring cultural connection between Korea and the United States'. (주한 미국 대사관이 28일 미국 건국 250주년을 맞아 ‘한미 양국의 지속적인 문화적 연결’을 주제로 한 기념행사를 열었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The embassy hosted 'Freedom of Expression: Freedom 250 Korea-U.S. Creative Dialogue' at the residence of the Chargé d'Affaires ad interim of the U.S. Embassy in Seoul in Seongbuk-gu. (대사관은 이날 서울 성북구 주한 미국 대사대리 관저에서 ‘표현의 자유: 프리덤(Freedom) 250 한미 창의 대화’를 개최했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ten works by artist Je Jeong-ja, who has been active in the United States, were exhibited at the residence where the event was held. It is said that Artist Je has built her artistic world by combining Eastern spirituality with the influence of innovative American artists such as Jackson Pollock and Andy Warhol. (행사가 열린 관저에는 미국에서 활동한 제정자 작가의 작품 10점이 전시됐다. 제 작가는 잭슨 폴록, 앤디 워홀 등 미국의 혁신적 작가의 영향을 받아 동양의 정신을 결합해 작품 세계를 구축했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The embassy stated, "We aim to commemorate the shared artistic spirit that connects our two countries and to highlight the important role of cultural exchange in promoting a more peaceful international community." (대사관은 “양국을 하나로 잇는 공동의 예술적 정신을 기념하고, 더욱 평화로운 국제사회를 증진하는 데 있어 문화 교류가 지닌 중요한 역할을 강조하고자 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;James Heller, Chargé d'Affaires ad interim of the U.S. Embassy in Korea, said, "Today's event is part of a campaign we will be running throughout the year," adding, "Through this, we showcase the ideals we have pursued together—freedom, creativity, and the belief that every individual should have the freedom of expression." (제임스 헬러 주한 미국 대사대리는 “오늘 이 행사는 저희가 1년 내내 진행할 캠페인의 일환”이라며 “이를 통해서 저희가 함께 추구해 온 이상들, 자유와 창의성, 모든 개인이 표현의 자유를 가지고 있어야 한다는 믿음들을 보여준다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chargé d'Affaires Heller arrived near the end of the event to deliver his remarks, saying, "I am late due to a schedule at the Blue House. I am truly sorry." While he did not disclose specific details regarding the reason for his visit to the Blue House, there is speculation that discussions related to recent issues took place. The U.S. Embassy in Korea sent a letter to the Korean government on the 13th urging the implementation of the Korea-U.S. Joint Fact Sheet agreement signed last November, and U.S. President Donald Trump recently mentioned Korean tariff increases. (헬러 대사대리는 이날 행사가 끝날 무렵 도착해 인사말을 하며 “청와대 일정 때문에 늦었다. 정말 죄송하다”고 했다. 청와대 방문 경위 등 구체적 내용을 밝히지는 않았지만, 최근 현안과 관련된 논의가 이뤄진 것 아니냐는 관측이 나온다. 주한 미국 대사관은 지난 13일 한국 정부에 지난해 11월 체결한 한미 조인트 팩트시트 합의 이행을 촉구하는 내용의 서한을 보냈고, 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령은 최근 한국 관세 인상을 언급했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Approximately 40 people, including Artist Je and other figures from the art world, embassy officials, and reporters, attended the event. The embassy announced plans to hold various commemorative events this year to celebrate the 250th anniversary. (이날 행사에는 제 작가 등 예술계 인사와 대사관 관계자, 취재진 등 40여 명이 참석했다. 대사관 측은 250주년을 축하하는 의미로 올해 다양한 기념행사를 개최할 예정이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Namba, Counselor for Public Affairs at the U.S. Embassy in Korea, stated, "This year marks the United States' 250th birthday," and conveyed that "President Trump has urged that we celebrate the 250th anniversary with close allies like Korea." (니콜라스 남바 주한 미국 대사관 공보공사참사관은 “올해는 미국이 250번째 생일을 맞는 해”라며 “트럼프 대통령께서 한국과 같은 긴밀한 동맹국들과 250주년 축하를 함께할 수 있도록 당부하셨다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "We plan not only to look back and celebrate the past 250 years together but also to explore together how the next 250 years will unfold and what that will mean for Korea and the United States." (그는 “지난 250년을 함께 되돌아보면서 축하하는 시간을 가질 뿐 아니라 향후 250년이 어떻게 펼쳐질지, 그것이 한국과 미국 간에 어떤 의미로 다가올지 함께 탐구해 갈 예정”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/28/UQ4FTHW4EFDHJHNVBGVBX7JYYA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2EK2VCPLOZMELLPRUSXGFKVLEA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:46:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Proposes 'Sugar Tax' Like on Tobacco, to be Used for Regional and Public Healthcare (李대통령 “담배처럼 ‘설탕세’ 부과해 지역·공공의료에 쓰자")</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/4XBBBQSWEZFDTEXJMW52PNRMYI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee Proposes 'Sugar Tax' Like on Tobacco, to be Used for Regional and Public Healthcare (李대통령 “담배처럼 ‘설탕세’ 부과해 지역·공공의료에 쓰자")&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GM4DQZLBMNRDQZJXGAZDKOBYGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung proposed on the 28th the introduction of a 'sugar tax' levied on food and beverages containing excessive sugar or sweeteners. (이재명 대통령은 28일 설탕이나 당류가 과도하게 들어간 식음료에 부과하는 ‘설탕세’를 도입하자고 제안했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sharing an article on X (formerly Twitter) that day introducing the results of a public opinion poll on the sugar tax, President Lee wrote, "Like with tobacco, suppress sugar use through a sugar levy, and reinvest that levy to strengthen regional and public healthcare... What are your thoughts?" (이 대통령은 이날 X(엑스·옛 트위터)에 설탕세 관련 여론조사 결과를 소개한 기사를 공유하며 “담배처럼 설탕 부담금으로 설탕 사용을 억제하고, 그 부담금으로 지역·공공의료를 강화하는 데 재투자…. 여러분 의견은 어떠신가요”라고 적었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sugar tax is primarily implemented to prevent diseases such as obesity and diabetes and promote public health, and has been introduced in over 120 countries overseas, including the UK and the US. Recently, discussions regarding the introduction of a sugar tax have also been progressing domestically. According to a survey conducted by Seoul National University's Health Culture Business Unit from the 12th to the 19th on 1,030 citizens, 80.1% were in favor of introducing the sugar tax. (설탕세는 주로 비만과 당뇨 등 질병 예방과 국민 건강 증진을 목적으로 시행되며 해외에서는 영국과 미국 등 120여 국가에서 도입됐다. 최근에는 국내에서도 설탕세 도입 관련 논의가 진행되고 있다. 서울대 건강문화사업단이 12~19일 국민 1030명을 대상으로 시행한 설문조사 결과, 80.1%가 설탕세 도입에 찬성했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee has recently posted multiple times on social media to express his opinions on government policies and other matters. On the same day, sharing an article about differing interest rates for municipal fund operations by local government, he also said, "Even 1% on 1 trillion won is 10 billion... It's worth comparative research on the level of democracy in that city and the interest rate." (이 대통령은 최근 소셜 미디어에 여러 차례 게시글을 올려 정부 정책 등에 관한 의견을 밝히고 있다. 이 대통령은 이날 지자체별 금고 운용 금리가 다르다는 내용의 기사를 공유하며 “1조원에 1%만 해도 100억…해당 도시의 민주주의 정도와 이자율을 비교 연구해 볼 가치가 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/4XBBBQSWEZFDTEXJMW52PNRMYI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GM4DQZLBMNRDQZJXGAZDKOBYGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:04:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee to Foreign Investors: "Please Invest in the Regions" (이 대통령, 외국인투자자들에게 “지방에 투자해달라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/URW5TC7FWZEJRCFOM3YM4VXU3Y/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVTGKY3CGU3WMY3CG42TQNJXGY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a meeting with foreign-invested companies held at the Blue House on the 28th, President Lee Jae-myung stated, "I think the fact that the Korean government is pursuing region-centric policies could serve as a direction for your future management and investment decisions." The government's policy direction is to disperse infrastructure and resources concentrated in the metropolitan area to the regions, and he called for foreign companies to respond accordingly. (이재명 대통령은 28일 청와대에서 열린 외국인 투자 기업 간담회에서 “한국 정부가 지방 중심의 정책을 편다는 점이 여러분이 앞으로 경영상 투자 결정을 할 때 하나의 방향이 되지 않을까 싶다”고 밝혔다. 정부의 정책 기조가 수도권에 집중된 인프라와 자원을 지방으로 분산시키는 데 있으니, 외국 기업들도 호응해 달라는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Korea is a small landmass, so the distance between Seoul and the provinces is no more than moving between provinces in China, and there is no significant difference in physical distance." However, he added, "Politically and economically, the difference is significant, and resources have been concentrated in the metropolitan area." He continued, "We intend to make a major shift in this regard," stating, "We plan to focus on the regions for renewable energy, prioritize the regions for securing infrastructure, and prioritize the regions for educational and residential conditions." (이 대통령은 “한국은 땅덩어리가 좁아 서울과 지방이라고 해 봤자 중국에서 성(省)과 성 사이를 움직이는 정도에 불과하며 거리상으로는 차이가 없다”면서도 “정치·경제적으로는 차이가 크고 수도권에 자원이 몰렸다”고 했다. 이어 “이를 대대적으로 전환하려 한다”며 “재생에너지도 지방 중심으로, 기반 시설 확보도 지방 먼저, 교육·정주 여건도 지방 먼저, 이렇게 하려고 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding a businessperson's request at the foreign-invested company meeting held at the Blue House that day for fostering green industries, mentioning that 'Korea's electricity prices are relatively less competitive compared to other regions,' President Lee said, "It is true that prices have recently become higher compared to international standards." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 열린 외국인 투자 기업 간담회에서 한 기업인이 녹색 산업 육성을 요청하며 ‘한국은 상대적으로 전력 가격이 다른 지역보다 경쟁력이 있지는 않다’고 언급한 것과 관련해 “국제 기준에 비하면 최근 비싸진 것이 사실”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then stated, "We are mobilizing national capabilities to intensively foster renewable energy and related industries and attract businesses, focusing on the southwestern coastal region," and requested, "We have a national strategy to supply electricity based on renewable energy at much lower costs than in the metropolitan area. Please consider this in your investment decisions or business operations." (그러면서 “서남해안 지역에 집중적으로 재생에너지와 연관 산업을 육성하고 산업 유치를 대대적으로 하려고 국가적 역량을 모으는 중”이라며 “수도권보다 훨씬 싸게 재생에너지 중심으로 전기를 공급할 국가적 전략을 가지고 있다. 투자 결정이나 기업 운영에 참고해 달라”고 요청했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also expressed strong confidence in enhancing the transparency of the domestic capital market and resolving the "Korea Discount." Regarding the recent upward trend in stock prices, President Lee said, "Looking at the fluctuations, it's surprising that the upward trend is faster than expected," adding, "There is an aspect of proper valuation now for what was previously evaluated below its fundamental strength." He further stated, "We will establish a rational corporate governance structure where shareholders are treated properly and ensure fairness and transparency in the stock market," expressing, "I am confident in carrying out such tasks." (국내 자본 시장의 투명성 강화와 ‘코리아 디스카운트’ 해소에 대한 강한 자신감도 내비쳤다. 이 대통령은 최근 주가 상승 흐름에 대해 “변동 상황을 보면 너무 (상승 흐름이) 예상보다 빨라 놀랍다”며 “원래 기초 체력 이하로 평가받던 것이 이제 제대로 평가받는 측면이 있다”고 했다. 그러면서 “주주가 제대로 대접받는 합리적 기업 지배 구조를 만들고, 주식시장의 공정성과 투명성을 확보하겠다”며 “제가 그런 일을 하는 데에는 자신이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding inter-Korean relations, cited as an external investment risk, he said, "Peace on the Korean Peninsula is very important, but there is no need to worry," adding, "We will not engage in unnecessary military confrontation with North Korea, and geopolitical risks will now disappear." (대외 투자 리스크로 꼽히는 남북 관계에 대해서는 “한반도의 평화가 매우 중요한데 걱정하지 않아도 된다”며 “불필요하게 북한과 군사적 대결을 하지 않을 것이며 지정학적 리스크는 이제 없어질 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign-invested companies refer to companies in which foreign investors hold a certain percentage or more of shares under the Foreign Investment Promotion Act. The meeting was attended by representatives from seven foreign chambers of commerce in Korea, including the American Chamber of Commerce in Korea, and executives from 31 foreign-invested companies. President Lee said, "We welcome the fact that last year's foreign investment scale was the largest ever, and we will ensure expectations do not turn into disappointment," urging, "Trust the government of the Republic of Korea and join us in building the future together." (외국인투자기업은 외국인투자 촉진법에 따라 외국인 투자자가 일정 비율 이상 출자한 기업을 뜻한다. 이날 간담회에는 주한 미국상공회의소 등 7개 주한 외국상의 대표와 외국인 투자기업 31개사 임원이 참석했다. 이 대통령은 “지난해 외국인 투자 규모가 사상 최대였다는 점을 환영하며, 기대가 실망으로 변하지 않게 하겠다”며 “대한민국 정부를 믿고 미래를 함께해 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/URW5TC7FWZEJRCFOM3YM4VXU3Y/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVTGKY3CGU3WMY3CG42TQNJXGY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:02:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Physical Contact with 'Paektu Bloodline'?... Defense Minister Who Pat Kim Ju-ae's Back, Future Fate in Question (‘백두혈통’ 신체 접촉?… 김주애 등 두드린 국방상, 향후 거취는)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/Y2HUKURQIVC3FH7V2LEK3I7DMY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Physical Contact with 'Paektu Bloodline'?... Defense Minister Who Pat Kim Ju-ae's Back, Future Fate in Question (‘백두혈통’ 신체 접촉?… 김주애 등 두드린 국방상, 향후 거취는)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/R7CZTOKDHRBAXAZP5EYR3KICAU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A scene appearing to show North Korea's military leadership pushing Kim Ju-ae, the daughter of North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong Un, on the back was broadcast on North Korean state television. Some analysts suggest this action may have breached a systemic 'taboo' and could potentially impact the future fate of the involved leadership. (김정은 북한 국무위원장의 딸 김주애의 등을 군 수뇌부가 떠미는 듯한 장면이 북한 국영 방송을 통해 공개됐다. 일각에선 이 행동이 체제의 ‘금기’를 건드린 것으로, 향후 해당 수뇌부 거취에 영향을 줄 수 있을 정도라는 분석까지 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The North Korea-specialized media outlet Daily NK Japan highlighted this scene in an article published on the 25th titled 'Problematic behavior of a military official who touched Kim Jong Un's daughter... There are also cases of execution for disrespectful attitude.' (북한 전문 매체 데일리NK재팬은 25일 ‘김정은의 딸을 만진 군 간부의 문제 행동… 불경한 태도로 처형된 사례도’라는 제목의 기사를 통해 이 같은 장면을 조명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scene in question was captured in a news video broadcast on the 5th, showing Kim Jong Un inspecting the construction site of the 'Combat Merits Memorial Hall for Overseas Military Operations,' a memorial hall for troops dispatched to Russia. (문제의 장면이 포착된 건 지난 5일 김정은이 러시아 파병군 추모기념관인 ‘해외군사작전 전투위훈기념관’ 건설 현장을 시찰하는 모습을 담은 보도 영상에서다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time, Kim Ju-ae, wearing a scarf mixing red, blue, and white colors seemingly symbolizing the artificial flag, participated in tree planting with her father Kim Jong Un while holding a shovel. Kim Jong Un's wife Ri Sol-ju, his sister Kim Yo-jong (Vice Department Director of the Workers' Party), and Foreign Minister Choe Son-hui also joined the tree-planting work. The scene was staged to show the total mobilization of the supreme leader's family and even officials to contribute labor to the memorial hall's construction. (당시 김주애는 인공기를 상징하는 듯 빨간색·파란색·흰색이 섞인 목도리를 매고 삽을 든 채 아버지 김정은과 나무 심기에 참여했다. 김정은의 아내 리설주와 여동생 김여정 노동당 부부장, 최선희 외무상도 식수 작업에 함께했다. 최고 지도자 가족은 물론 간부들까지 총동원돼 추모기념관 건설에 일손을 보태는 장면을 연출한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The video showed Kim Ju-ae standing behind Kim Jong Un as he shoveled, with Defense Minister Kang Sun-nam approaching her, lightly patting her back twice, and gesturing for her to step forward. Ri Sol-ju stared intently at this from behind before moving closer to Kim Ju-ae. In a subsequent cut, Kim Ju-ae moved from Kang Sun-nam's position to the front of Kim Jong Un to participate in the shoveling. (영상에는 김정은이 삽질을 하는 동안 김주애가 뒤편에 서 있었고, 노광철 국방상이 다가가 김주애의 등을 두 차례 가볍게 두드리며 앞으로 나서라는 제스처를 취하는 모습이 담겼다. 리설주는 뒤에서 이 모습을 뚫어지게 쳐다보다 김주애 가까이 다가갔다. 이후 전환된 화면에서 김주애는 노광철 자리에서 떨어진 김정은 앞으로 이동해 삽질에 참여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Ju-ae is considered a leading candidate for North Korea's next successor. To compensate for the political weakness of being a woman, she has recently been highlighting her 'Paektu Bloodline' image through public activities. In this context, analysts suggest Kim Jong Un might take issue with the fact that a broadcast showed a high-ranking military official, not a blood relative, making direct physical contact with Kim Ju-ae. (김주애는 북한의 차기 유력 후계자로 거론되는 인물로, 여성이라는 정치적 약점을 보완하기 위해 최근 공개 행보를 통해 ‘백두혈통’ 이미지를 부각해 온 바 있다. 이런 상황에서 혈연관계가 아닌 군 고위 인사가 김주애의 신체에 직접 접촉하는 장면이 방송에 그대로 노출된 점을 김정은이 문제 삼을 수 있다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Daily NK Japan's Editor-in-Chief Koh Young-ki stated, "In North Korea, the act of a non-blood relative touching the body of a member of the supreme leader's family, the 'Paektu Bloodline,' is extremely unusual in itself," adding, "It is highly likely to be perceived as disrespectful." (데일리NK재팬 고영기 편집장은 “북한에서는 최고지도자 일가인 ‘백두혈통’의 몸에 혈연관계가 아닌 인물이 손을 대는 행위 자체가 극히 이례적”이라며 “불경으로 받아들여질 가능성이 크다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "It is known that Kim Jong Un repeatedly reviews videos after official events, strictly checking the attitudes and behaviors of officials," and noted, "In the past, there have been quite a few officials reportedly executed for reasons such as dozing off or showing inappropriate attitudes during meetings." Furthermore, he said, "Among high-ranking defectors and intelligence agency officials, there is speculation that if this video is flagged as problematic during the censorship process, it could affect Kang Sun-nam's position amid the ongoing personnel reshuffling or purges ahead of the party congress." (이어 “김정은은 공식 행사 후 영상을 반복해서 확인하며, 간부들의 태도나 행동거지를 엄격하게 점검하는 것으로 알려져 있다”며 “과거에도 회의 중 졸거나 부적절한 태도를 보였다는 이유로 처형됐다고 전해지는 간부들이 적지 않다”고 했다. 그러면서 “고위 탈북자와 정보 당국 관계자들 사이에서는 이번 영상이 검열 과정에서 문제로 지적될 경우 당 대회를 앞두고 진행되는 인사 쇄신이나 숙청 흐름 속에서 노광철의 입지에 영향을 미칠 가능성이 있다는 관측이 나온다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, this is the first time North Korea has built a memorial hall honoring the sacrifices of troops dispatched overseas. During his inspection that day, Kim Jong Un ordered that the memorial hall be completed to the highest standard, stating, "No one in this world can match a military that shows absolute loyalty to the Party's orders and willingly sacrifices their lives for the dignity and honor of their homeland." (한편 북한이 해외 파병 군인의 희생을 기리는 기념관을 건립하는 건 이번이 처음이다. 김정은은 이날 건설 현장에서 “당의 명령 앞에 절대 충성하고 자기 조국의 존엄과 명예를 위해 목숨도 기꺼이 바치는 이런 군대를 이 세상 그 누구도 당해낼 수 없다”며 기념관을 최상의 수준으로 완공해야 한다고 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mobilizing family and officials to participate directly in the work is interpreted as an effort to accelerate the glorification of the dispatched troops by highlighting the act of 'honoring' and taking the lead in memorializing the Russian-dispatched soldiers. (가족과 간부까지 동원해 직접 작업에 참여한 건 러시아 파병군을 ‘예우’하고 추모 작업에 앞장서는 모습을 부각함으로써 파병군 영웅화에 박차를 가하는 것으로 해석된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/28/Y2HUKURQIVC3FH7V2LEK3I7DMY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/R7CZTOKDHRBAXAZP5EYR3KICAU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:53:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea: "Even if you twist the chicken's neck, dawn will come"... Jang: "We will proceed according to procedure" (韓 “닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다”...張 “절차 따라 진행”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/LDQSE5ZOR5FHVIAR4SCJM7XAD4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;South Korea: "Even if you twist the chicken's neck, dawn will come"... Jang: "We will proceed according to procedure" (韓 “닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다”...張 “절차 따라 진행”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/IFCCU7HENRACHEHN7GDTEJK4QI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former People Power Party (PPP) leader Han Dong-hoon attended a preview screening of a documentary film re-examining former President Kim Young-sam on the 28th and referenced YS's statement that "even if you twist the chicken's neck, dawn will come." (국민의힘 한동훈 전 대표가 28일 김영삼 대통령을 재조명한 다큐멘터리 영화 시사회에 참석한 뒤 “아무리 닭의 목을 비틀더라도 새벽은 온다”고 했던 YS 발언을 언급했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After attending the screening held in Yeongdeungpo-gu, Seoul, in the afternoon and watching the film, former leader Han said, "Just as former President Kim Young-sam said, 'Even if you twist the chicken's neck, dawn will come,' when he faced an unfair expulsion, I will continue forward with an unyielding spirit, trusting the people." This public appearance by former leader Han is his first since the party's Central Ethics Committee decided on his expulsion on the 14th. The PPP leadership plans to decide on whether to ratify the expulsion of former leader Han at a Supreme Council meeting as early as the 29th. (한 전 대표는 이날 오후 서울 영등포구에서 열린 시사회에 참석해 영화를 본 뒤 “부당한 제명을 당하면서 닭의 목을 비틀어도 새벽은 온다고 했던 김영삼 대통령님 말씀처럼 꺾이지 않는 마음으로 국민을 믿고 계속 가겠다”고 했다. 한 전 대표가 공개 일정에 나선 건 지난 14일 당 중앙윤리위원회의 제명 결정 이후 이번이 처음이다. 국민의힘 지도부는 이르면 29일 최고위원회에서 한 전 대표의 제명 의결 여부를 정할 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this day, former leader Han watched the documentary 'The Forgotten President: Kim Young-sam's Era of Reform,' which examines the life of the former president. He was accompanied by lawmakers considered close to him: Kim Hyung-dong, Park Jung-hoon, Ahn Sang-hoon, Jeong Seong-guk, and Jin Jong-oh. (이날 한 전 대표는 김 전 대통령의 일생을 조명한 다큐멘터리 ‘잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁 시대’를 관람했다. 한 전 대표는 친한계로 꼽히는 김형동·박정훈·안상훈·정성국·진종오 의원과 함께했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Hyun-chul, the second son of former President Kim and chairman of the Kim Young-sam Presidential Foundation, said, "(Former leader Han) said, 'I will find the identity of the People Power Party in YS,'" adding, "I hope it continues well." (김 전 대통령의 차남인 김현철 김영삼대통령기념재단 이사장은 “(한 전 대표는) ‘국민의힘 정체성을 YS에서 찾겠다’고 했다”며 “지속적으로 잘 이어나갔으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, on the same day, PPP leader Jang Dong-hyeok returned to party duties, starting with an inspection of agricultural and fisheries product prices ahead of the Lunar New Year holiday. This marks his first field schedule in six days since halting his hunger strike on the 22nd. (한편 같은 날 장동혁 국민의힘 대표는 설 명절을 앞두고 농수산물 물가 점검을 시작으로 당무에 복귀했다. 지난 22일 단식 중단 후 엿새 만에 현장 일정에 나선 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, leader Jang, along with floor leader Song Eon-seok, policy committee chairman Jeong Jeom-sik, and other party leaders, examined the cost of living at a Hanaro Mart in Seocho-gu, Seoul. Subsequently, he visited the integrated situation room at the Korea Agro-Fisheries &amp; Food Trade Corporation (aT) center and held a discussion on price stability with aT President Hong Moon-pyo and representatives from major distributors such as the National Agricultural Cooperative Federation (Nonghyup) and Lotte Mart. (장 대표는 이날 오후 송언석 원내대표, 정점식 정책위의장 등 지도부와 함께 서울 서초구 하나로마트에서 생활 물가를 살폈다. 이어 한국농수산식품유통공사(aT)센터 종합상황실을 찾아 홍문표 aT 사장, 농협·롯데마트 등 대형 유통 매장 관계자 등과 함께 물가 안정 관련 간담회를 진행했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang stated, "Eggs cost over 10,000 won per tray, and apple prices have risen more than 20% compared to last year," adding, "While prices are threatening the daily lives of ordinary people like this, continuing to distribute cash handouts is like feeding sugar water only to a diabetic patient." (장 대표는 “달걀은 한 판에 1만원이 넘고 사과는 작년에 비해 20% 이상 가격이 상승했다”며 “이렇게 물가가 서민 일상을 위협하는데도 계속해서 현금을 살포하는 것은 당뇨 환자에게 설탕물만 먹이는 것과 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the on-site discussion, when asked about the ratification of former leader Han's expulsion, he was cautious with his words, saying, "Sufficient time has been given according to procedure, and we will proceed according to procedure." He added, "What's important now is the people's lives, the economy, and public livelihood," and "Party internal matters will proceed according to procedure." (그는 현장 간담회 이후 한 전 대표의 제명 의결에 대한 질문에 “절차에 따라 충분한 시간이 주어졌고 절차에 따라 진행하도록 하겠다”며 말을 아꼈다. 그러면서 “지금 중요한 건 국민의 삶, 경제, 민생”이라며 “당내 문제는 절차에 따라 진행될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/28/LDQSE5ZOR5FHVIAR4SCJM7XAD4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/IFCCU7HENRACHEHN7GDTEJK4QI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 20:56:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>