<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:18:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>North Korea reports Xi Jinping's greeting cards with other countries... Putin is on page 1 of the Rodong Sinmun (北, 시진핑 연하장을 타국과 묶어서 보도… 푸틴은 노동신문 1면)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/XIEVGB55VJGEHJOWAFHV3RYE4M/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea reports Xi Jinping's greeting cards with other countries... Putin is on page 1 of the Rodong Sinmun (北, 시진핑 연하장을 타국과 묶어서 보도… 푸틴은 노동신문 1면)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA3TIYLFG5TDEMLFGU2DQMBVMM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean media do not report on the New Year's greeting cards exchanged between Chairman Kim Jong-un and Chinese President Xi Jinping, leading to observations that North Korea-China relations are cold. The contents of the New Year's greeting card that Kim Jong-un exchanged with Russian President Vladimir Putin were introduced in detail by the Rodong Sinmun. (북한 매체들이 김정은 국무위원장과 시진핑 중국 국가주석 간에 오간 신년 연하장을 비중 있게 보도하지 않아, 북중 관계가 냉랭하다는 관측이 나오고 있다. 김정은이 블라디미르 푸틴 러시아 대통령과 주고받은 신년 연하장 내용은 노동신문이 자세히 소개했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Rodong Sinmun published an article on page 2 on the 18th stating that Kim Jong-un "sent greeting cards to heads of party and state and officials of various countries." The first thing Kim Jong-un sent greeting cards to was "the President and wife of the People's Republic of China, General Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China," but the real names of Xi Jinping and Peng Liyuan were not mentioned. He also did not introduce China separately, but only mentioned the fact that he sent greeting cards in a line with the heads of state of eight countries, including Vietnam, Singapore, and Tajikistan. North Korean media reported that when President Xi and his wife sent a greeting card to Kim Jong-un on the 1st, they did not introduce the contents separately, but only reported that the "Chinese president and his wife" also sent greeting cards by combining them with other leaders of states. (노동신문은 18일 2면에 김정은이 “여러 나라 당 및 국가 수반들과 인사들에게 연하장을 보냈다”는 기사를 게재했다. 김정은이 연하장을 보낸 대상으로 가장 먼저 “중국공산당 중앙위원회 총서기인 중화인민공화국 주석과 부인”을 언급했지만, 시진핑·펑리위안이란 실명은 거론되지 않았다. 또 중국을 따로 소개하지 않고 베트남, 싱가포르, 타지키스탄 등 8국의 국가 수반과 한 줄에 묶어 연하장을 보냈다는 사실만 언급했다. 북한 매체들은 지난 1일 시 주석 부부가 김정은에게 연하장을 보낸 사실을 전할 때도 그 내용을 별도로 소개하지 않고 다른 국가 정상들과 묶어 ‘중국 주석 부부’도 연하장을 보내왔다고만 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, on the 27th of last month, the Rodong Sinmun published the contents of Putin's greeting card to Kim Jong-un on the front page, and on the 2st of last month, the second page of Kim Jong-un's reply to Putin was published. In his greeting card, Putin expressed his gratitude for North Korea's dispatch of troops to Kursk and said that he was confident that "we will continue to carry out constructive cooperation on regional and international issues (in the future)." Kim Jong-un called Putin "my dear comrade" and said that North Korea and Russia are "the most sincere alliance in which we share life and death in the same trench." (반면 지난달 27일 노동신문은 1면에 푸틴이 김정은에게 보낸 연하장 내용을 비중 있게 실었고, 지난달 31일 2면에는 김정은이 푸틴에게 보낸 답장 내용을 게재했다. 푸틴은 연하장에서 북한의 쿠르스크 파병 등에 사의를 표하며 “(앞으로도) 지역 및 국제 문제들에서 건설적인 협동을 진행하게 되리라고 확신”한다고 했다. 김정은은 푸틴을 “친애하는 나의 동지”로 부르며 북·러는 “한 전호(戰壕)에서 피를 나누며 생사고락을 함께 하는 가장 진실한 동맹 관계”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Kim Yo-yong, vice chairman of the Workers' Party of Korea, said in a speech to South Korea on the 13th, "Even if the ruling party goes abroad to solicit money, the reality of inter-Korean relations will never change." It was interpreted as expressing dissatisfaction with the South Korean side's announcement that President Xi held a summit meeting with President Lee Jae-myung, who was on a state visit to China, on the 5th and discussed "creative measures" for peace on the Korean Peninsula. Lim Eul-chul, a professor at the Institute of Far Eastern Studies at Kyungnam University, said, "North Korea will see China's welcome of the South Korean president, whom it has defined as its 'first main enemy,' as a challenge to its 'sovereign decision.'" (그런 한편 김여정 노동당 부부장은 지난 13일 대남 담화에서 “집권자가 해외에까지 돌아치며 청탁질을 해도 남북 관계의 현실은 절대로 달라질 수 없다”고 했다. 시 주석이 국빈 방중한 이재명 대통령과 지난 5일 정상회담을 하며 한반도 평화를 위한 ‘창의적 방안’ 등을 논의했다는 우리 측 발표에 불만을 드러낸 것으로 풀이됐다. 임을출 경남대 극동문제연구소 교수는 “북한은 자신들이 ‘제1의 주적’으로 규정한 한국 대통령을 중국이 국빈으로 맞이한 것 자체를 ‘주권적 결정’에 대한 도전으로 볼 것”이라며 “시진핑의 연하장을 홀대한 것도 김정은의 대중(對中) 불만이 상당하다는 신호”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/XIEVGB55VJGEHJOWAFHV3RYE4M/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA3TIYLFG5TDEMLFGU2DQMBVMM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Ik-pyo Appointed as New Senior Secretary for Political Affairs... Woo Sang-ho to Run for Gangwon Governor (신임 정무수석에 홍익표… 우상호는 강원지사 도전)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ITJXDOJNAVAEHB4EOZ3GSR5RJU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Hong Ik-pyo Appointed as New Senior Secretary for Political Affairs... Woo Sang-ho to Run for Gangwon Governor (신임 정무수석에 홍익표… 우상호는 강원지사 도전)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OEL34F6FI5D6PGIV7XOBREBZII.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House announced on the 18th that it has appointed former Democratic Party of Korea floor leader Hong Ik-pyo as the new Senior Secretary for Political Affairs. This appointment comes as the current Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, Woo Sang-ho, is stepping down to run in the Gangwon Province gubernatorial election in the June 3 local elections. (청와대는 18일 신임 정무수석에 홍익표 전 더불어민주당 원내대표를 임명했다고 밝혔다. 우상호 정무수석이 6·3 지방선거의 강원도지사 선거에 출마하면서 후임을 임명한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new Senior Secretary Hong served three terms (19th, 20th, and 21st National Assembly) as a lawmaker representing Seoul's Seongdong district. In 2023, he worked as the party's floor leader when President Lee Jae-myung was the party leader. He ran in the difficult Seoul Seocho-eul district for the Democratic Party in the 22nd general election but was defeated. By accepting the offer to become Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, he has decided not to run for Seoul Mayor, a position he had been preparing for. (홍 신임 수석은 서울 성동에서 3선(19·20·21대) 국회의원을 했고, 지난 2023년 이재명 대통령이 당대표일 때 당 원내대표로 호흡을 맞췄다. 22대 총선에서 민주당 험지인 서울 서초을 지역에 도전했지만 낙선했다. 정무수석 제안을 수락하면서 그동안 준비해왔던 서울시장 출마는 하지 않기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With Senior Secretary Woo stepping down, the resignation of Blue House aides running in the June 3 local elections and National Assembly by-elections is expected to accelerate. The personnel drawing the most attention are senior-level officials such as Chief of Staff Kang Ho-sik, Policy Chief Kim Yong-beom, and Senior Secretary for AI and Future Planning Ha Jeong-woo. Chief of Staff Kang, a former three-term lawmaker from Asan, South Chungcheong Province, is being mentioned as a potential ruling party candidate if the integrated special city of Daejeon and South Chungcheong Province is established. However, many observers note there is inevitably pressure for the Chief of Staff, who leads the Presidential Secretariat, to resign just over seven months after the administration's launch. (우 수석이 그만두면서, 6·3 지방선거 및 국회의원 보궐선거에 출마하는 청와대 참모진의 사퇴도 본격화될 전망이다. 가장 관심을 모으는 인사는 강훈식 비서실장과 김용범 정책실장, 하정우 AI미래기획수석 등 수석급 이상 인사들이다. 충남 아산 3선 의원 출신인 강 실장은 대전·충남 통합특별시가 출범할 경우 여당 후보로 거론된다. 다만 대통령비서실을 이끄는 실장이 정부 출범 7개월여 만에 직을 그만두는 데 대한 부담이 따를 수밖에 없다는 관측이 많다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Policy Chief Kim, who is from South Jeolla Province and attended high school in Gwangju, is being mentioned as a potential candidate for Gwangju Mayor or South Jeolla Province Governor, while Senior Secretary Ha, who is from Busan, is rumored to be considering a run for Busan Mayor. However, a Blue House official stated, "There was talk at one point, but the actual possibility of them running seems very slim." (전남 출신으로 광주에서 고등학교를 나온 김 실장은 광주시장 또는 전남지사, 부산 출신인 하 수석은 부산시장 출마설이 거론된다. 하지만 청와대 관계자는 “한때 얘기가 돌았지만 실제 출마할 가능성은 아주 작아 보인다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the secretary level, Political Affairs Secretary Kim Byeong-wook is coordinating the timing of his resignation to run for Seongnam Mayor. Former lawmaker Go Yong-jin, who was re-elected in Seoul's Nowon district, is a strong candidate to succeed him. Presidential Spokesperson Kim Nam-joon is expected to run in the Incheon Gyeyang-eul district by-election, which was President Lee's former National Assembly constituency. (비서관급에서는 김병욱 정무비서관이 성남시장 출마를 위해 사퇴 시기를 조율 중이다. 후임에는 서울 노원에서 재선을 한 고용진 전 의원이 유력하다. 이 대통령의 국회의원 지역구였던 인천 계양을 지역 보궐선거에는 김남준 청와대 대변인이 출마할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, National Listening Secretary Bae Jin-gyo is being mentioned as a possible candidate for Incheon Mayor, Autonomous Development Secretary Lee Seon-ho for Ulsan Mayor, former Digital Communication Secretary Kim Nam-guk for Ansan Mayor, and National Integration Secretary Heo Eun-ah for Seoul's Yeongdeungpo District Mayor. (이밖에 배진교 국민경청비서관은 인천시장, 이선호 자치발전비서관은 울산시장, 김남국 전 디지털소통비서관은 안산시장, 허은아 국민통합비서관은 서울 영등포구청장 출마 가능성이 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of the administration's launch in June last year, there was talk within the ruling party that 'the Blue House staff would be composed only of people who would not run in elections.' The intention was to minimize the impact of elections for stable state affairs management, but the atmosphere has changed significantly recently. A ruling party official said, "Wouldn't the situation, where President Lee's approval rating is fluctuating around 60% and the ruling party is significantly ahead of the opposition party's support rate, making it seem likely to win the local elections big, have had an influence?" (작년 6월 정부 출범 때만 해도 여권 내에선 ‘청와대 참모진은 선거에 안 나갈 사람으로만 구성하기로 했다’는 말이 나왔다. 안정적 국정 운영을 위해 선거 영향을 최소화한다는 것이었는데, 최근엔 분위기가 많이 변했다. 여권 관계자는 “이 대통령 지지율이 60%를 오르내리고, 여당이 야당 지지율을 크게 앞서면서 지방선거를 크게 이길 것 같은 상황이 영향을 미치지 않았겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ITJXDOJNAVAEHB4EOZ3GSR5RJU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OEL34F6FI5D6PGIV7XOBREBZII.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Ruling Camp's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Calculation'... "A Win-Win Whether She Passes or Falls" (與 ‘이혜훈 청문회 셈법’… “통과든 낙마든 꽃놀이패”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RSGLHRT43ZAQBJJ5ZBSU5UI4MA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The Ruling Camp's 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Calculation'... "A Win-Win Whether She Passes or Falls" (與 ‘이혜훈 청문회 셈법’… “통과든 낙마든 꽃놀이패”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HE4DSNJVGYYDCYLBHA3DSMJXHA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, the Presidential Office once again stated regarding the various suspicions surrounding Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, "We expect her to provide answers and explanations that meet the public's expectations through the confirmation hearing." This reaffirmed their existing stance of waiting to see the hearing's outcome. Within the ruling camp, there is talk that "If this conservative nominee passes the hearing, it will be evaluated as President Lee Jae-myung's effort for integration, and even if she fails, it won't be a significant loss for the ruling camp as a whole." (청와대는 18일에도 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 각종 의혹에 대해 “청문회를 통해 국민의 눈높이에 맞는 답변을 하고 해명할 것으로 기대한다”고 했다. 청문회를 지켜보겠다는 기존 입장을 재확인한 것이다. 여권에선 “보수 인사인 이 후보자가 청문회를 통과하면 이재명 대통령의 통합 노력이란 평가가 나올 것이고, 낙마해도 여권 전체에 손해는 아니다”란 말이 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee unprecedentedly nominated former three-term People Power Party lawmaker Lee Hye-hoon as the first Minister of Planning and Budget on the 28th of last month. At the time, the Presidential Office called it "President Lee's personnel choice for integration and pragmatism." Subsequently, as suspicions such as real estate speculation and staff misconduct surrounding the nominee were raised one after another, concerns emerged even within the Democratic Party that "this could become a major negative factor for the ruling camp." Calls for her voluntary resignation also came from the Democratic Party. (이 대통령은 지난달 28일 국민의힘에서 3선 의원을 지낸 이 후보자를 초대 기획예산처 장관 후보자로 파격 발탁했다. 당시 청와대는 “이 대통령의 통합과 실용 인사”라고 했다. 이후 후보자를 둘러싸고 부동산 투기, 보좌진 갑질 등의 의혹이 잇따라 제기되자 민주당 내에서도 “여권에 큰 악재가 될 수 있다”는 우려가 나왔다. 민주당에선 자진 사퇴 요구도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the Presidential Office maintains its position of "waiting to see the hearing" regarding this nominee. An interpretation has emerged that this is because the current controversy is not significantly damaging the approval ratings of the President and the Democratic Party. In various opinion polls, positive evaluations of this personnel appointment are in the 10-20% range. However, President Lee's approval rating has been maintaining around 60%. In a Gallup Korea survey from the 13th to the 15th, it was 58%. Although it fell 2 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week, it was actually 1%p higher than the third week of December, just before the nominee's designation. In a Realmeter survey from the 5th to the 9th, President Lee's approval rating hit 56.8%, its highest point in two months. During the same period, the Democratic Party's approval rating also steadily remained in the low 40% range. Public opinion experts said, "Since the nominee is a conservative figure, the emphasis is on 'the President's personnel choice for integration,' and her personal misconduct seems to be perceived as the fault of the conservative camp." (그런데도 청와대가 이 후보자에 대해 “청문회를 지켜보겠다”고 하고 있다. 이번 논란이 대통령과 민주당 지지율에 별다른 타격을 주지 않고 있기 때문이란 해석이 나온다. 실제 각종 여론조사에서 이 후보자 인사에 대한 긍정 평가는 10~20%대다. 하지만 이 대통령 지지율은 60% 안팎을 유지 중이다. 한국갤럽의 13~15일 조사에선 58%였다. 전주 대비 2%포인트(p) 하락했지만, 이 후보자 지명 직전인 12월 셋째 주와 비교하면 오히려 1%p 높았다. 지난 5~9일 리얼미터 조사에서 이 대통령 지지율은 56.8%로 두 달 만에 최고치를 찍기도 했다. 같은 기간 민주당 지지율도 꾸준히 40%대 초반을 유지했다. 여론조사 전문가들은 “이 후보자가 보수 인사이다 보니 ‘대통령의 통합 인사’에 방점이 찍혔고, 이 후보자 개인 비리는 보수 진영 잘못으로 인식하는 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of this, within the ruling camp, there is talk that the choice between forcefully appointing or letting this nominee fall is a "win-win." If the nominee sufficiently explains the various suspicions during the hearing and is appointed as minister, it can emphasize the image of a 'pragmatic government.' Even if she falls, she would have served her purpose as a symbol of 'conservative division.' One second-term lawmaker said, "Aren't most of the suspicions about this nominee things that happened during her time in the People Power Party?" adding, "On the contrary, the opposition camp is being divided due to President Lee's bold recruitment of talent." A Democratic Party official stated, "(Even if she falls,) just having made this nominee apologize about the martial law incident is a significant achievement for us." (이 때문에 여권에선 이 후보자를 두고 임명 강행이냐, 낙마냐는 선택은 꽃놀이패라는 말이 나온다. 이 후보자가 청문회에서 각종 의혹을 충분히 소명하면 장관으로 임명해 ‘실용 정부’ 이미지를 강조할 수 있고, 낙마하더라도 ‘보수 분열’의 상징으로 쓰임새를 다했다는 것이다. 한 재선 의원은 “이 후보자의 의혹 대부분이 국민의힘 시절 벌어진 일 아니냐”며 “오히려 이 대통령의 과감한 인재 영입으로 야권이 분열하고 있다”고 했다. 한 민주당 관계자는 “(낙마하더라도) 이 후보자가 비상계엄에 대해 사과하게 한 것만으로 우리는 상당한 성과”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RSGLHRT43ZAQBJJ5ZBSU5UI4MA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HE4DSNJVGYYDCYLBHA3DSMJXHA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The 'Jang Dong-hyeok vs. Han Dong-hoon' Conflict Comes at a Staggering Cost... It's Not a Personal Feud but a War Over the Party's Identity (막대한 비용 치를 ‘장동혁·한동훈’ 갈등...개인 싸움 아니라 黨 정체성 전쟁)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/19/DX5GJFRKHRADREMP6DVTA6E3VU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The 'Jang Dong-hyeok vs. Han Dong-hoon' Conflict Comes at a Staggering Cost... It's Not a Personal Feud but a War Over the Party's Identity (막대한 비용 치를 ‘장동혁·한동훈’ 갈등...개인 싸움 아니라 黨 정체성 전쟁)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/V672WGXQFBFCJJ6HR6ZXMSLXXY.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party's internal affairs are engulfed in a whirlwind due to the clash between Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok and former Chairman Han Dong-hoon. This is not merely a personal conflict or a leadership struggle. It is a structural turning point that will determine what kind of party the People Power Party will remain. Big data analysis indicates it is perceived as a critical juncture that will dictate the party's identity, competitiveness in local elections, and even its future survival strategy. (국민의힘 내부는 장동혁 대표와 한동훈 전 대표 충돌로 소용돌이에 휩싸여 있다. 이는 단순한 개인 간 갈등이나 리더십 다툼이 아니다. 국민의힘이 어떤 정당으로 남을 것인가를 가르는 구조적 분기점이다. 당의 정체성과 지방선거 경쟁력, 나아가 향후 생존 전략을 좌우할 중대 국면으로 인식한다는 게 빅 데이터 분석이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a keyword association analysis by SomeTrend (January 1-15, 2026), keywords surrounding Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok were primarily institution and tactics-focused words such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'special prosecution bill', 'proposal', 'promotion', 'strategy', 'operation', 'state administration'&lt;/mark&gt;. (썸트렌드(SomeTrend) 연관어 분석(2026년 1월 1~15일)에서 장동혁 대표를 둘러싼 키워드는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘특검법’, ‘제안’, ‘추진’, ‘전략’, ‘운영’, ‘국정운영’ &lt;/mark&gt;등 제도·전술 중심 단어들이 주를 이룬다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This signifies that Chairman Jang is positioning himself as a "practical leader at the forefront of political struggle." The frequent detection of words like 'special prosecution' and 'promotion' suggests his intention to use the Unified Church special prosecution not as a simple defensive argument but as an offensive tool—a card to shift the political landscape—is gaining traction. (장 대표가 자신을 “정치적 투쟁의 전면에 선 실천형 리더”로 포지셔닝하고 있다는 의미다. ‘특검’, ‘추진’이라는 단어가 많이 포착된 건 통일교 특검을 단순한 방어 논리가 아니라 공격 수단, 즉 정국 전환용 카드로 활용하고자 하는 의도가 먹히고 있다는 의미다..)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, keywords associated with former Chairman Han centered on words evoking conflict and division, such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'condemnation', 'outrage', 'riot', 'criticism', 'conflict', 'National Election Commission', 'Daegu Mayor', 'Jo Eun-seok'&lt;/mark&gt;. The image is more of conflict than unity. (반면 한 전 대표 연관어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘단죄’, ‘격앙’, ‘폭동’, ‘비판’, ‘갈등’, ‘중앙선관위’, ‘대구시장’, ‘조은석’&lt;/mark&gt; 등 충돌과 분열을 연상시키는 단어가 중심이다. 통합 보다는 갈등의 이미지가 강하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this indicates a fundamental clash over the party's direction and strategy. Big data points out that Chairman Jang insists on a 'hardline, rallying-type struggle,' while former Chairman Han does not agree with that struggle. (결국 이는 당의 노선과 전략을 둘러싼 근본적 충돌이 깔려 있다. 장 대표는 ‘강경 결집형 투쟁’을 고집하고, 한 전 대표는 그 투쟁에 동의하지 않고 있는 것으로 빅 데이터는 지적하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Big data sentiment keyword analysis (January 15) shows a similar pattern. The sentiment words appearing alongside 'Jang Dong-hyeok hunger strike' were mostly negative terms like &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'suspicion', 'criticism', 'money/gifts', 'illegal funds', but simultaneously, positive or neutral words like 'defend', 'essential', 'noteworthy' also stand out.&lt;/mark&gt; This suggests that while the hunger strike itself is controversial, there is an atmosphere acknowledging it has a certain justification and sincerity as a political act. (빅데이터 감성 연관어 분석(1월 15일)도 비슷하다. ‘장동혁 단식’과 함께 나타난 감성어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘의혹’, ‘비판’, ‘금품’, ‘불법자금’과 같은 부정어가 다수이지만, 동시에 ‘옹호하다’, ‘필수’, ‘주목되다’라는 긍정 또는 중립적 단어도 눈에 띈다.&lt;/mark&gt; 단식 자체는 논란의 여지가 있지만 정치적 행위로서 일정한 명분과 진정성을 인정하는 분위기가 있다는 얘기다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, sentiment words combined with 'Han Dong-hoon expulsion' were largely negative, such as &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;'criticize', 'controversy', 'conflict', 'backlash', 'mutual destruction', 'collapse'&lt;/mark&gt;. This implies that discussions surrounding former Chairman Han are solidifying into a framework of exhausting conflict. (반면 ‘한동훈 제명’과 결합한 감성어는 &lt;mark class="hl_red"&gt;‘비판하다’, ‘논란’, ‘갈등’, ‘반발하다’, ‘공멸’, ‘무너지다’ 등 부정적인 단어들이 많다.&lt;/mark&gt; 이는 한 전 대표를 둘러싼 논의가 소모적인 갈등 프레임으로 굳어지고 있다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public opinion perceives Chairman Jang's hunger strike as a "politically meaningful attempt" beyond simply being right or wrong. In contrast, former Chairman Han is still perceived as a "cause of conflict." Although former Chairman Han officially apologized on the 18th regarding the core conflict—the party bulletin board controversy—it remains to be seen if this will change the current trend. (여론은 장 대표 단식에 대해 “옳고 그름”을 넘어서 “정치적으로 의미 있는 시도”로 받아들인다. 반면 한 전 대표는 여전히 “갈등의 원인”으로 인식하고 있다. 18일 한 전 대표가 갈등의 핵심인 당내 게시판 논란에 대해 공식 사과하긴 했지만 이런 흐름을 바꿀 수 있을 지는 두고 봐야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Jang's hunger strike is assessed to have, for now, brought the issues of the Unified Church special prosecution and the investigation into Democratic Party nomination funds to the forefront. The hunger strike politically aims for two effects. (장 대표의 단식은 일단 통일교 특검과 민주당 공천헌금 수사를 전면으로 끌어올리는 효과를 냈다고 조사됐다. 단식은 정치적으로 두 가지 효과를 노린다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whether Chairman Jang Dong-hyeok's hunger strike will become a decisive turning point in pushing through the Unified Church special prosecution and the investigation into Democratic Party nomination funds is still unknown. &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;However, judging solely from big data trends, it appears to have succeeded to some extent at least in reviving and setting the agenda in motion again.&lt;/mark&gt; (장동혁 대표의 단식이 통일교 특검 관철과 민주당 공천헌금 수사에서 결정적 전환점이 될 수 있을지는 아직 미지수다. &lt;mark class="hl_yellow"&gt;다만 빅데이터 흐름만 놓고 보면, 최소한 의제를 다시 살아 움직이게 만드는 데에는 어느 정도 성공한 것으로 보인다.&lt;/mark&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But for this agenda shift to lead to tangible results, strategic follow-up measures at the party level are essential. In the context of local elections, it could create a simple yet powerful framework of "morality vs. corruption." (그러나 이 의제 전환이 실질적 성과로 이어지기 위해서는 당 차원의 전략적 후속 조치가 필수적이다. 지방선거 국면에서 “도덕성 대 부패”라는 단순하면서 강력한 구도를 만들 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discussions on expelling former Chairman Han will have complex implications for the local elections and the future of the People Power Party. In the short term, it could simplify the party's message by removing a source of conflict and induce consolidation among hardline supporters. However, big data reveals words like 'backlash' and 'mutual destruction,' meaning it could come at a high price. (한 전 대표 제명 논의는 지방선거와 국민의힘 미래에 복합적인 영향을 미칠 것이다. 단기적으로는 갈등 요인을 제거함으로써 당의 메시지를 단순화하고, 강경 지지층의 결집을 유도할 수 있다. 하지만 빅데이터는 ‘반발’, ‘공멸’이란 단어를 드러낸다. 비싼 대가를 치를 수 있다는 의미다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the mid-to-long term, there is a risk of losing centrist and non-partisan voters. If the expulsion is seen as a mere emotional decision, it could become a fatal weakness in closely contested metropolitan and swing regions during the local elections. (중장기적으로는 중도층과 무당층의 이탈 위험이 존재한다. 제명이 단순한 감정적 결단으로 비친다면, 지방선거에서 수도권과 접전 지역에서 치명적 약점으로 작용할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conflict, hunger strike, and expulsion controversy are highly likely to cause short-term fluctuations in the People Power Party's approval ratings. While the core support base may consolidate, fatigue among centrist voters is also growing. The appearance of sentiment words like 'concern' and 'collapse' in big data well illustrates this dual trend. Local elections cannot be won by consolidation alone. Ultimately, the key is whether the People Power Party can connect this situation to a strategy of "internal cleanup followed by external offensive." (이번 충돌과 단식, 제명 논란은 국민의힘 지지율을 단기적으로 출렁이게 할 가능성이 크다. 핵심 지지층은 결집할 수 있지만, 중도층의 피로감 또한 커지고 있다. 빅데이터 감성어에서 ‘우려’, ‘무너지다’라는 표현이 등장한 것은 이러한 이중적 흐름을 잘 보여준다. 지방선거는 결집만으로 이길 수 있는 선거가 아니다. 결국 국민의힘이 이번 사태를 “내부 정리 후 외부 공세”라는 전략으로 연결할 수 있느냐가 관건이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Jang Dong-hyeok and Han Dong-hoon conflict is forcing a choice upon the People Power Party. To mend the conflict or to clarify its direction through the conflict. Chairman Jang's hunger strike is a risky gamble, but it could also be a final, decisive move. Former Chairman Han's expulsion could also be a signal flare for cleanup or a fuse for division.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (장동혁과 한동훈 충돌은 국민의힘에 선택을 강요하고 있다. 갈등을 봉합할 것인가, 아니면 갈등을 통해 노선을 명확히 할 것인가. 장 대표의 단식은 위험한 도박이지만, 마지막 승부수일 수도 있다. 한 전 대표의 제명 역시 정리의 신호탄이 될 수도, 분열의 도화선이 될 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/2026/01/19/DX5GJFRKHRADREMP6DVTA6E3VU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/V672WGXQFBFCJJ6HR6ZXMSLXXY.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon Holds Firm Despite Opposition Boycott... Political Circles Say "Her Will for Power is Uncommon" (野 보이콧에도 버티는 이혜훈… 정치권 “권력 의지 남다른 사람”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/B3PLJEM76BAHTA3Y3U7PDQTOUY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon Holds Firm Despite Opposition Boycott... Political Circles Say "Her Will for Power is Uncommon" (野 보이콧에도 버티는 이혜훈… 정치권 “권력 의지 남다른 사람”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBIZ5ZC6SZFCXELBSVLAAYELWM.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the People Power Party declaring it will boycott the National Assembly confirmation hearings, the possibility of holding the hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, scheduled for the 19th, has become uncertain. Demands for her resignation are growing not only from the opposition but also within the ruling party itself. (국민의힘이 국회 인사청문회를 거부하겠다고 하면서 19일 예정된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 청문회 개최 여부가 불투명해졌다. 야당은 물론 여당 내부에서도 이 후보자에 대한 사퇴 요구가 커지고 있는 상황이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversies have been raised regarding the nominee, including allegations of abusive language and power abuse by her aides during her time as a lawmaker, the controversy over her eldest son's 'sham single status' to unfairly win a Gangnam apartment lottery, and suspicions of her husband's land speculation in Incheon's Yeongjong Island. (이 후보자에 대해선 국회의원 시절 보좌진 갑질·폭언, 장남의 ‘위장 미혼’을 통한 강남 아파트 부정 당첨 논란, 남편의 인천 영종도 땅 투기 의혹 등이 제기돼 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the nominee's side maintains the position that "there will be no resignation." Political figures familiar with the nominee said on the 18th, "She will not resign voluntarily and will hold out until the end," adding, "You can understand this if you look at the process of how she entered politics and pursued power." (그러나 이 후보자 측은 “사퇴는 없다”는 입장이다. 이 후보자를 잘 아는 정치권 인사들은 18일 “자진 사퇴하지 않고 끝까지 버틸 것”이라며 “이 후보자가 정치에 입문하고 권력을 쫓아간 과정을 보면 안다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An economist by background, the nominee is the eldest daughter-in-law of the late former Minister of Home Affairs Kim Tae-ho, who served four terms as a lawmaker from Ulsan in the 1980s-2000s. It was the daughter-in-law, nominee Lee, not her son Professor Kim Young-se of Yonsei University, who inherited the family business of 'politics'. The nominee maximized the use of that 'legacy'. (경제학자 출신인 이 후보자는 1980~2000년대 울산에서 4선 의원을 지낸 고(故) 김태호 전 내무부 장관의 맏며느리다. 아들인 김영세 연세대 교수가 아닌 며느리인 이 후보자가 가업(家業)인 ‘정치’를 물려받았다. 이 후보자는 그 ‘유산’을 최대한 활용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of the hearing, the formation process of the nominee's family wealth, amounting to 17.5 billion won, has also come to light. Apart from assets inflated through real estate like the Yeongjong Island land deal and the Gangnam apartment lottery, a significant portion originated from her mother-in-law. (청문회를 앞두고 175억원대인 이 후보자 가족 재산의 형성 과정도 알려지게 됐다. 영종도 땅 매매, 강남 아파트 당첨 등으로 부동산으로 불린 재산 외에, 상당 부분은 시어머니가 출발점이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"The Daughter-in-law Inherited the Family Business of 'Politics'"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“며느리가 家業인 ‘정치’ 승계”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho, passed away from leukemia in July 2002 during his 16th term as a lawmaker. That same year, the nominee entered the political arena as a policy advisor to Lee Hoi-chang, the Grand National Party's presidential candidate. In a media interview at the time, the nominee stated that her family strongly recommended her 'political entry'. (이 후보자 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관은 2002년 7월 16대 의원 임기 도중 골수암으로 별세했다. 그해 이 후보자는 한나라당 이회창 대통령 후보의 정책 자문역으로 정치권에 입문했다. 이 후보자는 당시 언론 인터뷰에서 가족이 ‘정치 입문’을 강력히 권유했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee served three terms as a lawmaker, all from Seocho Gap district, in the 2004, 2008, and 2016 general elections. In the 2012 general election, she failed to receive the party nomination due to the Grand National Party's 'principle prohibiting a third-term run in one's home turf'. Subsequently, she challenged the Seoul mayoral election in the 2014 local elections but lost in the primary. That year, she also threw her hat in the ring for the Ulsan Nam-eul by-election for the National Assembly but withdrew her nomination application amid criticism from inside and outside the party. (이 후보자는 2004·2008·2016년 총선까지 서초갑에서만 3선 의원을 했다. 2012년 총선 땐 한나라당의 ‘텃밭 3선 출마 금지 원칙’ 때문에 공천을 못 받았다. 그러자 2014년 지방선거에서 서울시장 선거에 도전했다가 경선에서 탈락했다. 그해 울산 남을 국회의원 보궐선거에도 출사표를 냈다가 당 안팎의 비난에 공천 신청을 철회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the impeachment motion against former President Park Geun-hye passed the National Assembly in 2017, the nominee left the Saenuri Party and served as the leader of the Bareun Party. Later, in the 2020 and 2024 general elections, she ran as a candidate for the United Future Party and the People Power Party in Seoul's Dongdaemun and Seoul Jung-Seongdong districts respectively, but lost. In the 2022 local elections, she also challenged the North Chungcheong Province governorship election but was eliminated in the primary. (이 후보자는 2017년 박근혜 전 대통령 탄핵소추안이 국회를 통과하자 새누리당을 탈당해 바른정당 대표를 지냈다. 이후 2020년, 2024년 총선 때 미래통합당과 국민의힘 후보로 서울 동대문을, 서울 중·성동을에 각각 출마했지만 낙선했다. 2022년 지방선거 땐 충북지사 선거에도 도전했다가 경선에서 떨어졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the current Democratic Party administration, she has switched camps and been nominated as a minister. A ruling party official said, "An influential politician recommended her to President Lee Jae-myung, and I understand the nominee accepted the offer immediately." An opposition party official stated, "The nominee's will for power was extraordinary, having inherited the family business from her in-laws on behalf of her husband." (이번 민주당 정권에서는 진영을 바꿔 장관 후보자에 올랐다. 여권 관계자는 “유력 정치인이 이재명 대통령에게 추천했고, 이 후보자는 제안을 받자 바로 수락한 걸로 안다”고 했다. 야권 관계자는 “남편을 대신해 시댁의 가업을 이어 받은 이 후보자의 권력 의지는 남달랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Family as a 'Community of Interest', Fails to Submit Documents&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇가족은 ‘이익공동체’, 자료제출 안해&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's family wealth amounts to 17.56952 billion won, most of which was formed through gifts from her mother-in-law or real estate investments. (이 후보자 가족 재산은 175억6952만원인데, 대부분 시어머니로부터 증여를 받거나 부동산 투자를 통해 형성했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, looking at the real estate transaction history, the nominee, at age 28 in 1992 while studying abroad in the US, purchased five commercial buildings in Eungbong-dong, Seongdong-gu, Seoul, in her and her husband's names, realizing a market price profit of about 1 billion won. Also, it was revealed that the nominee's husband purchased miscellaneous land on Incheon's Yeongjong Island in 2000, one year before the opening of Incheon International Airport, and made a profit of over 2 billion won. (먼저 부동산 변동 내역을 보면, 이 후보자는 스물여덟 살이던 1992년 미국 유학 시절에 본인과 남편 명의로 서울 성동구 응봉동 상가 5채를 사들여, 10억여 원의 시세 차익을 실현했다. 또 이 후보자 남편은 인천국제공항 개항 1년 전인 2000년 인천 영종도 잡종지를 매입해 20억원 이상의 차익을 본 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She also won the 'lottery subscription' for an apartment in Seoul's Gangnam area. The nominee's eldest son maintained his status as a household member under his parents without filing a marriage report ('sham single status'), thereby receiving a higher subscription score, and won the subscription for the 'Raemian One Pentas' apartment in Banpo-dong in July 2024. This apartment is currently valued in the 7 billion won range, with a market price profit exceeding 3 billion won. (서울 강남권 아파트 ‘로또 청약’에도 당첨됐다. 이 후보자 장남이 혼인 신고를 하지 않고 이 후보자 부부 아래 세대원을 유지하는 ‘위장 미혼’을 통해 청약 가점을 높게 받은 뒤, 2024년 7월 반포동 ‘래미안 원펜타스’ 아파트 청약에 당첨됐다. 이 아파트는 현재 70억원대이며 시세 차익은 30억원이 넘는다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Her three sons, in their 20s and 30s, each hold assets ranging from 1.2 to 1.7 billion won, totaling about 4.7 billion won. Most of this was gifted by the nominee's mother-in-law. The mother-in-law gifted 2,400 shares (worth about 3.1 billion won) of KSM, a semiconductor equipment company, to the nominee's three sons in 2016 and 2021, and in May of last year, also gifted a house in a redevelopment planned area in Jeonnong-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul, to the nominee's second son. (20~30대인 세 아들은 각자 12억~17억원씩 47억원 정도를 보유하고 있다. 대부분 이 후보자 시어머니가 증여해 준 것이다. 시어머니는 2016년과 2021년 이 후보자의 세 아들에게 반도체 장비 회사인 KSM의 주식 2400주(31억여 원)를 증여했고, 작년 5월 서울 동대문구 전농동 재개발 예정지 주택도 이 후보자의 차남에게 증여했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;KSM is a 'family company' operated by the brother of the nominee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho. The opposition has also raised suspicions that the nominee, during her time as a lawmaker, engaged in preferential legislation supporting specialized parts and materials companies like KSM. However, it was reported that as of the night of the 18th, the nominee's side had not submitted documents related to her sons, such as employment records, military service records, or gift tax payment details. (KSM은 이 후보자 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관의 동생이 운영 중인 ‘가족 회사’다. 야당은 이 후보자가 의원 시절 KSM 같은 부품·소재 전문 기업을 지원하는 특혜성 입법에 나섰다는 의혹도 제기했다. 하지만 이 후보자 측은 18일 밤까지 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 아들들과 관련 자료들은 제출하지 않은 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee's mother-in-law is also the founder of a social welfare corporation in Ulsan. According to People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young's office, this social welfare corporation received a total of 56.9 billion won in support from the Ulsan Office of Education from 2016 to 2025 under the title of 'private school financial deficit subsidy'. There are also suspicions that employees of this corporation were mobilized for the nominee's intra-party election campaign in 2010. In 2024, a case of habitual abuse of disabled persons occurred at a social welfare facility operated by this corporation, causing controversy in the Ulsan region. (이 후보자의 시어머니는 울산의 모 사회복지법인 설립자이기도 하다. 국민의힘 박수영 의원실에 따르면, 이 사회복지법인은 2016~2025년 울산교육청에서 ‘사립학교 재정 결함 보조금’ 명목으로 총 569억원을 지원받았다. 이 법인 직원들은 2010년 이 후보자의 당내 선거 운동에 동원됐다는 의혹도 있다. 지난 2024년 이 법인이 운영하는 사회복지시설에서 장애인 상습 학대 사건이 벌어져 울산 지역에서 논란이 일었다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/B3PLJEM76BAHTA3Y3U7PDQTOUY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBIZ5ZC6SZFCXELBSVLAAYELWM.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party: "Lee Hye-hoon is not a subject for verification, but for investigation" (국힘 “이혜훈, 검증 대상 아닌 수사 대상”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FXKZEQVLDVDJVCUZ4DPO2OX5HI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party: "Lee Hye-hoon is not a subject for verification, but for investigation" (국힘 “이혜훈, 검증 대상 아닌 수사 대상”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KXHPP5KCK5PQFGILZZUVLBNCMY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the People Power Party (PPP) refuses to hold a National Assembly confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, citing insufficient document submissions, the atmosphere has become uncertain regarding whether the hearing will be held on the 19th. The Democratic Party of Korea (DPK) stated it will consult with the PPP as much as possible to hold the hearing normally. (국민의힘이 자료 제출 미비 등을 이유로 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회를 거부하면서, 19일 청문회 개최 여부가 불투명해진 분위기다. 더불어민주당은 청문회 정상 개최를 위해 국민의힘과 최대한 협의해 본다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP is calling the nominee "not a subject for verification, but for investigation." PPP lawmakers belonging to the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee held a press conference on the 18th, stating they "completely refuse to hold a hearing for nominee Lee, a 'lawbreaker'." PPP member and committee chairperson Lim Lee-ja also said on the 16th that she could not hold the hearing as the nominee had not submitted a significant portion of the documents requested by the opposition party. (국민의힘은 이 후보자에 대해 “검증이 아닌 수사 대상”이라고 하고 있다. 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들은 18일 기자회견을 열어 “‘범법 행위자’ 이 후보자에 대한 청문회를 전면 거부한다”고 했다. 국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장도 지난 16일 이 후보자가 야당이 요구한 청문 자료를 상당 부분 제출하지 않고 있다며 청문회를 못 열겠다고 했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of the 15th, the nominee's document submission rate was known to be slightly over 15%. The nominee's side reportedly refuses to consent to submitting related documents regarding their children's employment, military service, and gift tax payment history, citing 'personal information.' (지난 15일 기준 이 후보자의 자료 제출률은 15% 남짓으로 알려졌다. 이 후보자 측은 자녀들의 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 관련 자료에 대해 ‘개인정보’를 이유로 동의하지 않고 있다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP holds the position that it cannot proceed with the hearing if documents related to the children and proof of full gift tax payment are not submitted. In response, it is known that the nominee informed the National Assembly on the afternoon of the 18th that they "will submit more documents." The PPP maintains that even if the nominee submits additional documents, holding the hearing immediately on the 19th is unreasonable as time is needed for analysis. (국민의힘은 자녀 관련 자료와 증여세 완납증명서 제출이 안 되면 청문회에 임할 수 없다는 입장이다. 그러자 이 후보자는 18일 오후 국회에 “자료를 더 제출하겠다”고 한 것으로 알려졌다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 자료를 추가로 제출하더라도 분석할 시간이 필요한 만큼 당장 19일 청문회 개최는 무리라는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The DPK submitted a request to the Strategy and Finance Committee to open the hearing on this day. DPK lawmakers belonging to the committee stated in a declaration today, "Refusing the hearing is the National Assembly abandoning its own authority and responsibility," adding, "The nominee's side is making efforts to submit the key documents requested by the People Power Party." (민주당은 이날 재경위에 청문회 개회 요구서를 냈다. 재경위 소속 민주당 의원들은 이날 성명에서 “청문회 거부는 국회 스스로 권한과 책임을 포기하는 것”이라며 “이 후보자 측은 국민의힘이 요구한 주요 자료를 제출하기 위해 노력하고 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some are mentioning the possibility that if the PPP continues to boycott the hearing, the DPK might hold the hearing alone. According to the National Assembly Act, if a standing committee chairperson refuses to proceed with the agenda, the majority party's secretary can conduct the meeting instead of the chairperson. However, it is reported that if Chairperson Lim does not hand over the authority to preside, disruption is inevitable, and the DPK also views it as realistically difficult to take over the presiding authority. Within the opposition party, there are also demands that the hearing should be held to receive the public's judgment on the nominee, so the possibility of a last-minute hearing cannot be ruled out. A DPK official said, "We plan to continue consultations until the morning of the 19th." (일각에선 국민의힘이 청문회를 계속 보이콧할 경우 민주당이 단독으로 청문회를 열 가능성도 거론된다. 국회법상 상임위원장이 의사 진행을 거부하면 다수당 간사가 위원장 대신 회의를 진행할 수 있다. 그러나 임 위원장이 사회권을 넘기지 않으면 파행이 불가피하고, 민주당도 사회권을 가져오는 것은 현실적으로 어렵다고 보는 것으로 전해졌다. 야당 내에도 이 후보자에 대한 국민 판단을 받아보려면 청문회를 열어야 한다는 요구가 있어 막판 청문회 개최 가능성도 배제할 수는 없다. 민주당 관계자는 “19일 아침까지도 계속 협의할 방침”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FXKZEQVLDVDJVCUZ4DPO2OX5HI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KXHPP5KCK5PQFGILZZUVLBNCMY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Han Dong-hoon Apologizes, Saying "I Am Sorry for Causing Concern to Party Members" (한동훈 “당원께 걱정 끼쳐 송구” 사과)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FTVQLLOADNFVNEOUQ52W3G2Z3I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Han Dong-hoon Apologizes, Saying "I Am Sorry for Causing Concern to Party Members" (한동훈 “당원께 걱정 끼쳐 송구” 사과)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ML4VNGYNQNOFPGFOY5J6THLU2A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon expressed his feelings regarding the party division related to the 'party member bulletin board' issue, stating, "As a responsible politician who led the party, I feel deeply sorry that the situation has come to this point and for causing concern to the public and party members." This marks his first apology in 14 months since the issue surfaced in November 2024. (국민의힘 한동훈 전 대표가 18일 ‘당원 게시판’ 문제로 인한 당내 분열과 관련해 “상황이 여기까지 오게 된 것, 국민과 당원께 걱정을 끼친 점에 대해서 당을 이끌었던 책임 있는 정치인으로서 송구한 마음”이라고 했다. 2024년 11월 이 사건이 불거진 지 14개월 만의 첫 사과다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a two-minute video message posted on Facebook, the former leader clarified his stance. However, regarding the party audit committee's investigation into him and the ethics committee's decision to expel him, he stated, "It is a clear fabrication and political retaliation." He further added, "They may be able to strip me of my party membership through political retaliation using party authority, but they cannot strip away the spirit and future of our party, which I love." (페이스북에 게시한 2분짜리 영상 메시지를 통해 이같이 밝힌 한 전 대표는 다만 자신에 대한 당무감사위원회 조사와 윤리위원회 제명 결정에 대해서는 “명백한 조작이자 정치 보복”이라고 했다. 또 “당권으로 정치 보복을 해서 저의 당적을 박탈할 수는 있어도 제가 사랑하는 우리 당의 정신과 미래는 박탈할 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among neutral figures within the party, reactions varied. Some called it a "half-hearted apology," while others urged, "In any case, former leader Han has made a concession, so leader Jang Dong-hyeok should also take a step back for unity." (중립 성향의 당내 인사들 사이에선 “반쪽 사과였다”는 반응과 “어쨌든 한 전 대표가 양보한 셈이니, 장동혁 대표도 한발 물러서서 통합하라”는 주문이 함께 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;Han Dong-hoon's Apology Amid Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike... Will It Find an Exit from the Internal Strife?&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;장동혁 단식 중에 나온 한동훈 사과… 내분 출구 찾을까&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ethics committee, officially formed by leader Jang Dong-hyeok on the 8th, held two meetings on the 9th and 13th before deciding on 'Han Dong-hoon's expulsion.' The Jang Dong-hyeok leadership attempted to finalize the expulsion decision on the 15th. However, People Power Party lawmakers, regardless of faction, strongly opposed, saying, "Expulsion is not acceptable." In response, leader Jang stepped back, stating, "I will suspend the decision until the 10-day appeal period." Former leader Han countered, saying, "I have no intention of appealing." (지난 8일 장동혁 대표가 공식 구성한 윤리위는 지난 9일과 13일 두 차례 회의를 가진 뒤 ‘한동훈 제명’ 결정을 내렸다. 장동혁 지도부는 지난 15일 한 전 대표 제명 결정을 ‘최종 의결’하려 했다. 그러나 국민의힘 의원들이 계파를 불문하고 “제명은 안 된다”고 강력 반발했고, 이에 장 대표는 “10일간의 재심 신청 기간까지 결정을 보류하겠다”고 물러섰다. 한 전 대표는 “재심 신청할 생각이 없다”고 맞받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, many lawmakers requested during the general meeting of lawmakers on the 15th that "an apology from former leader Han is also necessary." This opinion began to emerge even from the pro-Han faction. Party elders also called for a grand compromise between the two. It is reported that one elder visited leader Jang's hunger strike site at the National Assembly main building on the night of the 17th and spoke with former leader Han over the phone the same day, urging unity. (다만 의원 다수가 15일 의원 총회에서 “한 전 대표의 사과도 필요하다”고 주문했다. 친한계에서도 이런 의견이 나오기 시작했다. 당 원로들도 두 사람의 대승적 통합을 주문했다. 한 원로는 지난 17일 밤 국회 본청의 장 대표 단식장을 찾았고, 같은 날 한 전 대표와 통화하며 통합을 주문한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consequently, former leader Han had been contemplating a political apology message regarding the recent party member bulletin board issue. Within the pro-Han faction, opinions were divided between "should not apologize" and "should apologize for the responsibility in the party division." Some figures reportedly suggested, "Let's also apologize for the conflicts that occurred during former President Yoon Suk-yeol's term while serving as party leader." However, the prevailing opinion was that "the illegal/unfair investigation and disciplinary decision regarding the party member bulletin board issue are not subjects for apology," and it is understood that former leader Han took this stance today. (이에 한 전 대표는 최근 당원 게시판 문제를 두고 정치적 사과 메시지에 대해 고심해 왔다. 친한계 내부는 “사과를 해서는 안 된다”는 의견과 “당내 분열 부분에 대한 책임은 사과하자”는 의견으로 갈렸다. 일부 인사는 “윤석열 전 대통령 재임 시절 당 대표로서 갈등 국면에 있던 것도 사과하자”고 건의했다고 한다. 다만 “당원 게시판 문제에 대한 불법·부당한 조사, 징계 결정은 사과 대상이 아니다”라는 의견이 우세해, 한 전 대표가 이날 이 같은 입장을 낸 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reactions to former leader Han's apology today among neutral lawmakers and figures were mixed. Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon, after visiting leader Jang's hunger strike site today, told reporters, "It is fortunate that former leader Han mustered the courage to apologize," adding, "It will serve as an opportunity for party unity." A fourth-term lawmaker said, "This is just the beginning. There is now room for gradual, step-by-step reconciliation." Supreme Council member Yang Hyang-ja posted on Facebook today, "Let's gather everyone's wisdom for unity, the future, and victory." However, a second-term lawmaker commented, "It would have been better if it were only a political apology, but mentioning 'political retaliation' and such leaves room for further dispute." (한 전 대표의 이날 사과에 대해 중립 성향 의원들과 인사들 사이에선 복잡한 반응이 나왔다. 오세훈 서울시장은 이날 장 대표 단식장을 찾은 뒤 취재진에 “한 전 대표가 용기를 내서 (사과)해 준 것은 다행”이라며 “당 화합의 계기가 될 것”이라고 했다. 한 4선 의원은 “이제 시작이다. 한 걸음씩 차근차근 화합할 여지가 생긴 것”이라고 했다. 양향자 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에서 “화합과 미래, 승리를 위해 모두의 지혜를 모아가자”고 했다. 다만, 한 재선 의원은 “정치적 사과만 했으면 좋았을 텐데 ‘정치 보복’ 등을 운운해 분란의 여지를 남겼다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Geun-sik, chairman of the Seoul Songpa-gap district party committee, proposed to former leader Han on the 17th, "Let's show magnanimous politics by visiting and supporting leader Jang's hunger strike." A standing advisor also said, "Former leader Han should visit leader Jang's hunger strike site, and leader Jang should show a welcoming attitude." It is said that former leader Han currently has no plans to visit leader Jang's hunger strike site. Former lawmaker Kim Seong-tae said in a phone call, "Whether it's former leader Han or leader Jang, the one who shows courage and makes a decision first will be the winner." (김근식 서울 송파병 당협위원장은 지난 17일 한 전 대표를 향해 “장 대표의 단식을 지지 방문하며 통 큰 정치를 보여주자”고 제안했다. 한 상임고문도 “한 전 대표가 장 대표 단식장을 찾아가고 장 대표는 반기는 모습을 보여주라”고 했다. 한 전 대표는 아직 장 대표 단식장을 찾을 생각이 없다고 한다. 김성태 전 의원은 통화에서 “한 전 대표든 장 대표든 먼저 용기와 결단을 내리는 사람이 승자가 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang, who began his hunger strike on the 15th and entered his fourth day today, did not issue an official statement. When New Future Democratic Party leader Jeon Byeong-heon, who visited him today, said, "I hope you exercise political leadership to declare a truce with former leader Han and pool your strength," leader Jang smiled, said "Yes," and nodded. Floor leader Song Eon-seok said, "Regarding the content (of former leader Han's apology), it seems we need to think again about how many people are receiving it." (지난 15일 단식을 시작해 이날 나흘째를 맞은 장 대표는 공식 입장을 내지 않았다. 장 대표는 이날 자신을 찾은 새미래민주당 전병헌 대표가 “정치력을 발휘해서 한 전 대표와 휴전하고 힘을 모았으면 한다”고 하자, 웃으며 “예”라고 답한 뒤 고개를 끄덕였다. 송언석 원내대표는 “(한 전 대표의 사과) 내용에 대해 많은 분들이 어떻게 받아들이고 있는지 다시 한번 생각해봐야 할 듯하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Figures close to leader Jang criticized, saying, "Is this an apology?" and "Public opinion is unfavorable, so they pretend to apologize, but they don't want to admit wrongdoing." On the other hand, pro-Han lawmakers countered, "Despite the illegal investigation and disciplinary action, former leader Han mustered the courage to apologize." (장 대표 측 인사들은 “이게 사과냐” “여론이 불리하니 사과하는 척은 해야겠고, 잘못을 인정하기는 싫은 모습”이라며 비판했다. 반면 친한계 의원들은 “불법적인 조사와 징계에도 한 전 대표가 용기를 내서 사과한 것”이라고 맞섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some within the party predict that the ethics committee's decision regarding former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyeok, a pro-Han figure, will be one of the watershed moments determining whether the internal conflict can be resolved. Previously, the party audit committee recommended severe disciplinary action of 'two-year suspension of party membership rights' to the ethics committee, citing that former Supreme Council member Kim insulted the party leadership and members in media interviews and other statements. The ethics committee is scheduled to hold a meeting on the 19th to hear former Supreme Council member Kim's explanation. (당 일각에선 친한계인 김종혁 전 최고위원에 대한 윤리위 결정이 당내 갈등 봉합 여부의 분수령 중 하나가 될 것이란 전망이 나온다. 앞서 당무감사위는 김 전 최고위원이 언론 인터뷰 등에서 당 지도부와 당원을 모욕하는 언행을 했다며 ‘당원권 정지 2년’의 중징계를 윤리위에 건의했다. 윤리위는 19일 회의를 열고 김 전 최고위원의 소명을 들을 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/FTVQLLOADNFVNEOUQ52W3G2Z3I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ML4VNGYNQNOFPGFOY5J6THLU2A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:53:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jae-won Joins Hunger Strike in Solidarity with Jang Dong-hyk on 'Day 5'... Lee Jun-seok to Return Early (김재원, ‘단식 5일차’ 장동혁 옆에서 동조 단식...이준석은 조기 귀국)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jae-won Joins Hunger Strike in Solidarity with Jang Dong-hyk on 'Day 5'... Lee Jun-seok to Return Early (김재원, ‘단식 5일차’ 장동혁 옆에서 동조 단식...이준석은 조기 귀국)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyk continues his hunger strike for the fifth day, demanding the Democratic Party of Korea accept a special counsel probe into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won also began a solidarity hunger strike on the 19th. Kim is the first from the opposition camp to join a solidarity hunger strike in support of Leader Jang. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 더불어민주당의 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 농성을 벌이고 있는 가운데, 김재원 최고위원도 19일 동조 단식에 들어갔다. 야권에서 장 대표에 호응해 동조 단식에 나선 것은 김 최고위원이 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim posted on Facebook that day, "I've come to the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall. I begin my hunger strike struggle today." In a Facebook post the previous day, he had stated, "Leader Jang Dong-hyk's hunger strike, confronting the Lee Jae-myung administration with his whole body, continues into its fourth day," and added, "I will also participate in the hunger strike starting tomorrow (19th) at 6 AM at the National Assembly Rotunda Hall." At the time, Kim said, "I had postponed it due to unavoidable schedules until now," and added, "I don't know how long my frail body can endure, but I only hope it provides some comfort to Leader Jang." (김 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에 “국회 로텐더홀에 왔다. 오늘부터 단식 투쟁 시작한다”고 밝혔다. 그는 전날에도 페이스북 글에서 “이재명 정권에 온몸으로 맞서는 장동혁 대표의 단식이 4일째 계속되고 있다”면서 “저도 내일(19일) 오전 6시부터 국회 로텐더홀에서 단식에 참여하겠다”고 했었다. 당시 김 최고위원은 “그간 피치 못할 일정으로 미뤄왔다”며 “부실한 몸으로 얼마 버틸지 모르겠지만 장 대표에게 조금이라도 위안이 되길 바랄 뿐”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, who had been on parliamentary diplomacy activities in Mexico and Guatemala along with National Assembly Deputy Speaker Joo Ho-young, is scheduled to return early on the 21st. Leader Lee plans to cooperate with Leader Jang to urge the Democratic Party to accept the dual special counsel probes. However, it is reported that he is not currently considering a hunger strike. (주호영 국회부의장과 함께 멕시코·과테말라로 의원 외교 활동을 떠났던 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 귀국 일정을 앞당겨 21일 귀국할 예정이다. 이 대표는 장 대표와 공조해 민주당에 쌍특검 수용을 촉구할 방침이다. 다만 현재로선 단식을 고려하지는 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post the previous day, Leader Jang expressed his determination to continue the hunger strike, stating, "Since yesterday, a single rose has been guarding my side," and "It was prepared for death from the moment it came to my side. I must not collapse first." (장 대표는 전날 페이스북 글에서 “어제부터 장미 한 송이가 내 곁을 지키고 있다”면서 “내 곁에 올 때부터 죽기를 각오했다. 내가 먼저 쓰러지면 안 된다”고 단식 의지를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:24:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Min-seok: "Lee Hye-hoon, having run in elections multiple times after opposition verification... Refusing the hearing is feeble" (김민석 “이혜훈, 野 검증으로 여러번 선거 나가...  청문 거부 궁색”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/OSDHP4YRF5DFXIYZDPCFP7UBDQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok criticized the People Power Party's refusal to hold a confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, calling it "feeble." (김민석 국무총리는 국민의힘이 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 청문회 개최를 거부한 데 대해 “궁색하다”고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the night of the 18th, Prime Minister Kim posted on X (formerly Twitter), "It is nominee Lee Hye-hoon's role to answer. However, verification is the role of the National Assembly, especially the opposition party," and said, "The nominee refusing a hearing that was agreed upon by both ruling and opposition parties out of fear she might make false excuses is difficult to understand." He added, "Isn't that why a hearing is needed? There shouldn't be anything to fear from providing an explanation." (김 총리는 18일 밤 X(옛 트위터)에 “답하는 것은 이혜훈 후보자의 몫이다. 그러나 검증은 국회, 특히 야당의 몫”이라며 “후보자가 거짓 변명할까 봐 여야가 합의해서 하기로 했던 청문을 거부한다는 것은 이해하기 궁색하다”고 했다. 그러면서 “그래서 청문회가 필요한 것이 아닌가. 해명될까 두려울 게 없지 않나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the nominee, Prime Minister Kim said, "She is a candidate who has already undergone opposition party verification multiple times and run in elections," and added, "Therefore, I expect an even more thorough hearing. Shouldn't we ask for the public's judgment after the hearing?" (김 총리는 이 후보자에 대해 “이미 여러 번 야당의 검증을 거쳐 선거에 나갔던 후보자”라며 “그래서 더 철저한 청문회를 해 주시길 기대한다. 청문 후 국민의 판단을 여쭤야 하지 않겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties initially agreed to hold the nominee's confirmation hearing on the 19th, but the People Power Party held a press conference the day before and refused to hold it, claiming the nominee submitted inadequate documents. Members of the People Power Party belonging to the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee stated, "This nominee should be sitting in the suspect's seat of an investigative agency, not in the National Assembly hearing room," and declared, "We completely refuse the confirmation hearing for this nominee." They further said, "The nominee is not submitting any additional documents at all, using personal information as an excuse, and the ruling party is unilaterally pushing for the hearing on the 19th." (여야는 당초 19일 이 후보자의 인사청문회를 열기로 했으나, 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 자료를 부실하게 제출했다며 전날 기자회견을 열고 개최를 거부했다. 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들은 “이 후보자는 국회 청문회장이 아니라 수사기관 피의자 자리에 앉아야 할 사람”이라며 “이 후보자에 대한 인사청문회를 전면 거부한다”고 했다. 그러면서 “후보자는 개인정보 등을 핑계로 추가 자료 제출을 전혀 하지 않고 있고, 여당은 19일 청문회를 일방적으로 밀어붙이고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of the 15th, the nominee's document submission rate is known to be just over 15%. The nominee's side reportedly does not consent to submitting related documents such as details of their children's employment, military service, and gift tax payments, citing 'personal information.' The People Power Party maintains that if documents related to the children and proof of full gift tax payment are not submitted, they cannot proceed with the hearing. (지난 15일 기준 이 후보자의 자료 제출률은 15% 남짓으로 알려졌다. 이 후보자 측은 자녀들의 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 관련 자료에 대해 ‘개인정보’를 이유로 동의하지 않고 있다고 한다. 국민의힘은 자녀 관련 자료와 증여세 완납증명서 제출이 안 되면 청문회에 임할 수 없다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party holds the position that since the schedule has already been decided, the hearing should be held first. If the People Power Party maintains its boycott stance, the possibility of the Democratic Party holding the hearing alone is also being discussed. (민주당은 이미 개최 일정을 의결한 만큼, 일단 청문회를 열어야 한다는 입장이다. 국민의힘이 보이콧 입장을 고수할 경우, 민주당의 단독 개최 가능성도 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/OSDHP4YRF5DFXIYZDPCFP7UBDQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:34:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Open Debate Over 'Pro-Myung/Pro-Chung' Lines Reignites Over One-Member-One-Vote System... "Mentioning 'Such Acts' to Silence Critics" (1인1표제 놓고 ‘친명·친청’ 공개설전…“해당 운운하며 입틀막”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/PQAGSFALFNA5BMIGQMLG22MXXA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRDQMTCMYYTCZBTGM4WCMRUGY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conflict between pro-Myung and pro-Chung faction Supreme Council members has reignited over Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae's push to reintroduce the 'one-member-one-vote' system for delegates and party members. Recently, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun referred to the act of stirring controversy as a "such act," prompting pro-Myung faction Supreme Council members like Kang Deuk-gu and Hwang Myung-sun to respond with statements such as "We must eliminate any suspicion of self-serving revision" and "We should not be muzzled," eventually leading to demands for a public apology directed at Chief Spokesperson Park. (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 대의원·당원 ‘1인 1표제’를 재추진하는 것을 두고, 친명·친청계 최고위원 간 갈등이 재점화했다. 최근 박수현 수석대변인은 논란 촉발을 “해당 행위”라고 언급했는데, 친명계 강득구·황명선 최고위원 등은 “셀프 개정 오해 소지 없애야 한다” “재갈 물려선 안 된다”라고 했고, 급기야 박 수석대변인을 향한 공개 사과 요구까지 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the party's Supreme Council meeting that day, pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Hwang Myung-sun mentioned that the one-member-one-vote system had been rejected once in the Central Committee last month, stating, "We agree in principle, but we are asking to eliminate any room for misunderstanding." She further suggested, "Let's amend the party constitution and rules to introduce the one-member-one-vote system this time, but with its application starting after the next national convention," adding, "If the very parties who amended the election rules are immediately elected under those rules, it's hard to avoid criticism that it's a self-serving revision." (이날 당 최고위원회의에서 친명계 황명선 최고위원은 지난달 중앙위에서 1인 1표제가 한 차례 부결됐던 점을 언급하며 “원칙에는 동의하지만 오해의 소지를 없애라는 것”이라고 했다. 또 “이번에 1인 1표제를 도입하되 적용 시점은 다음 전당대회 이후로 하는 것으로 당헌당규를 개정”하자며 “선거 룰을 개정한 당사자들이 곧바로 그 규칙에 따라 선출된다면 셀프 개정이라는 비판을 피하기 어렵다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, pro-Chung faction Supreme Council member Moon Jung-bok rebutted Councilor Hwang's remarks. Councilor Moon stated, "To delay or question this again for other secondary reasons is an act of betraying the promises the Democratic Party has made to its members so far." Pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Lee Sung-yoon also holds the position that sufficient public discussion on the one-member-one-vote system has already taken place. This councilor said, "As the greatest concern of party members, it has been sufficiently discussed from the party leadership election in August last year to this Supreme Council election," adding, "For moving towards an era of member sovereignty, the one-member-one-vote system is a perfectly natural principle under the national constitution and the party constitution." (그러자 친청계 문정복 최고위원은 황 위원의 발언에 반박했다. 문 최고위원은 “다른 부차적인 이유로 이것을 다시 보류하거나 다시 문제를 삼는 것은 그동안 당원들에게 이야기했던 민주당의 약속을 저버리는 행위”라고 했다. 친명계 이성윤 최고위원도 1인 1표제 공론화 작업은 이미 충분히 진행됐다는 입장이다. 이 위원은 “당원들의 가장 큰 관심사로서 지난해 8월 당대표 선거부터 이번 최고위원 선거까지 충분히 공론화됐다”며 “당원 주권 시대를 향해 나아가기 위해 1인 1표제는 헌법, 당헌상 너무나 당연한 원리”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day before, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun, regarding claims linking the one-member-one-vote system to party leadership competition, had said, "If this act of stirring controversy goes a bit further, it could be condemned as a 'such act,' and there would be nothing to say in defense." (전날 박수현 수석대변인은 1인 1표제를 당권 경쟁과 연결 짓는 주장에 대해 “이런 논란을 촉발하는 것이 조금 더 가면 ‘해당 행위’라고 비난받아도 할 말 없는 상황”이라고 한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo also publicly targeted Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun's remarks through additional comments at the Supreme Council meeting that day. Councilor Lee said, "For some to dismiss this discussion by mentioning 'such acts' and 'muzzling' critics is abandoning the spirit of democracy," adding, "I believe this is not the party leader's intention either." (이언주 최고위원은 이날 최고위에서 추가 발언을 통해 박수현 수석대변인의 발언을 공개 저격하기도 했다. 이 위원은 “이런 토론을 뭐 일각에서 해당 행위 운운하면서 ‘입틀막’하는 것은 민주주의의 정신을 져버리는 것”이라며 “이것이 당 대표의 뜻도 아닐 거라고 믿는다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Kang Deuk-gu, after the party Supreme Council meeting, separately met with reporters and demanded a public apology from Chief Spokesperson Park. Councilor Kang said, "Does it make sense to define it as a 'such act'? It's like trying to muzzle someone like me," and added, "Spokesperson Park must apologize publicly and officially. If there is no apology, it is unacceptable from the standpoint of a Supreme Council member." He also warned that if no official apology is given by the 21st, he will make a public statement at the Supreme Council meeting that day. (친명계 강득구 최고위원은 당 최고위 이후 따로 기자들과 만나 박 수석대변인에게 공개 사과를 요구했다. 강 위원은 “‘해당 행위로 규정한다’는 게 말이 되나. 나 같은 사람한테 재갈을 물리겠다는 것”이라며 “박 대변인이 공개적, 공식적으로 사과해야 한다. 사과하지 않으면 최고위원 입장에서 용납이 안 되는 것”이라고 했다. 오는 21일까지 공식 사과를 하지 않으면 당일 최고위에서 공개 발언을 하겠다고도 예고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the one-member-one-vote system was submitted as an agenda item for the party affairs committee that day. If the agenda passes that day, it will undergo a three-day collection of member opinions starting from the 22nd, followed by a two-day Central Committee vote on the 2nd of next month for final passage. (한편, 이날 1인1표제는 당무위 안건으로 부의된다. 이날 안건이 통과되면 오는 22일부터 사흘간 당원의견 수렴을 거쳐 다음달 2일 이틀간 중앙위 투표를 거쳐 최종 통과된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/PQAGSFALFNA5BMIGQMLG22MXXA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRDQMTCMYYTCZBTGM4WCMRUGY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:11:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi: "Will not appeal 'expulsion' ethics tribunal decision and will leave the party" (김병기 “‘제명’ 윤리심판원 결정에 재심 신청 않고 당 떠나겠다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/7DEHBOX2PBFBTIY2H3DFTXAVAY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GCV5JARJ55GWVB6NDIFPJ4FJOQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, Kim Byeong-gi, who received an expulsion penalty from the party's ethics tribunal over suspicions including nomination-related donations, stated on the 19th, "I will not apply for a retrial and will leave the party." (공천 헌금 의혹 등으로 당 윤리심판원에서 제명 처분을 받은 김병기 전 더불어민주당 원내대표가 19일 “재심 신청을 하지 않고 당을 떠나겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At an emergency press conference held at the National Assembly Communication Center that day, Representative Kim stated as above, saying, "I thought that if disagreements arise within the party because of me, or if my colleagues bear even the slightest mental burden, I should fully shoulder that burden and go." (김 의원은 이날 국회 소통관에서 연 긴급 기자회견에서 “저로 인해서 당 안에 이견이 생기고 동료들에게 조금이라도 마음의 짐이 된다면 그 부담만큼은 제가 온전히 짊어지고 가야 한다고 생각했다”며 이 같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim said, "I earnestly request my beloved Democratic Party. In the situation where I am not applying for a retrial, if (the ethics tribunal) seeks expulsion, please consider a method to conclude it with a Supreme Council decision," adding, "I do not want to impose even the slightest mental burden on senior, fellow, and junior lawmakers by going through the process of a general assembly of lawmakers' ratification." The ethics tribunal's expulsion decision is finalized by a vote of the general assembly of lawmakers; he requested that no separate general assembly be held as he himself would accept the disciplinary action. (김 의원은 “사랑하는 민주당에 간곡하게 부탁드린다. 제가 재심 신청하지 않은 상황에서 (윤리심판원이) 제명을 청구한다면 최고위원회의 결정으로 종결하는 방안을 검토해달라”면서 " 굳이 의원총회 추인을 거치면서 선배, 동료, 후배 의원 여러분께 조금이라도 마음의 부담을 지우고 싶지 않다”고 했다. 윤리심판원의 제명 결정은 의원총회의 의결로 확정되는데, 김 의원 본인이 징계를 받아들일테니 별도의 의총을 열지 말아달라고 요청한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim said, "The police investigation is already proceeding swiftly. I ask that you calmly wait until the results come out," and added, "Materials to prove that the suspicions are not true are prepared." He continued, "The substantive truth will surely be revealed," and said, "I will faithfully undergo the investigation and submit all related evidence to prove my innocence." (김 의원은 “경찰 수사는 이미 신속하게 진행되고 있다. 결과가 나올 때까지 차분히 지켜봐 주시길 부탁드린다”면서 “의혹이 사실이 아님을 입증할 자료는 준비되어 있다”고 했다. 이어 “실체적 진실은 반드시 드러날 것”이라면서 “충실히 조사를 받고 관련 증거를 모두 제출해서 무죄를 입증할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party's ethics tribunal held a meeting on the 12th and resolved to impose the highest-level disciplinary action, expulsion, on Representative Kim. Immediately after the ethics tribunal's decision, Representative Kim expressed his intention to contest it, saying, "I will immediately apply for a retrial," but on this day, he reversed his initial stance and accepted the disciplinary action.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (민주당 윤리심판원은 지난 12일 회의를 열고 김 의원에 대해 최고 수위 징계인 제명 처분을 의결했다. 김 의원은 윤리심판원 결정 직후 “즉시 재심을 청구하겠다”며 불복 의사를 밝혔지만, 이날 당초 입장을 뒤집고 징계를 수용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/7DEHBOX2PBFBTIY2H3DFTXAVAY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GCV5JARJ55GWVB6NDIFPJ4FJOQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae: "Jang Dong-hyeok Must End His Groundless Hunger Strike... The People Power Party Should Be Prostrating in Repentance" (정청래 “장동혁, 명분 없는 단식 중단해야...국힘은 석고대죄할 때”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Chung Cheong-rae: "Jang Dong-hyeok Must End His Groundless Hunger Strike... The People Power Party Should Be Prostrating in Repentance" (정청래 “장동혁, 명분 없는 단식 중단해야...국힘은 석고대죄할 때”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, urged Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party who is on the fifth day of a hunger strike demanding a special investigation into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, saying, "End your groundless hunger strike quickly." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 통일교·공천 헌금 특검을 요구하며 5일째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 향해 19일 “명분 없는 단식을 얼른 중단하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the party's Supreme Council meeting held at the National Assembly that day, Representative Chung stated, "It is not the time for the People Power Party to be on a hunger strike; it is the time for them to be prostrating in repentance." (정 대표는 이날 국회에서 열린 당 최고위원회의에서 “국민의힘은 지금 단식할 때가 아니라 석고대죄할 때”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung said, "Having experienced a 24-day hunger strike myself at Gwanghwamun Square during the Sewol Ferry incident, I know very well how difficult a hunger strike is." He added, "From my experience, the periods from the 3rd to 4th day, the 7th to 8th day, and the 14th to 15th day are particularly tough. Representative Jang, you must be having a very hard time, so please end your groundless hunger strike quickly." He further advised, "Health is the most important thing. Eat and then fight." (정 대표는 “저도 세월호 때 광화문 광장에서 24일간 단식을 해봐서 단식이 얼마나 힘든가를 잘 알고 있다”면서 “제 경험으로는 3일에서 4일 넘어갈 때, 7일에서 8일 넘어갈 때, 14일에서 15일 넘어갈 때가 참 힘들더라. 장 대표님, 많이 힘드실 텐데 명분 없는 단식은 얼른 중단하시라”고 했다. 정 대표는 이어 “건강이 최고”라면서 “밥 먹고 싸우세요”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Representative Chung mentioned, "The law to establish a special tribunal for rebellion cases has already been passed and is awaiting implementation," and stated, "We will also pass judicial reform measures one by one without fail. We will pass legislation on the crime of distorting the law, judicial review petitions, and increasing the number of Supreme Court justices without any setbacks." (한편 정 대표는 “이미 내란재판부 설치법이 통과돼 시행을 앞두고 있다”면서 “사법 개혁도 따박따박 통과시키겠다. 법 왜곡죄, 재판소원, 대법관 증원 등 차질 없이 통과시킬 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the first-instance court's sentencing of former President Yoon Suk-yeol to five years in prison on charges of obstructing an arrest, Representative Chung said, "The outcome of a five-year prison sentence is somewhat disappointing," but added, "However, since you can't be full from the first bite, I evaluate this as our society taking its first step toward restoring democracy and constitutional order." Addressing former President Yoon, Representative Chung said, "An unrepentant, shameless, and ignorant ringleader of rebellion without any reflection or remorse must be permanently isolated from our society." (정 대표는 1심 법원이 윤석열 전 대통령의 체포 방해 혐의에 대해 징역 5년을 선고한 데 대해서는 “징역 5년이라는 결과는 다소 아쉽다”면서도 “무엇이든 첫술에 배부를 수는 없기에 우리 사회가 민주주의와 헌정 질서를 회복하는 첫걸음을 뗀 것이라고 평가한다”고 했다. 정 대표는 윤 전 대통령을 향해서는 “반성과 성찰이 없는 뻔뻔하고 무식한 내란 수괴는 우리 사회에서 영원히 격리시켜야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:41:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Party Bulletin Controversy', Shin Dong-wook Reiterates Demand for "Supreme Council Verification"... Yang Hyang-ja Urges "Let's Win Through Unity" (‘당게 논란’, 신동욱 “최고위 검증” 재차 요구...양향자 “단결로 승리하자”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W6V7PAHMGJFXDHZSYUCYLBJY6E/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SKGWRJ4NBZH5HNKFUDR2J7DESE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shin Dong-wook, a Supreme Council member of the People Power Party, on the 19th, reiterated his demand for a public verification at the Supreme Council level regarding the party's Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon over the 'party member bulletin incident'. He also addressed former leader Han, saying, "I hope he will respond whether he will accept the proposal or not." (신동욱 국민의힘 최고위원이 19일 당 윤리위원회가 ‘당원 게시판 사건’과 관련해 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명 결정을 한 것을 두고 최고위원회 차원의 공개 검증을 재차 요구했다. 그러면서 한 전 대표를 향해 “제안에 응할 것인지 말 것인지 답해주길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Shin, who had previously proposed a public verification at the Supreme Council level on the 17th, stated at the Supreme Council meeting held in the National Assembly Rotunda, where leader Jang Dong-hyuk is conducting a hunger strike, "This is not to deny or reject the results of the party audit committee's audit or the Ethics Committee's (expulsion) decision." (앞서 지난 17일에도 최고위 차원의 공개 검증을 제안했던 신 최고위원은 이날 장동혁 대표가 단식 투쟁 중인 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “당무감사위원회의 당무감사 결과나 윤리위원회의 (제명) 결정을 부정, 부인하는 게 아니다”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "There are various interpretations and evaluations different from my own thoughts," adding, "This is not an admission of a 'fabricated audit'. I expressed my concern that if evaluations and measures are not based on factual relationships and are handled emotionally, it could lead to major problems later." (그는 “여러 가지 제 생각과 다른 해석과 평가들이 있다”며 “조작감사라는 것에 대해 인정하는 게 아니다. 이 문제는 감정으로 처리할 게 아니라 사실관계에 기반한 평가와 조치가 내려지지 않는다면 나중에 큰 문제가 생길 수 있다는 제 걱정을 표현한 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "If the party audit committee or ethics committee cannot be trusted, then the Supreme Council members will make a calm judgment and evaluation," stating, "The Supreme Council is a place where various factions elected by our party members gather." (그러면서 “당감위나 윤리위를 못 믿겠다면 최고위원들이 냉정하게 판단해 평가를 내리겠다는 것”이라며 “최고위는 우리 당원이 선출한 여러 계파가 모인 곳”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Jo Gwang-han, appointed by leader Jang, commented on former leader Han's apology the previous day regarding the party bulletin controversy, calling it "insincere wordplay" and saying "it reminded me of 'crocodile tears'." (장 대표가 지명한 조광한 최고위원은 한 전 대표가 전날 당게 논란에 대해 사과한 것에 대해 “진정성 없는 말장난”이라며 “‘악어의 눈물’이 떠올랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Yang Hyang-ja urged reconciliation, saying, "Unfortunately, supporters of the People Power Party are divided into two." She said, "Can't we accept leader Jang's intention for the hunger strike as it is and believe in the sincerity of leader Han's apology?" and added, "How can our party, which treats a hunger strike as an object of ridicule and even an apology as an object of hatred, gain the public's trust and lead the country?" While expressing regret over the content of former leader Han's apology, she urged, "Let's end the conflict with a warm embrace for each other and win through unity." (양향자 최고위원은 “안타깝게도 국민의힘 지지자들은 둘로 나뉘어져 있다”며 봉합을 요구했다. 그는 “장 대표가 단식하는 의도를 있는 그대로 받아주고 한 대표가 사과하는 진심 그대로를 좀 믿어줄 순 없나”라며 “단식이 비아냥의 대상이 되고, 사과조차 혐오의 대상으로 여기는 우리 당이 어떻게 국민의 신뢰를 얻고 나라를 이끌겠나”라고 했다. 그러면서 한 전 대표의 사과 내용이 아쉽다면서도 “서로를 보듬는 따뜻한 품으로 갈등을 끝내고 단결로 승리하자”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, leader Jang Dong-hyuk, who is continuing his fifth day of a hunger strike demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination donations, stated today, "I will not break my initial resolve to fight with my life." He said, "If we stop here, there will be no future for the Republic of Korea." He added, "It's difficult. I am gradually reaching my limit," and appealed, "For the future of the Republic of Korea, I ask the public to join forces together." (한편 통일교와 공천 헌금 등 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 닷새째 단식을 이어가고 있는 장동혁 대표는 이날 “목숨 바쳐 싸우겠다는 처음 각오를 꺾지 않겠다”고 했다. 그는 “여기서 멈춘다면 대한민국의 미래는 없을 것”이라고 했다. 이어 “힘이 든다. 점차 한계가 오고 있다”며 “대한민국의 미래를 위해 국민 여러분께서 함께 힘을 보태 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W6V7PAHMGJFXDHZSYUCYLBJY6E/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SKGWRJ4NBZH5HNKFUDR2J7DESE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:10:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Breaches 4800, Yet President Lee's Approval Rating Drops to 53%... "Due to Rift Between Party and Government, Bribery Allegations in Nominations" (코스피 4800 돌파에도 李대통령 지지율 하락해 53%…“당정 엇박자·공천 뇌물 논란 탓")</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;KOSPI Breaches 4800, Yet President Lee's Approval Rating Drops to 53%... "Due to Rift Between Party and Government, Bribery Allegations in Nominations" (코스피 4800 돌파에도 李대통령 지지율 하락해 53%…“당정 엇박자·공천 뇌물 논란 탓" )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A public opinion poll released on the 19th showed that President Lee Jae-myung's job approval rating has turned downward for the first time in three weeks, standing at 53.1%. (이재명 대통령의 국정 수행 지지도가 53.1%로 3주 만에 하락세로 돌아섰다는 여론조사 결과가 19일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a survey conducted by Realmeter for the Energy Economy News from the 12th to the 16th, targeting 2,516 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, 53.1% of respondents gave a positive assessment of President Lee's job performance. This is a decrease of 3.7 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week. (리얼미터가 에너지경제신문 의뢰로 지난 12∼16일 전국 18세 이상 2516명을 대상으로 조사한 결과 이 대통령의 국정 수행을 긍정 평가한 응답자는 53.1%로 집계됐다. 지난주보다 3.7%포인트(p) 낮은 수치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negative assessments rose to 42.2%, up 4.4 percentage points from the previous survey. (부정 평가는 42.2%로 지난 조사 대비 4.4%p 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter analyzed, "Despite economic and diplomatic achievements such as the KOSPI breaking through the 4800 mark and the Korea-Japan summit, the approval rating showed a downward trend as controversies over morality overlapped, including the exposure of disagreements between the ruling party and the government regarding the prosecution reform bill and allegations of nomination bribes and illegal election funds (bribery) involving ruling party figures." (리얼미터는 “코스피 4800선 돌파와 한일 정상회담 등 경제·외교 성과가 있었는데도 정부의 검찰 개혁안을 둘러싼 당정 이견 노출과 여권 인사들의 공천 헌금·선거 불법 자금(뇌물) 의혹 등 도덕성 논란이 겹치며 지지율이 하락세를 보였다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a party support survey conducted from the 15th to the 16th of last month, targeting 1,004 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, the Democratic Party of Korea showed a support rate of 42.5%, while the People Power Party showed 37.0%. (지난달 15∼16일 전국 18세 이상 1004명을 대상으로 한 정당 지지도 조사에서는 더불어민주당이 42.5%, 국민의힘은 37.0%의 지지율을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party fell by 5.3 percentage points compared to the previous week, showing a decline for the first time in four weeks, while the People Power Party rose by 3.5 percentage points, showing a rebound for the first time in four weeks. (민주당은 지난주 대비 5.3%p 하락하며 4주 만에 하락세를 보인 반면 국민의힘은 3.5%p 상승하며 4주 만에 반등세를 나타냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform New Party was at 3.3%, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party at 2.5%, and the Progressive Party at 1.7%. The non-partisan group was 11.5%. (개혁신당은 3.3%, 조국혁신당은 2.5%, 진보당은 1.7%로 나타났다. 무당층은 11.5%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter explained, "It is judged that the Democratic Party's decline widened as controversies over morality grew with the full-scale investigation into the nomination bribery allegations involving lawmakers Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi, compounded by intra-party conflict due to criticism from hardliners within the party regarding the Serious Crime Investigation Office (SCIO) and the Public Prosecution Service Act." (리얼미터는 “민주당은 강선우·김병기 의원 공천 헌금 의혹 수사 본격화로 도덕성 논란이 커진 데다 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청법을 둘러싼 당내 강경파의 비판으로 당정 갈등이 겹치며 하락 폭을 키운 것으로 판단된다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the People Power Party, it interpreted, "It appears that the rebound in support was led by the consolidation of traditional supporters, such as those in the Daegu/Gyeongbuk region and conservative groups, due to the special prosecutor's demand for the death penalty for former President Yoon Suk-yeol and the controversy over the expulsion of Han Dong-hoon." (국민의힘에 대해서는 “특검의 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형과 한동훈 제명 논란으로 대구·경북과 보수층 등 전통 지지층이 결집해 지지율 반등을 이끈 것으로 보인다”고 해석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The margin of error for the presidential job approval rating survey is ±2.0 percentage points at a 95% confidence level, and for the party support survey, it is ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level. (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사의 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±2.0%p, 정당 지지도 조사 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±3.1%p다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response rate for the presidential job approval rating survey was 4.5%, and for the party support survey, it was 3.8%. For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사 응답률은 4.5%, 정당 지지도 조사 응답률은 3.8%였다. 자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 홈페이지 참조.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:09:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Board of Audit and Inspection: "Public Institutions' Regional Talent Hiring Rate Falls Below 30%... Mandatory Hiring Lacks Effectiveness" (감사원 “공공기관 지역인재 채용률 30% 미달…의무채용 실효성 떨어져“)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/HNA62OPYVZHSXADVWO67VVKJUM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EHC3AZG4JNGG7K5UN3ERFIOURA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;An audit by the Board of Audit and Inspection (BAI) released on the 19th revealed that 'relocated public institutions,' which moved their headquarters from the metropolitan area to regional areas, are not properly adhering to the mandatory hiring ratio (30%) for regional talent. (본사를 수도권에서 지방으로 옮긴 ‘이전 공공기관’에서 지역 인재 의무 채용 비율(30%)이 잘 지켜지지 않고 있다는 감사원 감사 결과가 19일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI announced the results of its audit on the 'Status of Public Institution Workforce Management' containing these findings. This audit, conducted from 2024 to 2025, was initiated in response to criticisms that the efficiency and productivity of public institution workforces are declining. It targeted a total of 37 public institutions, including Korea Electric Power Corporation (KEPCO). (감사원은 이날 이 같은 내용의 ‘공공기관 인력 운용 실태’ 감사 결과를 발표했다. 2024~2025년 진행된 이번 감사는 공공기관 인력의 효율성과 생산성이 하락하고 있다는 지적 등에 따라 실시됐다. 한국전력공사 등 총 37개 공공기관을 대상으로 진행됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the audit results, a significant number of relocated public institutions were found to have neglected hiring regional talent by excessively applying 'exception provisions' to the mandatory hiring requirement. Under current law, if the number of hires per examination field is five or fewer annually, the mandatory 30% hiring ratio does not apply. The audit found that this exception clause is being abused. (감사 결과에 따르면, 상당수 이전 공공기관은 의무 채용의 ‘예외 규정’을 과다 적용하는 방식으로 지역 인재 채용에 소홀했던 것으로 드러났다. 현행법상 시험 분야별 채용 인원이 연간 5명 이하이면, 의무 채용 비율 30%가 적용되지 않는다. 그런데 이 예외 조항이 남용되고 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, nine institutions, including Korea Gas Corporation, judged whether the number was 'five or fewer' based on individual examination units rather than on an 'annual' basis. Consequently, the mandatory hiring ratio was not properly applied in cases where it should have been. Three institutions, including Korea Expressway Corporation, also had issues with inconsistently applying 'job groups (e.g., administration)' and 'job series (e.g., management, legal affairs)' when classifying examination fields. (예를 들어 한국가스공사 등 9개 기관은 ‘연간’이 아닌 개별 시험 단위 기준으로 ‘5명 이하’ 여부를 판단했다. 결과적으로 의무 채용 비율이 적용돼야 할 경우에 제대로 적용되지 않은 것이다. 한국도로공사 등 3개 기관은 시험 분야를 분류할 때 ‘직군(행정 등)’과 ‘직렬(경영, 법정 등)’을 일관성 없이 적용하는 문제도 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to these problems, the hiring rate for regional talent compared to the total new hiring quota for relocated public institutions was 19.8% as of 2024, more than 10 percentage points lower than the mandatory hiring ratio (30%). (이런 문제 때문에 이전 공공기관의 총 신규 채용 정원 대비 지역 인재 채용률은 2024년 기준 19.8%로 의무 채용 비율(30%)보다 10%포인트 이상 낮았던 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some public institutions were found to have excessively applied preferential systems for regional talent. The BAI judged that 11 institutions, including Korea Tourism Organization, simultaneously applied a 'point addition system' that gives extra points to regional talent and a 'hiring target system' that mandates hiring over 30%, causing excessive disadvantage to general applicants. (반면 일부 공공기관은 지역 인재 우대 제도를 과도하게 적용한 것으로 나타났다. 한국관광공사 등 11개 기관은 지역 인재에 가산점을 주는 ‘가점제’와 30% 이상을 의무 채용하는 ‘채용 목표제’를 동시에 적용해 일반 지원자에게 과도한 불이익을 줬다는 것이 감사원 판단이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the BAI's simulation analysis, if it were assumed that only the hiring target system remained and the effect of the point addition system was removed over the past four years, an estimated 4,026 general applicants who had failed would have passed, while 563 regional talent who had passed would have failed. This essentially indicates a problem of 'reverse discrimination.' (감사원의 모의 분석 결과, 이 경우 만약 채용 목표제만 남기고 가점제 효과를 없앤다고 가정하면 지난 4년간 탈락했던 일반 지원자 4026명이 합격하고, 합격했던 지역 인재 563명이 탈락하는 것으로 추산됐다. ‘역차별’ 문제가 발생한 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the BAI did not judge the problems revealed regarding regional talent hiring as 'illegal.' A BAI official stated, "We view these issues as arising from insufficient detailed standards or regulations and have requested institutional improvements." (감사원은 다만 지역 인재 채용과 관련해 드러난 문제들을 ‘불법’이라고 판단하지는 않았다. 감사원 관계자는 “관련 세부 기준이나 규정이 미비해서 일어난 것으로 보고, 제도 개선을 주문했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in many public institutions, a phenomenon has emerged where employees are reluctant to be promoted to junior managerial positions at level 3/4 or higher or to executive positions. For instance, at KEPCO KPS, the competition rate for junior managerial positions was only 0.2 to 1 as of 2024. This is understood to be due to the excessive workload for managers and low compensation for executives. (이 밖에 상당수 공공기관에선 직원들이 3·4급 이상 초급 간부나 임원으로 승진하는 것을 기피하려는 현상이 나타났다. 예를 들어 한전KPS의 경우 2024년 기준 초급 간부 경쟁률이 0.2대 1에 불과했다. 간부들의 과중한 업무, 임원들의 낮은 보수 때문인 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another problem revealed was the poor work performance of wage-peak system participants. Particularly when these employees perform different tasks than before entering the wage-peak system, 28% of their department heads responded in a survey that the employees' actual working hours were "less than 5 hours per week." A BAI official said, "This is effectively an evaluation that they are not working properly." This was analyzed to be because it is difficult to provide personnel incentives like promotion to wage-peak system participants. (또 임금피크 대상자의 업무 실적이 저조하다는 문제점도 드러났다. 특히 해당 직원이 임금피크 전 업무와 다른 업무를 하는 경우, 소속 부서장들이 설문에서 해당 직원들의 실질 업무 시간에 대해 “주 5시간 미만”이라고 답하는 경우가 28%에 달했다. 감사원 관계자는 “사실상 제대로 업무를 하지 않는다고 평가한 것”이라고 했다. 이는 임금피크 대상자의 경우 승진 등 인사상 인센티브 제공이 어렵기 때문인 것으로 분석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI stated that it has notified relevant ministries, including the Ministry of Economy and Finance and the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, of the problems revealed in this audit and requested institutional improvements. (감사원은 이번 감사로 드러난 문제점에 대해 재경부·국토부 등에 통보 조치하고 제도 개선 등을 요구했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/HNA62OPYVZHSXADVWO67VVKJUM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EHC3AZG4JNGG7K5UN3ERFIOURA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 03:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk: "Government's Prosecution Service and Serious Crimes Investigation Agency Bills Must Be Completely Revised"... Pushes for Scrapping if No Revisions (조국 “공소청·중수청법 정부안 전면 수정해야”...수정 없으면 폐기 추진)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/UVVL2Y4JXFF6LLXAXXUDTRZYRE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EKQT7VHAS5MR5E6B6Q64WP7DS4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party demanded a complete revision of the Serious Crimes Investigation Agency (SCIA) and Prosecution Service bills, which the government has pre-announced for legislation, and stated that if the government does not comply, it will push for the complete scrapping of the bills. The demands include codifying the abolition of prosecutors' supplementary investigation rights in the Prosecution Service bill and unifying the dual structure of the SCIA into a single entity. (조국혁신당은 정부가 입법 예고한 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청법의 전면 수정을 요구하고, 정부가 응하지 않으면 법안 전면 폐기를 추진하겠다고 19일 밝혔다. 공소청법에 검사의 보완 수사권 폐지를 명문화하고, 중수청 이원화 구조를 일원화하라는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, made these remarks during a joint meeting of the party's Supreme Council, general assembly of lawmakers, and the 'We Go All the Way' special committee. He stated, "The government's pre-announced bill only mimics the separation of prosecution and investigation, which is the core of prosecution reform." (조국 조국혁신당 대표는 이날 당 최고위원회의·의원총회·‘끝까지 간다’ 특별위원회 연석회의에서 “정부 입법 예고안은 검찰 개혁의 핵심인 기소와 수사 분리를 흉내만 낸 것”이라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After unveiling the party's alternative bill, Representative Cho explained, "We have stipulated in the supplementary provisions of the Prosecution Service bill that Article 196 of the Criminal Procedure Act, which defines prosecutors' investigation rights, should be abolished." He also emphasized, "The SCIA must not become a revival of the Supreme Prosecutors' Office's SCIA, which was abolished in 2013," narrowing the SCIA's investigation scope from nine major crimes (as per the government bill) to four: corruption, economic crimes, defense project crimes, and investigations into insurrection and foreign aggression. Regarding the SCIA's organization, he said, "We eliminated the dual system of 'investigative judicial officers,' who are essentially prosecutors, and 'specialized investigators,' who only play a supporting role," and "We unified all investigators as 'investigators.'" (조 대표는 당 차원의 대안 법안을 공개한 뒤 “검사 수사권을 규정한 형사소송법 196조를 폐기하도록 공소청 법안 부칙에 명기했다”고 밝혔다. 또 “중수청이 2013년 폐지된 대검 중수부의 부활 조직이 돼서는 안 된다”면서 중수청의 수사 범위를 9대 범죄(정부안)에서 부패·경제·방위 사업 범죄, 내란·외환 수사 등 4개로 좁혔다. 중수청 조직에 대해서는 “사실상 검사인 ‘수사사법관’과 보조 역할만 하는 ‘전문 수사관’의 이원화 체제를 없앴다”면서 “수사하는 이는 모두 ‘수사관’으로 통일시켰다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Cho stated, "If the government does not accept this proposal, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party will pursue legislation led by the National Assembly instead of the government bill." (조 대표는 “정부가 이 안을 수용하지 않는다면 조국혁신당은 정부안 대신 국회 주도 입법을 추진할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the same day, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party also demanded a complete reorganization of the government's Prosecution Reform Promotion Team. The party has criticized the team, arguing that because many prosecutors are dispatched to it, it has produced prosecution-centric alternatives. The party stated, "If the government does not comply, we will push for the dissolution of the promotion team and pursue legislation led by the National Assembly." (조국혁신당은 이날 정부 검찰개혁추진단의 전면 재구성도 요구했다. 조국혁신당은 검찰개혁추진단에 검사가 다수 파견돼 있어 검찰 중심의 대안이 나왔다고 비판해왔다. 당은 “정부가 이에 응하지 않는 경우 추진단 해산 및 국회 주도 입법을 추진하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/UVVL2Y4JXFF6LLXAXXUDTRZYRE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EKQT7VHAS5MR5E6B6Q64WP7DS4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Opposition Party: "Only 15% of Requested Materials Submitted," Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Stalls and Adjourns (野 “요구 자료 중 15%만 제출” 이혜훈 청문회 파행 끝 정회)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/GMSUSEXDTZBNVBLQFJX3OHSOTU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7RMSOXZJRZIAPB5JGOMW2O4ENU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly held a confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, on the 19th. However, the ruling and opposition parties engaged in a war of words over the submission of materials by the nominee and whether to change the schedule. As a result, the morning session was adjourned without nominee Lee Hye-hoon even being able to attend. (국회는 19일 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회를 열었지만, 여야가 후보자 자료 제출과 일정 변경 여부를 놓고 설전을 벌이면서 정작 이혜훈 후보자는 참석도 못한 채 오전 회의를 정회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the meeting held for the Strategy and Finance Committee's confirmation hearing that day, the ruling and opposition parties clashed strongly, repeatedly making procedural motions. The ruling party maintained that since it had already been agreed upon and voted on by both parties to hold the hearing at 10 a.m. that day, the nominee should be brought in to undergo public verification. Democratic Party lawmaker Park Hong-geun stated, "Even if the materials are insufficient, there is no case of boycotting a hearing," adding, "Today's confirmation hearing should proceed as scheduled with the nominee present." (이날 열린 재경위 인사청문회를 위한 회의에서 여야는 강하게 충돌하며 의사진행발언만 거듭했다. 여당은 이미 여야 합의와 의결을 거쳐 이날 오전 10시 청문회를 열기로 한 만큼 후보자를 출석시켜 공개 검증에 나서야 한다는 입장이었다. 박홍근 민주당 의원은 “자료가 부실하다 해도 청문회를 보이콧하는 경우는 없다”면서 “오늘 인사청문회를 예정대로 후보자를 데려다 놓고 해야한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the opposition party insisted that the hearing could not be held because the nominee's side had failed to submit a significant portion of the requested materials by the deadline. Strategy and Finance Committee Chairwoman and People Power Party lawmaker Lim Lee-ja refused to place the hearing on the agenda, stating, "Since an agreement between the floor leaders of the two parties has not been reached, the hearing cannot be placed on the agenda." (반면 야당은후보자 측이 요구된 자료의 상당 부분을 기한 내 제출하지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 열 수 없다는 입장을 고수했다. 재경위원장 임이자 국민의힘 의원은 “양당 간사 간 합의가 이루어지지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 상정할 수 없다”며 안건 상정을 거부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, the opposition party's floor leader on the committee, also demanded additional material submission, saying, "Only 15% of the 2,187 requested items have been submitted. The 18 items that arrived last night are not the core materials." (야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원도 “자료 요구 2187건 중 15％만 제출됐다. 어젯밤 도착한 18건 자료는 핵심이 아니다”라며 추가 자료 제출을 요구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, opposition party lawmakers listed controversies surrounding nominee Lee Hye-hoon, such as allegations of unfair subscription, illegal gifting, suspicions regarding children's employment and study abroad, and controversy over staff misconduct. They argued, "With this level of suspicion, this is a matter that should first have the facts clarified by investigative agencies, not in a hearing room." (또 야당 의원들은 이혜훈 후보자와 관련해 제기된 부정 청약, 편법 증여, 자녀 채용·유학 의혹, 보좌진 갑질 논란 등을 나열하면서 “이 정도 의혹이면 청문회장이 아니라 수사기관에서 먼저 사실관계를 규명받아야 할 사안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the procedural motions dragged on, Chairwoman Lim Lee-ja adjourned the meeting, telling the floor leaders of both parties to "go and hold additional consultations on holding (the hearing)." For over an hour and a half, nominee Lee Hye-hoon was unable to even take a seat in the meeting room. (의사진행발언이 길어지자 임이자 위원장은 여야 간사를 향해 “개최 추가 협의해오라”라며 회의를 정회했다. 1시간 30분 넘게 이어진 시간 동안 이혜훈 후보자는 회의장에 착석조차 하지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, nominee Lee Hye-hoon met with reporters and said, "I submitted about 75% (of the materials)," and "I am preparing to submit as much as possible now. I have submitted everything that could be secured and am preparing to secure the rest." She also said, "I am waiting for the hearing to be held so I can have the opportunity to explain in detail before the public." (이후 이혜훈 후보자는 기자들과 만나 “(자료 제출) 75% 정도 냈다”며 “지금 최대한 내려고 준비하고 있다. 확보할 수 있는 것들은 다 냈고, 확보를 위해서 준비하고 있다”고 했다. 또 “청문회가 열려서 국민들 앞에 소상히 소명할 수 있는 기회를 갖기를 기다리고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the failure to submit some materials, she explained, "The data retention period has already passed, and (the opposition lawmakers) are even asking for things from 30-40 years ago. There were many items I couldn't submit because national institutions do not hold the data." (또 자료를 내지 못한 것과 관련해서는 “이미 자료 보존 기간이 지나서, (야당 의원들이) 심지어 30~40년 전 거를 달라고 하시니, 국가기관이 자료를 보유하고 있지 않아서 못 내는 것들이 많았다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, if this nominee's hearing is postponed for a long time, the appointment decision ultimately falls to the presidential office. The National Assembly must submit a hearing progress report within 20 days after submitting the request for a confirmation hearing. If the hearing progress report is not adopted, the President can request its resubmission within 10 days. If the report is not submitted even after the resubmission request, the appointment can be forcibly proceeded with. (한편, 이 후보자 청문회가 장기간 미뤄지면 임명 결정은 결국 청와대 몫으로 돌아간다. 국회는 인사청문요청안 제출 후 20일 이내에 청문경과보고서를 송부해야 한다. 청문경과보고서를 채택하지 않을 시 대통령은 10일 이내 재송부를 요청할 수 있고, 재송부 요청에도 청문경과보고서를 제출하지 않으면 임명을 강행할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/GMSUSEXDTZBNVBLQFJX3OHSOTU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7RMSOXZJRZIAPB5JGOMW2O4ENU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 02:42:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meloni: "My Daughter is a K-pop Fan, an Even Stronger Alliance" Lee: "Grazie" (멜로니 “제 딸이 K팝 팬, 더욱 굳건한 동맹으로” 李 “그라찌에”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/KTSW5EDMFFDKXHGWNCIUCHL53U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OC6NBGRHJVPITBSQ2MDHTL6DRI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung met with Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni, who is on an official visit to South Korea on the 19th, and stated, "In today's meeting, Prime Minister Meloni and I agreed to further develop bilateral relations to a future-oriented level befitting the title of strategic partners." (이재명 대통령은 19일 공식 방한한 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리와 만나 “오늘 회담에서 저와 멜로니 총리님은 전략적 동반자라는 명칭에 부합하는 미래 지향적인 수준으로 양국관계를 더욱 발전시켜 나가기로 합의했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks during a joint press conference after holding a summit with Prime Minister Meloni at the Presidential Office. He said, "South Korea and Italy are very old friends, having celebrated the 140th anniversary of diplomatic relations the year before last." The two leaders held small-group and expanded talks on the same day, followed by a signing ceremony for a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) covering cooperation in the semiconductor industry, among other areas. (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 멜로니 총리와 정상회담을 한 뒤 공동 언론 발표를 통해 “한국과 이탈리아는 재작년 수교 140주년을 기념할 만큼 아주 오래된 친구”라며 이 같이 밝혔다. 양국 정상은 이날 소인수·확대 회담을 한 뒤, 반도체 산업 협력 등을 담은 양해각서(MOU) 서명식을 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Cooperation in the trade sector will be further expanded to a level commensurate with the economic scale and brand power of both countries," adding, "To this end, we agreed to revitalize the Korea-Italy Business Forum, involving companies from both nations, as a venue for creating new opportunities and a channel for addressing corporate difficulties." (이 대통령은 “교역 분야의 협력은 양국의 경제 규모와 브랜드파워에 걸맞는 수준으로 더욱 확대될 것”이라며 “이를 위해 양국 기업이 참여하는 한-이탈리아 비즈니스 포럼을 새로운 기회 창출의 장이자 기업들의 애로상담 창구로 활성화하겠다는 데 뜻을 모았다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Cooperation in the science sector, which determines a nation's future, will be further expanded," stating, "We will continuously discover capable researchers through support for joint research in basic and applied fields and further broaden the horizon of cooperation into advanced industries such as artificial intelligence and aerospace." (이어 “국가의 미래가 달린 과학 분야의 협력이 더욱 확대될 것”이라며 “기초 응용 분야 공동연구 지원을 통해 역량 있는 연구자들을 지속 발굴하고 인공지능, 우주항공 같은 첨단산업으로 협력의 지평을 더욱 넓혀가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Meloni said, "This visit is a very important visit strategically," adding, "I want to once again maintain an even stronger alliance with South Korea." She further stated, "The two countries should further explore which areas have unlimited potential for development," citing key mineral supply chains, semiconductors, transportation and infrastructure, and investment as areas for future cooperation expansion. (멜로니 총리는 “이번 방문은 전략적으로 매우 중요한 방문”이라며 “다시 한 번 더욱 더 한국과 굳건한 동맹 관계를 유지하고자 한다”고 했다. 이어 “양국은 무한한 가능성을 가지고 발전시킬 수 있는 분야가 어떤 분야인지 더 탐색해야 한다”며 향후 협력 확대 분야로 핵심 광물 공급망, 반도체, 교통 및 인프라, 투자 등을 꼽았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Meloni said, "My daughter is also a K-pop fan," adding, "Currently, South Korea is promoting its soft power through K-pop, and we can explore ways to enhance cooperation in that field as well." Prime Minister Meloni once again invited President Lee for a state visit to Italy. She said, "I have always thought very positively of President Lee's practical approach, so I always want to hear his valuable opinions on the international crises or issues we face," adding, "I sincerely hope you will visit Italy on a state visit." President Lee responded in Italian, "Grazie (Thank you)." (멜로니 총리는 “제 딸이 K팝 팬이기도 하다”며 “지금 한국이 K팝으로 소프트파워를 알리고 있는데, 그 분야에서도 협력 증진을 탐색할 수 있다”고 했다. 멜로니 총리는 이날 이 대통령에게 이탈리아 국빈 방문을 재차 요청했다. 그는 “평소 이 대통령의 실용적 접근 방식을 굉장히 긍정적으로 생각해왔기에 우리가 당면한 국제적 위기 상황이나 현안에 대해 고견을 항상 듣고자 한다”며 “꼭 이탈리아를 국빈 방문해주셨으면 좋겠다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 이탈리아어로 “그라찌에(Grazie·감사합니다)”라고 화답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/KTSW5EDMFFDKXHGWNCIUCHL53U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OC6NBGRHJVPITBSQ2MDHTL6DRI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:59:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea's Kim Yong-chol, 'Mastermind Behind Cheonan Sinking', Denied Responsibility During 2018 PyeongChang Olympics Visit, Saying "We Didn't Do It" (‘천안함 폭침 주범’ 北 김영철, 2018년 평창올림픽 방한 때 “우린 안 해” 책임 부인)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/E67VUSKSCRBEHJUDDO2NTBUSS4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7AVNLUXPD5JPLGREIJ4O6FQCEE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed on the 19th that Kim Yong-chol, a senior advisor to the North Korean Workers' Party's United Front Department, denied responsibility for the 2010 Cheonan warship sinking incident to South Korean officials during his visit to South Korea for the 2018 PyeongChang Olympics, saying, "We did not do it." (김영철 북한 조선노동당 통일전선부 고문이 지난 2018년 평창올림픽 당시 방한한 자리에서 2010년 천안함 폭침 사건에 대해 한국 측에 “우리는 하지 않았다”며 책임을 부인한 것으로 19일 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advisor Kim, who previously headed the Reconnaissance General Bureau, North Korea's agency overseeing operations against the South, is considered one of the masterminds behind the Cheonan sinking incident. (김 고문은 북한의 대남 공작 총괄 기구인 정찰총국장을 지낸 인물로, 천안함 폭침 사건을 일으킨 주범 중 한 명으로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon Kun-young of the Democratic Party of Korea is scheduled to publish a memoir titled 'The Panmunjom Project' on the 21st, which contains these details. Rep. Yoon previously served as the Director of the National Situation Room in the Blue House during the Moon Jae-in administration. (더불어민주당 윤건영 의원은 이 같은 내용 등을 담은 회고록 ‘판문점 프로젝트’를 오는 21일 출간할 예정이다. 윤 의원은 문재인 정부 청와대 국정상황실장을 지냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the book, in 2018, Advisor Kim (then head of the Workers' Party's United Front Department) visited South Korea as part of a delegation ahead of the PyeongChang Olympics closing ceremony. Rep. Yoon, who was the National Situation Room Director at the time, reportedly met with Advisor Kim and asked about the Cheonan sinking. (책에 따르면, 2018년 김 고문(당시 노동당 통일전선부장)은 평창올림픽 폐회식을 앞두고 사절단으로 한국을 방문했다. 당시 국정상황실장이었던 윤 의원은 김 고문을 만나 천안함 폭침에 대해 물었다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Kim reportedly said, "At the time of the incident, I was in the provinces and came to Pyongyang the day after the Cheonan accident," and "We did not do it," the book relays. Advisor Kim also reportedly stated, "We clearly expressed regret to the South as fellow countrymen," and "We proposed a joint investigation, but former President Lee Myung-bak rejected it. Let's investigate jointly even now." (그러자 김 고문은 “사건 당시 (나는) 지방에 있었고, 천안함 사고가 일어난 다음 날 평양으로 왔다”며 “우리는 (천안함 폭침을) 하지 않았다”고 말했다고 책은 전했다. 김 고문은 “우리는 (사고에 대해) 동족으로서 남측에 유감 표명을 분명히 했다”, “우리는 공동 조사를 제안했으나 이명박 전 대통령이 거부했다. 지금이라도 공동으로 조사하자” 등 발언도 했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the book, Rep. Yoon said, "I was at a loss," and "He himself was strongly denying it, and it was a situation where we couldn't forcibly investigate someone who came as a congratulatory delegate for a national event." (윤 의원은 책에서 “난감했다”며 “본인은 강력하게 아니라고 하는데, 국가적 행사에 축하 사절단으로 온 사람을 강제로 조사할 수도 없는 상황이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advisor Kim led the Reconnaissance General Bureau, North Korea's agency in charge of operations against the South, from February 2009 to early 2016. The South Korean military and intelligence authorities concluded that the Cheonan sinking, which occurred in March 2010, was the work of the Reconnaissance General Bureau and have since pointed to Advisor Kim as being behind the incident. North Korean authorities have maintained to this day that "the Cheonan incident is a massive fabricated plot orchestrated by the conservative regime." They have never apologized. (김 고문은 2009년 2월부터 2016년 초까지 북한의 대남 공작 총괄 기구인 정찰총국을 이끌었다. 우리 군·정보 당국은 2010년 3월 발생한 천안함 폭침을 정찰총국의 소행으로 결론 내린 뒤 김 고문을 사건 배후로 지목해 왔다. 북한 당국은 현재까지 “천안함 사건은 보수 정권이 조작한 특대형 모략극”이라고 주장해 왔다. 사과한 적도 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"It's Regrettable That President Lee Did Not Consult Former President Moon Before the South Korea-U.S. Summit"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“李 대통령, 한미 회담 전 文 전 대통령 안 찾은 것은 아쉬워”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the book, Rep. Yoon also offered 'harsh criticism' regarding the foreign policy decision-making process of the Lee Jae-myung administration. (윤 의원은 책에서 이재명 정부의 외교 정책 결정 과정에 대한 ‘쓴소리’도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "One regret is, ahead of the first South Korea-U.S. summit last August, why didn't President Lee Jae-myung seek out former President Moon Jae-in?" adding, "Who is the South Korean leader who had the most conversations with President Trump and knows President Trump best? It is precisely former President Moon." (그는 “한 가지 아쉬운 것은, 지난 8월 첫 번째 한·미 정상회담을 앞두고 이재명 대통령이 왜 문재인 전 대통령을 찾지 않았을까 하는 부분”이라며 “트럼프 대통령과 가장 많은 대화를 나누고, 트럼프 대통령을 가장 잘 아는 대한민국 지도자는 누구인가. 바로 문 전 대통령”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "He should have met him to seek advice, or if he was really busy, he should have sought consultation over the phone, but he did not do so." He further stated, "(The Lee Jae-myung administration) also needs to actively utilize the foreign affairs and security capabilities of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration." (그러면서 “(문 전 대통령을) 만나서 조언을 구하거나, 정 바쁘다면 전화상으로 자문을 구할 법도 한데 그러지 않았다”고 했다. 이어 “(이재명 정부가) 윤석열 정부의 외교 안보 역량도 적극적으로 활용할 필요가 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon then mentioned the case where former President Moon, early in his term, personally met with then-Foreign Minister Yun Byung-se, who was appointed by his predecessor former President Park Geun-hye, and asked in detail about the South Korea-Japan comfort women agreement. Rep. Yoon said, "In diplomacy, no country can flip over agreements made by a previous government like turning over one's hand." (윤 의원은 그러면서 문 전 대통령이 집권 초기 전임인 박근혜 전 대통령이 임명한 윤병세 당시 외교부 장관을 직접 만나 한·일 위안부 합의에 대해 세세한 부분까지 물어봤던 사례를 언급했다. 윤 의원은 “외교에 있어서는 어느 국가라도 이전 정부가 맺은 합의를 손바닥 뒤집듯이 바꿀 수는 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Kim Jong-un Joked After Hearing 'Like Being Shot' Song, Saying "It Would Be Serious If N. Korean Youth Followed Along"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇김정은, ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ 노래 듣고 “北 젊은이들 따라 하면 심각” 농담도&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon also relayed an anecdote from the 'Spring Comes' performance held in Pyongyang in April 2018 by a South Korean art troupe. At the time, singer Baek Ji-young, a member of the troupe, sang songs like 'Like Being Shot' and 'Don't Forget', and the girl group Red Velvet performed stages for songs like 'Red Flavor' and 'Bad Boy'. (윤 의원은 2018년 4월 대한민국 측 예술단이 평양에서 연 ‘봄이 온다’ 공연의 후일담도 전했다. 당시 예술단 일원이었던 가수 백지영씨는 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ ‘잊지 말아요’ 등 노래를 불렀고, 걸그룹 레드벨벳은 ‘빨간맛’ ‘배드 보이’ 등 무대를 선보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon, who reportedly strongly recommended Ms. Baek and Red Velvet for the art troupe at the time, wrote in the book, "I wanted to properly show K-pop, which is hugely popular worldwide, to the citizens of Pyongyang," but "However, the only idol group I knew at the time was Red Velvet." He added, "Frankly, I also considered the fact that the team name contained 'Red'." (당시 백씨와 레드벨벳을 예술단으로 강력하게 추천했다는 윤 의원은 책에서 “세계적으로 큰 인기를 누리고 있는 K팝을 평양 시민에게 제대로 보여주고 싶었다”며 “그런데 당시 내가 알고 있던 아이돌 그룹이 레드벨벳뿐이었다”고 했다. 또 “솔직히 팀 이름에 ‘Red’가 들어가 있는 것도 참작했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Ms. Baek, he said, "She is also someone who sings exceptionally well, and I wondered what Pyongyang citizens would think if they heard her song 'Like Being Shot'. I thought it would be very interesting." (백씨에 대해선 “노래를 워낙 잘하시는 분이기도 하고, 그가 부른 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’을 평양 시민들이 들어보면 어떨까 생각했다. 무척 재미날 것 같았다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, after hearing performances including Baek Ji-young's 'Like Being Shot', Chairman Kim Jong-un reportedly joked, "It would be a serious situation if North Korean young people started singing along," Rep. Yoon wrote in the book. (실제 김정은 위원장은 백지영씨의 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ 등 공연을 듣고, “북측 젊은이들이 따라 부르면 심각한 상황이 오겠다”는 농담을 하기도 했다고 윤 의원은 책에 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/E67VUSKSCRBEHJUDDO2NTBUSS4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7AVNLUXPD5JPLGREIJ4O6FQCEE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:08:49 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>