<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:48:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>President Lee's Approval Rating at 59%... Democratic Party 40%, People Power Party 20% [NBS] (李대통령 지지율 59%…민주 40%·국힘 20%[NBS])</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/6IKM2DHHG5BGVEJULEADZIXJTE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee's Approval Rating at 59%... Democratic Party 40%, People Power Party 20% [NBS] (李대통령 지지율 59%…민주 40%·국힘 20%[NBS])&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VTXIUYXJ5FG3DB7MT3UMF7GXJY.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
A poll result released on the 22nd showed that 59% positively evaluated President Lee Jae-myung's state administration. ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the National Barometer Survey (NBS) conducted by Embrain Public, Kstat Research, Korea Research, and Hankook Research from the 19th to the 21st on 1,001 adults aged 18 and over and released today, respondents who positively evaluated President Lee's state administration were recorded at 59%, down 2 percentage points (p) from the previous survey two weeks prior. Negative evaluations were at 31%, up 2%p from the last survey. (이재명 대통령의 국정운영을 긍정적으로 평가한 비율이 59%로 집계됐다는 여론조사 결과가 22일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Positive evaluations of President Lee's state administration were higher than negative evaluations in all regions. By age group, positive evaluations recorded a majority in all age groups except those in their 20s and younger. However, among those in their 20s and younger, the negative evaluation rate (45%) exceeded the positive evaluation rate (34%). (엠브레인퍼블릭·케이스탯리서치·코리아리서치·한국리서치가 지난 19∼21일 만 18세 이상 1001명을 대상으로 진행해 이날 공개한 전국지표조사(NBS)에서 이 대통령의 국정운영을 긍정 평가한 응답자는 직전 조사인 2주 전보다 2%포인트(p) 내린 59%로 집계됐다. 부정 평가 응답은 31%로, 지난 조사보다 2%p 상승했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Party support rates were the Democratic Party of Korea at 40% and the People Power Party at 20%. Compared to the last survey, the Democratic Party rose by 1%p, and the People Power Party fell by 3%p. The Cho Kuk Innovation Party and the Reform Party each recorded 3%. (이 대통령 국정운영에 대한 긍정 평가는 모든 지역에서 부정 평가보다 높았다. 연령별로는 20대 이하를 제외한 전 연령대에서 긍정 평가가 과반을 기록했다. 다만 20대 이하에서는 부정 평가 비율(45%)이 긍정 평가 비율(34%)을 앞질렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the nature of the June local elections, more respondents answered 'should empower the ruling party for stability' (47%) than 'should empower the opposition party for checks and balances' (40%). (정당 지지도는 더불어민주당 40%, 국민의힘 20%로 나타났다. 지난 조사와 비교해 민주당은 1%p 올랐고, 국민의힘은 3%p 내렸다. 조국혁신당과 개혁신당은 각각 3%를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding administrative integration, a majority responded 'view it positively' (53%). Those who responded 'view it negatively' were only 30%. (6월 지방선거 성격에 대해서는 ‘안정을 위해 여당에 힘을 실어줘야 한다’(47%)는 응답이 ‘견제를 위해 야당에 힘을 실어줘야 한다’(40%)는 응답보다 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding suspicions of nomination bribes in the Democratic Party, the opinion that it is a 'structural problem with the nomination system' (57%) was nearly double the opinion that it is 'personal misconduct by some individuals' (30%). (행정통합에 대해서는 ‘긍정적으로 본다’(53%)는 응답이 과반이었다. ‘부정적으로 본다’는 응답은 30%에 그쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an item asking for opinions on the People Power Party's expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon, 'a good decision' was recorded at 43%, and 'a bad decision' at 38%. (민주당 공천헌금 의혹에 대해선 ‘공천 시스템 구조적 문제’(57%)라는 의견이 ‘일부 인사의 개인적 일탈’(30%)이라는 의견의 두 배에 달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the 'future direction for setting relations between our country and China', more respondents answered 'should strengthen relations' (50%) than 'should maintain principles and distance' (41%). (국민의힘의 한동훈 전 대표 제명에 대한 의견을 묻는 항목에선 ‘잘한 결정’이 43%, ‘잘못한 결정’은 38%로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding South Korea-Japan relations, 65% answered 'should continue improving relations', while 31% responded 'should be cautious about improving relations'. (‘향후 우리나라와 중국의 관계 설정 방향’에 대해선 ‘관계를 강화해야 한다’(50%)는 응답이 ‘원칙과 거리를 유지해야 한다’(41%)는 응답보다 많았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NBS survey was conducted via telephone interviews using mobile phone virtual numbers (100%), with a sampling error of ±3.1%p at a 95% confidence level. The response rate was 20.2%. For detailed information, please refer to the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission website. (한일 관계와 관련해선 ‘관계 개선을 이어가야 한다’고 답한 이가 65%였고, ‘관계 개선에 신중해야 한다’는 응답자는 31%로 집계됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/6IKM2DHHG5BGVEJULEADZIXJTE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VTXIUYXJ5FG3DB7MT3UMF7GXJY.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:03:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party's Yoo Yong-won: "Send a Presidential Special Envoy to Ukraine for the Repatriation of North Korean POWs" (국힘 유용원 “북한군 포로 송환 위해 우크라이나에 대통령 특사 보내야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/E5AA57AUDRDU3CFUM5FJ4HFQNM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party's Yoo Yong-won: "Send a Presidential Special Envoy to Ukraine for the Repatriation of North Korean POWs" (국힘 유용원 “북한군 포로 송환 위해 우크라이나에 대통령 특사 보내야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/XL7OVPSBOFCZ7FLN4IS4V3SSCQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party lawmaker Yoo Yong-won argued on the 22nd regarding North Korean soldiers detained in Ukraine that "a presidential special envoy should be sent to Ukraine for their repatriation to South Korea." It has been reported that the two North Korean soldiers detained in Ukraine wish to be repatriated to South Korea. (국민의힘 유용원 의원이 22일 우크라이나에 억류된 북한군 포로와 관련해 “한국 송환을 위해 우크라이나에 대통령 특사를 보내야 한다”고 주장했다. 우크라이나에 억류된 북한군 2명은 한국 송환을 희망하는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post that day, Rep. Yoo stated, "Based on Article 4 of the 'Treaty on Comprehensive Strategic Partnership' signed during the 2024 North Korea-Russia summit, the government must mobilize all national diplomatic capabilities for the domestic repatriation of North Korean POWs, Mr. Lee and Mr. Baek, who participated in the war and are now detained in Ukraine." (유 의원은 이날 페이스북에서 “2024년 북러 정상회담에서 체결된 ‘포괄적인 전략적 동반자 관계에 관한 조약’ 제4조에 의거해 참전했다가 우크라이나에 수용되어 있는 북한군 포로 이모씨와 백모씨의 국내 송환을 위해 정부가 국가적 외교 역량을 총동원해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoo said, "As the fourth anniversary of the Russia-Ukraine war approaches, voices urging the repatriation to South Korea of North Korean POWs detained in Ukraine are growing louder," adding, "With UN estimates putting the Russia-Ukraine war casualty count at over 1 million and the war becoming protracted, the issue of North Korean soldiers' participation and the subsequent handling of POWs is emerging as a significant human rights and security concern." (유 의원은 “러시아-우크라이나 전쟁 개전 4주년을 앞둔 가운데, 우크라이나에 억류된 북한군 포로들의 대한민국 송환을 촉구하는 목소리가 커지고 있다”며 “유엔(UN) 추산치 기준 러시아-우크라이나전 사상자 수가 100만명을 넘어서서 전쟁이 장기화되는 상황에서, 북한군의 참전과 그에 따른 포로 처리 문제가 중대한 인권 및 안보 현안으로 부상하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoo stated, "According to international law, including the Geneva Convention III, and the principles of 'Non-refoulement' and 'Voluntary Repatriation,' these individuals must not be sent back to North Korea, where it is clear they would be forcibly taken to their deaths against their will." (유 의원은 “제네바 제3협약 등 국제법상 ‘강제 송환 금지의 원칙(Principle of Non-refoulement)’과 ‘자발적 송환의 원칙’에 따라, 본인의 의사에 반하여 사지로 끌려갈 것이 명백한 북한으로 이들을 돌려보내서는 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "The government should not just stand by any longer. To coincide with the fourth anniversary of the Russia-Ukraine war next month, it should dispatch a 'cross-party special envoy, including ruling and opposition party lawmakers,' to Ukraine on the ground," and argued that "a decisive move is needed to finalize the repatriation procedures on humanitarian grounds through direct negotiations with local authorities." (그러면서 “정부는 더 이상 지켜만 볼 것이 아니라, 다음 달 러시아-우크라이나 전쟁 개전 4주년에 맞추어 우크라이나 현지로 ‘여야 의원을 포함한 초당적인 특사’를 파견해야 한다”며 “현지 당국과의 직접 협상을 통해 인도적 차원의 송환 절차를 마무리 짓는 결단이 필요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoo also claimed, "A national strategy must be established for the massive-scale Ukraine reconstruction projects that will unfold after the war ends." Rep. Yoo plans to hold a policy seminar on March 3rd at the National Assembly Members' Office Building on the topic 'North Korean POWs in Ukraine: How Should Domestic Repatriation Be Handled?' (유 의원은 또 “종전 이후 전개될 막대한 규모의 우크라이나 재건 사업에 대한 국가적 전략 수립을 해야 한다”고 주장했다. 유 의원은 다음 달 3일 국회 의원회관에서 ‘우크라이나 북한군 포로, 국내 송환 어떻게 해야 하나’를 주제로 정책 세미나를 개최할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/E5AA57AUDRDU3CFUM5FJ4HFQNM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/XL7OVPSBOFCZ7FLN4IS4V3SSCQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 20:56:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Meets with Ruling Party's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee…"Agreement on Swiftly Promoting 3rd Commercial Act Revision" (李 대통령 만난 與 코스피 5000 특위…“3차 상법 개정 조속 추진에 공감”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/AUFZU4XP2ZEZ3PURQXRDIIV54Q/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee Meets with Ruling Party's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee…"Agreement on Swiftly Promoting 3rd Commercial Act Revision" (李 대통령 만난 與 코스피 5000 특위…“3차 상법 개정 조속 추진에 공감”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DLVIPGROOFJ4FPNF2NNWCG2O4U.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, when the KOSPI broke through the 5,000-point mark for the first time ever during trading hours, it was reported that President Lee Jae-myung expressed agreement on promoting the '3rd Commercial Act Revision,' an additional stock market revitalization measure that includes mandatory treasury stock cancellation. (코스피가 사상 최초로 장중 5000포인트를 돌파한 22일, 이재명 대통령이 자사주 의무 소각 등 내용을 포함한 추가 증시 활성화책인 ‘3차 상법 개정’을 추진하는 데 공감을 표시한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Oh Ki-hyung, chairman of the Democratic Party of Korea's KOSPI 5000 Special Committee, stated this during a media briefing today, saying, "(Today) President Lee invited us to lunch, and the special committee members had a meal and shared opinions on several pending issues." (더불어민주당 코스피 5000 특별위원회 위원장인 오기형 의원은 이날 언론 브리핑에서 “(오늘) 이 대통령께서 오찬 초청을 해서 특위 위원들과 식사를 하고 몇 가지 현안에 대해 의견 공유를 했다”며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Oh said, "(Achieving KOSPI 5000) was President Lee's presidential election pledge, and achieving that pledge holds great significance," adding, "Especially, since his time as party leader, he has painstakingly established a capital market revitalization task force and promoted revisions to the Commercial Act, making this the result of consistent policy determination." (오 위원장은 “(코스피 5000 달성이) 이 대통령의 대선 공약이었고, 그 공약을 달성했다는 의미가 크다”며 “특히 (이 대통령의) 당대표 시절부터 공들여 자본시장 활성화 TF(태스크포스)를 만들었고, 그리고 상법 개정을 추진하는 등 일관된 정책 의지의 결과물”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Oh stated, "We should not be satisfied with the achievement of KOSPI 5000 and must now continuously pursue institutional reforms," and "We obtained (President Lee's) agreement on the need to swiftly proceed with the 3rd Commercial Act revision." (오 위원장은 “코스피 5000이라고 하는 성과에 만족하지 않고 이제 지속적으로 제도 개혁을 해야 된다”며 “제3차 상법 개정에 대해서는 조속히 하자는 데 (이 대통령의) 공감을 얻었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "We shared the view that (the 3rd Commercial Act revision) is being delayed due to internal parliamentary circumstances, but it should not be postponed any further," and "The sooner, the better." (그러면서 “(3차 상법 개정이) 국회 내부의 이제 우선 사정 때문에 미뤄지고 있는데 더 이상 미루면 안 된다라는 정도의 공감을 가졌다”며 “빠르면 빠를수록 좋다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, he said agreement was reached on promoting the 'Stock Price Suppression Prevention Act (Inheritance and Gift Tax Act revision bill)' aimed at preventing the phenomenon where companies deliberately lower their stock prices to reduce inheritance tax burdens, and on strictly addressing the 'duplicate listing' issue where companies that have undergone spin-offs list, causing harm to existing shareholders. (이 밖에 기업들이 상속세 부담을 줄이기 위해 일부러 주가를 낮추는 현상을 방지하는 내용의 ‘주가 누르기 방지법(상속·증여세법 개정안)’을 추진하고, 물적 분할한 회사가 상장해 기존 주주가 피해를 보는 ‘중복 상장’ 문제도 엄격하게 보는 데 대한 공감이 이뤄졌다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Oh also responded to a question implying 'whether there are plans to change the name of the KOSPI 5000 Special Committee in the future' by saying, "We will deliberate and inform you." (오 위원장은 또 ‘코스피 5000 특위의 명칭을 향후 변경할 계획은 없냐’는 취지의 질문에 “숙의해서 말씀드리겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/AUFZU4XP2ZEZ3PURQXRDIIV54Q/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DLVIPGROOFJ4FPNF2NNWCG2O4U.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 21:13:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blue House: "Received advance notice of merger proposal...Merger is Lee Jae-myung's consistent position" (靑 “합당 제안, 사전 연락 받았다...합당은 이재명 지론”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/E4BJ23CWARHHJCVRZFT7MYRWL4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Blue House: "Received advance notice of merger proposal...Merger is Lee Jae-myung's consistent position" (靑 “합당 제안, 사전 연락 받았다...합당은 이재명 지론”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6JEZAXTKX5OUDID23NE6QSM36A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Ik-pyo, the Blue House Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, stated on the 22nd regarding Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae's proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, "We received advance notice from Leader Chung." This indicates that the Blue House was also aware of and shared Leader Chung's merger proposal plan in advance. (홍익표 청와대 정무수석은 22일 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 것과 관련해 “사전에 정 대표에게서 연락 받았다”고 밝혔다. 정 대표의 합당 제안 계획을 청와대도 사전에 공유해 알고 있었다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, Senior Secretary Hong clarified that Leader Chung's proposal was not "conducted in consultation with the Blue House." The implication is that Leader Chung's side made the decision and then shared it with the Blue House. (홍 수석은 다만 정 대표의 제안이 청와대와 “협의하에 진행한 건 아니”라고 했다. 정 대표 측에서 결정하고 청와대와 공유했다는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Senior Secretary Hong added, "The integration of the two parties is President Lee Jae-myung's consistent position," and said, "We will watch as the discussions between the two parties proceed well." (홍 수석은 그러면서도 “양당의 통합은 이재명 대통령의 평소 지론”이라며 “양당 간 논의가 잘 진행되기를 지켜보겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, Kang Yu-jung, the Blue House spokesperson, said in the morning, "There was no particular prior discussion (with the Democratic Party regarding the merger proposal)." During the morning briefing, when asked about the matter, Spokesperson Kang said, "Since it is a matter being discussed in the National Assembly, we are watching those discussions." A Blue House official stated, "We did receive advance notice, but there were no related discussions," adding, "There is no change in position between the explanations of Spokesperson Kang and Senior Secretary Hong." (앞서 강유정 청와대 대변인은 이날 오전 “(합당 제안과 관련해 민주당과) 사전에 특별히 논의된 것은 없다”고 했다. 강 대변인은 이날 오전 브리핑에서 관련 질문에 “국회에서 논의되는 일이기 때문에 그 논의를 지켜보고 있다”며 이같이 말했다. 청와대 관계자는 “사전에 연락은 받았지만, 관련 논의가 있었던 것은 아니다”라며 “강 대변인과 홍 수석의 설명 사이에 입장이 바뀐 것은 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, inside and outside political circles, analysis emerged from the moment Leader Chung announced the merger proposal this morning that "it was likely discussed and proceeded with the Blue House in advance." The reason is that, with the June local elections approaching, it is unlikely that a party-level decision on inter-party integration would be made without discussion with the Blue House. (하지만 정치권 안팎에서는, 정 대표의 이날 오전 합당 제안 발표 때부터 “청와대와 사전에 협의하고 진행했을 것”이라는 분석이 나왔다. 오는 6월 지방선거를 앞두고 정당 간 통합을 청와대와 논의 없이 당 차원에서 결정할 리가 없다는 이유 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/E4BJ23CWARHHJCVRZFT7MYRWL4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6JEZAXTKX5OUDID23NE6QSM36A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 20:34:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "If it only increases pain and confusion, that is not reform." (李대통령 “고통과 혼란만 가중시키면, 그건 개혁 아니다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/CHFHRX6YVBDDDFO5ADVABBX2RU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "If it only increases pain and confusion, that is not reform." (李대통령 “고통과 혼란만 가중시키면, 그건 개혁 아니다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CNFWDAECYFJFRNFZ7CIQ7ZXNN4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 22nd, "If any reform measure, instead of improving the lives of the people, only increases pain and confusion while clinging to justification and grand causes, it cannot be called reform." (이재명 대통령은 22일 “어떤 개혁 조치가 국민의 삶을 개선하기는커녕 오히려 명분과 대의에 매달려서 고통과 혼란만 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a meeting of senior secretaries at the Blue House that day, President Lee said, "The reason we operate state affairs on behalf of the sovereign people is, first and foremost, solely to tangibly improve the lives and livelihoods of the people." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 수석보좌관 회의를 주재하면서 “우리가 주권자를 대리해서 국정을 운영하는 것은 첫째도 둘째도 오로지 국민의 삶, 민생을 실질적으로 개선하기 위한 것”이라며 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee added, "The same goes for so-called reform tasks," and stated, "Based on firm will and clear direction, we must carefully judge from a practical and effective perspective which plan helps protect the people's human rights and guarantee their substantive rights, and meticulously manage it." (이 대통령은 “소위 말하는 개혁 과제도 마찬가지”라며 “확고한 의지와 명확한 방향성을 바탕으로 어느 방안이 국민의 인권 보호와 실질적 권리 보장에 도움이 되는지를 실용적인 관점에서, 또 실효적인 관점에서 신중하게 판단하고 꼼꼼하게 챙겨봐야 되겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's mention that day that 'reform that increases pain and confusion is unacceptable' appears to be related to the controversial issue within the ruling party regarding 'the prosecution retaining supplementary investigation rights.' A Blue House official also said, "While no specific issue was mentioned, it can be interpreted as a remark related to prosecution reform." (이 대통령의 이날 ‘고통과 혼란을 가중시키는 개혁은 안 된다’는 언급은, 최근 여권 내에서 논란이 되고 있는 ‘검찰의 보완 수사권 보유’ 문제에 관한 것으로 보인다. 청와대 관계자도 “특정 사안을 언급하지 않았지만, 검찰 개혁 관련 언급으로 해석할 수 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the government recently announced a bill to establish a new Public Prosecution Service to handle prosecution duties instead of the Prosecution Service, debates within the ruling party have continued over whether prosecutors should retain supplementary investigation rights. The bill does not clearly state whether prosecutors in the Public Prosecution Service will have supplementary investigation rights, and hardliners and strong supporters within the Democratic Party of Korea have protested, saying, "The government's proposal essentially leaves supplementary investigation rights with prosecutors." The hardliners hold the position that since the Prosecution Service is being abolished and prosecutors' investigation rights are disappearing along with it, prosecutors should also not be granted supplementary investigation rights over police investigations. (최근 정부가 검찰청을 대신해 기소 업무를 하게 될 공소청 신설 법안을 발표한 뒤, 여권 내부는 검사의 보완 수사권 보유 여부로 논쟁이 계속됐다. 법안에 공소청 검사가 보완 수사권을 갖는지 여부는 명확히 나오지 않는데, 더불어민주당 강경파와 강성 지지층은 “정부안은 사실상 검사에게 보완 수사권을 남겨두겠다는 것”이라며 반발해 왔다. 강경파는 검찰청이 폐지되면서 검사의 수사권도 함께 사라지는 만큼, 경찰 수사에 대한 검사의 보완 수사권도 부여해선 안 된다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, at a New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee said, "I think it's right not to conduct supplementary investigations," but added, "However, there are exceptionally necessary cases." (하지만 이 대통령은 지난 21일 신년 기자회견에서 “저는 보완 수사를 안 하는 게 맞다고 생각한다”면서도 “그러나 예외적으로 필요한 경우가 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee explained, "When a case is transferred (from police to prosecution) with only two days left before the statute of limitations expires, if supplementary investigations are completely prohibited even for simple verification, sending it back to the police and having it returned would take up the remaining two days." He continued, "After blocking the possibility of abuse and creating safeguards, allowing such things is actually reform that efficiently handles state affairs." (이 대통령은 “공소시효가 이틀밖에 안 남았는데 (경찰에서 검찰로 사건이) 송치가 됐을 때, 간단히 확인할 게 있어도 보완 수사가 전면 금지돼 있으면 (사건을) 다시 경찰로 보내고 돌아오는 데 이틀이 끝나 버린다”며 “남용의 가능성을 봉쇄하고 안전장치를 만든 다음에 그런 것 정도는 허용해 주는 게 실제로 국가 업무를 효율적으로 처리하는 개혁”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee then addressed the hardliners, saying, "They should understand; hasn't the prosecution become a witch because it has committed so many misdeeds? Everything about it seems hateful." During that day's press conference, President Lee criticized the prosecution for a long time, accusing it of covering up cases or fabricating non-existent cases. President Lee also said, "(I) have been victimized by the prosecution the most. I've been indicted about 20 times," and added, "The Daejang-dong case was also something prosecutors colluded in." (이 대통령은 그러면서도 강경파를 향해선 “이해해 줘야 한다, 검찰이 하도 저지른 업보가 많아서 마녀가 된 것 아니냐, 뭐든지 미운 것”이라고 했다. 이 대통령은 이날 회견에서 검찰이 사건을 덮거나 없는 사건을 조작해 만든다며 비판을 한참 동안 했다. 이 대통령은 “(내가) 검찰에 가장 많이 당했다. 기소된 것만 한 20건”이라며 “대장동도 검사들이 한패로 해 먹은 것”이라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party official said, "The President mentioned his own experiences and tried to appease them in an effort to resolve the backlash from hardliners within the party." (여권 관계자는 “대통령이 당내 강경파 반발을 수습하려고 본인의 경험담까지 언급하며 달래기에 나선 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/CHFHRX6YVBDDDFO5ADVABBX2RU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CNFWDAECYFJFRNFZ7CIQ7ZXNN4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 21:39:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] Jeong Cheong-rae Explains at General Meeting of Lawmakers: "Merger Proposal Coordinated with the Presidential Office" ([단독] 정청래, 의총서 “합당 제안, 청와대와 조율” 설명)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/A4HZGC5OQNA65KKHPFZPRC7T6I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] Jeong Cheong-rae Explains at General Meeting of Lawmakers: "Merger Proposal Coordinated with the Presidential Office" ([단독] 정청래, 의총서 “합당 제안, 청와대와 조율” 설명)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VHS5FAUDVJNIDJG7I6JOCA5MRA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae stated at the party's general meeting of lawmakers on the 22nd that the proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party was "coordinated with the Presidential Office." (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 22일 당 의원총회에서 조국혁신당에 합당을 제안한 것과 관련해 “청와대와 조율한 것”이라고 한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jeong held an emergency press conference this morning, stating, "We propose to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. Let's merge with us," and added, "Let's contest the upcoming June 3 local elections together." (정 대표는 이날 오전 긴급 기자회견을 열어 “조국혁신당에 제안한다. 우리와 합치자”며 “이번 6·3 지방선거를 같이 치르자”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, some within the Democratic Party voiced criticism, saying, "We oppose pushing for a merger without consulting the party members' will." (이에 대해 민주당 일각에선 “당원의 뜻을 묻지 않은 합당 추진에 반대한다”며 비판의 목소리가 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Leader Jeong reportedly explained to lawmakers at the general meeting, "The push for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party was coordinated between the party and the Presidential Office." (그러자 정 대표는 의원총회에서 의원들에게 “조국혁신당 합당 추진은 당·청이 조율해서 한 것”이라고 설명했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is known that some lawmakers also expressed opposition at the general meeting today, stating in essence that "the push is too hasty." (일부 의원은 이날 의총에서도 “너무 급하게 추진하는 것”이라는 취지로 반대 의견을 낸 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there are lawmakers who welcome the merger. Lawmaker Shin Jung-hoon posted on his Facebook, "I welcome the merger proposal with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party," and added, "The party leader also does not intend to make a decision by bypassing the will of the party members. I respectfully request that he maintain balance and guide the process so that the voice of each and every party member can be sufficiently reflected." (반면 합당을 환영한다는 의견을 내는 의원들도 있다. 신정훈 의원은 자신의 페이스북에 “조국혁신당과의 합당 제안을 환영한다”며 “당대표께서도 당원 의사를 건너뛰고 결정하시려는 것은 아니다. 당원 한 분 한 분의 목소리가 충분히 반영될 수 있도록 중심을 잡고 이끌어주시기를 정중히 부탁드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/22/A4HZGC5OQNA65KKHPFZPRC7T6I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VHS5FAUDVJNIDJG7I6JOCA5MRA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 20:31:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NIS Launches Task Force to Investigate Truth of President Lee's Gadeokdo Assault Incident (국정원 , 李대통령 가덕도 피습 사건 진상규명 TF 가동)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/6XTI7CJXYZF2HCLIE4VROHWNPE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;NIS Launches Task Force to Investigate Truth of President Lee's Gadeokdo Assault Incident (국정원 , 李대통령 가덕도 피습 사건 진상규명 TF 가동)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GYYWENBTMVQTEMJXGUYWGY3CGM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Service (NIS) announced on the 22nd that it has launched and begun operating a follow-up measures task force (TF) to investigate the truth of the 'Gadeokdo Assault Incident' that occurred in 2024 when President Lee Jae-myung was the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea. (국가정보원은 22일 2024년 이재명 대통령이 더불어민주당 대표 시절 발생한 ‘가덕도 피습사건’에 대한 진상규명을 위한 후속조치 태스크포스(TF)를 출범하고 가동에 들어갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NIS stated in a press release that day that it has launched the 'Gadeokdo Terror Incident Designation Follow-up Measures TF', with NIS First Deputy Director Lee Dong-soo serving as the team leader. (국정원은 이날 보도자료를 통해 이동수 국정원 1차장을 팀장으로 하는 ‘가덕도 테러사건 지정 후속조치 TF’를 출범했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This action by the NIS follows the 'National Counterterrorism Committee's designation of the Gadeokdo assault incident, which occurred when President Lee was the Democratic Party leader, as terrorism under the Counter-Terrorism Act on the 20th. The NIS activated the TF that day and is proceeding with various measures, including designating 'persons posing a terror risk', within the authority and scope of duties granted by the Counter-Terrorism Act and other related laws. (국정원의 이번 조치는 ‘국가테러대책위원회’가 지난 20일 이 대통령이 더불어민주당 대표 시절 벌어진 가덕도 피습사건을 테러방지법상 테러로 지정한데 따른 것이다. 국정원은 이날 TF를 가동하고 테러방지법 등 관련 법령이 부여한 권한과 임무 범위내에서 ‘테러위험인물’ 지정 등 제반 조치를 진행하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NIS said, "Based on the circumstances of the perpetrator Mr. Kim's preparation and execution of the crime, we plan to designate him as a 'person posing a terror risk' under Article 2 of the Counter-Terrorism Act and meticulously reconfirm specific suspicions in accordance with Article 9 (Information Collection on Persons Posing a Terror Risk, etc.)." The NIS also stated its policy to support related information upon request from investigative agencies and back a swift investigation, as the National Investigation Headquarters of the police has launched a reinvestigation into the 'Gadeokdo Terror Incident'. (국정원은 “가해자인 김모씨의 범행 준비ㆍ실행 정황을 토대로 테러방지법 제2조상 ‘테러위험인물’로 지정하고 제9조(테러위험인물에 대한 정보 수집 등)에 의거해 구체적 혐의를 면밀 재확인할 계획”이라고 했다. 국정원은 또 경찰 국가수사본부가 ‘가덕도 테러사건’ 재수사에 나선 만큼 수사기관 요청시 관련 정보를 지원, 신속한 수사를 뒷받침한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NIS also plans to participate in the 'Counter-Terrorism Work Innovation TF' under the Prime Minister's Office, which is set to launch on the 26th. Through this, it intends to make multi-faceted efforts, such as improving response systems for suspected terror incidents, including the terror crisis management standard manual, and devising measures for swift response and strengthened cooperation among related agencies in case of similar incidents in the future. (국정원은 오는 26일 발족하는 총리실 산하 대테러센터 ‘대테러업무 혁신 TF’에도 참여할 예정이다. 이를 통해 테러위기관리 표준매뉴얼 등 테러의심사건 대응체계를 정비하고 향후 유사사건 발생시 신속 대응 및 유관기관간 협력강화 방안 강구 등 다각도의 노력을 기울여 나갈 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 20th, the government held the 22nd National Counterterrorism Committee, chaired by Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, and designated the assault incident at the new airport site on Busan's Gadeokdo Island, which occurred when President Lee was the Democratic Party leader, as 'the first state-recognized terror incident'. This is the first time a terror incident has been designated since the Counter-Terrorism Act was enacted in 2016. (정부는 앞서 지난 20일 김민석 국무총리 주재로 제22차 국가테러대책위원회를 열고 이 대통령이 민주당 대표이던 시절 벌어진 부산 가덕도 신공항 피습 사건을 ‘국가 공인 1호 테러’로 지정했다. 2016년 테러방지법이 제정된 이후 테러 사건이 지정된 것은 이 대통령 사례가 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/6XTI7CJXYZF2HCLIE4VROHWNPE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GYYWENBTMVQTEMJXGUYWGY3CGM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:04:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] The Yeongjongdo land from which Lee Hye-hoon gained '2 billion KRW profit' was sold by her husband's maternal uncle ([단독] ’20억 차익' 이혜훈 영종도 땅, 매도인은 남편의 외삼촌)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/PQVZBQAZVVEI5IODXOTY464FUE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] The Yeongjongdo land from which Lee Hye-hoon gained '2 billion KRW profit' was sold by her husband's maternal uncle ([단독] ’20억 차익' 이혜훈 영종도 땅, 매도인은 남편의 외삼촌)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3NV5DAHCQ5BFNJI4ZXVBCQW5MA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed on the 22nd that the person who sold the Yeongjongdo, Incheon land, which Planning and Budget Minister nominee Lee Hye-hoon and her spouse purchased a year before the opening of Incheon International Airport, gaining a market profit in the range of 2 billion KRW, is the nominee's husband's maternal uncle. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 부부가 인천국제공항 개항 1년 전 인천 영종도의 토지를 매입해 20억원대의 시세 차익을 얻은 것과 관련, 해당 영종도 토지를 판 사람이 이 후보자 남편의 외삼촌인 것으로 22일 밝혀졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominee Lee, an economist by background, is the eldest daughter-in-law of the late former Interior Minister Kim Tae-ho, who served as a four-term lawmaker in Ulsan from the 1980s to the 2000s. The family business of 'politics' was inherited by the daughter-in-law, nominee Lee, not by her son, Professor Kim Young-se of Yonsei University. The wife of former Minister Kim and mother-in-law of nominee Lee bequeathed assets worth tens of billions of won to nominee Lee's couple and their three sons. Furthermore, it has been revealed that the maternal uncle of nominee Lee's husband was also involved in the wealth accumulation process of nominee Lee's family. (경제학자 출신인 이 후보자는 1980~2000년대 울산에서 4선(選) 의원을 지낸 고(故) 김태호 전 내무부 장관의 맏며느리다. 아들인 김영세 연세대 교수가 아닌 며느리인 이 후보자가 가업(家業)인 ‘정치’를 물려받았다. 김 전 장관의 아내이자 이 후보자의 시어머니는 이 후보자 부부와 세 아들들에게 수십억 원의 자산을 물려줬다. 이에 더해 이 후보자 일가의 재산 형성 과정에 이 후보자 남편의 외삼촌까지 관여한 사실이 드러난 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to materials submitted by the Ministry of Planning and Budget to People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, the vice-chair of the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, nominee Lee stated regarding the purchase of the Yeongjongdo land, "We do not possess the contract related to the 2000 Yeongjongdo land purchase," but also revealed that "the seller of the said land is the maternal uncle of my spouse (Professor Kim Young-se) who resides overseas." (기획예산처가 이날 국회 재정경제기획위원회 국민의힘 간사인 박수영 의원에게 제출한 자료에 따르면, 이 후보자는 영종도 토지 매입에 대해 “2000년 영종도 토지 매입 관련 계약서를 보관하고 있지 않는다”면서도 “해당 토지의 매도자는 해외에 거주하는 배우자(김영세 교수)의 외삼촌”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nominee Lee's husband, Professor Kim, purchased 6,612㎡ (approx. 2,000 pyeong) of land (miscellaneous land) in Jungsan-dong, Yeongjongdo, Incheon on January 18, 2000. The purchase price at the time was 1.388 billion KRW based on the officially announced land price. The timing of Professor Kim's purchase of the Yeongjongdo land was when the opening of Incheon Airport was approaching, just one year away. This land is located 16km from Incheon Airport. In December 2006, the Korea Land &amp; Housing Corporation and Incheon Urban Development Corporation expropriated the Yeongjongdo land purchased by Professor Kim. According to nominee Lee's public official asset disclosure records, the expropriation price was 3.921 billion KRW. This represents a market profit of over 2 billion KRW in about six years. (이 후보자 남편인 김 교수는 2000년 1월 18일 인천 영종도 중산동 토지(잡종지) 6612㎡(약 2000평)를 매입했다. 매입 당시 가격은 공시지가 기준 13억 8800만원이었다. 김 교수가 영종도 땅을 사들인 시점은 인천공항 개항이 1년 앞으로 다가온 시기였다. 이 땅은 인천공항에서 16㎞ 떨어진 곳이다. 2006년 12월 한국토지공사·인천도시개발공사는 김 교수가 사들인 영종도 토지를 수용했다. 이 후보자의 공직자 재산 신고 기록에 따르면 수용가는 39억2100만원으로 나타났다. 약 6년 만에 20억원 이상의 시세 차익을 본 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until now, it was only known that the seller of this land to Professor Kim was a maternal aunt (born 1936) surnamed Lee residing in Canada. However, nominee Lee, in her parliamentary response materials, has for the first time disclosed that this person is Professor Kim's maternal uncle. (그동안 김 교수에게 이 땅을 판 매도자는 캐나다에 거주 중이라던 이모(1936년생)씨라는 사실만 알려져 있었다. 그런데 이 후보자가 국회 답변 자료에서 이씨가 김 교수의 외삼촌이란 사실을 처음 공개한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, regarding the reason why Professor Kim had no choice but to purchase the Yeongjongdo land from his maternal uncle, nominee Lee stated, "(Maternal uncle Lee) intended to sell the land, but due to the IMF crisis, he could not find a buyer, and as the public auction date approached, he urgently sold it to his nephew (Professor Kim)," adding, "(At the time, maternal uncle Lee) was in a difficult situation regarding property management related to the land, including tax delinquency and public auction notices." (다만, 이 후보자는 김 교수가 자신의 외삼촌으로부터 영종도 토지를 매입할 수밖에 없었던 이유에 대해 “(외삼촌 이씨가) 해당 토지를 매도하려 했으나, IMF 위기로 매수자를 찾을 수가 없어 공매일이 도래하자 조카(김 교수)에게 급하게 매도한 것”이라며 “(당시 외삼촌 이씨는) 해당 토지와 관련해 세금 체납, 공매 통지 등 재산 관리가 곤란한 상황이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, nominee Lee's family assets amount to 17.56958 billion KRW, most of which were formed through gifts from her mother-in-law or real estate investments. In 1992, when she was twenty-eight years old and studying in the United States, nominee Lee purchased five commercial buildings in Eungbong-dong, Seongdong-gu, Seoul in her and her husband's names, realizing a market profit of about 1 billion KRW. The funds for purchasing the commercial buildings were prepared with cash gifted from her mother-in-law. The mother-in-law gifted 2,400 shares (approx. 3.1 billion KRW) of KSM, a semiconductor equipment company, to nominee Lee's three sons in 2016 and 2021, and in May of last year, also gifted a house in a redevelopment planned area in Jeonnong-dong, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul to nominee Lee's second son. KSM is a 'family company' operated by the brother of nominee Lee's father-in-law, former Minister Kim Tae-ho. (한편 이 후보자 가족 재산은 175억6958만원인데, 대부분 시어머니로부터 증여를 받거나 부동산 투자를 통해 형성했다. 이 후보자는 스물여덟 살이던 1992년 미국 유학 시절에 본인과 남편 명의로 서울 성동구 응봉동 상가 5채를 사들여, 10억여 원의 시세 차익을 실현했다. 상가 매입 자금은 시어머니로부터 현금을 증여받아 마련한 것이다. 시어머니는 2016년과 2021년 이 후보자의 세 아들에게 반도체 장비 회사인 KSM의 주식 2400주(31억여 원)를 증여했고, 작년 5월에는 서울 동대문구 전농동 재개발 예정지 주택도 이 후보자의 차남에게 증여했다. KSM은 이 후보자 시아버지인 김태호 전 장관의 동생이 운영 중인 ‘가족 회사’다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Park Soo-young said, "It seems nominee Lee utilized not only the 'mother-in-law chance' but also the 'husband's family chance' when accumulating wealth in the past," adding, "We will thoroughly examine at tomorrow's (23rd) National Assembly confirmation hearing whether there were any illegal aspects such as tax evasion in the wealth formation process." (박수영 의원은 “이 후보자가 과거 재산을 불릴 때 ‘시어머니 찬스’에 이어 ‘시댁 찬스’까지 활용한 사실이 밝혀진 셈”이라며 “재산 형성 과정에서 세금 회피 등 위법 소지는 없었는지 내일(23일) 열리는 국회 인사청문회에서 철저히 따질 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/22/PQVZBQAZVVEI5IODXOTY464FUE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3NV5DAHCQ5BFNJI4ZXVBCQW5MA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 22:41:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Shows Conservative Consolidation Effect, But... "Raising People Power Party's Approval Rating is the Challenge" (장동혁 단식, 보수 결집 효과 봤지만… “국힘 지지율 상승이 과제”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/WQ5MB6M3ZNDBZMBLN4U2QXIIHA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z3MPVDHKMVHETKVRNUZPFK2B2I.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party (PPP), who had been on a hunger strike demanding the introduction of a special prosecution investigation (into alleged bribery related to the Unification Church and Democratic Party nominations), ended his fast on the 22nd. It was the 8th day since he began his hunger strike in the Central Hall of the National Assembly's main building on the 15th. While Representative Jang demonstrated a show of conservative consolidation through his fast, the recovery of the party's low approval rating ahead of the local elections is cited as a challenge. (쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검) 도입을 요구하며 단식을 해온 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 22일 단식을 중단했다. 지난 15일 국회 본청 중앙홀에서 단식을 시작한 지 8일째다. 장 대표는 단식을 통해 보수가 결집하는 모양새를 보여줬지만 지방선거를 앞두고 낮은 당 지지율 회복이 과제로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang was transported by ambulance to a hospital in Gwanak-gu, Seoul, near his residence, at noon that day. Before getting into the ambulance, Representative Jang said, "To fight a longer and bigger fight, I am ending my fast today," adding, "The people's lamentation towards the corrupt Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party of Korea's tyranny will flare up like a wildfire starting today." It is said that since taking office as party leader in August last year, Representative Jang's weight has decreased by nearly 10 kg due to factors like lack of sleep. As the fast continued in this condition, his health is known to have deteriorated rapidly. (장 대표는 이날 정오 구급차를 타고 자택 인근인 서울 관악구의 한 병원으로 이송됐다. 장 대표는 구급차에 오르기 전 “더 길고 더 큰 싸움을 위해서 오늘 단식을 중단한다”며 “부패한 이재명 정권과 더불어민주당의 폭정을 향한 국민의 탄식은 오늘부터 들불처럼 타오를 것”이라고 했다. 장 대표는 작년 8월 당대표 취임 이후 수면 부족 등으로 몸무게가 10㎏ 가까이 줄어들었다고 한다. 이런 상태에서 단식이 길어지자 건강 상태가 급격히 나빠진 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inside and outside the party, it is assessed that while Representative Jang did not succeed in pushing through the special prosecution investigation, he achieved results in consolidating the broader conservative camp. On this day, former President Park Geun-hye visited the hunger strike site to console Representative Jang. It is known to be former President Park's first visit to the National Assembly's main building in 10 years, since 2016. Former President Park said, "Thoughts may differ slightly, but as a politician, fighting a life-or-death struggle for what one believes is right—on this point, the public will recognize the representative's sincerity." (당 안팎에선 장 대표가 쌍특검을 관철하진 못했지만, 범보수 결집 성과를 거뒀다고 평가했다. 이날은 박근혜 전 대통령이 단식장을 찾아 장 대표를 위문했다. 박 전 대통령이 국회 본청을 찾은 건 지난 2016년 이후 10년 만으로 알려졌다.&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;박 전 대통령은 “생각이 조금씩 다를 순 있겠지만 정치인으로서 옳다고 생각한 것에 대해서 목숨을 건 투쟁을 한 것, 이 점에 대해서 국민께서는 대표님의 진정성을 인정할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min, from the old pro-Yoon faction that had taken a confrontational stance, and former Minister of Employment and Labor Kim Moo-sung, who competed in the previous party leadership election, visited the protest site in succession. Additionally, 11 PPP-affiliated provincial and metropolitan city governors, including Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon who had demanded a change in Representative Jang's course, also visited. Lawmakers who have advocated for severing ties with former President Yoon Seok-youl also supported the hunger strike. Following Representative Jang's decision to end his fast, an emergency general meeting of PPP lawmakers reportedly saw consecutive opinions stating, "Ahead of the local elections, we must show the conservative camp coming together." (옛 친윤계가 각을 세웠던 유승민 전 의원, 지난 당대표 선거에서 경쟁했던 김문수 전 고용노동부 장관이 차례로 농성장을 찾았고, 장 대표의 노선 전환을 요구해온 오세훈 서울시장 등 국민의힘 소속 시도지사 11명도 방문했다. 윤석열 전 대통령과의 절연을 주장해온 의원들도 단식을 지지했다. 장 대표 단식 중단 이후 열린 국민의힘 긴급 의원총회에서는 “지방선거를 앞두고 보수 진영이 결집하는 모습을 보여야 한다”는 의견이 잇따랐다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, also cut his overseas business trip short by two days to visit Representative Jang's protest site and expressed his intent to cooperate on the special prosecution investigation. While no officials from the Blue House or the Democratic Party visited the hunger strike site, Hong Ik-pyo, the Blue House Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, is planning to visit Representative Jang in the hospital soon. Having ended his fast, Representative Jang plans to announce a special advisory team composed of experts in various fields and hold a policy briefing for the local elections. However, as the Democratic Party is launching an offensive labeling the PPP as an 'unconstitutional party,' conflicts between the ruling and opposition parties are likely to continue. (이준석 개혁신당 대표도 외국 출장을 이틀 줄여 장 대표 농성장을 찾아 쌍특검 공조 의사를 밝혔다. 청와대와 민주당 인사는 단식장을 찾지 않았지만 홍익표 청와대 정무수석이 조만간 장 대표 병문안을 할 예정이다. 단식을 끝낸 장 대표는 분야별 전문가로 구성된 특보단을 발표하고, 지방선거 정책 발표회를 열 계획이다. 다만 민주당이 국민의힘을 상대로 ‘위헌 정당’이라고 공세를 펴면서 여야 갈등은 계속될 가능성이 높다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ahead of Representative Jang lies the task of boosting the party's stagnant approval rating before the June 3 local elections. In a Real Meter opinion poll (using an automated response method) released on the 19th, the fifth day of the fast, the PPP's approval rating was 37%, up 3.5 percentage points from the previous week. However, in a National Barometer Survey (NBS, using a telephone interview method) released on the last day of the fast, the PPP's approval rating was 20%, down 3 percentage points from the previous survey, marking the lowest level since Representative Jang took office in August last year. (장 대표 앞에는 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 정체된 당 지지율을 끌어올려야 하는 과제도 있다. 단식 닷새째인 지난 19일 발표된 리얼미터 여론조사(자동응답 방식)에서 국민의힘 지지율은 전주보다 3.5%포인트(P) 상승한 37%였다. 하지만 단식 마지막 날 발표된 전국지표조사(NBS·전화 면접 조사 방식)에서는 국민의힘 지지율이 직전 조사보다 3%P 하락한 20%로, 작년 8월 장 대표 취임 이후 최저 수준이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attention is also focused on whether Representative Jang will pass a resolution to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon at the Supreme Council meeting scheduled for the 26th. Some provincial and metropolitan city governors, along with a significant number of lawmakers including those from the Yeongnam region, are arguing that "the expulsion decision should be reconsidered ahead of the local elections." However, observations around Representative Jang lean towards the view that he will pass the expulsion in accordance with the ethics committee's decision. In that case, there are also opinions that the pro-Han faction will react strongly, pouring cold water on the atmosphere of broader conservative consolidation gained through the hunger strike. An opposition party official said, "At the end of 2019, when then-leader Hwang Kyo-ahn of the Liberty Korea Party (predecessor of the PPP) tried to establish a pro-Hwang system after an 8-day fast, he faced backlash from inside and outside the party, halving the effect of the fast." (장 대표가 오는 26일로 예정된 최고위원 회의에서 한동훈 전 대표 제명을 의결할지도 주목된다. 일부 시도지사, 영남권을 비롯해 상당수 의원은 “지방선거를 앞두고 제명 결정을 재고해야 한다”고 주장하고 있다. 하지만 장 대표 주변에선 윤리위 결정대로 제명을 의결할 것이라는 관측이 우세하다. 이 경우 친한계가 반발하며 단식으로 얻은 범보수 결집 분위기에 찬물을 끼얹을 것이라는 의견도 있다. 야권 관계자는 “2019년 말 황교안 당시 자유한국당(국민의힘 전신) 대표가 8일 단식 후 친정 체제를 구축하려다 당 안팎의 반발을 사며 단식 효과가 반감됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the sentencing in former President Yoon's sedition trial approaching, if the party is run centered on its hardcore supporters, it could also affect cooperation with the Reform Party. Leader Lee Jun-seok said on the radio that day, "While we are cooperating on the special prosecution investigation this time, I have doubts about whether (Representative Jang) can make judgments to broaden this within a narrowed spectrum." (윤 전 대통령 내란 재판 선고를 앞둔 상황에서 강성 지지층 중심으로 당을 운영할 경우 개혁신당과의 공조에도 영향을 미칠 수도 있다. 이준석 대표는 이날 라디오에서 “이번에 저희가 특검으로 공조하지만 (장 대표가) 좁아진 스펙트럼 속에서 이걸 넓히기 위한 판단을 할 수 있을지 의구심은 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/WQ5MB6M3ZNDBZMBLN4U2QXIIHA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z3MPVDHKMVHETKVRNUZPFK2B2I.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee, as opposition leader, requested 8 summit meetings... After becoming president, changed stance and rejected People Power Party's proposal (李, 야당 대표 땐 영수회담 8차례 요구… 대통령 되자 입장 바꿔 국힘 제안 거절)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/Q6JLVHPXYJC2DD36R42VFYFWIY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung rejected the People Power Party's request for a summit meeting during his New Year's press conference on the 21st, stating, "It seems dialogue between the ruling and opposition parties should take priority now." As the opposition leader, President Lee had requested a total of 8 summit meetings from former President Yoon Suk-yeol. The People Power Party criticized this, saying, "His stance changed after becoming president." (이재명 대통령은 21일 신년 기자회견에서 국민의힘의 영수회담 요구와 관련해 “지금은 여야 간 대화가 우선인 것 같다”며 거절했다. 이 대통령은 야당 대표 시절 윤석열 전 대통령에게 총 8차례 영수회담을 요청했다. 국민의힘에선 “대통령이 되더니 입장이 바뀐 것”이라는 비판이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Immediately after being elected leader of the Democratic Party of Korea on August 28, 2022, President Lee stated in his acceptance speech, "I will request a summit meeting (with former President Yoon) and put our heads together to find solutions." This was three months after the launch of the Yoon Suk-yeol administration. President Lee also requested a summit meeting during the Democratic Party's Supreme Council meeting on the 29th and in a phone call with former President Yoon on the 30th. (이 대통령은 2022년 8월 28일 더불어민주당 대표 당선 직후 수락 연설에서 “(윤 전 대통령에게) 영수회담을 요청해 머리를 맞대고 해법을 만들겠다”고 했다. 윤석열 정부 출범 3개월이 지난 시점이다. 이 대통령은 29일 민주당 최고위원 회의, 30일 윤 전 대통령과의 전화 통화에서도 영수회담을 요청했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On September 8, 2022, when prosecutors indicted him without detention on charges of violating the Public Official Election Act, then-Democratic Party leader President Lee posted on Facebook the same day, "Let's meet right after Chuseok (Korean Thanksgiving) to answer the people's questions about what our politics should do now." On the 13th of the same month, he also proposed a summit meeting on people's livelihoods and the economy during a party meeting, saying, "I will not be bound by procedure or formality." On October 28, 2022, at a party meeting held in Daegu, President Lee said, "I repeatedly urge the President to personally engage in dialogue." This was the day that Kim Yong, former vice president of the Democratic Research Institute and a close aide to President Lee, had his detention period extended by ten more days on charges of receiving "illegal presidential election funds worth 800 million won." (2022년 9월 8일 검찰이 공직선거법 위반 혐의로 불구속 기소하자 민주당 대표였던 이 대통령은 같은 날 페이스북에 “추석 직후에라도 바로 만나 지금 우리 정치가 무엇을 해야 하는지 국민의 물음에 답해드리자”고 했다. 같은 달 13일 당 회의에서도 민생 경제 영수회담을 제안하며 “절차와 형식에 구애받지 않겠다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 2022년 10월 28일 대구에서 열린 당 회의에서 “대통령이 직접 대화에 나설 것을 거듭 촉구드린다”고 했다. 이 대통령 최측근인 김용 전 민주연구원 부원장이 ‘8억원대 불법 대선 자금’ 수수 혐의로 구속 기간이 열흘 더 연장된 날이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On January 28, 2023, two days after undergoing prosecution investigation regarding the Daejang-dong development corruption case, he said, "I hope President Yoon doesn't keep summoning me only to the prosecution, but also to Yongsan (the presidential office), as it would help solve people's livelihood and economic issues." President Lee, who was receiving hospital treatment after a hunger strike demanding the resignation of the entire Yoon Suk-yeol administration cabinet, requested a summit meeting on August 29, 2023. (2023년 1월 28일 대장동 개발 비리 사건으로 검찰 조사를 받고 나서 이틀 후 “윤 대통령께서 저를 검찰청으로만 자꾸 부르지 마시고, 용산으로도 불러주시면 민생과 경제 문제 해결에 도움이 될 것”이라고 했다. 윤석열 정부 내각 총사퇴를 요구하며 단식을 한 후 병원에서 치료받던 이 대통령은 2023년 8월 29일 영수 회담을 요구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former President Yoon held his first bilateral meeting with President Lee at the Yongsan Presidential Office in Seoul on April 29, 2024. This was 720 days after the launch of the Yoon Suk-yeol administration, following the Democratic Party's major victory in the general election that April. Therefore, within the Democratic Party, there are comments that "former President Yoon was also stingy with summit meetings." (윤 전 대통령은 2024년 4월 29일 서울 용산 대통령실에서 이 대통령과의 첫 양자 회담을 열었다. 그해 4월 총선에서 민주당이 대승한 이후로, 윤석열 정부 출범 후 720일 만이었다. 때문에 민주당에선 “윤 전 대통령도 영수회담에 인색했다”는 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although President Lee hosted a luncheon meeting last September with Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae and People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, he has not held a separate one-on-one meeting with the opposition leader. People Power Party lawmaker Sung Il-jong said, "When he (President Lee) was the opposition leader, it was right to hold a summit meeting, but now that he's president, he's turning a blind eye (to it)."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령은 작년 9월 정청래 민주당 대표, 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 불러 오찬 회동을 했지만 야당 대표와 단독 회동은 하지 않았다. 국민의힘 성일종 의원은 “본인(이 대통령)이 야당 대표일 땐 영수회담을 하는 게 옳은 것이고 지금 대통령이 되니까 나 몰라라 (하고 있다)”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/Q6JLVHPXYJC2DD36R42VFYFWIY/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon's Confirmation Hearing Today... Additional Suspicions Arise Over 'Children's Early Overseas Education' (오늘 이혜훈 청문회… ‘자녀 조기유학’ 두고 추가 의혹)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/RAIUNGSQZFDWDB3CQU6UEVF5UM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5LBJC45K4NGUROBYCJXBR76N5E.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A National Assembly confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, who faces various allegations including real estate speculation and staff abuse of power, will be held on the 23rd. The People Power Party had refused to hold the hearing on the 19th, citing the nominee's failure to properly submit requested documents. However, the ruling and opposition parties agreed to summon the nominee to hear her explanations regarding the various allegations. (부동산 투기, 보좌진 갑질 등 각종 의혹이 제기된 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회 인사청문회가 23일 열린다. 국민의힘은 지난 19일 이 후보자가 요청한 자료를 제대로 제출하지 않았다는 이유로 청문회 개최를 거부했었다. 하지만 여야는 일단 이 후보자를 불러 각종 의혹에 대한 해명을 들어보기로 합의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, the Democratic Party also showed a passive attitude towards holding a hearing for this nominee. Although they could have held the hearing unilaterally without the People Power Party, internal voices said it was "a matter the President should decide." Subsequently, President Lee Jae-myung said at a press conference on the 21st regarding the nominee that "there do seem to be problems," but also indicated his intention to hold the hearing. The Democratic Party reportedly then persuaded the People Power Party. (당초 민주당에서도 이 후보자 청문회에 대해 소극적 태도를 보였었다. 국민의힘 없이 청문회 단독 개최도 가능했지만 내부에선 “대통령이 결정해야 할 문제”라는 말이 나왔다. 이후 이재명 대통령은 21일 기자회견에서 이 후보자에 대해 “문제는 있어 보이긴 한다”면서도 청문회는 열자는 취지로 말했다. 이에 민주당은 국민의힘을 설득했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party also reportedly judged that "there would be considerable political burden of neglecting parliamentary operations if the hearing is not held." The explanation provided by the nominee's side to the People Power Party regarding the 'insufficient document submission' issue is also said to have had an impact. (국민의힘도 “청문회를 열지 않으면 국회 운영 방기라는 정치적 부담이 상당하다”고 판단했다고 한다. 이 후보자 측이 ‘자료 제출 미비’ 문제에 대해 국민의힘에 해명한 것도 영향을 미쳤다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party plans to focus all its efforts on proving the nominee's 'unfitness for minister' during the hearing. Currently, the nominee is under suspicion for staff abuse of power and verbal abuse during her time as a lawmaker, and for winning the 'lottery subscription' for a 7-billion-won apartment in Seoul's Banpo One Pentas by having her married eldest son pose as 'unmarried'. (국민의힘은 청문회에서 이 후보자의 ‘장관 부적격성’을 입증하는 데 총력을 기울일 계획이다. 현재 이 후보자는 국회의원 시절 보좌진 갑질·폭언, 결혼한 장남의 ‘위장 미혼’을 통한 70억원대 서울 반포 원펜타스 아파트 ‘로또 청약’ 당첨 등 의혹을 받고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional suspicions emerged on this day. It was newly revealed that the nominee's husband bought land on Yeongjongdo one year before Incheon Airport opened and made a profit of around 2 billion won from the sale, and that the seller of the land in 2000 was her husband's maternal uncle. The People Power Party suspects this was a 'low-price sale' method to evade gift tax. (이날 추가 의혹도 나왔다. 이 후보자는 남편이 인천공항 개항 1년 전 영종도 땅을 사서 20억원대 매매 차익을 남겼는데, 2000년 당시 땅 매도인이 남편의 외삼촌이었다는 사실이 새롭게 드러났다. 국민의힘은 “증여세를 탈루하기 위한 ‘저가 매매’ 수법”이라고 의심하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, suspicions arose that the nominee violated the Elementary and Secondary Education Act by sending her children overseas to study between 2002 and 2004. The relevant regulations only permit studying abroad in cases such as 'when both parents go abroad to live together out of necessity,' but it is questioned whether the nominee was residing in Korea during that period for reasons like preparing for the general election. (또 이 후보자가 지난 2002~2004년 초·중등교육법을 위반해 자녀를 해외 유학 보냈다는 의혹도 나왔다. 관련 규정엔 ‘부모가 모두 출국해 동거할 목적으로 불가피할 경우’ 등에만 유학이 인정되는데, 해당 기간에 이 후보자가 총선 준비 등으로 한국에 거주했던 것 아니냐는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/RAIUNGSQZFDWDB3CQU6UEVF5UM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5LBJC45K4NGUROBYCJXBR76N5E.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:48:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae Contacts Cho Kuk Multiple Times... Proposes Merger After Exchanging Views with President Lee (정청래, 조국과 수차례 접촉… 李대통령과 교감 후 합당 제안)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/YJZL73NG7NBH7MW2ID7MFWSUME/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KVBJUVTEERBTXHQQLMOVCYOAWI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea was in an uproar all day on the 22nd due to party leader Chung Cheong-rae's surprise merger proposal. Lawmakers publicly attacked Leader Chung, asking, "Are you making major party decisions unilaterally?" Some Supreme Council members said they were unaware of the content until 20 minutes before the announcement. Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo called it a "railroaded merger" and even suggested questioning Leader Chung's decision to stay or step down. (더불어민주당은 22일 정청래 대표의 기습 합당 제안으로 온종일 시끄러웠다. 의원들은 “중대한 당무를 독단적으로 결정하냐”며 공개적으로 정 대표를 공격했다. 일부 최고위원은 발표 20분 전까지도 내용을 몰랐다고 했다. 이언주 최고위원은 “날치기 합당”이라며 정 대표의 진퇴 여부를 묻자고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, it is known that this announcement was made after secret, separate preliminary exchanges between the Blue House, Leader Chung, and Leader Cho Kuk. Ruling bloc officials said, "President Lee Jae-myung, Leader Chung, and Leader Cho joined hands before the common goal of 'seizing political initiative through a landslide victory in the local elections.'" Predictions have emerged that this merger will become a major variable in the ruling bloc's political landscape surrounding future power dynamics. (하지만 이번 발표는 청와대, 정 대표, 조국 대표가 극비리에 각자 사전 교감하면서 이뤄진 것으로 알려졌다. 여권 관계자들은 “이재명 대통령, 정 대표, 조 대표가 ‘지방선거 압승을 통한 정국 주도권 장악’이라는 공동의 목표 앞에서 손을 잡은 것”이라고 했다. 이번 합당이 차기 권력 등을 둘러싼 여권 정치 지형에 중대한 변수가 될 것이란 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The merger discussions are known to have gained sudden momentum recently. A key Democratic Party lawmaker said, "Leader Chung had been considering solidarity with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party since right after his election as party leader last August, and recently concluded that rather than just solidarity, they should merge." Leader Chung is said to have coordinated opinions with the Blue House and also met with Leader Cho multiple times. Leader Chung reportedly told a closed-door general meeting of lawmakers, "This merger was decided through coordination between the party and the Blue House," and expressed regret for not informing them in advance. To some lawmakers, he reportedly said, "I've been contemplating this for a long time and discussed it with the President multiple times. I judged that with the election approaching, we could no longer delay." Blue House Senior Presidential Secretary for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo also said, "The integration of the two parties is President Lee's longstanding principle," and added, "I will watch the discussion process." (이번 합당 논의는 최근 급물살을 탄 것으로 알려졌다. 민주당 핵심 의원은 “정 대표는 작년 8월 당대표 선출 직후부터 조국혁신당과의 연대를 고려해왔다가 최근 연대할 바엔 합당하자는 쪽으로 결론내렸다”고 했다. 정 대표는 청와대와 의견 조율을 해왔고, 조 대표와도 여러 차례 만났다고 한다. 정 대표는 비공개 의원총회에서 “이번 합당은 당청 간 조율을 통해 결정됐다”며 “미리 알리지 못해 미안하다”는 취지로 말했다고 한다. 일부 의원들에게는 “오래 전부터 고민해왔고, 대통령과도 수차례 논의했다. 선거를 앞두고 더 이상 미루면 안된다고 판단했다”고 말했다고 한다. 청와대 홍익표 정무수석도 “양당 통합은 이 대통령의 평소 지론”이라며 “논의 과정을 지켜보겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although President Lee is not stepping to the forefront in these merger discussions, he is reported to have had a strong will. Last year on August 15th, Liberation Day, it was also the President's thinking to strongly push for Leader Cho's pardon and reinstatement despite backlash from the hardcore support base. A ruling bloc official said, "The President seems to have viewed gathering ruling bloc figures into the Democratic Party to create a competitive structure as necessary for regime renewal." (이 대통령은 이번 합당 논의에서 전면에 나서지 않고 있지만 의지가 강했던 것으로 전해졌다. 작년 8·15 광복절 때 강성 지지층 반발에도 조 대표의 사면·복권을 강하게 밀어붙인 것도 대통령의 생각이었다. 여권 관계자는 “대통령은 여권 주자를 민주당에 모아서 경쟁 구도를 만드는 일이 정권 재창출을 위해 필요하다고 본 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Chung appears to have decided on the merger for a landslide victory in the local elections. The talk is that he considered the possibility of the political landscape fluctuating in his stronghold like the Honam region as the election nears. A key Democratic Party official said, "If the Cho Kuk Innovation Party fields candidates in some metropolitan areas and takes even 5%, it becomes a very troublesome situation." However, there are also reactions of surprise that Leader Chung quickly joined hands with Leader Cho, a potential competitor. Leader Chung is aiming for re-election in the upcoming August party leadership election, and if Leader Cho enters the Democratic Party, the number of competitors will increase. A Democratic Party second-term lawmaker said, "We could sufficiently win the local elections even without a merger, but it seems Leader Chung made a political decision," adding, "Isn't it confidence about his position as a future leading figure?" (정 대표는 지방선거 압승을 위해 합당을 결단한 것으로 보인다. 선거가 임박해 텃밭인 호남 등에서 판세가 요동칠 경우를 염두에 뒀다는 얘기다. 민주당 핵심 관계자는 “조국혁신당이 수도권 일부 지역에 후보를 내 5%라도 가져간다면 매우 피곤한 상황이 되는 것”이라고 했다. 하지만 정 대표가 잠재적 경쟁자인 조 대표와 빠르게 손을 잡은 것은 의아하다는 반응도 있다. 정 대표는 오는 8월 당대표 선거에서 연임을 노리고 있는데 조 대표가 민주당에 들어오면 경쟁 상대가 늘어나기 때문이다. 민주당 재선 의원은 “합당없이도 지방선거를 충분히 이길 수 있는데 정 대표가 정치적 결단을 내린 것 같다”며 “차기 주자 자리에 대한 자신감 아니겠냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an interview with this newspaper last October, Leader Cho hinted that he would not pursue a merger led by the Democratic Party, saying, "If the Democratic Party is a large corporation, we are a startup." However, it is known that he faced significant concerns recently as the Cho Kuk Innovation Party's approval rating remained stuck in the single digits of 2-3%. Recruiting candidates for the local elections was also reportedly very difficult. A key Cho Kuk Innovation Party official said, "Given the situation, the atmosphere was leaning towards proposing a merger." Leader Cho's likelihood of running in the National Assembly by-election held concurrently with the local elections has increased after the merger. A Democratic Party official said, "He could become a focal point for pro-Moon (supporters of former President Moon Jae-in) forces who have nowhere else to go." (조 대표는 작년 10월 본지 인터뷰에서 “민주당이 대기업이면 우리는 스타트업”이라며 민주당 주도의 합당은 하지 않겠다는 뜻을 내비쳤다. 하지만 최근 조국혁신당의 지지율이 2~3%대 한 자릿수에 머물자 고민이 컸던 것으로 알려졌다. 지방선거 출마자 영입도 매우 어려웠다고 한다. 조국혁신당 핵심 관계자는 “상황이 이러니 합당을 건의하는 분위기였다”고 했다. 조 대표는 합당 후 지방선거와 같이 치러지는 국회의원 재보궐 선거에 출마할 가능성이 커졌다. 민주당 관계자는 “갈 곳 잃은 친문 세력의 구심점이 될 수도 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the two parties have begun merger discussions, whether the merger will be easily achieved is uncertain. Some Democratic Party supporters are protesting, as they did during Leader Cho's pardon, saying, "The Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Party are fundamentally different, and especially cannot be together with the Moon faction (supporters of former President Moon Jae-in)." A Democratic Party official said, "A key point will also be to what extent Leader Cho demands a stake, such as candidate positions in some regions for the local elections." (양당이 합당 논의에 착수했지만 합당이 쉽게 이뤄질지는 미지수다. 민주당 일부 지지층에선 조 대표 사면 때처럼 반발하고 있다. “민주당과 조국당은 결이 다르고, 특히 문파(문재인 전 대통령 지지자들)와는 함께 할 수 없다”는 것이다. 민주당 관계자는 “조 대표가 지방선거 일부 지역 후보 자리 등 어느 정도 지분을 요구할지도 관건”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/YJZL73NG7NBH7MW2ID7MFWSUME/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KVBJUVTEERBTXHQQLMOVCYOAWI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Merger Expected to Consolidate Pro-Myung and Pro-Moon Support Base… Opposition Likely to Ultimately Pursue 'Election Alliance' (합당 땐 친명·친문 지지층 결집 기대… 야권도 결국 ‘선거 연대’로 갈 듯)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/KJBCULBTDVCGDP6GZLU2C5QE6A/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;As the Democratic Party of Korea and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party entered discussions on a 'merger' on the 22nd, attention is also focused on whether the People Power Party and the Reform Party will form an alliance for the June 3 local elections. While the Reform Party is maintaining a strong united front with the People Power Party in urging a special investigation into the 'Unification Church and Democratic Party nomination corruption scandals,' it maintains a stance against an election alliance. However, there are also voices suggesting that as the election campaign intensifies, an alliance may become inevitable in key areas like Seoul, Gyeonggi, and Busan, which could determine the success or failure of this local election. (더불어민주당과 조국혁신당이 22일 ‘합당’ 논의에 들어가면서 국민의힘과 개혁신당의 6·3 지방선거 연대 여부에도 관심이 쏠리고 있다. 개혁신당은 ‘통일교·민주당 공천 비리’ 쌍특검 촉구에 대해선 국민의힘과 강한 공동 전선을 펼치고 있으나, 선거 연대는 하지 않는다는 입장이다. 그러나 선거가 본격화하면 이번 지방선거의 성패를 좌우할 수 있는 서울·경기·부산 등에서 연대할 수밖에 없지 않겠냐는 말도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling camp, it is judged that if the merger between the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, represented by the 'pro-Myung' and 'pro-Moon' factions, materializes, it will be beneficial for elections in the capital region and Busan. A Democratic Party lawmaker from the capital region said, "We anticipate that the ruling camp's scattered support base will unite due to the merger, positively impacting the vote," adding, "Especially in Busan, the political home of pro-Roh and pro-Moon factions, we expect to see the effects of the merger." (여권에선 ‘친명(親明)’과 ‘친문(親文)’으로 대표되는 민주당-조국혁신당 합당이 이뤄지면 수도권과 부산 선거에 도움이 될 것으로 판단하고 있다. 민주당 수도권 의원은 “흩어져 있는 여권의 지지층이 합당 계기로 하나로 묶여 표에 긍정적 영향을 줄 것으로 보고 있다”이라며 “특히 친노, 친문의 정치적 고향인 부산도 합당 효과를 볼 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, an alliance between the People Power Party and the Reform Party appears difficult for now. The People Power Party is being tight-lipped about an alliance with the Reform Party ahead of the local elections. Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said on CBS Radio that day, "I have no interest in an election alliance." Leader Lee said, "We are cooperating (with the People Power Party) on the special investigation, but constantly steering that toward an election alliance is talk from onlookers." He also commented on People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, saying, "It's concerning. He should use the field broadly, but he seems clearly clustered on the right." (하지만 국민의힘과 개혁신당 간 연대는 당장 어려워 보인다. 국민의힘은 지방선거 전 개혁신당과의 연대에 대해 말을 아끼고 있다. 개혁신당 이준석 대표는 이날 CBS 라디오에서 “선거 연대는 관심이 없다”고 했다. 이 대표는 “(국민의힘과) 특검에 대해서 연대하는데, 자꾸 그걸 선거 연대로 몰고 가는 것은 호사가들의 얘기”라고 했다. 또 국민의힘 장동혁 대표에 대해 “우려스럽다. 운동장을 넓게 써야 되는데 확실히 오른쪽에 몰려 있는 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform Party has stated it will first contest the election on its own. Supreme Council member Kim Jung-chul has declared a run for Seoul Mayor, spokesperson Jeong Yi-han for Busan Mayor, and they are reportedly sounding out external figures for the Gyeonggi Governor candidate. Secretary-General Lee Ki-in revealed at the Supreme Council meeting that day, "We opened the online nomination application system on the 8th, and a total of 131 candidates have completed submitting the necessary documents to run for election, including six candidates for metropolitan government heads." For candidates for basic-level councilor positions, there are reportedly about 400-500 applicants, including those who have completed document submission, primarily in their 20s and 30s. (개혁신당은 일단 자체적으로 선거를 치르겠다고 하고 있다. 서울시장엔 김정철 최고위원, 부산시장은 정이한 대변인이 출마를 선언했고, 경기지사 후보는 외부 인사 영입을 타진 중이라고 한다. 이기인 사무총장은 이날 최고위원 회의에서 “지난 8일 온라인 공천 접수 시스템을 개방했고, 광역단체장 후보 6명을 포함해 선거 출마를 위한 필수 서류 제출을 완료한 후보는 총 131명”이라고 밝혔다. 기초 의원 등 후보 지원에는 20~30대를 중심으로 서류 제출 완료자 포함 지원자가 현재 400~500명 정도라고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, there are forecasts that an election alliance could naturally occur in major metropolitan government head elections such as Seoul, Busan, and Gyeonggi. The frequent meetings between People Power Party-affiliated Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon and Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok also lend weight to such observations. An opposition camp official said, "If a Reform Party candidate is more competitive among some candidates, wouldn't the People Power Party discuss a plan to concede?" (다만, 서울·부산·경기 등 주요 광역단체장 선거에선 자연스럽게 선거 연대가 이뤄질 수 있지 않겠느냐는 전망도 나온다. 국민의힘 소속 오세훈 서울시장과 이준석 대표가 자주 회동한 점도 이런 관측에 힘을 싣고 있다. 야권 관계자는 “일부 후보 중에서 개혁신당 후보가 더 경쟁력이 있다면, 국민의힘이 양보하는 방안도 논의하지 않겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/KJBCULBTDVCGDP6GZLU2C5QE6A/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Targets Hardliners' Backlash, Says "Reform is Not About Clinging to Grand Causes While Causing Public Suffering" (李, 강경파 반발 겨냥 “대의 명분에 매달려 국민 고통땐 개혁 아냐”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/SZQR5CUW4ZD63NEIKDRTKVFCAU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 22nd, "If, far from improving people's lives, we cling to causes and grand purposes and only increase suffering and confusion, that cannot be called reform." This is interpreted as targeting the backlash from hardliners within the ruling party regarding the government's bill to establish the Public Prosecution Service and the Major Crimes Investigation Agency (MCIA). (이재명 대통령은 22일 “국민의 삶을 개선하기는커녕 오히려 명분과 대의에 매달려서 고통과 혼란만 가중시킨다면 그것은 개혁이라고 할 수 없다”고 말했다. 정부의 공소청·중대범죄수사청(중수청) 설치법에 대한 여권 내 강경파 반발을 겨냥한 것으로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a meeting of senior secretaries at the Blue House that day, President Lee said, "We must carefully judge from a practical, effective perspective which option helps protect the people's human rights and guarantee their substantive rights, and meticulously check." In a press conference the previous day, President Lee had also targeted hardliners demanding the immediate abolition of prosecutors' supplementary investigation rights within the Public Prosecution Service, stating, "There are cases where supplementary investigation rights are exceptionally necessary." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 수석보좌관회의를 주재하고 “어느 방안이 국민의 인권 보호와 실질적인 권리 보장에 도움이 되는지를 실용적인, 실효적인 관점에서 신중하게 판단하고 꼼꼼하게 챙겨봐야겠다”며 이같이 말했다. 이 대통령은 전날 기자회견에서도 “공소청 검사의 보완 수사권을 당장 폐지하라”는 강경파를 겨냥해 “보완 수사권이 예외적으로 필요한 경우도 있다”고 했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the Democratic Party, opinions are converging towards allowing prosecutors in the Public Prosecution Service exceptional supplementary investigation rights, in line with President Lee's stance. The idea is to permit supplementary investigation rights only in limited cases, such as those nearing the statute of limitations. During the party's general meeting of lawmakers that day, discussions continued on the government's MCIA/Public Prosecution Service bill, and a significant number of lawmakers reportedly agreed with this opinion. However, some lawmakers opposed allowing limited supplementary investigation rights, arguing, "It can be sufficiently resolved through other means, such as the right to request supplementary investigations." (민주당에선 이 대통령 뜻대로 공소청 검사에게 예외적 보완 수사권을 허용하는 쪽으로 의견이 모아지고 있다. 공소시효가 임박한 사건 등에 한해 보완 수사권을 제한적으로 허용하자는 것이다. 이날 민주당의 의원총회에선 정부의 중수청·공소청법에 대한 논의가 이어졌는데, 상당수 의원이 이런 의견에 공감했다고 한다. 다만 일부 의원은 “보완 수사 요구권 등 다른 방식으로도 충분히 해결할 수 있다”며 제한적 보완 수사권 허용에 반대했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the general meeting, opinions were also exchanged regarding the MCIA's investigative scope and the dual-track system for investigative personnel. The government's proposal includes having legal professionals like prosecutors as 'investigative judicial officers' and non-legal professionals as 'special investigative officers' within the MCIA. Hardliners have objected, saying, "How is this different from prosecutors? The dual-track system is unacceptable." A Democratic Party official said, "It is highly likely the MCIA dual-track system will be scrapped." Some lawmakers argued, "If the investigative scope is set to nine major crimes as in the government proposal, it will essentially become 'Season 2' of the prosecution's special investigation unit," and suggested, "Only investigations into two major crimes, like corruption and economic crimes, should be allowed." Conversely, opinions were also raised that "all nine major crimes should be included as investigative targets, with specific details adjusted through enforcement decrees." (이날 의총에선 중수청의 수사 범위, 수사 인력 이원화 등에 관한 의견도 오갔다. 정부안에는 중수청에 검사 등 법률가를 ‘수사사법관’, 비법률관을 ‘전문수사관’으로 두자는 내용이 있는데, 강경파는 “검사와 뭐가 다르냐. 이원화는 안된다”며 반발해왔다. 민주당 관계자는 “중수청 이원화는 폐지할 가능성이 높다”고 했다. 일부 의원은 “정부안처럼 수사 범위를 9대 범죄로 하면 사실상 검찰 특수부 ‘시즌 2’가 될 것”이라면서 “부패·경제 범죄 등 2대 범죄 수사만 허용해야 한다”고 했다. 반면 “9대 범죄를 모두 수사 대상에 넣되 시행령으로 구체적 내용을 조정하면 된다”는 의견도 나왔다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party is strongly considering holding an additional general meeting of lawmakers next week to finalize the party's official stance and then convey it to the government. (민주당은 다음 주 중 추가 의원총회를 열어 당론을 정한 뒤 정부에 전달하는 방안을 유력하게 검토 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/23/SZQR5CUW4ZD63NEIKDRTKVFCAU/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:49:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Pulls Out the 'Nuclear Disarmament' Card... Only Raises Kim Jong-un's Price (‘핵 군축’ 카드 꺼낸 李… 김정은 몸값만 높여주나)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/4B75WKVPBRFGFDESD7BQ37CEGU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PPFKYDYZGNJQ5CROY4GZ7LJKQA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung, who has positioned himself as the 'pacemaker' for U.S.-North Korea summit talks, has made a risky proposal to the U.S. and North Korea ahead of U.S. President Trump's planned visit to Northeast Asia in April. At a New Year's press conference on the 21st, President Lee publicly presented a new approach: 'disarmament negotiations' premised on North Korea being a nuclear-armed state. (미·북 정상회담의 ‘페이스메이커’를 자처해 온 이재명 대통령이 오는 4월 트럼프 미국 대통령의 동북아 방문을 앞두고 미국과 북한에 위험한 제안을 했다. 이 대통령은 21일 신년 기자회견에서 북한을 핵 보유국으로 전제한 ‘군축 협상’이라는 새로운 접근법을 공개적으로 제시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding North Korea's denuclearization, President Lee said, "Let's negotiate a realistic freeze as the first step, and then negotiate nuclear disarmament." This is a shift from pursuing the 'ideal approach' of complete denuclearization to a more pragmatic response. This is the first time President Lee has clearly mentioned negotiating North Korean nuclear disarmament since taking office last June, and it is reigniting the possibility of a Trump-Kim summit, which fell through last year. If Trump follows President Lee's lead and hints at disarmament talks, analysis suggests Kim Jong-un could enter negotiations with a much higher 'price' than during the APEC summit in Gyeongju last October. (이 대통령은 북한 비핵화와 관련, “1단계로 가장 현실적인 중단 협상을 하고, 그다음 핵 군축 협상을 하자”고 했다. 북한의 완전한 비핵화를 추구하는 ‘이상적인 접근법’에서 벗어나, 현실적으로 대응하자는 것이다. 이 대통령이 지난해 6월 취임 후 북핵 군축 협상을 하자고 명확히 언급한 것은 처음으로, 지난해 무산됐던 트럼프·김정은 회동 가능성을 다시 쏘아 올리고 있다. 만약 이 대통령에 이어 트럼프가 군축 협상을 시사하면, 김정은으로서는 지난해 10월 경주 APEC 때보다 훨씬 높아진 ‘몸값’으로 협상에 나설 수 있다는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's proposal is particularly noteworthy as it came just three days after The Washington Post argued in an editorial that disarmament negotiations, rather than denuclearization, should be pursued. The newspaper stated, "Denuclearization of the Korean Peninsula is no longer a realistic option," and suggested that negotiations limiting the number of nuclear warheads and missiles could be a more practical risk management tool. Choi Kang, President of the Asan Institute for Policy Studies, said, "President Lee's proposal is identical to the logic of disarmament negotiations presented by The Washington Post," adding, "It reflects the perspective of Washington non-proliferation advocates, particularly the logic of former North Korea nuclear envoy Robert Gallucci, that freezing and reducing is better than doing nothing about North Korea's nuclear program." The Washington Post editorial starkly shows the perception prevalent within the White House and the U.S. foreign policy and security expert community, suggesting President Lee's proposal could become a public topic for discussion. (이 대통령의 제안은 특히 워싱턴포스트가 사흘 전 사설을 통해 비핵화 대신 군축 협상을 추진해야 한다고 주장한 직후 나왔다는 점에서 눈길을 끈다. 이 신문은 “한반도 비핵화는 더 이상 현실적인 선택지가 아니다”라며, 핵탄두와 미사일 수를 제한하는 협상이 오히려 실질적인 위험 관리 수단이 될 수 있다고 했다. 최강 아산정책연구원장은 “이 대통령의 제안은 워싱턴포스트가 제시한 군축 협상 논리와 똑같다”며 “북핵에 대해 아무것도 하지 않는 것보다는 일단 동결, 감축시키는 것이 낫다는 워싱턴 비확산론자들의 시각, 특히 로버트 갈루치 전 북핵 특사의 논리가 반영돼 있다”고 했다. 워싱턴포스트의 사설은 백악관과 미국 외교·안보 전문가 사회에 퍼져 있는 인식을 단적으로 보여주기에 이 대통령의 제안이 공론화될 수 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trump has repeatedly referred to North Korea as a 'nuclear power' over the past year and shown great interest in a U.S.-North Korea summit. Given his strong desire for a Nobel Peace Prize, the possibility that he is aiming for the 'visible achievement' of a North Korean nuclear freeze or reduction is not small. There is also speculation that Trump, with his April Northeast Asia visit in mind, has already begun preparations for U.S.-North Korea talks. Earlier this month, Kevin Kim, the U.S. chargé d'affaires to South Korea whom Trump trusts, moved to become Chief of Staff to Allison Hooker, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs. Deputy Assistant Secretary Hooker was deeply involved in the Trump administration's first-term North Korea policy and now oversees North Korea policy at the State Department. Kevin Kim accompanied Special Representative for North Korea Stephen Biegun on his visit to North Korea, handling practical matters such as agenda coordination. Accordingly, analysis suggests that personnel with experience dealing with North Korean issues are gathering again at the State Department to prepare for a U.S.-North Korea summit. (트럼프는 지난해 수 차례 북한을 ‘핵보유국(nuclear power)’으로 지칭하며 미·북 정상회담에 큰 관심을 보여왔다. 그가 노벨 평화상에 강한 집착을 보여 왔다는 점에서, 북핵 동결 또는 감축이라는 ‘가시적 성과’를 노릴 가능성이 적지 않다. 트럼프가 4월 동북아 방문을 염두에 두고 이미 미·북 회담 준비에 착수했다는 관측도 있다. 이달 초 트럼프가 신임하는 케빈 김 주한 미국 대사대리는 앨리슨 후커 국무부 정무차관의 비서실장으로 자리를 옮겼다. 후커 차관은 트럼프 1기 행정부의 대북 정책에 깊숙이 관여했으며 지금은 국무부에서 대북 정책을 총괄한다. 케빈 김은 스티븐 비건 대북특별대표를 수행, 북한을 방문하며 의제 조율 등의 실무를 담당한 바 있다. 이에 따라 북한 문제를 다뤄본 경험이 있는 인사들이 국무부에 다시 모여 미·북 정상회담을 준비중이라는 분석도 제기되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Also Aligns with China's 'Dual Suspension, Dual Track' Approach&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;중국의 쌍중단,쌍궤병행과도 맞닿아&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's proposal for disarmament negotiations also aligns with the solution to the North Korean nuclear issue that China has long advocated: the 'dual suspension, dual track' approach. 'Dual suspension' is the idea of simultaneously suspending North Korea's nuclear and missile development and South Korea-U.S. joint military exercises. 'Dual track' is the approach of pursuing the denuclearization of the Korean Peninsula and the establishment of a peace regime between the U.S. and North Korea in parallel. Among foreign policy and security experts, there is speculation that President Lee may have discussed this issue with Chinese President Xi Jinping during his state visit to China from the 4th to the 7th. Maintaining or stabilizing the status quo through nuclear disarmament negotiations with North Korea is a point where the interests of the leaders of South Korea, the U.S., and China—Lee Jae-myung, Trump, and Xi Jinping—all converge. Furthermore, Kim Jong-un suffered the humiliation of the 'Hanoi no-deal' at the second U.S.-North Korea summit in February 2019 due to 'lack of will for complete denuclearization,' but this time he has no such burden, so he may think differently. Above all, Kim Jong-un can showcase his nuclear possession achievement both domestically and internationally simply by sitting at the disarmament negotiation table with Trump. Given that sanctions against North Korea could be partially or fully lifted during the disarmament negotiation process, it can be seen as a game favorable to Kim Jong-un. (이 대통령의 군축 협상 제안은 중국이 그동안 주장해 온 북핵 해법인 ‘쌍중단·쌍궤병행(雙中斷·雙軌竝行)’과도 맞닿아 있다. 쌍중단은 북한의 핵·미사일 개발 중단과 한·미 연합 군사훈련 중지를 동시에 하자는 구상이고, 쌍궤병행은 한반도 비핵화와 미·북 평화 체제 전환을 병행하자는 접근법이다. 외교·안보 전문가들 사이에서는 이 대통령이 지난 4~7일 중국 국빈 방문 당시 시진핑 주석과 이 문제를 논의했을 가능성도 제기된다. 북한과 핵 군축 협상을 통해 현상 유지 또는 안정화를 도모하는 것은 이재명·트럼프·시진핑 등 한·미·중 3국 정상 모두가 이해관계를 공유하는 지점이다. 또 김정은은 2019년 2차 미·북 정상회담에서 ‘완전한 비핵화 의지 부족’을 이유로 ‘하노이 노딜’의 굴욕을 당했는데, 이번에는 그럴 부담이 없다는 점에서 달리 생각할 수 있다. 무엇보다 김정은은 트럼프와 군축 협상 테이블에 앉는 것만으로도 북한 안팎에 핵 보유 성과를 과시할 수 있다. 군축 협상 과정에서 대북 제재를 부분 또는 전면 해제시킬 수 있다는 점에서 김정은에게 유리한 게임이라고 할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Potential Backlash from Recognizing North Korea as a Nuclear State&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;북한 핵 보유국 인정 역풍 불 수도 &lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One expert said, "Having witnessed the U.S. invade Venezuela and extradite President Maduro, it will not be easy for Kim Jong-un to refuse dialogue again." This suggests Kim Jong-un might worry about Trump's 'retaliation' if he does not meet with him. (한 전문가는 “미국이 베네수엘라를 침공해 마두로 대통령을 압송한 사례를 지켜본 김정은으로서는 또다시 대화를 거부하기가 쉽지 않을 것”이라고 했다. 김정은이 트럼프를 만나지 않을 경우 그의 ‘보복’을 우려할 수도 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also significant skepticism. Some analysis suggests the possibility of resuming U.S.-North Korea summit talks is low as Trump's interest has shifted to other issues like Venezuela or Greenland. North Korea, having already secured China and Russia as 'backers,' might not respond. Professor Kim Jae-chun of the Graduate School of International Studies at Sogang University pointed out, "It is questionable whether Kim Jong-un would actually agree, given the unclear situation of what North Korea could gain from nuclear disarmament negotiations." (회의적인 시각도 적지 않다. 트럼프의 관심이 베네수엘라나 그린란드 등 다른 현안으로 옮겨가 있어 미·북 정상회담 재개 가능성은 낮다는 분석도 나온다. 이미 중국과 러시아를 ‘뒷배’로 확보한 북한이 이에 응하지 않을 수도 있다. 김재천 서강대 국제대학원 교수는 “북한이 핵 군축 협상을 통해 무엇을 얻을 수 있을지 불분명한 상황에서 김정은이 과연 응할지 의문”이라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee's proposal for nuclear disarmament negotiations could effectively grant 'amnesty' for North Korea's violations of the Geneva Agreed Framework and the September 19 Joint Statement and lead to recognizing North Korea as a nuclear-armed state, meaning the burden of failure is significant. If nuclear disarmament negotiations take place, it would inevitably be evaluated as a victory for Kim Jong-un's persistent strategy of pursuing nuclear possession. Choi Kang, President of the Asan Institute for Policy Studies, pointed out, "If this scenario becomes reality, South Korea could lose its footing." (이 대통령의 핵 군축 협상 제안은 북한의 제네바 합의, 9·19 공동성명 파기를 사실상 ‘사면’해주고, 북한의 핵 보유를 인정하는 수순으로 이어질 수 있다는 점에서 실패할 경우 부담이 크다. 핵 군축 협상이 이뤄지면 끈질기게 핵 보유를 추진해 온 김정은 전략의 승리로 평가될 수밖에 없다. 최강 아산정책연구원 원장은 “이 시나리오가 현실화되면 한국은 설 자리를 잃을 수 있다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; ()&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/4B75WKVPBRFGFDESD7BQ37CEGU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PPFKYDYZGNJQ5CROY4GZ7LJKQA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'April 3rd Colonel Park Jin-kyung' Likely to Have Patriot Status Revoked... Government Cites "Adopted Grandson Applied" as Issue (‘4·3 박진경 대령’ 결국 유공자 취소될 듯… 정부 “양손자가 신청” 문제 삼아)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/RW6LRAFBHBD6DI7BYLPFNCSMBA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7OTSORRC6ZGBDALILZ6NGOJMPQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed on the 22nd that the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs (MPVA) is strongly considering canceling the national patriot registration of the late Colonel Park Jin-kyung, who was in charge of initial recovery efforts during the 1948 Jeju April 3rd Incident, citing as an issue that the application was submitted by an adopted grandson. The reasoning is that an adopted grandson lacks the eligibility to apply, so the patriot registration should first be invalidated, and then the qualification for patriot status should be re-examined later by the Patriots Review Committee. The MPVA has begun its final legal review for this. However, as President Lee Jae-myung said during the MPVA's work report last month, "The bereaved families of the Jeju April 3rd victims are outraged. Let's find a way," it is effectively being said that the procedure for registration cancellation is underway. (국가보훈부가 1948년 제주 4·3 사건 초기에 수습을 맡았던 고(故) 박진경 대령의 국가유공자 등록을 양손자(養孫子)가 신청했던 점을 문제 삼아 취소하는 방안을 유력하게 검토 중인 것으로 22일 알려졌다. 양손자는 신청 자격이 없으니 일단 유공자 등록을 무효화하고, 추후 보훈심사위원회에서 다시 유공자 자격을 심사하겠다는 것이다. 보훈부는 이를 위한 최종 법률 검토에 들어갔다. 하지만 이재명 대통령이 지난달 보훈부 업무 보고에서 “제주 4·3유족들은 분개하고 계신다. 방법을 찾아보기로 하자”고 했기 때문에, 사실상 등록 취소 수순이란 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Colonel Park, who was assigned to Jeju about a year after his marriage, was assassinated one month later in June 1948, led by a subordinate who was a member of a South Korean Workers' Party cell. Having left no direct descendants, a nephew entered the family as an adopted son by family decision. When Colonel Park's adopted grandson, Reserve Brigadier General Park Cheol-gyun, applied for Colonel Park's national patriot registration, the MPVA approved it in October last year. The basis was that Colonel Park had received the Eulji Order of Military Merit in 1950 and 1952. (결혼 1년여 만에 제주에 부임한 박 대령은 한 달 후인 1948년 6월 남로당 세포였던 부하의 주동으로 암살당했다. 후손을 남기지 못해 집안 결정으로 조카가 양자로 들어갔다. 보훈부는 박 대령의 양손자인 박철균 예비역 준장이 박 대령의 국가유공자 등록을 신청하자, 지난해 10월 이를 승인했다. 박 대령이 1950년과 1952년 을지무공훈장을 받았다는 점이 근거였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to relevant laws, applications for national patriot status can only be made by the individual themselves or legal family members such as a spouse, children, or parents. Others are registered through deliberation and resolution by the MPVA's Patriots Review Committee. However, it is known that the MPVA has, in the past, approved registrations even when applied for by persons not legally considered family members, as long as no issues were found after procedures like verifying award records and checking for criminal history, without necessarily convening the Patriots Review Committee each time. (관련 법률에 따르면 국가유공자 신청은 본인이나 법률이 정한 유족인 배우자, 자녀, 부모 등만 할 수 있다. 그 외엔 보훈부 보훈심사위 심의·의결을 통해 등록한다. 그러나 보훈부는 그간 법률상 유족이 아닌 사람이 신청해도, 서훈 사실 및 범죄 경력 조회 등의 절차를 거쳐 문제가 없으면 보훈심사위를 일일이 열지 않고 등록을 승인해 온 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some bereaved families and organizations of victims of the April 3rd Incident have protested, claiming based on the testimony of a subordinate involved in Colonel Park's assassination that he was a 'chief perpetrator of the massacre.' The government had pursued a plan to review whether the awarding of the military merit medals, which served as the basis for the patriot registration, was appropriate and to cancel the registration, but faced difficulties as the related meritorious service records were not handed down. It then brought forward the logic that 'an adopted grandson is not eligible to apply for patriot registration.' The MPVA also conducted an internal audit targeting officials involved, on the grounds that Colonel Park's patriot registration was approved without going through the Patriots Review Committee. Reserve Brigadier General Park, the adopted grandson, told this newspaper in a phone call, "(The MPVA's logic) is really shabby," and stated, "There is testimony that Colonel Park never massacred civilians and records that the South Korean Workers' Party planned the assassination." (일부 4·3 사건 희생자 유가족과 단체들은 박 대령 암살에 가담한 부하의 진술을 근거로 그가 ‘학살 주범’이라고 주장하며 반발했다. 정부는 국가유공자 등록 근거가 된 무공훈장 수여가 적정했는지를 따져보고 국가유공자 등록을 취소하는 방안을 추진했지만 관련 공훈 기록이 전해지지 않아 어려움을 겪었다. 그러자 ‘양손자는 유공자 등록 신청 자격이 없다’는 논리를 들고나온 것이다. 보훈부는 보훈심사위를 거치지 않고 박 대령의 유공자 등록을 승인했다는 이유로 실무자 등에 대한 내부 감사도 실시했다. 양손자인 박 예비역 준장은 본지 통화에서 “(보훈부 논리가) 정말 군색하다”며 “박 대령이 민간인을 학살한 적 없다는 증언과 남로당이 암살을 계획한 기록이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/23/RW6LRAFBHBD6DI7BYLPFNCSMBA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7OTSORRC6ZGBDALILZ6NGOJMPQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea is sealing things off tightly... Jeong Dong-young says "All roads and railways to the continent must be opened" (北은 꽁꽁 틀어막는데…  정동영 “대륙으로 가는 모든 도로·철도 열어야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/23/6MVUF4KORJD7HLEYTINKQ3FABQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZXQWARHKORB2TD6ABWCAJ7BTT4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 22nd, Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young resumed the in-person meeting of the 'Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Promotion Council' after four years, stating, "We must lift the curtain of hostility and confrontation and reopen all roads and railways (via North Korea) to the continent." On the 13th, Kim Yo-jong, Vice Department Director of the Workers' Party of Korea, said the improvement in inter-Korean relations desired by the Unification Ministry was "an impossible delusion." A security expert commented, "While North Korea is building barriers north of the Demilitarized Zone (DMZ), Minister Jeong seems to be going his own way." (정동영 통일부 장관이 22일 ‘남북 교류 협력 추진 협의회(이하 교추협)’ 대면 회의를 4년 만에 재개하며 “적대와 대결의 장막을 걷어내고 (북한을 거쳐) 대륙으로 가는 모든 도로·철도를 다시 열어야 한다”고 말했다. 지난 13일 북한의 김여정 노동당 부부장은 통일부가 원하는 남북 관계 개선이 “실현 불가한 망상”이라고 했다. 한 안보 전문가는 “북한은 비무장지대(DMZ) 북쪽에 장벽을 쌓고 있는데 정 장관 혼자 ‘마이웨이’를 가는 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The in-person meeting of the Inter-Korean Exchange and Cooperation Promotion Council, which deliberates and coordinates inter-Korean exchange and cooperation policies, was last held in February 2022 during the Moon Jae-in administration and was subsequently replaced by written meetings during the Yoon Suk-yeol administration. Regarding the resumption of the in-person meeting, Minister Jeong said, "It is about rebuilding a house on the ruins of inter-Korean relations," adding, "We must also open the paths to Mount Kumgang, Kaesong, Wonsan-Kalma, and Samjiyon at Mount Paektu." He also mentioned the plan for a Seoul-Beijing high-speed rail construction disclosed during last month's presidential briefing. All of these are only possible if sanctions against North Korea are significantly eased or lifted. (남북 교류·협력 정책을 심의·조정하는 교추협 대면 회의는 문재인 정부 시절인 2022년 2월 열린 뒤, 윤석열 정부 시절 서면 회의로 대체됐다. 대면 회의 재개에 대해 정 장관은 “그동안 폐허가 돼버린 남북 관계 위에 다시 집을 짓겠다는 것”이라며 “금강산·개성, 원산·갈마, 백두산 삼지연으로 가는 길도 열어야 한다”고 했다. 지난달 대통령 업무 보고에서 밝힌 서울~베이징 간 고속철 건설 구상 등도 언급했다. 모두 대북 제재가 대폭 완화·해제돼야 가능한 일들이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day before, Minister Jeong visited the 'DMZ Peace Trail' in Goseong, Gangwon Province, and also stated, "We will reopen the sections inside the DMZ." The DMZ Peace Trail was created following the September 19 military agreement in 2018, which included provisions such as the 'complete withdrawal of adjacent guard posts (GPs) within the DMZ' during the inter-Korean summit. While most sections are located outside the southern part of the DMZ, some are inside it. In 2023, after North Korea nullified the September 19 agreement and began restoring GPs, the opening of the internal DMZ course was suspended in April 2024 due to security concerns. (정 장관은 전날 강원도 고성의 ‘DMZ 평화의 길’을 찾아 “DMZ 내부 구간을 다시 열겠다”고도 했다. DMZ 평화의 길은 2018년 남북 정상회담에서 ‘DMZ 내 인접 감시초소(GP) 완전 철수’ 등의 내용을 담은 9·19 군사합의가 체결되면서 조성됐다. 대부분 구간은 DMZ 남측 외부에 있지만 일부는 DMZ 안에 있다. 2023년 북한이 9·19 합의를 파기하고 GP 복원에 나서자, 2024년 4월 DMZ 내부 코스 개방은 안보 상황을 이유로 중단됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to Minister Jeong's remarks about reopening it, the United Nations Command (UNC), which holds control over access to the DMZ under the Armistice Agreement, stated, "Due to ongoing security considerations, access to the three courses inside the DMZ remains restricted," and "DMZ access policies and procedures will be maintained without change." This can be seen as effectively opposing the idea. (이를 다시 열자는 정 장관의 발언에 대해 정전협정상 DMZ 출입 통제권을 지닌 유엔사는 “현재도 지속 중인 안보상 고려 때문에 DMZ 내부 3개 코스는 출입이 제한돼 있다”며 “DMZ 출입 정책과 절차는 변경 없이 유지된다”고 밝혔다. 사실상 반대로 볼 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, the Unification Ministry initiated and then withdrew a legislative notice to transfer the Korea Institute for National Unification, under the Economic, Humanities and Social Sciences Research Council of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, to the ministry's jurisdiction without internal government coordination. During last month's presidential briefing, Minister Jeong requested the transfer by saying, "Give me a gift," but the Korea Institute for National Unification is known to have a negative stance on the matter. (최근 통일부는 정부 내 조율 없이 국무조정실 경제인문사회연구회 산하 통일연구원을 통일부 산하로 이관하는 입법예고를 했다가 철회하기도 했다. 정 장관은 지난달 대통령 업무 보고에서 “선물을 달라”며 이관을 부탁했지만, 통일연구원은 부정적 입장으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/23/6MVUF4KORJD7HLEYTINKQ3FABQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZXQWARHKORB2TD6ABWCAJ7BTT4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:50:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party and Cho Kuk Party Pursue Merger Ahead of Elections (선거 앞두고 민주·조국당 합당 추진)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/C2EQKTTE3JFGDDN3CD6LREPEBM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae unexpectedly proposed a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party on the 22nd. Cho Kuk, leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, stated, "We will discuss and decide according to the direction indicated by the people's hearts and intentions." With the June 3 local elections about four months away, the integration of the ruling bloc is expected to gain full momentum. (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 22일 조국혁신당에 전격적으로 합당을 제안했다. 조국혁신당 조국 대표는 “국민의 마음과 뜻이 가리키는 방향에 따라 논의하고 결정할 것”이라고 했다. 6·3 지방선거를 4개월여 앞두고 여권 통합이 본격화할 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Chung held an emergency press conference at the National Assembly that day, saying, "I propose to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. Let's merge with us," and added, "I hope a working-level table will be established promptly for the merger." Leader Chung noted, "The Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party fought together in the last presidential election for the launch of the Lee Jae-myung administration," and expressed, "I hope we can fight together in this local election as well." (정 대표는 이날 국회에서 긴급 기자회견을 열고 “조국혁신당에 제안한다. 우리와 합치자”며 “합당을 위해 조속히 실무 테이블이 만들어지길 바란다”고 했다. 정 대표는 “민주당은 조국혁신당과 이재명 정부 출범을 위한 지난 대선을 같이 치렀다”면서 “이번 지방선거도 같이 치렀으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Cho stated at a party meeting, "I met with Leader Chung late yesterday afternoon and received the merger proposal. It is sudden, but the weight of the proposal is by no means light." He continued, "The Cho Kuk Innovation Party fully agrees with the goals of the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the re-creation of the regime." (조국 대표는 당 회의에서 “어제 늦은 오후 정 대표를 만나 합당 제안을 전달받았다. 갑작스럽지만 제안의 무게가 결코 가볍지 않다”고 했다. 그러면서 “조국혁신당은 이재명 정부의 성공과 정권 재창출이라는 목표에 전적으로 동의한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cho Kuk Innovation Party was founded in March, just before the 2024 general election, led by Leader Cho, and secured 12 seats solely through proportional representation. If the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party merge this time, a massive ruling party with 174 seats will be born. (조국혁신당은 조 대표가 주도해 2024년 총선 직전인 3월 창당한 뒤 비례대표 국회의원으로만 12석을 얻었다. 이번에 민주당과 조국혁신당이 합치면 174석의 거대 여당이 탄생하는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/23/C2EQKTTE3JFGDDN3CD6LREPEBM/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 15:54:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The U.S., Obsessed Only with 'Ceasefire,' and the Hostile Chinese Communist Army Left Only South Korea in the Lurch (‘휴전’에만 매달린 미국과 험악한 중공군 사이 한국만 속탔다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/international/china/2026/01/23/CRL5GBGAU5BCZCQXUODVGGAHGQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NXRZ4H7ORZG7JMCJL3E2H3BPIY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Air superiority and sea control were the core keywords of the battlefield dominated by the U.S. military. In reality, the outcome of ground battles occurring within the strategic depth of the Korean Peninsula was inevitably determined by whether this air superiority and sea control were secured. China had a long supply line for equipment and materials sent from its own country to the front lines. Although the Korean Peninsula is small, as the line moving through its depth lengthened, it could not be free from U.S. aerial bombardment. (제공권(制空權)과 제해권(制海權)은 미군이 주도하는 전장(戰場)의 핵심 키워드였다. 실제 한반도 전략 종심(縱深)에서 벌어지는 육상 전투의 승패는 이 제공권과 제해권 확보 여부에 따라 갈릴 수밖에 없었다. 중국은 자국에서 전선으로 보내는 장비와 물자의 보급선이 길었다. 한반도가 작긴 하지만 종심으로 이동하는 선이 길어지자, 미군의 공중 폭격으로부터 자유로울 수 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The situation at sea was the same. With unmatched naval power, the U.S. military sailed the East Sea to Chongjin in North Hamgyong Province and areas north of it, and advanced to the mouth of the Yalu River in the West Sea, freely pouring on firepower. Therefore, the U.S. military could have continued to advance northward as much as they wanted if they so desired. Yet, they were very cautious about moving the front line northward. (바다 상황도 마찬가지였다. 상대가 되지 않는 해군력으로 미군은 동해 바다를 항행해 함경도 청진과 그 북쪽, 서해에서는 압록강 하구(河口)까지 나아가 자유롭게 화력(火力)을 퍼붓곤 했다. 따라서 미군은 마음만 먹으면 얼마든지 북진을 거듭할 수 있었다. 그럼에도 전선의 북상에는 매우 조심스러웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To restore the full functionality of the capital, Seoul, the strategic security of the Han River was necessary. For that, maintaining the Northern Limit Line (NLL) in the West Sea, where the Han River meets the Imjin River and flows out to the West Sea, and re-establishing an advance line covering the Imjin River area were again needed. Therefore, Paik Sun-yup, who became South Korea's first representative to the armistice talks, argued that the Yesong River must be recaptured. (수도 서울의 온전한 기능을 살리기 위해서는 한강의 전략적인 안전이 필요했다. 그를 위해서는 한강이 임진강과 만나 서해로 빠져나가는 서해 북방한계선(NLL)의 유지와 함께 임진강 일대를 커버하는 진출선이 다시 필요했다. 그래서 휴전회담 한국 첫 대표로 나선 백선엽은 예성강을 탈환해야 한다는 주장을 펼쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The North Korean delegation, led by Chief Representative Nam Il, merely repeated a stubborn position. They insisted, "Let's draw the armistice line at the pre-war 38th parallel." The UN delegation rejected the communist side's claim, stating that "the current battle line, created by the difference in military strength, is reasonable." However, they showed little interest in utilizing their overwhelming air superiority and sea control to push the front line further north. (남일을 수석대표로 하는 북한 대표단은 완고한 입장만 되풀이하고 있었다. 그들은 “전쟁 전의 38선을 휴전선으로 긋자”고 주장했다. 유엔 대표단은 공산 측의 주장을 일축하면서 “전력 차이로 생긴 현 전투선이 합리적”이라는 입장이었다. 그러나 막강한 제공권과 제해권을 활용해 전선을 더 북상시키는 데는 큰 관심을 기울이지 않는 편이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To Commander Matthew Ridgway, who frequently flew from Tokyo to Panmunjom to lead the armistice talks, Paik Sun-yup even suggested, "Since the communist side is stubbornly insisting on the 38th parallel as the armistice line, we should also advance to the Pyongyang–Wonsan line and make that the armistice line." There was no way Ridgway would accept that argument. (도쿄에서 판문점으로 자주 날아와 휴전회담을 이끄는 매슈 리지웨이 사령관에게 백선엽은 “공산 측이 38선을 휴전선으로 하자는 억지 주장을 펼치니, 우리도 평양~원산 선까지 진출해 그곳을 휴전선으로 삼아야 한다”는 제안을 하기도 했다. 리지웨이가 그 주장을 받아줄 리 없었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paik Sun-yup also said, "If we don't intend to abandon the Han River as a dead river, we must advance at least to the Yesong River." However, the U.S. administration, desperate to achieve an armistice by any means, and Ridgway, who faithfully represented it, did not change. (백선엽은 또 “한강을 죽은 강으로 버리지 않을 생각이면 예성강까지라도 진출해야 한다”고 했다. 하지만 어떻게든 휴전을 성사시키려는 미 행정부와 그를 충실히 대변하려는 리지웨이는 달라지지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean Chief Representative Lieutenant General Nam Il (Chief of the General Staff of the North Korean Army) was famous for chain-smoking cigarettes at the negotiating table. Often, the talks repeatedly stalled because he could not immediately receive instructions from the Pyongyang leadership, and when the talks resumed after several days, he was the type to create a certain impression with a grim expression and cigarettes constantly in his mouth. The near-curses he uttered every time he opened his mouth further solidified that unfavorable impression. North Korean Major General Lee Sang-jo, sitting opposite Paik Sun-yup, faithfully played the role of glaring at Paik Sun-yup across the table with a stern face. Another North Korean military representative, Jang Pyeong-san, was the same. (북한 수석 대표 남일 중장(북한군 총참모장)은 회담 석상에서 담배를 잇따라 피워 무는 것으로 유명했다. 평양 수뇌부 입장을 즉시 전달받지 못해 회담은 공전(空轉)을 거듭하기 일쑤였고, 며칠 걸렀다가 재개하는 회담에서 그는 험상궂은 표정에 잇따라 입에 무는 담배로 일정한 인상을 이루는 타입이었다. 입을 열 때마다 내뱉는 욕설에 가까운 발언도 그런 좋지 않은 인상을 더욱 굳혀갔다. 백선엽 맞은편에 앉은 북한 대표 이상조 소장은 굳은 얼굴로 맞은편 백선엽을 쏘아보는 역할에 충실했다. 다른 북한군 대표 장평산 역시 마찬가지였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One day, as the talks dragged on tediously, a bizarre scene unfolded. A black dung fly landed on Lee Sang-jo's face. During the armistice talks at that time, where only the chief representatives had the right to speak, both sides often faced each other in silence without much talk. That day too, both delegations were silently staring at each other without much comment. The dung fly sitting on Lee Sang-jo's face thus became a shared point of interest for our side's delegation. (회담이 지루하게 이어지던 어느 날, 기묘한 풍경이 펼쳐졌다. 이상조의 얼굴에 시커먼 똥파리가 앉았다. 수석 대표만이 발언권을 지니고 있던 당시 휴전회담에서 양측은 별다른 말 없이 침묵으로 대면하고 있을 때가 많았다. 그날도 양측 대표진이 별다른 발언 없이 상대와 침묵으로 마주 보고 있었다. 이상조의 얼굴에 앉은 똥파리는 따라서 아군 대표단의 공동 관심사로 떠올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That large dung fly began to crawl on Lee Sang-jo's face. Even though it must have stimulated his nerves, Lee Sang-jo remained motionless, intently focused only on glaring at Paik Sun-yup across from him. The dung fly crawled here and there on Lee Sang-jo's face, and Lee Sang-jo endured the filth and itchiness as if he were a superhuman. (그 몸집 큰 똥파리는 이상조의 얼굴에서 기어 다니기 시작했다. 신경줄을 자극했을 법한데도 이상조는 미동조차 없이 맞은편 백선엽을 쏘아보는 데만 열중하고 있었다. 그 똥파리는 이상조의 얼굴 이곳저곳을 기었고, 이상조는 마치 초인처럼 그 불결함과 가려움을 견뎌내고 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paik Sun-yup recalled that the dung fly on Lee Sang-jo's face was a major topic of conversation among the delegation members after they returned to our camp. The U.S. military delegation also closely observed that strange spectacle. Lee Sang-jo, with his grim expression meant to project a tough image, and the dung fly, were like symbols that well revealed the characteristic rigidity of the consistently stiff North Korean delegation. (이상조 얼굴의 똥파리는 아군 캠프로 돌아온 대표단 사이에서 커다란 화제였다고 백선엽은 술회했다. 미군 대표단도 그 희한한 광경을 자세히 지켜봤던 것이다. 딱딱한 인상을 풍기려고 험상궂은 표정을 짓는 북한 대표단의 이상조와 똥파리는 경직(硬直)으로 일관했던 북한 대표단의 속성을 잘 드러내는 상징과도 같았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deng Hua of the Chinese Communist delegation was the deputy commander of the Chinese Communist forces participating in the war. Under Commander-in-Chief Peng Dehuai, he was a powerful commander practically responsible for all the strategy and tactics of the Chinese Communist forces. The other Chinese Communist forces representative, Xie Fang, was Chief of Staff and Political Commissar. The two formed the complete opposite of the stiffness exuded by the North Korean delegation. They shrouded their faces with an inscrutable 'Chinese smile.' (중공 대표단의 덩화(鄧華)는 참전 중공군의 부사령관이었다. 펑더화이(彭德懷) 총사령관 밑에서 실질적으로 중공군의 전략과 전술을 모두 책임지는 유력한 지휘관이었다. 다른 중공군 대표 셰팡(解方)은 참모장 겸 정치위원이었다. 그 둘은 북한 대표단이 풍기는 딱딱함과는 정반대를 이뤘다. 그들은 속을 알 수 없는 ‘차이니스 스마일’로 얼굴을 감싸고 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The expressions of the Chinese Communist forces delegation, who did not reveal clear emotional states with faint smiles, created a very subtle contrast with the seemingly growling expressions of the North Korean delegation each time, somewhat soothing the atmosphere of the talks. Especially Xie Fang, who as Political Commissar led the political judgment of the Chinese Communist forces, in his own way also aroused the curiosity of the UN forces delegation. (엷은 미소로 뚜렷한 감정 상태를 드러내지 않는 중공군 대표단의 표정은 매번 으르렁거리는 듯했던 북한 대표단의 그것과 매우 미묘한 대조를 이루면서 회담장 분위기를 그나마 다독였다. 특히 정치위원으로서 중공군의 정치적 판단을 주도했던 셰팡은 나름대로 유엔군 대표단의 호기심을 끌기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major General Laurence C. Craigie, Deputy Commander of the Far East Air Force and a member of the talks delegation, asked Paik Sun-yup, "Please teach me one phrase of Chinese greeting." He thought of at least saying one greeting to Xie Fang, the Chinese Communist forces representative across from him, before entering the talks. Before sitting down upon entering the talks, Major General Craigie offered the Chinese greeting phrase he learned from Paik Sun-yup, and each time, Xie Fang responded with a faint smile. (회담 대표의 일원이었던 극동 미 공군 부사령관 로렌스 크레이기 소장은 백선엽에게 “중국어 인사법 한마디 가르쳐달라”고 했다. 회담에 들어서기 전 맞은편의 중공군 대표였던 셰팡에게 인사말이라도 한마디 건넬 생각이었다. 크레이기 소장은 회담에 들어서 자리에 앉기 전 백선엽으로부터 배운 중국어 인사말을 건넸고, 그럴 때마다 셰팡은 엷은 미소를 지으면서 화답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paik Sun-yup often recalled that these Chinese Communists, who gave the impression of being seasoned and repeatedly deliberate, were likely the behind-the-scenes leaders of the enemy camp in the armistice talks. Nevertheless, the chief representative was North Korea's Nam Il. He only repeated the position, "Let's draw the armistice line at the pre-war 38th parallel," and thus the talks repeatedly stalled without much progress. (그런 노련하면서 숙려(熟慮)를 거듭하는 듯한 인상의 중공군이 휴전회담의 적진 막후(幕後) 주도자였을 것으로 백선엽은 자주 회고했다. 그럼에도 수석대표는 북한 남일이 맡았다. 그는 내내 “전쟁 전의 38선으로 휴전선을 긋자”는 입장만 되풀이했고, 회담은 따라서 별다른 진전 없이 공회전만 거듭했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paik Sun-yup's argument that "we must recapture at least up to the Yesong River" was also completely disregarded, blocked by the U.S. administration's stance, which seemed to rush toward an armistice. The U.S. military leadership cited reasons that advancing north beyond the current front line would involve insufficient supply and significant troop casualties. Merely, the U.S. military only somewhat assuaged the South Korean government's suspicions by maintaining the current battle line created by the difference in military strength and leaving open the possibility of a northward advance of the front line, premised on strong air superiority and sea control. (“적어도 예성강까지는 탈환해야 한다”는 백선엽의 주장도 휴전을 서두르는 듯한 미 행정부의 입장에 막혀 전혀 고려되지 않았다. 미군 수뇌부는 현 전선을 넘어 북상하기에는 보급이 부족하고, 병력 희생도 클 것이라는 이유를 내세웠다. 단지, 미군은 전력 차이로 벌어진 현재의 전투선을 유지하면서 강력한 제공권과 제해권을 전제로 전선 북상의 가능성을 열어 둠으로써 한국 정부의 의구심을 어느 정도 달래주기만 할 뿐이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Paik Sun-yup General Memorial Foundation, a incorporated foundation established to promote and inherit General Paik Sun-yup's patriotic spirit, is opening a lecture on the topic of 'Paik Sun-yup's Battlefield Leadership.' We invite 40 Chosun Ilbo membership members to this event. (백선엽 장군의 구국정신을 선양하고 계승하기 위해 만든 재단법인 백선엽장군기념재단에서 ‘백선엽의 전쟁터 리더십‘을 주제로 강연회를 엽니다. 이 행사에 조선일보 멤버십 회원 40분을 초대합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foundation director and writer Yoo Gwang-jong (former JoongAng Ilbo Beijing correspondent) will provide a multidimensional look at how General Paik Sun-yup grafted and practiced the 'wave of civilization' brought by the participating U.S. forces onto this land amidst the turbulent waves of the Korean War.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (재단 이사인 유광종 작가(전 중앙일보 베이징 특파원)가 백선엽 장군이 6·25전쟁 격랑 속에서 참전 미군이 몰고 온 ‘문명의 물결’을 어떻게 이 땅에 접목하고 실천해 나갔는지를 입체적으로 살펴보는 내용입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/international/china/2026/01/23/CRL5GBGAU5BCZCQXUODVGGAHGQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NXRZ4H7ORZG7JMCJL3E2H3BPIY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>