<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:32:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Amidst This, Jang Dong-hyeok Makes Another 'Yoon Again' Personnel Appointment (이 와중에 장동혁은 또 ‘윤어게인’ 인사)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/SGZYQ6POMFAURKAU7LNVHAPFOI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Amidst This, Jang Dong-hyeok Makes Another 'Yoon Again' Personnel Appointment (이 와중에 장동혁은 또 ‘윤어게인’ 인사)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HVNHSIGTH5ONPAA4OBIDBOXMRU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was confirmed on the 15th that People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok has appointed Choi Jin-woong, former Presidential Message Secretary who handled messages for former President Yoon Suk Yeol, as the party leader's Message Office Chief. Within the party, concerns have been raised that "this could be seen as appointing figures close to former President Yoon to key positions." (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 당대표 메시지실장에 윤석열 전 대통령 메시지를 담당했던 최진웅 전 국정메시지비서관을 기용한 것으로 15일 확인됐다. 당내에서는 “주요 보직에 윤 전 대통령과 가까운 인사들을 임명하는 것으로 보일 수 있다”는 우려가 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Choi was appointed as a Presidential Message Secretary at the Presidential Office at the end of 2023. When the impeachment trial against former President Yoon began in December 2024, he submitted his resignation and supported the public relations work of former President Yoon's legal defense team. This was the first case of a Presidential Office aide resigning to support legal defense work. (최 실장은 2023년 말 대통령실 국정메시지비서관에 임명됐다. 2024년 12월 윤 전 대통령에 대한 탄핵 심판이 시작되자 사직서를 내고 윤 전 대통령 변호인단의 공보 업무를 지원했다. 대통령실 참모가 변호 업무를 지원하겠다며 사표를 낸 첫 사례였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A former broadcasting writer, he was in charge of messages for candidate Park Geun-hye during the 2007 Grand National Party presidential primary and the 2012 presidential election, and served as a Cheong Wa Dae Speech Recording Secretary. A party official stated, "Former Secretary Choi didn't only work in the Yoon Presidential Office; he has worked in this party for 30 years, including in the Park Geun-hye Cheong Wa Dae," adding, "He is a representative message expert for the party, so there should be no issue with the appointment." (방송 작가 출신인 그는 2007년 한나라당 대선 경선과 2012년 대선 당시 박근혜 후보 메시지를 담당했고, 청와대 연설기록비서관을 지냈다. 당 관계자는 “최 전 비서관은 윤 대통령실에만 있었던 게 아니라 박근혜 청와대 등 이 당에서 30년을 일한 사람”이라며 “당의 대표적인 메시지 전문가라 인사에 문제될 게 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The appointment of former announcer Lee Ji-ae as 'Media Spokesperson' by leader Jang on the 12th is also controversial. In a video posted on her YouTube channel last month on the first anniversary of the martial law declaration, Spokesperson Lee said, "I realized that the liberal democracy of the Republic of Korea is under threat and learned that the infiltration of anti-state forces is serious," adding, "I thank you (former President Yoon) for waking us up. You are our president." Media Spokesperson Park Min-young, who caused controversy by referring to the concerns of the party's standing advisory committee regarding the disciplinary action against former leader Han Dong-hoon as "the denunciation of advisors with an average age of 91," is also a former administrative officer from the Yoon Suk Yeol Presidential Office. Spokesperson Park caused controversy last November by saying on YouTube that "there is a problem with allocating too many (proportional representation seats) to the disabled," and submitted her resignation, but leader Jang only issued a warning and rejected the resignation. (장 대표가 지난 12일 ‘미디어 대변인’으로 임명한 이지애 전 아나운서도 논란이다. 이 대변인은 지난달 계엄 1주년 때 자신의 유튜브에 올린 영상에서 “대한민국 자유민주주의가 위협받고 있다는 것을 깨달았고 반국가 세력의 침투가 심각하다는 것을 알게 됐다”며 “우리를 잠에서 깨워준 당신(윤 전 대통령)께 감사드린다. 우리의 대통령은 당신입니다”라고 했다. 한동훈 전 대표 징계에 대한 당 상임고문단의 우려를 “평균 연령 91세 고문님들의 성토”라고 해 논란이 된 박민영 미디어 대변인도 윤석열 대통령실 행정관 출신이다. 박 대변인은 지난해 11월 유튜브에서 “장애인을 너무 많이 (비례대표에) 할당해서 문제”라고 해 논란이 되자 사표를 제출했지만 장 대표가 경고만 하고 사표는 반려했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, there is even talk of a 'Han Dong-hoon encirclement personnel' strategy, as leader Jang is placing figures from the old 'pro-Yoon faction' with anti-Han Dong-hoon leanings in key party positions. Assemblyman Jeong Jeom-sik, appointed as party policy committee chair, and former Gyeonggi Namyangju Mayor Cho Gwang-han, appointed as a designated Supreme Council member, opposed the impeachment of former President Yoon and had clashed with former leader Han Dong-hoon in the past. People Power Party Assemblyman Kim Jae-seop said on a radio program on the 13th, "If you exclude all (traditional) conservative voters from the support base and mistake those who are enthusiastic about former President Yoon Suk Yeol as the support base, then you are not qualified to be a leader."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (당내에선 장 대표가 반한동훈 성향의 옛 ‘친윤계’를 주요 당직에 배치하면서 ‘한동훈 포위 인사’라는 말까지 나온다. 당 정책위의장에 임명된 정점식 의원, 지명직 최고위원에 임명된 조광한 전 경기 남양주시장은 윤 전 대통령 탄핵에 반대하고, 과거 한동훈 전 대표와 대립했었다. 김재섭 국민의힘 의원은 13일 라디오에 나와 “(전통적인) 보수층을 전부 지지층에서 배제해 놓고 윤석열 전 대통령에게 열광하는 사람들을 지지층으로 착각하면 그건 지도자 자격이 없는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/SGZYQ6POMFAURKAU7LNVHAPFOI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HVNHSIGTH5ONPAA4OBIDBOXMRU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee: "Internal division will turn achievements into bubbles"... Was he targeting the hardliners in the ruling party? (李 “내부 분열땐 성과 물거품”… 與강경파 겨눴나)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/VAIYN2EPMBG3PGUCQUUMQM6JQY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee: "Internal division will turn achievements into bubbles"... Was he targeting the hardliners in the ruling party? (李 “내부 분열땐 성과 물거품”… 與강경파 겨눴나)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GEZTKYRUGIZWEY3CMJTGENLGGE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 13th, "If we are divided and in conflict internally, we will not be able to protect national interests against external headwinds, and it is clear that even the diplomatic achievements we have worked hard for will turn into bubbles." (이재명 대통령은 13일 “우리 내부가 분열하고 반목한다면 외풍에 맞서 국익을 지킬 수 없고, 애써 거둔 외교 성과조차 물거품이 될 게 분명하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a meeting of senior secretaries at the Blue House that day, President Lee said, "The government, the National Assembly, and both ruling and opposition parties are all joint entities responsible for state affairs on behalf of the sovereign people," and made these remarks. He added, "Please go beyond minor differences and demonstrate the spirit of responsible politics that prioritizes national interests." This is his first official message since returning from his visit to Japan. Regarding this, the Blue House explained that it was a remark aimed at the People Power Party's criticism that "although there was a lot of fuss, almost no substantive diplomatic or security benefits were secured." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 수석보좌관 회의를 주재하고 “정부와 국회, 여야 모두는 주권자를 대리해 국정을 책임지는 공동의 주체”라며 이같이 말했다. 이어 “작은 차이를 넘어 국익 우선의 책임 정치 정신을 발휘해 달라”고 했다. 일본 순방을 다녀온 뒤 첫 공식 메시지다. 이를 두고 청와대에선 “호들갑을 떨었지만 실질적인 외교·안보 이익은 거의 확보하지 못했다”는 국민의힘 비판을 겨냥한 발언이라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, there is also an interpretation that the 'internal division' mentioned by President Lee was aimed at the Democratic Party. Hardliners within the Democratic Party are saying they will completely overhaul the Prosecution Service and Major Crimes Investigation Agency (MCIA) establishment bill announced by the government on the 12th, calling it a "second Prosecutors' Office Act." Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae is also supporting the hardliners, stating that "the government's proposal is not a finalized bill but a draft," and even mentioned holding a public debate. Within the ruling party, there are comments about "signs of another conflict between the pro-Lee (pro-Lee Jae-myung) and pro-Jeong (pro-Jeong Cheong-rae) factions." (다만 이 대통령이 언급한 ‘우리 내부의 분열’은 민주당을 겨냥한 것이란 해석도 나온다. 민주당 강경파는 정부가 지난 12일 발표한 공소청과 중대범죄수사청(중수청) 설치 법안에 대해 “제2의 검찰청법”이라며 다 뜯어고치겠다고 하고 있다. 정청래 대표도 강경파에 힘을 싣고 “정부안은 확정된 법안이 아니라 초안”이라면서 대국민 토론회까지 언급한 상황이다. 여권 내에선 “또 명·청 갈등 조짐”이라는 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government's proposal is known to have been led by Blue House Senior Secretary for Civil Affairs Bong Wook. Hardliners within the ruling party are calling for "Senior Secretary Bong's resignation," citing issues such as the dual-track system of investigators in the MCIA divided into legal and non-legal professionals and the provision allowing prosecutors in the Prosecution Service room for supplementary investigation rights. It is said that at the Democratic Party's closed general meeting of lawmakers that day, some lawmakers also protested, asking if this wasn't a transformation of the prosecution structure. (정부안은 청와대 봉욱 민정수석이 주도해 온 것으로 알려졌는데, 여권 강경파는 중수청의 법률가와 비법률가로 나눈 수사관 이원화와 공소청 검사에게 보완 수사권을 허용할 여지를 둔 점 등을 들어 “봉 수석은 사퇴하라”고 하고 있다. 이날 민주당 비공개 의원총회에서도 일부 의원은 ‘검찰 구조의 변형이 아니냐’며 항의했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is an uncomfortable atmosphere at the Blue House. President Lee Jae-myung has instructed that the party's opinions be gathered first regarding the hardliners' backlash. A ruling party official said, "Isn't Senior Secretary Bong's position precisely President Lee Jae-myung's thinking?" and added, "Since the hardliners cannot directly target President Lee, they are targeting Senior Secretary Bong." Within the Democratic Party, there are also voices urging caution towards the hardliners. Lawmaker Kim Nam-hee said, "We cannot solve this complex equation by making the exclusion of a specific group (the prosecution) the goal of policy." Justice Minister Jeong Seung-ho, who participated in preparing the government proposal, 'liked' Rep. Kim's post. (청와대는 불편한 기류다. 이재명 대통령은 강경파 반발에 우선 당 의견을 수렴하라고 지시한 상태다. 여권 관계자는 “봉 수석의 입장이 곧 이재명 대통령 생각 아니겠냐”며 “강경파도 이 대통령을 직접 겨냥할 수 없으니 봉 수석을 겨냥하는 것”이라고 했다. 민주당에선 강경파를 향해 신중해야 한다는 목소리도 나온다. 김남희 의원은 “특정 집단(검찰)을 배제하는 것을 정책의 목표로 삼는 것으로 이 복잡한 방정식을 풀 수 없다”고 했다. 정부안 마련에 참여한 정성호 법무부 장관은 김 의원 글에 ‘좋아요’를 눌렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/VAIYN2EPMBG3PGUCQUUMQM6JQY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GEZTKYRUGIZWEY3CMJTGENLGGE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hye-hoon Submits Family Blood Donation Records, Omits Property Details (재산 내역은 쏙 빼고, 가족 헌혈 기록 제출한 이혜훈)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/SL722FTTW5ANHEPP2WSWIIDWWQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee Hye-hoon Submits Family Blood Donation Records, Omits Property Details (재산 내역은 쏙 빼고, 가족 헌혈 기록 제출한 이혜훈)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2CCVFYQYIJGFRCAWDGV345AH3U.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 15th, it was confirmed that Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, has refused to submit a significant portion of the materials requested by the opposition party, citing personal information, ahead of the National Assembly confirmation hearing scheduled for the 19th. The nominee is facing various allegations, including abuse of power towards her staff during her time as a lawmaker, real estate speculation, improper subscription for an apartment in Seoul's Banpo district, and her son's paper through 'professor dad chance'. However, it is reported that she did not submit materials related to these suspicions and only submitted documents such as the number of times her family participated in blood donations. Following the People Power Party and the Reform Party, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party also urged the nominee to step down on this day. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자가 오는 19일 국회 인사청문회를 앞두고 야당이 요청하는 자료 상당 부분을 개인 정보라는 이유로 제출하지 않은 것으로 15일 확인됐다. 이 후보자는 국회의원 시절 보좌진을 향한 갑질, 부동산 투기, 서울 반포 아파트 부정 청약, ‘교수 아빠 찬스’를 통한 아들 논문 등 각종 의혹이 제기된 상태다. 하지만 이와 관련한 자료는 내지 않고 가족이 헌혈에 참여한 횟수 등과 같은 자료만 제출했다고 한다. 국민의힘과 개혁신당에 이어 조국혁신당도 이날 이 후보자 사퇴를 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party criticized the nominee's failure to submit materials on this day and argued for a postponement of the confirmation hearing. Earlier, the ruling and opposition parties agreed that if the submission of materials was insufficient by 5 PM on the 15th, the hearing date (the 19th) could be postponed. The nominee submitted 748 out of the 2,187 items of data requested by the National Assembly, but among them, 415 items were effectively not submitted due to 'non-consent to provide personal information'. The data submission rate was only 15%. For this reason, the People Power Party takes the position that it is difficult to verify matters such as the process of the nominee and her spouse's wealth accumulation. (국민의힘은 이날 이 후보자의 자료 미제출을 비판하며 인사청문회 연기를 주장했다. 앞서 여야는 15일 오후 5시까지 자료 제출이 미흡할 경우 청문회 날짜(19일)를 미룰 수 있다고 합의한 바 있다. 이 후보자는 국회가 의결한 자료 2187건 가운데 &lt;b&gt;748건을 제출했지만, 그 중 415건을&lt;/b&gt; ‘개인 정보 제공 미동의’로&lt;b&gt; 사실상&lt;/b&gt; 제출하지 않았다. 자료 제출율이 15%에 그친 것이다. 이 때문에 국민의힘은 이 후보자 부부의 재산 형성 과정 등 검증이 어렵다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allegations against the nominee continued to emerge on this day. When suspicions arose that her eldest son received a 'living expense scholarship' for six years during his university days, Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, posted on Facebook, "I hope they will be verified with the same standard (as my daughter, who was investigated regarding scholarships)." A 'memorandum' also surfaced, alleging that the nominee contacted then-Seoul Central District Prosecutors' Office chief Yoon Suk-yeol in 2017 to quash an investigation into suspicions of illegal political funds. The nominee stated, "There is no way I wrote such a memorandum, and I have never written one." (이 후보자 의혹은 이날도 나왔다. 장남이 대학생 시절 6년간 ‘생활비 장학금’을 받았다는 의혹이 나오자, 조국혁신당 조국 대표는 페이스북에 “(장학금 관련 수사를 받았던 내 딸과) 똑같은 잣대로 검증하길 바란다”고 했다. 이 후보자가 2017년 자신의 불법 정치자금 의혹 수사를 무마하기 위해 윤석열 당시 서울중앙지검장을 접촉했다는 내용의 ‘비망록’도 나왔다. 이 후보자는 “제가 그런 비망록을 썼을 리도 없고, 쓴 적도 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Presidential Office and the Democratic Party maintain, for now, that they will observe the hearing. Kim Nam-joon, the Presidential Office spokesperson, said on MBC Radio this day, "The nominee herself should provide an explanation to the public, and the public should be allowed to make a judgment based on that." (청와대와 민주당은 아직까진 청문회를 지켜보겠다는 입장이다. 김남준 청와대 대변인은 이날 MBC라디오에서 “후보자 본인이 국민께 소명을 드리고, 이에 대해 국민이 판단할 수 있도록 해야 할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/SL722FTTW5ANHEPP2WSWIIDWWQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/2CCVFYQYIJGFRCAWDGV345AH3U.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Ambassador Muccio, Who Engaged in a Fierce Debate with Syngman Rhee, Pointed Out "Your Mistake" Three Times (이승만과 격렬한 논쟁 벌인 무초 미국대사, “당신네 잘못” 3차례나 지적)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/international/china/2026/01/16/UECVYI2GMJFKHM7HE63EH4EE4E/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;U.S. Ambassador Muccio, Who Engaged in a Fierce Debate with Syngman Rhee, Pointed Out "Your Mistake" Three Times (이승만과 격렬한 논쟁 벌인 무초 미국대사, “당신네 잘못” 3차례나 지적)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SGNRQVQJDZCATBJGIL3OY4EQK4.png" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The armistice talks that began in Kaesong in July 1951 dragged on tediously. With the Communists' actions, bordering on 'petty tricks,' irritating the nerves of the Allied forces, only a few incidents were reported by the media. The talks were already devolving into nothing but petty squabbles. However, behind the scenes, a power struggle was first brewing among the Allied forces participating in the talks. The topic of 'how to draw the armistice line' was a very heated point of contention from the start within the Allied camp, particularly between the Republic of Korea and the United States, which was directing the overall war. It was also an issue that needed to be resolved before negotiations with the Communist side. (1951년 7월 개성에서 벌어진 휴전회담은 지루하게 이어졌다. 공산 측의 ‘잔꾀’에 가까운 행위들이 아군의 신경을 자극하면서 몇 가지 해프닝만이 언론을 통해 알려지는 정도였다. 회담은 벌써 치졸한 말싸움으로만 번지고 있었다. 그러나 막후에서는 회담에 임하는 아군 진영 사이의 기 싸움이 먼저 번지고 있었다. ‘휴전선을 어떻게 그을까’라는 주제는 처음부터 아군 진영, 특히 대한민국과 전쟁 전반을 지휘하는 미국 사이의 매우 뜨거운 논쟁거리였다. 공산 측과 담판에 앞서 먼저 해결해야 할 대목이기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The armistice talks began on July 10, 1951, but there was virtually no progress. Before sitting down with the Communist camp to discuss an armistice, there was almost no 'consensus' between South Korea and the United States. This was especially true regarding how to demarcate the armistice line. It was July 16, six days after the talks began. In Kaesong, the UN Command delegation sat across from the Communist camp, but again, there was little gain. Paik Sun-yup's armistice diary records that after concluding the day's talks with the Communists, he suddenly visited the U.S. Eighth Army headquarters in Dongseong-dong, Seoul, by helicopter. (휴전회담을 시작한 날은 1951년 7월 10일이었으나 사실상 진전은 거의 없었다. 공산 진영과 마주 앉아 휴전을 논하기 전에 사실 한국과 미국 사이에는 ‘공감대’가 거의 없었다. 휴전선을 어떻게 획정하느냐에 대해서 특히 그랬다. 회담이 벌어진 지 6일이 지난 7월 16일이었다. 개성에서 유엔군 대표단은 공산 진영과 마주 앉았으나 역시 별다른 소득은 없었다. 백선엽이 적은 휴전 일지에는 이날 공산 진영과의 회담을 마친 뒤 돌연 헬리콥터 편으로 서울 동숭동 미 8군 사령부를 방문한 기록이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a meeting for South Korea and the United States to exchange opinions ahead of the full-fledged armistice talks. Having been notified in advance, Paik Sun-yup finished the talks in Kaesong at 3 PM and boarded a helicopter heading for Seoul. Attendees at the meeting were President Syngman Rhee, Defense Minister Lee Ki-poong, UN Command Commander-in-Chief Matthew Ridgway, U.S. Ambassador to Korea John Muccio, Lieutenant General John B. Coulter, U.S. Eighth Army Chief of Staff (Major General) Hank Hodges, who was also a representative to the armistice talks, and Paik Sun-yup. (본격적인 휴전회담을 앞두고 한국과 미국이 의견을 교환하기 위한 자리였다. 미리 통보를 받은 백선엽은 오후 3시 개성에서 회담을 마치고 헬리콥터에 올라 서울로 향한다. 회담 참석자는 이승만 대통령, 이기붕 국방장관, 매슈 리지웨이 유엔군 총사령관, 존 무초 주한 미국 대사, 존 B. 콜터 중장, 휴전회담 대표이기도 했던 행크 호디스 미 8군 참모부장(소장), 그리고 백선엽이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting began at 5 PM. According to the diary, Major General Hank Hodges first gave a briefing. He reportedly began drawing lines on a map. After first marking the Allied forces' sea control and air control, he finally seemed to draw the line representing 'U.S. intentions.' That line reportedly headed from south of Goseong, Gangwon Province, through Kimhwa, Cheorwon, and towards the Imjin River. It was the line where they were currently engaged in combat with the enemy. As the line was drawn by Major General Hodges' hand, the atmosphere seemed to grow very heavy. (회담 시작은 오후 5시였다. 일지에 따르면 먼저 행크 호디스 소장이 브리핑을 했다. 그는 지도에다가 선을 긋기 시작했다고 한다. 아군의 제해권(制海權)과 제공권(制空權)을 먼저 표시하면서 그는 마침내 ‘미국의 의도’를 선으로 그어갔던 모양이다. 그 선은 강원도 고성 남방~김화~철원~임진강을 향했다고 한다. 현재 적과 교전을 벌이고 있는 선이었다. 호디스 소장의 손에 따라 선이 그어지면서 분위기는 매우 가라앉았던 듯하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The armistice diary records President Syngman Rhee's remarks as follows: "Why not advance a bit (further)? Why not go all the way to the Amnok (Yalu) and Tuman (Tumen) Rivers?" This was akin to the President's unwavering conviction. The President was retorting to UN Command Commander-in-Chief General Ridgway. (휴전 일지는 이승만 대통령의 발언을 이렇게 적고 있다. “왜 좀(더) 전진하지 아니하냐? 왜 압록강과 두만강까지 가지 아니 하려는가?” 이 대통령의 결코 굽히지 않는 소신과도 같았다. 대통령은 유엔군 총사령관 리지웨이 대장에게 반문(反問)하고 있었던 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, only Ridgway's cold reply came back. The diary notes he emphasized, "Are you telling us to be surrounded (by the enemy)? Advancing further than this will disperse our forces. Also, there are no good supply routes. We need supply lines and logistical units for massive supplies (which we cannot currently provide), so it's difficult." Furthermore, Ridgway added, "This armistice plan is our government's policy." (그러나 리지웨이의 냉정한 답만 돌아왔다. “우리더러 (적에게) 포위당하라는 말인가? 이상 더 전진하면 부대가 분산(分散)된다. 또한 좋은 보급로가 없다. 막대한 보급품에 대한 보급선(과) 병참부대가 더욱 필요한데 (현재 갖출 수 없으니) 곤란하다”고 강조했다고 적고 있다. 아울러 리지웨이는 “이 휴전 계획은 우리 정부의 정책이다”라는 점을 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this small meeting, President Syngman Rhee 'consistently and persistently' rejected the U.S. position, Paik Sun-yup's armistice diary records. However, the atmosphere seemed to be growing very heated. The speaker in the armistice diary shifts from Ridgway to John Muccio, who was then the U.S. Ambassador to Korea. It seems he stepped in as President Rhee's unwavering arguments unfolded. (이 작은 회담에서 이승만 대통령은 미국의 이 같은 입장을 ‘종시일관(終始一貫)’ 부인했다고 백선엽의 휴전 일지는 적고 있다. 그러나 분위기는 매우 격해지고 있었던 듯하다. 휴전 일지 속 화자(話者)는 리지웨이에서 당시 주한 미국 대사였던 존 무초로 바뀌고 있었다. 이승만 대통령의 한결같은 주장이 펼쳐지자 그가 나섰던 듯하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The diary notes, "Ambassador Muccio emphasized his own country's national policy, telling (the President) 'your mistake' on three occasions." 'Your mistake' was a suddenly appearing accusatory remark. Judging from the context, it appears to have been a dispute over responsibility for the UN forces' northward advance at the end of 1950, the Chinese Communist forces' intervention, and the subsequent overall collapse of the Allied front line. Paik Sun-yup's brief comment in the diary immediately follows: "One could not bear to see the President's distress and could not hold back tears." (일지는 “무초 대사(가) 3차에 걸쳐 (이 대통령에게) ‘당신네 잘못(your mistake)’이라며 자국의 국책임을 강조했다”고 적고 있다. ‘당신네 잘못’은 갑자기 등장한 힐난조 발언이다. 문맥을 보면 1950년 말에 벌어진 유엔군의 북진, 중공군의 참전에 이어진 아군 전선의 전반적인 붕괴에 관한 책임 공방이었으리라고 보인다. 일지를 적는 백선엽의 짧은 평이 곧 이어진다. “이 대통령의 고충 눈으로 볼 수 없으며, 눈물을 금할 수 없었음”이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To put it simply, at that day's small gathering, the picture was dark: South Korea's President Syngman Rhee, who sought to achieve unification through continued northward advance, received strong rebukes and rebuttals from General Ridgway, the spokesperson for the U.S. administration seeking to solidify the war at the current front, and from the U.S. Ambassador to Korea. (쉽게 풀어 적자면, 이날 작은 모임에서 지속적인 북진에 이은 통일 달성을 추구했던 한국의 이승만 대통령은 전쟁을 현재 전선에서 고착화하려는 미 행정부의 대변인 리지웨이 총사령관과 주한 미국 대사로부터 강한 질책과 반박을 받는 어두운 그림이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In that atmosphere, which must have been very heavy, Paik Sun-yup's turn to speak seems to have arrived. His content first refuted Ambassador Muccio's point about 'your mistake.' He first explained "the failure of the U.S. Military Advisory Group, (its) intention not to strengthen the (Korean) army." For example, it meant that without bold support from the U.S. Military Advisory Group, the Korean army could not develop a high level of combat capability. He then "explained the operational failures of the U.S. Eighth Army and the U.S. X Corps last autumn," the diary notes. It also records he "emphasized the Sinanju-Hamhung, Wonsan-Pyongyang lines." (아주 가라앉았을 법한 그날의 분위기에서 백선엽의 발언 기회가 찾아왔던 모양이다. 무초 대사의 ‘당신네 잘못’이라는 지적을 논박하는 내용이 우선이었다. 그는 “미 군사고문단의 실책, (한)국군을 강화하여 주지 않은 뜻”을 먼저 설명했다. 이를 테면, 미 군사고문단의 과감한 지원이 없어 한국군이 고도의 전투력을 갖출 수 없었다는 내용이었다. 그는 이어 “지난해 가을 미 8군과 미 10군단의 작전 실패를 설명”했다고 적었다. 아울러 “신안주와 함흥, 원산과 평양선을 강조했다”고 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus, the thread of the fierce debate that erupted between President Syngman Rhee and Muccio is grasped. It can be seen that the two clashed over responsibility for the UN forces' powerless retreat following the Chinese Communist forces' intervention in December 1950. In response to Ambassador Muccio's three-time remark of 'your mistake,' Paik Sun-yup stepped forward to conversely point out the painful failures of the U.S. Eighth Army and the U.S. X Corps responsible for the eastern front, which failed to preemptively secure the defensive lines connecting Sinanju-Hamhung and Pyongyang-Wonsan. President Syngman Rhee soon had to return to the temporary Gyeongmudae in Busan. Keeping in mind the opinion gap between the two sides that was extremely difficult to bridge, the President reportedly left with the remark, "I will reply later in writing (regarding my position on this issue)." It was by no means a pleasant meeting. (이로써 이승만 대통령과 무초 사이에 벌어졌던 격한 논쟁의 실마리가 잡힌다. 두 사람은 1950년 12월 중공군 참전에 이어진 유엔군의 무기력한 후퇴의 책임을 두고 대립했음을 알 수 있다. ‘당신네 잘못’이라는 무초 대사의 3차례에 이은 발언을 두고 백선엽은 신안주~함흥, 평양~원산을 잇는 방어선 선제적 확보에 실패한 미 8군과 동부전선 담당 미 10군단의 뼈아픈 실책을 거꾸로 지적하고 나섰던 것이다. 이승만 대통령은 곧 부산의 임시 경무대로 돌아가야 했다. 양측 간의 결코 좁히기 힘든 의견 차이를 염두에 뒀던 이 대통령은 “나중에 서류로 (이 문제에 관한 입장에 대해) 회답하겠다”는 발언을 남기고 귀환했다고 일지는 적었다. 결코 유쾌하지 않은 자리였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus, a deep-seated friction, not easily apparent on the surface, was developing between South Korea and the United States. President Syngman Rhee consistently advocated for 'northward advance and unification' until the actual armistice agreement was reached, and he was always in conflict with the United States, which sought to suppress him, compromise at the current front, and stabilize the war situation. That 'spark' was gradually growing, and its origins are well revealed even in the armistice diary written by Paik Sun-yup. (그렇듯 한국과 미국 사이에는 겉으로는 좀체 드러나지 않은 깊은 알력이 생겨나고 있었다. 이승만 대통령은 실제 휴전 협정이 이뤄지기 전까지 늘 ‘북진통일’을 주장했고, 그를 누르고 현 전선에서 타협해 전쟁 국면을 안정시키려는 미국과 항상 갈등을 벌였다. 그 ‘불씨’가 조금씩 커져가고 있었으며, 그 단초는 백선엽이 적은 휴전 일지에서도 잘 드러나고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paik Sun-yup had to tread carefully. As a soldier of the Republic of Korea, he had to uphold the will of President Syngman Rhee, the commander-in-chief, yet he could not defy the U.S. military, which wielded immense power on the actual front. He had to grasp the major principle of 'just cause and principle,' yet he could not afford to lose the 'substance' that filled it. In that sense, the armistice talks were a test of a completely different nature for Paik Sun-yup. As the talks continued, his worries only deepened.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (백선엽은 조심스레 행보(行步)해야 옳았다. 대한민국 군인으로 통수권자인 이승만 대통령의 뜻을 받들어야 했으나, 실제 전선에서 막강한 힘을 행사하는 미군을 거스를 수도 없었다. ‘명분과 원칙’이라는 큰 줄기도 잡아야 했으나, 그를 채워가는 ‘실(實)’을 놓칠 수도 없는 노릇이었다. 휴전 회담은 그런 의미에서 백선엽에게는 전혀 다른 성질의 시험대이기도 했다. 회담이 이어질수록 고민은 더 깊어만 갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/international/china/2026/01/16/UECVYI2GMJFKHM7HE63EH4EE4E/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SGNRQVQJDZCATBJGIL3OY4EQK4.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Disadvantageous Special Prosecution Dismissed... Ruling Party Submits 'Second Special Prosecution' (불리한 특검은 뭉개고… 與 ‘2차 특검’ 상정)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/GVGLLLAN7JC2DFBBKB5AWB2L4U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Disadvantageous Special Prosecution Dismissed... Ruling Party Submits 'Second Special Prosecution' (불리한 특검은 뭉개고… 與 ‘2차 특검’ 상정)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/STOBBCMV5BPN3I64SGZQGSGSIQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea submitted the 'Second Comprehensive Special Prosecution Act (Special Prosecution Act for the Investigation of the Truth Regarding Acts of Rebellion, Foreign Interference, and State Affairs Manipulation by Yoon Suk-yeol and Kim Keon-hee)' to the National Assembly plenary session on the 15th. Last month, the months-long investigation by the three major special prosecutions (Rebellion, Kim Keon-hee, Marine Corps) concluded, and the special prosecution sought the death penalty for former President Yoon Suk-yeol on the 13th. However, ahead of the June local elections, the Democratic Party has brought out a second special prosecution again, stating they will "completely liquidate the rebellion." (더불어민주당은 15일 국회 본회의에 ‘2차 종합 특검법(윤석열·김건희에 의한 내란·외환 및 국정 농단 행위의 진상 규명을 위한 특검법)‘을 상정했다. 지난달 수개월에 걸친 3대 특검(내란·김건희·해병대원) 수사가 종료됐고 특검은 지난 13일 윤석열 전 대통령에게 사형을 구형했다. 하지만 민주당은 6월 지방선거를 앞두고 “내란을 완전 청산하겠다”며 또다시 2차 특검을 들고나온 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party and the Reform Party opposed this on the same day, calling the Democratic Party's second special prosecution "a rebellion hunt for the local elections," and initiated a filibuster (unlimited debate). As the first speaker in the filibuster, Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram said, "The special sword of a special prosecution cannot be used only for the posthumous punishment of a dead regime," adding, "What we need now is not a second comprehensive special prosecution that rehashes old issues, but a special prosecution to excise the corruption of the currently living power, like the Unification Church and money nomination scandals." (국민의힘과 개혁신당은 이날 “민주당의 2차 특검은 지방선거용 내란 몰이”라며 반대하며 무제한 토론(필리버스터)에 나섰다. 필리버스터 첫 주자로 나선 천하람 개혁신당 원내대표는 “특검이라는 특별한 칼을 이미 죽은 정권의 부관참시만을 위해 쓸 수는 없다”며 “지금 우리에게 필요한 건 재탕·삼탕의 2차 종합 특검이 아니라, 현재 살아 있는 권력의 부패를 도려내는 통일교·돈 공천 특검”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party plan to conclude the debate and process the bill on the afternoon of the 16th, 24 hours later. People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk began a hunger strike, demanding the acceptance of a 'twin special prosecution' into allegations of Democratic Party nomination bribes and the Unification Church's lobbying of the political sphere. This extreme confrontation between the ruling and opposition parties occurred just a day before the scheduled luncheon meeting on the 16th between President Lee Jae-myung and the leadership of both parties. (하지만 민주당과 조국혁신당 등은 24시간 뒤인 16일 오후 토론을 종결시키고 법안을 처리할 예정이다. 장동혁 국민의힘 대표는 민주당 공천 헌금 의혹과 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 단식을 시작했다. 16일 이재명 대통령과 여야 지도부 오찬 회동을 하루 앞두고 여야 간 극한 대치가 벌어진 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party also plans to process judicial reform bills in the January extraordinary session of the National Assembly, including the Supreme Court justice expansion, introduction of the crime of legal distortion, and introduction of trial petitions, which are opposed by the judiciary and the opposition party. They intend to process bills that the People Power Party has defined as "evil laws destroying the judiciary" and has threatened to filibuster. Accordingly, the confrontation between the ruling and opposition parties is expected to continue for the time being. (민주당은 1월 임시국회에서 사법부와 야당이 반대하는 대법관 증원, 법왜곡죄 도입, 재판 소원 도입 등 사법 개편 법안도 처리할 방침이다. 국민의힘이 ‘사법부 파괴 악법’이라고 규정하고 필리버스터를 예고한 법안들을 처리하겠다는 것이다. 이에 따라 여야 대치 국면은 당분간 이어질 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Despite 'Death Penalty Sought for Yoon'... Democratic Party Pushes Rebellion Frame Further&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇‘尹 사형 구형’ 나왔는데… 내란 프레임 더 굴리겠다는 민주당&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party floor leader Han Byung-do said at a party meeting ahead of the National Assembly plenary session on the 15th, "The punishment of the rebellion forces is not the end, but the beginning," and added, "Through the second comprehensive special prosecution, we must quickly uncover the truth of the rebellion and state affairs manipulation without a single doubt." (한병도 민주당 원내대표는 15일 국회 본회의를 앞둔 당 회의에서 “내란 세력에 대한 단죄는 끝이 아니라 이제 시작”이라며 “2차 종합 특검으로 하루빨리 내란과 국정 농단의 진실을 한 점 의혹도 없이 파헤쳐야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the three major special prosecutions extended their investigation period three times and conducted a comprehensive investigation for six months starting last June. Those involved have already been indicted and are on trial. The rebellion special prosecution sought the death penalty for former President Yoon, indicted as the ringleader of the rebellion, on the 13th. Nevertheless, the Democratic Party continues with the special prosecution, claiming "the truth about the rebellion and state affairs manipulation has still not been fully revealed." (앞서 3대 특검은 수사 기간을 세 차례 연장해가며 작년 6월부터 6개월 동안 전방위적으로 수사를 펼쳤고, 관련자들은 이미 기소돼 재판을 받고 있다. 내란 특검은 지난 13일 내란 우두머리 혐의로 기소된 윤 전 대통령에게 사형을 구형했다. 그럼에도 민주당이 “내란과 국정농단의 진상은 아직도 완전히 밝혀지지 않았다”며 특검을 이어가는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The content of the second special prosecution law is also controversial. The second special prosecution was already criticized as a large-scale special prosecution with 14 investigation targets and up to 156 personnel. However, during the review by the National Assembly Legislation and Judiciary Committee led by the Democratic Party, the second special prosecution expanded to 17 investigation targets and up to 251 personnel, becoming even larger. It has become a 'mammoth-level special prosecution,' similar in size to the rebellion special prosecution (up to 267 personnel) and larger than the Kim Keon-hee special prosecution (up to 205 personnel). The investigation period is up to 170 days, meaning if launched this month, the investigation would continue throughout the June 3 local election period. (2차 특검법의 내용도 논란이다. 2차 특검은 원래도 수사 대상 14개, 수사 인력 최대 156명으로 대형 특검이란 지적을 받았다. 그런데 2차 특검은 민주당 주도로 국회 법제사법위원회 심사를 거치면서 수사 대상 17개, 수사 인력 최대 251명으로 규모가 오히려 더 커졌다. 내란 특검(최대 267명)과 비슷하고 김건희 특검(최대 205명)보다도 큰 ‘매머드급 특검’이 된 것이다. 수사 기간은 최장 170일간으로, 이번 달 출범하면 6·3 지방선거 기간 내내 수사가 이어지게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the investigation targets include allegations that national agencies, local governments, and military units at various levels cooperated with the December 3 emergency martial law or ordered/implemented follow-up measures to martial law. This includes claims made by some in the ruling party that People Power Party-affiliated local government heads, like Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon, cooperated with martial law. Also under investigation are allegations that former President Yoon Suk-yeol and Mrs. Kim Keon-hee violated the Public Official Election Act and Political Funds Act during the presidential election. If a fine of 1 million won or more is confirmed for this, former President Yoon's election would be invalidated, and the People Power Party would have to return approximately 40 billion won in election subsidies. (또 수사 대상에는 국가기관·지방자치단체·군 각급 부대 등이 12·3 비상계엄에 동조하거나 계엄 후속 조치를 지시·수행했다는 혐의가 포함됐다. 여권 일각에서 오세훈 서울시장 등 국민의힘 소속 지자체장이 계엄에 동조했다고 주장해왔는데 이를 넣은 것이다. 윤석열 전 대통령과 김건희 여사가 대선 당시 공직선거법·정치자금법을 위반했다는 혐의도 수사 대상인데, 이에 대해 벌금 100만원 이상의 형이 확정되면 윤 전 대통령의 당선이 무효 처리되고 국민의힘은 선거 보조금 약 400억원을 반환해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of this, the opposition strongly opposes the second special prosecution, calling it a 'special prosecution for local elections' and a 'political retaliation special prosecution.' People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok said, "It means conducting a second comprehensive special prosecution on matters that have already undergone extensive, long-term investigations through the three major special prosecutions," calling it "the infinite repetition of opposition suppression and political retaliation investigations, not truth-finding." Lee Seok-yeon, chairman of the Presidential Committee on National Integration, also stated, "The three major special prosecutions investigated as much as they could, and insufficient parts are being transferred to the police's National Investigation Headquarters for continued investigation," adding, "It could be seen as political retaliation, so it would be good to withdraw it." (이 때문에 야권에선 2차 특검에 대해 ‘지방선거용 특검’ ‘정치 보복 특검’이라며 강하게 반발하고 있다. 송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 “이미 3대 특검으로 장기간 대대적인 수사가 진행된 사안들에 대해 또다시 2차 종합 특검을 하겠다는 것”이라며 “진상 규명이 아니라 야당 탄압·정치 보복 수사의 무한 반복”이라고 했다. 대통령 직속 국민통합위원회 이석연 위원장도 “3대 특검이 파헤칠 만큼 파헤쳤고 미흡한 부분은 경찰 국가수사본부로 이관해 계속 수사하고 있다”며 “자칫 정치 보복으로 비칠 수 있으므로 거둬들이는 게 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court's National Court Administration also expressed the view that "there is a concern that it may appear to be effectively re-extending the three major special prosecutions." In its opinion submitted to the National Assembly, the National Court Administration stated, "The operation of a special prosecution is an exceptional measure to the operation of the regular investigative system," and that "it necessarily involves the input of enormous budgets and personnel, and may cause incidental problems such as investigative delays in investigative agencies due to the dispatch of personnel." It also pointed out that "due to duplication with existing investigations, the efficiency of the special prosecution investigation may not be high." (대법원 법원행정처도 “사실상 3대 특검을 재차 연장하는 것으로 보일 우려가 있다”는 입장을 밝혔다. 법원행정처는 국회에 제출한 의견에서 “특검 운영은 통상적 수사 체계의 운영에 대한 예외적 조치”라며 “막대한 예산과 인력의 투입을 필연적으로 수반하고, 수사 인력 파견 등으로 인한 수사 기관의 수사 지연 등 부수적 문제가 발생할 수 있다”고 했다. 또 “기존 수사와의 중복으로 특검 수사의 효율성이 높지 않을 수 있다”고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite this opposition, the Democratic Party is pushing ahead with processing the second special prosecution law, plunging the ruling and opposition parties back into a confrontational situation. The luncheon meeting scheduled for the 16th between President Lee Jae-myung and the leadership of both parties is also expected to be half-hearted as the People Power Party has decided not to attend. The Reform Party plans to have floor leader Cheon Ha-ram attend the luncheon after finishing his filibuster. Leader Lee Jun-seok will not attend due to overseas schedules. (민주당이 이 같은 반대에도 2차 특검법 처리를 강행하면서 여야는 다시 대치 정국에 돌입했다. 16일 예정된 이재명 대통령과 여야 지도부의 오찬 간담회도 국민의힘이 참석하지 않기로 하면서 반쪽짜리에 그칠 전망이다. 개혁신당은 천하람 원내대표가 필리버스터를 마치고 오찬에 참석할 예정이다. 이준석 대표는 해외 일정으로 불참한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party also plans to process judicial reform bills at the plenary session by the end of this month. The Supreme Court Justice Expansion Act increases the number of Supreme Court justices from the current 14 to 26, which would allow President Lee to appoint a total of 22 justices during his term. The Constitutional Court Act amendment allowing constitutional complaints against trials is criticized as effectively introducing a four-tier trial system. There are also concerns that the law introducing the crime of legal distortion, which would allow punishing judges and prosecutors for distorting and applying the law, has a high potential for abuse. (민주당은 사법 개편 법안도 이달 말 본회의에서 처리할 방침이다. 대법관 증원법은 현재 14명인 대법관을 26명으로 증원하는 내용인데, 그러면 이 대통령은 임기 동안 대법관 총 22명을 임명하게 된다. 재판에 대한 헌법소원을 허용하는 헌법재판소법 개정안은 사실상 4심제 도입이란 지적을 받는다. 법을 왜곡해 적용했다는 이유로 판검사를 처벌할 수 있게 하는 법왜곡죄 도입법도 악용 소지가 크다는 우려가 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheon Dae-yeop, head of the National Court Administration, who is stepping down after completing his two-year term, said at his farewell ceremony that day, "Judicial reform excluding the judiciary has no precedent since the 1987 constitutional system," and added, "Judicial reform should not be in the direction of providing unlimited litigation opportunities to parties with time and resources, but should be in the direction of responding to the citizens' wish for disputes to be resolved swiftly in a single trial at the fact-finding stage in principle." (2년 임기를 마치고 물러나는 천대엽 법원행정처장은 이날 이임식에서 “사법부가 배제된 사법 개혁은 1987년 헌법 체제 이후 전례가 없다”며 “사법 개혁은 시간과 자력을 겸비한 당사자에게 무한소송의 기회를 제공하는 방향이 아니라, 원칙적으로 분쟁 해결이 사실심에서 한 번의 재판으로 신속히 이뤄지길 바라는 시민의 염원에 부응하는 방향이어야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk began a hunger strike that day, urging the introduction of a special prosecution to investigate allegations of Democratic Party nomination bribes and Unification Church money offerings. However, the Democratic Party argued again that day that a Unification Church special prosecution should also include allegations of the Shincheonji's intervention in the People Power Party primary. Regarding the nomination bribery allegations, they oppose a special prosecution, stating that the ongoing police investigation should be monitored. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표는 이날 민주당 공천 헌금 및 통일교 금품 수수 의혹을 수사할 특검 도입을 촉구하며 단식 농성에 돌입했다. 하지만 민주당은 이날도 통일교 특검에 신천지의 국민의힘 경선 개입 의혹도 포함시켜야 한다고 주장했다. 공천 헌금 의혹에 대해선 현재 진행 중인 경찰 수사를 지켜봐야 한다며 특검에 반대하는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party called Leader Jang's hunger strike a "strategic political offensive," suggesting it is a way out of the internal party controversy sparked by the expulsion of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon. Democratic Party spokesperson Moon Geum-ju said, "Leader Jang's hunger strike is a cowardly political show to avoid responsibility." (민주당은 장 대표의 단식을 ‘정략적인 정치 공세’라고 했다. 한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표 제명으로 불거진 당내 논란 수습을 위한 타개책이라는 것이다. 문금주 민주당 원내대변인은 “장 대표의 단식은 비겁한 책임 회피용 정치 쇼”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/GVGLLLAN7JC2DFBBKB5AWB2L4U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/STOBBCMV5BPN3I64SGZQGSGSIQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Amid Controversy Over 'Hasty Expulsion of Han'... Jang Dong-hyuk Buys Time (‘韓 졸속 제명’ 논란에… 시간 벌기 나선 장동혁)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/M4RS6YXAUBAPTG5CSWLQJZFJGI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Amid Controversy Over 'Hasty Expulsion of Han'... Jang Dong-hyuk Buys Time (‘韓 졸속 제명’ 논란에… 시간 벌기 나선 장동혁)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TCHJ2LADRVHR5HWYLN2VBKFTQM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party (PPP) leader Jang Dong-hyuk stated on the 15th that he would suspend the Ethics Committee's 'expulsion' decision against former leader Han Dong-hoon. He intends to give former leader Han an opportunity to explain himself until the 23rd, which is the deadline (within 10 days of receiving the disciplinary notice) for appealing the Ethics Committee's decision to a review committee. However, political circles analyzed this as "an intention to minimize legal controversies related to the Ethics Committee before proceeding with the disciplinary action." In response, former leader Han is known to have told those around him that he "will not request a review." As the standoff between the former and current leaders continues, a sense of crisis is growing both inside and outside the party, with concerns that "not only will we lose the local elections, but the entire conservative camp could face mutual destruction." (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 15일 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 윤리위원회 ‘제명’ 결정을 보류하겠다고 밝혔다. 한 전 대표에게 윤리위 재심 신청 기한(징계 통지 10일 이내)인 오는 23일까지 소명 기회를 주겠다는 것이다. 하지만 정치권에선 “윤리위 관련 법적 논란을 최소화한 후 징계하겠다는 의도”라는 분석이 나왔다. 이에 대해 한 전 대표는 “재심은 하지 않을 것”이라고 주변에 말한 것으로 알려졌다. 전·현직 대표의 대치가 이어지면서 당 안팎에선 “지방선거 패배는 물론이고 보수 전체가 공멸할 것”이라는 위기감이 커지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a Supreme Council meeting that day, Leader Jang said, "Former leader Han did not receive an opportunity to explain himself before the (Ethics Committee), and there are disputes over some facts," adding, "For a proper decision to come from the Ethics Committee, the party involved needs to attend and fully clarify matters." It is reported that while some within the leadership suggested finalizing the disciplinary action that day, the decision was postponed due to strong backlash within the party. (장 대표는 이날 최고위원 회의에서 “한 전 대표는 (윤리위) 소명 기회를 부여받지 못했고, 일부 사실관계에 다툼이 있다고 한다”면서 “윤리위에서 제대로 된 결정이 나오려면 당사자가 출석해서 충분히 밝힐 필요가 있다”고 했다. 지도부 일각에선 이날 징계를 의결하자는 의견도 있었지만 당내 반발이 거세자 결정을 미룬 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han's position is reportedly that he "has already stated he will not request a review." At a press conference the previous day, former leader Han said, "The Ethics Committee's decision was a formalistic act with a predetermined conclusion," and stated he would not appeal. Nevertheless, regarding Leader Jang's proposal to explain during the review process, those close to Han said, "Leader Jang, a former judge, is trying to secure procedural legitimacy in preparation for the issue going to court." Former leader Han's side is considering applying to the court for a suspension of the expulsion's effect if it becomes final. (한 전 대표는 “재심을 하지 않겠다고 이미 밝혔다”는 입장이라고 한다. 한 전 대표는 전날 기자회견에서 “윤리위 결정은 결론을 정하고 끼워 맞춘 요식 행위”라며 재심 신청을 하지 않겠다고 했었다. 그런데도 장 대표가 재심에서 소명하라고 제안한 데 대해 친한계에서는 “판사 출신인 장 대표가 문제가 법원에 가는 상황에 대비해 절차적 정당성을 확보하려는 것”이라는 말이 나왔다. 한 전 대표 측은 제명이 최종 결정되면 법원에 효력 정지 가처분 신청을 검토하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While this conflict originated from the 'party member bulletin board incident' involving former leader Han's family, political circles analyze it as a struggle between pro- and anti-impeachment factions of former President Yoon Suk-yeol over future party leadership. As the two sides are in extreme confrontation, voices urging political reconciliation poured out during the PPP's closed-door general meeting of lawmakers held that day, saying, "Leader Jang should withdraw the disciplinary action, and former leader Han should also apologize appropriately." Lawmakers from the Yeongnam region, a party stronghold, also said, "With the local elections approaching, we must avoid division above all else." (이번 갈등은 한 전 대표 가족이 연관된 ‘당원 게시판 사건’이 발단이지만, 정치권에선 윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵 찬반 진영이 향후 당내 주도권을 놓고 투쟁하는 것이라는 분석이 나온다. 양측이 극단적으로 대립하자 이날 열린 국민의힘 의원총회에선 “장 대표는 징계를 철회하고, 한 전 대표도 적절하게 사과해야 한다”며 정치적 봉합을 촉구하는 목소리가 쏟아졌다. 당 주류인 영남권 의원들도 “지방선거를 앞두고 분열만큼은 피해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Demands for Political Reconciliation Pour In: "Jang Should Withdraw Expulsion, Han Should Apologize"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“張은 제명 철회하고 韓은 사과하라” 정치적 봉합 요구 쏟아져&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the PPP's closed-door general meeting of lawmakers held at the National Assembly on the 15th, about ten speakers took the floor to request reconsideration of the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon. It is said there were no statements insisting on expelling former leader Han in accordance with the Ethics Committee's decision. The meeting, which lasted about two hours starting at 11 AM, was attended by around 70 out of 107 PPP lawmakers, including Leader Jang Dong-hyuk. (15일 국회에서 열린 국민의힘 비공개 의원총회에선 10여 명이 발언자로 나서 한동훈 전 대표의 제명을 재고하라고 요청했다. 윤리위 결정대로 한 전 대표를 제명해야 한다는 발언은 없었다고 한다. 이날 오전 11시부터 2시간가량 진행된 의총에는 장동혁 대표를 비롯, 국민의힘 의원 107명 가운데 70여 명이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Yoon Sang-hyun said, "The party member bulletin board incident is a problem that should be resolved politically," adding, "Former leader Han's political explanation was insufficient, and the Ethics Committee's (expulsion) punishment was excessive." Addressing Leader Jang, he said, "It is leadership to politically resolve the situation and unite the divided party." Lawmaker Cho Kyoung-tae said, "Now is a time for integration and unity," asking, "Would expelling former leader Han really help our party at this point?" Lawmaker Yoon Jae-ok was also reported to have said, "It would be good to gather various opinions from many lawmakers before making a decision." (윤상현 의원은 “당원 게시판 사태는 정치적으로 해결해야 할 문제”라며 “한 전 대표는 정치적 소명이 부족했고 윤리위 (제명) 처분도 과했다”고 했다. 장 대표를 향해선 “정치적으로 수습하고 분열된 당을 하나로 모으는 게 리더십”이라고 했다. 조경태 의원은 “지금은 통합과 단합의 시간”이라며 “한 전 대표 제명이 과연 이 시점에 우리 당에 도움이 되겠느냐”고 했고, 윤재옥 의원도 “여러 의원의 다양한 의견을 수렴해서 결정하는 것이 좋겠다”고 말한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were also many opinions that expelling a former leader over the party member bulletin board issue was excessive. The party member bulletin board incident refers to allegations raised in November 2024 that former leader Han's family defamed former President Yoon Suk-yeol and his wife on the PPP's member bulletin board. (당원 게시판 문제로 전직 대표를 제명하는 것은 지나치다는 의견도 많았다. 당원 게시판 사건은 2024년 11월 국민의힘 당원 게시판에서 한 전 대표 가족이 윤석열 전 대통령 부부 등을 비방했다는 의혹이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Kwon Young-jin said, "The expulsion of former leader Han should be withdrawn, and former leader Han should also express regret to party members and the public." Lawmaker Kim Jong-yang also said, "There is no precedent for expelling a person who held such an important position. Did (former leader Han) commit a crime grave enough to warrant expulsion?" He continued, "To win the local elections, let's show a changing attitude," adding, "(The party leadership) should not show a groupthink-driven appearance, being dragged along by hardline supporters." Leader Jang is reported to have listened to the lawmakers' remarks without any particular reaction. (권영진 의원은 “한 전 대표에 대한 제명을 철회해야 하고, 한 전 대표도 당원과 국민께 송구하다는 정도로 표현해야 한다”고 했다. 김종양 의원도 “중요한 위치에 있었던 인사를 제명한 사례가 없다. (한 전 대표가) 제명할 정도의 대역죄를 저질렀느냐”고 했다. 그러면서 “지선에서 승리하려면 변하는 모습을 보이자”면서 “(당 지도부가) 강성 지지층에 끌려다니는 집단사고주의적인 모습을 보이면 안 된다”고 했다. 장 대표는 별다른 반응 없이 의원들의 발언을 들은 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reason lawmakers poured out harsh words directly to Leader Jang is largely due to a strong sense of crisis that the controversy over expelling former leader Han will become a negative factor for the local elections approaching in about four months. Currently, the PPP's approval rating is stuck in the low 20% range (telephone interview surveys) or mid-30% range (ARS surveys), depending on the polling method. Surveys by the Yeouido Research Institute, the PPP's think tank, also indicate the party's approval rating is formed in the 30% range. (의원들이 장 대표 면전에서 고언(苦言)을 쏟아낸 것은 한 전 대표 제명 논란이 4개월여 앞으로 다가온 지방선거에 악재가 되리라는 위기감이 크기 때문이다. 현재 국민의힘 지지율은 여론조사 방식에 따라 20%대 초반(전화 면접 조사)이나 30%대 중반(ARS 조사)으로 고착화돼 있다. 국민의힘 싱크탱크인 여의도연구원 조사도 30%대에서 당 지지율이 형성되는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this situation, as the party is plunged into internal strife over the member bulletin board issue, warnings are emerging within the PPP that "we won't even be able to hold an election like this." Party elders are also urging both sides to resolve the situation. Permanent Advisor Yoo Joon-sang said, "Expelling former leader Han is like discarding the party's assets," adding, "If we fall into internal strife, we will inevitably suffer a crushing defeat in the local elections." Former lawmaker Choi Byung-gook also said, "Leader Jang and former leader Han should meet and talk unconditionally," stating, "The method of expulsion will only build resentment between them." PPP permanent advisors are known to have met at a location in Seoul that day and agreed on measures such as issuing a statement urging resolution of the 'Jang-Han conflict'. (이런 가운데 당원 게시판 문제로 당이 내홍에 빠지자, 국민의힘 내부에선 “이대로는 선거를 치를 수조차 없다”는 경고음이 나오고 있는 것이다. 당 원로들도 양측에 사태 해결을 촉구하고 있다. 유준상 상임고문은 “한 전 대표 제명은 당의 자산을 내치는 꼴”이라면서 “내분에 빠진다면 지방선거에서 필패(必敗)할 수밖에 없다”고 했다. 최병국 전 의원도 “장 대표와 한 전 대표가 조건 없이 만나서 대화해야 한다”며 “제명이라는 방식으로는 서로 원한만 쌓인다”고 했다. 국민의힘 상임고문들은 이날 서울 모처에서 만나 ‘장·한 갈등’ 해결을 촉구하는 성명서 발표 등에 공감한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the prevailing view is that the possibility of compromise between the two is currently not high. A PPP official said, "I understand the Jang Dong-hyuk leadership did not originally consider withdrawing the disciplinary action against former leader Han," adding, "Wasn't the suspension of the disciplinary decision intended to placate the lawmakers' backlash at the general meeting and minimize political damage to Leader Jang?" There is also talk that the party leadership will expel former leader Han in accordance with the Ethics Committee's decision at the Supreme Council meeting on the 26th, the first meeting after the appeal deadline passes. (그럼에도 현재로선 두 사람의 타협 가능성은 크지 않다는 전망이 우세하다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “장동혁 지도부는 한 전 대표의 징계 철회를 애초부터 염두에 두고 있지 않은 것으로 안다”며 “징계 의결이 보류된 것은 의원총회에서 의원들의 반발을 무마하고, 장 대표의 정치적 타격을 최소화하기 위한 목적이 아니겠느냐”고 했다. 당 지도부가 재심 신청 기한이 끝나고 처음 열리는 오는 26일 최고위원 회의에서 윤리위 의결대로 한 전 대표를 제명할 것이라는 말도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, those close to Han say, "In a situation where former leader Han has already stated he will not appeal, Leader Jang's proposal to 'explain during the review' is another attempt to frame him." They suspect an intention by Leader Jang's side to push a narrative that 'former leader Han voluntarily gave up his party membership rights.' A figure close to Han said, "Judging from various circumstances, Leader Jang appears to have no intention of withdrawing the expulsion," adding, "If they force through the ouster of former leader Han, we are also considering legal responses, such as applying for a suspension of the effect." (반면 친한계에선 “이미 한 전 대표가 재심 신청을 하지 않겠다고 밝힌 상황에서, 장 대표가 ‘재심에서 소명하라’고 제안한 것은 또 다른 프레임 씌우기”라는 말도 나온다. 장 대표 측에서 ‘한 전 대표 스스로 당원권을 포기했다’는 식으로 몰고 가려는 의도가 아니냐는 것이다. 친한계의 한 인사는 “여러 정황으로 볼 때 장 대표는 제명 철회 의사가 없는 것으로 판단된다”며 “한 전 대표 축출을 강행한다면 효력 정지 가처분 신청 등 법적 대응도 고려하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/M4RS6YXAUBAPTG5CSWLQJZFJGI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TCHJ2LADRVHR5HWYLN2VBKFTQM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party Local Government Heads Panic, Saying "Heading Down a Path of Self-Destruction" (국힘 지자체장들 “자멸의 길 가나” 패닉)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/N7BJ46UQXVDHXLPULV3WXYVTWM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party Local Government Heads Panic, Saying "Heading Down a Path of Self-Destruction" (국힘 지자체장들 “자멸의 길 가나” 패닉)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DJ5WE73W3NPPVCQW5PZTTIADIA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the People Power Party (PPP) faces internal strife over the issue of expelling former leader Han Dong-hoon with five months left until the local elections, PPP-affiliated local government heads are expressing concern. With the PPP's approval rating dropping to the 20% range, they argue that if the party continues its "household fight" due to the "Jang-Han conflict," everyone will be destroyed together. (국민의힘이 지방선거 5개월을 앞두고 한동훈 전 대표의 제명 문제로 내분을 겪자, 국민의힘 소속 지방자치단체장들은 우려를 표하고 있다. 국민의힘 지지율이 20%대로 떨어진 가운데, “‘장·한(張韓) 갈등’으로 집안싸움만 하다간 모두 공멸한다”는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon said on Facebook on the 15th regarding the PPP Ethics Committee's decision to 'expel Han Dong-hoon' that the party is "heading down an abnormal path." Mayor Oh asked, "Why on earth is the People Power Party heading down a path of self-destruction?" and added, "Have we forgotten the painful lesson of forcibly driving out former party leader Lee Jun-seok, an ally of unity, and ultimately heading down a path of collapse?" Mayor Oh stated, "The People Power Party is showing division and conflict when it should be demonstrating self-reflection and introspection," and said, "It is time to think about the people watching us with serious eyes." (오세훈 서울시장은 15일 페이스북에서 국민의힘 윤리위원회의 ‘한동훈 제명’ 결정에 대해 “비정상의 길을 가고 있다”고 했다. 오 시장은 “국민의힘이 도대체 왜 자멸의 길을 가고 있나”라며 “통합의 우군인 이준석 전 당 대표를 억지로 쫓아내고 결국 무너지는 길을 가야만 했던 그 뼈아픈 교훈을 잊었느냐”라고 했다. 오 시장은 “국민의힘은 자숙과 성찰을 보여야 할 때 분열과 충돌의 모습을 보이고 있다”며 “엄중한 눈빛으로 우리를 바라보는 국민을 생각해야 할 때”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP-affiliated Seoul district chiefs are also on high alert. In the 2022 local elections, PPP-affiliated district chiefs were elected in 17 out of 25 districts in Seoul. However, in a Gallup Korea poll for the second week of January, when asked which side's candidates should be elected more, responses favoring the election of many ruling party candidates (42%) were higher than those favoring many opposition party candidates (35%) in the Seoul area. (국민의힘 소속 서울 구청장들도 비상이 걸렸다. 2022년 지방선거 때는 서울 25구 가운데 17구에서 국민의힘 소속 구청장이 당선됐다. 그러나 한국갤럽의 1월 2주차 여론 조사에서 어느 쪽 후보가 많이 당선돼야 하느냐는 질문에 서울 지역의 경우 여당 후보 다수 당선(42%)이란 응답이 야당 후보 다수 당선(35%)보다 높게 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that local government heads in the Daejeon and South Chungcheong regions, where administrative integration is being promoted by the government and ruling party, are also concerned about the party conflict. South Chungcheong Province Governor Kim Tae-heum and Daejeon Mayor Lee Jang-woo have not issued official statements regarding the 'Jang-Han conflict'. However, it is reported that Governor Kim Tae-heum recently requested conservative integration and expansion of external reach in a meeting with party leader Jang Dong-hyuk. In the Gallup poll, public opinion favoring the election of many ruling party candidates (43%) is also higher than that favoring many opposition party candidates (31%) in the Daejeon/Sejong/Chungcheong region. (Refer to the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission website) (정부·여당이 행정 통합을 띄우고 있는 대전·충남 지역 지자체장들도 당 갈등 상황에 대해 우려하는 것으로 전해졌다. 김태흠 충남지사와 이장우 대전시장은 ‘장한 갈등’에 대해 공식 입장을 내지 않았다. 다만 김태흠 지사는 최근 장동혁 대표와의 만남에서 보수 통합과 외연 확장 등을 주문한 것으로 전해졌다. 갤럽 조사에서 대전·세종·충청 지역도 여당 다수 당선(43%) 여론이 야당 다수 당선(31%)보다 높다. (중앙선거여론조사심의위 홈페이지 참조))&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incheon Mayor Yoo Jeong-bok also expressed a sense of crisis at a PPP re-elected lawmakers' study group discussion last December, saying, "Public sentiment right now is, in a word, 'We can't trust the Democratic Party of Korea, it's unsettling. However, we can trust the People Power Party even less, we cannot support it.'" A PPP official said, "In this situation, if the party ends up expelling even former leader Han, many predict that the conservative vote will split and this local election will become even more difficult." (유정복 인천시장도 작년 12월 국민의힘 재선 의원 공부 모임 토론회에서 “지금 민심은 한마디로 ‘더불어민주당은 못 믿겠다, 불안하다. 그러나 국민의힘은 더 못 믿겠다, 지지할 수 없다’는 것”이라며 위기감을 토로한 바 있다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “이런 상황에서 당이 한 전 대표까지 결국 내치게 되면, 보수 표는 갈라지고 이번 지방선거가 더 어려워질 것이란 전망이 많다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/N7BJ46UQXVDHXLPULV3WXYVTWM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DJ5WE73W3NPPVCQW5PZTTIADIA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Kim: "Up to 20 Trillion Won Support Over 4 Years for Daejeon-South Chungcheong and Gwangju-South Jeolla Integrated Special Cities" (金총리 “대전·충남, 광주·전남 통합 특별시에 4년간 최대 20조 지원”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/16/TOXRKGBHBBFYRBJG3TFWUFSCAU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;The government announced that it will provide up to 5 trillion won per year for 4 years, totaling up to 20 trillion won, as administrative integration incentives to the Daejeon-South Chungcheong and Gwangju-South Jeolla integrated special cities. It also stated it would grant them status and autonomy comparable to Seoul Special City and provide benefits such as primarily receiving relocated public institutions. (정부가 대전·충남, 광주·전남 통합 특별시에 행정 통합 인센티브로 각각 연 최대 5조원씩 4년간 최대 20조원을 지원하겠다고 밝혔다. 또 서울특별시에 준하는 지위와 자치권을 주고, 공공기관을 주로 이전받을 수 있는 혜택도 주겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government announced this incentive plan at the Government Complex Seoul on the morning of the 16th. The plan was announced directly by Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, with vice ministers from the Ministry of Economy and Finance, Ministry of Education, Ministry of the Interior and Safety, Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy, Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, and the Office for Government Policy Coordination explaining the details. (정부는 16일 오전 정부서울청사에서 이 같은 내용의 인센티브안을 발표했다. 방안은 김민석 국무총리가 직접 발표했고, 재정경제부·교육부·행정안전부·산업통상부·국토교통부·기획예산처 차관들이 세부안을 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Full text of Prime Minister Kim Min-seok's announcement&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇김민석 국무총리 발표문 전문&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello, I am Prime Minister Kim Min-seok. (안녕하십니까, 국무총리 김민석입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Republic of Korea has achieved rapid economic growth by pursuing a capital region-centered national development strategy. However, the current concentration of industry, population, and infrastructure in the capital region is now acting as an obstacle to national development, not a growth engine. (대한민국은 그동안 수도권 중심 국가 발전 전략 추진으로 급속한 경제 성장을 이끌어 왔습니다. 하지만 지금 산업·인구·인프라의 수도권 집중은 성장 동력이 아닌 국가 발전의 걸림돌로 작용하고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to the deepening of the capital region's single-pole system, Seoul is experiencing severe inefficiencies such as skyrocketing housing prices and traffic congestion, while other regions face a crisis of regional extinction due to population decline. (수도권 일극 체제의 심화로 서울은 집값 폭등, 교통 혼잡 등 극심한 비효율이 발생하고, 지역은 인구 감소로 인한 지방 소멸 위기에 처해 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the Republic of Korea to become stronger, its regions must become stronger. Regional balanced development is not just a policy of consideration for regions, but a survival strategy for a sustainable future. (대한민국이 강해지기 위해서는 지역이 강해져야 합니다. 지역 균형 발전은 지역을 배려하는 정책이 아닌 지속 가능한 미래를 위한 생존 전략입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the Republic of Korea's renewed leap forward, the government plans to prioritize and pursue a major shift from capital region-led growth to region-led growth as its top national task this year. (정부는 대한민국의 재도약을 위해, 수도권 중심 성장에서 지방 주도 성장으로의 대전환을 올해 국정 과제 중 가장 우선순위에 두고 추진할 계획입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of its key means is administrative integration between wide-area local governments. Administrative integration is not simply redrawing the map. It is about linking living and economic zones into one and jointly designing transportation, industry, welfare, and safety. Through this, the integrated region will leap forward as a pillar of national development. (그 핵심 수단 중 하나가 바로 광역 지방정부 간 행정 통합입니다. 행정 통합은 단순히 지도를 다시 그리는 일이 아닙니다. 생활권과 경제권을 하나로 묶고, 교통과 산업, 복지와 안전을 함께 설계하는 일입니다. 이를 통해 통합된 지역이 국가 발전의 한 축으로 도약할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To successfully promote administrative integration and ensure that integration leads directly to regional growth, the government has prepared groundbreaking incentives in four areas that local residents can tangibly feel. (정부는 행정 통합을 성공적으로 추진하고, 통합이 곧 지방의 성장으로 연결될 수 있도록 지역 주민이 체감할 수 있는 4대 분야에 대한 파격적인 인센티브를 마련하였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First is financial support, second is strengthening the status of the integrated special city, third is priority relocation of public institutions, and fourth is industrial revitalization. (첫째는 재정 지원, 둘째는 통합특별시 위상 강화, 셋째는 공공기관 우선 이전, 넷째는 산업 활성화입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;First, the government will prepare a groundbreaking financial support plan of up to 5 trillion won per year, up to 20 trillion won over 4 years, for each integrated special city. (먼저 정부는 통합특별시에 각각 연간 최대 5조원, 4년간 최대 20조원 수준의 파격적인 재정 지원 방안을 마련하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will grant clear incentives and corresponding autonomy and responsibility to the integrating local governments. To this end, we will pursue the reallocation of national financial resources, including the creation of a provisional 'Administrative Integration Grant' and 'Administrative Integration Support Fund'. (통합하는 지방정부에는 확실한 인센티브와 그에 상응하는 자율성과 책임성을 부여하겠습니다. 이를 위해 가칭 ‘행정 통합 교부세’와 ‘행정 통합 지원금’ 신설 등을 포함해 국가 재원의 재배분을 추진하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is to build the financial capacity for the integrated special cities to plan and execute regional priority projects themselves. (통합특별시가 지역 현안 사업 등을 스스로 계획하고 실행할 수 있는 재정 체력을 만드는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will form a joint 'Integrated Local Government Financial Support Task Force' with related ministries to swiftly finalize detailed plans and closely cooperate with the National Assembly. (관계 부처 합동으로 ‘통합 지방정부 재정 지원 TF’를 구성하여 세부 방안을 신속히 확정하고, 국회와도 긴밀히 협력하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We hope that active integration of local governments will prevent regional extinction and usher in a genuine era of local autonomy. (지방정부 통합이 활발히 이뤄져 지방 소멸을 막고, 실질적인 지방자치 시대가 열리기를 기대합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Second, we will grant the integrated special cities a status equivalent to that of Seoul. We will expand the number of deputy mayors to four and raise their rank to vice-minister level. (둘째, 통합특별시에는 서울시에 준하는 지위를 부여하겠습니다. 부단체장 수를 4명으로 확대하고 직급도 차관급으로 상향하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will also allow key positions such as the Fire Chief and the Head of Planning and Coordination Office to be operated at the 1st grade (senior level). Furthermore, it will become possible to establish bureaus and offices reflecting regional characteristics, and autonomy in personnel management such as the selection, appointment, and promotion of affiliated civil servants will be strengthened. (소방본부장, 기획조정실장 등 핵심 보직도 1급 운영이 가능하도록 하겠습니다. 또한 지역 특성을 반영한 실·국 설치가 가능해지고, 소속 공무원 선발·임용·승진 등 인사 운영에 있어 자율성도 강화합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These measures go beyond integration that merely increases organizational size; they are aimed at creating a capable and effective local government where the mayor of the integrated special city, based on expanded authority, can better respond to complex administrative demands. (이러한 조치는 단순히 조직의 규모만 커지는 통합을 넘어, 통합특별시장이 확대된 권한을 바탕으로 복잡한 행정 수요에 더 잘 대응하는, 능력 있고 일 잘하는 지방정부를 만들기 위한 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through this, necessary personnel for responding to regional priority tasks can be deployed in a timely manner, enabling the smooth promotion of various policies of the integrated special city. (이를 통해 지역 현안 업무 대응을 위한 필요 인력을 적시에 배치하여 통합특별시의 각종 시책을 원활히 추진할 수 있을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it will enhance on-site response capabilities to minimize disaster damage and provide customized public safety services to residents. (또한, 재난 피해 최소화를 위한 현장 대응력을 제고하고, 주민들께 맞춤형 치안 서비스를 제공할 수 있을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government will support the integrated special cities so they can lead regional development as a competitive local government model. (정부는 통합특별시가 경쟁력 있는 지방정부 모델로서 지역 발전을 주도해 나갈 수 있도록 지원하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Third, we will actively favor the integrated special cities in matters such as the relocation of public institutions. (셋째, 공공기관 이전 등에 있어 통합특별시를 적극 우대하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the second phase of public institution relocations scheduled to be fully promoted in '27, we will prioritize consideration of the integrated special city areas. Specific institutions to be relocated will be discussed later, taking into account regional preferences and industrial conditions. (’27년 본격 추진 예정인 2차 공공기관 이전 시 통합특별시 지역을 우선 고려하되, 구체적인 이전 기관 등은 지역 선호, 산업 여건 등을 고려하여 추후 논의해 나가겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we will transfer the functions of special local administrative agencies under the national government currently located within the integrated special cities. (또한, 현재 통합특별시 내에 있는 국가 소속의 특별지방행정기관 업무도 이관하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Specific targets for transfer are scheduled to be decided by the Prime Minister's Integrated Special City Support Committee after legislation is enacted. (구체적인 이관 대상은 법 제정 후 국무총리 소속 통합특별시 지원위원회에서 결정할 예정입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The relocation of public institutions will serve as a direct catalyst for improving regional living conditions by creating quality public jobs within the region to prevent the outflow of young population and by building various living infrastructures such as education, healthcare, and transportation. (공공기관 이전은 지역 내 양질의 공공 일자리 창출을 통해 청년 인구 유출을 방지하고, 교육·의료·교통 등 각종 생활 인프라 구축을 통해 지역 생활 여건이 개선되는 직접적 계기가 될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If institutions linked to region-specific industries relocate, synergistic effects for industrial development can be created, and additional attraction of related public institutions and private companies will become possible. (지역 특화 산업과 연계된 기관이 이전할 경우 산업 발전의 시너지 효과가 창출될 수 있으며, 관련 공공기관과 민간 기업 등의 추가 유치도 가능해질 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will actively support the integrated special cities to become startup-friendly cities that are good for business. (마지막으로, 통합특별시가 기업하기 좋은 창업 중심 도시가 될 수 있도록 적극 지원하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will provide employment subsidies and education/training support funds to businesses that establish themselves there, and also pursue reductions in land lease fees and local taxes for various development projects. (입주 기업에 대해 고용 보조금과 교육·훈련 지원금을 지원하고, 토지 임대료 감면, 각종 개발 사업에 대한 지방세 감면 등도 추진하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And we will strengthen support for various zones such as Investment Promotion Zones and Cultural Industry Promotion Zones. (그리고 투자진흥지구, 문화산업진흥지구 등 각종 지구에 대한 지원도 강화하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we will pursue the extension of lease periods for state-owned properties and reductions in usage fees, and strengthen tax support to the level of Opportunity Development Special Zones for new special zones established within the integrated special cities. (또한, 국유 재산 임대 기간 확대와 사용료 감면을 추진하고, 통합특별시에 신설되는 특구에 대해 기회발전특구 수준으로 세제 지원을 강화하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We will support the swift progression of administrative procedures by simplifying complex approval and permit processes related to development projects and establishing a one-stop service organization for related tasks, and we will prioritize the adjustment of various regulations applied to the integrated special cities. (개발 사업과 관련된 복잡한 인·허가 절차를 간소화하고, 관련 업무 일괄 처리 기구를 설치하는 등 행정 절차가 신속히 추진되도록 지원하고, 통합특별시에 적용되는 각종 규제를 우선적으로 정비하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The core of the industrial revitalization policy is clear. It is to form industrial clusters centered on various zones and create cities where businesses, investment, and jobs increase through economies of scale and technological innovation. (산업 활성화 정책의 핵심은 분명합니다. 각종 지구를 중심으로 산업 클러스터를 형성하고, 규모의 경제와 기술 혁신을 통해 기업, 투자, 일자리가 늘어나는 도시를 만드는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the regional economy revives, this will lead to a virtuous cycle structure that can, in turn, lead to the expansion of local finances. (지역 경제가 살아나면, 이것이 다시 지방 재정 확충으로 이어질 수 있는 선순환 구조로 이어질 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Region-led growth is an essential strategy for the national development of the Republic of Korea, and administrative integration is the key to successfully promoting it. (지방 주도 성장은 대한민국 국가 발전을 위한 필수 전략이고 행정 통합은 이를 성공적으로 추진할 열쇠입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fellow citizens, local autonomy has never been an easy path. Through local autonomy, revived after 30 years by the late President Kim Dae-jung's life-threatening hunger strike in 1990, regional policies tailored to the level of local residents began to spread. (국민 여러분, 지방 자치는 결코 쉬운 길이 아니었습니다. 1990년 김대중 전 대통령의 목숨을 건 단식 투쟁으로 30년 만에 부활된 지방 자치를 통해 지역민의 눈높이에 맞춘 지역 정책이 보급되기 시작했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The integration of wide-area local governments will also not be an easy path. Harmonizing institutional differences that have arisen over decades of separation is by no means a small task. Above all, there may be those who prioritize small vested interests over the interests of the entire region. (광역 지방정부의 통합도 쉽지 않은 길일 것입니다. 분리된 지 수십 년이 지나면서 발생한 제도의 차이를 정비하는 것은 결코 작은 일이 아닙니다. 무엇보다 지역 전체의 이익보다 작은 기득권을 앞세우는 이들도 있을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, for the development of the Republic of Korea, we can no longer delay. Now is the right time for integration. It is the path toward completing genuine local autonomy. (하지만 대한민국의 발전을 위해서 우리는 더 이상 시간을 지체할 수 없습니다. 바로 지금이 통합의 적기입니다. 실질적인 지방자치의 완성으로 나아가는 길입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government will firmly back the integration so that it can bring you, the citizens, a better life, a better future, and more opportunities. (정부는 통합을 통해 국민 여러분께 더 나아진 삶, 더 나은 미래, 더 많은 기회가 생길 수 있도록 확실히 뒷받침하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not only through these incentives, but by establishing a support committee under the Prime Minister, we will continuously support the integrated special cities and ensure they can successfully launch and grow as core pillars of the '5 Poles, 3 Specials' framework. (이번 인센티브뿐만 아니라 국무총리 소속으로 지원위원회를 마련하여 통합특별시를 지속적으로 지원하고, 통합특별시가 5극 3특의 핵심 축으로서 성공적으로 출범·성장할 수 있도록 하겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We ask for your continued interest and support for the integrated special cities. (국민 여러분께서도 통합특별시에 대한 지속적인 관심과 응원을 부탁드립니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you. (감사합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/16/TOXRKGBHBBFYRBJG3TFWUFSCAU/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:32:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Breaking News] People Power Party Proposes "One-on-One Summit Between Party Leaders" to President Lee to "Discuss Shifting National Policy Direction" ([속보] 국힘, 李대통령에 “국정 기조 전환 논의 여야 단독 영수회담 제안”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/Y35IFP7PWFE3BE6W4OCP5DTSN4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/32UK7TNMIRPORCBG4FYX2JUMIU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok stated on the 16th, "I propose a one-on-one summit between ruling and opposition party leaders to discuss shifting the national policy direction." The People Power Party had expressed its intention not to attend the luncheon meeting with party leaders invited by President Lee that day, and instead proposed this 'one-on-one summit between ruling and opposition party leaders'. (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 16일 이재명 대통령을 향해 “국정 기조 전환을 논의하기 위한 여야 단독 영수회담을 제안한다”고 밝혔다. 국민의힘은 이날 이 대통령이 초청한 여야 지도부와의 오찬 간담회에 불참 의사를 밝혔는데 그 대신 ‘여야 단독 영수회담’을 제안한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a press conference held at the National Assembly this morning, Floor Leader Song said, "I hear President Lee has scheduled a luncheon today, but now is not the time for a leisurely 'luncheon show'." He added, "People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok has been continuing a hunger strike since yesterday urging for special prosecutors into the 'Unification Church gate' and the 'Democratic Party nomination bribery scandal'," and "Reform Party floor leader Chun Ha-ram has been continuing a filibuster for 18 hours opposing the three special prosecutor extension laws, calling them 'political retaliation and oppression of the opposition'." (송 원내대표는 이날 오전 국회에서 열린 기자간담회에서 “이 대통령이 이날 오찬을 예정하고 있다고 하는데 지금은 한가한 ‘오찬 쇼’를 할 때가 아니다”라며 이같이 말했다. 송 원내대표는 “국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 전날부터 ‘통일교 게이트’ 특검과 ‘민주당 공천 헌금 비리’ 특검을 촉구하는 단식 투쟁을 이어가고 있다”며 “개혁신당 천하람 원내대표는 ‘야당 탄압 정치 보복’ 3대 특검 연장법을 반대하는 필리버스터를 18시간째 계속 진행하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song said, "(President Lee) should come to the site of the main opposition party leader's hunger strike, hold his hand, and listen to what the opposition party desperately needs." (송 원내대표는 “(이 대통령은) 제1야당 대표의 단식 농성 현장에 찾아와서 손을 잡고, 야당이 절박하게 요구하는 것이 무엇인지 경청해야 할 때”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song said, "(I) hope (President Lee) will fully accept the two special prosecutor proposals," and "Even if the (second comprehensive) special prosecutor law, which the Democratic Party is trying to force through, passes the filibuster and is voted on, I ask President Lee to exercise his veto power to request renegotiation between the ruling and opposition parties." He stated, "If the three special prosecutor extension laws are processed unilaterally as the ruling party wishes, the June 3 local elections will be recorded in history as the most unfair elections due to special prosecutor intervention." (송 원내대표는 “(이 대통령은) 쌍특검을 전면 수용해주길 바란다”며 “(민주당이 강행 처리하려는 2차 종합) 특검법이 필리버스터를 뚫고 의결된다고 해도 이 대통령이 재의요구권을 행사해서 여야간 재협상을 요청해달라”고 했다. 그는 “집권 여당의 뜻대로 3대 특검 연장법이 일방 처리된다면 6·3 지방선거는 특검의 개입으로 최악의 불공정한 선거로 역사에 기록될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Floor Leader Song also said, "I propose holding a joint meeting of the ruling party, opposition parties, and the government to discuss measures to resolve the soaring exchange rate and prices, and the full revision of bad laws like the 'Yellow Envelope Law'." He added, "Immediately withdraw the nomination of Lee Hye-hoon as Minister of Planning and Finance and prepare measures to reform the personnel verification system," and "Withdraw the failed October 15 real estate measures and announce bold measures to increase supply in the metropolitan area." (또한 송 원내대표는 “환율·물가 폭등을 해소할 대책과 노란봉투법 등 악법 전면 개정을 논의하기 위한 여·야·정 연석 회의 개최를 제안한다”고도 했다. 그러면서 그는 “이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 지명을 즉각 철회하고 인사 검증 시스템 쇄신 대책을 마련해달라”며 “실패한 10·15 부동산 대책을 철회하고 과감한 수도권 공급 대책을 발표해달라”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/Y35IFP7PWFE3BE6W4OCP5DTSN4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/32UK7TNMIRPORCBG4FYX2JUMIU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:17:58 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>