<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 08:54:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Text Bombardment to the Spokesperson: 99% Are "Opposing Views Asking Why Merge with Cho Kuk" (與 수석에 날아온 문자폭탄 99%는 “조국과 왜 합당하냐는 반대 의견”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/HPQYOYT44RE2DF3OQCUSTVNHVA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Text Bombardment to the Spokesperson: 99% Are "Opposing Views Asking Why Merge with Cho Kuk" (與 수석에 날아온 문자폭탄 99%는 “조국과 왜 합당하냐는 반대 의견”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIZTEYJXHE2WKYJQHA3WEMLBG4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Soo-hyun, the chief spokesperson for the Democratic Party of Korea, expressed embarrassment, stating that the backlash from supporters regarding the merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party is more severe than expected. However, he also appealed for understanding, saying it is a necessary path to achieve an overwhelming victory in the June local elections. (박수현 더불어민주당 수석대변인은 조국혁신당과 합당에 대한 지지자들의 반발이 예상보다 심하다며 곤혹스럽다고 했다. 그러면서도 6월 지방선거 압승을 위해 가야 할 길이라며 이해를 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, he explained that there were circumstances behind Democratic Party leader Lee Jae-myung's sudden 'merger proposal' made without even informing the party's Supreme Council members, and also asked for their understanding. (더불어 정청래 민주당 대표가 당 최고위원들마저 모른 상태에서 전격 ‘합당 제안’을 한 건 나름대로 사정이 있다며 역시 양해를 구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Park said on a radio program on the night of the 23rd, "Party members are very bewildered (by the merger proposal), and even some Supreme Council members feel 'insulted'," adding, "They may be shocked and disappointed, but since it must go through a party member vote, the decision-making power lies with the party members, and there will be ample opportunity to voice opposition, support, and other opinions." (박 수석대변인은 23일 밤 라디오에서 “당원들이 (합당 제안에) 많이 당황해하고 심지어 ‘모멸감을 느낀다’는 최고위원들까지 있다”며 “놀라고 서운할 수 있지만 반드시 당원 투표를 거쳐야 하기에 결정권은 당원들이 가지고 있으며 반대·찬성 등 많은 이야기를 할 기회가 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "I also received about 400 text bombs, and 99% were opposing opinions like 'I dislike Cho Kuk' and 'Why are you trying to merge?'" (이어 “저도 400개가량 문자 폭탄을 받았는데 99%가 ‘조국 싫어’ ‘왜 합당하려고 하냐’는 등 반대 의견이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the host asked, "Do you see the controversy as more intense than expected?", Spokesperson Park replied, "Somewhat yes. Leader Lee Jae-myung probably anticipated significant controversy, but did he expect Supreme Council members to be this disappointed? I'm not sure about that point." (진행자가 “예상했던 것보다 논란이 더 거세다고 보는지” 묻자 박 대변인은 “약간 그렇다. 정청래 대표도 많은 논란이 있을 것으로 예상했겠지만 최고위원들이 이 정도까지 섭섭해할지 예상했을까? 그 점에 대해선 자신이 없다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, regarding the reason Leader Lee proposed the merger, Spokesperson Park said, "Looking at opinion polls asking whether the local elections are about 'checking the ruling party' or 'criticizing the opposition party', some polls show a very close split," explaining, "We cannot be optimistic about the election, and if we don't achieve an overwhelming victory in the local elections, we won't properly put a historical period on the 'judgment of the Yoon administration'." (그럼에도 정 대표가 합당을 제안한 까닭에 대해 박 대변인은 “지방선거가 여당 견제인지, 야당 비판인지’를 묻는 여론조사를 보면 근소하게 붙어 있는 여론조사도 있다”며 “선거를 낙관할 수 없고 지방선거에서 압승하지 않으면 ‘내란 심판’이라는 역사적 마침표를 제대로 찍지 못하기 때문”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council members like Lee Eon-joo and Kang Deuk-gu criticized Leader Lee for unilaterally pushing the merger proposal without any prior discussion and for announcing it on the day after the president's press conference and the day the KOSPI hit 5000, causing controversy. (이언주 수석최고위원, 강득구 최고위원 등은 정 대표가 합당 제안과 관련, 일절 사전 논의를 하지 않고 독단적으로 추진했다는 점, 대통령 회견 다음 날이자 코스피 5000 달성일 합당을 발표해 논란을 일으킨 점 등을 문제 삼았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this, Chief Spokesperson Park explained, "We would need to follow various internal procedures only after receiving a positive response from Representative Cho Kuk. There was no positive response until the day before the announcement, and a promise came late in the afternoon saying, 'If you propose (tomorrow), we will respond in some form,' which led to the hurried announcement." (이와 관련, 박 수석대변인은 “조국 대표로부터 긍정적 답변이 있어야 당내의 이런저런 절차를 밟을 텐데, 그동안 긍정적 답변이 안 오다가 발표 하루 전, 늦은 오후에 ‘(내일) 제안하면 우리가 어떤 형식으로든지 응답할게’라고 약속이 돼 서둘러 발표하게 된 사정이 있다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "In any case, the party leader will apologize for this regrettable matter, so please understand the party leader's circumstances as well." (그러면서 “어떤 경우든 죄송한 일로 당 대표가 이에 대해 사과할 것이니 당 대표 사정도 이해해 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/HPQYOYT44RE2DF3OQCUSTVNHVA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIZTEYJXHE2WKYJQHA3WEMLBG4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:48:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Says Japan's 'Strengthening of U.S.-Japan Alliance' Announcement is 'Declaration of Military Operational Zone' (‘미일 동맹 강화’ 발표에 北 “군작전지역 선포한 것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/AHNVUBU2QVF2HEDHDLUCGR4SIE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea Says Japan's 'Strengthening of U.S.-Japan Alliance' Announcement is 'Declaration of Military Operational Zone' (‘미일 동맹 강화’ 발표에 北 “군작전지역 선포한 것”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G4ZGIZLDGEYGGNTFHA2GMMZYMY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea criticized Japan, which expressed its will to strengthen its alliance with the United States, stating it "is no different from openly declaring neighboring countries as military operational zones." (북한은 미국과 동맹 강화 의지를 밝힌 일본을 향해 “주변 나라들을 군사작전지역으로 공개적으로 선포한 것이나 다름이 없다”고 비난했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Workers' Party organ, Rodong Sinmun, made this statement on the 24th, referencing Japanese Defense Minister Koizumi Shinjiro's recent visit to the United States where he pledged to 'focus on strengthening the U.S.-Japan alliance.' (노동당 기관지 노동신문은 24일 고이즈미 신지로 일본 방위상이 최근 미국을 방문해 ‘미일동맹을 강화하는데 주력하겠다고 다짐했다’는 점을 언급하면서 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The newspaper also criticized that Defense Minister Koizumi discussed introducing U.S. artificial intelligence, drone, and aerospace technology, in a situation where the Japanese government is pushing for the early revision of its 'three key security documents.' (신문은 또 일본 정부가 ‘3대 안보 문서’의 조기 개정을 추진하는 상황에서 고이즈미 방위상이 미국의 인공지능, 무인기, 우주항공 기술 도입을 논의했다는 점도 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodong Sinmun argued, "The adventurous tendency of Japanese reactionaries, who are unhesitatingly jumping onto the path of overseas expansion and peace destruction, has once again been clearly revealed," and claimed they are "racing headlong into infringing upon the interests of regional countries and making the security environment in Asia and the world even more precarious." (노동신문은 “해외팽창과 평화파괴의 길에 서슴없이 뛰어들려는 일본 반동들의 모험주의적인 경향이 다시 한 번 똑똑히 드러났다”며 “지역 국가들의 이익을 침해하고 아시아와 세계의 안보환경을 더욱 위태롭게 하는데로 줄달음치고있다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It further stated, "Koizumi's trip to the U.S., aimed at military great-power status, will only be a foolish step hastening Japan's self-destruction," adding, "The Japanese ruling forces must clearly understand that forgetting the past of defeat means losing the future." (이어 “군사대국화를 노린 고이즈미의 미국 행각은 일본의 자멸을 다그치는 어리석은 행보로 될뿐”이라며 “일본집권세력은 패망의 과거를 망각하면 미래를 잃는다는것을 똑똑히 알아야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Defense Minister Koizumi had previously met with U.S. Secretary of Defense Pete Haghes in Washington D.C. on the 15th, where they confirmed policies to strengthen bilateral deterrence and discussed cooperation plans in the defense field. (고이즈미 방위상은 앞서 15일 미국 워싱턴DC에서 피트 헤그세스 미 국방부 장관을 만나 양국 간 억지력 강화 방침을 확인하고 국방 분야 협력 방안을 논의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During that meeting, Defense Minister Koizumi, with China and North Korea in mind, stated, "There is absolutely no wavering in the U.S.-Japan alliance, and we confirmed that the two countries cooperate closely."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 자리에서 고이즈미 방위상은 중국과 북한을 염두에 두고 “미일 동맹에 전혀 흔들림이 없으며 양국이 긴밀하게 협력한다는 것을 확인했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/AHNVUBU2QVF2HEDHDLUCGR4SIE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/G4ZGIZLDGEYGGNTFHA2GMMZYMY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:36:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk Innovation Party Holds Emergency Assembly in the National Assembly... Begins Discussion on 'Ruling Party Merger Proposal' (조국혁신당, 국회서 긴급 의총…‘與합당 제안’ 논의 착수)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/QZBSBHDJORFA5AADXJDNWMT47E/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Cho Kuk Innovation Party Holds Emergency Assembly in the National Assembly... Begins Discussion on 'Ruling Party Merger Proposal' (조국혁신당, 국회서 긴급 의총…‘與합당 제안’ 논의 착수)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZE3QE2B7QJMZJDW4R4MVMZUMYQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Cho Kuk Innovation Party has fully commenced gathering internal opinions on the surprise merger proposal made by Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae. (조국혁신당이 더불어민주당 정청래 대표의 전격적인 합당 제안에 대한 당내 의견 수렴에 본격적으로 들어갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 24th, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party held an emergency general assembly of its lawmakers at the National Assembly, attended by all 12 of its members including party leader Cho Kuk and floor leader Seo Wang-jin. (조국혁신당은 24일 국회에서 조국 대표와 서왕진 원내대표 등 소속 의원 12명 전원이 참석한 가운데 긴급 의원총회를 열었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his opening remarks at the assembly, Floor Leader Seo stated, "Although it was sudden, it is a formal merger proposal from the leader of the largest party in the Assembly, so we will review it seriously," adding, "Today's assembly is a first step to gather the opinions of the lawmakers." (서 원내대표는 의총 모두 발언에서 “갑작스러웠지만 원내 1정당 대표의 공식 합당 제안이라는 점에서 엄중하게 검토할 것”이라며 “오늘 의총은 의원단 의견을 일차적으로 수렴하는 자리”라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "We will discuss how to achieve the common goal of the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the renewal of the government, as well as the realization of progressive policy visions like political reform that the Innovation Party has independently presented," and said, "We will proceed with orderly discussions centered around the party leader, following the principles and procedures outlined in the party constitution and rules." (이어 “이재명 정부의 성공과 정권 재창출이라는 공통의 목표와 혁신당이 독자적으로 제시해온 정치 개혁 등 진보적 정책 비전이 실현될 수 있는 길을 토론할 것”이라며 “당헌·당규에 따른 원칙과 절차에 따라 당 대표를 중심으로 질서 있게 논의하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "Above all, we will seek the wisest answer that respects the will of the people and the wishes of party members, and fulfills the calling of the times." (그는 “무엇보다 국민의 뜻과 당원의 염원을 받들어 시대적 소명에 부응할 수 있는 가장 지혜로운 해답을 찾겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following today's assembly, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party plans to continue gathering opinions by holding a party affairs committee meeting on the 26th. (조국혁신당은 이날 의총에 이어 26일 당무위를 여는 등 의견 수렴을 계속할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the merger proposal from Leader Chung the previous day, Party Leader Cho Kuk had said, "We have just begun discussions," and noted, "All possibilities are open. Each party will go through sufficient opinion-gathering procedures."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (조국 대표는 전날 정 대표의 합당 제안에 대해 “논의를 이제 막 시작한 상황”이라며 “모든 가능성은 열려 있다. 각 당에서 충분한 의견 수렴 절차를 거칠 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/QZBSBHDJORFA5AADXJDNWMT47E/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZE3QE2B7QJMZJDW4R4MVMZUMYQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:39:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk Responds to Chung Cheong-rae's Merger Proposal: "Our DNA Must Not Disappear" (정청래 합당 제안에 조국 “우리 DNA 사라져선 안 돼” )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/Z72VMTNHX5FKHDAGPFGK75GKFY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJTDSOLFGRSTOYZYMEZTQZTEG4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, stated on the 24th regarding the merger proposal from Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, that "Under no circumstances should the vision, values, and political DNA of politician Cho Kuk and the Innovation Party disappear." (조국혁신당 조국 대표는 더불어민주당 정청래 대표의 합당 제안에 대해 24일 “어떤 경우에도 정치인 조국과 혁신당의 비전과 가치, 정치적 DNA가 사라져서는 안 된다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After holding an emergency general meeting of party lawmakers at the National Assembly in Yeouido, Seoul, to discuss the Democratic Party's merger proposal, Representative Cho said, "We will discuss and decide based on the principle that the independent, political DNA of the Innovation Party must not only be preserved but also expanded." In the closed-door general meeting, he explained to the 12 party lawmakers the process of receiving the merger proposal from Representative Chung. (조 대표는 이날 서울 여의도 국회에서 긴급 의원총회를 열고 민주당의 합당 제안을 논의한 뒤 “혁신당의 독자적, 정치적 DNA가 보존돼야 함은 물론이고 확대돼야 한다는 원칙에 기초해 논의하고 결정할 것”이라며 이같이 말했다. 그는 비공개로 진행된 의총에서 소속 의원 12명에게 정 대표로부터 합당 제안을 받은 경과 등을 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters, Representative Cho said, "I shared the situation of how (Representative Chung) made the proposal and how I responded during the general meeting," adding, "Broadly speaking, I confirmed that (the lawmakers') views were almost no different from mine." (조 대표는 기자들과 만난 자리에서 “(의총에서) 합당 제안 과정에 대해 (정 대표가) 어떻게 제안했고 제가 어떻게 대응했는지 상황을 공유했다”며 “크게 봐서 (의원들이) 제 생각과 거의 차이가 없다는 점을 확인했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Starting with today's general meeting, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party will hold a party affairs committee meeting and follow official procedures," and said, "Through that, we will gather and discuss the opinions of party members and the public." (이어 “오늘 의원총회를 시작으로 조국혁신당은 당무위원회를 열고 공식적인 절차를 밟아 나갈 것”이라며 “그 속에서 당원의 의견이 어떤지, 국민의 생각이 어떤지 수렴하고 논의할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked if there were any lawmakers opposed to the merger at the general meeting, he said, "It seems there is debate within the Democratic Party, which proposed the merger, and I expect they will sort out their opinions through official procedures," adding, "We should respond after the Democratic Party's discussions are sorted out." (그는 ‘의원총회에서 합당에 반대하는 의원이 있었느냐’는 물음에 “합당을 제안한 민주당 내부에서 논쟁이 있는 것 같은데, 공식 절차를 통해 의견을 정리할 것으로 예상된다”며 “민주당 논의가 정리된 뒤 저희가 답해야 하는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the possibility of prolonged merger discussions, he also said, "It depends on the Democratic Party," and added, "I've seen media reports about heated debates within the Democratic Party. In this state, we probably can't proceed further." (이어 합당 논의 장기화 가능성에 대해서도 “민주당에 달려 있다”며 “민주당 내 격론이 있다는 언론 보도를 봤다. 이 상태에서 그다음으로는 가지 못하는 것 아니겠는가”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seo Wang-jin, the floor leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, also met with reporters after the general meeting and said, "No particular voices of concern were raised at the general meeting," and "I heard that party members are very calm and are watching the party-level discussions unfold." (조국혁신당 서왕진 원내대표도 의총 후 기자들과 만나 “의총에서 특별히 우려의 목소리가 나온 것은 없다”며 “당원들은 매우 차분하고, 당 차원의 논의를 지켜보는 분위기라고 전해 들었다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He conveyed, "The lawmakers' unified position is to calmly and orderly proceed with discussions, led by the party leader, to judge whether to merge as a way to realize the Innovation Party's values and vision." (그는 “혁신당의 가치와 비전을 실현하는 방안으로 합당 여부를 판단하는 논의를 당 대표 중심으로 차분하고 질서 있게 진행하자는 게 의원들의 일치된 입장”이라고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "The Democratic Party will also discuss internally, and the Innovation Party will discuss as well, but it doesn't seem like a conclusion will be reached quickly." (그러면서 “민주당도 자체적으로 논의할 것이고 혁신당도 논의하겠지만 빠른 속도로 결론이 나올 것 같지는 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the general meeting, the Innovation Party plans to continue gathering opinions, including holding a party affairs committee meeting on the 26th. (혁신당은 이날 의총에 이어 26일 당무위를 여는 등 의견 수렴을 지속할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/Z72VMTNHX5FKHDAGPFGK75GKFY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MJTDSOLFGRSTOYZYMEZTQZTEG4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 06:27:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Lee Hye-hoon, Who Failed to Explain the 8 Billion Won Banpo Apartment, Is Unqualified to Be a Minister": Even Ruling Bloc Parties Urge Resignation (“반포 80억 아파트 소명 못한 이혜훈, 장관 자격 없다” 범여도 사퇴 촉구)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/2M4FJJ2EPVB7DEZ475WKUELQTE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the Minister of Planning and Budget nominee appointed by President Lee Jae-myung for the sake of integration, lasted past midnight on the 24th. However, not only the opposition but also parties within the ruling bloc argued that 'Lee Hye-hoon is unacceptable,' stating, "Not a single suspicion has been clearly explained." As President Lee Jae-myung's position was to "review the hearing and then decide," he is expected to observe public opinion trends over this weekend and decide around the 26th whether to proceed with or withdraw the nomination. (이재명 대통령이 통합 차원에서 지명한 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 청문회가 24일 자정 넘어서까지 장시간 진행됐지만 야권은 물론 범여 정당들도 “개운하게 해명된 의혹이 하나도 없다”면서 ‘이혜훈 불가론’을 폈다. 이재명 대통령은 “청문회는 보고 결정하자”는 입장이었던만틈, 이번 주말 여론 추이를 살펴본 뒤 26일쯤 이 장관 후보자 지명을 강행할지 철회할지 결정할 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the hearing, questions from ruling and opposition party lawmakers focused on the circumstances of the nominee's eldest son's admission to Yonsei University, allegations of fraudulent apartment subscription, and the nominee's aides' high-handedness and verbal abuse. The nominee had previously claimed her eldest son was admitted to Yonsei University through a 'multi-child household special admissions track,' but during the hearing, she changed her statement, saying it was through a 'social contributor' track. Regarding suspicions that she registered her eldest son, who had held a wedding ceremony, as a dependent to win a subscription for the 'Raemian One Pentas' apartment in Banpo-dong, Seocho-gu, Seoul, she explained, "My eldest son faced a marital crisis immediately after his marriage." (청문회에서는 이 후보자 장남의 연세대 입학 경위와 아파트 부정 청약, 보좌진 갑질·폭언 등에 대해 여야 의원들의 질의가 집중됐다. 이 후보자는 앞서 장남이 ‘다자녀 전형’으로 연세대에 입학했다가 주장했지만, 청문회에서는 ‘사회기여자’ 전형으로 입학했다고 말을 바꿨다. 결혼식을 올린 장남을 부양가족으로 등재해 서울 서초구 반포동 ‘래미안 원펜타스’ 청약에 당첨됐다는 의혹에 대해선 “장남이 결혼 직후 파경 위기를 맞았다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Sung-hoon, the chief spokesperson for the People Power Party, urged her immediate resignation in a commentary after the hearing, stating, "In a situation where bowing her head before the public would not be enough, the nominee consistently offered sophistry instead of explanations, testing the public's patience." Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, also urged President Lee to withdraw the nomination, saying, "It was an unusual day where both ruling and opposition parties unanimously questioned the nominee's morality." (박성훈 국민의힘 수석대변인은 청문회 종료 후 논평에서 “이 후보자는 국민 앞에 고개를 숙여도 모자란 상황에 해명이 아닌 궤변으로 일관하며 국민의 인내심을 시험했다”며 즉각 사퇴를 촉구했다. 이준석 개혁신당 대표도 “여야가 한 목소리로 후보자의 도덕성에 의문을 제기한 이례적인 날이었다”며 이 대통령의 지명 철회를 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Progressive parties joined in as well. Son Sol, chief spokesperson for the Progressive Party, said, "The explanation the nominee provided regarding the fraudulent subscription allegations was far from common sense," adding, "No matter what family circumstances are cited as a reason, it has caused deep disappointment to the many homeless commoners who have been waiting for a fair opportunity." Han Ga-seon, spokesperson for the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, said, "The confirmation hearing proceeded with the frustration of having eaten 100 sweet potatoes," and "Not a single thing was properly explained." Noh Seo-young, spokesperson for the Basic Income Party, stated, "During the hearing, the nominee's suspicions were not magically resolved," and "It also could not change the public's judgment that she is an unqualified candidate." (진보 정당도 가세했다. 손솔 진보당 수석대변인은 “부정 청약 의혹에 대해 후보자가 내놓은 해명은 국민 상식과는 거리가 멀었다”며 “어떤 가정사를 이유로 대더라도 공정한 기회를 기다려온 수많은 무주택 서민에게 깊은 상실감을 안겨줬다”고 했다. 한가선 조국혁신당 대변인도 “인사청문회가 고구마 100개 먹은 듯한 답답함으로 진행됐다”며 “무엇 하나 제대로 소명된 게 없다”고 했다. 노서영 기본소득당 대변인은 “청문회에서 이 후보자의 의혹이 마법처럼 해소되는 일은 벌어지지 않았다”며 “부적격 인사라는 국민들의 판단도 바꿀 수 없었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed that the nominee's spouse applied for a subscription to the One Pentas 137A type (exclusive area 137㎡, approximately 54 pyeong) on July 30, 2024, and won it on August 7 of the same year. The subscription score was 74 points, the cutoff for winning. The non-homeowner period (32 points) and savings account period (17 points) were perfect scores, and points for four dependents (the nominee and her three sons, 25 points) were added. (이 후보자 남편은 2024년 7월 30일 원펜타스 137A 타입(전용면적 137㎡·약 54평) 청약 신청을 해서 그해 8월 7일 당첨된 것으로 나타났다. 청약 가점은 당첨 커트라인인 74점이었다. 무주택 기간(32점), 저축 가입 기간(17점)은 만점이었고 4명(이 후보자와 세 아들)의 부양가족 가점(25점)이 더해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the eldest son had registered his marriage, winning would have been difficult. This led to suspicions that, despite having held a wedding ceremony and even cohabiting, he was falsely presented as single to inflate the score. The nominee's position on this matter was inconsistent, and she presented a new claim at the hearing. She stated that although her son held a wedding ceremony, his relationship with his daughter-in-law suddenly deteriorated, leading to a state of de facto annulment where marriage registration was not possible, and they did not live together as a normal couple. Sighs of "This is too much" erupted in the hearing room. One committee member asked, "Aren't you ashamed before your conscience?" (만약 장남이 혼인 신고를 했다면 당첨은 어려웠다. 이 때문에 이미 결혼식을 올리고 동거까지 했는데도 미혼 상태로 가장해 가점을 끌어올렸다는 의혹이 제기된 것이다. 이 후보자는 이와 관련해 입장이 오락가락했는데 청문회장에서는 새로운 주장을 폈다. 그는 아들이 결혼식을 올렸지만 며느리와 사이가 갑자기 안 좋아져 사실상 파혼 지경에 이르러 혼인신고를 못하고 정상적인 부부와 같은 동거 생활을 하지 않았다고 한 것이다. 청문회장에서는 “해도 너무한다”면서 탄식이 터져나왔다. 한 청문위원은 “양심에 부끄럽지 않느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The exclusive 137㎡ (54 pyeong) A-type apartment won by the nominee's spouse had a sale price at the time of 3.6784 billion won (floors 6-14), but its current estimated market price reaches 8 billion won. The provisional capital gain the nominee and her spouse stand to gain amounts to 3 to 4 billion won. (이 후보자 배우자가 당첨된 전용 137㎡(54평)A형은 당시 분양가가 36억7840만원(6~14층)이었지만 현재 추정 시세는 80억원에 달한다. 이 후보자 부부가 거두고 있는 잠정 시세 차익은 30억~40억원에 이른다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/2M4FJJ2EPVB7DEZ475WKUELQTE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/Z7XSBQN7IJCJPPIFNN2IBWJLQA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:31:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Withdraw Han Dong-hoon's Expulsion” Supporters Hold Rally… What is Jang Dong-hyeok's First Move After Ending Hunger Strike? (“한동훈 제명 철회하라” 지지자들 집회…단식 끝 장동혁의 첫 수는?)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/DT7DD7KSLBCNFB2J32NUNPDHPM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZIGMH53EBRJVLAC43JFOKLGKDU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporters of former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon held a rally in Yeouido on the 24th, demanding the withdrawal of disciplinary measures against the former leader. Attention is focused on what decision People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok will make regarding the disciplinary case against former leader Han, as he is set to end his hunger strike and soon return to party duties. (국민의힘 한동훈 전 대표의 지지자들이 24일 여의도에서 집회를 열고 한 전 대표에 대한 징계 철회를 요구했다. 장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 단식을 끝내고 당무에 곧 복귀를 앞두고 있어 한 전 대표 징계 건과 관련해 어떤 결정을 내릴지 주목된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the rally held near the National Assembly Station that day, supporters of former leader Han chanted slogans such as “Withdraw the illegal expulsion,” “Jang Dong-hyeok, wake up,” and “Protect Han Dong-hoon.” (한 전 대표 지지자들은 이날 국회의사당역 인근에서 열린 집회에서 “불법제명 철회하라”, “장동혁은 각성하라”, “한동훈을 지켜내자” 등 구호를 외쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former spokesperson Park Sang-soo, who attended the rally, said, “The reason our party is not an unconstitutional party is because former leader Han prevented martial law,” adding, “Now they are expelling and ousting such a former leader. This means the conservative party of the Republic of Korea is closing its own doors. Let us protect former leader Han, the People Power Party, and conservative politics in Korea.” (집회에 참석한 박상수 전 대변인은 “우리 당이 위헌 정당이 아닌 이유는 계엄을 한 전 대표가 막았기 때문”이라며 “그런 한 전 대표를 제명하고 내쫓는다 한다. 대한민국 보수 정당이 스스로 문을 닫겠다고 하는 것이다. 우리가 한 전 대표와 국민의힘, 대한민국 보수 정치를 지키자”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The organizers estimated that 30,000 people gathered for the rally that day. (주최측은 이날 집회에 3만명이 모인 것으로 추산된다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, former leader Han did not attend the rally that day. Instead, he posted a message on 'Han-cut,' a platform for communicating with supporters, saying, “So many of you have come out on this cold day to prevent fake conservatives from driving out real conservatives and ruining conservatism and Korea. This is the true gathering of conservatives.” (다만, 한 전 대표는 이날 집회에 참석하지 않았다. 대신 그는 지지자들과 소통하는 플랫폼인 ‘한컷’에 글을 올려 “가짜 보수들이 진짜 보수 내쫓고 보수와 대한민국 망치는 것을 막기 위해 이 추운 날 이렇게 많이 나오셨다. 이것이 진짜 보수 결집”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'Support Han Dong-hoon' rally was held ahead of leader Jang Dong-hyeok's return to party duties. As leader Jang ended his eight-day 'twin special prosecutor hunger strike' last week, the issue of former leader Han's expulsion has resurfaced. (이날 ‘한동훈 지지’ 집회는 장동혁 대표의 당무 복귀를 앞두고 열렸다. 장 대표가 지난주 8일간의 ‘쌍특검 단식’을 끝내면서 한 전 대표이 제명 문제가 다시 떠오르고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ball is now back in leader Jang's court, as the deadline for requesting a retrial of the expulsion penalty imposed by the party's ethics committee on former leader Han regarding the so-called 'party member bulletin board incident' ended on the 23rd. (당 윤리위원회가 이른바 ‘당원게시판(당게) 사태’와 관련해 한 전 대표에게 내린 제명 처분에 대한 재심 청구 기한이 23일로 종료되면서 공은 다시 장 대표에게 넘어간 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang stated just before starting his hunger strike on the 15th that he would not take disciplinary action against former leader Han during the retrial period, but former leader Han did not apply for a retrial. (장 대표는 지난 15일 단식 돌입 직전에 한 전 대표에 대한 징계를 재심 기간에는 하지 않겠다고 밝혔으나, 한 전 대표는 재심을 신청하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before leader Jang's hunger strike, it was expected that the expulsion resolution would be made at the Supreme Council meeting on the 26th, the first meeting after the retrial deadline. However, due to leader Jang's health issues, related discussions are now expected to be further delayed. (장 대표의 단식 전에는 재심 기한 이후 처음 열리는 오는 26일 최고위원회의에서 제명 의결이 이뤄질 것으로 전망됐으나, 장 대표의 건강 문제로 관련 논의는 더 늦어질 것으로 전망된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang, having ended his hunger strike, plans to focus on recovery for the time being. (단식을 끝낸 장 대표는 당분간 회복에 집중한다는 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As his health deteriorated during the hunger strike, including experiencing chest pain, he plans to receive treatment with minimal external contact until this weekend, based on hospital examination results. (그는 단식 기간 흉통이 발생하는 등 건강 상태가 악화한 만큼 병원에서 검진 결과를 토대로 이번 주말까지는 외부 접촉을 최소화하며 치료를 받을 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the disciplinary schedule postponed, the leadership is agonizing over the level and direction of the penalty for former leader Han. (징계 일정이 미뤄지면서 지도부는 한 전 대표에 대한 처분 수위와 방향을 두고 고심 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, some within the party, seeing leader Jang and former leader Han heading for a head-on collision over the disciplinary issue, suggested a political resolution, saying, 'Former leader Han should apologize, and leader Jang should withdraw the expulsion.' (앞서 당 일각에서는 장 대표와 한 전 대표가 징계 문제로 정면충돌하는 모습을 보이자 ‘한 전 대표는 사과하고 장 대표는 제명을 철회해야 한다’며 정치적 수습을 해야 한다는 의견이 나온 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This stems from a sense of crisis that internal strife caused by so-called subtraction politics could lead to a split in the support base ahead of the June 3 local elections. In this situation, as the pan-opposition camp is moving towards unification, the need for opposition unity is also being raised. (6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 이른바 뺄셈 정치로 인한 내홍이 커질 경우 지지층이 분열될 수 있다는 위기감에 따른 것이다. 이런 상황에서 범여권이 통합에 나서고 있어 야권 통합 필요성도 제기되고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/24/DT7DD7KSLBCNFB2J32NUNPDHPM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZIGMH53EBRJVLAC43JFOKLGKDU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:52:23 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>