<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:04:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Kim Jae-won Joins Hunger Strike in Solidarity with Jang Dong-hyk on 'Day 5'... Lee Jun-seok to Return Early (김재원, ‘단식 5일차’ 장동혁 옆에서 동조 단식...이준석은 조기 귀국)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jae-won Joins Hunger Strike in Solidarity with Jang Dong-hyk on 'Day 5'... Lee Jun-seok to Return Early (김재원, ‘단식 5일차’ 장동혁 옆에서 동조 단식...이준석은 조기 귀국)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyk continues his hunger strike for the fifth day, demanding the Democratic Party of Korea accept a special counsel probe into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won also began a solidarity hunger strike on the 19th. Kim is the first from the opposition camp to join a solidarity hunger strike in support of Leader Jang. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 더불어민주당의 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 농성을 벌이고 있는 가운데, 김재원 최고위원도 19일 동조 단식에 들어갔다. 야권에서 장 대표에 호응해 동조 단식에 나선 것은 김 최고위원이 처음이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Kim posted on Facebook that day, "I've come to the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall. I begin my hunger strike struggle today." In a Facebook post the previous day, he had stated, "Leader Jang Dong-hyk's hunger strike, confronting the Lee Jae-myung administration with his whole body, continues into its fourth day," and added, "I will also participate in the hunger strike starting tomorrow (19th) at 6 AM at the National Assembly Rotunda Hall." At the time, Kim said, "I had postponed it due to unavoidable schedules until now," and added, "I don't know how long my frail body can endure, but I only hope it provides some comfort to Leader Jang." (김 최고위원은 이날 페이스북에 “국회 로텐더홀에 왔다. 오늘부터 단식 투쟁 시작한다”고 밝혔다. 그는 전날에도 페이스북 글에서 “이재명 정권에 온몸으로 맞서는 장동혁 대표의 단식이 4일째 계속되고 있다”면서 “저도 내일(19일) 오전 6시부터 국회 로텐더홀에서 단식에 참여하겠다”고 했었다. 당시 김 최고위원은 “그간 피치 못할 일정으로 미뤄왔다”며 “부실한 몸으로 얼마 버틸지 모르겠지만 장 대표에게 조금이라도 위안이 되길 바랄 뿐”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, who had been on parliamentary diplomacy activities in Mexico and Guatemala along with National Assembly Deputy Speaker Joo Ho-young, is scheduled to return early on the 21st. Leader Lee plans to cooperate with Leader Jang to urge the Democratic Party to accept the dual special counsel probes. However, it is reported that he is not currently considering a hunger strike. (주호영 국회부의장과 함께 멕시코·과테말라로 의원 외교 활동을 떠났던 이준석 개혁신당 대표는 귀국 일정을 앞당겨 21일 귀국할 예정이다. 이 대표는 장 대표와 공조해 민주당에 쌍특검 수용을 촉구할 방침이다. 다만 현재로선 단식을 고려하지는 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a Facebook post the previous day, Leader Jang expressed his determination to continue the hunger strike, stating, "Since yesterday, a single rose has been guarding my side," and "It was prepared for death from the moment it came to my side. I must not collapse first." (장 대표는 전날 페이스북 글에서 “어제부터 장미 한 송이가 내 곁을 지키고 있다”면서 “내 곁에 올 때부터 죽기를 각오했다. 내가 먼저 쓰러지면 안 된다”고 단식 의지를 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/RX2P6M64IVAQLLOMZJNY3CG4OU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3WALNJPUJFLM7A4ESE7X3Z4NQU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:24:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Min-seok: "Lee Hye-hoon, having run in elections multiple times after opposition verification... Refusing the hearing is feeble" (김민석 “이혜훈, 野 검증으로 여러번 선거 나가...  청문 거부 궁색”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/OSDHP4YRF5DFXIYZDPCFP7UBDQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Min-seok: "Lee Hye-hoon, having run in elections multiple times after opposition verification... Refusing the hearing is feeble" (김민석 “이혜훈, 野 검증으로 여러번 선거 나가...  청문 거부 궁색”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok criticized the People Power Party's refusal to hold a confirmation hearing for Minister of Planning and Budget nominee Lee Hye-hoon, calling it "feeble." (김민석 국무총리는 국민의힘이 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 청문회 개최를 거부한 데 대해 “궁색하다”고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the night of the 18th, Prime Minister Kim posted on X (formerly Twitter), "It is nominee Lee Hye-hoon's role to answer. However, verification is the role of the National Assembly, especially the opposition party," and said, "The nominee refusing a hearing that was agreed upon by both ruling and opposition parties out of fear she might make false excuses is difficult to understand." He added, "Isn't that why a hearing is needed? There shouldn't be anything to fear from providing an explanation." (김 총리는 18일 밤 X(옛 트위터)에 “답하는 것은 이혜훈 후보자의 몫이다. 그러나 검증은 국회, 특히 야당의 몫”이라며 “후보자가 거짓 변명할까 봐 여야가 합의해서 하기로 했던 청문을 거부한다는 것은 이해하기 궁색하다”고 했다. 그러면서 “그래서 청문회가 필요한 것이 아닌가. 해명될까 두려울 게 없지 않나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the nominee, Prime Minister Kim said, "She is a candidate who has already undergone opposition party verification multiple times and run in elections," and added, "Therefore, I expect an even more thorough hearing. Shouldn't we ask for the public's judgment after the hearing?" (김 총리는 이 후보자에 대해 “이미 여러 번 야당의 검증을 거쳐 선거에 나갔던 후보자”라며 “그래서 더 철저한 청문회를 해 주시길 기대한다. 청문 후 국민의 판단을 여쭤야 하지 않겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ruling and opposition parties initially agreed to hold the nominee's confirmation hearing on the 19th, but the People Power Party held a press conference the day before and refused to hold it, claiming the nominee submitted inadequate documents. Members of the People Power Party belonging to the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee stated, "This nominee should be sitting in the suspect's seat of an investigative agency, not in the National Assembly hearing room," and declared, "We completely refuse the confirmation hearing for this nominee." They further said, "The nominee is not submitting any additional documents at all, using personal information as an excuse, and the ruling party is unilaterally pushing for the hearing on the 19th." (여야는 당초 19일 이 후보자의 인사청문회를 열기로 했으나, 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 자료를 부실하게 제출했다며 전날 기자회견을 열고 개최를 거부했다. 국회 재정경제기획위원회 소속 국민의힘 의원들은 “이 후보자는 국회 청문회장이 아니라 수사기관 피의자 자리에 앉아야 할 사람”이라며 “이 후보자에 대한 인사청문회를 전면 거부한다”고 했다. 그러면서 “후보자는 개인정보 등을 핑계로 추가 자료 제출을 전혀 하지 않고 있고, 여당은 19일 청문회를 일방적으로 밀어붙이고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of the 15th, the nominee's document submission rate is known to be just over 15%. The nominee's side reportedly does not consent to submitting related documents such as details of their children's employment, military service, and gift tax payments, citing 'personal information.' The People Power Party maintains that if documents related to the children and proof of full gift tax payment are not submitted, they cannot proceed with the hearing. (지난 15일 기준 이 후보자의 자료 제출률은 15% 남짓으로 알려졌다. 이 후보자 측은 자녀들의 취업·병역·증여세 납부 내역 등 관련 자료에 대해 ‘개인정보’를 이유로 동의하지 않고 있다고 한다. 국민의힘은 자녀 관련 자료와 증여세 완납증명서 제출이 안 되면 청문회에 임할 수 없다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party holds the position that since the schedule has already been decided, the hearing should be held first. If the People Power Party maintains its boycott stance, the possibility of the Democratic Party holding the hearing alone is also being discussed. (민주당은 이미 개최 일정을 의결한 만큼, 일단 청문회를 열어야 한다는 입장이다. 국민의힘이 보이콧 입장을 고수할 경우, 민주당의 단독 개최 가능성도 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/OSDHP4YRF5DFXIYZDPCFP7UBDQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:34:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi: "Will not appeal 'expulsion' ethics tribunal decision and will leave the party" (김병기 “‘제명’ 윤리심판원 결정에 재심 신청 않고 당 떠나겠다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/7DEHBOX2PBFBTIY2H3DFTXAVAY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Byeong-gi: "Will not appeal 'expulsion' ethics tribunal decision and will leave the party" (김병기 “‘제명’ 윤리심판원 결정에 재심 신청 않고 당 떠나겠다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GCV5JARJ55GWVB6NDIFPJ4FJOQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, Kim Byeong-gi, who received an expulsion penalty from the party's ethics tribunal over suspicions including nomination-related donations, stated on the 19th, "I will not apply for a retrial and will leave the party." (공천 헌금 의혹 등으로 당 윤리심판원에서 제명 처분을 받은 김병기 전 더불어민주당 원내대표가 19일 “재심 신청을 하지 않고 당을 떠나겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At an emergency press conference held at the National Assembly Communication Center that day, Representative Kim stated as above, saying, "I thought that if disagreements arise within the party because of me, or if my colleagues bear even the slightest mental burden, I should fully shoulder that burden and go." (김 의원은 이날 국회 소통관에서 연 긴급 기자회견에서 “저로 인해서 당 안에 이견이 생기고 동료들에게 조금이라도 마음의 짐이 된다면 그 부담만큼은 제가 온전히 짊어지고 가야 한다고 생각했다”며 이 같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim said, "I earnestly request my beloved Democratic Party. In the situation where I am not applying for a retrial, if (the ethics tribunal) seeks expulsion, please consider a method to conclude it with a Supreme Council decision," adding, "I do not want to impose even the slightest mental burden on senior, fellow, and junior lawmakers by going through the process of a general assembly of lawmakers' ratification." The ethics tribunal's expulsion decision is finalized by a vote of the general assembly of lawmakers; he requested that no separate general assembly be held as he himself would accept the disciplinary action. (김 의원은 “사랑하는 민주당에 간곡하게 부탁드린다. 제가 재심 신청하지 않은 상황에서 (윤리심판원이) 제명을 청구한다면 최고위원회의 결정으로 종결하는 방안을 검토해달라”면서 " 굳이 의원총회 추인을 거치면서 선배, 동료, 후배 의원 여러분께 조금이라도 마음의 부담을 지우고 싶지 않다”고 했다. 윤리심판원의 제명 결정은 의원총회의 의결로 확정되는데, 김 의원 본인이 징계를 받아들일테니 별도의 의총을 열지 말아달라고 요청한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Kim said, "The police investigation is already proceeding swiftly. I ask that you calmly wait until the results come out," and added, "Materials to prove that the suspicions are not true are prepared." He continued, "The substantive truth will surely be revealed," and said, "I will faithfully undergo the investigation and submit all related evidence to prove my innocence." (김 의원은 “경찰 수사는 이미 신속하게 진행되고 있다. 결과가 나올 때까지 차분히 지켜봐 주시길 부탁드린다”면서 “의혹이 사실이 아님을 입증할 자료는 준비되어 있다”고 했다. 이어 “실체적 진실은 반드시 드러날 것”이라면서 “충실히 조사를 받고 관련 증거를 모두 제출해서 무죄를 입증할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party's ethics tribunal held a meeting on the 12th and resolved to impose the highest-level disciplinary action, expulsion, on Representative Kim. Immediately after the ethics tribunal's decision, Representative Kim expressed his intention to contest it, saying, "I will immediately apply for a retrial," but on this day, he reversed his initial stance and accepted the disciplinary action.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (민주당 윤리심판원은 지난 12일 회의를 열고 김 의원에 대해 최고 수위 징계인 제명 처분을 의결했다. 김 의원은 윤리심판원 결정 직후 “즉시 재심을 청구하겠다”며 불복 의사를 밝혔지만, 이날 당초 입장을 뒤집고 징계를 수용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/7DEHBOX2PBFBTIY2H3DFTXAVAY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GCV5JARJ55GWVB6NDIFPJ4FJOQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae: "Jang Dong-hyeok Must End His Groundless Hunger Strike... The People Power Party Should Be Prostrating in Repentance" (정청래 “장동혁, 명분 없는 단식 중단해야...국힘은 석고대죄할 때”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Chung Cheong-rae: "Jang Dong-hyeok Must End His Groundless Hunger Strike... The People Power Party Should Be Prostrating in Repentance" (정청래 “장동혁, 명분 없는 단식 중단해야...국힘은 석고대죄할 때”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Chung Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, urged Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party who is on the fifth day of a hunger strike demanding a special investigation into the Unification Church and nomination-related donations, saying, "End your groundless hunger strike quickly." (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 통일교·공천 헌금 특검을 요구하며 5일째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 향해 19일 “명분 없는 단식을 얼른 중단하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the party's Supreme Council meeting held at the National Assembly that day, Representative Chung stated, "It is not the time for the People Power Party to be on a hunger strike; it is the time for them to be prostrating in repentance." (정 대표는 이날 국회에서 열린 당 최고위원회의에서 “국민의힘은 지금 단식할 때가 아니라 석고대죄할 때”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Chung said, "Having experienced a 24-day hunger strike myself at Gwanghwamun Square during the Sewol Ferry incident, I know very well how difficult a hunger strike is." He added, "From my experience, the periods from the 3rd to 4th day, the 7th to 8th day, and the 14th to 15th day are particularly tough. Representative Jang, you must be having a very hard time, so please end your groundless hunger strike quickly." He further advised, "Health is the most important thing. Eat and then fight." (정 대표는 “저도 세월호 때 광화문 광장에서 24일간 단식을 해봐서 단식이 얼마나 힘든가를 잘 알고 있다”면서 “제 경험으로는 3일에서 4일 넘어갈 때, 7일에서 8일 넘어갈 때, 14일에서 15일 넘어갈 때가 참 힘들더라. 장 대표님, 많이 힘드실 텐데 명분 없는 단식은 얼른 중단하시라”고 했다. 정 대표는 이어 “건강이 최고”라면서 “밥 먹고 싸우세요”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Representative Chung mentioned, "The law to establish a special tribunal for rebellion cases has already been passed and is awaiting implementation," and stated, "We will also pass judicial reform measures one by one without fail. We will pass legislation on the crime of distorting the law, judicial review petitions, and increasing the number of Supreme Court justices without any setbacks." (한편 정 대표는 “이미 내란재판부 설치법이 통과돼 시행을 앞두고 있다”면서 “사법 개혁도 따박따박 통과시키겠다. 법 왜곡죄, 재판소원, 대법관 증원 등 차질 없이 통과시킬 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the first-instance court's sentencing of former President Yoon Suk-yeol to five years in prison on charges of obstructing an arrest, Representative Chung said, "The outcome of a five-year prison sentence is somewhat disappointing," but added, "However, since you can't be full from the first bite, I evaluate this as our society taking its first step toward restoring democracy and constitutional order." Addressing former President Yoon, Representative Chung said, "An unrepentant, shameless, and ignorant ringleader of rebellion without any reflection or remorse must be permanently isolated from our society." (정 대표는 1심 법원이 윤석열 전 대통령의 체포 방해 혐의에 대해 징역 5년을 선고한 데 대해서는 “징역 5년이라는 결과는 다소 아쉽다”면서도 “무엇이든 첫술에 배부를 수는 없기에 우리 사회가 민주주의와 헌정 질서를 회복하는 첫걸음을 뗀 것이라고 평가한다”고 했다. 정 대표는 윤 전 대통령을 향해서는 “반성과 성찰이 없는 뻔뻔하고 무식한 내란 수괴는 우리 사회에서 영원히 격리시켜야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/SO2BXTCZ5ZBN7NJPDDN7UJ4ZDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/CTYAWSXLDVOBBHPENQQAPTOCAA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:41:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KOSPI Breaches 4800, Yet President Lee's Approval Rating Drops to 53%... "Due to Rift Between Party and Government, Bribery Allegations in Nominations" (코스피 4800 돌파에도 李대통령 지지율 하락해 53%…“당정 엇박자·공천 뇌물 논란 탓")</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;KOSPI Breaches 4800, Yet President Lee's Approval Rating Drops to 53%... "Due to Rift Between Party and Government, Bribery Allegations in Nominations" (코스피 4800 돌파에도 李대통령 지지율 하락해 53%…“당정 엇박자·공천 뇌물 논란 탓" )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A public opinion poll released on the 19th showed that President Lee Jae-myung's job approval rating has turned downward for the first time in three weeks, standing at 53.1%. (이재명 대통령의 국정 수행 지지도가 53.1%로 3주 만에 하락세로 돌아섰다는 여론조사 결과가 19일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to a survey conducted by Realmeter for the Energy Economy News from the 12th to the 16th, targeting 2,516 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, 53.1% of respondents gave a positive assessment of President Lee's job performance. This is a decrease of 3.7 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week. (리얼미터가 에너지경제신문 의뢰로 지난 12∼16일 전국 18세 이상 2516명을 대상으로 조사한 결과 이 대통령의 국정 수행을 긍정 평가한 응답자는 53.1%로 집계됐다. 지난주보다 3.7%포인트(p) 낮은 수치다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Negative assessments rose to 42.2%, up 4.4 percentage points from the previous survey. (부정 평가는 42.2%로 지난 조사 대비 4.4%p 올랐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter analyzed, "Despite economic and diplomatic achievements such as the KOSPI breaking through the 4800 mark and the Korea-Japan summit, the approval rating showed a downward trend as controversies over morality overlapped, including the exposure of disagreements between the ruling party and the government regarding the prosecution reform bill and allegations of nomination bribes and illegal election funds (bribery) involving ruling party figures." (리얼미터는 “코스피 4800선 돌파와 한일 정상회담 등 경제·외교 성과가 있었는데도 정부의 검찰 개혁안을 둘러싼 당정 이견 노출과 여권 인사들의 공천 헌금·선거 불법 자금(뇌물) 의혹 등 도덕성 논란이 겹치며 지지율이 하락세를 보였다”고 분석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a party support survey conducted from the 15th to the 16th of last month, targeting 1,004 adults nationwide aged 18 and over, the Democratic Party of Korea showed a support rate of 42.5%, while the People Power Party showed 37.0%. (지난달 15∼16일 전국 18세 이상 1004명을 대상으로 한 정당 지지도 조사에서는 더불어민주당이 42.5%, 국민의힘은 37.0%의 지지율을 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party fell by 5.3 percentage points compared to the previous week, showing a decline for the first time in four weeks, while the People Power Party rose by 3.5 percentage points, showing a rebound for the first time in four weeks. (민주당은 지난주 대비 5.3%p 하락하며 4주 만에 하락세를 보인 반면 국민의힘은 3.5%p 상승하며 4주 만에 반등세를 나타냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform New Party was at 3.3%, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party at 2.5%, and the Progressive Party at 1.7%. The non-partisan group was 11.5%. (개혁신당은 3.3%, 조국혁신당은 2.5%, 진보당은 1.7%로 나타났다. 무당층은 11.5%였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realmeter explained, "It is judged that the Democratic Party's decline widened as controversies over morality grew with the full-scale investigation into the nomination bribery allegations involving lawmakers Kang Seon-woo and Kim Byeong-gi, compounded by intra-party conflict due to criticism from hardliners within the party regarding the Serious Crime Investigation Office (SCIO) and the Public Prosecution Service Act." (리얼미터는 “민주당은 강선우·김병기 의원 공천 헌금 의혹 수사 본격화로 도덕성 논란이 커진 데다 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청법을 둘러싼 당내 강경파의 비판으로 당정 갈등이 겹치며 하락 폭을 키운 것으로 판단된다”고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the People Power Party, it interpreted, "It appears that the rebound in support was led by the consolidation of traditional supporters, such as those in the Daegu/Gyeongbuk region and conservative groups, due to the special prosecutor's demand for the death penalty for former President Yoon Suk-yeol and the controversy over the expulsion of Han Dong-hoon." (국민의힘에 대해서는 “특검의 윤석열 전 대통령 사형 구형과 한동훈 제명 논란으로 대구·경북과 보수층 등 전통 지지층이 결집해 지지율 반등을 이끈 것으로 보인다”고 해석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The margin of error for the presidential job approval rating survey is ±2.0 percentage points at a 95% confidence level, and for the party support survey, it is ±3.1 percentage points at a 95% confidence level. (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사의 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±2.0%p, 정당 지지도 조사 표본 오차는 95% 신뢰 수준에 ±3.1%p다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The response rate for the presidential job approval rating survey was 4.5%, and for the party support survey, it was 3.8%. For detailed information, please refer to the website of the National Election Survey Deliberation Commission.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (대통령 국정 수행 지지도 조사 응답률은 4.5%, 정당 지지도 조사 응답률은 3.8%였다. 자세한 내용은 중앙선거여론조사심의위원회 홈페이지 참조.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/6VGDUB47RNGHXF257U34W34C7I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M4SECI3PFFE7LA22XS42WTKPAA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:09:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Board of Audit and Inspection: "Public Institutions' Regional Talent Hiring Rate Falls Below 30%... Mandatory Hiring Lacks Effectiveness" (감사원 “공공기관 지역인재 채용률 30% 미달…의무채용 실효성 떨어져“)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/HNA62OPYVZHSXADVWO67VVKJUM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Board of Audit and Inspection: "Public Institutions' Regional Talent Hiring Rate Falls Below 30%... Mandatory Hiring Lacks Effectiveness" (감사원 “공공기관 지역인재 채용률 30% 미달…의무채용 실효성 떨어져“)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EHC3AZG4JNGG7K5UN3ERFIOURA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;An audit by the Board of Audit and Inspection (BAI) released on the 19th revealed that 'relocated public institutions,' which moved their headquarters from the metropolitan area to regional areas, are not properly adhering to the mandatory hiring ratio (30%) for regional talent. (본사를 수도권에서 지방으로 옮긴 ‘이전 공공기관’에서 지역 인재 의무 채용 비율(30%)이 잘 지켜지지 않고 있다는 감사원 감사 결과가 19일 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI announced the results of its audit on the 'Status of Public Institution Workforce Management' containing these findings. This audit, conducted from 2024 to 2025, was initiated in response to criticisms that the efficiency and productivity of public institution workforces are declining. It targeted a total of 37 public institutions, including Korea Electric Power Corporation (KEPCO). (감사원은 이날 이 같은 내용의 ‘공공기관 인력 운용 실태’ 감사 결과를 발표했다. 2024~2025년 진행된 이번 감사는 공공기관 인력의 효율성과 생산성이 하락하고 있다는 지적 등에 따라 실시됐다. 한국전력공사 등 총 37개 공공기관을 대상으로 진행됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the audit results, a significant number of relocated public institutions were found to have neglected hiring regional talent by excessively applying 'exception provisions' to the mandatory hiring requirement. Under current law, if the number of hires per examination field is five or fewer annually, the mandatory 30% hiring ratio does not apply. The audit found that this exception clause is being abused. (감사 결과에 따르면, 상당수 이전 공공기관은 의무 채용의 ‘예외 규정’을 과다 적용하는 방식으로 지역 인재 채용에 소홀했던 것으로 드러났다. 현행법상 시험 분야별 채용 인원이 연간 5명 이하이면, 의무 채용 비율 30%가 적용되지 않는다. 그런데 이 예외 조항이 남용되고 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, nine institutions, including Korea Gas Corporation, judged whether the number was 'five or fewer' based on individual examination units rather than on an 'annual' basis. Consequently, the mandatory hiring ratio was not properly applied in cases where it should have been. Three institutions, including Korea Expressway Corporation, also had issues with inconsistently applying 'job groups (e.g., administration)' and 'job series (e.g., management, legal affairs)' when classifying examination fields. (예를 들어 한국가스공사 등 9개 기관은 ‘연간’이 아닌 개별 시험 단위 기준으로 ‘5명 이하’ 여부를 판단했다. 결과적으로 의무 채용 비율이 적용돼야 할 경우에 제대로 적용되지 않은 것이다. 한국도로공사 등 3개 기관은 시험 분야를 분류할 때 ‘직군(행정 등)’과 ‘직렬(경영, 법정 등)’을 일관성 없이 적용하는 문제도 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Due to these problems, the hiring rate for regional talent compared to the total new hiring quota for relocated public institutions was 19.8% as of 2024, more than 10 percentage points lower than the mandatory hiring ratio (30%). (이런 문제 때문에 이전 공공기관의 총 신규 채용 정원 대비 지역 인재 채용률은 2024년 기준 19.8%로 의무 채용 비율(30%)보다 10%포인트 이상 낮았던 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some public institutions were found to have excessively applied preferential systems for regional talent. The BAI judged that 11 institutions, including Korea Tourism Organization, simultaneously applied a 'point addition system' that gives extra points to regional talent and a 'hiring target system' that mandates hiring over 30%, causing excessive disadvantage to general applicants. (반면 일부 공공기관은 지역 인재 우대 제도를 과도하게 적용한 것으로 나타났다. 한국관광공사 등 11개 기관은 지역 인재에 가산점을 주는 ‘가점제’와 30% 이상을 의무 채용하는 ‘채용 목표제’를 동시에 적용해 일반 지원자에게 과도한 불이익을 줬다는 것이 감사원 판단이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the BAI's simulation analysis, if it were assumed that only the hiring target system remained and the effect of the point addition system was removed over the past four years, an estimated 4,026 general applicants who had failed would have passed, while 563 regional talent who had passed would have failed. This essentially indicates a problem of 'reverse discrimination.' (감사원의 모의 분석 결과, 이 경우 만약 채용 목표제만 남기고 가점제 효과를 없앤다고 가정하면 지난 4년간 탈락했던 일반 지원자 4026명이 합격하고, 합격했던 지역 인재 563명이 탈락하는 것으로 추산됐다. ‘역차별’ 문제가 발생한 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the BAI did not judge the problems revealed regarding regional talent hiring as 'illegal.' A BAI official stated, "We view these issues as arising from insufficient detailed standards or regulations and have requested institutional improvements." (감사원은 다만 지역 인재 채용과 관련해 드러난 문제들을 ‘불법’이라고 판단하지는 않았다. 감사원 관계자는 “관련 세부 기준이나 규정이 미비해서 일어난 것으로 보고, 제도 개선을 주문했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in many public institutions, a phenomenon has emerged where employees are reluctant to be promoted to junior managerial positions at level 3/4 or higher or to executive positions. For instance, at KEPCO KPS, the competition rate for junior managerial positions was only 0.2 to 1 as of 2024. This is understood to be due to the excessive workload for managers and low compensation for executives. (이 밖에 상당수 공공기관에선 직원들이 3·4급 이상 초급 간부나 임원으로 승진하는 것을 기피하려는 현상이 나타났다. 예를 들어 한전KPS의 경우 2024년 기준 초급 간부 경쟁률이 0.2대 1에 불과했다. 간부들의 과중한 업무, 임원들의 낮은 보수 때문인 것으로 파악됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another problem revealed was the poor work performance of wage-peak system participants. Particularly when these employees perform different tasks than before entering the wage-peak system, 28% of their department heads responded in a survey that the employees' actual working hours were "less than 5 hours per week." A BAI official said, "This is effectively an evaluation that they are not working properly." This was analyzed to be because it is difficult to provide personnel incentives like promotion to wage-peak system participants. (또 임금피크 대상자의 업무 실적이 저조하다는 문제점도 드러났다. 특히 해당 직원이 임금피크 전 업무와 다른 업무를 하는 경우, 소속 부서장들이 설문에서 해당 직원들의 실질 업무 시간에 대해 “주 5시간 미만”이라고 답하는 경우가 28%에 달했다. 감사원 관계자는 “사실상 제대로 업무를 하지 않는다고 평가한 것”이라고 했다. 이는 임금피크 대상자의 경우 승진 등 인사상 인센티브 제공이 어렵기 때문인 것으로 분석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BAI stated that it has notified relevant ministries, including the Ministry of Economy and Finance and the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, of the problems revealed in this audit and requested institutional improvements. (감사원은 이번 감사로 드러난 문제점에 대해 재경부·국토부 등에 통보 조치하고 제도 개선 등을 요구했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/HNA62OPYVZHSXADVWO67VVKJUM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EHC3AZG4JNGG7K5UN3ERFIOURA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk: "Government's Prosecution Service and Serious Crimes Investigation Agency Bills Must Be Completely Revised"... Pushes for Scrapping if No Revisions (조국 “공소청·중수청법 정부안 전면 수정해야”...수정 없으면 폐기 추진)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/UVVL2Y4JXFF6LLXAXXUDTRZYRE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Cho Kuk: "Government's Prosecution Service and Serious Crimes Investigation Agency Bills Must Be Completely Revised"... Pushes for Scrapping if No Revisions (조국 “공소청·중수청법 정부안 전면 수정해야”...수정 없으면 폐기 추진)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EKQT7VHAS5MR5E6B6Q64WP7DS4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party demanded a complete revision of the Serious Crimes Investigation Agency (SCIA) and Prosecution Service bills, which the government has pre-announced for legislation, and stated that if the government does not comply, it will push for the complete scrapping of the bills. The demands include codifying the abolition of prosecutors' supplementary investigation rights in the Prosecution Service bill and unifying the dual structure of the SCIA into a single entity. (조국혁신당은 정부가 입법 예고한 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청법의 전면 수정을 요구하고, 정부가 응하지 않으면 법안 전면 폐기를 추진하겠다고 19일 밝혔다. 공소청법에 검사의 보완 수사권 폐지를 명문화하고, 중수청 이원화 구조를 일원화하라는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk, the leader of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, made these remarks during a joint meeting of the party's Supreme Council, general assembly of lawmakers, and the 'We Go All the Way' special committee. He stated, "The government's pre-announced bill only mimics the separation of prosecution and investigation, which is the core of prosecution reform." (조국 조국혁신당 대표는 이날 당 최고위원회의·의원총회·‘끝까지 간다’ 특별위원회 연석회의에서 “정부 입법 예고안은 검찰 개혁의 핵심인 기소와 수사 분리를 흉내만 낸 것”이라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After unveiling the party's alternative bill, Representative Cho explained, "We have stipulated in the supplementary provisions of the Prosecution Service bill that Article 196 of the Criminal Procedure Act, which defines prosecutors' investigation rights, should be abolished." He also emphasized, "The SCIA must not become a revival of the Supreme Prosecutors' Office's SCIA, which was abolished in 2013," narrowing the SCIA's investigation scope from nine major crimes (as per the government bill) to four: corruption, economic crimes, defense project crimes, and investigations into insurrection and foreign aggression. Regarding the SCIA's organization, he said, "We eliminated the dual system of 'investigative judicial officers,' who are essentially prosecutors, and 'specialized investigators,' who only play a supporting role," and "We unified all investigators as 'investigators.'" (조 대표는 당 차원의 대안 법안을 공개한 뒤 “검사 수사권을 규정한 형사소송법 196조를 폐기하도록 공소청 법안 부칙에 명기했다”고 밝혔다. 또 “중수청이 2013년 폐지된 대검 중수부의 부활 조직이 돼서는 안 된다”면서 중수청의 수사 범위를 9대 범죄(정부안)에서 부패·경제·방위 사업 범죄, 내란·외환 수사 등 4개로 좁혔다. 중수청 조직에 대해서는 “사실상 검사인 ‘수사사법관’과 보조 역할만 하는 ‘전문 수사관’의 이원화 체제를 없앴다”면서 “수사하는 이는 모두 ‘수사관’으로 통일시켰다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Cho stated, "If the government does not accept this proposal, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party will pursue legislation led by the National Assembly instead of the government bill." (조 대표는 “정부가 이 안을 수용하지 않는다면 조국혁신당은 정부안 대신 국회 주도 입법을 추진할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the same day, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party also demanded a complete reorganization of the government's Prosecution Reform Promotion Team. The party has criticized the team, arguing that because many prosecutors are dispatched to it, it has produced prosecution-centric alternatives. The party stated, "If the government does not comply, we will push for the dissolution of the promotion team and pursue legislation led by the National Assembly." (조국혁신당은 이날 정부 검찰개혁추진단의 전면 재구성도 요구했다. 조국혁신당은 검찰개혁추진단에 검사가 다수 파견돼 있어 검찰 중심의 대안이 나왔다고 비판해왔다. 당은 “정부가 이에 응하지 않는 경우 추진단 해산 및 국회 주도 입법을 추진하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/UVVL2Y4JXFF6LLXAXXUDTRZYRE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/EKQT7VHAS5MR5E6B6Q64WP7DS4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:36:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea's Kim Yong-chol, 'Mastermind Behind Cheonan Sinking', Denied Responsibility During 2018 PyeongChang Olympics Visit, Saying "We Didn't Do It" (‘천안함 폭침 주범’ 北 김영철, 2018년 평창올림픽 방한 때 “우린 안 해” 책임 부인)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/E67VUSKSCRBEHJUDDO2NTBUSS4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea's Kim Yong-chol, 'Mastermind Behind Cheonan Sinking', Denied Responsibility During 2018 PyeongChang Olympics Visit, Saying "We Didn't Do It" (‘천안함 폭침 주범’ 北 김영철, 2018년 평창올림픽 방한 때 “우린 안 해” 책임 부인)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7AVNLUXPD5JPLGREIJ4O6FQCEE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was revealed on the 19th that Kim Yong-chol, a senior advisor to the North Korean Workers' Party's United Front Department, denied responsibility for the 2010 Cheonan warship sinking incident to South Korean officials during his visit to South Korea for the 2018 PyeongChang Olympics, saying, "We did not do it." (김영철 북한 조선노동당 통일전선부 고문이 지난 2018년 평창올림픽 당시 방한한 자리에서 2010년 천안함 폭침 사건에 대해 한국 측에 “우리는 하지 않았다”며 책임을 부인한 것으로 19일 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advisor Kim, who previously headed the Reconnaissance General Bureau, North Korea's agency overseeing operations against the South, is considered one of the masterminds behind the Cheonan sinking incident. (김 고문은 북한의 대남 공작 총괄 기구인 정찰총국장을 지낸 인물로, 천안함 폭침 사건을 일으킨 주범 중 한 명으로 꼽힌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon Kun-young of the Democratic Party of Korea is scheduled to publish a memoir titled 'The Panmunjom Project' on the 21st, which contains these details. Rep. Yoon previously served as the Director of the National Situation Room in the Blue House during the Moon Jae-in administration. (더불어민주당 윤건영 의원은 이 같은 내용 등을 담은 회고록 ‘판문점 프로젝트’를 오는 21일 출간할 예정이다. 윤 의원은 문재인 정부 청와대 국정상황실장을 지냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the book, in 2018, Advisor Kim (then head of the Workers' Party's United Front Department) visited South Korea as part of a delegation ahead of the PyeongChang Olympics closing ceremony. Rep. Yoon, who was the National Situation Room Director at the time, reportedly met with Advisor Kim and asked about the Cheonan sinking. (책에 따르면, 2018년 김 고문(당시 노동당 통일전선부장)은 평창올림픽 폐회식을 앞두고 사절단으로 한국을 방문했다. 당시 국정상황실장이었던 윤 의원은 김 고문을 만나 천안함 폭침에 대해 물었다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Kim reportedly said, "At the time of the incident, I was in the provinces and came to Pyongyang the day after the Cheonan accident," and "We did not do it," the book relays. Advisor Kim also reportedly stated, "We clearly expressed regret to the South as fellow countrymen," and "We proposed a joint investigation, but former President Lee Myung-bak rejected it. Let's investigate jointly even now." (그러자 김 고문은 “사건 당시 (나는) 지방에 있었고, 천안함 사고가 일어난 다음 날 평양으로 왔다”며 “우리는 (천안함 폭침을) 하지 않았다”고 말했다고 책은 전했다. 김 고문은 “우리는 (사고에 대해) 동족으로서 남측에 유감 표명을 분명히 했다”, “우리는 공동 조사를 제안했으나 이명박 전 대통령이 거부했다. 지금이라도 공동으로 조사하자” 등 발언도 했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the book, Rep. Yoon said, "I was at a loss," and "He himself was strongly denying it, and it was a situation where we couldn't forcibly investigate someone who came as a congratulatory delegate for a national event." (윤 의원은 책에서 “난감했다”며 “본인은 강력하게 아니라고 하는데, 국가적 행사에 축하 사절단으로 온 사람을 강제로 조사할 수도 없는 상황이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Advisor Kim led the Reconnaissance General Bureau, North Korea's agency in charge of operations against the South, from February 2009 to early 2016. The South Korean military and intelligence authorities concluded that the Cheonan sinking, which occurred in March 2010, was the work of the Reconnaissance General Bureau and have since pointed to Advisor Kim as being behind the incident. North Korean authorities have maintained to this day that "the Cheonan incident is a massive fabricated plot orchestrated by the conservative regime." They have never apologized. (김 고문은 2009년 2월부터 2016년 초까지 북한의 대남 공작 총괄 기구인 정찰총국을 이끌었다. 우리 군·정보 당국은 2010년 3월 발생한 천안함 폭침을 정찰총국의 소행으로 결론 내린 뒤 김 고문을 사건 배후로 지목해 왔다. 북한 당국은 현재까지 “천안함 사건은 보수 정권이 조작한 특대형 모략극”이라고 주장해 왔다. 사과한 적도 없다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"It's Regrettable That President Lee Did Not Consult Former President Moon Before the South Korea-U.S. Summit"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“李 대통령, 한미 회담 전 文 전 대통령 안 찾은 것은 아쉬워”&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the book, Rep. Yoon also offered 'harsh criticism' regarding the foreign policy decision-making process of the Lee Jae-myung administration. (윤 의원은 책에서 이재명 정부의 외교 정책 결정 과정에 대한 ‘쓴소리’도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "One regret is, ahead of the first South Korea-U.S. summit last August, why didn't President Lee Jae-myung seek out former President Moon Jae-in?" adding, "Who is the South Korean leader who had the most conversations with President Trump and knows President Trump best? It is precisely former President Moon." (그는 “한 가지 아쉬운 것은, 지난 8월 첫 번째 한·미 정상회담을 앞두고 이재명 대통령이 왜 문재인 전 대통령을 찾지 않았을까 하는 부분”이라며 “트럼프 대통령과 가장 많은 대화를 나누고, 트럼프 대통령을 가장 잘 아는 대한민국 지도자는 누구인가. 바로 문 전 대통령”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "He should have met him to seek advice, or if he was really busy, he should have sought consultation over the phone, but he did not do so." He further stated, "(The Lee Jae-myung administration) also needs to actively utilize the foreign affairs and security capabilities of the Yoon Suk Yeol administration." (그러면서 “(문 전 대통령을) 만나서 조언을 구하거나, 정 바쁘다면 전화상으로 자문을 구할 법도 한데 그러지 않았다”고 했다. 이어 “(이재명 정부가) 윤석열 정부의 외교 안보 역량도 적극적으로 활용할 필요가 있다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon then mentioned the case where former President Moon, early in his term, personally met with then-Foreign Minister Yun Byung-se, who was appointed by his predecessor former President Park Geun-hye, and asked in detail about the South Korea-Japan comfort women agreement. Rep. Yoon said, "In diplomacy, no country can flip over agreements made by a previous government like turning over one's hand." (윤 의원은 그러면서 문 전 대통령이 집권 초기 전임인 박근혜 전 대통령이 임명한 윤병세 당시 외교부 장관을 직접 만나 한·일 위안부 합의에 대해 세세한 부분까지 물어봤던 사례를 언급했다. 윤 의원은 “외교에 있어서는 어느 국가라도 이전 정부가 맺은 합의를 손바닥 뒤집듯이 바꿀 수는 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Kim Jong-un Joked After Hearing 'Like Being Shot' Song, Saying "It Would Be Serious If N. Korean Youth Followed Along"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇김정은, ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ 노래 듣고 “北 젊은이들 따라 하면 심각” 농담도&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon also relayed an anecdote from the 'Spring Comes' performance held in Pyongyang in April 2018 by a South Korean art troupe. At the time, singer Baek Ji-young, a member of the troupe, sang songs like 'Like Being Shot' and 'Don't Forget', and the girl group Red Velvet performed stages for songs like 'Red Flavor' and 'Bad Boy'. (윤 의원은 2018년 4월 대한민국 측 예술단이 평양에서 연 ‘봄이 온다’ 공연의 후일담도 전했다. 당시 예술단 일원이었던 가수 백지영씨는 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ ‘잊지 말아요’ 등 노래를 불렀고, 걸그룹 레드벨벳은 ‘빨간맛’ ‘배드 보이’ 등 무대를 선보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Yoon, who reportedly strongly recommended Ms. Baek and Red Velvet for the art troupe at the time, wrote in the book, "I wanted to properly show K-pop, which is hugely popular worldwide, to the citizens of Pyongyang," but "However, the only idol group I knew at the time was Red Velvet." He added, "Frankly, I also considered the fact that the team name contained 'Red'." (당시 백씨와 레드벨벳을 예술단으로 강력하게 추천했다는 윤 의원은 책에서 “세계적으로 큰 인기를 누리고 있는 K팝을 평양 시민에게 제대로 보여주고 싶었다”며 “그런데 당시 내가 알고 있던 아이돌 그룹이 레드벨벳뿐이었다”고 했다. 또 “솔직히 팀 이름에 ‘Red’가 들어가 있는 것도 참작했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Ms. Baek, he said, "She is also someone who sings exceptionally well, and I wondered what Pyongyang citizens would think if they heard her song 'Like Being Shot'. I thought it would be very interesting." (백씨에 대해선 “노래를 워낙 잘하시는 분이기도 하고, 그가 부른 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’을 평양 시민들이 들어보면 어떨까 생각했다. 무척 재미날 것 같았다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In reality, after hearing performances including Baek Ji-young's 'Like Being Shot', Chairman Kim Jong-un reportedly joked, "It would be a serious situation if North Korean young people started singing along," Rep. Yoon wrote in the book. (실제 김정은 위원장은 백지영씨의 ‘총 맞은 것처럼’ 등 공연을 듣고, “북측 젊은이들이 따라 부르면 심각한 상황이 오겠다”는 농담을 하기도 했다고 윤 의원은 책에 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/E67VUSKSCRBEHJUDDO2NTBUSS4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7AVNLUXPD5JPLGREIJ4O6FQCEE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:08:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Installs "South Korea is the Primary Enemy State" Signage at Ideological Education Facility (北 사상교육 시설에 “한국은 제1의 적대국” 게시물 설치)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/RM7XOBEYWZGZJP4KG6ML3KEF6Q/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/T5IV6XCMHROQNK7QA67BILCZVQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea, which has declared inter-Korean relations as a 'relationship between two hostile states,' has reportedly installed signage stating "South Korea is the primary enemy state" at a 'Class Education Hall,' a space used to instill anti-U.S. and anti-South Korea hostility. (남북관계를 ‘적대적 두 국가 관계’로 선언한 북한이 대미·대남 적개심을 주입하는 공간인 ‘계급교양관’에 “한국은 제1의 적대국”이라는 내용의 게시물을 설치한 것으로 나타났다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Central News Agency reported on the 19th that participants in an event commemorating the 80th anniversary of the founding of the Socialist Patriotic Youth League (Youth League) visited the Central Class Education Hall in Pyongyang, and included a photo of soldiers listening to an instructor's explanation. (조선중앙통신은 19일 사회주의애국청년동맹(청년동맹) 창립 80주년 기념행사 참가자들이 평양 시내 중앙계급교양관을 참관했다며 군인들이 강사의 설명을 듣는 사진을 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interior view revealed in the photo shows two wall surfaces densely covered with content inciting anti-South Korea hostility. The upper parts of the walls prominently display phrases such as "South Korea is the primary enemy state, the unchanging main enemy," "Our 'system overthrow'," and "confrontation frenzy." Also captured was a display of Article 3 of the South Korean constitution, which states, "The territory of the Republic of Korea shall consist of the Korean Peninsula and its adjacent islands." This appears to be using Article 3 as propaganda to claim that South Korea maintains a hostile policy towards North Korea and aims for absorption unification. (사진에 공개된 내부 모습을 보면 두 개 벽면에 대남 적개심을 부추기는 내용이 빼곡히 설치돼 있다. 벽면 상단에는 각각 “한국은 제1의 적대국, 불변의 주적” “우리의 ‘제도전복’, “대결광기” 등의 문구가 크게 부착됐다. 또 “대한민국의 영토는 한반도와 그 부속도서로 한다”는 내용의 남한 헌법 3조를 게시한 모습도 포착됐다. 한국이 북한에 적대 노선을 유지하고 흡수통일을 노리고 있다는 선전의 근거로 헌법 3조를 활용하고 있는 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a speech at the Supreme People's Assembly last September, Chairman of the State Affairs Commission Kim Jong Un criticized former President Syngman Rhee for promulgating a constitution in July 1948 that included the clause "The territory of the Republic of Korea shall consist of the Korean Peninsula and its adjacent islands," which contained the will for absorption unification, stating it "codified the most hostile innate nature towards our state." In a Supreme People's Assembly speech in January 2024, Kim Jong Un also instructed that it should be stipulated in constitutional clauses to "strengthen educational and indoctrination work to firmly regard the Republic of Korea as the primary enemy state and the unchanging main enemy." (김정은 국무위원장은 지난해 9월 최고인민회의 연설에서 이승만 전 대통령이 1948년 7월 흡수통일 의지가 담긴 ‘대한민국의 영토는 한반도와 그 부속 도서로 한다’는 조문이 포함된 헌법을 공포했다면서 “우리 국가에 가장 적대적인 태생적 본성을 성문화했다”고 비난했었다. 김정은은 2024년 1월 최고인민회의 연설에선 “대한민국을 철두철미 제1의 적대국으로, 불변의 주적으로 확고히 간주하도록 교육교양사업을 강화한다는 것”을 헌법 조문에 명기해야 할 것을 지시하기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Central Class Education Hall is a facility for the North Korean authorities' ideological education of residents. It opened in 2016 on the banks of the Pothong River in Pyongyang. It is a space filled with exhibits aimed at fostering hostility towards free democratic countries with different systems from North Korea, such as South Korea, the United States, and Japan. (중앙계급교양관은 북한 당국의 주민들에 대한 사상교육을 위한 곳으로 평양 보통강변에 2016년 개관했다. 한국, 미국, 일본 등 북한과 체제가 다른 자유민주주의 국가들에 대한 적대감을 고취하는 내용의 전시물로 꾸려진 공간이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/19/RM7XOBEYWZGZJP4KG6ML3KEF6Q/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/T5IV6XCMHROQNK7QA67BILCZVQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:42:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Byeong-gi, Who Said He Would Accept Expulsion, Voluntarily Leaves Democratic Party (제명 따르겠다던 김병기, 민주당 자진 탈당)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/AIHPNCAF3VB7JPPGFJBDONCAJ4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VRSNPY2JGJC2BABUGD7P7EYAIE.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been reported that former floor leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, Kim Byeong-gi, submitted a letter of resignation to the party's Seoul chapter on the 19th. (김병기 전 더불어민주당 원내대표가 19일 민주당 서울시당에 탈당계를 제출한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This comes just seven days after he received an 'expulsion' ruling from the party's Ethics Tribunal on the 12th over various allegations, including receiving nomination-related donations. (그가 지난 12일 민주당 윤리심판원에서 공천 헌금 수수 등 각종 의혹으로 ‘제명’ 처분을 받은 지 7일 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier that day, former floor leader Kim held a press conference at the National Assembly Communication Center and stated, "I have not yet received the official decision document from the Ethics Tribunal, but I will leave without applying for a retrial." (앞서 김 전 원내대표는 이날 국회 소통관에서 기자회견을 열고 “아직까지 윤리심판원의 결정문을 통보받지 못했지만 재심을 신청하지 않고 떠나겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the press conference, he also drew a line at voluntary resignation, saying, "I have said that even if I am expelled, I will not choose to leave the party on my own. That position remains the same." However, he appears to have reversed his stance afterward.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (그는 또 기자회견에서 “제명당하더라도 스스로 당을 떠나는 선택은 하지 않겠다고 말해왔다. 그 입장은 지금도 같다”며 자진 탈당에 선을 그었다. 그러나 이후 입장을 선회한 것으로 보인다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/AIHPNCAF3VB7JPPGFJBDONCAJ4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VRSNPY2JGJC2BABUGD7P7EYAIE.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:01:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meloni: "My Daughter is a K-pop Fan, an Even Stronger Alliance" Lee: "Grazie" (멜로니 “제 딸이 K팝 팬, 더욱 굳건한 동맹으로” 李 “그라찌에”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/KTSW5EDMFFDKXHGWNCIUCHL53U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Meloni: "My Daughter is a K-pop Fan, an Even Stronger Alliance" Lee: "Grazie" (멜로니 “제 딸이 K팝 팬, 더욱 굳건한 동맹으로” 李 “그라찌에”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OC6NBGRHJVPITBSQ2MDHTL6DRI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung met with Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni, who is on an official visit to South Korea on the 19th, and stated, "In today's meeting, Prime Minister Meloni and I agreed to further develop bilateral relations to a future-oriented level befitting the title of strategic partners." (이재명 대통령은 19일 공식 방한한 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리와 만나 “오늘 회담에서 저와 멜로니 총리님은 전략적 동반자라는 명칭에 부합하는 미래 지향적인 수준으로 양국관계를 더욱 발전시켜 나가기로 합의했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks during a joint press conference after holding a summit with Prime Minister Meloni at the Presidential Office. He said, "South Korea and Italy are very old friends, having celebrated the 140th anniversary of diplomatic relations the year before last." The two leaders held small-group and expanded talks on the same day, followed by a signing ceremony for a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) covering cooperation in the semiconductor industry, among other areas. (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 멜로니 총리와 정상회담을 한 뒤 공동 언론 발표를 통해 “한국과 이탈리아는 재작년 수교 140주년을 기념할 만큼 아주 오래된 친구”라며 이 같이 밝혔다. 양국 정상은 이날 소인수·확대 회담을 한 뒤, 반도체 산업 협력 등을 담은 양해각서(MOU) 서명식을 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Cooperation in the trade sector will be further expanded to a level commensurate with the economic scale and brand power of both countries," adding, "To this end, we agreed to revitalize the Korea-Italy Business Forum, involving companies from both nations, as a venue for creating new opportunities and a channel for addressing corporate difficulties." (이 대통령은 “교역 분야의 협력은 양국의 경제 규모와 브랜드파워에 걸맞는 수준으로 더욱 확대될 것”이라며 “이를 위해 양국 기업이 참여하는 한-이탈리아 비즈니스 포럼을 새로운 기회 창출의 장이자 기업들의 애로상담 창구로 활성화하겠다는 데 뜻을 모았다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Cooperation in the science sector, which determines a nation's future, will be further expanded," stating, "We will continuously discover capable researchers through support for joint research in basic and applied fields and further broaden the horizon of cooperation into advanced industries such as artificial intelligence and aerospace." (이어 “국가의 미래가 달린 과학 분야의 협력이 더욱 확대될 것”이라며 “기초 응용 분야 공동연구 지원을 통해 역량 있는 연구자들을 지속 발굴하고 인공지능, 우주항공 같은 첨단산업으로 협력의 지평을 더욱 넓혀가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Meloni said, "This visit is a very important visit strategically," adding, "I want to once again maintain an even stronger alliance with South Korea." She further stated, "The two countries should further explore which areas have unlimited potential for development," citing key mineral supply chains, semiconductors, transportation and infrastructure, and investment as areas for future cooperation expansion. (멜로니 총리는 “이번 방문은 전략적으로 매우 중요한 방문”이라며 “다시 한 번 더욱 더 한국과 굳건한 동맹 관계를 유지하고자 한다”고 했다. 이어 “양국은 무한한 가능성을 가지고 발전시킬 수 있는 분야가 어떤 분야인지 더 탐색해야 한다”며 향후 협력 확대 분야로 핵심 광물 공급망, 반도체, 교통 및 인프라, 투자 등을 꼽았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Meloni said, "My daughter is also a K-pop fan," adding, "Currently, South Korea is promoting its soft power through K-pop, and we can explore ways to enhance cooperation in that field as well." Prime Minister Meloni once again invited President Lee for a state visit to Italy. She said, "I have always thought very positively of President Lee's practical approach, so I always want to hear his valuable opinions on the international crises or issues we face," adding, "I sincerely hope you will visit Italy on a state visit." President Lee responded in Italian, "Grazie (Thank you)." (멜로니 총리는 “제 딸이 K팝 팬이기도 하다”며 “지금 한국이 K팝으로 소프트파워를 알리고 있는데, 그 분야에서도 협력 증진을 탐색할 수 있다”고 했다. 멜로니 총리는 이날 이 대통령에게 이탈리아 국빈 방문을 재차 요청했다. 그는 “평소 이 대통령의 실용적 접근 방식을 굉장히 긍정적으로 생각해왔기에 우리가 당면한 국제적 위기 상황이나 현안에 대해 고견을 항상 듣고자 한다”며 “꼭 이탈리아를 국빈 방문해주셨으면 좋겠다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 이탈리아어로 “그라찌에(Grazie·감사합니다)”라고 화답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/KTSW5EDMFFDKXHGWNCIUCHL53U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OC6NBGRHJVPITBSQ2MDHTL6DRI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:59:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Seong-gyu, Progressive Party Chief Spokesperson, Runs for Gyeonggi Governor... "Will Appoint a Vice Governor for Labor" (홍성규 진보당 수석대변인, 경기도지사 출마…“노동부지사 임명”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/G3YQD4IHWZBG5HYZKDE5QA45SQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4TQMTDGQ4DKMZWME3DQOBTGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hong Seong-gyu, the Progressive Party's chief spokesperson, held a press conference at the Gyeonggi Provincial Council briefing room on the 19th and declared his candidacy for governor of Gyeonggi Province in the June 3 local elections. (홍성규 진보당 수석대변인은 19일 경기도의회 브리핑룸에서 기자회견을 열어 6·3 지방선거 경기도지사 출마를 선언했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Hong stated, "The four years under Governor Kim Dong-yeon of the Democratic Party of Korea were a period of 'regression and chaos.' Governor Kim never once met with the Korean Confederation of Trade Unions throughout his term, and while claiming to be a climate governor, he did not let go of the scam that is the Gyeonggi International Airport," adding, "A decisive break from the past four years is the start of a new Gyeonggi Province." (홍 수석대변인은 “김동연 더불어민주당 경기도지사의 4년은 ‘퇴행과 혼란’이었다. 김 지사는 임기 내내 단 한 번도 민주노총을 만나지 않았고 기후도지사를 자처하면서 경기국제공항이라는 사기극을 놓지 않았다”며 “지난 4년과 단호히 결별하는 것이 새로운 경기도의 시작”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He pledged, "Respect for labor is the solid foundation of the new Gyeonggi provincial administration, irreplaceable by anything else. I will appoint a 'Vice Governor for Labor' to be part of the provincial administration from start to finish," and "As fundamental solutions to the pressing issues of waste and care, I will establish a 'Gyeonggi-type circular economy model' and a 'tailored public care system.'" (그는 “노동 존중은 무엇과도 대체할 수 없는 새로운 경기도정의 단단한 근간으로 ‘노동부지사’를 임명해 도정의 처음부터 끝까지 함께 하겠다”며 “당면 과제인 쓰레기 문제와 돌봄에 대한 근본 해법으로 경기도형 순환경제모델과 맞춤형 공공돌봄체계’를 구축하겠다”고 공약했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the Progressive Party elected Chief Spokesperson Hong as its candidate for Gyeonggi governor through a vote of all eligible party members from September 26 to 30 last year. (앞서 진보당은 지난해 9월 26~30일 권리당원 총투표를 통해 홍 수석대변인을 경기도지사 후보로 선출했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chief Spokesperson Hong had previously run as the Gyeonggi governor candidate for the People's Party, the predecessor of the Progressive Party, in the 7th local elections eight years ago in 2018. (홍 수석대변인은 8년 전인 2018년 제7회 지방선거에서 진보당의 전신인 민중당 경기도지사 후보로 출마한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/G3YQD4IHWZBG5HYZKDE5QA45SQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4TQMTDGQ4DKMZWME3DQOBTGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:22:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Party Bulletin Controversy', Shin Dong-wook Reiterates Demand for "Supreme Council Verification"... Yang Hyang-ja Urges "Let's Win Through Unity" (‘당게 논란’, 신동욱 “최고위 검증” 재차 요구...양향자 “단결로 승리하자”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W6V7PAHMGJFXDHZSYUCYLBJY6E/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;'Party Bulletin Controversy', Shin Dong-wook Reiterates Demand for "Supreme Council Verification"... Yang Hyang-ja Urges "Let's Win Through Unity" (‘당게 논란’, 신동욱 “최고위 검증” 재차 요구...양향자 “단결로 승리하자”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SKGWRJ4NBZH5HNKFUDR2J7DESE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shin Dong-wook, a Supreme Council member of the People Power Party, on the 19th, reiterated his demand for a public verification at the Supreme Council level regarding the party's Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon over the 'party member bulletin incident'. He also addressed former leader Han, saying, "I hope he will respond whether he will accept the proposal or not." (신동욱 국민의힘 최고위원이 19일 당 윤리위원회가 ‘당원 게시판 사건’과 관련해 한동훈 전 대표에 대한 제명 결정을 한 것을 두고 최고위원회 차원의 공개 검증을 재차 요구했다. 그러면서 한 전 대표를 향해 “제안에 응할 것인지 말 것인지 답해주길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Shin, who had previously proposed a public verification at the Supreme Council level on the 17th, stated at the Supreme Council meeting held in the National Assembly Rotunda, where leader Jang Dong-hyuk is conducting a hunger strike, "This is not to deny or reject the results of the party audit committee's audit or the Ethics Committee's (expulsion) decision." (앞서 지난 17일에도 최고위 차원의 공개 검증을 제안했던 신 최고위원은 이날 장동혁 대표가 단식 투쟁 중인 국회 로텐더홀에서 열린 최고위원회의에서 “당무감사위원회의 당무감사 결과나 윤리위원회의 (제명) 결정을 부정, 부인하는 게 아니다”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "There are various interpretations and evaluations different from my own thoughts," adding, "This is not an admission of a 'fabricated audit'. I expressed my concern that if evaluations and measures are not based on factual relationships and are handled emotionally, it could lead to major problems later." (그는 “여러 가지 제 생각과 다른 해석과 평가들이 있다”며 “조작감사라는 것에 대해 인정하는 게 아니다. 이 문제는 감정으로 처리할 게 아니라 사실관계에 기반한 평가와 조치가 내려지지 않는다면 나중에 큰 문제가 생길 수 있다는 제 걱정을 표현한 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "If the party audit committee or ethics committee cannot be trusted, then the Supreme Council members will make a calm judgment and evaluation," stating, "The Supreme Council is a place where various factions elected by our party members gather." (그러면서 “당감위나 윤리위를 못 믿겠다면 최고위원들이 냉정하게 판단해 평가를 내리겠다는 것”이라며 “최고위는 우리 당원이 선출한 여러 계파가 모인 곳”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Jo Gwang-han, appointed by leader Jang, commented on former leader Han's apology the previous day regarding the party bulletin controversy, calling it "insincere wordplay" and saying "it reminded me of 'crocodile tears'." (장 대표가 지명한 조광한 최고위원은 한 전 대표가 전날 당게 논란에 대해 사과한 것에 대해 “진정성 없는 말장난”이라며 “‘악어의 눈물’이 떠올랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Yang Hyang-ja urged reconciliation, saying, "Unfortunately, supporters of the People Power Party are divided into two." She said, "Can't we accept leader Jang's intention for the hunger strike as it is and believe in the sincerity of leader Han's apology?" and added, "How can our party, which treats a hunger strike as an object of ridicule and even an apology as an object of hatred, gain the public's trust and lead the country?" While expressing regret over the content of former leader Han's apology, she urged, "Let's end the conflict with a warm embrace for each other and win through unity." (양향자 최고위원은 “안타깝게도 국민의힘 지지자들은 둘로 나뉘어져 있다”며 봉합을 요구했다. 그는 “장 대표가 단식하는 의도를 있는 그대로 받아주고 한 대표가 사과하는 진심 그대로를 좀 믿어줄 순 없나”라며 “단식이 비아냥의 대상이 되고, 사과조차 혐오의 대상으로 여기는 우리 당이 어떻게 국민의 신뢰를 얻고 나라를 이끌겠나”라고 했다. 그러면서 한 전 대표의 사과 내용이 아쉽다면서도 “서로를 보듬는 따뜻한 품으로 갈등을 끝내고 단결로 승리하자”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, leader Jang Dong-hyuk, who is continuing his fifth day of a hunger strike demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into the Unification Church and nomination donations, stated today, "I will not break my initial resolve to fight with my life." He said, "If we stop here, there will be no future for the Republic of Korea." He added, "It's difficult. I am gradually reaching my limit," and appealed, "For the future of the Republic of Korea, I ask the public to join forces together." (한편 통일교와 공천 헌금 등 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 닷새째 단식을 이어가고 있는 장동혁 대표는 이날 “목숨 바쳐 싸우겠다는 처음 각오를 꺾지 않겠다”고 했다. 그는 “여기서 멈춘다면 대한민국의 미래는 없을 것”이라고 했다. 이어 “힘이 든다. 점차 한계가 오고 있다”며 “대한민국의 미래를 위해 국민 여러분께서 함께 힘을 보태 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W6V7PAHMGJFXDHZSYUCYLBJY6E/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/SKGWRJ4NBZH5HNKFUDR2J7DESE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:10:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Italian Prime Minister, Accompanied by Her 'K-Pop Superfan' Daughter, Visits South Korea... Arrives Holding a BLACKPINK Lightstick (‘K팝 열성팬’ 딸과 방한한 이탈리아 총리... 블랙핑크 응원봉 들고 입국)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/ONQQYNUKQ5BLPOT5ULUNQ4DICY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FU7KA2F2DVIGRLEWKMLNGYYFTY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni, who is visiting South Korea for a summit with President Yoon Suk Yeol, drew attention by bringing along her 10-year-old daughter Ginevra, known as a 'K-pop superfan'. Although Ginevra did not appear in the official schedule, she was spotted disembarking from the official aircraft holding a BLACKPINK lightstick. (이재명 대통령과의 정상회담을 위해 한국을 방문 중인 조르자 멜로니 이탈리아 총리가 ‘K팝 열성팬’으로 알려진 딸 지네브라(10)를 동행해 눈길을 끌었다. 지네브라는 공식 일정엔 등장하지 않았으나, 블랙핑크의 응원봉을 손에 든 채 전용기에서 내린 모습이 포착됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 18th, Prime Minister Meloni's official YouTube account released footage from the previous day showing her and her daughter disembarking from the official aircraft at Seoul Airport and receiving an honor guard review from the Korean side. In Ginevra's hand was a BLACKPINK lightstick with a black handle and pink hammer-shaped ends on both sides. Lightsticks are 'goods' used by K-pop fans at concerts or events, symbolizing K-pop fandom culture. (18일 멜로니 총리의 공식 유튜브 계정엔 전날 서울공항에 도착한 멜로니 총리가 딸과 함께 전용기에서 내려 우리 측 의장대 사열을 받는 모습이 공개됐다. 지네브라의 손에는 검은색 손잡이에 분홍색 망치 모양이 양옆으로 달린 블랙핑크 응원봉이 들려있었다. 응원봉은 K팝 팬들이 콘서트나 행사장에서 사용하는 ‘굿즈’로, K팝 팬클럽 문화를 상징한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Prime Minister Meloni first met President Yoon in New York last September, she introduced her daughter as "the most enthusiastic K-pop fan in the world." She also became a topic of discussion last August when she attended a BLACKPINK concert in Milan, Italy, with her daughter. (멜로니 총리는 작년 9월 뉴욕에서 이 대통령을 처음 만나 자신의 딸이 “전세계에서 가장 열광적인 K팝 팬”이라고 소개했었다. 그는 작년 8월엔 이탈리아 밀라노에서 열린 블랙핑크 콘서트를 딸과 함께 관람해 화제가 되기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Yoon and Prime Minister Meloni also talked extensively about K-pop during their summit on the 19th. When President Yoon mentioned during the expanded meeting that "Recently, the popularity of K-culture has increased in Italy as well, leading to more Italian citizens visiting Korea," Prime Minister Meloni burst into laughter, seemingly reminded of her daughter. (이 대통령과 멜로니 총리는 19일 정상회담에서도 K팝에 대한 대화를 한참 나눴다. 이 대통령이 확대 회담에서 “최근에는 이탈리아에서도 K컬처의 인기가 높아져서 한국을 찾는 이탈리아 국민들이 늘어나고 있다”고 말하자, 멜로니 총리는 딸이 생각난 듯 웃음을 크게 터트렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the official luncheon, President Yoon said, "Hearing that your daughter is an ardent fan of K-pop made me realize anew the power of high-quality culture." Prime Minister Meloni responded, "Behind the success of K-culture, there were very smart choices and strategies," adding, "It is a strategy that masterfully blends the extremely global with the extremely national."
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령은 공식 오찬에서 “따님이 K-팝에 열렬한 팬이라는 말씀을 듣고 새삼스럽게 높은 문화의 힘을 실감했다”고 했고, 멜로니 총리는 “K컬처의 성공 뒤에는 굉장히 똑똑한 선택과 전략이 있었다”며 “그것은 바로 지극히 세계적인 것과 지극히 국가적인 것을 오묘하게 섞은 전략”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/19/ONQQYNUKQ5BLPOT5ULUNQ4DICY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/FU7KA2F2DVIGRLEWKMLNGYYFTY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:49:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Following the Disruption of Lee Hye-hoon's Hearing...People Power Party Announces "All Standing Committee Meetings This Week Suspended" (이혜훈 청문회 파행 이어...국힘 “이번 주 상임위 모두 중단” )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/IT5MKGWSH5CKDD7NAKV57SRXKY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62ZU2375YBKXJD3756JOMUG2VQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the People Power Party announced it would boycott all standing committee meetings scheduled for this week, in a show of support for its leader, Jang Dong-hyuk, who is on the fifth day of a hunger strike demanding the acceptance of special counsel probes into the Unification Church and election nomination bribes. This announcement came after the confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for the inaugural Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, scheduled for the same day, was disrupted following a heated argument between the ruling and opposition parties. (국민의힘이 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 5일째 단식 중인 장동혁 대표에게 힘을 싣는 차원에서 이번 주 예정된 상임위원회를 모두 보이콧하겠다고 19일 밝혔다. 이 같은 공지는 이날 예정됐던 이혜훈 초대 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회가 여야 간 설전 끝에 파행된 이후 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party's intra-parliamentary administration office stated in a parliamentary notice that day, "Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike struggle for the acceptance of the dual special counsel probes (into the Unification Church and nomination bribes) has entered its fifth day," adding, "Our party will postpone all standing committee schedules planned for this week from this time onward and join forces in supporting Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk's resolute actions." (국민의힘 원내행정국은 이날 원내 공지에서 “쌍특검(통일교·공천 뇌물) 수용을 위한 장동혁 당 대표의 단식 투쟁이 5일째 이어지고 있다“면서 “우리 당은 이 시간 이후 금주 예정된 모든 상임위 일정을 순연하고, 장동혁 당 대표의 결연한 행보에 힘을 모으도록 하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The intra-parliamentary administration office also said, "We request that each standing committee suspend its schedule until the hunger strike struggle concludes and join the struggle for the immediate acceptance of the dual special counsel probes by President Lee Jae-myung and the Democratic Party of Korea." (원내행정국은 “각 상임위에서는 단식 투쟁이 종료되는 시점까지 상임위 일정을 중단해주시고, 이재명 대통령과 더불어민주당의 쌍특검 즉각 수용을 위한 투쟁에 함께해 달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly had planned to hold the nominee's confirmation hearing that day, but as the ruling and opposition parties argued over the submission of the nominee's documents and whether to change the schedule, the meeting was adjourned without Lee Hye-hoon even being able to attend. The People Power Party maintained that the hearing could not proceed because the nominee had failed to submit a significant portion of the requested documents by the deadline, while the Democratic Party countered that the nominee should be brought in for public verification. Ultimately, People Power Party member and chairman of the Strategy and Finance Committee, Im I-jae, adjourned the meeting, telling the floor leaders of both parties to "go and hold further consultations." (국회는 이날 이 후보자의 인사청문회를 열기로 했지만, 여야가 후보자 자료 제출과 일정 변경 여부를 놓고 설전을 벌이면서 정작 이혜훈 후보자는 참석도 못한 채 회의를 정회했다. 국민의힘은 이 후보자가 요구된 자료의 상당 부분을 기한 내 제출하지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 열 수 없다는 입장을 고수한 반면, 민주당은 후보자를 출석시켜 공개 검증에 나서야 한다고 맞섰다. 결국 국민의힘 소속 임이자 재경위원장은 여야 간사를 향해 “추가 협의해 오라”며 회의를 정회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/IT5MKGWSH5CKDD7NAKV57SRXKY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62ZU2375YBKXJD3756JOMUG2VQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:49:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unification Minister Jeong Dong-young's Requested 'Gift' of Transferring the Institute for National Unification to the Ministry Faces Inevitable Delays (정동영이 ‘선물’로 달라던 통일연구원의 통일부 이관 차질 불가피)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W4LKCKOIK5F45KMWHWLGN26FJA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3TGOLFHA3TIMRRGJSWKMJZHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The transfer of the Institute for National Unification to the Ministry of Unification, which Minister Jeong Dong-young had requested from President Lee Jae-myung as a 'gift,' has been halted. (정동영 통일부 장관이 이재명 대통령에게 ‘선물’로 달라고 요청했던 통일연구원의 통일부 이관 작업이 중단됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 17th, the Ministry of Unification announced on its website, "We are withdrawing the legislative notice for the Institute for National Unification Act (draft) as additional consultations with related agencies are necessary." This came just three days after the ministry had issued the legislative notice for a bill to transfer the state-funded research institute, the Institute for National Unification, under its jurisdiction. (통일부는 지난 17일 홈페이지에 “통일연구원법(안) 입법예고 관련 관계기관과 추가적인 협의가 필요함에 따라 이를 철회한다”고 공지했다. 국책연구기관인 통일연구원을 통일부 산하로 이관하는 내용의 법안을 입법예고한 지 사흘 만에 거둬들인 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 14th, the Ministry of Unification had issued a legislative notice for the 'Draft Act on the Institute for National Unification,' stating its intention to change the affiliation of the Institute for National Unification, which is currently supported and managed by the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences under the Office for Government Policy Coordination, to "under the Ministry of Unification." As reasons for the legislative notice, the ministry cited that "research outcomes in the unification and security fields have a significant impact on inter-Korean relations and national security" and the "need for organic linkage between policy and research." (통일부는 지난 14일 ‘통일연구원법 제정안’을 입법 예고하고 현재 국무조정실 산하 경제인문사회연구회가 지원·관리하는 통일연구원을 “통일부 산하로 변경하고자 한다”고 했었다. 통일부는 입법예고 사유로 “통일·안보 분야 연구 결과가 남북 관계와 국가 안보에 미치는 영향이 심대하다”는 점과 “정책과 연구의 유기적 연계 필요성”을 들었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during a presidential briefing on December 19 last year, Minister Jeong Dong-young said, "I request... that the Institute for National Unification be transferred to the Ministry of Unification... I ask the President to give us one gift," and President Lee instructed Prime Minister Kim Min-seok on the spot to discuss the matter. Minister Jeong stated, "The Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of National Defense, and the National Intelligence Service all have think tanks, but the Ministry of Unification does not," adding, "During the IMF (International Monetary Fund foreign exchange crisis), (affiliated institutions) were merged or abolished; powerful ministries kept theirs, but the Ministry of Unification, lacking power, saw the Institute for National Unification separated." (앞서 정동영 장관은 지난해 12월 19일 대통령 업무보고에서 “통일연구원을 통일부로 이관해 주십사 하는…, 대통령님께서 선물을 하나 주십사 하는 부탁을 드립니다”라고 했고 이 대통령은 그 자리에서 김민석 국무총리에게 관련 논의를 할 것을 지시했다. 정 장관은 “외교부와 국방부, 국가정보원은 모두 싱크탱크가 있지만 통일부는 없다”며 “IMF(국제통화기금 외환 위기) 때 (산하 기관들이) 통폐합됐는데 힘 있는 부처는 다 남았고 통일부가 힘이 없어서 통일연구원이 분리됐다”고 했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Personnel at the Institute for National Unification reportedly only learned of Minister Jeong's proposal to transfer the institute to the ministry after watching the live televised presidential briefing. One researcher said, "There was absolutely no prior consultation with the Ministry of Unification regarding the transfer of the institute before the presidential briefing," and "we were extremely embarrassed by the Minister's remarks during the live broadcast, asking for the institute as a 'gift.'" It is reported that the institute later conveyed its negative stance on the transfer to the Ministry of Unification during a briefing to Prime Minister Kim Min-seok by the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences on the 9th, but the Ministry of Unification proceeded with the legislative notice anyway, and during this process, proper prior consultations were not adequately conducted with the council or the Office for Government Policy Coordination, to which the institute belongs. (통일연구원 소속 인사들은 정 장관의 연구원의 통일부 이관 건의를 TV로 생중계된 대통령 업무보고를 보고서야 알았다고 한다. 한 연구원은 “대통령 업무보고 전 연구원의 통일부 이관에 대해 통일부와 사전에 협의한 게 전혀 없었다”며 “생중계된 방송에서 연구원을 ‘선물’로 달라는 장관의 발언에 굉장히 당혹스러웠다”고 했다. 연구원은 이후 지난 9일 김민석 국무총리에 대한 경제인문사회연구회(경인사연) 업무보고에서 연구원의 통일부 이관에 대해 부정적 입장을 전달했으나 통일부는 입법예고를 강행했고 이 과정에서 연구원이 속한 경인사연, 국조실과도 사전 협의가 제대로 이뤄지지 않았다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Institute for National Unification was initially established under the Ministry of Unification in 1991 and was transferred under the National Research Council for Economics, Humanities and Social Sciences in 1999 following the enactment of relevant legislation. This was based on the Kim Dae-jung administration's plan to guarantee independent research for state-funded research institutes, following the judgment that such institutes had failed to foresee the IMF economic crisis and take preemptive measures. An official from the Institute for National Unification stated, "If the institute were to come under a ministry, there is a high risk that the minimum autonomy and independence in research required for a state-funded research institute would be compromised, which is why the dominant stance within the institute was negative towards the transfer to the Ministry of Unification." (통일연구원은 1991년 설립 초기 통일부 산하에서 1999년 관련 법 제정에 따라 경인사연 산하로 이관됐다. 국책 연구기관이 IMF 경제 위기를 예견하지 못하고 사전 대응에 실패했다는 판단에 국책 연구기관들의 독립적 연구를 보장하겠다는 김대중 정부의 구상에 따른 것이었다. 통일연구원의 한 관계자는 “연구원이 부처 산하로 들어가게 되면 국책 연구기관에 요구되는 최소한의 연구의 자율성과 독립성이 훼손될 위험이 크기 때문에 연구원의 통일부 이관에 부정적 입장이 지배적이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/W4LKCKOIK5F45KMWHWLGN26FJA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3TGOLFHA3TIMRRGJSWKMJZHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:31:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Independence Hall of Korea Board of Trustees Passes Motion Demanding Dismissal of Director Kim Hyung-seok (독립기념관 이사회, 김형석 관장 해임요구안 의결)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/MR45LMOKMJFQFPJGZSWIVFPFDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZM46ANT6FZD77FNUVTDOLWY5C4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Board of Trustees of the Independence Hall of Korea passed a motion on the 19th recommending the dismissal of Director Kim Hyung-seok. (독립기념관 이사회가 19일 김형석 독립기념관장 해임 건의안을 가결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, on the 13th, the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs had publicly disclosed 14 alleged irregularities by Director Kim, including the privatization of the Independence Hall, and recommended his dismissal. (앞서 국가보훈부는 지난 13일 김 관장의 독립기념관 사유화 등 14가지 비위 사실을 공개하며 해임을 건의했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is reported that the board meeting proceeded with 13 out of the 15 registered members in attendance, excluding members Bae Joon-young (a People Power Party lawmaker) and Park Yi-taek. (이날 이사회는 재적 인원 15명 중 배준영(국민의힘 의원), 박이택 이사 2명을 제외한 13명이 참석한 가운데 진행된 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among the 12 members present (excluding Director Kim), 10 voted in favor, leading to the passage of the dismissal recommendation motion. (이 가운데 김형석 관장을 제외한 12명 중 10명이 찬성하면서 해임건의안은 가결됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs plans to submit the request for Director Kim's dismissal to President Lee Jae-myung. (국가보훈부는 김 관장에 대한 해임을 이재명 대통령에게 제청할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the board meeting, Director Kim stated at a press conference, "The audit by the Ministry of Patriots and Veterans Affairs, which formed the basis for the dismissal decision, was unjustly conducted with the sole purpose of dismissing the Director of the Independence Hall, disregarding substantive facts," adding, "I cannot agree with the contents of the audit report." (김 관장은 이사회 후 가진 기자간담회에서 “해임 의결의 근거가 된 보훈부 감사는 실체적 사실과 무관하게 독립기념관장의 해임을 목적으로 부당하게 진행됐다”며 “감사결과보고서 내용에 대해 동의할 수 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/MR45LMOKMJFQFPJGZSWIVFPFDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZM46ANT6FZD77FNUVTDOLWY5C4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:30:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Jun-seok to Visit Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site Immediately Upon Early Return on the 21st (이준석, 21일 조기 귀국하자마자 장동혁 단식장 찾는다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ZEPLWIWMPVFYRBFJ2PM455PAW4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WPBM63BRWRPBLGPLAKNP3S3C4Q.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, continues his hunger strike for the fifth day, demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of Democratic Party of Korea nomination donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians, Lee Jun-seok, the leader of the Reform Party, will return early on the 21st and immediately visit Jang's hunger strike site. However, it is reported that a joint hunger strike with Jang, who declared an indefinite hunger strike, is not currently under consideration. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 더불어민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 닷새째 단식을 이어가는 가운데 이준석 개혁신당 대표가 21일 조기 귀국해 곧바로 장 대표 단식장을 찾는다. 다만 무기한 단식을 선언한 장 대표와의 공동 단식은 현재로선 검토하지 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Reform Party announced on the 19th that Lee, who was originally scheduled to return on the 23rd, will return early on the 21st to cooperate on issues like the twin special prosecutor. Lee's itinerary involved returning via Mexico and Guatemala after visiting the United States, but it is said he canceled his U.S. schedule. Lee told this newspaper, "I plan to go directly from the airport to the National Assembly Rotunda Hall, the site of Jang's hunger strike, immediately after returning early in the morning on the 21st." A Reform Party official stated, "The cooperation between the two parties for the twin special prosecutor was originally proposed by Lee," adding, "This is to show support for Jang, who is on a hunger strike for the twin special prosecutor." (개혁신당은 19일 당초 23일 귀국 예정이었던 이 대표가 21일 조기 귀국해 쌍특검 등에 대해 공조할 예정이라고 밝혔다. 이 대표는 멕시코와 과테말라를 거쳐 미국을 들렀다 귀국하는 일정이었는데 미국 일정은 취소했다고 한다. 이 대표는 이날 본지에 “21일 새벽 귀국 직후 공항에서 곧바로 장 대표의 국회 로텐더홀 단식 현장을 찾을 예정”이라고 밝혔다. 개혁신당 관계자는 “당초 쌍특검을 위한 양 당의 공조는 이 대표가 먼저 제안했던 것”이라며 “쌍특검을 위해 단식하는 장 대표에게 힘을 실어주는 차원”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Reform Party is drawing a line at joining the hunger strike. Cheon Ha-ram, the party's floor leader, met with reporters and said, "Doing everything exactly the same is not necessarily the right answer," adding, "Last week, while Jang began his hunger strike, the Reform Party conducted a filibuster. Although our methods were different, we made cooperative efforts to strongly appeal to the public about the necessity of the twin special prosecutor." He further stated, "We plan to persuade the public about the necessity of the twin special prosecutor in various ways." A party official said, "Since Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won also began a hunger strike starting today, we believe it would not be helpful for Lee to join and sit with them." (다만 개혁신당은 동조 단식에는 선을 긋고 있다. 천하람 원내대표는 이날 기자들과 만나 “모든 걸 똑같이 하는 것만이 정답은 아닐 것”이라며 “지난주 장 대표는 단식에 들어가고 개혁신당은 필리버스터를 하는 형태로 서로 모습은 다르지만 국민들께 쌍특검의 필요성을 강하게 어필하기 위한 공조 노력을 했다”고 했다. 그러면서 “다양한 형태로 국민들께 쌍특검 필요성을 설득할 예정”이라고 말했다. 당 관계자는 “이날부터 김재원 최고위원이 함께 단식을 시작한 만큼 이 대표가 함께 앉는 그림이 도움이 되진 않는다고 보고 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, after a meeting between leaders Jang and Lee on the 13th, the two parties began full-fledged so-called 'special prosecutor cooperation.' Subsequently, when Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram began an unlimited debate on the 15th to oppose the second comprehensive special prosecutor bill pushed by the Democratic Party, Jang started his hunger strike at the Rotunda Hall. Jang, who is facing internal party backlash over the push to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon, is reportedly viewing solidarity with the Reform Party as an escape route. (앞서 지난 13일 장·이 대표가 회동한 뒤 두 당은 이른바 ‘특검 공조’를 본격화했다. 이후 장 대표는 개혁신당 천하람 원내대표가 15일 민주당이 추진하는 2차 종합 특검법 반대를 위한 무제한 토론을 시작하자 로텐더홀에서 단식을 시작했다. 장 대표는 한동훈 전 대표 제명 추진을 두고 당내 반발에 직면한 상황에서 개혁신당과의 연대를 탈출구로 보고 있는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/ZEPLWIWMPVFYRBFJ2PM455PAW4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/WPBM63BRWRPBLGPLAKNP3S3C4Q.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:35:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Representative Visits U.S... Shared Understanding on 'Prompt Consultations' (한미 원자력협력 대표 미국 방문... ‘조속한 협의’ 공감)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/HVWAX4JHJVBEFHDBH2XWR5DCIU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUH7SFDPFFPAFG3C5NEWLQKLOE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im Gap-su, the head of the South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Pan-Government Consultative Body (TF) tasked with negotiating with the United States to expand rights for uranium enrichment and spent nuclear fuel reprocessing, visited Washington D.C. last week to meet with U.S. officials and coordinate the negotiation schedule. (우라늄 농축 및 사용후핵연료 재처리 권한 확대를 미국과 협상할 ‘한미 원자력 협력 범정부협의체(TF)’의 임갑수 대표가 지난주 미국 워싱턴DC를 방문해 미 당국자들과 만나 협상 일정 등을 조율했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced that Representative Im visited the U.S. for two days on the 15th and 16th, meeting with U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Arms Control and Nonproliferation Christopher Ye and Deputy Administrator of the National Nuclear Security Administration Matthew Napoli. (19일 외교부는 임 대표가 지난 15~16일 양일간 방미해 미 국무부 군비통제·비확산국 크리스토퍼 여 차관보, 매튜 나폴리 핵안보청 부청장 등을 만났다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs stated, "Representative Im held introductory meetings with key figures and exchanged views on the overall plan for future cooperation to secure our commercial and peaceful enrichment and reprocessing capabilities." (외교부는 “임 대표가 주요 인사들과 상견례 차 면담을 갖고, 우리의 상업적·평화적 농축·재처리 역량 확보를 위한 향후 협력 추진 전반에 대해 의견을 교환했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Foreign Affairs further stated, "It was agreed that a U.S. working-level delegation will visit South Korea as soon as possible for follow-up consultations to promptly implement the agreement between the two leaders contained in the joint fact sheet from the South Korea-U.S. summit." (외교부는 또 “한미 정상회담 공동 설명 자료(조인트 팩트 시트)에 담긴 양국 정상 간 합의를 조속히 이행하기 위한 후속 협의를 위해 가급적 빠른 시일 내에 미 실무 대표단이 방한하기로 했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, working-level negotiations between South Korea and the U.S. are expected to commence in Seoul in the near future. However, who the U.S. representative will be has not yet been disclosed. (이에 따라 조만간 서울에서 한미 양측의 실무 협상이 개시될 것으로 보인다. 다만 미국 측 대표가 누가 될지는 아직 공개되지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, National Security Advisor Wi Sung-lak visited the U.S. last month and met with Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Secretary of Energy Chris Wright. After the meetings, he stated, "It was agreed that a U.S. working-level delegation will visit South Korea at the earliest possible time early next year to begin full-fledged (specific) consultations on each security issue included in the two countries' joint fact sheet." (앞서 위성락 국가안보실장은 지난달 미국을 방문해 마코 루비오 국무장관, 크리스 라이트 에너지부 장관 등과 면담한 뒤 “내년 초 가능한 이른 시기에 미 측 실무 대표단이 방한, 양국의 조인트 팩트시트에 포함된 안보 사안별로 (구체적인) 본격 협의를 갖기로 했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The South Korean side's 'South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Pan-Government Consultative Body' held its first meeting on the 9th at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs building in Seoul. The government plans to use the consultative body to detail how to address the expansion of enrichment and reprocessing rights—whether through a full revision or partial amendment of the existing South Korea-U.S. Nuclear Cooperation Agreement—and then enter into negotiations with the United States. (우리 측 ‘한미 원자력 협력 범정부협의체’는 지난 9일 서울 외교부 청사에서 첫 회의를 열었다. 정부는 협의체를 통해 농축·재처리 권한 확대를 기존 한미 원자력협력 협정의 전면 개정 내지 일부 수정 등 어떤 방식으로 풀어낼지를 구체화한 뒤 미국과 협상에 나설 방침이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/19/HVWAX4JHJVBEFHDBH2XWR5DCIU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/DUH7SFDPFFPAFG3C5NEWLQKLOE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:16:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Opposition Party: "Only 15% of Requested Materials Submitted," Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Stalls and Adjourns (野 “요구 자료 중 15%만 제출” 이혜훈 청문회 파행 끝 정회)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/GMSUSEXDTZBNVBLQFJX3OHSOTU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Opposition Party: "Only 15% of Requested Materials Submitted," Lee Hye-hoon Hearing Stalls and Adjourns (野 “요구 자료 중 15%만 제출” 이혜훈 청문회 파행 끝 정회)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7RMSOXZJRZIAPB5JGOMW2O4ENU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Assembly held a confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, on the 19th. However, the ruling and opposition parties engaged in a war of words over the submission of materials by the nominee and whether to change the schedule. As a result, the morning session was adjourned without nominee Lee Hye-hoon even being able to attend. (국회는 19일 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 인사청문회를 열었지만, 여야가 후보자 자료 제출과 일정 변경 여부를 놓고 설전을 벌이면서 정작 이혜훈 후보자는 참석도 못한 채 오전 회의를 정회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the meeting held for the Strategy and Finance Committee's confirmation hearing that day, the ruling and opposition parties clashed strongly, repeatedly making procedural motions. The ruling party maintained that since it had already been agreed upon and voted on by both parties to hold the hearing at 10 a.m. that day, the nominee should be brought in to undergo public verification. Democratic Party lawmaker Park Hong-geun stated, "Even if the materials are insufficient, there is no case of boycotting a hearing," adding, "Today's confirmation hearing should proceed as scheduled with the nominee present." (이날 열린 재경위 인사청문회를 위한 회의에서 여야는 강하게 충돌하며 의사진행발언만 거듭했다. 여당은 이미 여야 합의와 의결을 거쳐 이날 오전 10시 청문회를 열기로 한 만큼 후보자를 출석시켜 공개 검증에 나서야 한다는 입장이었다. 박홍근 민주당 의원은 “자료가 부실하다 해도 청문회를 보이콧하는 경우는 없다”면서 “오늘 인사청문회를 예정대로 후보자를 데려다 놓고 해야한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the opposition party insisted that the hearing could not be held because the nominee's side had failed to submit a significant portion of the requested materials by the deadline. Strategy and Finance Committee Chairwoman and People Power Party lawmaker Lim Lee-ja refused to place the hearing on the agenda, stating, "Since an agreement between the floor leaders of the two parties has not been reached, the hearing cannot be placed on the agenda." (반면 야당은후보자 측이 요구된 자료의 상당 부분을 기한 내 제출하지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 열 수 없다는 입장을 고수했다. 재경위원장 임이자 국민의힘 의원은 “양당 간사 간 합의가 이루어지지 않았기 때문에 청문회를 상정할 수 없다”며 안건 상정을 거부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, the opposition party's floor leader on the committee, also demanded additional material submission, saying, "Only 15% of the 2,187 requested items have been submitted. The 18 items that arrived last night are not the core materials." (야당 간사인 박수영 국민의힘 의원도 “자료 요구 2187건 중 15％만 제출됐다. 어젯밤 도착한 18건 자료는 핵심이 아니다”라며 추가 자료 제출을 요구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, opposition party lawmakers listed controversies surrounding nominee Lee Hye-hoon, such as allegations of unfair subscription, illegal gifting, suspicions regarding children's employment and study abroad, and controversy over staff misconduct. They argued, "With this level of suspicion, this is a matter that should first have the facts clarified by investigative agencies, not in a hearing room." (또 야당 의원들은 이혜훈 후보자와 관련해 제기된 부정 청약, 편법 증여, 자녀 채용·유학 의혹, 보좌진 갑질 논란 등을 나열하면서 “이 정도 의혹이면 청문회장이 아니라 수사기관에서 먼저 사실관계를 규명받아야 할 사안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the procedural motions dragged on, Chairwoman Lim Lee-ja adjourned the meeting, telling the floor leaders of both parties to "go and hold additional consultations on holding (the hearing)." For over an hour and a half, nominee Lee Hye-hoon was unable to even take a seat in the meeting room. (의사진행발언이 길어지자 임이자 위원장은 여야 간사를 향해 “개최 추가 협의해오라”라며 회의를 정회했다. 1시간 30분 넘게 이어진 시간 동안 이혜훈 후보자는 회의장에 착석조차 하지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, nominee Lee Hye-hoon met with reporters and said, "I submitted about 75% (of the materials)," and "I am preparing to submit as much as possible now. I have submitted everything that could be secured and am preparing to secure the rest." She also said, "I am waiting for the hearing to be held so I can have the opportunity to explain in detail before the public." (이후 이혜훈 후보자는 기자들과 만나 “(자료 제출) 75% 정도 냈다”며 “지금 최대한 내려고 준비하고 있다. 확보할 수 있는 것들은 다 냈고, 확보를 위해서 준비하고 있다”고 했다. 또 “청문회가 열려서 국민들 앞에 소상히 소명할 수 있는 기회를 갖기를 기다리고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the failure to submit some materials, she explained, "The data retention period has already passed, and (the opposition lawmakers) are even asking for things from 30-40 years ago. There were many items I couldn't submit because national institutions do not hold the data." (또 자료를 내지 못한 것과 관련해서는 “이미 자료 보존 기간이 지나서, (야당 의원들이) 심지어 30~40년 전 거를 달라고 하시니, 국가기관이 자료를 보유하고 있지 않아서 못 내는 것들이 많았다”고 해명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, if this nominee's hearing is postponed for a long time, the appointment decision ultimately falls to the presidential office. The National Assembly must submit a hearing progress report within 20 days after submitting the request for a confirmation hearing. If the hearing progress report is not adopted, the President can request its resubmission within 10 days. If the report is not submitted even after the resubmission request, the appointment can be forcibly proceeded with. (한편, 이 후보자 청문회가 장기간 미뤄지면 임명 결정은 결국 청와대 몫으로 돌아간다. 국회는 인사청문요청안 제출 후 20일 이내에 청문경과보고서를 송부해야 한다. 청문경과보고서를 채택하지 않을 시 대통령은 10일 이내 재송부를 요청할 수 있고, 재송부 요청에도 청문경과보고서를 제출하지 않으면 임명을 강행할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/GMSUSEXDTZBNVBLQFJX3OHSOTU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7RMSOXZJRZIAPB5JGOMW2O4ENU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 17:42:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Open Debate Over 'Pro-Myung/Pro-Chung' Lines Reignites Over One-Member-One-Vote System... "Mentioning 'Such Acts' to Silence Critics" (1인1표제 놓고 ‘친명·친청’ 공개설전…“해당 운운하며 입틀막”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/PQAGSFALFNA5BMIGQMLG22MXXA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Open Debate Over 'Pro-Myung/Pro-Chung' Lines Reignites Over One-Member-One-Vote System... "Mentioning 'Such Acts' to Silence Critics" (1인1표제 놓고 ‘친명·친청’ 공개설전…“해당 운운하며 입틀막”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRDQMTCMYYTCZBTGM4WCMRUGY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conflict between pro-Myung and pro-Chung faction Supreme Council members has reignited over Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae's push to reintroduce the 'one-member-one-vote' system for delegates and party members. Recently, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun referred to the act of stirring controversy as a "such act," prompting pro-Myung faction Supreme Council members like Kang Deuk-gu and Hwang Myung-sun to respond with statements such as "We must eliminate any suspicion of self-serving revision" and "We should not be muzzled," eventually leading to demands for a public apology directed at Chief Spokesperson Park. (정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 대의원·당원 ‘1인 1표제’를 재추진하는 것을 두고, 친명·친청계 최고위원 간 갈등이 재점화했다. 최근 박수현 수석대변인은 논란 촉발을 “해당 행위”라고 언급했는데, 친명계 강득구·황명선 최고위원 등은 “셀프 개정 오해 소지 없애야 한다” “재갈 물려선 안 된다”라고 했고, 급기야 박 수석대변인을 향한 공개 사과 요구까지 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the party's Supreme Council meeting that day, pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Hwang Myung-sun mentioned that the one-member-one-vote system had been rejected once in the Central Committee last month, stating, "We agree in principle, but we are asking to eliminate any room for misunderstanding." She further suggested, "Let's amend the party constitution and rules to introduce the one-member-one-vote system this time, but with its application starting after the next national convention," adding, "If the very parties who amended the election rules are immediately elected under those rules, it's hard to avoid criticism that it's a self-serving revision." (이날 당 최고위원회의에서 친명계 황명선 최고위원은 지난달 중앙위에서 1인 1표제가 한 차례 부결됐던 점을 언급하며 “원칙에는 동의하지만 오해의 소지를 없애라는 것”이라고 했다. 또 “이번에 1인 1표제를 도입하되 적용 시점은 다음 전당대회 이후로 하는 것으로 당헌당규를 개정”하자며 “선거 룰을 개정한 당사자들이 곧바로 그 규칙에 따라 선출된다면 셀프 개정이라는 비판을 피하기 어렵다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, pro-Chung faction Supreme Council member Moon Jung-bok rebutted Councilor Hwang's remarks. Councilor Moon stated, "To delay or question this again for other secondary reasons is an act of betraying the promises the Democratic Party has made to its members so far." Pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Lee Sung-yoon also holds the position that sufficient public discussion on the one-member-one-vote system has already taken place. This councilor said, "As the greatest concern of party members, it has been sufficiently discussed from the party leadership election in August last year to this Supreme Council election," adding, "For moving towards an era of member sovereignty, the one-member-one-vote system is a perfectly natural principle under the national constitution and the party constitution." (그러자 친청계 문정복 최고위원은 황 위원의 발언에 반박했다. 문 최고위원은 “다른 부차적인 이유로 이것을 다시 보류하거나 다시 문제를 삼는 것은 그동안 당원들에게 이야기했던 민주당의 약속을 저버리는 행위”라고 했다. 친명계 이성윤 최고위원도 1인 1표제 공론화 작업은 이미 충분히 진행됐다는 입장이다. 이 위원은 “당원들의 가장 큰 관심사로서 지난해 8월 당대표 선거부터 이번 최고위원 선거까지 충분히 공론화됐다”며 “당원 주권 시대를 향해 나아가기 위해 1인 1표제는 헌법, 당헌상 너무나 당연한 원리”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The day before, Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun, regarding claims linking the one-member-one-vote system to party leadership competition, had said, "If this act of stirring controversy goes a bit further, it could be condemned as a 'such act,' and there would be nothing to say in defense." (전날 박수현 수석대변인은 1인 1표제를 당권 경쟁과 연결 짓는 주장에 대해 “이런 논란을 촉발하는 것이 조금 더 가면 ‘해당 행위’라고 비난받아도 할 말 없는 상황”이라고 한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo also publicly targeted Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun's remarks through additional comments at the Supreme Council meeting that day. Councilor Lee said, "For some to dismiss this discussion by mentioning 'such acts' and 'muzzling' critics is abandoning the spirit of democracy," adding, "I believe this is not the party leader's intention either." (이언주 최고위원은 이날 최고위에서 추가 발언을 통해 박수현 수석대변인의 발언을 공개 저격하기도 했다. 이 위원은 “이런 토론을 뭐 일각에서 해당 행위 운운하면서 ‘입틀막’하는 것은 민주주의의 정신을 져버리는 것”이라며 “이것이 당 대표의 뜻도 아닐 거라고 믿는다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pro-Myung faction Supreme Council member Kang Deuk-gu, after the party Supreme Council meeting, separately met with reporters and demanded a public apology from Chief Spokesperson Park. Councilor Kang said, "Does it make sense to define it as a 'such act'? It's like trying to muzzle someone like me," and added, "Spokesperson Park must apologize publicly and officially. If there is no apology, it is unacceptable from the standpoint of a Supreme Council member." He also warned that if no official apology is given by the 21st, he will make a public statement at the Supreme Council meeting that day. (친명계 강득구 최고위원은 당 최고위 이후 따로 기자들과 만나 박 수석대변인에게 공개 사과를 요구했다. 강 위원은 “‘해당 행위로 규정한다’는 게 말이 되나. 나 같은 사람한테 재갈을 물리겠다는 것”이라며 “박 대변인이 공개적, 공식적으로 사과해야 한다. 사과하지 않으면 최고위원 입장에서 용납이 안 되는 것”이라고 했다. 오는 21일까지 공식 사과를 하지 않으면 당일 최고위에서 공개 발언을 하겠다고도 예고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the one-member-one-vote system was submitted as an agenda item for the party affairs committee that day. If the agenda passes that day, it will undergo a three-day collection of member opinions starting from the 22nd, followed by a two-day Central Committee vote on the 2nd of next month for final passage. (한편, 이날 1인1표제는 당무위 안건으로 부의된다. 이날 안건이 통과되면 오는 22일부터 사흘간 당원의견 수렴을 거쳐 다음달 2일 이틀간 중앙위 투표를 거쳐 최종 통과된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/19/PQAGSFALFNA5BMIGQMLG22MXXA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRDQMTCMYYTCZBTGM4WCMRUGY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 16:11:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Regarding the Ilta Instructor·Teacher Exam Question Backdoor Deal... Kang Ho-sik Says "Education Authorities Should Apologize" (일타강사·교사 문제 뒷거래에... 강훈식 “교육 당국 사과해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/DH5N2JB3JJEUZKEFBDDUDA3IMI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 19th, Presidential Chief of Staff Kang Ho-sik stated regarding the 'exam question trading' incident involving school teachers and private education instructors, "A sincere reflection and apology at the level of the education authorities is necessary for the sense of betrayal and helplessness the students must have felt." Presiding over a senior secretary meeting at the Blue House that day, Chief of Staff Kang emphasized, "The starting point of a fair Republic of Korea is managing the college entrance system without foul play." (강훈식 대통령 비서실장은 19일 학교 교사들과 사교육 강사들의 ‘시험 문항 거래’ 사건과 관련해 “학생들이 느꼈을 허탈감과 무력감에 대해 교육 당국 차원의 진정성 있는 성찰과 사과가 필요하다”고 밝혔다. 강 실장은 이날 청와대에서 주재한 수석보좌관 회의에서 “공정한 대한민국의 출발점은 반칙 없는 입시제도 관리”라며 이같이 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "Recently, cases that fundamentally undermine the fairness of the college entrance system, such as illegal trading and leaking of exam questions across the educational field, have been revealed one after another, seriously damaging public trust," adding, "This is a significant issue that infringes upon the entire education system and social order, going beyond simple individual misconduct." Furthermore, he instructed, "The Ministry of Education and national education offices must thoroughly inspect whether there are any additional foul plays in the overall management of the college entrance system and school records, and report any areas requiring system improvement." (그는 “최근 교육 현장 전반에서 불법적인 시험문제 거래와 유출 등 입시제도의 공정성을 근본적으로 훼손한 사례들이 잇따라 드러나며 국민적 신뢰를 심각하게 무너뜨렸다”며 “이는 단순한 개인 비리를 넘어 교육제도 전반과 사회질서를 침해하는 중대한 문제”라고 했다. 아울러 “교육부와 전국 교육청에서 입시제도와 학교 내신 관리 전반에 추가적인 반칙은 없는지 철저히 점검하고 제도 개선이 필요한 사항을 보고하라”고 지시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Chief of Staff Kang pointed out, "As the global popularity of K-beauty and K-food increases, the distribution of counterfeit products cleverly imitating Korean brands is spreading overseas," and "Beyond our companies suffering damage, this threatens the health and safety of overseas consumers and can damage the overall trust in Korean products." He then ordered, "The counterfeit Korean goods problem has limitations if addressed only by individual companies' responses," and instructed, "Relevant ministries such as the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and the Korean Intellectual Property Office should cooperate to conduct a comprehensive inspection of the current system operation status and, if necessary, promptly prepare and report on measures such as legal revisions and budget support." (이어 강 실장은 “K-뷰티와 K-푸드 등의 세계적 인기가 높아지면서 한국 브랜드를 교묘하게 위조한 가짜 상품 유통이 해외에서 확산하고 있다”며 “우리 기업이 피해를 보는 것을 넘어 해외 소비자의 건강과 안전을 위협하고 한국 상품 전반의 신뢰를 훼손할 수 있다”고 지적했다. 그러면서 “가짜 한국 상품 문제는 개별 기업의 대응만으로는 한계가 있다”며 “산업통상부, 외교부, 지식재산처 등 관계부처가 협력해 제도 운영 현황을 전면 점검하고 필요한 경우 법 개정과 예산 지원 방안 등을 신속히 마련해 보고하라”고 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/19/DH5N2JB3JJEUZKEFBDDUDA3IMI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YTJBRFYE2BJEFDXES3ORP4IJLA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:37:22 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>