<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:20:01 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Blue House: "No Official Notification from U.S. on Tariff Hike...Emergency Meeting Today" (靑 “美, 관세인상 공식 통보 없어…오늘 대책회의 개최”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/BSCNGZYVM5HHDDAJDXDY6GD3WU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Blue House: "No Official Notification from U.S. on Tariff Hike...Emergency Meeting Today" (靑 “美, 관세인상 공식 통보 없어…오늘 대책회의 개최”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSWMZJSGY3DKOJZHA2WEMZUME.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, the Blue House stated regarding U.S. President Donald Trump's declaration of reciprocal tariff increases, "We have not yet received an official notification or detailed explanation from the U.S. government." (청와대는 27일 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 상호관세 인상 선언에 대해 “미국 정부로부터 공식적인 통보나 세부내용에 대한 설명은 아직 없는 상황”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House spokesperson's office announced this in a press release, adding, "A meeting chaired by the Policy Chief with relevant ministries participating is scheduled for this morning." The Blue House also said, "Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jeong-gwan, who is currently in Canada, plans to visit the U.S. as soon as possible to discuss the matter with Commerce Secretary Lighthizer." (청와대는 대변인실은 이날 언론 공지를 통해 이같이 밝히며 “오늘 오전 정책실장 주재로 관계부처가 참여하는 대책회의를 개최할 예정”이라고 했다. 청와대는 “현재 캐나다에 체류 중인 김정관 산업통상부 장관도 조속히 미국을 방문하여 러트닉 상무장관과 관련 내용을 협의할 계획”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, President Trump posted on his social media platform 'Truth Social', notifying that he would "increase tariffs on Korean automobiles, lumber, pharmaceuticals, and all other reciprocal tariff items from 15% to 25% because the Korean National Assembly has not enacted our historic trade agreement." President Trump stated, "President Lee Jae-myung and I reached a great agreement for both countries on July 30, 2025, and I reconfirmed these terms when I visited Korea on October 29, 2025," adding, "Why hasn't the Korean National Assembly approved this yet?" (앞서 트럼프 대통령은 자신의 소셜미디어 ‘트루스소셜’에 올린 게시글을 통해 “한국 국회가 우리의 역사적인 무역 협정을 제정하지 않았기 때문에 한국산 자동차, 목재, 의약품 및 기타 모든 상호 관세 품목에 대한 관세를 15%에서 25%로 인상한다”고 통보했다. 트럼프 대통령은 “이재명 대통령과 나는 지난 2025년 7월 30일 양국을 위한 훌륭한 합의에 도달했고, 내가 2025년 10월 29일 한국을 방문했을 때 이 조건을 재확인했다”며 “왜 한국 국회는 아직도 이를 승인하지 않는가?”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Korean and U.S. authorities reached a trade agreement last July amid U.S. threats of imposing universal tariffs. The agreement set a tariff ceiling of 15% on Korean products and included expanded investment in the U.S. Initially, the Korean government stated that parliamentary ratification was required for the Korea-U.S. tariff agreement document. However, it later changed its position, stating it would specify the contents through domestic implementation bills like the 'Special Act on Investment in the United States' without parliamentary ratification. The reason given was that the Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) is not a treaty, is non-binding, and the U.S. also does not seek congressional ratification. However, with the delay in processing the ratification bill in the National Assembly, it is interpreted that President Trump has played the hardline card of tariff increases. (한미 당국은 지난 7월 미국의 보편적 관세 부과 위협 속에서 한국산 제품에 대한 관세 상한을 15%로 설정하고 대미 투자를 확대하는 내용의 무역 협정을 타결한 바 있다. 우리 정부는 한미 관세합의 문건과 관련해 당초 국회 비준동의 절차가 필요하다고 했다가, 국회 비준 동의 없이 ‘대미투자특별법’ 등 국내 이행 법안으로 내용을 구체화하겠다고 입장을 바꿨다. 양해각서(MOU)의 경우 조약이 아니고 비구속적 성격을 갖고 있고, 미국도 의회 비준 동의를 받지 않기 때문이라는 이유에서다. 그러나 국회에서 비준 동의안 처리가 지연되면서 트럼프 대통령이 관세 인상이라는 강경 카드를 꺼내 든 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In relation to this, the Special Act on Investment in the United States (Special Act for Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Management), proposed by Democratic Party lawmakers last November, was referred to the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee but has not been reviewed even once. The special act includes contents such as ▲the promotion system and procedures for strategic investment, ▲the establishment of a Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Fund, and ▲the temporary establishment of a Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Corporation. (이와 관련, 작년 11월 민주당 의원들이 발의한 대미 투자 특별법(한미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법)은 국회 재정경제기획위원회에 회부됐지만, 아직 한 번도 심의되지 않은 상태다. 특별법은 ▲전략적 투자의 추진체계 및 절차 ▲한미전략투자기금의 설치 ▲한미전략투자공사의 한시적 설립 등의 내용을 담고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The processing of this bill is facing difficulties as the ruling and opposition parties hold differing views. The People Power Party holds the position that the trade agreement ratification should be done first before processing this bill. They cite Article 60, Paragraph 1 of the Constitution, which states, 'Treaties that impose significant financial burdens on the state or its people require the consent of the National Assembly for ratification.' On the other hand, the Democratic Party views the Korea-U.S. trade agreement as a non-binding 'Memorandum of Understanding (MOU)' that does not require National Assembly approval. (해당 법안에 대해 여야가 이견을 보이면서 법 처리는 난항을 겪고 있다. 국민의힘은 이 법 처리에 앞서 무역 합의 비준을 먼저 해야 한다는 입장이다. ‘국가나 국민에게 중대한 재정적 부담을 지우는 조약은 국회의 비준 동의를 받아야 한다’는 헌법 제60조1항을 근거로 들어서다. 반면, 민주당은 한미 무역합의가 법적 구속력이 없는 ‘양해각서(MOU)’이므로 국회 승인이 필요없다고 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A ruling party member of the Strategy and Finance Committee said, "In December last year, there were tax-related deliberations, and in January, there was the confirmation hearing for Minister of Economy and Finance nominee Lee Hye-hoon, so there was insufficient time to fully discuss the special act." Currently, the chairman of the Strategy and Finance Committee is People Power Party member Lim Lee-ja. (재경위 소속 한 여당 의원은 “작년 12월엔 조세 관련 심의, 1월엔 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자 인사 청문회 때문에 특별법을 충분히 논의할 시간도 부족했다”고 말했다. 현재 재경위 위원장은 국민의힘 소속 임이자 의원이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; ()&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/BSCNGZYVM5HHDDAJDXDY6GD3WU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSWMZJSGY3DKOJZHA2WEMZUME.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:03:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruling Party Lawmaker's Harsh Words for Kim Eo-joon: "Opinion Polls with Political Intent Are Dangerous" (김어준에 쓴소리한 與 의원 “정치적 의도 담은 여론조사는 위험”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/HWELWKF4FZCEJAH4JT7OVXY6NA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Ruling Party Lawmaker's Harsh Words for Kim Eo-joon: "Opinion Polls with Political Intent Are Dangerous" (김어준에 쓴소리한 與 의원 “정치적 의도 담은 여론조사는 위험”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GZRDSM3CGU2TSYJQGFQTSMZYGE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, Jang Cheol-min, a lawmaker of the Democratic Party of Korea, said regarding broadcaster Kim Eo-joon, "It is a dangerous thing to embed any political intent into opinion polls." (장철민 더불어민주당 의원이 방송인 김어준씨를 향해 “여론조사에 어떤 정치적인 의도를 심는다는 건 위험한 일”이라고 27일 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a KBS radio interview that day, regarding Kim Eo-joon's refusal to exclude Prime Minister Kim Min-seok from his own opinion poll despite the Prime Minister's Office's request, Representative Jang stated, "I am concerned that it could operate quite dangerously within democratic politics." (장 의원은 이날 KBS 라디오에서 김어준씨가 총리실의 제외 요청을 거절하고 자체 여론조사에 김민석 총리를 포함시키는 것 관련, “민주 정치 내에서 꽤 위험하게 작동할 수 있지 않을까라는 걱정을 가지고 있다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang said, "The fact that they include him despite the request to exclude him (from the candidate list) reveals that it is not genuinely to check the actual approval rating for the candidate during the election process," adding, "I am very worried that they are expressing a (political) will, indicating they have some other intent, through an opinion poll." (장 의원은 “(후보에서) 빼달라고 요청을 했음에도 불구하고 넣는다는 건 선거 과정에서 그게 딱 후보에 대한 실제로 지지율을 확인해 보기 위한 게 아니라는 걸 밝힌 것”이라며 “어떤 다른 의도를 가지고 있다는 (정치적) 의지 표명을 여론조사를 통해서 하는 게 굉장히 걱정이 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also presented the opinion that the principles of opinion polling must be upheld. He said, "Isn't it necessary to maintain the principle that the opinion poll itself is conducted fairly and not carried out with other intentions?" (여론조사의 원칙을 바로 세워야 한다는 의견도 냈다. 그는 “여론조사 자체가 공정하게 이루어지고 있고 다른 의도로 진행되는 것은 아니라는 원칙적인 부분을 가지고 가는 것이 필요하지 않나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/HWELWKF4FZCEJAH4JT7OVXY6NA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GZRDSM3CGU2TSYJQGFQTSMZYGE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:16:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party: "Government and Ruling Party Ignored National Assembly Ratification... Also Dragged Their Feet on Special Act" (국민의힘 “정부·여당, 국회 비준도 무시…특별법도 시간 끌어”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/YDSTXOFIHJBXFMUR55PTU5PBJY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;People Power Party: "Government and Ruling Party Ignored National Assembly Ratification... Also Dragged Their Feet on Special Act" (국민의힘 “정부·여당, 국회 비준도 무시…특별법도 시간 끌어”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRWGMLGHBSWEZLEMQYDKNJWGU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, the People Power Party criticized the announcement by U.S. President Donald Trump to increase tariffs on Korean automobiles and other goods (from 15% to 25%), stating, "This is the result of the government and ruling party ignoring our party's repeated insistence that National Assembly ratification consent must come first for the Korea-U.S. tariff agreement." They also claimed, "The government and ruling party also dragged their feet on the U.S. Investment Special Act, being overly cautious of the U.S." Earlier, U.S. President Trump posted on his social media that day, stating, "The Korean National Assembly is not ratifying the trade agreement between the two countries," and announced he would raise tariffs on Korean automobiles, lumber, pharmaceuticals, etc., from the existing 15% to 25%. (국민의힘이 26일 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 한국산 자동차 등 관세 인상(15%→25%)을 예고한 데 대해 “한미 관세 합의는 국회 비준 동의가 우선이라는 우리 당의 말을 정부·여당이 무시한 결과”라며 “대미 투자 특별법도 정부·여당이 미국 눈치를 보며 시간을 끌었다”고 비판했다. 앞서 트럼프 미 대통령은 이날 자신의 SNS에 “한국 국회가 양국 간 무역 합의를 비준하지 않고 있다”며 한국산 자동차·목재·의약품 등의 관세를 기존 15%에서 25%로 인상하겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok said at a party meeting that day, "This situation starkly reveals how unstable the structure of the Korea-U.S. tariff agreement, which the Lee Jae-myung administration has so proudly praised as a success, truly is." Floor Leader Song stated, "The tariff agreement concluded last year was clearly designed to retroactively lower tariffs from the point the bill was submitted to the National Assembly," adding, "However, the vulnerable structure, where retaliatory tariff increases can be imposed at President Trump's will without a clear agreement on the ratification deadline, has been fully exposed." (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 이날 원내 대책 회의에서 “이번 사태는 이재명 정부가 그토록 성공이라 자화자찬했던 한미 관세 합의가 얼마나 불안정한 구조 위에 놓여있는가를 극명하게 보여준 것”이라고 했다. 송 원내대표는 “지난해 체결된 관세 합의는 분명히 국회에 법안 제출되는 시점으로 관세 소급을 인하하기로 설계돼 있다”며 “그런데 국회 비준 시한에 대한 명확한 합의가 없는 상황에서 트럼프 대통령 뜻대로 관세 인상 보복이 가해질 취약한 구조가 그대로 드러난 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song said, "Regarding last year's Korea-U.S. tariff negotiations, our party repeatedly emphasized that National Assembly ratification consent must come first," and added, "It was the natural course of action to propose and pass a bill if necessary after ratification consent." He stated, "However, the government and ruling party said National Assembly ratification consent was not needed. Ultimately, the responsibility for this entire situation lies with President Lee Jae-myung and his administration, who concluded a major trade agreement requiring National Assembly ratification but have neglected the ratification process." (송 원내대표는 “지난해 한미 관세 협의에 대해 우리 당은 국회 비준 동의가 우선이라고 누차 강조한 바 있다”며 “비준 동의 후 필요하다면 법안을 발의해 통과하는 게 당연한 수순이었다”고 했다. 그는 “그러나 정부·여당은 국회 비준 동의가 없다고 했다. 결과적으로 이 모든 사태 책임은 국회 비준이 필요한 중대한 통상 합의를 체결해 놓고 비준 절차를 외면해왔던 이재명 대통령과 정부에 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the situation since the Democratic Party of Korea proposed the U.S. Investment Special Act on November 26 last year, Floor Leader Song said, "The government made no request or demand to the National Assembly (for swift processing of the bill, etc.)," adding, "This is clear proof they were sitting idly by, completely unaware this situation was approaching." He continued, "The People Power Party proposes meeting with the government and ruling party to put our heads together to resolve this situation," and suggested, "To assess the Korea-U.S. trade situation, we propose holding an urgent question-and-answer session in the National Assembly immediately, even now." (송 원내대표는 작년 11월 26일 더불어민주당이 대미투자특별법을 발의한 이후 상황에 대해 “정부는 국회에 (법안 신속 처리 등) 아무런 요청도, 요구도 없었다”며 “이런 상황이 다가올 것을 전혀 파악하지 못하고 손 놓고 있었단 방증”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “국민의힘은 이번 사태 해결을 위해 정부·여당과 만나 머리를 맞대고 해결할 것을 제안한다”며 “대미 통상 상황을 파악하기 위해 지금 당장이라도 국회에서 긴급 현안 질의를 열 것을 제안한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party lawmaker Park Soo-young, who serves as the party's secretary on the National Assembly's Planning and Finance Committee, said on Facebook that day, "Another stab in the back for the Lee Jae-myung administration," adding, "This comes just one day after Prime Minister Kim Min-seok returned from meeting with U.S. Vice President Vance, boasting about establishing a hotline." Lawmaker Park stated, "It seems the Lee Jae-myung administration knew nothing until President Trump made this decision," and claimed, "Specifically, it is the Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party that dragged their feet on the U.S. Investment Special Act, being overly cautious of the U.S. instead of processing it according to procedure." (국회 재정경제기획위 국민의힘 간사인 박수영 의원은 이날 페이스북에서 “또 뒤통수 맞은 이재명 정부”라며 “김민석 국무총리가 밴스 미국 부통령과 회담을 마치고 핫라인을 구축했다며 귀국한 지 하루 만에 뒤통수를 맞은 것”이라고 했다. 박 의원은 “트럼프 대통령이 이런 결정을 내리기까지 이재명 정부는 아무것도 몰랐던 것 아닌가”라며 “특히 대미투자특별법을 절차대로 처리하지 않고 미국 눈치 보며 시간을 끈 것은 이재명 정부와 민주당”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said on Facebook that day, "Issues like the ratification process and transparent disclosure of negotiation details kept arising, and today we even have President Trump's sudden declaration of tariff reinstatement," noting, "It is unusual to specifically point out the other country's legislature." Leader Lee stated, "Yet, the government and ruling party still have not clarified whether this agreement is a 'treaty' requiring National Assembly ratification or simply an 'MOU'." (개혁신당 이준석 대표는 이날 페이스북에서 “비준 절차나 협상 내용의 투명한 공개 등의 문제가 계속 발생하더니, 오늘 트럼프 대통령의 돌발적인 관세 환원 선언까지 나왔다”며 “이례적으로 상대국 입법부를 지목한 것”이라고 했다. 이 대표는 “그런데 아직도 정부·여당은 이 합의가 국회 비준이 필요한 ‘조약’인지, ‘MOU’인지조차 명확히 하지 않고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee asked, "If it was a memorandum of understanding that did not require ratification, why could the U.S. use 'failure to approve' as grounds for retaliation? Conversely, if ratification was required, why did they try to bypass it with a special act?" He stated, "Either way, the public and opposition parties are not receiving accurate information," and urged, "Even now, the government must sincerely explain the situation to the public and opposition parties." (이 대표는 “비준이 필요 없는 양해각서였다면, 왜 미국은 ‘승인 거부’를 보복 명분으로 삼을 수 있었느냐. 반대로 비준이 필요했다면, 왜 특별법으로 우회하려 했느냐”고 했다. 이 대표는 “어느 쪽이든 국민과 야당은 정확한 정보를 받지 못하고 있다”며 “지금이라도 정부는 국민과 야당에 성의 있게 설명해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/YDSTXOFIHJBXFMUR55PTU5PBJY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MRRWGMLGHBSWEZLEMQYDKNJWGU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:56:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Drives Home Point on Multiple-Homeowners' Capital Gains Tax Surcharge... "We Cannot Change It Just Because Someone Is Powerful" (李대통령, 다주택자 양도세 중과에 쐐기... “힘 세다고 바꿔주면 안돼”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/OGCO5UK6O5AEROS4LBNA2MECDY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee Drives Home Point on Multiple-Homeowners' Capital Gains Tax Surcharge... "We Cannot Change It Just Because Someone Is Powerful" (李대통령, 다주택자 양도세 중과에 쐐기... “힘 세다고 바꿔주면 안돼”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TD6IX76FEJI4HG6GQZJQHZUATI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 27th, "The capital gains tax surcharge on multiple-homeowners was extended for only one year last year, and it is clearly scheduled to end on May 9 this year," adding, "There are also attacks on the policy (claiming) as if we are newly imposing a capital gains tax surcharge on real estate. We must not be swayed by unfair attacks." (이재명 대통령은 27일 “다주택자에 대한 양도세 중과는 작년에 1년만 연장한다고 했고, 올해 5월 9일에 끝난다는 건 명백하게 예정된 것”이라며 “마치 새롭게 부동산 양도세를 중과하는 것처럼 (주장하는) 정책에 대한 공격도 있다. 부당한 공격에 휘둘리면 안 된다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a Cabinet meeting held at the Blue House that day, President Lee said, "When we say (the bill) will sunset, there is resistance, it becomes an issue, and that has become routine. We absolutely must not act in a way that changes things for the powerful and leaves things as they are for the powerless," making these remarks. (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 열린 국무회의를 주재하면서 “(법안을) 일몰한다고 하면 저항하고, 문제 삼고, 그게 일상이 돼 버렸다. 힘 세면 바꿔주고 힘 없으면 그냥 하고, 절대로 그렇게 하면 안 된다”며 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee had stated on the 23rd that he was "not considering an extension at all" for the multiple-homeowners' capital gains tax surcharge system, which expires on the upcoming May 9. After reactions emerged in the market such as 'they are applying the multiple-homeowner surcharge again to suppress housing prices' and 'they are trying to use taxes again to control housing prices,' he made the related comments at today's Cabinet meeting. (이 대통령은 지난 23일 오는 5월 9일 만료되는 다주택자 양도세 중과 제도 유예에 대해 “연장을 전혀 고려하지 않고 있다”고 했다. 이후 시장에서 ‘다주택자 중과세를 다시 적용해 집값을 누르려는 것’, ‘집값을 잡는 데 다시 세금을 이용하려 한다’는 반응이 나오자 이날 국무회의에서 관련 언급을 한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting that day, President Lee said, "Recently, real estate issues have become controversial," and added, "To properly realize growth for all, we must correct the distortion in resource allocation that is abnormally concentrated in real estate." (이 대통령은 이날 회의에서 “요즘 부동산 문제가 논란이 되고 있다”며 “모두의 성장이 제대로 실현하기 위해서는 부동산에 비정상적으로 집중된 자원 배분의 왜곡을 반드시 바로잡아야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "The excessive expansion of unproductive real estate inevitably inflates bubbles," and added, "It not only undermines growth potential but can also inflict severe damage on the national economy as a whole." (이 대통령은 “비생산적인 부동산의 과도한 팽창은 필연적으로 거품을 키우게 된다”며 “성장 잠재력을 훼손할 뿐만 아니라 국민 경제 전반에 심대한 타격을 더할 수 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "We must never leave unfairness and abnormality unattended out of fear of immediate pain and resistance," and added, "At the same time, we must also actively pursue the measures the market desires." (이 대통령은 “당장 눈앞의 고통과 저항이 두려워 불공정과 비정상을 절대로 방치해서는 안 된다”며 “동시에 시장이 원하는 적극적인 대책도 동시에 추진해 나가야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also emphasized policy consistency. He said, "Once a policy direction is set, we must not be swept away by minor waves, nor be elated or dejected by every turn, but firmly ensure policy stability," and added, "We must definitely control the misguided expectations of pursuing unfair benefits." (이 대통령은 정책의 일관성도 강조했다. 이 대통령은 “정책 방향을 정하면 잔파도에 휩쓸리지 말고, 일희일비하지 않고 꿋꿋하게 정책 안정성을 확보해야 한다”며 “부당한 이익을 추구하는 잘못된 기대를 반드시 제어해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Because they are swayed by such things, there is a tendency to have expectations like 'government policy will change again, it will change if we apply pressure'," calling it "an unfair expectation and a mistaken expectation." This indicates that predictions of the capital gains tax surcharge being extended again are wrong. (이 대통령은 “그런 데 휘둘리다 보니까 정부 정책이 또 바뀌겠지, 우리가 압력 넣으면 바뀌겠지, 이런 기대를 하는 경향이 존재한다”며 “부당한 기대이자 잘못된 기대”라고 했다. 양도세 중과가 다시 유예될 것이라는 예측은 잘못됐다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/OGCO5UK6O5AEROS4LBNA2MECDY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TD6IX76FEJI4HG6GQZJQHZUATI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:11:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>He Boasted of a "Hotline with the U.S."... But Prime Minister Kim Min-seok Falls Silent Over 'Trump Tariffs' (“미국과 핫라인” 자랑했는데… ‘트럼프 관세’에 입 닫은 김민석 총리)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/Z3OXMGOHYVHXHICY7TJBUUCZPA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;He Boasted of a "Hotline with the U.S."... But Prime Minister Kim Min-seok Falls Silent Over 'Trump Tariffs' (“미국과 핫라인” 자랑했는데… ‘트럼프 관세’에 입 닫은 김민석 총리)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/I6EKZAC6MJMJNGY3XWH6WMIZQU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who recently boasted of establishing a "hotline with the U.S." during his visit, found himself in an awkward situation at a cabinet meeting. In the early hours of the 27th (Korean time), former President Donald Trump abruptly announced plans to impose sweeping 'universal tariffs' on South Korea. Just hours after emphasizing the "presidential-level treatment" he received and promoting the achievements of his U.S. visit, Prime Minister Kim passed up the opportunity to speak. (최근 미국 방문을 통해 ‘미국과의 핫라인’을 구축했다고 밝힌 김민석 국무총리가 국무회의 석상에서 민망한 상황에 처했다. 27일 새벽(한국 시간) 도널드 트럼프 전 대통령이 한국에 전격적인 ‘보편 관세’ 부과를 예고하자, 불과 몇 시간 전까지 “대통령급 대우”를 강조하며 방미 성과를 홍보하던 김 총리가 발언 기회를 포기한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cabinet meeting that morning began under circumstances where Prime Minister Kim, serving as the permanent chairman of the funeral committee for the late former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan, had to leave midway due to a condolence schedule. Prime Minister Kim usually presides over cabinet meetings. As he left, Deputy Prime Minister for Economic Affairs Koo Yun-cheol, the next in line by convention, took over the chairmanship. Upon receiving the gavel, Deputy Prime Minister Koo immediately set the stage by saying, "I understand the Prime Minister has something to say regarding the achievements of his U.S. visit." (이날 오전 국무회의는 고(故) 이해찬 전 총리의 상임 장례위원장을 맡은 김 총리가 조문 일정으로 인해 도중에 이석해야 하는 상황에서 시작됐다. 평소 국무회의는 김 총리가 사회를 맡아왔다. 김 총리 이석에 따라 관례대로 차선임자인 구윤철 경제부총리가 사회를 맡았는데, 구 부총리는 사회권을 넘겨받자마자 김 총리에게 “총리님이 방미 성과 관련해 하실 말씀이 있으시다고 해서요”라고 운을 뗐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, even before Deputy Prime Minister Koo finished speaking, Prime Minister Kim, seemingly flustered, hastily waved his hands in refusal, declining to speak. This is interpreted as his awareness that the effectiveness of the hotline he had boasted about was now under scrutiny due to the 'Trump tariff bomb' that exploded overnight. (그러나 구 부총리의 말이 끝나기도 전에 김 총리는 당황한 듯 급하게 손사래를 치며 발언을 사양했다. 새벽 사이 터진 ‘트럼프 관세 폭탄’으로 인해 본인이 자랑한 핫라인의 실효성이 도마 위에 오른 상황을 의식한 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Indeed, just before the cabinet meeting, in an interview broadcast on Sampo TV, Prime Minister Kim had unusually praised the results of his U.S. trip. In the interview, he said, "This is the first time since 1985, in 41 years, that a Prime Minister has visited the U.S. for official duties," adding, "Even the Ministry of Foreign Affairs said we've written a completely new chapter in history." (실제로 김 총리는 국무회의 직전 방송된 삼프로TV와의 인터뷰에서 이번 방미 성과를 이례적인 표현을 써가며 자평한 바 있다. 김 총리는 인터뷰에서 “1985년 이후 41년 만에 국무총리가 고유 업무로 미국을 방문한 것은 처음”이라며 “외교부에서도 완전히 새로운 역사를 하나 썼다고 하더라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding his meeting with Vice President J.D. Vance, he highlighted the establishment of a close hotline as an achievement, stating, "Vice President Vance gave me his direct phone number on the spot and even wrote down his national security advisor's number for me." He added that Vice President Vance was very courteous in the conversation and that he received "quite proactive responses regarding nuclear energy, nuclear submarines, and shipbuilding industry cooperation." (또한 J.D. 밴스 부통령과의 회담에 대해 “밴스 부통령이 즉석에서 자기 직통 번호를 알려줬고, 안보 보좌관의 전화번호도 적어서 줬다”며 긴밀한 핫라인 구축을 성과로 내세웠다. 그는 “원자력, 핵잠수함, 조선 산업 협력에 대해 상당히 적극적인 답을 들었다”며 밴스 부통령이 매우 정중하게 대화에 임했다고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These 'heroic tales' from Prime Minister Kim were rendered meaningless just hours later by a single social media post from former President Trump. In the early hours of the 27th, Trump threatened South Korea with reciprocal tariff imposition. Less than a day after Prime Kim promoted that he had "secured channels to communicate with the core of U.S. power anytime," tariff pressure that could shake the Korean economy came as a surprise attack. (김 총리의 이러한 ‘무용담’은 불과 몇 시간 뒤 트럼프 대통령의 SNS 한 방에 무색해졌다. 트럼프 대통령은 27일 새벽 한국에 대해 상호 관세 부과를 위협했다. 김 총리가 “미국 권력 핵심부와 언제든 소통할 채널을 확보했다”고 홍보한 지 하루도 채 지나지 않아 한국 경제를 뒤흔들 관세 압박이 기습적으로 날아온 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/Z3OXMGOHYVHXHICY7TJBUUCZPA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/I6EKZAC6MJMJNGY3XWH6WMIZQU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:32:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blue House: "U.S. Tariff Increase Requires Administrative Action to Take Effect... Will Respond Calmly" (靑 “美 관세인상, 행정조치 있어야 발효... 차분히 대응할것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/J4MVZ7GGKRAM5BKMRJH5SEPBGE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Blue House: "U.S. Tariff Increase Requires Administrative Action to Take Effect... Will Respond Calmly" (靑 “美 관세인상, 행정조치 있어야 발효... 차분히 대응할것”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LJI3TNI2PROIRJBAEBDAFH7U2E.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, regarding U.S. President Donald Trump's mention of 're-raising tariffs on South Korea', the Blue House stated, "Since a tariff increase takes effect only after administrative actions such as publication in the U.S. Federal Register, we plan to calmly respond while conveying our government's will to implement the tariff agreement to the U.S. side." (청와대는 27일 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 ‘한국 관세 재인상’ 언급과 관련해 “관세 인상은 (미국) 연방 관보 게재 등 행정 조치가 있어야 발효되는 만큼, 우리 정부의 관세 합의 이행 의지를 미 측에 전달하는 한편 차분하게 대응해 나갈 계획”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although President Trump publicly mentioned raising tariffs again, since the tariff increase does not take effect immediately, the intention is to convey and persuade the U.S. side regarding our position on tariff negotiations. (트럼프 대통령이 공개적으로 관세를 다시 올리겠다고 언급했지만, 관세 인상이 즉각 이뤄지는 것은 아닌 만큼 미 측에 관세 협상과 관련한 우리 입장을 전달하고 설득하겠다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blue House held an emergency countermeasure meeting this morning, chaired by Policy Chief Kim Yong-beom and National Security Office Director Wi Sung-lak. At the meeting, a review was conducted on the progress of the 'Special Act for Korea-U.S. Strategic Investment Management', which is being pursued as a follow-up measure to the tariff negotiations, according to Blue House Spokesperson Kang Yu-jung. (청와대는 이날 오전 김용범 정책실장과 위성락 국가안보실장이 주재하는 긴급 대책 회의를 열었다. 이날 회의에서는 관세 협상의 후속 조치로 추진 중인 ‘한미 전략적 투자 관리를 위한 특별법안’의 진행 상황 등에 대한 점검이 이뤄졌다고 강유정 청와대 대변인은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the Blue House announced that Minister of Trade, Industry and Energy Kim Jeong-gwan, currently on a business trip to Canada, will travel to the U.S. upon completion of his Canadian schedule to discuss related matters with U.S. Secretary of Commerce Howard Lutnick. Yeo Han-koo, head of the Office of Trade Negotiations, will also go to the U.S. to consult with USTR (U.S. Trade Representative) representative Jamieson Greer. (청와대는 이날 회의 뒤, 현재 캐나다에 출장 중인 김정관 산업통상부 장관이 캐나다 일정이 종료되는 대로 미국으로 건너가 하워드 러트닉 미 상무장관과 관련 내용을 논의하기로 했다고 밝혔다. 여한구 통상교섭본부장도 미국으로 가 제이미슨 그리어 USTR(미 무역대표부) 대표와 협의하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The meeting was attended by Vice Ministers from related ministries, including Yeo Han-koo, head of the Office of Trade Negotiations; Lee Hyung-il, First Vice Minister of Economy and Finance; and Kim Jin-ah, Second Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs. From the Blue House, attendees included Senior Secretary for Economic Growth Ha Joon-kyung, Third Deputy Director of the National Security Office Oh Hyun-joo, and Senior Secretary for AI and Future Planning Ha Jung-woo. Chief of Staff Kang Hoon-sik, currently in Canada as a Special Envoy for Strategic Economic Cooperation, and Minister Kim Jeong-gwan participated via telephone. (이날 회의에는 여한구 통상교섭본부장, 이형일 재정경제부 1차관, 김진아 외교부 2차관 등 관계 부처 차관이 참석했다. 청와대에서는 하준경 경제성장수석, 오현주 국가안보실 3차장, 하정우 AI미래기획수석 등이 참석했다. 현재 전략 경제 협력 특사로 캐나다에 있는 강훈식 대통령 비서실장과 김정관 산업통상부 장관은 유선으로 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/J4MVZ7GGKRAM5BKMRJH5SEPBGE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/LJI3TNI2PROIRJBAEBDAFH7U2E.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:56:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fasting Lawmaker Jang Dong-hyeok, After Hospital Discharge, Says "President Lee Shouldn't Hide Behind Aides, Call Trump" (단식 퇴원 장동혁 “李대통령, 참모 뒤에 숨지 말고 트럼프에 전화하라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/6KNEG4KN7BHMTBUFXZRVWLVB7U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Fasting Lawmaker Jang Dong-hyeok, After Hospital Discharge, Says "President Lee Shouldn't Hide Behind Aides, Call Trump" (단식 퇴원 장동혁 “李대통령, 참모 뒤에 숨지 말고 트럼프에 전화하라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HSPLDVBVANB3LBNGMRZITNYDCE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok said on the 27th regarding U.S. President Donald Trump's notice of re-raising tariffs on Korean automobiles and other goods, "President Lee Jae-myung should not hide behind his aides and should call President Trump." (국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 27일 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령의 한국산 자동차 등 관세 재인상 예고와 관련해 “이재명 대통령은 참모들 뒤에 숨지 말고 트럼프 대통령에게 전화하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang stated this in a Facebook post this afternoon, saying, "The presidency is a position of responsibility, and diplomacy is about capability, not a show." (장 대표는 이날 오후 페이스북에서 “대통령은 책임지는 자리이고, 외교는 쇼가 아니라 실력”이라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang said, "Trump does not answer calls from those who break promises," listing "an immature prime minister who was happy to receive a hotline number, and a president who just gets angry, blaming legislation passed by the parliament they control." He then added, "In the meantime, a 25% tariff bomb has fallen on the people's wallets." (장 대표는 “트럼프는 약속을 어긴 사람의 전화를 받지 않는다”면서 “핫라인 번호를 받았다고 좋아하는 철없는 총리, 자기들이 장악한 국회의 입법을 탓하며 화만 내는 대통령”을 나열했다. 이어 장 대표는 “그 사이 국민 지갑에는 25% 관세 폭탄이 떨어졌다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang, who had been fasting for 8 days demanding a special investigation into bribery allegations involving the Unification Church and Democratic Party nominations, was transferred to a hospital on the 22nd. After being discharged on the 26th, his first public statement targeted the Lee Jae-myung administration's U.S.-Korea tariff negotiations. (장 대표는 통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검 도입을 요구하며 8일간 단식하다 지난 22일 병원으로 이송됐다. 이후 26일 퇴원했는데 첫 일성으로 이재명 정부의 한미 관세 협의를 겨냥한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, U.S. President Trump posted on his social media that day, stating, "The Korean National Assembly is not ratifying the trade agreement between the two countries," and announced he would raise tariffs on Korean automobiles, lumber, pharmaceuticals, etc., from the existing 15% to 25%. (앞서 트럼프 미 대통령은 이날 자신의 소셜미디어에 “한국 국회가 양국 간 무역 합의를 비준하지 않고 있다”며 한국산 자동차·목재·의약품 등의 관세를 기존 15%에서 25%로 인상하겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/6KNEG4KN7BHMTBUFXZRVWLVB7U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HSPLDVBVANB3LBNGMRZITNYDCE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:43:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gwangju·Jeonnam Integrated Name 'Jeonnam Gwangju Special City'... To Have Three Main Office Locations (광주·전남 통합 명칭 ‘전남광주특별시’… 청사는 3곳 두기로)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/2YYEFSJ2S5GQJN3QP4TLT4W2GA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Gwangju·Jeonnam Integrated Name 'Jeonnam Gwangju Special City'... To Have Three Main Office Locations (광주·전남 통합 명칭 ‘전남광주특별시’… 청사는 3곳 두기로)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PI5DFK42VVNYDAJUXVVLDWGV3Y.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, it was decided that the name for the integrated local government of Gwangju and Jeonnam would be 'Jeonnam Gwangju Special City', with the abbreviated name being Gwangju Special City. It was also decided not to have a single main office building, but to use offices in Gwangju City Hall, Jeonnam's Muan, and Jeonnam's eastern region in a balanced manner. (광주·전남 통합 자치단체 명칭을 ‘전남광주특별시’로 하기로 하고 약칭은 광주특별시로 하기로 27일 결정됐다. 주 청사는 두지 않고 광주시청, 전남 무안, 전남 동부 등 청사를 균형 있게 사용하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the '4th Meeting of City/Provincial Governors and National Assembly Members for Review of the Gwangju-Jeonnam Special Act' held at the National Assembly on the 27th, the city/provincial governors and assembly members stated, "The promotion committee held a long meeting and agreed that having a single main office itself becomes an obstacle to integration, so they ultimately decided not to designate one." (27일 국회에서 열린 ‘광주전남 특별법 검토 시·도지사-국회의원 제4차 간담회’에 참석한 시·도지사와 국회의원들은 “추진위는 장시간 회의를 했고, 주 청사를 두는 것 자체가 통합에 걸림돌이 된다는 데에 의견이 일치했기 때문에 결론적으로 정하지 않기로 했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until now, Gwangju City and Jeonnam Province had shown differing opinions on whether the integrated local government name should be 'Gwangju Jeonnam Special City' or 'Jeonnam Gwangju Special City'. They had also been in conflict over the location of the main office. (그동안 광주시와 전남도는 통합 자치단체 명칭을 ‘광주전남특별시’로 할지, ‘전남광주특별시’로 할지를 두고 의견차를 보여왔다. 주청사 위치를 두고도 갈등을 빚어왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this agreement, it is observed that Gwangju and Jeonnam assembly members will propose the special act around the 28th to accelerate the integration process. (이번 합의로 광주·전남 의원들은 28일 정도에 특별법을 발의해 통합 추진에 속도를 낼 것으로 관측된다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/2YYEFSJ2S5GQJN3QP4TLT4W2GA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PI5DFK42VVNYDAJUXVVLDWGV3Y.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:53:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] Jang Dong-hyeok to Return to Party Duties Tomorrow... Focusing on Prices First ([단독] 장동혁, 내일 당무 복귀... 물가부터 챙긴다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/CU6WWTBC4NEPJLAMB45CRG372Y/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] Jang Dong-hyeok to Return to Party Duties Tomorrow... Focusing on Prices First ([단독] 장동혁, 내일 당무 복귀... 물가부터 챙긴다)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MQ4DEN3FGEZDGMLDGVSDQZLBMQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party, will return to party duties on the 28th. This comes just six days after he was transferred to a hospital on the 22nd, following an eight-day hunger strike demanding the introduction of a special prosecutor investigation into alleged bribery related to the Unification Church and the Democratic Party's nominations. (장동혁 국민의힘 대표가 28일 당무(黨務)에 복귀한다. 통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검 도입을 요구하며 8일간 단식하다 지난 22일 병원으로 이송된 지 엿새 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on comprehensive coverage by this newspaper on the 27th, it has been confirmed that Representative Jang is considering returning to party duties on the afternoon of the 28th. A People Power Party official stated, "While Representative Jang's health has not yet fully recovered, he has expressed his will to return to party duties quickly due to the grave political situation and other factors." (27일 본지 취재를 종합하면 장 대표는 28일 오후 당무에 복귀하는 것을 검토하고 있는 것으로 확인됐다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “장 대표 건강이 아직 완전히 회복되지는 않은 상태지만 엄중한 정국 상황 등으로 당무에 빠르게 복귀하겠다는 의지를 내비쳤다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang is expected to choose a public livelihood site for his first schedule. He, along with the party leadership, will visit the integrated situation room of the Korea Agro-Fisheries &amp; Food Trade Corporation (aT) in Seocho-gu, Seoul, this afternoon to inspect agricultural and fisheries product prices. Prior to this schedule, visiting a Hanaro Mart is also under consideration. (장 대표는 첫 일정으로 민생 현장을 택할 전망이다. 장 대표는 지도부와 함께 이날 오후 서울 서초구 한국농수산식품유통공사(aT) 종합상황실을 찾아 농수산 물가를 점검한다. 이 일정에 앞서 하나로마트를 들르는 것도 검토하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang and the People Power Party leadership plan to focus on shopping basket prices ahead of the Lunar New Year. This is because shipments of vegetables have decreased due to recent cold waves and reduced sunlight, leading to significant price increases for some items. At this event, Representative Jang is known to launch a major offensive, mentioning issues such as prices, exchange rates, and the failures of the Lee Jae-myung administration's economic policies. (장 대표와 국민의힘 지도부는 설을 앞두고 장바구니 물가를 챙긴다는 계획이다. 최근 한파와 일조량 감소로 채소류 출하가 줄면서 일부 품목 가격이 크게 오르고 있어서다. 이 자리에서 장 대표는 물가와 환율 등 이재명 정부의 경제 정책 실정 등을 언급하며 대여 공세에 나설 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, Representative Jang began a hunger strike on the 15th, demanding a dual special prosecutor investigation. However, on the 22nd, he halted the fast at the request of former President Park Geun-hye as his health deteriorated rapidly. He was transferred to a hospital in Gwanak-gu, Seoul, that day and was discharged on the 26th, receiving outpatient treatment since.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (앞서 장 대표는 지난 15일 쌍특검을 요구하며 단식에 돌입했다. 그러다 지난 22일 건강이 급격히 악화된 상태에서 박근혜 전 대통령의 요청에 단식을 중단했다. 당일 서울 관악구의 한 병원에 이송됐다 26일 퇴원해 통원 치료를 받아왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/CU6WWTBC4NEPJLAMB45CRG372Y/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MQ4DEN3FGEZDGMLDGVSDQZLBMQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 21:08:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "We're not saying we won't do a supplementary budget all year... Implement it in advance." (李대통령 “올해 내내 추경 안 할 건 아냐... 미리 시행하라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/255GW77I6VF4BJ5W3QL7FSEVDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "We're not saying we won't do a supplementary budget all year... Implement it in advance." (李대통령 “올해 내내 추경 안 할 건 아냐... 미리 시행하라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YFBXPXNCWJKXFFLINF2277RT5A.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung suggested on the 27th that a supplementary budget could be drawn up within the year, stating, "It's not that we won't do a supplementary budget all year long, though we don't know when it will be." (이재명 대통령은 27일 “언제가 될 지 모르지만 올해 내내 추가경정예산(추경)을 안 할 건 아니다”라며 올해 내 추경 편성을 시사했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a cabinet meeting that day, when Minister of the Interior and Safety Yoon Ho-joong requested central government budget support for local governments to operate personnel for delinquency management teams, President Lee responded as above, saying, "There obviously won't be a budget item (for personnel expenses) for that right now, but shouldn't we adjust the budget appropriately through a supplementary budget anyway?" (이 대통령은 이날 국무회의에서 윤호중 행정안전부 장관이 지방자치단체의 체납관리단 인력 운영을 위한 중앙정부 예산 지원을 요청하자 “지금 해당 예산 항목(인건비)은 당연히 없을 거고, 어차피 적정한 시기에 예산을 추경으로 조정해야하지 않냐”며 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, regarding the possible timing of the supplementary budget, he said, "though we don't know when it will be." President Lee instructed, "Proceed with the implementation in advance, including the premise of a supplementary budget and the Planning and Budget Office providing funds to local governments, which will be reimbursed later." (다만 추경 가능 시점에 대해서는 “언제가 될 지 모르지만”이라고 했다. 이 대통령은 “추경을 하는 걸 전제로 하고, 기획예산처가 지방정부에 예산을 지급하면, 나중에 보전해주는 걸 포함해서 미리 시행하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Deputy Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination Lim Ki-geun said, "May I say something?" and added, "It's not that central government revenue has increased, but there is an aspect of local government revenue increasing. This (operation of delinquency management teams) clearly falls under the aspect of local autonomous affairs as stated in Article 13 of the Local Autonomy Act." (그러자 임기근 기획예산처 차관은 “한 말씀 드려도 되겠냐”며 “중앙정부 세입이 늘어난 게 아니고 지방정부 세입이 늘어나는 측면이 있다. 이건(체납관리단 운영) 명백하게 지방자치법 13조에 나오는 지방 자치사무 측면이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a rebuttal implying that it is difficult to provide budget support at the government level because the operation of local government delinquency management teams, which Minister Yoon requested, is a local government affair. (윤 장관이 요구한 지자체 체납관리단 운영은 지자체 사무이기 때문에 정부 차원의 예산 지원이 어렵다는 취지로 반박한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Minister Lim further stated, "Looking at past precedents in Seongnam City and Gyeonggi Province, there were times when Seongnam City bore all the costs, and times when Gyeonggi Province and Seongnam City shared the costs half and half," and added, "Therefore, we shouldn't definitively decide that the state will unconditionally support it; we need to comprehensively examine such circumstances." To this, President Lee laughed and said, "Let's not finalize it today." (임 차관은 “과거 성남시와 경기도 시행 선례를 보면 그때는 성남시가 다 부담한 적도 있고, 경기도와 성남시가 절반씩 부담한 적도 있다”며 “그래서 국가가 무조건 지원한다 확정짓지 말고 그런 사정을 종합적으로 살펴봐야 한다”고 했다. 이에 이 대통령은 웃으며 “오늘 확정은 말죠”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/255GW77I6VF4BJ5W3QL7FSEVDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YFBXPXNCWJKXFFLINF2277RT5A.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 21:19:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "The National Assembly's legislative pace is too slow... We can't get work done" (李대통령 “국회 입법 속도 너무 느려…일을 할 수가 없다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/7YYANIVY2JCVJIMXD5M42AQJCY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "The National Assembly's legislative pace is too slow... We can't get work done" (李대통령 “국회 입법 속도 너무 느려…일을 할 수가 없다”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/IW4U6VHOUBD4XBNN53NBH2ABMA.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, President Lee Jae-myung said, "Nearly eight months (since the government's inauguration) have passed, yet legislation on the government's basic policy directions has only reached about 20%," adding, "The National Assembly is currently too slow, putting us in a state where we can't get work done." (이재명 대통령은 27일 “(정부 출범) 8개월이 다 돼 가는데, 정부의 기본적인 정책 방침에 대한 입법조차도 20%밖에 안 됐다”며 “지금 국회가 너무 느려서 일을 할 수가 없는 상태”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The President made these remarks during a State Council meeting held at the Blue House while discussing measures to collect overdue non-tax national revenue. When National Tax Service Commissioner Lim Kwang-hyun mentioned the need for legal amendments, President Lee responded, "I fully understand, but the National Assembly's legislative pace is too slow." He then asked, "We can't keep waiting indefinitely. Couldn't we, even before that, recruit and dispatch personnel under the name of each ministry or implement joint management?" (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 체납된 국세 외 수입의 징수 방안을 논의하는 과정에서 이같이 말했다. 임광현 국세청장이 법 개정이 필요하다고 언급하자 이 대통령은 “충분히 이해하겠지만 국회의 입법 속도가 너무 느리다”며 “계속 기다릴 수는 없으니 그 전이라도 각 부처 명의로 (인력을) 뽑아서 파견하든지 합동 관리를 해 주면 되지 않느냐”고 물었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Commissioner Lim replied that legislation might be faster, President Lee said, "Oh, honestly..." and continued, "The National Assembly is currently too slow; who knows when (the legislation) will be passed. Are you going to wait until then?" He urged, "Start now. There's no guarantee it will be done by February. There are hundreds of bills pending in the National Assembly now; at this pace, who knows when they'll be processed." He added, "Given this situation, let's not delay and take emergency measures," and emphasized, "Speed is crucial in administration; we can't afford to wait." (임 청장이 입법하는 것이 더 빠를 것 같다고 답하자 이 대통령은 “아이, 참 말을…”이라며 “국회가 지금 너무 느려서 어느 세월에 (입법이) 될지 모른다. 그때까지 기다리실 거냐”고 했다. 그러면서 “지금부터 시작하라. 2월에 된다는 보장이 없다”며 “지금 국회에 계류된 법률이 수백 개인데, 저런 속도로 해서 어느 세월에 될지 모른다”고 했다. 이어 “상황이 이러니 미루지 말고 비상조치를 좀 하자”며 “행정은 속도가 중요한데 기다리면 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee also made remarks to strengthen the Financial Supervisory Service's authority to initiate investigations. He asked Lee Eok-won, Chairman of the Financial Services Commission, "Is (the FSS) a supervisory agency or an administrative office?" and questioned, "What are we supposed to do if (the supervisory agency) can't initiate investigations? Should we report to the prosecution and ask them to initiate?" He further stated, "Civil servants in administrative agencies handling duties are quasi-public institutions, like the authorized, specialized FSS, an organization entrusted with public duties," and argued, "Yet, requiring only prosecutors to approve the correction of illegal acts is strange, isn't it? Shouldn't we fix what's wrong?" (이 대통령은 금융감독원의 인지수사 권한에 힘을 실어주는 발언도 했다. 이 대통령은 이억원 금융위원장에게 “(금감원이) 감독기관인가 사무기관인가”라고 물으며 “(감독기관에 인지수사를) 못하게 하면 어떡하냐. 검찰 보고해서 인지하라고 하냐”고 했다. 이어 “업무를 담당하는 행정기관 공무원은 승인받은 금감원 같은 전문적인 단체, 공무를 위임받은 단체니까 준 공무기관”이라며 “그런데도 불법 교정하는 것을 굳이 검사만이 승인하는 것은 이상하지 않나. 잘못된 것은 고쳐야 되는 거 아니냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/7YYANIVY2JCVJIMXD5M42AQJCY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/IW4U6VHOUBD4XBNN53NBH2ABMA.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:53:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] Han Dong-hoon to Attend YS Documentary Film Preview on the 28th... First Public Appearance Since Expulsion Recommendation ([단독] 한동훈, 28일 YS 다큐 영화 시사회 참석...제명 권고 후 첫 공개 행보)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/2F6C45KVY5FWTGVPHQECKIZWJM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] Han Dong-hoon to Attend YS Documentary Film Preview on the 28th... First Public Appearance Since Expulsion Recommendation ([단독] 한동훈, 28일 YS 다큐 영화 시사회 참석...제명 권고 후 첫 공개 행보)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7MY56QGZCFKZBNR7U2BEGX57HU.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former People Power Party leader Han Dong-hoon will attend a preview of a documentary film re-examining former President Kim Young-sam on the 28th. This marks his first public appearance since the party's Central Ethics Committee recommended his expulsion on the 14th. (국민의힘 한동훈 전 대표가 28일 김영삼 대통령을 재조명한 다큐멘터리 영화 시사회에 참석한다. 지난 14일 당 중앙윤리위원회의 제명 권고 이후 첫 공개 행보다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on comprehensive coverage by this newspaper on the 27th, the former leader will attend the preview of 'The Forgotten President: Kim Young-sam's Era of Reform' in Yeongdeungpo, Seoul, on the afternoon of the 28th. This film is the first documentary to focus intensely on former President Kim. It is reported that former leader Han will be accompanied by some pro-Han faction lawmakers, including PPP lawmaker Jin Jong-oh. (27일 본지 취재를 종합하면 한 전 대표는 28일 오후 서울 영등포에서 열리는 ‘잊혀진 대통령: 김영삼의 개혁 시대’ 시사회를 찾는다. 이 영화는 김 전 대통령을 집중 조명한 최초의 다큐 영화다. 한 전 대표는 국민의힘 진종오 의원 등 일부 친한계 의원과 동행할 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this event, former leader Han is expected to honor former President Kim and emphasize conservative spirit. Previously, in a speech at a party chapter in Dongdaemun, Seoul, on the 9th, ahead of his ethics committee ruling, he stated, "I believe former President Kim should be the politician symbolizing the spirit of the People Power Party now," emphasizing the YS spirit. He continued, "Then we become the force that led democracy. We become the force that initiated economic democratization," adding, "I believe true conservatism is that spirit." (이 자리에서 한 전 대표는 김 전 대통령을 기리며 보수 정신을 강조할 전망이다. 앞서 그는 자신의 윤리위 의결을 앞둔 지난 9일 서울 동대문을 당협을 찾아 한 강연에서 “김 전 대통령이 지금 국민의힘 정신을 상징하는 정치인이어야 한다고 생각한다”며 YS 정신을 강조했다. 이어 “그러면 우리는 민주주의를 이끈 세력이 되는 겁니다. 경제민주화 시초를 만든 세력이 되는 것”이라며 “진짜 보수는 그런 정신이라고 생각한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the same day, former leader Han wrote on his Facebook, "Our People Power Party must be a liberal democratic party." Regarding the party's Central Ethics Committee issuing what is effectively an expulsion recommendation—'advice to leave the party'—to former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyuk, a pro-Han figure, the previous day, he said, "An illegal martial law is currently underway within the People Power Party," and added, "We must protect true conservatism from pseudo-conservatives like the Yoon faction. I will lead the charge." (한 전 대표는 이날 자신의 페이스북에 “우리 국민의힘은 자유민주주의 정당이어야 한다”고 썼다. 그는 전날 당 중앙윤리위원회가 친한계인 김종혁 전 최고위원에게 사실상 제명인 ‘탈당 권유’를 내린 데 대해 “지금 국민의힘에서 불법 계엄이 진행 중”이라며 “윤어게인 사이비 보수로부터 진짜 보수를 지켜내야 한다. 제가 앞장서겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the party's Central Ethics Committee recommended the expulsion of former leader Han around 1 a.m. on the 24th, citing the so-called 'party member bulletin board' incident involving his family. Subsequently, opinions across party factions emerged stating, "Expulsion is excessive," and party leader Jang Je-won said on the 15th, "I will postpone the expulsion ruling during the ethics committee reconsideration period (within 10 days)." Party leader Jang, who is recovering after ending an 8-day hunger strike, is expected to attend the party's Supreme Council meeting on the 29th to decide whether to proceed with the expulsion ruling for former leader Han. (앞서 당 중앙윤리위원회는 지난 24일 새벽 1시쯤 한 전 대표의 가족이 연루된 이른바 ‘당원 게시판’ 사건으로 한 전 대표의 제명을 권고했다. 이후 당내에서 계파를 불문하고 “제명은 과하다”는 의견이 잇따랐고 장 대표는 15일 “윤리위 재심 기간(10일 이내) 동안 제명 의결을 미루겠다”고 했었다. 8일간의 단식을 마치고 회복 중인 장 대표는 29일 당 최고위원회에 참석해 한 전 대표 제명의 의결 여부를 결정할 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Lee Jun-seok, leader of the Reform Party, and former UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon will also attend the film preview on the same day. However, they are reported to be attending at different times than former leader Han. Leader Lee appeared on YTN Radio the previous day and commented on former leader Han, saying, "He is suddenly claiming 'I am the mainstream of conservatism,' but the context is lacking." (한편 이준석 개혁신당 대표와 반기문 전 유엔 사무총장도 같은 날 영화 시사회에 참석한다. 다만 한 전 대표와 다른 시간대에 참석할 것으로 알려졌다. 이 대표는 전날 YTN 라디오에 출연해 한 전 대표에 대해 “갑자기 ‘내가 보수의 본류다’라는 식으로 주장하고 계시는데 맥락이 부족하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/2F6C45KVY5FWTGVPHQECKIZWJM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7MY56QGZCFKZBNR7U2BEGX57HU.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 22:09:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Expulsion Inevitable” vs. “Pseudo-Conservative”: Jang-Han Conflict Reaches Extreme Levels (“제명 불가피” “사이비 보수” 극한으로 치닫는 張·韓 갈등)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/4TY5DMUHMJBNDEG74ORM46ACQ4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;“Expulsion Inevitable” vs. “Pseudo-Conservative”: Jang-Han Conflict Reaches Extreme Levels (“제명 불가피” “사이비 보수” 극한으로 치닫는 張·韓 갈등)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62QCFQJDQBERBK6LGD4LL366JA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the People Power Party's Ethics Committee took the severe disciplinary measure of 'recommending withdrawal from the party' against former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyeok, who is part of the pro-Han faction (Han Dong-hoon faction), the internal party conflict over handling the expulsion motion against former leader Han Dong-hoon has intensified. On the 27th, close associates of leader Jang Dong-hook publicly stated that "the expulsion of former leader Han must be handled swiftly," while former leader Han is also countering strongly, saying he will "confront the pseudo-conservatives." As the extreme confrontation between the former and current party leaders continues, concerns are growing within the party that "if a political solution is not sought, we will all face mutual destruction in the upcoming local elections." (국민의힘 윤리위원회가 친한계(한동훈계) 김종혁 전 최고위원에 대해 중징계인 ‘탈당 권유’ 조치에 나서면서 한동훈 전 대표의 제명안(案) 처리를 둘러싼 당내 갈등이 격화되고 있다. 27일 장동혁 대표 측근 인사들은 공개적으로 “한 전 대표 제명을 신속하게 처리해야 한다”고 했고, 한 전 대표 또한 “사이비 보수에 맞서겠다”면서 강공으로 맞서고 있다. 전·현직 당대표 간의 극한 대치가 이어지면서 당 내부에선 “정치적 해법을 모색하지 않는다면 다가오는 지방선거에서 우리 모두가 공멸(共滅)할 것”이란 우려가 커지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party Supreme Council member Kim Jae-won said on YTN Radio that day, "Indefinitely postponing the issue of former leader Han only causes confusion," adding, "It is necessary to reach a conclusion by passing (the disciplinary motion) within a short period." When asked by the host what conclusion he thought should be reached, Supreme Council member Kim replied, "(As a member of the leadership) it is inappropriate to comment in advance because I personally will have to participate in the vote." (국민의힘 김재원 최고위원은 이날 YTN 라디오에서 “한 전 대표 문제를 마냥 미루는 것은 혼란만 야기한다”면서 “빠른 시일 내에 (징계안을) 의결함으로써 결론 맺을 필요가 있다”고 말했다. 어떤 결론이 나와야 한다고 생각하느냐는 진행자 물음에 김 최고위원은 “(지도부로서) 개인적으로 표결에 참여해야 할 상황이기 때문에 미리 말하는 것은 부적절하다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Ye-chan, Vice President of the Yeouido Research Institute and a close associate of leader Jang, also appeared on MBC Radio the previous night, stating, "There are quite a few traditional supporters who say they cannot support the party if Han Dong-hoon is left in an ambiguous state," and that "the prevailing opinion within the Supreme Council is that the expulsion of former leader Han is now unavoidable." He also said, "Former leader Han will be expelled at the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th." Leader Jang is also known to have held the position until recently that the expulsion of former leader Han is inevitable. (장 대표 측근인 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장도 전날 밤 MBC 라디오에 나와 “한동훈씨를 어설프게 놔둔 상태로는 지지하지 못하겠다는 전통 지지층도 상당히 많다”면서 “이제는 한 전 대표 제명을 피할 수 없다는 것이 최고위 내부 중론”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “오는 29일 최고위원회의에서 한 전 대표가 제명될 것”이라고도 했다. 장 대표 또한 최근까지 한 전 대표 제명이 불가피하다는 입장이었던 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, former leader Han did not back down regarding the Ethics Committee's decision to severely discipline former Supreme Council member Kim, stating, "This is not normal. It must be corrected." Particularly regarding the part where the Ethics Committee defined leader Jang as "the sum of the free will of each individual party member," former leader Han pointed out that it was akin to "totalitarianism like North Korea's leader theory or Nazism." He criticized, "It means that if a party member criticizes the party leader, they should be expelled from the party," adding, "It is astonishing that anti-democratic, anti-intellectual statements are being made openly in the Ethics Committee's decision document." (이에 대해 한 전 대표는 김 전 최고위원을 중징계한 윤리위 결정에 대해 “이것은 정상이 아니다. 바로잡아야 한다”면서 물러서지 않았다. 특히 윤리위가 장 대표를 “당원 개개인의 자유의지 총합”이라고 규정한 대목과 관련해서 한 전 대표는 “북한 수령론이나 나치즘과 같은 전체주의”라고 지적했다. 그러면서 “당원이 당대표를 비판하면 당에서 내쫓아야 한다는 것”이라며 “반민주, 반지성적인 말을 놀랍게도 윤리위 결정문에서 대놓고 한다”고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ethics Committee's statement that it "hopes this disciplinary action will serve as a precedent to achieve not only 'specific deterrence' but also 'general deterrence' within the party" while effectively expelling (recommending withdrawal) former Supreme Council member Kim is also becoming controversial. The disciplined party member, former Supreme Council member Kim, stated, "Simply put, they have blatantly revealed that this severe disciplinary action is not just for me but to intimidate all party members," and announced, "I will take legal measures, including applying for a provisional injunction to suspend the effect." (윤리위가 김 전 최고위원을 사실상 제명(탈당 권유)하면서 “이 징계가 선례가 되어 정당 내에 ‘개별 억제’뿐만 아니라 ‘일반 억제’가 이루어질 수 있기를 기대한다”고 했던 것도 논란이 되고 있다. 징계 대상자인 김 전 최고위원은 “쉽게 말해 이번 중징계가 저뿐만이 아니라 당원 전체를 겁주기 위한 거라고 노골적으로 밝힌 것”이라면서 “효력 정지 가처분 신청 등 법적 조치에 나서겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former leader Han is reportedly predicting that the party leadership will finalize his expulsion. If an expulsion decision is made, former leader Han plans to inform public opinion of its unfairness while also taking legal action. Pro-Han faction figures are planning a 'second rally urging withdrawal of the expulsion' in front of the National Assembly on the 31st, and former leader Han is also scheduled to attend a talk concert at Jamsil Indoor Stadium on the 8th of next month. Within the pro-Han faction, there is also talk that "if the party forcibly carries out an unreasonable expulsion, former leader Han could consider running as an independent in the upcoming National Assembly by-election." (한 전 대표는 당 지도부가 자신에 대한 제명을 최종 확정할 것으로 예측하는 것으로 알려졌다. 만약 제명 결정이 이뤄진다면 한 전 대표는 여론에 부당함을 알리는 동시에 법적 대응에도 나선다는 방침이다. 친한계 인사들은 오는 31일 국회 앞에서 ‘2차 제명 철회 촉구 집회’를 계획하고 있고, 한 전 대표도 다음 달 8일 잠실 실내체육관에서 토크 콘서트에 참석할 예정이다. 친한계 내부에선 “당이 비상식적인 제명을 강행한다면, 한 전 대표가 다가오는 국회의원 보궐선거에 무소속 출마하는 방법도 생각해 볼 수 있을 것”이라는 얘기도 나오고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Inside and outside the People Power Party, voices worried about this extreme Jang-Han conflict are growing. 'Alternative and Future,' a reform-minded lawmakers' group within the People Power Party, urged the Jang Dong-hook leadership that day to "reconsider the Ethics Committee's decision to expel former leader Han." The group's secretary, lawmaker Lee Seong-kwon, met with reporters that day and stated this, saying, "Efforts should be made to ensure leader Jang's hunger strike leads to party unity." The lawmaker also said to former leader Han, "He should seek a political solution, such as requesting his supporters to stop holding rallies." Lawmaker Kim Yong-tae, who has little factional color, also said, "(If the expulsion decision is made) both leader Jang and former leader Han will become losers, leaving only wounds." (국민의힘 안팎에선 이 같은 극한으로 치닫는 장·한(張韓) 갈등을 걱정하는 목소리가 커지고 있다. 국민의힘 개혁 성향 의원 모임인 ‘대안과 미래’는 이날 장동혁 지도부에 “한 전 대표를 제명한 윤리위원회의 결정을 재고해 달라”고 촉구했다. 모임 간사인 이성권 의원은 이날 기자들과 만나 “장 대표의 단식이 당의 통합으로 이어지도록 노력해야 한다”면서 이같이 밝혔다. 이 의원은 한 전 대표를 향해서도 “지지자들에게 집회 중지를 요청하는 등 정치적 해법 모색에 나서야 한다”고 했다. 계파색이 옅은 김용태 의원도 “(제명 결정이 이뤄지면) 장 대표, 한 전 대표 모두 패자가 되고 상처만 남을 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/4TY5DMUHMJBNDEG74ORM46ACQ4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/62QCFQJDQBERBK6LGD4LL366JA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 22:12:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea Fires Multiple Short-Range Ballistic Missiles into East Sea (北, 동해상으로 단거리 탄도미사일 여러 발 발사)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/N4FABGZLV5DKFJU3QEXZOEWKSE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;North Korea Fires Multiple Short-Range Ballistic Missiles into East Sea (北, 동해상으로 단거리 탄도미사일 여러 발 발사 )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ME3DCMBUMFSTSMZXGY3WMOBVHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
The Joint Chiefs of Staff (JCS) announced on the 27th that North Korea fired short-range ballistic missiles (SRBMs) into the East Sea. This launch occurred shortly after U.S. Undersecretary of Defense for Policy, Elbridge Colby, concluded his visit to South Korea and departed for Japan. This marks North Korea's second ballistic missile provocation this year. ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the JCS and Japan's Ministry of Defense, North Korea fired multiple SRBMs from an area north of Pyongyang into the East Sea around 3:50 PM today. The JCS stated the North Korean SRBMs flew approximately 350 km. Japan's Ministry of Defense estimated that the objects, presumed to be ballistic missiles, all fell outside Japan's Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ). (북한이 동해상으로 단거리 탄도미사일(SRBM)을 발사했다고 합동참모본부가 27일 밝혔다. 미국 엘브리지 콜비 미국 국방부(전쟁부) 정책담당 차관이 방한 일정을 마치고 일본으로 출국한 직후 단거리 탄도미사일(SRBM)을 발사한 것이다. 북한의 탄도미사일 도발은 올 들어 두번째다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The JCS said, "Our military, while strengthening surveillance and vigilance in preparation for additional launches, is maintaining a full readiness posture and closely sharing information related to 'North Korean ballistic missiles' with the U.S. and Japan." The military is currently analyzing detailed specifications of the missiles, such as their type, flight distance, and altitude. (합참과 일본 방위성 등에 따르면 북한은 이날 오후 3시 50분쯤 평양 북방 일대에서 동해상으로 SRBM 여러 발을 발사했다. 북한 SRBM은 약 350㎞를 비행했다고 합참은 밝혔다. 일본 방위성은 탄도미사일 추정 물체가 모두 일본 배타적경제수역(EEZ) 바깥에 낙하한 것으로 추정된다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This North Korean provocation occurred after U.S. Undersecretary of Defense Colby, who was in South Korea from the 25th to the 27th, departed this morning. Military authorities are reportedly closely monitoring the possibility that the missiles launched by North Korea could be 600mm super-large multiple rocket launchers. The super-large multiple rocket launcher, known to have a maximum range of around 400 km, is assessed as a weapon aimed solely at striking South Korea. (합참은 “우리 군은 추가 발사에 대비하여 감시 및 경계를 강화한 가운데, 미·일 측과 ‘북 탄도미사일’ 관련 정보를 긴밀하게 공유하면서 만반의 대비 태세를 유지하고 있다”고 전했다. 현재 군은 미사일의 종류와 비행 거리, 고도 등 세부 제원을 분석 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last month, on the 30th, North Korea released footage of Kim Jong Un, Chairman of the State Affairs Commission, conducting an on-site inspection of a factory producing 600mm super-large multiple rocket launchers. At the time, Kim Jong Un stated it was "literally a super-powerful weapons system that can annihilate the enemy with concentrated and surprise strikes and can also be used as a strategic attack means." North Korea is highlighting its claim that the tactical nuclear warhead 'Hwasan-31' can be mounted on the 600mm multiple rocket launcher. (이번 북한 도발은 콜비 미 국방차관이 25~27일 방한 일정을 마치고 이날 오전 출국한 이후 이뤄졌다. 군 당국은 북한이 발사한 미사일이 600㎜ 초대형 방사포일 가능성을 예의 주시하고 있는 것으로 전해졌다. 최대 사거리가 400㎞ 남짓으로 알려진 초대형 방사포는 한국 타격만을 겨냥한 무기로 평가된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korea also conducted a test launch of a missile, presumed to be the 'Hwasong-11ma', a hypersonic missile, into the East Sea on the 4th. This was one day before the summit meeting between President Lee Jae-myung and Chinese President Xi Jinping. It was presumed to be a combination of a hypersonic glide vehicle and a launch vehicle from the KN-23 series, the 'North Korean version of Iskander' SRBM. At that time, it flew approximately 900 km before impact. (북한은 지난달 30일 김정은 북한 국무위원장이 600㎜ 초대형 방사포 생산 공장을 현지 지도하는 모습을 공개했다. 당시 김정은은 “타격의 집중성과 불의성으로 적을 초토화할 수 있으며 전략적 공격 수단으로도 이용할 수 있는 말 그대로 초강력적인 무기 체계”라고 말했다. 북한은 전술 핵탄두 ‘화산-31’을 600㎜ 방사포에 탑재할 수 있다고 주장하고 있는데 이를 부각한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/N4FABGZLV5DKFJU3QEXZOEWKSE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ME3DCMBUMFSTSMZXGY3WMOBVHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 22:03:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Breaking News] President Lee Visits Funeral Altar of Former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan... Posthumously Awards Mugunghwa Medal ([속보] 李대통령, 이해찬 전 총리 빈소 조문... 무궁화장 추서)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/JLQ5NQWO4RH2HLTVHBCUGTXORY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Breaking News] President Lee Visits Funeral Altar of Former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan... Posthumously Awards Mugunghwa Medal ([속보] 李대통령, 이해찬 전 총리 빈소 조문... 무궁화장 추서 )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/42ECLEXN7ZJQFO7VNKCUF3ADAA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung visited the funeral altar of the late former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan on the 27th to pay his respects. The President posthumously awarded the late former Prime Minister the Mugunghwa Medal, the highest grade of the National Order of Merit. (이재명 대통령이 27일 고(故) 이해찬 전 국무총리의 빈소를 찾아 조문했다. 이 대통령은 고인에게 최고 등급의 국민훈장인 무궁화장을 추서했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee, accompanied by First Lady Kim Hye-kyung, visited the funeral altar set up at the Seoul National University Hospital funeral hall in Jongno-gu, Seoul, this afternoon. President Lee met with the bereaved family of the former Prime Minister to offer his condolences and presented the National Order of Merit, the Mugunghwa Medal. (이 대통령은 이날 오후 김혜경 여사와 함께 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장에 마련된 이 전 총리 빈소를 찾았다. 이 대통령은 이 전 총리 유족들을 만나 위로하고, 국민훈장인 무궁화장을 전달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The National Order of Merit is awarded to individuals who have made clear contributions to the welfare of the people and the development of the nation through distinguished service in the fields of politics, economy, society, education, or academia. The Mugunghwa Medal is the highest grade (1st class) among the five grades of the National Order of Merit. (국민훈장은 정치·경제·사회·교육·학술 분야에 공적을 세워 국민의 복지향상과 국가발전에 기여한 공적이 뚜렷한 사람에게 수여된다. 무궁화장은 5등급으로 구분되는 국민훈장 가운데서도 가장 높은 1등급 훈장에 해당한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former Prime Minister showed symptoms of respiratory distress on the 23rd while on a business trip to Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam, and was urgently transferred to a local hospital. Local medical staff diagnosed a myocardial infarction and performed medical procedures, including 'stent insertion,' but the deceased did not regain consciousness. (이 전 총리는 지난 23일 베트남 호찌민 출장 중 호흡 곤란 증세를 보여 현지 병원으로 긴급 이송됐다. 현지 의료진은 심근경색 진단을 내리고 ‘스텐트 삽입’ 시술 등 의료 조치를 했지만, 고인은 의식을 되찾지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/27/JLQ5NQWO4RH2HLTVHBCUGTXORY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/42ECLEXN7ZJQFO7VNKCUF3ADAA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:11:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Kim on Jeong Cheong-rae's Proposal for Merger with the Cho Kuk Party: "Much Controversy Over Timing and Method" (金총리, 정청래의 조국당 합당 제안에 “시점·방식에 많은 논란”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/27/KVMLUT6T6ZFCBH3HLR2C3WTMTY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KU6WTMT72RNQ5PQVXFB6J7345Y.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 27th, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok pointed out regarding Democratic Party of Korea leader Jeong Cheong-rae's proposal for a merger with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, "It was raised in such a manner at this point in time, causing much controversy," and stated, "There are various opinions on whether the method or timing of the push was appropriate." (김민석 국무총리가 27일 정청래 더불어민주당 대표의 조국혁신당 합당 제안에 대해 “이 시점에 그런 방식으로 제기돼서 많은 논란이 되고 있다”며 “추진 방식이나 시기가 적절했는지에 대해 여러 의견이 있는 상태”라고 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During an interview released that day on the YouTube channel 'Sampo TV', the Prime Minister was asked by the host, 'There are many reports that the merger proposal was not coordinated in advance (with the Blue House). Were you aware of the merger proposal beforehand?' Prime Minister Kim replied, "I did not know it would be announced in that manner on that day." (김 총리는 이날 공개된 유튜브 ‘삼프로TV’와 한 인터뷰에서 진행자에게서 ‘합당 제안이 사전에 (청와대와) 조율되지 않았다는 보도가 많이 있다. 합당 제안을 사전에 알고 있었느냐’는 질문을 받았다. 김 총리는 “그날 그런 방식으로 발표될 것이라는 점은 몰랐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim continued, "However, I have been a principled advocate for grand democratic unity for a very long time," and added, "I have always been someone who couldn't quite find enough distinctiveness for the Cho Kuk Innovation Party to exist as a party separate from the Democratic Party." He said, "If you look at the start of the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, there is an aspect of it being created out of necessity because the environment made it difficult for Representative Cho Kuk to engage in politics within the Democratic Party," and explained, "So, I have always thought that under normal circumstances, Representative Cho would also be doing politics within the Democratic Party, and most of the people there would also be doing so within the Democratic Party, wouldn't they?" (김 총리는 이어서 “다만 저는 아주 오래전부터 원칙적인 민주 대통합론자”라며 “원래부터 조국혁신당이 민주당과 다른 정당으로 존재해야 할 만큼의 차별성을 잘 발견하지 못하는 사람”이라고 했다. 김 총리는 “조국혁신당의 출발도 따지고 보면 조국 대표가 민주당에서 정치를 하기가 마땅치 않은 환경 때문에 어쩔 수 없이 만들어진 측면이 있다”며 “그래서 정상적인 상황이었다면 조 대표도 민주당에서 정치를 하고, 거기 계신 분들도 대부분 민주당에서 하는 것이 맞지 않는가라는 생각을 저는 원래부터 하고 있었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim emphasized, "In that sense, I have thought that a merger or integration is normal and natural." However, the issue lies in the timing and method of Representative Jeong's announcement. Prime Minister Kim, who had departed for the United States on the 22nd for a meeting with US Vice President JD Vance, is known to have not been informed in advance that Representative Jeong would propose a merger that day. (김 총리는 “그런 의미에서 합당 또는 통합이 정상적이고 자연스럽다고 생각해왔다”고 강조했다. 다만 정 대표의 발표 시점이나 방식이 문제라는 것이다. 지난 22일 JD 밴스 미국 부통령과의 회담을 위해 미국으로 출발했던 김 총리는 그날 정 대표가 합당을 제안할 것이라는 이야기를 사전에 전달받지 못한 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim said, "Nevertheless, I hold the view that, in the grand scheme of things, it would be good to see it moving in a direction that resolves well (towards the merger)." (김 총리는 “그럼에도 불구하고, 큰 틀에 있어서는 (합당이) 잘되도록 풀어가는 방향으로 보는 것이 좋지 않을까 하는 생각을 갖고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling party, while Representative Jeong is known to be preparing to run for re-election as party leader, forecasts have also emerged that Prime Minister Kim will run in the Democratic Party's upcoming party leadership election. Regarding this, Prime Minister Kim stated, "I grew up within the Democratic Party and am someone who loves the Democratic Party, so becoming the party leader of the Democratic Party is a very proud thing," and added, "Naturally, I have an aspiration (to become party leader)." He said, "I have the thought that I would like to try (being party leader) and play a role in guiding the party in a certain direction." (여권에서는 정 대표가 당대표직 연임에 나설 것으로 알려진 가운데, 김 총리도 민주당 차기 당대표 선거에 나올 것이라는 전망이 나온다. 이와 관련해 김 총리는 “저는 민주당에서 성장했고 민주당을 사랑하는 사람이기 때문에, 민주당의 당대표가 된다는 것은 굉장히 자랑스러운 일”이라며 “당연히 (당대표가 되는 것에 대한) 로망이 있다”고 했다. 김 총리는 “(당대표를) 해보고, 당을 어떤 방향으로 가도록 하는 데 역할을 했으면 좋겠다는 생각이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the argument that he should be nominated for the Seoul mayoral election rather than the party leadership election, Prime Minister Kim said, "The Seoul mayor is actually my long-held aspiration." Born in 1964, Prime Minister Kim said, "I ran in the Seoul mayoral election in my 30s (2002 local elections), I've wanted to be Seoul mayor for a long time, always thought about it, and in fact, I have many things (thought out about what I would do if I became mayor)." However, Prime Minister Kim added, "The moment I became Prime Minister, I thought 'Maybe this (becoming Seoul mayor) is not my path,' and from my perspective, I let go of my regretful feelings and settled (the Seoul mayor dream)." (당대표 선거가 아니라 서울시장 선거에 차출해야 한다는 주장에 대해서는 김 총리는 “서울시장은 사실은 저의 오랜 로망”이라고 했다. 1964년생인 김 총리는 “제가 30대(2002년 지방선거)에 서울시장 선거에 나왔는데, 오랫동안 (서울시장을) 해보고 싶었고, 늘 생각하고, 사실은 (서울시장이 되면 할 일을) 생각해 놓은 게 많다”고 했다. 다만 김 총리는 “총리가 된 순간 ‘이것(서울시장이 되는 것)이 내 길은 아닌가 보구나’ 하면서, 저로서는 아쉬운 마음을 덜어내면서 (서울시장 꿈을) 정리한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim argued, "The Seoul mayoral election is something you run for or get nominated for purely because you want to," and stated, "It hasn't even been a year (since I became Prime Minister). I should do well as Prime Minister and then see what role is given next, so right now I have no other thoughts (like running for Seoul mayor or party leader)." He also said, "Since the President is the appointing authority, I cannot speak as I please," and "I've been around in this field enough to know that the world doesn't work just because you desire something." (김 총리는 “서울시장 선거는 그야말로 자기가 원해서 나가거나 차출되는 것”이라며 “지금 (총리를 한 지) 1년도 안 됐다. 총리로서 잘하다가 그다음 어떤 역할을 부여받으면 그때 가서 봐야 하는 것이어서, 지금 저는 (서울시장 선거나 당대표 선거 출마 같은) 다른 생각은 없다”고 주장했다. “저는 대통령이 임명권자이기 때문에 제 마음대로 말할 수 없다” “세상이 자기가 욕심을 낸다고 되는 것이 아니다 하는 정도는 알 만큼 이 바닥을 굴렀다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim's Sampo TV interview took place on the afternoon of the 26th, after he returned in the early morning of that day following his meeting with Vice President Vance on the 23rd (local time). It was before US President Donald Trump made a surprise announcement that he would raise tariffs on South Korea back from 15% to 25%. In the interview, regarding his visit to the US, Prime Minister Kim said, "Meeting Vice President Vance and establishing a hotline was the biggest purpose." He added, "After the Korea-US tariff negotiations, there were some delays in actually implementing the agreed-upon contents like the Joint Factsheet, so we had to take care of those." (김 총리의 삼프로TV 인터뷰는 지난 23일(현지 시각) 밴스 부통령과의 회담 뒤 26일 새벽 귀국해 그날 오후에 이뤄졌다. 도널드 트럼프 미국 대통령이 한국에 대한 관세를 15%에서 25%로 도로 올리겠다고 기습 발표하기 전이었다. 인터뷰에서 김 총리는 방미에 관해 “밴스 부통령을 만나서 핫라인을 구축하는 게 제일 큰 목적이었다”고 했다. “한미 관세 협상 이후에 조인트 팩트시트(Joint Factsheet·합의 내용을 담은 공동 설명 자료) 등 타결된 내용을 실제로 이행하는 데 좀 지연된 것들이 있어서 그것들을 챙겨야 했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim continued, "In the tariff negotiations, the US would be interested in things like tariff rates, but for us, the three priorities that could be a plus are nuclear power (permission for spent nuclear fuel reprocessing), nuclear submarines (permission for construction), and shipbuilding (cooperation), so I talked about those (with Vice President Vance)." Regarding the delay in related practical cooperation, Prime Minister Kim relayed that Vice President Vance said, "There are bureaucratic obstacles not only in Korea but also in the US," and that he said, "It would be good to set schedules like one month, three months, six months and proceed with the plan." Prime Minister Kim said, "(Korea-US cooperation) might not be his own inherent area, but (Vice President Vance) responded quite proactively." (김 총리는 그러면서 “관세 협상에서 미국이야 관세율 등에 관심이 있겠지만, 우리에게 플러스가 될 수 있는 것은 원전(사용 후 핵연료 재처리 허용), 핵잠수함(건조 허용), 조선(협력) 등 세 개가 우선이기 때문에 그 이야기를 (밴스 부통령에게) 했다”고 말했다. 밴스 부통령은 이와 관련된 실무 협력이 지연되는 데 대해 “한국에도 그렇지만 미국에도 관료적인 막힘이 있다”며 “한 달, 세 달, 여섯 달 식으로 일정을 잡아서 계획을 진행해 갔으면 좋겠다라고 했다”고 김 총리는 전했다. 김 총리는 “(한·미 협력이) 본인의 고유 영역이 아닐 수도 있는데, (밴스 부통령이) 상당히 적극적으로 대응했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This means Prime Minister Kim brought up and discussed only the agenda items desired by Korea with Vice President Vance. Prime Minister Kim is known to have not mentioned during the meeting the situation where the processing of the Special Act on Investment in the United States, which must be passed by the National Assembly to fulfill Korea's promised investment to the US, is being delayed. (김 총리가 밴스 부통령에게 한국이 원하는 의제에 대해서만 말을 꺼내 이야기하고 왔다는 것이다. 김 총리는 한국이 미국에 약속한 투자를 이행하기 위해 국회에서 통과시켜야 하는 대미투자특별법안 처리가 지연되는 상황에 대해서는 회담에서 언급하지 않은 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/27/KVMLUT6T6ZFCBH3HLR2C3WTMTY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KU6WTMT72RNQ5PQVXFB6J7345Y.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:41:27 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>