<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:41:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok Discharged After Five Days... To Resume Party Duties While Receiving Outpatient Treatment (장동혁, 닷새만에 퇴원…당분간 통원 치료하며 당무)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/WDT6KZCLT5G7FHIFS43YTT7PSA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok Discharged After Five Days... To Resume Party Duties While Receiving Outpatient Treatment (장동혁, 닷새만에 퇴원…당분간 통원 치료하며 당무)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HFSWMMZXMY2WCNBWGVSTQYZVHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok, the leader of the People Power Party who was hospitalized due to aftereffects of a hunger strike, was discharged on the 26th. The People Power Party announced that day, "Leader Jang Dong-hyeok was discharged around noon today based on the medical staff's judgment." (단식 후유증으로 입원 치료 중이던 국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 26일 퇴원했다. 국민의힘은 이날 “장동혁 대표는 오늘 점심 무렵 의료진 판단에 따라 퇴원했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang had conducted an eight-day hunger strike from the 15th to the 22nd, urging the government and ruling party to accept a 'twin special probe' (into the Unification Church and Democratic Party nomination funds), before halting it at the request of former President Park Geun-hye. He subsequently received inpatient treatment at a hospital in Gwanak-gu, Seoul, for five days. (장 대표는 지난 15일부터 8일간인 지난 22일까지 정부·여당에 ‘쌍특검(통일교·민주당 공천 헌금)’ 수용 촉구 단식을 한 뒤, 박근혜 전 대통령의 요청에 단식 중단을 했다. 이후 닷새간 서울 관악구의 한 병원에서 입원 치료를 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party stated, "The medical staff presented the opinion that sufficient rest and recovery treatment were necessary, but the decision for discharge was made after comprehensively considering the rehabilitation and recovery environment," adding, "Even after discharge, necessary tests and treatments will continue on an outpatient basis." (국민의힘은 “의료진은 충분한 휴식과 회복 치료가 필요하다는 소견을 제시했으나, 재활 및 회복 환경 등을 종합적으로 고려해 퇴원을 결정했다”며 “퇴원 이후에도 필요한 검사와 치료는 통원 치료로 이어갈 예정”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party said, "Leader Jang expressed his will to quickly recover his health and return to party duties, considering the serious political situation," and noted, "The timing of his return to party duties has not been decided at present, and it is planned to be determined after comprehensively considering the leader's health recovery status going forward." (국민의힘은 “장 대표는 엄중한 정국 상황을 고려해 조속히 건강을 회복하고 당무에 복귀하겠다는 의지를 밝혔다”며 “당무 복귀 시점은 현재로서는 정해지지 않았으며, 향후 대표의 건강 회복 상태를 종합적으로 고려해 결정할 계획”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once Leader Jang returns to his party duties, he is expected to immediately make a decision on the issue of expelling former leader Han Dong-hoon. The People Power Party's Supreme Council meeting is scheduled for the 29th. It has not yet been decided whether Leader Jang will return to the Supreme Council meeting that day, but observations suggest a high possibility of his return. (장 대표가 당무에 복귀하면 당장 한동훈 전 대표 제명 문제에 대한 결정을 내릴 전망이다. 국민의힘 최고위원 회의는 오는 29일 열릴 예정이다. 장 대표가 이날 최고위원 회의에 복귀할지는 아직 정해지지 않았으나, 복귀 가능성이 높다는 관측이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, supporters of former leader Han and figures close to him held a rally in Yeouido on the 24th demanding the 'withdrawal of Han Dong-hoon's expulsion'. At the rally, slogans urging Leader Jang's resignation also emerged. Regarding this, Park Seong-hoon, the chief spokesperson, relayed that during the party meeting that day, Supreme Council members expressed "concerns about remarks that undermine party discipline." (앞서 한 전 대표 지지자들과 친한계 인사들은 지난 24일 여의도에서 ‘한동훈 제명 철회’ 집회를 열었다. 이 자리에선 장 대표의 사퇴를 촉구하는 구호 등도 나왔다. 이에 대해 국민의힘 최고위원들은 이날 당 회의에서 “당의 기강을 해치는 발언에 대한 우려의 목소리가 나왔다”고 박성훈 수석대변인은 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/WDT6KZCLT5G7FHIFS43YTT7PSA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HFSWMMZXMY2WCNBWGVSTQYZVHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 20:17:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "If you mess with Koreans, you will be ruined. Actively publicize this in Southeast Asia." (李대통령 “한국인 건드리면 패가망신, 동남아 현지에 적극 알려라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/26/B6UAKQTREJFHVDLIFTKZCK2V4I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "If you mess with Koreans, you will be ruined. Actively publicize this in Southeast Asia." (李대통령 “한국인 건드리면 패가망신, 동남아 현지에 적극 알려라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBSDMYLGHFSDKYRRG5TDOM3EMU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung made a surprise visit to the office of the 'Special Task Force for Transnational Crime Response' located in the Changseong-dong annex of the Government Complex Seoul on the 26th. He encouraged the personnel and instructed a high-intensity response to overseas-based scam crimes. (이재명 대통령은 26일 정부서울청사 창성동 별관에 있는 ‘초국가범죄 특별대응 TF’ 사무실을 깜짝 방문해 관계자들을 격려하고, 해외 거점 스캠(사기) 범죄에 대한 강도 높은 대응을 지시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a briefing on the prevention status that day, President Lee emphasized, "Actively publicize, including through cooperation with local media in Southeast Asia, the fact that if you mess with Koreans, you will be ruined." This is intended to send a strong warning message to sophisticated scam crime organizations, such as voice phishing and online gambling, that target Korean citizens from overseas bases. (이 대통령은 이날 방지 현황을 보고받는 자리에서 “한국인들을 건드리면 패가망신한다는 사실을 동남아 현지 언론과도 공조하는 등 적극적으로 알리라”고 강조했다. 이는 해외를 거점으로 한국 국민을 노리는 보이스피싱, 온라인 도박 등 지능형 스캠 범죄 조직에 대해 강력한 경고 메시지를 보내라는 취지다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee was briefed on the results showing a sharp decline in reports of various scam crimes, including voice phishing and no-show fraud, since the TF's launch. He stated, "Various scam crimes are destroying people's lives and becoming increasingly sophisticated," and ordered, "Continue to deal with them even more strictly." In particular, he mentioned the recent arrest of criminals in Cambodia and the largest-ever repatriation case to date, reiterating the importance of an organic cooperative system that breaks down inter-agency barriers. (이 대통령은 TF 출범 이후 보이스피싱과 노쇼(No-show) 사기 등 각종 스캠 범죄 신고 건수가 급감하고 있다는 성과를 보고받고, “각종 스캠 범죄가 국민의 삶을 파괴하고 갈수록 지능화되고 있다”며 “앞으로도 더욱 엄정하게 대처하라”고 주문했다. 특히 최근 캄보디아에서의 범죄자 검거와 역대 최대 규모의 국내 송환 사례를 언급하며, 부처 간 벽을 허문 유기적 공조 체제의 중요성을 거듭 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the visit, President Lee held a video conference with staff of the 'Korea Dedicated Team' active on-site in Cambodia. President Lee encouraged them, saying, "It must be tough being separated from your families and working in difficult conditions," and "All citizens are grateful for your hard work, so you can take pride in it." (이날 방문에서 이 대통령은 캄보디아 현지에서 활동 중인 ‘코리아전담반’ 직원들과 영상 회의를 진행했다. 이 대통령은 “가족들과 떨어져 열악한 환경 속에서도 고생이 많다”며 “여러분의 노고에 대해 국민 모두가 감사하게 생각하고 있으니 자부심을 가져도 좋다”고 격려했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When President Lee told the on-site staff, "It's all thanks to you all, I should buy each of you a chicken," one staff member on the video call responded, "Please buy us pizza!" President Lee instructed full budgetary and personnel support for the local Korea Dedicated Team, saying, "Tell me whatever you need." (이 대통령이 현지 직원들에게 “다 여러분 덕분이다, 통닭이라도 한 마리씩 사줘야겠다”고 말하자, 화상 통화 중이던 한 직원이 “피자 사주십시오!”라고 화답하기도 했다. 이 대통령은 “필요한 건 뭐든지 말하라”며 현지 코리아전담반에 대한 예산과 인력의 전폭적인 지원을 지시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 'Special Task Force for Transnational Crime Response' is a pan-governmental control tower established under President Lee's directive to respond to cross-border crimes such as drugs, scams, online gambling, and digital sex crimes. Currently, 10 related agencies, including the National Intelligence Service, the Financial Services Commission, the Supreme Prosecutors' Office, the National Tax Service, the Korea Customs Service, the National Police Agency, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, the Ministry of Justice, the Korea Communications Commission, and the Korea Internet &amp; Security Agency (KISA), are working together. Spokesperson Kang Yoo-jung explained in a written briefing, "This move reflects the President's will to eradicate transnational crimes by pooling all national capabilities." (‘초국가범죄 특별대응 TF’는 이 대통령의 지시에 따라 마약, 스캠, 온라인 도박, 디지털 성범죄 등 국경을 넘나드는 범죄에 대응하기 위해 만들어진 범정부 컨트롤타워다. 현재 국가정보원을 비롯해 금융위원회, 검찰청, 국세청, 관세청, 경찰청, 외교부, 법무부, 방송통신위원회, 한국인터넷진흥원(KISA) 등 10개 유관 기관이 합심해 활동하고 있다. 강유정 대변인은 서면 브리핑을 통해 “국가 역량을 총결집해 초국가범죄를 뿌리 뽑겠다는 대통령의 의지가 반영된 행보”라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/26/B6UAKQTREJFHVDLIFTKZCK2V4I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GBSDMYLGHFSDKYRRG5TDOM3EMU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 20:28:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Kuk Innovation Party "Party Merger Talks, Full Authority Delegated to Representative Cho Kuk" (조국혁신당 “합당 협의, 조국 대표에 전권 위임”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/OXVBNT7UD5ACVLKSGZJHY3YOL4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Cho Kuk Innovation Party "Party Merger Talks, Full Authority Delegated to Representative Cho Kuk" (조국혁신당 “합당 협의, 조국 대표에 전권 위임” )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZEIWTW6XARLVHHRHBXESQQQDF4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party decided at its party affairs committee meeting to delegate all authority regarding merger talks with the Democratic Party of Korea to Representative Cho Kuk. (조국혁신당은 26일 당무위원회의에서 더불어민주당 합당 협의의 모든 권한을 조국 대표에게 위임키로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this day, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party held its party affairs committee meeting at the Korea Federation of SMEs office in Yeongdeungpo-gu, Seoul, and clarified two positions regarding the merger. First, it stated that any decision on a merger would be judged based on the party's independent vision, values, and policies, and in accordance with the collective will of its members. Second, it stated that full authority concerning negotiations related to the Democratic Party's proposal would be delegated to the party representative. (이날 조국혁신당은 서울 영등포구 중소기업중앙회 사무실에서 당무위를 열고 합당과 관련한 두 가지 입장을 정리했다. 첫째는 조국혁신당의 독자적인 비전, 가치, 정책에 기초해 당원의 총의에 따라 합당 여부를 판단한다는 것이고, 둘째는 민주당의 제안과 관련된 협의 등의 전권은 당 대표에게 위임한다는 것이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is known that opinions such as "we should not be swayed too much by the Democratic Party's proposal" were exchanged during the party affairs committee meeting. Spokesperson Park Byeong-eon met with reporters immediately after the meeting and said, "The party affairs committee held serious and heated discussions for and against the Democratic Party's merger proposal," adding, "There was an opinion that our party should not be swayed too much because, from the Democratic Party's standpoint, this is a proposal that could be withdrawn under certain circumstances." (이날 당무위에서는 “민주당의 제안에 너무 휘둘려서는 안 된다”는 의견도 오간 것으로 알려졌다. 박병언 대변인은 회의 직후 기자들과 만나 “당무위는 민주당의 합당 제안에 대해 진지하고도 결렬한 찬반 논의를 했다”며 “민주당의 입장에선 어떤 경우에 철회될 수도 있는 제안이기 때문에 우리 당이 너무 많이 휘둘려서는 안 된다는 의견이 있었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Park also said, "Because our party's structure is small, we could be swayed. We should not be swayed too much by a single proposal that could be withdrawn. Therefore, everyone agreed with the view that we should respond in an orderly and calm manner, centered on the party representative." (또 박 대변인은 “저희당의 구성이 작기 때문에 휘둘릴 수 있다. 철회될 수 있는 하나의 제안 때문에 너무 휘둘려선 안 된다. 그래서 당 대표 중심으로 질서 있고 차분하게 대처해야 한다는 견해에 모두 일치했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party also stated its position that it would proceed with preparations for the upcoming June local elections independently for the time being. Spokesperson Park said, "Currently, the merger has not happened, and it seems we cannot prepare for the local elections on the premise that the merger proposed by the Democratic Party will be realized. The possibility of it falling through is also open," adding, "Our party intends to proceed with the local election preparations as originally planned." (일단 오는 6월 지방선거 준비는 독자적으로 하겠다는 입장도 밝혔다. 박 대변인은 “지금은 합당이 안 된 상태고 민주당이 지금 제안한 것도 합당이 이루어질 것이라는 걸 전제로 지방선거를 준비할 수는 없는 상황인 것 같다. 결렬될 가능성도 열려 있다”며 “우리 당은 원래 있었던 지방선거 준비는 예정대로 진행할 예정”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The party also expressed dissatisfaction with remarks by the Democratic Party that seemed to suggest an 'absorption merger'. Spokesperson Park said, "Criticism was also raised at the party affairs committee meeting that Democratic Party Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae's unilateral announcement of 'doing it within two months' was itself an inappropriate remark, considering that a merger is a relationship involving partners." (민주당이 ‘흡수 합당’을 시사하는 듯한 발언에 불만스러운 기색도 드러냈다. 박 대변인은 “또 조승래 민주당 사무총장이 ‘2개월 안에 하겠다’며 일방적으로 발표한 것 자체가 합당이라는 것이 파트너가 있는 관계라는 점에서 적절하지 않은 발언이라는 비판도 당무위에서 나왔다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/OXVBNT7UD5ACVLKSGZJHY3YOL4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZEIWTW6XARLVHHRHBXESQQQDF4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 20:27:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "I hope the half-price sanitary pads become properly established" (李 대통령 “반값 생리대, 제대로 자리 잡길”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/26/5KHIFFNGIBCFNJ7DEHKJDQFQ44/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "I hope the half-price sanitary pads become properly established" (李 대통령 “반값 생리대, 제대로 자리 잡길”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TDBQFIYYKNCZFDC7YFT6I75AHU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th, President Lee Jae-myung shared an article on his X (formerly Twitter) titled "Sanitary pad companies expand supply of 'half-price sanitary pads'... also launch mid-to-low-priced products" and wrote, "I hope they become properly established." (이재명 대통령이 26일 자신의 X(옛 트위터)에 “생리대 업체들, ‘반값 생리대’ 공급 확대... 중저가 제품 출시도”라는 제목의 기사를 공유하며 “제대로 자리 잡으면 좋겠는데요”라고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The article stated that major sanitary pad manufacturers have recently decided to move away from their high-price premium strategies and increase the supply of standard products with significantly reduced prices. Previously, at the end of last year, during a Fair Trade Commission work report, President Lee instructed, "I hear sanitary pads in our country are about 39% more expensive than overseas. Investigate whether it's due to an oligopolistic structure." (해당 기사는 최근 주요 생리대 제조사들이 고가 프리미엄 전략에서 벗어나 가격을 대폭 낮춘 표준형 제품 공급을 늘리기로 했다는 내용이다. 앞서 이 대통령은 작년 말 공정거래위원회 업무 보고에서 “우리나라 생리대가 해외보다 약 39% 비싸다고 한다. 독과점 구조 때문인지 조사해 보라”고 지시한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a Cabinet meeting on the 20th of this month, he ordered, "If the government provides subsidies, it just fattens corporate profits while overcharging consumers," and "Research a plan for the state to commission production and provide them free of charge to those in need." President Lee mentioned that the price of sanitary pads in Korea is nearly 40% higher on average compared to other countries due to distribution structures or the harms of oligopoly, and even suggested inducing real competition, including allowing duty-free imports from overseas if necessary. (이달 20일 국무회의에서는 “정부 지원금을 주면 바가지를 씌워 기업 배만 불리는 꼴”이라며 “아예 국가가 위탁 생산해 필요한 계층에 무상 공급하는 방안을 연구하라”고 주문했다. 이 대통령은 한국 생리대 가격이 유통 구조나 독과점 폐해로 인해 다른 국가 대비 평균 40% 가까이 비싸다며, 필요시 관세 없는 해외 수입 허용 등을 통한 실질 경쟁 유도까지 언급한 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/26/5KHIFFNGIBCFNJ7DEHKJDQFQ44/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/TDBQFIYYKNCZFDC7YFT6I75AHU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 22:44:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Government Launches 'Counter-Terrorism Task Force for Innovation'... "Reviewing Strengthening Protection for Politicians" (정부 ‘대테러 업무 혁신 TF’까지 출범… “정치인 신변 보호 강화 검토”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/26/WBUA72R4BZF5HMLW37IWIOQUBQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Government Launches 'Counter-Terrorism Task Force for Innovation'... "Reviewing Strengthening Protection for Politicians" (정부 ‘대테러 업무 혁신 TF’까지 출범… “정치인 신변 보호 강화 검토”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZCW377BXHBPFFKFKER2VBE7RKU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government launched a 'Public-Private Counter-Terrorism Task Force for Innovation' on the 26th, stating it will comprehensively re-examine the entire counter-terrorism system. Citing the Gadeokdo attack on President Lee Jae-myung, which was designated as 'Terrorism Incident No. 1' under the Anti-Terrorism Act on the 20th, the government said the TF will also review "the need to strengthen personal protection for politicians and other key figures during election periods and to raise the terrorism alert level." This follows the National Intelligence Service and the police each forming their own Gadeokdo TFs to re-investigate the Gadeokdo incident, and now the government is moving to change counter-terrorism policy itself at a pan-governmental level. (정부가 대테러 체계 전반을 재점검하겠다며 26일 ‘민·관 대테러 업무 혁신 TF(태스크포스)’를 출범했다. 정부는 지난 20일 테러방지법상 ‘1호 테러’로 지정한 이재명 대통령 가덕도 피습 사건을 거론하면서, TF에서 “선거 기간 정치인 등 주요 인사에 대한 신변 보호 강화 및 테러 경보 단계 상향 필요성”을 함께 검토하겠다고 했다. 국가정보원과 경찰이 각각 가덕도 TF를 꾸려 가덕도 사건 재조사에 나선 데 이어, 범정부 차원에서 대테러 정책 자체를 바꾸는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office for Government Policy Coordination held the TF launch ceremony at the Government Complex Seoul in the afternoon, presided over by Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, Yoon Chang-ryeol, and announced, "We have embarked on innovation across all national counter-terrorism tasks to respond to the rapidly changing terrorism environment." (국무조정실은 이날 오후 정부서울청사에서 윤창렬 국무조정실장 주재로 TF 출범식을 열고, “급변하는 테러 환경에 대응하기 위한 국가 대테러 업무 전반의 혁신에 착수했다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the Office for Government Policy Coordination, "The launch of this TF was prepared to mark the 10th anniversary of the enactment of the Anti-Terrorism Act and the launch of the National Counter-Terrorism Committee, to fundamentally review the counter-terrorism system to date and connect it to practical institutional improvements and task innovation." (국조실에 따르면, “이번 TF 출범은 테러방지법 제정 및 국가테러대책위원회 출범 10주년을 맞아, 그간의 대테러 체계를 원점에서 점검하고 실질적인 제도 개선과 업무 혁신으로 연결하기 위해 마련됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office for Government Policy Coordination particularly emphasized the Gadeokdo incident. It stated, "Especially as the Gadeokdo attack was designated as terrorism for the first time at the 22nd National Counter-Terrorism Committee on the 20th, we plan to also review the direction for developing national counter-terrorism activities to protect constitutional values and democratic order, including the need to strengthen personal protection for politicians and other key figures during election periods and to raise the terrorism alert level." (국조실은 특히 가덕도 사건을 강조했다. 국조실은 “특히 지난 20일 제22차 국가테러대책위원회에서 최초로 가덕도 피습 사건이 테러로 지정됨에 따라, 선거 기간 정치인 등 주요 인사에 대한 신변 보호 강화 및 테러 경보 단계 상향 필요성 등을 포함해, 헌법적 가치와 민주적 질서를 보호하기 위한 국가 대테러 활동의 발전 방향도 함께 검토할 예정”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The TF consists of about 30 members. Park Won-ho, head of the Counter-Terrorism Center at the Office for Government Policy Coordination, and civilian Lee Man-jong, president of the Korean Association of Terrorism Studies, serve as co-chairpersons. It includes 20 civilian expert members and working-level members from counter-terrorism related agencies such as the NIS, police, and military. It will initially operate for three months until March, but has decided to extend the operation period if necessary. (TF는 30여 명으로 구성됐다. 박원호 국무조정실 대테러센터장과 민간인인 이만종 한국테러학회장이 공동위원장을 맡았고, 민간 전문위원 20명과 국정원과 경찰, 군 등 대테러 관계 기관 실무위원이 참여한다. 또 1차로 오는 3월까지 3개월간 운영하되, 필요 시 운영 기간을 연장하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Office for Government Policy Coordination stated, "The TF has decided to fundamentally re-examine all national counter-terrorism tasks and derive actionable improvement tasks." Key review tasks include "redefining the definition of terrorism, systematizing terrorism identification procedures, measures to protect citizens' human rights when promoting counter-terrorism tasks, a comprehensive review of the counter-terrorism organizational system, and strengthening international counter-terrorism cooperation and coordination." (국조실은 “TF는 국가 대테러 업무 전반을 근본적으로 재검토하고, 실행 가능한 개선 과제를 도출하기로 했다”고 밝혔다. 주요 검토 과제는 “테러의 정의 재정립, 테러 규명 절차 체계화, 대테러 업무 추진 시 국민 인권 보호 방안, 테러 대응 조직 체계의 전면 재검토, 대테러 국제 협력 및 공조 강화” 등이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government stated that among the TF discussion results, tasks that can be implemented immediately will be swiftly promoted, and matters requiring legal or institutional improvements will be promoted step by step following deliberation and resolution by the National Counter-Terrorism Committee chaired by the Prime Minister. (정부는 TF 논의 결과 가운데 즉시 추진할 수 있는 과제는 신속히 추진하고, 법·제도 개선이 필요한 사항은 국무총리가 주재하는 국가테러대책위원회 심의·의결을 거쳐 단계적으로 추진하겠다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/26/WBUA72R4BZF5HMLW37IWIOQUBQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZCW377BXHBPFFKFKER2VBE7RKU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 23:22:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Force Aerial Photography Team, Gimhae Base Fire and Rescue Company, etc. Selected as '2025 Figures Who Brought Honor to the Air Force' (2025년 ‘공군을 빛낸 인물’에 항공촬영팀, 김해기지 소방구조중대 등 선정)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/26/67RBZCOJQ5EGHH3JAF2BQPFJAU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Air Force Aerial Photography Team, Gimhae Base Fire and Rescue Company, etc. Selected as '2025 Figures Who Brought Honor to the Air Force' (2025년 ‘공군을 빛낸 인물’에 항공촬영팀, 김해기지 소방구조중대 등 선정 )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3VV7KOLZF5JXXEZHHUF7GVIBDA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
The Air Force announced on the 26th that it presented awards for the '2025 Figures and Organizations Who Brought Honor to the Air Force' across four categories—Challenge, Dedication, Expertise, and Teamwork—at the Air Force Headquarters in Gyeryongdae. ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Air Force Aerial Photography Team, which contributed to the development of the K-defense industry through its own aerial photography, was selected in the Challenge category. The Air Force Aerial Photography Team was recognized for vividly conveying to the public the various aspects of the Air Force's aerial missions by riding in fighter jets like the F-15K, enduring dynamic maneuvers and G-forces. The Air Force stated, "Until about 20 years ago, aerial photography was the exclusive domain of foreign professional photographers," adding, "As a result of in-house training since 2005, unlike in the past, the public can now vividly see Air Force aircraft performing various air-to-air and air-to-ground missions with dynamic maneuvers at high altitudes." (공군은 26일 계룡대 공군본부에서 ’2025년 공군을 빛낸 인물·단체’를 도전·헌신·전문성·팀워크 등 4개 부문에 걸쳐 시상했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Dedication category, the Gimhae Base Fire and Rescue Company, which was the first to enter the scene during the Air Busan aircraft fire at Gimhae Airport in January last year, was selected. In the Expertise category, the Intelligent Information Systems Management Group, which developed 'Air Wars,' the military's first defense network-based generative artificial intelligence, and Senior Master Sergeant Park Nam-suk of the Education and Training Command, who developed a participatory gender awareness education program, received awards. (도전 부문에는 자체적인 공중 촬영으로 K-방산 발전에 기여한 공군 항공촬영팀이 선정됐다. 공군 항공촬영팀은 F-15K 등 전투기에 동승해 역동적인 기동과 중력가속도를 이겨내며 공군의 다양한 공중임무 모습을 국민들에게 생생하게 전달해왔다는 평가다. 공군 측은 “20여 년 전만 해도 항공 촬영은 외국 전문 사진작가들의 전유물이었다”며 “2005년부터 자체 양성한 결과 과거와 달리 고공에서 역동적으로 기동하며 다양한 공대공·공대지 임무를 수행하는 공군기 모습을 국민이 생생히 볼 수 있게 됐다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Teamwork category, the 82nd Aviation Maintenance Depot under the Logistics Command, which received the highest rating for two consecutive years in the military's Responsible Operating Organization evaluation, was chosen. The 82nd Aviation Maintenance Depot, responsible for the depot-level maintenance of major aircraft such as the F-15K, F-16, and C-130, was selected as the top organization for two consecutive years in the Ministry of National Defense's Responsible Operating Organization evaluation. Furthermore, it was selected as an 'Enterprise with Excellent Quality Competitiveness' for nine consecutive years, a first in the entire military. (헌신 부문에는 지난해 1월 김해공항 에어부산 항공기 화재 시 가장 먼저 진입한 김해기지 소방구조중대가 선정됐다. 전문성 부문에는 전군 최초 국방망 기반 생성형 인공지능인 ‘에어워즈’를 개발한 지능정보체계관리단과 참여형 성인지 교육 프로그램을 개발한 교육사령부 박남숙 상사가 수상했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Air Force Chief of Staff General Son Seok-rak said to the awardees, "I am proud of you, the awardees, who have elevated the status of the Air Force by practicing the valuable values of challenge, dedication, expertise, and teamwork in your respective positions," adding, "I ask for your continued best efforts to build a 'cutting-edge elite Air Force trusted by the people.'"
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (팀워크 부문에는 군 책임 운영기관 평가에서 2년 연속 최우수를 받은 군수사령부 제82항공정비창이 뽑혔다. F-15K, F-16, C-130 등 주요 항공기들의 창정비 임무를 맡고 있는제82항공정비창은 국방부 주관 군 책임운영기관 평가에서 2년 연속 최우수 기관으로 선정됐다. 또 전군 최초로 ‘품질경쟁력 우수기업’에 9년 연속 선정됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/26/67RBZCOJQ5EGHH3JAF2BQPFJAU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/3VV7KOLZF5JXXEZHHUF7GVIBDA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:25:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] People Power Party Ethics Committee Effectively Expels Kim Jong-hyeok... A Prelude to Pushing Out Han Dong-hoon? ([단독] 국힘 윤리위, 김종혁 사실상 제명... 한동훈 몰아내기 예고편인가)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/27QJUTMM7FGOLE5O7T4QU4NTNU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Exclusive] People Power Party Ethics Committee Effectively Expels Kim Jong-hyeok... A Prelude to Pushing Out Han Dong-hoon? ([단독] 국힘 윤리위, 김종혁 사실상 제명... 한동훈 몰아내기 예고편인가)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYDAZDGHE3TCYRZGUZGMZJXGE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
It has been confirmed that the People Power Party's Ethics Committee decided on the 26th to recommend expulsion from the party for former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyeok, a figure close to the Han Dong-hoon faction, on grounds including "words and actions contrary to the party's official stance." This is a stronger disciplinary measure than the "two-year suspension of party membership rights" previously recommended to the Ethics Committee by the party's internal audit committee. ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ethics Committee notified the former Supreme Council member Kim by phone today, stating that the decision to recommend his expulsion was made on the 23rd. The Ethics Committee judged that former Supreme Council member Kim's criticism of former President Yoon Suk-yeol and party leader Jang Dong-hyeok in various media appearances constituted a serious violation of the party constitution and regulations. (국민의힘 윤리위원회가 26일 ‘당론에 어긋나는 언행’ 등의 이유로 친한계(친 한동훈계) 인사인 김종혁 전 최고위원에 대해 탈당 권고 결정을 내린 것으로 확인됐다. 이는 앞서 국민의힘 당무감사위원회가 윤리위에 권고했던 ‘당원권 정지 2년’보다 더 강한 징계 수위다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, in a media interview, former Supreme Council member Kim had referred to leader Jang as "a party leader barely elected" and "someone who sold his soul for power and votes." The Ethics Committee also took issue with former Supreme Council member Kim's use of expressions like 'people spreading delusion viruses' towards election fraud theorists. (윤리위는 이날 김 전 최고위원에게 전화로 “지난 23일 탈당 권고 결정이 내려졌다”는 취지로 통보했다. 윤리위는 김 전 최고위원이 각종 매체에 나와 윤석열 전 대통령과 장동혁 대표 등을 비판한 것이 중대한 당헌·당규 위반이라고 판단했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In its decision document, the Ethics Committee stated, "The remarks by the respondent (former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyeok), which incite excessive hatred towards the leadership of his own party, fellow members, and the affiliated political party itself, exceed the threshold of ordinary legitimate criticism." (앞서 김 전 최고위원은 언론 인터뷰에서 장 대표에 대해 “간신히 당선된 당대표” “집권과 득표를 위해 영혼을 판 것”이라고 했었다. 윤리위는 또 김 전 최고위원이 부정선거론자들에게 ‘망상 바이러스를 퍼뜨리는 사람들’ 등의 표현을 쓴 것도 문제 삼았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The expulsion recommendation issued to former Supreme Council member Kim is a severe disciplinary action where, if he does not leave the party within 10 days of receiving the disciplinary decision notice, he is automatically expelled. Among the disciplinary actions the People Power Party can impose, it is the highest level of punishment, second only to 'expulsion.' Since the expulsion recommendation is finalized according to the Ethics Committee's decision without requiring a Supreme Council resolution, former Supreme Council member Kim is effectively expelled from the People Power Party as of today. (윤리위는 결정문에서 “피조사인(김종혁 전 최고위원)의 자신이 속한 당의 리더십과 동료 구성원, 그리고 소속 정당에 대한 과도한 혐오 자극의 발언들은 통상의 정당한 비판의 임계치를 넘어선다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to this, the Ethics Committee had decided to expel former party leader Han Dong-hoon, holding him responsible for the management of the party member bulletin board incident. However, expulsion requires a resolution from the People Power Party's Supreme Council. Inside and outside the party, there is talk that "the conclusion on whether to expel will likely be reached at the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th, which is mentioned as the timing for leader Jang Dong-hyeok's return." Leader Jang, who ended an 8-day hunger strike, was discharged from the hospital today and plans to focus on recovery treatment through outpatient care for the time being. (김 전 최고위원에게 내려진 탈당 권고는 징계 의결 통지를 받은 날로부터 10일 이내에 탈당하지 않으면 자동으로 제명되는 중징계다. 국민의힘에서 내릴 수 있는 징계 가운데서는 ‘제명’ 다음으로 최고 수위 징계다. 탈당 권고는 최고위원회 의결 없이 윤리위 결정대로 확정되기 때문에 김 전 최고위원은 이날로 사실상 국민의힘에서 제명된 셈이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Supreme Council member Kim told this newspaper in a phone call, "We will of course take political countermeasures, and we will also pursue legal actions, including applying for a provisional injunction to suspend the effect." A People Power Party official said, "The effective expulsion of former Supreme Council member Kim is interpreted as a prelude to removing even former leader Han Dong-hoon." (이보다 앞서 윤리위는 당원 게시판 사건의 관리 책임 등을 물어 한동훈 전 대표에게 제명 결정을 내린 바 있다. 다만 제명은 국민의힘 최고위원회의 의결이 필요하다. 국민의힘 안팎에선 “장동혁 대표의 복귀 시점으로 거론되는 29일 최고위원 회의에서 제명 여부가 결론 날 것”이란 이야기가 나온다. 8일간의 단식을 마친 장 대표는 이날 병원에서 퇴원, 당분간 통원하면서 회복 치료에 집중할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Supporters of former leader Han plan to hold a second outdoor rally opposing the 'illegal expulsion' in front of the National Assembly on the 31st. (김 전 최고위원은 본지 통화에서 “정치적 대응은 물론이고 효력 정지 가처분 신청 등 법적 조치에도 나설 것”이라고 말했다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “김 전 최고위원을 사실상 제명한 것은 한동훈 전 대표까지 제거하겠다는 예고편으로 풀이된다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/27QJUTMM7FGOLE5O7T4QU4NTNU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYDAZDGHE3TCYRZGUZGMZJXGE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 23:11:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Yong, 'Lee Jae-myung's Close Aide' Sentenced to 5 Years, Brazenly Holds Nationwide Book Concert Tour (징역 5년 ‘李 최측근’ 김용, 대놓고 전국 투어 북콘서트)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/6RTSJEJP4ZEHJDH7CNXQCNQ3DA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Yong, 'Lee Jae-myung's Close Aide' Sentenced to 5 Years, Brazenly Holds Nationwide Book Concert Tour (징역 5년 ‘李 최측근’ 김용, 대놓고 전국 투어 북콘서트)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UYLWMABGEFEM3BGRBHTZWCLF6Y.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt;
It was revealed on the 26th that Kim Yong, former vice president of the Democratic Research Institute and a close aide to President Lee Jae-myung, is causing controversy by holding publication commemorative events nationwide while on bail. It is reported that many key figures from the ruling party, including Democratic Party of Korea lawmakers, are attending these events. Former Vice President Kim is a key aide whom President Lee previously described as "someone like my own self." However, he was detained in court on charges including violating the Political Funds Act and was released on bail in August last year. At the time, the Supreme Court set conditions for his bail, including restrictions on his place of residence. Even within the Democratic Party, there are voices questioning "whether former Vice President Kim's nationwide tour events are appropriate." ()&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Vice President Kim is holding a publication commemorative event at the National Assembly Members' Office Building on the 12th of next month, ahead of the publication of his book 'The Usefulness of a President.' It is known that he received help from Supreme Council member Hwang Myeong-seon for matters like venue reservation. The first part of the event will feature a talk about former Vice President Kim's recent situation and his book, while the second part will proceed under the theme 'The President's Dream, Seoul's Dream' with Seoul mayoral candidates including lawmakers Park Ju-min, Park Hong-geun, Seo Young-kyo, Jeon Hyun-hee, and Seongdong District Mayor Jeong Won-o. An associate close to former Vice President Kim said, "Starting with Seoul, we plan to tour five regions including Daegu and the Honam region to hold events," adding, "We will finalize the schedule around the 27th and also invite lawmakers from each region." (이재명 대통령의 최측근 김용 전 민주연구원 부원장이 보석 중에 전국을 돌며 출판 기념회를 여는 것으로 26일 알려져 논란이 되고 있다. 행사에는 더불어민주당 국회의원 등 여권의 주요 인사가 다수 참석한다고 한다. 김 전 부원장은 이 대통령이 과거 “제 분신과 같은 사람”이라고 한 핵심 측근이다. 하지만 정치자금법 위반 혐의 등으로 법정 구속됐다가 작년 8월 보석으로 풀려난 상황이다. 당시 대법원은 거주지 제한 등을 보석 조건으로 걸었다. 민주당 내에서도 “김 전 부원장의 전국 투어 행사가 적절한지 의문”이란 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After being released on bail, former Vice President Kim actively appeared on YouTube and gave media interviews, emphasizing his wrongful accusation. Pro-Lee Jae-myung lawmakers within the Democratic Party have also publicly asserted former Vice President Kim's innocence and demanded the prosecution drop the charges. In the introduction for this book concert event, former Vice President Kim's side also explained, "(Former Vice President Kim is) a victim of the political prosecution's fabrication, the greatest victim. A comrade of ours who, undaunted by 550 days of detention and three arrests, protected Lee Jae-myung." (김 전 부원장은 자신의 책 ‘대통령의 쓸모’ 발간을 앞두고 다음 달 12일 국회 의원회관에서 출판 기념회를 연다. 장소 대관 등은 황명선 최고위원의 도움을 받은 것으로 알려졌다. 1부 행사는 김 전 부원장의 근황과 책에 대한 토크, 2부 행사는 ‘대통령의 꿈, 서울의 꿈’이라는 주제로 박주민·박홍근·서영교·전현희 의원, 정원오 성동구청장 등 서울시장 후보들과 함께 진행한다. 김 전 부원장 측근 관계자는 “서울을 첫 시작으로 대구, 호남 등 5개 지역을 순회하며 행사를 진행할 것”이라며 “27일쯤 일정을 확정해 각 지역 국회의원들도 초청할 예정”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling party, there is an interpretation that former Vice President Kim's public activities are in anticipation of an upcoming Supreme Court ruling. A Democratic Party lawmaker close to him said, "Former Vice President Kim believes there is a high possibility of being declared not guilty this time and is considering running for the National Assembly, among other things." However, there are also voices saying it is inappropriate. A senior lawmaker said, "This is something that places a great burden on the President." (김 전 부원장은 보석 후 유튜브 출연, 언론 인터뷰 등에 적극 응하며 자신의 억울함을 강조했었다. 민주당 친명 의원들도 공개적으로 김 전 부원장의 무죄를 주장하며 검찰에 공소 취소를 요구해왔다. 김 전 부원장 측은 이번 북콘서트 행사 소개 글에서도 “(김 전 부원장은) 정치 검찰의 조작, 최대의 피해자. 550일 구금, 3차례의 구속에도 굴하지 않고 이재명을 지켜낸 우리의 동지”라고 설명했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Vice President Kim was found guilty of receiving 600 million won in illegal election funds during President Lee's Democratic Party presidential primary period and receiving 70 million won in bribes in return for favors in the Daejang-dong project. He was sentenced to five years in prison and a forfeiture of 670 million won in the second trial, was detained in court, and was released on bail in August last year. (여권에선 김 전 부원장의 공개 행보를 두고 조만간 있을 대법원 선고를 염두에 둔 것이란 해석이 나왔다. 그와 가까운 민주당 의원은 “김 전 부원장은 이번에 무죄가 선고될 가능성이 크다고 보고 국회의원 출마 등을 고민 중”이라고 했다. 하지만 부적절하다는 얘기도 나온다. 한 중진 의원은 “대통령에게 큰 부담을 지우는 일”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/26/6RTSJEJP4ZEHJDH7CNXQCNQ3DA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UYLWMABGEFEM3BGRBHTZWCLF6Y.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 02:45:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Core of U.S. Security Lies in Deterring China at the First Island Chain" (“美 안보 핵심은 제1도련선에서 中 억제”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/TPEQDUIKOBCIDL6PIYRUFWPSJM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYGKNBYHAZTGMJXGA4GIOBVGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elbridge Colby, the U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Strategy and Force Development, who is visiting South Korea, stated on the 26th, "The U.S. defense strategy in the Indo-Pacific region focuses on 'deterrence by denial' at the first island chain." He added, "This includes modernizing and developing resilient and distributed forces across Japan, the Philippines, and the Korean Peninsula." This signifies the intent to block China from establishing itself as a regional hegemon along the first island chain stretching from the Japanese archipelago to Taiwan and the South China Sea. This not only implies a change in the role of U.S. forces in Korea but also increases the likelihood of South Korea's involvement. (방한 중인 엘브리지 콜비 미 전쟁부(국방부) 정책담당 차관이 26일 “인도·태평양 지역에서 미국의 국방 전략은 제1도련선에서 ‘거부에 의한 억지(deterrence by denial)’를 하는 데 중점을 두고 있다”며 “여기에는 일본, 필리핀, 한반도에 걸쳐 회복력 있고 분산된 전력을 현대화하고 발전시키는 것이 포함된다”고 말했다. 중국이 역내 패권국으로 자리매김하지 못하도록 일본 열도~대만~남중국해를 잇는 제1도련선에서 막겠다는 뜻으로 주한미군의 역할 변경은 물론, 한국이 연루될 가능성도 커졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In an invited speech at the Sejong Institute in Jongno-gu, Seoul, that afternoon, Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby said, "The Indo-Pacific is now the hub of global economic growth and a center for global manufacturing, including South Korea. The long-term security, prosperity, and freedom of the United States will be determined by what happens here." He stated the goal is to find "a balance of power that prevents any single nation from dominating this critical region." The speech seemed to be a warning, right on China's doorstep, that "China will not become Asia's hegemon." (콜비 차관은 이날 오후 서울 종로구 세종연구소에서 열린 초청 연설에서 “인도·태평양은 이제 글로벌 경제 성장의 중추이자 한국을 포함한 글로벌 제조업의 허브다. 미국의 장기적 안보, 번영, 자유는 여기서 벌어지는 일들에 의해 결정될 것”이라며 “이 핵심적 지역을 어떤 국가도 지배하지 못하도록 막는 힘의 균형”을 찾겠다고 했다. 중국의 코앞에서 ‘중국이 아시아의 패권국이 되는 일은 없을 것’이라고 경고하는 듯한 연설이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In his approximately 18-minute speech, Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby mentioned China seven times but did not mention North Korea even once. He said, "What we seek is a stable balance that works not only for the United States but also for our allies, a favorable balance of power where no nation can impose hegemony," and that "this stability is precisely the foundation for a 'decent peace'." He also stated that allies with military power, industrial capacity, and political resolve are necessary for this. (18분 안팎의 연설에서 콜비 차관은 중국을 7차례 언급했고 북한은 단 한 차례도 언급하지 않았다. 그는 “우리가 추구하는 바는 미국뿐 아니라 동맹국에도 효과가 있는 안정적인 균형, 어떤 국가도 패권을 강요할 수 없는 유리한 힘의 균형”이라며 “이러한 안정은 바로 ‘괜찮은 평화(decent peace)의 토대’”라고 했다. 이를 위해서는 군사력·산업 능력·정치적 결의를 갖춘 동맹국이 필요하다고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby, who led the drafting of the 'National Defense Strategy (NDS)' announced by the Trump administration on the 23rd (local time), reportedly conveyed this content in meetings with high-level South Korean government officials on the same day. He said, "President Donald Trump has long emphasized that alliances must be based on shared responsibility, not unilateral dependence," and added, "The Republic of Korea is the country that understands and practices this most deeply. That's why (after taking office) he chose the Republic of Korea as his first overseas visit destination." The South Korean government, through last year's summit meeting, agreed to increase defense spending to 3.5% of GDP and take the lead in conventional defense against North Korea. (지난 23일(현지 시각) 트럼프 행정부가 발표한 ‘국방전략(NDS)’ 작성을 주도한 콜비 차관은 이런 내용을 이날 우리 정부 고위 당국자들과의 면담에서도 전한 것으로 전해졌다. 그는 “도널드 트럼프 대통령은 오랫동안 동맹이 일방적인 의존이 아닌 공동 책임에 기반해야 한다고 강조해왔다”며 “대한민국이야말로 이를 가장 깊이 이해하고 실천하는 나라다. 그래서 (취임 후) 첫 해외 방문지로 대한민국을 선택했다”고 했다. 정부는 지난해 한미 정상회담을 통해 국방비를 GDP(국내총생산) 대비 3.5%로 증액하고, 대북 재래식 방위를 주도하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇"Alliance Cannot Be Built on Sentiment Alone... Many Countries Underinvest in Defense"&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“감정만으론 동맹 안돼… 많은 나라가 방어에 과소 투자"&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elbridge Colby, U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Strategy and Force Development, delivered a speech for about 18 minutes at the Sejong Institute's invited lecture on the 26th. An attendee said, "He mostly repeated the security situation assessment outlined in the U.S. National Defense Strategy (NDS), which likely indicates how deeply involved Colby, a policy expert, was in the NDS." (엘브리지 콜비 미 전쟁부 정책담당 차관은 26일 세종연구소 초청 연설에서 약 18분간 연설했다. 참석한 관계자는 “미 국방전략(NDS)에 명시된 안보 상황 평가 내용을 대부분 반복했는데, 그만큼 NDS에 정책통인 콜비가 깊게 관여했다는 뜻 아니겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Known as a China hawk, Colby said in his speech that day, "We are focused on building a military preparedness posture that ensures any (Chinese) aggression across the first island chain is impossible, escalation is unattractive, and war is an irrational choice." However, he also moderated his tone towards China, stating, "We (the U.S.) do not seek regime change in Beijing and do not aim to dominate China. We know and respect China's proud history." The latter part of his speech focused on emphasizing the role of alliances. (대중 강경파로 알려져 있는 콜비는 이날 연설에서 “제1도련선을 넘는 (중국의) 침략은 불가능하고, 확전은 매력적이지 않으며, 전쟁은 비합리적인 선택이 되도록 보장하는 군사 준비 태세를 구축하는 데 집중하고 있다”고 했다. 하지만 “우리(미국)는 베이징의 정권 교체를 추구하지 않으며 중국을 지배하려 하지 않는다. 중국의 자랑스러운 역사를 알고 존중한다”며 중국에 대한 발언 수위를 조절하는 모습도 보였다. 그러면서 연설 후반부는 동맹의 역할을 강조하는 데 초점을 뒀다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding South Korea's announcement to increase defense spending, Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby said, "President Lee Jae-myung's decision is very wise and realistic," and called South Korea "a model ally." He also stated, "Alliances must be based on shared risk, proportional contribution, and sustained mutual benefit." He said, "The ROK-U.S. alliance is based on shared history and values," but added, "Ultimately, an alliance cannot be built on sentiment alone." He continued, "For too long, security in key regions has been disproportionately dependent on the United States, and many allies have underinvested in their own defense. Such imbalances are neither fair nor sustainable." (콜비 차관은 한국의 국방비 증액 발표를 두고 “이재명 대통령의 결정은 매우 현명하고 현실적”이라며 “한국은 모범 동맹”이라고 했다. 또 “동맹은 위험 공유, 비례적 기여, 지속적인 상호 이익에 기반해야 한다”고 했다. 그는 “한미동맹은 공유된 역사와 가치에 기반을 두고 있다”면서도 “결국 동맹은 감정(sentiment)만으로는 구축될 수 없다”고 했다. 그러면서 “너무 오랫동안 주요 지역의 안보가 미국에 불균형적으로 의존해 왔고, 많은 동맹국들은 자체 방어에 과소 투자해 왔다. 그러한 불균형은 공정하지도 지속 가능하지도 않다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yang Uk, a research fellow at the Asan Institute for Policy Studies, said, "This essentially re-emphasized that the U.S. security package has changed to a 'subscription-based service,'" adding, "If in the past it was given away for free to everyone, from now on, the U.S. will also provide support based on the level of contribution from allies." (양욱 아산정책연구원 연구위원은 “사실상 미국의 안보 패키지가 ‘구독형 서비스’로 바뀌었다는 것을 재차 강조한 것”이라며 “과거에는 무상으로 모두 퍼줬다면 앞으로는 동맹이 기여한 정도를 따져서 미국도 지원을 해주겠다는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A military source said, "Visiting South Korea before Japan and emphasizing South Korea's contribution could also be seen as a move to pressure Japan." The Trump administration is known to have informally requested Japan to also meet the '3.5% of GDP' level, similar to NATO and South Korea. (군 소식통은 “일본에 앞서 한국을 찾아 한국의 기여를 강조한 것은 일본을 압박하려는 포석으로 볼 수도 있다”고 했다. 트럼프 행정부는 NATO 및 한국과 같은 수준인 ‘GDP 대비 3.5%’를 일본에도 비공식적으로 요구한 것으로 알려져 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/TPEQDUIKOBCIDL6PIYRUFWPSJM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYGKNBYHAZTGMJXGA4GIOBVGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>'Extended Deterrence' Disappears from U.S. Defense Strategy Document... Can We Trust the Nuclear Umbrella Promise? (美 국방전략서 사라진 ‘확장억제’… 핵우산 제공 믿을 수 있나)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/QUZZFBTYXBBVVJSXV7KA63IZII/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZXL7DJMUCFMFJNCASKUT22R56U.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new National Defense Strategy (NDS) unveiled by the Trump administration on the 23rd (local time) does not contain the term 'Extended Deterrence'—which signifies the provision of a 'nuclear umbrella' to allies—even once, sparking various interpretations. Following last month's National Security Strategy (NSS), the term 'extended deterrence' itself has also vanished from the NDS, alongside the goal of 'North Korean denuclearization,' raising concerns that it has become unclear to what extent the U.S. commitment to provide a nuclear umbrella in a regional contingency can be trusted. (트럼프 미국 행정부가 지난 23일(현지시각) 공개한 새 국방전략(NDS)에 동맹에 대한 ‘핵우산 제공’을 의미하는 ‘확장억제(Extended Deterrence)’라는 표현이 단 한 차례도 등장하지 않으면서 여러 해석이 나오고 있다. 지난달 트럼프 행정부가 발표한 국가안보전략(NSS)에 이어 NDS에서도 ‘북한 비핵화’ 목표와 함께 ‘확장억제’란 단어 자체가 사라지면서, 역내 유사시 미국의 핵우산 제공 의지를 어느 정도 신뢰할 수 있을지 불분명해졌다는 우려도 제기된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This NDS states that South Korea "has the capability to lead deterrence against North Korea," and that U.S. forces will provide only "critical but more limited support." In the NDS released by the Biden administration in 2022, terms like 'extended deterrence' and 'nuclear extended deterrence' appeared five times, and when combined with the Nuclear Posture Review and Missile Defense Review reports attached to the NDS, the phrase 'extended deterrence' was mentioned 23 times. (이번 NDS는 한국이 “대북 억제를 책임질 능력이 있다”며 미군은 “결정적(critical)이지만 더욱 제한적(more limited)인 지원”만 하겠다고 했다. 2022년 바이든 행정부가 발표한 NDS에는 ‘확장억제’ ‘핵 확장억제’ 등의 표현이 5차례 등장했고, NDS에 첨부된 핵 태세·미사일 방어 검토 보고서까지 합치면 ‘확장 억제’란 말이 23차례나 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding this change, former Vice Foreign Minister Shin Kak-soo said, "The expression 'critical support' for allies can be seen as meaning the provision of a nuclear umbrella," adding, "More importantly, we need to have substantive discussions with the U.S. on how to respond, especially as China's nuclear capabilities are also increasing." Another security expert stated, "If the U.S. were not to provide a nuclear umbrella, the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT) regime would collapse, so the absence of a mention of extended deterrence likely doesn't mean they won't provide it." It is suggested that expressions that could provoke North Korea and China may have been omitted, considering the planned visit of President Donald Trump to China in April and efforts to initiate dialogue with North Korean Chairman Kim Jong-un. (이런 변화에 대해 신각수 전 외교부 차관은 “동맹에 대한 ‘핵심적(critical) 지원’이란 표현이 핵우산 제공을 뜻한다고 볼 수 있다”며 “그보다는 중국 핵 전력도 증강되고 있는데 어떻게 대응할지 등에 대한 실질적 협의를 미국과 해야 한다”고 말했다. 또 다른 안보 전문가도 “미국이 핵우산 제공을 안 한다면 핵확산금지조약(NPT) 체제가 붕괴할 텐데 확장억제 언급이 없다고 안 한다는 뜻은 아닐 것”이라고 했다. 4월로 예정된 도널드 트럼프 대통령의 방중이나 김정은 북한 국무위원장과의 대화 추진 등을 염두에 두고 북·중을 자극하는 표현을 뺐을 수 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During his visit to South Korea last November, former U.S. Secretary of War Pete Hegseth reaffirmed in the joint statement of the South Korea-U.S. Security Consultative Meeting (SCM) that "the United States reaffirms its ironclad commitment to provide extended deterrence to the Republic of Korea, utilizing the full range of U.S. military capabilities, including nuclear." U.S. government officials are also known to maintain this position. (지난해 11월 방한한 피트 헤그세스 미 전쟁부 장관은 한미 안보협의회의(SCM) 공동성명에서 “핵을 포함한 미국의 모든 범주의 군사능력을 운용해 대한민국에 확장억제를 제공한다는 미국의 굳건한 공약을 재강조”했다. 미 정부 당국자들도 이런 입장을 유지하고 있는 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, a former high-ranking official from the foreign affairs and security sector said, "Trump's defense strategy ultimately aims to minimize costs for the U.S. and prioritize the defense of the U.S. homeland," adding, "We must seriously consider whether the U.S. would risk exposing its homeland to a North Korean nuclear attack to provide a nuclear umbrella to South Korea if a real crisis occurs on the Korean Peninsula." (하지만 외교·안보 부서의 한 고위 전직 당국자는 “트럼프의 국방전략이란 결국 미국이 들이는 비용은 최소화하고 미국 본토를 우선 방어하겠다는 것”이라며 “한반도에 진짜 무슨 일이 생겼을 때 미국이 본토가 북한의 핵 공격을 받을 위험을 무릅쓰면서까지 한국에 핵우산을 제공할지 심각하게 생각해 봐야 한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elbridge Colby, the U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Strategy and Force Development, who led the drafting of this NDS and visited South Korea on the 25th to explain its contents, previously stated regarding the Biden administration's 2024 extended deterrence commitment that there is "a risk of exposing multiple U.S. cities and Americans to North Korean nuclear attack in order to provide a nuclear umbrella to South Korea," and that "the United States cannot keep this promise." Indeed, the recently released NDS also includes expressions noting that North Korea's nuclear capabilities are "growing in scale and sophistication," posing a "clear and present danger to the U.S. homeland." (이번 NDS 작성을 주도하고 그 내용을 설명하기 위해 25일 방한한 엘브리지 콜비 미 전쟁부(국방부) 정책 담당 차관은 지난 2024년 바이든 행정부의 확장억제 공약에 대해 “한국에 핵우산을 제공하기 위해 미국 여러 도시와 미국인을 북핵 공격에 노출시키는 위험”이 있다며 “미국은 이 약속을 지킬 수 없다”고 말한 적 있다. 실제 이번에 발표된 NDS에도 북한 핵 능력의 “규모가 커지고 정교해 지고 있다”며 “미 본토에 대한 명확하고 현존하는 위협”이란 표현이 담겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former official also said, "If in the future, to counter China, U.S. Forces Korea are reorganized to focus on naval and air forces, reducing and withdrawing ground troops, and even wartime operational control is transferred to the South Korean military, how much would the U.S. military intervene on the Korean Peninsula in a contingency? We must also consider the possibility of only limited support, such as providing intelligence from a distance and conducting airstrikes with conventional medium- to long-range missiles." (이 전직 당국자는 “앞으로 중국 견제를 위해 주한미군을 해·공군 위주로 재편해 지상군을 감축·철수하고, 전시작전통제권까지 한국군한테 넘겨준다면 한반도 유사시 미군이 한반도에 얼마나 개입하겠나”라며 “원거리에서 정보를 제공하고 재래식 중장거리 미사일로 공습해 주는 정도의 제한적 지원만 할 가능성도 염두에 둬야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also a perspective that the U.S. not expressing its extended deterrence commitment itself is problematic. A military source said, "The very act of the U.S. publicly declaring its extended deterrence commitment through official documents has a deterrent effect. If it's only discussed in bilateral talks or private settings between South Korea and the U.S., the deterrent power is bound to weaken." There are also observations that the deployment of U.S. strategic assets to the Korean Peninsula, which gained momentum under the Biden administration, could decrease due to cost issues. (미국이 확장억제 공약을 표현하지 않는 것 자체가 문제란 시각도 있다. 군 소식통은 “미국이 공식 문서를 통해 확장억제 의지를 만천하에 천명하는 것 자체가 주는 억지 효과가 있는데, 한미 간 논의나 비공개 석상에서만 얘기한다면 억지력이 약화될 수밖에 없다”고 말했다. 비용 문제로 바이든 정부에서 본격화했던 미국 전략자산의 한반도 전개도 줄어들 수 있다는 지적이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also an aspect of diminished U.S. interest in North Korea itself. This NDS includes statements like "South Korea must continue to guard against the threat of North Korean invasion." However, the description of the North Korean threat consisted of only 118 English words, much shorter than the descriptions for China (347 words), Russia (369 words), and Iran (446 words). (북한에 대한 미국의 관심 자체가 줄어든 측면도 있다. 이번 NDS에는 “한국은 북한의 침공 위협을 계속 경계해야 한다”는 등의 표현이 담겼다. 하지만 북한의 위협에 대한 서술은 영단어 118개로 중국(347단어), 러시아(369단어), 이란(446단어)에 대한 서술보다 훨씬 짧았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Professor Park Won-gon of Ewha Womans University said, "We should recognize that not only extended deterrence, but also U.S. interest in or priority regarding North Korea has become lower than before," adding, "The Biden administration's Nuclear Posture Review included phrases like 'the end of the North Korean regime' in case of North Korean nuclear use, but such expressions are also highly likely to disappear in the future." (박원곤 이화여대 교수는 “확장억제는 물론 북한에 대한 미국의 관심이나 우선순위가 이전보다 낮아졌다고 봐야 한다”며 “바이든 행정부의 핵태세 검토보고서에는 ‘북핵 사용시 북한 정권 종말’ 같은 표현도 담겨있었는데 앞으로 이런 표현도 사라질 가능성이 크다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;☞Extended Deterrence&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;☞확장억제(Extended Deterrence)&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A U.S. commitment to provide a level of nuclear deterrence to its allies equivalent to that for the U.S. homeland. Expanding on the concept of a nuclear umbrella, it includes conventional weapons, missile defense, etc., declaring that if a potential enemy attacks an ally with nuclear weapons, the U.S. will retaliate with all its capabilities, thereby deterring the attack. The U.S. formally documented its provision of a nuclear umbrella to South Korea in 1978 and promised extended deterrence after North Korea's first nuclear test in 2006. (동맹국에 대해서도 미 본토와 같은 수준의 핵 억제력을 제공하겠다는 미국의 공약. 핵우산 개념에 재래식 무기, 미사일 방어 등을 더해 잠재적 적국이 동맹국을 핵 공격하면 미국이 모든 역량을 동원해 보복하겠다고 천명해 공격을 억지한다. 미국은 1978년 한국에 대한 핵우산 제공을 명문화했고, 2006년 북한의 1차 핵실험 이후 확장억제를 약속했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/QUZZFBTYXBBVVJSXV7KA63IZII/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/ZXL7DJMUCFMFJNCASKUT22R56U.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Colby Meets with Ahn Gyu-back, Cho Hyun, and Wi Sung-rak in Succession to Discuss Nuclear-powered Submarines and Wartime Operational Control (콜비, 안규백·조현·위성락 잇따라 만나 원잠·전작권 논의)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/RTPES63CYREQDN26AX4EDEPG2M/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYGKNBYHAZTGMJXGA4GIOBVGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elbridge Colby, the U.S. Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Policy, who is visiting South Korea for the first time since taking office, met with high-ranking South Korean government officials on the 26th to discuss follow-up measures from last year's South Korea-U.S. summit, including South Korea's pursuit of nuclear-powered submarines. It is reported that Colby also explained the 'National Defense Strategy' released by the Trump administration on the 23rd (local time) and requested cooperation. (취임 후 처음 한국을 방문한 엘브리지 콜비 미국 전쟁부(국방부) 정책 담당 차관은 26일 우리 정부 고위 당국자들을 잇따라 만나 한국의 원자력 추진 잠수함 도입 등 지난해 한미 정상회담 후속 조치를 논의했다. 콜비 차관은 트럼프 미 행정부가 지난 23일(현지 시각) 공개한 ‘국가방위전략’에 대해서도 설명하고, 협력을 당부한 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of National Defense announced that Defense Minister Ahn Gyu-back met with Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby at the Ministry of National Defense headquarters in Seoul this morning to discuss alliance issues such as the security situation on the Korean Peninsula, the transfer of wartime operational control (OPCON), and the strengthening of defense capabilities. In particular, regarding cooperation for South Korea's construction of nuclear-powered submarines, both sides reportedly "agreed that it would be an important milestone in enhancing the Republic of Korea (ROK)-led defense capabilities for the defense of the Korean Peninsula while further elevating the South Korea-U.S. military alliance" and decided to proceed with close cooperation. (국방부는 이날 오전 안규백 국방장관이 서울 국방부 청사에서 콜비 차관을 접견하고 한반도 안보 정세, 전시작전통제권 전환, 국방력 강화 등 동맹 현안을 논의했다고 밝혔다. 특히 양측은 한국의 원잠 건조를 위한 협력과 관련해 “한반도 방위에 있어 한국군 주도의 방위 역량을 강화하는 한편, 한미 군사동맹을 한층 격상시키는 중요한 이정표가 될 것이라는 데 공감”하고 긴밀한 공조를 해나가기로 했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby is also known to have explained the U.S.'s new National Defense Strategy (NDS), which emphasizes South Korea's leading role in the defense of the Korean Peninsula. The Ministry of National Defense relayed that Minister Ahn told Colby, "The transfer of OPCON is essential to realize ROK-led defense of the Korean Peninsula," and requested cooperation. Observations are emerging that the transfer of OPCON will gain momentum as both countries agree on the principle of 'South Korea's leading role in the conventional defense of the Korean Peninsula.' (콜비 차관은 한반도 방위에서 한국의 주도적 역할을 강조한 미국의 새 국방 전략(NDS)에 대해서도 설명한 것으로 알려졌다. 안 장관은 콜비 차관에게 “한국군 주도의 한반도 방위를 구현하기 위해 전작권 전환이 필수적”이라며 협력을 당부했다고 국방부는 전했다. 양국이 모두 ‘한국의 한반도 재래식 방위 주도’ 원칙에 공감하면서 전작권 전환에 속도가 붙을 것이라는 관측이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Cho Hyun also had a breakfast meeting with Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby at a hotel in Seoul this morning and requested cooperation on nuclear-powered submarines. Colby also met with Wi Sung-rak, the National Security Office Director at the Blue House. U.S. Forces Korea Commander General Robert B. Abrams was also present at Colby's meetings with South Korean officials today. (조현 외교부 장관도 이날 아침 서울의 한 호텔에서 콜비 차관과 조찬 회동을 하며 원잠 협력을 당부했다. 콜비 차관은 위성락 청와대 국가안보실장과도 만났다. 콜비 차관이 이날 한국 당국자들과 만나는 자리에는 제이비어 브런슨 주한미군사령관도 배석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On his X (formerly Twitter), Deputy Assistant Secretary Colby emphasized that South Korea is the first country he is visiting overseas since taking office in April last year, writing, "I look forward to discussing ways to modernize and advance our vital alliance." Colby is leading defense policies such as 'alliance modernization,' which focuses on expanding the strategic flexibility of U.S. forces in South Korea. In the afternoon, Colby gave an invited speech at the Sejong Institute in Jongno-gu and then visited Camp Humphreys in Pyeongtaek. (콜비 차관은 자신의 X(옛 트위터)에 지난해 4월 부임 후 첫 해외 순방국이 한국이란 점을 강조하면서 “우리의 중요한 동맹을 현대화하고 발전시키는 방안에 대해 논의할 수 있기를 기대한다”고 썼다. 콜비 차관은 주한 미군의 전략적 유연성 확대를 골자로 한 ‘동맹 현대화’ 등 국방 정책을 주도하고 있다. 콜비 차관은 오후에는 종로구 세종연구소에서 초청 연설을 한 뒤 평택에 있는 캠프 험프리스를 방문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/27/RTPES63CYREQDN26AX4EDEPG2M/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GIYGKNBYHAZTGMJXGA4GIOBVGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Internal Voices in the Cho Kuk Innovation Party Say "Local Election Candidates Must Be Guaranteed"... A Bill Presented Before Merger Negotiations (조국혁신당 내부 “지방선거 후보 보장해야”… 합당 협상前 청구서)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/JLEW3OKGCFA6LBVFTIJ55GSOBU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MNRTOYRRGRQTQNDDHE2TMOJSHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party are engaging in a war of nerves, making conflicting claims regarding a potential merger. While the Democratic Party has in mind an 'absorption merger,' the Cho Kuk Innovation Party maintains that "an absorption merger is out of the question." This is interpreted as essentially demanding a certain share of influence ahead of the June 3 local elections. Consequently, some potential candidates from regions like the Honam area within the Democratic Party are strongly opposing, stating, "We absolutely cannot give away candidacies to the Cho Kuk Party." (더불어민주당과 조국혁신당이 합당을 둘러싸고 서로 다른 주장을 하며 신경전을 벌이고 있다. 민주당은 ‘흡수 합당’을 염두에 두고 있지만, 조국혁신당은 “흡수 합당은 있을 수 없는 일”이라는 입장이다. 사실상 6.3 지방선거를 앞두고 어느 정도 지분을 요구하는 것이란 해석이 나온다. 이 때문에 민주당 내 호남 등 일부 지역 출마자들은 “조국당에 후보 나눠주기는 절대 안 된다”며 강하게 반발하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk Innovation Party floor leader Seo Wang-jin expressed at a Supreme Council meeting on the 26th, "I strongly regret that misunderstandings are arising even before full-fledged integration discussions with the Democratic Party begin," adding, "Integration should not be a mere expansion of size but a value-based alliance that presents new hope." This statement of regret came in response to remarks by Democratic Party Secretary-General Cho Seung-rae at a press briefing the previous day, where he said, "The DNA of the Innovation Party will also blend well within the large organism that is the Democratic Party," which was interpreted as suggesting an 'absorption merger.' Secretary-General Cho also implied that even if the parties merge, the Democratic Party's name would be retained. The Cho Kuk Innovation Party's stance on this is also that it is "a matter to be discussed at the official table." (조국혁신당 서왕진 원내대표는 26일 최고위원회의에서 “민주당과 본격적인 통합 논의가 시작되기도 전에 오해가 생기는 것에 강력한 유감을 표한다”면서 “통합은 뻔한 몸집 불리기가 아니라 새로운 희망을 제시하는 가치 연합이 돼야 한다”고 밝혔다. 전날 민주당 조승래 사무총장이 기자간담회에서 “민주당이라는 큰 생명체 내에서 혁신당의 DNA도 잘 섞이게 될 것”이라며 ‘흡수 통합’으로 해석되는 발언을 하자 이에 유감을 표명한 것이다. 조 사무총장은 합당을 하더라도 민주당 당명을 그대로 사용할 것처럼 말했다. 조국혁신당은 이에 대해서도 “공식 테이블에서 논의할 문제”라는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Currently, some Democratic Party lawmakers are protesting against party leader Lee Jae-myung's surprise merger proposal on the 22nd, calling it a "unilateral announcement that ignored both timing and procedure." However, underlying their discontent is dissatisfaction with the idea of a 'party-to-party merger' with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, which has an approval rating around 5%. They argue that a 162-seat mega ruling party should not engage in a merger involving an exchange of shares with a minor party consisting of 12 proportional representation lawmakers. A key member of the Democratic Party leadership said, "I think Leader Lee also initially thought of an absorption merger and believed a merger could be easily achieved," but added, "However, the current position is that we cannot accept all the demands coming from the Cho Kuk Innovation Party." (현재 민주당 일부 의원들은 정청래 대표의 지난 22일 기습 합당 제안에 대해 “시기도, 절차도 무시한 일방 발표”라며 반발하고 있다. 하지만 이들 속내에는 5% 안팎의 지지율을 받고 있는 조국혁신당과 ‘당 대 당 통합’에 대한 불만이 녹아있다. 162석 거대 여당이 비례대표 국회의원 12명으로 구성된 소수 정당과 지분을 주고 받는 합당을 해선 안된다는 얘기다. 민주당 지도부 핵심 의원은 “정 대표도 처음엔 흡수 통합을 생각하고 쉽게 합당할 수 있을 것으로 생각한 것 같다”며 “하지만 지금은 조국혁신당에서 흘러나오는 요구를 다 수용할 수 없다는 입장”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party leadership faces a situation where it cannot ignore the backlash from regional candidates ahead of the local elections. Dissatisfaction is particularly growing within the Honam region. Honam is both a stronghold for the Democratic Party and a support base for the Cho Kuk Innovation Party. Democratic Party North Jeolla Province Committee Chairman, lawmaker Yoon Jun-byeong, recently targeting Cho Kuk Innovation Party candidates, said, "Conflict arising from the unreasonable demands for merger shares by disqualified individuals is already visible." A Democratic Party lawmaker whose constituency is in Honam said, "Rumors are circulating that the party leadership will concede some regional candidates to the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, causing unease," adding, "This is not just the case in Honam but in other regions as well." (민주당 지도부는 지방선거를 앞두고 지역 출마자들의 반발도 무시할 수 없는 상황이다. 특히 호남 내 불만이 커지고 있다. 호남은 민주당 텃밭이면서, 조국혁신당의 지지기반이다. 민주당 전북도당위원장인 윤준병 의원은 최근 조국혁신당 후보들을 겨냥해 “결격자들의 억지성 합당 지분권 요구로 인한 갈등이 벌써 눈에 보인다”고 했다. 호남이 지역구인 민주당 의원은 “당 지도부가 조국혁신당에 일부 지역 후보를 양보할 것이란 소문이 돌고 있어 들썩이고 있다”며 “이건 비단 호남뿐 아니라 타 지역도 같은 상황”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Cho Kuk Innovation Party also plans not to proceed with a Democratic Party-led merger, stating, "An absorption merger is absolutely unacceptable." A party official said, "There will be no merger in the form of Chairman Cho Kuk and the 12 lawmakers simply joining the Democratic Party." It is reported that opinions within the Cho Kuk Innovation Party regarding merger negotiations are also divided. Amid this, the party has decided to first delegate full authority to Chairman Cho. A Cho Kuk Innovation Party official stated, "Some Cho Kuk Innovation Party lawmakers have already officially announced their candidacy for the local elections, and Chairman Cho's likelihood of running in the National Assembly by-elections held concurrently with the local elections has increased," adding, "Since everyone must run under the Democratic Party banner, clear guarantees regarding candidate confirmation, etc., must follow." (하지만 조국혁신당도 “흡수 합당은 절대 안 된다”며 민주당 주도의 합당은 하지 않겠다는 계획이다. 조국혁신당 관계자는 “민주당에 조국 대표와 의원 12명이 입당하는 형식의 합당은 없을 것”이라고 했다. 조국혁신당 내부에서도 합당 협상에 대한 의견이 갈리고 있다고 한다. 이런 가운데 당은 일단 전권을 조 대표에게 일임하기로 결정했다. 조국혁신당 관계자는 “조국혁신당 일부 의원은 지방선거 출마를 이미 공식화했고 조 대표도 지방선거와 함께 치러지는 국회의원 재·보궐선거 출마 가능성이 커졌다”며 “모두 민주당 간판으로 선거를 치러야 하기 때문에 후보 확정 등 확실한 보장이 따라야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the Democratic Party and the Cho Kuk Innovation Party hold their respective positions, forecasts are emerging within the ruling bloc that the merger process may not proceed as smoothly as expected. (이처럼 민주당과 조국혁신당이 각자 다른 주장을 하면서 여권 내에서도 예상보다 합당 과정이 매끄럽지 않을 수 있다는 전망이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, open criticism of Leader Lee within the Democratic Party continues. Supreme Council member Lee Eon-joo criticized on the radio, "Leader Lee is turning the party into his personal faction and unilaterally pushing for the merger." The claim is that Leader Lee aims to secure control of the party through the merger and then seek re-election in the August party leadership election. Pro-Myung (referring to former President Moon Jae-in) faction lawmaker Lee Geon-tae also said, "To win in fiercely contested areas like Seoul and the metropolitan area, we must win over the centrist voters, and it's hard to agree that merging with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party, which is positioned further 'to the left,' is advantageous." Democratic Party lawmaker Jang Cheol-min also said, "We should be discussing how to form electoral alliances not just with the Cho Kuk Innovation Party but among progressive parties overall, but in the merger process, it suddenly became 'puffed up' before we could even wash the rice, steam it, and cook the meal." (이런 가운데 민주당에선 여전히 정 대표에 대한 공개 비판도 계속되고 있다. 이언주 최고위원은 라디오에서 “정 대표가 당을 사당화해 합당을 일방적으로 추진하고 있다”고 비판했다. 정 대표가 합당을 통해 당을 장악한 뒤 오는 8월 당대표 선거에서 연임할 목적이라는 주장이다. 친명계인 이건태 의원도 “서울·수도권 등 격전 지역에서 승리하려면 중도층 싸움에서 이겨야 하는데, 보다 ‘왼쪽’에 있는 조국혁신당과의 합당 시 유리한지에 대해 동의하기 어렵다”고 했다. 장철민 민주당 의원도 “조국혁신당뿐 아니라 전체적인 진보 정당 사이에서 선거 연대를 어떻게 가져갈지 토론해야 하는데, 합당 과정에서 쌀을 씻고 뜸을 들여 밥을 하기 전에 갑자기 ‘뻥튀기’가 돼 버렸다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/JLEW3OKGCFA6LBVFTIJ55GSOBU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MNRTOYRRGRQTQNDDHE2TMOJSHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister's Office says "We asked to be left out of the poll," Kim Eo-jun says "That's for me to decide" (총리실 “여론조사서 빼달라니까”  김어준 “그건 내가 결정”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/opinion-poll/2026/01/27/LS4Z6RN4GRC35NU5LTV743SYCI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6Y5U3FGSDZBZFGFBFLZQT4LLNE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pro-government YouTuber Kim Eo-jun effectively rejected a request from Prime Minister Kim Min-seok's office on the 26th to exclude the Prime Minister from a Seoul mayoral election poll, saying, "I'll handle it as I see fit. That's for this side to decide." A person from the Prime Minister's side said, "We made the request politely, so this reaction is disconcerting." (친여 성향 유튜버 김어준씨가 26일 김민석 국무총리를 서울시장 선거 여론조사에 넣지 말아 달라는 총리실 요구를 “알아서 하겠다. 이쪽이 결정할 일”이라며 사실상 거부했다. 김 총리 측 관계자는 “정중하게 요구한 것인데 이런 반응은 당황스럽다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The polling firm 'Polling Flower,' led by Kim Eo-jun, included Prime Minister Kim as one of the Democratic Party candidates in a hypothetical two-way race survey for the June 3 local elections Seoul mayoral candidates conducted from the 19th to the 21st. Prime Minister Kim led the People Power Party's Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon and lawmaker Na Kyung-won, and the gap was larger than with other Democratic Party candidates. Kim Eo-jun disclosed these poll results on the 23rd. (김씨가 주도하는 여론조사 업체 ‘여론조사꽃’은 지난 19~21일 6·3 지방선거 서울시장 후보 가상 양자 대결 조사에 김 총리를 민주당 후보 중 한 명으로 넣었다. 김 총리는 국민의힘 오세훈 서울시장과 나경원 의원에 앞섰고, 격차도 다른 민주당 후보들보다 컸다. 김씨는 이 같은 조사 결과를 지난 23일 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Prime Minister's Office issued a statement the same day, saying, "We express deep regret regarding some polls that continue to include him despite requests to be excluded." The Prime Minister's Office stated, "Continuously including him in polls against his will is highly inappropriate and crosses the line of polling ethics." (하지만 총리실은 같은 날 입장문을 배포해 “여론조사에 포함시키지 말아달라는 요청에도 불구하고 계속 포함시키는 일부 조사에 대해 매우 심각한 유감을 표시한다”고 했다. 총리실은 “본인의 의사에 반해 계속 조사에 포함시키는 것은 매우 부적절하며 조사 기관의 금도를 넘은 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim was visiting the United States at the time but reportedly instructed the statement to be issued. The Prime Minister has stated multiple times that he has no intention of running in the Seoul mayoral election. Within the ruling party, it is widely believed that Prime Minister Kim is more likely to run in the upcoming August Democratic Party leadership election rather than the Seoul mayoral election. Consequently, polls including Prime Minister Kim as a Seoul mayoral candidate have become rare, but Kim Eo-jun's 'Polling Flower' continued its survey. Regarding this, voices inside and outside the Democratic Party have suggested, "Isn't Kim Eo-jun trying to push Prime Minister Kim into the Seoul mayoral race to secure Representative Chung Cheong-rae's re-election as party leader?" (김 총리는 당시 미국 방문 중이었으나 입장문을 내라고 지시했다고 한다. 김 총리는 서울시장 선거 출마 의사가 없다는 뜻을 여러 번 밝혔다. 여권에서는 김 총리가 서울시장 선거가 아니라 오는 8월 민주당 당대표 선거에 나올 가능성이 크다고 보고 있다. 이에 따라 김 총리를 서울시장 후보로 넣은 여론조사는 찾아보기 어려워졌지만, 김씨의 ‘여론조사꽃’은 조사를 계속했다. 이를 두고 민주당 안팎에선 “김씨가 김 총리를 서울시장 선거에 출마시켜 정청래 대표를 당대표로 연임시키려는 것 아니냐”는 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Kim Eo-jun said on YouTube on the 26th, "There's talk that (I'm) doing this to get Chung Cheong-rae re-elected and to block Kim Min-seok from running for party leader," adding, "Does including the Prime Minister's name in a poll block his run for party leader?" He argued, "Everyone knows the Prime Minister isn't running," but also claimed, "The Prime Minister leading in a hypothetical matchup is called presence. During elections, that kind of presence gives (Democratic Party supporters) a sense of relief." (이에 대해 김어준씨는 26일 유튜브에서 “(내가) 정청래를 연임시키려고, 김민석 당대표 출마를 막으려고 그런다는 이야기가 있다”며 “여론조사에 김 총리 이름을 넣으면 당대표 출마가 막아지나”라고 했다. 그는 “김 총리가 출마하지 않는다는 것은 다 안다”면서도 “김 총리가 가상 대결 1위 하는 것을 존재감이라고 한다. 선거 때는 그런 존재감이 (민주당 지지자들에게) 안도감을 준다”고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is an atmosphere of displeasure around Prime Minister Kim. An official from the Prime Minister's Office said, "We don't necessarily see it as Kim pressuring the Prime Minister to run for Seoul mayor, but his claim that he's 'utilizing the Prime Minister's presence' is also hard to accept." However, it is understood that the Prime Minister's Office will not take any further action. (김 총리 주변에선 불쾌해하는 분위기다. 총리실 관계자는 “김씨가 총리의 서울시장 출마를 압박한다고까지 보지는 않지만, ‘총리의 존재감을 활용한다’는 김씨 주장도 납득하기 어렵다”고 했다. 다만 총리실은 추가 대응은 하지 않을 것으로 알려졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/opinion-poll/2026/01/27/LS4Z6RN4GRC35NU5LTV743SYCI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/6Y5U3FGSDZBZFGFBFLZQT4LLNE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Hae-chan's Funeral to be Held as a Public Funeral Until the 31st... Prime Minister Kim Serves as Standing Funeral Committee Chairman (이해찬 장례, 31일까지 사회장으로…  金총리가 상임 장례위원장)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/FFK3KDAFKZCQ3JDV4PXIWHM5DA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HWYXVK6NWZH3LG5RZR553COFMM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The funeral for former Prime Minister Lee Hae-chan will be held over five days from the 27th to the 31st as a public funeral, concurrently serving as the funeral for the head of the National Unification Advisory Council. A public funeral is a funeral format organized by a self-formed funeral committee comprising representatives from various sectors of society, held when a figure who has made contributions to the state and society passes away. The former Prime Minister passed away on the 25th after his health rapidly deteriorated during a business trip to Vietnam in his capacity as the Senior Vice Chairman of the National Unification Advisory Council. (이해찬 전 국무총리의 장례가 27일부터 31일까지 닷새 동안 민주평화통일자문회의 기관장(葬) 겸 사회장으로 치러진다. 사회장은 국가와 사회에 공적을 남긴 인물이 사망했을 때, 사회 각계 대표가 자체적으로 장의위원회를 구성해 치르는 장례 방식이다. 이 전 총리는 민주평통 수석부의장 자격으로 베트남 출장 중 건강이 급속도로 나빠져 25일 별세했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the National Unification Advisory Council, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok will serve as the standing funeral committee chairman. The standing co-chairmen for civil society and political parties will be Baek Nak-cheong, Emeritus Professor at Seoul National University, and Jeong Cheong-rae, the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea. Cho Jung-sik, the President's Special Advisor for Political Affairs and a Democratic Party lawmaker, will serve as the standing executive chairman. Jo Seung-rae, the Democratic Party's Secretary-General, Lee Sang-min, the Minister of the Interior and Safety, and Bang Yong-seung, the Secretary-General of the National Unification Advisory Council, are scheduled to serve as co-executive chairmen. (민주평통에 따르면 상임 장례위원장은 김민석 국무총리가 맡고, 시민사회 및 정당 상임공동 장례위원장은 백낙청 서울대 명예교수, 정청래 더불어민주당 대표가 맡는다. 민주당 의원인 조정식 대통령 정무특보가 상임 집행위원장을, 조승래 민주당 사무총장, 윤호중 행정안전부 장관, 방용승 민주평통 사무처장이 공동집행위원장을 맡을 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party has designated this week, the period of the deceased's funeral, as a 'period of mourning and remembrance' and will set up memorial altars by city and provincial party chapters. Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae stated, "A symbol of South Korea's democratization, a great star of the Democratic Party, has fallen." The Democratic Party has expressed its position to refrain from political disputes during the mourning period. (민주당은 고인의 장례 기간인 이번 주를 ‘애도·추모 기간’으로 지정하고 시도당별로 추모 빈소를 설치한다. 정청래 당대표는 “대한민국 민주화의 상징, 민주당의 큰 별이 졌다”고 했다. 민주당은 애도 기간 중 정쟁을 자제하겠다는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok also minimized his schedule on this day, including canceling a national policy briefing. He posted on Facebook, "(The deceased) was an unwavering symbol and pride of the entire democratic camp that produced four presidents." (김민석 국무총리도 이날 국정설명회를 취소하는 등 일정을 최소화했다. 그는 페이스북에 “(고인은) 네 분의 대통령을 배출한 민주 세력 전체의 흔들리지 않는 상징이고 자존심이었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deceased's body, which was temporarily placed at a local hospital in Vietnam, is scheduled to arrive at Incheon Airport via a flight in the early morning of the 27th and then be moved to the funeral hall at Seoul National University Hospital in Jongno-gu, Seoul, which will serve as the mourning site. Both Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae and Prime Minister Kim Min-seok plan to personally go to Incheon Airport to receive the remains. A political circle insider commented, "It appears that key figures from the ruling party are trying to take the initiative in leading the 'mourning political atmosphere'." (베트남 현지 병원에 임시로 안치된 고인의 시신은 27일 새벽 항공편으로 인천공항에 들어온 뒤, 빈소인 서울 종로구 서울대병원 장례식장으로 옮겨질 예정이다. 정청래 대표와 김민석 총리는 모두 인천공항에 직접 나가 유해를 맞이한다는 계획이다. 정치권 관계자는 “여권의 중심 인물들이 ‘추모 정국’의 주도권을 가져가려는 모습”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/FFK3KDAFKZCQ3JDV4PXIWHM5DA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HWYXVK6NWZH3LG5RZR553COFMM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Discharged from Hospital, Kim Jong-hyuk Effectively Expelled... Is the End Goal to Drive Out Han Dong-hoon? (張 퇴원날, 김종혁 사실상 제명… 결국 한동훈 몰아내나)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/OCQRYNUVPRFCLNZBJTDPB4SZ6U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BAJRSMOD5BKNTCGGKEBXEFENOY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party (PPP) leader Jang Dong-hyuk was discharged from the hospital on the 26th. This came four days after he was transferred to the hospital on the 22nd, following an eight-day hunger strike demanding a special counsel investigation into alleged bribery involving the Unification Church and the Democratic Party's nomination process. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 26일 병원에서 퇴원했다. 통일교·민주당 공천 뇌물 특검 도입을 요구하며 8일간 단식하다 지난 22일 병원으로 이송된 지 나흘 만이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the same day, the PPP's Ethics Committee (Chairman Yoon Min-woo, a professor at Gachon University) decided to "recommend withdrawal from the party" for former Supreme Council member Kim Jong-hyuk, a member of the pro-Han (pro-Han Dong-hoon) faction, who was referred to the committee for "words and actions contrary to the party's official stance," among other reasons. The Ethics Committee had previously decided on the "expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon" on the 14th, pending approval by the Supreme Council. (이날 국민의힘 윤리위원회(위원장 윤민우 가천대 교수)는 ‘당론에 어긋나는 언행(言行)’ 등으로 회부된 친한(친한동훈)계 김종혁 전 최고위원에 대해 ‘탈당 권유’를 결정했다. 윤리위는 앞서 지난 14일 ‘한동훈 전 대표 제명’을 결정했고 최고위원회 의결을 남겨 놓고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disciplinary reasons stated by the Ethics Committee include that former Supreme Council member Kim "denounced and defamed Leader Jang and others using hateful and provocative expressions" in media interviews and YouTube broadcasts. In an interview with a monthly magazine last September, former Supreme Council member Kim said, "(Due to claims of election fraud, etc.) Because he joined hands with extreme people spreading a delusional virus, a decline in approval ratings was inevitable." He also said, "It means Leader Jang made a dangerous deal (with conservative YouTubers) to the extent that it was no different from selling his soul for gaining power and votes." The Ethics Committee described these remarks as "hateful, provocative attacks" and "psychological warfare information that exceeds the limits of legitimate criticism or freedom of expression." (윤리위가 밝힌 징계 사유는 김 전 최고위원이 언론 인터뷰와 유튜브 방송에서 장 대표 등을 “혐오·자극적 표현을 사용해 비난·비방”했다는 것 등이다. 김 전 최고위원이 지난해 9월 한 월간지 인터뷰에서 “(부정선거 주장 등) 망상 바이러스를 퍼뜨리고 있는 극단적인 사람들과 손을 잡았기 때문에 지지율 하락은 피할 수 없는 일”이라고 했다. 그는 또 “장 대표가 집권과 득표를 위해 자신의 영혼을 판 것과 다름없을 정도로 (보수 유튜버와) 위험한 거래를 했다는 뜻”이란 말도 했다. 윤리위는 이를 두고 “혐오 자극 공격”, “정당한 비판이나 표현의 자유 한도를 넘어서는 정보심리전”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ethics Committee also stated that former Supreme Council member Kim appeared in the media and "perpetrated a very planned and deliberate media terror attack by introducing only specific opinion polls showing low party approval ratings to attack the party leadership." The Ethics Committee said, "The party leader is not merely a natural person's personality but a party institution," adding, "The party leader's authority, prestige, and leadership derive from the 'aggregate of free will' of each party member as the party's 'steward.'" (윤리위는 또 김 전 최고위원이 언론에 출연해 “당의 지지율이 낮게 나오는 특정 여론조사만 소개하며 당 지도부를 공격하는, 매우 계획적이고 용의주도한 매체 테러 공격을 자행”했다고 했다. 윤리위는 “당 대표는 단순한 자연인 인격체가 아니며 하나의 정당 기관”이라며 “당 대표의 권한, 권위, 리더십은 정당의 ‘청지기(steward)’로서 그 당원 개개인의 ‘자유의지의 총합’으로부터 나온다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PPP's Party Affairs Audit Committee, which previously investigated the case, recommended a "two-year suspension of party membership rights" to the Ethics Committee, but the Ethics Committee raised the disciplinary level to a recommendation to leave the party. If a recommendation to leave the party is not appealed for reconsideration within 10 days, the member is expelled without separate procedures if they do not voluntarily leave the party within that period. (앞서 사건을 조사한 국민의힘 당무감사위원회는 윤리위에 ‘당원권 정지 2년’을 권고했는데 윤리위는 탈당 권유로 징계 수위를 높였다. 탈당 권유는 10일 내 재심을 청구하지 않을 경우, 그 기간에 자진 탈당하지 않으면 별도 절차 없이 제명된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the party, there were criticisms such as, "He is not the only one who criticized the Jang leadership system by citing opinion polls with low party approval ratings. Should we also drive out those party members?" and "The intention to oust the pro-Han faction is obvious." Former Supreme Council member Kim said, "It feels like watching Nazi claims," and added, "I received the disciplinary notice today (the 26th), but I heard it was decided on the 23rd. I will also take legal measures, including applying for a suspension of effect injunction." Former leader Han said on Facebook, "An illegal martial law is underway in the People Power Party." (당내에서는 “당 지지율이 낮은 여론조사를 인용해 장 대표 체제를 비판했던 사람이 한둘이 아닌데 그런 당원들도 쫓아내야 하는 것이냐”며 “친한계 축출 의도가 뻔히 보인다”는 지적이 나왔다. 김 전 최고위원은 “나치 주장을 보는 것 같다”며 “오늘(26일) 징계 통보를 받았는데 지난 23일 결정됐다고 들었다. 효력 정지 가처분 신청 등 법적 조치에도 나서겠다”고 했고, 한 전 대표는 페이스북을 통해 “국민의힘에서 불법 계엄이 진행 중”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang's side maintains the position that they do not receive reports or intervene in the Ethics Committee's decisions as it is an independent body. However, people around Leader Jang are encouraged by the results of a Realmeter opinion poll announced that day. Jang Ye-chan, Vice President of the Yeouido Research Institute, said, "It's the effect of Leader Jang's hunger strike, conservative consolidation, and the expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon." (장 대표 측은 윤리위가 독립 기구이기 때문에 보고를 받거나 결정에 관여하지 않는 입장이다. 하지만 장 대표 주변 인사들은 이날 발표된 리얼미터 여론조사 결과에 고무된 분위기다. 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장은 “장 대표의 단식과 보수 결집, 한동훈 전 대표 제명 효과”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to an opinion poll (ARS·automatic response survey) conducted by Realmeter on the 22nd and 23rd and released that day, the PPP's approval rating rose 2.5 percentage points (p) compared to the previous week to 39.5%. This is the highest rating since Leader Jang Dong-hyuk took office in August last year, based on this survey's criteria. The gap with the Democratic Party of Korea's approval rating (42.7%) was 2.2%p, within the margin of error. (리얼미터가 지난 22~23일 실시해 이날 공개한 여론조사(ARS·자동 응답 조사)에 따르면 국민의힘 지지율은 전주 대비 2.5%포인트(p) 상승한 39.5%였다. 이 조사 기준으로 작년 8월 장동혁 대표 취임 이후 최고치다. 더불어민주당 지지율(42.7%)과 격차는 오차 범위 내인 2.2%p였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, in surveys conducted via telephone interviews by Gallup Korea (20th-22nd) and National Indicator Survey (NBS) (19th-21st), the PPP's approval ratings were 22% and 20%, respectively. The PPP's approval rating has shown significant gaps depending on whether it's an ARS survey or a telephone interview survey, and this time the gap was the largest. (반면, 전화 면접 방식으로 실시된 한국갤럽 조사(20~22일), 전국지표조사(NBS) 조사(19~21일)에서 국민의힘 지지율은 각각 22%, 20%였다. 국민의힘 지지율은 ARS 조사냐, 전화 면접 조사냐에 따라 상당한 격차를 보여왔는데 이번 격차가 가장 컸다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang is expected to return to party duties as early as the 28th and attend the Supreme Council meeting on the 29th. Political attention is focused on whether the Supreme Council will approve the "expulsion of Han Dong-hoon" at this meeting. A ruling party official predicted, "The ball has been passed to Leader Jang," and "If he trusts the ARS opinion poll that turned out favorably for him, the likelihood of him choosing the 'expulsion of Han Dong-hoon' is high." (장 대표는 이르면 28일 당무에 복귀하고 29일 최고위에 참석할 전망이다. 정치권의 관심은 이 최고위에서 ‘한동훈 제명’을 의결하느냐에 쏠려 있다. 여권 관계자는 “공은 장 대표에게로 넘어갔다”며 “자신에게 유리하게 나온 ARS 여론조사를 신뢰한다면 ‘한동훈 제명’을 선택할 가능성이 크다”고 전망했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a closed-door general meeting of PPP lawmakers held at the National Assembly that day, a heated debate erupted over the issue of expelling former leader Han. About 20 non-parliamentary district party chairmen also attended the meeting to discuss measures for the lease struggle, and some district party chairmen mentioned the ARS opinion poll results showing an increase in the party's approval rating and argued for a decision to expel former leader Han. In response, Rep. Song Seok-jun (Icheon, Gyeonggi) spoke to the effect that, "With local elections imminent, now is not the time to expel former leader Han. Let's join forces." Some pro-Han faction lawmakers left the meeting venue.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이날 국회에 열린 국민의힘 비공개 의원총회에서 한 전 대표 제명 문제를 놓고 격론이 벌어졌다. 이날 의총에는 대여 투쟁 방안을 논의하기 위해 원외 당협위원장 20여 명도 참석했는데, 일부 당협위원장은 당 지지율이 오른 ARS 여론조사 결과를 언급하며 한 전 대표에 대한 제명 의결을 주장했다. 이에 대해 송석준(경기 이천) 의원은 “지방선거가 목전인데 한 전 대표를 제명할 때가 아니다. 힘을 합치자”는 취지로 말했다. 일부 친한계 의원은 의총장을 나가기도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/OCQRYNUVPRFCLNZBJTDPB4SZ6U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BAJRSMOD5BKNTCGGKEBXEFENOY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Sedition Trial Court Act Poses Risk of Infringing Basic Rights" People Power Party Files Constitutional Appeal (“내란전담재판부법, 기본권 침해 소지” 국힘, 헌법소원 제기)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/RBF24PRPB5CYXDODTCIY3KKEOU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GRSTGNRZMU2WGNBSGZSDON3FGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party filed a constitutional appeal with the Constitutional Court on the 26th, regarding the recently passed Sedition Trial Court Establishment Act, which was led by the ruling party, stating it "poses a significant risk of infringing upon constitutional basic rights." The People Power Party also raised issues with the handling process of the Sedition Trial Court Establishment Act and the so-called False and Manipulated Information Eradication Act (Amendment to the Information and Communications Network Act), claiming "it infringed upon the People Power Party lawmakers' right to deliberate on bills," and filed a jurisdictional dispute adjudication request with the Constitutional Court against National Assembly Speaker Woo Won-shik. (국민의힘은 26일 최근 여당 주도로 국회를 통과한 내란 전담 재판부 설치법에 대해 “헌법상 기본권 침해 소지가 다분하다”며 헌법재판소에 헌법소원을 청구했다. 국민의힘은 또 내란 재판부 설치법과 이른바 허위 조작 정보 근절법(정보통신망법 개정안)의 처리 과정을 문제 삼고 “국민의힘 의원들의 법안 심의권을 침해했다”며 우원식 국회의장을 대상으로 헌재에 권한쟁의 심판을 청구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Sedition Trial Court Establishment Act and the Amendment to the Information and Communications Network Act are laws that the Democratic Party repeatedly made patchwork revisions to due to controversies over their unconstitutionality. The Sedition Trial Court Establishment Act, which was processed in the National Assembly plenary session led by the Democratic Party on the 23rd of last month, stipulates the establishment of dedicated trial courts at the Seoul Central District Court and the Seoul High Court for cases involving sedition, foreign aggression, and rebellion crimes. The Constitution stipulates only military courts as the sole special courts, and it has been pointed out that the sedition trial court is effectively no different from a special court, making it unconstitutional. (내란 전담 재판부 설치법과 정보통신망법 개정안은 위헌 논란 등이 있어 민주당이 땜질 수정을 거듭했던 법들이다. 지난달 23일 민주당 주도로 국회 본회의에서 처리된 내란 전담 재판부 설치법은 내란·외환·반란죄 사건에 대해 서울중앙지법과 서울고법에 전담 재판부를 설치하는 내용이다. 헌법은 군사법원만을 유일한 특별법원으로 규정하고 있는데, 내란 전담 재판부는 사실상 특별법원과 다름없어 위헌이라는 지적이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There have also been criticisms that it contains many elements infringing upon constitutional basic rights. People Power Party's Legal Advisory Committee Chairman Kwak Kyo-taek stated, "Discriminating against specific crimes and their defendants without reasonable grounds infringes upon the constitutional 'right to equality,' and it is a clearly unconstitutional law that also deprives the 'right to a fair trial by judges' as prescribed by the Constitution and laws." (헌법상 기본권 침해 요소도 많다는 지적도 있었다. 국민의힘 곽규택 법률자문위원장은 “합리적인 이유없이 특정 범죄와 그 피고인을 차별하는 것은 헌법상 ‘평등권’을 침해하는 것이고, 헌법과 법률이 정한 법관에 의한 ‘공정한 재판을 받을 권리’ 또한 박탈하는 명백한 위헌 법률”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the Sedition Trial Court Establishment Act, the Amendment to the Information and Communications Network Act, which passed the National Assembly plenary session on the 24th of last month, has also been widely criticized as posing a high risk of unconstitutionality. This law allows for punitive damage claims when false/manipulated information is circulated. Even pro-government leaning groups demanded its repeal, calling it a "gag law that infringes on freedom of the press," and also publicly urged President Lee Jae-myung to exercise his veto power. (내란 재판부 설치법에 이어 지난달 24일 국회 본회의에서 통과된 정보통신망법 개정안도 위헌 소지가 크다는 지적이 많았다. 이 법은 허위·조작 정보를 유통할 경우 징벌적 손해배상 청구가 가능하게 한 것인데, 친여 성향 단체에서도 “언론의 자유를 침해하는 입틀막법”이라며 폐지를 요구했었다. 이재명 대통령에게 공개적으로 거부권을 행사라고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the jurisdictional dispute adjudication request against Speaker Woo Won-shik, the People Power Party stated, "Speaker Woo's surprise submission and passage/declaration of the two bills, which pose a significant risk of unconstitutionality, fundamentally blocked the People Power Party lawmakers' right to deliberate on bills." They further added, "It is an unconstitutional act that renders the National Assembly standing committee system nominal and directly violates parliamentarism." (국민의힘은 우원식 의장을 대상으로 한 권한쟁의 심판 청구에 대해 “우 의장이 위헌 소지가 다분한 두 법안을 기습 상정해 가결·선포한 것은 국민의힘 의원들의 법안 심의권을 원천 봉쇄한 것”이라고 했다. 또 “국회 상임위원회 제도를 형해화하고, 의회주의 등을 정면으로 위반한 위헌적 행위”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/27/RBF24PRPB5CYXDODTCIY3KKEOU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GRSTGNRZMU2WGNBSGZSDON3FGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>There is no opposition party... There is only the ruling party (야당은 없다… 여당만 있을 뿐)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/WV3JJRBV7BFTLBUM6KE6755DFI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;1980 is passing. On December 31, the last day of 1980, YS wrote in his diary, "I sincerely pray to God that 1981 will be a hopeful new year where the peace, love, and liberal democracy that all the people desire will arrive." When asked to write calligraphy, he wrote '夫政者正也, 義人之路也' (Fu zheng zhe zheng ye, yi ren zhi lu ye) and said, "Those who truly engage in politics must walk righteously and like a righteous person." (1980년이 지나갑니다. YS는 1980년 마지막 날인 12월 31일 일기에서 “1981년은 온 국민이 바라는 평화와 사랑과 자유민주주의가 찾아오는 희망의 새해가 되기를 진심으로 하나님께 기도한다”고 적었습니다. 붓글씨를 써달라는 요청을 받고 ‘夫政者正也(부정자정야), 義人之路也(의인지로야)’라고 써주면서 “정말 정치하는 사람은 바르게 또한 의인 답게 걸어야 하는 것”이라고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also criticizes the 'government-controlled opposition party' created after the launch of the Fifth Republic. YS wrote, "There is no such thing as an opposition party now, only a 1st party, 2nd party, and 3rd party," and "These people's mischief is making most of the citizens indifferent to politics and making it seem as if there are both ruling and opposition parties." (5공화국 출범 후 만들어진 ‘관제 야당’도 비판합니다. YS는 “지금 야당이란 것은 없고 1당, 2당, 3당이 있을 뿐”이라며 “국민들 대부분이 정치에 관심이 없게 만들고 정당이 마치 여당도 있고 야당도 있는 것처럼 하고 있는 것이 이 사람들의 작난”이라고 적었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On December 24, Christmas Eve, he had dinner with his wife and children for the first time in a while. He even wrote a bitter joke, wondering if it was thanks to the house arrest that a family meal was possible. "My wife, Eun-cheol, Hyeon-cheol, and Hye-suk all gathered for dinner together for the first time in years, prayed for the country and the people, and talked. I think this is also thanks to Jeon (Jeon Doo-hwan)." (크리스마스 전날인 12월 24일 모처럼 아내 및 자녀들과 저녁 식사를 함께 했습니다. 가택 연금 덕분에 가족 식사가 가능한 게 아닌가 하며 씁쓸한 농담도 적었습니다. “집사람, 은철, 현철, 혜숙 모두 몇 년 만에 같이 모여 저녁 식사를 하며 나라와 민족을 위하여 기도하며 이야기들을 했다. 이것도 전(全·전두환) 덕분인가 생각된다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today is truly a White Christmas. It's not too cold a day. For the first time in a very long time, just our family gathered in one place and had dinner together: my wife, Eun-cheol (恩哲), Hyeon-cheol (賢哲), Hye-suk (惠淑). All of us gathered for dinner together for the first time in years, prayed for the country and the people, and talked. I think this is also thanks to Jeon. (오늘은 정말 White Christmas다. 가위 춥지 않은 날이다. 정말 오래간만에 우리 가족들만 한자리에 모여 저녁 식사(食事)를 같이 했다 집사람, 은철(恩哲), 현철(賢哲), 혜숙(惠淑). 모두 몇 년만에 같이 모여 저녁 식사(食事)를 하며 나라와 민족(民族)을 위하여 기도하며 이야기들을 했다. 이것도 전(全) 덕분인가 생각된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I talked separately with Eun-cheol (恩哲) for about an hour. He says he doesn't know why I went out to the Apt (apartment) and that the food is no good. The side dishes for meals are only kimchi, and during the day he only eats ramen. He says he has only seen that person called Mr. Lee (李先生) for these three days, hasn't seen him otherwise, and has never even ridden in his own car. Now, thinking about his future in various ways, he says he will take the entrance exam for a company next March, do something, and get married around the year after next. And he says he wants to come back home. I promised he could return home by the end of January next year. I truly hope he thinks "Who am I?" and "What should I do?" and becomes a new person. (은철(恩哲)이와 따로 이야기를 한 시간(時間) 정도 했다. 내가 웨(*왜) Apt에 나가게 되었는지 모르겠다고 하고 엄식(*음식)이 말이 아니라고 한다. 밥 반찬은 김치 뿐이며 낮에는 레면(*라면)만 먹고 있다고 한다. 이선생(李先生)인가 하는 자(者)는 요 이 3일동안만 봤고 보지도 못하며 제 자동차(自動車)는 타본 일도 없다고 한다. 이제는 여러가지로 저의 장래(將來)를 생각하며 내년(來年) 3월에는 회사(会社)에 입사(入社) 시험(試驗)을 처서(*쳐서) 들어가 무엇인가 하고 후내년(后來年·*내후년)쯤 결혼(結婚)하겠다고 한다. 그리고 집으로 돌아오구 싶다고 한다. 내년(來年) 일월(一月) 말일(末日)까지는 집에 돌아오도록 약속(約束)했다. 정말로 “내가 누구인가” “내가 무엇을 해야 하는가”를 생각하며 새 사람이 되었으면 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today is also cold weather, 15 degrees below zero. It's the last Sunday of this year. This year will also pass in three days. Seeing out this tiresome year of 1980, my heart is more troubled than anything. Spending nearly a year like this, unable to come and go freely, not only unable to meet the people I want to meet, but also living lonely days, what is it that troubles my heart so. (오늘도 0하(下) 15도(度)의 추운 날씨다. 금년(今年)의 마주막(*마지막) 주일(主日)이다. 금년(今年)도 3일(日)이면 다 지나간다. 지긋지긋한 1980년(年)을 다 보내며 있어서 무섯(*무엇)보다도 마음이 착잡하다. 이렇게 늘 출입(出入)도 못하고 맞나고(*만나고) 싶은 사람들도 맞나지(*만나지) 못할 뿐 아니라 고독한 나날을 근(近) 일년간(一年間) 보내니 무엇이 마음이 착잡하다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the house of "Lee Nam," "Jeonggan-sa" brought a pair of honey. He said upon seeing me, my face didn't look good. A few days ago, I also received a greeting call from Mr. Lee Jae-hyung. (“이남” 댁(宅)에서 “정간사”가 꿀 한 개 짝을 가지고 왔다. 나를 보고 얼굴이 안 되었다고 한다 요 몇 일전(日前)에는 이(李)재형 씨(氏)로부터 문안(問安) 전화(電話)가 왔더라.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lately, when I look at my face reflected in the mirror, it seems wrinkles have suddenly increased a lot this year. I will grow old like a different person... But it seems many more wrinkles have formed on my face. (요지음 내가 나의 얼굴을 거울을 통(通)해서 비처(*비춰)보면 주름이 금년(今年) 들어 갑자기 많아진 것 같다. 나는 딴 사람처럼 늙겠지… 그러나 한층 더 얼굴에 주름이 많이 생긴 것 같다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evening before last, Seo Seok-jae came and we talked about this and that. Regarding the political party called the Minhandang (民韓黨) or something, I say that I already knew it wasn't an opposition party, but I hadn't realized it would be that severe. There is no such thing as an opposition party now, only a 1st party, 2nd party, and 3rd party. There are only ruling parties, all of which assist this coup d'état force. (그저께 저녁에는 서석재(徐錫宰)가 왔어(*와서) 이런저런 이야기를 하고 같다. 민한당(民韓黨)인가 하는 정당(政黨)에 대(対)해서 나는 이미 야당(野黨)이 아닌 것을 알고 있었지만 그가 그처럼 심할 것이라고는 미처 몰랐다고 말한다. 지금 야당(野黨)이란 것은 없고 일당(一党) 이당(二党) 3당(党)이 있을 뿐이다. 전부(全部)가 이 구데타(*쿠데타) 세력(勢力)을 도우는 여당만이 있을 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because these people are doing covert operation politics even before information politics! Their mischief is making most of the citizens indifferent to politics and making it seem as if there are both ruling and opposition parties. (이 사람들이 정보 정치(政治) 이전(以前)에 공작(工作) 정치(政治) 하고 있어(*으)니까! 국민(囗民)들 대부분(大部分)이 정치(政治)에 관심(關心)이 없게 만들고 정당(政黨)이 마치 여당도 있고 야당(野黨)도 있는 것처럼 하고 있는 것이 이 사람들의 작난이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This morning is also 14 degrees below zero. At year's end, as the new year approaches tomorrow, what awaits our people is not a hopeful new morning, but a year-end frozen solid, wondering where this country is going. Perhaps in my memory, I don't recall the end of December being this continuously cold. The day before yesterday, it snowed so much that several young students froze to death in the Jeonbuk region. (오늘 아침도 0하(下) 14도(度)다. 연말(年末)에 새해가 모래면 다처(*닥쳐)오는데 우리 백성(百姓)들에게는 희망(希望)찬 새 아침이 기다리고 있는 것이 아니라 이 나라가 어디로 가는 것인지 꽁꽁 얼어붙어 버린 연말(年末)이다. 아마 내 기억으로는 12월말(月末)이 이처럼 계속해서 추었(*웠)던 기억이 없다. 그저께는 눈이 너무 많이 내려 전북(全北) 지방(地方)이 어린 학생(學生)들이 여럿 얼어 죽었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trial of Jiang Qing and others in China, the trial of the century, seems to be almost over. Jiang Qing was sentenced to death. Jiang Qing's final words were fitting for Mao Zedong's wife. "I fought on the front lines with Mao Zedong to save the country. I am the wife of the great Mao. To execute me is to kill Mao. If you are going to execute me, do it in front of over a million people at Tiananmen Square." (세기(世紀)의 재판(裁判)인 중공(中共)의 강청(江靑) 등(等)의 재판(裁判)이 거위(*거의) 끝났는 것 같다. 강청(江靑)에게 사형(死刑)이 내려졌다. 강청(江靑)의 최후(最后)의 말은 역시 모택동(毛澤東)의 아네(*아내) 답다. “나는 나라를 구(救)하기 위하여 모택동(毛澤東)과 함께 전선(戰線)에서 싸웠다. 나는 위대(偉大)한 모(毛)의 처다. 나를 사형(死刑)하는 것은 모(毛)를 죽이는 것이다. 나를 사형(死刑) 할려거던 천안문(天安門) 앞에서 백만명(百萬名) 이상(以上)의 사람들이 보는 가운데서 하라”고….)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't know when it will be published, but I will try to write a book. I will try to write a book containing political philosophy and vision. A book I want to let the people know about someday. Since May 20th, I have been under continuous house arrest. The loneliness and boredom of my life spent only inside the house, the waiting... What words should I use to properly express my feelings? It's agonizing. Suffocating. (언제인가 출판(出版)이 될런지 모르지마는 책을 한 권 써보겠다. 정치철학(政治哲學)이 담기고 비존(*비전)이 담긴 책을 하나 써보겠다. 어느 때인가 국민(囗民)에게 알리고 싶은 책. 지난 5월(月)20일(日)부터 줄곧 연금 상태니까. 집안에서만 지나는 나의 생활(生活) 고독과 지루함, 기다림 무슨 말을 사용(使用)해야 나의 마음을 제대로 표현(表現)할 수 있을런지 괴로움. 답답함.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today is the last day of 1980. How should I describe this past year? It is a year where everything was destroyed and created by the dictator. The top 10 domestic news stories are all those forced news stories they destroyed and smashed. This tiresome year... It was a year I don't even want to think back on. Kim Jong-pil, Kim Dae-jung, Jeon Doo-hwan. I don't even want to think about them. (오늘은 1980년(年)의 마주막(*마지막) 날이다. 금년(今年) 일년(一年)을 무엇이라고 표현(表現)할가(*까)? 독제(*재)자(者)에 위(*의)해서 모든 것이 파괴되고 만드려진(*만들어진) 한해다. 국내(國內) 10대 News는 다 그들이 파괴하고 뿌수고(*부수고) 한 억지 News들이다. 이 지긋지긋한 한해… 생각하고 돌려켜(*돌이켜) 보기도 싫은 한해였다. 김종필(金鍾泌) 김대중(金大中) 전두환(全斗煥). 모두 생각하기도 싫다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A society where justice has disappeared, a society where truth has disappeared, is it okay for there to be only injustice without truth and justice? (정의(正義)가 없어진 사회(社会), 진리(眞理)가 없어진 사회(社会), 진실(眞實)과 정의(正義)가 없이 불의(不義)마니(*만이) 있어도 갠(*괜)찮은 것인가?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bok Jin-poong said he is building a new house and moving to a 1000-pyeong property, so he asked me to write something, and I wrote it. Seeing out the end of the year, I wrote: "夫政者正也 (Fu zheng zhe zheng ye), 義人之路也 (Yi ren zhi lu ye)" (Those who govern must be upright; it is the path of the righteous). Those who truly engage in politics must walk righteously and like a righteous person. (복진풍(卜鎭豊)이가 집을 새로 지어 1000평짜리로 이사(移舍)간다고 해서 글을 하나 써달라고 해서 썼다. 이해를 마주막(*마지막) 보내면서 “夫政者正也(부정자정야·*무릇 정치는 바른 것이다), 義人之路也(의인지로야·*올바른 사람이 갈 길이다)”. 정말 정치(政治)하는 사람은 바르게 또한 의인(義人)답게 걸어야 하는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wouldn't this be the hope of all our people? I sincerely pray to God that this truly tiresome year passes completely, becomes a year I never want to look back on again, and that 1981 becomes a hopeful new year where the peace, love, and liberal democracy that all the people desire arrive. (이것이 우리 온 국민(囗民)의 소망(所望)이 아니겠나. 정말 지긋지긋한 금년(今年)이 다 지나가고 다시는 뒤에도 돌아보기 싫은 해가 되고 1981년(年)은 온 국민(囗民)이 바라는 평화(平和)와 사랑과 자유민주주의(自由民主主義)가 찾아오는 희망(希望)의 새해가 되기를 진심(眞心)으로 하나님께 기도한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I only pray that the evil year never comes again and that a warm new year where the hopeful "Seoul Spring" arrives awaits us. (악(惡)한 해가 다시는 오지 않게 하시고 희망(希望)의 “서울의 봄”이 찾아드는 따스한 새해가 우리들을 기다리기를 빌 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope the new year awaiting us is filled only with clear, bright, and beautiful hopeful news. (맑고 밝고 아름다운 희망(希望)의 News마니(*만이) 우리를 기다리는 새해가 되기를 바란다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Starting today, because of the birds, the room got dirty, so I moved all the birds down to the living room. (오늘부터 너무 샛(*새) 때문에 방이 드러워(*더러워) 새들을 언접실(*응접실)로 다 내려갔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/27/WV3JJRBV7BFTLBUM6KE6755DFI/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>