<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 23:24:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Oh Se-hoon Says "Political Special Prosecutor Passed... Lee Must Exercise Veto" (오세훈 “정치 특검 통과...李, 거부권 행사해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/4URVOHIW7FF5VMVL2YUR26OLHM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Oh Se-hoon Says "Political Special Prosecutor Passed... Lee Must Exercise Veto" (오세훈 “정치 특검 통과...李, 거부권 행사해야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRTOMBUG42TSNTGGZSTINLBMI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, after the passage of the 'Second Comprehensive Special Prosecutor Act' led by the Democratic Party of Korea, Seoul Mayor Oh Se-hoon stated, "Another political special prosecutor has been passed," and urged President Lee Jae-myung to exercise his veto (right to request reconsideration). (오세훈 서울시장이 16일 더불어민주당 주도로 ‘2차 종합 특검법‘이 통과되자 “또 하나의 정치 특검이 통과됐다”며 이재명 대통령을 향해 거부권(재의요구권)을 행사하라고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh made these remarks in a Facebook post this afternoon, saying, "This is an admission that they lack confidence in maintaining power without a special prosecutor." Today, the National Assembly held a plenary session and passed the Second Comprehensive Special Prosecutor Act (Special Prosecutor Act for the Investigation of the Truth Regarding Acts of Rebellion, Foreign Interference, and State Affairs Manipulation by Yoon Suk-yeol and Kim Keon-hee), aiming to investigate additional suspicions not covered by the three major special prosecutors on rebellion, Kim Keon-hee, and Chae Hae-byeong. (오 시장은 이날 오후 자신의 페이스북에서 “특검이 없으면 정권 유지에 자신이 없다는 실토”라며 이같이 밝혔다. 이날 국회는 본회의를 열고 내란·김건희·채해병 등 3대 특검에서 다루지 못한 추가적인 의혹을 더 수사하겠다며 2차 종합 특검법(윤석열·김건희에 의한 내란·외환 및 국정 농단 행위의 진상 규명을 위한 특검법)을 통과시켰다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mayor Oh asked, "Who are the people who really need a 'comprehensive' special prosecutor?" He continued, "Billions in illicit funds were exchanged in return for nominations. While trying to investigate collusion with a specific religion by targeting the opposition party, suspicions of this administration's minister receiving bribes were exposed. Corruption and irregularities from a person who even served as the ruling party's floor leader keep surfacing endlessly." He added, "The special prosecutor exists to investigate these people." (오 시장은 “진짜 ‘종합적’ 특검이 필요한 사람들이 누구냐”고 했다. 이어 “공천을 대가로 ‘억’ 소리 나는 검은돈이 오갔다. 야당을 표적 삼아 특정 종교와의 유착 관계를 캐려다 이 정권 장관의 금품 수수 의혹을 들켰다. 여당 실세 원내대표까지 지낸 사람의 비리·부패는 끝도 없이 터져 나온다”며 “이런 사람들 수사하라고 있는 게 특검”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then said, "For the first time in a while, opposition forces have united and coordinated their efforts," and "If all forces that can check this reckless power come together, the people will join them." Mayor Oh stated, "Only stronger unity and solidarity are the forces that protect the people," and "The behavior of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party is the prelude to this power's miserable end." He urged, "The President must exercise his veto on the comprehensive special prosecutor," and "And he must uproot the rotten foundations of the Democratic Party's power." (그러면서 “모처럼 야권이 뜻을 모았고 호흡을 맞췄다”며 “무도한 권력을 견제할 모든 세력이 모인다면 국민도 함께하실 것”이라고 했다. 오 시장은 “더 단단한 통합과 연대만이 국민을 지키는 힘”이라며 “이재명 정권과 민주당의 행태는 이 권력의 처참한 말로의 복선”이라고 했다. 그러면서 “대통령은 종합 특검에 거부권을 행사하라”며 “그리고 민주당 권력의 썩은 뿌리부터 뽑으시라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Earlier, the People Power Party and the Reform Party showed solidarity when the Democratic Party attempted to force through the processing of the Second Comprehensive Special Prosecutor Act. The previous day, when the related bill was submitted to the plenary session led by the Democratic Party, Chun Ha-ram, the Reform Party's floor leader, opposed the bill and became the first filibuster (unlimited debate) speaker. At that time, party leader Jang Dong-hyuk said, "The moment Reform Party floor leader Chun Ha-ram stands to begin the filibuster as the first speaker in the plenary hall, I will start a hunger strike here in the Rotunda Hall of the National Assembly, where the voices of the people gather." (앞서 국민의힘과 개혁신당은 더불어민주당이 2차 종합 특검 강행 처리를 시도하자 연대하는 모습을 보였다. 전날 관련 법안이 민주당 주도로 본회의에 상정되자 천하람 개혁신당 원내대표는 이 법에 반대해 첫 필리버스터(무제한 토론) 주자로 나섰다. 그 시각 장동혁 대표는 “천하람 개혁신당 원내대표가 1번 주자로 본회의장에서 필리버스터를 하기 위해 서는 순간 저는 국민 목소리가 모이는 이곳 국회 본회의장 로텐더홀에서 단식을 시작하겠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After floor leader Chun concluded his filibuster lasting 18 hours and 59 minutes and stepped down from the podium, leader Jang entered the plenary hall and gave a standing ovation, sharing an encouraging hug and handshake with floor leader Chun. Leader Jang said, "I kept watching floor leader Chun Ha-ram, who was 50 meters away on the screen, conducting the filibuster," and "I renew my promise to explore all possible methods to persuade and appeal to the people and fight to the end alongside the Reform Party." (장 대표는 천 원내대표가 18시간 59분에 걸친 필리버스터 이후 연단에서 내려오자 본회의장으로 들어가 기립 박수를 보냈고, 천 원내대표와 격려의 포옹과 악수를 나눴다. 장 대표는 “화면을 통해 50m 거리에 있는 천 원내대표가 필리버스터를 하는 모습을 계속 지켜봤다”며 “국민을 설득하고 호소드릴 수 있는 모든 방법을 강구해 끝까지 개혁신당과 함께 싸워나가겠다는 약속을 다시 드린다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/16/4URVOHIW7FF5VMVL2YUR26OLHM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GVRTOMBUG42TSNTGGZSTINLBMI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:32:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Japanese PM Aso, who met with Lee, says "We must prepare together for the movements of North Korea, China, and Russia" (李 만난 아소 전 日총리 “북·중·러 움직임에 함께 대비해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/16/65OMZGW7TBA2JHW325YESEELTI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Former Japanese PM Aso, who met with Lee, says "We must prepare together for the movements of North Korea, China, and Russia" (李 만난 아소 전 日총리 “북·중·러 움직임에 함께 대비해야” )&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5ESZ7EG7LVOU5FP3YTYN3OOFY4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 16th, in a meeting with former Japanese Prime Minister Aso Taro, "Japan and South Korea are like neighbors sharing a front yard," adding, "It is desirable to find as many areas as possible for cooperation and develop a relationship that is mutually beneficial." (이재명 대통령은 16일 아소 다로 전 일본 총리를 만나 “일본과 한국은 앞마당을 함께 쓰는 옆집 같은 존재”라며 “협력할 수 있는 부분을 최대한 찾아내 서로에게 도움이 되는 관계로 발전하는 게 바람직하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks during a meeting with former Prime Minister Aso, who visited South Korea to participate in the Seoul-Tokyo Forum, at the Blue House main office in the afternoon. (이 대통령은 이날 오후 청와대 본관에서 서울-도쿄포럼 참석차 방한한 아소 전 총리를 접견하고 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Since I am meeting (former Prime Minister Aso) right after having a truly beneficial meeting with Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi in Japan, our citizens are expecting that 'Korea-Japan relations might suddenly advance a step,'" adding, "I hope this visit also becomes a good opportunity for the improvement of Korea-Japan relations." (이 대통령은 “다카이치 사나에 총리님과 일본에서 정말 유익한 회담을 한 직후에 (아소 전) 총리님을 뵙게 되니까, 우리 국민들께서 ‘한일관계가 갑자기 한 단계 나아지는 것 아니냐’는 기대를 하고 있다”며 “이번 방문에서도 한일관계가 개선되는 좋은 계기가 되길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Prime Minister Aso said, "The international situation surrounding Japan and South Korea is changing now," and "We must prepare for the movements of countries close to Japan and South Korea, such as Russia, China, and North Korea." (아소 전 총리는 “일본과 한국을 둘러싼 국제정세는 지금 변화하고 있다”며 “러시아, 중국, 북한 등 일본이랑 한국과 가까운 나라에 움직임에 대해서 우리는 대비를 해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, he said, "Compared to the past, closely cooperating in Japan-South Korea relations now benefits both sides," and "Having such active discussions between leaders in a short period is also beneficial for both Japan and South Korea." He added, "It seems that if political relations are good, an environment where economic relations can easily develop is created," and "I am looking forward to it." (아울러 “옛날과 비교해 지금의 일본과 한국 관계는 긴밀히 협력하는 것이 양쪽에 이익이 된다”며 “정상 간에 그런 논의가 단시간에 활발히 이뤄지는 것은 일본과 한국 양국에도 도움이 된다”고 했다. 그러면서 “정치관계가 좋으면 경제관계도 발전하기 쉬운 환경이 만들어지는 것 같다”며 “기대하고 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/16/65OMZGW7TBA2JHW325YESEELTI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/5ESZ7EG7LVOU5FP3YTYN3OOFY4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:56:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Controversy Over 'Price Gouging' Accommodation in Busan for BTS Concert?... President Lee: "Must Eradicate Malicious Extortion" (BTS 공연에 부산 ‘바가지’ 숙박 논란?... 李 “악질 횡포 뿌리뽑아야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/16/PGBBIH23AFFRLESTAGFOUPP67A/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Controversy Over 'Price Gouging' Accommodation in Busan for BTS Concert?... President Lee: "Must Eradicate Malicious Extortion" (BTS 공연에 부산 ‘바가지’ 숙박 논란?... 李 “악질 횡포 뿌리뽑아야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/W3KVJWRGXZELFJ5NKVOPOYJPBU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung said on the 16th, regarding the soaring accommodation prices in Busan ahead of a BTS concert, that "we must ensure the losses are far greater than any unfairly obtained profits." (이재명 대통령은 16일 방탄소년단(BTS) 공연을 앞두고 부산 숙박 요금이 치솟았다며 “부당 취득한 이익보다 손해가 훨씬 크도록 해야 할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The President shared an article on his X (formerly Twitter) that day about the 'price gouging controversy' erupting as accommodation prices in the Busan area, where the BTS concert is being held, have skyrocketed by up to 10 times, and made these remarks. (이 대통령은 이날 자신의 X(구 트위터)에 BTS 공연이 열리는 부산 지역에서 숙박 요금이 최대 10배까지 폭등해 ‘바가지 논란’이 불거졌다는 기사를 공유하며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "We must definitely eradicate the malicious extortion that destroys the order of the entire market and causes great harm to everyone." Previously, at a cabinet meeting on the 16th of last month, President Lee had also pointed out that "price gouging and unfriendliness are hindering tourism revitalization" and instructed the Ministry of Culture, Sports and Tourism to prepare related countermeasures.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령은 “시장 전체의 질서를 무너뜨리고 모두에게 큰 피해를 주는 악질적 횡포 반드시 뿌리 뽑아야 한다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 앞서 지난달 16일 국무회의에서도 “바가지 (요금), 불친절이 관광 활성화를 막고 있다”며 문체부에 관련 대책 마련을 지시한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/16/PGBBIH23AFFRLESTAGFOUPP67A/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/W3KVJWRGXZELFJ5NKVOPOYJPBU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 03:15:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Assemblyman Ha Soon-bong Passes Away (하순봉 前 의원 별세)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/national/people/2026/01/17/DPI67UVPZ5AZNMAODU76TOIJIY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Former Assemblyman Ha Soon-bong Passes Away (하순봉 前 의원 별세)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/H6TPN6Q45NBGJKZHQ4UTSD6EQ4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former Assemblyman Ha Soon-bong (85), who served four terms, passed away on the 16th. Former Assemblyman Ha was born in Jinju, South Gyeongsang Province in 1941 and graduated from Seoul National University's Department of German Language Education. After working as a teacher at Jinju High School, he served as a journalist for MBC and the Kyunghyang Shinmun from 1967 to 1981. He entered politics in 1981 as a member of the Democratic Justice Party, elected to the 11th National Assembly via proportional representation. Later, in the 14th general election in 1992, he was elected as an independent from Jinju, South Gyeongsang Province, and then joined the Democratic Liberal Party. He was subsequently re-elected in the 15th and 16th general elections. He also served as chairman of the Gyeongnam Ilbo from 2010 to 2017. The funeral hall is at Hanil Hospital Funeral Home in Jinju, South Gyeongsang Province. He is survived by his wife Park Ok-ja, daughter Jeong-min, and son Jong-hoon. The funeral procession will depart at 7 a.m. on the 20th. Contact: (055)756-9009. (4선 의원을 지낸 하순봉(85) 전 의원이 16일 별세했다. 하 전 의원은 1941년 경남 진주에서 태어나, 서울대 독어교육과를 졸업했다. 진주고 교사를 거쳐 1967~1981년 MBC와 경향신문 기자로 일했다. 1981년 민정당 소속 11대 의원(전국구)으로 정치에 입문했다. 이후 1992년 14대 총선 때 경남 진주에서 무소속 출마해 당선된 뒤 민자당에 들어갔고, 15·16대 총선에서도 내리 당선됐다. 2010~2017년 경남일보 회장도 역임했다. 빈소는 경남 진주시 한일병원 장례식장. 유족은 부인 박옥자씨와 딸 정민씨, 아들 종훈씨가 있다. 발인 20일 7시, (055)756-9009.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/national/people/2026/01/17/DPI67UVPZ5AZNMAODU76TOIJIY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/H6TPN6Q45NBGJKZHQ4UTSD6EQ4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Opposition Unilaterally Passes 2nd Special Prosecutor Act... Cheon Ha-ram Asks Lee to "Veto It" (與 2차 특검법 일방 처리… 천하람, 李에 “거부해달라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/E72EH4F3RVFZHP52GDKJ3ODI24/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Opposition Unilaterally Passes 2nd Special Prosecutor Act... Cheon Ha-ram Asks Lee to "Veto It" (與 2차 특검법 일방 처리… 천하람, 李에 “거부해달라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea passed the 'Second Comprehensive Special Prosecutor Act,' which follows the three major special prosecutions (sedition, Kim Keon-hee, and Chae Hae-byeong), in the National Assembly plenary session on the 16th. Cheon Ha-ram, the floor leader of the Reform Party, who opposed it and conducted a 19-hour unlimited debate (filibuster), attended a luncheon meeting with President Lee Jae-myung and ruling and opposition party leaders that day and requested, "Please exercise your right to request reconsideration (veto) regarding the second special prosecutor act." President Lee reportedly did not give an answer. (더불어민주당이 16일 3대 특검(내란, 김건희, 채해병)의 뒤를 이을 ‘2차 종합 특검법’을 국회 본회의에서 통과시켰다. 이를 반대하며 19시간 동안 무제한 토론(필리버스터)을 벌인 천하람 개혁신당 원내대표는 이날 이재명 대통령과 여야 지도부의 오찬에 참석해 “2차 특검법에 대해 재의 요구권(거부권)을 행사해달라”고 했다. 이 대통령은 답을 하지 않았다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party forced an end to the opposition's filibuster in the plenary session that day and put the second comprehensive special prosecutor bill to a vote. It passed with 172 votes in favor and 2 against out of 174 members present. Two Reform Party members cast dissenting votes, while People Power Party members left the chamber without voting. People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok has been on a hunger strike in the National Assembly since the previous day, demanding a special prosecution into the Democratic Party's nomination funds, among other things. (민주당은 이날 본회의에서 야당의 필리버스터를 강제 종결시킨 뒤 2차 종합 특검 법안을 표결에 부쳤다. 재석 174명 중 찬성 172표, 반대 2표로 가결됐다. 개혁신당 의원 2명이 반대표를 던졌고, 국민의힘 의원들은 투표하지 않고 퇴장했다. 국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 전날부터 국회에서 민주당의 공천 헌금 특검 등을 요구하며 단식 투쟁을 벌이고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investigative personnel for the second special prosecution is a maximum of 251, similar to the sedition special prosecution (maximum 267) and more than the Kim Keon-hee special prosecution (maximum 205). The activity period is up to 170 days, meaning the investigation will continue throughout the June 3 local elections period. Furthermore, several items directly targeting the People Power Party were included in the investigation's scope. (2차 특검의 수사 인력은 최대 251명으로 내란 특검(최대 267명)과 비슷하고 김건희 특검(최대 205명)보다 많다. 활동 기간은 최장 170일로 6·3 지방선거 기간 내내 수사가 이어지게 된다. 또 수사 대상에 국민의힘을 직접 겨냥한 항목이 여럿 포함됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the opposition is protesting, saying, "The second special prosecution is for the June local elections and for suppressing the opposition," noting that former President Yoon Suk-yeol and martial law-related figures are already indicted and on trial. The special prosecution sought the death penalty for former President Yoon Suk-yeol on the 13th on charges of being the ringleader of sedition, and the court sentenced former President Yoon to five years in prison that day on charges including obstruction of arrest. (이에 야당은 “2차 특검은 6월 지방선거용이자 야당 탄압용”이라며 반발하고 있다. 이미 윤석열 전 대통령과 계엄 관련자들이 기소돼 재판을 받고 있다는 것이다. 특검은 지난 13일 내란 우두머리 혐의로 윤석열 전 대통령에게 사형을 구형했고 법원은 이날 윤 전 대통령의 체포 방해 등의 혐의에 대해 징역 5년을 선고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid this, President Lee Jae-myung held a luncheon meeting with ruling and opposition party leaders at Sangchunjae in the Blue House that day. Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram expressed opposition to the second special prosecution to President Lee, stating, "Rather than setting a bad precedent of repeatedly conducting special prosecutions to desecrate a dead power, it would be more efficient and cost-effective if the police and prosecutors dispatched to the special prosecution formed a joint investigation headquarters." The People Power Party did not attend the luncheon that day, and among conservative opposition parties, only Floor Leader Cheon attended. (이런 가운데 이재명 대통령은 이날 청와대 상춘재에서 여야 지도부와 오찬 간담회를 열었다. 천하람 개혁신당 원내대표는 이 대통령에게 “죽은 권력을 부관참시하기 위해 특검을 재차 하는 나쁜 선례를 만들기보다, 특검에 파견됐던 경찰과 검찰이 합동수사본부를 만들면 효율적이고 비용도 적게 들 것”이라며 2차 특검 반대 의견을 냈다. 이날 오찬엔 국민의힘은 불참했고 보수 야당에선 천 원내대표만이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/E72EH4F3RVFZHP52GDKJ3ODI24/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:55:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyuk Desperately Needs an Alliance... But Lee Jun-seok Keeps His Distance (장동혁은 연대 절실한데… 이준석은 거리두기)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/MRNDYY47Q5C73OCWDITWROZHP4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jang Dong-hyuk Desperately Needs an Alliance... But Lee Jun-seok Keeps His Distance (장동혁은 연대 절실한데… 이준석은 거리두기)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7DRYEVCPKZPXPDV4K7B5AMIUDU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Reform Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram concluded his unlimited debate (filibuster) opposing the 'Second Comprehensive Special Prosecutor Act' on the morning of the 16th and stepped down from the podium, People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk entered the main assembly hall, gave a standing ovation, and embraced him. Leader Jang stated, "I understand that leader Lee Jun-seok, who is on an overseas business trip, is also hurrying back upon hearing the news of my hunger strike," adding, "I will fight alongside the Reform Party until the end." (개혁신당 천하람 원내대표가 16일 오전 ‘2차 종합 특검법’ 반대 무제한 토론(필리버스터)을 마치고 연단을 내려오자, 국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 본회의장으로 들어가 기립 박수를 치고 그를 끌어 안았다. 장 대표는 “(해외) 출장을 간 이준석 대표도 제가 단식한다는 소식에 서둘러 귀국하는 걸로 안다”며 “끝까지 개혁신당과 함께 싸워 나가겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the meeting between leaders Jang and Lee on the 13th, the two parties have reportedly begun full-fledged so-called 'special prosecutor cooperation.' Both parties are demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into suspicions surrounding the Democratic Party of Korea's nomination-related donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of political circles. Leader Jang's hunger strike, which began on the 15th in the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall, is seen as an extension of this effort. (앞서 지난 13일 장·이 대표가 만난 뒤 두 당은 이른바 ‘특검 공조’를 본격화했다. 두 당은 더불어민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하고 있다. 15일 시작된 장 대표의 국회 로텐더홀 단식도 그 연장선에 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within political circles, observations have emerged stating, "Leader Jang Dong-hyuk is currently facing internal backlash over the push to expel Han Dong-hoon," and "He needs an exit strategy to break through this, and it seems he has chosen 'alliance with the Reform Party' as one of them." An opposition party official commented, "To dilute criticism that Leader Jang is engaging in 'subtractive politics,' he likely has no choice but to show a united front with Leader Lee." (정치권에서는 “지금 장동혁 대표는 ‘한동훈 제명 추진’에 대한 당내 반발에 직면해 있다”며 “이를 타개할 출구가 필요한데 그중 하나로 ‘개혁신당과의 연대’를 잡은 것 같다”는 관측이 나왔다. 야권 관계자는 “장 대표가 ‘뺄셈의 정치’를 한다는 비판을 희석시키려면 이 대표와 손을 잡는 모습을 보일 수밖에 없을 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the Reform Party's perspective, a certain level of 'cooperation' with the People Power Party is necessary to contest the June 3 local elections. Their 'special prosecutor cooperation with the People Power Party,' channeled through floor leader Cheon Ha-ram, is also understood to have been pursued within this context. However, as interpretations arise linking Leader Jang's hunger strike demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' to the internal conflict within the People Power Party over 'Han Dong-hoon's expulsion,' the Reform Party also appears to be hesitating. (개혁신당으로서도 6·3 지방선거를 치르려면 국민의힘과는 일정 수준의 ‘공조’가 필요하다는 입장이다. 천하람 원내대표를 창구로 한 ‘국민의힘과의 특검 공조’도 그런 차원에서 진행해 왔던 것으로 알려졌다. 하지만 장 대표의 ‘쌍특검’ 요구 단식이 ‘한동훈 제명’이라는 국민의힘 내부 갈등과 연계돼 있다는 해석이 나오면서 개혁신당도 주춤하는 모양새다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initially, when Leader Jang began his hunger strike, there was a possibility that Leader Lee, who was on an overseas diplomatic trip, might cut his trip short and return, but the atmosphere is said to have changed. It is reported that within the Reform Party, there are many opinions stating, "The justification for actively joining has weakened because Leader Jang's hunger strike, ostensibly for passing the special prosecutor act, has a strong aspect of being for 'internal party politics.'" A key Reform Party official told this newspaper, "While we are gathering strength for Leader Jang's hunger strike, we are not immediately considering measures like a joint hunger strike," adding, "We are keeping our options open and reviewing what method would be most appealing to the public, beyond just a hunger strike." (당초 장 대표가 단식에 들어갈 경우, 의원 외교차 해외 출장 중인 이 대표가 중도 귀국할 가능성이 있었는데 기류가 바뀌었다고 한다. 개혁신당 내부에서는 “특검법 통과를 명분으로 내세운 장 대표의 단식이 ‘당내 정치용’이란 측면이 강해 적극적으로 함께할 명분이 약해졌다”는 의견이 다수 있는 것으로 전해졌다. 개혁신당 핵심 관계자는 본지에 “장 대표의 단식에 힘을 모으고는 있지만 당장 공동 단식 등의 방안을 검토하고 있지는 않다”며 “단식 외에도 국민께 가장 소구력 있는 방안이 무엇인지 열어 놓고 검토 중”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 12th, during a radio appearance, Leader Lee stated, "Cooperation and alliance are different," and said, "The dumbest thing the Reform Party could do is to lose by forming an alliance. So, there's no need to even consider it." Reform Party officials also remarked, "An 'election alliance' with the Jang Dong-hyuk leadership, which failed to 'sever ties with Yoon Suk-yeol,' would only further lower our approval ratings." (이 대표는 지난 12일 라디오에서 “공조와 연대는 다르다”며 “개혁신당이 제일 바보 되는 게 연대해서 지는 것이다. 그러니까 검토할 필요도 없는 것”이라고 했다. 개혁신당 인사들도 “‘윤석열 절연’에 실패한 장 대표 체제와의 ‘선거 연대’는 오히려 우리 지지율만 더 떨어뜨릴 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/MRNDYY47Q5C73OCWDITWROZHP4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/7DRYEVCPKZPXPDV4K7B5AMIUDU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Political Inside] Conflict between Myeong and Cheong over Prosecution Reform Bill? 'Bone-chilling Conversation' at Airport En Route to Japan ([정치 인사이드] 검찰 개편안 두고 명청 갈등? 日 가던 공항서 ‘뼈있는 대화’)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/TQYGB4UTRRH3ZP5D3L3DRQM6MY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;[Political Inside] Conflict between Myeong and Cheong over Prosecution Reform Bill? 'Bone-chilling Conversation' at Airport En Route to Japan ([정치 인사이드] 검찰 개편안 두고 명청 갈등? 日 가던 공항서 ‘뼈있는 대화’)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YRLWBYW6QJDBRK44NC7NZJ7QFA.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Signs of a rift within the ruling party are emerging over the Public Prosecution Service and the Major Crimes Investigation Agency bills announced by the government on the 12th. The bills are known to have been led by Bong Wook, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Civil Affairs. As Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae and hardliners announced major revisions, stating "the government's proposal is merely a draft," talk of "another Myeong-Cheong conflict?" has surfaced. (정부가 지난 12일 발표한 공소청·중수청(중대범죄수사청) 법안을 두고 여권 내 균열 조짐이 일고 있다. 이 안은 봉욱 청와대 민정수석이 주도한 것으로 알려져 있는데, 민주당 정청래 대표와 강경파가 “정부안은 초안일 뿐”이라며 대대적인 수정을 예고하고 나서면서 “이번에도 명·청 갈등이냐”는 말이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable atmosphere within the ruling party surrounding the government's proposal was sensed during a conversation between President Lee Jae-myung and Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae on the morning of the 13th. That day, as President Lee was departing for the Korea-Japan summit, a scene of him engaging in a close conversation with Leader Jeong, who had come to Seoul Airport to see him off, was captured by media cameras. (정부안을 둘러싼 여권 내 불편한 기류는 지난 13일 아침 이재명 대통령과 정청래 민주당 대표와의 대화에서 감지됐다. 이날은 이 대통령이 한일 정상회담 참석을 위해 출국하는 날이었는데, 배웅 차 서울공항에 나온 정 대표와 긴밀하게 대화하는 장면이 언론사 카메라에 포착됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, Leader Jeong reportedly conveyed that there was significant backlash against the government proposal revealed the previous day. He explained that hardcore supporters and hardline lawmakers are demanding revisions, arguing that the government's proposal bifurcates MCIA investigators into legally-trained 'investigative judicial officers' and non-legally-trained 'professional investigators,' and leaves room for granting supplementary investigation authority to Public Prosecution Service prosecutors. (여기서 정 대표는 전날 공개된 정부안에 대한 반발이 큰 상황이라는 말을 전했다고 한다. 강성 지지층과 강경파 의원들이 정부안을 두고 중수청 수사관을 법률가인 ‘수사사법관’과 비법률가인 ‘전문수사관’으로 이원화하고, 공소청 검사에게 보완수사권을 줄 여지를 남겨뒀다며 수정을 요구하고 있다는 얘기였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, President Lee reportedly told Leader Jeong, "The prosecution's authority is being eliminated," "at this stage," "we must have mutual checks." This seemed to be a remark supporting the government's proposal, implying that all investigative authority cannot be given to the police. However, a few hours later, the President issued an instruction through a Cheong Wa Dae announcement, saying, "The party should deliberate, and the government should gather those opinions." The Prime Minister also wrote that "abolishing supplementary investigation authority is the principle," and the promotion team under the Prime Minister's Office, which created the government proposal, stated it would go through a discussion process with the party. A ruling party official said, "It seems the President also thought the backlash was larger than expected." (이에 대해 이 대통령은 정 대표에게 “검찰의 권한이 없어지는데”, “지금 단계에서는”, “상호 견제를 해야지”라고 했다. 사실상 경찰에 모든 수사 권한을 줄 수 없다는 의미로, 정부안에 힘을 싣는 듯한 발언이었다. 그러나 대통령은 몇 시간 후 청와대 공지를 통해 “당이 숙의하고 정부가 그 의견을 수렴하라”는 지시를 내렸다. 국무총리도 “보완수사권 폐지가 원칙”이라는 글을 썼고, 정부안을 만든 총리실 산하 추진단도 당과 논의 과정을 거치겠다고 했다. 여권 관계자는 “대통령도 예상과 달리 반발이 크다고 생각한 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, Leader Jeong stated in pro-government YouTube channels and party meetings regarding his conversation with the President that "it was well coordinated." He added, "There are momentarily worrying issues, but ultimately, one cannot go against the tide of the times. The President is also very well aware of this point." He then immediately announced revisions, saying, "The government proposal is a draft, and the authority and responsibility for prosecution reform lie with the National Assembly." He instructed newly appointed floor leader Han Byung-do to hold a public hearing on the 20th and even mentioned a national debate. Some members of the Legislation and Judiciary Committee appeared on channels like Kim Eo-jun's YouTube, calling the government proposal "a second Prosecutors' Office Act" and stating, "We will completely overhaul it." Mr. Kim also criticized the government proposal. In some quarters, calls for Senior Secretary Bong Wook's resignation have emerged. (이후 정 대표는 친여 유튜브, 당 회의 등에서 대통령과의 대화에 대해 “잘 조율이 됐다”고 했다. 이어 “잠시 걱정되는 일이 있지만 결국은 시대의 물결을 비켜갈 수 없다. 대통령께서도 이 점을 너무나 잘 알고 계신다”고 했다. 그러면서 “정부안은 초안이고 검찰개혁의 권한과 책임은 국회에 있다”며 곧바로 수정하겠다고 했다. 한병도 신임 원내대표에겐 오는 20일 공청회 개최 지시를 내렸고 대국민토론회까지 언급했다. 법사위 소속 일부 의원은 김어준씨 유튜브 등에 나가 “정부안은 제2의 검찰청법”이라며 “다 뜯어고치겠다”고 했다. 김씨 역시 정부안을 욕했다. 일각에선 봉욱 수석 사퇴론도 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An uncomfortable atmosphere seems to linger at Cheong Wa Dae. A ruling party official said, "Shouldn't the government proposal be seen as essentially reflecting the President's thoughts?" adding, "However, it's quite displeasing that Leader Jeong is taking the lead and pushing forward as if he persuaded the President and decided to change the law as the hardliners want." (청와대는 불편한 듯한 기류다. 여권 관계자는 “정부안은 사실상 대통령의 생각이라고 봐야 하는 것 아니냐”며 “하지만 정 대표가 앞장서서 마치 자신이 대통령을 설득하고 강경파가 원하는 대로 법을 바꾸기로 했다는 식으로 몰아가는 건 상당히 언짢다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dissatisfaction has also emerged from the Ministry of Justice, which was significantly involved in preparing the government proposal. Jo Sang-ho, a senior advisor to the Minister of Justice, said on the radio that day, "The MCIA is an organization where even investigative judicial officers do not have the right to request warrants," adding, "(Hardliners) speak as if investigative judicial officers will exercise the strong authority prosecutors had, but that's impossible." Within the government, it is said many opinions hold that Public Prosecution Service prosecutors also need supplementary investigation authority. Pro-Myeong (pro-President) lawmakers within the Democratic Party sent a message urging caution towards hardliners, stating, "Prosecution reform cannot be solved by excluding a specific group (the prosecution)." (정부안 마련에 상당 부분 개입한 법무부에서도 불만이 나온다. 조상호 법무부 장관 보좌관은 이날 라디오에 나와 “중수청은 수사사법관조차도 영장 청구권이 없는 조직”이라며 “(강경파 쪽에선) 수사 사법관이 검사가 갖고 있던 강력한 권한을 행사할 것처럼 말하지만 그건 불가능하다”고 했다. 정부 내부에선 공소청 검사의 보완수사권도 필요하다는 의견이 많다고 한다. 민주당 친명 의원들은 “검찰개혁은 특정집단(검찰) 배제로는 못 푼다”며 강경파를 향해 신중해야 한다는 메시지를 보냈다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Within the ruling party, some say it's hard to understand the party's resistance in a situation where the President's approval rating, around 60%, is pulling along the Democratic Party's rating, around 40%. Ruling party officials said, "If party-government conflict accumulates like this, we don't know when or how it might explode." Since Leader Jeong's election last August, the party and government have experienced discord over major policy issues each time, but they have managed the situation each time by saying, "We are one team," "There is no Myeong-Cheong conflict." (여권 내에선 60%안팎의 대통령 지지율이 40%안팎의 민주당 지지율을 끌고 가고 있는 상황에서 당의 반기가 이해하기 힘들다는 말도 나온다. 여권 관계자들은 “이대로 당청 갈등이 누적되면 언제 어떤 식으로 폭발할 지 모른다”고 했다. 작년 8월 정 대표 선출 이후 당청은 주요 정책 현안마다 불협화음이 일었지만 그때마다 “우리는 원팀이다” “명청 갈등은 없다”며 상황을 정리했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One pro-Myeong lawmaker said, "Regarding Leader Jeong pushing not only for a second special prosecutor but also for special prosecutors on the Unification Church and Shincheonji, Cheong Wa Dae is not exactly welcoming either," adding, "The President has his own path. Following supporters' demands might be the easiest, but that is not President Lee's path." (한 친명 의원은 “정 대표가 2차 특검에 이어 통일교·신천지 특검까지 밀어붙이는 것에 대해서도 청와대는 썩 반기는 분위기는 아니다”라며 “대통령은 대통령의 길이 있다. 지지층 요구대로 가는 게 가장 쉽겠지만 그건 이 대통령의 길은 아니다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the Jeong Cheong-rae leadership stated that they might soon pass a party constitution amendment allowing major party affairs and party policies to be decided by 'all-member vote,' potentially putting the MCIA Act and others to a vote. Chief Spokesperson Park Soo-hyun said regarding such a procedure, "All possibilities are open." (하지만 정청래 지도부는 주요 당무와 당의 정책을 ‘전당원 투표’로 정할 수 있게 한 당헌 개정안을 조만간 통과시켜 중수청법 등의 찬반 여부를 물을 수도 있다고 했다. 박수현 수석대변인은 이런 절차에 대해 “가능성은 다 열려 있다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/TQYGB4UTRRH3ZP5D3L3DRQM6MY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YRLWBYW6QJDBRK44NC7NZJ7QFA.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee: "I am a representative of the people, not of the Democratic Party... If I only care for blue, red will feel left out" (李 “난 민주당 아닌 국민 대표… 파란색만 위하면 빨간색이 섭섭”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/17/2R4NXBAJNBCT5BBC7AKAQDH3T4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Lee: "I am a representative of the people, not of the Democratic Party... If I only care for blue, red will feel left out" (李 “난 민주당 아닌 국민 대표… 파란색만 위하면 빨간색이 섭섭”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YGD4Z3SQ4ZJKTJFS3R4K4UV54I.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, President Lee Jae-myung said, "Although I served as the leader of the Democratic Party of Korea, I am now in a position where I must represent all the people," adding, "If I work only for the blue (the symbolic color of the Democratic Party), wouldn't the red (the symbolic color of the People Power Party) feel left out?" This is interpreted as an intention to pursue a line that encompasses all citizens, including opposition supporters. (이재명 대통령은 16일 “제가 더불어민주당 대표를 했지만, 이제는 전 국민을 대표해야 하는 위치에 있다”며 “파란색(민주당 상징색)을 위해서만 노력하면 빨간색(국민의힘 상징색)이 섭섭하지 않겠느냐”고 했다. 야당 지지층까지 전 국민을 포괄하는 노선을 펴겠다는 취지로 해석됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee made these remarks during a luncheon meeting with ruling and opposition party leaders held at Sangchunjae in the Blue House. He stated, "National unity is truly important in the role of the president." President Lee said, "Our people hold very diverse thoughts and positions, and the idea that we must make efforts to reflect all of them has grown stronger and stronger," adding, "Although there are diverse views on national unity, I would appreciate it if the leaders of both the ruling and opposition parties show considerable consideration and help." (이 대통령은 이날 청와대 상춘재에서 열린 여야 지도부 오찬 간담회에서 “대통령의 역할에 국민 통합이 정말로 중요하다”며 이같이 말했다. 이 대통령은 “우리 국민들은 아주 다양한 생각을 가지고 계시고 입장도 다양한데, 그분들을 전체적으로 다 반영하는 노력을 해야되겠다는 생각이 점점 더 강해졌다”며 “국민 통합에 대한 입장이 다양하긴 하지만, 여야 대표 여러분께서도 많이 배려해 주시고 도와주시면 감사하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attending the luncheon meeting were Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae, floor leader Han Byung-do; Cho Kuk Innovation Party leader Cho Kuk, floor leader Seo Wang-jin; Progressive Party leader Kim Jae-yeon, floor leader Yoon Jong-oh; Reform New Party floor leader Cheon Ha-ram; Basic Income Party leader and floor leader Yong Hye-in; and Social Democratic Party leader and floor leader Han Chang-min. The leadership of the People Power Party did not attend. (이날 오찬 간담회에는 민주당 정청래 대표, 한병도 원내대표, 조국혁신당 조국 당대표, 서왕진 원내대표, 진보당 김재연 당대표, 윤종오 원내대표, 개혁신당 천하람 원내대표, 기본소득당 용혜인 당대표 겸 원내대표, 사회민주당 한창민 당대표 겸 원내대표가 참석했다. 국민의힘 지도부는 참석하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok held a press conference on the same day and proposed a summit meeting between President Lee and the People Power Party leadership. The Blue House stated, "It is not at a stage where we are reviewing it." It is known that President Lee is coordinating a dinner meeting schedule with the ruling party leadership for next week. In response, voices within the People Power Party said, "Isn't the president just paying lip service to unity?" (송언석 국민의힘 원내대표는 이날 기자회견을 열고 이 대통령과의 국민의힘 지도부 간 영수회담을 제안했다. 청와대는 “검토하고 있는 단계는 아니다”라고 했다. 이 대통령은 다음 주중 여당 지도부와의 만찬 간담회 일정을 조율하고 있는 것으로 알려졌다. 그러자 국민의힘에선 “대통령이 말로만 통합을 외치는 것 아니냐”는 말이 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "Considering national interests or the external standing of our entire people, we should try to pool our strength together as much as possible in external relations." In the private meeting, President Lee also urged cooperation regarding the government's 'Economic Penalty Rationalization Plan,' including the mitigation of breach of trust charges. Blue House Senior Secretary for Public Communication Lee Gyu-yeon said in a briefing, "I understand that our country's economic penalties are 3-4 times higher than those in advanced countries, and (President Lee) spoke with the intention that party leaders should jointly recognize the seriousness of that part and work to improve it." (이 대통령은 “국가적 이익이나 우리 국민 전체의 대외적인 위상이나 이런 것들을 고려하면 대외적 관계에서는 가급적 함께 힘을 모아 가야 되겠다”고 했다. 이 대통령은 비공개 자리에선 배임죄 완화 등 정부가 추진하는 ‘경제 형벌 합리화 방안’에 대해서도 힘을 모아달라고 당부했다. 이규연 청와대 홍보소통수석은 브리핑에서 “우리나라가 선진국에 비해 경제 형벌이 3~4배 이상 되는 것으로 알고 있고, (이 대통령이) 그 부분에 대해 정당 지도자들이 같이 심각성을 인식하고 개선해 나가자는 취지로 말했다”고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, Democratic Party leader Jeong Cheong-rae said, "We are writing a new history of proud Korean democracy through the Candlelight Revolution (protests demanding the impeachment of former President Park Geun-hye) and the Light Revolution (protests demanding the impeachment of former President Yoon Suk-yeol)," adding, "The whole world is actually amazed by the remarkable resilience of K-democracy." He continued, "The KOSPI is racing towards 5000, and there are forecasts that 6000-7000 is possible." (이날 정청래 민주당 대표는 “우리는 촛불 혁명(박근혜 전 대통령 탄핵 요구 시위)과 빛의 혁명(윤석열 전 대통령 탄핵 요구 시위)으로 자랑스러운 대한민국의 민주주의 역사를 새로 쓰고 있는 중”이라며 “K-민주주의의 놀라운 회복력에 전 세계인이 사실 놀라고 있다”고 했다. 이어 “코스피가 5000을 향해 달려가고 있고, 6000~7000도 가능하다는 전망이 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cho Kuk Innovation Party leader Cho Kuk said, "Party members are circulating a four-character idiom, 'Myeongseongjodong' (明成祖同), which means 'The Cho Kuk Innovation Party stands together for the success of the Lee Jae-myung administration.'" Regarding the establishment of the Public Prosecution Service and the Major Crimes Investigation Service, he added, "I hope (prosecutorial reform) can be definitively concluded." (조국 조국혁신당 대표는 “당원들이 ‘명성조동’이라는 사자성어를 돌리는데, ‘이재명 정부의 성공을 위해 조국혁신당은 함께한다’는 뜻”이라고 했다. 또 공소청·중대범죄수사청(중수청) 신설과 관련, “(검찰 개혁을) 확실하게 결말지었으면 좋겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/17/2R4NXBAJNBCT5BBC7AKAQDH3T4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YGD4Z3SQ4ZJKTJFS3R4K4UV54I.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee to Hold New Year's Press Conference on the 21st... 90 Minutes at the Blue House (李대통령, 21일 신년 기자회견… 청와대서 90분간 진행)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/OO2LP6UGDZF4PEOXWWRA62NNKI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee to Hold New Year's Press Conference on the 21st... 90 Minutes at the Blue House (李대통령, 21일 신년 기자회견… 청와대서 90분간 진행)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung will hold a 'New Year's Press Conference' on the 21st. Lee Gyu-yeon, the Senior Presidential Secretary for Public Communication, announced this during a briefing on the 16th. (이재명 대통령이 21일 ‘신년 기자회견’을 개최한다. 이규연 청와대 홍보소통수석은 16일 브리핑을 통해 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This press conference, the first to be held after the presidential office moved to the Blue House, is scheduled to take place for 90 minutes at the Blue House's Yeongbingwan (State Guest House). 160 domestic and foreign journalists will attend. The slogan has been set as 'A Great Transformation Achieved Together, A Great Leap Forward Enjoyed by All'. President Lee is expected to unveil his vision for state affairs this year at the event. (대통령 집무실 청와대 이전 후 처음 열리는 이번 기자회견은 청와대 영빈관에서 90분간 진행될 예정이다. 내외신 기자 160명이 참석한다. 슬로건은 ‘함께 이루는 대전환, 모두 누리는 대도약’으로 정해졌다. 이 대통령은 이 자리에서 올해 국정 비전을 밝힐 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the format of the press conference, Senior Secretary Lee explained, "As with previous press conferences, there is no pre-arranged scenario. It will be a format of free Q&amp;A between the President and journalists." The Q&amp;A session will be divided into three areas: people's livelihoods/economy, diplomacy/security/defense, and society/culture. Notably, in the economy and culture segments, two youth-specialist YouTubers, known for their video content, will also be given the opportunity to ask questions. Senior Secretary Lee stated, "The key visual for this press conference symbolizes the light of a great transformation that will create active communication with the people." (기자회견 방식에 대해 이 수석은 “지난 기자회견과 마찬가지로 약속대련(약속된 시나리오)은 없다. 대통령과 기자 사이에 자유로운 질의응답이 오가는 방식”이라고 설명했다. 질의응답은 민생·경제, 외교·안보·국방, 사회·문화 등 세 분야로 나눠 진행된다. 특히 경제와 문화 분야에서는 영상 중심의 청년 전문 유튜버 2명에게도 질문 기회를 부여할 예정이다. 이 수석은 “이번 기자회견의 키비주얼(핵심 시각물)은 국민과의 적극적인 소통을 만들어낼 대전환의 빛을 상징한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is not President Lee's first press conference at the Blue House. His official press conferences marking 30 days and 100 days in office last year, when the presidential office was in Yongsan, were also held at the Blue House's Yeongbingwan. While presidential New Year's press conferences are typically held in early January, this one was scheduled for the third week of January due to his state visits to China (4th-7th) and Japan (13th-14th). (이번이 이 대통령의 첫 청와대 기자회견은 아니다. 대통령 집무실이 용산에 있었던 작년 취임 30일, 취임 100일 공식 기자회견은 청와대 영빈관에서 열렸다. 통상 대통령 신년 기자회견은 1월 초에 열리지만, 이번 기자회견은 중국 순방(4~7일)과 일본 순방(13~14일) 일정에 따라 1월 3주 차로 잡혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/OO2LP6UGDZF4PEOXWWRA62NNKI/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chung Cheong-rae Pushes Forward with 'One Member, One Vote' System Again (정청래, 또다시 ‘1인 1표’ 속도전)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/37AWA4UVRFAZJPNYH4B46XVYFU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Chung Cheong-rae Pushes Forward with 'One Member, One Vote' System Again (정청래, 또다시 ‘1인 1표’ 속도전)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GRTDQMDDGBRTEYRYGRRDIOLFMI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party of Korea leader Chung Cheong-rae has initiated the process to once again push for the 'one delegate, one vote / one rights-holding member, one vote' system, which was previously rejected. Within the party, his accelerated push for the one-member-one-vote system is seen as groundwork for his re-election bid in the party leadership election this August. (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 한 차례 부결됐던 ‘대의원·권리당원 1인1표제’를 다시 추진하는 절차에 들어갔다. 당내에선 정 대표의 1인1표제 속도전을 두고 올해 8월 당대표 선거에서의 연임을 위한 사전 작업으로 보고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party finalized the decision on the one-member-one-vote system during a closed-door Supreme Council meeting today. Until now, in the Democratic Party, one vote from a delegate (typically a National Assembly member) held power equivalent to about 20 votes from rights-holding party members. However, Chung, who became party leader with overwhelming support from party members, made one-member-one-vote a key pledge during last August's leadership election and held a vote on the matter last month. Although there was significant support at that time, the proposal was ultimately rejected due to failing to meet the required quorum. Chung had stated it would be "difficult to resubmit the proposal for the time being." However, it appears he is now accelerating the party constitution revision process after pro-Chung figures gained a majority on the Supreme Council following a recent by-election. The one-member-one-vote system is expected to be finalized through a two-day online vote starting on the 2nd of next month. (민주당은 이날 비공개 최고위원회의에서 1인1표제를 최종 의결했다. 그동안 민주당에선 국회의원 표인 대의원 1표가 권리당원 20표 정도의 권한을 가져왔다. 하지만 당원들의 압도적 지지로 당대표가 된 정 대표는 작년 8월 당대표 선거 때 1인1표를 핵심 공약으로 내세웠고 지난달 이에 대한 찬반 투표를 진행했다. 당시 찬성이 많이 나왔지만 정족수 미달로 1인1표제는 최종 부결됐었다. 정 대표는 “당분간 재부의하기 어렵다”고 했다. 그러나 최근 최고위원 보궐선거를 통해 최고위 내 친청 인사가 과반을 차지하자 당헌 개정에 속도를 내는 것으로 보인다. 1인 1표제는 다음 달 2일 이틀간 온라인 투표를 통해 최종 처리될 전망이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, concerns have been raised about Chung's accelerated push. Even today, opposing opinions were reportedly voiced within the party, such as "Wouldn't it be better to delay the timing of the discussion?" and "Isn't the one-member-one-vote system just for Leader Chung?" One Democratic Party lawmaker said, "During last year's leadership election, Leader Chung lost to his rival, lawmaker Park Chan-dae, in the delegate vote but was elected with overwhelming support in the party member vote. In a situation where his re-election bid this August seems certain, the one-member-one-vote system is absolutely advantageous for Leader Chung, so even Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, who is being mentioned as a potential leadership candidate, cannot help but feel burdened about running." (하지만 정 대표의 속도전에 대한 우려의 목소리가 나온다. 이날도 당내에선 “논의 시기를 늦추는 것이 어떤가” “1인 1표는 정 대표만을 위한 것 아니냐” 등의 반대 의견이 나왔다고 한다. 민주당 한 의원은 “작년 당대표 선거 때 정 대표는 대의원 투표에선 경쟁 상대인 박찬대 의원에게 졌지만 당원 투표에서 압도적 지지를 받아 당선됐다”며 “올해 8월 연임 도전이 확실시되는 상황에서 1인 1표제는 정 대표에게 절대적으로 유리한 것이라서 당대표 후보로 거론되는 김민석 총리도 출마에 부담을 느낄 수밖에 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, the Democratic Party leadership also passed a resolution to newly establish Article 6-2 of the party constitution, 'All-Member Voting System,' which will allow major party affairs and policy matters to be put to a vote by all party members. Matters decided by the Supreme Council can also be subject to such votes. A ruling party official commented, "If this happens, the voices of the hardcore supporter base, rather than National Assembly members, will determine the party's direction going forward. It's essentially handing the party over to the 'dog-daughter' supporters." (이날 민주당 지도부는 당헌 제6조의2 ‘전당원 투표제’를 신설해 당의 주요 당무 및 정책에 관한 사항을 전당원 투표에 부칠 수 있게 하는 내용도 의결했다. 최고위가 의결한 사항 등도 투표 대상이다. 여권 관계자는 “이렇게 되면 앞으로 국회의원보다 강성 지지층 목소리가 당의 방향을 결정하게 될 것”이라며 “개딸에게 당을 넘기는 셈”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/37AWA4UVRFAZJPNYH4B46XVYFU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GRTDQMDDGBRTEYRYGRRDIOLFMI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Choo Mi-ae's "Second-class Citizens, Imitation Citizens" in Gyeonggi Province... Residents Furious (추미애 “경기 2등 시민, 아류 시민”... 도민들 분노)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/WHMUWPJCDRBEVLZEZ6BRQAK5EE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Choo Mi-ae's "Second-class Citizens, Imitation Citizens" in Gyeonggi Province... Residents Furious (추미애 “경기 2등 시민, 아류 시민”... 도민들 분노)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YZTBKISB5JIZJNLOL5IMRHO3CM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;A controversy has erupted after it was belatedly revealed that Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Choo Mi-ae used expressions like "second-class citizen mentality" and "imitation citizens" regarding residents of Gyeonggi Province. While Rep. Choo has explained that her intention was "to create a first-class Gyeonggi Province," criticism is pouring in not only from the opposition party, People Power Party, but also from within the ruling Democratic Party, with remarks like "it was careless" and "it was an inappropriate expression," leading to a growing backlash. (더불어민주당 추미애 의원이 경기도 주민들에 대해 “2등 시민 의식” “아류 시민”같은 표현을 사용한 것이 뒤늦게 알려져 논란이 되고 있다. 추 의원은 “1등 경기도를 만들겠다는 취지였다”고 해명하고 있지만, 국민의힘 등 야권뿐 아니라 민주당 등 여권에서도 “경솔했다” “부적절한 표현이었다”는 지적이 나오며 후폭풍이 일고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The controversial remarks were made during an appearance on MBN's current affairs program 'Jung Woong-gap's Focused Analysis' on the 11th. (문제의 발언은 지난 11일 MBN 시사 프로그램 ‘정운갑의 집중분석’ 출연에서 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Choo Mi-ae, who chairs the Legislation and Judiciary Committee, nodded in response to the host's question about whether she would run for Gyeonggi Province governor in the June local elections, answering, "I am firmly preparing myself mentally." (법제사법위원회 위원장인 추미애 의원은 방송에서 6월 지방선거 때 경기도지사 출마 여부를 묻는 진행자의 질문에 고개를 끄덕이며 “마음의 준비는 단단히 하고 있다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Choo then said, "Until now, Gyeonggi Province has lacked its own identity," adding, "Since jobs are centered in Seoul and education is also in Seoul, there's this mentality of 'if you fall behind in competition in Seoul, you move to Gyeonggi Province'—that kind of second-class citizen mentality. Gyeonggi Province's independent identity, these issues have been very difficult to resolve." (추 의원은 그러면서 “지금까지 경기도의 정체성이 부족했다”면서 “서울 중심으로 일자리가 있고 교육도 서울이다 보니, ‘서울에서 경쟁에 뒤처지면 경기도로 이전하는구나’ 하는 그런 2등 시민 의식, 경기도의 독자적인 정체성, 이런 문제들을 참 풀기가 어려웠다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Choo continued, "When you think about the residents of Gyeonggi Province who, in terms of transportation, education, and various other issues, pay a lot in transportation costs but have to endure the worst traffic hell as it is, I think it will be easily understood." (추 의원은 이어 “교통, 교육 여러 문제에 있어서 많은 교통비를 지불하지만 가장 교통지옥을 고스란히 겪어야 하는 경기도 주민들을 생각하면 쉽게 이해되실 것 같다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She then said, "The future Gyeonggi Province should escape from being such imitation citizens, and I want to try to create a first-class Gyeonggi Province that can have its own identity, culture, education, transportation, and in terms of housing and jobs." (그러면서 “미래의 경기도는 그런 아류 시민에서 탈출하고 경기도만의 정체성, 문화·교육·교통 여러 면에서 주거·일자리 면에서 가질 수 있는 그런 1등 경기도를 한 번 만들어보고 싶다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After Rep. Choo's remarks were broadcast, various opinions flooded Gyeonggi Province mom cafes and resident online communities, such as "Are we people who were pushed out of competition in Seoul and came to Gyeonggi?" "Are we second-class citizens?" "We need to escape from being imitation citizens?" (추 의원의 이 같은 발언이 방송되자 경기도 맘카페와 주민 인터넷 커뮤니티에서는 “우리가 서울에서 경쟁하다 밀려서 경기도에 온 것이냐” “우리가 2등 시민이냐” “아류 시민에서 탈출해야 한다고?” 등 각종 의견이 쏟아졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The political sphere also reacted, calling it "a discriminatory remark against a region" and "a revival of the past 'Ibu-mangcheon' (a derogatory term for Gyeonggi Province) gaffe controversy." A Democratic Party lawmaker with a district in Gyeonggi Province said, "Even if the intention was to make Gyeonggi Province a better place to live, it was an inappropriate method of argument and a linguistic expression." (정치권에서도 “지역 차별적 발언” “과거 ‘이부망천’ 망언 논란이 다시 터졌다”는 반응이 나왔다. 경기도에 지역구를 둔 한 민주당 의원은 “경기도를 더 살기 좋게 하겠다는 취지였다고 해도 부적절한 방식의 논법이었고, 언어적 표현이었다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The People Power Party said in a spokesperson's commentary on the 14th, "For a politician aiming to become Gyeonggi governor to call the residents who supported her 'second-class citizens' is itself disqualifying," adding, "Does the Democratic Party have DNA for regional disparagement?" (국민의힘은 지난 14일 대변인 논평을 통해 “경기지사를 노린다는 정치인이 자신을 지지해준 도민에게 ‘2등 시민’ 운운하는 것 자체가 자격 미달”이라며 “민주당에는 지역 비하 DNA라도 있나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Byeong-joo (Namyangju-eul) wrote on Facebook, "Gyeonggi Province is already first-class. Now it's time for its value to be properly recognized. Gyeonggi Province is not a second choice after being pushed out of Seoul. It is neither Seoul's shadow nor an alternative." (김병주 민주당 의원(남양주을)은 페이스북에 “경기도는 이미 1등이다. 이제 그 가치를 제대로 대접받게 할 차례다. 경기도는 서울에서 밀려난 두 번째 선택지가 아니다. 서울의 그림자도, 대안도 아니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding such media reports and political criticism, Rep. Choo Mi-ae's office stated, "The intention is to change the outdated perception that views Gyeonggi Province as inferior to Seoul, and to establish Gyeonggi Province's potential and status correctly to create a 'first-class Gyeonggi Province.' It is regrettable that only some expressions are being excerpted, distorting the overall context of the remarks." (추미애 의원실 측은 이 같은 언론 보도와 정치권 지적에 대해 “경기도를 서울시보다 못하다고 보는 낡은 인식을 전환하고, 경기도의 잠재력과 위상을 바로 세워 ‘1등 경기도’를 만들겠다는 취지다. 일부 표현만을 발췌해 발언의 전체 맥락을 왜곡하는 것이다. 유감이다”는 입장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/16/WHMUWPJCDRBEVLZEZ6BRQAK5EE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/YZTBKISB5JIZJNLOL5IMRHO3CM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:56:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>[Exclusive] 40 trillion won over 4 years for integrated special cities… Support amount doubled following a single remark from the Blue House ([단독] 통합 특별시에 4년간 40조… 靑 한마디에 지원액 2배로)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/17/HTKTB7PZCRHS7EP2UQTCU4R53I/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, ahead of the June 3 local elections, the government announced that it would provide up to 5 trillion won annually for four years, totaling 40 trillion won, as incentives to the integrated special cities of Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam. It also stated it would grant them a status equivalent to that of Seoul Special City and prioritize them as target regions in the second phase of public institution relocation from the metropolitan area, set to begin next year. (정부가 6·3 지방선거를 앞두고 대전·충남, 광주·전남 특별시에 인센티브로 각각 연 최대 5조원씩 4년간 총 40조원을 주겠다고 16일 밝혔다. 또 서울특별시에 준하는 지위를 주고, 내년에 시작되는 수도권 공공기관 2차 지방 이전에서 대상 지역으로 우선적으로 고려하겠다고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea and the government held a high-level party-government meeting this morning and finalized this plan. Announcing this, Prime Minister Kim Min-seok said, "We have prepared unprecedented incentives that residents can tangibly feel." The budgets for Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam this year are 19.521 trillion won and 20.3846 trillion won, respectively. This means increasing each by about 25% starting next year. (더불어민주당과 정부는 이날 아침 고위당정협의회를 열어 이 같은 방안을 확정했다. 김민석 국무총리는 이를 발표하면서 “지역 주민이 체감할 수 있는 파격적인 인센티브를 마련했다”고 했다. 대전·충남과 광주·전남의 올해 예산은 각각 19조5210억원, 20조3846억원이다. 이를 내년부터 약 25%씩 늘려주겠다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This large-scale support is known to have been decided suddenly recently. Initially, the government reportedly explained a confidential integrated incentive plan to some ruling and opposition party lawmakers, involving support of about 1.2 trillion won annually each to Daejeon and Chungnam. However, following instructions from the Blue House, the support scale more than doubled, and Gwangju-Jeonnam is also set to receive 5 trillion won annually. However, the government failed to explain on this day how it would secure the funds for this. (이런 대규모 지원은 최근 갑자기 결정된 것으로 알려졌다. 당초 정부 측은 일부 여야 국회의원에게 대전과 충남에 각각 연 1조2000억원가량 지원하는 통합 인센티브안을 비공개로 설명했다고 한다. 그러나 청와대 지시로 지원 규모가 2배 이상으로 늘었고, 광주·전남도 연 5조원을 받게 된 것으로 알려졌다. 하지만 정부는 이날 이같은 재원을 어떻게 마련할지에 대해선 설명하지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticism emerged from the opposition, calling it "vote-buying for the election." The integration of Daejeon-Chungnam was promoted by current local government heads affiliated with the People Power Party, and it became a major issue after President Lee brought up the integration theory for the region at a town hall meeting in Cheonan, Chungnam, on the 5th of last month. Subsequently, the Democratic Party accelerated efforts, including proposing a related special law, saying, "We will make it possible to elect an integrated local government head in the June local elections." The integration of Gwangju-Jeonnam, where the Democratic Party holds all seats, also rapidly progressed. (야권에서는 “선거용 매표 행위”라는 비판이 나왔다. 대전·충남 통합은 국민의힘 소속 현 단체장들이 추진했는데, 이 대통령이 지난달 5일 충남 천안에서 열린 타운홀미팅에서 이 지역 통합론을 꺼내면서 주요 이슈로 떠올랐다. 이후 민주당은 “6월 지방선거 때 통합 단체장을 뽑을 수 있게 하겠다”며 관련 특별법 발의 등에 속도를 냈다. 민주당이 모든 의석을 가진 광주·전남 통합도 급진전됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Park Sung-hoon, chief spokesperson for the People Power Party, said, "Although they presented unprecedented support measures, upon closer look, it's a half-baked integration missing the transfer of authority and finances that local governments have demanded," and added, "We condemn the government's announcement, which is driven by hasty support plans for the election and political calculations." (국민의힘 박성훈 수석대변인은 “파격적인 지원책을 내놨다지만 내용을 뜯어보면 지방이 요구해온 권한·재정 이양은 빠진 반쪽짜리 통합”이라며 “선거를 위한 성급한 지원 방안과 정치적 계산이 앞선 정부 발표를 규탄한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;◇Government says "Support at a preferential level for integrated cities"... Plans to secure funds by cutting 10 trillion won from other budgets&lt;/b&gt; (&lt;b&gt;◇“통합시, 특혜 수준 지원“… 다른 예산 10조 줄여 재원 만든다는 정부&lt;/b&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee Jae-myung brought up administrative integration during a luncheon with ruling and opposition party leadership on the 16th and requested cooperation. President Lee said, "From the perspective of balanced regional development, if metropolitan cities are born, it can be advantageous in international competition and serve as a significant opportunity for balanced regional development, so please join forces." He also said, "We are trying to guarantee the maximum incentives." (이재명 대통령은 16일 여야 지도부와의 오찬에서 행정 통합을 꺼내며 여야 협조를 당부했다. 이 대통령은 “지역 균형 발전 측면에서 광역 도시들이 탄생하면 국제적 경쟁에서도 유리하고 지역 균형 발전에도 큰 계기가 될 수 있기 때문에 힘을 모아 달라”고 했다. “최대한의 인센티브를 보장하려고 한다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok, announcing the 40 trillion won support plan for the integrated special cities of Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam on this day, called it an "unprecedented financial plan." Regarding this, a Prime Minister's Office official said it was "support at a preferential level." The government plans to process the special bill containing this support plan before the June 3 local elections. To this end, it plans to bypass the government legislative process, which takes over three months including legislative notice, various impact assessments, and vice-ministerial and cabinet meetings review, and propose the bill in the name of a ruling party lawmaker. If this happens, the bill will pass the National Assembly plenary session within next month. (김민석 총리는 이날 대전·충남, 광주·전남 통합 특별시 40조원 지원 계획을 발표하면서 “파격적인 재정 방안”이라고 했다. 이에 대해 국무총리실 관계자는 “특혜 수준의 지원”이라고 했다. 정부는 이 지원안을 담은 특별법안을 6·3 지방선거 전에 처리할 예정이다. 이를 위해 입법 예고와 각종 영향 평가, 차관·국무회의 심의 등으로 3개월 넘게 걸리는 정부 입법 절차를 건너뛰고 법안을 여당 의원 명의로 발의할 방침이다. 이렇게 되면 이 법안은 다음 달 내 국회 본회의에서 통과된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To provide an additional 40 trillion won over four years to Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam, the government decided to create a separate subsidy in addition to the local allocation tax, which is 19.24% of the central government's domestic tax general revenue. It plans to newly create a tentatively named 'Administrative Integration Subsidy' and provide up to 5 trillion won annually each under this title. (정부는 대전·충남과 광주·전남에 4년간 40조원을 더 주기 위해, 중앙정부가 거둔 내국세 일반세 수입의 19.24%를 떼어주게 돼 있는 지방교부세와 별개의 교부세를 만들기로 했다. 가칭 ‘행정 통합 교부세’를 새로 만들어, 이 명목으로 연 최대 5조원씩을 주기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the government did not specifically explain on this day how it would secure the enormous funds. The bill disclosed by the Democratic Party also did not include this content. A government official only said, "We will arrange a separate briefing soon." (하지만 정부는 이날 막대한 재원을 어떻게 마련할지에 대해선 구체적으로 설명하지 않았다. 민주당이 공개한 법안에도 이 내용은 포함되지 않았다. 정부 관계자는 “조만간 따로 설명하는 자리를 마련할 것”이라고만 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For now, the government is known to plan to secure the funds through 'expenditure restructuring,' reducing central government expenditure by up to 10 trillion won annually. The government stated that it secured 27 trillion won through expenditure restructuring while formulating this year's budget, and from next year, it plans to save an additional 10 trillion won to give to the integrated special cities. However, even within the government, there are voices saying this is unrealistic. A ruling party official said, "Ultimately, we will end up printing more deficit bonds." (일단 정부는 재원은 중앙정부 지출을 연 최대 10조원 줄이는 ‘지출 구조조정’을 통해 마련할 계획으로 알려졌다. 정부는 올해 예산을 편성하면서 27조원을 지출 구조조정으로 마련했다고 밝혔는데, 내년부터는 10조원을 더 아껴서 통합 특별시에 주겠다는 것이다. 하지만 정부 내에서도 비현실적이라는 말이 나온다. 여권 관계자는 “결국 적자 국채를 더 찍게 될 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government also decided to grant administrative organization and civil servant personnel special provisions to the integrated special cities. Among current city and provincial governors, only the Seoul Mayor receives minister-level treatment, while the rest receive vice-minister-level treatment. Also, only Seoul City has three vice-minister-level deputy mayors, while deputy mayors/vice governors of other cities/provinces are at the 1st grade level. This is to match the level of the Ministry of the Interior and Safety, which oversees local autonomy affairs. However, for integrated special cities, it was decided to allow up to four deputy mayors, more than Seoul City, and elevate all to vice-minister level. Accordingly, integrated special city mayors will also receive de facto minister-level treatment. Key positions under the deputy mayors will also rise from the 2nd grade to the 1st grade. They will also be able to autonomously conduct organizational restructuring and the selection, appointment, and promotion of affiliated civil servants. (정부는 또 통합 특별시에 행정 조직과 공무원 인사 특례를 주기로 했다. 현재 시·도지사 가운데 서울시장만 장관급, 나머지는 차관급 예우를 받는다. 또 서울시만 차관급 부시장을 3명 두고, 나머지 시·도의 부시장·부지사는 1급이다. 지방자치 사무를 맡은 행정안전부와 격을 맞추기 위한 것이다. 그러나 통합 특별시는 부시장을 서울시보다도 많은 4명을 둘 수 있게 하고, 모두 차관급으로 격상하기로 했다. 이에 따라 통합 특별시장들도 사실상 장관급 예우를 받게 된다. 부시장 아래에 있는 핵심 보직도 2급에서 1급으로 덩달아 오른다. 직제 개편과 소속 공무원 선발·임용·승진도 자율적으로 할 수 있게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government decided to prioritize the integrated special cities as relocation target regions in the second phase of public institution relocation to local areas, which is set to be resumed next year after being halted since 2019. While it was decided to specifically determine which institutions will relocate where through future discussions, both Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam, which have competed with other regions to attract public institutions, are expected to gain an advantage in the competition. (정부는 2019년 이후 중단됐으나 내년부터 재추진되는 공공기관 지방 이전 2단계 사업에서는 통합 특별시들을 이전 대상 지역으로 우선적으로 고려하기로 했다. 구체적으로 어느 기관을 어디로 이전할지는 추후 논의를 통해 확정하기로 했지만, 공공기관 유치를 두고 다른 지역과 경쟁했던 대전·충남과 광주·전남 모두 경쟁에서 우위에 서게 될 것으로 전망된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government also decided to provide employment subsidies and education/training support funds to companies entering the integrated special cities, and to pursue reductions in land lease fees and various local tax exemptions for development projects. For investment promotion zones and cultural industry promotion zones within the integrated special cities, it decided to provide more support than for zones in other regions and simplify various administrative procedures, including development project approvals. (정부는 통합 특별시에 입주하는 기업에도 고용 보조금과 교육·훈련 지원금을 주고, 토지 임대료 감면과 각종 개발 사업에 대한 지방세 감면 제공도 추진하기로 했다. 통합 특별시 내 투자진흥지구, 문화산업진흥지구 등에 대해서는 다른 지역 지구보다 지원을 더 해주고, 개발 사업 승인을 비롯한 각종 행정 절차도 간소화하기로 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, many of the People Power Party's demands were omitted. These included exemptions for 10 years from investment reviews, preliminary feasibility studies, and feasibility studies, as well as granting authority to designate and lift greenbelt areas, permit foreigner-only casinos, and allow Uber taxis. Current local government heads affiliated with the People Power Party expressed disappointment, calling it "temporary support." Daejeon Mayor Lee Jang-woo said, "It falls short of expectations compared to the president's bold promise of authority transfer and support," and Chungnam Governor Kim Tae-heum said, "The government's support plan is insufficient compared to the 257 special provision clauses we requested." (하지만 국민의힘 요구는 상당 부분 빠졌다. 10년간 투자 심사, 예비 타당성 조사, 타당성 조사 등을 면제해 줄 것과 개발제한구역(그린벨트) 지정·해제 권한, 외국인 전용 카지노 허가 권한, 우버 택시 허용 권한을 줄 것 등이다. 국민의힘 소속 현 단체장들은 “일시적 지원”이라며 실망스럽다고 했다. 이장우 대전시장은 “대통령의 과감한 권한 이양과 지원 약속에 비해 기대에 못 미친다”고 했고, 김태흠 충남지사는”우리가 요구한 257개 특례 조항에 비해 정부의 지원안이 미흡하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Busan and Gyeongnam also expressed opposition. Although this region recently had a public deliberation committee announce an integration roadmap, it was excluded from the incentive provision. Busan said, "Administrative integration must be guaranteed by substantial fiscal decentralization and administrative decentralization," and Gyeongnam expressed concern about government-led administrative integration rather than resident-led integration. (부산·경남도 반발했다. 이 지역은 최근 공론화위원회가 통합 로드맵까지 발표했지만 인센티브 제공에서 제외됐다. 부산은 “행정 통합은 실질적 재정 분권과 사무 분권이 담보돼야 한다”고 했고, 경남은 주민 주도가 아닌 정부 주도 행정 통합에 우려를 표했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/goverment/2026/01/17/HTKTB7PZCRHS7EP2UQTCU4R53I/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MI4DEMBTGEYGKNZUGQ4TEN3EHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok's Strategy to Take Over the People Power Party by 'Bringing the 20% Hardline Conservatives to His Side' (‘20% 강성 보수를 내 편으로’ 장동혁의 국힘 접수 전략)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/EYXG562JGFBV5G2PNG5XOF7D4U/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok's Strategy to Take Over the People Power Party by 'Bringing the 20% Hardline Conservatives to His Side' (‘20% 강성 보수를 내 편으로’ 장동혁의 국힘 접수 전략)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UMZYTHRG25K37LPMFBW53WGB2M.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok began a hunger strike at the National Assembly main building on the 15th. His stated reason is to pressure the Democratic Party of Korea to accept a special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church and nomination funds. However, both inside and outside the party, there is a significant view that sees Leader Jang's hunger strike as a 'political event to resolve internal party strife'. (국민의힘 장동혁 대표는 지난 15일부터 국회 본청에서 단식 투쟁에 들어갔다. 명분은 더불어민주당에 통일교·공천 헌금 특검을 받으라는 것이다. 하지만 당 안팎에선 장 대표의 단식을 두고 ‘당 내분을 수습하기 위한 정치적 이벤트’로 보는 시각도 적지 않다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In recent various opinion polls, the People Power Party's approval rating has been stuck in the 20-30% range. Regarding this figure, opposition circles say, "A considerable portion of these are likely hardline supporters who opposed the impeachment," adding, "Leader Jang appears to have a strategy to absorb these as his own support base and completely take over the People Power Party." A People Power Party official said, "Leader Jang's side's strategy is likely not limited to this local election but is also looking ahead to the 2030 presidential election." Regarding Leader Jang's appointments since last month of anti-impeachment figures like Supreme Council member Cho Gwang-han, Policy Committee Chairman Jeong Jeom-sik, and Yeouido Research Institute Vice President Jang Ye-chan to key party positions, there is also analysis that it is a move to maintain his leadership system through any unforeseen future situations. (최근 각종 여론조사에서 국민의힘 지지율은 20~30%대 박스권에 갇혀 있다. 이 수치에 대해 야권에서는 “상당수가 탄핵을 반대한 강성 지지층일 것”이라며 “장 대표는 이를 자신의 지지층으로 흡수해 국민의힘을 완전히 접수해 나가겠다는 전략을 갖고 있는 것으로 보인다”는 말이 나온다. 국민의힘 관계자는 “장 대표 측의 전략은 이번 지방선거에 머물지 않고 2030년 대선까지 염두에 두고 있을 것”이라고 했다. 장 대표가 지난달부터 조광한 최고위원, 정점식 정책위의장, 장예찬 여의도연구원 부원장 등 반탄파를 주요 당직에 임명한 것을 두고도, 향후 어떤 돌발 상황에도 자신의 지도 체제를 유지하려는 차원이라는 분석이 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 16th, Leader Jang continued his second day of hunger strike at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall. Leader Jang hugged Reform Party floor leader Chun Ha-ram, who had just finished a filibuster on the second comprehensive special prosecutor bill, and said, "We too will fight to the end using all methods, including a hunger strike, to persuade and appeal to the public." Leader Jang's side refuted interpretations from some within the party that the hunger strike was to avoid internal backlash over the 'expulsion of former leader Han Dong-hoon,' calling them completely groundless. They stated he had expressed his intention to fast to those around him since last month. On this day, not only party leadership lawmakers but also senior lawmakers took turns keeping vigil at Leader Jang's hunger strike site. Figures mentioned as potential candidates for the local elections also visited the site. Busan Mayor Park Hyung-joon posted on Facebook, "I hope Leader Jang Dong-hyeok's hunger strike serves as a wake-up call (against the Democratic Party's legislative rampage)." (장 대표는 16일 국회 로텐더홀에서 이틀째 단식을 이어갔다. 장 대표는 2차 종합 특검법 필리버스터(무제한 토론)를 마친 개혁신당 천하람 원내대표와 포옹하고 “저희도 단식을 포함해 국민을 설득하고 호소드릴 모든 방법으로 끝까지 싸워나가겠다”고 했다. 장 대표 측은 당 일각에서 단식을 두고 ‘한동훈 전 대표 제명’에 대한 당내 반발을 피하기 위한 것이라고 해석하자 사실 무근이라고 했다. 지난달부터 주위에 단식 의사를 밝혔다는 것이다. 이날 장 대표 단식장에는 당 지도부 의원뿐 아니라 중진 의원들도 번갈아 자리를 지켰다. 지방선거 출마가 거론되는 인사도 단식장을 찾았다. 박형준 부산시장은 페이스북에 “장동혁 대표의 단식 투쟁이 (민주당의 입법 폭주에) 경종을 울리는 계기가 되길 바란다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang is known to believe that to contest the June local elections, he must strongly unite the support base that remains loose due to the impeachment and the presidential election defeat. The hunger strike is also seen as part of that strategy. A party leadership official said, "When the first trial verdict on former President Yoon's rebellion charges comes out next month, party members will be greatly shaken, and it's clear the Democratic Party will launch an offensive for the unconstitutional party dissolution. We must soothe and gather the angry sentiment of party members before that to contest the election." (장 대표는 6월 지방선거를 치르려면 탄핵과 대선 패배로 여전히 느슨해져 있는 지지층을 강하게 결속해야 한다고 보는 것으로 알려졌다. 단식 역시 그런 전략이라는 것이다. 당 지도부 관계자는 “다음 달 윤 전 대통령의 내란 혐의 1심 선고가 나오면 당원들이 크게 동요하고, 민주당은 위헌 정당 해산 공세를 펼 게 분명하다”며 “그전에 성난 당원 민심을 달래고 모아야 선거를 치르지 않겠느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the current People Power Party approval rating is stuck in the 20% range (based on telephone interview surveys). In the third week of January survey released by Gallup Korea that day, the People Power Party's approval rating was 24%, down 2 percentage points from the previous week (26%). This is 17 percentage points lower than the vote share (41.2%) recorded by People Power Party candidate Kim Moon-soo in the last presidential election. Within the party, voices are saying that with things as they are, defeat in the local elections is inevitable. There are calls particularly for a strategy targeting the traditional conservative support base. A party official said, "Isn't Leader Jang's attempt to build his own faction ultimately an intention to go to the presidential election with only the hardline supporters even after the local elections?" (하지만 현재 국민의힘 지지율은 20%대(전화 면접 조사 기준)에 갇혀 있다. 한국갤럽이 이날 발표한 1월 3주 차 조사에서 국민의힘 지지율은 24%로 전주(26%)보다 2%포인트(p) 떨어졌다. 지난 대선에서 국민의힘 김문수 후보가 기록한 득표율(41.2%)보다 17%p 낮은 수치다. 당내에서도 이대론 지방선거에서 필패한다는 목소리가 나온다. 특히 전통 보수 지지층에 대한 전략이 필요하다는 말이 나온다. 당 관계자는 “장 대표가 자기만의 세력을 구축하려는 건 결국 지방선거 이후에도 강성 지지층만을 데리고 대선까지 가겠다는 의도 아니겠냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Jang's side expects that as the election approaches in a situation of heightened political polarization, 'anti-Lee Jae-myung' sentiment will coalesce. However, concerns are also raised that "there is a precedent of the failed hunger strike strategy by then-leader Hwang Kyo-ahn in November 2019." Then-leader Hwang Kyo-ahn of the Liberty Korea Party (predecessor of the People Power Party) fasted for 8 days about four months before the general election, demanding the withdrawal of the Corruption Investigation Office for High-ranking Officials Act, but the Liberty Korea Party only won 103 seats in the April 2020 general election. (장 대표 측은 정치 양극화가 심해진 상황에서 선거가 임박하면 ‘반(反) 이재명’ 여론이 결집할 것으로 기대하고 있다. 하지만 “2019년 11월 황교안 대표 단식 전략이 실패했던 전례가 있다”는 우려도 나온다. 황교안 자유한국당(국민의힘 전신) 대표는 총선을 4개월여 앞두고 고위공직자범죄수사처법 철회 등을 주장하며 8일간 단식했지만 자유한국당은 2020년 4월 총선에서 103석에 그쳤다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/EYXG562JGFBV5G2PNG5XOF7D4U/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UMZYTHRG25K37LPMFBW53WGB2M.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Will the 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing' Not Be Held at All? (‘이혜훈 청문회’ 아예 안 열리나)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/4JDGJBNB75HBFK72IXKIZK7OKE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Will the 'Lee Hye-hoon Hearing' Not Be Held at All? (‘이혜훈 청문회’ 아예 안 열리나)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/U64G66NXQNKVTFIL3PGGIW5U44.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the National Assembly confirmation hearing for Lee Hye-hoon, the nominee for Minister of Planning and Budget, is scheduled for the 19th, suspicions surrounding the nominee are pouring in, leading to a growing sentiment even within the ruling party that this is an "inappropriate appointment." Lim Lee-ja, a People Power Party lawmaker and chairperson of the National Assembly's Strategy and Finance Committee, which is conducting the hearing, expressed on the 16th her intention to potentially refuse to hold the hearing, citing the nominee's failure to submit required documents. (이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자의 국회 인사청문회가 오는 19일 열리는 가운데, 이 후보 의혹이 쏟아지자 여당에서도 “부적절한 인사”라는 기류가 확산되고 있다. 청문회를 진행하는 국회 재정경제기획위원회 위원장인 국민의힘 임이자 의원은 16일 이 후보자의 자료 미제출을 이유로 청문회 거부 의사까지 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nominee faces allegations including abuse of power and verbal abuse by her aides during her time as a lawmaker, her eldest son's thesis and employment facilitated through 'professor dad connections,' and winning a lottery-style subscription for a 7-billion-won apartment in Seoul's Banpo-dong (One Pentas) by falsely registering her married eldest son as 'single.' Furthermore, suspicions of 'habitual fraudulent subscriptions' have been raised, alleging that even before winning the apartment subscription in July 2024, she repeatedly attempted lottery-style subscriptions in the Gangnam area while maintaining her married eldest son as a dependent. It is reported that the nominee and her spouse attempted but failed to win subscriptions for apartments such as 'DH Firstier I-Park' in Gaepo-dong and 'Raemian One Bailey' in Banpo-dong between February and May 2024. The nominee stated, "I regret the situation," and added, "I will follow the results of the investigation by state authorities." (이 후보자는 국회의원 시절 보좌진 갑질·폭언, ‘교수 아빠 찬스’를 통한 장남의 논문·취업, 결혼한 장남의 ‘위장 미혼’을 통한 70억원대 서울 반포 원펜타스 아파트 ‘로또 청약’ 당첨 등의 의혹이 제기돼 있다. 또한 이 아파트 청약에 당첨된 2024년 7월 이전에도 결혼한 장남을 부양 가족으로 유지한 채 수차례 강남권 로또 청약에 도전했다는 ‘상습 부정 청약’ 의혹도 제기됐다. 이 후보자 부부는 2024년 2~5월 개포 ‘디에이치 퍼스티어 아이파크’, 반포 ‘래미안 원베일리’ 등 청약에 도전했다가 탈락했다고 한다. 이 후보자는 “유감스럽게 생각한다”며 “국가기관 조사 결과를 따르겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been revealed that the nominee spent 198 days abroad during her four-year term as a 20th-term National Assembly member. She made 29 trips to 17 countries, including the U.S., U.K., and France, meaning she spent 13.5% of her four-year term overseas. The nominee only recently paid 2.8 million won in administrative fines (51 cases) and 30,000 won in traffic fines (1 case) accumulated over five years. (이 후보자는 20대 국회의원 4년 임기 동안 해외에서 198일을 체류한 것으로 알려졌다. 당시 미국·영국·프랑스 등 17국에 29차례 출국했는데, 4년간 13.5%를 해외에서 보낸 셈이다. 이 후보자는 최근에서야 5년간 과태료 280만원(51건), 범칙금 3만원(1건)을 납부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During her 12-year tenure as a 17th, 18th, and 20th-term National Assembly member, a total of 87 aides were appointed to her office, and 57 of them (65.5%) did not last more than one year. People Power Party lawmaker Joo Jin-woo commented, "How desperate must they have been, being driven out after just one year?" (이 후보자는 17대와 18대, 20대 국회의원으로 재직하던 12년 동안 의원실에 임면된 보좌진이 총 87명이었고, 이들 중 57명(65.5%)이 근무 기간 1년을 넘기지 못한 것으로 나타났다. 국민의힘 주진우 의원은 “1년 만에 쫓겨나면서 얼마나 막막했을까”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Notably, in her hearing response materials, the nominee spoke highly of local currency programs, which she had previously criticized. Regarding the Lee Jae-myung administration's consumption coupon policy, she called it "a priming water for economic recovery." This marks a complete reversal from her previous stance, having criticized 'expansionary fiscal policy' on multiple occasions. (특히 이 후보자는 청문회 답변 자료에서 과거 자신이 비판했던 지역 화폐 등을 높게 평가했다. 이재명 정부의 소비 쿠폰 정책에 대해 “경제 회복의 마중물”이라고 했다. 그간 ‘확장 재정’을 수차례 비판해 왔던 입장을 확 바꾼 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party of Korea lawmaker Kim Tae-nyeon said on a radio program that day, "If the explanations at the hearing are insufficient, the nominee herself should make a decision," while lawmaker Yoon Gun-young stated, "The situation has reached a point where it burdens state affairs." The Presidential Office reaffirmed its existing position, stating, "We are taking the public's concerns very seriously," and that it will monitor the hearing. (더불어민주당 김태년 의원은 이날 라디오에서 “청문회에서 소명이 안 된다면 이 후보자 스스로 결단해야 한다”고 했고, 윤건영 의원은 “국정 운영에 부담을 줄 정도의 상황이 됐다”고 말했다. 청와대는 “국민 우려를 굉장히 무겁게 인식하고 있다”며 청문회를 지켜보겠다는 기존 입장을 재확인했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/17/4JDGJBNB75HBFK72IXKIZK7OKE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/U64G66NXQNKVTFIL3PGGIW5U44.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Apologize and Resolve It" Han Dong-hoon Remains Silent Despite Party Mediation (“사과하고 풀자” 당내 중재에도 말 없는 한동훈)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/6TEOYBNLNVFZLD7UTIIQMDGMDA/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;"Apologize and Resolve It" Han Dong-hoon Remains Silent Despite Party Mediation (“사과하고 풀자” 당내 중재에도 말 없는 한동훈)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HFSTKNZXGA4WEM3FHE3GCOJZGI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid the People Power Party leadership's decision on the 15th to postpone the Ethics Committee's 'expulsion of Han Dong-hoon,' former leader Han Dong-hoon has remained silent for two days regarding whether he will apologize for the 'party member bulletin board' issue. The party member bulletin board incident involves Han's family posting articles on the People Power Party's member bulletin board that disparaged former President Yoon Suk-yeol and his wife. Among People Power Party lawmakers, voices are growing louder saying, "Former leader Han should apologize to the party members, and the expulsion should be withdrawn to end this." Opinions are divided even within the pro-Han faction. (국민의힘 지도부가 지난 15일 윤리위원회의 ‘한동훈 제명’ 결정을 보류한 가운데, 한동훈 전 대표가 ‘당원 게시판’ 문제에 대한 사과 여부에 대해 이틀째 침묵하고 있다. 당원 게시판 사건은 한 전 대표 가족이 국민의힘 당원 게시판에 윤석열 전 대통령 부부 등을 비방하는 글을 올린 사건이다. 국민의힘 의원들 사이에선 “한 전 대표가 당원에게 사과하고, 제명도 철회해 끝내자”는 목소리가 높다. 친한계 내에서 이를 두고 의견이 갈리고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the general meeting of lawmakers on the 15th, People Power Party lawmakers protested against the leadership, including leader Jang Dong-hyuk, who attempted to expel former leader Han, saying, "Expulsion is not acceptable." However, opinions also emerged that "an apology from former leader Han is also necessary." A pro-Han lawmaker reportedly said that day, while likening it to "expelling a tardy student," they also requested, "Please create a space where former leader Han can apologize." (국민의힘 의원들은 15일 의원 총회에서 한 전 대표를 제명하려 한 장동혁 지도부에 대해 “제명은 안 된다”고 반발했다. 그러면서도 “한 전 대표의 사과도 필요하다”는 의견도 나왔다. 한 친한계 의원은 그날 “지각한 학생에게 퇴학 조치를 내리는 것”이라면서도 “한 전 대표가 사과할 수 있는 공간을 마련해 달라”고 했다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In fact, some within the pro-Han faction are reportedly voicing the opinion to "apologize politically and resolve it." A pro-Han lawmaker said, "There are several pro-Han lawmakers who sympathize with the calls for an apology from both inside and outside the party." Many party elders also reportedly hold the opinion that "Leader Jang absolutely must not expel former leader Han, and former leader Han should seek a political solution through apology, not legal response." (실제 친한계 일각에선 “정치적으로 사과하고 풀자”는 의견이 나온다고 한다. 한 친한계 의원은 “당 안팎의 사과 요구에 공감하는 친한계 의원들도 몇몇 있다”고 했다. 당 원로들도 “장 대표는 한 전 대표 제명을 절대 해선 안 되고, 한 전 대표도 법적 대응이 아니라 사과를 통한 정치적 해법을 모색해야 한다”는 의견이 많다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, within the pro-Han faction, there are also many opinions that "now is not the time to apologize." They point out that the Party Affairs Audit Committee raised issues even with bulletin board posts that former leader Han did not write, and that the Ethics Committee made the decision to expel former leader Han after finalizing its conclusion while revising the disciplinary decision document twice. (반면 친한계 내부에선 “지금은 사과할 시기가 아니다”는 의견도 많다. 당무감사위원회가 한 전 대표가 쓰지 않은 게시글까지 문제 삼았고, 윤리위는 징계 결정문을 두 차례 수정하면서도 결론을 정한 상태에서 한 전 대표 제명 결정을 내렸다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A pro-Han figure said, "Only if Leader Jang states that 'there were errors in the Party Affairs Audit Committee investigation and the Ethics Committee decision,' will there be room for former leader Han to apologize." Another pro-Han lawmaker said, "Former leader Han first extended his hand by saying 'you worked hard' regarding Leader Jang's 24-hour filibuster, but didn't Leader Jang reject it?" (한 친한계 인사는 “장 대표가 ‘당무감사위 조사와 윤리위 결정에 오류가 있다’고 해야, 한 전 대표의 사과 여지도 생길 것”이라고 했다. 다른 친한계 의원은 “한 전 대표가 장 대표의 24시간 필리버스터(무제한 토론)에 ‘고생했다’고 먼저 손 내밀었는데, 장 대표가 거부하지 않았느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In contrast, a party leadership figure said, "The issue of apologizing to party members is a problem the individual should resolve; does the party have to create a platform for former leader Han to apologize?" An opposition party official said, "If both Leader Jang and former leader Han do not each take a step back, the party will plummet to the bottom." (반면, 당 지도부 인사는 “당원 사과 문제는 본인이 해결해야 할 문제인데, 당이 한 전 대표 사과 자리까지 만들어줘야 하느냐”고 했다. 야권 관계자는 “장 대표와 한 전 대표 둘 다 한 발씩 양보하지 않으면, 당은 바닥까지 추락할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/17/6TEOYBNLNVFZLD7UTIIQMDGMDA/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/HFSTKNZXGA4WEM3FHE3GCOJZGI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:56:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>