<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>조선일보 (Full Text, Bilingual)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/arc/outboundfeeds/rss/category/politics/?outputType=xml</link><description>Full-text Chosun Politics RSS feed (Bilingual)</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>ko</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:11:17 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The World Changed Overnight with the May 17 Coup (5·17 쿠데타로 하룻밤 사이 세상이 바뀌었다)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6JVOBAMFDNCNRMUCG5UFH34VEM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;The World Changed Overnight with the May 17 Coup (5·17 쿠데타로 하룻밤 사이 세상이 바뀌었다)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;As 1980 drew to a close, YS looked back on the past year. His house arrest had been ongoing for over seven months. "The world changed overnight with the unexpected coup of May 17 (the incident where the new military regime expanded the state of emergency nationwide). I was placed under house arrest. My indescribably painful days began. I had to overcome myself." (YS는 1980년 한 해가 저물면서 지난 한 해를 돌아봅니다. 가택 연금이 7개월 넘게 지속되고 있었습니다. “뜻하지 않던 5.17의 쿠데타(신군부가 비상계엄을 전국으로 확대 조치했던 사건)로 하룻밤 사이에 세상은 바뀌었다. 나는 연금되었다. 나의 말할 수 없는 고통의 나날은 시작되었다. 나 자신에게 이기는 일을 나는 해내야만 했다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although surrounded by police forces, there were occasional moments when people managed to slip through the lax security and enter his home. On December 18, Assemblyman Kim Dong-young and two female university students, after several failed attempts, came to YS's house. He expresses his feelings about the students participating in protests. "When I think of the students' demonstrations, I also have a sense of the sublime. If they are caught demonstrating, it means expulsion and prison. They might even lose their entire lives. Yet, when I think of them fighting for justice, we feel ashamed." (경찰 병력에 둘러싸인 채였지만 경비가 느슨한 순간을 뚫고 집으로 들어오는 이들도 간혹 있었습니다. 12월 18일 김동영 의원을 비롯해 여자 대학생 2명이 몇 차례 실패 끝에 YS 집으로 왔습니다. 시위에 나서는 대학생들에 대한 소감을 피력합니다. “대학생들의 데모를 생각할 때 숭고한 생각도 든다. 그들이 데모하다가 붙들리면 퇴학이며 감옥이다. 어쩌면 자기의 일생을 다 잃는 것이다. 그러나 정의를 위하여 싸우는 그들을 생각할 때 우리들은 부끄러운 일이다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;YS brought in another pair of canaries to his home. Following the munjo, parakeets, and society finches, the number increased to eight birds. Recalling an anecdote about how India's former Prime Minister Nehru kept lizards and such when he was in prison in the past, he writes: "I once read in the autobiography of India's former Prime Minister Nehru that before becoming Prime Minister, while in prison, he kept insects or lizards living in the prison on a mountainside because he had to do something. During this house arrest, I will raise birds and live as friends with them." (YS는 집에 카나리아 한 쌍을 더 들였습니다. 문조·잉꼬·십자매에 이어 여덟 마리로 늘었습니다. 인도 네루 총리가 과거 감옥에 있을 때 도마뱀 등을 길렀다는 일화를 떠올리며 적습니다. “인도의 전 네루 수상의 자서전 가운데 수상이 되기 전에 감옥에 있을 때 무엇인가 해야 하기 때문에 산비탈에 있는 감옥 안에 살고 있는 벌레나 도마뱀 등을 길렀다는 것을 읽은 적이 있다. 나는 이 연금 중에 새를 기르며 새와 더불어 벗하며 지내련다.”)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our household's bird family increased by another pair. Today, a pair of 'canaries,' known for singing well among birds, arrived. For someone like me who doesn't know much about birds, a cute, petite pair of orange-colored birds has been added. Altogether, that's four pairs, so eight birds. At first, they didn't sing, which was worrying, but now they sing so much it's almost noisy, as if the birds are competing. Raising birds is not that simple. Even today, I woke up at 6:30 AM, cleaned all the droppings from the four birdcages, laid fresh newspaper, washed the water dishes, changed the water, and gave them feed like millet and perilla seeds, and it took a full 40 minutes. And that's because I had prepared and placed the newspaper sheets to lay under the cages last night, so it took less time. Even as I write this, it's noisy. Since my wife says it smells, I'll have to clean the droppings frequently. It was a book I read 5 or 6 years ago, but I remember reading in the autobiography of India's former Prime Minister Nehru that before becoming Prime Minister, while in prison, he kept insects or 'lizards' living in the prison on a mountainside because he had to do something. During this house arrest, I will raise birds and live as friends with them. (우리집 새 식구가 한 쌍이 더 늘었다. 오늘 새 중에 잘 운다는 ‘카나리야’ 한 쌍이 들어왔다. 새에 대(対)해서 잘 모르는 나로써(*서)는 “오렌지” 색의 아담하고 자그마한 기여운(*귀여운) 새 한 쌍이 늘어났다. 모두 합처(*쳐)서 넷 쌍이니까 여덜(*여덟)마리다. 처음에는 울지 않아서 걱정이더니 이제는 시꺼(*끄)러울 정도(程度)로 새들이 경쟁하는 것처럼 울어댄다. 새를 길런다(*기른다)는 것이 그렇게 간단치 않다. 오늘도 아침 6시(時)30분(分)에 일어나 새 집 넷의 새똥을 다 치우고 새 신문지로 새로 깔아주고 물그릇을 씻고 새물을 바구고(*바꾸고) 조와 들개(*들깨) 등 모이를 주고 나니 40분(分)이나 시간(時間)이 걸였다(*걸렸다). 그것도 어제 밤에 새집 밑에 깔 신문지 종이를 마(*맞)추어서 만들어 났(*놨)기 때문에 시간(時間)이 적게 걸린 것이다. 이 글을 써고(*쓰고) 있는데도 씨꺼(*시끄)럽다. 집 사람이 냄새가 난다고 해서 자주 똥 소제를 하지 않으면 안 되겠다. 5, 6년전(年前)에 읽은 책이지마는 인도(印度)의 전(前) 네루 수상(首相)의 자서전 가운데 수상(首相)이 되기 전(前)에 감옥에 있을 때 무엇인가 해야하기 때문에 산 삣탈(*비탈)에 있는 감옥 안에 살고 있는 벌레나 “도마비암(*도마뱀)” 등(等)을 길렀다는 것을 읽은 적이 있다. 나는 이 연금 중(中)에 새를 길루며(*기르며) 새와 더불어 벗하며 지내련다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last night, Assemblyman Kim Dong-young managed to visit stealthily for the first time in a while, and today during the day, Pastor Kim Ha-jin and a female evangelist visited together. We happily talked about various church matters and the current political situation. Also during the day, somehow they managed to get in—two young female students who used to follow me, Na Seon-im and Kim Mi-hye, had tried to come several times but couldn't enter, but today they were able to come in. They came and asked, with their young hearts, how I had been and what I would do going forward. I think they are precious children. When I think of the recent university students' demonstrations, I also have a sense of the sublime. (어제 밤에는 모처럼 숨어서 김동영(金東英) 의원(議員)이 왔더니 오늘 낮에는 김(金)하진 목사(牧使)와 여(女) 전도사(傳道師)가 같이 방문(訪問)했다. 여러가지 교회(敎会) 이야기와 시국(時局) 이야기 등을 즐겁게 이야기했다. 또 낮에는 어떻게들 들어왔는지 전(前)에 나를 따르던 어린 여학생(女學生) 나선임(羅宣任)와 김미혜(金美惠)가 여러 차례 왔다가 못 들어왔는데 오늘 들어 올 수 있어서 들어왔다. 찾아와서 그동안 어떻게 지냈으며 앞으로 어떻게 할 것인가 등(等)을 어린 마음에서나마 물어본다. 귀(貴)여운 아이들이라고 생각한다. 요지음의 대학생(大學生)들의 데모를 생각할 때 숭고한 생각도 든다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If they are caught demonstrating, it means expulsion and prison. They might even lose their entire lives. Yet, when I think of them fighting for justice, we feel ashamed. I also heard from Pastor Kim Ha-jin about the sermon story of Pastor Park from Yeongnak Church. He said, 'When I came down from the North as a refugee, it was to spread the gospel, not to live a dirty life...' (그들이 데모하다가 붓들리면(*붙들리면) 퇴학(退學)이며 감옥이다. 어쩌면 자기(自己)의 일생(一生)을 다 잃는 것이다. 그러나 정의(正義)를 위하여 싸우는 그들을 생각할 때 우리들은 부꺼(*끄)러운 일이다. 영락교회(永樂敎会)의 박(朴) 목사(牧師)의 설교(說敎) 이야기도 김하진 목사(牧師)로부터 들었다. 나가(*내가) 이북에서 피난올 때 복음(福音) 전(傳)하려 내려왔지 더럽게 살아가기 위해서 내려 온 것은 아니다 라고….)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It has been exactly seven months and two days since I was placed under house arrest. With ten more days passing, the Year of the Gapsin (1980) will also be completely over. How can I define the year 1980? (내가 연금 된지가 만 7개월(個月)하고 이틀이 지났다. 1980년도(年度)도 10일(日)이 지나면 경신(庚申)도 다 지나간다. 80년도(年度) 한 해를 어떻게 규정지울(*을) 수 있을까?)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was a New Year and spring filled with glorious hope. All citizens were thinking of liberal democracy, recalling the suffering under Park Chung-hee's dictatorial system, and yearning for freedom, peace, and liberal democracy. However, the world changed overnight with the unexpected coup of May 17. I was placed under house arrest. My indescribably painful days began. As I have always thought, I had to overcome myself. I had to get through the 24 hours somehow. (영광(榮光)스러운 희망(希望)에 찬 신년(新年)과 봄이였다. 모든 국민(囗民)이 모두가 자유민주주의(自由民主主義)를 생각하며 박정희(朴正熙)의 독제(*독재) 체제(體制) 아래에서 고통받던 생각을 하며 자유(自由)와 평화(平和) 그리고 자유민주주의(自由民主主義)를 갈구했다. 그러나 뜻하지 않던 5.17의 구테타(*쿠데타)로 하로(*하루)밤 사이에 세상(世上)은 바뀌었다. 나는 연금되었다. 나의 말할 수 없는 고통의 나날은 시작(始作)되었다. 늘 생각해온 것이지만 나 자신(自身)에게 이기는 일은 나는 해내야만 했다. 나는 24시간(時間)을 어떻게던(*든)지 보내야만 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the new year of 1981, I pray to God that true peace and justice are realized for me and our people, and that a democratic society returns. Yesterday, after Seop-kwon's wedding ceremony, Hye-young's mother and Hyeon-cheol returned. This morning, a call came from Seop-kwon and his wife in Jeju Island. I pray they build a happy new life together. (1981년(年)의 새해에는 나와 우리 백성(百姓)에게 참 평화(平和)와 정의(正義)가 구현되며 민주주의(民主主義) 사회(社会)가 돌아오기를 하나님께 기도한다. 어제 섭권(燮權)이 결혼식(結婚式)을 마치고 혜영(惠英) 어머니와 현철(賢哲)이가 돌아왔다. 아침에 제주도(濟州島)에서 섭권(燮權)이와 가기로부터 전화(電話)가 왔다. 행복(幸福)한 새 생활을 꾸미기를 기도한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teacher Kang Nam-seok and Pastor Son Sang-seok have passed away. Both were over 80, so they lived a full life, but both were healthy... The world is turning so strangely that it seems they turned their backs on this chaotic world and went to heaven. How much these two must have waited for a good world, a new world. In spring, these people visited me in good health... Life, in a word, is impermanent. I can only pray for their eternal life. (강남석(姜南錫) 선생(先生) 손상석(孫相錫) 목사(牧師)가 세상(世上)을 떠나셨다. 두분 다 80이 넘었어서 살 만큼은 살았지마는 두 분 다 건강(健康)했는데…. 하도 세상(世上)이 이상하게 돌아가니까 어수선한 세상(世上)을 등지고 하늘나라로 간 것 같다. 이 두 분 다 좋은 세상(世上) 새 세상(世上)을 얼마나 기다렸겠나. 봄에도 나에게 이분들이 건강(健康)한 몸으로 다녀갔는데…. 인생(人生)이란 한마디로 무상(無常)하다. 부디 영생(永生)을 빌 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the new year, I only wish for a happy year, a peaceful year, a just year, a free year, a year where the general public and masses can live well. (새해에는 행복(幸福)한 해, 평화(平和)로운 해, 정의(正義)로운 해, 자유(自由)로운 해, 일반(一般) 국민(囗民) 대중(大衆)이 살기 좋은 해를 맞이하기를 빌 뿐이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The snow that began to fall quietly last night covered the whole world in white by morning. The white-covered snow truly blanketed the mountains, houses, trees, and the entire world in white. Going out into the yard early in the morning and walking lightly on the snow, it's not like this chaotic present world. I wish this beautiful white snow would swallow up the painful, unwanted, and unlooked-back-upon Year of the Gapsin (1980). Probably today, people with no work will go out on the streets in countless numbers to see the snow. Especially young people will go out to see the snow; although I cannot go outside to see today's spectacle, more than half the people will likely go out to see the snow. That fellow Hyeon-cheol also got excited by the snowy wind and went out since noon. Hye-suk said she wished for a White Christmas this year, and it seems it will be so. (어제 밤부터 고요히 나리기 시작(始作)한 눈은 아침에는 온 세상을 하얗게 덥었다. 하얗게 덥힌 눈은 그야말로 산(山)과 집과 나무와 모든 온 누리를 하얗게 덥었(*덮었)다. 아침 일찍이 뜰에 나가 뜰에 나가 눈 우이(*위)로 삿풋삿푼(*사뿐사뿐) 걸어(*으)니 마치 어지러운 지금 이 세상(世上) 같이(*같지) 않다. 1980년(年)의 고통스럽고 다시 생각하기 싫고 다시 돌아보기 싫은 경신년(庚申年)을 이 아름다운 하얀 눈이 집어 삼켜 갔으면 한다. 아마 오늘은 일 없는 사람들이 눈 구경하기 위하여 거리에 수(數) 없이 많이 나다닐 것이다. 특(特)(*특히) 젊은 사람들이 눈을 구경하기 위하여 나는 밖에 나기(*가)지 못하니 오늘의 강경(*관경)을 구경하지 못하지마는 반수(半數) 이상(以上)의 사람들은 눈구경하려 다닐 것이다. 현철(賢哲)이란 놈도 눈바람에 신이 나서 낮부터 나갔다. 혜숙(惠淑)이가 금년(今年)은 White Christmas가 되었으면 하더니 그렇게 될 모양이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even the dictator 'Marcos' announced that he will release about 1,400 political prisoners and abolish the military tribunals next January to lift martial law. But in our country, they create all sorts of strange laws, even merging and shutting down media outlets, and now they've made a law to control the media. For whom and why are they strengthening the dictatorship like this... (독제(*재)자(者) “마르코스”도 내년(來年) 정월(正月)에 계엄을 해제하기 위하여 정치(政治)범들을 1400명(名)이나 석방하고 계엄 군법회의(軍法會議)도 폐지한다고 발표(發表)했다. 그런데 우리나라는 온갖 이상한 법(法)을 만들고 심지어 언론(言論)을 통폐합 하더니 이제는 언론(言論)을 통제하는 법(法)까지 만들었다. 어저(*쩌)자고 누구를 위하여 이렇게 독제(*재)를 강화(强化)하는지….)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking far out the window from the inner room, the poor houses covered in white snow on the mountain slopes today, on this snowy day, come sharply into view, and the thought of them suffering in cold and poverty fills my heart completely. I even feel like going to see them and comfort them, and an even more lonely feeling comes over me. I live making friends with loneliness. (안방에서 창밖을 멀리 내다보니 산기슬기(*산기슭)에 하얀 눈에 덥힌(*덮인) 가난한 집들 오늘 눈오는날 더욱이 눈에 싹 들어오며 춥고 가난 속에서 고생한다는 생각이 마음 다 차지 한다. 흘흘(*훌훌) 가보구 싶고 위로해 주고 싶은 생각마저 들며 더욱히(*이) 고독한 생각이 던(*든)다. 고독과 함께 벗을 하며 살아간다)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6JVOBAMFDNCNRMUCG5UFH34VEM/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kim Jong Un Fires Vice Premier at Factory Inspection Site: "Get Out on Your Own Two Feet" (김정은, 공장시찰 현장서 부총리 해임 “제 발로 나가라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/20/3P2OGVHNMFFNRPRDAW73GBMUJQ/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Kim Jong Un Fires Vice Premier at Factory Inspection Site: "Get Out on Your Own Two Feet" (김정은, 공장시찰 현장서 부총리 해임 “제 발로 나가라”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UD7TKP2DJNIMLHFM5QCVMHDM7Y.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;North Korean State Affairs Commission Chairman Kim Jong Un criticized the self-preservationist attitude of Cabinet officials at a factory completion ceremony and dismissed the Vice Premier in charge of the project. (김정은 북한 국무위원장이 공장 준공식 현장에서 내각 간부들의 보신주의를 질타하면서 사업을 담당한 내각부총리를 해임했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Korean Central News Agency reported on the 20th that the completion ceremony for the first-stage renovation and modernization project of the Ryongsong Machine Complex in Hamhung City, South Hamgyong Province, was held the previous day, and that Chairman Kim gave a speech. (조선중앙통신은 20일 함경남도 함흥시의 룡성기계연합기업소 1단계 개건 현대화대상 준공식이 전날 개최됐다며 김 위원장이 연설을 했다고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un stated that the achievement was not the modernization of the complex itself, but rather "dealing a heavy blow to the chronic irresponsibility and self-preservationism" during the process. He criticized that this project, "a very important matter with significant impact on the entire national economy," had gone awry from the very first stage. (김정은은 기업소의 현대화 자체보다 그 진행 과정에서 “고질적인 무책임성과 보신주의에 된타격을 가한 것”이 성과라며 “국가경제 전반에 큰 영향을 미칠 매우 중요한 사안”인 이 사업이 첫 공정부터 어그러졌다고 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding Vice Premier Yang Sung Ho, in charge of the machine industry sector, he said, "He is a person unfit for his current position," and added, "I recommend to Comrade Premier (Pak Tae Song) that he appoint someone else in place of this Vice Premier when forming the new government." (그는 기계공업 부문을 담당한 양승호 내각 부총리에 대해 “지금의 위치에 맞지 않는 사람”이라며 “나는 이 부총리 대신 새 정부 구성 때 다른 사람을 등용할 것을 총리 동무(박태성)에게 권고한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then said, "Comrade Vice Premier, get out on your own two feet while you still can, before it's too late," and declared, "I hereby dismiss Comrade Vice Premier from his position at this site today." (그러면서 “부총리 동무는 제 발로 나갈 수 있을 때, 더 늦기 전에 제 발로 나가라”며 “나는 오늘 이 자리에서 부총리 동무를 해임시킨다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un stated that he did not view Vice Premier Yang as having "acted against the Party," but that he "attempted to deceive the Party Central with improper words and actions." (김정은은 양 부총리가 “반당을 했다고는 보지 않는다”면서도 “바르지 못한 언동으로 당중앙을 우롱하려 들었다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "It was like hitching a wagon to a goat," and asked, "Does an ox pull a wagon, or does a goat pull a wagon?" (그는 “염소에게 달구지를 메워놓았던 것과 같은 격”이라며 “황소가 달구지를 끌지 염소가 달구지를 끄나”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among North Korea's several Vice Premiers, Yang Sung Ho was responsible for the machine industry. He is a high-ranking official who served as manager of the Taean Heavy Machine Complex and Minister of Machine-Building Industry, and was also promoted to an alternate member of the Party Political Bureau. (북한의 여러 내각부총리 중 양승호는 기계공업을 담당했다. 대안중기계연합기업소 지배인, 기계공업상 등을 지내고 당 정치국 후보위원으로도 올라 있는 고위관료다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un also stated, "Although already criticized, not only the former Premier (Kim Tok Hun), but also the responsible officials in the policy guidance sector, who neglected their policy guidance duties and merely acted as spectators regarding the Ryongsong Machine Complex renovation and modernization project, should rightly feel remorse." (김정은은 “이미 비판되었지만 전 내각총리(김덕훈)는 물론이고 룡성기계연합기업소 개건 현대화 사업에 대한 정책적 지도를 태공하고 구경꾼 노릇만 해온 정책지도 부문의 책임간부들도 마땅히 가책을 받아야 한다”고도 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This suggests the possibility that former Premier Kim Tok Hun, whose activities have not been seen since the 13th Plenary Meeting of the 8th Party Central Committee last month, may have been held accountable. (지난달 제8기 13차 당 전원회의 후 활동이 보이지 않고 있는 김덕훈 전 내각 총리가 문책을 받았을 가능성이 있는 것으로 풀이된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un detailed the internal circumstances that caused the delays, stating that over 60 problems requiring correction had been raised regarding the first-stage modernization project of the Ryongsong Machine Complex. (김정은은 룡성기계연합기업소 1단계 현대화 사업이 바로잡아야 할 문제가 60여 건이나 제기됐다며 차질을 빚은 내막에 대해서도 자세히 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He also criticized that responsible Cabinet officials, even after being criticized, engaged in 'sloppy behavior' and 'clever self-preservation' by shifting responsibility back to the munitions industry sector. (내각 책임간부들은 비판을 받고도 다시 군수공업 부문에 책임을 넘기는 ‘너절한 행위’, ‘교묘한 몸사리기’를 했다고도 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un emphasized the need to "decisively root out the deeply entrenched extreme irresponsibility, self-preservationism, and hooliganism among officials," and stated, "We must target phenomena where, while putting on a show of devoting oneself to implementing Party decisions, they are actually concerned with their own safety and self-preservation and cannot shake off escapism and short-sighted attitudes, and apply ideological education and an ideological offensive." (김정은은 “일군(간부)들 속에 뿌리깊은 극심한 무책임성, 보신주의와 건달풍을 결정적으로 적출”해야 한다며 “당결정 집행에 투신한다고 생색을 내면서 실은 자기 안위와 보신에 신경을 쓰고 현실도피와 근시안적인 태도를 털어버리지 못하는 현상들에 과녁을 정하고 사상교양, 사상공세를 들이대야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kim Jong Un has publicly criticized bureaucrats' complacency and self-preservationism at various economic sites. (김정은은 여러 경제 현장에서 관료들의 무사안일주의와 보신주의 등을 공개적으로 비판해 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is also an interpretation that this measure is part of an effort to 'tighten discipline' targeting the Cabinet responsible for the economy ahead of the expected 9th Party Congress next month. (이번 조치는 다음 달로 예상되는 노동당 9차 대회를 앞두고 경제를 담당하는 내각을 상대로 ‘기강잡기’에 나선 것이라는 해석도 나온다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/north_korea/2026/01/20/3P2OGVHNMFFNRPRDAW73GBMUJQ/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/UD7TKP2DJNIMLHFM5QCVMHDM7Y.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:33:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Private drone infiltration into North Korea is an unthinkable act... There are even theories of state agency involvement" (李대통령 “민간 무인기 北 침투, 있을수 없는일...국가기관 연관설도 있어”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/7HMZK5PTZ5CE3EWD4T3RE3HVUI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;President Lee: "Private drone infiltration into North Korea is an unthinkable act... There are even theories of state agency involvement" (李대통령 “민간 무인기 北 침투, 있을수 없는일...국가기관 연관설도 있어”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PIEQDK64TRPVZBXXE7JBJOT4N4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding North Korea's recent demand for an explanation and apology, claiming a drone that took off from our side violated its airspace, President Lee Jae-myung said on the 20th, "It is an unthinkable act," adding, "We must conduct a thorough investigation and impose severe sanctions to prevent such acts from happening again." President Lee stated that if inter-Korean relations deteriorate due to such incidents, it could negatively impact the economy, and also ordered the strengthening of surveillance against drones heading towards North Korea. (이재명 대통령은 최근 북한이 우리 측에서 이륙한 무인기가 북측 영공을 침범했다며 설명과 사과를 요구한 것과 관련해 20일 “있을 수 없는 일”이라며 “철저하게 수사해서 다시는 이런 짓을 못 하게 엄중 제재해야 한다”고 말했다. 이 대통령은 이런 일로 남북 관계가 악화되면 경제에도 악영향이 생길 수 있다며, 북측으로 넘어가는 무인기에 대한 경계 강화도 주문했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Presiding over a Cabinet meeting at the Blue House that day, President Lee said, "The idea that civilians are sending drones to North Korea to conduct intelligence gathering activities is suspicious—how could civilians even conceive of such a thing? We must continue the investigation, but there are also theories that state agencies are involved." The police are currently investigating a man in his 30s suspected of manufacturing the drone that North Korea recently claimed violated its airspace. (이 대통령은 이날 청와대에서 국무회의를 주재하면서 “민간인들이 북측에 무인기를 보내서 정보 수집 활동을 한다는, 어떻게 민간인들이 이런 상상을 할 수 있는지 의심스럽다. 수사를 계속해 봐야겠지만, 국가 기관이 연관되어 있다는 설도 있다”면서 이같이 말했다. 경찰은 최근 북한이 영공을 침범했다고 주장한 무인기를 제작한 것으로 의심되는 30대 남성을 특정해 조사 중이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "It's not yet confirmed, but what has been revealed so far is that civilians arbitrarily infiltrated North Korea with a drone." He continued, "There are legal provisions to punish individuals who arbitrarily commit acts of initiating war against another country," adding, "It's the same as firing a gun (at North Korea). I don't understand how anyone could boldly do such a thing." (이 대통령은 “아직 확정된 건 아니지만, 지금까지 드러난 건 민간인들이 멋대로 북한에 무인기를 침투시켰다는 것”이라고 했다. 이어 “개인이 제멋대로 상대국에 전쟁 개시 행위를 하면 처벌하는 법조문이 있다”며 “(북한에) 총을 쏜 것이나 마찬가지다. 어떻게 이런 걸 과감하게 할 수 있는지 이해가 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee then said, "Another astonishing fact is that, despite our current state of advanced science, technology, and defense capabilities, we failed to detect a drone making multiple trips back and forth." Addressing Defense Minister Ahn Gyu-back, he asked, "Are you aware of the situation? Even with surveillance posts on duty, they couldn't detect it." (이 대통령은 그러면서 “또 한 가지 놀라운 사실은 지금 이런 최첨단 과학기술, 국방 역량이 발달한 상태에서 무인기가 몇 번씩 왔다 갔다 한 걸 체크를 못 했다는 것”이라며, 안규백 국방부 장관을 향해 “상황을 아느냐, 경계근무 하는데서 체크도 못 했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Minister Ahn replied, "We check with local air defense radar, but (the drone) reportedly appears only as a tiny dot." (이에 안 장관은 “국지방공 레이더로 체크를 하는데 (무인기는) 미세한 점만 보인다고 한다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "It appears as just a tiny dot? Anyway, it means there is some kind of loophole." He added, "During past North Korean drone infiltrations, we reportedly tracked them to some extent, so why can't we detect drones heading to North Korea?" and noted, "This leads to (North Korea) having suspicions (because detection failed)." (이 대통령은 “미세한 점 정도로 보인다? 하여간 무언가 구멍이 났다는 얘기”라고 했다. 이 대통령은 “(과거에) 북한의 무인기 침투 때도 추적은 일부 했다고 하는데, 북한으로 가는 무인기는 왜 체크를 못 하나”라며 “(체크가 안 되니까 북한에서) 의심받는 측면이 있는 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee stated, "If necessary, we must improve facilities and equipment," and asked, "If unnecessary tensions escalate and a confrontational atmosphere is created between North and South due to such incidents, wouldn't it negatively impact the economy?" President Lee urged careful management to prevent the trust relationship between North and South from being broken due to this incident and called for a swift and thorough investigation by the investigative agencies. (이 대통령은 “필요하면 시설 장비를 개선하든지 해야 한다”며 “이런 걸로 불필요하게 긴장이 고조되고 남북 간 대결 분위기가 조성되면 경제에도 악영향을 미치지 않느냐”라고 했다. 이 대통령은 이번 사태로 남북 간 신뢰 관계가 깨지지 않도록 잘 관리하고, 수사 기관에도 신속하고 철저한 수사를 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/7HMZK5PTZ5CE3EWD4T3RE3HVUI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/PIEQDK64TRPVZBXXE7JBJOT4N4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:33:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party's Young Faction Group "Supports Jang's Hunger Strike... What the Party Needs Now is Unity" (국힘 소장파 모임 “張 단식 지지… 지금 필요한 건 당 통합”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/FRHNZ5CMQ5EI3AJP4ZNWAE27ZM/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GZTDSSKLKNPJFETCI2RCJ7PKSM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, 'Alternative and Future,' a study group of the young faction within the People Power Party, stated, "We actively support Party Leader Jang Dong-hyuk's hunger strike," and added, "What the People Power Party needs now is party unity." (국민의힘 소장파 공부 모임인 ‘대안과 미래’가 20일 “장동혁 당 대표의 단식을 적극적으로 지지한다”며 “지금 국민의힘에 필요한 건 당의 통합”이라고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Lee Seong-kwon, who serves as the secretary for Alternative and Future, met with reporters after a breakfast meeting at the National Assembly Members' Office Building this morning and said, "We have resolved to join the struggle of Leader Jang, who is fighting against the reckless state administration of the Lee Jae-myung administration and the Democratic Party of Korea." (대안과 미래 간사를 맡고 있는 이성권 의원은 이날 오전 국회 의원회관에서 조찬 모임을 한 뒤 기자들과 만나 “이재명 정권과 더불어민주당의 무도한 국정 운영에 맞서 싸우는 장 대표의 투쟁에 함께하기로 결의했다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He further stated, "If the Democratic Party, as the ruling party responsible for state affairs, had even a shred of conscience and sense of responsibility, they should visit the site of the main opposition party leader's hunger strike," and added, "They must also accept the dual special prosecutor (Unification Church/primary election donations)." (그러면서 “민주당이 국정을 책임지는 여당으로서 조금의 양심과 책임감이 있다면 제1 야당 대표의 단식 현장을 찾아야 한다”며 “반드시 쌍특검(통일교·공천 헌금)도 수용해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Lee also said, "What the People Power Party needs now is party unity," and noted, "We have resolved that any words or actions that hinder party unity must cease." (이 의원은 또 “지금 국민의힘에 필요한 건 당의 통합”이라며 “당 통합을 저해하는 어떠한 언행도 중단돼야 한다는 것을 결의했다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is interpreted as criticism regarding the deepening internal conflict between factions supporting the party leadership and the pro-Han faction (supporters of Han Dong-hoon) over the recent decision by the party's Central Ethics Committee to expel former leader Han Dong-hoon. While some pro-Han lawmakers have disparaged Leader Jang's hunger strike, some hardline figures have criticized the recent apology by former leader Han regarding the so-called 'party member bulletin board' incident, saying he "only pretended to apologize." (최근 당 중앙윤리위원회의 한동훈 전 대표 제명 결정을 둘러싸고 당 지도부를 지지하는 계파와 친한계(친 한동훈)의 내분이 깊어지고 있는 데 대한 비판으로 해석됐다. 일부 친한계 의원들이 장 대표의 단식을 폄훼하는 한편 일부 강성 성향의 인사들은 최근 있었던 한 전 대표의 이른바 ‘당원 게시판’ 사건에 대한 사과를 두고 “사과하는 척만 했다”며 비판했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about 'words or actions that hinder party unity,' Rep. Lee said, "(At the breakfast meeting) we did not specifically mention whose remarks or what kind of remarks, but it is true that there have been remarks (recently) that seem to incite conflict," and explained, "Since Leader Jang is fighting with his life on the line to secure the dual special prosecutor, there should be absolutely no remarks, whether from the leadership or not, that hinder unity by bringing up other political issues." (이 의원은 ‘당 통합을 저해하는 언행’에 대한 질문에 “(조찬 모임에서) 구체적으로 누구의 어떤 발언이라고 언급한 부분은 없었지만, 갈등을 조장하는 듯한 발언이 (최근) 있었던 건 사실”이라며 “장 대표가 목숨을 걸고 쌍특검 쟁취를 위해 싸우는 상황이기 때문에 다른 정치적 현안을 갖고 지도부든 지도부가 아니든 간에 통합을 저해하는 발언이 일절 있어서는 안 된다는 뜻”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;About ten lawmakers attended the breakfast meeting today, including Ahn Cheol-soo (4th term), Kim Seong-won and Song Seok-jun (both 3rd term), Kwon Young-jin, Park Jeong-ha, Seo Beom-soo, Eom Tae-young, Lee Seong-kwon, and Choi Hyeong-du (all re-elected), and Jeong Yeon-uk, Go Dong-jin, Kim Geon, Yoo Yong-won, and Ahn Sang-hoon (all first-term). (이날 조찬 모임에는 안철수(4선), 김성원·송석준(이상 3선), 권영진·박정하·서범수·엄태영·이성권·최형두(이상 재선), 정연욱·고동진·김건·유용원·안상훈(이상 초선) 등 의원 10여 명이 참석했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/FRHNZ5CMQ5EI3AJP4ZNWAE27ZM/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GZTDSSKLKNPJFETCI2RCJ7PKSM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:06:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jang Dong-hyeok on Sixth Day of Hunger Strike for 'Dual Special Prosecutors' Says "Change Will Surely Come" (‘쌍특검’ 단식 엿새째 장동혁 “변화는 반드시 올 것”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/C72ZHVLYX5DPPML3PWBGVFWIPI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Jang Dong-hyeok on Sixth Day of Hunger Strike for 'Dual Special Prosecutors' Says "Change Will Surely Come" (‘쌍특검’ 단식 엿새째 장동혁 “변화는 반드시 올 것”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BGHVIGEA3ZIVHK2U5YTB2KM3BQ.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on the sixth day of a hunger strike demanding 'dual special prosecutors' investigations into the Unification Church and Democratic Party nomination donations, stepped outside the National Assembly for the first time since starting his fast on the 20th. He stated, "I am risking my life and even resorting to extreme measures to demand an answer from the Democratic Party of Korea," adding, "Change will surely come." (통일교·민주당 공천 헌금 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 엿새째 단식 중인 국민의힘 장동혁 대표가 20일 단식 돌입 이후 처음으로 국회 밖으로 나와 “목숨 걸고 극단적 방법까지 동원해서 더불어민주당에 답을 요구하고 있다”며 “변화는 반드시 올 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters in front of the National Assembly main building around 9:20 AM this day, Representative Jang said, "Although it's the same trees and buildings I see every day, the air reaching me after six days feels new," and made these remarks. (장 대표는 이날 오전 9시 20분쯤 국회 본관 앞에서 기자들과 만나 “매일 보던 나무와 건물이지만 6일 만에 저한테 다가오는 공기는 새로운 느낌”이라며 이같이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "Spring does not come because flowers bloom; flowers bloom because spring comes," and added, "I think many people raising their voices like this is the process of flowers blooming. That means spring is approaching." (그는 “꽃이 피기 때문에 봄이 오는 것이 아니라 봄이 오기 때문에 꽃이 피는 것”이라며 “많은 사람들이 이렇게 목소리를 내는 건 꽃을 피우는 과정이라 생각한다. 그 말은 곧 봄이 다가오고 있다는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A former judge, Representative Jang said, "Thinking back to my experience presiding over trials, we repeatedly ask the same questions to a defendant who keeps denying." He continued, "It's not to hear an answer, but because if they don't answer the same question, judges essentially consider it a confession." He then added, "Perhaps my hunger strike is also not necessarily to hear an answer from the Democratic Party," and stated, "If the Democratic Party does not answer, I consider that in itself a confession." (판사 출신인 장 대표는 “재판할 때 경험을 생각해보면 계속 부인하는 피고인에게 똑같은 질문을 반복한다”며 “답을 듣기 위해서가 아니라, 똑같은 질문에 답을 하지 않으면 사실상 판사들은 자백했다고 인정한다”고 했다. 그러면서 “제가 단식하는 것도 어쩌면 민주당의 답을 듣기 위한 것이 아닐 수도 있다”며 “민주당이 답을 하지 않으면 그 자체가 자백이라 생각한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang posted a handwritten note on his Facebook this day, writing, "Sixth day of hunger strike, the Democratic Party shows no movement. It has become even clearer now. There is corruption significant enough to shake the regime." (장 대표는 이날 페이스북에 자필로 글을 올리고 “단식 엿새째, 민주당은 미동도 없다. 이제 더욱 분명해졌다. 정권이 흔들릴 정도의 부패가 있는 것”이라고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He wrote, "The longer I endure, the stronger that conviction will become," and added, "The Democratic Party is repeating its confession even at this moment. The judgment of the people, the special prosecutor by the people, has already begun." (그는 “내가 버틸수록 그 확신은 강해질 것”이라며 “민주당은 이 순간에도 자백을 반복하고 있다. 국민의 심판은, 국민의 특검은 이미 시작됐다”고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/C72ZHVLYX5DPPML3PWBGVFWIPI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/BGHVIGEA3ZIVHK2U5YTB2KM3BQ.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:42:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democratic Party: "People Power Party's 'Refusal to Hold Lee Hye-hoon Hearing' is Outrageous Obstruction of Work" (민주당 “국힘의 ‘이혜훈 청문회 거부’, 막가파식 업무방해”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/QHBBNG57EJALRERG7QAASGU3JE/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Democratic Party: "People Power Party's 'Refusal to Hold Lee Hye-hoon Hearing' is Outrageous Obstruction of Work" (민주당 “국힘의 ‘이혜훈 청문회 거부’, 막가파식 업무방해”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/QLEVNHJBTFPGZNIXFH7RNEIU7Q.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, one day before the deadline for the National Assembly to send the personnel hearing report on candidate for Minister of Planning and Budget Lee Hye-hoon, the Democratic Party of Korea urged the People Power Party, stating, "A hearing must be reopened even today." (더불어민주당은 이혜훈 기획예산처 장관 후보자에 대한 국회의 인사청문경과보고서 송부 시한을 하루 앞둔 20일 국민의힘을 향해 “오늘이라도 청문회를 다시 열어야 한다”고 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding the failure to properly hold the candidate's personnel hearing the previous day, Floor Leader Han Byung-do stated this at a party leadership meeting held at the National Assembly, calling it "a clear dereliction of duty by the People Power Party and an infringement on the people's right to choose." (한병도 원내대표는 이날 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 전날 이 후보자의 인사청문회가 제대로 열리지 못한 것과 관련, “국민의힘의 명백한 직무 유기이자 국민 선택권 침해”라며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "(The People Power Party) first hindered the processing of people's livelihood bills with a sham filibuster, and now, by refusing the hearing, they have even abandoned the verification of public office candidates," adding, "If the submitted materials are insufficient and there are various suspicions, shouldn't they summon the candidate to the hearing venue to question and interrogate them?" (그는 “(국민의힘이) 엉터리 필리버스터로 민생법안 처리를 발목 잡더니 청문회를 거부하며 공직 후보자 검증까지 내팽개쳤다”며 “자료가 미비하고 각종 의혹이 있다면 청문회장에서 후보자를 불러 따지고 물으면 되는 것 아니냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Policy Committee Chairperson Han Jeong-ae also stated, "If there are insufficient aspects, verifying them through a hearing should come first," and said, "Not even opening the venue for verification is not only neglecting the role of the National Assembly but also depriving the people of their right to know." (한정애 정책위의장도 “미흡한 부분이 있다면 청문회를 통해 검증하는 것이 우선”이라며 “검증 자리조차 열지 않겠다는 것은 국회 역할을 방기한 것뿐 아니라 국민의 알권리도 박탈한 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Senior Deputy Floor Leader Cheon Jun-ho said, "I express strong regret over the People Power Party's outrageous obstruction of work," and added, "The people have the right to watch the hearing and judge, and the People Power Party does not have the authority to declare a candidate unqualified while depriving them of that right." (천준호 원내운영수석부대표는 “국민의힘의 막가파식 업무방해 행태에 강한 유감을 표한다”며 “국민은 청문회를 보고 판단할 권리가 있고, 국민의힘이 그 권리를 빼앗은 채 자격 미달을 선고할 권한은 없다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Although the People Power Party cites insufficient submission of materials as a reason, according to the Planning and Budget Office's tally, about 60% of the requested materials have been submitted," and stated, "Even if the submission of materials was insufficient, it cannot be grounds for unilaterally canceling the hearing schedule itself." (이어 “국민의힘이 자료 제출 미비를 이유로 들고 있지만, 예산처 집계에 따르면 자료 요구 중 60%가량이 제출됐다고 한다”며 “설령 자료 제출이 미비했더라도 청문회 일정 자체를 무단 파기할 근거는 될 수 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/QHBBNG57EJALRERG7QAASGU3JE/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/QLEVNHJBTFPGZNIXFH7RNEIU7Q.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:49:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Eon-seok: "Blue House Chief of Staff for Political Affairs Should Visit Representative Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site" (송언석 “靑 정무수석, 장동혁 대표 단식 농성장 방문해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/BAXTYT4RLZBA3H7B2ZMQPBLXBI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Song Eon-seok: "Blue House Chief of Staff for Political Affairs Should Visit Representative Jang Dong-hyeok's Hunger Strike Site" (송언석 “靑 정무수석, 장동혁 대표 단식 농성장 방문해야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OYXGUELBRFMETJJT6PS4BW54W4.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok said on the 20th, regarding newly appointed Blue House Chief of Staff for Political Affairs Hong Ik-pyo, that "His first action should be to visit the hunger strike site of People Power Party Representative Jang Dong-hyeok." (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표가 20일 홍익표 신임 청와대 정무수석을 향해 “첫 행보는 장동혁 국민의힘 대표의 단식 농성장 방문이어야 할 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song stated this during the party's morning emergency response meeting at the National Assembly in Yeouido, Seoul, saying, "I hope the new Chief of Staff for Political Affairs will seriously recognize the life-risking hunger strike struggle of the main opposition party leader, who is urging the acceptance of the dual special prosecutor laws (Unification Church/primary nomination bribery)." (송 원내대표는 이날 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 열린 원내대책회의에서 “신임 정무수석은 쌍특검법(통일교·공천 헌금) 수용을 촉구하고 있는 제1 야당 당대표의 목숨 건 단식 투쟁을 심각하게 인식하길 바란다”며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He said, "The fundamental role of the Presidential Chief of Staff for Political Affairs is to establish a communication structure between the Blue House and the ruling and opposition parties," adding, "As Chief of Staff Hong is known to be a reasonable person, I expect him to play a positive role in communication with the opposition party." (그는 “대통령 정무수석의 기본 역할은 청와대와 여야 간 소통 구조를 가지는 것”이라며 “홍 수석은 평소 합리적인 분으로 정평이 나 있는 만큼 야당과의 소통에도 긍정적인 역할을 기대한다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song and People Power Party lawmakers plan to visit the Blue House at 11 AM today to hold a rally condemning and urging the acceptance of the dual special prosecutor laws and to deliver a demand letter to the Blue House. Floor Leader Song said, "I look forward to meeting Chief of Staff Hong not only in front of the Blue House but also together at the main opposition party leader's protest site." (송 원내대표와 국민의힘 의원들은 이날 오전 11시 청와대를 찾아 쌍특검 촉구 규탄 대회를 열고 청와대에 쌍특검 수용 요구서를 전달할 예정이다. 송 원내대표는 “홍 수석을 청와대 앞에서뿐만 아니라 제1 야당 대표의 농성장에서 함께 만날 수 있게 되길 기대한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Representative Jang has been on a hunger strike for the sixth day since the 15th, demanding the Democratic Party of Korea accept a special prosecutor investigation into the Unification Church/primary nomination bribery allegations. Despite receiving medical advice the previous day that his vital signs, such as blood pressure, had dropped sharply, necessitating IV treatment and hospital transfer, Representative Jang has not stopped his hunger strike. It is reported that he is sustaining himself by drinking only water with salt. (장 대표는 지난 15일부터 더불어민주당에 통일교·공천 헌금 특검 수용을 요구하며 엿새 째 단식을 진행 중이다. 장 대표는 전날 혈압 등 바이털 수치가 급격히 떨어져 의료진으로부터 수액 치료와 병원 후송이 필요하다는 의견을 받았는데도 단식을 멈추지 않고 있다. 장 대표는 맹물에 소금만 마시며 버티고 있는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/BAXTYT4RLZBA3H7B2ZMQPBLXBI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OYXGUELBRFMETJJT6PS4BW54W4.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:53:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Up to 40 trillion won in support for integrated cities... Blue House "Forms TF for financial support to integrated local governments" (통합시에 최대 40조 지원... 靑 “통합 지방정부 재정지원 TF 구성”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/20/QS35N3URKNEBZPJ5ZSSG6SDN2E/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MZRWKOBUG43WIN3EHAYGIMJUGE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, the Blue House announced through a written briefing by spokesperson Kim Nam-jun that it has formed a 'Task Force (TF) for Financial Support to Integrated Local Governments' to discuss financial support for integrated local governments. (청와대는 20일 통합 지방정부에 대한 재정 지원을 논의하기 위해 ‘통합 지방정부 재정지원 태스크포스(TF)’를 구성했다고 김남준 대변인이 서면브리핑을 통해 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This move comes as the government has stated its policy to provide up to 5 trillion won annually for four years, totaling 40 trillion won, to integrated special cities such as Daejeon-Chungnam and Gwangju-Jeonnam, and aims to begin the practical work for this. TF leader will be Kim Yong-beom, the Blue House Policy Chief, with Ryu Deok-hyun, the Financial Planning Senior Secretary, and Lim Ki-geun, the Vice Minister of the Office for Government Policy Coordination, serving as co-chief secretaries. (정부가 대전·충남, 광주·전남 등 통합특별시에 각각 연 최대 5조원씩 4년간 총 40조원을 주겠다는 방침을 밝힌 가운데, 이를 위한 실무에 착수하겠다는 것이다. TF단장은 김용범 청와대 정책실장이 맡고, 류덕현 재정기획보좌관과 임기근 기획예산처 차관이 공동 간사를 담당한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the Blue House, Hong Ik-pyo, Senior Secretary for Political Affairs, and Ha Jun-kyung, Senior Secretary for Economic Growth, will participate. From related ministries, vice ministers from the Ministry of Economy and Finance, the Ministry of the Interior and Safety, the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, the Ministry of Trade, Industry and Energy, and the Ministry of Education will attend. (청와대에서는 홍익표 정무수석과 하준경 경제성장수석이 참여하며, 관계부처에서는 재정경제부·행정안전부·국토교통부·산업통상부·교육부 차관 등이 참석한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, plans are in place to operate a working-level TF, led by the Blue House's Financial Planning Senior Secretary and composed of director-general level officials from related ministries and administrative officers from the Blue House's senior secretaries' and secretaries' offices. Spokesperson Kim stated, "With the launch of the TF, the government will promptly hold its first meeting within January and swiftly prepare and announce detailed plans for financial support to integrated local governments." (이와 함께, 청와대 재정기획보좌관 주관으로 관계부처 국장급과 청와대 관련 수석·비서관실 행정관으로 구성된 실무TF도 함께 운영할 계획이다. 김 대변인은 “정부는 TF출범과 함께 1월 중 신속히 1차 회의를 개최하고, 통합 지방정부 재정지원 세부 방안을 속도감 있게 마련해 발표하겠다”고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/20/QS35N3URKNEBZPJ5ZSSG6SDN2E/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MZRWKOBUG43WIN3EHAYGIMJUGE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:11:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Kim Meets with KDB Chairman... "Must Lead 'Productive Finance' by Supporting High-Tech Industries" (金총리, 산은 회장 면담…“첨단산업 지원으로 ‘생산적 금융’ 선도해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6RO3J45UUBB7RJIV47XLKHZZCU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OODWQ3Y3YBO2BJMOBY5VPH6BEE.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim Min-seok met with Park Sang-jin, Chairman of the Korea Development Bank (KDB), on the morning of the 20th and urged KDB to actively implement policy finance measures to enhance Korea's growth potential. (김민석 국무총리는 20일 오전 박상진 산업은행 회장을 만나 한국의 성장 잠재력을 높이기 위해 산은이 적극적 정책 금융 정책을 펴 줄 것을 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the meeting held at the Prime Minister's Official Residence in Samcheong-dong, Jongno-gu, Seoul, Prime Minister Kim stated, "It is important for policy financial institutions like KDB to lead the financial sector's 'productive finance,' including support for high-tech and strategic industries." (김 총리는 이날 서울 종로구 삼청동 국무총리 공관에서 박 회장과 면담하고 “산은 등 정책금융기관이 첨단·전략산업 지원 등 금융권의 생산적 금융을 선도해 나가는 것이 중요하다”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He added, "The government will do its utmost to make 2026 the first year of a great economic leap forward by revitalizing investment in national strategic industries and realizing a super-innovation economy through AX (AI Transformation) and GX (Green Transformation)." (이어 “정부는 국가전략산업 투자 활성화와 AX(인공지능 대전환), GX(녹색 대전환) 등 초혁신경제 구현을 통해 2026년이 경제 대도약의 원년이 되도록 최선을 다하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Kim further noted, "To ensure the economic rebound is not limited to a 'K-shaped recovery,' support and structural innovation for regions, non-IT sectors, and vulnerable industries must also be promoted," and requested, "KDB should play a leading role in processes such as industrial restructuring to enhance industrial competitiveness and revitalizing regional finance." (김 총리는 또 “성장률 반등이 ‘K자형 반등’에 그치지 않도록 지역, 비(非)IT, 취약 산업 등에 대한 지원과 구조혁신도 촉진할 필요가 있다”며 “산은이 산업경쟁력 강화를 위한 산업구조 재편, 지역 금융 활성화 등 과정에서 주도적 역할을 해달라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A K-shaped recovery refers to a phenomenon during an economic recovery period where specific industries or groups recover while others stagnate or worsen, deepening polarization. (K자형 반등이란 경제 회복기에 특정 산업·계층 중심으로 회복하고 나머지는 침체하거나 더 악화해 양극화가 심화하는 현상을 뜻한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, Chairman Park said, "KDB will foster future strategic industries based on funds like the National Growth Fund, enhance national industrial competitiveness by supporting industrial restructuring, and further strengthen communication and cooperation with the government." (이에 박 회장은 “산은은 국민성장펀드 등을 바탕으로 미래 전략 산업을 육성하고, 산업 구조 재편 지원을 통하여 국가 산업 경쟁력을 높이며, 정부와의 소통과 협력을 더욱 강화해 나가겠다”고 답했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This meeting is the second one Prime Minister Kim has held with key figures in the economy and finance sector, following his meeting with Bank of Korea Governor Lee Chang-yong last month. An official from the Prime Minister's Office stated, "We plan to regularly arrange in-depth discussions with experts on major economic and financial issues going forward." (이번 간담회는 김 총리가 지난달 이창용 한은 총재와의 면담에 이어 경제·금융계 주요 인사와 가진 두 번째 만남이다. 총리실 관계자는 “앞으로도 주요 경제·금융 이슈에 대해 전문가들과 깊은 대화의 자리를 주기적으로 마련할 계획”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/6RO3J45UUBB7RJIV47XLKHZZCU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/OODWQ3Y3YBO2BJMOBY5VPH6BEE.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:22:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Incheon Airport CEO Lee Hak-jae: "The Blue House is Illegally Intervening in Personnel Matters... Just Fire Me Instead" (이학재 인천공항 사장 “靑, 인사 불법 개입... 차라리 나를 해임하라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/SF3K42SCIZGNLIRK5XTOO45IJI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JBTLLIN5PROJBNR7YTCXIHUTNM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, Lee Hak-jae, the CEO of Incheon International Airport Corporation (IIAC), stated, "The illegal personnel intervention by the Presidential Office in Incheon International Airport Corporation, a national key facility, has gone too far," adding, "Don't torment the working-level staff; just fire me, the CEO, instead." CEO Lee, a former three-term lawmaker of the Saenuri Party (predecessor of the People Power Party), had previously been publicly rebuked by President Lee Jae-myung during a year-end presidential briefing last year. (이학재 인천국제공항공사 사장이 20일 “국가 중추 시설인 인천국제공항공사에 대한 대통령실의 불법 인사 개입이 도를 넘고 있다”며 “실무자들을 괴롭히지 말고 차라리 사장인 저를 해임하라”고 했다. 새누리당(국민의힘 전신) 3선 의원 출신인 이 사장은 앞서 지난해 말 대통령 업무 보고에서 이재명 대통령에게 공개적으로 질타를 당했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CEO Lee held a press conference at the National Assembly in Yeouido, Seoul, this morning and revealed, "The Blue House's illegal pressure is continuing, using regular personnel appointments as a means to force the CEO's resignation, demanding the postponement of personnel actions such as promotions and position transfers until a new head of the institution takes office." (이 사장은 이날 오전 서울 여의도 국회에서 기자회견을 열고 “정기 인사를 사장 퇴진의 수단으로 삼아 승진, 보직 이동 등 인사권 행사를 신임 기관장 취임 이후로 미루라는 청와대의 불법적인 압박이 이어지고 있다”고 폭로했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He claimed, "Since mid-November last year, there has been continuous pressure through the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, citing 'the Presidential Office's intention,' to not carry out any personnel appointments until a new head of the institution arrives." According to CEO Lee, when he emphasized the inevitability of regular personnel appointments and refused to back down from implementing them, the Blue House continued its intervention by presenting guidelines such as 'only implement appointments for positions at level 3 and below,' 'switch to an acting system for vacant managerial positions,' and 'implement personnel matters only after prior reporting to and approval from the Presidential Office.' (그는 “지난해 11월 중순부터 ‘대통령실의 뜻’이라며 신임 기관장이 올 때까지 인사를 시행하지 말라는 국토부를 통한 지속적인 압력이 있었다”고 주장했다. 이 사장에 따르면 청와대는 이 사장이 정기 인사의 불가피성을 강조하며 인사 시행의 뜻을 굽히지 않자 ‘3급 이하 하위직만 시행’ ‘관리자 공석 시 직무 대행 체제 전환’ ‘인사 내용 대통령실 사전 보고 및 승인 후 시행’ 등 가이드라인을 제시하며 인사 개입을 이어 갔다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CEO Lee said, "Nevertheless, as we proceeded with necessary personnel appointments, overt displeasure was conveyed through the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport, saying 'the Presidential Office is very uncomfortable.'" He added, "By blocking the resignation of a vice president who was supposed to be appointed as the head of an overseas business corporation in Kuwait after his term ended on December 31 last year, it has caused disruptions to overseas projects, including the failure of the local corporation head's return. This is also an abuse of authority and obstruction of business." (이 사장은 “그럼에도 필요한 인사를 이어가자 ‘대통령실에서 많이 불편해한다’는 노골적인 불쾌감을 국토교통부를 통해 알려 왔다”고 했다. 또 “지난해 12월 31일 자로 퇴임 후 쿠웨이트 해외 사업 법인장으로 부임해야 할 부사장의 퇴임을 막음으로써 현지 법인장의 복귀가 무산되는 등 해외 사업에 차질이 빚어지고 있다”며 “이 또한 직권남용이고 업무방해”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CEO Lee also claimed that the corporation has been subjected to targeted audits since the controversy over the 'bookmark foreign currency smuggling search' during last year's briefing to the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport. CEO Lee said, "After the briefing, out of the blue, Presidential Chief of Staff Kang Hoon-sik ordered the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport to conduct an audit regarding the 'Incheon International Airport parking proxy service improvement plan,' and the Presidential Office spokesperson even unusually held a press briefing on it. Accordingly, the airport is currently undergoing an unprecedented specific audit for the first time in 10 years. Is the Presidential Office really that idle?" (이 사장은 지난해 국토부 업무 보고 당시 ‘책갈피 외화 밀반출 검색 논란’ 이후 공사가 표적 감사를 받고 있다고도 주장했다. 이 사장은 “업무 보고 이후 뜬금없이 강훈식 대통령 비서실장이 ‘인천국제공항 주차 대행 서비스 개선안’에 대해 국토부에 감사 지시를 내리고 이를 대통령실 대변인이 이례적으로 언론 브리핑까지 했다”며 “이에 따라 공항은 현재 10년 만에 유례없는 특정 감사를 받고 있다. 대통령실이 이토록 한가한 곳인가”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then addressed the Blue House, saying, "If you really dislike the CEO, don't torment the employees; just fire the CEO." (이어 청와대를 향해 “정말 사장이 밉다면 직원들 괴롭히지 말고 그냥 사장을 해임하라”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the press conference, when meeting with reporters regarding the possibility of running for Mayor of Incheon raised by some, CEO Lee said, "I think it's inappropriate to express any views (related to running) while serving as the incumbent CEO of Incheon Airport." CEO Lee served as a three-term lawmaker from Incheon under the Saenuri Party (predecessor of the People Power Party) and is being mentioned as a potential candidate for Mayor of Incheon in next year's June local elections. (이 사장은 기자회견 후 기자들과 만나 일각에서 제기되는 인천시장 출마 가능성에 대해 “현직 인천공항 사장으로 있는 한 (출마 관련) 견해를 밝히는 건 맞지 않는다고 생각한다”고 말했다. 이 사장은 새누리당(국민의힘 전신) 소속으로 인천에서 3선 의원을 지냈고, 내년 6월 지방선거에서 인천시장 후보로 거론된다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previously, during a briefing from the Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport and others in December, President Lee publicly reprimanded CEO Lee Hak-jae, leading to talk of 'public humiliation.' When CEO Lee explained in response to a question about whether 'smuggling $100 bills by placing them in a bookmark is possible,' saying, "We mainly search for hazardous materials" and "We work with customs," President Lee cut him off, saying, "Don't beat around the bush" and "It's really infuriating." (앞서 이 대통령은 지난 12월 국토교통부 등의 업무 보고를 받으면서 이학재 사장을 공개 질책해 ‘망신주기’라는 말이 나왔었다. ‘100달러짜리를 책갈피로 끼워 해외 밀반출이 가능하냐’는 질문에 이 사장이 “주로 유해 물질을 검색한다” “세관하고 같이한다”고 설명하자 말을 끊으며 “옆으로 새지 말라” “참 말이 기십니다”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/SF3K42SCIZGNLIRK5XTOO45IJI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/JBTLLIN5PROJBNR7YTCXIHUTNM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:35:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Second Comprehensive Special Prosecution Bill Passes Cabinet Meeting... Investigation Period Up to 170 Days (2차 종합특검법 국무회의 통과… 최장 170일 수사)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/2ZGFKZUJFZFVJNK6HZKHZAXSWY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSTSNZVGM3DEMBSMUZDQZDBGU.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second comprehensive special prosecution bill has passed the Cabinet meeting. On the 20th, a Cabinet meeting presided over by President Lee Jae-myung at the Blue House deliberated and decided on five bills for promulgation, nine legislative bills, 13 presidential decree proposals, and three general agenda items, including the second comprehensive special prosecution bill. (2차 종합특검법이 국무회의를 통과했다. 20일 이재명 대통령 주재로 청와대에서 열린 국무회의에서 2차 종합특검법을 포함한 법률공포안 5건, 법률안 9건, 대통령령안 13건, 일반안건 3건 등을 심의·의결했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investigation targets of the second comprehensive special prosecution bill are a total of 17 items, including suspicions related to the 'Roh Sang-won notebook' that were not covered in the previous three major special prosecutions. It will also investigate allegations against former President Yoon Suk-yeol, including sedition and "foreign exchange/military rebellion," as well as various suspicions surrounding election and power interference involving former President Yoon and his wife. (2차 종합특검법의 수사 대상은 앞서 3대 특검에서 다루지 못했던 ‘노상원 수첩’ 관련 의혹 등 총 17가지다. 윤석열 전 대통령의 내란 및 ‘외환·군사 반란’ 혐의, 윤 전 대통령 부부를 둘러싼 각종 선거·권력 개입 의혹 등도 수사한다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The investigation period is up to 170 days, including 20 days for preparation, and the maximum number of investigators is 251. An agenda item was also approved to expend 13,085.16 million won from the general account's contingency reserve for purposes such as maintaining the prosecution of the three major special investigations and covering activity expenses for the permanent special prosecution investigation into suspicions related to Gwanbong rights and Coupang. (수사 기간은 수사 준비 20일을 포함해 최장 170일이며, 수사 인력은 최대 251명이다. 3대 특검의 공소 유지 및 관봉권·쿠팡 의혹 상설특검 수사를 위한 활동비 등 130억8516만원을 일반회계 목적예비비에서 지출하는 내용의 안건도 의결됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/2ZGFKZUJFZFVJNK6HZKHZAXSWY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MVSTSNZVGM3DEMBSMUZDQZDBGU.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:01:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yoo Seung-min Visits Jang Dong-hyeok on Hunger Strike, Says "Must Unite to Find Path for Conservative Reconstruction" (유승민, 단식 중인 장동혁 찾아 “하나 돼서 보수 재건 길 찾아야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/KLRRRRIWWJDU3JRUJ4EEF7IKKY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;h1&gt;Yoo Seung-min Visits Jang Dong-hyeok on Hunger Strike, Says "Must Unite to Find Path for Conservative Reconstruction" (유승민, 단식 중인 장동혁 찾아 “하나 돼서 보수 재건 길 찾아야”)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/RTABTZEHUNMFHC73GTBNNSL4EQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Yoo Seung-min visited Representative Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on the sixth day of a hunger strike at the National Assembly's Rotunda Hall on the morning of the 20th, and stated, "The most sincere task the party must undertake now is to rebuild conservatism by earning the public's trust and support." (유승민 전 의원이 20일 오전 국회 로텐더홀에서 엿새째 단식 농성을 하고 있는 장동혁 대표를 찾아 “지금 당이 가장 성실하게 해야 할 일은 국민의 신뢰와 지지를 받아 보수를 재건하는 것”이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After meeting with Representative Jang, former lawmaker Yoo told reporters, "Even if we have differing views on some issues, we must put our heads together to find solutions on how to be reborn as a trustworthy conservative force for the people," adding, "Only by restoring the public's trust and support can we stand as an alternative that can halt the Lee Jae-myung administration's misgovernment and recklessness and offer hope to the people." (유 전 의원은 이날 장 대표를 찾은 뒤 기자들과 만나 “일부 문제에 있어서 서로 생각이 다르더라도 어떻게 국민이 신뢰할 수 있는 보수로 어떻게 거듭날 수 있을지 머리를 맞대고 해결책을 찾아야 한다”며 “우리가 국민의 신뢰와 지지를 회복해야 이재명 정권의 실정과 폭주를 막아내고 국민들께 희망을 드릴 수 있는 대안으로 설 수 있다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding questions about deepening internal party strife, such as the recent disciplinary issue involving former leader Han Dong-hoon, former lawmaker Yoo said, "I have been watching with regret." He stated, "Even if our methods or expressions have differed, a far more important issue is how our party can earn the public's trust and support," and added, "For the greater cause, it is time for us to put our heads together, deliberate, and find solutions, even if we have different thoughts." (유 전 의원은 최근 한동훈 전 대표 징계 문제 등으로 당 내홍이 깊어지는 것과 관련한 질문에 “계속 좀 안타깝게 지켜보고 있다”고 했다. 그는 “그간 방식이나 표현이 달랐다고 하더라도 그보다 훨씬 중요한 문제는 우리 당이 어떻게 국민들에게 신뢰와 지지를 받을 수 있느냐의 문제”라며 “큰 대의명분을 위해 우리가 서로 생각이 다르더라도 머리를 맞대고 고민하고 해결책을 찾아야 할 때”라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When asked about the possibility of running for Gyeonggi Province governor in the upcoming June 3 local elections, he responded, "I am not considering it at all," and said, "It seems inappropriate to discuss that today." (그는 오는 6·3 지방선거에서 경기지사 출마 가능성이 있냐는 질문에는 “전혀 생각하지 않고 있다”며 “오늘 그 말씀 드리는 건 적절치 않은 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/KLRRRRIWWJDU3JRUJ4EEF7IKKY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/RTABTZEHUNMFHC73GTBNNSL4EQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:33:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Jung Cheong-rae "Consensus on the Dual Structure of the Serious Crime Investigation Agency and the Issue of the 'Investigation Judicial Officer' Title"... Ruling Party's 'Prosecution Reform Public Hearing' (정청래 “중수청 이원화·수사사법관 명칭 문제 공감대”…與 ‘검찰개혁 공청회’)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/2FXTHBBYQJEZFCOEH6SGFQH2G4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NJ6SO5RSMBG3BHB5MREVKTPAJM.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amid Democratic Party of Korea leader Jung Cheong-rae stating his intention to revise the government's bill to establish the Serious Crime Investigation Agency (SCIA) and the Public Prosecution Service, arguments emerged at a public hearing held by the Democratic Party on the 20th to gather opinions, suggesting that the dual personnel structure of the SCIA and the title 'Investigation Judicial Officer' should be changed. The Democratic Party plans to hold a general meeting of lawmakers on the 22nd to further gather opinions from its members. (더불어민주당 정청래 대표가 정부의 중대범죄수사청(중수청)·공소청 설치법에 대해 수정 방침을 밝힌 가운데, 민주당이 20일 의견 수렴을 위해 개최한 공청회에선 중수청 인력의 이원화 구조와 ‘수사사법관’ 명칭을 바꿔야 한다는 주장이 나왔다. 민주당은 오는 22일 의원총회를 열어 의원들의 의견을 더 수렴할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party held a policy general meeting with a public hearing character at the National Assembly this day, attended by Yoon Chang-ryul, head of the Office for Government Policy Coordination who also leads the Prosecution Reform Promotion Team under the Prime Minister's Office. Director Yoon stated, "We are well aware that various opinions and concerns have been raised since the announcement of the legislative notice draft," and added, "We will thoroughly review the advice and diverse opinions presented at this public hearing." (민주당은 이날 국회에서 국무총리실 산하 검찰개혁추진단 단장인 윤창렬 국무조정실장 등이 참석한 가운데 대국민 공청회 성격의 정책 의원총회를 개최했다. 윤 실장은 “입법예고안 발표 이후 여러 의견도 주시고 우려도 있는 것을 잘 안다”며 “공청회에서 주시는 조언과 다양한 의견에 대해선 면밀하게 검토해 나가도록 하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the side supporting the government's proposal were Professor Choi Ho-jin of Dankook University's Department of Law, lawyer Shin In-gyu, and political commentator Kim Min-ha. On the opposing side were Professor Hwang Moon-gyu of Joongbu University's Department of Police Administration, lawyer Kim Pil-seong, and lawyer Jang Beom-sik. The three individuals on the opposing side had served as advisory committee members for the Prosecution Reform Promotion Team but resigned in opposition to the content of the government's bill. (정부안 찬성 측은 최호진 단국대 법학과 교수, 신인규 변호사, 김민하 정치평론가가 나왔고, 반대 측에선 황문규 중부대 경찰행정학과 교수와 김필성 변호사, 장범식 변호사가 나섰다. 반대 측으로 나온 세 사람은 검찰개혁추진단에서 자문위원으로 활동했으나 정부 법안 내용에 반대하며 사퇴한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;They engaged in a pros and cons debate over the SCIA's personnel structure, which is divided into Investigation Judicial Officers and Professional Investigators. Professor Choi Ho-jin, supporting the bill, said, "It is an unavoidable practical method to secure legal expertise and field investigation know-how," and added, "The bill establishes a functional cooperative relationship, not a hierarchical one. All are judicial police officers, and their authority is identical and equal." (이들은 수사사법관과 전문수사관으로 나뉘는 중수청 인력 구조를 놓고 찬반 토론을 벌였다. 찬성 측 최호진 교수는 “법률 전문성과 현장 수사 노하우를 확보하기 위한 어쩔 수 없는 실용적인 방법”이라며 “법안상 상하 관계가 아닌 기능적인 협력 관계로 설정해놨다. 모두 사법경찰관이고 권한은 모두 동일하고 대등하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, opposing Professor Hwang Moon-gyu pointed out, implying a high probability that prosecutors would take on the roles of Investigation Judicial Officers under the SCIA Act, and asked, "Why shouldn't they conduct investigations from the same (position as Professional Investigators)?" Regarding the government's proposal for the SCIA to investigate nine major crimes, Professor Hwang said, "The scope of investigation targets should be minimized." (반면 반대 측 황문규 교수는 중수청법상 수사사법관들을 검사들이 맡게 될 개연성이 크다는 취지로 지적하며 “(전문수사관과) 똑같은 (지위에서) 수사를 하면 안 되느냐”고 했다. 황 교수는 중수청이 9대 범죄를 수사하도록 한 정부안에 대해 “수사 대상을 최소한으로 정리해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding whether the government's announced reform proposal aligns with the principle of separating investigation and prosecution, Professor Choi stated, "Under the Public Prosecution Service Act, criminal investigation has been removed from the scope of prosecutors' duties," and added, "The most significant feature is that Public Prosecution Service prosecutors cannot initiate investigations." Conversely, Professor Hwang said, "Separation can only be achieved if accompanied by revisions to the Criminal Procedure Act," and expressed concern, "I worry whether the Democratic Party can actually revise the Criminal Procedure Act." (정부가 입법 예고한 개혁안이 수사와 기소의 분리라는 원칙에 부합하느냐를 두고 최 교수는 “공소청법상 검사의 직무 범위에서 범죄 수사는 삭제됐다”며 “공소청 검사가 수사 개시를 못 하는 게 가장 큰 특징”이라고 했다. 반면 황 교수는 “형사소송법 개정이 수반돼야 분리가 이뤄진다”며 “민주당이 과연 형사소송법 개정을 할 수 있을까 우려된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three-tier structure (High Public Prosecution Service, District Public Prosecution Service, Local Public Prosecution Service), similar to the existing prosecution, was also a point of contention. Professor Choi said, "I am aware there are differing opinions on whether the three-tier structure should be maintained," but added, "It is clear that an institution is needed to handle functions like appeals and re-appeals, which are currently handled by the High Prosecutors' Office." Professor Hwang pointed out, "There have been criticisms that the High Prosecutors' Office in the existing prosecution system is practically idle," and questioned, "Is it necessary to establish such a complex three-tier structure?" (기존 검찰청과 같은 대·고등·지방공소청 3단 구조도 쟁점이었다. 최 교수는 “3단 구조를 유지해야 하는지 이견이 있는 것을 안다”면서도 “고등검찰청이 담당하는 항고·재항고 등 기능을 담당할 기관이 필요한 것은 분명하다”고 했다. 황 교수는 “기존 검찰청에서 고검은 사실상 놀고먹는 것이나 다름없다는 지적이 있었다”며 “복잡한 3단 구조로 설치할 필요가 있느냐”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opinions also differed on measures to check the prosecution and police. Lawyer Shin In-gyu pointed out issues like the prosecution's non-indictment decisions, stating, "Control mechanisms are needed, such as a Citizens' Indictment Committee to oversee non-indictment decisions and increasing impeachment for fabricated indictments." Lawyer Kim Pil-seong argued, "A third-party authority is needed, such as establishing a National Investigation Commission to oversee the appropriateness of investigations and deliberate on investigation results." (검찰과 경찰에 대한 견제 방안에 대한 의견도 오갔다. 신인규 변호사는 검찰의 불기소 문제 등을 지적하며 “시민기소위원회 등으로 불기소 결정을 통제하고, 조작기소 등에 대해서는 탄핵을 늘리는 등의 견제 장치가 필요하다”고 했다. 김필성 변호사는 “국가수사위원회 등을 설치해 수사 적정성을 감찰하고, 수사 결과를 심의하는 등 제3의 권한 기구가 필요하다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Democratic Party leader Jung Cheong-rae concluded the discussion, stating, "It seems there is some problem with the dual investigation structure of the SCIA, and it appears both sides reached a consensus that using the title 'Investigation Judicial Officer' is prone to misunderstanding." (민주당 정청래 대표는 토론을 마치고 “중수청의 수사 이원화는 좀 문제가 있는 것 같다, 수사사법관의 명칭을 사용하는 것은 오해의 소지가 있다는 부분은 양측에서 공감대를 이룬 것 같다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/2FXTHBBYQJEZFCOEH6SGFQH2G4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/NJ6SO5RSMBG3BHB5MREVKTPAJM.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:50:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee Presents Letter of Appreciation to Ruling Party's Han Jun-ho for 'Special Envoy to Bolivia' Role (李 대통령, ‘볼리비아 특사’ 與 한준호에 감사패 수여)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/2YP3FYV23FD3DL2PQWBCIIXHFI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/QIVFN4AF6ZKT5OHDNMARUO7NUE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ruling Democratic Party lawmaker Han Jun-ho announced on the 20th that he received a letter of appreciation from President Lee Jae-myung in recognition of his contribution to elevating bilateral relations by being dispatched as a special envoy to Bolivia. (더불어민주당 한준호 의원은 20일 볼리비아 특사 파견을 통해 양국 관계를 격상시킨 공로를 인정받아 이재명 대통령으로부터 감사패를 받았다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Han attended the inauguration ceremony of Bolivia's new President Rodrigo Paz in November last year in his capacity as a special envoy of the President and delivered a presidential letter. (한 의원은 작년 11월 로드리고 파스 볼리비아 신임 대통령 취임식에 이 대통령 특사 자격으로 참석해 대통령 친서를 전달했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During a meeting with Bolivia's new Vice President Edmundo Lara at the time, Lawmaker Han requested visa-free entry for South Korean nationals to expand bilateral exchanges, stating, "For the future expansion of resource diplomacy, the entry procedures for our companies or related personnel into Bolivia should be simplified." Bolivia was effectively the only major South American country that required South Korean nationals to obtain a visa for visits. (한 의원은 당시 에드만 라라 볼리비아 신임 부통령과 면담에서 “향후 자원 외교 확대를 위해 우리 기업이나 관계자들의 볼리비아 입국 절차가 간소화돼야 한다”며 양국 간 교류 확대를 위한 대한민국 국민의 입국 비자 면제를 요청했다. 볼리비아는 남미 주요국 중 우리 국민이 방문할 때 비자를 발급받아야 하는 사실상 유일한 국가였다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response, the Bolivian government announced in December last year that it would allow visa-free entry for nationals of eight countries, including South Korea. (이에 볼리비아 정부는 작년 12월 우리나라를 포함한 8개국에 대한 무비자 입국을 허용한다고 발표했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the letter of appreciation, President Lee told Lawmaker Han, "You have greatly contributed to the development of relations between South Korea and Bolivia, as well as to securing visa-free entry and safety for our nationals in Bolivia," adding, "I commend your dedicated efforts for national interest and public convenience." (이 대통령은 감사패를 통해 한 의원에게 “귀하는 대한민국과 볼리비아의 관계 발전과 더불어 우리 국민의 볼리비아 무사증(무비자) 입국 및 안전 확보에 크게 기여했다”며 “국익과 국민 편익을 위해 헌신한 노고를 치하한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lawmaker Han said, "Our citizens can now visit Bolivia more freely and conveniently," and added, "I expect not only people-to-people exchanges between the two countries but also economic cooperation to become even more active." (한 의원은 “우리 국민들이 보다 자유롭고 편리하게 볼리비아를 방문할 수 있게 됐다”며 “양국의 인적 교류는 물론 경제 협력 또한 한층 활성화될 것으로 기대된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/assembly/2026/01/20/2YP3FYV23FD3DL2PQWBCIIXHFI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/QIVFN4AF6ZKT5OHDNMARUO7NUE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:25:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Lee: "Sanitary pads are too expensive... Review providing them for free" (李대통령 “생리대 너무 비싸... 무상 공급 검토하라”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/20/4YIQDWRXJVHC5AZMBRBWSHQFSU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA4DCNLEMEYGGZBTGE3WGOJTHE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, President Lee Jae-myung, noting that domestic sanitary pad prices are higher than those overseas, said, "Please review commissioning production and providing them for free." (이재명 대통령은 20일 국내 생리대 가격이 해외보다 비싸다며 “아예 위탁생산해서 무상 공급하는 것을 검토해 달라”고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At a Cabinet meeting held at the Blue House main office that day, President Lee stated, "It seems to be true that sanitary pads in our country are 40% more expensive compared to overseas. Shouldn't we also make and sell cheap ones so that poor people can use them?" (이 대통령은 이날 청와대 본관에서 열린 국무회의에서 “생리대는 우리나라가 40% 해외 대비 비싼 게 사실인가 본데, 싼 것도 만들어서 팔아야 가난한 사람도 쓸 것 아니냐”며 이같이 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "They claim (sanitary pads) are expensive because they are high-end," and added, "Then why aren't they producing cheap ones? People should use ones that have good basic quality." (이 대통령은 “(생리대가) 고급화해서 비싸다고 주장한다면서요”라며 “(그렇다면) 싼 건 왜 생산을 안 하나. 기본적인 품질을 잘 갖춘 것을 써야한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He continued, "Right now, the burden is too great, and if the government provides support, it's like, to put it bluntly, just giving money to those who are overcharging," and said, "I'm thinking of researching how to produce very basic, necessary, quality sanitary pads cheaply and provide them for free." (이어 “지금은 너무 부담이 크고, 정부에서 지원해주면 속된 말로 바가지를 씌우는 데 돈만 주는 꼴”이라며 “아주 기본적인, 필요한, 품질을 갖춘 생리대를 싸게 만들어서 무상 공급하는 것을 연구해 볼 생각”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee has been interested in sanitary pad support projects for low-income groups since his time as Mayor of Seongnam. When he was Gyeonggi Province Governor, he supported the purchase costs of sanitary pads for all female adolescents in the province, and during the presidential election, he pledged to expand this nationwide. (이 대통령은 성남시장 시절부터 저소득층을 위한 생리대 지원 사업에 관심을 가져왔다. 경기지사 땐 도내 모든 여성 청소년들에게 생리대 구입 비용을 지원했고, 대선 땐 이를 전국적으로 확대하겠다는 공약을 내세웠다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Targeting some public institutions, President Lee instructed, "Even though the President pointed it out, there are places that still show the same attitude when the minister receives reports again," adding, "For such places, tell them to impose whatever sanctions they can." (이 대통령은 일부 공공기관을 겨냥해선 “대통령이 지적했는데도 여전히 장관이 다시 보고받을 때 똑같은 태도를 보이는 곳이 있더라”며 “이런 데는 할 수 있는 제재를 좀 하도록 하라”고 지시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;President Lee said, "I won't say where, but they need to be sternly reprimanded," and added, "Don't public institutions have larger execution budgets than the government? But they shouldn't act like that. They need to get their act together and do well." (이 대통령은 “어디라고 말은 안 하겠지만, 좀 엄히 훈계해야 한다”며 “공공기관이 정부보다 집행예산이 많다는 것 아니냐. 그런데 그렇게 하면 안 된다. 정신 차리고 잘해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding President Lee's remarks, some interpret them as targeting Incheon International Airport Corporation President Lee Hak-jae. Previously, President Lee Hak-jae was publicly rebuked during a work report to President Lee last year, and subsequently, during a Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport work report on the 14th, he was again criticized for needing an attitude of listening to issues raised.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARA&gt;&gt;&gt; (이 대통령의 발언을 두고 일각에서는 이학재 인천공항공사 사장을 겨냥한 것 아니냐는 해석이 나온다. 앞서 지난해 이 대통령 업무보고에서 공개적으로 질타당했던 이 사장은 이후 지난 14일 국토교통부 업무보고에서도 문제 제기를 경청하는 태도가 필요하다는 질책을 받았었다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/blue_house/2026/01/20/4YIQDWRXJVHC5AZMBRBWSHQFSU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GA4DCNLEMEYGGZBTGE3WGOJTHE.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:51:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cho Hyun to Visit Türkiye to Discuss Follow-up Measures from Summit... Also Visiting Belgium (조현, 튀르키예 찾아 정상회담 후속조치 논의... 벨기에도 방문 )</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/20/4RJ5MCA52NEA3CGTEU6R6GPCOU/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MUVLDQUY65LR7MAV6LSPPFQU4Y.JPG" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Minister Cho Hyun will visit Türkiye and Belgium from the 21st to the 24th, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced. (조현 외교부 장관은 오는 21∼24일 튀르키예와 벨기에를 방문한다고 외교부가 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 21st, Minister Cho will hold a meeting with Foreign Minister Hakan Fidan in Türkiye. At a regular briefing on the 20th, Deputy Spokesperson Lee Moon-bae stated, "This meeting is part of the follow-up measures to our President's state visit to Türkiye in November 2025, and is planned to review the progress of key outcome projects such as nuclear power plants, defense industry, bio, and infrastructure." (조 장관은 21일 튀르키예에서 하칸 피단 외교장관과 회담을 진행한다. 이문배 부대변인은 20일 정례브리핑에서 “이번 회담은 2025년 11월 우리 대통령의 튀르키예 국빈 방문 후속 조치의 일환으로, 원전·방산·바이오·인프라 등 주요 성과 사업의 진행 상황을 점검할 계획”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Cho will travel to Belgium on the 22nd to hold the second ROK-EU Foreign Ministers' Strategic Dialogue with EU High Representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy Kaja Kallas. This is the second strategic dialogue, following the first one held in Seoul in November 2024. (조 장관은 22일 벨기에로 이동, 카야 칼라스 유럽연합(EU) 외교안보 고위대표와 제2차 한-EU 외교장관 전략대화를 개최한다. 2024년 11월 서울에서 열린 제1차 대화에 이은 두 번째 전략대화다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The two sides are expected to discuss the overall ROK-EU relationship, including high-level exchanges, and exchange views on major regional situations such as the Korean Peninsula and Ukraine. Discussions on the Greenland issue, which has recently emerged as a major topic in Europe, may also take place. (양측은 고위급 교류를 포함한 한-EU 관계 전반을 논의하고, 한반도와 우크라이나 등 주요 지역 정세에 대해서도 의견을 교환할 예정이다. 최근 유럽 지역 최대 이슈로 부상한 그린란드 문제에 대한 논의도 있을 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minister Cho is scheduled to meet with Belgian Deputy Prime Minister and Minister of Employment, Economy, and Agriculture David Clarinval on the 23rd. (조 장관은 23일 다비드 클라린발 벨기에 부총리 겸 고용·경제·농업 장관과 면담을 가질 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this meeting, they plan to discuss ways to strengthen cooperation in various fields such as economy and culture, including high-level exchanges between the two countries commemorating the 125th anniversary of diplomatic relations this year. (이 자리에서는 올해 수교 125주년을 기념하는 양국 간 고위급 교류를 비롯해 경제·문화 등 다양한 분야의 협력 강화 방안을 논의할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/diplomacy-defense/2026/01/20/4RJ5MCA52NEA3CGTEU6R6GPCOU/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/MUVLDQUY65LR7MAV6LSPPFQU4Y.JPG" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:16:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Good if fasting Jang Dong-hyeok dies" Controversy over former DP lawmaker Kim Hyung-joo's outrageous remarks… PPP says "mocking life" (“단식 장동혁 죽으면 좋고” 與 김형주 전 의원 막말 논란… 국힘 “생명 조롱”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/ADVQJIPYN5DEPHG2J4X7GAZ7YI/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5SF6V4UIVDPBILDQVCAAF2MOI.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Controversy is brewing after former Democratic Party lawmaker Kim Hyung-joo made remarks such as "it would be good if he dies" targeting People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok, who is on his sixth day of fasting. (김형주 전 더불어민주당 의원이 엿새째 단식 중인 장동혁 국민의힘 대표를 향해 “죽으면 좋다” 등의 발언을 해 논란이 일고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to political circles on the 20th, the former lawmaker appeared on a YouTube channel the previous day and commented on PPP leader Jang's hunger strike, which demands the acceptance of the so-called 'dual special prosecutor' probes into the Unification Church and nomination donations. He said, "He picked a bad time to fast," and added, "He's pretending to be dead so people won't criticize him after he messed with Han Dong-hoon and then felt awkward. And he acts as if he's a martyr." (20일 정치권에 따르면, 전 의원은 전날 한 유튜브 채널에 출연해 장 대표가 통일교와 공천 헌금 등 이른바 ‘쌍특검’ 수용을 요구하며 단식 투쟁을 하고 있는 것과 관련, “나쁜 단식 타이밍을 잡았다”며 “자기가 한동훈 쳐놓고 난 다음에 머쓱하니까 자기에게 욕하지 말라고 죽은 척하는 거다. 그러면서 마치 자기가 순교자인 양한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regarding some arguments that former PPP leader Han Dong-hoon should visit the fasting site to encourage Leader Jang, he said, "It's still too early for former leader Han to go to the fasting site," and "Even if he goes, he still can't manage his facial expressions." (한동훈 전 국민의힘 대표가 단식장을 방문해서 장 대표를 격려해야 한다는 일각의 주장에 대해서는 “한 전 대표가 단식장에 가는 것은 아직 때가 이르다”며 “가더라도 아직 표정 관리가 안 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Former lawmaker Kim said, "(The place to meet an opponent experiencing conflict) is only for rotten politicians to go," and added, "They go and act as if they are truly reconciled, but Han Dong-hoon hasn't reached that stage yet." (김 전 의원은 “(갈등을 겪고 있는 상대를 만나는 자리는) 썩은 정치인들만이 갈 수 있다”며 “가서 마치 정말 화해된 것처럼 표현하는데 한동훈은 아직 그 단계까지 못 나갔다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He then said, "Former leader Han doesn't need to go to the fasting site. Let him fast to the end, eat salt, get dehydrated, almost pass out, get taken to the hospital, and then (he should go)," and added, "It would be good if he dies. When he wakes up there, if someone says 'give him a hand,' then he can go at that time." (그러면서 “한 전 대표가 단식장에 갈 필요가 없고 끝까지 단식하게 해서 소금 먹고 물 빠져서 거의 기절초풍하고 병원에 실려 가고 난 다음에 (가야 한다)”라며 “죽으면 좋고. 거기서 깨어났을 때 손 좀 잡아주쇼 하면 그때 가면 된다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the host said, 'Leader Jang is still full of energy,' former lawmaker Kim said, "What is he supposed to talk about when he has nothing to say?" and added, "During this period, (former leader Han) could get criticized again for doing his own politics. 'I wish Jang Dong-hyeok would die. That's why I'm not going.' That's more honest." (진행자가 ‘아직은 장 대표가 팔팔하다’고 하자 김 전 의원은 “할 말도 없는데 가서 무슨 이야기를 하란 말이냐”며 “이 기간에 자기 정치한다고 (한 전 대표가) 또 욕먹을 수 있다. ‘나는 장동혁이 죽었으면 좋겠다. 그래서 난 안 간다’ 이게 더 솔직한 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;PPP spokesperson Lee Chung-hyeong said in a commentary that day, "The Democratic Party's political culture has already exceeded a dangerous level from the perspective of ordinary citizens' common sense," and added, "Democratic Party leader Chung Cheong-rae has already mocked and disparaged Jang Dong-hyeok's fast as a 'fasting tantrum' and a 'fasting show.' Now, the Democratic Party's political culture, which even brings the word 'death' to its lips, is causing humanitarian issues beyond political stances." He said, "It is a mockery and challenge to life and humanity, beyond simple hatred for the opposition party." (이충형 국민의힘 대변인은 이날 논평을 통해 “민주당의 정치 문화는 이미 일반 국민의 양식으로 보기에 위험 수위를 넘어섰다”며 “정청래 민주당 대표가 이미 장동혁 대표의 단식에 대해 ‘단식 투정’ ‘단식 쇼’라고 조롱하고 폄훼한 바 있다. 이제는 죽음이라는 단어까지 입에 올리는 민주당의 정치 문화는 정치적 입장을 넘어 인도적인 문제까지 낳고 있다”고 했다. 그는 “야당에 대한 단순한 혐오를 넘어 생명과 인륜에 대한 조롱과 도전”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spokesperson Lee said, "It is said that President Lee Jae-myung invited the Democratic Party leadership to the presidential office for a dinner and burst into laughter," and added, "Neither the President nor the Democratic Party has even made a single courtesy visit to the opposition leader's fasting site. Before politics, they should not lose the minimum dignity and basic human decency." (이 대변인은 “이재명 대통령은 민주당 지도부를 청와대로 초청해 만찬을 벌이며 폭소를 터뜨렸다고 한다”며 “대통령이나 민주당은 야당 대표의 단식 현장에 의례적인 위로 방문조차 한 번 하지 않고 있다. 정치 이전에, 최소한의 품격과 인간적인 금도는 잃지 말아야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/ADVQJIPYN5DEPHG2J4X7GAZ7YI/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/M5SF6V4UIVDPBILDQVCAAF2MOI.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:26:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Jun-seok Bolsters Jang Dong-hyeok, Says "No Reason to Doubt His Sincerity" (장동혁에 힘 실어준 이준석 “진정성 의심할 이유가 없다”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/JGIJYS6SIJGULCZQIBNPAHC7BY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3GKNJUMFSTOYLEGY3WCMJQGQ.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reform Party leader Lee Jun-seok said on the 20th, "Having completed my parliamentary diplomacy schedule, I am returning home and turning my attention back to domestic politics. Upon my return, I will visit People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyeok to discuss ways to further strengthen opposition cooperation." (개혁신당 이준석 대표가 20일 “의회 외교 일정을 마치고 귀국길에 올라 다시 국내 정치로 시선을 돌린다. 귀국하는 대로 국민의힘 장동혁 대표를 찾아 야권의 추가적인 공조 강화 방안을 논의하겠다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Originally scheduled to return on the 23rd, Leader Lee is now set to return early on the 21st and visit the site of Leader Jang's hunger strike. Leader Lee's itinerary included stops in Mexico and Guatemala before visiting the US and returning, but it is reported he canceled the US leg. Leader Jang is continuing his hunger strike for the sixth day, demanding a 'twin special prosecutor' investigation into allegations of the Democratic Party of Korea's nomination slush funds and the Unification Church's lobbying of politicians. However, it is reported that a joint hunger strike with Leader Jang, who declared an indefinite fast, is not currently under consideration. (당초 23일 귀국 예정이었던 이 대표는 21일 조기 귀국해 장 대표 당식장을 찾을 예정이다. 이 대표는 멕시코와 과테말라를 거쳐 미국을 들렀다 귀국하는 일정이었는데 미국 일정은 취소했다고 한다. 장 대표는 더불어민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 엿새째 단식을 이어가고 있다. 다만, 무기한 단식을 선언한 장 대표와의 공동 단식은 현재로선 검토하지 않는 것으로 전해졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On Facebook that day, Leader Lee said, "These are heavy times. When someone resorts to extreme measures, it is to demonstrate their sincerity through physical hardship," adding, "There is no reason to doubt the sincerity of Leader Jang's push for the passage of the special prosecutor bill." (이 대표는 이날 페이스북에서 “무거운 시절이다. 누군가가 극단적인 수단에 의존할 때, 그것은 육신의 고달픔으로 자신의 진정성을 드러내 보이려는 것”이라며 “장 대표의 특검 통과를 향한 진정성에 어떤 의심을 할 이유가 없다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leader Lee stated, "Under the heavy political situation created by Leader Jang, all figures in the political world must ponder whether each and every word they utter is a step towards restoring order in the Republic of Korea," and "They should contemplate how to fight effectively, rather than making insensitive complaints to cover up their own faults." (이 대표는 “장 대표가 만든 무거운 정국 아래에서 정치권의 모든 인사는 자신의 말 한마디, 한마디가 대한민국의 질서를 바로 세우기 위한 한발짝인지 고민해야 할 것”이라며 “자신의 과오를 덮기 위한 눈치 없는 투정보다는 어떻게 효율적으로 투쟁할지를 고민해야 할 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Leader Lee said, "The opposition must restore public trust with its clear-cut weapons," adding, "If it remains true to its fundamental role as the opposition, a path to prevent (the government and ruling party's) one-sided dominance will surely open." (그러면서 이 대표는 “야당은 야당의 선명한 무기로 국민께 신뢰를 회복해야 한다”며 “야당 본연에 충실하다면 (정부·여당의) 독주를 막을 길은 반드시 열릴 것”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/JGIJYS6SIJGULCZQIBNPAHC7BY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/GU3GKNJUMFSTOYLEGY3WCMJQGQ.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:00:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>"Tricked by the promise of $2,000 for two weeks' work at a Vietnamese hotel, I was sold and trafficked among Southeast Asian crime syndicates" (“베트남 호텔서 2주 일하면 2000달러 준다는 말에 속아 동남아 범죄조직에 팔려다녀”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/L3L5L5J3SBBFZKQ7T4VBWLOOCY/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VJ6MPFM3KROLVAPTQFTZPHGEHY.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 20th, the National Intelligence Service (NIS) disclosed detailed information on specific damage cases, including the actual recorded phone call between a rescued victim, Mr. A, who was tricked by a 'high-income' overseas job scam and captured by a Southeast Asian crime syndicate, and his mother. (국가정보원은 20일 ‘고수익’ 해외취업 사기에 속아 동남아 범죄조직에 붙잡혀있다 구출된 A씨와 A씨 어머니의 실제 통화 녹취를 비롯해 구체적 피해 사례를 자세히 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the NIS, Mr. A (25) received a job offer via Telegram from someone he met there, promising "$2,000 in cash for staying about two weeks at a hotel in Vietnam," and he departed for Ho Chi Minh City. However, upon arriving in Vietnam, Mr. A had his passport and mobile phone confiscated by a crime syndicate and was subsequently sold and trafficked among various criminal organizations, moving between Vietnam and Cambodia. (국정원에 따르면 A(25)씨는 텔레그램으로 알게 된 사람으로부터 “베트남에 있는 호텔에 2주 정도만 있으면 현금으로 2000달러를 주겠다”는 취업 제안을 받고 호치민으로 출국했다. 하지만 A씨는 베트남에 도착하자마자 범죄조직에게 여권과 휴대폰을 빼앗긴 채 여러 범죄조직에 팔려다니며 베트남과 캄보디아를 전전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mr. A reportedly resisted the crime syndicate but was forced into a life of confinement due to threats that "if it becomes known you crossed the border illegally, you will be arrested by local police." Mr. A was sold and moved from Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam → Poipet, Cambodia → Phnom Penh, Cambodia → Moc Bai, Vietnam, and finally to a scam compound in Mondulkiri Province, Cambodia, which borders Vietnam. The final scam compound in Mondulkiri Province, Cambodia, where Mr. A was held, is described as a remote jungle area bordering Vietnam, making escape impossible without external help. Mr. A was coerced into participating in criminal activities with promises like "if you work well for six months, we'll send you home," and he told investigators, "I witnessed one Korean in the scam compound being beaten with a stun gun and a club for poor performance, which caused severe psychological pressure." (A씨는 범죄조직에 저항하기도 했으나 “불법 월경했다는 사실이 알려지면 현지 경찰에 체포된다”는 협박에 감금 생활을 할 수 밖에 없었다고 한다. A씨는 베트남 호치민 → 캄보디아 포이펫 → 캄보디아 프놈펜 → 베트남 목바이를 거쳐 베트남과 접경한 캄보디아 몬돌끼리 주 스캠단지까지 팔려갔다. A씨가 최종 감금된 캄보디아 몬돌끼리 주 스캠 단지는 베트남과 국경이 맞닿은 오지로, 타인의 도움 없이는 탈출이 불가능한 밀림지대라고 한다. A씨는 “6개월 동안 일을 잘하면 집에 보내주겠다”며 범죄 가담을 강요받았고 “스캠 단지에 있던 한국인 중 1명이 실적이 저조하다는 이유로 전기충격기와 몽둥이로 맞는 것을 목격하고 심리적 압박이 심했다”고 수사 기관에 진술했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on a report call last month on the 17th from his mother residing in Korea, stating her son was held captive by a crime syndicate, the NIS rescued Mr. A, who was confined in a scam compound located in Mondulkiri Province, Cambodia, through location tracking and other means, and apprehended 26 Korean members of the organization. (국정원은 지난달 17일 아들이 범죄조직에 감금되어있다는 국내 거주 어머니의 신고전화를 토대로 위치추적 등을 통해 캄보디아 몬돌끼리 주 소재 스캠 단지에 감금되어 있던 A씨를 구출하고 26명의 한국인 조직원을 검거했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The phone conversation between Mr. A and his mother, disclosed by the NIS with the parties' consent, contained the mother's worried words to her son: "Is there someone next to you so you can't properly say (where you are)?" and "Contact me at least once every three days." When Mr. A tearfully told his mother, "Mom, don't ask things like that, just check that I'm okay," his mother also cried and worried, saying, "Can't you even tell me where you are? Is it Vietnam? Can't you even tell me that?" While exchanging words with his mother, Mr. A ultimately said, "I can't talk about that, Mom," burst into tears, and ended the call. (국정원이 당사자 동의하에 공개한 A씨와 어머니 간 이뤄진 통화 내용에는 어머니가 아들에게 “너 옆에 누가 있어서 (어디 있는건지) 제대로 말 못하는거냐” “3일에 한번씩이라도 (연락)해라”며 걱정하는 내용이 담겼다. A씨는 어머니에게 “엄마 그런거 물어보지 말고 그냥 나 잘 있는거 확인하라고”라고 울먹이자 어머니도 울면서 “어딘지도 말해주면 안돼? 베트남이야? 그것도 얘기해주면 안된대?”라며 아들을 걱정했다. 어머니와 말을 주고 받던 A씨는 끝내 “그거는 얘기하면 안돼 엄마”라고 말하다 울음을 터뜨리며 통화를 종료했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The NIS stated, "To prevent further involvement of young people in crime, we have disclosed, with the parties' consent, part of the phone call with the mother, which shows the desperate feelings of the family along with the circumstances of how victim Mr. A was sold to the crime syndicate." An NIS official urged caution, saying, "Cases of our young people in their 20s and 30s being tricked by high-income job offers from overseas crime syndicates and traveling to Southeast Asia are still occurring." (국정원은 “청년층의 추가적인 범죄 연루를 방지하기 위해 피해자 A씨가 범죄 조직에게 팔려 가게 된 경위와 함께 가족들의 절박한 심정을 보여주는 모친과의 통화 일부를 당사자 동의하에 공개한 것”이라고 했다. 국정원 관계자는 “우리 2030 청년층이 해외범죄조직의 고수익 취업 제안 등에 속아 동남아로 출국하는 일이 여전히 발생하고 있다”며 주의를 당부했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since November of last year, as a result of uncovering and apprehending Cambodian scam crime syndicates, the NIS has rescued 3 Koreans and apprehended 157 participants in scams. (국정원은 지난해 11월부터 캄보디아 스캠 범죄조직을 적발·검거한 결과 한국인 3명을 구출하고 스캠 가담자 157명을 검거했다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/L3L5L5J3SBBFZKQ7T4VBWLOOCY/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/VJ6MPFM3KROLVAPTQFTZPHGEHY.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:27:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>People Power Party: "Shincheonji and Unification Church suspicions should be investigated in separate special probes" (국힘 “신천지·통일교 의혹, 별도 특검에서 각각 수사해야”)</title><link>https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/Y5HNFSZG4NGEFG7KYGKXHZVNG4/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;img src="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KHGPCXQX5RLWVDIUFWBYEJBTL4.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;People Power Party floor leader Song Eon-seok reiterated his position on the 20th, calling for the launch of separate special probes: one into the 'suspicion of Shincheonji's interference in the People Power Party primary' and another into the 'suspicion of the Unification Church's lobbying of political circles'. (국민의힘 송언석 원내대표는 20일 ‘신천지의 국민의힘 경선 개입 의혹’ 특검과 ‘통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹’ 특검을 각각 출범시키자는 입장을 거듭 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Party of Korea has consistently argued that a 'Unification Church and Shincheonji special probe' encompassing both suspicions should be launched in response to the People Power Party's demand for a Unification Church probe. Floor leader Song's argument is that these should be investigated separately in distinct special probes. (그간 더불어민주당은 국민의힘의 통일교 특검 도입 요구에 대해 신천지 의혹도 함께 포함시킨 ‘통일교·신천지 특검’을 출범해야 한다고 주장해 왔는데, 이를 별도 특검에서 각각 수사하자는 게 송 원내대표의 주장이다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meeting with reporters at the National Assembly this afternoon, Floor Leader Song stated, "The People Power Party proposed a bill for a special probe because there are issues regarding the receipt of money and valuables related to the Unification Church. However, the Democratic Party submitted a bill to investigate the Shincheonji suspicion together, attempting to dilute the focus (of the Unification Church probe bill)." (송 원내대표는 이날 오후 국회에서 기자들과 만나 “국민의힘은 통일교와 관련한 금품 수수 문제가 있어 특검을 하자는 법안을 발의했다. 그런데 민주당은 거기(통일교 특검 법안)에 물타기를 하려고 신천지 의혹을 함께 수사하자는 법안을 냈다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song clarified, "(Our party's existing position) was not to oppose a Shincheonji special probe," adding, "Even investigating just the suspicion of Unification Church money and valuables will be vast and complex." He continued, "Our party's proposal is for the Unification Church probe to focus on Unification Church suspicions, and for the Shincheonji probe to uncover substantive truth through an in-depth investigation via a separate special probe." (송 원내대표는 “(기존 당 입장은) 신천지 특검을 하지 말자는 것이 아니었다”며 “통일교 금품 수수 의혹에 대한 수사만 해도 방대하고 복잡할 것”이라고 했다. 그러면서 그는 “통일교 특검은 통일교 의혹에 집중하고, 신천지 특검은 별도 특검을 통해 깊이 있는 수사로 실체적 진실을 밝히자는 게 우리 당의 제안”이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Floor Leader Song also said, "(The previous Min Jung-ki special probe, which investigated Unification Church suspicions) secured a statement last August about the provision of Unification Church money and valuables (through a person related to the Unification Church), but dragged its feet for over four months and then transferred the case to the police around December when the statute of limitations was nearly expired." He emphasized, "The part where the Min Jung-ki special probe concealed the statement for over four months must definitely be included and investigated in the Unification Church special probe." (송 원내대표는 “(앞서 통일교 의혹을 수사했던) 민중기 특검이 작년 8월 (통일교 관련자를 통해) 통일교 금품 제공 진술을 확보하고도 4개월 넘게 뭉개다가 공소시효가 다 돼가던 12월쯤 경찰에 이첩했다” “민중기 특검이 4개월 넘게 진술을 은폐한 부분은 꼭 통일교 특검에 포함해 수사해야 한다”고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Floor Leader Song added, "I once again strongly urge the Democratic Party to seriously view the life-threatening hunger strike by People Power Party leader Jang Dong-hyuk, now in its sixth day." Leader Jang is continuing his hunger strike for the sixth day, demanding 'twin special probes' to investigate suspicions of the Democratic Party's nomination-related political donations and the Unification Church's lobbying of political circles. (또 송 원내대표는 “민주당은 6일차로 계속되는 국민의힘 장동혁 대표의 목숨을 건 단식에 대해 심각하게 바라보기를 다시 한번 강력히 촉구한다”고도 했다. 장 대표는 민주당의 공천 헌금 의혹, 통일교의 정치권 로비 의혹 등을 수사할 ‘쌍특검’을 요구하며 엿새째 단식을 이어가고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.chosun.com/politics/politics_general/2026/01/20/Y5HNFSZG4NGEFG7KYGKXHZVNG4/</guid><enclosure url="https://cloudfront-ap-northeast-1.images.arcpublishing.com/chosun/KHGPCXQX5RLWVDIUFWBYEJBTL4.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:42:08 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>