<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 05:34:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Tesla kills Autopilot, locks lane-keeping behind $99/month fee</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/tesla-wants-recurring-revenue-discontinues-autopilot-in-favor-of-fsd/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1415090444-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With falling sales and shrinking profits, the recurring revenue will be most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love it or hate it, Tesla has been responsible for helping to shape the tastes of automotive consumers over the past decade-plus. Over-the-air updates that add more features, an all-touchscreen human-machine interface, large castings, and hands-free driver assists were all introduced or popularized by Tesla’s electric vehicles,prompting other automakers to copy them, mostly in the hopes of seeing the same stratospheric gains in their stock prices. But starting on Valentine’s Day, if you want your Tesla to steer itself, you’ll have to pay a $99 monthly subscription fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla currently offers a pair of so-called “level 2” partially automated driver assist systems. Autopilot is the older of these, combining Tesla’s adaptive cruise control (Tesla calls this TACC) and lane-keeping assist (Tesla calls this Autosteer).FSD is the newer system, meant to be more capable and for use on surface streets and divided-lane highways. Although the company and Tesla CEO Elon Musk regularly tout these systems’ capabilities, both still require the human driver to provide situational awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Autopilot has been under fire from regulators and the courts. Multiple wrongful death lawsuits are in the works, and aftera high-profile loss resulting in a $329 million judgmentagainst Tesla, expect many of these suits to be settled. Both thefederal governmentandCaliforniahave investigated whether Tesla misled customers, and in December, an administrative law judgeruled that Tesla indeed engaged in deceptive marketingby implying that its cars could drive themselves. The judge suspended Tesla’s license to sell cars in California, a decision that the California Department of Motor Vehicles stayed for 60 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla was told that if it couldn’t resolve the deceptive marketing within those 60 days, the sales suspension would take effect. That would be bad for the automaker, as California is far and away its largest market in the US, albeitone thatis shrinkingeach quarter. Having to suspend sales entirely in the state would be disastrous. Some had speculated that Tesla could change Autopilot’s name to something less misleading, but the company chose a more drastic approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you want your new Tesla to steer itself—while you pay attention to the road—you will have to pay for FSD. Until the middle of February, that can be done for a one-time fee of $8,000. But starting on February 14, that option goes away, too, and the sole choice will be a $99/month FSD subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But probably not for very long. Last night, Muskrevealed on his social media platformthat “the $99/month for supervised FSD will rise as FSD’s capabilities improve. The massive value jump is when you can be on your phone or sleeping for the entire ride (unsupervised FSD).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quest for recurring revenue streams is becoming something of a holy grail in the automotive industry as OEMs that previously treated their customers as a single sale now hope to make themselves more attractive to investors by encouraging customers to give them regular payouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may have contributed to General Motors’decision to drop Apple CarPlay and Android Automotive. BMW has alsoexperimentedwithsubscription services. Tesla’s stock price remains so high that such games are probably unnecessary here, but with falling profit margins, declining sales, and the loss of emissions credits to bolster the bottom line, one can see why regular cash infusions from Tesla drivers would be desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/tesla-wants-recurring-revenue-discontinues-autopilot-in-favor-of-fsd/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:54:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok deal is done; Trump wants praise while users fear MAGA tweaks</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-finalizes-trump-deal-that-allows-bytedance-to-maintain-some-control/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257704699-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am so happy”: Trump closes deal that hands TikTok US to his allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TikTok deal is done, and Donald Trump is claiming a win, although it remains unclear if the joint venture he arranged with ByteDance and the Chinese government actually resolves Congress’ national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In apress releaseThursday, TikTok announced the “TikTok USDS Joint Venture LLC,” an entity established to keep TikTok operating in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving Americans majority ownership, ByteDance retains 19.9 percent of the joint venture, the release said, which has been valued at $14 billion. Three managing investors—Silver Lake, Oracle, and MGX—each hold 15 percent, while other investors, including Dell Technologies CEO Michael Dell’s investment firm, Dell Family Office, hold smaller, undisclosed stakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans will also have majority control over the joint venture’s seven-member board. TikTok CEO Shou Chew holds ByteDance’s only seat. Finalizing the deal was a “great move,” Chew told TikTok employees in an internal memo, The New York Timesreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two former TikTok employees will lead the joint venture. Adam Presser, who previously served as TikTok’s global head of Operations and Trust &amp; Safety, has been named CEO. And Kim Farrell, TikTok’s former global head of Business Operations Protection, will serve as chief security officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has claimed the deal meets requirements for “qualified divestiture” to avoid a TikTok ban otherwise required under the Protecting Americans from Foreign Adversary Controlled Applications Act. However, questions remain, as lawmakers have not yet analyzed the terms of the deal to determine whether that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law requires the divestment “to end any ‘operational relationship’ between ByteDance and TikTok in the United States,” critics told the NYT. That could be a problem, since TikTok’s release makes it clear that ByteDance will maintain some control over the TikTok US app’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, while the US owners will retrain the algorithm and manage data security, ByteDance owns the algorithm and “will manage global product interoperability and certain commercial activities, including e-commerce, advertising, and marketing.” The Trump administration seemingly agreed to these terms to ensure that the US TikTok isn’t cut off from the rest of the world on the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Interoperability enables the Joint Venture to provide US users with a global TikTok experience, ensuring US creators can be discovered and businesses can operate on a global scale,” the release said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps also concerning to Congress, Slatenoted,while ByteDance may be a minority owner, it remains the largest individual shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Sobolik, an expert on US-China policy and senior fellow at the right-leaning think tank the Hudson Institute, told the NYT that the Trump administration “may have saved TikTok, but the national security concerns are still going to continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some critics, including Republicans, have vowed to scrutinize the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Senator Edward Markey (D-Mass.) complained that the White House had repeatedly denied requests for information about the deal. They’ve provided “virtually no details about this agreement, including whether TikTok’s algorithm is truly free of Chinese influence,” Markey said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This lack of transparency reeks,” Markey said. “Congress has a responsibility to investigate this deal, demand transparency, and ensure that any arrangement truly protects national security while keeping TikTok online.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, Representative John Moolenaar (R-Mich.), chair of the House Select Committee on China, said thathe wants to hold a hearing with TikTok leadershipto discuss how the deal addresses national security concerns. On Thursday, Moolenaar said he “has two specific questions for TikTok’s new American owners,” Punchbowl Newsreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Can we ensure that the algorithm is not influenced by the Chinese Communist Party?” Moolenaar said. “And two, can we ensure that the data of Americans is secure?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moolenaar may be satisfied by the terms, as the NYT suggested that China hawks in Washington appeared to trust that Trump’s arrangement is a qualified divestiture. TikTok’s release said that Oracle will protect US user data in a secure US cloud data environment that will regularly be audited by third-party cybersecurity experts. The algorithm will be licensed from ByteDance and retrained on US user data, the release said, and Vice President JD Vance has confirmed that the joint venture “will have control over how the algorithm pushes content to users.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last September, a spokesperson for the House China Committeetold Politicothat “any agreement must comply with the historic bipartisan law passed last year to protect the American people, including the complete divestment of ByteDance control and a fully decoupled algorithm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am so happy to have helped in saving TikTok!” Trump said on Truth Social after the deal was finalized. “It will now be owned by a group of Great American Patriots and Investors, the Biggest in the World, and will be an important Voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it’s unclear to TikTokers how the app might change as Trump allies take control of the addictive algorithm that drew millions to the app. Lawmakers had feared the Chinese Communist Party could influence the algorithm to target US users with propaganda, and Trump’s deal was supposed to mitigate that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do critics worry that if ByteDance maintains ownership of the algorithm, it could allow the company to continue to influence content, but there is now concern that the app’s recommendations could take a right-leaning slant under US control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has already said thathe’d like to see TikTok go “100 percent MAGA,”and his allies will now be in charge of “deciding which posts to leave up and which to take down,” the NYT noted. Anupam Chander, a law and technology professor at Georgetown University, told the NYT that the TikTok deal offered Trump and his allies “more theoretical room for one side’s views to get a greater airing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My worry all along is that we may have traded fears of foreign propaganda for the reality of domestic propaganda,” Chander said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For business owners who rely on the app, there’s also the potential thatthe app could be glitchyafter US owners start porting data and retraining the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump clearly hopes the deal will endear him to TikTok users. He sought praise on Truth Social, writing, “I only hope that long into the future I will be remembered by those who use and love TikTok.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the Chinese government has not commented on the deal’s finalization, but Trump thanked Chinese President Xi Jinping in his Truth Social post “for working with us and, ultimately, approving the Deal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He could have gone the other way, but didn’t, and is appreciated for his decision,” Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts have suggested that China benefits from the deal by keeping the most lucrative part of TikTok while the world watches it export its technology to the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Trump first announced the deal in September, critics immediately attacked him for letting China keep the algorithm. One US advisor close to the dealtold the Financial Timesthat “Trump always chickens out,” noting that “after all this, China keeps the algorithm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Soboliktold Politicothat Trump “got played” by Xi after taking “terrible advice from his staff” during trade negotiations that some critics saidgave China the upper hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump sees things differently, writing on Truth Social that the TikTok deal came to “a very dramatic, final, and beautiful conclusion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the deal is “dramatic,” “final,” or “beautiful” depends on who you ask, though, as it could face legal challenges and disrupt TikTok’s beloved content feeds. The NYT suggested that the deal took so long to finalize that TikTokers don’t even care anymore, while several outlets noted that Trump’s deal is very close to the Project Texas arrangement that Joe Biden pushed until it was deemed inadequate to address national security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Project Texas, Oracle was supposed to oversee TikTok US user data, auditing for security risks while ByteDance controlled the code. The joint venture’s “USDS” “coinage even originated from Project Texas,” Slate noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lindsay Gorman, a former senior advisor in the Biden administration, told NYT that “we’ve gone round and round and ended up not too far from where we started.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-finalizes-trump-deal-that-allows-bytedance-to-maintain-some-control/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 08:29:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Telly’s “free” ad-based TVs make notable revenue—when they’re actually delivered</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/652fa4f61e054d1c335ce241_Rectangle_20180_203.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LA startup said it would ship “millions” of TVs by 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly, a company that accepts advertising data instead of cash for its TVs, has reportedly had a hard time getting its “free” TVs into people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly debuted in May 2023. Its dual-screen design can show ads, even when people aren’t watching. Although the smaller, secondary screen can be used for more helpful applications, like showing the weather or sports scores, its primary purpose is to serve as a billboard south of the 55-inch primary display. Owners cannot disabletrackingor cover up the secondary screen (or they have to pay for the TV, which Telly claims is worth $1,000), and they must fill out a lengthy, detailed survey to get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it debuted its TV, Telly said it expected to ship 500,000 devices that summer. In June 2023, the startupsaid250,000 people signed up to get a Telly. In a 2024press release, Telly said that it planned to ship “millions more in 2024.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a report fromLowpassthis week, citing a “Q3 update sent to investors in November 2025,” said the startup had 35,000 TVs in people’s homes at that time. In Q2 2025, there were 28,000 Telly TVs in use, the note said, according to Lowpass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The publication reported that the investor note suggests Telly will order 100,000 TVs from supplier Foxconn and increase deliveries soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly declined to comment to Lowpass and didn’t respond to Ars Technica’s requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Based on early registration numbers, it seems Telly has generated enough interest to ship more than 35,000 TVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue seems to be poor shipping. Per the investor note that Lowpass reviewed, Telly claimed that FedEx delivered 10 percent of its shipments of Telly TVs broken. Since moving to a different company—seeminglySamsung partnerRXO, based on Redditposts—fewer Tellys are arriving broken, the company reportedly said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Lowpass noted,dozensof onlinecomplaintsclaim that the free TVs, which ship directly from Telly, were broken upon arrival.The Vergealso reported receiving a broken unit in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, thesubredditdedicated to Telly TVs seems to show numerous other technical difficulties Telly users are experiencing. Technical complaints are common on subreddits for tech gadgets, but the forum highlights the problems Telly owners might encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly’s reported failure to meet its high shipment goals or even fulfill reported demand demonstrates the scaling complexities startups can face. While some companies struggle to get people interested in their product, Telly’s “free” pitch has been successful enough to lure thousands. But in its early stages, Telly has reportedly struggled with its direct-to-consumer model and smaller team compared to other TV makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Telly’s ad-centric business model may be starting to show its value. The investor update reportedly said Telly made $22 million in annualized revenue in Q3 2025. This could equate to about $52 in advertising revenue per Telly in use per month ($22 million divided by 35,000 TVs divided by 12 months in a year is $52.38).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s notably more than what other TV companies report, as Lowpass pointed out. As a comparison to other budget TV brands that rely heavily on ads and user tracking, Roku reported an average revenue per user (ARPU) of $41.49 for 2024. Vizio, meanwhile, reported an ARPU of $37.17 in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investor note reportedly said that Telly recently raised $350 million in debt funding over two rounds. The note didn’t specify when the funding occurred or how much equity Telly has raised overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assmart TVs at every price pointincreasinglyrelyonsoftware-integratedadvertisementsanduser trackingto offset declining hardware margins and rising competition, Telly argues that its premise is forward-thinking, not far-fetched. Some longtime Telly users point to the sets’ decent image and audio quality but question their reliance on an (included) streaming stick to access popular apps, their default AI-avatar home screen, and repetitive ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Verge writer Emma Rothsaidher Telly showed her “three of the same ads in Spanish (which I don’t speak) in a row.” There’s also concern about potentially invasive uses of the TV’s integrated camera and mic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the leaked investor report highlights, there are plenty of other challenges standing in the way of free, ad-supported TVs. Still, Telly’s early ARPU figures are notable enough to keep the idea alive.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:32:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White House alters arrest photo of ICE protester, says “the memes will continue”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nekima-levy-white-house-manipulated-image-1152x648-1769192287.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyer calls it “outrageous that the White House would make up stories.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump White House yesterday posted a manipulated photo of Nekima Levy Armstrong, a Minnesota civil rights attorney who was arrested after protesting in a church where a pastor is allegedly also an Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noempostedwhat seems to be the original photo of Armstrong being led away by an officer yesterday morning. A half hour later, the official White House X accountpostedan altered version in which Armstrong’s face was manipulated to make it appear that she was crying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The White House shared an AI-edited photo of Nekima, depicting her in tears and scared when, in actuality, she was poised, determined, and unafraid,” NAACP President and CEO Derrick Johnsonsaidyesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reader-added context on X said, “This photo has been digitally altered to make Nekima Levy Armstrong appear to be in distress. The Director of DHS herself posted the unedited photo in an earlier announcement.” White House Deputy Communications Director Kaelan Dorr defended the post after criticism of the image manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Enforcement of the law will continue. The memes will continue. Thank you for your attention to this matter,” Dorrwrote. The White House post with the manipulated image called Levy Armstrong a “far-left agitator” who “orchestrated[ed] church riots in Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DHSpress releaseabout the arrest used the same image posted by Noem, without the alteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Kushner, an attorney for Levy Armstrong, said, “It is just so outrageous that the White House would make up stories about someone to try and discredit them. She was completely calm and composed and rational. There was no one crying. So this is just outrageous defamation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to The Associated Press, Kushner also said that the “video Levy Armstrong’s husband shot ‘dismantles what they claim’ and that the video would be released soon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protestersdisrupted serviceson Sunday at the Cities Church in St. Paul, chanting “ICE OUT” and “Justice for Renee Good.” The St. Paul Pioneer Pressquoted Levy Armstrongas saying, “When you think about the federal government unleashing barbaric ICE agents upon our community and all the harm that they have caused, to have someone serving as a pastor who oversees these ICE agents is almost unfathomable to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The churchwebsitelists David Easterwood as one of its pastors. Protesters said this is the same David Easterwood who is listed as a defendant in a lawsuit that Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison filed against Noem and other federal officials. Thelawsuitlists Easterwood as a defendant “in his official capacity as Acting Director, Saint Paul Field Office, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levy Armstrong, who is also a former president of the NAACP’s Minneapolis branch, was arrested yesterday morning. Announcing the arrest, Attorney General Pam Bondiwrote, “WE DO NOT TOLERATE ATTACKS ON PLACES OF WORSHIP.” Bondi alleged that Levy Armstrong “played a key role in organizing the coordinated attack on Cities Church in St. Paul, Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noem said Levy Armstrong “is being charged with a federal crime under 18 USC 241,” whichprohibits“conspir[ing] to injure, oppress, threaten, or intimidate any person in any State, Territory, Commonwealth, Possession, or District in the free exercise or enjoyment of any right or privilege secured to him by the Constitution or laws of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Religious freedom is the bedrock of the United States—there is no first amendment right to obstruct someone from practicing their religion,” Noem wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul School Board member Chauntyll Allen was also arrested. Attorneys for the Cities Church issuedstatementssupporting the arrests and saying they “are exploring all legal options to protect the church and prevent further invasions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal magistrate judge initially ruled that Levy Armstrong and Allen could be released, but they were still being held last night after the government “made a motion to stay the release for further review, claiming they might be flight risks,” the Pioneer Presswrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner called the arrests a “farce” and alleged that Bondi and Noem ordered the arrests only so they could celebrate them on social media, according to the Pioneer Press. “This doesn’t happen in a legitimate prosecution,” Kushner said. “These are officials making a political decision, and purposely making a political spectacle and a political circus out of the court system for their own purposes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner also “said federal agents detained one of Armstrong’s friends two days [previously], using force to tackle her in a hotel lobby, under the mistaken impression she was Armstrong,” the Pioneer Press wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marques Armstrong, Levy Armstrong’s husband, said she offered to turn herself in after the mistaken detention of her friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Initially they agreed and then a call came from up high and said, ‘No, we have to take her there (at the hotel).’ They wanted her in handcuffs,” he was quoted as saying. An “agent took photos and said it won’t go on social media. I knew it was a lie,” he also said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House’s posting of a manipulated version of the arrest photo could be used in Levy Armstrong’s legal defense. As the New York Timeswrote, her lawyer could argue that the post was an improper extrajudicial statement that may prejudice potential jurors and that it shows the Justice Department filed charges vindictively. We contacted Kushner about the manipulated photo and case today and will update this article if he provides any comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NAACP called for the release of Levy Armstrong, Allen, and a third arrestee, William Kelly. “Their arrests violated their constitutional rights and NAACP demands their immediate release,” the NAACP said. “Ms. Armstrong and her fellow demonstrators gathered peacefully at a church over the pastor’s alleged leadership within the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). The protests follow the increase in ICE activity and the fatal shooting of Minneapolis resident Renee Nicole Good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department also tried to bring charges against journalist Don Lemon, but a judgerejected the charges. Lemon was at the demonstration but said he was there as a journalist and not a protester.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:46:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask anonymous ICE critics online</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257128839-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community watch groups have a playbook to keep ICE away from subscriber information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security (DHS) has backed down from afight to unmask the owners of Instagram and Facebook accountsmonitoring Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) activity in Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anonymous account holders, John Doe, sued to block ICE from identifying him and other critics online through summonses to Meta that he claimed infringed on core First Amendment-protected activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS initially fought Doe’s motion to quash the summonses, arguing that the community watch groups endangered ICE agents by posting “pictures and videos of agents’ faces, license plates, and weapons, among other things.” This was akin to “threatening ICE agents to impede the performance of their duties,” DHS alleged. DHS’s arguments echoed DHS Secretary Kristi Noem, who has claimed that identifying ICE agents is a crime, even thoughWired notedthat ICE employees often post easily discoverable LinkedIn profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Doe, the agency seemed intent on testing the waters to see if it could seize authority to unmask all critics online by invoking a customs statute that allows agents to subpoena information on goods entering or leaving the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, on January 16, DHS abruptly reversed course, withdrawing its summonses from Meta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acourt filingconfirmed that DHS dropped its requests for subscriber information last week, after initially demanding Doe’s “postal code, country, all email address(es) on file, date of account creation, registered telephone numbers, IP address at account signup, and logs showing IP address and date stamps for account accesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filing does not explain why DHS decided to withdraw its requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, previously, DHS requested similar information from Meta about six Instagram community watch groups that shared information about ICE activity in Los Angeles and other locations. DHS withdrew those requests, too, after account holders defended their First Amendment rights and filed motions to quash their summonses, Doe’s court filing said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To defeat DHS’ summonses, Doe shared all his group’s online posts with the court. An attorney representing Doe at the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, Ariel Shapell, told Ars that Doe’s groups posted “pretty innocuous” content, like “information and resources about immigrant rights, due process rights, fundraising, and vigils.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible DHS caved due to lack of evidence supporting claims that Doe’s groups’ posts carried implicit threats to “assault, kidnap, or murder any federal official,” as DHS hadargued. But it’s also possible that DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask ICE critics due to strong First Amendment protections working to preserve the right to post anonymously online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attempt to unmask Doe’s accounts came as criticism of ICE is mounting nationwide, and a win could have given ICE broad authority to attack that growing base of critics if DHS had dug in and its defense actually held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses could signal that the argument the agency tried to raise—weirdly using a statute tied to the “importation/exportation of merchandise”to seize “unlimited subpoena authority” of ICE critics online—is clearly not a winning one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment. But Meta did play a role in challenging DHS’ summonses, initially by seeking more information from the agency and then notifying account holders to provide an opportunity to quash the summonses before information was shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the playbook for community watch groups on Facebook and Instagram has been to follow Meta’s advice in order to block identifying information from being shared. But it remains unclear if Meta may have complied with DHS’s requests if account holders were not able to legally fight to quash them, perhaps leaving a vulnerable gray area for community watch groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Doe and any others involved in “MontCo Community Watch,” DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses likely comes as a relief. But this wasn’t the first time DHS tried and failed to unmask online critics, so it’s just as likely that fears remain that DHS will continue trying to identify groups that are posting footage to raise awareness of ICE’s most controversial moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE critics have used footage of tragic events—like Renee Good’s killing andeight other ICE shootings since September—to support calls to remove ICE from embattled communities and abolish ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions remain high as US citizens defend both their neighbors and their own constitutional rights. Most recently, shocking footage ofICE using a 5-year-old boy as baitto trap other family members intensified calls to defund ICE. Public backlash also raged after videos showedICE removing a US citizen from his home in his underwear. That arrest happened while ICE was conducting a warrantless search that awhistleblower warnedis becoming the new ICE norm after an internal memo said that agents can enter homes without a judicial warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some politicians are starting to take up the call to diminish ICE’s power. On Thursday, the majority of House Democrats voted to defund ICE, which Politiconotedwas a “remarkable shift from when dozens of them voted to expand the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement authority just one year ago.” Of course, the ICE budget bill passed anyway, since Republicans control the House, but withpublic approval of ICE tanking, any ongoing pushback could hurt Republicans in midterms and eventually even doom ICE if momentum is sustained.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:10:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demand for Intel’s processors is apparently there, but the supply is not</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/intel-core-ultra-series-3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel is allocating more of its own production to its money-making server chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel reportedits earnings for the fourth quarter of 2025 yesterday, and the news both for the quarter and for the year was mixed: year-over-year revenue was down nearly imperceptibly, from $53.1 billion to $52.9 billion, while revenue for the quarter was down about four percent, from $14.3 billion last year to $13.7 billion this year. (That number was, nevertheless, on the high end of Intel’s guidance for the quarter, which ranged from $12.8 to $13.8 billion.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving deeper into the numbers makes it clear exactly where money is being made and lost: Intel’s data center and AI products were up 9 percent for the quarter and 5 percent for the year, while its client computing group (which sells Core processors, Arc GPUs, and other consumer products) was down 7 percent for the quarter and 3 percent for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That knowledge makes it slightly easier to understand the bind that company executives talked about on Intel’s earnings call (as transcribed by Investing.com). In short, Intel is having trouble making (and buying) enough chips to meet demand, and it makes more sense to allocate the chips itcanmake to the divisions that are actually making money—which means that we could see shortages of or higher prices for consumer processors, just as Intel is gearing up to launch the promising Core Ultra Series 3 processors (codenamed Panther Lake).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel CFO David Zinsner indicated that Intel is “prioritizing [its] internal wafer supply to data center” and having more of its consumer chips made externally. Substantial portions of the Core Ultra Series 3 processors are manufactured at Intel, after the company primarily used TSMC’s chip factories for the Core Ultra Series 2 designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can’t completely vacate the client market,” said Zinsner, but Intel is “shifting as much as we can over to data center to meet the high demand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounding this is that yields for the new 18A process—that is, the number of chips in a wafer with no defects that can work as designed—are still improving. Intel CEO Lip-Bu Tan said that “while yields are in line with our internal plans, they are still below what I want them to be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yields are currently improving by 7 or 8 percent every month, according to Intel. But that could be building on pretty low initial yields—reporting from last summer suggested that just 10 percent of the chips coming off of the 18A production lines were meeting Intel’s requirements at the time. Intel predicts that its supply will have ramped up enough within the next few months to help alleviate shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do believe that the first quarter is the trough,” said Zinsner. “We will improve supply in the second quarter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Intel can start making enough chips to meet its demand, it ought to help brighten the company’s earnings reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We delivered [our Q4 2025] results despite supply constraints, which meaningfully limited our ability to capture all of the strengths in our underwriting markets,” said Tan. “We are working aggressively to address this and better support our customers’ needs going forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel has been signaling for a while now that it was selling essentially all of the chips it could get its hands on. Intel investor relations VP John Pitzersaidlast month that Intel would be selling more of both its Lunar Lake and Arrow Lake Core Ultra Series 2 chips for consumers, as well as its Granite Rapids chips for data centers, if it could get more of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Intel seeks to improve its position in the short term, the company also says that it’s still making progress on its future manufacturing nodes, including different versions of the 18A process and the upcoming 14A process. Intel is working to engage “potential external customers” who would use the 14A process to make their own chips. If these third parties decide to use Intel’s manufacturing facilities, Intel expects to know about it “starting in the second half of this year and extending into the first half of 2027,” and then it expects to build out manufacturing capacity based on the number of external customers it finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the chip design side, Intel also expects to have its first next-generation Nova Lake chips ready “at the end of 2026.” We don’t know much about Nova Lake yet, but it should be Intel’s next architecture to cover both desktop and laptop processors, while Panther Lake chips are intended mainly for laptops. At least part of the chip will also be manufactured using the 18A process.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:48:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TR-49 is interactive fiction for fans of deep research rabbit holes</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/4-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dense narrative deduction game tells a compellingly academia-tinged sci-fi tale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developer:InklePublisher: InklePlatform: MacOS (reviewed), Windows, iOSRelease Date:Jan. 21, 2026ESRB Rating:N/APrice: $7Links:iOS App Store|Steam|Official website&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever fallen downa Wikipedia rabbit holeor spent a pleasant evening digging through college library stacks, you know the joy of a good research puzzle. Every new source and cross-reference you find unlocks an incremental understanding of a previously unknown world, forming a piecemeal tapestry of knowledge that you can eventually look back at as a cohesive and well-known whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49takes this research process and operationalizes it into an engrossing and novel piece of heavily non-linear interactive fiction. Researching the myriad sources contained in the game’s mysterious computer slowly reveals a tale that’s part mystery, part sci-fi allegory, part family drama, and all-compelling alternate academic history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entirety ofTR-49takes place from a first-person perspective as you sit in front of a kind of Steampunk-infused computer terminal. An unseen narrator asks you to operate the machine but is initially cagey about how or why or what you’re even looking for. There’s a creepy vibe to the under-explained circumstances that brought you to this situation, but the game never descends into the jump scares or horror tropes of so many other modern titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your only real form of interaction with the world ofTR-49is through a sepia-toned tube display on the left and a four-charactersplit-flapon the right that serves as the computer’s only input. You quickly discover that entering specific sequences—each with two letters followed by two numbers, as suggested by the game’s name—brings up library catalog-style entries referring to a vast web of literary works that form the core of the game’s wider fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the catalog contains short excerpts from each of these discovered works, it’s the additional notes added to each entry by subsequent researchers that place each title in its full context. You’ll end up poring through these research notes for clues about the existence and chronology of other authors and works. Picking out specific names and years points to the codes and titles needed to unlock even more reference pages in the computer, pushing you further down the rabbit hole. Picture something likeHer Story, but replace the cinéma vérité surveillance video clips with a library card catalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll slowly start to unravel and understand how the game world’s myriad authors are influencing each other with their cross-pollinating writings. The treatises, novels, pamphlets, and journals discussed in this database are full of academic sniping, intellectual intrigue, and interpersonal co-mingling across multiple generations of work. It all ends up circling a long-running search for a metaphysical key to life itself, which most of the authors manage to approach but never quite reach a full understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you explore, you also start to learn more about the personal affairs of the researchers who collected and cataloged all this reference material and the vaguely defined temporal capabilities of the information-synthesis engine in the computer you’ve all worked on. Eventually, you’ll stumble on the existence of core commands that can unlock hidden parts of the computer or alter the massive research database itself, which becomes key to your eventual final goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through it all, there’s a slowly unfolding parallel narrative involving Liam, the unseen voice guiding you through the research process itself. Through occasional voice clips, Liam eventually hints at the existence of a powerful and quickly encroaching threat that wants to stop your progress by any means necessary, adding a bit of dramatic tension to your academic pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m being intentionally vague about the specifics here because I thinkTR-49‘s subtle and well-crafted sci-fi world-building is best experienced by exploring the game for yourself. There’s a real satisfaction in staring at a once impenetrably obtuse research note, recalling a bit of information from a recent cross-reference, and feeling your understanding suddenly click into place. And while the vocal performances can verge on cheesy, the writing captures the monomaniacal intensity of truly obsessive academics to a tee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the game’s best features is a “Notes” sub-menu, which automatically outlines relevant facts (and potential facts) about various authors, groups, and publications as you discover them. This means you don’t have to take page after page of hand-written notes to keep track of the game’s complex connections (and potential connections), as you do in games likeBlue PrinceorLorelei and the Laser Eyes. It makes for a much smoother puzzle-solving experience, even if the automatic notes sometimes pick up on things you may have missed while skimming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49also benefits from being relatively compact compared to some other narrative deduction games. A diligent investigator can reach a conclusion in four or five hours, depending on how thorough they want to be. That makes it relatively easy to keep the broad outlines of the game’s dense but parsable world in your head over a couple of evening play sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are bound to be some people who seeTR-49as akin to a homework simulator, with painful flashbacks to all-nighters spent desperately researching a last-minute college term paper. For anyone who knows the inherent appeal of diving deep into a previously unknown world, though,TR-49is an engrossing work of world-building fiction presented in a truly memorable way.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:52:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>