<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:49:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Macaque facial gestures are more than just a reflex, study finds</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/macaque-facial-gestures-are-more-than-just-a-reflex-study-finds/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2243934190-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study is first to implant micro-electrode arrays to record neurons as they produce facial gestures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in brain-computer interfaces have made it possible to more accurately extract speech from neural signals in humans, but language is just one of the tools we use to communicate. “When my young nephew asks for ice cream before dinner and I say ‘no,’ the meaning is entirely dictated by whether the word is punctuated with a smirk or a stern frown,” says Geena Ianni, a neuroscientist at the University of Pennsylvania. That’s why in the future, she thinks, neural prostheses meant for patients with a stroke or paralysis will decode facial gestures from brain signals in the same way they decode speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To lay a foundation for these future facial gesture decoders, Ianni and her colleagues designed an experiment to find out how neural circuitry responsible for making faces really works. “Although in recent years neuroscience got a good handle on how the brain perceives facial expressions, we know relatively little about how they are generated,” Ianni says. And it turned out that a surprisingly large part of what neuroscientists assumed about facial gestures was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, neuroscientists thought facial gestures in primates stemmed from a neat division of labor in the brain. “Case reports of patients with brain lesions suggested some brain regions were responsible for certain types of emotional expressions while other regions were responsible for volitional movements like speech,” Ianni explains. We’ve developed a clearer picture of speech by tracing the origin of these movements down to the level of individual neurons. But we’ve not done the same for facial expressions. To fill this gap, Ianni and her team designed a study using macaques—social primates that share most of their complex facial musculature with humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study started by putting the macaques in an fMRI scanner to monitor their brain activity while recording their faces with a high-resolution camera. The team then exposed their participants to various stimuli: videos with other macaques making faces at them, interactive avatars, or other live macaques. “This elicited socially meaningful facial expressions that are part of the subjects’ natural repertoire,” Ianni says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the video analysis, scientists identified three facial gestures they wanted to focus on: the lipsmack macaques use to signal receptivity or submission; the threat face they make when they want to challenge or chase off an adversary; and chewing, a non-social, volitional movement. Then, using the fMRI scans, the team located key brain areas involved in triggering these gestures. And when this was done, Ianni and her colleagues went deeper—quite literally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We targeted these brain areas with sub-millimeter precision for implantation of micro-electrode arrays,” Ianni explains. This, for the first time, allowed her team to simultaneously record the activity from many neurons spaced across the areas where the brain generates facial gestures. The electrodes went into the primary motor cortex, the ventral premotor cortex, the primary somatosensory cortex, and the cingulate motor cortex. When they were in, the team once again exposed the macaques to the same set of social stimuli, looking for neural signatures of the three selected facial gestures. And that’s when things took a surprising turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers expected to see a clear division of responsibilities, one where the cingulate cortex governs social signals, while the motor cortex is specialized in chewing. Instead, they found that every single region was involved in every type of gesture. Whether the macaques were threatening a rival or simply enjoying a snack, all four brain areas were firing in a coordinated symphony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led Ianni’s team to the question of how the brain distinguished between social gestures and chewing, since it apparently wasn’t about where the brain processed the information. The answer was in different neural codes—different ways that neurons represent and transmit information in the brain over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By analyzing neural population dynamics, the team identified a temporal hierarchy across the cortex in macaques. The cingulate cortex used a static neural code. “The static means the firing pattern of neurons is persistent across both multiple repetitions of the same facial gesture and across time,” Ianni explains, and maintained their firing pattern till 0.8 seconds after that. “A single decoder which learns this pattern could be used at any timepoint or during any trial to read out the facial expression,” Ianni says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firing rates in the motor and somatosensory cortex, on the other hand, looked radically different. This suggests there is a dynamic neural code defined by rapidly changing firing rate relationships amongst the neural populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team thinks this means that the cingulate cortex manages the social purpose and context of the facial gesture, which is relatively stable. This may be where the brain integrates sensory cues—like the look of another monkey’s expression—with its own internal state to produce the right facial gesture for the occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dynamic code areas implement this expression by driving individual muscles. “They’re driving the kinematics like ‘move this lip a millimeter to the left, now a millimeter to the right,’” Ianni explains. These constant miniscule movements of muscles are necessary because facial expressions are usually dynamic—macaques’ eyelids, lips, cheeks, and ears are constantly twitching and changing their position even if the end effect looks still from a distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s just the beginning of a long journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There have been such fabulous, impressive advances in the field of assistive communication devices even since I started this project,” Ianni says, and points to neural prostheses developed by Maitreyee Wairagkar’s team Arscoveredin 2025 as one of the examples. Building a similar neural prosthesis for decoding facial gestures is unlikely to happen overnight, though. We’re a rather long way away from truly restoring the ability to communicate through facial gestures to patients who lost it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ianni’s study is the first that recorded neurons producing facial gestures with multi-electrode arrays. This means we’ve only just begun to build up base science on the neural mechanism behind making faces. This is the point where neural speech decoding technology was in the late 1990s, and we still can’t make that reliable enough for regular clinical products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ianni remains hopeful. “I hope our work goes towards enabling the field, even the tiniest bit, towards more naturalistic and rich communication designs that will improve lives of patients after brain injury,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science:https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aea0890&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/macaque-facial-gestures-are-more-than-just-a-reflex-study-finds/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:25:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Flesh-eating flies are eating their way through Mexico, CDC warns</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/be-on-the-lookout-for-flesh-eating-flies-cdc-tells-clinicians-in-alert/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/CSIRO_ScienceImage_115_The_Tip_of_a_Screw_Worm_Fly_Larvae.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eight animal cases in Mexico’s Tamaulipas spur CDC to warn doctors of festering wounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention issueda health alert to cliniciansTuesday, warning that the savage, flesh-eating parasitic fly—the New World Screwworm—is not only approaching the Texas border, but also felling an increasing number of animals in the bordering Mexican state of Tamaulipas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advisory, released through the agency’s Health Alert Network, directs doctors, veterinarians, and other health workers to be on the lookout forpatients with wounds teeming with ferocious maggotsburrowing into their living flesh. The alert also provides guidance on what to do if any such festering wounds are encountered—namely, remove each and every maggot to prevent the patient from dying, and, under no circumstance allow any of the parasites to survive and escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New World Screwworm (NWS) is a fly that lays its eggs—up to 400 at a time—in the wounds, orifices, and mucus membranes of any warm-blooded animal. The eggs hatch into flesh-eating maggots, which look and act much like screws, twisting and boring into their victims while eating them alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the flies are indiscriminate killers, they’re particularly devastating to livestock and are estimated to cause hundreds of millions of dollars in damage each year. As such, the US Department of Agriculture has been leading the response to the threat, which had been held far at bay until recently. NWS used to be endemic in the US, causing heavy losses to cattle in the country. But, in the 1950s, US scientists developed a strategy to eliminate the flies by raising and releasing sterile male flies. The method exploits the fact that female flies mate only once in their 21-day lifespan. Thus, unproductive mating with a flood of sterile males can cause the population to crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this strategy, screwworms were eradicated from the US around 1966 and, through coordinated efforts, cleared out from Central America in the subsequent decades. They were declared eradicated from Panama in 2006 and actively held at bay with continual sterile-fly releases along the Darién Gap, creating a biological barrier. But the barrier was breached in 2022 amid development and movement through and around the gap. Since then, the flies have quickly been marching north with the help of unregulated cattle movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across Central America and Mexico, there have been 1,190 human cases of NWS reported and seven deaths. More than 148,000 animals have been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September, the USDA warned that an 8-month-old cow with an active NWS infection was found in a feedlot in the Mexican state of Nuevo León, just 70 miles from the border. The finding prompted Texas Agriculture Commissioner Sid Miller to step up warnings about the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The screwworm is dangerously close,” Miller said at the time. “It nearly wiped out our cattle industry before; we need to act forcefully now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According tothe USDA’s latest data, Nuevo León has seen three cases in the outbreak, with none that are currently active. But, its neighboring state, Tamaulipas, is having a flare-up, with eight animal cases considered active. The Mexican state shares a border with the southern-most portion of Texas. Mexico overall has reported 24 hospitalizations among people and 601 animal cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the NWS has not been detected in the US, and the CDC considers the risk to people to be low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“However, given the potential for geographic spread, CDC is issuing this Health Advisory to increase awareness of the outbreak and to summarize CDC recommendations for clinicians and health departments in the United States on case identification and reporting, specimen collection, diagnosis, and treatment of NWS, as well as guidance for the public,” the agency said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the agency advises being on the lookout for egg masses or fly larvae in wounds or infection sites, especially if there’s destruction of living tissue or feelings of movement. Once discovered, health care workers should report the case and promptly remove and kill all larvae and eggs, preferably by drowning in a sealed, leak-proof container of 70 percent ethanol. “Failure to kill and properly dispose of all larvae or eggs could result in the new introduction and spread of NWS in the local environment,” the CDC warns in bold. At least 10 dead larvae should then be sent to the CDC for confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The USDA is currently releasing 100 million sterile male flies per week in Mexico to try to establish a new biological barrier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the fly’s first attempt at a US comeback since the 1960s. In 2016, the flies were somehowreintroduced to the Florida Keys, where they viciously attacked Key Deer, an endangered species and the smallest of North America’s white-tailed deer. The flies were eliminated again in 2017 using the sterile fly method.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/be-on-the-lookout-for-flesh-eating-flies-cdc-tells-clinicians-in-alert/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:59:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google temporarily disabled YouTube’s advanced captions without warning</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/google-temporarily-disabled-youtubes-advanced-captions-without-warning/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/youtube-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google says SRV3 was causing playback errors, so it has “temporarily” disabled them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTubers have been increasingly frustrated with Google’s management of the platform, withdisinformation welcomed backand anaggressive push for more AI(except where Googledoesn’t like it). So it’s no surprise that creators have been up in arms over the suspicious removal of YouTube’s advanced SRV3 caption format. You don’t have to worry too much just yet—Google says this is only temporary, and it’s working on a fix for the underlying bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google added support for this custom subtitle format around 2018, giving creators more customization options than with traditional captions. SRV3 (also known as YTT or YouTube Timed Text) allows for custom colors, transparency, animations, fonts, and precise positioning in videos. Uploaders using this format can color-code and position captions to help separate multiple speakers, create sing-along animations, or style them to match the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last several days, creators who’ve become accustomed to this level of controlhave been dismayedto see that YouTube is no longer accepting videos with this Google-created format. Many worried Google had ditched the format entirely, which could be problematic for all those previously uploaded videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has now posted abrief statementand confirmed to Ars that it has not ended support for SRV3. However, all is not well. The company says it has temporarily limited the serving of SRV3 caption files because they may break playback for some users. That’s pretty vague, but it sounds like developers made a change to the platform without taking into account how it might interfere with SRV3 captions. Rather than allow those videos to be non-functional, it’s disabling most of the captions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google’s forum post says that while SRV3 is disabled, creators will not be able to upload new SRV3 captions. Videos that already have them may not show any captions until the feature is restored. However, Google notes most uploaders use other caption formats and are not affected by the playback bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Google also notes that the changes should be temporary foralmostall videos. That implies some features of SRV3 may not be fully supported with whatever Google is doing on the back end. The company makes no promises about a timeline to re-enable SRV3—creators who have relied heavily on it may have to go back and re-create their captions in less capable formats or simply rely on AI-generated captions in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether Google knew this would happen, it shouldn’t have left the community to stew about it for a week. This also suggests Google isn’t very serious about supporting its in-house CC format, which it has opted not to officially document. Creators should probably factor that into their future plans.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/google-temporarily-disabled-youtubes-advanced-captions-without-warning/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:17:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Verizon starts requiring 365 days of paid service before it will unlock phones</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-starts-requiring-365-days-of-paid-service-before-it-will-unlock-phones/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/verizon-1152x648-1752087139.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon changed prepaid brands’ policy a week after FCC waived unlocking rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon has started enforcing a 365-day lock period on phones purchased through its TracFone division, one week after the Federal Communications Commissionwaived a requirementthat Verizon unlock handsets 60 days after they are activated on its network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon was previously required to unlock phones automatically after 60 days due to restrictions imposed on itsspectrum licensesandmerger conditionsthat helped Verizon obtain approval of itspurchase of TracFone. But an update applied today to theTracFone unlocking policysaid new phones will be locked for at least a year and that each customer will have to request an unlock instead of getting it automatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “new” TracFone policy is basically a return to the yearlong locking itimposedbefore Verizon bought the company in 2021. TracFone first agreed to provide unlocking in a 2015settlement with the Obama-era FCC, which alleged that TracFone failed to comply with a commitment to unlock phones for customers enrolled in the Lifeline subsidy program. TracFone later shortened the locking period from a year to 60 days as a condition of the Verizon merger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a locked phone is tied to the network of one carrier, an unlocked phone can be switched to another carrier if the device is compatible with the other carrier’s network. But the new TracFone unlocking policy is stringent, requiring customers to pay for a full year of service before they can get a phone unlocked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For all cellphones Activated on or after January 20, 2026, the cellphone will be unlocked upon request after 365 days of paid and active service,” the policy says. A customer who doesn’t maintain an active service plan for the whole 12 months will thus have their unlocking eligibility date delayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides TracFone, the change applies to prepaid brands Straight Talk, Net10 Wireless, Clearway, Total Wireless, Simple Mobile, SafeLink Wireless, and Walmart Family Mobile. Customers who bought phones before today are still eligible for unlocks after 60 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AsDroidLife points out, the Verizon-owned prepaid brand Visible is also requiring a year of paid service. TheVisible policy updated todayrequires “at least 365 days of paid service” for an unlocking request. “If you stop paying for service, your progress toward the 365-day requirement pauses. It will resume once you reactivate your account and continue until you reach a total of 365 paid days of service,” the policy says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unlocking policy for Verizon-branded phones has not been updated since May 2025. Thepolicycalls for phones to be unlocked automatically after 60 days of paid service, but it will probably be changed soon because of the FCC waiver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once updated, the primary Verizon policy will presumably match the TracFone subsidiary’s 365-day locking period, or at least require something longer than 60 days. It’s also likely to require customers to request an unlock since the FCC no longer requires Verizon to unlock phones automatically. We contacted Verizon about its plans today and will update this article if it provides a response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AT&amp;T’s policyallows unlocking of phones on postpaid plans after 60 days if the device has been paid in full, or after six months for phones on prepaid plans.T-Mobile’s policyallows unlocking of phones on postpaid plans after 40 days if the device has been paid in full, or after 365 days for phones on prepaid plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon and FCC Chairman Brendan Carr have justified longer locking periods as a method of deterring fraud. When approving Verizon’s waiver request, the Carr FCC said the Verizon rule “required one wireless carrier to unlock their handsets well earlier than standard industry practice, thus creating an incentive for bad actors to steal those handsets for purposes of carrying out fraud and other illegal acts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer advocacy groups disputed the argument, telling the FCC that “Verizon offers no specific evidence that a longer lock period would have prevented the fraudulent acquisition of the devices it identifies,” and that Verizon is capable of detecting and responding to fraud within 60 days of a phone’s activation. Consumers and small carriers will be hurt by the decision, thegroups told the FCC, saying that automatic unlocking “facilitates the resale and reuse of mobile devices, reduces e-waste, and enables low-cost carriers and MVNOs to compete on a more level playing field.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Biden-era FCC’s leadershipcriticizedyearlong locking periods and proposed a 60-day unlocking requirement for all carriers, the Trump FCC appears likely to write a new industry-wide standard that would be welcomed by large mobile carriers. The FCC rejected arequestto limit Verizon’s locking period to 180 days, and said the Verizon waiver will stay in effect until the agency “decides on an appropriate industry-wide approach for the unlocking of handsets.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-starts-requiring-365-days-of-paid-service-before-it-will-unlock-phones/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:35:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zuck stuck on Trump’s bad side: FTC appeals loss in Meta monopoly case</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/zuck-stuck-on-trumps-bad-side-ftc-appeals-loss-in-meta-monopoly-case/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/zuck-the-monopolist-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FTC will appeal ruling that found Meta has no monopoly in social networking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still feeling uneasy about Meta’s acquisition of Instagram in 2012 and WhatsApp in 2014, the Federal Trade Commission will be appealing aNovember rulingthat cleared Meta of allegations that it holds an illegal monopoly in a market dubbed “personal social networking.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FTC hopes the US Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia will agree that “robust evidence at trial” showed that Meta’s acquisitions were improper. In the initial trial, the FTC sought a breakup of Meta’s apps, with Meta risking forced divestments of Instagram or WhatsApp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In apress releaseTuesday, the FTC confirmed that it “continues to allege” that “for over a decade Meta has illegally maintained a monopoly in personal social networking services through anticompetitive conduct—by buying the significant competitive threats it identified in Instagram and WhatsApp.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to press, FTC spokesperson Joe Simonson pointed out that the case against Meta originated during Donald Trump’s prior term, Reutersreported. Back then, Trump was frustrated with Facebook, claiming the company and its CEO, Mark Zuckerberg, were “anti-Trump” in 2017, the BBCreported. His frustrations only grew whenMeta banned his Facebook and Instagram accountsin 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahead of Trump’s second term, Zuckerberg has attempted to improve relations with Trump, donating $1 million to Trump’s inauguration fund in a move the BBC reported was intended to “repair his and his firm’s relationship with Trump.” Last January, Meta also paid Trump $25 million to settle lawsuits over his Facebook and Instagram suspensions, NPRreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these moves have seemingly not affected the FTC’s resolve to undo Meta’s alleged monopoly. On Tuesday, Simonson said the Meta crackdown remained a priority because the agency believes that “Meta violated our antitrust laws when it acquired Instagram and WhatsApp,” and “consequently, American consumers have suffered from Meta’s monopoly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Meta, the renewed fight comes at a time when most tech companies are walking tightropes to avoid any possible retaliation from Trump, not just social platforms. After defeating the FTC last fall, Meta’s chief legal officer, Jennifer Newstead, didn’t dunk on the FTC but coolly celebrated the ruling for recognizing that “Meta faces fierce competition.” In the same breath, Newstead also seemed to want to take the opportunity to remind the Trump administration that Meta was a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our products are beneficial for people and businesses and exemplify American innovation and economic growth,” Newstead said. “We look forward to continuing to partner with the Administration and to invest in America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, this week, Meta has offered a rather neutral response to the FTC’s announcement. Asked for comment on the FTC’s decision to appeal, Meta’s spokesperson simply told Ars that James Boasberg, the US district judge who sided with Meta, got it right the first time, then repeated one of Trump’s favorite refrains from tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The District Court’s decision to reject the FTC’s arguments is correct and recognizes the fierce competition we face,” Meta’s spokesperson said. “We will remain focused on innovating and investing in America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political tensions have remained at the center of the case, perhaps peaking after Boasberg’s ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, Simonson criticized Boasberg,telling CNBCthat “the deck was always stacked against us with Judge Boasberg, who is currently facing articles of impeachment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thatpush to impeach Boasbergcame from Republican lawmaker Brandon Gill, who alleged the judge was abusing his power to censor conservatives, but no actions have been taken since the proposed resolution was submitted to a House committee that month. Republicans,including Trump’s attorney general Pam Bondi, have complained that Boasberg is a rogue partisan judge, but Boasberg so far has withstood their attacks while continuing to settle cases. Trump’s Truth Social tirades against the judge required along fact-checking piecefrom PBS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Meta case itself may be hard to win even with a judge that Republicans favor. Last year, the FTC had tried to argue that Meta faced no real competition in the personal social networking market, with only two rivals to speak of, Snapchat and an app called MeWe. But for social media users, Instagram and TikTok are interchangeable, Meta successfully argued, and that makes TikTok as much a rival as Snapchat, Boasberg agreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Boasberg was not sold on the FTC’s argument that Meta was allegedly abusing its monopoly power and harming consumers by degrading the quality of the app while increasing ad loads. Rather, he agreed with Meta that the company had added many features “continuously” improving its apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, social media has changed so much since the days of Facebook competing for user engagement with Instagram that Boasberg emphasized that “the Court finds it impossible to believe that consumers would prefer the versions of Instagram and Facebook that existed a decade ago to the versions that exist today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the FTC revives the case, a new judge will weigh Meta’s arguments, the general thrust of which is that social networking as it was known in the early days of Facebook is dead, making the FTC’s case moot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear whether a different judge will see Meta as a monopolist or if Boasberg was right to conclude that the days of grouping apps into “separate markets of social networking and social media” are over.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/zuck-stuck-on-trumps-bad-side-ftc-appeals-loss-in-meta-monopoly-case/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:22:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Webb reveals a planetary nebula with phenomenal clarity, and it is spectacular</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/webb-has-given-us-with-a-stunning-new-view-of-a-well-known-planetary-nebula/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/STScI-01KCMAMZ8ZSMRTR9KKD8Y6EMRJ-2000x1440.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colors show the star’s final breath transforming into the raw ingredients for new worlds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Helix Nebula is one of the most well-known and commonly photographed planetary nebulae because it resembles the “Eye of Sauron.” It is also one of the closest bright nebulae to Earth, located approximately 655 light-years from our Solar System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may not know what this particular nebula looks like when reading its name, but the Hubble Space Telescope has taken some iconic images of it over the years. And almost certainly, you’ll recognize a photograph of the Helix Nebula, shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many objects in astronomy, planetary nebulae have a confusing name, since they are formed not by planets but by stars like our own Sun, though a little larger. Near the end of their lives, these stars shed large amounts of gas in an expanding shell that, however briefly in cosmological time, put on a grand show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the James Webb Space Telescope has turned its sights on the Helix Nebula, and, oh my, does it have a story to tell. NASAreleased the new imagesof the nebula on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this image, there are vibrant pillars of gas along the inner region of the nebula’s expanding shell of gas. According to the space agency, this is what we’re seeing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blazing white dwarf, the leftover core of the dying star, lies right at the heart of the nebula, out of the frame of the Webb image. Its intense radiation lights up the surrounding gas, creating a rainbow of features: hot ionized gas closest to the white dwarf, cooler molecular hydrogen farther out, and protective pockets where more complex molecules can begin to form within dust clouds. This interaction is vital, as it’s the raw material from which new planets may one day form in other star systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Webb’s image of the Helix Nebula, color represents the temperature and chemistry. A touch of a blue hue marks the hottest gas in this field, energized by intense ultraviolet light from the white dwarf. Farther out, the gas cools into the yellow regions where hydrogen atoms join into molecules. At the outer edges, the reddish tones trace the coolest material, where gas begins to thin and dust can take shape. Together, the colors show the star’s final breath transforming into the raw ingredients for new worlds, adding to the wealth of knowledge gained from Webb about the origin of planets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, in a word, phenomenal.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/webb-has-given-us-with-a-stunning-new-view-of-a-well-known-planetary-nebula/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:33:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>