<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 23:20:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>This 67,800-year-old hand stencil is the world’s oldest human-made art</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/this-67800-year-old-hand-stencil-is-the-worlds-oldest-human-made-art/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Narrowed-finger-hand-stencils-from-Leang-Jarie-Maros-Sulawesi-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s oldest art has an unintentional story to tell about human exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s oldest surviving rock art is a faded outline of a hand on an Indonesian cave wall, left 67,800 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a tiny island just off the coast of Sulawesi (a much larger island in Indonesia), a cave wall bears the stenciled outline of a person’s hand—and it’s at least 67,800 years old, according to a recent study. The hand stencil is now the world’s oldest work of art (at least until archaeologists find something even older), as well as the oldest evidence of our species on any of the islands that stretch between continental Asia and Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologist Adhi Agus Oktaviana, of Indonesia’s National Research and Innovation Agency, and his colleagues have spent the last six years surveying 44 rock art sites, mostly caves, on Sulawesi’s southeastern peninsula and the handful of tiny “satellite islands” off its coast. They found 14 previously undocumented sites and used rock formations to date 11 individual pieces of rock art in eight caves—including the oldest human artwork discovered so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 67,800 years ago, someone stood in the darkness of Liang Metanduno and placed their hand flat against the limestone wall. They, or maybe a friend, then blew a mixture of pigment and water onto the wall, covering and surrounding their hand. When they pulled their hand carefully away from the rock, careful not to disturb the still-wet paint, they left behind a crisp outline of their palm and fingers, haloed by a cloud of deep red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is basically the negative of a handprint, and it’s a visceral, tangible link to the past. Someone once laid their hand on the cave wallright here, and you can still see its outline like a lingering ghost, reaching out from the other side of the rock. If you weren’t worried about damaging the already faded and fragile image, you could lay your hand in the same spot and meet them halfway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the stencil is so faded that you can barely see it, but if you look closely, it’s there: a faint halo of reddish-orange pigment, outlining the top part of a palm and the base of the fingers. A thin, nearly transparent layer of calcite covers the faded shape, left behind by millennia of water dripping down the cave wall. The ratio of uranium and thorium in a sheet of calcite suggests that it formed at least 71,000 years ago—so the outline of the hand beneath it must have been left behind sometime before that, probably around 67,800 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes Liang Metanduno the home of the oldest known artwork in the world, beating the previous contender (a Neanderthal hand stencil in Spain) by about 1,100 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These findings support the growing view that Sulawesi was host to a vibrant and longstanding artistic culture during the late Pleistocene epoch,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues in their recent paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The karst caves of Sulawesi’s southwestern peninsula, Maros-Pangkep, area treasure trove of deeply ancient artwork: hand stencils, as well asdrawings of wild animals, people, and strange figures that seem to blend the two. A cave wall at Liang Bulu’Sipong 4 featuresa 4.5-meter-long mural of humanlike figuresfacing off against wild pigs and dwarf buffalo, anda 2024 studypushed the mural’s age back to 51,200 years ago, making it the second-oldest artwork that we know of (after the Liang Metanduno hand stencil in the recent study).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists have only begun to rediscover the rock art of Maros-Pangkep in the last decade or so, and other areas of the island, like Southeast Sulawesi and its tiny satellite islands, have received even less attention—so we don’t know what’s still there waiting for humanity to find again after dozens of millennia. We also don’t know what the ancient artist was trying to convey with the outline of their hand on the cave wall, but part of the message rings loud and clear across tens of millennia: At least 67,800 years ago, someone was here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hand stencil on the wall of Liang Metanduno is, so far, the oldest evidence of our presence in Wallacea, the group of islands stretched between the continental shelves of Asia and Australia. Populating these islands is “widely considered to have involved the first planned, long-distance sea crossing undertaken by our species,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when the long-lost artist laid their hand on the wall, sea levels were about 100 meters lower than they are today. Mainland Asia, Sumatra, and Borneo would have been high points in a single landmass, joined by wide swaths of lowlands that today lie beneath shallow ocean. The eastern shore of Borneo would have been a jumping-off point, beyond which lay several dozen kilometers of water and (out of view over the horizon) Sulawesi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first few people may have washed ashore on Sulawesi on some misadventure: lost fishermen or tsunami survivors, maybe. But at some point, people must have started making the crossing on purpose, which implies that they knew how to build rafts or boats, how to steer them, and that land awaited them on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liang Metanduno pushes back the timing of that crossing by nearly 10,000 years. It also lends strong support to arguments that people arrived in Australia earlier than archaeologists had previously suspected. Archaeological evidence from a rock shelter called Madjedbebe, in northern Australia, suggests that people were living there by 65,000 years ago. But that evidence is still debated (such is the nature of archaeology), and some archaeologists argue that humans didn’t reach the continent until around 50,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With the discovery of rock art dating to at least 67,800 years ago in Sulawesi, a large island on the most plausible colonization route to Australia, it is increasingly likely that the controversial date of 65,000 years for the initial peopling of Australia is correct,” Griffith University archaeologists Adam Brumm, a coauthor of the recent study, told Ars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists are still trying to work out exactly when, where, and how the first members of our species made the leap from the continent of Asia to the islands of Wallacea and, eventually, via several more open-water crossings, to Australia. Our picture of the process is pieced together from archaeological finds and models of ancient geography and sea levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s been all sorts of work done on this (not by me), but often researchers consider the degree of intervisibility between islands, as well as other things like prevailing ocean currents and wind directions, changes in sea levels and how this affects the land area of islands and shorelines and so on,” Brumm said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of those models suggest that people crossed the Makassar Strait from Borneo to Sulawesi, then island-hopped through what’s now Indonesia until they reached the western edge of New Guinea. At the time, lower sea levels would have left New Guinea, Australia, and New Zealand as one big land mass, so getting from New Guinea to what’s now Australia would actually have been the easy part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a sense of deep, deep time in Liang Metanduno. The cave wall is a palimpsest on which the ancient hand stencil is nearly covered by a brown-hued drawing of a chicken, which (based on its subject matter) must have been added sometime after 5,000 years ago, when a new wave of settlers brought domesticated chickens to the island. It seems almost newfangled against the ghostly faint outline of the Paleolithic hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few centimeters away is another hand stencil, done in darker pigment and dating to around 21,500 years ago; it overlays a lighter stencil dating to around 60,900 years ago. Over tens of thousands of years, generations of people returned here with the same impulse. We have no way of knowing whether visitors 21,500 years ago, or 5,000 years ago might have seen a more vibrantly decorated cave wall than what’s preserved today—but we know that they decided to leave their mark on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the people who visited the cave 21,500 years ago shared a sense of style with the artists who left their hands outlined on the wall nearly 40,000 years before them: both handprints have slightly pointed fingers, as if the artist either turned their fingertip or just touched-up the outline with some paint after making the stencil. It’s very similar to other hand stencils, dated to around 17,000 years ago, from elsewhere on Sulawesi, and it’s a style that seems unique to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We may conclude that this regionally unique variant of stencil art is much older than previously thought,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AndHomo sapienswasn’t the first hominin species to venture as far as Indonesia; at least 200,000 years earlier,Homo erectusmade a similar journey, leaving behind fossils and stone tools to mark that they, too, were once here. On some of the smaller islands, isolated populations ofHomo erectusstarted to evolve along their own paths, eventually leading to diminutive species likeHomo floresiensis(the O.G. hobbits) on FloresandHomo luzonensison Luzon.Homo floresiensisco-discoverer Richard Roberts has suggested thatother isolated hominin species may have existedon other scattered islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropologists haven’t found any fossil evidence of these species after 50,000 years ago, but if our species was in Indonesia by nearly 68,000 years ago, we would have been in time to meet our hominin cousins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature, 2026. DOI:10.1038/s41586-025-09968-y(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/this-67800-year-old-hand-stencil-is-the-worlds-oldest-human-made-art/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:00:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>2026 Lucid Air Touring review: This feels like a complete car now</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/2026-lucid-air-touring-review-this-feels-like-a-complete-car-now/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/2026-Lucid-Air-Touring-1-e1768932171844-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s efficient, easy to live with, and smooth to drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life as a startup carmaker is hard—just ask Lucid Motors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When wemet the brand and its prototype Lucid Air sedan in 2017, the company planned to put the first cars in customers’ hands within a couple of years. But you know what they say about plans. A lack of funding paused everything until late 2018, when Saudi Arabia’s sovereign wealth fundbought itself a stake. A billion dollars meant Lucid could build a factory—at the cost of alienating some former fans because of the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the pandemic happened,further pushing back timelinesas supply shortages took hold. But the Air did go on sale, and it has more recently been joined by theGravity SUV. There’s even a much more affordable midsize SUV in the works called the Earth. Sales more than doubled in 2025, and after spending a week with a model year 2026 Lucid Air Touring, I can understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now quite a few different versions of the Air to choose from. Forjust under a quarter of a million dollars, there’s the outrageously powerful Air Sapphire, which offers acceleration so rapid it’s unlikely your internal organs will ever truly get used to the experience. At the other end of the spectrum is the $70,900 Air Pure, a single-motor model that’s currently the brand’s entry point but whichalso stands as a darn good EV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time I tested a Lucid, it was the Air Grand Touring almost three years ago. That car mostly impressed me but still felt a little unfinished, especially at $138,000. This time, I looked at the Air Touring, which starts at $79,900, and the experience was altogether more polished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Touring features a less-powerful all-wheel-drive powertrain than the Grand Touring, although to put “less-powerful” into context, with 620 hp (462 kW) on tap, there are almost as many horses available as in the legendary McLaren F1. (That remains a mental benchmark for many of us of a certain age.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Touring’s 885 lb-ft (1,160 Nm) is far more than BMW’s 6-liter V12 can generate, but at 5,009 lbs (2,272 kg), the electric sedan weighs twice as much as the carbon-fiber supercar. The fact that the Air Touring can reach 60 mph (98 km/h) from a standing start in just 0.2 seconds more than the McLaren tells you plenty about how much more accessible acceleration has become in the past few decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, it will if you choose the fastest of the three drive modes, labeled Sprint. There’s also Swift, and the least frantic of the three, Smooth. Helpfully, each mode remembers your regenerative braking setting when you lift the accelerator pedal. Unlike many other EVs, Lucid does not use a brake-by-wire setup, and pressing the brake pedal will only ever slow the car via friction brakes. Even with lift-off regen set to off, the car does not coast well due to its permanent magnet electric motors, unlike the electric powertrains developed by German OEMs like Mercedes-Benz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to suggest that Lucid is doing something wrong—not with its efficiency numbers. On 19-inch aero-efficient wheels, the car has an EPA range of 396 miles (673 km) from a 92 kWh battery pack. As just about everyone knows, you won’t get ideal EV efficiency during winter, and our test with the Lucid in early January coincided with some decidedly colder temperatures, as well as larger ($1,750) 20-inch wheels. Despite this, I averaged almost 4 miles/kWh (15.5 kWh/100 km) on longer highway drives, although this fell to around 3.5 miles/kWh (17.8 kWh/100 km) in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recharging the Air Touring also helped illustrate how the public DC fast-charging experience has matured over the years. The Lucid uses the ISO 15118 “plug and charge” protocol, so you don’t need to mess around with an app or really do anything more complicated than plug the charging cable into the Lucid’s CCS1 socket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the car and charger complete their handshake, the car gives the charger account and billing info, then the electrons flow. Charging from 27 to 80 percent with a manually preconditioned battery took 36 minutes. During that time, the car added 53.3 kWh, which equated to 209 miles (336 km) of range, according to the dash. Although we didn’t test AC charging, 0–100 percent should take around 10 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit, I’m a bit of a sucker for the way the Air looks when it’s not two-tone. That’s the Stealth option ($1,750), and the dark Fathom Blue Metallic paint ($800) and blacked-out aero wheels pushed many of my buttons. I found plenty to like from the driver’s seat, too. The 34-inch display that wraps around the driver once looked massive—now it feels relatively restrained compared to the “Best Buy on wheels” effect in some other recent EVs. The fact that the display isn’t very tall helps its feeling of restraint here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle is a minimalist display for the driver, with touch-sensitive displays on either side. To your left are controls for the lights, locks, wipers, and so on. These icons are always in the same place, though there’s no tactile feedback. The infotainment screen to the right is within the driver’s reach, and it’s here that (wireless) Apple CarPlay will show up. As you can see in a photo below, CarPlay fills the irregularly shaped screen with a wallpaper but keeps its usable area confined to the rectangle in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curved display floats above the textile-covered dash, and the daylight visible between them helps the cabin’s sense of spaciousness, even without a panoramic glass roof. A stowable touchscreen display lower down on the center console is where you control vehicle, climate, seat, and lighting settings, although there are also physical controls for temperature and volume on the dash. The relatively good overall ergonomics take a bit of a hit from the steeply raked A pillar, which creates a blind spot for the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the Air Touring’s power, it isn’t a car that goads you into using it all. In fact, I spent most of the week in the gentlest setting, Smooth. It’s an easy car to drive slowly, and the rather artificial feel of the steering at low speeds means you probably won’t take it hunting apices on back roads. I should note, though, that each drive mode has its own steering calibration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, as a daily driver and particularly on longer drives, the Touring did a fine job. Despite being relatively low to the ground, it’s easy to get into and out of. The rear seat is capacious, and the ride is smooth, so passengers will enjoy it. Even more so if they sit up front—Lucid has some of the best (optional, $3,750) massaging seats in the business, which vibrate as well as kneading you. There’s a very accessible 22 cubic foot (623 L) trunk as well as a 10 cubic foot (283 L) frunk, so it’s practical, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our test Air was fitted with Lucid’s DreamDrive Pro advanced driver assistance system ($6,750), which includes a hands-free “level 2+” assist that requires you to pay attention to the road ahead but which handles accelerating, braking, and steering. Using the turn signal tells the car to perform a lane change if it’s safe, and I found it to be an effective driver assist with an active driver monitoring system (which uses a gaze-tracking camera to ensure the driver is doing their part).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucidrolled outthe more advanced features of DreamDrive Pro last summer, and it plans to develop the system into a more capable “level 3” partially automated system that lets the driver disengage completely from the act of driving, at least at lower speeds. Although that system is some ways off—and level 3 systems are only road-legal in Nevada and California right now anyway—even the current level 2+ system leverages lidar as well as cameras, radar, and ultrasonics, and the dash display does a good job of showing you what other vehicles the Air is perceiving around it when the system is active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the model year 2026 Air feels polished, far more so than the last Lucid I drove. Designed by a refugee from Tesla, the car promised to improve on the EVs from that brand in every way. And while early Airs might have fallen short in execution, the cars can now credibly be called finished products, with much better fit and finish than a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll go so far as to say that I might have a hard time deciding between an Air or an equivalently priced Porsche Taycan were I in the market for a luxury electric four-door, even though they both offer quite different driving experiences. Be warned, though, like with the Porsche, the options can add up quickly, and the resale prices can be shockingly low.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/2026-lucid-air-touring-review-this-feels-like-a-complete-car-now/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tiny falcons are helping keep the food supply safe on cherry farms</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/tiny-falcons-are-helping-keep-the-food-supply-safe-on-cherry-farms/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/kestrel-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their presence appears to lower the risk of food-borne illnesses from pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every spring, raptors return to nesting sites across northern Michigan. The smallest of these birds of prey, a falcon called the American kestrel (Falco sparverius), flies through the region’s many cherry orchards and spends its days hunting for even tinier creatures to eat. This quest keeps the kestrels fed, but it also benefits the region’s cherry farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fruit farmers have been working symbiotically with kestrels for decades, adding nesting boxes and reaping the benefits of the birds eliminating the mice, voles, songbirds, and other pests that wreak havoc by feeding on not-yet-harvested crops. In addition to limiting the crop damage caused by hungry critters, new research suggests kestrels also lower the risk of food-borne illnesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, published in November in theJournal of Applied Ecology, suggests the kestrels help keep harmful pathogens off of fruit headed to consumers by eating and scaring off small birds that carry those pathogens. Orchards housing the birds in nest boxes saw fewer cherry-eating birds than orchards without kestrels on site. This translated to an 81 percent reduction in crop damage—such as bite marks or missing fruit—and a 66 percent decrease in branches contaminated with bird feces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kestrels are not very expensive to bring into orchards, but they work pretty well” at deterring unwanted bird species, said Olivia Smith, lead study author and assistant professor of horticulture at Michigan State University. “And people just like kestrels a lot, so I think it’s an attractive strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a good strategy for managing pests is essential for cherry farmers. Pests cause expensive damage that worsens yields already impacted byother threatsto the cherry industry, such as climate change, labor shortages, and the vagaries of international trade. To stop the added damage from pests, growers have turned to nets covering their trees, noisemakers, scarecrows, pesticides, and even the removal of natural habitats around crop-growing areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these options can be expensive and aren’t always effective. Even with these management strategies in place, birds like starlings, robins, and crows cost farms in some top cherry growing states—including Michigan, New York, Oregon, Washington, and California—about$85 million annually. For many growers, this is where the kestrels come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem counterintuitive to solve a bird problem by bringing in more birds, but kestrels are skilled hunters whose presence drives off songbirds afraid of being eaten. Habitat loss, competition for food, and climate change are leading to slow and steadypopulation declinesfor the American kestrel, losses of about1.4 percent annually. Still, these birds are abundant enough that, in many areas of the continental United States, all farmers need to do to attract them is add a nesting box to their land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve noticed a difference having the kestrels around, hovering over the spring crops,” said Brad Thatcher, a farmer based in Washington state who has housed kestrels on April Joy Farm, an organic fruit and vegetable farm, for over 13 years. “There’s very little fecal damage from small songbirds at that time of year versus the fall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With farmers who already had kestrels on their land reporting fewer songbirds and less crop damage, study authors hypothesized that food safety risks associated with pathogens birds carry may also be lower for farms harboring kestrels. To test this, the researchers evaluated 16 sweet cherry orchards in Michigan’s Leelanau and Grand Traverse counties (the latter of which is considered the “Cherry Capital of the World”). Eight of the orchards studied had nesting boxes for kestrels and eight did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study authors randomly selected two areas of each orchard to search for crop damage and fecal contamination. The orchards frequented by kestrels saw the amount of damaged fruit drop from 2.5 percent to 0.47 percent. The number of crops contaminated by bird droppings also saw a three-fold decrease, falling from 6.88 percent to 2.33 percent. When researchers tested this excrement, they found that more than 10 percent contained campylobacter, a type of bacteria that is common in birds and causes food-borne illness in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Campylobacter is a common cause of food poisoning and ison the rise in Michiganandaround the world. It spreads to humans through food products made from, or that come into contact with, infected animals, primarily chickens and other birds. So far, only one outbreak of campylobacteriosis has beendefinitively linkedto feces from wild birds. Still, because it causes milder symptoms than some other types of bacteria, the Centers for Disease Control considers campylobacter asignificantly underreportedcause of food-borne illness that may be more common than current data indicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trying to get more birds of prey would be beneficial to farmers,” Smith said. “If you have one predator, versus a bunch of prey, you have fewer birds overall. If you have a lot fewer birds, even if the ones that are there are carrying bacteria, then you can reduce the transmission risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study’s findings that kestrels significantly reduce physical damage and food safety risks on Michigan cherry farms demonstrate that managing crops and meeting conservation goals—by bolstering local kestrel populations and eliminating the need to clear wildlife habitat around agricultural areas—can be done in tandem, study authors say. They recommend farmers facing pest-management issues consider building kestrel boxes, which cost about $100 per box and require minimal maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether nesting boxes in a given region will be successfully inhabited by kestrels depends on whether there is an abundance of the birds there. In Michigan’s cherry-growing region, kestrels are so abundant that 80 percent to 100 percent of boxes become home for kestrels rather than other nesting birds, said Catherine Lindell, avian ecologist at Michigan State University and senior author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems like this is just a great tool for farmers,” Lindell said, suggesting interested farmers “put up a couple boxes and see what happens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K.R. Callaway is a reporter and editor specializing in science, health, history, and policy stories. She is currently pursuing a master’s degree in journalism at New York University, where she is part of the Science, Health, and Environmental Reporting Program (SHERP). Her writing has appeared in Scientific American, Sky &amp; Telescope, Fast Company and Audubon Magazine, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story originally appeared onInside Climate News.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/tiny-falcons-are-helping-keep-the-food-supply-safe-on-cherry-farms/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:10:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rocket Report: Chinese rockets fail twice in 12 hours; Rocket Lab reports setback</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/rocket-report-rocket-lab-reports-neutron-setback-australia-backs-launch-startup/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/54643108625_7db2967a37_k-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another partially reusable Chinese rocket, the Long March 12B, is nearing its first test flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Edition 8.26 of the Rocket Report! The past week has been one of advancements and setbacks in the rocket business. NASA rolled the massive rocket for the Artemis II mission to its launch pad in Florida, while Chinese launchers suffered back-to-back failures within a span of approximately 12 hours. Rocket Lab’s march toward a debut of its new Neutron launch vehicle in the coming months may have stalled after a failure during a key qualification test. We cover all this and more in this week’s Rocket Report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, wewelcome reader submissions. If you don’t want to miss an issue, please subscribe using the box below (the form will not appear on AMP-enabled versions of the site). Each report will include information on small-, medium-, and heavy-lift rockets, as well as a quick look ahead at the next three launches on the calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia invests in sovereign launch.Six months after its first orbital rocket cleared the launch tower for just 14 seconds before crashing back to Earth, Gilmour Space Technologies has secured 217 million Australian dollars ($148 million) in funding that CEO Adam Gilmour says finally gives Australia a fighting chance in the global space race,the Sydney Morning Herald reports. The funding round, led by the federal government’s National Reconstruction Fund Corporation and superannuation giant Hostplus with $75 million each, makes the Queensland company Australia’s newest unicorn—a fast-growth start-up valued at more than $1 billion—and one of the country’s most heavily backed private technologyventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homegrown rocket… “We’re a rocket company that has never had access to the capital that our American competitors have,” Gilmour told the newspaper. “This is the first raise where I’ve actually raised a decent amount of capital compared to the rest of the world.” The investment reflects growing concern about Australia’s reliance on foreign launch providers—predominantly Elon Musk’s SpaceX—to put government, defense, and commercial satellites into orbit. With US launch queues stretching beyond two years and geopolitical tensions reshaping access to space infrastructure, Canberra has identified sovereign launch capability as a strategic priority. Gilmour’s first Eris rocket lifted off from the Bowen Orbital Spaceport in North Queensland on July 30 last year. It achieved 14 seconds of flight before falling back to the ground, a result Gilmour framed as a partial success in an industry where first launches routinely fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isar Aerospace postpones test flight.Isar Aerospace scrubbed a potential January 21 launch of its Spectrum rocket to address a technical fault,Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology reports. Hours before the launch window was set to open, the German company said that it was addressing “an issue with a pressurization valve.” A valve issue was one of the factors that caused a Spectrum to crash moments after liftoff on Isar’s first test flight last year. “The teams are currently assessing the next possible launch opportunities and a new target date will be announced shortly,” the company wrote in a post on its website. The Spectrum rocket, designed to haul cargoes of up to a metric ton (2,200 pounds) to low-Earth orbit, is awaiting liftoff from Andøya Spaceport in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geopolitics at play... The second launch of Isar’s Spectrum rocket comes at a time when Europe’s space industry looks to secure the continent’s sovereignty in spaceflight. European satellites are no longer able to launch on Russian rockets, and the continent’s leaders don’t have much of an appetite to turn to US rockets amid strained trans-Atlantic relations. Europe’s satellite industry is looking for more competition for the Ariane 6 and Vega C rockets developed by ArianeGroup and Avio, and Isar Aerospace appears to be best positioned to become a new entrant in the European launch market. “I’m well aware that it would be really good for us Europeans to get this one right,” said Daniel Metzler, Isar’s co-founder and CEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A potential buyer for Orbex?UK-based rocket builder Orbex has signed a letter of intent to sell its business to European space logistics startup The Exploration Company,European Spaceflight reports. Orbex was founded in 2015 and is developing a small launch vehicle called Prime. The company also began work on a larger medium-lift launch vehicle called Proxima in December 2024. On Wednesday, Orbex published a brief press release stating that a letter of intent had been signed and that negotiations had begun. The company added that all details about the transaction remain confidential at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time’s up... A statement from Orbex CEO Phil Chambers suggests that the company’s financial position factored into its decision to pursue a buyer. “Our Series D fundraising could have led us in many directions,” said Chambers. “We believe this opportunity plays to the strengths of both businesses, and we look forward to sharing more when the time is right.” The Exploration Company, headquartered near Munich, Germany, is developing a reusable space capsule to ferry cargo to low-Earth orbit and a high-thrust reusable rocket engine. It is one of the most well-financed space startups in Europe. Orbex is one of five launch startups in Europe selected by the European Space Agency last year to compete in the European Launcher Challenge and receive funding from ESA member states. But the UK company’s financial standing is in question. Orbex’s Danish subsidiary is filing for bankruptcy, and its main UK entity is overdue in filing its 2024 financial accounts. (submitted by EllPeaTea)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bad day for Chinese rockets.China suffered a pair of launch failures January 16, seeing the loss of a classified Shijian satellite and the failed first launch of the Ceres-2 rocket,Space News reports. The first of the two failures involved the attempted launch of a Shijian military satellite aboard a Long March 3B rocket from the Xichang launch base in southwestern China. The Shijian 32 satellite was likely heading for a geostationary transfer orbit, but a failure of the Long March 3B’s third stage doomed the mission. The Long March 3B is one of China’s most-flown rockets, and this was the first failure of a Long March 3-series vehicle since 2020, ending a streak of 50 consecutive successful flights of the rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then… Less than 12 hours later, another Chinese rocket failed on its climb to orbit. This launch, using a Ceres-2 rocket, originated from the Jiuquan space center in northwestern China. It was the first flight of the Ceres-2, a larger variant of the light-class Ceres-1 rocket developed and operated by a Chinese commercial startup named Galactic Energy. Chinese officials did not disclose the payloads lost on the Ceres-2 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neutron in neutral.Rocket Lab suffered a structural failure of the Neutron rocket’s Stage 1 tank during testing, setting back efforts to get to the inaugural flight for the partially reusable launcher,Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology reports. The mishap occurred during a hydrostatic pressure trial, the company said Wednesday. “There was no significant damage to the test structure or facilities,” Rocket Lab added. Rocket Lab last year pushed the first Neutron mission from 2025 to 2026, citing the volume of testing ahead. The US-based company said it is now analyzing what transpired to determine the impact on Neutron launch plans. Rocket Lab said it would provide an update during its next quarterly financials, due in a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to go from here?… The Neutron rocket is designed to catapult Rocket Lab into more direct competition with legacy rocket companies like SpaceX and United Launch Alliance. “The next Stage 1 tank is already in production, and Neutron’s development campaign continues,” the company said. Setbacks like this one are to be expected during the development of new rockets. Rocket Lab has publicized aggressive, or aspirational, launch schedules for the first Neutron rocket, so it’s likely the company will hang onto its projection of a debut launch in 2026, at least for now. (submitted by EllPeaTea)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Falcon 9 launches NRO spysats.SpaceX executed a late night Falcon 9 launch from Vandenberg Space Force Base on January 16, carrying an undisclosed number of intelligence-gathering satellites for the National Reconnaissance Office,Spaceflight Now reports. The mission, NROL-105, hauled a payload of satellites heading to low-Earth orbit, which are believed to be Starshield, a government variant of the Starlink satellites. “Today’s mission is the twelfth overall launch of the NRO’s proliferated architecture and first of approximately a dozen NRO launches scheduled throughout 2026 consisting of proliferated and national security missions,” the NRO said in a post-launch statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mysteries abound… A public accounting of the agency’s proliferated constellation suggests it now numbers nearly 200 satellites with the ability to rapidly image locations around the world. The NRO has dozens more satellites serving other functions. “Having hundreds of NRO satellites on orbit is critical to supporting our nation and its partners,” the agency said in a statement. “This growing constellation enhances mission resilience and capability through reduced revisit times, improved persistent coverage, and accelerated processing and delivery of critical data.” What was unusual about the January 16 mission is it may have only carried two satellites, well short of the 20-plus Starshield satellites launched on most previous Falcon 9 launches,according to Jonathan McDowell, an astrophysicist and expert tracker of global space launch activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long March 12B hot-fired at Jiuquan.China’s main space contractor performed a static fire test of a new reusable Long March rocket Friday, paving the way for a test flight,Space News reports. The test-firing of the Long March 12B rocket’s first stage engines occurred on a launch pad at the Dongfeng Commercial Space Innovation Test Zone at Jiuquan spaceport in northwestern China. The mere existence of the Long March 12B rocket was not publicly known until recently. The new rocket was developed by a subsidiary of the state-owned China Aerospace Science Technology Corporation, with the capacity to carry a payload of 20 metric tons to low-Earth orbit in expendable mode. It’s unknown if the first Long March 12B test flight will include a booster landing attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one… The Long March 12B has a reusable first stage with landing legs, similar to the recovery architecture of SpaceX’s Falcon 9 rocket. The booster is designed to land downrange at a recovery zone in the Gobi Desert. The Long March 12B is the latest in a line of partially reusable Chinese rockets to reach the launch pad, following soon after the debut launches of the Long March 12A and Zhuque 3 rocket last month. Several more companies in China are working on their own reusable boosters. Of them all, the Long March 12B appears to be the closest to a clone of SpaceX’s Falcon 9. Like the Falcon 9, the Long March 12B will have nine kerosene-fueled first stage engines and a single kerosene-fueled upper stage engine. Chinese officials have not announced when the Long March 12B will launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artemis II rolls to the launch pad.Preparations for the first human spaceflight to the Moon in more than 50 years took a big step forward last weekend with the rollout of the Artemis II rocket to its launch pad,Ars reports. The rocket reached a top speed of just 1 mph on the four-mile, 12-hour journey from the Vehicle Assembly Building to Launch Complex 39B at NASA’s Kennedy Space Center in Florida. At the end of its nearly 10-day tour through cislunar space, the Orion capsule on top of the rocket will exceed 25,000 mph as it plunges into the atmosphere to bring its four-person crew back to Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key test ahead…“This is the start of a very long journey,” said NASA Administrator Jared Isaacman. “We ended our last human exploration of the Moon on Apollo 17.” The Artemis II mission will set several notable human spaceflight records. Astronauts Reid Wiseman, Victor Glover, Christina Koch, and Jeremy Hansen will travel farther from Earth than any human in history as they travel beyond the far side of the Moon. They won’t land. That distinction will fall to the next mission in line in NASA’s Artemis program. This will be the first time astronauts have flown on the Space Launch System rocket and Orion spacecraft. The launch window opens February 6, but the exact date of Artemis II’s liftoff will be determined by the outcome of a critical fueling test of the SLS rocket scheduled for early February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Origin confirms rocket reuse plan.Blue Origin confirmed Thursday that the next launch of its New Glenn rocket will carry a large communications satellite into low-Earth orbit for AST SpaceMobile,Ars reports. The rocket will launch the next-generation Block 2 BlueBird satellite “no earlier than late February” from Launch Complex 36 at Cape Canaveral Space Force Station. However,the update from Blue Originappears to have buried the real news toward the end: “The mission follows the successful NG-2 mission, which included the landing of the ‘Never Tell Me The Odds’ booster. The same booster is being refurbished to power NG-3,” the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressive strides…The second New Glenn mission launched on November 13, just 10 weeks ago. If the company makes the late-February target for the next mission—and Ars was told last week to expect the launch to slip into March—it will represent a remarkably short turnaround for an orbital booster. By way of comparison, SpaceX did not attempt to refly the first Falcon 9 booster it landed in December 2015. Instead, initial tests revealed that the vehicle’s interior had been somewhat torn up. It was scrapped and inspected closely so that engineers could learn from the wear and tear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan. 25:Falcon 9 | Starlink 17-20 | Vandenberg Space Force Base, California | 15:17 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan. 26:Falcon 9 | GPS III SV09 | Cape Canaveral Space Force Station, Florida | 04:46 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan. 26:Long March 7A | Unknown Payload | Wenchang Space Launch Site, China | 21:00 UTC&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/rocket-report-rocket-lab-reports-neutron-setback-australia-backs-launch-startup/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:31:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla kills Autopilot, locks lane-keeping behind $99/month fee</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/tesla-wants-recurring-revenue-discontinues-autopilot-in-favor-of-fsd/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1415090444-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With falling sales and shrinking profits, the recurring revenue will be most welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love it or hate it, Tesla has been responsible for helping to shape the tastes of automotive consumers over the past decade-plus. Over-the-air updates that add more features, an all-touchscreen human-machine interface, large castings, and hands-free driver assists were all introduced or popularized by Tesla’s electric vehicles,prompting other automakers to copy them, mostly in the hopes of seeing the same stratospheric gains in their stock prices. But starting on Valentine’s Day, if you want your Tesla to steer itself, you’ll have to pay a $99 monthly subscription fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla currently offers a pair of so-called “level 2” partially automated driver assist systems. Autopilot is the older of these, combining Tesla’s adaptive cruise control (Tesla calls this TACC) and lane-keeping assist (Tesla calls this Autosteer).FSD is the newer system, meant to be more capable and for use on surface streets and divided-lane highways. Although the company and Tesla CEO Elon Musk regularly tout these systems’ capabilities, both still require the human driver to provide situational awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Autopilot has been under fire from regulators and the courts. Multiple wrongful death lawsuits are in the works, and aftera high-profile loss resulting in a $329 million judgmentagainst Tesla, expect many of these suits to be settled. Both thefederal governmentandCaliforniahave investigated whether Tesla misled customers, and in December, an administrative law judgeruled that Tesla indeed engaged in deceptive marketingby implying that its cars could drive themselves. The judge suspended Tesla’s license to sell cars in California, a decision that the California Department of Motor Vehicles stayed for 60 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla was told that if it couldn’t resolve the deceptive marketing within those 60 days, the sales suspension would take effect. That would be bad for the automaker, as California is far and away its largest market in the US, albeitone thatis shrinkingeach quarter. Having to suspend sales entirely in the state would be disastrous. Some had speculated that Tesla could change Autopilot’s name to something less misleading, but the company chose a more drastic approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you want your new Tesla to steer itself—while you pay attention to the road—you will have to pay for FSD. Until the middle of February, that can be done for a one-time fee of $8,000. But starting on February 14, that option goes away, too, and the sole choice will be a $99/month FSD subscription.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But probably not for very long. Last night, Muskrevealed on his social media platformthat “the $99/month for supervised FSD will rise as FSD’s capabilities improve. The massive value jump is when you can be on your phone or sleeping for the entire ride (unsupervised FSD).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quest for recurring revenue streams is becoming something of a holy grail in the automotive industry as OEMs that previously treated their customers as a single sale now hope to make themselves more attractive to investors by encouraging customers to give them regular payouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may have contributed to General Motors’decision to drop Apple CarPlay and Android Automotive. BMW has alsoexperimentedwithsubscription services. Tesla’s stock price remains so high that such games are probably unnecessary here, but with falling profit margins, declining sales, and the loss of emissions credits to bolster the bottom line, one can see why regular cash infusions from Tesla drivers would be desirable.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/tesla-wants-recurring-revenue-discontinues-autopilot-in-favor-of-fsd/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:54:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok deal is done; Trump wants praise while users fear MAGA tweaks</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-finalizes-trump-deal-that-allows-bytedance-to-maintain-some-control/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257704699-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am so happy”: Trump closes deal that hands TikTok US to his allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TikTok deal is done, and Donald Trump is claiming a win, although it remains unclear if the joint venture he arranged with ByteDance and the Chinese government actually resolves Congress’ national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In apress releaseThursday, TikTok announced the “TikTok USDS Joint Venture LLC,” an entity established to keep TikTok operating in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving Americans majority ownership, ByteDance retains 19.9 percent of the joint venture, the release said, which has been valued at $14 billion. Three managing investors—Silver Lake, Oracle, and MGX—each hold 15 percent, while other investors, including Dell Technologies CEO Michael Dell’s investment firm, Dell Family Office, hold smaller, undisclosed stakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans will also have majority control over the joint venture’s seven-member board. TikTok CEO Shou Chew holds ByteDance’s only seat. Finalizing the deal was a “great move,” Chew told TikTok employees in an internal memo, The New York Timesreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two former TikTok employees will lead the joint venture. Adam Presser, who previously served as TikTok’s global head of Operations and Trust &amp; Safety, has been named CEO. And Kim Farrell, TikTok’s former global head of Business Operations Protection, will serve as chief security officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has claimed the deal meets requirements for “qualified divestiture” to avoid a TikTok ban otherwise required under the Protecting Americans from Foreign Adversary Controlled Applications Act. However, questions remain, as lawmakers have not yet analyzed the terms of the deal to determine whether that’s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law requires the divestment “to end any ‘operational relationship’ between ByteDance and TikTok in the United States,” critics told the NYT. That could be a problem, since TikTok’s release makes it clear that ByteDance will maintain some control over the TikTok US app’s operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, while the US owners will retrain the algorithm and manage data security, ByteDance owns the algorithm and “will manage global product interoperability and certain commercial activities, including e-commerce, advertising, and marketing.” The Trump administration seemingly agreed to these terms to ensure that the US TikTok isn’t cut off from the rest of the world on the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Interoperability enables the Joint Venture to provide US users with a global TikTok experience, ensuring US creators can be discovered and businesses can operate on a global scale,” the release said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps also concerning to Congress, Slatenoted,while ByteDance may be a minority owner, it remains the largest individual shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Sobolik, an expert on US-China policy and senior fellow at the right-leaning think tank the Hudson Institute, told the NYT that the Trump administration “may have saved TikTok, but the national security concerns are still going to continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some critics, including Republicans, have vowed to scrutinize the deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Senator Edward Markey (D-Mass.) complained that the White House had repeatedly denied requests for information about the deal. They’ve provided “virtually no details about this agreement, including whether TikTok’s algorithm is truly free of Chinese influence,” Markey said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This lack of transparency reeks,” Markey said. “Congress has a responsibility to investigate this deal, demand transparency, and ensure that any arrangement truly protects national security while keeping TikTok online.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, Representative John Moolenaar (R-Mich.), chair of the House Select Committee on China, said thathe wants to hold a hearing with TikTok leadershipto discuss how the deal addresses national security concerns. On Thursday, Moolenaar said he “has two specific questions for TikTok’s new American owners,” Punchbowl Newsreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Can we ensure that the algorithm is not influenced by the Chinese Communist Party?” Moolenaar said. “And two, can we ensure that the data of Americans is secure?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moolenaar may be satisfied by the terms, as the NYT suggested that China hawks in Washington appeared to trust that Trump’s arrangement is a qualified divestiture. TikTok’s release said that Oracle will protect US user data in a secure US cloud data environment that will regularly be audited by third-party cybersecurity experts. The algorithm will be licensed from ByteDance and retrained on US user data, the release said, and Vice President JD Vance has confirmed that the joint venture “will have control over how the algorithm pushes content to users.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last September, a spokesperson for the House China Committeetold Politicothat “any agreement must comply with the historic bipartisan law passed last year to protect the American people, including the complete divestment of ByteDance control and a fully decoupled algorithm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am so happy to have helped in saving TikTok!” Trump said on Truth Social after the deal was finalized. “It will now be owned by a group of Great American Patriots and Investors, the Biggest in the World, and will be an important Voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it’s unclear to TikTokers how the app might change as Trump allies take control of the addictive algorithm that drew millions to the app. Lawmakers had feared the Chinese Communist Party could influence the algorithm to target US users with propaganda, and Trump’s deal was supposed to mitigate that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do critics worry that if ByteDance maintains ownership of the algorithm, it could allow the company to continue to influence content, but there is now concern that the app’s recommendations could take a right-leaning slant under US control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has already said thathe’d like to see TikTok go “100 percent MAGA,”and his allies will now be in charge of “deciding which posts to leave up and which to take down,” the NYT noted. Anupam Chander, a law and technology professor at Georgetown University, told the NYT that the TikTok deal offered Trump and his allies “more theoretical room for one side’s views to get a greater airing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My worry all along is that we may have traded fears of foreign propaganda for the reality of domestic propaganda,” Chander said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For business owners who rely on the app, there’s also the potential thatthe app could be glitchyafter US owners start porting data and retraining the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump clearly hopes the deal will endear him to TikTok users. He sought praise on Truth Social, writing, “I only hope that long into the future I will be remembered by those who use and love TikTok.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the Chinese government has not commented on the deal’s finalization, but Trump thanked Chinese President Xi Jinping in his Truth Social post “for working with us and, ultimately, approving the Deal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He could have gone the other way, but didn’t, and is appreciated for his decision,” Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts have suggested that China benefits from the deal by keeping the most lucrative part of TikTok while the world watches it export its technology to the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Trump first announced the deal in September, critics immediately attacked him for letting China keep the algorithm. One US advisor close to the dealtold the Financial Timesthat “Trump always chickens out,” noting that “after all this, China keeps the algorithm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Soboliktold Politicothat Trump “got played” by Xi after taking “terrible advice from his staff” during trade negotiations that some critics saidgave China the upper hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump sees things differently, writing on Truth Social that the TikTok deal came to “a very dramatic, final, and beautiful conclusion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the deal is “dramatic,” “final,” or “beautiful” depends on who you ask, though, as it could face legal challenges and disrupt TikTok’s beloved content feeds. The NYT suggested that the deal took so long to finalize that TikTokers don’t even care anymore, while several outlets noted that Trump’s deal is very close to the Project Texas arrangement that Joe Biden pushed until it was deemed inadequate to address national security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Project Texas, Oracle was supposed to oversee TikTok US user data, auditing for security risks while ByteDance controlled the code. The joint venture’s “USDS” “coinage even originated from Project Texas,” Slate noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lindsay Gorman, a former senior advisor in the Biden administration, told NYT that “we’ve gone round and round and ended up not too far from where we started.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-finalizes-trump-deal-that-allows-bytedance-to-maintain-some-control/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 08:29:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Telly’s “free” ad-based TVs make notable revenue—when they’re actually delivered</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/652fa4f61e054d1c335ce241_Rectangle_20180_203.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LA startup said it would ship “millions” of TVs by 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly, a company that accepts advertising data instead of cash for its TVs, has reportedly had a hard time getting its “free” TVs into people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly debuted in May 2023. Its dual-screen design can show ads, even when people aren’t watching. Although the smaller, secondary screen can be used for more helpful applications, like showing the weather or sports scores, its primary purpose is to serve as a billboard south of the 55-inch primary display. Owners cannot disabletrackingor cover up the secondary screen (or they have to pay for the TV, which Telly claims is worth $1,000), and they must fill out a lengthy, detailed survey to get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it debuted its TV, Telly said it expected to ship 500,000 devices that summer. In June 2023, the startupsaid250,000 people signed up to get a Telly. In a 2024press release, Telly said that it planned to ship “millions more in 2024.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a report fromLowpassthis week, citing a “Q3 update sent to investors in November 2025,” said the startup had 35,000 TVs in people’s homes at that time. In Q2 2025, there were 28,000 Telly TVs in use, the note said, according to Lowpass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The publication reported that the investor note suggests Telly will order 100,000 TVs from supplier Foxconn and increase deliveries soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly declined to comment to Lowpass and didn’t respond to Ars Technica’s requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Based on early registration numbers, it seems Telly has generated enough interest to ship more than 35,000 TVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue seems to be poor shipping. Per the investor note that Lowpass reviewed, Telly claimed that FedEx delivered 10 percent of its shipments of Telly TVs broken. Since moving to a different company—seeminglySamsung partnerRXO, based on Redditposts—fewer Tellys are arriving broken, the company reportedly said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Lowpass noted,dozensof onlinecomplaintsclaim that the free TVs, which ship directly from Telly, were broken upon arrival.The Vergealso reported receiving a broken unit in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, thesubredditdedicated to Telly TVs seems to show numerous other technical difficulties Telly users are experiencing. Technical complaints are common on subreddits for tech gadgets, but the forum highlights the problems Telly owners might encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly’s reported failure to meet its high shipment goals or even fulfill reported demand demonstrates the scaling complexities startups can face. While some companies struggle to get people interested in their product, Telly’s “free” pitch has been successful enough to lure thousands. But in its early stages, Telly has reportedly struggled with its direct-to-consumer model and smaller team compared to other TV makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Telly’s ad-centric business model may be starting to show its value. The investor update reportedly said Telly made $22 million in annualized revenue in Q3 2025. This could equate to about $52 in advertising revenue per Telly in use per month ($22 million divided by 35,000 TVs divided by 12 months in a year is $52.38).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s notably more than what other TV companies report, as Lowpass pointed out. As a comparison to other budget TV brands that rely heavily on ads and user tracking, Roku reported an average revenue per user (ARPU) of $41.49 for 2024. Vizio, meanwhile, reported an ARPU of $37.17 in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investor note reportedly said that Telly recently raised $350 million in debt funding over two rounds. The note didn’t specify when the funding occurred or how much equity Telly has raised overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assmart TVs at every price pointincreasinglyrelyonsoftware-integratedadvertisementsanduser trackingto offset declining hardware margins and rising competition, Telly argues that its premise is forward-thinking, not far-fetched. Some longtime Telly users point to the sets’ decent image and audio quality but question their reliance on an (included) streaming stick to access popular apps, their default AI-avatar home screen, and repetitive ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Verge writer Emma Rothsaidher Telly showed her “three of the same ads in Spanish (which I don’t speak) in a row.” There’s also concern about potentially invasive uses of the TV’s integrated camera and mic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the leaked investor report highlights, there are plenty of other challenges standing in the way of free, ad-supported TVs. Still, Telly’s early ARPU figures are notable enough to keep the idea alive.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:32:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White House alters arrest photo of ICE protester, says “the memes will continue”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nekima-levy-white-house-manipulated-image-1152x648-1769192287.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyer calls it “outrageous that the White House would make up stories.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump White House yesterday posted a manipulated photo of Nekima Levy Armstrong, a Minnesota civil rights attorney who was arrested after protesting in a church where a pastor is allegedly also an Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noempostedwhat seems to be the original photo of Armstrong being led away by an officer yesterday morning. A half hour later, the official White House X accountpostedan altered version in which Armstrong’s face was manipulated to make it appear that she was crying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The White House shared an AI-edited photo of Nekima, depicting her in tears and scared when, in actuality, she was poised, determined, and unafraid,” NAACP President and CEO Derrick Johnsonsaidyesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reader-added context on X said, “This photo has been digitally altered to make Nekima Levy Armstrong appear to be in distress. The Director of DHS herself posted the unedited photo in an earlier announcement.” White House Deputy Communications Director Kaelan Dorr defended the post after criticism of the image manipulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Enforcement of the law will continue. The memes will continue. Thank you for your attention to this matter,” Dorrwrote. The White House post with the manipulated image called Levy Armstrong a “far-left agitator” who “orchestrated[ed] church riots in Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DHSpress releaseabout the arrest used the same image posted by Noem, without the alteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Kushner, an attorney for Levy Armstrong, said, “It is just so outrageous that the White House would make up stories about someone to try and discredit them. She was completely calm and composed and rational. There was no one crying. So this is just outrageous defamation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to The Associated Press, Kushner also said that the “video Levy Armstrong’s husband shot ‘dismantles what they claim’ and that the video would be released soon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protestersdisrupted serviceson Sunday at the Cities Church in St. Paul, chanting “ICE OUT” and “Justice for Renee Good.” The St. Paul Pioneer Pressquoted Levy Armstrongas saying, “When you think about the federal government unleashing barbaric ICE agents upon our community and all the harm that they have caused, to have someone serving as a pastor who oversees these ICE agents is almost unfathomable to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The churchwebsitelists David Easterwood as one of its pastors. Protesters said this is the same David Easterwood who is listed as a defendant in a lawsuit that Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison filed against Noem and other federal officials. Thelawsuitlists Easterwood as a defendant “in his official capacity as Acting Director, Saint Paul Field Office, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levy Armstrong, who is also a former president of the NAACP’s Minneapolis branch, was arrested yesterday morning. Announcing the arrest, Attorney General Pam Bondiwrote, “WE DO NOT TOLERATE ATTACKS ON PLACES OF WORSHIP.” Bondi alleged that Levy Armstrong “played a key role in organizing the coordinated attack on Cities Church in St. Paul, Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noem said Levy Armstrong “is being charged with a federal crime under 18 USC 241,” whichprohibits“conspir[ing] to injure, oppress, threaten, or intimidate any person in any State, Territory, Commonwealth, Possession, or District in the free exercise or enjoyment of any right or privilege secured to him by the Constitution or laws of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Religious freedom is the bedrock of the United States—there is no first amendment right to obstruct someone from practicing their religion,” Noem wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul School Board member Chauntyll Allen was also arrested. Attorneys for the Cities Church issuedstatementssupporting the arrests and saying they “are exploring all legal options to protect the church and prevent further invasions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal magistrate judge initially ruled that Levy Armstrong and Allen could be released, but they were still being held last night after the government “made a motion to stay the release for further review, claiming they might be flight risks,” the Pioneer Presswrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner called the arrests a “farce” and alleged that Bondi and Noem ordered the arrests only so they could celebrate them on social media, according to the Pioneer Press. “This doesn’t happen in a legitimate prosecution,” Kushner said. “These are officials making a political decision, and purposely making a political spectacle and a political circus out of the court system for their own purposes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner also “said federal agents detained one of Armstrong’s friends two days [previously], using force to tackle her in a hotel lobby, under the mistaken impression she was Armstrong,” the Pioneer Press wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marques Armstrong, Levy Armstrong’s husband, said she offered to turn herself in after the mistaken detention of her friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Initially they agreed and then a call came from up high and said, ‘No, we have to take her there (at the hotel).’ They wanted her in handcuffs,” he was quoted as saying. An “agent took photos and said it won’t go on social media. I knew it was a lie,” he also said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House’s posting of a manipulated version of the arrest photo could be used in Levy Armstrong’s legal defense. As the New York Timeswrote, her lawyer could argue that the post was an improper extrajudicial statement that may prejudice potential jurors and that it shows the Justice Department filed charges vindictively. We contacted Kushner about the manipulated photo and case today and will update this article if he provides any comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NAACP called for the release of Levy Armstrong, Allen, and a third arrestee, William Kelly. “Their arrests violated their constitutional rights and NAACP demands their immediate release,” the NAACP said. “Ms. Armstrong and her fellow demonstrators gathered peacefully at a church over the pastor’s alleged leadership within the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). The protests follow the increase in ICE activity and the fatal shooting of Minneapolis resident Renee Nicole Good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department also tried to bring charges against journalist Don Lemon, but a judgerejected the charges. Lemon was at the demonstration but said he was there as a journalist and not a protester.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:46:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask anonymous ICE critics online</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257128839-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community watch groups have a playbook to keep ICE away from subscriber information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security (DHS) has backed down from afight to unmask the owners of Instagram and Facebook accountsmonitoring Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) activity in Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anonymous account holders, John Doe, sued to block ICE from identifying him and other critics online through summonses to Meta that he claimed infringed on core First Amendment-protected activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS initially fought Doe’s motion to quash the summonses, arguing that the community watch groups endangered ICE agents by posting “pictures and videos of agents’ faces, license plates, and weapons, among other things.” This was akin to “threatening ICE agents to impede the performance of their duties,” DHS alleged. DHS’s arguments echoed DHS Secretary Kristi Noem, who has claimed that identifying ICE agents is a crime, even thoughWired notedthat ICE employees often post easily discoverable LinkedIn profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Doe, the agency seemed intent on testing the waters to see if it could seize authority to unmask all critics online by invoking a customs statute that allows agents to subpoena information on goods entering or leaving the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, on January 16, DHS abruptly reversed course, withdrawing its summonses from Meta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acourt filingconfirmed that DHS dropped its requests for subscriber information last week, after initially demanding Doe’s “postal code, country, all email address(es) on file, date of account creation, registered telephone numbers, IP address at account signup, and logs showing IP address and date stamps for account accesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filing does not explain why DHS decided to withdraw its requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, previously, DHS requested similar information from Meta about six Instagram community watch groups that shared information about ICE activity in Los Angeles and other locations. DHS withdrew those requests, too, after account holders defended their First Amendment rights and filed motions to quash their summonses, Doe’s court filing said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To defeat DHS’ summonses, Doe shared all his group’s online posts with the court. An attorney representing Doe at the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, Ariel Shapell, told Ars that Doe’s groups posted “pretty innocuous” content, like “information and resources about immigrant rights, due process rights, fundraising, and vigils.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible DHS caved due to lack of evidence supporting claims that Doe’s groups’ posts carried implicit threats to “assault, kidnap, or murder any federal official,” as DHS hadargued. But it’s also possible that DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask ICE critics due to strong First Amendment protections working to preserve the right to post anonymously online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attempt to unmask Doe’s accounts came as criticism of ICE is mounting nationwide, and a win could have given ICE broad authority to attack that growing base of critics if DHS had dug in and its defense actually held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses could signal that the argument the agency tried to raise—weirdly using a statute tied to the “importation/exportation of merchandise”to seize “unlimited subpoena authority” of ICE critics online—is clearly not a winning one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment. But Meta did play a role in challenging DHS’ summonses, initially by seeking more information from the agency and then notifying account holders to provide an opportunity to quash the summonses before information was shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the playbook for community watch groups on Facebook and Instagram has been to follow Meta’s advice in order to block identifying information from being shared. But it remains unclear if Meta may have complied with DHS’s requests if account holders were not able to legally fight to quash them, perhaps leaving a vulnerable gray area for community watch groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Doe and any others involved in “MontCo Community Watch,” DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses likely comes as a relief. But this wasn’t the first time DHS tried and failed to unmask online critics, so it’s just as likely that fears remain that DHS will continue trying to identify groups that are posting footage to raise awareness of ICE’s most controversial moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE critics have used footage of tragic events—like Renee Good’s killing andeight other ICE shootings since September—to support calls to remove ICE from embattled communities and abolish ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions remain high as US citizens defend both their neighbors and their own constitutional rights. Most recently, shocking footage ofICE using a 5-year-old boy as baitto trap other family members intensified calls to defund ICE. Public backlash also raged after videos showedICE removing a US citizen from his home in his underwear. That arrest happened while ICE was conducting a warrantless search that awhistleblower warnedis becoming the new ICE norm after an internal memo said that agents can enter homes without a judicial warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some politicians are starting to take up the call to diminish ICE’s power. On Thursday, the majority of House Democrats voted to defund ICE, which Politiconotedwas a “remarkable shift from when dozens of them voted to expand the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement authority just one year ago.” Of course, the ICE budget bill passed anyway, since Republicans control the House, but withpublic approval of ICE tanking, any ongoing pushback could hurt Republicans in midterms and eventually even doom ICE if momentum is sustained.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:10:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demand for Intel’s processors is apparently there, but the supply is not</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/intel-core-ultra-series-3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel is allocating more of its own production to its money-making server chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel reportedits earnings for the fourth quarter of 2025 yesterday, and the news both for the quarter and for the year was mixed: year-over-year revenue was down nearly imperceptibly, from $53.1 billion to $52.9 billion, while revenue for the quarter was down about four percent, from $14.3 billion last year to $13.7 billion this year. (That number was, nevertheless, on the high end of Intel’s guidance for the quarter, which ranged from $12.8 to $13.8 billion.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving deeper into the numbers makes it clear exactly where money is being made and lost: Intel’s data center and AI products were up 9 percent for the quarter and 5 percent for the year, while its client computing group (which sells Core processors, Arc GPUs, and other consumer products) was down 7 percent for the quarter and 3 percent for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That knowledge makes it slightly easier to understand the bind that company executives talked about on Intel’s earnings call (as transcribed by Investing.com). In short, Intel is having trouble making (and buying) enough chips to meet demand, and it makes more sense to allocate the chips itcanmake to the divisions that are actually making money—which means that we could see shortages of or higher prices for consumer processors, just as Intel is gearing up to launch the promising Core Ultra Series 3 processors (codenamed Panther Lake).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel CFO David Zinsner indicated that Intel is “prioritizing [its] internal wafer supply to data center” and having more of its consumer chips made externally. Substantial portions of the Core Ultra Series 3 processors are manufactured at Intel, after the company primarily used TSMC’s chip factories for the Core Ultra Series 2 designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can’t completely vacate the client market,” said Zinsner, but Intel is “shifting as much as we can over to data center to meet the high demand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounding this is that yields for the new 18A process—that is, the number of chips in a wafer with no defects that can work as designed—are still improving. Intel CEO Lip-Bu Tan said that “while yields are in line with our internal plans, they are still below what I want them to be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yields are currently improving by 7 or 8 percent every month, according to Intel. But that could be building on pretty low initial yields—reporting from last summer suggested that just 10 percent of the chips coming off of the 18A production lines were meeting Intel’s requirements at the time. Intel predicts that its supply will have ramped up enough within the next few months to help alleviate shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do believe that the first quarter is the trough,” said Zinsner. “We will improve supply in the second quarter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Intel can start making enough chips to meet its demand, it ought to help brighten the company’s earnings reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We delivered [our Q4 2025] results despite supply constraints, which meaningfully limited our ability to capture all of the strengths in our underwriting markets,” said Tan. “We are working aggressively to address this and better support our customers’ needs going forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel has been signaling for a while now that it was selling essentially all of the chips it could get its hands on. Intel investor relations VP John Pitzersaidlast month that Intel would be selling more of both its Lunar Lake and Arrow Lake Core Ultra Series 2 chips for consumers, as well as its Granite Rapids chips for data centers, if it could get more of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Intel seeks to improve its position in the short term, the company also says that it’s still making progress on its future manufacturing nodes, including different versions of the 18A process and the upcoming 14A process. Intel is working to engage “potential external customers” who would use the 14A process to make their own chips. If these third parties decide to use Intel’s manufacturing facilities, Intel expects to know about it “starting in the second half of this year and extending into the first half of 2027,” and then it expects to build out manufacturing capacity based on the number of external customers it finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the chip design side, Intel also expects to have its first next-generation Nova Lake chips ready “at the end of 2026.” We don’t know much about Nova Lake yet, but it should be Intel’s next architecture to cover both desktop and laptop processors, while Panther Lake chips are intended mainly for laptops. At least part of the chip will also be manufactured using the 18A process.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:48:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TR-49 is interactive fiction for fans of deep research rabbit holes</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/4-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dense narrative deduction game tells a compellingly academia-tinged sci-fi tale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developer:InklePublisher: InklePlatform: MacOS (reviewed), Windows, iOSRelease Date:Jan. 21, 2026ESRB Rating:N/APrice: $7Links:iOS App Store|Steam|Official website&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever fallen downa Wikipedia rabbit holeor spent a pleasant evening digging through college library stacks, you know the joy of a good research puzzle. Every new source and cross-reference you find unlocks an incremental understanding of a previously unknown world, forming a piecemeal tapestry of knowledge that you can eventually look back at as a cohesive and well-known whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49takes this research process and operationalizes it into an engrossing and novel piece of heavily non-linear interactive fiction. Researching the myriad sources contained in the game’s mysterious computer slowly reveals a tale that’s part mystery, part sci-fi allegory, part family drama, and all-compelling alternate academic history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entirety ofTR-49takes place from a first-person perspective as you sit in front of a kind of Steampunk-infused computer terminal. An unseen narrator asks you to operate the machine but is initially cagey about how or why or what you’re even looking for. There’s a creepy vibe to the under-explained circumstances that brought you to this situation, but the game never descends into the jump scares or horror tropes of so many other modern titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your only real form of interaction with the world ofTR-49is through a sepia-toned tube display on the left and a four-charactersplit-flapon the right that serves as the computer’s only input. You quickly discover that entering specific sequences—each with two letters followed by two numbers, as suggested by the game’s name—brings up library catalog-style entries referring to a vast web of literary works that form the core of the game’s wider fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the catalog contains short excerpts from each of these discovered works, it’s the additional notes added to each entry by subsequent researchers that place each title in its full context. You’ll end up poring through these research notes for clues about the existence and chronology of other authors and works. Picking out specific names and years points to the codes and titles needed to unlock even more reference pages in the computer, pushing you further down the rabbit hole. Picture something likeHer Story, but replace the cinéma vérité surveillance video clips with a library card catalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll slowly start to unravel and understand how the game world’s myriad authors are influencing each other with their cross-pollinating writings. The treatises, novels, pamphlets, and journals discussed in this database are full of academic sniping, intellectual intrigue, and interpersonal co-mingling across multiple generations of work. It all ends up circling a long-running search for a metaphysical key to life itself, which most of the authors manage to approach but never quite reach a full understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you explore, you also start to learn more about the personal affairs of the researchers who collected and cataloged all this reference material and the vaguely defined temporal capabilities of the information-synthesis engine in the computer you’ve all worked on. Eventually, you’ll stumble on the existence of core commands that can unlock hidden parts of the computer or alter the massive research database itself, which becomes key to your eventual final goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through it all, there’s a slowly unfolding parallel narrative involving Liam, the unseen voice guiding you through the research process itself. Through occasional voice clips, Liam eventually hints at the existence of a powerful and quickly encroaching threat that wants to stop your progress by any means necessary, adding a bit of dramatic tension to your academic pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m being intentionally vague about the specifics here because I thinkTR-49‘s subtle and well-crafted sci-fi world-building is best experienced by exploring the game for yourself. There’s a real satisfaction in staring at a once impenetrably obtuse research note, recalling a bit of information from a recent cross-reference, and feeling your understanding suddenly click into place. And while the vocal performances can verge on cheesy, the writing captures the monomaniacal intensity of truly obsessive academics to a tee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the game’s best features is a “Notes” sub-menu, which automatically outlines relevant facts (and potential facts) about various authors, groups, and publications as you discover them. This means you don’t have to take page after page of hand-written notes to keep track of the game’s complex connections (and potential connections), as you do in games likeBlue PrinceorLorelei and the Laser Eyes. It makes for a much smoother puzzle-solving experience, even if the automatic notes sometimes pick up on things you may have missed while skimming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49also benefits from being relatively compact compared to some other narrative deduction games. A diligent investigator can reach a conclusion in four or five hours, depending on how thorough they want to be. That makes it relatively easy to keep the broad outlines of the game’s dense but parsable world in your head over a couple of evening play sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are bound to be some people who seeTR-49as akin to a homework simulator, with painful flashbacks to all-nighters spent desperately researching a last-minute college term paper. For anyone who knows the inherent appeal of diving deep into a previously unknown world, though,TR-49is an engrossing work of world-building fiction presented in a truly memorable way.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:52:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>