<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 06:42:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>TSMC says AI demand is “endless” after record Q4 earnings</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/tsmc-says-ai-demand-is-endless-after-record-q4-earnings/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/tsmc_factory-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amid fears of bubble, world’s top chipmaker TSMC says customers just keep asking for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company (TSMC)reportedrecord fourth-quarter earnings and said it expects AI chip demand to continue for years. During an earnings call, CEO C.C. Wei told investors that while he cannot predict the semiconductor industry’s long-term trajectory, he remains bullish on AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TSMC manufactures chips for companies including Apple, Nvidia, AMD, and Qualcomm, making it a linchpin of the global electronics supply chain. The company produces the vast majority of the world’s most advanced semiconductors, and its factories in Taiwan have become a focal point ofUS-China tensionsover technology and trade. When TSMC reports strong demand and ramps up spending, it signals that the companies designing AI chips expect years of continued growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All in all, I believe in my point of view, the AI is real—not only real, it’s starting to grow into our daily life. And we believe that is kind of—we call it AI megatrend, we certainly would believe that,” Weisaidduring the call. “So another question is ‘can the semiconductor industry be good for three, four, five years in a row?’ I’ll tell you the truth, I don’t know. But I look at the AI, it looks like it’s going to be like an endless—I mean, that for many years to come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TSMCpostednet income of NT$505.7 billion (about $16 billion) for the quarter, up 35 percent year over year and above analyst expectations. Revenue hit $33.7 billion, a 25.5 percent increase from the same period last year. The company expects nearly 30 percent revenue growth in 2026 and plans to spend between $52 billion and $56 billion on capital expenditures this year, up from $40.9 billion in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wei’s optimism stands in contrast to months ofspeculationabout whether the AI industry is in a bubble. In November, Google CEO Sundar Pichaiwarnedof “irrationality” in the AI market and said no company would be immune if a potential bubble bursts. OpenAI’s Sam Altmanacknowledgedin August that investors are “overexcited” and that “someone” will lose a “phenomenal amount of money.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But TSMC, which manufactures the chips that power the AI boom, is betting the opposite way, with Wei telling analysts he spoke directly to cloud providers to verify that demand is real before committing to the spending increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I want to make sure that my customers’ demand are real. So I talked to those cloud service providers, all of them,” Wei said. “The answer is that I’m quite satisfied with the answer. Actually, they show me the evidence that the AI really helps their business.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earnings report landed the same day the US and Taiwanfinalizeda trade agreement that cuts tariffs on Taiwanese goods to 15 percent, down from 20 percent. The deal commits Taiwanese companies to $250 billion in direct US investment, and TSMC is accelerating the expansion of its Arizona chip fabrication facilities to match.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/tsmc-says-ai-demand-is-endless-after-record-q4-earnings/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 07:55:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Calif. counters FCC attack on DEI with conditions on Verizon/Frontier merger</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-frontier-to-complete-10b-merger-after-approvals-from-fcc-and-states/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/verizon-sign-logo-1152x648-1739298990.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon touts “expanded reach of almost 30 million fiber passings” across US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon has received all approvals it needs for a $9.6 billion acquisition of Frontier Communications, an Internet service provider with about 3.3 million broadband customers in 25 states. Verizon said it expects to complete the merger on January 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lastapprovalcame from the California Public Utilities Commission (CPUC), which allowed the deal in a 5–0 vote yesterday. There were months of negotiations that resulted in requirements to deploy more fiber and wireless infrastructure, offer $20-per-month Internet service to people with low incomes for the next decade, and other commitments, including some designed to replace the DEI (diversity, equity, and inclusion) policies that Verizon had to end because of demands by the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The approval follows extensive public participation, testimony from multiple parties, and negotiated settlement agreements with consumer advocates and labor organizations,” the CPUCsaid yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizonstruck the merger dealwith Frontier in September 2024, agreeing to pay $9.6 billion in cash and assume over $10 billion in debt held by Frontier. The all-cash transaction is valued at $20 billion including debt. Verizonsaidyesterday that the merged firm “will have an expanded reach of almost 30 million fiber passings across 31 states and Washington, DC.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’s interest in its home Internet business has waxed and waned over the years, but the company seems pretty committed to fiber and fixed wireless home Internet these days. Part of the deal involves Verizon buying back a former portion of its network that it sold to Frontier almost 10 years ago. In 2016,Frontier boughtVerizon’s FiOS and DSL operations in Florida, California, and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atyesterday’s CPUC meeting, Commissioner John Reynolds described Verizon’s commitments. Verizon will deploy fiber to 75,000 new locations within five years, prioritizing census blocks with income at or below 90 percent of the county median, he said. For wireless service, Verizon is required to deploy 250 new cell sites with 5G and fixed wireless capability in areas eligible for state broadband grants and areas with high fire threats, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within seven years, Verizon is required to offer service with 100Mbps download speeds and 20Mbps upload speeds to 88 wire centers that serve rural and lower-income customers, Reynolds said. Verizon must meet interim deadlines toward this goal after three and five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A low-cost Internet plan commitment centers on theVerizon Forwardservice that offers home Internet for as low as $20 a month. Reynolds said the deal with Verizon “locked in” the $20-per-month plans for low-income consumers for the next 10 years. As wepreviously reported, the $20 plans can be fiber with symmetrical speeds of 300Mbps or fixed wireless with download speeds of 100Mbps and upload speeds of 20Mbps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon committed to an audit of Frontier’s fiber and copper networks and to bringing the networks up to the CPUC’s wireline service quality standards, the commission said. This could help improve reliability in Frontier areas that have only copper service. For customers who are upgraded from copper to fiber, Verizon must offer a 24-hour battery backup unit at no charge and a free 72-hour backup in areas with high fire threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California was more interested in extracting consumer-focused commitments from Verizon than the Federal Communications Commission was. FCC Chairman Brendan Carr’s chief demand of companies seeking merger approval is to eliminate DEI initiatives that he calls “invidious forms of discrimination.” The FCCapproved the Verizon/Frontiermerger in May 2025, one day after Verizon committed to end DEI policies related to hiring and supplier diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reynolds said the FCC is attempting “to remake society by withholding regulatory approvals to tear down programs meant to support our communities,” and that California regulators have “refused to let this FCC chair’s coercion pass without scrutiny.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon agreed to give $40 million to the California Emerging Technology Fund for digital literacy programs, and $10 million to California universities for a workforce development program. The CPUC decision said Verizon “shall establish a recruiting pipeline from California State Universities and California community colleges, aiming to recruit from underrepresented populations in consultation with the Commission’s ESJ [Environmental and Social Justice] Working Group, for both Verizon and Frontier’s workforce, and the workforce of supplier companies working with Verizon and Frontier.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CPUC required quarterly employee satisfaction surveys with questions on belonging and inclusion, broken out by demographic characteristics, and annual transparency reports showing the effects of policy changes on workforce and supplier diversity, Reynolds said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We couldn’t mandate that Verizon restore its former programs, but we could build accountability mechanisms and require investment in California and our diverse communities,” Reynolds said. Verizon also must maintain its “Small Business Supplier Accelerator” program with spending of at least $500 million to support California small businesses over five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several advocacy groups issued a press release praising the CPUC for obtaining “an agreement that directly puts funds into the pockets of minority-owned supply chains across the state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“California has shown that states can stand up for workers and consumers and resist Trump’s efforts to undermine employees’ and customers’ rights,” said Lisa Graves, founder and executive director ofTrue North Research. “More states and companies should follow suit to show they won’t be bullied into abandoning equal opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also commitments related to union jobs and infrastructure in tribal areas. Verizon committed to hire 600 new union employees over six years and provide layoff protection to existing union employees for48 months. Verizon is required to provide tribes with maps of infrastructure in and around ancestral territories and give tribes a right of first offer when Frontier disposes of real property in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enforce the conditions, Verizon will put up $150 million in performance bonds, and the CPUC will have an enforcement program with citation authority for violations. An independent compliance monitor, paid for by Verizon but hired by the commission, will report annually on Verizon’s compliance with commitments, Reynolds said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-frontier-to-complete-10b-merger-after-approvals-from-fcc-and-states/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 10:12:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>RAM shortage chaos expands to GPUs, high-capacity SSDs, and even hard drives</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/ram-shortage-chaos-expands-to-gpus-high-capacity-ssds-and-even-hard-drives/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_2659-1-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GPU makers may prioritize more profitable models; large SSDs are harder to find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big Tech’s AI-fueled memory shortageis set to be the PC industry’s defining story for 2026 and beyond. Standalone, direct-to-consumer RAM kits were some of the first products to feel the bite, with prices spiking by 300 or 400 percentby the end of 2025; prices for SSDs had also increased noticeably, albeit more modestly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of 2026 is going to be all about where, how, and to what extent those price spikes flow downstream intocomputers, phones, and other components that use RAM and NAND chips—areas where the existing supply of products and longer-term supply contracts negotiated by big companies have helped keep prices from surging too noticeably so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we’re seeing signs that the RAM crunch is starting to affect the GPU market—Asus made some waves when it inadvertentlyannouncedthat it was discontinuing itsGeForce RTX 5070 Ti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the company has since tried to walk this announcement back, if you’re a GPU manufacturer, there’s a strong argument for either discontinuing this model or de-prioritizing it in favor of other GPUs. The 5070 Ti uses 16GB of GDDR7, plus a partially disabled version of Nvidia’s GB203 GPU silicon. This is the same chip and the same amount of RAM used in the higher-end RTX 5080—the thinking goes, why continue to build a graphics card with an MSRP of $749 when the same basic parts could go to a cardwith a $999 MSRP instead?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether Asus or any other company is canceling production or not, you can see why GPU makers would be tempted by the argument: Street prices for the RTX 5070 Ti modelsstartin the $1,050 to $1,100 range on Newegg right now, where RTX 5080 cardsstartin the $1,500 to $1,600 range. Though 5080 models may need more robust boards, heatsinks, and other components than a 5070 Ti, if you’rejusttrying to maximize the profit-per-GPU you can get for the same amount of RAM, it makes sense to shift allocation to the more expensive cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, those GPUs are selling for at least 40 or 50 percent more than their original MSRP right now—it’s a bad time to want a graphics card that can hit 4K without leaning too heavily on upscaling technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news, if there is any, is that it’s still not a historically awful time to want a low-end to midrange GPU for 1080p or 1440p gaming. The regular RTX 5070 ishanging out around$560 or $570, just a hair over its $549 MSRP. The situation is similar for the Radeon RX 9070 (MSRP $549, currentstreet pricearound $580), the 16GB version of the RX 9060 XT (MSRP $349,street price$400-ish), and the GeForce RTX 5060 (currently availableat its $300 MSRP). The Radeon RX 9070 XT is faring a bit worse, though not as badly as the RTX 5070 Ti or 5080 (MSRP $599, street pricearound$730 or $750).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re past the period late last year where you could consistently find many of these cards forunderMSRP, but we aren’t (yet?) at the point where you have to fight with scalpers for the privilege of payingjust1.5 times the normal price for any of them. It’s something to bear in mind if you’re thinking about upgrading an existing build to get around having to buy new RAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSD prices have been climbing alongside RAM prices for months, but as of last month, the price increases for 500GB, 1TB, and 2TB drives were around twice as expensive as they had been in August 2025, compared to three or four times as expensive for DDR5 RAM kits. But things are moving in a bad direction, and high-capacity SSDs in particular are being hit hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a 1TB internal M.2 SSD from a recognizable company, that willgenerallyrun you somewhere between $120 and $150—often a little higher than the $135 we recorded for a 1TB WD Blue drive back in January, but not absurdly so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s still possible to finda decent 2TB drive like this SiliconPower model for around $230, the price we quoted for a 2TB Western Digital SN7100 in December. But currently, SSDs from big-name companies like Samsung and WD/SanDisk (currentlyin a state of flux, but the SanDisk-branded versions of these drives don’t appear to be at retail yet) are either out of stock at many major retailers or have shot up dramatically in price. Best Buywill sell youa 2TB SN7100 for $370, which the site proclaims is a “deal” because it’s marked down from a regular price of $490. A 2TB Samsung 990 Evo Plus will run you $440; Amazon had listed the same drive in new condition for $177as recently as mid-December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drives with 4TB capacities are in a similar place: it’s possible to find reasonable-ish options (another SiliconPower UD90 for $360; aCrucial P310 for $345), but the bigger-name drives I’d usually default to are either much more expensive or out of stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even spinning hard drive prices are beginning to climb, albeit more gradually. A6TB WD Red NAS drivethat retailed for $140 in August of 2025 is listed at $160 now. The4TB version, as well as a4TB Seagate IronWolf NAS drive, is around $100, which was its typical price for most of last year. But historical data sourced fromCamelCamelCamelshows that both drives went on sale for $80 or $85 several times last year, something that stopped happening for both drives after September. A12TB IronWolf drivethat was usually priced at $240 last year is $270 now;the 16TB versionhas climbed from $330 to $350.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t expect these prices to continue to shoot upward like RAM and SSD prices have—the level of demand isn’t the same, there isn’t a ton of RAM or flash memory in them, and data centers mostly aren’t going to bother competing with home users to buy 4TB or 8TB drives when they can fit 20 or 30TB in a drive that takes up the same amount of physical space. But the increases are still worth keeping an eye on, as price increases and shortages change buying patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/ram-shortage-chaos-expands-to-gpus-high-capacity-ssds-and-even-hard-drives/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 10:56:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandiant releases rainbow table that cracks weak admin password in 12 hours</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/mandiant-releases-rainbow-table-that-cracks-weak-admin-password-in-12-hours/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/password-login-1000x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows laggards still using the vulnerable hashing function: Your days are numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security firm Mandiant has released a database that allows any administrative password protected by Microsoft’s NTLM.v1 hash algorithm to be hacked in an attempt to nudge users who continue using the deprecated function despite known weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database comes in the form of arainbow table, which is a precomputed table of hash values linked to their corresponding plaintext. These generic tables, which work against multiple hashing schemes, allow hackers to take over accounts by quickly mapping a stolen hash to its password counterpart. NTLMv1 rainbow tables are particularly easy to construct because of NTLMv1’s limited keyspace, meaning the relatively small number of possible passwords the hashing function allows for. NTLMv1 rainbow tables have existed for two decades but typically require large amounts of resources to make any use of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mandiantsaidit hadreleasedan NTLMv1 rainbow table that will allow defenders and researchers (and, of course, malicious hackers, too) to recover passwords in under 12 hours using consumer hardware costing less than $600 USD. The table is hosted in Google Cloud. The database works against Net-NTLMv1 passwords, which are used in network authentication for accessing resources such as SMB network sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its long- and well-known susceptibility to easy cracking, NTLMv1 remains in use in some of the world’s more sensitive networks. One reason for the lack of action is that utilities and organizations in industries, including health care and industrial control, often rely on legacy apps that are incompatible with more recently released hashing algorithms. Another reason is that organizations relying on mission-critical systems can’t afford the downtime required to migrate. Of course, inertia and penny-pinching are also causes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By releasing these tables, Mandiant aims to lower the barrier for security professionals to demonstrate the insecurity of Net-NTLMv1,” Mandiant said. “While tools to exploit this protocol have existed for years, they often required uploading sensitive data to third-party services or expensive hardware to brute-force keys.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft released NTLMv1 in the1980swith the release of OS/2. In 1999, cryptanalyst Bruce Schneier and Mudgepublishedresearch that exposed key weaknesses in the NTLMv1 underpinnings. At the 2012 Defcon 20 conference, researchers released atool setthat allowed attackers to move from untrusted network guest to admin in 60 seconds, by attacking the underlying weakness. With the 1998 release ofWindows NT SP4in 1998, Microsoft introduced NTLMv2, which fixed the weakness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations that rely on Windows networking aren’t the only laggards. Microsoft onlyannouncedplans to deprecate NTLMv1 last August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the public awareness that NTLMv1 is weak, “Mandiant consultants continue to identify its use in active environments,” the company said. “This legacy protocol leaves organizations vulnerable to trivial credential theft, yet it remains prevalent due to inertia and a lack of demonstrated immediate risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tables first assist attackers in providing per-byte hash results with theknown plaintextchallenge 1122334455667788. Because Net-NTLM hashes are generated with the user’s password and the challenge, a known plaintext attack, it becomes trivial with these tables to compromise the accont. Typically tools including Responder, PetitPotam, and DFSCoerce are involved in attacks against Net-NTLM. Typically tools includingResponder,PetitPotam, andDFSCoerceare involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In athreadon Mastodon, researchers and admins applauded the move, because they said it would give them added ammunition when trying to convince decision makers to make the investments to move off the insecure function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve had more than one instance in my (admittedly short) infosec career where I’ve had to prove the weakness of a system and it usually involves me dropping a sheet of paper on their desk with their password on it the next morning,” one personsaid. “These rainbow tables aren’t going to mean much for attackers as they’ve likely already got them or have far better methods, but where it will help is in making the argument that NTLMv1 is unsafe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandiant post provides basic steps required to move off of NTLMv1. It links to more detailed instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Organizations should immediately disable the use of Net-NTLMv1,” Mandiant said. Organizations that get hacked because they failed to heed will have only themselves to blame.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/mandiant-releases-rainbow-table-that-cracks-weak-admin-password-in-12-hours/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:05:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI to test ads in ChatGPT as it burns through billions</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/openai-to-test-ads-in-chatgpt-as-it-burns-through-billions/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/openai_glowing_green-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ads coming to free tier and new $8/month ChatGPT Go plan in US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, OpenAIannouncedit will begin testing advertisements inside the ChatGPT app for some US users in a bid to expand its customer base and diversify revenue. The move represents a reversal for CEO Sam Altman, who in 2024describedadvertising in ChatGPT as a “last resort” and expressed concerns that ads could erode user trust, although he did not completely rule out the possibility at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner ads will appear in the coming weeks for logged-in users of the free version of ChatGPT as well as the new $8 per monthChatGPT Goplan, which OpenAI also announced Friday is now available worldwide. OpenAI first launched ChatGPT Go in India in August 2025 and has since rolled it out to over 170 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users paying for the more expensive Plus, Pro, Business, and Enterprise tiers will not see advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to OpenAI’s blog post, the company plans to test ads “at the bottom of answers in ChatGPT when there’s a relevant sponsored product or service.” Ads will be labeled and separated from the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In example screenshots shared by the company, the ads look like blocked off sections of the chat window with a small image and some advertising copy. Asking ChatGPT for places to visit in Mexico could result in holiday ads appearing, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our enterprise and subscription businesses are already strong,” Fidji Simo, OpenAI’s CEO of applications,wrotein the blog post. “We believe in having a diverse revenue model where ads can play a part in making intelligence more accessible to everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s announcement follows the company’s April 2025introduction of shopping featuresto ChatGPT Search. At that time, OpenAI’s Adam Fry told Wired that product recommendations were “not ads” and “not sponsored,” but it felt like a potential step in that direction at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI is not the only AI company exploring advertising revenue. Googlebegan testingAdSense ads in chatbot experiences through partnerships with AI startups in late 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s advertising experiment reflects the enormous financial pressures facing the company. OpenAI does not expect to be profitable until 2030 and hascommittedto spend about $1.4 trillion onmassive data centersand chips for AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to financial documentsobtainedby The Wall Street Journal in November, OpenAI expects to burn through roughly $9 billion this year while generating $13 billion in revenue. Only about 5 percent of ChatGPT’s 800 million weekly userspayfor subscriptions, so it’s not enough to cover all of OpenAI’s operating costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is convinced ads will solve OpenAI’s financial problems. “I am extremely bearish on this ads product,” tech critic Ed Zitronwrote on Bluesky. “Even if this becomes a good business line, OpenAI’s services cost too much for it to matter!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s embrace of ads appears to come reluctantly, since it runs counter to a “personal bias” against advertising that Altman has shared in earlier public statements. For example, during a fireside chat at Harvard University in 2024, Altmansaidhe found the combination of ads and AI “uniquely unsettling,” implying that he would not like it if the chatbot itself changed its responses due to advertising pressure. He added: “When I think of like GPT writing me a response, if I had to go figure out exactly how much was who paying here to influence what I’m being shown, I don’t think I would like that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those lines, OpenAI’s approach appears to be a compromise between needing ad revenue and not wanting sponsored content to appear directly within ChatGPT’s written responses. By placing banner ads at the bottom of answers separated from the conversation history, OpenAI appears to be addressing Altman’s concern: The AI assistant’s actual output, the company says, will remain uninfluenced by advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Simowrotein a blog post that OpenAI’s ads will not influence ChatGPT’s conversational responses and that the company will not share conversations with advertisers and will not show ads on sensitive topics such as mental health and politics to users it determines to be under 18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As we introduce ads, it’s crucial we preserve what makes ChatGPT valuable in the first place,” Simo wrote. “That means you need to trust that ChatGPT’s responses are driven by what’s objectively useful, never by advertising.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/openai-to-test-ads-in-chatgpt-as-it-burns-through-billions/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:20:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This may be the grossest eye pic ever—but the cause is what’s truly horrifying</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/this-may-be-the-grossest-eye-pic-ever-but-the-cause-is-whats-truly-horrifying/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Screenshot-2026-01-16-at-3.38.03-PM-910x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypervirulent germ nearly destroys man, invading brain and blowing out an eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generally healthy 63-year-old man in the New England area went to the hospital with a fever, cough, and vision problems in his right eye. His doctors eventually determined that a dreaded hypervirulent bacteria—which is rising globally—was ravaging several of his organs, including his brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the man, the problems started three weeks before his hospital visit, when he said he ate some bad meat and started vomiting and having diarrhea. Those symptoms faded after about two weeks, but then new problems began—he started coughing and having chills and a fever. His cough only worsened from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the hospital, doctors took X-rays and computed tomography (CT) scans of his chest and abdomen. The images revealed over 15 nodules and masses in his lungs. But that’s not all they found. The imaging also revealed a mass in his liver that was 8.6 cm in diameter (about 3.4 inches). Lab work pointed toward an infection, so doctors admitted him to the hospital and provided oxygen to help with his breathing, as well as antibiotics. But his chills and cough continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his third day, he woke up with vision loss in his right eye, which was so swollen he couldn’t open it. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed another surprise: There were multiple lesions in his brain. (His brain lesions and eye at this point can be seenhere.A later-stage image of his eye is further down in the story.) At that point, he was transferred to Massachusetts General Hospital. Ina case report in this week’s issue of the New England Journal of Medicine, doctors explained how they solved the case and treated the man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to the correct diagnosis was his eye, which kept getting worse. He seemed to have an infection inside his eyeball, affecting the jelly or aqueous parts of the inside (endophthalmitis). The most common cause of this is an eye injury or previous surgery that allows an infection-sparking germ to get in—but he had no such injury or surgery. Also, the condition of his eye was worse than that. He appeared to have panophthalmitis, which is a rare, extremely severe, and rapidly progressing condition in which every part of the eye becomes infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever was laying waste to his eye seemed to have come from inside his own body, carried in his bloodstream—possibly the same thing that could explain the liver mass, lung nodules, and brain lesions. There was one explanation that fit the condition perfectly: hypervirulentKlebsiella pneumoniaeor hvKP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ClassicalK. pneumoniaeis a germ that dwells in people’s intestinal tracts and is one that’s familiar to doctors. It’s known for lurking in health care settings and infecting vulnerable patients, often causing pneumonia or urinary tract infections. But hvKP is very different. In comparison, it’s a beefed-up bacteria with a rage complex. It was first identified in the 1980s in Taiwan—not for stalking weak patients in the hospital but for devastating healthy people in normal community settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An infection with hvKP—even in otherwise healthy people—is marked by metastatic infection. That is, the bacteria spreads throughout the body, usually starting with the liver, where it creates a pus-filled abscess. It then goes on a trip through the bloodstream, invading the lungs, brain, soft tissue, skin, and the eye (endogenous endophthalmitis). Putting it all together, the man had a completely typical clinical case of an hvKP infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, definitively identifying hvKP is tricky. Mucus from the man’s respiratory tract grew a species ofKlebsiella, but there’s not yet a solid diagnostic test to differentiate hvKP from the classical variety. Since 2024, researchers have worked outa strategyof using the presence offive different virulence genes found on plasmids(relatively small, circular pieces of DNA, separate from chromosomal DNA, that can replicate on their own and be shared among bacteria.) But the method isn’t perfect—some classicalK. pneumoniaecan also carry the five genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another much simpler method is the string test, in which clinicians basically test the goopy-ness of the bacteria—hvKP is known for being sticky. For this test, a clinician grows the bacteria into a colony on a petri dish, then touches an inoculation loop to the colony and pulls up. If the string of attached goo stretches more than 5 mm off the petri dish, it’s considered positive for hvKP. This is (obviously) not a precise test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the man’s case, the bacteria from his respiratory tract was positive in the string test. Doctors treated him with antibiotics that testing found could kill off the hvKP strain he had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it was too late for the man’s eye. By his eighth day in the hospital, the swelling had gotten extremely severe (you can see an imagehere, but be warned that it is very disturbing). His eye was now bulging out of his head, and imaging suggested another abscess had formed on the side of the eyeball. He had severe stretching of his optic nerve. Overall, there was no chance of him recovering sight in that eye. Given the worsening situation—which was despite the effective antibiotics—doctors removed his eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these cases, it’s sometimes recommended to drain the liver abscess and surgically remove the brain lesions, too. But doctors ruled out both of those options. The liver abscess was too varied for simple drainage, and the brain lesions were too small and numerous to make surgery safe. Instead, he went through an intense antibiotic regimen that lasted nine months. Fortunately, by then, imaging confirmed that his liver abscess had resolved, his lung nodules nearly vanished, and his brain lesions significantly shrank or disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His doctors also noted that he was fortunate to have an hvKP strain that did not carry significant antibiotic resistance. In recent years,health officials have flaggednot just a global increase of hvKP cases overall but also an increase in hvKP cases that are resistant to critical antibiotics, specifically carbapenemases or extended-spectrum beta-lactamases. These cases can have fatality rates of above 50 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/this-may-be-the-grossest-eye-pic-ever-but-the-cause-is-whats-truly-horrifying/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:32:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge orders Anna’s Archive to delete scraped data; no one thinks it will comply</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-annas-archive-to-delete-scraped-data-no-one-thinks-it-will-comply/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/library-shelves-1152x648-1768598730.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WorldCat operator hopes default judgment will convince web hosts to take action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operator of WorldCat won a default judgment against Anna’s Archive, with a federal judge ruling yesterday that the shadow library must delete all copies of its WorldCat data and stop scraping, using, storing, or distributing the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive is a shadow library and search engine for other shadow libraries that was launched in 2022. It archives books and other written materials and makes them available via torrents, and recently expanded its ambitions byscraping Spotify to make a 300TB copyof the most-streamed songs. Anna’s Archivelost its .org domaina couple of weeks ago but remains online at other domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s ruling is in a case filed by OCLC, a nonprofit that operates the WorldCat library catalog on behalf of member libraries. OCLC alleged that Anna’s Archive “illegally hacked WorldCat.org” to steal 2.2TB of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive, whichbills itselfas “the world’s largest shadow library,” did not respond to the lawsuit and doesn’t seem likely to comply with the judgment. The shadow library creator haswrittenthat “we deliberately violate the copyright law in most countries. This allows us to do something that legal entities cannot do: making sure books are mirrored far and wide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the court order has value for OCLC, which said in aNovember 2025 motionthat it “hopes to take the judgment to website hosting services so that OCLC’s WorldCat data will be removed from Anna’s Archive’s websites.” We contacted OCLC about its plans today and will update this article if it provides any information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thecourt order, which was previouslyreportedby TorrentFreak, was issued by Judge Michael Watson in US District Court for the Southern District of Ohio. “Plaintiff has established that Defendant crashed its website, slowed it, and damaged the servers, and Defendant admitted to the same by way of default,” the ruling said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive allegedly began scraping and harvesting data from WorldCat.org in October 2022, “and Plaintiff suffered persistent attacks for roughly a year,” the ruling said. “To accomplish such scraping and harvesting, Defendant allegedly used search bots (automated software applications) that ‘called or pinged the server directly’ and appeared to be ‘legitimate search engine bots from Bing and Google.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court granted OCLC’s motion for default judgment on a breach-of-contract claim related to WorldCat.org terms and conditions, and a trespass-to-chattels claim related to the alleged harm to its website and servers. The court rejected the plaintiff’s tortious-interference-with-contract claim because OCLC’s allegation didn’t include all necessary components to prove the charge, and rejected OCLC’s unjust enrichment claim because it “is preempted by federal copyright law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment said Anna’s Archive is permanently enjoyed from “scraping or harvesting WorldCat data from WorldCat. org or OCLC’s servers; using, storing, or distributing the WorldCat data on Anna’s Archive’s websites; and encouraging others to scrape, harvest, use, store, or distribute WorldCat data.” It also must “delete all copies of WorldCat data in possession of or easily accessible to it, including all torrents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Anna” behind Anna’s Archive revealed the WorldCat scraping in an October 2023blog post. The post said that because WorldCat has “the world’s largest library metadata collection,” the data would help Anna’s Archive make a “list of books that need to be preserved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even though OCLC is a nonprofit, their business model requires protecting their database,” Anna wrote. “Well, we’re sorry to say, friends at OCLC, we’re giving it all away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s blog said the scraping took place over a year and relied on security flaws that were gradually patched. The “security flaws were slowly fixed one by one, until the final one we found was patched about a month ago,” the October 2023 post said. “By that time we had pretty much all records, and were only going for slightly higher quality records.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCLC filed itslawsuitin January 2024. “Beginning in the fall of 2022, OCLC began experiencing cyberattacks on WorldCat.org and OCLC’s servers that significantly affected the speed and operations of WorldCat.org, other OCLC products and services, and OCLC’s servers and network infrastructure,” the lawsuit said. “These attacks continued throughout the following year, forcing OCLC to devote significant time and resources toward non-routine network infrastructure enhancements, maintenance, and troubleshooting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCLC finally learned the perpetrator was Anna’s Archive when the shadow library made its October 2023 announcement. “Anna’s Archive has since made OCLC’s WorldCat data available for en masse for free download and now is actively encouraging its visitors to make use of the data in ‘interesting’ ways,” the lawsuit said, adding that the defendants “have no legal justification for their actions and admit that their general operations violate US and other jurisdictions’ copyright laws.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s default judgment is not the end of proceedings in the case. OCLC was ordered to file a status report within 30 days “suggesting next steps on the claims for which the Court denied default judgment, unless it files a motion to dismiss its remaining claims against Defendant before then.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-annas-archive-to-delete-scraped-data-no-one-thinks-it-will-comply/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:43:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Archaeologists find a supersized medieval shipwreck in Denmark</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/archaeologists-find-a-supersized-medieval-shipwreck-in-denmark/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Ubena_von_Bremen_Kiel2007_1_cropped-941x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sunken ship reveals that the medieval European economy was growing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists recently found the wreck of an enormous medieval cargo ship lying on the seafloor off the Danish coast, and it reveals new details of medieval trade and life at sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists discovered the shipwreck while surveying the seabed in preparation for a construction project for the city of Copenhagen, Denmark. It lay on its side, half-buried in the sand, 12 meters below the choppy surface of the Øresund, the straight that runs between Denmark and Sweden. By comparing the tree rings in the wreck’s wooden planks and timbers with rings from other, precisely dated tree samples, the archaeologists concluded that the ship had been built around 1410 CE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Svaelget 2, as archaeologists dubbed the wreck (its original name is long since lost to history), was a type of merchant ship called a cog: a wide, flat-bottomed, high-sided ship with an open cargo hold and a square sail on a single mast. A bigger, heavier, more advanced version of the Viking knarrs of centuries past, the cog was the high-tech supertanker of its day. It was built to carry bulky commodities from ports in the Netherlands, north around the coast of Denmark, and then south through the Øresund to trading ports on the Baltic Sea—but this one didn’t quite make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cogs would have been about 15 to 25 meters long and 5 to 8 meters wide, capable of carrying about 200 tons of cargo—big, impressive ships for their time. But Svaelget 2, an absolute unit of a ship, measured about 28 meters from bow to stern, 9 meters wide, and could have carried about 300 tons. Its size alone was a surprise to the archaeologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We now know, undeniably, that cogs could be this large—that the ship type could be pushed to this extreme,” said archaeologist Otto Uldum of Denmark’s Viking Ship Museum, who led the excavation,in a press release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval Europe’s merchant class was growing in both size and wealth in the early 1400s, and the cog was both a product of that growth and the engine driving it. The mere fact of its existence points to a society that could afford to invest in building big, expensive trading ships (and could confidently expect a return on that investment). And physically, it’s a product of the same trading networks it supplied: while the heavy timbers of its frame were cut locally in the Netherlands, the Pomeranian oak planks of Svaelget 2’s hull came from Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cog revolutionized trade in northern Europe,” said Uldum. “It made it possible to transport goods on a scale never seen before.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For about 600 years, layers of sand had protected the starboard (right, for you landlubbers) side of the wreck from erosion and decay. Nautical archaeologists usually find only the very bottoms of cogs; the upper structures of the ship—rigging, decks, and castles—quickly decay in the ocean. That means that some of the most innovative parts of the ships’ construction appear only in medieval drawings and descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Svaelget 2 offers archaeologists a hands-on look at the real deal, from rigging to the ship’s galley and the stern castle: a tall wooden structure at the back of the ship, where crew and passengers could have sought at least a little shelter from the elements. Medieval drawings and texts describe cogs having high castles at both bow and stern, but archaeologists have never gotten to examine a real one to learn how it’s put together or how it connects with the rest of the ship’s construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have plenty of drawings of castles, but they have never been found because usually only the bottom of the ship survives,” said Uldum. “[The castle] is a big step forward compared to Viking Age ships, which had only open decks in all kinds of weather.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lying on and around the remains of the cog’s decks, Uldum and his colleagues also found stays (ropes that would have held the mast in place) and lines for controlling the ship’s single square sail, along with ropes and chains that would once have secured the merchant vessel’s cargo in the open hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cog would probably have sailed with between 30 and 45 crew members. No remains were found on the wreck, but the lost crew left behind small, tantalizing traces of their lives and their presence. Uldum and his colleagues found combs, shoes, and rosary beads, along with dishes and tableware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The sailor brought his comb to keep his hair neat and his rosary to say his prayers,” said Uldum (and one has to picture the sailor’s grandmother beaming proudly at that description). “These personal objects show us that the crew brought everyday items with them. They transferred their life on land to life at sea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life at sea, for the medieval sailors aboard Svaelget 2, would have included at least occasional hot meals, cooked in bronze pots over an open fire in the ship’s galley and eaten on dishes of ceramic and painted wood. Bricks (about 200 of them) and tiles formed a sort of fireplace where the cook could safely build a fire aboard the otherwise very flammable ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It speaks of remarkable comfort and organization on board,” said Uldum. “Now sailors could have hot meals similar to those on land, instead of the dried and cold food that previously dominated life at sea.” Plenty of dried meat and cold biscuits still awaited sailors for the next several centuries, of course, but when weather and time permitted, at least the crew of Svaelget 2 could gather around a hot meal. The galley would have been a relatively new part of shipboard life for sailors in the early 1400s—and it quickly became a vital one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing usually marks the site of a shipwreck, even when everything else has disintegrated into the ocean: ballast stones. When merchant ships were empty, they carried stones in their holds to help keep the ship stable; otherwise, the empty ship would be top-heavy and prone to tipping over, which is usually not ideal. (Modern merchant vessels use water, in special tanks, for ballast.) But Uldum and his colleagues didn’t find ballast stones on Svaelget 2, which means the cog was probably fully laden with cargo when it sank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the cargo is also conspicuously absent. Cogs were built to carry bulk goods—things like bricks, grain and other staple foods, fabric, salt, and timber. Those goods would have been stowed in an open hold amidships, secured by ropes and chains (some of which remain on the wreck). But barrels, boards, and bolts of fabric all float. As the ship sank and water washed into the hold, it would have carried away the cargo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of it may have washed up on the shores or even more distant beaches, becoming a windfall for local residents. The rest probably sank to the bottom of the sea, far from the ship and its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/archaeologists-find-a-supersized-medieval-shipwreck-in-denmark/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:07:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rackspace customers grapple with “devastating” email hosting price hike</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/rackspace-raises-email-hosting-prices-by-as-much-as-706-percent/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2206289956-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reseller says Rackspace plans to charge it 706 percent more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s new pricing for its email hosting services is “devastating,” according to a partner that has been using Rackspace as its email provider since 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, Rackspaceupdated its email hosting pricing. Its standard plan is now $10 per mailbox per month. Businesses can also pay for the Rackspace Email Plus add-on for an extra $2/mailbox/month (for “file storage, mobile sync, Office-compatible apps, and messaging”), and the Archiving add-on for an extra $6/mailbox/month (for unlimited storage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As recently as November 2025, Rackspace charged $3/mailbox/month for its Standard plan, and an extra $1/mailbox/month for the Email Plus add-on, and an additional $3/mailbox/month for the Archival add-on, according to the Internet Archive’sWayback Machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s reseller partners have been especially vocal about the impacts of the new pricing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ablog poston Thursday, web hosting service provider and Rackspace reseller Laughing Squid said Rackspace is “increasing our email pricing by an astronomical 706 percent, with only a month-and-a half’s notice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laughing Squid founder Scott Beale told Ars Technica that he received the “devastating” news via email on Wednesday. The last time Rackspace increased Laughing Squid’s email prices was by 55 percent in 2019, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The price increase has a major impact on the ability to make money due to the fact that email is now our largest expense, and we were only given a month-and-a-half notice,” Beale told Ars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online, there are reports of Rackspace partners being quoted email pricing increases of110 percent to nearly 500 percent.The reports say that the new, higher-per-mailbox quotes don’t include volume pricing discounts. Beale noted that Laughing Squid’s quote doesn’t include discounts that the company previously received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We had really good reseller pricing that we negotiated with Rackspace due to the number of mailboxes we had with them and how long we had been a customer. All of that seemed to vanish when they notified us of their new pricing,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars contacted Rackspace asking about the 706 percent price hike that Laughing Squid says it’s facing, why Rackspace decided to increase its prices now, and why it didn’t give its partners more advanced notice. A company spokesperson responded, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace Email is a reliable and secure business-class email solution for small businesses. To continue delivering the service levels our customers expect, effective March 2026, Rackspace Technology is increasing the price of Rackspace Email. We have a support team available to help our customers to discuss their options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson added that Rackspace’s “mission is to deliver quality, trusted and reliable hosted email solution for businesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Rackspace’s stated commitment to email hosting, the prohibitive pricing seems like a deterrent for a business being viewed as high-effort and low-margin. Email has grown complex over the years, requiring time and expertise for proper management at scale. It’s become simpler, or more lucrative, for some cloud companies to focus on selling their managed services on top of offerings like Microsoft 365—as Rackspace does—or Google Workspace and let the larger companies behind those solutions deal with infrastructure costs and complexities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s price hike also comes as anAI-driven RAM shortageisimpactingthe availability and affordability of other computing components,including storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Rackspace, whichwent public in 2020, also havingquit hosting Microsoft Exchangefollowing a costly2022 ransomware attack, the Texas-headquartered company may be looking to minimize its email hosting duties as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Laughing Squid is increasing prices for Rackspace mailboxes and offering services with a different email provider, PolarisMail, to customers at lower prices. Beale said he has reached out to Rackspace about the new pricing but hasn’t heard back yet.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/rackspace-raises-email-hosting-prices-by-as-much-as-706-percent/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:15:27 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>