<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 11:06:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask anonymous ICE critics online</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257128839-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community watch groups have a playbook to keep ICE away from subscriber information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security (DHS) has backed down from afight to unmask the owners of Instagram and Facebook accountsmonitoring Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) activity in Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anonymous account holders, John Doe, sued to block ICE from identifying him and other critics online through summonses to Meta that he claimed infringed on core First Amendment-protected activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS initially fought Doe’s motion to quash the summonses, arguing that the community watch groups endangered ICE agents by posting “pictures and videos of agents’ faces, license plates, and weapons, among other things.” This was akin to “threatening ICE agents to impede the performance of their duties,” DHS alleged. DHS’s arguments echoed DHS Secretary Kristi Noem, who has claimed that identifying ICE agents is a crime, even thoughWired notedthat ICE employees often post easily discoverable LinkedIn profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Doe, the agency seemed intent on testing the waters to see if it could seize authority to unmask all critics online by invoking a customs statute that allows agents to subpoena information on goods entering or leaving the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, on January 16, DHS abruptly reversed course, withdrawing its summonses from Meta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acourt filingconfirmed that DHS dropped its requests for subscriber information last week, after initially demanding Doe’s “postal code, country, all email address(es) on file, date of account creation, registered telephone numbers, IP address at account signup, and logs showing IP address and date stamps for account accesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filing does not explain why DHS decided to withdraw its requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, previously, DHS requested similar information from Meta about six Instagram community watch groups that shared information about ICE activity in Los Angeles and other locations. DHS withdrew those requests, too, after account holders defended their First Amendment rights and filed motions to quash their summonses, Doe’s court filing said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To defeat DHS’ summonses, Doe shared all his group’s online posts with the court. An attorney representing Doe at the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, Ariel Shapell, told Ars that Doe’s groups posted “pretty innocuous” content, like “information and resources about immigrant rights, due process rights, fundraising, and vigils.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible DHS caved due to lack of evidence supporting claims that Doe’s groups’ posts carried implicit threats to “assault, kidnap, or murder any federal official,” as DHS hadargued. But it’s also possible that DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask ICE critics due to strong First Amendment protections working to preserve the right to post anonymously online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attempt to unmask Doe’s accounts came as criticism of ICE is mounting nationwide, and a win could have given ICE broad authority to attack that growing base of critics if DHS had dug in and its defense actually held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses could signal that the argument the agency tried to raise—weirdly using a statute tied to the “importation/exportation of merchandise”to seize “unlimited subpoena authority” of ICE critics online—is clearly not a winning one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment. But Meta did play a role in challenging DHS’ summonses, initially by seeking more information from the agency and then notifying account holders to provide an opportunity to quash the summonses before information was shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the playbook for community watch groups on Facebook and Instagram has been to follow Meta’s advice in order to block identifying information from being shared. But it remains unclear if Meta may have complied with DHS’s requests if account holders were not able to legally fight to quash them, perhaps leaving a vulnerable gray area for community watch groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Doe and any others involved in “MontCo Community Watch,” DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses likely comes as a relief. But this wasn’t the first time DHS tried and failed to unmask online critics, so it’s just as likely that fears remain that DHS will continue trying to identify groups that are posting footage to raise awareness of ICE’s most controversial moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE critics have used footage of tragic events—like Renee Good’s killing andeight other ICE shootings since September—to support calls to remove ICE from embattled communities and abolish ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions remain high as US citizens defend both their neighbors and their own constitutional rights. Most recently, shocking footage ofICE using a 5-year-old boy as baitto trap other family members intensified calls to defund ICE. Public backlash also raged after videos showedICE removing a US citizen from his home in his underwear. That arrest happened while ICE was conducting a warrantless search that awhistleblower warnedis becoming the new ICE norm after an internal memo said that agents can enter homes without a judicial warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some politicians are starting to take up the call to diminish ICE’s power. On Thursday, the majority of House Democrats voted to defund ICE, which Politiconotedwas a “remarkable shift from when dozens of them voted to expand the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement authority just one year ago.” Of course, the ICE budget bill passed anyway, since Republicans control the House, but withpublic approval of ICE tanking, any ongoing pushback could hurt Republicans in midterms and eventually even doom ICE if momentum is sustained.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:10:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demand for Intel’s processors is apparently there, but the supply is not</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/intel-core-ultra-series-3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel is allocating more of its own production to its money-making server chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel reportedits earnings for the fourth quarter of 2025 yesterday, and the news both for the quarter and for the year was mixed: year-over-year revenue was down nearly imperceptibly, from $53.1 billion to $52.9 billion, while revenue for the quarter was down about four percent, from $14.3 billion last year to $13.7 billion this year. (That number was, nevertheless, on the high end of Intel’s guidance for the quarter, which ranged from $12.8 to $13.8 billion.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving deeper into the numbers makes it clear exactly where money is being made and lost: Intel’s data center and AI products were up 9 percent for the quarter and 5 percent for the year, while its client computing group (which sells Core processors, Arc GPUs, and other consumer products) was down 7 percent for the quarter and 3 percent for the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That knowledge makes it slightly easier to understand the bind that company executives talked about on Intel’s earnings call (as transcribed by Investing.com). In short, Intel is having trouble making (and buying) enough chips to meet demand, and it makes more sense to allocate the chips itcanmake to the divisions that are actually making money—which means that we could see shortages of or higher prices for consumer processors, just as Intel is gearing up to launch the promising Core Ultra Series 3 processors (codenamed Panther Lake).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel CFO David Zinsner indicated that Intel is “prioritizing [its] internal wafer supply to data center” and having more of its consumer chips made externally. Substantial portions of the Core Ultra Series 3 processors are manufactured at Intel, after the company primarily used TSMC’s chip factories for the Core Ultra Series 2 designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can’t completely vacate the client market,” said Zinsner, but Intel is “shifting as much as we can over to data center to meet the high demand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounding this is that yields for the new 18A process—that is, the number of chips in a wafer with no defects that can work as designed—are still improving. Intel CEO Lip-Bu Tan said that “while yields are in line with our internal plans, they are still below what I want them to be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yields are currently improving by 7 or 8 percent every month, according to Intel. But that could be building on pretty low initial yields—reporting from last summer suggested that just 10 percent of the chips coming off of the 18A production lines were meeting Intel’s requirements at the time. Intel predicts that its supply will have ramped up enough within the next few months to help alleviate shortages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do believe that the first quarter is the trough,” said Zinsner. “We will improve supply in the second quarter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Intel can start making enough chips to meet its demand, it ought to help brighten the company’s earnings reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We delivered [our Q4 2025] results despite supply constraints, which meaningfully limited our ability to capture all of the strengths in our underwriting markets,” said Tan. “We are working aggressively to address this and better support our customers’ needs going forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel has been signaling for a while now that it was selling essentially all of the chips it could get its hands on. Intel investor relations VP John Pitzersaidlast month that Intel would be selling more of both its Lunar Lake and Arrow Lake Core Ultra Series 2 chips for consumers, as well as its Granite Rapids chips for data centers, if it could get more of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Intel seeks to improve its position in the short term, the company also says that it’s still making progress on its future manufacturing nodes, including different versions of the 18A process and the upcoming 14A process. Intel is working to engage “potential external customers” who would use the 14A process to make their own chips. If these third parties decide to use Intel’s manufacturing facilities, Intel expects to know about it “starting in the second half of this year and extending into the first half of 2027,” and then it expects to build out manufacturing capacity based on the number of external customers it finds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the chip design side, Intel also expects to have its first next-generation Nova Lake chips ready “at the end of 2026.” We don’t know much about Nova Lake yet, but it should be Intel’s next architecture to cover both desktop and laptop processors, while Panther Lake chips are intended mainly for laptops. At least part of the chip will also be manufactured using the 18A process.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:48:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TR-49 is interactive fiction for fans of deep research rabbit holes</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/4-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dense narrative deduction game tells a compellingly academia-tinged sci-fi tale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developer:InklePublisher: InklePlatform: MacOS (reviewed), Windows, iOSRelease Date:Jan. 21, 2026ESRB Rating:N/APrice: $7Links:iOS App Store|Steam|Official website&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever fallen downa Wikipedia rabbit holeor spent a pleasant evening digging through college library stacks, you know the joy of a good research puzzle. Every new source and cross-reference you find unlocks an incremental understanding of a previously unknown world, forming a piecemeal tapestry of knowledge that you can eventually look back at as a cohesive and well-known whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49takes this research process and operationalizes it into an engrossing and novel piece of heavily non-linear interactive fiction. Researching the myriad sources contained in the game’s mysterious computer slowly reveals a tale that’s part mystery, part sci-fi allegory, part family drama, and all-compelling alternate academic history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entirety ofTR-49takes place from a first-person perspective as you sit in front of a kind of Steampunk-infused computer terminal. An unseen narrator asks you to operate the machine but is initially cagey about how or why or what you’re even looking for. There’s a creepy vibe to the under-explained circumstances that brought you to this situation, but the game never descends into the jump scares or horror tropes of so many other modern titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your only real form of interaction with the world ofTR-49is through a sepia-toned tube display on the left and a four-charactersplit-flapon the right that serves as the computer’s only input. You quickly discover that entering specific sequences—each with two letters followed by two numbers, as suggested by the game’s name—brings up library catalog-style entries referring to a vast web of literary works that form the core of the game’s wider fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the catalog contains short excerpts from each of these discovered works, it’s the additional notes added to each entry by subsequent researchers that place each title in its full context. You’ll end up poring through these research notes for clues about the existence and chronology of other authors and works. Picking out specific names and years points to the codes and titles needed to unlock even more reference pages in the computer, pushing you further down the rabbit hole. Picture something likeHer Story, but replace the cinéma vérité surveillance video clips with a library card catalog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll slowly start to unravel and understand how the game world’s myriad authors are influencing each other with their cross-pollinating writings. The treatises, novels, pamphlets, and journals discussed in this database are full of academic sniping, intellectual intrigue, and interpersonal co-mingling across multiple generations of work. It all ends up circling a long-running search for a metaphysical key to life itself, which most of the authors manage to approach but never quite reach a full understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you explore, you also start to learn more about the personal affairs of the researchers who collected and cataloged all this reference material and the vaguely defined temporal capabilities of the information-synthesis engine in the computer you’ve all worked on. Eventually, you’ll stumble on the existence of core commands that can unlock hidden parts of the computer or alter the massive research database itself, which becomes key to your eventual final goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through it all, there’s a slowly unfolding parallel narrative involving Liam, the unseen voice guiding you through the research process itself. Through occasional voice clips, Liam eventually hints at the existence of a powerful and quickly encroaching threat that wants to stop your progress by any means necessary, adding a bit of dramatic tension to your academic pursuits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m being intentionally vague about the specifics here because I thinkTR-49‘s subtle and well-crafted sci-fi world-building is best experienced by exploring the game for yourself. There’s a real satisfaction in staring at a once impenetrably obtuse research note, recalling a bit of information from a recent cross-reference, and feeling your understanding suddenly click into place. And while the vocal performances can verge on cheesy, the writing captures the monomaniacal intensity of truly obsessive academics to a tee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the game’s best features is a “Notes” sub-menu, which automatically outlines relevant facts (and potential facts) about various authors, groups, and publications as you discover them. This means you don’t have to take page after page of hand-written notes to keep track of the game’s complex connections (and potential connections), as you do in games likeBlue PrinceorLorelei and the Laser Eyes. It makes for a much smoother puzzle-solving experience, even if the automatic notes sometimes pick up on things you may have missed while skimming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49also benefits from being relatively compact compared to some other narrative deduction games. A diligent investigator can reach a conclusion in four or five hours, depending on how thorough they want to be. That makes it relatively easy to keep the broad outlines of the game’s dense but parsable world in your head over a couple of evening play sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are bound to be some people who seeTR-49as akin to a homework simulator, with painful flashbacks to all-nighters spent desperately researching a last-minute college term paper. For anyone who knows the inherent appeal of diving deep into a previously unknown world, though,TR-49is an engrossing work of world-building fiction presented in a truly memorable way.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:52:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>