<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 16:48:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Japan lost a 5-ton navigation satellite when it fell off a rocket during launch</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/heres-the-story-of-how-japans-h3-rocket-lost-its-cargo-and-just-kept-going/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/jaxa_h3_f8_anim1.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine: You lost your car’s cargo rack, but didn’t notice until you reached your destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the space business long enough, you learn there are numerous ways a rocket can fail. I’ve written my share of stories about misbehaving rockets and the extensive investigations that usually—but not always—reveal what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I never expected to write this story. Maybe this was a failure of my own imagination. I’m used to writing about engine malfunctions, staging issues, guidance glitches, or structural failures. Last April, Arsreported on the bizarre failureof Firefly Aerospace’s commercial Alpha rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan’s H3 rocket found a new way to fail last month, apparently eluding the imaginations of its own designers and engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The H3 is a relatively new vehicle, with last month’s launch marking the eighth flight of Japan’s flagship rocket. The launcher falls on the medium-to-heavy section of the lift spectrum. The eighth H3 rocket lifted off from Tanegashima Island in southern Japan on December 22, local time, carrying a roughly 5-ton navigation satellite into space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket was supposed to place the Michibiki 5 satellite into an orbit ranging more than 20,000 miles above the Earth. Everything was going well until the H3 jettisoned its payload fairing, the two-piece clamshell covering the satellite during launch, nearly four minutes into the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials from the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency (JAXA) are starting to get a handle on what happened. Agency officials briefed the government ministry overseeing Japan’s space activities last week, and the presentation (in Japanese) wasposted on a government website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is rich in information, with illustrations, a fault tree analysis, and a graph of in-flight measurements from sensors on the H3 rocket. It offers a treasure trove of detail and data most launch providers decline to release publicly after a rocket malfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the material is difficult to grasp for a non-Japanese speaker unfamiliar with the subtle intricacies of the H3 rocket’s design. What is clear is that something went wrong when the rocket released its payload shroud. Video beamed back from the rocket’s onboard cameras showed a shower of debris surrounding the satellite, which started wobbling and leaning in the moments after fairing separation. Sensors also detected sudden accelerations around the attachment point connecting the spacecraft with the top of the H3 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the mission, the H3 rocket was well above the thick lower layers of the atmosphere. Aerodynamic forces were not a significant factor, but the rocket continued accelerating on the power of its two hydrogen-fueled main engines. The Michibiki 5 satellite held on for a little more than a minute, when the H3’s first stage shut down and separated from the rocket’s second stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jolt from staging dislodged the satellite from its mooring atop the rocket. Then, the second stage lit its engine and left the satellite in the dust. A rear-facing camera on the upper stage captured a fleeting view of the satellite falling back to Earth. In the briefing package, Japanese space officials wrote that Michibiki 5 fell into the Pacific Ocean in the same impact zone as the H3’s first stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever caused the satellite to break free of the rocket damaged more than its attach fitting. Telemetry data downlinked from the H3 showed a pressure drop in the second stage’s liquid hydrogen tank after separation of the payload fairing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A decrease in LH2 tank pressure was confirmed almost simultaneously,” officials wrote. A pressurization valve continued to open to restore pressure to the tank, but the pressure did not recover. “It is highly likely that the satellite mounting structure was damaged due to some factor, and as a result, the pressurization piping was damaged.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second stage engine lost 20 percent of its thrust, but it fired long enough to put the rocket into a low-altitude orbit. The rocket’s temporary recovery was likely aided by the absence of its multi-ton payload, meaning it needed a lower impulse to reach orbital velocity. The orbit was too low to sustain, and the second stage of the H3 rocket reentered the atmosphere and burned up within several hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators now have a grasp of what happened, but they are still piecing together why. JAXA presented a fault tree analysis to the Japanese science and technology ministry, showing which potential causes engineers have ruled out, and which ones remain under investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The branches of the fault tree still open include the possibility of an impact or collision between part of the payload fairing and the Michibiki 5 satellite or its mounting structure. Engineers continue to probe the possibility that residual strain energy in the connection between the satellite and the rocket was suddenly released at the moment of fairing separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket is supposed to vent pressure inside the fairing as it ascends through thinner air and into space. Measurements from the rocket indicate the pressure inside the fairing decreased as expected during the launch. Officials don’t believe this was a factor in the launch failure, but engineers are examining whether the measurements were in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket and satellite also carried combustible propellants, high-pressure gases, and pyrotechnics. “While no data indicating leakage of these substances has been confirmed, the possibility that they caused the abnormal acceleration cannot be ruled out at this time,” JAXA said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the probe has found no evidence that a structural problem with the satellite itself was the root cause of the failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With last month’s incident, the H3 rocket has a record of six successful launches in eight flights. The H3’s debut launch in 2023 faltered due to an ignition failure on the rocket’s second stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JAXA must complete the latest H3 failure investigation in the coming months to clear the rocket to launch the nation’s Martian Moons Exploration (MMX) mission in a narrow planetary launch window that opens in October. MMX is an exciting robotic mission to land on and retrieve samples from the Martian moon Phobos for return to Earth. MMX’s launch was previously set for 2024, but Japan’s space agency delayed it to this year due to earlier problems with the H3 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/heres-the-story-of-how-japans-h3-rocket-lost-its-cargo-and-just-kept-going/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:15:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Users flock to open source Moltbot for always-on AI, despite major risks</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/viral-ai-assistant-moltbot-rapidly-gains-popularity-but-poses-security-risks/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/clawdbot_1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The open source “Jarvis” chats via WhatsApp but requires access to your files and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An open source AI assistant called Moltbot (formerly “Clawdbot”) recently crossed 69,000 stars onGitHubafter a month, making it one of the fastest-growing AI projects of 2026. Created by Austrian developerPeter Steinberger, the tool lets users run a personal AI assistant and control it through messaging apps they already use. While some say it feels like the AI assistant of the future, running the tool as currently designed comes with serious security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the dozens of unofficial AI bot apps that never rise above the fray, Moltbot is perhaps most notable for its proactive communication with the user. The assistant works with WhatsApp, Telegram, Slack, Discord, Google Chat, Signal, iMessage, Microsoft Teams, and other platforms. It can reach out to users with reminders, alerts, or morning briefings based on calendar events or other triggers. The project has drawn comparisons to Jarvis, the AI assistant from the Iron Man films, for its ability to actively attempt to manage tasks across a user’s digital life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we’ll tell you up front that there are plenty of drawbacks to the still-hobbyist software: While the organizing assistant code runs on a local machine, the tool effectively requires a subscription to Anthropic or OpenAI for model access (or using an API key). Users can run local AI models with the bot, but they are currently less effective at carrying out tasks than the best commercial models. Claude Opus 4.5, which is Anthropic’s flagship large language model (LLM), is a popular choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up Moltbot requires configuring a server, managing authentication, and understanding sandboxing for even a slice of security in a system that basically demands access to every facet of your digital life. Heavy use can rack up significant API costs, since agentic systems make many calls behind the scenes and use up a lot of tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve only just begun to try Moltbot ourselves (more on that soon), but we’ve seen plenty of discussions circulating in the AI community about the new assistant. The all-in approach has serious security drawbacks, since it requires access to messaging accounts, API keys, and in some configurations, shell commands. Also, an always-on agent with access to messaging channels and personal systems can quickly expand your attack surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with all the drawbacks listed above, people are still using Moltbot. MacStories editor Federico Viticci, who spent a week testing the tool,describedit as “Claude with hands,” referring to how it connects a large language model (LLM) backend with real-world capabilities like browser control, email management, and file operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s documentation describes it as a tool for users who want “a personal, single-user assistant that feels local, fast, and always-on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the project’s GitHub page, Steinberger designed the bot to retain long-term memory and execute commands directly on the user’s system, unlike current web-based chatbots from major AI labs. It’s closer toClaude CodeandCodex CLI(which also operate on local files using a cloud AI model), but with more latitude to take local actions on the user’s behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moltbot stores memory as Markdown files and an SQLite database on the user’s machine. It auto-generates daily notes that log interactions and uses vector search to retrieve relevant context from past conversations. The memory persists across sessions because the bot runs as a background daemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to Claude Code, which is session-based, Moltbot runs persistently (24/7) and maintains its stored memory indefinitely. It can reportedly recall what you discussed weeks ago. With Claude Code, when you close it, the conversation context is gone (unless you use CLAUDE.md files for project context).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s rapid rise has not come without complications. On Monday, AnthropicaskedSteinberger to change the project’s name due to trademark concerns (since “Clawd” sounds like “Claude”), prompting the rebrand from Clawdbot to Moltbot. “Clawdbot” was originally named after the ASCII art creature that appears when you launch Claude Code on a terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the transition enabled bad actors to hijack Steinberger’s old social media and GitHub handles,reportsThe Register. Crypto scammers launched fake tokens using the project’s name, with one reaching a $16 million market cap before crashing. Steinbergerrespondedon X: “Any project that lists me as a coin owner is a SCAM. No, I will not accept fees. You are actively damaging the project.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security researchers have alsofoundvulnerabilities in misconfigured public deployments. Bitdefender reported that exposed dashboards allowed outsiders to view configuration data, retrieve API keys, and browse full conversation histories from private chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there’s plenty of hype about Moltbot right now, be advised that any LLM that has access to your local machine is susceptible toprompt injectionattacks that can “trick” the AI model to share your personal data with other people or remote servers. While Moltbot offers a glimpse at what future AI assistants from major vendors might look like, it’s still experimental and not yet ready for users who aren’t comfortable trading today’s AI convenience (such as it is) for major security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/viral-ai-assistant-moltbot-rapidly-gains-popularity-but-poses-security-risks/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:30:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The origin story of syphilis goes back far longer than we thought</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/the-origin-story-of-syphilis-goes-back-far-longer-than-we-thought/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/3f05379v-e1360003011507-634x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 5,500-year-old fossil from Colombia has scientists rethinking syphilis origins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When King Charles VIII of France occupied Naples in 1495, his army of nearly 20,000 mercenaries became the ground zero of the “Great Pox,” the first massive venereal syphilis pandemic in Europe, which went on to cause up to 5 million deaths. For a long time, the siege of Naples was considered the first time syphilis entered European accounts and culture. “But the evolutionary history ofTreponema pallidum, the lineage of bacteria including the one that causes syphilis, goes way deeper in time,” says Elizabeth Nelson, an anthropologist at the Southern Methodist University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson and her colleagues found a 5,500-year-oldTreponema pallidumgenome in an individual excavated from a rock shelter in Colombia—a discovery that shows pathogens causing treponemal diseases like syphilis, bejel, or yaws are several millennia older than we thought. And this means we might have been thinking about the origins of syphilis in an entirely wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the French occupation of Naples did not introduce syphilis to this world, it created the perfect storm that shaped the perception of this disease and its origins for centuries to come. The first ingredient of this storm was the French army and its leader. Charles VIII invaded Naples with a vast melting pot of brigands and mercenaries from all over Europe, including the French, Swiss, Poles, and Spaniards. The king himself wasn’t exactly the epitome of morality. Chroniclers like Johannes Burckard noted his “fondness of copulation” and reported that, once he’d been with a woman, he “cared no more about her” and immediately sought another partner—a behavior eagerly mirrored by his soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second ingredient was the city of Naples, which back in the 15thcentury was famous as the center of luxury and sex. When the city surrendered and opened its gates, the invading army spent months on what Joseph Grünpeck, a secretary to the Holy Roman Emperor Maximillian I, described as “gluttony, debauchery, and consorting with prostitutes.” This created the ideal set of conditions for syphilis, a sexually transmitted disease, to spread massively among the armies. When the mercenaries, incapable of fighting anymore, deserted the infected army and fled to their home countries, the disease rapidly spread across Europe. These conditions also immediately defined the narrative about syphilis in terms of cultural and national blame games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Neapolitans called syphilis Morbus Gallicus, which means the French disease. The French returned the favor and called it the Neapolitan disease. The English naturally called it the French Pox, and so on. Ultimately, fingers ended up pointing at a few Spaniards from Charles VIII’s army. They allegedly served as crew members on Columbus’ ships that returned from the New World in 1493, just one year before the siege of Naples started. The syphilis was declared a “gift” Columbus brought to Europe from the Americas, a curse the New World cast upon the old one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blame game naturally assumed syphilis must have had a single place of origin, be it Naples, France, Europe, or the Americas. The 5,500-year-oldTreponema pallidumgenome discovered by Nelson and her colleagues suggests it might not have been the case at all. “I would not say our work makes popular syphilis origin stories irrelevant, but it shows there’s more ecological and evolutionary depth here,” Nelson says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discovery was, in a way, a lucky break. The team was sequencing the DNA of an individual excavated from the Tequendama I rock shelter, located in the Sabana de Bogotá, Colombia, as part of a broader research project on the population history of the Americas. The individual in question, labeled TE1-3, was an adult male hunter-gatherer who lived in Middle Holocene, roughly 5,500 years ago. “We weren’t looking for the origins of syphilis, this wasn’t the main focus of our research,” says Nasreen Broomandkhoshbacht, a geneticist at the University of Vermont and co-author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, scientists hunting for ancientTreponemagenomes look for bones with telltale signs of treponematosis like altered shins or pitted skull lesions. But the skeleton of TE1-3 showed no macroscopic signs of infection. Usually, this would make it a poor candidate for pathogen recovery. However, thanks to the sheer volume of data generated—1.5 billion fragments of genetic material—scientists could detect traces ofTreponema pallidum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the bacterial DNA making up a minuscule portion of the total sequencing data, the team succeeded in reconstructing the ancient pathogen’s genome, and right from the start it appeared a little bit special. Thetreponema pallidumlineage today comprises three subspecies responsible for syphilis, bejel, and yaws. “We noticed that the genome we recovered differed from those three much more than they differ from each other,” Broomandkhoshbacht says. That indicates the newly discovered bacterium wasn’t a direct ancestor of modern syphilis, yaws, or bejel. “It was a sister lineage that diverged from all known modern subspecies approximately 13,700 years ago in Late Pleistocene,” says Davide Bozzi, a computational biologist at the University of Lausanne and lead author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13,700 years ago was roughly when humans first started populating South America and rapidly spread around the continent. And, based on this discovery, the bacteria of theTreponema pallidumlineage were already diverse and capable of infecting people by then. This Late Pleistocene divergence, the authors note in their study, hints at the ancient pan-human distribution. VariousTreponema pallidumsubspecies were probably our fellow travelers spreading globally with the first humans that migrated out of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s much more we need to learn before the “Columbian” syphilis origin debate is settled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 1495 siege of Naples remains the moment syphilis etched itself into the European psyche as a new and terrifying plague, it was likely just one violent flare-up in a relationship between humans andTreponemapathogens that spans continents and millennia. What we don’t know is when and where the important turning points in this relationship took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear when and whyTreponema pallidumevolved its sexual transmission, so evidently present in the subspecies that caused the outbreak in Naples. It’s also unclear whether the 1495 pandemic was triggered by a newly imported strain or a mutation of a lineage already present in Europe. The team hopes analyzing other ancient pathogen genomes hosted by people from different places on the globe and different social contexts—hunter-gatherers, farmers, city dwellers—will answer at least some of these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, it’s hard to infer a specific pathogen’s features from ancient genomes. “With the data we have today, we can’t say anything about the virulence of this ancientTreponema pallidumsubspecies, about how the symptoms of the disease it caused looked like, or about its mode of transmission,” Bozzi says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we do know, however, is that thousands of years ago, theTreponema pallidumlineage was likely way more diverse than it is today. “In the future we’d love to look at broader ecological interactions between humans, animals, the environment, and the pathogens,” says Nelson. “We’d love to explore this diversity further.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science, 2026. DOI:10.1126/science.adw3020&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/the-origin-story-of-syphilis-goes-back-far-longer-than-we-thought/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:55:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ryzen 9850X3D review: AMD's bragging-rights gaming CPU gets more to brag about</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/review-amds-ryzen-7-9850x3d-is-a-little-faster-and-a-lot-more-power-hungry/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_7105-1152x648-1769617334.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tradeoffs for the $499 9850X3D make it hard to get excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD has released three distinct generations of its 3D V-Cache technology, which initially appeared in theRyzen 7 5800X3Din 2022. The kernel of the idea has remained the same throughout AMD’s efforts: take an existing desktop processor design and graft 64MB of additional L3 cache onto it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach disproportionately helps apps that benefit from more cache, particularly games, and the size of the boost that 3D V-Cache gives to game performance has always been enough to offset any downsides these chips have come with. And in the four years since the 5800X3D was released, AMD has steadily chipped away at those disadvantages, adding more CPU cores, improving power consumption and temperatures, and re-adding the typical Ryzen range of overclocking controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD’s new Ryzen 7 9850X3D, which launches for $499 starting tomorrow, is the very definition of a mild upgrade. It’s the year-old Ryzen 7 9800X3D but with an extra 400 MHz of turbo boost speed. That’s it. That’s the chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is mildly interesting that the 9800X3D’s 5.6GHz boost clock is now 100 MHzhigherthan that of the Ryzen 7 9700X, the chip’s nearest non-V-Cache equivalent. It’s not nearly as interesting as an actual new chip, but it does mean AMD has closed the last major functional gap between the V-Cache and non-V-Cache Ryzen chips (the pricing gap remains; the 9700X currently retails for around $329).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means that the 9850X3D behaves more like a 9700X in other ways—differences that likely won’t matter to its target audience but which do distinguish it from being “just a faster 9800X3D.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest change AMD made to the Ryzen 9000 version of the X3D chips is that the 3D V-Cache is now stacked underneath the CPU silicon rather than on top. This has the benefit of moving the CPU cores closer to your heatsink or AIO loop, making them easier to keep cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9850X3D remains an eight-core chip based on AMD’s Zen 5 architecture. All eight of those CPU cores have access to the 3D V-Cache, unlike the 12-core and 16-core Ryzen 9 9900X3D and 9950X3D. In each of those chips, one of the CPU chiplets has access to the 3D V-Cache and one doesn’t; AMD’s chipset software is responsible for making sure apps run on the type of CPU core that will maximize the app’s performance. AMD’s software is pretty good at this, but it’s not foolproof, which can make the 9800X3D and 9850X3D more appealing and cost-effective options for PCs that will mainly be used for gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specs in our CPU testbed are the same as they’ve been for a while. We’ll be focused on comparing the 9850X3D to its predecessors, the 5800X3D, 7800X3D, and 9800X3D, as well as the non-V-Cache 7700X and 9700X. We’ll also include numbers from the higher-end 9900X3D and 9950X3D. Intel’s side of the fence will be represented by the Core Ultra 9 285K and the last few generations of Core i9 chips, though Intel has yet to release any chips that are truly performance-competitive with the 3D V-Cache chips in gaming workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though our testbed continues to rely on DDR5-6000, AMD’s slide deck takes the current (horrible) state of the RAM market into account. While DDR5-6000 or DDR5-6400 is generally still the performance sweet spot for all socket AM5 CPUs, AMD notes that game performance between the 9850X3D with DDR5-6000 and the same chip with DDR5-4800 can be as little as 1 to 2 percent. In other words, pair whatever RAM you can find with this chip and don’t worry about it too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice about the 9850X3D is that its multi-core performance is essentially indistinguishable from the 9800X3D. If anything, the 9800X3D seems marginally better-behaved in our Handbrake video encoding tests, which could come down to anything or nothing—maybe it’s an actual difference between the chips, maybe it’s the silicon lottery, maybe it’s something else. Overall, it’s mostly a wash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9850X3Ddoesimprove significantly on the 9800X3D’s single-core performance, closing the gap with both the Ryzen 9900X3D and 9950X3D (both of which have regular Zen 5 cores with no 3D V-Cache) and the 9700X (which has no 3D V-Cache at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a world in which AMD can get this extra performance for “free” without changing anything about the architecture or manufacturing process. AMD could have been “binning” silicon lottery winners, or the reliability of the manufacturing process could have improved enough to allow AMD to hit better numbers that weren’t as consistently achievable a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it looks like AMD improved the 9850X3D’s single-core performance mainly by making it behave more like a non-X3D chip. The chip’s power consumption while gaming suggests this is more or less what’s happening—the 9850X3D’s CPU package power while gaming is some 25 or 30 W higher than the 9800X3D playing the same games, despite the single-digit-at-best performance improvement (in both our testing and AMD’s advertising).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 9850X3D’s power consumption while gaming isn’t wildly out of step with the 9700X’s or the 9950X3D’s, it does make the tiny performance gains on display here hard to get excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is on top of the cost trade-off you’re already making when you buy an X3D-series chip. Game performance is always impressive, but you notice those benefits themostin situations where your CPU, not the GPU, is the performance bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time in a gaming PC, that’s only going to be the case when you’re trying to play games at extremely high frame rates at lower resolutions. It’s less useful when trying to play games at 4K or even 1440p, where your graphics card will be the limiter. If you’re building a system around any GPU slower than an RTX 4080 or 5080, going with a regular 9700X and putting the savings toward your GPU (or toward an eye-wateringly expensive RAM kit) will usually be a better use of funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ryzen 7 9850X3D mostly does what it says it does: It’s a mild speed bump to AMD’s best gaming processor that, in most cases, very slightly extends the company’s performance lead over Intel chips like the Core Ultra 9 285K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the vanilla 9800X3D isalmostas fast, it uses 25 or 30 W less power during gaming (which also results in temperatures that are 10 to 15 degrees Celsius cooler), and it’s $30 cheaper as of this writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who routinely runs his own Ryzen desktop chips in Eco Mode to reduce power consumption and temperatures and hit a more efficient spot on the performance-per-Watt curve, the numbers that the 9850X3D posted in our testing make it seem like an undesirable trade-off, even if you’re in the target market for a fast-as-possible, money-no-object, bragging-rights gaming PC.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/review-amds-ryzen-7-9850x3d-is-a-little-faster-and-a-lot-more-power-hungry/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 07:41:40 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>