<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:22:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>As data from space spikes, an innovative ground station company seeks to cash in</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/as-data-from-space-spikes-an-innovative-ground-station-company-seeks-to-cash-in/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/2405e3f23bdc3b88ca609d0a228cb64fe0761063-3840x2160-1.avif" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s why we’re here, that’s why we’re building what we’re building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company that seeks to disrupt the way in which data from space is received and transmitted has found some key investors and customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning Northwood Space announced that it has closed a $100 million Series B round of funding to support a rapid ramp-up in the deployment of its phased-array radar system, known as Portal. The company also said it has received a $49.8 million contract from the US Space Force to augment the Satellite Control Network, which provides telemetry and tracking for the military’s satellites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We made our last fundraise announcement in April of 2025, so less than a year, but there’s been a lot of activity and progress on the Northwood side that reflects the importance of ground as an enabler for pushing forward more capable missions on shorter timelines,” said Bridgit Mendler, co-founder and CEO of Northwood, during a media roundtable. “That’s why we’re here, that’s why we’re building what we’re building, is because we believe that there’s a lot of important capability in space that needs to be built faster, and the way to do that is through a vertically integrated ground network.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funding announcements cap a busy year for Northwood, which emerged from stealth as a small startup in February 2024. The company was founded on the premise that there is a bottleneck in the capability of commercial ground stations to download increasing amounts of data gathered by satellites in orbit, and that this will only get worse. Northwood and its investors are betting that the existing network of commercial ground stations, many of which were deployed a decade or longer ago, cannot keep up with the pace of new satellites arriving in orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June, the company demonstrated its second-generation phased-array antenna, known as Portal. Instead of needing to point directly at their target to collect a signal, like a parabolic dish antenna, phased-array antennas produce a beam of radio waves that can “point” in different directions without moving the antenna. It can also communicate with multiple satellites, in multiple orbits, at a single time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the year, Northwood, based in El Segundo, California, had shown the ability to build eight of these Portal arrays a month. And in January, the company had deployed operational Portal antennas across two continents. These deployments, which comprise an area of 8 to 15 meters, have the equivalent capability of a 7-meter parabolic dish, said Griffin Cleverly, co-founder and chief technical officer of Northwood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Across our initial Portal sites, it will be a few dozen spacecraft that each of them can handle,” he said. “And then, as we get into 2027, with much more scale manufacturing, we’ll easily be able to handle hundreds of satellites with our network.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Northwood’s entry into the development of ground stations—there are about half a dozen major players in the industry, some long-established, others new—came as the Space Force was looking to modernize its Satellite Control Network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According toa government reportpublished in 2023, the network makes 450 daily contacts with satellites and supports the launch and operations of these vehicles. The report found that the network faced “sustainment and obsolescence issues while demands on the system are increasing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Space Force is seeking to address these issues as well as the proliferation of satellites in low-Earth orbit, and came to Northwood looking to scale up its system to meet these needs. Northwood began working with the Space Force in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company seeks to address both government and commercial customers with the Portal system and future antennas. One growth area much discussed in recent months has been orbital data centers, which would require moving large amounts of data to and from space. Mendler said Northwood was “enthusiastic” to support such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our overall perspective on the space industry was that volume of data was going to go up, use cases were going to go up,” Mendler said of the reasons for founding Northwood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And that has definitely borne out, whether we’re talking about communications, which has also been surging, or manufacturing or energy or compute, all of these different use cases in space, there’s a lot of appetite to address them,” she added. “The way that we think about ourselves is someone who conceives of solutions for how to make that all happen and then is accountable to actually see them through.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/as-data-from-space-spikes-an-innovative-ground-station-company-seeks-to-cash-in/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:16:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meet the mysterious electrides</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/meet-the-mysterious-electrides/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/earthcore-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These chemical oddities may explain why Earth seems to be deficient in certain elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For close to a century, geoscientists have pondered a mystery: Where did Earth’s lighter elements go? Compared to amounts in the Sun and in some meteorites, Earth has less hydrogen, carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur, as well as noble gases like helium—in some cases, more than 99 percent less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the disparity is explained by losses to the solar system as our planet formed. But researchers have long suspected that something else was going on too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, a team of scientists reported a possible explanation—that the elements are hiding deep in the solid inner core of Earth. At its super-high pressure—360 gigapascals, 3.6 million times atmospheric pressure—the iron there behaves strangely, becoming an electride: a little-known form of the metal that can suck up lighter elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study coauthor Duck Young Kim, a solid-state physicist at the Center for High Pressure Science &amp; Technology Advanced Research in Shanghai, says the absorption of these light elements may have happened gradually over a couple of billion years—and may still be going on today. It would explain why the movement of seismic waves traveling through Earth suggests an inner core density that is 5 percent to 8 percent lower than expected were it metal alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrides, in more ways than one, are having their moment. Not only might they help solve a planetary mystery, they can now be made at room temperature and pressure from an array of elements. And since all electrides contain a source of reactive electrons that are easily donated to other molecules, they make ideal catalysts and other sorts of agents that help to propel challenging reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One electride is already in use to catalyze theproduction of ammonia, a key component of fertilizer; its Japanese developers claim the process uses 20 percent less energy than traditional ammonia manufacture. Chemists, meanwhile, are discovering new electrides that could lead to cheaper and greener methods of producing pharmaceuticals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today’s challenge is to find more of these intriguing materials and to understand the chemical rules that govern when they form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most solids are made from ordered lattices of atoms, but electrides are different. Their lattices have little pockets where electrons sit on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normal metals haveelectronsthat are not stuck to one atom. These are the outer, or valence, electrons that are free to move between atoms, forming what is often referred to as a delocalized “sea of electrons.” It explains why metals conduct electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outer electrons of electrides no longer orbit a particular atom either, but they can’t freely move. Instead, they become trapped at sites between atoms that are called non-nuclear attractors. This gives the materials unique properties. In the case of the iron in Earth’s core, the negative electron charges stabilize lighter elements at non-nuclear attractors that were formed at those super-high pressures, 3,000 times than at the bottom of the deepest ocean. The elements would diffuse into the metal, explaining where they disappeared to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first metal found to form an electride at high pressure was sodium, reported in 2009. At a pressure of 200 gigapascals (2 million times greater than atmospheric pressure) it transforms from a shiny, reflective, conducting metal into a transparent glassy, insulating material. This finding was “very weird,” says Stefano Racioppi, a computational and theoretical chemist at the University of Cambridge in the United Kingdom, who worked on sodium electrides while in the lab of Eva Zurek at the University at Buffalo in New York state. Early theories, he says, had predicted that at high pressure, sodium’s outer electrons would move even more freely between atoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sign that things were different came from predictions in the late 1990s, whenscientists were using computational simulationsto model solids, based on the rules ofquantum theory. These rules define the energy levels that electrons can have, and hence the probable range of positions in which they are found in atoms (their atomic orbitals).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulating solid sodium showed that at high pressures, as the sodium atoms get squeezed closer together, so do the electrons orbiting each atom. That causes them to experience increasing repulsive forces with one another. This changes the relative energies of every electron orbiting the nucleus of each atom, Racioppi explains—leading to a reorganization of electron positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result? Rather than occupying orbitals that allow them to be delocalized and move between atoms, the orbitals take on a new shape that forces electrons into the non-nuclear attractor sites. Since the electrons are stuck at these sites, the solid loses its metallic properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding to this theoretical work, Racioppi and Zurek collaborated with researchers at the University of Edinburgh to find experimental evidence for a sodium electride at extreme pressures. Squeezing crystals of sodium between two diamonds, they used X-ray diffraction to map electron density in the metal structure. This, they reported in September 2025, confirmed that electronsreally were located in the predicted non-nuclear attractor sitesbetween sodium atoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrides are ideal candidates for catalysts—substances that can speed up and lower the energy needed for chemical reactions. That’s because the isolated electrons at the non-nuclear attractor sites can be donated to make and break bonds. But to be useful, they would need to function at ambient conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several such stable electrides have been discovered over the last 10 years, made from inorganic compounds or organic molecules containing metal atoms. One of the most significant, mayenite, was found by surprise in 2003 when material scientist Hideo Hosono at the Institute of Science Tokyo was investigating a type of cement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayenite is a calcium aluminate oxide that forms crystals with very small pores—a few nanometers across—called cages, that contain oxygen ions. If a metal vapor of calcium or titanium is passed over it at high temperature, it removes the oxygen, leaving behind just electrons trapped at these sites—an electride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the high-pressure metal electrides that switch from conductors to insulators, mayenite starts as an insulator. But now its trapped electrons can jump between cage sites (via a process called quantum tunnelling)—making it a conductor, albeit 100 to 1,000 times less conductive than a metal like aluminum or silver. It also becomes an excellent catalyst, able to surrender electrons to help make and break bonds in reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2011, Hosono had begun to develop mayenite as a greener and more efficient catalyst for synthesizing ammonia. Over 170 million metric tons of ammonia, mostly for fertilizers, is produced annually via the Haber-Bosch process, in which metal oxides facilitate hydrogen and nitrogen gases reacting together at high pressure and temperature. It is an energy-intensive, expensive process—Haber-Bosch plants account for some 2 percent of the world’s energy use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Haber-Bosch, the catalysts bind the two gases to their surfaces and donate electrons to help break the strong triple bond that holds the two nitrogen atoms together in nitrogen gas, as well as the bonds in hydrogen gas. Because mayenite has a strong electron-donating nature, Hosono thought mayenite would be able to do it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hosono’s reaction, mayenite itself does not bind the gases but acts as a support bed for nanoparticles of a metal called ruthenium. First, the nanoparticles absorb the nitrogen and hydrogen gases. Then the mayenite donates electrons to the ruthenium. These electrons flow into the nitrogen and hydrogen molecules, making it easier to break their bonds. Ammonia thus forms at a lower temperature—300 to 400° C—and lower pressure—50 to 80 atmospheres— than with Haber-Bosch, which takes place at 400 to 500° C and 100 to 400 atmospheres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the company Tsubame BHB was formed to commercialize Hosono’s catalyst, with the first pilot plant opening in 2019, producing 20 metric tons of ammonia per year. The company has since opened a larger facility in Japan and is setting up a 20,000-ton-per year green ammonia plant in Brazil to replace some of the nation’s fossil-fuel-based fertilizer production. The company estimates that this will avoid 11,000 tons of CO2emissions annually—about equal to the annual emissions of 2,400 cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other applications for a mayenite catalyst, says Hosono, including a lower-energy conversion of CO2into useful chemicals like methane, methanol, or longer-chain hydrocarbons. Other scientists have suggested that mayenite’s cage structure also makes it suitable for immobilizing radioactive isotope waste in nuclear power stations: The electrons could capture negative ions like iodine and bromide and trap them in the cages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayenite has even been studied as a low-temperature propulsion system for satellites in space. When it is heated to 600° C in a vacuum, its trapped electrons blast from the cages, causing propulsion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of materials known to form electrides keeps growing. In 2024, a team led by chemist Fabrizio Ortu at the University of Leicester in the UK accidentally discovered another room-temperature-stable electride made from calcium ions surrounded by large organic molecules, together known as a coordination complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was using a method known as mechanical chemistry—“You put something in a milling jar, you shake it really hard, and that provides the energy for the reaction,” he says. But to his surprise, electrons from the potassium he had added to his calcium complex were not donated to the calcium ion. Instead, what formed “had these electrons that were floating in the system,” he says, trapped in sites between the two metals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike mayenite, this electride is not a conductor—its trapped electrons do not jump. But they allow it to facilitate reactions that are otherwise hard to get started, by activating unreactive bonds, doing a job much like a catalyst. These are reactions that currently rely on expensive palladium catalysts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientists successfully used the electride on a reaction that joins two pyridine rings—carbon rings containing a nitrogen atom. They are now examining whether the electride could assist in other common organic reactions, such as substituting a hydrogen atom on a benzene ring. These substitutions are difficult because the bond between the benzene ring carbon and its attached hydrogen is very stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still problems to sort out: Ortu’s calcium electride is too air- and water-sensitive for use in industry. He is now looking for a more stable alternative, which could prove particularly useful in the pharmaceutical industry to synthesize drug molecules, where the sorts of reactions Ortu has demonstrated are common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There remain many unresolved mysteries about electrides, including whether Earth’s inner core definitely contains one. Kim and his collaborators used simulations of the iron lattice to find evidence for non-nuclear attractor sites, but their interpretation of the results remains “a little bit controversial,” Racioppi says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sodium and other metals in Group 1 and Group 2 of the periodic table of elements—such as lithium, calcium, and magnesium—have loosely bound outer electrons. This helps make it easy for electrons to shift to non-nuclear attractor sites, forming electrides. But iron exerts more pulling power on its outer electrons, which sit in differently shaped orbitals. This makes the increase in electron repulsion under pressure less significant and thus the shift to electride formation difficult, Racioppi says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrides are still little known and little studied, says computational materials scientist Lee Burton of Tel Aviv University. There is still no theory or model to predict when a material will become one. “Because electrides are not typical chemically, you can’t bring your chemical intuition to it,” he says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burton has been searching for rules that might help with predictions and has had some success finding electrides from a screen of 40,000 known materials. He is now using artificial intelligence to find more. “It’s a complex interplay between different properties that sometimes can all depend on each other,” he says. “This is where machine learning can really help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key is having reliable data to train any model. Burton’s team only has actual data from the handful of electride structures experimentally confirmed so far, but they also are using the kind of modeling based on quantum theory that was carried out by Racioppi to create high-resolution simulations of electron density within materials. They are doing this for as many materials as they can; those that are confirmed by real-world experiments will be used to train an AI model to identify more materials that are likely to be electrides—ones with the discrete pockets of high electron density characteristic of trapped electron sites. “The potential,” says Burton, “is enormous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowable Magazine, 2026. DOI:10.1146/knowable-012626-2(About DOIs)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This article originally appeared inKnowable Magazine, a nonprofit publication dedicated to making scientific knowledge accessible to all.Sign up for Knowable Magazine’s newsletter.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/meet-the-mysterious-electrides/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:48:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why NASA, IMSA, and tech companies are teaming up on tech transfer</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/why-nasa-imsa-and-tech-companies-are-teaming-up-on-tech-transfer/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257524943-2560x1440-1769523247.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMSA Labs will use the vast amount of race car data collected during a race to improve simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DAYTONA BEACH, Fla.—The annual 24-hour race that kicks off the American racing season took place this past weekend at Daytona International Speedway. Each year, the crowd gets bigger and bigger, drawn in large part by the hybrid prototypes that contest the GTP class for overall victory. After Formula 1, these are some of the most complex, sophisticated race cars ever to turn a wheel—and it doesn’t hurt that they look extremely cool, too. But yet again, endurance racing wants to offer more than just entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large number of automotive technologies or safety features that we mostly take for granted todaymade their way into road cars from the race track. Seatbelts, rear-view mirrors, turbocharged engines, aerodynamics, direct-injection engines, dual-clutch gearboxes, and more owe their existence to competition. Althoughdirect examples of racing technology transferin the mid-21st century seem less common than the intangible benefits gained when a bunch of motorsports-trained engineers have lunch every day with their road car colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is starting to change, though, and now the domain is in simulation. Vast amounts of data are generated during the course of a race—each of the 11 GTP cars that raced at Daytona collects 1,600 different channels of data from onboard sensors, with nearly as many on the GTD machines that are based on road-going cars like Porsche’s 911 or Chevrolet’s Corvette. With 60 cars running for 24 hours—and that’s just the first race of the year—that’s a heck of a lot of high-quality data being generated, and now IMSA wants to leverage that to help automotive and technology companies develop better simulation tools, with the creation of IMSA Labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sanctioning body has also extendedits activities with NASA, signing a partnership with the space agency to work together on “telemetry, diagnostics and sensor methodologies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Car racing is, at its heart, a sport. And it’s also entertainment. But it also serves as an engineering exercise, with each race series balancing those three elements to different degrees. And the engineering is why companies like Bosch get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have our technology up from the Bosch side that we use in our everyday vehicle engineering,” said Joe Capuano, regional president of Bosch Engineering. “We’re able to bring those components in different ways to the racetrack, where obviously the requirements are different, and it’s really a loop of learning. So we take our base components, we apply ’em in different ways to the needs of the race teams, and then we take the feedback from the races and we can improve our products that we have in our automotive portfolio.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A company like General Motors, which competes in IMSA under both the Cadillac and Chevrolet brands, mostly does it to beat other automakers. But that’s not the only reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It really teaches engineers, teaches us to advance quickly, be able to analyze data, adapt, discard things. And inside General Motors we really connect engineering and motorsports directly,” said Eric Warren, vice president of global motorsports competition at GM. “Motorsports really resides in the engineering groups. So as we develop new simulation methods and things… it directly connects with the groups that are designing our cars. And so not only do we get to compete from that standpoint, that drives this brand against brand, but also helps us train engineers to really relate to those technologies and drive that technology that ends up on the road,” Warren said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Literally what we do is we learn here on the weekend and then Monday morning we’re back in the office and we’re designing based on what we learned over the weekend into the products that we can drive ourselves through the rest of the week,” explained Matthew Cabe, president and CEO of Michelin North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This season, the tire maker has introduced a new tire for IMSA’s GTP class, as well as the near-identical cars in the World Endurance Championship, that contains more than 50 percent recycled and renewable material, while being more durable and no less performant than its older, less sustainable versions of seasons past. And the payoff for road cars is real: the tire maker’s CrossClimate tires make use of the same “slick intermediate” technology that adds grip in the wet that the French company proved at Le Mans a little over a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest frontier in the automotive industry is the rise of the software-defined vehicle. Automakers are redesigning from scratch the electronic systems and architectures that run their cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ll read and see a lot about software defined vehicles… and you think we’ve been doing that in racing forever,” said David Salters, president of Honda Racing Corporation USA. “So typically you have the minimum number of [electronic control unit] boxes on the car, you try and control the system end to end, and your engineers write the software. And the lovely thing about GTP is it is open software architecture. If we can think it, we can write it and do it. So in our case, we have an F1 ECU sat there, and we control all the software platform. We have a group of people—it actually helped us recruit people because it’s super interesting—and we literally develop stuff in days and hours,” Salters said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So we’re sort of walking the walk, it’s underneath. And so just software development, energy management, traction control; the traction control system we have on the car, Honda has a technical forum once a year, and we were asked to present what we’ve done with the traction control. It’s sort of self-aware,” Salters said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As David said, the vehicle is very software driven, but what is unique about particularly this race is, the conditions change, right? You have different drivers and totally different conditions,” said Warren. “You look at other race series: you have a short window, you’re optimizing on the razor’s edge, and you’re like, okay, you hit that. In this form of racing, particularly IMSA, it’s overnight, the track’s cold, you’ve got tire choices, and so you have to broaden your ability to model the vehicle, how to control the vehicle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going racing to make better road cars is a pretty obvious reason to get involved if you’re a car company, but the sport can have benefits to other industries.For example, the Williams F1 team’s engineering arm took its knowledge of aerodynamics and used it to make open-front supermarket freezer cabinets stay colder with less energy. With IMSA Labs, the idea is to take the data from a race full of cars and use it to make better simulations. And like most other industries, it’s hard to escapethe presence of machine learning and AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems natural that an automaker and a tire company and a company like Bosch would want to use this space,” said IMSA President John Doonan. “But now it is our goal that the companies that I just mentioned and others will use this space to develop the next version of software that’s maybe not used in racing, maybe used in a broader audience, or prove out a product that’s already on the market. And as David and Eric mentioned, the data-rich environment that we have allows them to do that in real time in a very extreme—it doesn’t get more extreme than 24 hours across the street—environment like that,” Doonan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just by training imitationary techniques on the human data that’s generated, we can, with just a few hundred laps, drive cars at the top 1 percent of human performance. And to me that speaks volumes about quality of the data,” said Siddhartha Sen, principal research manager at Microsoft Research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You wouldn’t be able to do that if the data wasn’t high quality. Machine learning is all about cleaning noisy data and dealing with, honestly, all kinds of crap that you get right? And here the quality of the data, the sensors that’s collected, the attention that’s paid to that data is amazing… So honestly, as an AI researcher, as someone running an AI program, it is kind of a dream, you’re almost like at a candy store when you see this kind of quality of data and the diverse ways in which people drive,” Sen said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In general, I found that the gap between simulation and reality can be made quite low with racing, and the only demand I’ve seen, that kind of low gap, [is] maybe the flight simulators… it’s just uncanny how people who, in online racing sims, perform, and that can kind of translate to what they see on the actual track. And I think that kind of low gap is a reason why we’re able to create models that can actually be useful in real life. And this is why I’m very excited about the platform in general, not just because of the data we’re going to collect, [but] the fact that it’s human data, and it’s diverse human data, which, by the way, is all the craze these days. Everything we’re doing with LLMs, we’re just trying to imitate how humans do things,” Sen said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/why-nasa-imsa-and-tech-companies-are-teaming-up-on-tech-transfer/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:17:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade wars muzzle allied talks on Trump’s Golden Dome missile shield</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/trade-wars-muzzle-allied-talks-on-trumps-golden-dome-missile-shield/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2216141394-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“International partners, I have not been allowed to talk to yet because of the trade wars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen. Michael Guetlein, the senior officer in charge of the US military’s planned Golden Dome missile defense shield, has laid out an audacious schedule for deploying a network of space-based sensors and interceptors by the end of President Donald Trump’s term in the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three-year timeline is aggressive, with little margin for error in the event of budget or technological setbacks. The shield is designed to defend the US homeland against a range of long-range weapons, including intercontinental ballistic missiles (ICBMs), cruise missiles, and newer threats like hypersonic weapons and drones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By the summer of ’28, we will be able to defend the entire nation against ballistic missiles, as well as other generation aerial threats, and we will continue to grow that architecture through 2035,” Guetlein said Friday in a presentation to representatives from the US defense industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supporters of Golden Dome say it is necessary to defend the United States against emerging threats from potential adversaries like Russia and China, each of which has a vast arsenal of ballistic missiles and more maneuverable hypersonic missiles that are difficult to detect and even harder to track and shoot down. Critics cite Golden Dome’s high cost and itspotential to disrupt the global order, an eventuality they say would make the US homeland more prone to attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guetlein’s team is moving fast in many areas. The Pentagon has inked deals with companies to develop prototypes for space-based missile interceptors, and Golden Dome is underpinned by billions of dollars of preexisting investment in sensor technology, reusable launchers, and mass-produced satellites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These investments give Golden Dome a head start that former President Ronald Reagan’s similarly scopedStrategic Defense Initiativelacked in the 1980s. The initiative, nicknamed “Star Wars,” was drastically downsized as the Cold War wound down and the government struggled with ballooning costs and technical roadblocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But progress in at least one important area has stalled on the Golden Dome program. The Pentagon will need cooperation, if not tangible contributions, from allies to create the best possible version of the missile defense shield. Fundamentally, it comes down to geography. Places like the Canadian Arctic and Greenland are well-positioned to detect incoming missiles coming over the horizon from Russia or China. They might also be useful for hosting next-gen ground-based interceptors, which today are based in Alaska and California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guetlein said his interactions with allies have been limited. It’s the consequence of another of the Trump administration’s core policies: tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“International partners, I have not been allowed to talk to yet because of the trade wars,” Guetlein said. “The administration wants to get all that laying flat before I start having conversations with our allied partners. But everything we are doing is allied by design.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without detailed discussions with allies, the Pentagon’s Golden Dome appears to be one-sided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are already planning on how to integrate our allied partners into our architecture,” Guetlein said. [We’re] already understanding what they can bring to the fight, whether that be capability, whether that be through FMS (foreign military sales), or whether that be territory that we need to access to put sensors, or what have you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada and Denmark, which count Greenland as an autonomous territory, are longtime allies of the United States. Both nations are members of NATO, and Canada is part of the North American Aerospace Defense Command (NORAD), an organization whose mission is already aligned with that of the Golden Dome. However, the Trump administration has targeted both nations for high tariffs, apparently in a bid to achieve the White House’s trade and security objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s obsession with acquiring Greenland, where the Space Force already has amilitary base, soured US relations with Denmark over the last year. The White House threatened additional tariffs on Denmark and other European countries until Denmark agreed to sell Greenland to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after strong European pushback, Trump suddenly reversed course last week at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. He withdrew threats to take Greenland by force and announced an unspecified “framework” with NATO for a future deal regarding the island.Trump told CNBCthe framework involved partnerships on missile defense and mining: “They’re going to be involved in the Golden Dome, and they’re going to be involved in mineral rights, and so are we.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Danish Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen responded to Trump signaling an openness to a “constructive dialogue” on Arctic security, including the Golden Dome, “provided that this is done with respect for our territorial integrity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House’s backpedaling may have lowered the temperature of US relations with Denmark, at least for now. But Canada is still in Trump’s crosshairs. In a social media post on Friday, Trump claimed Canada was “against” plans to include Greenland in the Golden Dome program. Kirsten Hillman, Canada’s ambassador to the United States,told CBS Newsshe didn’t know what Trump was talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The back-and-forth followed Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney’srebuke of Trump’s foreign policyduring a speech at Davos last week. In another sign of the withering US-Canada partnership, Trump threatened in a social media post Saturday toimpose a 100 percent tariffon Canada if it follows through on a trade deal with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canadian officials last year disclosed they were in talks to participate in the Golden Dome. In aninterview with The War Zonepublished earlier this month, the operational commander of NORAD’s Canadian region advocated for “integrated missile defense” and “ground-based effectors” but said Canada’s role in a space-based layer would be a “political decision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We look at it as Continental Shield,” said Royal Canadian Air Force Maj. Gen. Chris McKenna. “Golden Dome is the US brand on it. From our point of view, it’s great air missile defense and what we will put on the table to defend the continent with. And so I think there are ongoing negotiations between our governments with respect to what the specific investments will be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guetlein’s comments on Golden Dome last week were part of an “industry day” hosted by Space Systems Command, the Los Angeles-based unit charged with procurement for most of the Space Force’s major programs. Asked what his top priority is this year, Guetlein said his emphasis is on the shield’s command and control system, the “glue layer” that ties together everything else necessary to make Golden Dome work. His deadline to demonstrate the command-and-control system is this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kinetic, or hit-to-kill, elements of the missile shield will come next. “In the summer of ’27, I have to integrate the interceptors, and in ’28 I have to demonstrate operational capability that is fielded against credible threats,” Guetlein said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would bring some version of Golden Dome into service before President Trump leaves the White House, a timetable used for several other programs, including NASA’s Artemis mission toland astronauts on the Moon. Officials are willing to trade perfection for speed. Guetlein’s intention is to “rapidly get an 85 percent product in the field.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a comprehensive missile defense shield, if economically and technically feasible, would take many more years to complete. Some pieces of what could become Golden Dome already exist, such as ground-based midcourse interceptors and an array of missile detection sensors on land, at sea, and in space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other elements were well along in development before Trump’s second term in the White House. These include a constellation of low-Earth-orbit satellites to better track hypersonic missiles and relay data to help US and allied forces shoot them down. This network, led by the Space Development Agency, began launching in 2023 but is not yet operational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon has already kicked off the preliminary steps to buy space-based interceptors. The shield will need hundreds or thousands of orbiting platforms on alert to shoot down a ballistic missile in flight. The Defense Department also aims to field modernized ground-based interceptors and Golden Dome’s command and control network, the system Guetlein identified as his top priority for this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satellites are getting cheaper and easier to build. SpaceX has manufactured and launchedapproximately 11,000 Starlink satellitesin less than seven years. No other company comes close to this number, but there arebusinesses looking at building standardized satellitesthat could be integrated with a range of payloads, including Earth-viewing cameras, radars, communication antennas, or perhaps, a missile interceptor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the interceptors themselves are brand new. Nothing like them has ever been put into space and tested before. Last year, the Space Force asked companies to submit their ideas for space-based interceptor (SBI) prototypes. The military awarded 18 companies small prototype development deals in November. The Space Force did not identify the winners, and the value of each contract fell below the $9 million public disclosure threshold for Pentagon programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These 18 awards are focused on boost-phase SBIs, weapons that can take out a missile soon after it leaves its silo. From a physics perspective, this is one of the most difficult things to ask an interceptor to do, because the weapon must account for atmospheric disturbances and reentry heating to reach its target. In December, the Space Force issued a follow-up request for prototype proposals looking at space-based midcourse interceptors capable of destroying a ballistic missile while it is coasting through space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon has not said how many SBIs it will need for Golden Dome, or what they will look like. Essentially, an orbiting interceptor will be a flying fuel tank with a rocket and a sensor package to home in on its target. But the Space Force and its prospective Golden Dome contractors, which include industry giantsNorthrop Grumman and Lockheed Martin, have not disclosed the interceptors’ design specs or how many the shield will need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guetlein said Pentagon leaders have empowered him with “unprecedented authorities” on the Golden Dome program. He said Friday his office has full authority over the program’s technical aspects, along with Golden Dome’s procurement, contracting, hiring, security, and budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump directed the military to start the Golden Dome program in an executive order last January and nominated Guetlein to head the effort. The Senate confirmed him for the job in a voice vote last July. After the initial pomp of Golden Dome’s announcement, including multiple Oval Office photo ops, military officials went quiet. Guetlein cited security concerns for the Pentagon’s silence on one of Trump’s marquee defense programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was confirmed on the 18th of July. On the 19th of July, I popped No. 1 on the intel collect list for our adversaries,” Guetlein said. “On the 20th of July, they started hacking our defense industrial base, and the Secretary (of Defense) asked us to go silent. So, we have been quiet. I have not been talking to industry consortiums. I have not been talking to the press. I have not been talking to the think tanks. And it wasn’t until September that I was allowed to even start talking to the Hill (Congress).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this absence of dialogue, lawmakers approved $23 billion in a down payment for Golden Dome last summer. The final cost of the system is anyone’s guess, but the deployment and sustainment of Golden Dome will certainlycost hundreds of billions of dollarsover multiple decades. Just getting the missile shield through a partial activation will cost $175 billion over three years, according to the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guetlein is off and running with the one-time infusion of $23 billion Congress gave him last year. “The budget authority… for the first $23 billion, it has no strings, no color, no year,” he said. “I can move that money around at will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He’s about to receive another $13.4 billion in this year’s defense budget, pending the appropriation bill’s final passage in the Senate and President Trump’s signature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve got the Space Force buying SBIs. I’ve got the Army buying munitions and sensors. I’ve got the Navy buying munitions. I’ve got the Missile Defense Agency buying next-generation interceptors, glide phase interceptors, and a whole host of other capabilities,” Guetlein said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their willingness to fund Golden Dome, lawmakers still aren’t satisfied with the information they are getting from the Pentagon. In a document adjoining this year’s defense budget bill, members of the House and Senate defense appropriations subcommittees wrote they were “unable to effectively assess resources available” and unable to “conduct oversight” of the Golden Dome program “due to insufficient budgetary information” provided by the Department of Defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawmakers wrote that they “support the operational objectives of Golden Dome” and directed the Pentagon to “provide a comprehensive spend plan” for the missile shield within 60 days of the budget bill becoming law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Unfortunately because of the intel threat, we can only brief you at the classified level on what the architecture is,” Guetlein said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/trade-wars-muzzle-allied-talks-on-trumps-golden-dome-missile-shield/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:42:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple patches ancient iOS versions to keep iMessage, FaceTime, other services working</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-patches-ancient-ios-versions-to-keep-imessage-facetime-other-services-working/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_0205-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple renews certificates for old iOS versions to keep the lights on longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Apple stops supporting older iPhones and iPads with the latest version of iOS or iPadOS, it usually isn’t the end of the line—Apple keeps releasing new security-only patches for those devices for another year or two, keeping them usable while their hardware is still reasonably capable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once those updates dry up, it’s rare for Apple to revisit those older operating systems, but the company does sometimes make exceptions. That was the case yesterday, when the company released a batch of updates for long-retired iOS and iPadOS versions that otherwise hadn’t seen a new patch in months or years. Those updates include iOS 12.5.8, available for devices as old as 2013’s iPhone 5S and 2014’s iPhone 6; iOS 15.8.6, available for devices like the iPhone 6S, iPhone 7, and iPad Air 2; and iOS 16.7.13, available for devices like the iPhone 8 and iPhone X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both iOS 15 and iOS 16 were last patched in mid-2025, but iOS 12’s last patch was released in January 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These updates don’t patch security flaws or add new features. According to Apple’s release notes for theiOS 12andiOS 15 updates, all they do is update a security certificate to ensure that iMessage, FaceTime, and Apple account sign-in will continue working past January 2027, when the operating systems’ original certificate would have expired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’s iOS 18.7.4 update also changes out the certificate, though that update is less surprising, since iOS 18 is still being actively patched for the iPhone XS, iPhone XR, and other devices that can’t run iOS 26. Oddly, the iOS 16 update doesn’t mention the security certificate, and there’s no equivalent update for devices stuck on iOS 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devices running old iOS versions like iOS 12, 15, and 16 are difficult, if not impossible, to use as general-purpose smartphones and tablets these days. Many of these devices have just 1 or 2GB of RAM, and their built-in Safari versions will be missing features and security patches needed to browse the modern Internet safely. Third-party apps also mostly stop supporting old iOS versions after a year or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But plenty of old iPhones and iPads find second or third lives as single-use appliances and simple messaging devices—up until just a couple of years ago, my own iPhone 5S served as a kid’s white noise machine on overnight trips. I wouldn’t call these 12- and 13-year-old phones and tablets “actively supported,” but it’s nice to see Apple commit to keeping them minimally functional over such an extended period.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-patches-ancient-ios-versions-to-keep-imessage-facetime-other-services-working/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:49:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Volvo invented the three-point seat belt 67 years ago; now it has improved it</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/how-volvos-new-adaptive-seat-belts-will-reduce-injuries-during-a-crash/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/436-F-Seat-With-B-Pillar-Final-short-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EX60 senses a passenger’s size and weight, determining how much force to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the launch of itsall-new, all-electric EX60, Volvo has put lessons learned from theEX30andEX90to use. The EX60 is built on Volvo’s new SPA3 platform, made only for battery-electric vehicles. It boasts up to 400 miles (643 km) of range, with fast-charging capabilities Volvo says add 173 miles (278 km) in 10 minutes. Mega casting reduces the number of parts of the rear floor from 100-plus to one piece crafted of aluminum alloy, reducing complexities and weld points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the cabin, however, the real achievement is Volvo’s new multi-adaptive safety belt. Volvo has a history with the modern three-point safety belt, which was perfected by in-house engineer Nils Bohlin in 1959 before the patent was shared with the world. Today at the Volvo Cars Safety Center lab, at least one brand-new Volvois crashedevery day in the name of science. The goal: to test not just how well its vehicles are protecting passengers but what the next frontier is in safety technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior Safety Technical Leader Mikael Ljung Aust is a driving behavior specialist with 20 years under his belt at Volvo. He says it’s easy to optimize testing toward one person or one test point and come up with a good result. However, both from the behavioral perspective and from physics, people are different. What’s not different, he points out, is how people drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re shaped into a very similar automated behavior when we drive, so that makes the collision prevention side of things a bit easier,” Ljung Aust says. “But on the injury-prevention side of things is where the seat belt comes in, we’re working on the principle of equal safety for all. The idea is that independent of who you are in terms of size, shape, weight, all of these things, you should have exactly the same protection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, a seat belt is made up of a retractor mechanism, buckle assembly, webbing material, and a pretensioner device. Of these parts, the pretensioner is the one tasked with tightening the seatbelt webbing in a collision. As such, it reduces the forward movement of the passenger before the airbag deploys at speeds of up to 200 mph (321 km/h). All of these parts remain the same for Volvo’s newest seat belt iteration. It’s the tiny brain attached to the assemblage that’s different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volvo’snew central computing system, HuginCore(named after a bird in Norse mythology), runs the EX60 with more than 250 trillion operations per second. It has been developed in-house, together with its partners Google, Nvidia, and Qualcomm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With the HuginCore system we can collect a lot of data and make decisions in the car instantly and combine that with the belt’s ability to choose different load levels,” says Åsa Haglund, head of the Volvo Cars Safety Center. “A box of possibilities opens up where you can detect what type of crash it is and who is in the car and choose a more optimal belt force.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Load limiters control how much force the safety belt applies on the human body during a crash. Volvo’s new system pushes the load-limiting profiles from three to 11, marking a major increase in adjustability. It’s kind of like an audio system, Ljung Aust muses. A sound system with 10 discrete steps up the volume ladder offers varied profiles along the way, while one with only one or two steps addresses fewer preference levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using data from exterior, interior, and crash sensors, the car reacts to a collision in milliseconds—less than the blink of an eye, Ljung Aust says. In the case of a crash, it’s critical to hold the hips into the car, he explains, but the upper body should fold forward in a frontal crash in a nice, smooth motion to meet the airbag. Otherwise, the body is exposed to the same force as the slowing car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tempering that motion means adjusting for the size of the passenger to avoid injury; for instance, if the sensors detect a larger occupant in a severe crash, it’s designed to reduce the risk of head injury by using a higher belt load setting. Conversely, a smaller passenger in a lesser fender bender gets a lower belt load setting to reduce the incidence of rib fractures. Haglund notes that while one might make assumptions about what body type is more vulnerable in a crash, it has more to do with the kind of crash itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no one-size-fits-all approach to crash safety, but the multi-adaptive seat belt is a closer step toward individual protection. Ljung Aust likens the new seat belt system to an octopus; the “tentacles” are the sensors that feed information to the brain. From there, the processor collects the data that Volvo uses to make improvements over time. Over-the-air updates will send future improvements to the car’s HuginCore system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timing is where artificial intelligence plays a big part. For every crash, there is an optimal set of outcomes to trigger the belt force. The result needs to happen like that, he says with a snap of his fingers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern safety belts use load limiters to control how much force the safety belt applies on the human body during a crash. But with the new safety belt’s expanded load-limiting profiles, it can optimize performance for each situation and individual. “What is changing is the level of sophistication in how we act on that information,” Ljung Aust says. “We can now be more nuanced with the forces we apply to keep you under the lowest pressure possible [in a crash].”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not enough people know how a seat belt works, says Ljung Aust, and they should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you find out how it works, you realize it’s pretty cool and it actually makes a difference,” he says. “And to the extent that you were not inclined to wear it before or not be happy about it, maybe that has a positive influence on your attitude. Having a seat belt is literally the best thing you can do.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/how-volvos-new-adaptive-seat-belts-will-reduce-injuries-during-a-crash/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:16:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>AI Overviews gets upgraded to Gemini 3 with a dash of AI Mode</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/ai-overviews-gets-upgraded-to-gemini-3-with-a-dash-of-ai-mode/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Gemini-3-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Overviews may get it right more often with the move to Gemini 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be hard sometimes to keep up with the deluge of generative AI in Google products. Even if you try to avoid it all, there are some features that still manage to get in your face. Case in point: AI Overviews. This AI-powered search experience has a reputation for getting things wrong, but you may notice some improvements soon. Google says AI Overviews is being upgraded to the latestGemini 3 modelswith a more conversational bent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In just the last year, Google has radically expanded the number of searches on which you get an AI Overview at the top. Today, the chatbot will almost always have an answer for your query, which has relied mostly on models in Google’s Gemini 2.5 family. There was nothing wrong with Gemini 2.5 as generative AI models go, but Gemini 3 is a little better by every metric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, multiple flavors of Gemini 3, and Google doesn’t like to be specific about which ones appear in your searches. What Google does say is that AI Overviews chooses the right model for the job. So if you’re searching for something simple for which there are a lot of valid sources, AI Overviews may manifest something like Gemini 3 Flash without running through a ton of reasoning tokens. For a complex “long tail” query, it could step up the thinking or move to Gemini 3 Pro (for paying subscribers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake—Gemini 3 can still make mistakes like any other gen AI system. That said, it doesget things right more oftenthan the previous model. The lightweight Gemini 3 Flash model more than doubled its score in knowledge-based benchmarks compared to the 2.5 branch. Since you really can’t get away from AI Overviews (without leaving Google), it’s at least nice Google is deploying models that get things right more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of this update, Google is also pushing AI Mode even harder by creating a bridge between it and AI Overviews. Google says that testers prefer an experience that can move naturally from a search paradigm to a conversational one. Thus, AI Overviews will gain the ability to hand off follow-up questions to AI Mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Google, this “fluid” experience is better at giving people what they want when they type something into the search bar—a quick factoid or a deep conversation. However, the expansion of AI Mode into the traditional search experience will also continue to pull people away from Google’sincreasingly forsaken list of blue links. AI Mode may be scraping its content from those sites, but it keeps users bottled up in the Google bubble. That’s search in the AI era.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/ai-overviews-gets-upgraded-to-gemini-3-with-a-dash-of-ai-mode/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:00:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian plumber is a YouTube sensation</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/australian-plumber-is-a-youtube-sensation/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/draincleaning1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce of Drain Cleaning Australia wants everyone to share his deep abiding love for a free-flowing drain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large swathes of the US were blanketed in snow and ice over the weekend, and what better way to spend a snow day than going down a YouTube rabbit hole? Everyone has their favorite oddity:ASMR,jazzy pop song covers,cooking channels, or what have you. ButDIY enthusiastsin particular are missing out if they’re not watchingDrain Cleaning Australia, featuring an Australian plumber known only as Bruce as he goes about his daily business of shooting high-powered water jets into stubborn clogged drainage systems. It’s “the YouTube channel you never knew you needed.” And it’s done so well that he’s now launched a second channel,Bruce the Plumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon the Drain Cleaning Australia channel viaAmy Poehler‘sGood Hangpodcast episodewith Kate McKinnon, who is a big fan and does a dead-on delivery of Bruce’s trademark lines (“You little rippah!”). Bruce never appears in his videos, apart from his hands and the occasional shadow as he films various challenging jobs with his intrepid smartphone. He seems to have struck a good balance between online popularity and protecting his personal privacy. (Bruce did not respond to our interview request. It’s okay, mate, we know all those drains Down Under aren’t going to unclog themselves.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armed with his trusty collection of jet nozzles and “Mister Plungey,” Bruce has removed all manner of nasty things from drains over the years: masses ofhuman hairfrom shower drains;tree roots; plastic bags andother refusethat somehow found their way intodrainage systems; and the less said about the manyclogged toilets, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mypersonal favoritesare when Bruce takes on clogged restaurantgrease traps, including the one at the top of this article in which he pulls out a massive greaseberg “the size of a chihuahua.” When it’s Bruce versus a nasty grease trap, the man remains undefeated (well,almost—sometimes he needs to get a grease trap pumped out before he can fix the problem). And I have learned more than I probably ever needed to know about how grease traps work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each video is its own little adventure. Bruce arrives on a job, checks out the problem (“she is chock-a-block, mate!”), and starts methodically working that problem until he solves it, which inevitably involves firing up “the bloody jet” to blast through blockages with 5,000 psi of water pressure (“Go, you good thing!”). This being Australia, he’ll occasionally encounter not just cockroaches but poisonous spiders and snakes. And he’s caught so many facefulls of wastewater and sewage while jetting that he really ought to invest in a hazmat suit. Even the cheesy canned techno-music playing during lulls in the action is low-budget perfection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bruce isn’t the only plumber with a YouTube channel—it’s a surprisingly good-size subgenre—but he’s the most colorful and entertaining. His unbridled enthusiasm for what many would consider the dirtiest of jobs is positively infectious. He regularly effuses about having the best job in the world, insisting that unclogging gross drains is “living the dream,” and regularly asks his audience, “How good is this? I mean, where else would you rather be?” Sure, he says it with an ironic (unseen) wink at the camera, but deep down, you know he truly loves the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know what? Bruce is right. It might not beyourdefinition of “what dreams are made of,” but there really is something profoundly satisfying about a free-flowing drain—and a job well done.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/australian-plumber-is-a-youtube-sensation/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:37:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“IG is a drug”: Internal messages may doom Meta at social media addiction trial</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-settles-hours-before-landmark-social-media-addiction-trial-starts/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1967879006-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A loss could cost social media companies billions and force changes on platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anxiety, depression, eating disorders, and death. These can be the consequences for vulnerable kids who get addicted to social media, according to more than 1,000 personal injury lawsuits that seek to punish Meta and other platforms for allegedly prioritizing profits while downplaying child safety risks for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media companies have faced scrutiny before, with Congressional hearingsforcing CEOs to apologize, but until now, they’ve never had to convince a jury that they aren’t liable for harming kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, the first high-profile lawsuit—considered a “bellwether” case that could set meaningful precedent in the hundreds of other complaints—goes to trial. That lawsuit documents the case of a 19-year-old, K.G.M, who hopes the jury will agree that Meta and YouTube caused psychological harm by designing features like infinite scroll and autoplay to push her down a path that she alleged triggered depression, anxiety, self-harm, and suicidality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok and Snapchat were also targeted by the lawsuit, but both have settled. The Snapchat settlement came last week, while TikTok settled on Tuesday just hours before the trial started, Bloombergreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, YouTube and Meta remain in the fight. K.G.M. allegedly started watching YouTube when she was 6 years old and joined Instagram by age 11. She’s fighting to claim untold damages—including potentially punitive damages—to help her family recoup losses from her pain and suffering and to punish social media companies and deter them from promoting harmful features to kids. She also wants the court to require prominent safety warnings on platforms to help parents be aware of the risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A loss could cost social media companies billions, CNNreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid that, platforms have alleged that other factors caused K.G.M.’s psychological harm—like school bullies and family troubles—while insisting that Section 230 and the First Amendment protect platforms from being blamed for any harmful content targeted to K.G.M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also argued that K.G.M.’s mom never read the terms of service and, therefore, supposedly would not have benefited from posted warnings. And ByteDance, before settling, seemingly tried to pass the buck by claiming that K.G.M. “already suffered mental health harms before she began using TikTok.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the judge, Carolyn B. Kuhl, wrote in arulingdenying all platforms’ motions for summary judgment that K.G.M. showed enough evidence that her claims don’t stem from content to go to trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, platforms can’t liken warnings buried in terms of service to prominently displayed warnings, Kuhl said, since K.G.M.’s mom testified she would’ve restricted the minor’s app usage if she were aware of the alleged risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two platforms settling before the trial seems like a good sign for K.G.M. However, Snapchat has not settled other social media addiction lawsuits that it’s involved in, including one raised by school districts, and perhaps is waiting to see how K.G.M.’s case shakes out before taking further action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To win, K.G.M.’s lawyers will need to “parcel out” how much harm is attributed to each platform, due to design features, not the content that was targeted to K.G.M., Clay Calvert, a technology policy expert and senior fellow at a think tank called the American Enterprise Institute,wrote. Internet law expert Eric Goldmantold The Washington Postthat detailing those harms will likely be K.G.M.’s biggest struggle, since social media addiction has yet to be legally recognized, and tracing who caused what harms may not be straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Matthew Bergman, founder of the Social Media Victims Law Center and one of K.G.M.’s lawyers, told the Post that K.G.M. is prepared to put up this fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She is going to be able to explain in a very real sense what social media did to her over the course of her life and how in so many ways it robbed her of her childhood and her adolescence,” Bergman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research is unclear on whether social media is harmful for kids or whether social media addiction exists, Tamar Mendelson, a professor at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, told the Post. And so far, research only shows a correlation between Internet use and mental health, Mendelson noted, which could doom K.G.M.’s case and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, social media companies’ internal research might concern a jury, Bergman told the Post. On Monday, the Tech Oversight Project, a nonprofit working to rein in Big Tech, published areportanalyzing recently unsealed documents in K.G.M.’s case that supposedly provide “smoking-gun evidence” that platforms “purposefully designed their social media products to addict children and teens with no regard for known harms to their wellbeing"—while putting increased engagement from young users at the center of their business models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the report, Sacha Haworth, executive director of The Tech Oversight Project, accused social media companies of “gaslighting and lying to the public for years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the recently unsealed documents highlighted in the report came from Meta, which also faces a trial from dozens of state attorneys general on social media addiction this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those documents included an email stating that Mark Zuckerberg—who is expected to testify at K.G.M.’s trial—decided that Meta’s top priority in 2017 was teens who must be locked in to using the company’s family of apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next year, a Facebook internal document showed that the company pondered letting “tweens” access a private mode inspired by the popularity of fake Instagram accounts teens known as “finstas.” That document included an “internal discussion on how to counter the narrative that Facebook is bad for youth and admission that internal data shows that Facebook use is correlated with lower well-being (although it says the effect reverses longitudinally).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other allegedly damning documents showed Meta seemingly bragging that “teens can’t switch off from Instagram even if they want to” and an employee declaring, “oh my gosh yall IG is a drug,” likening all social media platforms to “pushers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a 2020 Google document detailed the company’s plan to keep kids engaged “for life,” despite internal research showing young YouTube users were more likely to “disproportionately” suffer from “habitual heavy use, late night use, and unintentional use” deteriorating their “digital well-being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shorts, YouTube’s feature that rivals TikTok, also concerns parents suing, and three years later, documents showed Google choosing to target teens with Shorts, despite research flagging that the “two biggest challenges for teen wellbeing on YouTube” were prominently linked to watching shorts. Those challenges included Shorts bombarding teens with “low quality content recommendations that can convey &amp; normalize unhealthy beliefs or behaviors” and teens reporting that “prolonged unintentional use” was “displacing valuable activities like time with friends or sleep.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bergman told the Post that these documents will help the jury decide if companies owed young users better protections sooner but prioritized profits while pushing off interventions that platforms have more recently introduced amid mounting backlash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Internal documents that have been held establishing the willful misconduct of these companies are going to—for the first time—be given a public airing,” Bergman said. “The public is going to know for the first time what social media companies have done to prioritize their profits over the safety of our kids.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One seeming advantage K.G.M. has heading into the trial is that tech companies failed to get expert testimony that backs up her claims dismissed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Platforms tried to exclude testimony from several experts, including Kara Bagot, a board-certified adult, child, and adolescent psychiatrist, as well as Arturo Bejar, a former Meta safety researcher andwhistleblower. Theyclaimedthat experts’ opinions were irrelevant because they were based on K.G.M.’s interactions with content. They also suggested that child safety experts’ opinions “violate the standards of reliability” since the causal links they draw don’t account for “alternative explanations” and allegedly “contradict the experts’ own statements in non-litigation contexts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Kuhl ruled that platforms will have the opportunity to counter experts’ opinions at trial, whileremindingsocial media companies that “ultimately, the critical question of causation is one that must be determined by the jury.” Only one expert’s testimony was excluded, Social Media Victims Law Centernoted, a licensed clinical psychologist deemed unqualified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Testimony by Bagot as to design features that were employed on TikTok as well as on other social media platforms is directly relevant to the question of whether those design features cause the type of harms allegedly suffered by K.G.M. here,” Kuhl wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means that a jury will get a chance to weigh Bagot’s opinion that “social media overuse and addiction causes or plays a substantial role in causing or exacerbating psychopathological harms in children and youth, including depression, anxiety and eating disorders, as well as internalizing and externalizing psychopathological symptoms.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jury will also consider Bejar’s insights as a fact witness sharing information about Meta’s internal safety studies as a former consultant and researcher for the company. That includes hearing about “hispersonalknowledgeandexperiencerelatedtohowdesign defectsonMeta’splatformscancauseharmtominors(e.g.,ageverification,reportingprocesses,beautyfilters,publiclikecounts,infinitescroll,defaultsettings,privatemessages,reels,ephemeralcontent,andconnectingchildrenwithadultstrangers),” as well as “harmsassociatedwithMeta’splatformsincludingaddiction/problematicuse,anxiety,depression,eatingdisorders,bodydysmorphia,suicidality,self-harm,andsexualization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If K.G.M. can convince the jury that she was not harmed by platforms failing to remove content but by companies “designing their platforms to addict kids” and “developing algorithms that show kids not what they want to see but what they cannot look away from,” Bergman thinks her case could become a “data point” for “settling similar cases en masse,” hetold Barrons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She is very typical of so many children in the United States—the harms that they’ve sustained and the way their lives have been altered by the deliberate design decisions of the social media companies,” Bergman told the Post.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-settles-hours-before-landmark-social-media-addiction-trial-starts/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:07:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>LG’s new subscription program charges up to £277 per month to rent a TV</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/lgs-new-subscription-program-charges-up-to-277-per-month-to-rent-a-tv/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/TV_OLED83B5PUA_brilliant-lg-oled-picture_features_900x600.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significant discounts come with committing to 1- to 3-year rental periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG has launched a subscriptionprogram in the UKthat allows people to make monthly payments in order to rent LG TVs, soundbars, monitors, and speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG Flex customers can sign up for one, two, or three-year subscriptions in order to get lower monthly payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At the end of your subscription, you can apply for a free upgrade, keep paying monthly, or return your device,” the LG Flex website says. Subscribers will have to pay a £50 (about $69) fee for a “full removal service,” including dismounting and packaging, of rental TVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG also claims on its website that it won’t penalize customers for “obvious signs of use, such as some scratching, small dents, or changes in the paintwork.” However, if you damage the rental device, LG “may charge you for the cost of repair as outlined by the Repair Charges set out in your agreement.” LG’s subscription partner, Raylo, also sells insurance for coverage against “accidental damage, loss, and theft” of rented devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, you can buy LG’s 83-inch OLED B5 2025 TV on LG’s UK website for £2,550 (about $3,515). Monthly rental prices range from £93 ($128), if you commit to a three-year-long rental period, to £277 ($382), if you only commit to a one-month rental period. Under the three-year plan, you can rent the TV for 27 months before you end up paying more to rent the TV than you would have to own it. At the highest rate, your rental payments will surpass MSRP after nine months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cheapest item available through LG Flex as of this writing is LG’s 3.1.1 channel soundbar with Dolby Atmos from 2024. You can buy it from LG’s UK website for £600 ($827) or rent it for £22 ($30) to £76 ($105) per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG Flex can grant people instant access to electronics they may not be able to pay for currently. There are other options, like interest-free payment programs (which LG also offers), but those programs can require larger monthly payments than rentals do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, renting gadgets from LG won’t make financial sense for many. The program can be handy for people, businesses, and other entities that require high-end gadgets for a limited amount of time or that want frequent upgrades. But renting electronics quickly becomes more costly than buying something. It’s often more prudent to save money that would have been used for monthly payments and instead invest it in something that you can own and maintain for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG’s rental gadgets are only available in the UK. Ars Technica reached out to LG about whether it has plans to rent electronics in the US and will update this article if we hear back. As it stands, the program adds to a slowly growing number of tech companies encouraging people to rent, instead of buy, their products. HP, for instance, has aprinter rental program, and NZXT launched agaming desktop rental programin 2024. Logitech CEO Hanneke Faber has also floated the idea of asubscription-based mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LG Flex is just one example of how the Seoul-headquartered company is finding creative ways to build recurring revenue instead of relying solely on sales of its expensive gadgets, as such purchases occur sparingly and less predictably. Last year, LG launched a similar rental program for home appliances in Singapore and Malaysia.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/lgs-new-subscription-program-charges-up-to-277-per-month-to-rent-a-tv/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:37:32 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>