<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 11:42:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Mandiant releases rainbow table that cracks weak admin password in 12 hours</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/mandiant-releases-rainbow-table-that-cracks-weak-admin-password-in-12-hours/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/password-login-1000x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows laggards still using the vulnerable hashing function: Your days are numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security firm Mandiant has released a database that allows any administrative password protected by Microsoft’s NTLM.v1 hash algorithm to be hacked in an attempt to nudge users who continue using the deprecated function despite known weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database comes in the form of arainbow table, which is a precomputed table of hash values linked to their corresponding plaintext. These generic tables, which work against multiple hashing schemes, allow hackers to take over accounts by quickly mapping a stolen hash to its password counterpart. NTLMv1 rainbow tables are particularly easy to construct because of NTLMv1’s limited keyspace, meaning the relatively small number of possible passwords the hashing function allows for. NTLMv1 rainbow tables have existed for two decades but typically require large amounts of resources to make any use of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mandiantsaidit hadreleasedan NTLMv1 rainbow table that will allow defenders and researchers (and, of course, malicious hackers, too) to recover passwords in under 12 hours using consumer hardware costing less than $600 USD. The table is hosted in Google Cloud. The database works against Net-NTLMv1 passwords, which are used in network authentication for accessing resources such as SMB network sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its long- and well-known susceptibility to easy cracking, NTLMv1 remains in use in some of the world’s more sensitive networks. One reason for the lack of action is that utilities and organizations in industries, including health care and industrial control, often rely on legacy apps that are incompatible with more recently released hashing algorithms. Another reason is that organizations relying on mission-critical systems can’t afford the downtime required to migrate. Of course, inertia and penny-pinching are also causes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By releasing these tables, Mandiant aims to lower the barrier for security professionals to demonstrate the insecurity of Net-NTLMv1,” Mandiant said. “While tools to exploit this protocol have existed for years, they often required uploading sensitive data to third-party services or expensive hardware to brute-force keys.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft released NTLMv1 in the1980swith the release of OS/2. In 1999, cryptanalyst Bruce Schneier and Mudgepublishedresearch that exposed key weaknesses in the NTLMv1 underpinnings. At the 2012 Defcon 20 conference, researchers released atool setthat allowed attackers to move from untrusted network guest to admin in 60 seconds, by attacking the underlying weakness. With the 1998 release ofWindows NT SP4in 1998, Microsoft introduced NTLMv2, which fixed the weakness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations that rely on Windows networking aren’t the only laggards. Microsoft onlyannouncedplans to deprecate NTLMv1 last August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the public awareness that NTLMv1 is weak, “Mandiant consultants continue to identify its use in active environments,” the company said. “This legacy protocol leaves organizations vulnerable to trivial credential theft, yet it remains prevalent due to inertia and a lack of demonstrated immediate risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tables first assist attackers in providing per-byte hash results with theknown plaintextchallenge 1122334455667788. Because Net-NTLM hashes are generated with the user’s password and the challenge, a known plaintext attack, it becomes trivial with these tables to compromise the accont. Typically tools including Responder, PetitPotam, and DFSCoerce are involved in attacks against Net-NTLM. Typically tools includingResponder,PetitPotam, andDFSCoerceare involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In athreadon Mastodon, researchers and admins applauded the move, because they said it would give them added ammunition when trying to convince decision makers to make the investments to move off the insecure function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve had more than one instance in my (admittedly short) infosec career where I’ve had to prove the weakness of a system and it usually involves me dropping a sheet of paper on their desk with their password on it the next morning,” one personsaid. “These rainbow tables aren’t going to mean much for attackers as they’ve likely already got them or have far better methods, but where it will help is in making the argument that NTLMv1 is unsafe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandiant post provides basic steps required to move off of NTLMv1. It links to more detailed instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Organizations should immediately disable the use of Net-NTLMv1,” Mandiant said. Organizations that get hacked because they failed to heed will have only themselves to blame.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/mandiant-releases-rainbow-table-that-cracks-weak-admin-password-in-12-hours/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:05:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI to test ads in ChatGPT as it burns through billions</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/openai-to-test-ads-in-chatgpt-as-it-burns-through-billions/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/openai_glowing_green-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ads coming to free tier and new $8/month ChatGPT Go plan in US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, OpenAIannouncedit will begin testing advertisements inside the ChatGPT app for some US users in a bid to expand its customer base and diversify revenue. The move represents a reversal for CEO Sam Altman, who in 2024describedadvertising in ChatGPT as a “last resort” and expressed concerns that ads could erode user trust, although he did not completely rule out the possibility at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner ads will appear in the coming weeks for logged-in users of the free version of ChatGPT as well as the new $8 per monthChatGPT Goplan, which OpenAI also announced Friday is now available worldwide. OpenAI first launched ChatGPT Go in India in August 2025 and has since rolled it out to over 170 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users paying for the more expensive Plus, Pro, Business, and Enterprise tiers will not see advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to OpenAI’s blog post, the company plans to test ads “at the bottom of answers in ChatGPT when there’s a relevant sponsored product or service.” Ads will be labeled and separated from the answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In example screenshots shared by the company, the ads look like blocked off sections of the chat window with a small image and some advertising copy. Asking ChatGPT for places to visit in Mexico could result in holiday ads appearing, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our enterprise and subscription businesses are already strong,” Fidji Simo, OpenAI’s CEO of applications,wrotein the blog post. “We believe in having a diverse revenue model where ads can play a part in making intelligence more accessible to everyone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s announcement follows the company’s April 2025introduction of shopping featuresto ChatGPT Search. At that time, OpenAI’s Adam Fry told Wired that product recommendations were “not ads” and “not sponsored,” but it felt like a potential step in that direction at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI is not the only AI company exploring advertising revenue. Googlebegan testingAdSense ads in chatbot experiences through partnerships with AI startups in late 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s advertising experiment reflects the enormous financial pressures facing the company. OpenAI does not expect to be profitable until 2030 and hascommittedto spend about $1.4 trillion onmassive data centersand chips for AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to financial documentsobtainedby The Wall Street Journal in November, OpenAI expects to burn through roughly $9 billion this year while generating $13 billion in revenue. Only about 5 percent of ChatGPT’s 800 million weekly userspayfor subscriptions, so it’s not enough to cover all of OpenAI’s operating costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everyone is convinced ads will solve OpenAI’s financial problems. “I am extremely bearish on this ads product,” tech critic Ed Zitronwrote on Bluesky. “Even if this becomes a good business line, OpenAI’s services cost too much for it to matter!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI’s embrace of ads appears to come reluctantly, since it runs counter to a “personal bias” against advertising that Altman has shared in earlier public statements. For example, during a fireside chat at Harvard University in 2024, Altmansaidhe found the combination of ads and AI “uniquely unsettling,” implying that he would not like it if the chatbot itself changed its responses due to advertising pressure. He added: “When I think of like GPT writing me a response, if I had to go figure out exactly how much was who paying here to influence what I’m being shown, I don’t think I would like that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those lines, OpenAI’s approach appears to be a compromise between needing ad revenue and not wanting sponsored content to appear directly within ChatGPT’s written responses. By placing banner ads at the bottom of answers separated from the conversation history, OpenAI appears to be addressing Altman’s concern: The AI assistant’s actual output, the company says, will remain uninfluenced by advertisers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Simowrotein a blog post that OpenAI’s ads will not influence ChatGPT’s conversational responses and that the company will not share conversations with advertisers and will not show ads on sensitive topics such as mental health and politics to users it determines to be under 18.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As we introduce ads, it’s crucial we preserve what makes ChatGPT valuable in the first place,” Simo wrote. “That means you need to trust that ChatGPT’s responses are driven by what’s objectively useful, never by advertising.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/openai-to-test-ads-in-chatgpt-as-it-burns-through-billions/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:20:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>This may be the grossest eye pic ever—but the cause is what’s truly horrifying</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/this-may-be-the-grossest-eye-pic-ever-but-the-cause-is-whats-truly-horrifying/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Screenshot-2026-01-16-at-3.38.03-PM-910x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypervirulent germ nearly destroys man, invading brain and blowing out an eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A generally healthy 63-year-old man in the New England area went to the hospital with a fever, cough, and vision problems in his right eye. His doctors eventually determined that a dreaded hypervirulent bacteria—which is rising globally—was ravaging several of his organs, including his brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the man, the problems started three weeks before his hospital visit, when he said he ate some bad meat and started vomiting and having diarrhea. Those symptoms faded after about two weeks, but then new problems began—he started coughing and having chills and a fever. His cough only worsened from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the hospital, doctors took X-rays and computed tomography (CT) scans of his chest and abdomen. The images revealed over 15 nodules and masses in his lungs. But that’s not all they found. The imaging also revealed a mass in his liver that was 8.6 cm in diameter (about 3.4 inches). Lab work pointed toward an infection, so doctors admitted him to the hospital and provided oxygen to help with his breathing, as well as antibiotics. But his chills and cough continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his third day, he woke up with vision loss in his right eye, which was so swollen he couldn’t open it. Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed another surprise: There were multiple lesions in his brain. (His brain lesions and eye at this point can be seenhere.A later-stage image of his eye is further down in the story.) At that point, he was transferred to Massachusetts General Hospital. Ina case report in this week’s issue of the New England Journal of Medicine, doctors explained how they solved the case and treated the man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to the correct diagnosis was his eye, which kept getting worse. He seemed to have an infection inside his eyeball, affecting the jelly or aqueous parts of the inside (endophthalmitis). The most common cause of this is an eye injury or previous surgery that allows an infection-sparking germ to get in—but he had no such injury or surgery. Also, the condition of his eye was worse than that. He appeared to have panophthalmitis, which is a rare, extremely severe, and rapidly progressing condition in which every part of the eye becomes infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever was laying waste to his eye seemed to have come from inside his own body, carried in his bloodstream—possibly the same thing that could explain the liver mass, lung nodules, and brain lesions. There was one explanation that fit the condition perfectly: hypervirulentKlebsiella pneumoniaeor hvKP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ClassicalK. pneumoniaeis a germ that dwells in people’s intestinal tracts and is one that’s familiar to doctors. It’s known for lurking in health care settings and infecting vulnerable patients, often causing pneumonia or urinary tract infections. But hvKP is very different. In comparison, it’s a beefed-up bacteria with a rage complex. It was first identified in the 1980s in Taiwan—not for stalking weak patients in the hospital but for devastating healthy people in normal community settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An infection with hvKP—even in otherwise healthy people—is marked by metastatic infection. That is, the bacteria spreads throughout the body, usually starting with the liver, where it creates a pus-filled abscess. It then goes on a trip through the bloodstream, invading the lungs, brain, soft tissue, skin, and the eye (endogenous endophthalmitis). Putting it all together, the man had a completely typical clinical case of an hvKP infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, definitively identifying hvKP is tricky. Mucus from the man’s respiratory tract grew a species ofKlebsiella, but there’s not yet a solid diagnostic test to differentiate hvKP from the classical variety. Since 2024, researchers have worked outa strategyof using the presence offive different virulence genes found on plasmids(relatively small, circular pieces of DNA, separate from chromosomal DNA, that can replicate on their own and be shared among bacteria.) But the method isn’t perfect—some classicalK. pneumoniaecan also carry the five genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another much simpler method is the string test, in which clinicians basically test the goopy-ness of the bacteria—hvKP is known for being sticky. For this test, a clinician grows the bacteria into a colony on a petri dish, then touches an inoculation loop to the colony and pulls up. If the string of attached goo stretches more than 5 mm off the petri dish, it’s considered positive for hvKP. This is (obviously) not a precise test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the man’s case, the bacteria from his respiratory tract was positive in the string test. Doctors treated him with antibiotics that testing found could kill off the hvKP strain he had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it was too late for the man’s eye. By his eighth day in the hospital, the swelling had gotten extremely severe (you can see an imagehere, but be warned that it is very disturbing). His eye was now bulging out of his head, and imaging suggested another abscess had formed on the side of the eyeball. He had severe stretching of his optic nerve. Overall, there was no chance of him recovering sight in that eye. Given the worsening situation—which was despite the effective antibiotics—doctors removed his eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these cases, it’s sometimes recommended to drain the liver abscess and surgically remove the brain lesions, too. But doctors ruled out both of those options. The liver abscess was too varied for simple drainage, and the brain lesions were too small and numerous to make surgery safe. Instead, he went through an intense antibiotic regimen that lasted nine months. Fortunately, by then, imaging confirmed that his liver abscess had resolved, his lung nodules nearly vanished, and his brain lesions significantly shrank or disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His doctors also noted that he was fortunate to have an hvKP strain that did not carry significant antibiotic resistance. In recent years,health officials have flaggednot just a global increase of hvKP cases overall but also an increase in hvKP cases that are resistant to critical antibiotics, specifically carbapenemases or extended-spectrum beta-lactamases. These cases can have fatality rates of above 50 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/this-may-be-the-grossest-eye-pic-ever-but-the-cause-is-whats-truly-horrifying/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:32:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge orders Anna’s Archive to delete scraped data; no one thinks it will comply</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-annas-archive-to-delete-scraped-data-no-one-thinks-it-will-comply/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/library-shelves-1152x648-1768598730.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WorldCat operator hopes default judgment will convince web hosts to take action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operator of WorldCat won a default judgment against Anna’s Archive, with a federal judge ruling yesterday that the shadow library must delete all copies of its WorldCat data and stop scraping, using, storing, or distributing the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive is a shadow library and search engine for other shadow libraries that was launched in 2022. It archives books and other written materials and makes them available via torrents, and recently expanded its ambitions byscraping Spotify to make a 300TB copyof the most-streamed songs. Anna’s Archivelost its .org domaina couple of weeks ago but remains online at other domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s ruling is in a case filed by OCLC, a nonprofit that operates the WorldCat library catalog on behalf of member libraries. OCLC alleged that Anna’s Archive “illegally hacked WorldCat.org” to steal 2.2TB of data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive, whichbills itselfas “the world’s largest shadow library,” did not respond to the lawsuit and doesn’t seem likely to comply with the judgment. The shadow library creator haswrittenthat “we deliberately violate the copyright law in most countries. This allows us to do something that legal entities cannot do: making sure books are mirrored far and wide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the court order has value for OCLC, which said in aNovember 2025 motionthat it “hopes to take the judgment to website hosting services so that OCLC’s WorldCat data will be removed from Anna’s Archive’s websites.” We contacted OCLC about its plans today and will update this article if it provides any information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thecourt order, which was previouslyreportedby TorrentFreak, was issued by Judge Michael Watson in US District Court for the Southern District of Ohio. “Plaintiff has established that Defendant crashed its website, slowed it, and damaged the servers, and Defendant admitted to the same by way of default,” the ruling said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive allegedly began scraping and harvesting data from WorldCat.org in October 2022, “and Plaintiff suffered persistent attacks for roughly a year,” the ruling said. “To accomplish such scraping and harvesting, Defendant allegedly used search bots (automated software applications) that ‘called or pinged the server directly’ and appeared to be ‘legitimate search engine bots from Bing and Google.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court granted OCLC’s motion for default judgment on a breach-of-contract claim related to WorldCat.org terms and conditions, and a trespass-to-chattels claim related to the alleged harm to its website and servers. The court rejected the plaintiff’s tortious-interference-with-contract claim because OCLC’s allegation didn’t include all necessary components to prove the charge, and rejected OCLC’s unjust enrichment claim because it “is preempted by federal copyright law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment said Anna’s Archive is permanently enjoyed from “scraping or harvesting WorldCat data from WorldCat. org or OCLC’s servers; using, storing, or distributing the WorldCat data on Anna’s Archive’s websites; and encouraging others to scrape, harvest, use, store, or distribute WorldCat data.” It also must “delete all copies of WorldCat data in possession of or easily accessible to it, including all torrents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Anna” behind Anna’s Archive revealed the WorldCat scraping in an October 2023blog post. The post said that because WorldCat has “the world’s largest library metadata collection,” the data would help Anna’s Archive make a “list of books that need to be preserved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even though OCLC is a nonprofit, their business model requires protecting their database,” Anna wrote. “Well, we’re sorry to say, friends at OCLC, we’re giving it all away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s blog said the scraping took place over a year and relied on security flaws that were gradually patched. The “security flaws were slowly fixed one by one, until the final one we found was patched about a month ago,” the October 2023 post said. “By that time we had pretty much all records, and were only going for slightly higher quality records.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCLC filed itslawsuitin January 2024. “Beginning in the fall of 2022, OCLC began experiencing cyberattacks on WorldCat.org and OCLC’s servers that significantly affected the speed and operations of WorldCat.org, other OCLC products and services, and OCLC’s servers and network infrastructure,” the lawsuit said. “These attacks continued throughout the following year, forcing OCLC to devote significant time and resources toward non-routine network infrastructure enhancements, maintenance, and troubleshooting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OCLC finally learned the perpetrator was Anna’s Archive when the shadow library made its October 2023 announcement. “Anna’s Archive has since made OCLC’s WorldCat data available for en masse for free download and now is actively encouraging its visitors to make use of the data in ‘interesting’ ways,” the lawsuit said, adding that the defendants “have no legal justification for their actions and admit that their general operations violate US and other jurisdictions’ copyright laws.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday’s default judgment is not the end of proceedings in the case. OCLC was ordered to file a status report within 30 days “suggesting next steps on the claims for which the Court denied default judgment, unless it files a motion to dismiss its remaining claims against Defendant before then.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-annas-archive-to-delete-scraped-data-no-one-thinks-it-will-comply/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:43:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Archaeologists find a supersized medieval shipwreck in Denmark</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/archaeologists-find-a-supersized-medieval-shipwreck-in-denmark/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Ubena_von_Bremen_Kiel2007_1_cropped-941x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sunken ship reveals that the medieval European economy was growing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists recently found the wreck of an enormous medieval cargo ship lying on the seafloor off the Danish coast, and it reveals new details of medieval trade and life at sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists discovered the shipwreck while surveying the seabed in preparation for a construction project for the city of Copenhagen, Denmark. It lay on its side, half-buried in the sand, 12 meters below the choppy surface of the Øresund, the straight that runs between Denmark and Sweden. By comparing the tree rings in the wreck’s wooden planks and timbers with rings from other, precisely dated tree samples, the archaeologists concluded that the ship had been built around 1410 CE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Svaelget 2, as archaeologists dubbed the wreck (its original name is long since lost to history), was a type of merchant ship called a cog: a wide, flat-bottomed, high-sided ship with an open cargo hold and a square sail on a single mast. A bigger, heavier, more advanced version of the Viking knarrs of centuries past, the cog was the high-tech supertanker of its day. It was built to carry bulky commodities from ports in the Netherlands, north around the coast of Denmark, and then south through the Øresund to trading ports on the Baltic Sea—but this one didn’t quite make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cogs would have been about 15 to 25 meters long and 5 to 8 meters wide, capable of carrying about 200 tons of cargo—big, impressive ships for their time. But Svaelget 2, an absolute unit of a ship, measured about 28 meters from bow to stern, 9 meters wide, and could have carried about 300 tons. Its size alone was a surprise to the archaeologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We now know, undeniably, that cogs could be this large—that the ship type could be pushed to this extreme,” said archaeologist Otto Uldum of Denmark’s Viking Ship Museum, who led the excavation,in a press release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval Europe’s merchant class was growing in both size and wealth in the early 1400s, and the cog was both a product of that growth and the engine driving it. The mere fact of its existence points to a society that could afford to invest in building big, expensive trading ships (and could confidently expect a return on that investment). And physically, it’s a product of the same trading networks it supplied: while the heavy timbers of its frame were cut locally in the Netherlands, the Pomeranian oak planks of Svaelget 2’s hull came from Poland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cog revolutionized trade in northern Europe,” said Uldum. “It made it possible to transport goods on a scale never seen before.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For about 600 years, layers of sand had protected the starboard (right, for you landlubbers) side of the wreck from erosion and decay. Nautical archaeologists usually find only the very bottoms of cogs; the upper structures of the ship—rigging, decks, and castles—quickly decay in the ocean. That means that some of the most innovative parts of the ships’ construction appear only in medieval drawings and descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Svaelget 2 offers archaeologists a hands-on look at the real deal, from rigging to the ship’s galley and the stern castle: a tall wooden structure at the back of the ship, where crew and passengers could have sought at least a little shelter from the elements. Medieval drawings and texts describe cogs having high castles at both bow and stern, but archaeologists have never gotten to examine a real one to learn how it’s put together or how it connects with the rest of the ship’s construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have plenty of drawings of castles, but they have never been found because usually only the bottom of the ship survives,” said Uldum. “[The castle] is a big step forward compared to Viking Age ships, which had only open decks in all kinds of weather.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lying on and around the remains of the cog’s decks, Uldum and his colleagues also found stays (ropes that would have held the mast in place) and lines for controlling the ship’s single square sail, along with ropes and chains that would once have secured the merchant vessel’s cargo in the open hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cog would probably have sailed with between 30 and 45 crew members. No remains were found on the wreck, but the lost crew left behind small, tantalizing traces of their lives and their presence. Uldum and his colleagues found combs, shoes, and rosary beads, along with dishes and tableware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The sailor brought his comb to keep his hair neat and his rosary to say his prayers,” said Uldum (and one has to picture the sailor’s grandmother beaming proudly at that description). “These personal objects show us that the crew brought everyday items with them. They transferred their life on land to life at sea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life at sea, for the medieval sailors aboard Svaelget 2, would have included at least occasional hot meals, cooked in bronze pots over an open fire in the ship’s galley and eaten on dishes of ceramic and painted wood. Bricks (about 200 of them) and tiles formed a sort of fireplace where the cook could safely build a fire aboard the otherwise very flammable ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It speaks of remarkable comfort and organization on board,” said Uldum. “Now sailors could have hot meals similar to those on land, instead of the dried and cold food that previously dominated life at sea.” Plenty of dried meat and cold biscuits still awaited sailors for the next several centuries, of course, but when weather and time permitted, at least the crew of Svaelget 2 could gather around a hot meal. The galley would have been a relatively new part of shipboard life for sailors in the early 1400s—and it quickly became a vital one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing usually marks the site of a shipwreck, even when everything else has disintegrated into the ocean: ballast stones. When merchant ships were empty, they carried stones in their holds to help keep the ship stable; otherwise, the empty ship would be top-heavy and prone to tipping over, which is usually not ideal. (Modern merchant vessels use water, in special tanks, for ballast.) But Uldum and his colleagues didn’t find ballast stones on Svaelget 2, which means the cog was probably fully laden with cargo when it sank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the cargo is also conspicuously absent. Cogs were built to carry bulk goods—things like bricks, grain and other staple foods, fabric, salt, and timber. Those goods would have been stowed in an open hold amidships, secured by ropes and chains (some of which remain on the wreck). But barrels, boards, and bolts of fabric all float. As the ship sank and water washed into the hold, it would have carried away the cargo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of it may have washed up on the shores or even more distant beaches, becoming a windfall for local residents. The rest probably sank to the bottom of the sea, far from the ship and its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/archaeologists-find-a-supersized-medieval-shipwreck-in-denmark/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:07:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rackspace customers grapple with “devastating” email hosting price hike</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/rackspace-raises-email-hosting-prices-by-as-much-as-706-percent/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2206289956-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reseller says Rackspace plans to charge it 706 percent more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s new pricing for its email hosting services is “devastating,” according to a partner that has been using Rackspace as its email provider since 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, Rackspaceupdated its email hosting pricing. Its standard plan is now $10 per mailbox per month. Businesses can also pay for the Rackspace Email Plus add-on for an extra $2/mailbox/month (for “file storage, mobile sync, Office-compatible apps, and messaging”), and the Archiving add-on for an extra $6/mailbox/month (for unlimited storage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As recently as November 2025, Rackspace charged $3/mailbox/month for its Standard plan, and an extra $1/mailbox/month for the Email Plus add-on, and an additional $3/mailbox/month for the Archival add-on, according to the Internet Archive’sWayback Machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s reseller partners have been especially vocal about the impacts of the new pricing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In ablog poston Thursday, web hosting service provider and Rackspace reseller Laughing Squid said Rackspace is “increasing our email pricing by an astronomical 706 percent, with only a month-and-a half’s notice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laughing Squid founder Scott Beale told Ars Technica that he received the “devastating” news via email on Wednesday. The last time Rackspace increased Laughing Squid’s email prices was by 55 percent in 2019, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The price increase has a major impact on the ability to make money due to the fact that email is now our largest expense, and we were only given a month-and-a-half notice,” Beale told Ars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online, there are reports of Rackspace partners being quoted email pricing increases of110 percent to nearly 500 percent.The reports say that the new, higher-per-mailbox quotes don’t include volume pricing discounts. Beale noted that Laughing Squid’s quote doesn’t include discounts that the company previously received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We had really good reseller pricing that we negotiated with Rackspace due to the number of mailboxes we had with them and how long we had been a customer. All of that seemed to vanish when they notified us of their new pricing,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars contacted Rackspace asking about the 706 percent price hike that Laughing Squid says it’s facing, why Rackspace decided to increase its prices now, and why it didn’t give its partners more advanced notice. A company spokesperson responded, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace Email is a reliable and secure business-class email solution for small businesses. To continue delivering the service levels our customers expect, effective March 2026, Rackspace Technology is increasing the price of Rackspace Email. We have a support team available to help our customers to discuss their options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spokesperson added that Rackspace’s “mission is to deliver quality, trusted and reliable hosted email solution for businesses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Rackspace’s stated commitment to email hosting, the prohibitive pricing seems like a deterrent for a business being viewed as high-effort and low-margin. Email has grown complex over the years, requiring time and expertise for proper management at scale. It’s become simpler, or more lucrative, for some cloud companies to focus on selling their managed services on top of offerings like Microsoft 365—as Rackspace does—or Google Workspace and let the larger companies behind those solutions deal with infrastructure costs and complexities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rackspace’s price hike also comes as anAI-driven RAM shortageisimpactingthe availability and affordability of other computing components,including storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Rackspace, whichwent public in 2020, also havingquit hosting Microsoft Exchangefollowing a costly2022 ransomware attack, the Texas-headquartered company may be looking to minimize its email hosting duties as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Laughing Squid is increasing prices for Rackspace mailboxes and offering services with a different email provider, PolarisMail, to customers at lower prices. Beale said he has reached out to Rackspace about the new pricing but hasn’t heard back yet.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/rackspace-raises-email-hosting-prices-by-as-much-as-706-percent/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:15:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Managers on alert for “launch fever” as pressure builds for NASA’s Moon mission</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/managers-on-alert-for-launch-fever-as-pressure-builds-for-nasas-moon-mission/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Artemis-II-Trajectory-Thumbnail-1-1152x648-1768622903.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve got one job, and it’s the safe return of Reid, Victor, Christina, and Jeremy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KENNEDY SPACE CENTER, Florida—The rocket NASA is preparing to send four astronauts on a trip around the Moon will emerge from its assembly building on Florida’s Space Coast early Saturday for a slow crawl to its seaside launch pad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riding atop one of NASA’s diesel-powered crawler transporters, the Space Launch System rocket and its mobile launch platform will exit the Vehicle Assembly Building at Kennedy Space Center around 7:00 am EST (11:00 UTC). The massive tracked transporter, certified by Guinness as the world’s heaviest self-propelled vehicle, is expected to cover the four miles between the assembly building and Launch Complex 39B in about eight to 10 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rollout marks a major step for NASA’s Artemis II mission, the first human voyage to the vicinity of the Moon since the last Apollo lunar landing in December 1972. Artemis II will not land. Instead, a crew of four astronauts will travel around the far side of the Moon at a distance of several thousand miles, setting the record for the farthest humans have ever ventured from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight will culminate with a scorching 25,000 mph (40,000 km per hour) reentry over the Pacific Ocean. The four Artemis II astronauts—NASA’s Reid Wiseman, Victor Glover, Christina Koch, and Canada’s Jeremy Hansen—will become the fastest humans in history, edging out a speed record set during the Apollo era of lunar exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey for the fully-assembled Moon rocket will begin early Saturday at a slower pace. After leaving the Vehicle Assembly Building, the moving 11 million-pound structure will head east, then make a left turn before climbing the ramp to Pad 39B overlooking the Atlantic Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will be at a cruising speed of under one mile per hour,” said Charlie Blackwell-Thompson, NASA’s launch director for the Artemis II mission. “It’ll be a little slower around the turns and up the hill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crawler carrying the SLS rocket and Orion spacecraft was built 60 years ago to haul NASA’s Saturn V rockets, then kept around for the Space Shuttle Program. Now, the vehicle is back to its original purpose of positioning Moon-bound rockets on their launch pads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These are the kinds of days that we live for when you do the kind of work that we do,” said John Honeycutt, chair of NASA’s Mission Management Team for the Artemis II mission. “The rocket and the spacecraft, OrionIntegrity, are getting ready to roll to the pad …It really doesn’t get much better than this, and we’re making history.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can watch live views of the rollout in this YouTube stream provided by NASA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;﻿&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artemis II is the first crew flight of NASA’s Artemis program, an initiative named for the twin sister of Apollo in Greek mythology. NASA named the program Artemis in 2019, but some of the building blocks have been around for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA selected Orion contractor Lockheed Martin to oversee the development of a deep space capsule in 2006 as part of the George W. Bush administration’s soon-to-be canceled Constellation program. In 2011, a political bargain between the Obama administration and Congress revived the Orion program and kicked off development of the Space Launch System. Theannouncement of the Artemis programin 2019 leaned on work already underway on Orion and the SLS rocket as the centerpieces of an architecture to return US astronauts to the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tens of billions of dollars later, everything is finally coming together for the final all-important milestone in developing the vehicles for transporting crews between the Earth and the Moon. A human-rated lunar lander and spacesuits tailored for Moonwalking astronauts are still a few years away from readiness. NASA has contracts with SpaceX and Blue Origin for landers, and with Axiom Space for suits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful Artemis II mission would demonstrate to NASA’s managers and engineers that the Orion spacecraft and SLS rocket fulfill their roles in the Artemis architecture. NASA is expected to rely on the SLS rocket, whichcosts more than $2 billion per flightand is expendable by design, for several more missions until commercial alternatives are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America’s return to the Moon now has a geopolitical imperative. China is working to land its own astronauts on the lunar surface by 2030, and US officials want to beat the Chinese to the Moon for the motivation of national prestige and the material benefits of accessing lunar resources, among other reasons. For now, budget-writing lawmakers in Congress and President Donald Trump’s new NASA chief, Jared Isaacman, agree the existing SLS/Orion architecture, despite its cost and shortcomings, offers the surest opportunity to beat the Chinese space program to a crew lunar landing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, if all goes according to plan, NASA can turn to cheaper (and in one case, more capable) rockets to help the government afford the expenditure required to construct a Moon base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Putting crew on the rocket and taking the crew around the Moon, this is going be our first step toward a sustained lunar presence,” Honeycutt said. “It’s 10 days [and] four astronauts going farther from Earth than any other human has ever traveled. We’ll be validating the Orion spacecraft’s life support, navigation and crew systems in the really harsh environments of deep space, and that’s going to pave the way for future landings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is still much work ahead before NASA can clear Artemis II for launch. At the launch pad, technicians will complete final checkouts and closeouts before NASA’s launch team gathers in early February for a critical practice countdown. During this countdown, called a Wet Dress Rehearsal (WDR), Blackwell-Thompson and her team will oversee the loading of the SLS rocket’s core stage and upper stage with super-cold liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen propellants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cryogenic fluids,particularly liquid hydrogen, gave fits to the Artemis launch team as NASA prepared to launch the Artemis I mission—without astronauts—on the SLS rocket’s first test flight in 2022. Engineers resolved the issues and successfully launched the Artemis I mission in November 2022, and officials will apply the lessons for the Artemis II countdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Artemis I was a test flight, and we learned a lot during that campaign getting to launch,” Blackwell-Thompson said. “And the things that we’ve learned relative to how to go load this vehicle, how to load LOX (liquid oxygen), how to load hydrogen, have all been rolled in to the way in which we intend to do for the Artemis II vehicle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming the countdown rehearsal goes according to plan, NASA could be in a position to launch the Artemis II mission as soon as February 6. But the schedule for February 6 is tight, with no margin for error. Officials typically have about five days per month when they can launch Artemis II, when the Moon is in the right position relative to Earth, and the Orion spacecraft can follow the proper trajectory toward reentry and splashdown to limit stress on thecapsule’s heat shield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February, the available launch dates are February 6, 7, 8, 10, and 11, with launch windows in the overnight hours in Florida. If the mission isn’t off the ground by February 11, NASA will have to stand down until a new series of launch opportunities beginning March 6. The space agency hasposted a documentshowing all available launch dates and times through the end of April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA’s leaders are eager for Artemis II to fly. NASA is not only racing China, a reality the agency’s former administrator acknowledged during the Biden administration. Now, the Trump administration is pushing NASA to accomplish a human landing on the Moon by the end of his presidential term on January 20, 2029.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Honeycutt’s jobs as chair of the Mission Management Team (MMT) is ensuring all the Is are dotted and Ts are crossed amid the frenzy of final launch preparations. While the hardware for Artemis II is on the move in Florida, the astronauts and flight controllers are wrapping up their final training and simulations at Johnson Space Center in Houston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think I’ve got a good eye for launch fever,” he said Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As chair of the MMT, I’ve got one job, and it’s the safe return of Reid, Victor, Christina, and Jeremy. I consider that a duty and a trust, and it’s one I intend to see through.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/managers-on-alert-for-launch-fever-as-pressure-builds-for-nasas-moon-mission/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 19:45:33 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>