<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:27:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meta wants to block data about social media use, mental health in child safety trial</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/meta-wants-to-block-data-about-social-media-use-mental-health-in-child-safety-trial/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/meta-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Company is pulling out all the stops to protect itself in advance of New Mexico trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Meta heads to trial in the state of New Mexico for allegedly failing to protect minors from sexual exploitation, the company is making an aggressive push to have certain information excluded from the court proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company has petitioned the judge to exclude certain research studies and articles around social media and youth mental health; any mention of a recent high-profile case involving teen suicide and social media content; and any references to Meta’s financial resources, the personal activities of employees, and Mark Zuckerberg’s time as a student at Harvard University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta’s requests to exclude information, known as motions in limine, are a standard part of pretrial proceedings, in which a party can ask a judge to determine in advance which evidence or arguments are permissible in court. This is to ensure the jury is presented with facts and not irrelevant or prejudicial information and that the defendant is granted a fair trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has emphasized in pretrial motions that the only questions the jury should be asked are whether Meta violated New Mexico’s Unfair Practices Act because of how it has allegedly handled child safety and youth mental health, and that other information—such as Meta’s alleged election interference and misinformation, or privacy violations—shouldn’t be factored in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some of the requests seem unusually aggressive, two legal scholars tell WIRED, including requests that the court not mention the company’s AI chatbots, and the extensive reputation protection Meta is seeking. WIRED was able to review Meta’s in limine requests through a public records request from the New Mexico courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These motions are part of a landmark case brought by New Mexico Attorney General Raúl Torrez in late 2023. The state is alleging that Meta failed to protect minors from online solicitation, human trafficking, and sexual abuse on its platforms. It claims the company proactively served pornographic content to minors on its apps and failed to enact certain child safety measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statecomplaintdetails how its investigators were easily able to set up fake Facebook and Instagram accounts posing as underage girls, and how these accounts were soon sent explicit messages and shown algorithmically amplified pornographic content. In another test case cited in the complaint, investigators created a fake account as a mother looking to traffic her young daughter. According to the complaint, Meta did not flag suggestive remarks that other users commented on her posts, nor did it shut down some of the accounts that were reported to be in violation of Meta’s policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta spokesperson Aaron Simpson told WIRED via email that the company has, for over a decade, listened to parents, experts, and law enforcement, and has conducted in-depth research, to “understand the issues that matter the most,” and to “use these insights to make meaningful changes—like introducing Teen Accounts with built-in protections and providing parents with tools to manage their teens’ experiences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While New Mexico makes sensationalist, irrelevant and distracting arguments, we’re focused on demonstrating our longstanding commitment to supporting young people,” Simpson said. “We’re proud of the progress we’ve made, and we’re always working to do better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its motions ahead of the New Mexico trial, Meta asked that the court exclude any references to a public advisory published by Vivek Murthy, the former US surgeon general, about social media and youth mental health. It also asked the court to exclude an op-ed article by Murthy and Murthy’s calls for social media to come witha warning label. Meta argues that the former surgeon general’s statements treat social media companies as a monolith and are “irrelevant, inadmissible hearsay, and unduly prejudicial.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has also insisted that the state of New Mexico should not be able to admit in court any third-party surveys—or Meta’s own internal surveys—that purport to show a high amount of inappropriate content on Meta’s platforms, because the surveys are, in legal terms, hearsay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social media giant seems particularly concerned that its CEO’s reputation, the company’s past privacy violations, and its overall dominance in social media could unfairly sway the jury. Meta has asked the court to preclude the state from introducing any argument, testimony, or evidence about Zuckerberg’s college years, saying “any effort by the state to pluck unflattering comments or incidents from when Mr. Zuckerberg (now in his 40s) was a college student would be both unfairly prejudicial and an impermissible use of propensity evidence to attack Mr. Zuckerberg’s and Meta’s character.” (Zuckerberg famously created an attractiveness-rating website in 2003; Meta’s lawyers have also sought tokeep this information out of courtin a consolidated trial in California that’s set to begin later this month.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has also requested that any evidence regarding Meta’s finances, “including its financial size, financial condition, market capitalization, revenues, profits, and wealth—as well as the wealth, compensation, and personal activities of its officers and employees,” be precluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It asks that the court not refer to former Meta employees or contractors who the state may call as witnesses as “whistleblowers,” insisting the word “whistleblower” is a legal term of art and that inaccurate or misleading references to people who may not qualify as whistleblowers “would serve only to inflame and confuse the jury.” And it has asked the court that any law enforcement officials who appear as witnesses not appear in uniform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta also wants the court to exclude any reference toMolly Russell, a British teenager who died by suicide in 2017 after consuming content on social media that depicted self-harm and suicide. Meta has argued that “evidence about her use of Instagram and material she allegedly saw on Instagram, her tragic death by suicide, and the United Kingdom Coroner’s investigation into her death” bear no connection to New Mexico or Meta’s case there, nor does the testimony of Russell’s father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, despite the company’s recent massive investments into and promotions of its artificial intelligence products, Meta has asked the New Mexico court to exclude any mention of its AI chatbots, stating, “This case has never been about AI chatbots,” and that introducing a “new, complex subject—emerging AI chatbot technology—would risk confusing and misleading the jury about the conduct and statements actually at issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these requests, such as withholding references to “previous cases, Meta’s wealth, or Mark Zuckerberg’s college hotness-rating app, seem pretty standard and straightforward,” says Mark Lemley, a partner at litigation firm Lex Lumina and the William H. Neukom professor at Stanford Law School. “But other requests from Meta seem quite aggressive, such as no reference to self-harm, or state-wide harms, or chatbots, for instance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s hard to know without being closer to the case whether there is a specific reason for those requests, though,” Lemley added. (Lemley previously defended Meta in a high-profile copyright lawsuit, then parted ways with the company because ofwhat he describedas the company’s “descent into toxic masculinity and neo-Nazi madness.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta’s alleged failures to prevent child exploitation on its apps have beenpreviously reported. Over the past two years the social media company has been sued by more than 40 US states forallegedly harming youth mental healthand has come under fire forreportedly halting internal researchthat showed that people who stopped using Facebook apps were less depressed and anxious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New Mexico case is now headed to trial court for jury selection in Santa Fe on February 2; hearings have been ongoing leading up to the trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story originally appeared onwired.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/meta-wants-to-block-data-about-social-media-use-mental-health-in-child-safety-trial/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:25:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>All sorts of interesting flags and artifacts will fly to the Moon on Artemis II</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasa-to-fly-apollo-aviation-artifacts-on-artemis-ii/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/news-012226a-lg-1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 2,300 commemorative items fill the duffel bag-size pouch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA’s first astronauts to fly to the Moon in more than 50 years will pay tribute to the lunar and space exploration missions that preceded them, as well as aviation and American history, by taking with them artifacts and mementos representing those past accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA, on Wednesday, January 21, revealed the contents of the Artemis II mission’s Official Flight Kit (OFK), continuing a tradition dating back to the Apollo program of packing a duffel bag-sized pouch of symbolic and celebratory items to commemorate the flight and recognize the people behind it. The kit includes more than 2,300 items, including a handful of relics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This mission will bring together pieces of our earliest achievements in aviation, defining moments from human spaceflight and symbols of where we’re headed next,” Jared Isaacman, NASA’s administrator, said in a statement. “Historical artifacts flying aboard Artemis II reflect the long arc of American exploration and the generations of innovators who made this moment possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TheArtemis II mission, which may launch as soon as early February, is set to take three NASA astronauts—commander Reid Wiseman, pilot Victor Glover, and mission specialist Christina Koch—and a representative of theCanadian Space Agency, mission specialist Jeremy Hansen, on a 10-day flight that takes them farther out into space than any humans have ever traveled before and then return them safely to Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mission includes a flyby of the Moon, affording the crew an opportunity to see parts of the far side never observed directly by human eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“DuringAmerica’s 250th anniversary, Orion will carry astronauts around the Moon, while also carrying our history forward into the next chapter beyond Earth,” said Isaacman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the OFK are numerous flags of different types, including hundreds of US and “America 250” flags for post-flight presentation. The kit also holds two special examples of the stars and stripes, one that is returning to space for its third time, and another that is finally getting its chance to fly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Legacy Flag,” which first flew on STS-1, the inaugural space shuttle mission in 1981, was thenlaunched to the International Space Stationon STS-135, the final space shuttle mission, in 2011 andbrought back to Earthby the SpaceX Demo-2 crew, the first astronauts to fly into orbit on a US commercial spacecraft in 2020. NASA then pledged to fly the 13×8 inch (33×20 centimeter) American flag yet again on the next crewed flight to the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A larger, 3×5-foot (0.9×1.5-meter) US flag is also in the Artemis II OFK. It was prepared like at least seven others to be deployed on the lunar surface until its mission, Apollo 18, was canceled due to budget cuts. The banner was instead put on display at NASA Headquarters in Washington until recently, when it was taken off exhibit to make its premiere flight to the Moon on Artemis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other flags inside the mission’s OFK include those representing US states and military branches, the United Nations, various schools, and other countries. The European Space Agency (ESA), which provided the service module for the Artemis II Orion spacecraft, has aboard one of its logo flags for display after the mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TheArtemis I OFKthat flew on an uncrewed test flight in 2022 carried tree seeds around the Moon, similar to how Apollo 14 astronaut Stuart Roosa did in 1971. The resulting Artemis Moon trees, like the Apollo Moon trees before them, have sincegrown to become living remindersof what humanity is capable of achieving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Artemis II, NASA is flying soil samples collected from the base ofestablished Artemis Moon treesthat were planted at the agency’s 10 centers. The packets of earth represent “the full cycle of exploration: launch, flight, growth and return to space again,” as explained by NASA. The Canadian Space Agency will restart that cycle with tree seeds it is flying on Artemis II to be planted around Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smithsonian’s National Air and Space Museum has loaned a 1×1-inch (2.54×2.54 cm) swatch of muslin fabric that was cut from the right wing of the original Flyer that the Wright Brothers used to make the first powered flight in 1903. The swatch was cut from a larger sample that previously launched on the space shuttleDiscovery‘s STS-51D mission in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Artemis II, NASA will return the fabric to the museum, which displays the Wright Flyer as well as other space-flown swatches, including pieces that were landed on the Moon by Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin in 1969.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Apollo 11 touched down with the first humans, NASA’s Ranger 7 became the first US mission to successfully make contact with the lunar surface. Artemis II will carry a copy of a 4×5 inch (10×13 cm) negative of a photo from that 1964 robotic mission. The photo represents “a major turning point in the race to the Moon that will be echoed today through the success of Artemis,” according to NASA officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond patches, pins, and decals, a few other standout items in the 10 lb (4.5 kg) Artemis II Official Flight Kit include an SD card recorded with thenames of 2.9 million (and counting)people who signed up to be on the mission and metal shavings from the construction of the Space Launch System (SLS) core stage, the largest component of the mission’s launch vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a badge and a “leather back number” from the Houston Livestock Show and Rodeo, an annual event in “Space City,” home to the Johnson Space Center in Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the OFK, the astronauts each have their own Personal Preference Kit (PPK), a smaller pouch in which they can carry mementos that have significance to them. As examples, Wiseman said he is flying a notecard to take down his thoughts during the flight; Glover has a Bible, heirlooms for his wife and children, and a collection of inspirational quotes compiled by Apollo 9 astronaut Rusty Schweickart; Koch has handwritten notes from people she loves to serve as a tactile connection between her and them; and Hansen has four Moon pendants that he is taking for his wife and three children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click herefor the complete Artemis II Official Flight Kit (OFK) manifest as released by NASA and transcribed by collectSPACE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listing image:
     Cole Simmons via collectSPACE.com&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasa-to-fly-apollo-aviation-artifacts-on-artemis-ii/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:41:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>eBay bans illicit automated shopping amid rapid rise of AI agents</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/ebay-bans-illicit-automated-shopping-amid-rapid-rise-of-ai-agents/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/robot_shopper_1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New policy requires “buy for me” AI tools and chatbots to obtain permission before accessing the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, eBay updated itsUser Agreementto explicitly ban third-party “buy for me” agents and AI chatbots from interacting with its platform without permission, first spotted byValue Added Resource. On its face, a one-line terms of service update doesn’t seem like major news, but what it implies is more significant: The change reflects the rapid emergence of what some are calling “agentic commerce,” a new category of AI tools designed to browse, compare, and purchase products on behalf of users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eBay’s updated terms, which go into effect on February 20, 2026, specifically prohibit users from employing “buy-for-me agents, LLM-driven bots, or any end-to-end flow that attempts to place orders without human review” to access eBay’s services without the site’s permission. The previous version of the agreement contained a general prohibition on robots, spiders, scrapers, and automated data gathering tools but did not mention AI agents or LLMs by name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the phrase “agentic commerce” may sound like aspirational marketing jargon, but the tools are already here, and people are apparently using them. While fitting loosely under one label, these tools come in many forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI firstaddedshopping features to ChatGPT Search in April 2025, allowing users to browse product recommendations. By September, the companylaunchedInstant Checkout, which lets users purchase items from Etsy and Shopify merchants directly within the chat interface. (In November, eBay CEO Jamie Iannonesuggestedthe company might join OpenAI’s Instant Checkout program in the future.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere, Perplexityoffers“Buy with Pro,” a one-click checkout feature for its paying subscribers. Google recentlyannouncedits Universal Commerce Protocol, an open standard for AI agents to interact with retailers. And Amazonoffersa “Buy For Me” feature, which uses AI to purchase items from external brand websites within the Amazon app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eBay’s policy update follows the company’squiet changestoits robots.txt filein December, a special file on a web server that lists rules and prohibitions that sites hope web-crawling bots will follow. According toModern Retail, eBay added a new “Robot &amp; Agent Policy” to the file that prohibited automated scraping and buy-for-me agents. eBay later updated the file to add explicit blocks against bots from Perplexity, Anthropic, Amazon, and others, though it allowed Google’s shopping bot to access the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, restrictions in robots.txt files are basically honor-system suggestions. By adding the language to its User Agreement, eBay can now more easily take legal action against users or companies who violate the policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, even with this general mood against robotic commerce from outsiders, eBay’s new User Agreement policy does not prevent the company from developing its own AI shopping tools. CEO Jamie Iannonesaidon an October earnings call that eBay is “testing a variety of agentic experiences in search and shopping.” The rules also allow such bots “with the prior express permission of eBay,” which could open the door to official shopping partnerships with companies like OpenAI.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/ebay-bans-illicit-automated-shopping-amid-rapid-rise-of-ai-agents/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 06:56:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Finally, a new controller that solves the Switch 2’s “flat Joy-Con” problem</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/finally-a-new-controller-that-solves-the-switch-2s-flat-joy-con-problem/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/hyperion3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Nyxi’s Hyperion 3 upgrade comes with a pretty high asking price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ireviewed the Switch 2 back in June, I noted that the lack of any sort of extended grip on the extremely thin Joy-Con 2 controllers made them relatively awkward to hold, both when connected to the system and when cradled in separate hands. At the time, I said that “my Switch 2 will probably need something likethe Nyxi Hyperion Pro, which I’ve come to rely on to make portable play on the original Switch much more comfortable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over half a year later, Nyxi is once again addressing my Switch controller-related comfort concerns with theHyperion 3, which wasmade available for preorder earlier this weekahead of planned March 1 shipments. Unfortunately, it looks like players will have to pay a relatively high price for a potentially more ergonomic Switch 2 experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there areplentyofthird-party controllersfor the Switch 2, none of the current options mimic the official Joy-Cons’ ability to connect magnetically to the console tablet itself (controllers designed to slide into the grooves on the original Switch tablet also can’t hook to the successor console). The Hyperion 3 is the first Switch 2 controller to offer this magnetic connection, making it uniquely suited for handheld play on the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And although I haven’t held the Hyperion 3 in my hands yet, my experience with the similar Hyperion 2 on the original Switch suggests that the ergonomic design here will be a welcome upgrade from the relatively small buttons and cramp-inducing flat back of the official Switch 2 Joy-Cons (“Say Goodbye to Tendonitis,” as Nyxi claims in its marketing materials). The controller can also connect wirelessly via Bluetooth 5.0 for when you want to switch to docked play, unlike some Switch Joy-Con replacements that only work in portable mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hyperion 3 boasts many of the added features you’d expect from a high-end third-party controller these days, including gyro controls, turbo support, programmable rear buttons, and Hall Effect joysticks that should be more resistant tothe dreaded stick drift that has plagued Nintendo controllers. The controller can even wake up a sleeping Switch 2 wirelessly, somethingoriginal Switch controllers can’t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, all these upgrades come at a price. Nyxi is asking $170 for the Hyperion 3, a significant increase over the already-high $100 that Nintendo charges for the official Switch 2 Joy-Cons. Even with a current 30 percent preorder discount, the upgraded controllers will still set you back nearly $120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That asking price puts the Hyperion 3 in the same class as premium first-party controllers likeMicrosoft’s Xbox Elite 2orSony’s DualSense Edge. But although you can findcheaperalternativesfor PS5 or Xbox Series X|S controllers, Nyxi’s expensive Hyperion 3 is currently the only third-party option for Switch 2 players who want a more comfortable portable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame that Nintendo’s official Joy-Con design practically demands this kind of costly upgrade if you want a truly comfortable portable experience. For those looking for a slightly cheaper upgrade option, though,this Mobapad adapterlets you connect your favorite Switch-compatible Joy-Con replacement to the Switch 2.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/finally-a-new-controller-that-solves-the-switch-2s-flat-joy-con-problem/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 07:15:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google adds your Gmail and Photos to AI Mode to enable “Personal Intelligence”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-ai-mode-can-now-customize-responses-with-your-email-and-photos/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/AI-Mode-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personal Intelligence is optional and rolling out first to AI Pro and AI Ultra subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google believes AI is the future of search, and it’snot shy about saying it. After addingaccount-level personalizationto Gemini earlier this month, it’s now updatingAI Modewith so-called “Personal Intelligence.” According to Google, this makes the bot’s answers more useful because they are tailored to your personal context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting today, the feature is rolling out to all users who subscribe to Google AI Pro or AI Ultra. However, it will be aLabs featurethat needs to be explicitly enabled (subscribers will be prompted to do this). Google tends to expand access to new AI features to free accounts later on, so free users will most likely get access to Personal Intelligence in the future. Whenever this option does land on your account, it’s entirely optional and can be disabled at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide to integrate your data with AI Mode, the search bot will be able to scan your Gmail and Google Photos. That’s less extensive than the Gemini app version, which supports Gmail, Photos, Search, and YouTube history. Gmail will probably be the biggest contributor to AI Mode—a great many life events involve confirmation emails. Traditional search results when you are logged in are adjusted based on your usage history, but this goes a step further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re going to use AI Mode to find information, Personal Intelligence could actually be quite helpful. When you connect data from other Google apps, Google’s custom Gemini search model will instantly know about your preferences and background—that’s the kind of information you’d otherwise have to include in your search query to get the best output. With Personal Intelligence, AI Mode can just pull those details from your email or photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, as in the video below, you could ask about clothing options for an upcoming trip. Instead of telling the robot when and where you’re going in the prompt, it can get that information from your email confirmation. When AI Mode uses your personal context in a response, it will cite it in-line the same way it does for websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google says, as it often does, that AI is not perfect. AI Mode with Personal Intelligence can make mistakes, drawing the wrong conclusions from the data it mines from your account. In that case, Google suggests using a follow-up prompt to correct it and get more accurate information. It’s similar to the way you might refine a traditional Google search when the links aren’t to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI Mode and Google AI are generally supposed to improve over time to reduce such failures. The way you use the service contributes to that, but Google says the model is not being trained directly on your email or photos, even if you connect them to AI Mode. Instead, Google uses your prompts and the resulting output to train its AI models. Access to Gmail and Photos can be revoked at any time, but it sounds like there won’t be a simple way to toggle off Personal Intelligence for a single query, which is possible in Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-ai-mode-can-now-customize-responses-with-your-email-and-photos/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 07:35:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Blue Origin makes impressive strides with reuse—next launch will refly booster</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/blue-origin-makes-impressive-strides-with-reuse-next-launch-will-refly-booster/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/blue-bird-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this quick turnaround, Blue Origin takes a step toward a faster cadence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Origin confirmed Thursday that the next launch of its New Glenn rocket will carry a large communications satellite into low-Earth orbit for AST SpaceMobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket will launch the next-generation Block 2 BlueBird satellite “no earlier than late February” from Launch Complex 36 at Cape Canaveral Space Force Station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However,the update from Blue Originappears to have buried the real news toward the end: “The mission follows the successful NG-2 mission, which included the landing of the ‘Never Tell Me The Odds’ booster. The same booster is being refurbished to power NG-3,” the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second New Glenn mission launched on November 13, just 10 weeks ago. If the company makes the late-February target for the next mission—and Ars was told last week to expect the launch to slip into March—it will represent a remarkably short turnaround for an orbital booster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By way of comparison, SpaceX did not attempt to refly the first Falcon 9 booster it landed in December 2015. Instead, initial tests revealed that the vehicle’s interior had been somewhat torn up. It was scrapped and inspected closely so that engineers could learn from the wear and tear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX successfully landed its second Falcon 9 booster in April 2016, on the 23rd overall flight of the Falcon 9 fleet. This booster was refurbished and, after a lengthy series of inspections, it was reflown successfully in March 2017, nearly 11 months later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With New Glenn, Blue Origin is seeking to refly a booster on just the third overall flight of the New Glenn fleet and turn the rocket around in less than four months. Even for a well-capitalized program with the benefit of learning from both Blue Origin’s own suborbital New Shepard rocket and the industry’s experience with the Falcon 9, this represents an impressive turnaround in first stage reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue Origin originally planned to launch its MK1 lunar lander on the third flight of New Glenn, but it pivoted to a commercial launch as the lunar vehicle continues preparatory work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday,the company announcedthat it had completed the integration of the MK1 vehicle and put it on a barge bound for Johnson Space Center in Houston. There, it will undergo vacuum chamber testing before a launch later this spring—or, more likely, sometime this summer.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/blue-origin-makes-impressive-strides-with-reuse-next-launch-will-refly-booster/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:49:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Check out the first trailer for Masters of the Universe</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/check-out-the-first-trailer-for-masters-of-the-universe/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/heman4-1152x648-1769098758.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Talking tigers, spaceships, and magic swords that can make a man as mighty as a god.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars readers of a certain age no doubt remember the 1980sHe-Man and the Masters of the Universeseries (and its spinoff,She-Ra: Princess of Powers) and the many, many offshoots of this hugelypopular Mattel franchise, including an extensive line of action figures. Amazon MGM Studios no doubt hopes to cash in on any lingering nostalgia with its forthcoming film,Masters of the Universe.Judging by the extended teaser trailer, we’re getting an origin story for He-Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not the first time someone has turned He-Man into a feature film: Dolph Lundgren starred in 1987’sMasters of the Universe, a critical and box office bomb that also featured Frank Langella as arch-villain Skeletor. Its poor reception might have stemmed from the 1987 film deviating significantly from the original cartoon, angering fans. But frankly, it was just a bad, cheesy movie, though it still has its share of cult fans today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This latest big-screen live-action adaptation has been languishing in development hell for nearly two decades. There were rumors in 2007 that John Woo would direct a He-Man feature for Warner Bros., but the project never got the green light. Sony Pictures gained the rights in 2009, and there were multiple script rewrites and much shuffling of possible directors (with John Chu, McG, and David S. Goyer among the candidates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This went on until 2022, when Netflix acquired the rights on the heels of its success with a pair of animated shows starring Kyle Allen as He-Man. Netflix canceled the project the following year, citing budget concerns, so Allen never got that big-screen break. And Amazon MGM stepped in, tapping Travis Knight (Bumblebee,Kubo and the Two Strings) as director and casting Nicholas Galitzine (2021’sCinderella,100 Nights of Hero) as He-Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to Galitzine, the cast includes Camila Mendes as Teela; Jared Leto as Keldor/Skeletor; Alison Brie as Professor Evelyn Powers, aka Evil-Lyn, lieutenant to Skeletor; Idris Elba as Duncan/Man-at-Arms; Morena Baccarin as the Sorceress of Castle Grayskull; Johannes Haukur as Malcolm/Fisto; James Purefoy and Charlotte Riley as King Randor and Queen Marlena, rulers of Eternia; Sasheer Zamata as Suzie, Adam/He-Man’s BFF on Earth; Kristen Wiig as Roboto; Jon Xue Zhang as Ram-Man; Kojo Attah as the bounty hunter Tri-Klops; Sam C. Wilson as cyborg/weapons expert Kronis/Trap-Jaw; and Hafþór Júlíus Björnsson as Goat Man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learn from the teaser trailer that when he was 10 years old, Adam Glenn, prince of Eternia and our future He-Man, crash-landed on Earth—the home planet of his ex-astronaut mother, Queen Marlena, who sent him there for protection from the forces of Skeletor. The now-grown Adam is an office drone with a penchant for nerd culture that doesn’t exactly impress human resources, and he has been searching online for his magic sword, convinced it will show him “the way home.” We suspect the sword he finds in a comic shop is just a replica, but soon Teela shows up to whisk him off to Eternia in a spaceship. Cue a series of battles and Adam tapping into the real magical sword’s power just in time to take on Skeletor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Masters of the Universehits theaters on June 5, 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/check-out-the-first-trailer-for-masters-of-the-universe/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 10:18:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google begins offering free SAT practice tests powered by Gemini</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-begins-offering-free-sat-practice-tests-powered-by-gemini/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Gemini-SAT-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google says more kinds of standardized tests will be added in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s no secret that students worldwide use AI chatbots to do their homework and avoid learning things. On the flip side, students can also use AI as a tool to beef up their knowledge and plan for the future with flashcards or study guides. Google hopes its latest Gemini feature will help with the latter. The company hasannouncedthat Gemini can now create free SAT practice tests and coach students to help them get higher scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a standardized test, the content of the SAT follows a predictable pattern. So there’s no need to use a lengthy, personalized prompt to get Gemini going. Just say something like, “I want to take a practice SAT test,” and the chatbot will generate one complete with clickable buttons, graphs, and score analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, generative AI can go off the rails and provide incorrect information, which is a problem when you’re trying to learn things. However, Google says it has worked with education firms like The Princeton Review to ensure the AI-generated tests resemble what students will see in the real deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interface for Gemini’s practice tests includes scoring and the ability to review previous answers. If you are unclear on why a particular answer is right or wrong, the questions have an “Explain answer” button right at the bottom. After you finish the practice exam, the custom interface (which looks a bit like Gemini’s Canvas coding tool) can help you follow up on areas that need improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the SAT is the most widely used test in US college admissions, it’s not the only one. Google is starting with the SAT but says it plans to support other tests in the future. It does not specify if future tests will be US-centric or if they could branch out to other regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, SAT prep courses and tutoring are a big business. Practice tests and books can cost several hundred dollars, and a one-on-one tutor can run into the thousands. Overall, Americans spend billions of dollars every year on these products and services in hopes of giving their kids a leg up in college admissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI is already making a dent in the industry—even without a dedicated test prep mode, students regularly use chatbots for tutoring, hallucinations be damned. The addition of this feature to Gemini for all users will likely accelerate declines in test prep and tutoring services.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-begins-offering-free-sat-practice-tests-powered-by-gemini/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 11:46:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Asking Grok to delete fake nudes may force victims to sue in Musk’s chosen court</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/asking-grok-to-delete-fake-nudes-may-force-victims-to-sue-in-musks-chosen-court/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2255893185-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millions likely harmed by Grok-edited sex images as X advertisers shrugged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalists and advocates have been trying to grasp how many victims in total were harmed byGrok’s nudifying scandalafterxAI delayed restricting outputsandapp stores refused to cut off accessfor days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest estimates show that perhaps millions were harmed in the days immediately after Elon Musk promoted Grok’s undressing feature on his own X feed by posting a pic of himself in a bikini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over just 11 days after Musk’s post, Grok sexualized more than 3 million images, of which 23,000 were of children, the Center for Countering Digital Hate (CCDH)estimatedin research published Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That figure may be inflated, since CCDH did not analyze prompts and could not determine if images were already sexual prior to Grok’s editing. However, The New York Timessharedthe CCDH report alongside its own analysis, conservatively estimating that about 41 percent (1.8 million) of 4.4 million images Grok generated between December 31 and January 8 sexualized men, women, and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For xAI and X, the scandal brought scrutiny, but it also helped spike X engagement at a time when Meta’s rival app, Threads, has begun inching ahead of X in daily usage by mobile device users, TechCrunchreported. Without mentioning Grok, X’s head of product, Nikita Bier, celebrated the “highest engagement days on X” in an X post on January 6, just days before X finallystarted restricting some of Grok’s outputs for free users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not xAI intended the Grok scandal to surge X and Grok use, that appears to be the outcome. The TimeschartedGrok trends and found that in the nine days prior to Musk’s post, combined, Grok was only used about 300,000 times to generate images, but after Musk’s post, “the number of images created by Grok surged to nearly 600,000 per day” on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In anarticledeclaring that “Elon Musk cannot get away with this,” writers for The Atlantic suggested that X users “appeared to be imitating and showing off to one another,” believing that using Grok to create revenge porn “can make you famous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X has previously warned that X users who generate illegal content risk permanent suspensions, but X has not confirmed if any users have been banned since public outcry over Grok’s outputs began. Ars asked and will update this post if X provides any response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, X only limited Grok’s image editing for some free users, which The Atlantic noted made it seem like X was “essentially marketing nonconsensual sexual images as a paid feature of the platform.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, on January 14, X took itsstrongest action to restrict Grok’s harmful outputs—blocking outputs prompted by both free and paid X users. That move came after several countries, perhapsmost notably the United Kingdom, and at least one state,California, launched probes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, X’s updates did not apply to the Grok app or website; however, it canreportedlystill be used to generate nonconsensual images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a problem for victims targeted by X users, according to Carrie Goldberg, a lawyer representing Ashley St. Clair, one of the first Grok victims to sue xAI; St. Clair also happens to be the mother of one of Musk’s children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldberg told Ars that victims like St. Clair want changes on all Grok platforms, not just X. But it’s not easy to “compel that kind of product change in a lawsuit,” Goldberg said. That’s why St. Clair is hoping the court will agree that Grok is a public nuisance, a claim that provides some injunctive relief to prevent broader social harms if she wins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, St. Clair is seeking a temporary injunction that would block Grok from generating harmful images of her. But before she can get that order, if she wants a fair shot at winning the case, St. Clair must fight an xAI push counter-suing her and trying to move her lawsuit into Musk’s preferred Texas court, a recent court filing suggests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that fight, xAI is arguing that St. Clair is bound by xAI’s terms of service, which were updated the day after she notified the company of her intent to sue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alarmingly, xAI argued that St. Clair effectively agreed to the TOS when she started prompting Grok to delete her nonconsensual images—which is the only way X users had to get images removed quickly, St. Clair alleged. It seems xAI is hoping to turn moments of desperation, where victims beg Grok to remove images, into a legal shield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the filing, Goldberg wrote that St. Clair’s lawsuit has nothing to do with her own use of Grok, noting that the harassing images could have been made even if she never used any of xAI’s products. For that reason alone, xAI should not be able to force a change in venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, St. Clair’s use of Grok was clearly under duress, Goldberg argued, noting that one of the photos that Grok edited showed St. Clair’s toddler’s backpack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“REMOVE IT!!!” St. Clair asked Grok, allegedly feeling increasingly vulnerable every second the images remained online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldberg wrote that Barry Murphy, an X Safety employee, provided an affidavit that claimed that this instance and others of St. Clair “begging @Grok to remove illegal content constitutes an assent to xAI’s TOS.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But “such cannot be the case,” Goldberg argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with “the implicit threat that Grok would keep the images of St. Clair online and, possibly, create more of them,” St. Clair had little choice but to interact with Grok, Goldberg argued. And that prompting should not gut protections under New York law that St. Clair seeks to claim in her lawsuit, Goldberg argued, asking the court to void St. Clair’s xAI contract and reject xAI’s motion to switch venues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should St. Clair win her fight to keep the lawsuit in New York, the case could help set precedent for perhaps millions of other victims who may be contemplating legal action but fear facing xAI in Musk’s chosen court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It would be unjust to expect St. Clair to litigate in a state so far from her residence, and it may be so that trial in Texas will be so difficult and inconvenient that St. Clair effectively will be deprived of her day in court,” Goldberg argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The estimated volume of sexualized images reported this week is alarming because it suggests that Grok, at the peak of the scandal, may have been generating more child sexual abuse material (CSAM) than X finds on its platform each month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, X Safety reported 686,176 instances of CSAM to the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children, which, on average, is about 57,000 CSAM reports each month. If the CCDH’s estimate of 23,000 Grok outputs that sexualize children over an 11-day span is accurate, then an average monthly total may have exceeded 62,000 if Grok was left unchecked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NCMEC did not immediately respond to Ars’ request to comment on how the estimated volume of Grok’s CSAM compares to X’s average CSAM reporting. But NCMEC previously told Ars that “whether an image is real or computer-generated, the harm is real, and the material is illegal.” That suggests Grok could remain a thorn in NCMEC’s side, as the CCDH has warned that even when X removes harmful Grok posts, “images could still be accessed via separate URLs,” suggesting that Grok’s CSAM and other harmful outputs could continue spreading. The CCDH also found instances of alleged CSAM that X had not removed as of January 15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why child safety experts have advocated for more testing to ensure that AI tools like Grok don’t roll out capabilities like the undressing feature. NCMEC previously told Ars that “technology companies have a responsibility to prevent their tools from being used to sexualize or exploit children.” Amid a rise in AI-generated CSAM, the UK’s Internet Watch Foundation similarlywarnedthat “it is unacceptable that technology is released which allows criminals to create this content.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, for Musk and xAI, there have been no meaningful consequences for Grok’s controversial outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible that recently launched probes will result in legal action in California or fines in the UK or elsewhere, but those investigations will likely take months to conclude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While US lawmakers have done little to intervene, some Democratic senators haveattemptedto ask Google and Apple CEOs why X and the Grok app were never restricted in their app stores, demanding a response by January 23. One day ahead of that deadline, senators confirmed to Ars that they’ve received no responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, neither Google nor Apple responded to Ars’ request to confirm whether a response is forthcoming or provide any statements on their decisions to keep the apps accessible. Both companies have been silent for weeks, along with other Big Tech companies that appear to be afraid to speak out against Musk’s chatbot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft and Oracle, which “run Grok on their cloud services,” as well as Nvidia and Advanced Micro Devices, “which sell xAI the computer chips needed to train and run Grok,” declined The Atlantic’s request to comment on how the scandal has impacted their decisions to partner with xAI. Additionally, a dozen of xAI’s key investors simply didn’t respond when The Atlantic asked if “they would continue partnering with xAI absent the company changing its products.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, dozens of advertisers refusedPopular Information’s requestto explain why there was no ad boycott over the Grok CSAM reports. That includes companies that onceboycotted X over an antisemitic post from Musk, like “Amazon, Microsoft, and Google, all of which have advertised on X in recent days,” Popular Information reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible that advertisers fear Musk’s legal wrath if they boycott his platforms. The CCDH overcame a lawsuit from Musk last year, but that’s pending an appeal. And Musk’s so-called“thermonuclear” lawsuit against advertisersremains ongoing, with a trial date set for this October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Atlantic suggested that xAI stakeholders are likely hoping the Grok scandal will blow over and they’ll escape unscathed by staying silent. But so far, backlash has seemed to remain strong, perhaps because, while “deepfakes are not new,” xAI “has made them a dramatically larger problem than ever before,” The Atlantic opined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the largest forums dedicated to making fake images of real people,” Mr. Deepfakes,shut down in 2024after public backlash over 43,000 sexual deepfake videos depicting about 3,800 individuals, the NYT reported. If the most recent estimates of Grok’s deepfakes are accurate, xAI shows how much more damage can be done when nudifying becomes a feature of one of the world’s biggest social networks, and nobody who has the power to stop it moves to intervene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is industrial-scale abuse of women and girls,” Imran Ahmed, the CCDH’s chief executive, told NYT. “There have been nudifying tools, but they have never had the distribution, ease of use or the integration into a large platform that Elon Musk did with Grok.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/asking-grok-to-delete-fake-nudes-may-force-victims-to-sue-in-musks-chosen-court/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:16:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Report: Apple plans to launch AI-powered wearable pin device as soon as 2027</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/apple/2026/01/report-apple-plans-to-launch-ai-powered-wearable-pin-device-as-soon-as-2027/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/AirTag-1-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple, OpenAI, Meta, and more are all racing toward AI hardware products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple is working on a wearable device that will allow the user to take advantage of AI models, according to sources familiar with the product who spokewith tech publication The Information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product is said to be “the same size as an AirTag, only slightly thicker,” and will be worn as a pin, inviting comparisons to the failed Humane AI pin that launched to bad reviews and lackluster sales in 2024. The Humane product was criticized for sluggish performance and low battery life, but those shortcomings could potentially be addressed by Apple’s solution, should Apple offload the processing to a synced external device like an iPhone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Information’s sources don’t specify whether that’s the plan, or if it will be a standalone device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wearable will have a single physical button “along its edges” and will feature a speaker. It will have three microphones and two cameras (one regular and one wide-angle) for capturing information about the user’s surroundings. It will use a magnetic inductive wireless charging surface similar to the one used to charge the Apple Watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report didn’t include any information about pricing, but it did say that Apple has fast-tracked the product with the hope to release it as early as 2027. Twenty million units are planned for launch, suggesting the company does not expect it to be a sensational consumer success at launch the way some of its past products, like AirPods, have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, it was reported that OpenAI (the company behind ChatGPT) plans to releaseits own hardware, though the specifics and form factor are not publicly known. Apple is expecting fierce competition there, as well as with Meta, which Apple already expected to compete with in the emerging and related smart glasses market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple has experienced significant internal turmoil over AI, withformerAI lead John Giannandrea’s conservative approach to the technology failing to lead to a usable, true LLM-based Siri or other products analysts expect would make Apply stay competitive in the space with other Big Tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few days ago, it was revealed that Apple willtap Google’s Geminilarge language models for an LLM overhaul of Siri. Other AI-driven products like smart glasses and an in-home smart display are also planned.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/apple/2026/01/report-apple-plans-to-launch-ai-powered-wearable-pin-device-as-soon-as-2027/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:32:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hacker who stole 120,000 bitcoins wants a second chance—and a security job</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/hacker-who-stole-120000-bitcoins-wants-a-second-chance-and-a-security-job/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/getty-hacker-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crypto theft was “the worst thing I had ever done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Ilya Lichtenstein, who was at the center of a massive 2016 crypto heist worth billions at the time, wrote online that he is now out of prison and has changed his ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ten years ago, I decided that I would hack the largest cryptocurrency exchange in the world,” Lichtenstein wrote onLinkedIn, detailing a time when his startup was barely making money and he decided to steal some instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This was a terrible idea. It was the worst thing I had ever done,” he added. “It upended my life, the lives of people close to me, and affected thousands of users of the exchange. I know I disappointed a lot of people who believed in me and grossly misused my talents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Lichtenstein and his wife, Heather Morgan, pleaded guilty to money laundering conspiracy in a wild2016 scheme to steal 120,000 bitcoins(worth over $10 billion today) from Bitfinex, a cryptocurrency exchange. The pair were arrested at their Manhattan home in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lichtenstein quickly flipped, helping the government recover the assets he had stolen and then helping the feds “on a variety of crypto cases.” He says that he enjoyed working with the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I was a black hat hacker, I was isolated and paranoid,” he wrote. “Working with the good guys, being part of a team solving a bigger problem felt surprisingly good. I realized that I could use my technical skills to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lichtenstein, who did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment, noted that he wassentencedto 60 months in prison and spent “nearly [four] years in some of the harshest jails in the country.” While in prison, Lichtenstein says that he spent as much time as he could in the prison library studying math books to engage his mind and distract himself from his surroundings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 38-year-old added that he was “released to home confinement earlier this month.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convicted hackers cooperating with federal authorities orturning their lives aroundis not without precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One notable example is the lateKevin Mitnick, who was convicted of multiple phone and computer crime cases in the 1980s and 1990s. Mitnick eventually started his own security consulting company and became a penetration tester and public speaker for many years before his death in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now begins the real challenge of regaining the community’s trust,” Lichtenstein concluded, noting that he wants to work in cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think like an adversary,” he said. “I’ve been an adversary. Now I can use those same skills to stop the next billion-dollar hack.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/hacker-who-stole-120000-bitcoins-wants-a-second-chance-and-a-security-job/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:23:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Overrun with AI slop, cURL scraps bug bounties to ensure “intact mental health”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/overrun-with-ai-slop-curl-scraps-bug-bounties-to-ensure-intact-mental-health/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ai-slop-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The onslaught includes LLMs finding bogus vulnerabilities and code that won’t compile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project developer for one of the Internet’s most popular networking tools is scrapping its vulnerability reward program after being overrun by a spike in the submission of low-quality reports, much of it AI-generated slop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are just a small single open source project with a small number of active maintainers,” Daniel Stenberg, the founder and lead developer of the open source app cURL,said Thursday. “It is not in our power to change how all these people and their slop machines work. We need to make moves to ensure our survival and intact mental health.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His comments came as cURL users complained that the move was treating the symptoms caused by AI slop without addressing the cause. The users said they were concerned the move would eliminate a key means for ensuring and maintaining the security of the tool. Stenberg largely agreed, but indicated his team had little choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In aseparate poston Thursday, Stenberg wrote: “We will ban you and ridicule you in public if you waste our time on crap reports.” Anupdateto cURL’s official GitHub account made the termination, which takes effect at the end of this month, official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cURL was first released three decades ago, under the name httpget and later urlget. It has since become an indispensable tool among admins, researchers, and security professionals, among others, for a wide range of tasks, including file transfers, troubleshooting buggy web software, and automating tasks. cURL is integrated into default versions of Windows, macOS, and most distributions of Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such a widely used tool for interacting with vast amounts of data online, security is paramount. Like many other software makers, cURL project members have relied on private bug reports submitted by outside researchers. To provide an incentive and to reward high-quality submissions, the project members have paid cash bounties in return for reports of high-severity vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last May, Stenbergsaidthe number of low-quality AI-generated reports was putting a strain on the cURL security team and was likely to metastasize, hampering other software developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“AI slop is overwhelming maintainers *today* and it won’t stop at curl but only starts there,” he said at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lead developer has also posted apagelisting some of the specious reports submitted in recent months. In response to onesuch report, a cURL project member wrote: “I think you’re a victim of LLM hallucination.” The member continued:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text has some similarities to the (bogus) CVE-2020-19909 and other reports. There are plenty of clues that Bard has manufactured bogus information: that code snippet of “curl_easy_setopt” doesn’t match the actual signature of the function (and wouldn’t even compile), a changelog that don’t match reality, and more indications that this is completely bogus. I’m curious to hear what your exploit does against a made-up vulnerability. Care to share it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the bug reporter complained and reiterated the risk posed by the non-existent vulnerability, Stenberg jumped in and wrote: “You were fooled by an AI into believing that. In what way did we not meet our end of the deal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stenberg isn’t critical of AI-assisted bug reports in all cases. In September, hepublicly applaudeda researcher for sending a “massive list” of bugs that were found using a set of AI-assisted tools. The reports had resulted in 22 bug fixes at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, Stenberg said that the reporter, Joshua Rogers, mostly used AI-powered code analyzer called ZeroPath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A clever person using a powerful tool,” Stenberg wrote. “I believe most of the worst reports we get are from people just asking an AI bot without caring or understanding much about what it reports.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, such cases seem to be the exception. AI slop has already flooded music-streaming services with so many songs—often misattributed to real artists—that the platforms are slowly becoming unusable for music discovery. cURL’s move may be an early indication that something similar is happening to bug bounty programs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/overrun-with-ai-slop-curl-scraps-bug-bounties-to-ensure-intact-mental-health/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:46:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US officially out of WHO, leaving hundreds of millions of dollars unpaid</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/us-stiffs-who-hundreds-of-millions-as-it-officially-withdrawals/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1250822831-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US did not pay $278 million in 2024–2025 dues and millions more in promised funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of today, the US is no longer a member of the World Health Organization—and it leaves the United Nations health agency with hundreds of millions of dollars in unpaid bills, according toreporting by Stat News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year ago today, the USinformed the WHOof its intent to exit, setting the clock for a one-year withdrawal period mandated in a 1948 joint resolution of Congress. But, in practice, the withdrawal was immediate, with the Trump administration cutting all ties with WHO upon the announcement. In explaining his reasoning for leaving the WHO, Trump referenced his long-standing complaints about the agency’s handling of the COVID-19 pandemic, dues payments, and alleged protection of China. Trump had attempted extract the US from WHOduring his first term, but the Biden administration rescinded the withdrawal on the first day in office, well before the one-year notice period was reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint resolution also stipulated that the US would have to pay its financial obligations in full before departing. But, that too has not been honored by the Trump administration. According to Stat, the US owed the WHO $278 million in dues, which are a percentage of each member state’s gross domestic product. That dues payment covered the country’s 2024–2025 membership, as WHO runs on a two-year budget cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, such payments were made through the State Department’s international agencies bureau. A spokesperson for the department told Stat that there was no way the US would pay its debt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The United States will not be making any payments to the WHO before our withdrawal on January 22, 2026,” the spokesperson said in an emailed statement. “The cost [borne] by the US taxpayer and US economy after the WHO’s failure during the COVID pandemic—and since—has been too high as it is. We will ensure that no more US funds are routed to this organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the US had also promised to provide $490 million in voluntary contributions for those two years. The funding would have gone toward efforts such as the WHO’s health emergency program, tuberculosis control, and the polio eradication effort, Stat reports. Two anonymous sources told Stat that some of that money was paid, but they couldn’t provide an estimate of how much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loss of both past and future financial support from the US has been a hefty blow to the WHO. Immediately upon notification last January,the WHO began cutting costs. Those included freezing recruitment, restricting travel expenditures, making all meetings virtual, limiting IT equipment updates, and suspending office refurbishment. The agency also began cutting staff and leaving positions unfilled.According to Stat, the WHO staff is on track to be down 22 percent by the middle of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent press conference, WHO Director-General Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus said the US withdrawal is a “lose-lose situation” for the US and the rest of the world. The US will lose access to infectious disease intelligence and sway over outbreak responses, and global health security will be weakened overall. “I hope they will reconsider,” Tedros said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/us-stiffs-who-hundreds-of-millions-as-it-officially-withdrawals/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 14:07:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>