<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 04:12:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Did Edison accidentally make graphene in 1879?</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/did-edison-accidentally-make-graphene-in-1879/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/edison3-1152x632.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rice University chemists replicated Thomas Edison’s seminal experiment and found a surprising byproduct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphene is the thinnest material yet known, composed of a single layer of carbon atoms arranged in a hexagonal lattice. That structure gives it many unusual properties that hold great promise for real-world applications: batteries, super capacitors, antennas, water filters, transistors, solar cells, and touchscreens, just to name a few. The physicists who first synthesized graphene in the lab won the2010 Nobel Prize in Physics. But 19th century inventor Thomas Edison may have unknowingly created graphene as a byproduct of his original experiments on incandescent bulbs over a century earlier, according to anew paperpublished in the journal ACS Nano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To reproduce whatThomas Edisondid, with the tools and knowledge we have now, is very exciting,”said co-author James Tour, a chemist at Rice University. “Finding that he could have produced graphene inspires curiosity about what other information lies buried in historical experiments. What questions would our scientific forefathers ask if they could join us in the lab today? What questions can we answer when we revisit their work through a modern lens?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edison didn’t invent the concept of incandescent lamps; there were several versions predating his efforts. However, they generally had a a very short life span and required high electric current, so they weren’t well suited to Edison’s vision of large-scale commercialization. He experimented with different filament materials starting with carbonized cardboard and compressed lampblack. This, too, quickly burnt out, as did filaments made with various grasses and canes, like hemp and palmetto. Eventually Edison discovered that carbonized bamboo made for the best filament, with life spans over 1200 hours using a 110 volt power source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucas Eddy, Tour’s  grad student at Rice, was trying to figure out ways to mass produce graphene using the smallest, easiest equipment he could manage, with materials that were both affordable and readily available. He considered such options as arc welders and natural phenomena like lightning striking trees—both of whichhe admittedwere “complete dead ends.” Edison’s light bulb, Eddy decided, would be ideal, since unlike other early light bulbs, Edison’s version was able to achieve the critical 2000 degree C temperatures required for flash Joule heating—the best method for making so-calledturbostratic graphene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, Eddy had access to Edison’s original 1879 patent describing the invention process. Eddy recreated Edison’s experiment, attaching light bulbs to a 110-volt power source and switching it on for 20 seconds at a time to rapidly heat the carbon-based material to between 2000 to 3000 degrees C. (Switch it on for any longer and you get graphite rather than graphene.) Then he examined the results using a modern optical microscope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His first attempt didn’t work out because the bulbs he bought turned out to use tungsten rather than carbon filaments. “You can’t fool a chemist,”said Eddy. “But I finally found a small art store in New York City selling artisan Edison-style light bulbs.” Those artisan bulbs used bamboo filaments, with diameters a mere 5 micrometers larger than Edison’s original filaments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, Eddy noticed that the carbon filament turned to a “lustrous silver.” Raman spectroscopy revealed that parts of the filament had turned into turbostratic graphene. The team also took before and after images usingtransmission electron microscopy. Eddy and his co-authors acknowledge that this is not definitive proof that Edison produced graphene. The inventor lacked the means to detect it even if he had been aware that such a material existed. And even if one were to analyze Edison’s original bulb, any graphene would have long since turned into graphite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors concluded by noting the research potential of revisiting other early technologies using the tools of modern materials science, such as vacuum tubes, arc lamps, and early X-ray tubes. These also may have accidentally produced unusual materials or reactions that weren’t analyzed or even noticed at the time. “Innovation can emerge from reinterpreting the past with fresh tools and new questions,” they wrote. “In the case of ‘Edison graphene,’ a 140-year-old invention continues to shed light not just literally but scientifically.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOI: ACS Nano, 2026.10.1021/acsnano.5c12759(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/did-edison-accidentally-make-graphene-in-1879/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 09:36:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Poland’s energy grid was targeted by never-before-seen wiper malware</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/wiper-malware-targeted-poland-energy-grid-but-failed-to-knock-out-electricity/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/data-wiper-malware-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Destructive payload unleashed on 10-year anniversary of Russia’s attack on Ukraine’s grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers on Friday said that Poland’s electric grid was targeted by wiper malware, likely unleashed by Russia state hackers, in an attempt to disrupt electricity delivery operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cyberattack,Reuters reported, occurred during the last week of December. The news organization said it was aimed at disrupting communications between renewable installations and the power distribution operators but failed for reasons not explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, security firm ESETsaidthe malware responsible was a wiper, a type of malware that permanently erases code and data stored on servers with the goal of destroying operations completely. After studying the tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs) used in the attack, company researchers said the wiper was likely the work of a Russian government hacker group tracked under the name Sandworm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Based on our analysis of the malware and associated TTPs, we attribute the attack to the Russia-aligned Sandworm APT with medium confidence due to a strong overlap with numerous previous Sandworm wiper activity we analyzed,” said ESET researchers. “We’re not aware of any successful disruption occurring as a result of this attack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sandworm has a long history of destructive attacks waged on behalf of the Kremlin and aimed at adversaries. Most notable was one in Ukraine inDecember 2015. It left roughly  230,000 people without electricity for about six hours during one of the coldest months of the year. The hackers used general purpose malware known as BlackEnergy to penetrate power companies’ supervisory control and data acquisition systems and, from there, activate legitimate functionality to stop electricity distribution. The incident was the first known malware-facilitated blackout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ESET said the attack targeting Poland occurred on the 10th anniversary of that event. The security firm provided few other details about the attack other than the malware used has been dubbed DynoWiper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Custom Wipers have long been a preferred tool for Russian hackers. In2022, government attackers used wiper malware dubbed AcidRain to knock out 270,000 satellite modems in Ukraine in an attempt to disrupt communications. At the time, it was the seventh wiper Russia had used against since invading the neighboring country. ESET saidlast yearthat Sandworm had unleashed multiple wipers on universities and critical infrastructure in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known case of Russia’s use of wiperscame in 2017with the release of NotPetya. The destructive worm was intended to target only Ukraine, but quickly spread around the world and wreaked havoc as it disrupted computer operations. The event is estimated to have cost governments and businesses$10 billion, making it likely the most expensive computer intrusion in history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no indication how or why DynoWiper failed to take out power. It’s possible Russia planned it to do so in an attempt to send a message without provoking Polish allies. Another possibility is that cyber defenses prevented the wiper from working as intended.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/wiper-malware-targeted-poland-energy-grid-but-failed-to-knock-out-electricity/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:08:06 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>