<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:54:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>There’s a rash of scam spam coming from a real Microsoft address</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/theres-a-rash-of-scam-spam-coming-from-a-real-microsoft-address/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/08/social-engineering-scam-call-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abusing Microsoft’s reputation may make scam harder to spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are reports that a legitimate Microsoft email address—which Microsoft explicitly says customers should add to their allow list—is delivering scam spam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emails originate from no-reply-powerbi@microsoft.com, an address tied toPower BI. The Microsoft platform provides analytics and business intelligence from various sources that can be integrated into a single dashboard.Microsoft documentationsays that the address is used to send subscription emails tomail-enabled security groups. To prevent spam filters from blocking the address, the company advises users to add it to allow lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to an Ars reader, the address on Tuesday sent her an email claiming (falsely) that a $399 charge had been made to her. It provided a phone number to call to dispute the transaction. A man who answered a call asking to cancel the sale directed me to download and install a remote access application, presumably so he could then take control of my Mac or Windows machine (Linux wasn’t allowed). The email, captured in the two screenshots below, looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online searchesreturnedadozen or soaccounts ofother peoplereporting receiving the same email. Some of the spam wasreportedon Microsoft’s own website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sarah Sabotka, a threat researcher at security firm Proofpoint, said the scammers are abusing a Power Bi function that allows external email addresses to be added as subscribers for the Power Bi reports. The mention of the subscription is buried at the very bottom of the message, where it’s easy to miss. The researcher explained:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abuse of a legitimate service, like Microsoft Power BI, adds an additional layer of credibility to the social engineering. The actual scam occurs during the voice interaction, which helps attackers evade traditional email-based detection and security controls. Further, attackers gain two advantages at once: the email is sent from a trusted Microsoft domain, and the lack of malicious links or attachments reduces the likelihood of automated filtering. While the emails originate from Microsoft infrastructure, the content and intent are fully controlled by the attacker via misuse of a legitimate feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scammers have abused Microsoft Power Bi functionality in the past. Security firm Cofensereportedin September that it found a spam campaign that transmitted phishing links that were hosted on the platform. Companies besides Microsoft that have experienced similar abuse include Google,according to Check Point. The security firm found a run of nearly 9,400 emails that were sent through the Google Cloud Application Integration platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key detail that’s currently unknown is: Do users have to explicitly opt in to receiving emails from email addresses like no-reply-powerbi@microsoft.com, and can scammers send them to any external address automatically? A Microsoft representative said he’s looking into reports and didn’t have information immediately available. For more experienced Internet users, scams like this one are easy to spot. For others, scams that originate from a known sender with a clean reputation are more believable.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/theres-a-rash-of-scam-spam-coming-from-a-real-microsoft-address/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:34:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok users “absolutely justified” for fearing MAGA makeover, experts say</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-claimed-bugs-blocked-anti-ice-videos-epstein-mentions-experts-call-bs/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/tik-tok-maga-hat-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok’s tech issues abound as censorship fears drive users to delete app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok wants users to believe that errorsblocking uploads of anti-ICE videosordirect messages mentioning Jeffrey Epsteinaredue to technical errors—not the platform seemingly shifting to censor content critical of Donald Trump after he hand-picked theUS owners who took over the applast week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, experts say that TikTok users’ censorship fears are justified, whether the bugs are to blame or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ioana Literat, an associate professor of technology, media, and learning at Teachers College, Columbia University, has studied TikTok’s politics since the app first shot to popularity in the US in 2018. She told Ars that “users’ fears are absolutely justified” and explained why the “bugs” explanation is “insufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even if these are technical glitches, the pattern of what’s being suppressed reveals something significant,” Literat told Ars. “When your ‘bug’ consistently affects anti-Trump content, Epstein references, and anti-ICE videos, you’re looking at either spectacular coincidence or systems that have been designed—whether intentionally or through embedded biases—to flag and suppress specific political content.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok users are savvy, Literat noted, and what’s being cast as “paranoia” about the app’s bugs actually stems from their “digital literacy,” she suggested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’ve watchedInstagram suppress Palestine content, they’ve seenTwitter’s transformation under Musk, they’ve experienced shadow-banning and algorithmic suppression, including on TikTok prior to this,” Literat said. “So, their pattern recognition isn’t paranoia, but rather digital literacy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casey Fiesler, an associate professor of technology ethics and internet law at the University of Colorado, Boulder, agreed that TikTok’s “bugs” explanation wasn’t enough to address users’ fears. Shetold CNNthat TikTok risks losing users’ trust the longer that errors damage the perception of the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even if this isn’t purposeful censorship, does it matter? In terms of perception and trust, maybe,” Fiesler told CNN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some users are already choosing to leave TikTok. A quick glance at theTikTok subredditshows many users grieving while vowing to delete the app, Literat pointed out, though some are reportedly struggling to delete accounts due to technical issues. Even with some users blocked from abandoning their accounts, however, “the daily average of TikTok uninstalls are up nearly 150 percent in the last five days compared to the last three months,” data analysis firm Sensor Tower told CNN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A TikTok USDS spokesperson told Ars that US owners have not yet made any changes to the algorithm or content moderation policies. So far, the only changes have been to the US app’s terms of use and privacy policy, which impacted what location data is collected, how ads are targeted, and how AI interactions are monitored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For TikTok, the top priority appears to be fixing the bugs, which were attributed to a power outage at a US data center. A TikTok USDS spokespersontold NPRthat TikTok is also investigating the issue where some users can’t talk about Epstein in DMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t have rules against sharing the name ‘Epstein’ in direct messages and are investigating why some users are experiencing issues,” TikTok’s spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok’s response came after California governor Gavin Newsom declared on X that “it’s time to investigate” TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am launching a review into whether TikTok is violating state law by censoring Trump-critical content,” Newsom said. Hispostquote-tweeted an X user who shared a screenshot of the error message TikTok displayed when some users referenced Epstein and joked, “so the agreement for TikTok to sell its US business to GOP-backed investors was finalized a few days ago,” and “now you can’t mention Epstein lmao.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday afternoon, the results of TikTok’s investigation into the “Epstein” issue were not publicly available, but TikTok may post an updatehereas technical issues are resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve made significant progress in recovering our US infrastructure with our US data center partner,” TikTok USDS’s latest statement said. “However, the US user experience may still have some technical issues, including when posting new content. We’re committed to bringing TikTok back to its full capacity as soon as possible. We’ll continue to provide updates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For TikTok’s new owners, the tech issues risk confirming fears that Trump wasn’t joking when he said he’d like to seeTikTok be tweaked to be “100 percent MAGA.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this bumpy transition, it seems likely that TikTok will continue to be heavily scrutinized once the USDS joint venture officially starts retraining the app on US data. As the algorithm undergoes tweaks, frequent TikTok users will likely be the first to pick up on subtle changes, especially if content unaligned with their political views suddenly starts appearing in their feeds when it never did before, Literat suggested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literat has researched both left- and right-leaning TikTok content. She told Ars that although left-leaning young users have for years loudly used the app to promote progressive views on topics like racial justice, gun reforms, or climate change, TikTok has never leaned one way or the other on the political spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider Christian or tradwife TikTok, Literat suggested, which grew huge platforms on TikTok alongside leftist bubbles advocating for LGBTQ+ rights or Palestine solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Political life on TikTok is organized into overlapping sub-communities, each with its own norms, humor, and tolerance for disagreement,” Literat said, adding that “the algorithm creates bubbles, so people experience very different TikToks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literat told Ars that she wasn’t surprised when Trump suggested that TikTok would be better if it were more right-wing. But what concerned her most was the implication that Trump viewed TikTok “as a potential propaganda apparatus” and “a tool for political capture rather than a space for authentic expression and connection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The historical irony is thick: we went from ‘TikTok is dangerous because it’s controlled by the Chinese government and might manipulate American users’ to ‘TikTok should be controlled by American interests and explicitly aligned with a particular political agenda,’” Literat said. “The concern was never really about foreign influence or manipulation per se—it was about who gets to do the influencing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Greene, senior counsel for the Electronic Frontier Foundation, which fought the TikTok ban law, told Ars that users are justified in feeling concerned. However, technical errors or content moderation mistakes are nearly always the most likely explanations for issues, and there’s no way to know “what’s actually happening.” He noted that lawmakers have shaped how some TikTok users view the app after insisting that they accept that China was influencing the algorithm without providing evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For years, TikTok users were being told that they just needed to follow these assumptions the government was making about the dangers of TikTok,” Greene said. And “now they’re doing the same thing, making these assumptions that it’s now maybe some content policy is being done either to please the Trump administration or being controlled by it. We conditioned TikTok users to basically to not have trust in the way decisions were made with the app.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok USDS likely wants to distance itself from Trump’s comments about making the app more MAGA. But new owners have deep ties with Trump, including Larry Ellison, the chief technology officer of Oracle, whom some critics suggest hasbenefited more than anyone else from Trump’s presidency.Greene noted that Trump’s son-in-law, Jared Kushner, is a key investor in Silver Lake. Both firms now have a 15 percent stake in the TikTok USDS joint venture, as well as MGX, which also seems to have Trump ties.CNBC reportedMGX used the Trump family cryptocurrency, World Liberty Financial, to invest $2 billion in Binance shortly before Trump pardoned Binance’s CEO from money laundering charges, which someviewed as a possible quid pro quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greene said that EFF warned during theSupreme Court fight over the TikTok divest-or-ban lawthat “all you were doing was substituting concerns for Chinese propaganda, for concerns for US propaganda. That it was highly likely that if you force a sale and the sale is up to the approval of the president, it’s going to be sold to President’s lackeys.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t see how it’d be good for users or for democracy, for TikTok to have an editorial policy that would make Trump happy,” Greene said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If suddenly, the app were tweaked to push more MAGA content into more feeds, young users who are critical of Trump wouldn’t all be brainwashed, Literat said. They would adapt, perhaps eventually finding other apps for activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, TikTok may be hard to leave behind at a time when other popular apps seem to carry their own threats of political suppression, she suggested. Beyond the video-editing features that made TikTok a behemoth of social media, perhaps the biggest sticking point keeping users glued to TikTok is “fundamentally social,” Literat said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“TikTok is where their communities are, where they’ve built audiences, where the conversations they care about are happening,” Literat said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than a mass exodus, Literat expects that TikTok’s fate could be “gradual erosion” or “death by a thousand cuts,” as users “likely develop workarounds, shift to other platforms for political content while keeping TikTok for entertainment, or create coded languages and aesthetic strategies to evade detection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CNN reported that one TikTok user already found that she could finally post an anti-ICE video after claiming to be a “fashion influencer” and speaking in code throughout the video, which criticized ICE fordetaining a 5-year-old named Liam Conejo Ramos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Fashion influencing is in my blood,” she said in the video, which featured “a photo of Liam behind her,” CNN reported. “And even a company with bad customer service won’t keep me from doing my fashion review.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short-term, Literat thinks that longtime TikTok users experiencing inconsistent moderation will continue testing boundaries, documenting issues, and critiquing the app. That discussion will perhaps chill more speech on the platform, possibly even affecting the overall content mix appearing in feeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-term, however, TikTok’s changes under US owners “could fundamentally reshape TikTok’s role in political discourse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I wouldn’t be surprised, unfortunately, if it suffers the fate of Twitter/X,” Literat said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literat told Ars that her TikTok research was initially sparked by a desire to monitor the “kind of authentic political expression the platform once enabled.” She worries that because user trust is now “damaged,” TikTok will never be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The tragedy is that TikTok genuinely was a space where young people—especially those from marginalized communities—could shape political conversations in ways that felt authentic and powerful,” Literat said. “I’m sad to say, I think that’s been irretrievably broken.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-claimed-bugs-blocked-anti-ice-videos-epstein-mentions-experts-call-bs/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:17:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Dozens of CDC vaccination databases have been frozen under RFK Jr.</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/rfk-jr-lets-cdc-vaccination-data-rot-dozens-of-databases-frozen/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/GettyImages-2201503706-1536x1024.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-vaccine Kennedy may be “enacting a self-fulfilling prophecy,” expert says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly half of the databases that public health officials at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention were updating on a monthly basis have been frozen without notice or explanation, according to astudy published in the Annals of Internal Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study—led by Janet Freilich, a law expert at Boston University, and Jeremy Jacobs, a medical professor at Vanderbilt University—examined the status of all CDC databases, finding a total of 82 that had, as of early 2025, been receiving updates at least monthly. But, of those 82, only 44 were still being regularly updated as of October 2025, with 38 (46 percent) having their updates paused without public notice or explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examining the databases’ content, it appeared that vaccination data was most affected by the stealth data freezes. Of the 38 outdated databases, 33 (87 percent) included data related to vaccination. In contrast, none of the 44 still-updated databases relate to vaccination. Other frozen databases included data on infectious disease burden, such as data on hospitalizations from respiratory syncytial virus (RSV).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common vaccination types included in the out-of-date data were vaccinations against influenza, COVID-19, and RSV. Two frozen databases included data on all three vaccines. When the researchers checked in on the databases again in December, only one had been updated, leaving 37 still entirely out of date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finding stood out given that Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. is a fervent anti-vaccine advocate who has worked for decades to undermine trust in and use of life-saving vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Given the vaccine skepticism of the Secretary of Health and Human Services, it is concerning that nearly 90 percent of the paused databases related to vaccination surveillance, with additional gaps in respiratory disease monitoring,” Freilich, Jacobs, and their co-authors write in the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, a lack of updated data can make it more difficult, if not impossible, for federal and state health officials to identify and rapidly respond to emerging outbreaks. It can also prevent the identification of communities or demographics that could benefit most from targeted vaccination outreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inan accompanying editorial, Jeanne Marrazzo, CEO of the Infectious Disease Society of America and former director of the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, stated the concern in starker terms, writing: “The evidence is damning: The administration’s anti-vaccine stance has interrupted the reliable flow of the data we need to keep Americans safe from preventable infections. The consequences will be dire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study authors note that the unexplained pauses could be direct targeting of vaccine-related data collection by the administration—or they could be an indirect consequence of the tumult Kennedy and the Trump administration have inflicted on the CDC, including brutal budget and staff cuts. But Marrazzo argues that the exact mechanism doesn’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Either causative pathway demonstrates a profound disregard for human life, scientific progress, and the dedication of the public health workforce that has provided a bulwark against the advance of emerging, and reemerging, infectious diseases,” she writes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marrazzo emphasizes that the lack of current data not only hampers outbreak response efforts but also helps the health secretary realize his vision for the CDC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kennedy, “who has stated baldly that the CDC failed to protect Americans during the COVID-19 pandemic, is now enacting a self-fulfilling prophecy. The CDC as it currently exists is no longer the stalwart, reliable source of public health data that for decades has set the global bar for rigorous public health practice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Hilliard, a spokesperson for the Department of Health and Human Services, sent Ars Technica a statement saying: “Changes to individual dashboards or update schedules reflect routine data quality and system management decisions, not political direction. Under this administration, public health data reporting is driven by scientific integrity, transparency, and accuracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/rfk-jr-lets-cdc-vaccination-data-rot-dozens-of-databases-frozen/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:28:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>