<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:12:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>This 67,800-year-old hand stencil is the world’s oldest human-made art</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/this-67800-year-old-hand-stencil-is-the-worlds-oldest-human-made-art/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Narrowed-finger-hand-stencils-from-Leang-Jarie-Maros-Sulawesi-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s oldest art has an unintentional story to tell about human exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s oldest surviving rock art is a faded outline of a hand on an Indonesian cave wall, left 67,800 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a tiny island just off the coast of Sulawesi (a much larger island in Indonesia), a cave wall bears the stenciled outline of a person’s hand—and it’s at least 67,800 years old, according to a recent study. The hand stencil is now the world’s oldest work of art (at least until archaeologists find something even older), as well as the oldest evidence of our species on any of the islands that stretch between continental Asia and Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologist Adhi Agus Oktaviana, of Indonesia’s National Research and Innovation Agency, and his colleagues have spent the last six years surveying 44 rock art sites, mostly caves, on Sulawesi’s southeastern peninsula and the handful of tiny “satellite islands” off its coast. They found 14 previously undocumented sites and used rock formations to date 11 individual pieces of rock art in eight caves—including the oldest human artwork discovered so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 67,800 years ago, someone stood in the darkness of Liang Metanduno and placed their hand flat against the limestone wall. They, or maybe a friend, then blew a mixture of pigment and water onto the wall, covering and surrounding their hand. When they pulled their hand carefully away from the rock, careful not to disturb the still-wet paint, they left behind a crisp outline of their palm and fingers, haloed by a cloud of deep red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is basically the negative of a handprint, and it’s a visceral, tangible link to the past. Someone once laid their hand on the cave wallright here, and you can still see its outline like a lingering ghost, reaching out from the other side of the rock. If you weren’t worried about damaging the already faded and fragile image, you could lay your hand in the same spot and meet them halfway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the stencil is so faded that you can barely see it, but if you look closely, it’s there: a faint halo of reddish-orange pigment, outlining the top part of a palm and the base of the fingers. A thin, nearly transparent layer of calcite covers the faded shape, left behind by millennia of water dripping down the cave wall. The ratio of uranium and thorium in a sheet of calcite suggests that it formed at least 71,000 years ago—so the outline of the hand beneath it must have been left behind sometime before that, probably around 67,800 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes Liang Metanduno the home of the oldest known artwork in the world, beating the previous contender (a Neanderthal hand stencil in Spain) by about 1,100 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These findings support the growing view that Sulawesi was host to a vibrant and longstanding artistic culture during the late Pleistocene epoch,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues in their recent paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The karst caves of Sulawesi’s southwestern peninsula, Maros-Pangkep, area treasure trove of deeply ancient artwork: hand stencils, as well asdrawings of wild animals, people, and strange figures that seem to blend the two. A cave wall at Liang Bulu’Sipong 4 featuresa 4.5-meter-long mural of humanlike figuresfacing off against wild pigs and dwarf buffalo, anda 2024 studypushed the mural’s age back to 51,200 years ago, making it the second-oldest artwork that we know of (after the Liang Metanduno hand stencil in the recent study).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists have only begun to rediscover the rock art of Maros-Pangkep in the last decade or so, and other areas of the island, like Southeast Sulawesi and its tiny satellite islands, have received even less attention—so we don’t know what’s still there waiting for humanity to find again after dozens of millennia. We also don’t know what the ancient artist was trying to convey with the outline of their hand on the cave wall, but part of the message rings loud and clear across tens of millennia: At least 67,800 years ago, someone was here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hand stencil on the wall of Liang Metanduno is, so far, the oldest evidence of our presence in Wallacea, the group of islands stretched between the continental shelves of Asia and Australia. Populating these islands is “widely considered to have involved the first planned, long-distance sea crossing undertaken by our species,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back when the long-lost artist laid their hand on the wall, sea levels were about 100 meters lower than they are today. Mainland Asia, Sumatra, and Borneo would have been high points in a single landmass, joined by wide swaths of lowlands that today lie beneath shallow ocean. The eastern shore of Borneo would have been a jumping-off point, beyond which lay several dozen kilometers of water and (out of view over the horizon) Sulawesi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first few people may have washed ashore on Sulawesi on some misadventure: lost fishermen or tsunami survivors, maybe. But at some point, people must have started making the crossing on purpose, which implies that they knew how to build rafts or boats, how to steer them, and that land awaited them on the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liang Metanduno pushes back the timing of that crossing by nearly 10,000 years. It also lends strong support to arguments that people arrived in Australia earlier than archaeologists had previously suspected. Archaeological evidence from a rock shelter called Madjedbebe, in northern Australia, suggests that people were living there by 65,000 years ago. But that evidence is still debated (such is the nature of archaeology), and some archaeologists argue that humans didn’t reach the continent until around 50,000 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With the discovery of rock art dating to at least 67,800 years ago in Sulawesi, a large island on the most plausible colonization route to Australia, it is increasingly likely that the controversial date of 65,000 years for the initial peopling of Australia is correct,” Griffith University archaeologists Adam Brumm, a coauthor of the recent study, told Ars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeologists are still trying to work out exactly when, where, and how the first members of our species made the leap from the continent of Asia to the islands of Wallacea and, eventually, via several more open-water crossings, to Australia. Our picture of the process is pieced together from archaeological finds and models of ancient geography and sea levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s been all sorts of work done on this (not by me), but often researchers consider the degree of intervisibility between islands, as well as other things like prevailing ocean currents and wind directions, changes in sea levels and how this affects the land area of islands and shorelines and so on,” Brumm said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of those models suggest that people crossed the Makassar Strait from Borneo to Sulawesi, then island-hopped through what’s now Indonesia until they reached the western edge of New Guinea. At the time, lower sea levels would have left New Guinea, Australia, and New Zealand as one big land mass, so getting from New Guinea to what’s now Australia would actually have been the easy part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a sense of deep, deep time in Liang Metanduno. The cave wall is a palimpsest on which the ancient hand stencil is nearly covered by a brown-hued drawing of a chicken, which (based on its subject matter) must have been added sometime after 5,000 years ago, when a new wave of settlers brought domesticated chickens to the island. It seems almost newfangled against the ghostly faint outline of the Paleolithic hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few centimeters away is another hand stencil, done in darker pigment and dating to around 21,500 years ago; it overlays a lighter stencil dating to around 60,900 years ago. Over tens of thousands of years, generations of people returned here with the same impulse. We have no way of knowing whether visitors 21,500 years ago, or 5,000 years ago might have seen a more vibrantly decorated cave wall than what’s preserved today—but we know that they decided to leave their mark on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the people who visited the cave 21,500 years ago shared a sense of style with the artists who left their hands outlined on the wall nearly 40,000 years before them: both handprints have slightly pointed fingers, as if the artist either turned their fingertip or just touched-up the outline with some paint after making the stencil. It’s very similar to other hand stencils, dated to around 17,000 years ago, from elsewhere on Sulawesi, and it’s a style that seems unique to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We may conclude that this regionally unique variant of stencil art is much older than previously thought,” wrote Oktaviana and his colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AndHomo sapienswasn’t the first hominin species to venture as far as Indonesia; at least 200,000 years earlier,Homo erectusmade a similar journey, leaving behind fossils and stone tools to mark that they, too, were once here. On some of the smaller islands, isolated populations ofHomo erectusstarted to evolve along their own paths, eventually leading to diminutive species likeHomo floresiensis(the O.G. hobbits) on FloresandHomo luzonensison Luzon.Homo floresiensisco-discoverer Richard Roberts has suggested thatother isolated hominin species may have existedon other scattered islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropologists haven’t found any fossil evidence of these species after 50,000 years ago, but if our species was in Indonesia by nearly 68,000 years ago, we would have been in time to meet our hominin cousins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nature, 2026. DOI:10.1038/s41586-025-09968-y(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/this-67800-year-old-hand-stencil-is-the-worlds-oldest-human-made-art/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:00:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>2026 Lucid Air Touring review: This feels like a complete car now</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/2026-lucid-air-touring-review-this-feels-like-a-complete-car-now/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/2026-Lucid-Air-Touring-1-e1768932171844-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s efficient, easy to live with, and smooth to drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life as a startup carmaker is hard—just ask Lucid Motors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When wemet the brand and its prototype Lucid Air sedan in 2017, the company planned to put the first cars in customers’ hands within a couple of years. But you know what they say about plans. A lack of funding paused everything until late 2018, when Saudi Arabia’s sovereign wealth fundbought itself a stake. A billion dollars meant Lucid could build a factory—at the cost of alienating some former fans because of the source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the pandemic happened,further pushing back timelinesas supply shortages took hold. But the Air did go on sale, and it has more recently been joined by theGravity SUV. There’s even a much more affordable midsize SUV in the works called the Earth. Sales more than doubled in 2025, and after spending a week with a model year 2026 Lucid Air Touring, I can understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now quite a few different versions of the Air to choose from. Forjust under a quarter of a million dollars, there’s the outrageously powerful Air Sapphire, which offers acceleration so rapid it’s unlikely your internal organs will ever truly get used to the experience. At the other end of the spectrum is the $70,900 Air Pure, a single-motor model that’s currently the brand’s entry point but whichalso stands as a darn good EV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time I tested a Lucid, it was the Air Grand Touring almost three years ago. That car mostly impressed me but still felt a little unfinished, especially at $138,000. This time, I looked at the Air Touring, which starts at $79,900, and the experience was altogether more polished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Touring features a less-powerful all-wheel-drive powertrain than the Grand Touring, although to put “less-powerful” into context, with 620 hp (462 kW) on tap, there are almost as many horses available as in the legendary McLaren F1. (That remains a mental benchmark for many of us of a certain age.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Touring’s 885 lb-ft (1,160 Nm) is far more than BMW’s 6-liter V12 can generate, but at 5,009 lbs (2,272 kg), the electric sedan weighs twice as much as the carbon-fiber supercar. The fact that the Air Touring can reach 60 mph (98 km/h) from a standing start in just 0.2 seconds more than the McLaren tells you plenty about how much more accessible acceleration has become in the past few decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, it will if you choose the fastest of the three drive modes, labeled Sprint. There’s also Swift, and the least frantic of the three, Smooth. Helpfully, each mode remembers your regenerative braking setting when you lift the accelerator pedal. Unlike many other EVs, Lucid does not use a brake-by-wire setup, and pressing the brake pedal will only ever slow the car via friction brakes. Even with lift-off regen set to off, the car does not coast well due to its permanent magnet electric motors, unlike the electric powertrains developed by German OEMs like Mercedes-Benz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to suggest that Lucid is doing something wrong—not with its efficiency numbers. On 19-inch aero-efficient wheels, the car has an EPA range of 396 miles (673 km) from a 92 kWh battery pack. As just about everyone knows, you won’t get ideal EV efficiency during winter, and our test with the Lucid in early January coincided with some decidedly colder temperatures, as well as larger ($1,750) 20-inch wheels. Despite this, I averaged almost 4 miles/kWh (15.5 kWh/100 km) on longer highway drives, although this fell to around 3.5 miles/kWh (17.8 kWh/100 km) in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recharging the Air Touring also helped illustrate how the public DC fast-charging experience has matured over the years. The Lucid uses the ISO 15118 “plug and charge” protocol, so you don’t need to mess around with an app or really do anything more complicated than plug the charging cable into the Lucid’s CCS1 socket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the car and charger complete their handshake, the car gives the charger account and billing info, then the electrons flow. Charging from 27 to 80 percent with a manually preconditioned battery took 36 minutes. During that time, the car added 53.3 kWh, which equated to 209 miles (336 km) of range, according to the dash. Although we didn’t test AC charging, 0–100 percent should take around 10 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit, I’m a bit of a sucker for the way the Air looks when it’s not two-tone. That’s the Stealth option ($1,750), and the dark Fathom Blue Metallic paint ($800) and blacked-out aero wheels pushed many of my buttons. I found plenty to like from the driver’s seat, too. The 34-inch display that wraps around the driver once looked massive—now it feels relatively restrained compared to the “Best Buy on wheels” effect in some other recent EVs. The fact that the display isn’t very tall helps its feeling of restraint here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle is a minimalist display for the driver, with touch-sensitive displays on either side. To your left are controls for the lights, locks, wipers, and so on. These icons are always in the same place, though there’s no tactile feedback. The infotainment screen to the right is within the driver’s reach, and it’s here that (wireless) Apple CarPlay will show up. As you can see in a photo below, CarPlay fills the irregularly shaped screen with a wallpaper but keeps its usable area confined to the rectangle in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The curved display floats above the textile-covered dash, and the daylight visible between them helps the cabin’s sense of spaciousness, even without a panoramic glass roof. A stowable touchscreen display lower down on the center console is where you control vehicle, climate, seat, and lighting settings, although there are also physical controls for temperature and volume on the dash. The relatively good overall ergonomics take a bit of a hit from the steeply raked A pillar, which creates a blind spot for the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the Air Touring’s power, it isn’t a car that goads you into using it all. In fact, I spent most of the week in the gentlest setting, Smooth. It’s an easy car to drive slowly, and the rather artificial feel of the steering at low speeds means you probably won’t take it hunting apices on back roads. I should note, though, that each drive mode has its own steering calibration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, as a daily driver and particularly on longer drives, the Touring did a fine job. Despite being relatively low to the ground, it’s easy to get into and out of. The rear seat is capacious, and the ride is smooth, so passengers will enjoy it. Even more so if they sit up front—Lucid has some of the best (optional, $3,750) massaging seats in the business, which vibrate as well as kneading you. There’s a very accessible 22 cubic foot (623 L) trunk as well as a 10 cubic foot (283 L) frunk, so it’s practical, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our test Air was fitted with Lucid’s DreamDrive Pro advanced driver assistance system ($6,750), which includes a hands-free “level 2+” assist that requires you to pay attention to the road ahead but which handles accelerating, braking, and steering. Using the turn signal tells the car to perform a lane change if it’s safe, and I found it to be an effective driver assist with an active driver monitoring system (which uses a gaze-tracking camera to ensure the driver is doing their part).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucidrolled outthe more advanced features of DreamDrive Pro last summer, and it plans to develop the system into a more capable “level 3” partially automated system that lets the driver disengage completely from the act of driving, at least at lower speeds. Although that system is some ways off—and level 3 systems are only road-legal in Nevada and California right now anyway—even the current level 2+ system leverages lidar as well as cameras, radar, and ultrasonics, and the dash display does a good job of showing you what other vehicles the Air is perceiving around it when the system is active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the model year 2026 Air feels polished, far more so than the last Lucid I drove. Designed by a refugee from Tesla, the car promised to improve on the EVs from that brand in every way. And while early Airs might have fallen short in execution, the cars can now credibly be called finished products, with much better fit and finish than a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll go so far as to say that I might have a hard time deciding between an Air or an equivalently priced Porsche Taycan were I in the market for a luxury electric four-door, even though they both offer quite different driving experiences. Be warned, though, like with the Porsche, the options can add up quickly, and the resale prices can be shockingly low.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/2026-lucid-air-touring-review-this-feels-like-a-complete-car-now/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 03:00:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tiny falcons are helping keep the food supply safe on cherry farms</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/tiny-falcons-are-helping-keep-the-food-supply-safe-on-cherry-farms/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/kestrel-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their presence appears to lower the risk of food-borne illnesses from pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every spring, raptors return to nesting sites across northern Michigan. The smallest of these birds of prey, a falcon called the American kestrel (Falco sparverius), flies through the region’s many cherry orchards and spends its days hunting for even tinier creatures to eat. This quest keeps the kestrels fed, but it also benefits the region’s cherry farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fruit farmers have been working symbiotically with kestrels for decades, adding nesting boxes and reaping the benefits of the birds eliminating the mice, voles, songbirds, and other pests that wreak havoc by feeding on not-yet-harvested crops. In addition to limiting the crop damage caused by hungry critters, new research suggests kestrels also lower the risk of food-borne illnesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, published in November in theJournal of Applied Ecology, suggests the kestrels help keep harmful pathogens off of fruit headed to consumers by eating and scaring off small birds that carry those pathogens. Orchards housing the birds in nest boxes saw fewer cherry-eating birds than orchards without kestrels on site. This translated to an 81 percent reduction in crop damage—such as bite marks or missing fruit—and a 66 percent decrease in branches contaminated with bird feces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kestrels are not very expensive to bring into orchards, but they work pretty well” at deterring unwanted bird species, said Olivia Smith, lead study author and assistant professor of horticulture at Michigan State University. “And people just like kestrels a lot, so I think it’s an attractive strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding a good strategy for managing pests is essential for cherry farmers. Pests cause expensive damage that worsens yields already impacted byother threatsto the cherry industry, such as climate change, labor shortages, and the vagaries of international trade. To stop the added damage from pests, growers have turned to nets covering their trees, noisemakers, scarecrows, pesticides, and even the removal of natural habitats around crop-growing areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, these options can be expensive and aren’t always effective. Even with these management strategies in place, birds like starlings, robins, and crows cost farms in some top cherry growing states—including Michigan, New York, Oregon, Washington, and California—about$85 million annually. For many growers, this is where the kestrels come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem counterintuitive to solve a bird problem by bringing in more birds, but kestrels are skilled hunters whose presence drives off songbirds afraid of being eaten. Habitat loss, competition for food, and climate change are leading to slow and steadypopulation declinesfor the American kestrel, losses of about1.4 percent annually. Still, these birds are abundant enough that, in many areas of the continental United States, all farmers need to do to attract them is add a nesting box to their land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve noticed a difference having the kestrels around, hovering over the spring crops,” said Brad Thatcher, a farmer based in Washington state who has housed kestrels on April Joy Farm, an organic fruit and vegetable farm, for over 13 years. “There’s very little fecal damage from small songbirds at that time of year versus the fall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With farmers who already had kestrels on their land reporting fewer songbirds and less crop damage, study authors hypothesized that food safety risks associated with pathogens birds carry may also be lower for farms harboring kestrels. To test this, the researchers evaluated 16 sweet cherry orchards in Michigan’s Leelanau and Grand Traverse counties (the latter of which is considered the “Cherry Capital of the World”). Eight of the orchards studied had nesting boxes for kestrels and eight did not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study authors randomly selected two areas of each orchard to search for crop damage and fecal contamination. The orchards frequented by kestrels saw the amount of damaged fruit drop from 2.5 percent to 0.47 percent. The number of crops contaminated by bird droppings also saw a three-fold decrease, falling from 6.88 percent to 2.33 percent. When researchers tested this excrement, they found that more than 10 percent contained campylobacter, a type of bacteria that is common in birds and causes food-borne illness in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Campylobacter is a common cause of food poisoning and ison the rise in Michiganandaround the world. It spreads to humans through food products made from, or that come into contact with, infected animals, primarily chickens and other birds. So far, only one outbreak of campylobacteriosis has beendefinitively linkedto feces from wild birds. Still, because it causes milder symptoms than some other types of bacteria, the Centers for Disease Control considers campylobacter asignificantly underreportedcause of food-borne illness that may be more common than current data indicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trying to get more birds of prey would be beneficial to farmers,” Smith said. “If you have one predator, versus a bunch of prey, you have fewer birds overall. If you have a lot fewer birds, even if the ones that are there are carrying bacteria, then you can reduce the transmission risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study’s findings that kestrels significantly reduce physical damage and food safety risks on Michigan cherry farms demonstrate that managing crops and meeting conservation goals—by bolstering local kestrel populations and eliminating the need to clear wildlife habitat around agricultural areas—can be done in tandem, study authors say. They recommend farmers facing pest-management issues consider building kestrel boxes, which cost about $100 per box and require minimal maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether nesting boxes in a given region will be successfully inhabited by kestrels depends on whether there is an abundance of the birds there. In Michigan’s cherry-growing region, kestrels are so abundant that 80 percent to 100 percent of boxes become home for kestrels rather than other nesting birds, said Catherine Lindell, avian ecologist at Michigan State University and senior author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems like this is just a great tool for farmers,” Lindell said, suggesting interested farmers “put up a couple boxes and see what happens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K.R. Callaway is a reporter and editor specializing in science, health, history, and policy stories. She is currently pursuing a master’s degree in journalism at New York University, where she is part of the Science, Health, and Environmental Reporting Program (SHERP). Her writing has appeared in Scientific American, Sky &amp; Telescope, Fast Company and Audubon Magazine, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story originally appeared onInside Climate News.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/tiny-falcons-are-helping-keep-the-food-supply-safe-on-cherry-farms/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:10:48 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>