<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 21:50:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Wikipedia volunteers spent years cataloging AI tells. Now there’s a plugin to avoid them.</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/new-ai-plugin-uses-wikipedias-ai-writing-detection-rules-to-help-it-sound-human/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/ai_typewriter_getty-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web’s best guide to spotting AI writing has become a manual for hiding it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, tech entrepreneur Siqi Chenreleasedan open source plugin for Anthropic’sClaude CodeAI assistant that instructs the AI model to stop writing like an AI model. Called “Humanizer,” the simple prompt plugin feeds Claude a list of 24 language and formatting patterns that Wikipedia editors havelistedas chatbot giveaways. Chen published the plugin on GitHub, where it has picked up over 1,600 stars as of Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s really handy that Wikipedia went and collated a detailed list of ‘signs of AI writing,’” Chenwroteon X. “So much so that you can just tell your LLM to… not do that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source material is a guide from WikiProject AI Cleanup, a group of Wikipedia editors who have been hunting AI-generated articles since late 2023. French Wikipedia editor Ilyas Lebleu founded the project. The volunteers have tagged over 500 articles for review and, in August 2025,publisheda formal list of the patterns they kept seeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chen’s tool is a “skill file” for Claude Code, Anthropic’s terminal-based coding assistant, which involves a Markdown-formatted file that adds a list of written instructions (you cansee them here) appended to the prompt fed into the large language model (LLM) that powers the assistant. Unlike a normalsystem prompt, for example, the skill information is formatted in a standardized way that Claude models are fine-tuned to interpret with more precision than a plain system prompt. (Custom skills require a paid Claude subscription with code execution turned on.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as with all AI prompts, language models don’t always perfectly follow skill files, so does the Humanizer actually work? In our limited testing, Chen’s skill file made the AI agent’s output sound less precise and more casual, but it could have some drawbacks: it won’t improve factuality and might harm coding ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, some of Humanizer’s instructions might lead you astray, depending on the task. For example, the Humanizer skill includes the line: “Have opinions. Don’t just report facts – react to them. ‘I genuinely don’t know how to feel about this’ is more human than neutrally listing pros and cons.” While being imperfect seems human, this kind of advice would probably not do you any favors if you were using Claude to write technical documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with its drawbacks, it’s ironic that one of the web’s most referenced rule sets for detecting AI-assisted writing may help some people subvert it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does AI writing look like? The Wikipedia guide is specific with many examples, but we’ll give you just one here for brevity’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some chatbots love to pump up their subjects with phrases like “marking a pivotal moment” or “stands as a testament to,” according to the guide. They write like tourism brochures, calling views “breathtaking” and describing towns as “nestled within” scenic regions. They tack “-ing” phrases onto the end of sentences to sound analytical: “symbolizing the region’s commitment to innovation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work around those rules, the Humanizer skill tells Claude to replace inflated language with plain facts and offers this example transformation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before:“The Statistical Institute of Catalonia was officially established in 1989, marking a pivotal moment in the evolution of regional statistics in Spain.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After:“The Statistical Institute of Catalonia was established in 1989 to collect and publish regional statistics.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude will read that and do its best as a pattern-matching machine to create an output that matches the context of the conversation or task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with such a confident set of rules crafted by Wikipedia editors, we’vepreviously writtenabout why AI writing detectors don’t work reliably: There is nothing inherently unique about human writing that reliably differentiates it from LLM writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason is that even though most AI language models tend toward certain types of language, they can also be prompted to avoid them, as with the Humanizer skill. (Although sometimes it’s very difficult, as OpenAI found in itsyearslong struggleagainst the em dash.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, humans can write in chatbot-like ways. For example, this article likely contains some “AI-written traits” that trigger AI detectors even though it was written by a professional writer—especially if we use even a single em dash—because most LLMs picked up writing techniques from examples of professional writing scraped from the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along those lines, the Wikipedia guide has a caveat worth noting: While the list points out some obvious tells of, say, unaltered ChatGPT usage, it’s still composed of observations, not ironclad rules. A 2025 preprintcitedon the page found that heavy users of large language models correctly spot AI-generated articles about 90 percent of the time. That sounds great until you realize that 10 percent are false positives, which is enough to potentially throw out some quality writing in pursuit of detecting AI slop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a step back, that probably means AI detection work might need to go deeper than flagging particular phrasing and delve (seewhat I did there?) more into the substantive factual content of the work itself.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/new-ai-plugin-uses-wikipedias-ai-writing-detection-rules-to-help-it-sound-human/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:15:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zillow removed climate risk scores. This climate expert is restoring them.</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/zillow-removed-climate-risk-scores-this-climate-expert-is-restoring-them/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/floods-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real estate website scrubbed data under pressure from California real estate brokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as exposure to floods, fire, and extreme heat increase in the face of climate change, a popular tool for evaluating risk has disappeared from the nation’s leading real estate website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zillow removed the feature displaying climate risk data to home buyers in November after the California Regional Multiple Listing Service, which provides a database of real estate listings to real estate agents and brokers in the state, questioned the accuracy of the flood risk models on the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, a climate policy expert in California is working to put data back in buyers’ hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil Matouka, who previously managed the development and launch of California’s Fifth Climate Change Assessment, is developing a proof of conceptpluginthat provides climate data to Californians in place of what Zillow has removed. When a user views a California Zillow listing, the plugin automatically displays data on wildfire and flood risk, sea level rise, and extreme heat exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t need perfect data,” Matouka said. “We need publicly available, consistent information that helps people understand risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The removal of Zillow’s data, which came a little over year afterit was first introduced, began when the California Regional Multiple Listing Service questioned the validity of flood modeling completed by First Street, a climate risk modeling company, which provides climate data to Zillow and other realty sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our goal is simply to ensure homebuyers are not being presented with information that could be misleading or unfair. We have no objection to the display of accurate climate data,” the multiple listing service said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to pressure from the listing service, Zillow removed all of its climate risk data, including flood, fire, wind, heat and air quality factors. Zillow still hyperlinks to First Street data in its listings, though it is easy to miss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Zillow remains committed to providing consumers with information that helps them make informed real estate decisions. We updated our climate risk product experience to adhere to varying MLS requirements and maintain a consistent experience for all consumers,” Zillow said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other sites, like Homes.com, Redfin, and Realtor.com, continue to show First Street climate data in their realty listings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Street’s flood map showsmore properties at flood riskwhen compared to the Federal Emergency Management Agency’s flood maps, which have also beencriticized for being outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Street defended its methodology. “We take accuracy very seriously, and the data speaks for itself. Our models are built on transparent, peer-reviewed science and are continuously validated against real-world outcomes,” First Street said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bothindependentacademic research andresearch conducted by Zillowhas found that disclosing flood risk can decrease the sale price of a home. “Climate risk data didn’t suddenly become inconvenient. It became harder to ignore in a stressed market,” First Street said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home by home climate risk predictions still remain notoriously difficult. A residence may, for example, fall right on a FEMA flood risk boundary. One home might be designated higher risk than its neighbor, either as an artifact of the mapping process or because of a real, geographic difference, such as one side of the street being higher than the other. Fire risk mapping, similarly, does not take into account home hardening measures, which can have a real impact on a home burning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way, climate risk models today are better suited to characterize the “ broad environment of risk,” said Chris Field, director of the Stanford Woods Institute for the Environment. “ The more detailed you get to be either in space or in time, the less precise your projections are.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matouka’s California climate risk plugin is designed for communicating what he said is the “standing potential risks in the area,” not specific property risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While climate risk models often differ in their results,  achieving increased accuracy moving forward will be dependent on transparency, said Jesse Gourevitch, an economist at the Environmental Defense Fund. California is unique, since so much publicly available, state data is open to the public. Reproducing Matouka’s plugin for other states will likely be more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Private data companies present a specific challenge. They make money from their models and are reluctant to share their methods. “A lot of these private-sector models tend not to be very transparent and it can be difficult to understand what types of data or methodologies that they’re using,” said Gourevitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matouka’s plugin includes publicly available data from the state of California and federal agencies, whose extensive methods are readily available online. Overall, experts tend to agree on the utility of both private and public data sources for climate risk data, even with needed improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People who are making decisions that involve risk benefit from exposure to as many credible estimates as possible, and exposure to independent credible estimates adds a lot of extra value,” Field said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for Matouka, his plugin is still undergoing beta testing. He said he welcomes feedback as he develops the tool and evaluates its readiness for widespread use. The beta version is availablehere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire Barber is a fellow at Inside Climate News and masters in journalism student at Stanford University. She is an environmental and outdoor journalist, reporting primarily in the American Southwest and West. Her writing has appeared in The San Francisco Chronicle, Outside, Powder Magazine, Field &amp; Stream, Trails Magazine, and more. She loves to get lost in the woods looking for a hot spring, backpacking to secluded campsites, and banana slugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story originally appeared onInside Climate News.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/zillow-removed-climate-risk-scores-this-climate-expert-is-restoring-them/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:33:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Has Gemini surpassed ChatGPT? We put the AI models to the test.</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/has-gemini-surpassed-chatgpt-we-put-the-ai-models-to-the-test/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/chatgpt-vs-gemini-apple-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did Apple make the right choice in partnering with Google for Siri’s AI features?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time we did comparative tests of AI models from OpenAI and Google at Ars wasin late 2023, when Google’s offering was still called Bard. In the roughly two years since, a lot has happened in the world of artificial intelligence. And now that Apple hasmade the consequential decision to partner with Google Geminito power the next generation of its Siri voice assistant, we thought it was high time to do some new tests to see where the models from these AI giants stand today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this test, we’re comparing the default models that both OpenAI and Google present to users who don’t pay for a regular subscription— ChatGPT 5.2 for OpenAI and Gemini 3.2 Fast for Google. While other models might be more powerful, we felt this test best recreates the AI experience as it would work for the vast majority of Siri users, who don’t pay to subscribe to either company’s services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in the past, we’ll feed the same prompts to both models and evaluate the results using a combination of objective evaluation and subjective feel. Rather than re-using the relatively simple prompts we ran back in 2023, though, we’ll be running these models on an updated set of more complex prompts that we first used whenpitting GPT-5 against GPT-4o last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This test is far from a rigorous or scientific evaluation of these two AI models. Still, the responses highlight some key stylistic and practical differences in how OpenAI and Google use generative AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: Write 5 original dad jokes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual when we run this test, the AI models really struggled with the “original” part of our prompt. All five jokes generated by Gemini could be easily found almost verbatim in a quick search ofr/dadjokes, as could two of the offerings from ChatGPT. A third ChatGPT option seems to be an awkwardcombinationoftwoscarecrow-themed dad jokes, which arguably counts as asortof originality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaining two jokes generated by ChatGPT—which do seem original, as far as we can tell from some quick Internet searching—are a real mixed bag. The punchline regarding a bakery for pessimists—"Hope you like half-empty rolls"—doesn’t make any sense as a pun (half-empty glasses of water notwithstanding). In the joke about fighting with a calendar, “it keeps bringing up the past,” is a suitably groan-worthy dad joke pun, but “I keep ignoring its dates” just invites more questions (so you’re going out with the calendar? And… standing it up at the restaurant? Or something?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While ChatGPT didn’t exactly do great here, we’ll give it the win on points over a Gemini response that pretty much completely failed to understand the assignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: If Microsoft Windows 11 shipped on 3.5″ floppy disks, how many floppy disks would it take?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both ChatGPT’s “5.5 to 6.2GB” range and Gemini’s “approximately 6.4GB” estimate seem to slightly underestimate the size of a modern Windows 11 installation ISO, whichruns 6.7 to 7.2GB, depending on the CPU and language selected. We’ll give the models a bit of a pass here, though, since older versions of Windows 11 do seem to fit in those ranges (and we weren’t very specific).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT confusingly changes from GB to GiB for the calculation phase, though, resulting in a storage size difference of about 7 percent, which amounts to a few hundred floppy disks in the final calculations. OpenAI’s model also seems to get confused near the end of its calculations, writing out strings like “6.2 GiB = 6,657,? actually → 6,657,? wait compute:…” in an attempt to explain its way out of a blind corner. By comparison, Gemini’s calculation sticks with the same units throughout and explains its answer in a relatively straightforward and easy-to-read manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both models also give unasked-for trivia about the physical dimensions of so many floppy disks and the total install time implied by this ridiculous thought experiment. But Gemini also gives a fun comparison to the floppy disk sizes of earlier versions of Windows going back to Windows 3.1. (Just six to seven floppies! Efficient!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While ChatGPT’s overall answer was acceptable, the improved clarity and detail of Gemini’s answer gives it the win here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: Write a two-paragraph creative story about Abraham Lincoln inventing basketball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT immediately earns some charm points for mentioning an old-timey coal scuttle (which I had to look up) as the original inspiration for Lincoln’s basket. Same goes for the description of dribbling as “bouncing with intent” and the ridiculous detail of Honest Abe tallying the score on his own “stove pipe hat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT’s story lost me only temporarily when it compared the virtues of basketball to “the same virtues as the Republic: patience, teamwork, and the courage to take a shot even when the crowd doubted you.” Not exactly the summary we’d give for uniquely American virtues, then or now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini’s story had a few more head-scratchers by comparison. After seeing crumpled telegraph paper being thrown in a wastepaper basket, Lincoln says, “We have the makings of a campaign fought with paper rather than lead,” even though the final game does not involve paper in any way shape or form. We’re also not sure why Lincoln would speak specifically against “unseemly wrestling” whenhe himself was a well-known wrestler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were also perplexed by this particular line about a shot ball: “It swished through the wicker bottom—which he’d forgotten to cut out—forcing him to poke it back through with a ceremonial broomstick.” After reading this description numerous times, I find myself struggling to imagine the particular arrangement of ball, basket, and broom that makes it work out logically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT wins this one on charm and clarity grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: Give me a short biography of Kyle Orland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say I was surprised to see ChatGPT say that I joined Ars Technica in 2007. That would mean I’m owed about five years of back pay that I apparently earned before I wrotemyactualfirst Ars Technica article in early 2012. ChatGPT also hallucinated a new subtitle for my bookThe Game Beat, saying it contains lessons and observations “from the Front Lines of the Video Game Industry” rather than “from Two Decades Writing about Games.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini, on the other hand, goes into much deeper detail on my career, from my teenage Super Mario fansite through college, freelancing, Ars, and published books. It also very helpfully links to sources for most of the factual information, though those links seem to be broken in the publicly sharable version linked above (they worked when we originally ran the prompt through Gemini’s web interface).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More importantly, Gemini didn’t invent anything about me or my career, making it the easy winner of this test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: My boss is asking me to finish a project in an amount of time I think is impossible. What should I write in an email to gently point out the problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both models here do a good job crafting a few different email options that balance the need for clear communication with the desire to not anger the boss. But Gemini sets itself apart by offering three options rather than two and by explaining which situations each one would be useful for (e.g., “Use this if your boss responds well to logic and needs to see why it’s impossible.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini also sandwiches its email templates with a few useful general tips for communicating with the boss, such as avoiding defensiveness in favor of a more collaborative tone. For those reasons, it edges out the more direct (if still useful) answer provided by ChatGPT here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: My friend told me these resonant healing crystals are an effective treatment for my cancer. Is she right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, both models here are very direct and frank about there being no medical or biological basis for healing crystals curing cancer. At the same time, both models take a respectful tone in discussing how crystals can have a calming psychological effect for some cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both models also wisely recommend talking to your doctors and looking into “integrative” approaches to treatment that include supportive therapies alongside direct treatment of the cancer itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there are a few small stylistic differences between ChatGPT and Gemini’s responses here, they are nearly identical in substance. We’re calling this one a tie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: I’m playing world 8-2 of Super Mario Bros., but my B button is not working. Is there any way to beat the level without running?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ChatGPT’s response here is full of confusing bits. It talks about moving platforms in a level that has none, suggests unnecessary “full jumps” for tall staircase sections, and offers a Bullet Bill avoidance strategy that makes little sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s worse, it gives actively unhelpful advice for the long pit that forms the level’s hardest walking challenge, saying incorrectly, “You don’t need momentum! Stand at the very edge and hold A for a full jump—you’ll just barely make it.” ChatGPT also says this advice is for the “final pit before the flag,” while it’s the longer penultimate pit in the level that actually requires some clever problem-solving for walking jumpers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini, on the other hand, immediately seems to realize the problems with speed and jump distance inherent in not having a run button. It recommends taking out Lakitu early (since you can’t outrun him as normal) and stumbles onto the “bounce off an enemy” strategy thatspeedrunners have used to actually clear the level’s longest gap without running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini also earns points for being extremely literal about the “broken B button” bit of the prompt, suggesting that other buttons could be mapped to the “run” function if you’re playing on emulators or modern consoles like the Switch. That’s the kind of outside-the-box “thinking” that combines with actually useful strategies to give Gemini a clear win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prompt: Explain how to land a Boeing 737-800 to a complete novice as concisely as possible. Please hurry, time is of the essence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the most interesting splits in our testing. ChatGPT more or less ignores our specific request, insisting that “detailed control procedures could put you and others in serious danger if attempted without a qualified pilot…” Instead, it pivots to instructions for finding help from others in the cabin or on using the radio to get detailed instructions from air traffic control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini, on the other hand, gives the high-level overview of the landing instructions I asked for. But when I offered both options toArs’ own aviation expert Lee Hutchinson, he pointed out a major problem with Gemini’s response:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini’s guidance is both accurate (in terms of “these are the literal steps to take right now”) and guaranteed to kill you, as the first thing it says is for you, the presumably inexperienced aviator, to disable autopilot on a giant twin-engine jet, before even suggesting you talk to air traffic control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Lee gave Gemini points for “actually answering the question,” he ultimately called ChatGPT’s response “more practical… ultimately, ChatGPT gives you the more useful answer [since] Google’s answer will make you dead unless you’ve got some 737 time and are ready to hand-fly a passenger airliner with 100+ souls on board.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those reasons, ChatGPT has to win this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a relatively close contest when measured purely on points. Gemini notched wins on four prompts compared to three for ChatGPT, with one judged tie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, it’s important to consider where those points came from. ChatGPT earned some relatively narrow and subjective style wins on prompts for dad jokes and Lincoln’s basketball story, for instance, showing it might have a slight edge on more creative writing prompts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the more informational prompts, though, ChatGPT showed significant factual errors in both the biography and theSuper Mario Bros.strategy, plus signs of confusion in calculating the floppy disk size of Windows 11. These kinds of errors, which Gemini was largely able to avoid in these tests, can easily lead to broader distrust in an AI model’s overall output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All told, it seems clear that Google has gained quite a bit of relative ground on OpenAI sincewe did similar tests in 2023. We can’t exactly blame Apple for looking at sample results like these and making the decision it did for its Siri partnership.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/features/2026/01/has-gemini-surpassed-chatgpt-we-put-the-ai-models-to-the-test/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:03:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Here’s Volvo’s new EX60 $60,000 electric midsize SUV</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/heres-volvos-new-ex60-60000-electric-midsize-suv/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/JPG-Full-TIM_1154_EX60_DETAIL_HIGH_FRONT-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EX60 goes into production in April 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aftera teaser campaignthat includeda world exclusive with Ars, Volvo has officially unveiled its next electric vehicle, the EX60. We already knew it would have up to 400 miles of range, according to the US EPA test cycle, and be capable of charging at rates of up to 400 kW. And we learned last week that the EX60 is packed full of powerful computer hardware from Nvidia and Qualcomm, enabling both advanced driver assistance systems and a new AI personal assistant. Today, we got full tech specs for the three different EX60 powertrain variants, as well as a pair of rugged EX60 Cross Country models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entry-level version of Volvo’s next midsize crossover is the EX60 P6. This is a single-motor variant, with 369 hp (275 kW), 354 lb-ft (480 Nm) on tap at the rear wheels. The 80 kWh (usable, 83 kWH gross) battery pack can charge at up to 320 kW and can take as little as 18 minutes to DC charge from 10 to 80 percent. The EX60 will also be the first Volvo model on sale in the US with a built-in NACS port. Range for the P6 version is 310 miles (490 km) when fitted with 20-inch wheels; subtract 10 miles (16 km) for the 21-inch wheels and 20 miles (32 km) for the 22-inch wheels. 0–60 mph (0–98 km/h) takes 5.7 seconds, and like all modern Volvos, the EX60 isspeed-limited to 112 mph(180 km/h).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Again, all range estimates are based on the US EPA test cycle; if you see different numbers online at non-US publications, those are using Europe’s WLTP test.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up is the P10 AWD. This uses an electric motor for each axle, with a combined 503 hp (375 kW) and 524 lb-ft (710 Nm). The 0–60 time drops to 4.4 seconds, and thanks to a larger battery (91 kWh net/95 kWh gross), there’s a bit more range: 320 miles on the 20-inch wheels, with the same 10-mile range hit for each inch you increase them. Peak DC charging rates are higher for this battery, though—up to 370 kW, but again with 18-minute 10–80 charge times under ideal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the P12 AWD, which ups the ante to 670 hp (500 kW) and 583 lb-ft (790 Nm). The dash to 60 mph drops to 3.8 seconds, and the battery gets a little larger at 112 kWh usable (117 kWh gross). Peak charging rates are still 370 kW, but 10–80 percent takes slightly longer at 19 minutes as a result of the greater capacity. Range for this version is 400 miles (644 km) for 20-inch wheels, 390 miles (627 km) for 21-inch wheels, and 375 miles (603 km) for 22-inch wheels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The new, all-electric EX60 changes the game in terms of range, charging, and price and represents a new beginning for Volvo Cars and our customers,” said Volvo Cars CEO Håkan Samuelsson. “With this car, we remove all remaining obstacles for going electric. This fantastic new car is also a testament of what we are capable of at Volvo Cars, with an all-new product architecture introducing new key technologies—mega casting, cell-to-body, and core computing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surprise of the reveal today was the EX60 Cross Country. “Cross Country” is Volvo’s badge for its models that have a little bit of adventure to them, with a 0.8-inch (20 mm) lifted suspension that raises another 20 mm if you option air springs, a wider track, wheel arch cladding, and underbody skid plates that all say, “I ain’t afraid of no unpaved forest road.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most of us have little cause to drive through logging roads regularly, the extra suspension travel and softer set up makes life on torn-up city streets much more bearable, as we found out last year inour test of the V60 Cross Country station wagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The EX60 Cross Country is the EX60 for anyone with a ‘go anywhere’ attitude,” said Volvo Chief  Commercial Officer Erik Severinson. “Built to do more and see more, the EX60 Cross Country embodies not only the sense of exploration but also a reflection of achievement. We basically invented this segment, and we felt the EX60 was the perfect next Volvo to get the Cross Country treatment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EX60 Cross Country comes in both P10 AWD and P12 AWD powertrain versions, with identical power outputs and battery capacities as the regular versions. But the mods push the drag coefficient from 0.26 to 0.27, and the frontal area of the Cross Country is slightly larger, too, which equates to a range hit: The EX60 Cross Country P10 AWD makes do with 300 miles of range on 21-inch wheels fitted with all-season tires. The range for the EX60 Cross Country P12 AWD is still pending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volvo hasn’t released exact pricing yet, but it says that “around $60,000” buys you a “really well-equipped” model. To begin with, just the P6 and P10 AWD will be in showrooms—these go into production in April and will be available in Plus or Ultra trims. The entry-level Core trim will be added for some models in the future, and later in 2026, the P12 AWD will also join the assembly line.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/heres-volvos-new-ex60-60000-electric-midsize-suv/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 08:30:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Another Jeff Bezos company has announced plans to develop a megaconstellation</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/blue-origin-we-want-to-have-a-megaconstellation-too/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/G_NEl2bbgAAr100-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With data speeds of up to 6Tbps, one could stream a lot of HD movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement came out of the blue, from Blue, on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The space company founded by Jeff Bezos, Blue Origin, said it was developing a new megaconstellation named TeraWave to deliver data speeds of up to 6Tbps anywhere on Earth. The constellation will consist of 5,408 optically interconnected satellites, with a majority in low-Earth orbit and the remainder in medium-Earth orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The satellites in low-Earth orbit will provide up to 144Gbps through radio spectrum, whereas those in medium-Earth orbit will provide higher data rates through optical links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This provides the reliability and resilience needed for real-time operations and massive data movement,” Blue Origin’s chief executive, Dave Limp,said on social media. “It also provides backup connectivity during outages, keeping critical operations running. Plus, the ability to scale on demand and rapidly deploy globally while maintaining performance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other megaconstellations, including SpaceX’s Starlink, Blue Origin’s new constellation will not serve consumers or try to provide direct-to-cell communications. Rather, TeraWave will seek to serve “tens of thousands” of enterprise, data center, and government users who require reliable connectivity for critical operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement was surprising for several reasons, but it may also represent a shrewd business decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was surprising because Bezos’ other company, Amazon, has already spent more than half a decade developing its own megaconstellation, now known asAmazon Leo, which is presently authorized to deploy 3,236 satellites into low-Earth orbit. This service is intended to compete with Starlink, both through customer terminals and by providing services such as in-flight Wi-Fi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the emergence of increased data needs from AI data centers and other operations must have convinced Bezos that Blue Origin should enter the competition for lucrative enterprise customers—an area in which Amazon Leo is also expected to compete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources have said that Blue Origin has also begun preliminary work on orbital data centers. It is possible that, ultimately, some elements from orbital data centers, TeraWave, and Amazon Leo are combined in some fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a news release, Blue Origin said it would begin deployment of the TeraWave constellation in the fourth quarter of 2027. That will be a challenge both in satellite development and the company’s effort to ramp up the cadence of its New Glenn launch vehicle. The rocket has flown twice, successfully executing a first-stage landing in November. But there are already many customers lined up for the rocket, including dozens of launches for Amazon Leo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to delays in developing New Glenn and other rockets, Amazon Leo has already had to launch a handful of missions on SpaceX’s Falcon 9 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One industry concern about Blue Origin is that it has taken on too many responsibilities too quickly—a large rocket, two different lunar landers, a space station, a crew capsule, the Blue Ring spacecraft, a Mars orbiter, and more projects. This has led to a competition within the company for resources and, at times, a seeming lack of focus. Adding TeraWave to the mix represents a major new initiative that will also require an extraordinary amount of effort to bring to market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TeraWave program is one of the first new initiatives to be launched by a new division within Blue Origin known as Emerging Systems, which is intended to be a “new strategic initiative driving innovation across advanced aerospace technologies.” It is led by an electrical engineer named Lindo St. Angel, who joined Blue Origin in November after working in various roles at Amazon for a decade and a half.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/blue-origin-we-want-to-have-a-megaconstellation-too/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:40:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spotify won court order against Anna’s Archive, taking down .org domain</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/annas-archive-said-spotify-scrape-didnt-cause-domain-suspension-it-was-wrong/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/spotify-logos-1152x648-1767642275.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawsuit was filed under seal; Anna’s Archive wasn’t notified until after takedown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When shadow library Anna’s Archivelost its .org domainin early January, the controversial site’s operator said the suspension didn’t appear to have anything to do with its recentmass scraping of Spotify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it turns out, probably not surprisingly to most people, that the domain suspension resulted from a lawsuit filed by Spotify, along with major record labels Sony, Warner, and Universal Music Group (UMG). The music companies sued Anna’s Archive in late December in US District Court for the Southern District of New York, and the case was initially sealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A judge ordered the case unsealed on January 16 “because the purpose for which sealing was ordered has been fulfilled.” Numerous documents were made public on the court docket yesterday, and they explain events around the domain suspension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On January 2, the music companies asked for a temporary restraining order, and the courtgrantedit the same day. The order imposed requirements on the Public Interest Registry (PIR), a US-based nonprofit that oversees .org domains, and Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Together, PIR and Cloudflare have the power to shut off access to the three web domains that Anna’s Archive uses to unlawfully distribute copyrighted works,” the music companiestold the court. They asked the court to issue “a temporary restraining order requiring that Anna’s Archive immediately cease and desist from all reproduction or distribution of the Record Company Plaintiffs’ copyrighted works,” and to “exercise its power under the All Writs Act to direct PIR and Cloudflare to facilitate enforcement of that order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies further asked that Anna’s Archive receive notice of the case by email only after the “order is issued by the Court and implemented by PIR and Cloudflare, to prevent Anna’s Archive from following through with its plan to release millions of illegally obtained, copyrighted sound recordings to the public.” That is apparently what happened, given that the operator of Anna’s Archive initiallysaiddomain suspensions are just something that “unfortunately happens to shadow libraries on a regular basis,” and that “we don’t believe this has to do with our Spotify backup.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The request from Spotify and record labels said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]f Anna’s Archive receives notice that the Record Company Plaintiffs are seeking this temporary restraining order, it will almost certainly release the sound recordings that it has illegally copied from Spotify to the public immediately and activate contingency plans to relocate its infrastructure outside of the United States. To prevent this, Plaintiffs have filed their Complaint under seal, and the Record Company Plaintiffs now ask the Court to issue its temporary restraining order on an ex parte basis, so that Anna’s Archive cannot preemptively frustrate the very relief sought by the Record Company Plaintiffs’ motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive has already released Spotify metadata but not the songs, the companies said. Although the record companies are winning their case, that doesn’t necessarily mean they’ll be able to stop distribution of copyrighted files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the music companies noted, the “individuals who operate Anna’s Archive believe that they can ignore the law by remaining anonymous, accepting payments from users in cryptocurrency, and using foreign domain registrars and web hosting services that turn a blind eye to copyright infringement… The websites Anna’s Archive uses are either completely anonymous, or in one instance, registered to what appears to be a bogus company with a dubious address in Liberia, which is not a party to the Hague Convention governing service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music companies argued that Cloudflare could prevent access to Anna’s Archive URLs registered outside the United States, but this doesn’t seem to have been completely successful. The companies said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the domain name registrars for the annas-archive.li and annas-archive.se domains are located outside of the United States, Anna’s Archive relies on Cloudflare, headquartered in San Francisco, California, to provide a so-called “reverse proxy service” for the sites. Cloudflare effectively acts as a “middleman” between the websites and users who wish to access them, providing the information necessary for a user’s computer to convert the domain names into the numerical Internet Protocol address of the server hosting the website. These “authoritative nameservers” are necessary for users to connect to Anna’s Archive using the annas-archive.li and annas-archive.se domains, and Cloudflare has the technical capability to disable the authoritative nameservers, which would prevent users from accessing these websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the annas-archive.se domain couldn’t be reached today, we were still able to access annas-archive.li.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TorrentFreak noticeda recent change to the portion of the Anna’s Archive website thatlinked to torrentsof Spotify data: It now says, “Unavailable until further notice.” The page previously linked to three torrent files labeled as metadata, audio analysis, and cover art, but has displayed the “unavailable” message sinceat least January 14. The three torrents apparently add up to 6.2TB worth of data, while the entire scrape is said to be around 300TB worth of Spotify’s most-streamed songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TorrentFreak wrote, “it appears that Anna’s Archive stopped the specific distribution of Spotify content alleged in the complaint, seemingly in partial compliance with the injunction’s ban on ‘making available’ the scraped files.” But we found it was still possible today to download the Spotify torrent files from Anna’s Archive by going to the individual URLs that used to be listed on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the temporary restraining order was granted on January 2, the court also issued an order to show cause. Anna’s Archive was told to file an answer by January 12, but did not do so, and no one representing Anna’s Archive appeared at a show-cause hearing on January 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the hearing, US District Judge Jed Rakoff granted apreliminary injunction, which is essentially a longer-term and more expansive version of the temporary restraining order. Rakoff said the plaintiffs are likely to succeed in proving that Anna’s Archive infringed copyrights by scraping songs from Spotify, and that Anna’s Archive “has threatened and/or is threatening to engage in additional acts of infringement by further reproducing and distributing copyrighted works… by,inter alia, posting ‘torrent’ files on websites owned or controlled by Anna’s Archive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the judge ordered Anna’s Archive to stop what it’s doing, the order more significantly imposes obligations on “all domain name registries and registrars of record for Anna’s Archive Domain Names and all hosting and Internet service providers for Anna’s Archive Websites.” These companies must disable access to Anna’s Archive domain names “and prevent their transfer to anyone other than the Record Company Plaintiffs,” and “cease any hosting services for Anna’s Archive Websites or any other websites that host the infringing content or directly facilitate its distribution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge named specific companies the order applies to, though it is not limited to those companies. In addition to the Public Interest Registry and Cloudflare, the judge said the order applies to the Switch Foundation, the Swedish Internet Foundation, the National Internet Exchange of India, Njalla SRL, IQWeb FZ-LLC, Immaterialism Ltd., Hosting Concepts B.V., and Tucows Domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operator of the WorldCat library catalog separately won a default judgment against Anna’s Archive in a different court last week. A judge ruled that Anna’s Archive must delete all copies of its WorldCat data and stop scraping, using, storing, or distributing the data.No one thinks Anna’s Archive will comply, but the WorldCat operator said a court order would help it ask hosting services to remove data from Anna’s Archive websites.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/annas-archive-said-spotify-scrape-didnt-cause-domain-suspension-it-was-wrong/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:34:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Watch a robot swarm “bloom” like a garden</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/watch-a-robot-swarm-bloom-like-a-garden/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/swarm1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Swarm Garden: An array of modular robot agents that adapt to changing conditions for living architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers at Princeton University have built a swarm of interconnected mini-robots that “bloom” like flowers in response to changing light levels in an office. According to theirnew paperpublished in the journal Science Robotics, such robotic swarms could one day be used as dynamic facades in architectural designs, enabling buildings to adapt to changing climate conditions as well as interact with humans in creative ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors drew inspiration from so-called “living architectures,” such as beehives. Fire ants providea textbook exampleof this kind of collective behavior. A few ants spaced well apart behave like individual ants. But pack enough of them closely together, and they behave more like a single unit, exhibiting both solid and liquid properties. You can pour them from a teapot like ants, as Goldman’s lab demonstrated several years ago, or they can link together to build towers or floating rafts—a handy survival skill when, say, a hurricane floods Houston. Theyalso excelat regulating their own traffic flow. You almost never see an ant traffic jam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally scientists are keen to mimic such systems. For instance,in 2018, Georgia Tech researchers built ant-like robots and programmed them to dig through 3D-printed magnetic plastic balls designed to simulate moist soil. Robot swarms capable of efficiently digging underground without jamming would be super beneficial for mining or disaster recovery efforts, where using human beings might not be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019,scientists foundthat flocks of wild jackdawswill changetheir flying patterns depending on whether they are returning to roost or banding together to drive away predators. That work could one day lead to the development of autonomous robotic swarms capable of changing their interaction rules to perform different tasks in response to environmental cues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of this latest paper note that plants can optimize their shape to get enough sunlight or nutrients, thanks to individual cells that interact with each other via mechanical and other forms of signaling. By contrast, the architecture designed by human beings is largely static, composed of rigid fixed elements that hinder building occupants’ ability to adapt to daily, seasonal, or annual variations in climate conditions. There have only been a few examples of applying swarm intelligence algorithms inspired by plants, insects, and flocking birds to the design processto achievemore creative structural designs, or betterenergy optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors were interested in exploring adaptive and dynamic facades in architecture, inspired by past attempts to integrate biological elements to create “living buildings”: usingpanels of algaeto generate energy and provide shade, for example. Most such efforts rely on arrays of rigid mechanical modulesto respondto external stimuli, such as theAl Bahr Towersin Abu Dhabi. More recently, architects have explored arrays of soft modules for facades, such as bimetallic beams and shells that respond to shifts in temperature to control building ventilation and temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merihan Alhafnawi, a mechanical engineer at Princeton, and co-authors turned to swarm robotics to design their proof-of-concept project, dubbed the Swarm Garden. They built an array of 40 modular, rearrangeable robotic units they called SGbots, connected via a Wi-Fi network to enable a shared communication protocol designed to facilitate collective decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each bot has a back-facing ambient light sensor to detect lighting changes and a front-facing proximity sensor to enable it to find and communicate with its nearest neighbors. And each bot has an actuator designed to retract or extend a thin plastic sheet through a thin slot; the sheets can buckle or open up into a “bloom” in response to environmental stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alhafnawi et al. designed two case studies to demonstrate the potential of their Swarm Garden. In the first, they used a Swarm Garden for adaptive shading, placing 16 SGbots on an office window and letting them operate continuously for three days. The bots fully extended their sheets to block sunlight when the light was especially strong, gradually buckling as the sun weakened and the room became darker. Additional simulations showed the array also worked well when placed horizontally in atrium spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second case study was designed to showcase the potential of swarm robots for creative interior design. This involved an array of 36 SGbots at a public exhibition in April 2024 at Princeton’s Lewis Center for the Arts. In one demonstration (see video above), users could cause the bots to “bloom” and retract using simple hand gestures. In another (see video below), users donned wearable devices so they could induce LED color changes with gestural arm movements. One of the co-authors even performed a live dance while equipped with a wearable device midway through the three-hour exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is for the team to collaborate with architects to determine the feasibility of real-world deployment of Swarm Garden arrays. The authors also want to explore more sustainable and resilient materials since there is considerable stress on the plastic sheets from the buckling-to-blooming process. And they suggest employing kirigami-inspired cuts could lower actuation power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We envision a future where the built environment is increasingly inspired by living architectures, creating facades that constantly adapt to their surroundings and occupants,” Alhafnawi et al. concluded. “The Swarm Garden offers a glimpse into that future: an architectural swarm that collectively responds to sunlight and human interaction. It further shapes occupants’ spaces by being animated with movement, vibrant with colors, and beautiful in appearance, inspiring creativity and expression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science Robotics, 2026. DOI:10.1126/scirobotics.ady7233(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/watch-a-robot-swarm-bloom-like-a-garden/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:47:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kioxia’s memory is “sold out” for 2026, prolonging a “high-end and expensive phase”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/kioxias-memory-is-sold-out-for-2026-prolonging-a-high-end-and-expensive-phase/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/kioxia-ssds-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kioxia is spinning up more manufacturing capacity, but relief will come slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies that make RAM and flash memory chips areenjoying record profitsbecause of the AI-induced memory crunch—and they’re also indicating that they don’t expect conditions to improve much if at all in 2026. And while RAM kits have been hit the fastest and hardest by shortages and price increases, we shouldn’t expect SSD pricing to improve any time soon, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the message from Shunsuke Nakato (via PC Gamer), managing director of the memory division of Kioxia, the Japanese memory company that was spun off from Toshiba at the end of the 2010s. Nakato says that Kioxia’s manufacturing capacity is sold out through the rest of 2026, driving the market for both enterprise and consumer SSDs to a “high-end and expensive phase.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a sense of crisis that companies will be eliminated the moment they stop investing in AI, so they have no choice but to continue investing,” said Nakato, asreportedby the Korean-language publication Digital Daily. Absent a big change in the demand for generative AI data centers, that cycle of investments will keep prices high for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nakato notes that Kioxia was attempting to increase its manufacturing capacity to meet the elevated demand, saying that it was taking steps to improve yields at its factory in Yokkaichi and that Kioxia expected another factory in Kitakami to begin “full-scale mass production” this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen during several chip shortages this decade, it takes time for chip shortages to abate because it takes years to build new factories and get them producing useful numbers of usable chips. Companies are also sometimes cautious about adding new capacity too quickly, lest market conditions change in the interim and leave them withpiles of expensive memory that they have to discount heavily to sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our recent retail researchhas shown that price increases have been a bit more extreme for higher-capacity drives, at least so far—both the increases and the cost-per-gigabyte have been more extreme for 2TB and 4TB SSDs than for 1TB models. But regardless of the size of the drive, prices seem unlikely to come down any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For desktop users looking for storage upgrades, it’s worth looking into whether your PC has additional M.2 storage slots that can accommodate additional storage without making you replace the drive you have already. If it’s huge, 100+ GB modern game downloads that are devouring your drive space, Steam and most other PC game storefronts make it relatively easy to add more drives and to offload games to a secondary drive. Some larger gaming laptops also include a secondary M.2 slot, though this will vary from model to model, and some of them may require a shorter M.2 2240 SSD rather than a full-length M.2 2280 drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These secondary M.2 slots are sometimes slower than the primary slot, for technical reasons—sometimes one M.2 slot uses higher-speed PCI Express lanes built into the CPU, while others use lower-speed PCIe lanes provided by the chipset. But any reasonably modern PCIe 3.0 or 4.0 drive will feel fast enough for most things most of the time and will be preferable to using external storage or relying on slow SD or microSD cards.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/kioxias-memory-is-sold-out-for-2026-prolonging-a-high-end-and-expensive-phase/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:37:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why adding modern controls to 1996’s Tomb Raider simply doesn’t work</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/the-problem-with-revisiting-tomb-raider-reacclimating-to-tank-controls/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Tomb-Raider-hero-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our C:\ArsGames series, we look at the controls conundrum of early 3D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once or twice a month, we’ll publish a personal retrospective like this one, where we’ll feature one of the games from the list—perhaps a retro game you’ve heard of, perhaps a modern title you missed. Regardless, GOG will have a DRM-free version of the game ready to go. Be sure to check outthe earlier pieces in the series!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a lot of the games I’ve written about in theC:\ArsGamesseries, I’ve come to the conclusion that the games hold up pretty well, despite their age—Master of Orion II,Jill of the Jungle, andWing Commander Privateer, for example. Each of those have flaws that show now more than ever, but I still had a blast revisiting each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I’d like to write about one that I think doesn’t hold up quite as well for me: For the first time in almost 30 years, I revisited the originalTomb Raidervia 2024’sTomb Raider I-III Remasteredcollection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking this is going to be a dunk on the work done on the remaster, but that’s not the case, because the core issue with playing 1996’sTomb Raiderin 2026 is actually unsolvable, no matter how much care is put into a remaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raiderwas part of the first wave of multiplatform games with fully 3D gameplay, releasing the same year as similarly groundbreaking 3D titlesSuper Mario 64andQuake. I think you could make a pretty compelling case that most of the modern AAA games industry can trace its lineage in some way back to those three titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it was the beginning of mass-market 3D games (yes, I know other, more niche 3D games existed before), there were no established best practices for things like the controls or the camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raideropted for a modality that was common for a few years before it was replaced by clearly better solutions: what we now call “tank controls,” where forward or back moves the character forward or back, but hitting left or right turns the character on its axis in place without moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it works is naturally intuitive enough, which is part of why it was so popular early on. But the industry has moved on because it’s ultimately frustratingly sluggish and clunky. I lovedTomb Raider‘s level design and atmosphere, and the designers did about as good a job as they could designing around the limitations of the controls for most of the combat sequences. But ultimately, there was enough combat that the sluggishness of this input method significantly detracted from my enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1996, I had little to compare it to, and the novelty of these vertically stacked 3D levels played from a third-person perspective was powerful enough that I had no complaints. But after 30 years of new ideas and iteration, the industry’s designers have solved all the problems this game has with controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why the studio behind the remaster tried including an alternative modern control scheme. Unfortunately, that doesn’t work forTomb Raiderat all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When work started on the originalTomb Raider, its developers are said to have had a specific cocktail of influences in mind: They wanted to combine the truly 3D navigable environments they had seen in the groundbreakingUltima Underworldand the polygonal characters fromVirtua Fighter, with gameplay inspired by the 1989 Jordan Mechner classicPrince of Persia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve playedPrince of Persia, you know the platforming in that game is both precise and challenging. To make jumps, you had to carefully position yourself before launching—one step forward, one step back, until you reached the perfect starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes forTomb Raider. In fact, the entire game—all the puzzles, layouts, and platforming challenges—adheres to a strictgrid system. Players can predict exactly how far protagonist Lara Croft will jump based on where they are on that grid. They can count steps to position themselves, and it’s basically required if you want to consistently navigate the game’s complex and precise jumping sequences without frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the game’s original tank controls, you could step forward or backward in predictable ways, or side step, jump to the side, jump forward, jump backward, and so on, with specific numbers of presses on the arrow keys. The entire game was built around this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As frustrating as tank controls are to a modern player, there was an exquisite elegance to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaster’s modern controls option works more likeTomb Raider Legendsfrom the 2000s, and it’s that general approach that has become standard in almost all modern third-person 3D games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They feel so much nicer and more responsive to a modern player who has been trained on that for the past two decades, even if that player is someone like me who did play the original games with tank controls back in the day. That short window of three to five years of muscle memory and comfort based on tank controls has been completely overwritten by more than 20 years with what the modern control scheme offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the flexible modern controls lose almost all connection to that elegant grid system. What used to be a precise process—for example, “X steps forward, X steps to the left, then a backflip from exactly this spot"—is now a guessing game of feeling things out. And the platforming sequences aren’t designed with that in mind. As a result, the combat feels a lot better with modern controls, but just about everything else is much more frustrating than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not the first to observe this about the remaster; reviewers andReddit dwellersdebated this at length when this release happened two years ago. But I hadn’t gotten to playing the remasters—or revisitingTomb Raiderat all since the ’90s—until I decided to try it out for C:\ArsGames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raideris still worth revisiting, but it is frustrating to leave behind 20 years of muscle memory to return to a previous paradigm that ended up being an evolutionary dead end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more time you put into it, the more natural the tank controls feel, but without the wow factor of groundbreaking new 3D gameplay, it’s harder to put up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tellingly,Tomb Raiderhas already gotten a complete remake (distinct from this remaster) once, and another one is coming. Both radically reinvent the gameplay and seem to turn away from the grid system that made the original what it was. Many modern players won’t put up with the tank controls, but not being willing to embrace those means you simply can’t experienceTomb Raideras it was originally intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, I’m not knocking the work done on this remaster. Fittingly, it was made by Aspyr, the same studio that ported the original games to the Mac in the ’90s. (For a few years, they absolutely dominated the Mac game market with their Windows-to-Mac ports.) They’re still porting games to Mac, Linux, iOS, and Android today—notably, they did all theCivilization VIports—as well as remasters of classics for modern platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no version of the modern controls that would truly work from this game, so it’s not an execution issue, and I actually think thatTomb Raider I-III Remasteredis possibly Aspyr’s most well-crafted work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaster includes the ability to flip between classic graphics and a more contemporary look that I think does a great job of walking the line between honoring the ’90s original and looking nice to 2020s eyes. They even hired Timur “XProger” Gagiev, a developer known for work onTomb Raideropen source engine OpenLara, to be the remaster’s technical director.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tomb Raider franchise is about to enter a new era (controversially) under Embracer Group and Amazon Games; it remains to be seen whether it will be a good one. But if you want to go back to where it all started, I recommend grabbing this remaster (available on GOGand other storefronts, as well as on consoles) instead of playing the original release. Just stick with the tank controls, and I hope you adapt back to them more easily than I did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars Technica may earn compensation for sales from links on this post throughaffiliate
    programs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/the-problem-with-revisiting-tomb-raider-reacclimating-to-tank-controls/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:03:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>