<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 10:11:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Spotify won court order against Anna’s Archive, taking down .org domain</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/annas-archive-said-spotify-scrape-didnt-cause-domain-suspension-it-was-wrong/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/spotify-logos-1152x648-1767642275.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawsuit was filed under seal; Anna’s Archive wasn’t notified until after takedown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When shadow library Anna’s Archivelost its .org domainin early January, the controversial site’s operator said the suspension didn’t appear to have anything to do with its recentmass scraping of Spotify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it turns out, probably not surprisingly to most people, that the domain suspension resulted from a lawsuit filed by Spotify, along with major record labels Sony, Warner, and Universal Music Group (UMG). The music companies sued Anna’s Archive in late December in US District Court for the Southern District of New York, and the case was initially sealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A judge ordered the case unsealed on January 16 “because the purpose for which sealing was ordered has been fulfilled.” Numerous documents were made public on the court docket yesterday, and they explain events around the domain suspension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On January 2, the music companies asked for a temporary restraining order, and the courtgrantedit the same day. The order imposed requirements on the Public Interest Registry (PIR), a US-based nonprofit that oversees .org domains, and Cloudflare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Together, PIR and Cloudflare have the power to shut off access to the three web domains that Anna’s Archive uses to unlawfully distribute copyrighted works,” the music companiestold the court. They asked the court to issue “a temporary restraining order requiring that Anna’s Archive immediately cease and desist from all reproduction or distribution of the Record Company Plaintiffs’ copyrighted works,” and to “exercise its power under the All Writs Act to direct PIR and Cloudflare to facilitate enforcement of that order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies further asked that Anna’s Archive receive notice of the case by email only after the “order is issued by the Court and implemented by PIR and Cloudflare, to prevent Anna’s Archive from following through with its plan to release millions of illegally obtained, copyrighted sound recordings to the public.” That is apparently what happened, given that the operator of Anna’s Archive initiallysaiddomain suspensions are just something that “unfortunately happens to shadow libraries on a regular basis,” and that “we don’t believe this has to do with our Spotify backup.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The request from Spotify and record labels said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I]f Anna’s Archive receives notice that the Record Company Plaintiffs are seeking this temporary restraining order, it will almost certainly release the sound recordings that it has illegally copied from Spotify to the public immediately and activate contingency plans to relocate its infrastructure outside of the United States. To prevent this, Plaintiffs have filed their Complaint under seal, and the Record Company Plaintiffs now ask the Court to issue its temporary restraining order on an ex parte basis, so that Anna’s Archive cannot preemptively frustrate the very relief sought by the Record Company Plaintiffs’ motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anna’s Archive has already released Spotify metadata but not the songs, the companies said. Although the record companies are winning their case, that doesn’t necessarily mean they’ll be able to stop distribution of copyrighted files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the music companies noted, the “individuals who operate Anna’s Archive believe that they can ignore the law by remaining anonymous, accepting payments from users in cryptocurrency, and using foreign domain registrars and web hosting services that turn a blind eye to copyright infringement… The websites Anna’s Archive uses are either completely anonymous, or in one instance, registered to what appears to be a bogus company with a dubious address in Liberia, which is not a party to the Hague Convention governing service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music companies argued that Cloudflare could prevent access to Anna’s Archive URLs registered outside the United States, but this doesn’t seem to have been completely successful. The companies said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the domain name registrars for the annas-archive.li and annas-archive.se domains are located outside of the United States, Anna’s Archive relies on Cloudflare, headquartered in San Francisco, California, to provide a so-called “reverse proxy service” for the sites. Cloudflare effectively acts as a “middleman” between the websites and users who wish to access them, providing the information necessary for a user’s computer to convert the domain names into the numerical Internet Protocol address of the server hosting the website. These “authoritative nameservers” are necessary for users to connect to Anna’s Archive using the annas-archive.li and annas-archive.se domains, and Cloudflare has the technical capability to disable the authoritative nameservers, which would prevent users from accessing these websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the annas-archive.se domain couldn’t be reached today, we were still able to access annas-archive.li.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TorrentFreak noticeda recent change to the portion of the Anna’s Archive website thatlinked to torrentsof Spotify data: It now says, “Unavailable until further notice.” The page previously linked to three torrent files labeled as metadata, audio analysis, and cover art, but has displayed the “unavailable” message sinceat least January 14. The three torrents apparently add up to 6.2TB worth of data, while the entire scrape is said to be around 300TB worth of Spotify’s most-streamed songs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TorrentFreak wrote, “it appears that Anna’s Archive stopped the specific distribution of Spotify content alleged in the complaint, seemingly in partial compliance with the injunction’s ban on ‘making available’ the scraped files.” But we found it was still possible today to download the Spotify torrent files from Anna’s Archive by going to the individual URLs that used to be listed on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the temporary restraining order was granted on January 2, the court also issued an order to show cause. Anna’s Archive was told to file an answer by January 12, but did not do so, and no one representing Anna’s Archive appeared at a show-cause hearing on January 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the hearing, US District Judge Jed Rakoff granted apreliminary injunction, which is essentially a longer-term and more expansive version of the temporary restraining order. Rakoff said the plaintiffs are likely to succeed in proving that Anna’s Archive infringed copyrights by scraping songs from Spotify, and that Anna’s Archive “has threatened and/or is threatening to engage in additional acts of infringement by further reproducing and distributing copyrighted works… by,inter alia, posting ‘torrent’ files on websites owned or controlled by Anna’s Archive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the judge ordered Anna’s Archive to stop what it’s doing, the order more significantly imposes obligations on “all domain name registries and registrars of record for Anna’s Archive Domain Names and all hosting and Internet service providers for Anna’s Archive Websites.” These companies must disable access to Anna’s Archive domain names “and prevent their transfer to anyone other than the Record Company Plaintiffs,” and “cease any hosting services for Anna’s Archive Websites or any other websites that host the infringing content or directly facilitate its distribution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge named specific companies the order applies to, though it is not limited to those companies. In addition to the Public Interest Registry and Cloudflare, the judge said the order applies to the Switch Foundation, the Swedish Internet Foundation, the National Internet Exchange of India, Njalla SRL, IQWeb FZ-LLC, Immaterialism Ltd., Hosting Concepts B.V., and Tucows Domains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operator of the WorldCat library catalog separately won a default judgment against Anna’s Archive in a different court last week. A judge ruled that Anna’s Archive must delete all copies of its WorldCat data and stop scraping, using, storing, or distributing the data.No one thinks Anna’s Archive will comply, but the WorldCat operator said a court order would help it ask hosting services to remove data from Anna’s Archive websites.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/annas-archive-said-spotify-scrape-didnt-cause-domain-suspension-it-was-wrong/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:34:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Watch a robot swarm “bloom” like a garden</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/watch-a-robot-swarm-bloom-like-a-garden/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/swarm1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Swarm Garden: An array of modular robot agents that adapt to changing conditions for living architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers at Princeton University have built a swarm of interconnected mini-robots that “bloom” like flowers in response to changing light levels in an office. According to theirnew paperpublished in the journal Science Robotics, such robotic swarms could one day be used as dynamic facades in architectural designs, enabling buildings to adapt to changing climate conditions as well as interact with humans in creative ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors drew inspiration from so-called “living architectures,” such as beehives. Fire ants providea textbook exampleof this kind of collective behavior. A few ants spaced well apart behave like individual ants. But pack enough of them closely together, and they behave more like a single unit, exhibiting both solid and liquid properties. You can pour them from a teapot like ants, as Goldman’s lab demonstrated several years ago, or they can link together to build towers or floating rafts—a handy survival skill when, say, a hurricane floods Houston. Theyalso excelat regulating their own traffic flow. You almost never see an ant traffic jam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally scientists are keen to mimic such systems. For instance,in 2018, Georgia Tech researchers built ant-like robots and programmed them to dig through 3D-printed magnetic plastic balls designed to simulate moist soil. Robot swarms capable of efficiently digging underground without jamming would be super beneficial for mining or disaster recovery efforts, where using human beings might not be feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019,scientists foundthat flocks of wild jackdawswill changetheir flying patterns depending on whether they are returning to roost or banding together to drive away predators. That work could one day lead to the development of autonomous robotic swarms capable of changing their interaction rules to perform different tasks in response to environmental cues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors of this latest paper note that plants can optimize their shape to get enough sunlight or nutrients, thanks to individual cells that interact with each other via mechanical and other forms of signaling. By contrast, the architecture designed by human beings is largely static, composed of rigid fixed elements that hinder building occupants’ ability to adapt to daily, seasonal, or annual variations in climate conditions. There have only been a few examples of applying swarm intelligence algorithms inspired by plants, insects, and flocking birds to the design processto achievemore creative structural designs, or betterenergy optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors were interested in exploring adaptive and dynamic facades in architecture, inspired by past attempts to integrate biological elements to create “living buildings”: usingpanels of algaeto generate energy and provide shade, for example. Most such efforts rely on arrays of rigid mechanical modulesto respondto external stimuli, such as theAl Bahr Towersin Abu Dhabi. More recently, architects have explored arrays of soft modules for facades, such as bimetallic beams and shells that respond to shifts in temperature to control building ventilation and temperature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merihan Alhafnawi, a mechanical engineer at Princeton, and co-authors turned to swarm robotics to design their proof-of-concept project, dubbed the Swarm Garden. They built an array of 40 modular, rearrangeable robotic units they called SGbots, connected via a Wi-Fi network to enable a shared communication protocol designed to facilitate collective decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each bot has a back-facing ambient light sensor to detect lighting changes and a front-facing proximity sensor to enable it to find and communicate with its nearest neighbors. And each bot has an actuator designed to retract or extend a thin plastic sheet through a thin slot; the sheets can buckle or open up into a “bloom” in response to environmental stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alhafnawi et al. designed two case studies to demonstrate the potential of their Swarm Garden. In the first, they used a Swarm Garden for adaptive shading, placing 16 SGbots on an office window and letting them operate continuously for three days. The bots fully extended their sheets to block sunlight when the light was especially strong, gradually buckling as the sun weakened and the room became darker. Additional simulations showed the array also worked well when placed horizontally in atrium spaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second case study was designed to showcase the potential of swarm robots for creative interior design. This involved an array of 36 SGbots at a public exhibition in April 2024 at Princeton’s Lewis Center for the Arts. In one demonstration (see video above), users could cause the bots to “bloom” and retract using simple hand gestures. In another (see video below), users donned wearable devices so they could induce LED color changes with gestural arm movements. One of the co-authors even performed a live dance while equipped with a wearable device midway through the three-hour exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is for the team to collaborate with architects to determine the feasibility of real-world deployment of Swarm Garden arrays. The authors also want to explore more sustainable and resilient materials since there is considerable stress on the plastic sheets from the buckling-to-blooming process. And they suggest employing kirigami-inspired cuts could lower actuation power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We envision a future where the built environment is increasingly inspired by living architectures, creating facades that constantly adapt to their surroundings and occupants,” Alhafnawi et al. concluded. “The Swarm Garden offers a glimpse into that future: an architectural swarm that collectively responds to sunlight and human interaction. It further shapes occupants’ spaces by being animated with movement, vibrant with colors, and beautiful in appearance, inspiring creativity and expression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science Robotics, 2026. DOI:10.1126/scirobotics.ady7233(About DOIs).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/watch-a-robot-swarm-bloom-like-a-garden/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:47:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kioxia’s memory is “sold out” for 2026, prolonging a “high-end and expensive phase”</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/kioxias-memory-is-sold-out-for-2026-prolonging-a-high-end-and-expensive-phase/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/kioxia-ssds-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kioxia is spinning up more manufacturing capacity, but relief will come slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies that make RAM and flash memory chips areenjoying record profitsbecause of the AI-induced memory crunch—and they’re also indicating that they don’t expect conditions to improve much if at all in 2026. And while RAM kits have been hit the fastest and hardest by shortages and price increases, we shouldn’t expect SSD pricing to improve any time soon, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the message from Shunsuke Nakato (via PC Gamer), managing director of the memory division of Kioxia, the Japanese memory company that was spun off from Toshiba at the end of the 2010s. Nakato says that Kioxia’s manufacturing capacity is sold out through the rest of 2026, driving the market for both enterprise and consumer SSDs to a “high-end and expensive phase.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a sense of crisis that companies will be eliminated the moment they stop investing in AI, so they have no choice but to continue investing,” said Nakato, asreportedby the Korean-language publication Digital Daily. Absent a big change in the demand for generative AI data centers, that cycle of investments will keep prices high for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nakato notes that Kioxia was attempting to increase its manufacturing capacity to meet the elevated demand, saying that it was taking steps to improve yields at its factory in Yokkaichi and that Kioxia expected another factory in Kitakami to begin “full-scale mass production” this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we’ve seen during several chip shortages this decade, it takes time for chip shortages to abate because it takes years to build new factories and get them producing useful numbers of usable chips. Companies are also sometimes cautious about adding new capacity too quickly, lest market conditions change in the interim and leave them withpiles of expensive memory that they have to discount heavily to sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our recent retail researchhas shown that price increases have been a bit more extreme for higher-capacity drives, at least so far—both the increases and the cost-per-gigabyte have been more extreme for 2TB and 4TB SSDs than for 1TB models. But regardless of the size of the drive, prices seem unlikely to come down any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For desktop users looking for storage upgrades, it’s worth looking into whether your PC has additional M.2 storage slots that can accommodate additional storage without making you replace the drive you have already. If it’s huge, 100+ GB modern game downloads that are devouring your drive space, Steam and most other PC game storefronts make it relatively easy to add more drives and to offload games to a secondary drive. Some larger gaming laptops also include a secondary M.2 slot, though this will vary from model to model, and some of them may require a shorter M.2 2240 SSD rather than a full-length M.2 2280 drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These secondary M.2 slots are sometimes slower than the primary slot, for technical reasons—sometimes one M.2 slot uses higher-speed PCI Express lanes built into the CPU, while others use lower-speed PCIe lanes provided by the chipset. But any reasonably modern PCIe 3.0 or 4.0 drive will feel fast enough for most things most of the time and will be preferable to using external storage or relying on slow SD or microSD cards.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/kioxias-memory-is-sold-out-for-2026-prolonging-a-high-end-and-expensive-phase/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:37:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why adding modern controls to 1996’s Tomb Raider simply doesn’t work</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/the-problem-with-revisiting-tomb-raider-reacclimating-to-tank-controls/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Tomb-Raider-hero-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our C:\ArsGames series, we look at the controls conundrum of early 3D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once or twice a month, we’ll publish a personal retrospective like this one, where we’ll feature one of the games from the list—perhaps a retro game you’ve heard of, perhaps a modern title you missed. Regardless, GOG will have a DRM-free version of the game ready to go. Be sure to check outthe earlier pieces in the series!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a lot of the games I’ve written about in theC:\ArsGamesseries, I’ve come to the conclusion that the games hold up pretty well, despite their age—Master of Orion II,Jill of the Jungle, andWing Commander Privateer, for example. Each of those have flaws that show now more than ever, but I still had a blast revisiting each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I’d like to write about one that I think doesn’t hold up quite as well for me: For the first time in almost 30 years, I revisited the originalTomb Raidervia 2024’sTomb Raider I-III Remasteredcollection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking this is going to be a dunk on the work done on the remaster, but that’s not the case, because the core issue with playing 1996’sTomb Raiderin 2026 is actually unsolvable, no matter how much care is put into a remaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raiderwas part of the first wave of multiplatform games with fully 3D gameplay, releasing the same year as similarly groundbreaking 3D titlesSuper Mario 64andQuake. I think you could make a pretty compelling case that most of the modern AAA games industry can trace its lineage in some way back to those three titles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it was the beginning of mass-market 3D games (yes, I know other, more niche 3D games existed before), there were no established best practices for things like the controls or the camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raideropted for a modality that was common for a few years before it was replaced by clearly better solutions: what we now call “tank controls,” where forward or back moves the character forward or back, but hitting left or right turns the character on its axis in place without moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way it works is naturally intuitive enough, which is part of why it was so popular early on. But the industry has moved on because it’s ultimately frustratingly sluggish and clunky. I lovedTomb Raider‘s level design and atmosphere, and the designers did about as good a job as they could designing around the limitations of the controls for most of the combat sequences. But ultimately, there was enough combat that the sluggishness of this input method significantly detracted from my enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1996, I had little to compare it to, and the novelty of these vertically stacked 3D levels played from a third-person perspective was powerful enough that I had no complaints. But after 30 years of new ideas and iteration, the industry’s designers have solved all the problems this game has with controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why the studio behind the remaster tried including an alternative modern control scheme. Unfortunately, that doesn’t work forTomb Raiderat all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When work started on the originalTomb Raider, its developers are said to have had a specific cocktail of influences in mind: They wanted to combine the truly 3D navigable environments they had seen in the groundbreakingUltima Underworldand the polygonal characters fromVirtua Fighter, with gameplay inspired by the 1989 Jordan Mechner classicPrince of Persia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve playedPrince of Persia, you know the platforming in that game is both precise and challenging. To make jumps, you had to carefully position yourself before launching—one step forward, one step back, until you reached the perfect starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same goes forTomb Raider. In fact, the entire game—all the puzzles, layouts, and platforming challenges—adheres to a strictgrid system. Players can predict exactly how far protagonist Lara Croft will jump based on where they are on that grid. They can count steps to position themselves, and it’s basically required if you want to consistently navigate the game’s complex and precise jumping sequences without frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the game’s original tank controls, you could step forward or backward in predictable ways, or side step, jump to the side, jump forward, jump backward, and so on, with specific numbers of presses on the arrow keys. The entire game was built around this principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As frustrating as tank controls are to a modern player, there was an exquisite elegance to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaster’s modern controls option works more likeTomb Raider Legendsfrom the 2000s, and it’s that general approach that has become standard in almost all modern third-person 3D games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They feel so much nicer and more responsive to a modern player who has been trained on that for the past two decades, even if that player is someone like me who did play the original games with tank controls back in the day. That short window of three to five years of muscle memory and comfort based on tank controls has been completely overwritten by more than 20 years with what the modern control scheme offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the flexible modern controls lose almost all connection to that elegant grid system. What used to be a precise process—for example, “X steps forward, X steps to the left, then a backflip from exactly this spot"—is now a guessing game of feeling things out. And the platforming sequences aren’t designed with that in mind. As a result, the combat feels a lot better with modern controls, but just about everything else is much more frustrating than before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not the first to observe this about the remaster; reviewers andReddit dwellersdebated this at length when this release happened two years ago. But I hadn’t gotten to playing the remasters—or revisitingTomb Raiderat all since the ’90s—until I decided to try it out for C:\ArsGames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomb Raideris still worth revisiting, but it is frustrating to leave behind 20 years of muscle memory to return to a previous paradigm that ended up being an evolutionary dead end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more time you put into it, the more natural the tank controls feel, but without the wow factor of groundbreaking new 3D gameplay, it’s harder to put up with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tellingly,Tomb Raiderhas already gotten a complete remake (distinct from this remaster) once, and another one is coming. Both radically reinvent the gameplay and seem to turn away from the grid system that made the original what it was. Many modern players won’t put up with the tank controls, but not being willing to embrace those means you simply can’t experienceTomb Raideras it was originally intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, I’m not knocking the work done on this remaster. Fittingly, it was made by Aspyr, the same studio that ported the original games to the Mac in the ’90s. (For a few years, they absolutely dominated the Mac game market with their Windows-to-Mac ports.) They’re still porting games to Mac, Linux, iOS, and Android today—notably, they did all theCivilization VIports—as well as remasters of classics for modern platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no version of the modern controls that would truly work from this game, so it’s not an execution issue, and I actually think thatTomb Raider I-III Remasteredis possibly Aspyr’s most well-crafted work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remaster includes the ability to flip between classic graphics and a more contemporary look that I think does a great job of walking the line between honoring the ’90s original and looking nice to 2020s eyes. They even hired Timur “XProger” Gagiev, a developer known for work onTomb Raideropen source engine OpenLara, to be the remaster’s technical director.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tomb Raider franchise is about to enter a new era (controversially) under Embracer Group and Amazon Games; it remains to be seen whether it will be a good one. But if you want to go back to where it all started, I recommend grabbing this remaster (available on GOGand other storefronts, as well as on consoles) instead of playing the original release. Just stick with the tank controls, and I hope you adapt back to them more easily than I did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars Technica may earn compensation for sales from links on this post throughaffiliate
    programs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/the-problem-with-revisiting-tomb-raider-reacclimating-to-tank-controls/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:03:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump FCC threatens to enforce equal-time rule on late-night talk shows</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/trump-fcc-tries-to-get-more-republicans-on-late-night-and-daytime-talk-shows/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/jimmy-kimmel-return-1152x648-1758739114.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FCC disputes long-standing view that the shows are exempt from equal-time rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Communications Commission today issued a warning to late-night and daytime talk shows, saying these shows may no longer qualify for an exemption to the FCC’s equal-time rule. Because the FCC is chaired byvocal Trump supporter Brendan Carr, changing how the rule is enforced could pressure shows into seeking out more interviews with Republican candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thepublic noticeproviding what the FCC calls “guidance on political equal opportunities requirement for broadcast television stations” appears to be part of the Trump administration’s campaign against alleged liberal bias on broadcast TV. Carr, who haseroded the FCC’s historical independencefrom the White House, previouslypressured ABC to suspend Jimmy Kimmeland threatened ABC’sThe Viewwith the equal-time rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Carr FCC’s public notice today said that federal rules “prevent broadcast television stations, which have been given access to a valuable public resource (namely, spectrum), from unfairly putting their thumbs on the scale for one political candidate or set of candidates over another.” These rules come from “the decision by Congress that broadcast television stations have an obligation to operate in the public interest—not in any narrow partisan, political interest,” the Carr FCC said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the public notice doesn’t make allegations against any specific station or program, a conservative group that has filed FCC complaints against broadcast stations treated the move as a victory against “left-wing” shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This major announcement from the FCC should stop one-sided left-wing entertainment shows masquerading as ‘bona fidenews,'”wroteDaniel Suhr, president of the Center for American Rights. “The abuse of the airwaves by ABC &amp; NBC as DNC-TV must end. FCC is restoring respect for the equal time rules enacted by Congress.” Suhr’s group filed bias complaints against CBS, ABC, and NBC stations that were dismissed during the Biden era, but the group’s complaints wererevived by Carrin January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equal-time rule, formally known as the Equal Opportunities Rule, applies to radio or TV broadcast stations with FCC licenses to use the public airwaves. When a station gives time to one political candidate, it must provide comparable time and placement to an opposing candidate if an opposing candidate makes a request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rule has an exemption for candidate appearances onbona fidenews programs. As the FCCexplainedin 2022, “appearances by legally qualified candidates onbona fidenewscasts, interview programs, certain types of news documentaries, and during on-the-spot coverage ofbona fidenews events are exempt from Equal Opportunities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entertainment talk shows have generally been treated asbona fidenews programs for this purpose. But Carrsaid in Septemberthat he’s not sure shows likeThe Viewshould qualify for the exemption, and today’s public notice suggests the FCC may no longer treat these shows as exempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commissioner Anna Gomez, the only Democrat on the FCC, issued a press release criticizing the FCC for “a misleading announcement suggesting that certain late-night and daytime programs may no longer qualify for the long-standing ‘bona fidenews interview’ exemption under the commission’s political broadcasting rules.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nothing has fundamentally changed with respect to our political broadcasting rules,” Gomez said. “The FCC has not adopted any new regulation, interpretation, or commission-level policy altering the long-standing news exemption or equal time framework. For decades, the commission has recognized thatbona fidenews interviews, late-night programs, and daytime news shows are entitled to editorial discretion based on newsworthiness, not political favoritism. That principle has not been repealed, revised, or voted on by the commission. This announcement therefore does not change the law, but it does represent an escalation in this FCC’s ongoing campaign to censor and control speech.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Carr FCC’s public notice said that talk shows aren’t necessarily eligible for thebona fidenews exception despite a 2006 decision in which “the FCC’s Media Bureau determined that the interview portion of ‘The Tonight Show with Jay Leno’ qualified for the equal opportunities exemption as abona fidenews interview.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notice said, “Concerns have been raised that the industry has taken the Media Bureau’s 2006 staff-level decision to mean that the interview portion of all arguably similar entertainment programs—whether late night or daytime—are exempted from the section 315 equal opportunities requirement under abona fidenews exemption. This is not the case. As noted above, these decisions are fact-specific and the exemptions are limited to the program that was the subject of the request.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public notice pointedly said that “the FCC has not been presented with any evidence that the interview portion of any late-night or daytime television talk show program on air presently would qualify for thebona fidenews exemption.” The notice encouraged programs or stations to promptly file petitions with the FCC if they want “formal assurance that the equal opportunities requirement does not apply” to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gomez urged broadcasters to exercise their free speech rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Broadcasters should not feel pressured to water down, sanitize, or avoid critical coverage out of fear of regulatory retaliation,” she said. “Broadcast stations have a constitutional right to carry newsworthy content, even when that content is critical of those in power. That does not change today, it will not change tomorrow, and it will not change simply because of this administration’s desire to silence its critics.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/trump-fcc-tries-to-get-more-republicans-on-late-night-and-daytime-talk-shows/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:50:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>mRNA cancer vaccine shows protection at 5-year follow-up, Moderna and Merck say</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/mrna-cancer-vaccine-shows-protection-at-5-year-follow-up-moderna-and-merck-say/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/GettyImages-1290558683.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vaccines are tailor-made to target each patient’s unique cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a small clinical trial, customized mRNA vaccines against high-risk skin cancers appeared to reduce the risk of cancer recurrence and death by nearly 50 percent over five years when compared with standard treatment alone. That’saccording to Moderna and Merck, the two pharmaceutical companies that have collaborated on the experimental cancer vaccine, called intismeran autogene (mRNA-4157 or V940).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the companies have only reported the top-line results in a press release this week. However, the results align closely with previous, more detailed analyses from the trial, which examined rates of recurrence and death at earlier time points, specifically attwo yearsandthree yearsafter the treatment. More data from the trial—a Phase 2 trial—will soon be presented at a medical conference, the companies said. A Phase 3 trial is also underway, with enrollment complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ongoing Phase 2 trial included 157 patients who were diagnosed with stage 3 or stage 4 melanoma and were at high risk of having it recur after surgical removal. A standard treatment to prevent recurrence after such surgery is immunotherapy, including Merck’s Keytruda (pembrolizumab). This drug essentially enables immune cells, specifically T cells, to attack and kill cancer cells—something they normally do. But, in many types of cancers, including melanoma, cancer cells have the ability to bind to receptors on T cells (called PD-1 receptors), which basically shuts the T cells down. Keytruda works by physically blocking the PD-1 receptors, preventing cancer cells from binding and keeping the T cells activated so they can kill the cancer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the trial, all 157 patients received Keytruda, a standard treatment. But they were randomized in a 2:1 ratio so that some would also get the customized mRNA vaccines. These vaccines were tailored specifically to each patient’s melanomas, carrying genetic instructions to build up to 34 unique markers of their mutated cancer cells. Once in the patient, healthy cells produce those markers and use them to train T cells to identify and attack the cancer cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous data from the trial reported that 107 participants received the mRNA vaccine and Keytruda treatment, while the remaining 50 only received Keytruda. At the two-year follow-up, 24 of the 107 (22 percent) who got the experimental vaccine and Keytruda had recurrence or death, while 20 of 50 (40 percent) treated with just Keytruda had recurrence or death, indicating a 44 percent risk reduction. The companies did not report the breakdown of the two groups in the press release this week for the five-year follow-up, but said the risk reduction was 49 percent, which is also what the companies reported for the three-year follow-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for side effects, the companies reported that little had changed from previous analyses; adverse events were similar between the two groups. The top side effects linked to the vaccine were fatigue, injection site pain, and chills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results “highlight the potential of a prolonged benefit” of the vaccine combined with Keytruda in patients with high-risk melanoma,” Kyle Holen, a senior vice president at Moderna, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also “illustrate mRNA’s potential in cancer care,” he said, noting that the company has eight more Phase 2 and Phase 3 trials going for mRNA vaccines against a variety of other cancers, including lung, bladder, and kidney cancers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marjorie Green, a senior vice president at Merck, called the five-year follow-up data a “meaningful milestone” and “encouraging.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“[W]e look forward to late-stage data from the INTerpath clinical development program with Moderna, across a range of tumor types where significant unmet needs remain,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the top-line results appear positive, conclusions can’t be drawn until the full data from the trial are published. The vaccines are also being developed amid a political environment hostile to mRNA vaccines. Anti-vaccine Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. has railed against mRNA COVID-19 vaccines, making false claims about their safety and efficacy. In August, Kennedy unilaterallycanceled $500 million in grant fundingfor the development of mRNA-based vaccines against diseases that pose pandemic threats.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/mrna-cancer-vaccine-shows-protection-at-5-year-follow-up-moderna-and-merck-say/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:51:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Millions of people imperiled through sign-in links sent by SMS</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/millions-of-people-imperiled-through-sign-in-links-sent-by-sms/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/sms-phone-risk-trap-privacy-security-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even well-known services with millions of users are exposing sensitive data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Websites that authenticate users through links and codes sent in text messages are imperiling the privacy of millions of people, leaving them vulnerable to scams, identity theft, and other crimes, recently published research has found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The links are sent to people seeking a range of services, including those offering insurance quotes, job listings, and referrals for pet sitters and tutors. To eliminate the hassle of collecting usernames and passwords—and for users to create and enter them—many such services instead require users to provide a cell phone number when signing up for an account. The services then send authentication links or passcodes by SMS when the users want to log in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apaperpublished last week has found more than 700 endpoints delivering such texts on behalf of more than 175 services that put user security and privacy at risk. One practice that jeopardizes users is the use of links that are easily enumerated, meaning scammers can guess them by simply modifying the security token, which usually appears at the right of a URL. By incrementing or randomly guessing the token—for instance, by first changing 123 to 124 or ABC to ABD and so on—the researchers were able to access accounts belonging to other users. From there, the researchers could view personal details, such as partially completed insurance applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other cases, the researchers could have transacted sensitive business while masquerading as the other user. Other links used so few possible token combinations that they were easy to brute force. Other examples of shoddy practices were links that allowed attackers who gained unauthorized access to access or modify user data with no other authentication other than clicking on a link sent by SMS. Many of the links provide account access for years after they were sent, further raising the risk of unauthorized access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We argue that these attacks are straightforward to test, verify, and execute at scale,” the researchers, from the universities of New Mexico, Arizona, Louisiana, and the firm Circle, wrote. “The threat model can be realized using consumer-grade hardware and only basic to intermediate Web security knowledge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SMS messages are sent unencrypted. In past years, researchers have unearthed public databases of previously sent texts that contained authentication links and private details, including people’s names and addresses. One such discovery,from 2019, included millions of stored sent and received text messages over the years between a single business and its customers. It included usernames and passwords, university finance applications, and marketing messages with discount codes and job alerts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the known insecurity, the practice continues to flourish. For ethical reasons, the researchers behind the study had no way to capture its true scale, because it would require bypassing access controls, however weak they were. As a lens offering only a limited view into the process, the researchers viewed public SMS gateways. These are typically ad-based websites that let people use a temporary number to receive texts without revealing their phone number. Examples of such gateways arehereandhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With such a limited view of SMS-sent authentication messages, the researchers were unable to measure the true scope of the practice and the security and privacy risks it posed. Still, their findings were notable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers collected 322,949,000 unique SMS-delivered URLs extracted from over 33 million texts, sent to more than 30,000 phone numbers. The researchers found numerous evidence of security and privacy threats to the people receiving them. Of those, the researchers said, messages originating from 701 endpoints sent on behalf of the 177 services exposed “critical personally identifiable information.” The root cause of the exposure was weak authentication based on tokenized links for verification. Anyone with the link could then obtain users’ personal information—including social security numbers, dates of birth, bank account numbers, and credit scores—from these services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the 701 services, 125 allowed “mass enumeration of valid URLs due to low entropy.” Attackers who had received links from the same service could then easily modify the tokens they had to access other people’s accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the limited view into the practice, these numbers likely significantly undercount the true number of services jeopardizing users’ security and privacy by sending such links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The likely widespread sending of unsafe links in SMS messages means there are few concrete steps most people can take to protect themselves. Stepping back and assessing the weak authentication processes in general, Muhammad Danish, the lead author of the paper, wrote in an email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The root causes we found are related to service providers and the burden is on them. We can say users should not give sensitive details to untrusted sources, but that suggestion fails in our case as our list includes even well-established service providers with millions of active users. Users can help us by reporting to the service providers or removing their data until fixed if they see any of these issues in a website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of the offending services can be found in the paper linked above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice is popular because it imposes lower perceived friction on potential customers. Another benefit is that endpoints don’t have to collect and store usernames and passwords, which have proven over and over to be easily stolen by hackers. Another reason they’re used is the false assumption by the people setting up the service that such links will restrict all others than those who sent the text and endpoint misconfigurations or lack of security reviews of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muhammad, like other security professionals, said authentication links sent by SMS or email aren’t automatically unsafe as long as links are short lived, expires after the first login, and have a cryptographically secure token. Privacy-minded sites, including DuckDuckGo and 404 Media, have opted to authenticate users with a “magic link” that’s sent to an account holder’s email address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By not creating a password with us you have no risk of it leaking, and we don’t have to deal with the responsibility of keeping it secure, 404 Media editorswrote. “The sign in link is going to your email, which presumably is protected with two-factor authentication, if you have it set up (which you should!).” Many people who object to the use of magic links fail to realize that many services that require a password already fall back to the equivalent of magic links for account recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be safe, magic links must be time-limited to lessen the chances of them being used by others. 404 Media says that links expire within 24 hours. DuckDuckGo’s authentication email system works differently. It sends a long one-time password. It’s unclear how long the passcode remains valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magic links also aren’t suitable for sites like Gmail, Office365, or banks that store large amounts of user data and must rely on robust account recovery mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to strengthen the security of SMS- or email-based authentication is to require a second factor, in addition to the link sent, although a birthdate, zip code, or other low-entropy factor is insufficient. Further, login attempts must be rate-limited to prevent an attacker from making attempt after attempt until arriving at the right one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, people should recognize that many of the SMS-delivered authentication links they receive may be exposing their sensitive data, and this practice isn’t likely to change soon. Of the 150 affected service providers the researchers were able to contact, only 18 responded and only seven have fixed the failure.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/millions-of-people-imperiled-through-sign-in-links-sent-by-sms/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:22:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge orders stop to FBI search of devices seized from Washington Post reporter</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-stop-to-fbi-search-of-devices-seized-from-washington-post-reporter/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/judges-gavel-1152x648-1747771043.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Order says gov’t must stop search while court reviews Washington Post motions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge today ordered the US government to stop searching devices seized from the house of a Washington Post reporter. It may be only a temporary reprieve for the Post and reporter Hannah Natanson, however. Further proceedings will be held on whether the search can resume or whether the government must return the devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natanson herself isn’t the subject of investigation, but the FBI executed a search warrant at her home andseized her work and personal deviceslast week as part of an investigation into alleged leaks by a Pentagon contractor. The Post filed a motion to force the return of the reporter’s property, and a separate motion for a standstill order that would prevent review of the seized devices until the court rules on whether they must be returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Almost none of the seized data is even potentially responsive to the warrant, which seeks only records received from or relating to a single government contractor,” a Postcourt filingtoday said. “The seized data is core First Amendment-protected material, and some is protected by the attorney-client privilege.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materials “should be returned because the search and seizure of Natanson’s reporting materials was an unconstitutional prior restraint—government action that blocks expressive activity before it can occur,” the filing said, adding that the “government’s legitimate interests can be satisfied by issuing a subpoena to Natanson and/or The Post for the same items sought by the warrant.” The multi-device seizure has “suppressed The Post and Natanson’s ability to publish stories on completely unrelated topics,” the filing said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US Magistrate Judge William Porter todaygrantedthe motion for a standstill order. “The government must preserve but must not review any of the materials that law enforcement seized pursuant to search warrants the Court issued… until the Court authorizes review of the materials by further order,” the ruling said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Post asked for an expedited briefing and hearing schedule. Porter ordered the government to file a reply by January 28 and scheduled oral arguments for February 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FBI agents reportedly seized Natanson’s phone, a 1TB portable hard drive, a device for recording interviews, a Garmin watch, a personal laptop, and a laptop issued by The Washington Post. Natanson has said she’s built up a contact list of 1,100 current and former government employees and communicates with them in encrypted Signal chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The day the FBI raided Natanson’s residence, undersigned counsel reached out to the government to advise that the seized items contain materials protected by the First Amendment and the attorney-client privileges,” attorneys for The Washington Post and Natansontold the court. “Undersigned counsel asked the government to refrain from reviewing the documents pending judicial resolution of the dispute, but the government refused.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filing said that unless a standstill order is issued, “the government will commence an unrestrained search of a journalist’s work product that violates the First Amendment and the attorney-client privilege, ignores federal statutory safeguards for journalists, and threatens the trust and confidentiality of sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The six devices seized from Natanson “contain essentially her entire professional universe: more than 30,000 Post emails from the last year alone, confidential information from and about sources (including her sources and her colleagues’ sources), recordings of interviews, notes on story concepts and ideas, drafts of potential stories, communications with colleagues about sources and stories, and The Post’s content management system that houses all articles in progress,” the Post said. “The devices also housed Natanson’s encrypted Signal messaging platform that she used to communicate with her more than 1,100 sources. Without her devices, she ‘literally cannot contact’ these sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devices also contain personal records like medical information, financial information, and details on wedding planning, the Post said. “The government seized this proverbial haystack in an attempt to locate a needle,” the Post said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case involves Aurelio Perez-Lugones, a system administrator with a top-secret security clearance, who was accused of taking classified intelligence reports home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even the government cannot expect to find many records responsive to the warrant in this ocean of data because its criminal complaint alleges that Perez-Lugones possessed only a small number of documents potentially containing classified or secret information, which he only began collecting three months ago,” the Post said. “Meanwhile, Natanson has thousands of communications across her more than 1,100 sources. And her devices contain years of data about past and current confidential sources and other unpublished materials. At best, the government has a legitimate interest in only an infinitesimal fraction of the data it has seized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Post suggested that instead of poring through all of Natanson’s devices, the government could get a subpoena “for the same items sought by the warrant—communications with Perez-Lugones, or records allegedly received from him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Freedom of the Press Foundation today said the judge was right to temporarily block the review of materials and should block the review permanently after the scheduled hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The search and seizure of Washington Post reporter Hannah Natanson’s records is unconstitutional and illegal in its entirety,”saidSeth Stern, the group’s chief of advocacy. “But even the Trump administration’s policies require searches of journalists’ materials to be narrow and targeted and that authorities use filter teams and other measures to avoid searching protected records. That the administration wouldn’t follow its own guidelines shows that the raid on Natanson’s home wasn’t about any criminal investigation, and certainly wasn’t about national security. It was a fishing expedition intended to intimidate and retaliate against a journalist who had managed to cultivate sources all over the government.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/judge-orders-stop-to-fbi-search-of-devices-seized-from-washington-post-reporter/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:33:43 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>