<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ars Technica Bilingual Feed</title><link>https://feeds.arstechnica.com/arstechnica/index</link><description>Ars Technica articles translated into Korean</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:23:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meta’s layoffs leave Supernatural fitness users in mourning (메타의 구조조정, 슈퍼내추럴 피트니스 사용자들에게 애도를 남기다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/metas-layoffs-leave-supernatural-fitness-users-in-mourning/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/06_Lifestyle-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supernatural has had its staff cut and won’t receive any more content updates.&lt;br/&gt;(슈퍼내추럴은 직원을 감원했으며 더 이상 콘텐츠 업데이트를 받지 못할 예정입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tencia Benavidez, a Supernatural user who lives in New Mexico, started her VR workouts during the Covid pandemic. She has been a regular user in the five years since, calling the ability to work out in VR ideal, given that she lives in a rural area where it’s hard to get to a gym or work out outside during a brutal winter. She stuck with Supernatural because of the community and the eagerness of Supernatural’s coaches.&lt;br/&gt;(뉴멕시코에 거주하는 슈퍼내추럴 사용자 텐시아 베나비데즈는 코로나 팬데믹 기간에 VR 운동을 시작했습니다. 그 후 5년 동안 꾸준히 사용해왔으며, 농촌 지역에 살아 체육관에 가기 어렵거나 혹독한 겨울에 야외 운동하기 힘든 점을 고려할 때 VR에서 운동할 수 있는 능력이 이상적이라고 말합니다. 그녀는 슈퍼내추럴의 커뮤니티와 코치들의 열정 때문에 계속 이용해왔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They seem like really authentic individuals that were not talking down to you,” Benavidez says. “There’s just something really special about those coaches.”&lt;br/&gt;("그들은 정말 진정성 있는 사람들로, 당신을 깔보지 않았어요,"라고 베나비데즈는 말합니다. "그 코치들에게는 정말 특별한 무언가가 있었죠.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta bought Supernatural in 2022, folding it into its then-heavily-invested-in metaverse efforts. The purchase was not a smooth process, as it triggered a lengthy legal battle in which the US Federal Trade Commission tried to block Meta from purchasing the service due to antitrust concerns about Meta “trying to buy its way to the top” of the VR market. Meta ultimately prevailed. At the time, some Supernatural users were cautiously optimistic, hoping that big bag of Zuckerbucks could keep its workout juggernaut afloat.&lt;br/&gt;(메타는 2022년 슈퍼내추럴을 인수하여 당시 막대한 투자를 받던 메타버스 사업에 편입시켰습니다. 이 인수는 순조롭지 않았는데, 메타가 VR 시장에서 "돈으로 정상을 사려 한다"는 반독점 우려로 미국 연방거래위원회가 메타의 서비스 인수를 막으려는 긴 법적 다툼을 촉발시켰기 때문입니다. 메타는 결국 승리했습니다. 당시 일부 슈퍼내추럴 사용자들은 주커버그의 거대한 자금이 이 운동 강국의 생존을 유지해줄 수 있기를 조심스럽게 낙관했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Meta fought the government to buy this thing,” Benavidez says. “All that just for them to shut it down? What was the point?”&lt;br/&gt;("메타는 정부와 싸워서 이걸 샀잖아요," 베나비데즈는 말합니다. "그 모든 것들이 그냥 문을 닫기 위해서였나요? 무슨 의미가 있었죠?")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Meta and Supernatural, and neither responded to my requests for comment.&lt;br/&gt;(저는 메타와 슈퍼내추럴에 연락을 취했지만, 둘 다 제 의견 요청에 응답하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Bloomberg reported that Meta has laid off more than 1,000 people across its VR and metaverse efforts. The move comes after years of the company hemorrhaging billions of dollars on its metaverse products. In addition to laying off most of the staff at Supernatural, Meta has shut down three internal VR studios that made games like Resident Evil 4 and Deadpool VR .&lt;br/&gt;(화요일, 블룸버그는 메타가 VR 및 메타버스 사업 전반에서 1,000명 이상의 직원을 해고했다고 보도했습니다. 이 조치는 회사가 수년간 메타버스 제품에 수십억 달러를 쏟아부은 후에 이루어졌습니다. 슈퍼내추럴 직원 대부분을 해고하는 것 외에도, 메타는 '레지던트 이블 4'와 '데드풀 VR' 같은 게임을 제작한 내부 VR 스튜디오 3곳을 폐쇄했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If it was a bottom-line thing, I think they could have charged more money,” Goff Johnson says about Supernatural. “I think people would have paid for it. This just seems unnecessarily heartless.”&lt;br/&gt;("수익성 문제였다면, 그들은 더 많은 돈을 청구할 수도 있었을 거예요," 고프 존슨은 슈퍼내추럴에 대해 말합니다. "사람들이 지불했을 거라고 생각해요. 이건 불필요하게 무정한 것 같아요.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a split in the community about who will stay and continue to pay the subscription fee and who will leave. Supernatural has more than 3,000 lessons available in the service, so while new content won’t be added, some feel there is plenty of content left in the library. Other users worry about how Supernatural will continue to license music from big-name bands.&lt;br/&gt;(커뮤니티 내에서는 누가 남아 구독료를 계속 지불할지, 누가 떠날지에 대한 의견이 갈립니다. 슈퍼내추럴에는 서비스 내에 3,000개 이상의 레슨이 준비되어 있어, 새로운 콘텐츠는 추가되지 않더라도 일부는 라이브러리에 아직 많은 콘텐츠가 남아 있다고 느낍니다. 다른 사용자들은 슈퍼내추럴이 유명 밴드로부터 음악 라이선스를 어떻게 계속 유지할지 걱정합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Supernatural is amazing, but I am canceling it because of this,” Chip told me. “The library is large, so there’s enough to keep you busy, but not for the same price.”&lt;br/&gt;("슈퍼내추럴은 놀라워요, 하지만 이 때문에 해지할 거예요," 칩이 저에게 말했습니다. "라이브러리가 크니까 바쁘게 할 만큼은 있지만, 같은 가격으로는 아니에요.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other VR workout experiences like FitXR or even the VR staple Beat Saber , which Supernatural cribs a lot of design concepts from. Still, they don’t hit the same bar for many of the Supernatural faithful.&lt;br/&gt;(FitXR나 심지어 슈퍼내추럴이 많은 디자인 개념을 차용한 VR 필수품인 Beat Saber와 같은 다른 VR 운동 경험들이 있습니다. 그래도, 그들은 많은 슈퍼내추럴 신봉자들에게 같은 수준에 미치지 못합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m going to stick it out until they turn the lights out on us,” says Stefanie Wong, a Bay Area accountant who has used Supernatural since shortly after the pandemic and has organized and attended meetup events. “It’s not the app. It’s the community, and it’s the coaches that we really, really care about.”&lt;br/&gt;("그들이 우리에게 불을 끌 때까지 버틸 거예요," 팬데믹 직후부터 슈퍼내추럴을 사용해왔고 미팅 이벤트를 조직하고 참석해온 베이 에리어 회계사 스테파니 웡은 말합니다. "앱이 중요한 게 아니에요. 우리가 정말, 정말 소중히 여기는 건 커뮤니티와 코치들이죠.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried out Supernatural’s Together feature on Wednesday, the day after the layoffs. It’s where I met Chip and Alisa. When we could stop to catch our breath, we talked about the changes coming to the service. They had played through previous sessions hosted by Jane Fonda or playlists with a mix of music that would change regularly. This one was an artist series featuring entirely Imagine Dragons songs.&lt;br/&gt;(저는 수요일, 구조조정 다음 날 슈퍼내추럴의 '투게더' 기능을 시도해봤습니다. 거기서 칩과 알리사를 만났습니다. 우리가 숨을 고를 수 있을 때, 서비스에 다가올 변화에 대해 이야기했습니다. 그들은 제인 폰다가 진행한 이전 세션이나 정기적으로 바뀌는 다양한 음악이 섞인 플레이리스트를 통해 운동해왔습니다. 이번 세션은 전곡 Imagine Dragons 노래로 구성된 아티스트 시리즈였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the session, as we punched blocks while being serenaded by this shirtless dude crooning , recorded narrations from Supernatural coach Dwana Olsen chimed in to hype us up.&lt;br/&gt;(세션 중, 우리는 이 셔츠를 입지 않은 남자가 노래하는 동안 블록을 주먹으로 치고 있었고, 슈퍼내추럴 코치 드와나 올슨의 녹음된 해설이 우리를 응원하며 끼어들었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Take advantage of these moments,” Olsen said as we punched away. “Use these movements to remind you of how much awesome life you have yet to live.”&lt;br/&gt;("이 순간들을 활용하세요," 올슨이 우리가 주먹을 휘두르며 말했습니다. "이 동작들을 통해 앞으로 살아갈 멋진 삶이 얼마나 많은지 상기시키세요.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankly, it was downright invigorating. And bittersweet. We ended another round, sweaty, huffing and puffing. Chip, Alisa, and I high-fived like crazy and readied for another round.&lt;br/&gt;(솔직히, 그것은 정말 활기를 주는 경험이었습니다. 그리고 씁쓸하기도 했죠. 우리는 또 다른 라운드를 끝내고, 땀에 젖고, 헐떡거렸습니다. 칩, 알리사, 그리고 저는 미친 듯이 하이파이브를 나누고 또 다른 라운드를 준비했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Beautiful,” Alisa said. “It’s just beautiful, isn’t it?”&lt;br/&gt;("아름다워요," 알리사가 말했습니다. "정말 아름다워요, 그렇지 않나요?")&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/metas-layoffs-leave-supernatural-fitness-users-in-mourning/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/06/06_Lifestyle-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 03:00:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ocean damage nearly doubles the cost of climate change (기후 변화 비용, 해양 피해 포함 시 약 2배로 증가)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/ocean-damage-nearly-doubles-the-cost-of-climate-change/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2245161347-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the blue economy has left a multi-trillion-dollar blind spot in climate finance.&lt;br/&gt;(청색 경제를 간과한 탓에 기후 재정 분야에 수조 달러 규모의 맹점이 생겼습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global cost of greenhouse gas emissions is nearly double what scientists previously thought, according to a study published Thursday by researchers at the University of California, San Diego’s Scripps Institution of Oceanography.&lt;br/&gt;(캘리포니아대학교 샌디에이고 캠퍼스 소속 스크립스 해양연구소 연구진이 목요일 발표한 연구에 따르면, 온실가스 배출로 인한 전 세계적 비용은 과학자들이 이전에 생각했던 것보다 거의 두 배에 달합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the first time a social cost of carbon (SCC) assessment—a key measure of economic harm caused by climate change—has included damages to the ocean. Global coral loss, fisheries disruption, and coastal infrastructure destruction are estimated to cost nearly $2 trillion annually, fundamentally changing how we measure climate finance.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 기후 변화로 인한 경제적 피해를 측정하는 핵심 지표인 탄소 사회적 비용(SCC) 평가에 해양 피해가 포함된 최초의 사례입니다. 전 세계적인 산호초 손실, 어업 붕괴, 해안 기반시설 파괴로 인해 연간 약 2조 달러의 비용이 발생하는 것으로 추산되며, 이는 기후 재정 측정 방식을 근본적으로 바꾸고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For decades, we’ve been estimating the economic cost of climate change while effectively assigning a value of zero to the ocean,” said Bernardo Bastien-Olvera, who led the study during his postdoctoral fellowship at Scripps. “Ocean loss is not just an environmental issue, but a central part of the economic story of climate change.”&lt;br/&gt;(이 연구를 이끈 베르나르도 바스티엔-올베라(스크립스 연구소 박사후 연구원 시절)는 "수십 년 동안 우리는 기후 변화의 경제적 비용을 추정하면서 사실상 해양의 가치를 0으로 책정해 왔습니다"라고 말했습니다. "해양 손실은 단순한 환경 문제가 아니라, 기후 변화의 경제적 이야기에서 핵심적인 부분입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social cost of carbon is an accounting method for working out the monetary cost of each ton of carbon dioxide released into the atmosphere. “[It] is one of the most efficient tools we have for internalizing climate damages into economic decision-making,” said Amy Campbell, a United Nations climate advisor and former British government COP negotiator.&lt;br/&gt;(탄소 사회적 비용은 대기 중으로 배출되는 이산화탄소 1톤당 화폐적 비용을 계산하는 회계 방법입니다. 유엔 기후 자문관이자 영국 정부의 전 COP 협상가인 에이미 캠벨은 "[이것은] 기후 피해를 경제적 의사결정에 내재화하는 데 우리가 가진 가장 효율적인 도구 중 하나입니다"라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculations have historically been used by international organizations and state departments like the US Environmental Protection Agency to assess policy proposals—though a 2025 White House memo from the Trump administration instructed federal agencies to ignore the data during cost-benefit analyses unless required by law.&lt;br/&gt;(이 계산법은 역사적으로 미국 환경보호청과 같은 국제기구 및 정부 부처가 정책 제안을 평가하는 데 사용해 왔습니다. 다만 2025년 트럼프 행정부의 백악관 각서는 법률에 명시되지 않는 한 비용편익 분석 시 해당 데이터를 무시하도록 연방 기관에 지시한 바 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It becomes politically contentious when deciding whose damages are counted, which sectors are included and most importantly how future and retrospective harms are valued,” Campbell said.&lt;br/&gt;(캠벨은 "어떤 피해를 계산에 포함할지, 어떤 부문을 포함할지, 가장 중요한 것은 미래와 과거의 피해를 어떻게 평가할지 결정할 때 정치적으로 논란이 됩니다"라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Excluding ocean harm, the social cost of carbon is $51 per ton of carbon dioxide emitted. This increases to $97.20 per ton when the ocean, which covers 70 percent of the planet, is included. In 2024, global CO2 emissions were estimated to be 41.6 billion tons , making the 91 percent cost increase significant.&lt;br/&gt;(해양 피해를 제외할 경우, 탄소 사회적 비용은 배출된 이산화탄소 1톤당 51달러입니다. 지구 표면의 70%를 덮고 있는 해양을 포함하면 이 금액은 1톤당 97.20달러로 증가합니다. 2024년 전 세계 이산화탄소 배출량은 약 416억 톤으로 추산되므로, 91%에 달하는 비용 증가는 상당합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using greenhouse gas emission predictions, the report estimates the annual damages to traditional markets alone will be $1.66 trillion by 2100.&lt;br/&gt;(온실가스 배출 예측을 활용한 이 보고서는 전통 시장만의 연간 피해액이 2100년까지 1조 6600억 달러에 달할 것으로 추산합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, which began in 2021, brought together scientists from multiple disciplines: Fisheries experts, coral reef researchers, biologists and climate economists. They assessed downstream climate change costs across four key sectors—corals, mangroves, fisheries, and seaports—measuring everything from straightforward market loss of reduced fisheries and marine trade to reductions in ocean-based recreational industries.&lt;br/&gt;(2021년 시작된 이 연구는 여러 분야의 과학자들—어업 전문가, 산호초 연구원, 생물학자, 기후 경제학자—을 한자리에 모았습니다. 그들은 산호초, 맹그로브, 어업, 항만이라는 네 가지 핵심 부문에 걸친 기후 변화의 하류 비용을 평가했으며, 어획량 및 해상 무역 감소로 인한 직접적인 시장 손실부터 해양 기반 레저 산업의 축소에 이르기까지 모든 것을 측정했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers also placed a monetary figure on what economists call non-use values. “Something has value because it makes the world feel more livable, meaningful, or worth protecting, even if we never directly use it,” said Bastien-Olvera, referencing the fiscal merit of ecosystem enjoyment and the cultural loss caused by climate change. “Most people will never visit a coral reef during a full-moon spawning event, or see a deep-sea jellyfish glowing in total darkness. But many still care deeply that these things exist.”&lt;br/&gt;(연구진은 또한 경제학자들이 '비사용 가치'라고 부르는 것에 금액을 부여했습니다. 바스티엔-올베라는 생태계를 즐기는 것의 재정적 가치와 기후 변화로 인한 문화적 손실을 언급하며 "우리가 직접 사용하지 않더라도, 어떤 것이 세상을 더 살기 좋고 의미 있으며 보호할 가치가 있다고 느끼게 해주기 때문에 가치를 지닙니다"라고 말했습니다. "대부분의 사람들은 만월 시 산호초 산란 행사를 보거나 완전한 어둠 속에서 빛나는 심해 해파리를 보지 못할 것입니다. 하지만 많은 사람들은 여전히 이러한 것들이 존재한다는 사실 자체를 깊이 염려합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Island economies, which rely more on seafood for nutrition, will face disproportionate financial and health impacts from ocean warming and acidification, the study said. “The countries that have the most responsibility for causing climate change and the most capacity to fix it are not generally the same countries that will experience the largest or most near-term damages,” said Kate Ricke, co-author and climate professor at UCSD’s School of Global Policy and Strategy. Including ocean data in social cost of carbon assessments reveals increased consequences for morbidity and mortality in low-income countries facing increased nutrition deficiency.&lt;br/&gt;(연구에 따르면, 영양 공급원으로 해산물에 더 많이 의존하는 섬나라 경제는 해양 온난화와 산성화로 인해 불균형적인 재정적, 건강적 영향을 받게 될 것입니다. 공동 저자이자 UCSD 글로벌 정책·전략 대학원의 기후 교수인 케이트 리케는 "기후 변화를 초래하는 데 가장 큰 책임이 있고, 그것을 해결할 수 있는 역량이 가장 큰 국가들은 일반적으로 가장 크거나 가장 가까운 시일에 가장 큰 피해를 입을 국가들과 일치하지 않습니다"라고 말했습니다. 탄소 사회적 비용 평가에 해양 데이터를 포함하면, 영양 결핍 증가에 직면한 저소득 국가들의 발병률과 사망률에 대한 영향이 더욱 커짐이 드러납니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the scale of the scientific discovery, Bastien-Olvera and Ricke are optimistic this data will be a wake-up call for international decision-making. “I hope that the high value of ‘blueSCC’ can motivate further investment in adaptation and resilience for ocean systems,” said Ricke, using the term of the ocean-based social cost of carbon and referencing the opportunities to invest in coral reef and mangrove restoration projects.&lt;br/&gt;(이 과학적 발견의 규모에도 불구하고, 바스티엔-올베라와 리케는 이 데이터가 국제적 의사결정에 경종을 울릴 것이라고 낙관합니다. 리케는 해양 기반 탄소 사회적 비용을 의미하는 '블루SCC'라는 용어를 사용하며 산호초와 맹그로브 복원 프로젝트에 투자할 기회를 언급하면서 "'블루SCC'의 높은 가치가 해양 시스템의 적응력과 회복탄력성에 대한 추가 투자를 촉진할 수 있기를 바랍니다"라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Bastien-Olvera believes centering the framework on oceans also recognizes the longstanding conservation approaches of coastal communities, ocean scientists and Indigenous peoples. “For a long time, climate economics treated the ocean values as if it were worth zero,” he said. “This is a first step toward finally acknowledging how wrong that was.”&lt;br/&gt;(한편, 바스티엔-올베라는 이 프레임워크를 해양에 중점을 두는 것이 해안 지역 사회, 해양 과학자, 원주민들의 오랜 보전 접근법을 인정하는 길이기도 하다고 믿습니다. 그는 "오랫동안 기후 경제학은 해양의 가치를 마치 0인 것처럼 취급해 왔습니다"라고 말했습니다. "이것은 그 생각이 얼마나 틀렸는지를 마침내 인정하기 위한 첫 걸음입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article originally appeared on Inside Climate News , a nonprofit, non-partisan news organization that covers climate, energy, and the environment. Sign up for their newsletter here .&lt;br/&gt;(이 기사는 원래 비영리, 비당파 뉴스 조직인 Inside Climate News(기후, 에너지, 환경을 다룸)에 실렸습니다. 뉴스레터 구독은 여기에서 할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/ocean-damage-nearly-doubles-the-cost-of-climate-change/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2245161347-2560x1440.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 03:00:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>10 things I learned from burning myself out with AI coding agents (AI 코딩 에이전트로 지쳐버리며 배운 10가지)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/10-things-i-learned-from-burning-myself-out-with-ai-coding-agents/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/super-programmer-hes-heating-up-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opinion: As software power tools, AI agents may make people busier than ever before.&lt;br/&gt;(의견: 소프트웨어 파워 툴로서 AI 에이전트는 사람들을 그 어느 때보다 바쁘게 만들 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever used a 3D printer, you may recall the wondrous feeling when you first printed something you could have never sculpted or built yourself. Download a model file, load some plastic filament, push a button, and almost like magic, a three-dimensional object appears. But the result isn’t polished and ready for mass production, and creating a novel shape requires more skills than just pushing a button. Interestingly, today’s AI coding agents feel much the same way.&lt;br/&gt;(3D 프린터를 사용해 본 적이 있다면, 자신이 직접 조각하거나 만들 수 없었던 것을 처음으로 출력했을 때의 경이로운 느낌을 기억할지도 모릅니다. 모델 파일을 다운로드하고, 플라스틱 필라멘트를 장전하고, 버튼을 누르면 마치 마법처럼 3차원 물체가 나타납니다. 하지만 결과물은 다듬어지지 않았고 대량 생산 준비가 되어 있지 않으며, 새로운 형태를 창조하는 데는 단순히 버튼을 누르는 것보다 더 많은 기술이 필요합니다. 흥미롭게도, 오늘날의 AI 코딩 에이전트도 이와 매우 비슷하게 느껴집니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since November, I have used Claude Code and Claude Opus 4.5 through a personal Claude Max account to extensively experiment with AI-assisted software development (I have also used OpenAI’s Codex in a similar way, though not as frequently). Fifty projects later, I’ll be frank: I have not had this much fun with a computer since I learned BASIC on my Apple II Plus when I was 9 years old. This opinion comes not as an endorsement but as personal experience: I voluntarily undertook this project, and I paid out of pocket for both OpenAI and Anthropic’s premium AI plans.&lt;br/&gt;(11월부터 저는 개인 Claude Max 계정을 통해 Claude Code와 Claude Opus 4.5를 사용하여 AI 지원 소프트웨어 개발을 광범위하게 실험해왔습니다(비슷한 방식으로 OpenAI의 Codex도 사용했지만, 그렇게 자주는 아니었습니다). 50개의 프로젝트를 거친 후 솔직히 말씀드리자면, 9살 때 Apple II Plus에서 BASIC을 배운 이후로 컴퓨터로 이렇게 재미있게 놀아본 적이 없습니다. 이 의견은 추천이 아니라 개인적인 경험에서 비롯된 것입니다: 저는 자발적으로 이 프로젝트를 시작했고, OpenAI와 Anthropic의 프리미엄 AI 플랜 비용을 모두 개인적으로 지불했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my life, I have dabbled in programming as a utilitarian coder, writing small tools or scripts when needed. In my web development career, I wrote some small tools from scratch, but I primarily modified other people’s code for my needs. Since 1990, I’ve programmed in BASIC, C, Visual Basic, PHP, ASP, Perl, Python, Ruby, MUSHcode, and some others. I am not an expert in any of these languages—I learned just enough to get the job done. I have developed my own hobby games over the years using BASIC, Torque Game Engine, and Godot, so I have some idea of what makes a good architecture for a modular program that can be expanded over time.&lt;br/&gt;(평생 동안 저는 실용적인 코더로서 프로그래밍을 취미삼아 해왔고, 필요할 때 작은 도구나 스크립트를 작성했습니다. 웹 개발 경력에서 저는 몇 가지 작은 도구들을 처음부터 작성하기도 했지만, 주로 다른 사람들의 코드를 제 필요에 맞게 수정했습니다. 1990년 이후로 저는 BASIC, C, Visual Basic, PHP, ASP, Perl, Python, Ruby, MUSHcode 등을 프로그래밍했습니다. 저는 이 언어들 중 어느 것에도 전문가는 아닙니다—그저 일을 해내기에 충분한 정도만 배웠습니다. 저는 수년 동안 BASIC, Torque Game Engine, Godot를 사용하여 나만의 취미 게임들을 개발해왔기 때문에, 시간이 지남에 따라 확장 가능한 모듈식 프로그램을 위한 좋은 아키텍처가 무엇인지에 대한 감이 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claude Code, Codex, and Google’s Gemini CLI , can seemingly perform software miracles on a small scale. They can spit out flashy prototypes of simple applications, user interfaces, and even games, but only as long as they borrow patterns from their training data. Much like a 3D printer, doing production-level work takes far more effort. Creating durable production code, managing a complex project, or crafting something truly novel still requires experience, patience, and skill beyond what today’s AI agents can provide on their own.&lt;br/&gt;(Claude Code, Codex, 그리고 Google의 Gemini CLI는 소규모로 소프트웨어 기적을 수행하는 것처럼 보일 수 있습니다. 그들은 간단한 애플리케이션, 사용자 인터페이스, 심지어 게임의 화려한 프로토타입을 뱉어낼 수 있지만, 그들의 훈련 데이터에서 패턴을 차용하는 한에서만 가능합니다. 3D 프린터와 마찬가지로, 프로덕션 수준의 작업을 수행하는 데는 훨씬 더 많은 노력이 듭니다. 내구성 있는 프로덕션 코드를 생성하거나, 복잡한 프로젝트를 관리하거나, 진정으로 새로운 것을 창조하는 것은 여전히 경험, 인내, 그리고 오늘날의 AI 에이전트가 단독으로 제공할 수 있는 것 이상의 기술을 필요로 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet these tools have opened a world of creative potential in software that was previously closed to me, and they feel personally empowering. Even with that impression, though, I know these are hobby projects, and the limitations of coding agents lead me to believe that veteran software developers probably shouldn’t fear losing their jobs to these tools any time soon. In fact, they may become busier than ever.&lt;br/&gt;(그럼에도 불구하고 이 도구들은 이전에는 제게 닫혀있던 소프트웨어의 창의적 잠재력 세계를 열어주었고, 개인적으로 권한을 부여받은 느낌을 줍니다. 그런 인상에도 불구하고, 저는 이것들이 취미 프로젝트라는 것을 알고 있으며, 코딩 에이전트의 한계는 베테랑 소프트웨어 개발자들이 당분간 이 도구들 때문에 일자리를 잃을까 두려워할 필요가 없을 것이라고 믿게 만듭니다. 사실, 그들은 그 어느 때보다 바빠질 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I have created over 50 demo projects in the past two months, fueled in part by a bout of COVID that left me bedridden with a laptop and a generous 2x Claude usage cap that Anthropic put in place during the last few weeks of December. As I typed furiously all day, my wife kept asking me, “Who are you talking to?”&lt;br/&gt;(지금까지 저는 지난 두 달 동안 50개가 넘는 데모 프로젝트를 만들었는데, 부분적으로는 COVID로 인해 침대에 누워 노트북을 가지고 있었고, Anthropic가 12월 마지막 몇 주 동안 시행한 관대한 2배 Claude 사용 한도 덕분이었습니다. 하루 종일 미친 듯이 타이핑을 하는 동안, 아내는 계속해서 저에게 "누구랑 얘기하는 거야?"라고 물었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see a few of the more interesting results listed on my personal website. Here are 10 interesting things I’ve learned from the process.&lt;br/&gt;(제 개인 웹사이트에 나열된 더 흥미로운 결과물 몇 가지를 볼 수 있습니다. 여기 제가 이 과정에서 배운 10가지 흥미로운 점들이 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with the best AI coding agents available today, humans remain essential to the software development process. Experienced human software developers bring judgment, creativity, and domain knowledge that AI models lack. They know how to architect systems for long-term maintainability, how to balance technical debt against feature velocity, and when to push back when requirements don’t make sense.&lt;br/&gt;(오늘날 이용 가능한 최고의 AI 코딩 에이전트가 있다고 해도, 인간은 여전히 소프트웨어 개발 과정에서 필수적입니다. 경험 많은 인간 소프트웨어 개발자는 AI 모델이 결여한 판단력, 창의성, 도메인 지식을 가져옵니다. 그들은 장기적인 유지 관리성을 위해 시스템을 설계하는 방법, 기능 개발 속도에 맞춰 기술 부채를 균형 잡는 방법, 그리고 요구사항이 말이 안 될 때 어떻게 반박할지 알고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For hobby projects like mine, I can get away with a lot of sloppiness. But for production work, having someone who understands version control, incremental backups, testing one feature at a time, and debugging complex interactions between systems makes all the difference. Knowing something about how good software development works helps a lot when guiding an AI coding agent—the tool amplifies your existing knowledge rather than replacing it.&lt;br/&gt;(저와 같은 취미 프로젝트의 경우, 저는 많은 부주의를 용인할 수 있습니다. 하지만 프로덕션 작업의 경우, 버전 관리, 증분 백업, 한 번에 하나의 기능 테스트, 시스템 간 복잡한 상호작용 디버깅을 이해하는 사람이 있다는 것은 모든 것이 달라집니다. 좋은 소프트웨어 개발이 어떻게 이루어지는지에 대한 지식은 AI 코딩 에이전트를 안내할 때 많은 도움이 됩니다—이 도구는 당신의 기존 지식을 대체하는 것이 아니라 증폭시킵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As independent AI researcher Simon Willison wrote in a post distinguishing serious AI-assisted development from casual “ vibe coding ,” “AI tools amplify existing expertise. The more skills and experience you have as a software engineer the faster and better the results you can get from working with LLMs and coding agents.”&lt;br/&gt;(독립 AI 연구원 Simon Willison이 진지한 AI 지원 개발과 캐주얼한 "바이브 코딩"을 구분하는 글에서 썼듯이, "AI 도구는 기존 전문성을 증폭시킵니다. 소프트웨어 엔지니어로서 당신이 가진 기술과 경험이 많을수록 LLM과 코딩 에이전트와 협업하여 얻을 수 있는 결과는 더 빠르고 더 좋아집니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With AI assistance, you don’t have to remember how to do everything. You just need to know what you want to do.&lt;br/&gt;(AI의 도움을 받으면, 모든 것을 어떻게 하는지 기억할 필요가 없습니다. 당신이 무엇을 하고 싶은지 알기만 하면 됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I like to remind myself that coding agents are software tools best used to enact human ideas, not autonomous coding employees. They are not people (and not people replacements) no matter how the companies behind them might market them.&lt;br/&gt;(그래서 저는 코딩 에이전트가 자율적인 코딩 직원이 아니라 인간의 아이디어를 실행하기에 가장 적합한 소프트웨어 도구라고 스스로 상기시키는 것을 좋아합니다. 그들을 뒷받침하는 회사들이 어떻게 마케팅하든, 그들은 사람이 아니며(그리고 사람을 대체하는 것도 아닙니다).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, everything you do on a computer was once a manual process. Programming a computer like the ENIAC involved literally making physical bits (connections) with wire on a plugboard . The history of programming has been one of increasing automation, so even though this AI-assisted leap is somewhat startling, one could think of these tools as an advancement similar to the advent of high-level languages, automated compilers and debugger tools, or GUI-based IDEs. They can automate many tasks, but managing the overarching project scope still falls to the person telling the tool what to do.&lt;br/&gt;(생각해보면, 컴퓨터로 하는 모든 것은 한때 수동 과정이었습니다. ENIAC과 같은 컴퓨터를 프로그래밍하는 것은 말 그대로 플러그보드에 와이어로 물리적 비트(연결)를 만드는 것을 포함했습니다. 프로그래밍의 역사는 증가하는 자동화의 역사였습니다. 따라서 이 AI 지원 도약이 다소 놀랍긴 하지만, 누군가는 이 도구들을 고급 언어, 자동화된 컴파일러 및 디버거 도구, 또는 GUI 기반 IDE의 등장과 유사한 진보로 생각할 수 있습니다. 그들은 많은 작업을 자동화할 수 있지만, 전체적인 프로젝트 범위를 관리하는 것은 여전히 도구에게 무엇을 해야 할지 지시하는 사람의 몫입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they can have rapidly compounding benefits. I’ve now used AI tools to write better tools—such as changing the source of an emulator so a coding agent can use it directly—and those improved tools are already having ripple effects. But a human must be in the loop for the best execution of my vision. This approach has kept me very busy, and contrary to some prevailing fears about people becoming dumber due to AI, I have learned many new things along the way.&lt;br/&gt;(그리고 그들은 빠르게 복리 효과를 낼 수 있습니다. 저는 이제 AI 도구를 사용하여 더 나은 도구를 작성했습니다—예를 들어 에뮬레이터의 소스를 변경하여 코딩 에이전트가 직접 사용할 수 있도록 하는 것—그리고 그 개선된 도구들은 이미 파급 효과를 내고 있습니다. 하지만 제 비전을 최상으로 실행하기 위해서는 인간이 루프 안에 있어야 합니다. 이 접근 방식은 저를 매우 바쁘게 만들었고, AI 때문에 사람들이 더 멍청해질 것이라는 일부 우려와는 반대로, 저는 그 과정에서 많은 새로운 것들을 배웠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all AI models based on the Transformer architecture , the large language models (LLMs) that underpin today’s coding agents have a significant limitation: They can only reliably apply knowledge gleaned from training data, and they have a limited ability to generalize that knowledge to novel domains not represented in that data.&lt;br/&gt;(Transformer 아키텍처를 기반으로 하는 모든 AI 모델과 마찬가지로, 오늘날의 코딩 에이전트를 뒷받침하는 대규모 언어 모델(LLM)은 중요한 한계가 있습니다: 그들은 훈련 데이터에서 얻은 지식만을 신뢰성 있게 적용할 수 있으며, 그 지식을 해당 데이터에 나타나지 않은 새로운 도메인으로 일반화하는 능력이 제한적입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is training data? In this case, when building coding-flavored LLMs, AI companies download millions of examples of software code from sources like GitHub and use them to make the AI models. Companies later specialize them for coding through fine-tuning processes.&lt;br/&gt;(훈련 데이터란 무엇일까요? 이 경우, 코딩 특화 LLM을 구축할 때 AI 회사들은 GitHub와 같은 소스에서 수백만 개의 소프트웨어 코드 예제를 다운로드하여 AI 모델을 만드는 데 사용합니다. 회사들은 이후 미세 조정 과정을 통해 코딩에 특화시킵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability of AI agents to use trial and error—attempting something and then trying again—helps mitigate the brittleness of LLMs somewhat. But it’s not perfect, and it can be frustrating to see a coding agent spin its wheels trying and failing at a task repeatedly, either because it doesn’t know how to do it or because it previously learned how to solve a problem but then forgot because the context window got compacted (more on that here ).&lt;br/&gt;(AI 에이전트가 시행착오를 사용하는 능력—무언가를 시도하고 다시 시도하는 것—은 LLM의 취약성을 어느 정도 완화하는 데 도움이 됩니다. 하지만 완벽하지는 않으며, 코딩 에이전트가 작업을 반복적으로 시도하고 실패하며 헛돌고 있는 것을 보는 것은 좌절스러울 수 있습니다. 그것이 방법을 모르기 때문이거나, 이전에 문제를 해결하는 방법을 배웠지만 컨텍스트 창이 압축되어 잊어버렸기 때문일 수 있습니다(여기에 대해 더 자세히).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get around this, it helps to have the AI model take copious notes as it goes along about how it solved certain problems so that future instances of the agent can learn from them again. You also want to set ground rules in the claude.md file that the agent reads when it begins its session.&lt;br/&gt;(이를 극복하기 위해, AI 모델이 특정 문제를 어떻게 해결했는지에 대해 진행하면서 상세한 노트를 많이 작성하도록 하는 것이 도움이 됩니다. 그래야 미래의 에이전트 인스턴스가 그것들을 다시 배울 수 있습니다. 또한 에이전트가 세션을 시작할 때 읽는 claude.md 파일에 기본 규칙을 설정하는 것도 좋습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brittleness means that coding agents are almost frighteningly good at what they’ve been trained and fine-tuned on—modern programming languages, JavaScript, HTML, and similar well-represented technologies—and generally terrible at tasks on which they have not been deeply trained, such as 6502 Assembly or programming an Atari 800 game with authentic-looking character graphics.&lt;br/&gt;(이 취약성은 코딩 에이전트가 훈련되고 미세 조정된 것—현대 프로그래밍 언어, JavaScript, HTML 및 유사하게 잘 표현된 기술들—에 대해서는 거의 무섭도록 뛰어나지만, 6502 어셈블리나 Atari 800 게임을 진짜 같은 캐릭터 그래픽으로 프로그래밍하는 것과 같이 깊이 훈련되지 않은 작업에 대해서는 일반적으로 형편없다는 것을 의미합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me five minutes to make a nice HTML5 demo with Claude but a week of torturous trial and error, plus actual systematic design on my part, to make a similar demo of an Atari 800 game. To do so, I had to use Claude Code to invent several tools, like command-line emulators and MCP servers , that allow it to peek into the operation of the Atari 800’s memory and chipset to even begin to make it happen.&lt;br/&gt;(Claude로 멋진 HTML5 데모를 만드는 데는 5분이 걸렸지만, 비슷한 Atari 800 게임 데모를 만드는 데는 고통스러운 일주일의 시행착오와 제 자신의 실제 체계적인 설계가 필요했습니다. 이를 위해 저는 Claude Code를 사용하여 명령줄 에뮬레이터와 MCP 서버와 같은 여러 도구를 발명해야 했습니다. 이 도구들은 Atari 800의 메모리와 칩셋 동작을 엿볼 수 있게 해주어 그것을 시작할 수 있게 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to what might poetically be called “preconceived notions” baked into a coding model’s neural network (more technically, statistical semantic associations), it can be difficult to get AI agents to create truly novel things, even if you carefully spell out what you want.&lt;br/&gt;(코딩 모델의 신경망에 구워진(더 기술적으로 말하면 통계적 의미론적 연관) 시적으로 "선입견"이라고 부를 수 있는 것 때문에, 당신이 원하는 것을 조심스럽게 설명하더라도 AI 에이전트가 진정으로 새로운 것을 창조하도록 하는 것은 어려울 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I spent four days trying to get Claude Code to create an Atari 800 version of my HTML game Violent Checkers , but it had trouble because in the game’s design, the squares on the checkerboard don’t matter beyond their starting positions. No matter how many times I told the agent (and made notes in my Claude project files), it would come back to trying to center the pieces to the squares, snap them within squares, or use the squares as a logical basis of the game’s calculations when they should really just form a background image.&lt;br/&gt;(예를 들어, 저는 Claude Code가 제 HTML 게임 '폭력적인 체커'의 Atari 800 버전을 만들도록 하는 데 4일을 소비했습니다. 하지만 게임 디자인상 체커보드의 사각형들은 시작 위치를 넘어서는 중요성이 없는데도 불구하고, 에이전트에게 몇 번을 말하고(제 Claude 프로젝트 파일에 메모를 남기고)도, 에이전트는 조각들을 사각형 중앙에 맞추거나, 사각형 안에 고정시키거나, 게임 계산의 논리적 기초로 사각형을 사용하려고 돌아왔습니다. 사실 그 사각형들은 단지 배경 이미지를 형성해야 했는데도 말이죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get around this in the Atari 800 version, I started over and told Claude that I was creating a game with a UFO (instead of a circular checker piece) flying over a field of adjacent squares—never once mentioning the words “checker,” “checkerboard,” or “checkers.” With that approach, I got the results I wanted.&lt;br/&gt;(Atari 800 버전에서 이를 극복하기 위해, 저는 처음부터 다시 시작하여 Claude에게 "체커", "체커보드", "체커스"라는 단어를 한 번도 언급하지 않고, 인접한 사각형들 위를 날아다니는 UFO(원형 체커 조각 대신)가 있는 게임을 만들고 있다고 말했습니다. 그 접근 방식으로 저는 원하는 결과를 얻었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this matter? Because with LLMs, context is everything, and in language, context changes meaning. Take the word “bank” and add the words “river” or “central” in front of it, and see how the meaning changes. In a way, words act as addresses that unlock the semantic relationships encoded in a neural network. So if you put “checkerboard” and “game” in the context, the model’s self-attention process links up a massive web of semantic associations about how checkers games should work, and that semantic baggage throws things off.&lt;br/&gt;(왜 이것이 중요할까요? LLM에서는 컨텍스트가 전부이며, 언어에서 컨텍스트는 의미를 바꿉니다. "bank"라는 단어에 "river"나 "central"이라는 단어를 앞에 붙여보고 의미가 어떻게 변하는지 보세요. 어떤 면에서, 단어들은 신경망에 인코딩된 의미론적 관계를 해제하는 주소 역할을 합니다. 따라서 "체커보드"와 "게임"을 컨텍스트에 넣으면, 모델의 자기 주의 과정은 체커 게임이 어떻게 작동해야 하는지에 대한 방대한 의미론적 연관 웹을 연결하고, 그 의미론적 짐이 일을 엉망으로 만듭니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of tricks can help AI coders navigate around these limitations. First, avoid contaminating the context with irrelevant information. Second, when the agent gets stuck, try this prompt: “What information do you need that would let you implement this perfectly right now? What tools are available to you that you could use to discover that information systematically without guessing?” This forces the agent to identify (semantically link up) its own knowledge gaps, spelled out in the context window and subject to future action, instead of flailing around blindly.&lt;br/&gt;(몇 가지 트릭이 AI 코더들이 이러한 한계를 극복하는 데 도움이 될 수 있습니다. 첫째, 관련 없는 정보로 컨텍스트를 오염시키지 마세요. 둘째, 에이전트가 막히면 이 프롬프트를 시도해보세요: "지금 당장 이것을 완벽하게 구현할 수 있게 해줄 정보가 무엇이 필요합니까? 추측 없이 체계적으로 그 정보를 발견하는 데 사용할 수 있는 도구들은 무엇입니까?" 이것은 에이전트가 맹목적으로 허우적대는 대신, 자신의 지식 격차를 식별(의미론적으로 연결)하도록 강제합니다. 이 격차는 컨텍스트 창에 명시되고 향후 조치의 대상이 됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first 90 percent of an AI coding project comes in fast and amazes you. The last 10 percent involves tediously filling in the details through back-and-forth trial-and-error conversation with the agent. Tasks that require deeper insight or understanding than what the agent can provide still require humans to make the connections and guide it in the right direction. The limitations we discussed above can also cause your project to hit a brick wall.&lt;br/&gt;(AI 코딩 프로젝트의 첫 90%는 빠르게 진행되어 당신을 놀라게 합니다. 마지막 10%는 에이전트와의 왕복 시행착오 대화를 통해 세부 사항을 지루하게 채우는 것을 포함합니다. 에이전트가 제공할 수 있는 것보다 더 깊은 통찰이나 이해를 필요로 하는 작업은 여전히 인간이 연결을 만들고 올바른 방향으로 안내해야 합니다. 위에서 논의한 한계들도 당신의 프로젝트가 벽에 부딪히게 할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I have observed over the years, larger LLMs can potentially make deeper contextual connections than smaller ones. They have more parameters (encoded data points), and those parameters are linked in more multidimensional ways, so they tend to have a deeper map of semantic relationships. As deep as those go, it seems that human brains still have an even deeper grasp of semantic connections and can make wild semantic jumps that LLMs tend not to.&lt;br/&gt;(제가 수년간 관찰한 바에 따르면, 더 큰 LLM은 잠재적으로 더 작은 LLM보다 더 깊은 컨텍스트 연결을 만들 수 있습니다. 그들은 더 많은 매개변수(인코딩된 데이터 포인트)를 가지고 있으며, 그 매개변수들은 더 다차원적인 방식으로 연결되어 있기 때문에 더 깊은 의미론적 관계 지도를 가지는 경향이 있습니다. 그 지도가 아무리 깊어도, 인간의 뇌는 여전히 의미론적 연결을 훨씬 더 깊이 파악하고 있으며, LLM이 잘 하지 않는 급격한 의미론적 도약을 할 수 있는 것 같습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creativity, in this sense, may be when you jump from, say, basketball to how bubbles form in soap film and somehow make a useful connection that leads to a breakthrough. Instead, LLMs tend to follow conventional semantic paths that are more conservative and entirely guided by mapped-out relationships from the training data. That limits their creative potential unless the prompter unlocks it by guiding the LLM to make novel semantic connections. That takes skill and creativity on the part of the operator, which once again shows the role of LLMs as tools used by humans rather than independent thinking machines.&lt;br/&gt;(이러한 의미에서 창의성은, 예를 들어 농구에서 비누막에 거품이 어떻게 형성되는지로 뛰어넘어 어떻게 유용한 연결을 만들어 돌파구로 이끄는 것일 수 있습니다. 대신, LLM은 더 보수적이고 훈련 데이터에서 매핑된 관계에 의해 완전히 안내되는 전통적인 의미론적 경로를 따르는 경향이 있습니다. 이는 프롬프터가 LLM이 새로운 의미론적 연결을 만들도록 안내하여 그것을 해제하지 않는 한, 그들의 창의적)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/10-things-i-learned-from-burning-myself-out-with-ai-coding-agents/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/super-programmer-hes-heating-up-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 03:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meet Veronika, the tool-using cow (도구를 사용하는 소 베로니카를 만나다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/meet-veronika-the-tool-using-cow/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/cowtool1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronika uses sticks to scratch herself, suggesting scientists have underestimated cow cognition&lt;br/&gt;(베로니카는 몸을 긁기 위해 나뭇가지를 사용하며, 이는 과학자들이 소의 인지 능력을 과소평가했음을 시사한다)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far Side fans might recall a classic 1982 cartoon called “ Cow Tools ,” featuring a cow standing next to a jumble of strange objects—the joke being that cows don’t use tools. That’s why a pet Swiss brown cow in Austria named Veronika has caused a bit of a sensation: she likes to pick up random sticks and use them to scratch herself. According to a new paper published in the journal Current Biology, this is a form of multipurpose tool use and suggests that the cognitive capabilities of cows have been underestimated by scientists.&lt;br/&gt;('파 사이드' 팬들은 1982년 고전 만화 "Cow Tools(소 도구)"를 기억할지 모른다. 이 만화는 이상한 물건들이 뒤죽박죽 쌓여 있는 옆에 서 있는 소를 그렸는데, 농담의 핵심은 소가 도구를 사용하지 않는다는 것이었다. 그래서 오스트리아에 사는 애완용 스위스 갈색소 베로니카가 약간의 센세이션을 일으킨 것이다: 그녀는 무작위로 나뭇가지를 집어들어 자신의 몸을 긁는 것을 좋아한다. 저널 '커런트 바이올로지'에 발표된 새로운 논문에 따르면, 이는 다목적 도구 사용의 한 형태이며 소의 인지 능력이 과학자들에 의해 과소평가되었음을 시사한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As previously reported , tool use was once thought to be one of the defining features of humans, but examples of it were eventually observed in primates and other mammals. Dolphins can toss objects as a form of play which some scientists consider to be a type of tool use, particularly when it involves another member of the same species. Potential purposes include a means of communication, social bonding, or aggressiveness. (Octopuses have also been observed engaging in similar throwing behavior.)&lt;br/&gt;(이전에 보도된 바와 같이, 도구 사용은 한때 인간을 정의하는 특징 중 하나로 여겨졌지만, 결국 영장류 및 다른 포유류에서도 그 사례가 관찰되었다. 돌고래는 물건을 던지는 놀이를 하는데, 일부 과학자들은 이를 도구 사용의 한 유형으로 간주하며, 특히 같은 종의 다른 개체를 대상으로 할 때 그렇다. 잠재적 목적에는 의사소통 수단, 사회적 유대감 형성, 또는 공격성 등이 포함될 수 있다. (문어들도 비슷한 던지기 행동을 하는 것이 관찰되었다.))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the biggest surprise came when birds were observed using tools in the wild. After all, birds are the only surviving dinosaurs, and mammals and dinosaurs hadn’t shared a common ancestor for hundreds of millions of years. In the wild, observed tool use has been limited to the corvids (crows and jays), which show a variety of other complex behaviors—they’ll remember your face and recognize the passing of their dead .&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 가장 큰 놀라움은 야생에서 새들이 도구를 사용하는 것이 관찰되었을 때 찾아왔다. 결국, 새들은 유일하게 살아남은 공룡이며, 포유류와 공룡은 수억 년 동안 공통 조상을 공유하지 않았다. 야생에서 관찰된 도구 사용은 까마귀과(까마귀와 어치)에 국한되어 왔으며, 이들은 다양한 다른 복잡한 행동을 보인다—그들은 당신의 얼굴을 기억하고 죽은 동료의 죽음을 인식한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, a captive cockatoo named Figaro was trying to retrieve a stone that had fallen behind a metal divider and picked up a stick to increase his reach. He failed but then the researchers placed a nut behind the divider as an added incentive. Figaro initially picked up a stick from the enclosure’s floor, but this proved to be too short to reach the food. So, he actually splintered off a piece of the enclosure’s wooden base, and successfully used that to pull the nut towards the wire until he could use his beak to grab it.&lt;br/&gt;(2012년, 피가로라는 이름의 사육된 카카투가 금속 칸막이 뒤로 떨어진 돌을 회수하려고 시도하다가, 도달 범위를 늘리기 위해 나뭇가지를 집어들었다. 그는 실패했지만, 이후 연구자들은 추가 동기부여로 칸막이 뒤에 견과류를 놓았다. 피가로는 처음에 우리 바닥에서 나뭇가지를 집어들었지만, 이것은 음식에 닿기에는 너무 짧은 것으로 판명되었다. 그래서 그는 실제로 우리의 나무 바닥에서 조각을 떼어내어, 그것을 성공적으로 사용하여 견과류를 철망 쪽으로 끌어당겨 부리로 잡을 수 있었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figaro used a different tool in each subsequent trial, and in most cases made some modifications to it before successfully retrieving a nut. In at least one case, he performed four separate modifications before putting a stick to use in retrieving the nut. He also managed to use the tool in two different ways, often alternating dragging and sweeping motions in his efforts to pull the food within reach. Other cockatoos who repeatedly watched Figaro’s performance were also able to do so. By 2022, Figaro and his cockatoo cronies had learned how to combine tools —in this case, a stick and a ball—to play a rudimentary form of “golf.”&lt;br/&gt;(피가로는 이후의 각 시도마다 다른 도구를 사용했으며, 대부분의 경우 견과류를 성공적으로 회수하기 전에 약간의 수정을 가했다. 적어도 한 경우에는, 견과류를 회수하는 데 나뭇가지를 사용하기 전에 네 번의 별도 수정을 수행했다. 그는 또한 도구를 두 가지 다른 방식으로 사용하는 데 성공했는데, 음식을 손이 닿는 범위 안으로 끌어오기 위한 노력에서 끄는 동작과 쓸어내리는 동작을 종종 번갈아 가며 사용했다. 피가로의 수행을 반복적으로 지켜본 다른 카카투들도 그렇게 할 수 있었다. 2022년까지, 피가로와 그의 카카투 친구들은 도구를 결합하는 방법—이 경우, 나뭇가지와 공—을 배워 초보적인 형태의 "골프"를 즐길 수 있게 되었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the scientific interest in animal tool use, there has been almost no research into the cognitive capabilities of livestock like cows, or their possible tool use, according to the authors of this latest paper. Alice Auersperg, a cognitive biologist at the University of Veterinary Medicine in Vienna, was intrigued when she watched the footage of Veronika’s scratching behavior. “It was clear that this was not accidental,” said Auersperg . “This was a meaningful example of tool use.”&lt;br/&gt;(동물의 도구 사용에 대한 모든 과학적 관심에도 불구하고, 소와 같은 가축의 인지 능력이나 그들의 가능한 도구 사용에 대한 연구는 거의 이루어지지 않았다고 이 최신 논문의 저자들은 말한다. 비엔나 수의과대학의 인지 생물학자 앨리스 오이어스페르그는 베로니카의 긁기 행동 영상을 보고 흥미를 느꼈다. "이것이 우연이 아니라는 것은 분명했습니다."라고 오이어스페르그는 말했다. "이것은 의미 있는 도구 사용의 사례였습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test the extent of Veronika’s tool use, Auersperg and her postdoc, Antonio Osuna-Mascaro, visited the farm where Veronika lives. Her owner, Witgar Wiegele, is an organic farmer and baker who keeps the cow as a pet. With Wiegele’s permission, they conducted a series of randomized trials with a deck scrub broom, chosen for its asymmetrical shape, placed in different orientations. The pair recorded 76 instances of Veronika using the broom over seven sessions of ten trials.&lt;br/&gt;(베로니카의 도구 사용 정도를 테스트하기 위해, 오이어스페르그와 그녀의 박사후 연구원 안토니오 오수나-마스카로는 베로니카가 사는 농장을 방문했다. 그녀의 주인 비트가르 비게레는 유기농 농부이자 베이커로, 이 소를 애완동물로 키우고 있다. 비게레의 허락 하에, 그들은 비대칭 형태로 선택된 갑판용 스크럽 브러시를 다양한 방향으로 놓고 일련의 무작위 시험을 실시했다. 두 사람은 10번의 시도로 구성된 7회의 세션 동안 베로니카가 브러시를 사용한 76건의 사례를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each time, Veronika used her tongue to lift and position the broom in her mouth, clamping down with her teeth for a stable grip. This enabled her to use the broom to scratch otherwise hard-to-reach areas on the rear half of her body. Veronika seemed to prefer the brush end to the stick end (i.e., the exploitation of distinct properties of a single object for different functions) although which end she used depended on body area. For example, she used the brush end to scratch her upper body using a scrubbing motion, while using the stick end to scratch more sensitive lower areas like her udders and belly skin flaps using precisely targeted gentle forward pushes. She also anticipated the need to adjust her grip.&lt;br/&gt;(매번 베로니카는 혀를 사용하여 브러시를 들어 입에 위치시켰고, 이를 치아로 꽉 물어 안정적인 그립을 유지했다. 이것은 그녀가 브러시를 사용하여 그렇지 않으면 닿기 어려운 몸 뒷부분의 부위를 긁을 수 있게 해주었다. 베로니카는 브러시 끝을 막대 끝보다 선호하는 것처럼 보였지만(즉, 단일 물체의 뚜렷한 특성을 다른 기능에 활용), 어느 쪽 끝을 사용하는지는 몸 부위에 달려 있었다. 예를 들어, 그녀는 브러시 끝을 사용하여 몸 윗부분을 문지르는 동작으로 긁었고, 반면에 막대 끝을 사용하여 젖통과 배의 피부 주름과 같은 더 민감한 아래쪽 부위를 정확하게 조준된 부드러운 앞으로 밀기 동작으로 긁었다. 그녀는 또한 그립을 조정해야 할 필요성을 예상했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors conclude that this behavior demonstrates “goal-directed, context-sensitive tooling,” as well as versatility in her tool-use anticipation, and fine-motor targeting. Veronika’s scratching behavior is likely motivated by the desire to relieve itching from insect bites, but her open, complex environment, compared to most livestock, and regular interactions with humans enabled her unusual cognitive abilities to emerge.&lt;br/&gt;(저자들은 이 행동이 "목표 지향적이고 상황에 민감한 도구 사용" 뿐만 아니라, 그녀의 도구 사용 예측에서의 다양성, 그리고 정밀 운동 조준 능력을 보여준다고 결론지었다. 베로니카의 긁기 행동은 아마도 곤충 물림으로 인한 가려움을 완화하려는 욕구에 의해 동기가 부여되었을 것이지만, 대부분의 가축에 비해 그녀의 개방적이고 복잡한 환경, 그리고 인간과의 정기적인 상호작용이 그녀의 특이한 인지 능력이 나타나도록 가능하게 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The implication is that this kind of technical problem-solving is not confined to species with large brains and hands or beaks. “[Veronika] did not fashion tools like the cow in Gary Larson’s cartoon, but she selected, adjusted, and used one with notable dexterity and flexibility,” the authors wrote. “Perhaps the real absurdity lies not in imagining a tool-using cow, but in assuming such a thing could never exist.”&lt;br/&gt;(이것이 의미하는 바는 이러한 종류의 기술적 문제 해결이 큰 뇌와 손 또는 부리를 가진 종에만 국한되지 않는다는 것이다. "[베로니카는] 게리 라슨의 만화 속 소처럼 도구를 만들지는 않았지만, 그녀는 주목할 만한 민첩성과 유연성으로 하나를 선택, 조정, 사용했습니다."라고 저자들은 썼다. "아마도 진정한 부조리는 도구를 사용하는 소를 상상하는 데 있는 것이 아니라, 그러한 것이 결코 존재할 수 없다고 가정하는 데 있을 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOI: Current Biology, 2025. 10.1016/j.cub.2025.11.059 ( About DOIs ).&lt;br/&gt;(DOI: Current Biology, 2025. 10.1016/j.cub.2025.11.059 (DOIs 정보).)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/meet-veronika-the-tool-using-cow/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/cowtool1-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:00:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The race to build a super-large ground telescope is likely down to two competitors (초대형 지상 망원경 건설 경쟁, 이제 두 강자만 남았다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/as-europes-large-ground-telescope-project-advances-how-is-its-us-competitor-faring/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GMT-Rendering-IDOM-Enclosure-2024-1-scaled-1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars checks in with the new president of the Giant Magellan Telescope.&lt;br/&gt;(아스 테크니카가 자이언트 마젤란 망원경의 새 총괄 이사와 이야기를 나눴다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been writing about the Giant Magellan Telescope for a long time. Nearly two decades ago , for example, I wrote that time was “running out” in the race to build the next great optical telescope on the ground.&lt;br/&gt;(나는 오랫동안 자이언트 마젤란 망원경에 대해 글을 써왔다. 예를 들어, 거의 20년 전에는 차세대 대형 지상 광학 망원경 건설 경쟁에서 시간이 "다 되어간다"고 쓴 적이 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time the proposed telescope was one of three contenders to make a giant leap in mirror size from the roughly 10-meter diameter instruments that existed then, to approximately 30 meters. This represented a huge increase in light-gathering potential, allowing astronomers to see much further into the universe—and therefore back into time—with far greater clarity.&lt;br/&gt;(당시 제안된 이 망원경은 당시 존재하던 직경 약 10미터급 장비에서 약 30미터로 거울 크기를 도약시키려는 세 개의 후보 중 하나였다. 이는 빛을 모으는 능력이 엄청나게 증가함을 의미했으며, 천문학자들이 훨씬 더 먼 우주, 즉 더 먼 과거를 훨씬 더 선명하게 관측할 수 있게 해줄 것이었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then the projects have advanced at various rates. An international consortium to build the Thirty Meter Telescope in Hawaii ran into local protests that have bogged down development. Its future came further into question when the US National Science Foundation dropped support for the project in favor of the Giant Magellan Telescope. Meanwhile the European Extremely Large Telescope (ELT) has advanced on a faster schedule, and this 39.5-meter telescope could observe its first light in 2029.&lt;br/&gt;(그 이후로 이 프로젝트들은 각기 다른 속도로 진전을 보였다. 하와이에 30미터 망원경(TMT)을 건설하려는 국제 컨소시엄은 현지 주민들의 반대로 개발이 지연되었다. 미국 국립과학재단(NSF)이 이 프로젝트 지원을 중단하고 자이언트 마젤란 망원경(GMT)을 지지하기로 하면서 그 미래는 더욱 불확실해졌다. 한편, 유럽 극대망원경(ELT)은 더 빠른 일정으로 진행되어 이 39.5미터 망원경은 2029년에 첫 관측을 시작할 수 있을 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves the Magellan telescope. Originally backers of the GMT intended it to be fully operational by now, but it has faced funding and technology challenges. It has a price tag of approximately $2 billion, and although it is smaller than the European project, the 25.4-meter telescope now represents the best avenue for US-based astronomy to remain competitive in the field.&lt;br/&gt;(이제 마젤란 망원경이 남았다. 원래 GMT 후원자들은 지금쯤 완전 가동될 것으로 기대했지만, 자금과 기술적 도전에 직면했다. 약 20억 달러의 가격표가 붙은 이 25.4미터 망원경은 유럽 프로젝트보다는 작지만, 현재 미국 기반 천문학이 이 분야에서 경쟁력을 유지할 수 있는 최선의 길을 대표한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given all of this, I recently spoke with University of Texas at Austin astronomer Dan Jaffe, who is the new president of the telescope’s executive team, to get an update on things. Here is a lightly edited transcript of our conversation.&lt;br/&gt;(이 모든 것을 고려하여, 나는 최근 망원경 운영팀의 새 총괄 이사이자 텍사스 대학교 오스틴 캠퍼스의 천문학자인 댄 재프와 이야기를 나누어 최근 상황을 알아보았다. 다음은 우리 대화를 약간 편집한 내용이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars Technica : What should we know about the Giant Magellan Telescope?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 테크니카 : 자이언트 마젤란 망원경에 대해 우리가 알아야 할 것은 무엇인가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Jaffe : This is going to be one of the premier next-generation optical infrared telescopes in the world. It will give the United States astronomical community access that helps us to be a leading nation in this field, inspire students to go into science and engineering, and really enrich the human experience through the new knowledge that we get about the nature of the universe. So I think it covers both this kind of aspiration that we have to enrich humanity in some way, to help foster the future economy by bringing more people into these technical fields, and also by driving technology in some areas. The kinds of work we’re doing on adaptive optics, for example, in building sensitive detector systems and spectrometers, drive the frontier of what you can do with these systems.&lt;br/&gt;(댄 재프 : 이것은 세계 최고의 차세대 광학/적외선 망원경 중 하나가 될 것입니다. 미국 천문학계에 접근성을 제공하여 우리가 이 분야의 선도국가가 되도록 도울 것이며, 학생들이 과학과 공학에 진출하도록 고무하고, 우리가 우주의 본성에 대해 얻는 새로운 지식을 통해 인류의 경험을 진정으로 풍요롭게 할 것입니다. 그래서 저는 이것이 우리가 인류를 어떤 식으로든 풍요롭게 하고, 더 많은 사람들을 이러한 기술 분야로 끌어들여 미래 경제를 촉진하며, 또한 일부 분야에서 기술을 주도하려는 우리의 열망을 모두 포괄한다고 생각합니다. 예를 들어, 우리가 적응광학, 민감한 검출기 시스템 및 분광기 구축에서 하고 있는 종류의 작업은 이러한 시스템으로 할 수 있는 것의 최전선을 주도합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Why has this taken so long?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 왜 이렇게 오래 걸렸나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : Well, it’s large, it’s complicated, and it’s unique. Those are the three things together that drive that. It involves a large amount of technology that’s needed to make something like this go in terms of size and precision and speed. And those things together make it take a long time, and also cost a fairly large amount of money. We’ve raised about half of the money. And many of the most difficult parts of the project are well underway in terms of construction or prototyping. All seven mirrors that are needed for the telescope are cast, and a number of them are already finished.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 음, 규모가 크고, 복잡하며, 독특하기 때문입니다. 이 세 가지가 합쳐져서 그렇게 만듭니다. 크기, 정밀도, 속도 측면에서 이런 것을 작동시키기 위해 필요한 많은 양의 기술이 포함됩니다. 그리고 그런 것들이 합쳐져서 오랜 시간이 걸리게 하고, 상당히 많은 비용이 들게 합니다. 우리는 필요한 자금의 약 절반을 모았습니다. 그리고 프로젝트의 가장 어려운 부분들 중 많은 부분이 건설이나 시제품 제작 측면에서 잘 진행 중입니다. 망원경에 필요한 7개의 거울은 모두 주조되었고, 그 중 몇 개는 이미 완성되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : How is the telescope’s site in the Atacama Desert in Chile coming along?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 칠레 아타카마 사막에 있는 망원경 부지 상황은 어떻습니까?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : We’ve broken ground on the site, and it’s been leveled in the foundation. Areas have been dug out, and the utilities have all been installed. It’s now kind of in a free state, waiting for some of the other parts of the project to catch up to it.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 우리는 현장에서 착공했고, 기초 공사가 완료되어 평탄해졌습니다. 구역이 굴착되었고, 모든 기반 시설이 설치되었습니다. 이제는 일종의 대기 상태로, 프로젝트의 다른 부분들이 따라잡기를 기다리고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Since the European telescope is now likely to be completed first, does that mean GMT will miss out on a lot of science discoveries?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 유럽 망원경이 이제 먼저 완공될 가능성이 높으니, GMT가 많은 과학적 발견을 놓치게 될까요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : These telescopes are complementary in many ways. It depends not just on the glass itself, but on the instruments you put behind them, and what they’re capable of. And I expect that at this size scale there’ll be plenty of discoveries for all of us to make. And also with other things coming online, like the (Vera) Rubin telescope that will provide new types of phenomena to investigate, there won’t be a list of things we’ve got to do, and the first person to get to the finish line will do them. I think there’s going to be exciting science for all of us. Our community is growing right now. MIT and Northwestern have joined our consortium in the last year-and-a-half or two years, and I think we’re going to have plenty of very exciting science to do. As a public-private partnership for the whole US community, there’s a tremendous amount of brain power out there to be creative about new things and to be innovative, both in the kind of instrumentation we build and in the ways we use it.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 이 망원경들은 여러 면에서 상호 보완적입니다. 단지 유리 자체뿐만 아니라 그 뒤에 설치하는 장비와 그 장비들의 능력에 달려 있습니다. 그리고 저는 이 규모에서는 우리 모두가 할 발견이 많을 것이라고 예상합니다. 또한 (베라) 루빈 망원경처럼 새로운 유형의 현상을 조사할 수 있게 해주는 다른 것들이 등장하면서, 우리가 해야 할 일들의 목록이 있고 결승선에 먼저 도달한 사람이 그것들을 하는 식이 되지는 않을 것입니다. 저는 우리 모두에게 흥미로운 과학이 있을 것이라고 생각합니다. 우리 공동체는 지금 성장하고 있습니다. MIT와 노스웨스턴 대학교가 지난 1년 반에서 2년 사이에 우리 컨소시엄에 합류했고, 우리는 할 매우 흥미로운 과학 연구가 많을 것이라고 생각합니다. 전체 미국 공동체를 위한 공공-민간 파트너십으로서, 우리가 구축하는 장비의 종류와 그것을 사용하는 방법 모두에서 새로운 것에 대해 창의적이고 혁신적일 수 있는 엄청난 두뇌 역량이 존재합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : How concerned are you about megaconstellations impacting observations by GMT?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 메가컨스텔레이션이 GMT 관측에 미치는 영향에 대해 얼마나 걱정하십니까?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : Astronomers have always had to manage sources of noise including satellites, high-energy particles detected by instruments, and electronic noise. We address these with a variety of well-tested observing strategies and data-processing techniques that generally mitigate such issues very effectively. Satellites are most problematic for telescopes that are specifically designed to do surveys that cover wide areas of the sky and focus on imaging, not spectroscopy. The data and discoveries from these projects become the input and starting points for research on larger telescopes. The Giant Magellan Telescope will focus on spectroscopy of objects over small fields of view compared to a survey telescope—even when those targets are spread across wide areas of the sky. As a result, we are far less affected than large survey telescopes. We are, of course, always working to further improve our observing and data-processing strategies. At the same time, the astronomical community is working collaboratively with satellite operators to reduce their impact on science by altering satellite brightness and altitude and improving prediction and tracking. We’re confident that continued cooperation will allow ground-based astronomy to advance and coexist successfully with satellite technologies.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 천문학자들은 항상 위성, 장비가 감지하는 고에너지 입자, 전자 노이즈를 포함한 노이즈 원인들을 관리해야 했습니다. 우리는 일반적으로 이러한 문제들을 매우 효과적으로 완화하는 다양한 검증된 관측 전략과 데이터 처리 기술로 이를 해결합니다. 위성은 특히 넓은 하늘 영역을 커버하고 분광법이 아닌 이미징에 초점을 맞춘 탐사를 수행하도록 설계된 망원경에 가장 문제가 됩니다. 이러한 프로젝트의 데이터와 발견은 더 큰 망원경을 이용한 연구의 입력과 출발점이 됩니다. 자이언트 마젤란 망원경은 탐사 망원경에 비해 작은 시야에서 천체의 분광법에 초점을 맞출 것입니다. 심지어 그 대상들이 넓은 하늘 영역에 퍼져 있을 때도 말이죠. 결과적으로, 우리는 대형 탐사 망원경보다 훨씬 덜 영향을 받습니다. 물론, 우리는 항상 우리의 관측 및 데이터 처리 전략을 더욱 개선하기 위해 노력하고 있습니다. 동시에, 천문학계는 위성 운영자들과 협력하여 위성의 밝기와 고도를 변경하고 예측 및 추적을 개선함으로써 과학에 미치는 영향을 줄이기 위해 노력하고 있습니다. 우리는 지속적인 협력이 지상 기반 천문학이 발전하고 위성 기술과 성공적으로 공존할 수 있게 할 것이라고 확신합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : What are you most excited to observe with the telescope?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 이 망원경으로 무엇을 관측하는 것이 가장 기대되십니까?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : My own interest is in studying planetary systems, how they evolve, and how they form planets. And there I would say the giant telescopes, in particular the GMT because the implementation it has, will help to move us from a discovery phase to an investigation phase, where we try to learn about these planets around other stars. What are they made of? How hot are they? How are their atmospheres behaving? Things like that. So the capabilities of this telescope will put us into an era in the exoplanet world of really starting to learn about the nature of these exoplanets, not just finding more.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 제 개인적인 관심사는 행성계, 그들이 어떻게 진화하는지, 그리고 어떻게 행성을 형성하는지 연구하는 것입니다. 그리고 거기서 말하자면, 대형 망원경들, 특히 GMT는 그 구현 방식 때문에, 우리를 발견 단계에서 조사 단계로 이동시키는 데 도움이 될 것입니다. 즉, 우리가 다른 별 주위의 이러한 행성들에 대해 알아보려고 노력하는 단계로 말이죠. 그들은 무엇으로 만들어졌나요? 얼마나 뜨거운가요? 그들의 대기는 어떻게 행동하나요? 그런 것들입니다. 그래서 이 망원경의 능력은 우리를 외계행성 세계에서 단지 더 많은 것을 찾는 것이 아니라, 이러한 외계행성들의 본성에 대해 실제로 알아가기 시작하는 시대로 데려갈 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : What kinds of things could we learn?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 우리는 어떤 종류의 것들을 배울 수 있을까요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : Well, in particular with my instrument, which breaks up the light into very fine intervals, you can study which molecules are present in exoplanet atmospheres much more precisely, and the ratio of the different isotopes, which tells you about where those molecules came from. You can measure temperatures. You can look at wind velocities. There are many, many things you can do that help you to study these planets in much more detail.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 음, 특히 제 장비는 빛을 매우 세밀한 간격으로 분해하기 때문에, 외계행성 대기에 어떤 분자가 존재하는지 훨씬 더 정밀하게 연구할 수 있고, 서로 다른 동위원소의 비율을 알 수 있으며, 이는 그 분자들이 어디에서 왔는지 알려줍니다. 온도를 측정할 수 있습니다. 풍속을 볼 수 있습니다. 이 행성들을 훨씬 더 자세히 연구하는 데 도움이 되는 많은 것들을 할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : We’ve got this new generation of ground-based observatories coming online. What could we be doing with new space telescopes to complement this?&lt;br/&gt;(아스&gt;&gt;&gt;
아스 : 우리에게는 이 새로운 세대의 지상 관측소들이 등장하고 있습니다. 이것을 보완하기 위해 새로운 우주 망원경으로 무엇을 할 수 있을까요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jaffe : Generically, I would say there are two things you can do in space that are particularly helpful for ground-based astronomy. You can look at wavelengths that you can’t see from the ground. So ultraviolet and X-rays, in particular, are very important in that respect. The other thing is that you can look at things continuously, if you are in certain types of orbits. And so people are building a number of very small, specialized telescopes to just look at things for a long time. The Kepler observatory is a great example of this, for looking for those little dips as planets move in front of their host stars, something that people do from the ground, but it’s much, much harder. So depending upon the field, there are various complementary space projects of different scale that could be important. And you know, the GMT will follow-up on some of the discoveries with the James Webb Space Telescope. We have higher spatial resolution, so we’re able to look in more detail at some of the objects that were looked at there. We have different types of instrumentation that were not thought of when JWST was developed that can help with things. And I think the reverse will happen, as you were alluding to, that as we start to move into this era with the Giant Magellan Telescope, that this will engender certain types of space experiments that are that are targeted to the kinds of questions that we raise.&lt;br/&gt;(재프 : 일반적으로 말하면, 지상 천문학에 특히 도움이 되는 두 가지 일을 우주에서 할 수 있습니다. 지상에서는 볼 수 없는 파장을 볼 수 있습니다. 그래서 자외선과 X선은 특히 그 점에서 매우 중요합니다. 다른 한 가지는 특정 유형의 궤도에 있다면, 물체를 지속적으로 관찰할 수 있다는 것입니다. 그래서 사람들은 오랫동안 물체를 관찰하기 위한 많은 매우 작고 전문화된 망원경을 만들고 있습니다. 케플러 관측소는 이것의 훌륭한 예로, 행성이 모항성 앞을 지나갈 때 발생하는 작은 밝기 감소를 찾는 데 사용되었습니다. 사람들이 지상에서도 하는 일이지만, 훨씬, 훨씬 더 어렵죠. 그래서 분야에 따라, 중요할 수 있는 다양한 규모의 보완적인 우주 프로젝트들이 있습니다. 그리고 알다시피, GMT는 제임스 웹 우주 망원경(JWST)의 일부 발견들을 후속 관측할 것입니다. 우리는 더 높은 공간 분해능을 가지고 있으므로, 거기서 관측된 일부 천체들을 더 자세히 살펴볼 수 있습니다. 우리는 JWST가 개발될 때 생각지 못했던 다른 유형의 장비들을 가지고 있어서 여러 가지 일에 도움이 될 수 있습니다. 그리고 제 생각에는, 당신이 암시했듯이, 반대의 상황도 일어날 것입니다. 우리가 자이언트 마젤란 망원경과 함께 이 시대에 들어서기 시작하면, 이것이 우리가 제기하는 종류의 질문들을 대상으로 하는 특정 유형의 우주 실험들을 촉발할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/as-europes-large-ground-telescope-project-advances-how-is-its-us-competitor-faring/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GMT-Rendering-IDOM-Enclosure-2024-1-scaled-1-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:06:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Reports of ad-supported Xbox game streams show Microsoft’s lack of imagination (광고 지원 Xbox 게임 스트리밍 소식, 마이크로소프트의 상상력 부족 드러내)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/reports-of-ad-supported-xbox-game-streams-show-microsofts-lack-of-imagination/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/Cloud-Gaming_iPadSurfaceiPhone-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xbox maker needs some fresher ideas for expanding access to cloud gaming.&lt;br/&gt;(Xbox 제작사는 클라우드 게이밍 접근성을 확대하기 위한 더 신선한 아이디어가 필요하다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, Microsoft’s long-running Cloud Gaming service is limited to players that have a Microsoft’s Game Pass subscription . Now, new reporting suggests Microsoft is planning to offer non-subscribers access to game streams paid for by advertising in the near future, but only in extremely limited circumstances.&lt;br/&gt;(현재 마이크로소프트의 장기 운영 중인 클라우드 게이밍 서비스는 마이크로소프트 게임 패스 구독을 가진 플레이어로 제한되어 있다. 이제 새로운 보도에 따르면, 마이크로소프트가 가까운 시일 내에 비구독자에게 광고로 수익을 창출하는 게임 스트리밍 접근권을 제공할 계획이라고 하지만, 극히 제한된 상황에서만 가능할 것이라고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest wave of rumors was set off late last week when The Verge’s Tom Warren shared an Xbox Cloud Gaming loading screen with a message mentioning “1 hour of ad supported playtime per session.” That leaked message comes after Windows Central reported last summer that Microsoft has been “exploring video ads for free games for quite some time,” à la the two-minute sponsorships that appear before free-tier game streams on Nvidia’s GeForce Now service .&lt;br/&gt;(최근의 루머 물결은 지난주 말 더 버지의 톰 워렌이 "세션당 1시간의 광고 지원 플레이타임"을 언급하는 메시지가 포함된 Xbox 클라우드 게이밍 로딩 화면을 공유하면서 시작되었다. 이 유출된 메시지는 윈도우 센트럴이 지난여름 마이크로소프트가 "무료 게임을 위한 동영상 광고를 꽤 오랫동안 탐색해 왔다"고 보도한 이후에 나온 것이다. 이는 엔비디아 지포스 나우 서비스의 무료 티어 게임 스트리밍 전에 나타나는 2분짜리 스폰서십과 유사한 방식이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t get your hopes up for easy, free, ad-supported access to the entire Xbox Cloud Gaming library, though. Windows Central now reports that Microsoft will be using ads merely to slightly expand access to its “Stream your own game” program . That program currently offers subscribers to the Xbox Game Pass Essentials tier (or higher) the privilege of streaming versions of some of the Xbox games they’ve already purchased digitally. Windows Central’s unnamed sources suggest a “session-based ad-supported access tier” to stream those purchased games will be offered to non-subscribers as soon as “this year.”&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 Xbox 클라우드 게이밍 라이브러리 전체에 대한 쉽고 무료이며 광고 지원 접근을 기대하지는 말자. 윈도우 센트럴은 현재 마이크로소프트가 광고를 단순히 "자신의 게임 스트리밍" 프로그램 접근성을 약간 확대하는 데 사용할 것이라고 보도한다. 이 프로그램은 현재 Xbox 게임 패스 에센셜 티어(또는 그 이상) 구독자에게 이미 디지털로 구매한 일부 Xbox 게임의 스트리밍 버전을 즐길 수 있는 특권을 제공한다. 윈도우 센트럴의 익명 소식통은 비구독자에게 구매한 게임을 스트리밍할 수 있는 "세션 기반 광고 지원 접근 티어"가 "올해" 안에 제공될 것이라고 시사한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a moderately useful option for cloud-curious Xbox players that might not be willing to take the plunge on a monthly subscription, we suppose. But it also feels like Microsoft could come up with some more imaginative ways to use Cloud Gaming to reach occasional players in new ways.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 월간 구독에 뛰어들기 어려울 수 있는 클라우드에 관심 있는 Xbox 플레이어에게 다소 유용한 선택일 수 있다고 우리는 추측한다. 하지만 마이크로소프트가 클라우드 게이밍을 통해 가끔 플레이하는 유저에게 새로운 방식으로 접근하는 더 상상력 있는 방법을 고안해낼 수도 있을 것 같다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s stopping Microsoft from offer streaming players a 30-minute timed demo stream of any available Xbox Cloud Gaming title—perhaps in exchange for watching a short ad, or perhaps simply as an Xbox Live Arcade-style sales juicing tactic ? Or why not offer discounted access to a streaming-only Game Pass subscription for players willing to watch occasional ads, like Netflix ? Microsoft could even let players spend a couple of bucks to rent a digital copy of the title for a few days, much as services like iTunes do for newer films.&lt;br/&gt;(마이크로소프트가 왜 스트리밍 플레이어에게 사용 가능한 Xbox 클라우드 게이밍 타이틀의 30분 제한 데모 스트리밍을 제공하지 않는가? 아마 짧은 광고를 시청하는 대가로, 아니면 단순히 Xbox 라이브 아케이드 스타일의 판매 촉진 전략으로 말이다. 또는 넷플릭스처럼 가끔 광고를 시청할 의사가 있는 플레이어에게 스트리밍 전용 게임 패스 구독 할인 접근권을 제공하는 것은 어떨까? 마이크로소프트는 아이튠즈가 최신 영화에 대해 하는 것처럼 플레이어가 몇 달러를 지불하고 며칠 동안 타이틀의 디지털 복사본을 대여할 수 있게 할 수도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are just a few ideas off the top of our heads. And they all feel potentially more impactful than using ads as a way to let Xbox players stream copies of games they already purchased.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 우리가 즉석에서 떠올린 몇 가지 아이디어일 뿐이다. 그리고 이 모두가 Xbox 플레이어가 이미 구매한 게임 복사본을 스트리밍할 수 있도록 광고를 사용하는 방법보다 잠재적으로 더 영향력 있을 것 같다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2019, we noted how Stadia’s strictly buy-before-you-play streaming business model limited the appeal of what ended up as a doomed cloud-gaming experiment . Microsoft should take some lessons from Google’s failure and experiment with new ways to use streaming to reach players that might not have access to the latest high-end hardware for their gaming experiences.&lt;br/&gt;(2019년에 우리는 스테이디아의 엄격한 "구매 후 플레이" 스트리밍 비즈니스 모델이 결국 실패한 클라우드 게이밍 실험의 매력을 제한했음을 지적한 바 있다. 마이크로소프트는 구글의 실패로부터 교훈을 얻고, 최신 하이엔드 하드웨어에 접근하지 못할 수 있는 플레이어에게 게임 경험을 제공하기 위해 스트리밍을 활용하는 새로운 방법을 실험해야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/reports-of-ad-supported-xbox-game-streams-show-microsofts-lack-of-imagination/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/Cloud-Gaming_iPadSurfaceiPhone-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:16:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Asus confirms its smartphone business is on indefinite hiatus (아수스, 스마트폰 사업 '무기한 중단' 확인)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/asus-confirms-its-smartphone-business-is-on-indefinite-hiatus/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ROG-2-1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asus chairman Jonney Shih sees AI applications as the company’s main focus going forward.&lt;br/&gt;(아수스의 조니 쉬(Jonney Shih) 회장은 앞으로 AI 응용 제품을 회사의 주요 초점으로 삼을 것이라고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unconfirmed report early this month suggested Asus was pulling back on its smartphone plans, but the company declined to comment at the time. Asus chairman Jonney Shih has now confirmed the wind-down of its smartphone business during an event in Taiwan. Instead, Asus will focus on AI products like robots and smart glasses.&lt;br/&gt;(이달 초 확인되지 않은 보도에 따르면 아수스가 스마트폰 계획을 축소할 것이라고 제안했지만, 당시 회사는 논평을 거부했습니다. 아수스 조니 쉬 회장은 이제 대만에서 열린 행사에서 스마트폰 사업의 단계적 축소를 확인했습니다. 대신 아수스는 로봇과 스마트 안경 같은 AI 제품에 집중할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shih addressed the company’s future plans during a 2026 kick-off event in Taiwan, as reported by Inside . “Asus will no longer add new mobile phone models in the future,” said Shih (machine translated).&lt;br/&gt;(Inside의 보도에 따르면, 쉬 회장은 대만에서 열린 2026년 기념 행사에서 회사의 미래 계획에 대해 언급했습니다. 쉬 회장은 "아수스는 앞으로 더 이상 새로운 휴대폰 모델을 추가하지 않을 것"이라고 말했습니다(기계 번역).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So don’t expect a new Zenfone or ROG Phone from Asus in 2026. That said, very few phone buyers were keeping tabs on the latest Asus phones anyway, which is probably why Asus is throwing in the towel. Shih isn’t saying Asus won’t ever release a new phone, but the company will take an “indefinite wait-and-see” approach. Again, this is a translation and could be interpreted in multiple ways.&lt;br/&gt;(따라서 2026년에 아수스로부터 새로운 젠폰(Zenfone)이나 ROG 폰을 기대하지 마십시오. 그렇다고 해도, 매우 소수의 휴대폰 구매자만이 최신 아수스 휴대폰을 주시하고 있었는데, 아마도 이것이 아수스가 수건을 던지는 이유일 것입니다. 쉬 회장은 아수스가 결코 새로운 휴대폰을 출시하지 않을 것이라고 말하는 것은 아니지만, 회사는 "무기한 지켜보기" 접근 방식을 취할 것이라고 합니다. 다시 말하지만, 이것은 번역이며 여러 가지 방식으로 해석될 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Zenfone line might not be missed—its claim to fame was being slightly smaller and cheaper than competing devices, but Asus’ support and update policy were lightyears behind the market leaders. The ROG Phone line has been prominent in the gaming phone niche, offering the latest chipsets with active cooling, multiple USB-C ports, game controller accessories, blinking lights, and even a headphone jack. However, ROG Phones are even more expensive than Samsung’s flagship devices, with the most recent ROG Phone 9 Pro starting at $1,200. Apparently, the market of those who aren’t happy gaming on the latest iPhone or Samsung Galaxy is miniscule.&lt;br/&gt;(젠폰 라인은 아마도 그리워지지 않을 것입니다—그것의 명성은 경쟁 기기보다 약간 더 작고 저렴하다는 것이었지만, 아수스의 지원 및 업데이트 정책은 시장 선두주자들보다 훨씬 뒤떨어져 있었습니다. ROG 폰 라인은 게이밍 폰 틈새 시장에서 두드러졌으며, 능동 냉각, 여러 USB-C 포트, 게임 컨트롤러 액세서리, 깜빡이는 불빛, 심지어 헤드폰 잭까지 갖춘 최신 칩셋을 제공했습니다. 그러나 ROG 폰은 삼성의 플래그십 기기보다 더 비싸며, 가장 최근의 ROG 폰 9 프로는 1,200달러부터 시작합니다. 분명히, 최신 아이폰이나 삼성 갤럭시에서 게임을 즐기지 못하는 사람들의 시장은 매우 작습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Existing Asus devices should continue to get updates, but Asus never took the lead there. The lavishly expensive ROG Phone 9 Pro is only guaranteed two OS updates and five years of security patches. The most recent Zenfones are also only eligible for two Android version updates, but they get just four years of security support.&lt;br/&gt;(기존 아수스 기기는 계속 업데이트를 받을 것이지만, 아수스는 그 분야에서 결코 선두를 차지하지 않았습니다. 매우 비싼 ROG 폰 9 프로는 단지 두 번의 OS 업데이트와 5년간의 보안 패치만 보장받습니다. 가장 최근의 젠폰도 단지 두 번의 안드로이드 버전 업데이트만 받을 자격이 있지만, 단지 4년간의 보안 지원만 받습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shih’s comments imply that Asus won’t get back into the phone game unless something changes, and that’s not likely. Asus is not the first OEM to drop phone plans, and this is a continuation of a trend that has been underway for years as people upgrade phones less often.&lt;br/&gt;(쉬 회장의 발언은 아수스가 무언가 변화하지 않는 한 휴대폰 시장으로 돌아오지 않을 것임을 시사하며, 그럴 가능성은 높지 않습니다. 아수스는 휴대폰 계획을 포기한 첫 번째 OEM(주문자 상표 부착 생산) 업체가 아니며, 이는 사람들이 휴대폰을 덜 자주 업그레이드하면서 수년간 진행되어 온 추세의 연속입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asus used to be a major player in the Android device ecosystem, offering myriad phones, tablets, phones that turned into tablets, and tablets that turned into PCs (sort of). The rapidly expanding market and advancing technology in the late 2000s and early 2010s left room for companies like Asus to operate alongside bigger OEMs like Samsung and Apple. Those were the days when every smartphone preference was served, from keyboarded sliders, to devices with integrated projectors, to the flat slab phones that eventually won out.&lt;br/&gt;(아수스는 한때 안드로이드 기기 생태계의 주요 플레이어였으며, 수많은 휴대폰, 태블릿, 태블릿으로 변하는 휴대폰, 그리고 PC로 변하는(일종의) 태블릿을 제공했습니다. 2000년대 후반과 2010년대 초반의 빠르게 확장되는 시장과 발전하는 기술은 아수스와 같은 회사들이 삼성과 애플과 같은 더 큰 OEM 업체들과 함께 운영할 여지를 남겼습니다. 그때는 모든 스마트폰 선호도가 충족되던 시절이었습니다, 키보드가 달린 슬라이더부터, 내장 프로젝터가 있는 기기까지, 결국 승리한 평평한 슬래브 폰까지.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, smartphones have become a mature technology, and there simply isn’t as much room for improvement year-to-year. Combine that with rising prices, and people are apt to keep their devices longer. The continued rise of Chinese OEMs like Vivo, Xiaomi, and Huawei also makes it more difficult for niche players—particularly those focused on markets outside the US—to earn money designing and manufacturing a new smartphone every year. And as soon as you stop doing that, other brands are faster and more well-supported when the time does come to pick up a new phone.&lt;br/&gt;(오늘날, 스마트폰은 성숙한 기술이 되었으며, 매년 개선할 여지가 단순히 그만큼 많지 않습니다. 그것에 가격 상승이 결합되면, 사람들은 자신의 기기를 더 오래 유지하려는 경향이 있습니다. 비보, 샤오미, 화웨이와 같은 중국 OEM 업체들의 지속적인 성장은 틈새 시장 플레이어들—특히 미국 외 시장에 집중하는 업체들—이 매년 새로운 스마트폰을 설계하고 제조하여 돈을 버는 것을 더 어렵게 만듭니다. 그리고 일단 그렇게 하기를 멈추면, 새 휴대폰을 살 때가 되면 다른 브랜드들이 더 빠르고 더 잘 지원됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, no Android device maker that has taken a break from releasing phones has ever ramped back up. Just ask LG, which once traded blows with hometown rival Samsung in smartphones. LG’s mobile division lost money for years, leading it to scale back its release schedule in 2019. At the time, the company was adamant it would release new phones when it had a good reason. A few years later, LG’s mobile division called it quits .&lt;br/&gt;(지금까지, 휴대폰 출시를 중단한 안드로이드 기기 제조업체 중 다시 규모를 확장한 업체는 없습니다. 한때 스마트폰에서 고향 라이벌 삼성과 경쟁했던 LG에게 물어보십시오. LG의 모바일 부문은 수년간 손실을 냈고, 이는 2019년에 출시 일정을 축소하게 만들었습니다. 당시 회사는 합당한 이유가 있을 때 새로운 휴대폰을 출시할 것이라고 단호했습니다. 몇 년 후, LG의 모바일 부문은 사업을 중단했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible end of Asus phones further narrows the market, leaving phone buyers with fewer choices. That doesn’t matter to Asus, though, which is a company that exists to make money. While announcing an indefinite pause in smartphone releases, Shih also noted that the company saw a 26.1 percent increase in revenue for 2025, thanks in large part to a doubling of its AI server business. So Asus is focusing on that part of the market. Maybe that’s not the best long-term strategy, but neither is losing money on smartphones.&lt;br/&gt;(아수스 휴대폰의 가능한 종말은 시장을 더욱 좁히며, 휴대폰 구매자들에게 더 적은 선택지를 남깁니다. 그러나 그것은 돈을 벌기 위해 존재하는 회사인 아수스에게는 중요하지 않습니다. 스마트폰 출시의 무기한 중단을 발표하면서, 쉬 회장은 또한 회사가 2025년에 매출이 26.1% 증가했으며, 이는 주로 AI 서버 사업이 두 배로 증가한 덕분이라고 언급했습니다. 따라서 아수스는 시장의 그 부분에 집중하고 있습니다. 아마도 그것이 최고의 장기 전략은 아닐 수 있지만, 스마트폰에서 손실을 보는 것도 아닙니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/asus-confirms-its-smartphone-business-is-on-indefinite-hiatus/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ROG-2-1-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:24:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Elon Musk accused of making up math to squeeze $134B from OpenAI, Microsoft (일론 머스크, 오픈AI와 마이크로소프트로부터 1,340억 달러 뜯어내기 위해 '수학 지어낸' 혐의 받아)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/elon-musk-accused-of-making-up-math-to-squeeze-134b-from-openai-microsoft/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2087343447-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk’s math reduced ChatGPT inventors’ contributions to “zero,” OpenAI argued.&lt;br/&gt;(머스크의 계산법은 ChatGPT 발명자들의 기여를 "0%"로 축소했다고 오픈AI가 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk is going for some substantial damages in his lawsuit accusing OpenAI of abandoning its nonprofit mission and “ making a fool out of him” as an early investor .&lt;br/&gt;(일론 머스크는 오픈AI가 비영리 미션을 저버리고 초기 투자자로서의 자신을 "바보로 만들었다"고 비난하는 소송에서 상당한 배상금을 요구하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Musk filed a notice on remedies sought in the lawsuit, confirming that he’s seeking damages between $79 billion and $134 billion from OpenAI and its largest backer, co-defendant Microsoft.&lt;br/&gt;(지난 금요일, 머스크는 소송에서 구하는 구제 조치에 대한 통지를 제출하며, 오픈AI와 최대 후원사이자 공동 피고인 마이크로소프트로부터 790억 달러에서 1,340억 달러 사이의 손해배상을 요구하고 있음을 확인했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk hired an expert he has never used before, C. Paul Wazzan, who reached this estimate by concluding that Musk’s early contributions to OpenAI generated 50 to 75 percent of the nonprofit’s current value. He got there by analyzing four factors: Musk’s total financial contributions before he left OpenAI in 2018, Musk’s proposed equity stake in OpenAI in 2017, Musk’s current equity stake in xAI, and Musk’s nonmonetary contributions to OpenAI (like investing time or lending his reputation).&lt;br/&gt;(머스크는 이전에 한 번도 사용한 적 없는 전문가 C. 폴 와잔을 고용했는데, 그는 머스크의 오픈AI 초기 기여가 해당 비영리 단체 현재 가치의 50~75%를 창출했다는 결론을 내려 이 추정치에 도달했다. 그는 네 가지 요소를 분석하여 이 수치를 도출했다: 머스크가 2018년 오픈AI를 떠나기 전까지의 총 금전적 기여, 머스크가 2017년 제안한 오픈AI 지분 소유 비율, 머스크의 현재 xAI 지분 소유 비율, 그리고 머스크의 오�AI에 대한 비금전적 기여(시간 투자 또는 명성 제공 등).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eye-popping damage claim shocked OpenAI and Microsoft, which could also face punitive damages in a loss.&lt;br/&gt;(이 놀라운 손해배상 청구는 오픈AI와 마이크로소프트를 충격에 빠뜨렸으며, 패소 시 양사는 징벌적 손해배상까지 직면할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tech giants immediately filed a motion to exclude Wazzan’s opinions, alleging that step was necessary to avoid prejudicing a jury. Their filing claimed that Wazzan’s math seemed “made up,” based on calculations the economics expert testified he’d never used before and allegedly “conjured” just to satisfy Musk.&lt;br/&gt;(이 기술 거대 기업들은 즉시 와잔의 의견을 배제하라는 동의를 제출하며, 이 조치는 배심원의 편견을 피하기 위해 필요하다고 주장했다. 그들의 서류에는 와잔의 계산이 "지어낸" 것 같다고 주장하며, 해당 경제 전문가는 자신이 이전에 사용한 적 없는 계산법을 증언했고 머스크를 만족시키기 위해 "꾸며낸" 것이라고 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, Wazzan allegedly ignored that Musk left OpenAI after leadership did not agree on how to value Musk’s contributions to the nonprofit. Problematically, Wazzan’s math depends on an imaginary timeline where OpenAI agreed to Musk’s 2017 bid to control 51.2 percent of a new for-profit entity that was then being considered. But that never happened, so it’s unclear why Musk would be owed damages based on a deal that was never struck, OpenAI argues.&lt;br/&gt;(예를 들어, 와잔은 머스크가 오픈AI 리더십이 머스크의 비영리 단체에 대한 기여를 어떻게 평가할지 합의하지 못한 후 떠났다는 사실을 무시한 것으로 알려졌다. 문제는 와잔의 계산이, 오픈AI가 당시 검토 중이던 새로운 영리 기업의 51.2%를 통제하겠다는 머스크의 2017년 제안에 동의했다는 가상의 타임라인에 의존한다는 점이다. 하지만 그런 일은 결코 일어나지 않았으므로, 체결되지 않은 거래를 바탕으로 왜 머스크에게 배상금이 지급되어야 하는지 불분명하다고 오픈AI는 주장한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also unclear why Musk’s stake in xAI is relevant, since OpenAI is a completely different company not bound to match xAI’s offerings. Wazzan allegedly wasn’t even given access to xAI’s actual numbers to help him with his estimate, only referring to public reporting estimating that Musk owns 53 percent of xAI’s equity. OpenAI accused Wazzan of including the xAI numbers to inflate the total damages to please Musk.&lt;br/&gt;(또한, 오픈AI는 xAI와 완전히 다른 회사이며 xAI의 제안과 일치할 의무가 없는데, 왜 머스크의 xAI 지분이 관련이 있는지도 불분명하다. 와잔은 자신의 추정치를 도출하는 데 도움을 받기 위해 xAI의 실제 수치에 접근조차 허용되지 않았으며, 머스크가 xAI 지분의 53%를 소유한다고 추정하는 공개 보고서만 참조했다고 한다. 오픈AI는 와잔이 머스크를 기쁘게 하기 위해 총 손해배상액을 부풀리기 위해 xAI 수치를 포함했다고 비난했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By all appearances, what Wazzan has done is cherry-pick convenient factors that correspond roughly to the size of the ‘economic interest’ Musk wants to claim, and declare that those factors support Musk’s claim,” OpenAI’s filing said.&lt;br/&gt;("모든 정황상, 와잔이 한 일은 머스크가 주장하고 싶은 '경제적 이익' 규모와 대략적으로 일치하는 편리한 요소들을 선택하고, 그 요소들이 머스크의 주장을 뒷받침한다고 선언한 것뿐입니다,"라고 오픈AI의 서류는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further frustrating OpenAI and Microsoft, Wazzan opined that Musk and xAI should receive the exact same total damages whether they succeed on just one or all of the four claims raised in the lawsuit.&lt;br/&gt;(오픈AI와 마이크로소프트를 더욱 좌절시킨 것은, 와잔이 머스크와 xAI가 소송에서 제기된 네 가지 청구 중 단 하나만 성공하든 모두 성공하든 정확히 동일한 총 손해배상금을 받아야 한다고 의견을 제시했다는 점이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI and Microsoft are hoping the court will agree that Wazzan’s math is an “unreliable… black box” and exclude his opinions as improperly reliant on calculations that cannot be independently tested.&lt;br/&gt;(오픈AI와 마이크로소프트는 법원이 와잔의 계산이 "신뢰할 수 없는... 블랙박스"라고 동의하고, 그의 의견을 독립적으로 검증할 수 없는 계산에 부적절하게 의존한 것으로 배제하기를 바라고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft could not be reached for comment, but OpenAI has alleged that Musk’s suit is a harassment campaign aimed at stalling a competitor so that his rival AI firm, xAI, can catch up.&lt;br/&gt;(마이크로소프트는 논평을 구할 수 없었지만, 오픈AI는 머스크의 소송이 경쟁사를 지연시켜 그의 라이벌 AI 회사인 xAI가 따라잡을 수 있도록 하기 위한 괴롭힘 캠페인이라고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Musk’s lawsuit continues to be baseless and a part of his ongoing pattern of harassment, and we look forward to demonstrating this at trial,” an OpenAI spokesperson said in a statement provided to Ars. “This latest unserious demand is aimed solely at furthering this harassment campaign. We remain focused on empowering the OpenAI Foundation, which is already one of the best resourced nonprofits ever.”&lt;br/&gt;("머스크의 소송은 근거가 없으며 그의 지속적인 괴롭힘 패턴의 일부로 남아 있으며, 우리는 재판에서 이를 입증할 것을 기대합니다,"라고 오픈AI 대변인은 Ars에 제공된 성명에서 말했다. "이번 최신의 경솔한 요구는 단지 이 괴롭힘 캠페인을 더욱 진행시키기 위한 것입니다. 우리는 이미 역사상 가장 잘 자원을 갖춘 비영리 단체 중 하나인 오픈AI 재단에 힘을 실어주는 데 계속 집중하고 있습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wazzan is “a financial economist with decades of professional and academic experience who has managed his own successful venture capital firm that provided seed-level funding to technology startups,” Musk’s filing said.&lt;br/&gt;(와잔은 "수십 년의 전문 및 학술 경험을 가진 재정 경제학자이며, 기술 스타트업에 시드 단계 자금을 제공하는 자신의 성공적인 벤처 캐피털 회사를 운영했다"고 머스크 측 서류는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI explained how Musk got connected with Wazzan, who testified that he had never been hired by any of Musk’s companies before. Instead, three months before he submitted his opinions, Wazzan said that Musk’s legal team had reached out to his consulting firm, BRG, and the call was routed to him.&lt;br/&gt;(오픈AI는 머스크가 와잔과 어떻게 연결되었는지 설명했는데, 와잔은 머스크의 어떤 회사에서도 이전에 고용된 적이 없다고 증언했다. 대신, 자신의 의견을 제출하기 3개월 전, 머스크의 법률 팀이 그의 컨설팅 회사인 BRG에 연락했고 그 통화가 자신에게 연결되었다고 와잔은 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wazzan’s task was to figure out how much Musk should be owed after investing $38 million in OpenAI—roughly 60 percent of its seed funding. Musk also made nonmonetary contributions Wazzan had to weigh, like “recruiting key employees, introducing business contacts, teaching his cofounders everything he knew about running a successful startup, and lending his prestige and reputation to the venture,” Musk’s filing said.&lt;br/&gt;(와잔의 임무는 머스크가 오픈AI에 3,800만 달러(시드 자금의 약 60%)를 투자한 후 얼마를 받아야 하는지 알아내는 것이었다. 머스크는 또한 와잔이 고려해야 할 비금전적 기여도 했는데, "핵심 직원 채용, 비즈니스 연락처 소개, 공동 창립자들에게 성공적인 스타트업 운영에 대해 자신이 아는 모든 것을 가르치고, 자신의 명성과 평판을 벤처에 빌려주는 것" 등이었다고 머스크 측 서류는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “fact pattern” was “pretty unique,” Wazzan testified, while admitting that his calculations weren’t something you’d find “in a textbook.”&lt;br/&gt;("사실 관계"는 "꽤 독특했다"고 와잔은 증언했으며, 자신의 계산이 "교과서에서 찾을 수 있는" 것이 아니라는 점을 인정했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Wazzan had to factor in Microsoft’s alleged wrongful gains, by deducing how much of Microsoft’s profits went back into funding the nonprofit. Microsoft alleged Wazzan got this estimate wrong after assuming that “some portion of Microsoft’s stake in the OpenAI for-profit entity should flow back to the OpenAI nonprofit” and arbitrarily decided that the portion must be “equal” to “the nonprofit’s stake in the for-profit entity.” With this odd math, Wazzan double-counted value of the nonprofit and inflated Musk’s damages estimate, Microsoft alleged.&lt;br/&gt;(게다가, 와잔은 마이크로소프트의 부당 이득 중 얼마가 비영리 단체 자금 조달로 다시 흘러들어갔는지 추론함으로써 이를 고려해야 했다. 마이크로소프트는 와잔이 "마이크로소프트의 오픈AI 영리 기업 지분의 일부가 오픈AI 비영리 단체로 다시 흘러들어가야 한다"고 가정한 후 이 추정치를 틀렸다고 주장하며, 그 비율이 "비영리 단체의 영리 기업 내 지분"과 "동등"해야 한다고 임의로 결정했다고 말했다. 이 이상한 계산법으로 와잔은 비영리 단체의 가치를 이중 계산하고 머스크의 손해배상 추정치를 부풀렸다고 마이크로소프트는 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wazzan offers no rationale—contractual, governance, economic, or otherwise—for reallocating any portion of Microsoft’s negotiated interest to the nonprofit,” OpenAI’s and Microsoft’s filing said.&lt;br/&gt;("와잔은 마이크로소프트의 협상된 지분의 일부를 비영리 단체에 재배분해야 할 계약적, 거버넌스적, 경제적 또는 기타 어떤 근거도 제시하지 않습니다,"라고 오픈AI와 마이크로소프트의 서류는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most glaringly, Wazzan reached his opinions without ever weighing the contributions of anyone but Musk, OpenAI alleged. That means that Wazzan’s analysis did not just discount efforts of co-founders and investors like Microsoft, which “invested billions of dollars into OpenAI’s for-profit affiliate in the years after Musk quit.” It also dismissed scientists and programmers who invented ChatGPT as having “contributed zero percent of the nonprofit’s current value,” OpenAI alleged.&lt;br/&gt;(아마도 가장 눈에 띄는 점은, 와잔이 머스크 외 다른 누구의 기여도 고려하지 않고 자신의 의견에 도달했다는 오픈AI의 주장이다. 이는 와잔의 분석이 마이크로소프트와 같은 공동 창립자 및 투자자들의 노력을 단지 할인한 것이 아니라, "머스크가 떠난 후 수년 동안 오픈AI의 영리 자회사에 수십억 달러를 투자한" 노력을 무시한 것이다. 또한 ChatGPT를 발명한 과학자와 프로그래머들의 기여가 "비영리 단체 현재 가치의 0%를 기여했다"고 무시했다고 오픈AI는 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t need to know all the other people,” Wazzan testified.&lt;br/&gt;("다른 모든 사람들을 알 필요는 없습니다,"라고 와잔은 증언했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wazzan supposedly also did not bother to quantify Musk’s nonmonetary contributions, which could be in the thousands, millions, or billions based on his vague math, OpenAI argued.&lt;br/&gt;(와잔은 머스크의 비금전적 기여를 정량화하려고도 하지 않았다고 오픈AI는 주장했다. 그의 모호한 계산에 따르면 그 가치는 수천, 수백만, 또는 수십억 달러가 될 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Musk’s legal team seemed to contradict Wazzan, OpenAI’s filing noted. In Musk’s filing on remedies, it’s acknowledged that the jury may have to adjust the total damages. Because Wazzan does not break down damages by claims and merely assigns the same damages to each individual claim, OpenAI argued it will be impossible for a jury to adjust any of Wazzan’s black box calculations.&lt;br/&gt;(심지어 머스크의 법률 팀도 와잔과 모순되는 것처럼 보였다고 오픈AI 서류는 지적했다. 머스크의 구제 조치 관련 서류에는 배심원이 총 손해배상액을 조정해야 할 수도 있다는 점이 인정되어 있다. 와잔은 청구별로 손해배상을 세분화하지 않고 각 개별 청구에 동일한 손해배상을 할당하기 때문에, 배심원이 와잔의 블랙박스 계산 중 어떤 것도 조정하는 것이 불가능할 것이라고 오픈AI는 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wazzan’s methodology is made up; his results unverifiable; his approach admittedly unprecedented; and his proposed outcome—the transfer of billions of dollars from a nonprofit corporation to a donor-turned competitor—implausible on its face,” OpenAI argued.&lt;br/&gt;("와잔의 방법론은 지어낸 것이고, 그의 결과는 검증 불가능하며, 그의 접근법은 인정하건대 전례가 없고, 그의 제안된 결과—비영리 법인으로부터 기부자이자 경쟁사로 변한 자에게 수십억 달러를 이전하는 것—는 표면적으로도 믿기 어렵습니다,"라고 오픈AI는 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a trial starting in April, Musk will strive to convince a court that such extraordinary damages are owed. OpenAI hopes he’ll fail, in part since “it is legally impossible for private individuals to hold economic interests in nonprofits” and “Wazzan conceded at deposition that he had no reason to believe Musk ‘expected a financial return when he donated… to OpenAI nonprofit.’”&lt;br/&gt;(4월에 시작될 재판에서 머스크는 그러한 엄청난 배상금이 지급되어야 한다고 법원을 설득하기 위해 노력할 것이다. 오픈AI는 그가 실패하기를 바라고 있는데, 부분적으로는 "사적 개인이 비영리 단체에 경제적 이익을 가질 수 있는 것은 법적으로 불가능"하고 "와잔은 증언 조서에서 머스크가 '오픈AI 비영리 단체에 기부할 때 금전적 수익을 기대했다고 믿을 이유가 없다'고 인정했기" 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Allowing a jury to hear a disgorgement number—particularly one that is untethered to specific alleged wrongful conduct and results in Musk being paid amounts thousands of times greater than his actual donations—risks misleading the jury as to what relief is recoverable and renders the challenged opinions inadmissible,” OpenAI’s filing said.&lt;br/&gt;("특히 특정 부당 행위와 분리되어 있고 머스크가 실제 기부금의 수천 배에 달하는 금액을 지급받는 결과를 초래하는 배심원에게 몰수 금액을 듣도록 허용하는 것은, 어떤 구제 조치가 회복 가능한지에 대해 배심원을 오도할 위험이 있으며 이로 인해 도전받는 의견들은 허용될 수 없게 됩니다,"라고 오픈AI의 서류는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wazzan declined to comment. xAI did not immediately respond to Ars’ request to comment.&lt;br/&gt;(와잔은 논평을 거절했다. xAI는 Ars의 논평 요청에 즉시 응답하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/elon-musk-accused-of-making-up-math-to-squeeze-134b-from-openai-microsoft/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2087343447-1024x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:04:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Signs point to a sooner-rather-than-later M5 MacBook Pro refresh (M5 맥북 프로 업데이트, 조만간 출시될 가능성)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/signs-point-to-a-sooner-rather-than-later-m5-macbook-pro-refresh/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_6215-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delayed shipping times for current models sometimes means an update is imminent.&lt;br/&gt;(현재 모델의 배송 지연은 때때로 업데이트가 임박했음을 의미합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mac power users waiting on new high-end MacBook Pro models may have been disappointed last fall, when Apple released an M5 upgrade for the low-end 14-inch MacBook Pro without touching the M4 Pro or Max versions of the laptop. But the wait for M5 Pro and M5 Max models may be nearing its end.&lt;br/&gt;(고성능 맥북 프로 신제품을 기다리는 맥 파워 유저들은 지난 가을 실망했을 수 있습니다. 애플이 저가형 14인치 맥북 프로에 M5 업그레이드를 적용했지만, M4 Pro나 Max 버전 노트북은 건드리지 않았기 때문입니다. 하지만 M5 Pro와 M5 Max 모델을 위한 기다림이 곧 끝날 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tea-leaf readers at MacRumors noticed that shipping times for a handful of high-end MacBook Pro configurations have slipped into mid-to-late February, rather than being available immediately as most Mac models are. This is often, though not always, a sign that Apple has slowed down or stopped production of an existing product in anticipation of an update.&lt;br/&gt;(MacRumors의 예측가들은 일부 고성능 맥북 프로 구성의 배송 시기가 대부분의 맥 모델처럼 즉시 구매 가능한 상태가 아니라 2월 중순에서 말로 밀려난 것을 발견했습니다. 이는 항상 그런 것은 아니지만, 애플이 업데이트를 앞두고 기존 제품 생산을 늦추거나 중단했다는 신호인 경우가 많습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the shipping delays affect the M4 Max versions of both the 14-inch and 16-inch MacBook Pros. If you order them today, these models will arrive sometime between February 3 and February 24, depending on the configuration you choose; many M4 Pro versions are still available for same-day shipping, though adding a nano-texture display or upgrading RAM can still add a week or so to the shipping time.&lt;br/&gt;(현재 배송 지연은 14인치와 16인치 맥북 프로의 M4 Max 버전 모두에 영향을 미치고 있습니다. 오늘 주문하면 선택한 구성에 따라 이 모델들은 2월 3일부터 2월 24일 사이에 도착할 예정입니다. 많은 M4 Pro 버전은 여전히 당일 배송이 가능하지만, 나노 텍스처 디스플레이를 추가하거나 RAM을 업그레이드하면 배송 시간이 일주일 정도 더 걸릴 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple could choose to launch new Pro hardware on January 28, to go with the new Creator Studio subscription it announced last week. Aimed primarily at independent content creators that make their own video, audio, and images, the Creator Studio subscription bundles Final Cut Pro, Logic Pro, Pixelmator Pro, and enhancements for the Pages, Numbers, and Keynote apps (along with some other odds and ends) for $13 a month or $130 a year. None of these apps require a MacBook Pro, but many would benefit in some way from the additional CPU and GPU power, RAM, and storage available in Apple’s high-end laptops.&lt;br/&gt;(애플은 지난주 발표한 새로운 크리에이터 스튜디오 구독 서비스와 함께 1월 28일에 새로운 프로 하드웨어를 출시할 수도 있습니다. 주로 자체 비디오, 오디오, 이미지를 제작하는 독립 콘텐츠 크리에이터를 대상으로 하는 크리에이터 스튜디오 구독은 파이널 컷 프로, 로직 프로, 픽셀메이터 프로, 그리고 페이지스, 넘버스, 키노트 앱의 향상된 기능(그 외 몇 가지 다른 기능들 포함)을 월 13달러 또는 연 130달러에 묶어 제공합니다. 이 앱들 중 어느 것도 맥북 프로가 필수는 아니지만, 애플의 고성능 노트북에서 제공하는 추가적인 CPU 및 GPU 성능, RAM, 저장 공간으로부터 많은 이점을 얻을 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, an imminent replacement isn’t the only reason why the shipping estimates for any given Mac might slip. Ongoing, AI-fueled RAM shortages could be causing problems, and Apple probably prioritizes production of the widely-used base-model M4 and M5 chips to the larger, more expensive, more complex Max models.&lt;br/&gt;(물론, 특정 맥의 배송 예상 시기가 밀리는 유일한 이유가 곧 출시될 대체 모델 때문만은 아닙니다. 지속되는 AI 수요로 인한 RAM 부족이 문제를 일으키고 있을 수 있으며, 애플은 널리 사용되는 기본형 M4 및 M5 칩의 생산을 더 크고 비싸며 복잡한 Max 모델보다 우선시할 가능성이 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the only other device in Apple’s lineup that offers the M4 Max and similar RAM configuration options is the high-end Mac Studio, which currently isn’t subject to the same shipping delays. That does imply that the delays are specific to the MacBook Pro—and one explanation for this is that the laptop is about to be replaced.&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 애플 제품 라인업에서 M4 Max와 유사한 RAM 구성 옵션을 제공하는 다른 유일한 장치는 고성능 맥 스튜디오인데, 현재 이 제품은 동일한 배송 지연을 겪고 있지 않습니다. 이는 지연이 맥북 프로에 특화된 문제임을 시사하며, 그 이유 중 하나는 이 노트북이 곧 교체될 예정이기 때문일 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtually every Mac in Apple’s lineup is ready for an M5-series refresh. Only the low-end 14-inch MacBook Pro got an M5 upgrade last year, a relatively restrained rollout compared to the M3 and M4 generations—the M4 generation hit all the MacBook Pros, the iMac, and the Mac mini all at the same time. That’s left a lot of Macs eligible for an update at some point in 2026, including the Pros, the MacBook Airs, the Mac mini, the iMac, the Mac Studio, and the Mac Pro tower.&lt;br/&gt;(애플 라인업의 거의 모든 맥은 M5 시리즈 업데이트가 필요한 상태입니다. 작년에 저가형 14인치 맥북 프로만 M5 업그레이드를 받았는데, 이는 M3 및 M4 세대에 비해 상대적으로 제한적인 출시였습니다. M4 세대는 모든 맥북 프로, 아이맥, 맥 미니에 동시에 적용되었습니다. 이로 인해 프로 모델, 맥북 에어, 맥 미니, 아이맥, 맥 스튜디오, 맥 프로 타워를 포함한 많은 맥들이 2026년 중 언젠가 업데이트 대상이 되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple has been known to skip Apple Silicon chip generations for some models in the past, so a handful of systems may stick with the M4 until the M6 rolls around. The MacBook Pros and Airs are reliably updated with each new chip generation, but the desktop Macs have all missed at least one chip update since the Apple Silicon era began.&lt;br/&gt;(애플은 과거 일부 모델에 대해 애플 실리콘 칩 세대를 건너뛰는 경우가 있었기 때문에, 일부 시스템은 M6가 등장할 때까지 M4를 유지할 수도 있습니다. 맥북 프로와 에어는 각각의 새로운 칩 세대마다 꾸준히 업데이트되지만, 데스크탑 맥들은 애플 실리콘 시대가 시작된 이후 최소 한 번 이상의 칩 업데이트를 놓쳤습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting from Bloomberg’s Mark Gurman also suggests that the Mac Pro may be on life support—even if an M5 Ultra chip arrives for the Mac Studio, there’s no guarantee that the Mac Pro (currently still rocking an M2 Ultra) will get the same chip.&lt;br/&gt;(블룸버그의 마크 거먼 기자의 보도에 따르면, 맥 프로가 존폐 위기에 처해 있을 수도 있습니다. 맥 스튜디오를 위해 M5 Ultra 칩이 등장하더라도, 맥 프로(현재 여전히 M2 Ultra를 사용 중)가 동일한 칩을 받을 것이라는 보장은 없습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of the existing Macs that we expect to see updated, Apple is rumored to be introducing an all-new Mac this year: a new entry-level model with an iPhone-class Apple A-series processor inside. This device is said to be a direct replacement for the M1 MacBook Air that Apple still sells for $599 via Walmart in the US, years after removing the model from its own retail and online stores.&lt;br/&gt;(업데이트될 것으로 예상되는 기존 맥들 외에도, 애플이 올해 완전히 새로운 맥을 선보일 것이라는 소문이 있습니다. 아이폰 급의 애플 A 시리즈 프로세서가 탑재된 새로운 입문급 모델입니다. 이 장치는 애플이 자체 리테일 및 온라인 스토어에서 제거한 지 수년이 지난 후에도 미국에서 월마트를 통해 599달러에 판매 중인 M1 맥북 에어를 직접 대체할 것이라고 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect any replacement to share a lot in common with the old M1 Air, including its 13-inch screen size and (possibly) its paltry-by-modern-standards 8GB of RAM. But for $400 less than the starting price of the M4 MacBook Air, this low-end Mac would still serve a kind of customer that would otherwise have only Windows laptops and Chromebooks to consider.&lt;br/&gt;(대체 모델은 13인치 화면 크기와 (아마도) 현대 기준으로는 부족한 8GB RAM을 포함해 이전 M1 에어와 많은 공통점을 공유할 것으로 예상됩니다. 하지만 M4 맥북 에어의 시작 가격보다 400달러 저렴한 가격으로, 이 저가형 맥은 그렇지 않았다면 윈도우 노트북과 크롬북만을 고려했을 특정 고객층에게 여전히 서비스를 제공할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Walmart website currently has “low stock” of the M1 MacBook Air—it may be that we can also expect that new low-end MacBook sooner rather than later.&lt;br/&gt;(월마트 웹사이트는 현재 M1 맥북 에어의 재고가 "적음"으로 표시되고 있습니다. 이는 새로운 저가형 맥북도 조만간 출시될 것으로 기대할 수 있음을 의미할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/signs-point-to-a-sooner-rather-than-later-m5-macbook-pro-refresh/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_6215-1152x648.jpeg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:52:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The first newMarathongame in decades will launch on March 5 (수십 년 만의 첫 신작 '마라톤' 게임, 3월 5일 출시 확정)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/bungies-delayed-marathon-revival-will-finally-launch-march-5/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/marathon-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development hasn’t exactly been smooth since the extraction shooter’s 2023 announcement.&lt;br/&gt;(이 추출 슈팅 게임이 2023년 발표된 이후 개발 과정이 순탄치만은 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s been nearly three years now since Destiny maker (and Sony subsidiary ) Bungie formally announced a revival of the storied Marathon FPS franchise. And it has been about seven months since the game’s original announced release date of September 23, 2025 was pushed back indefinitely after a reportedly poor response to the game’s first Alpha test.&lt;br/&gt;(데스티니 제작사(소니 자회사)인 Bungie가 역사적인 FPS 프랜차이즈 '마라톤'의 부활을 공식 발표한 지 거의 3년이 됐다. 그리고 게임의 첫 알파 테스트에 대한 반응이 부진했다는 보도 이후, 원래 발표된 출시일인 2025년 9월 23일이 무기한 연기된 지도 약 7개월이 지났다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But today, in a post on the PlayStation Blog , Bungie revealed that the new Marathon would finally be hitting PS5, Windows, and Xbox Series X|S on March 5, narrowing down the month-long March release window announced back in December .&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 오늘, 플레이스테이션 블로그 게시물을 통해 Bungie는 새 '마라톤'이 결국 3월 5일에 PS5, Windows, Xbox Series X|S에 출시될 것이라고 밝혔다. 이는 지난 12월에 발표된 '3월 출시'라는 한 달 간의 출시 기간을 구체화한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Destiny 2 , which transitioned to a free-to-play model in 2019 , the new Marathon sells for $40 in a Standard Edition or a $60 Deluxe Edition that includes some digital rewards and cosmetics. That mirrors the pricing of the somewhat similar Arc Raiders , which recently hit 12 million sales in less than 12 weeks.&lt;br/&gt;(2019년 무료 플레이 모델로 전환한 '데스티니 2'와 달리, 새 '마라톤'은 스탠다드 에디션 40달러, 디지털 보상과 코스메틱이 포함된 디럭스 에디션 60달러에 판매된다. 이는 다소 유사한 '아크 레이더스'의 가격 정책과 비슷한데, 해당 게임은 최근 12주도 안 되어 1200만 판매를 기록했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the original Marathon trilogy on the ’90s Macintosh—which closely followed on the single-player campaign corridors and deathmatch multiplayer of the original Doom —the new Marathon is described as a “PvPvE survival extraction shooter.” That means gameplay based around exploring distinct zones and scavenging for cosmetics and gear upgrades in exploratory missions alone or with up to two friends, then seeing those missions “break into fast-paced PvP combat” at a moment’s notice, according to the game’s official description.&lt;br/&gt;(90년대 매킨토시용 원작 '마라톤' 3부작(원조 '둠'의 싱글플레이 캠페인 복도와 데스매치 멀티플레이어를 가까이 따름)과 달리, 새 '마라톤'은 "PvPvE 생존 추출 슈팅 게임"으로 설명된다. 게임 공식 설명에 따르면, 이는 독특한 지역을 탐험하고 탐사 미션(최대 두 명의 친구와 함께 또는 혼자)에서 코스메틱과 장비 업그레이드를 수집하는 데 기반한 게임플레이를 의미하며, 그러다가 언제든 "신속한 PvP 전투로 돌변"할 수 있다고 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new preorder trailer expands on other more gameplay-focused videos showcasing the poisoned world of Tau Ceti IV and the six competing factions of highly customizable “runner shells” they’ll inhabit. Bungie has also revealed a scavenging-focused “Rook” option for players that want to queue up solo and join a match in progress with nothing but a starting kit.&lt;br/&gt;(새로운 사전 예약 트레일러는 독이 든 세계 타우 세티 IV와 그곳에 거주하게 될 맞춤화 가능성이 높은 "러너 셸"의 여섯 경쟁 파벌을 보여주는 다른, 더 게임플레이에 초점을 맞춘 영상들을 보충한다. Bungie는 또한 솔로로 대기열에 참여해 진행 중인 매치에 시작 키트만 가지고 합류하고 싶은 플레이어들을 위한 수집 중심의 "룩" 옵션도 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Instead of focusing on progression and questing and things of that sort, [Rook] is a mode where we make it easy for you to just kind of drop into a match that’s in progress and run about and try to scavenge as much as possible and get out with it, so that you can populate your vault a little bit more for future runs,” Game Director Joe Ziegler said in a recent video .&lt;br/&gt;("진행과 퀘스트, 그런 종류의 것들에 초점을 두는 대신, [룩]은 진행 중인 매치에 쉽게 뛰어들어 돌아다니며 최대한 많이 수집하고 그것을 가지고 탈출하여, 향후 플레이를 위해 금고를 조금 더 채울 수 있게 해주는 모드입니다."라고 게임 디렉터 조 지글러가 최근 영상에서 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Marathon revival project has faced its fair share of development troubles in recent years. That includes public accusations that early test gameplay included plagiarized artwork , leading the development team to announce a “thorough review of our in-game assets.” Internal plans to release the game in 2024 were reportedly pushed back and entire year amid pessimism among developers. More recently, the game got a new creative director in June , which isn’t exactly a sign of confidence that late in a long-running project.&lt;br/&gt;(마라톤 부활 프로젝트는 최근 몇 년간 개발 문제를 적지 않게 겪었다. 여기에는 초기 테스트 게임플레이에 표절된 아트워크가 포함되었다는 공개적인 비난도 있어, 개발팀이 "게임 내 자산에 대한 철저한 검토"를 발표하게 만들었다. 2024년에 게임을 출시하려던 내부 계획은 개발자들의 비관론 속에 무려 1년이나 연기되었다고 전해진다. 더 최근에는 6월에 새로운 크리에이티브 디렉터가 임명되었는데, 이는 오랜 프로젝트 말미에 자신감을 보여주는 신호라고 보기 어렵다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that—and given a Bungie gaming pedigree that dates back to the original Marathon —it’s fair to say that the new Marathon is going to get more than its fair share of attention when it finally gets into players’ hands in just six weeks.&lt;br/&gt;(이 모든 일이 있었고, 원조 '마라톤'까지 거슬러 올라가는 Bungie의 게임 제작 혈통을 고려하면, 새 '마라톤'이 불과 6주 후에 플레이어의 손에 들어갈 때 공정한 몫 이상의 관심을 받을 것이라고 말하는 것이 타당할 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/bungies-delayed-marathon-revival-will-finally-launch-march-5/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/marathon-1152x648.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:07:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The fastest human spaceflight mission in history crawls closer to liftoff (역대 가장 빠른 유인 우주 비행 임무가 발사를 향해 더욱 다가서다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasas-artemis-ii-rocket-rolls-to-launch-pad-but-key-test-looms-ahead/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_0127-1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a remarkably smooth launch campaign, Artemis II reached its last stop before the Moon.&lt;br/&gt;(매우 순조로운 발사 준비 과정을 거친 후, 아르테미스 II가 달을 향한 마지막 중간 기착지에 도달했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KENNEDY SPACE CENTER, Florida—Preparations for the first human spaceflight to the Moon in more than 50 years took a big step forward this weekend with the rollout of the Artemis II rocket to its launch pad.&lt;br/&gt;(플로리다 케네디 우주 센터—50년 이상 만에 처음으로 달을 향한 유인 우주 비행 준비가 이번 주말 아르테미스 II 로켓을 발사대로 옮기는 작업과 함께 큰 진전을 보였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket reached a top speed of just 1 mph on the four-mile, 12-hour journey from the Vehicle Assembly Building to Launch Complex 39B at NASA’s Kennedy Space Center in Florida. At the end of its nearly 10-day tour through cislunar space, the Orion capsule on top of the rocket will exceed 25,000 mph as it plunges into the atmosphere to bring its four-person crew back to Earth.&lt;br/&gt;(이 로켓은 플로리다 NASA 케네디 우주 센터의 조립 건물(Vehicle Assembly Building)에서 발사대 39B(Launch Complex 39B)까지 4마일(약 6.4km)을 12시간에 걸쳐 이동하는 동안 최고 속도가 시속 1마일에 불과했습니다. 그러나 지구-달 공간을 가로지르는 약 10일간의 여정 끝에, 로켓 꼭대기에 있는 오리온 캡슐은 4인승 승무원을 지구로 데려오기 위해 대기권으로 돌입할 때 시속 25,000마일(약 40,000km/h)을 초과할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the start of a very long journey,” said NASA Administrator Jared Isaacman. “We ended our last human exploration of the moon on Apollo 17.”&lt;br/&gt;(NASA 국장 재러드 아이작맨은 "이것은 매우 긴 여정의 시작입니다."라고 말했습니다. "우리는 마지막 달 탐사인 아폴로 17호로 달에 대한 인간의 탐사를 마쳤습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Artemis II mission will set several notable human spaceflight records. Astronauts Reid Wiseman, Victor Glover, Christina Koch, and Jeremy Hansen will travel farther from Earth than any human in history. They won’t land. That distinction will fall to the next mission in line in NASA’s Artemis program.&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 II 임무는 몇 가지 주목할 만한 유인 우주 비행 기록을 세울 것입니다. 우주비행사 리드 와이즈먼, 빅터 글로버, 크리스티나 코크, 제레미 한센은 역사상 그 어떤 인간보다 지구에서 더 멀리 여행할 것입니다. 그들은 달에 착륙하지는 않습니다. 그 영광은 NASA 아르테미스 프로그램의 다음 임무에 돌아갈 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Artemis II astronauts will travel more than 4,000 miles beyond the far side of the Moon (the exact distance depends on the launch date), setting up for a human spaceflight speed record during their blazing reentry over the Pacific Ocean a few days later. Koch will become the first woman to fly to the vicinity of the Moon, and Hansen will be the first non-US astronaut to do the same.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 아르테미스 II 우주비행사들은 달의 뒷면 너머 4,000마일(약 6,400km) 이상을 여행할 것이며(정확한 거리는 발사 날짜에 따라 다름), 며칠 후 태평양 상공에서 불타는 듯한 재진입 동안 유인 우주 비행 속도 기록을 세우게 될 것입니다. 코크는 달 근처를 비행하는 첫 여성이 되고, 한센은 같은 일을 하는 첫 비(非)미국인 우주비행사가 될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We really are ready to go,” said Wiseman, the Artemis II commander, during Saturday’s rollout to the launch pad. “We were in a sim [in Houston] for about 10 hours yesterday doing our final capstone entry and landing sim. We got in T-38s last night and we flew to the Cape to be here for this momentous occasion.”&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 II 사령관 와이즈먼은 토요일 발사대로의 이동 중에 "우리는 정말 갈 준비가 되어 있습니다."라고 말했습니다. "우리는 어제(휴스턴에서) 약 10시간 동안 시뮬레이션을 하며 최종 캡스톤 진입 및 착륙 시뮬레이션을 수행했습니다. 우리는 지난밤 T-38기에 탑승해 케이프로 날아와 이 역사적인 순간을 위해 여기에 왔습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rollout began around sunrise Saturday, with NASA’s Space Launch System rocket and Orion capsule riding a mobile launch platform and a diesel-powered crawler transporter along a throughway paved with crushed Alabama river rock. Employees, VIPs, and guests gathered along the crawlerway to watch the 11 million-pound stack inch toward the launch pad. The rollout concluded about an hour after sunset, when the crawler transporter’s jacking system lowered the mobile launch platform onto pedestals at Pad 39B.&lt;br/&gt;(이동 작업은 토요일 해뜰 무렵 시작되었으며, NASA의 우주 발사 시스템(SLS) 로켓과 오리온 캡슐은 이동식 발사대와 디젤 크롤러 운반차에 실려 앨라배마 강에서 채취한 부순 돌로 포장된 도로를 따라 이동했습니다. 직원들, VIP, 손님들이 크롤러웨이를 따라 모여 1,100만 파운드(약 5,000톤)에 달하는 덩어리가 발사대로 조금씩 움직이는 것을 지켜보았습니다. 이동 작업은 해가 진 지 약 한 시간 후, 크롤러 운반차의 잭킹 시스템이 이동식 발사대를 패드 39B의 받침대 위에 내려놓으면서 끝났습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rollout keeps the Artemis II mission on track for liftoff as soon as next month, when NASA has a handful of launch opportunities on February 6, 7, 8, 10, and 11.&lt;br/&gt;(이번 이동으로 아르테미스 II 임무는 다음 달인 2월 6일, 7일, 8일, 10일, 11일에 NASA가 확보한 몇 차례의 발사 기회에 맞춰 발사될 수 있도록 준비가 순조롭게 진행되고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big milestone leading up to launch day will be a practice countdown or Wet Dress Rehearsal (WDR), currently slated for around February 2, when NASA’s launch team will pump more than 750,000 gallons of super-cold liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen into the rocket. NASA had trouble keeping the cryogenic fluids at the proper temperature, then encountered hydrogen leaks when the launch team first tried to fill the rocket for the unpiloted Artemis I mission in 2022. Engineers implemented the same fixes on Artemis II that they used to finally get over the hump with propellant loading on Artemis I.&lt;br/&gt;(발사일까지의 주요 이정표는 현재 2월 2일경으로 예정된 연습 카운트다운 또는 습식 드레스 리허설(WDR)입니다. 이때 NASA 발사팀은 로켓에 75만 갤런(약 280만 리터) 이상의 초저온 액체 수소와 액체 산소를 주입할 것입니다. NASA는 극저온 유체를 적절한 온도로 유지하는 데 어려움을 겪었고, 이후 2022년 무인 아르테미스 I 임무를 위해 로켓에 처음 연료를 주입하려 했을 때 수소 누출 문제를 만났습니다. 기술자들은 아르테미스 I에서 추진제 주입 문제를 극복하는 데 사용했던 동일한 해결책을 아르테미스 II에 적용했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the odds NASA can actually get the Artemis II mission off the ground next month?&lt;br/&gt;(그렇다면 NASA가 실제로 다음 달에 아르테미스 II 임무를 발사할 수 있을 확률은 얼마나 될까요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ll have to have things go right,” said Matt Ramsey, NASA’s Artemis II mission manager, in an interview with Ars on Saturday. “There’s a day of margin there for weather. There’s some time after WDR that we’ve got for data reviews and that sort of thing. It’s not unreasonable, but I do think it’s a success-oriented schedule.”&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 아르테미스 II 임무 매니저 맷 램지는 토요일 Ars와의 인터뷰에서 "모든 것이 순조롭게 진행되어야 합니다."라고 말했습니다. "날씨를 위한 하루의 여유가 있습니다. WDR 이후 데이터 검토 등을 위한 시간도 약간 있습니다. 불가능한 일은 아니지만, 저는 성공을 전제로 한 일정이라고 생각합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Moon has to be in the right position in its orbit for the Artemis II launch to proceed. There are also restrictions on launch dates to ensure the Orion capsule returns to Earth and reenters the atmosphere at an angle safe for the ship’s heat shield . If the launch does not happen in February, NASA has a slate of backup launch dates in early March.&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 II 발사가 진행되려면 달이 궤도상 적절한 위치에 있어야 합니다. 또한 오리온 캡슐이 지구로 귀환하고 우주선의 열 차폐체에 안전한 각도로 대기권에 재진입할 수 있도록 발사 날짜에 대한 제한 사항도 있습니다. 만약 2월에 발사가 이루어지지 않으면, NASA는 3월 초에 대체 발사 일정을 준비하고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars was at Kennedy Space Center for the rocket’s move to the launch pad Saturday. The photo gallery below shows the launcher emerging from the Vehicle Assembly Building, the same facility once used to stack Saturn V rockets during the Apollo Moon program. The Artemis II astronauts were also on hand for a question and answer session with reporters.&lt;br/&gt;(Ars는 토요일 로켓이 발사대로 이동하는 모습을 케네디 우주 센터에서 취재했습니다. 아래 사진 갤러리는 아폴로 달 프로그램 당시 새턴 V 로켓을 조립하는 데 사용되었던 동일한 시설인 조립 건물에서 나오는 발사체를 보여줍니다. 아르테미스 II 우주비행사들도 기자들과의 질의응답 시간에 참석했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first flight of astronauts on the SLS rocket and Orion spacecraft is running at least five years late. The flight’s architecture, trajectory, and goals have changed multiple times, and technical snags discovered during manufacturing and testing repeatedly shifted the schedule. The program’s engineering and budgetary problems are well documented .&lt;br/&gt;(SLS 로켓과 오리온 우주선을 이용한 첫 유인 비행은 최소 5년 이상 지연되었습니다. 비행의 구조, 궤적, 목표는 여러 번 변경되었으며, 제조 및 테스트 과정에서 발견된 기술적 문제점들이 일정을 반복적으로 변경시켰습니다. 이 프로그램의 공학적 및 예산 문제는 잘 알려져 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the team readying the rocket and spacecraft for launch has hit a stride in recent months. Technicians inside the Vehicle Assembly Building started stacking the SLS rocket in late 2024, beginning with the vehicle’s twin solid-fueled boosters. Then ground teams added the core stage, upper stage, and finally installed the Orion spacecraft on top of the rocket last October.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 로켓과 우주선을 발사 준비하는 팀은 최근 몇 달 동안 탄력을 받고 있습니다. 조립 건물 내부의 기술자들은 2024년 말, 로켓의 고체 연료 부스터 두 개부터 시작하여 SLS 로켓 조립을 시작했습니다. 그런 다음 지상팀이 코어 스테이지와 상단 스테이지를 추가하고, 지난 10월 마침내 로켓 꼭대기에 오리온 우주선을 설치했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working nearly around the clock in three shifts, it took about 12 months for crews at Kennedy to assemble the rocket and prepare it for rollout. But the launch campaign inside the VAB was remarkably smooth. Ground teams shaved about two months off the time it took to integrate the SLS rocket and Orion spacecraft for the Artemis I mission, which launched on the program’s first full-up unpiloted test flight in 2022.&lt;br/&gt;(3교대로 거의 24시간 내내 작업한 결과, 케네디의 작업팀이 로켓을 조립하고 이동 준비를 하는 데 약 12개월이 걸렸습니다. 그러나 조립 건물 내부의 발사 준비 과정은 놀랍도록 순조로웠습니다. 지상팀은 2022년 프로그램 최초의 완전 무인 시험 비행으로 발사된 아르테미스 I 임무를 위해 SLS 로켓과 오리온 우주선을 통합하는 데 걸린 시간을 약 2개월 단축했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“About a year ago, I was down here and we set the rollout date, and we hit it within a day or two,” said Matt Ramsey, NASA’s mission manager for Artemis II. “Being able to stay on schedule, it was a daily grind to be able to do that.”&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 아르테미스 II 임무 매니저 맷 램지는 "약 1년 전, 제가 여기 내려와 이동 날짜를 정했고, 우리는 그 날짜를 하루 이틀 차이로 맞췄습니다."라고 말했습니다. "일정을 지킬 수 있었다는 것은, 매일 매일 꾸준히 노력한 결과입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engineers worked through a handful of technical problems last year, including an issue with a pressure-assisted device used to assist the astronauts in opening the Orion hatch in the event of an emergency. More recently, NASA teams cleared a concern with caps installed on the rocket’s upper stage, according to Ramsey.&lt;br/&gt;(기술자들은 지난해 비상 시 우주비행사들이 오리온 해치를 열 수 있도록 돕는 데 사용되는 압력 보조 장치 문제를 포함한 몇 가지 기술적 문제를 해결했습니다. 램지에 따르면, 더 최근에는 NASA 팀이 로켓 상단 스테이지에 설치된 캡에 대한 문제도 해결했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant engineering review focused on proving the Orion heat shield is safe to fly. That assessment occurred in the background from the perspective of the technicians working on Artemis II at Kennedy.&lt;br/&gt;(가장 중요한 공학적 검토는 오리온 열 차폐체의 비행 안전성을 입증하는 데 초점을 맞췄습니다. 그 평가는 케네디에서 아르테미스 II 작업을 하는 기술자들의 관점에서는 배경에서 진행되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Artemis II team is now focused on activities at the launch pad. This week, NASA plans to perform a series of tests extending and retracting the crew access mark. Next, the Artemis II astronauts will rehearse an emergency evacuation from the launch pad. That will be followed by servicing of the rocket’s hydraulic steering system.&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 II 팀은 이제 발사대에서의 활동에 집중하고 있습니다. 이번 주에 NASA는 승무원 출입 암을 신축하는 일련의 테스트를 수행할 계획입니다. 다음으로, 아르테미스 II 우주비행사들은 발사대에서의 비상 대피 훈련을 할 것입니다. 그 후 로켓의 유압 조향 시스템 점검이 이어질 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this leads up to the crucial practice countdown early next month. The astronauts won’t be aboard the rocket for the test, but almost everything else will look like launch day. The countdown will halt around 30 seconds prior to the simulated liftoff.&lt;br/&gt;(이 모든 것은 다음 달 초 중요한 연습 카운트다운으로 이어집니다. 우주비행사들은 이 테스트에 로켓에 탑승하지는 않지만, 거의 모든 것이 발사일과 유사하게 진행될 것입니다. 카운트다운은 모의 발사 약 30초 전에 중단될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took repeated tries to get through the Wet Dress Rehearsal for the Artemis I mission. There were four attempts at the countdown practice run before the first actual Artemis I launch countdown. After encountering hydrogen leaks on two scrubbed launch attempts, NASA performed another fueling test before finally successfully launching Artemis I in November 2022.&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 I 임무의 습식 드레스 리허설을 완료하는 데는 여러 번의 시도가 필요했습니다. 첫 번째 실제 아르테미스 I 발사 카운트다운 전에 카운트다운 연습 실행을 네 번 시도했습니다. 두 번의 발사 중단 시도에서 수소 누출을 겪은 후, NASA는 2022년 11월 마침내 아르테미스 I을 성공적으로 발사하기 전에 또 다른 연료 주입 테스트를 수행했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The launch team repaired a leaky hydrogen seal and introduced a gentler hydrogen loading procedure to overcome the problem. Hydrogen is an extremely efficient fuel for rockets, but its super-cold temperature and the tiny size of hydrogen molecules make it prone to leakage. The hydrogen feeds the SLS rocket’s four core stage engines and single upper stage engine.&lt;br/&gt;(발사팀은 누출되는 수소 실을 수리하고 더 부드러운 수소 주입 절차를 도입하여 문제를 해결했습니다. 수소는 로켓에 매우 효율적인 연료이지만, 그 초저온 온도와 수소 분자의 작은 크기 때문에 누출되기 쉽습니다. 수소는 SLS 로켓의 코어 스테이지 엔진 4개와 상단 스테이지 엔진 1개에 공급됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Artemis I was a test flight, and we learned a lot during that campaign getting to launch,” said Charlie Blackwell-Thompson, NASA’s Artemis II launch director. “The things that we’ve learned relative to how to go load this vehicle, how to load LOX (liquid oxygen), how to load hydrogen, have all been rolled in to the way in which we intend to load the Artemis II vehicle.”&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 아르테미스 II 발사 책임자 찰리 블랙웰-톰슨은 "아르테미스 I은 시험 비행이었고, 우리는 발사에 이르는 그 과정에서 많은 것을 배웠습니다."라고 말했습니다. "이 차량에 연료를 주입하는 방법, LOX(액체 산소)를 주입하는 방법, 수소를 주입하는 방법에 대해 우리가 배운 모든 것들이 아르테미스 II 차량을 주입하는 방식에 반영되었습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA is hesitant to publicly set a target launch date until the agency gets through the dress rehearsal, but agency officials say a February launch remains feasible.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA는 드레스 리허설을 마칠 때까지 공개적으로 목표 발사일을 설정하는 것을 꺼리고 있지만, 당국 관계자들은 2월 발사가 여전히 가능하다고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve held schedule pretty well getting to rollout today,” Isaacman said. “We have zero intention of communicating an actual launch date until we get through wet dress. But look, that’s our first window, and if everything is tracking accordingly, I know the teams are prepared, I know this crew is prepared, we’ll take it.”&lt;br/&gt;(아이작맨은 "우리는 오늘 이동까지 일정을 아주 잘 지켰습니다."라고 말했습니다. "우리는 습식 드레스를 마칠 때까지 실제 발사 날짜를 발표할 의도가 전혀 없습니다. 하지만 보세요, 그것이 우리의 첫 번째 발사 기회 창입니다. 그리고 모든 것이 그에 따라 진행된다면, 저는 팀들이 준비되어 있고, 이 승무원이 준비되어 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다. 우리는 그 기회를 잡을 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wet dress is the driver to launch,” Blackwell-Thompson said. “ With a wet dress that is without significant issues, if everything goes to plan, then certainly there are opportunities within February that could be achievable.”&lt;br/&gt;(블랙웰-톰슨은 "습식 드레스가 발사의 관건입니다."라고 말했습니다. "중대한 문제 없이 습식 드레스가 진행되고, 모든 것이 계획대로 된다면, 확실히 2월 내에 달성 가능한 발사 기회가 있습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One constraint that threw a wrench into NASA’s Artemis I launch campaign is no longer a significant factor for Artemis II. On Artemis I, NASA had to roll the rocket back to the Vehicle Assembly Building (VAB) after the wet dress rehearsal to complete final installation and testing on its flight termination system, which consists of a series of pyrotechnic charges designed to destroy the rocket if it flies off course and threatens populated areas after liftoff.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 아르테미스 I 발사 준비에 차질을 빚었던 한 가지 제약 조건은 이제 아르테미스 II에서는 큰 문제가 되지 않습니다. 아르테미스 I에서는 NASA가 습식 드레스 리허설 후 로켓을 다시 조립 건물로 옮겨, 발사 후 비행 경로를 이탈해 인구 밀집 지역을 위협할 경우 로켓을 파괴하도록 설계된 일련의 폭발 장치로 구성된 비행 종료 시스템에 대한 최종 설치 및 테스트를 완료해야 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Space Force’s Eastern Range, responsible for public safety for all launches from Florida’s Space Coast, requires the flight termination system be retested after 28 to 35 days, a clock that started ticking last week before rollout. During Artemis I, technicians could not access the parts of the rocket they needed to in order to perform the retest at the launch pad. NASA now has structural arms to give ground teams the ability to reach parts higher up the rocket for the retest without returning to the hangar.&lt;br/&gt;(플로리다 스페이스 코스트에서의 모든 발사에 대한 공공 안전을 책임지는 미 우주군 동부 관할 구역(Eastern Range)은 비행 종료 시스템을 28일에서 35일 후에 재검사해야 하며, 이 시계는 이동 전인 지난주부터 시작되었습니다. 아르테미스 I 당시 기술자들은 발사대에서 재검사를 수행하기 위해 필요한 로켓 부분에 접근할 수 없었습니다. NASA는 이제 지상팀이 격납고로 돌아가지 않고도 로켓 상부의 부품에 접근하여 재검사를 할 수 있도록 하는 구조적 암을 갖추고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this new capability, Artemis II could remain at the pad for launch opportunities in February and March before officials need to bring it back to the VAB to replace the flight termination system’s batteries, which still can’t be accessed at the pad.&lt;br/&gt;(이 새로운 능력 덕분에, 아르테미스 II는 당국이 비행 종료 시스템의 배터리를 교체하기 위해(이는 여전히 발사대에서 접근할 수 없음) 조립 건물로 다시 가져가야 할 때까지 2월과 3월의 발사 기회를 위해 발사대에 머무를 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/nasas-artemis-ii-rocket-rolls-to-launch-pad-but-key-test-looms-ahead/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_0127-1-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:01:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The first commercial space station, Haven-1, is now undergoing assembly for launch (최초의 상업용 우주정거장 '헤이븐-1', 발사를 위한 조립 진행 중)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/the-first-commercial-space-station-haven-1-is-now-undergoing-assembly-for-launch/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Vast_Haven-1_Integration_Phase-1_ISO8_Cleanroom_Spring_2026-01-15-DSC_1375-3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have a very strong incentive to send a crew as quickly as we can safely do so.”&lt;br/&gt;("우리는 가능한 한 안전하게, 그리고 빠르게 승무원을 보낼 강력한 동기를 가지고 있습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Ars reported last week , NASA’s plan to replace the International Space Station with commercial space stations is running into a time crunch.&lt;br/&gt;(아스 테크니카(Ars)가 지난주 보도한 바와 같이, NASA가 국제우주정거장(ISS)을 상업용 우주정거장으로 대체하려는 계획은 시간적 압박에 직면해 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sprawling International Space Station is due to be decommissioned less than five years from now, and the US space agency has yet to formally publish rules and requirements for the follow-on stations being designed and developed by several different private companies.&lt;br/&gt;(거대한 국제우주정거장은 지금으로부터 5년도 채 남지 않은 시점에 퇴역할 예정이며, 미국 우주국은 아직 여러 민간 기업들이 설계 및 개발 중인 후속 정거장에 대한 공식적인 규칙과 요구사항을 발표하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although there are expected to be multiple bidders in “phase two” of NASA’s commercial space station program, there are at present four main contenders: Voyager Technologies, Axiom Space, Blue Origin, and Vast Space. At some point later this year, the space agency is expected to select one, or more likely two, of these companies for larger contracts that will support their efforts to build their stations.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 상업용 우주정거장 프로그램 '2단계'에는 여러 입찰자가 있을 것으로 예상되지만, 현재 주요 경쟁자는 네 곳입니다: 보이저 테크놀로지스(Voyager Technologies), 액시엄 스페이스(Axiom Space), 블루 오리진(Blue Origin), 그리고 배스트 스페이스(Vast Space)입니다. 올해 후반 어느 시점에 NASA는 이들 기업 중 하나, 혹은 더 가능성 높게는 두 곳을 선정해 그들의 정거장 건설 노력을 지원할 더 큰 규모의 계약을 체결할 것으로 보입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a sense of the overall landscape as the competition heats up, Ars recently interviewed Voyager chief executive Dylan Taylor about his company’s plans for a private station, Starlab. Today we are publishing an interview with Max Haot, the chief executive of Vast. The company is furthest along in terms of development, choosing to build a smaller, interim space station, Haven-1, capable of short-duration stays. Eventually, NASA wants facilities capable of continuous habitation, but it is not clear whether that will be a requirement starting in 2030.&lt;br/&gt;(경쟁이 가열되면서 전체적인 상황을 파악하기 위해, 아스는 최근 보이저의 최고경영자 딜런 테일러(Dylan Taylor)를 만나 민간 정거장 '스타랩(Starlab)'에 대한 그의 회사 계획에 대해 인터뷰했습니다. 오늘은 배스트의 최고경영자 맥스 하오트(Max Haot)와의 인터뷰를 게시합니다. 이 회사는 개발 측면에서 가장 앞서 있으며, 단기 체류가 가능한 소형의 임시 우주정거장인 '헤이븐-1(Haven-1)'을 건설하기로 선택했습니다. 궁극적으로 NASA는 지속적인 거주가 가능한 시설을 원하지만, 2030년부터 그것이 요구사항이 될지는 불분명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until today, Haven-1 had a public launch date of mid-2026. However, as Haot explained in our interview, that launch date is no longer tenable.&lt;br/&gt;(오늘까지, 헤이븐-1의 공개 발사일은 2026년 중반이었습니다. 그러나 하오트가 우리 인터뷰에서 설명한 바와 같이, 그 발사일은 더 이상 유효하지 않습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : You’re slipping the launch of Haven-1 from the middle of this year to the first quarter of 2027. Why?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 헤이븐-1의 발사를 올해 중반에서 2027년 1분기로 미루셨습니다. 이유는 무엇인가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Max Haot : This is obviously our first space station, and we’re moving as safely and as fast as we can. That’s the date right now that we are confident we will meet. We’ve been tracking that date, without slip, for quite a while. And that’s still a year, probably two years or even more, ahead of anyone else. It will be building the world’s first commercial space station from scratch, from an empty building and no team, in under four years.&lt;br/&gt;(맥스 하오트 : 이것은 분명히 우리의 첫 우주정거장이며, 우리는 가능한 한 안전하고 빠르게 진행하고 있습니다. 그것이 현재 우리가 확신을 가지고 맞출 수 있는 날짜입니다. 우리는 꽤 오랫동안 그 날짜를 지연 없이 추적해 왔습니다. 그리고 그것은 여전히 다른 어떤 기업보다도 아마 1년, 2년 혹은 그 이상 앞서 있는 것입니다. 빈 건물과 팀 없이 시작해서, 4년도 채 안 되는 시간 안에 세계 최초의 상업용 우주정거장을 처음부터 구축하게 될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Where are you with the hardware?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 하드웨어는 현재 어느 단계에 있나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : Last Saturday (January 10) we reached the key milestone of fully completing the primary structure, and some of the secondary structure; all of the acceptance testing occurred in November as well. Now we are starting clean room integration, which starts with TCS (thermal control system), propulsion, interior shells, and then moving on to avionics. And then final close out, which we expect will be done by the fall, and then we have on the books with NASA a full test campaign at the end of the year at Plum Brook . Then the launch in Q1 next year.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 지난 토요일(1월 10일) 우리는 주요 구조물과 일부 2차 구조물을 완전히 완성하는 중요한 이정표에 도달했으며, 모든 수락 테스트도 11월에 이루어졌습니다. 이제 우리는 클린룸 통합 작업을 시작하고 있는데, 이는 TCS(열 제어 시스템), 추진 시스템, 내부 쉘부터 시작하여 항공전자 장비로 이어집니다. 그리고 가을까지 완료될 것으로 예상되는 최종 마무리 작업 후, NASA와 계획된 대로 연말에 플럼 브룩(Plum Brook)에서 전면적인 테스트 캠페인을 진행할 예정입니다. 그다음 해 1분기에 발사가 이뤄집니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : What happens after you launch Haven-1?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 헤이븐-1을 발사한 후에는 어떤 일이 벌어지나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : We are not launching Haven-1 with crew inside. It’s a 15-ton, very valuable and expensive satellite, but still no humans involved, launching on a Falcon 9. So then we have a period that we can monitor it and control it uncrewed and confirm everything is functioning perfectly, right? We are holding pressure. We are controlling attitude. These checkouts can happen in as little as two weeks.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 우리는 헤이븐-1을 승무원이 탑승한 채로 발사하지 않습니다. 이는 15톤짜리 매우 가치 있고 비싼 위성이며, 팰컨 9으로 발사되지만 여전히 인간은 관여하지 않습니다. 따라서 우리는 무인 상태로 모니터링하고 제어하며 모든 것이 완벽하게 작동하는지 확인할 수 있는 기간을 가집니다. 압력을 유지하고, 자세를 제어합니다. 이러한 점검은 2주 이내에도 가능합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of it, we have to basically convince SpaceX, both contractually and with many verification events, that it will be safe to dock Dragon. And if they agree with the data we provide them, they will put a fully trained crew on board Dragon and bring them up. It could be as early as two weeks after, and it could be as late as any time within three years, which is a lifetime of Haven-1. But we have a very strong incentive to send a crew as quickly as we can safely do so.&lt;br/&gt;(그 과정이 끝나면, 우리는 기본적으로 계약상 그리고 많은 검증 절차를 통해 스페이스X에게 드래곤 캡슐이 도킹하는 것이 안전하다는 것을 납득시켜야 합니다. 그리고 그들이 우리가 제공한 데이터에 동의한다면, 그들은 완전히 훈련된 승무원을 드래곤에 태우고 올려보낼 것입니다. 이는 발사 후 2주 후일 수도 있고, 헤이븐-1의 수명인 3년 내 어느 때라도 늦을 수 있습니다. 하지만 우리는 가능한 한 안전하게, 그리고 빠르게 승무원을 보낼 강력한 동기를 가지고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Have you picked the crew yet?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 이미 승무원을 선정했나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : We are in deep negotiations, maybe more than that, with both private individuals and nation states. But there’s nothing we are ready to announce yet. Especially with the Q1 launch date, in our desire to follow with the crew right after, this is now becoming pretty urgent. We believe, with our partner at SpaceX, one year for training is very comfortable, and we think we can compress it to maybe as little as six months for both training on Dragon and Haven-1 so long as we have an experienced crew. So we have a bit of time left to announce it.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 우리는 민간 개인과 국가 기관 모두와 깊은 협상, 어쩌면 그 이상의 단계에 있습니다. 하지만 아직 발표할 준비가 된 것은 없습니다. 특히 1분기 발사 날짜와 승무원을 바로 뒤이어 보내고자 하는 우리의 바람에 따라, 이제 이 일은 꽤 시급해지고 있습니다. 우리는 스페이스X 파트너와 함께, 1년의 훈련 기간은 매우 여유롭다고 믿으며, 경험 많은 승무원이 있다면 드래곤과 헤이븐-1에 대한 훈련을 아마 6개월 정도로 단축할 수 있다고 생각합니다. 따라서 발표할 시간은 약간 남아 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : You mentioned Haven-1 has a three-year lifetime. How many crews will you try to cycle through?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 헤이븐-1의 수명이 3년이라고 언급하셨는데, 몇 명의 승무원을 순환시키려 하나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : The nominal plan is for a two-week mission, and we have one fully contracted with SpaceX, as well as a second one that we have a deposit and an option on. And then we plan to do two more. That’s assuming they are 10-day missions with two days of transfer on either side. So two-week missions. We also have the option to maybe do a 30-day mission if we want. So the exact duration and makeup will be decided as we make progress with customers and potentially NASA.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 명목상 계획은 2주 임무이며, 우리는 스페이스X와 완전히 계약된 첫 번째 임무와, 보증금과 옵션이 있는 두 번째 임무를 가지고 있습니다. 그리고 두 번 더 수행할 계획입니다. 이는 각 측면에 2일의 이동 시간을 포함한 10일 임무라고 가정한 것입니다. 따라서 2주 임무입니다. 원한다면 30일 임무를 수행할 옵션도 있습니다. 따라서 정확한 기간과 구성은 고객 및 잠재적으로 NASA와의 진행 상황에 따라 결정될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : What is the plan after Haven-1?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 헤이븐-1 이후 계획은 무엇인가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : If you look at the first module of our second station, what will be the difference? We have two docking ports, not one. We expect to have more power, and potentially more volume, depending on the launch vehicle. What you see on our website and what we do might be different. We have a lot of optionality. But other than that, it’s all of the exact same components of Haven demo and Haven-1, which are basically being iterated on. And so that’s the key. The life support system, the air revitalization system, the software, the primary structure—the first module of Haven-2 will be just tweaks on Haven-1. That’s why we think we’re in the best position of all of the competitors. And that’s not been enabled by chance, right? It’s been enabled by a billion-dollar investment in 1,000 employees and all the facilities to mass produce the follow-on modules.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 우리의 두 번째 정거장의 첫 번째 모듈을 보면, 차이점은 무엇일까요? 우리는 도킹 포트가 하나가 아니라 두 개입니다. 발사체에 따라 더 많은 전력과 잠재적으로 더 많은 부피를 가질 것으로 예상합니다. 우리 웹사이트에 보이는 것과 우리가 하는 일은 다를 수 있습니다. 우리는 많은 선택권을 가지고 있습니다. 하지만 그 외에는, 기본적으로 반복 개발 중인 헤이븐 데모와 헤이븐-1의 모든 정확히 동일한 구성 요소들입니다. 그것이 핵심입니다. 생명 유지 시스템, 공기 재생 시스템, 소프트웨어, 주요 구조물—헤이븐-2의 첫 번째 모듈은 헤이븐-1을 약간 개선한 것일 뿐입니다. 그것이 우리가 모든 경쟁자들 중 최고의 위치에 있다고 생각하는 이유입니다. 그리고 그것은 우연히 가능해진 것이 아닙니다. 후속 모듈을 대량 생산하기 위한 1,000명의 직원과 모든 시설에 대한 10억 달러 규모의 투자가 이를 가능하게 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : NASA is nearing the second phase of its competition for commercial space stations, known as CLDs. Do you plan to compete with Haven-1 or Haven-2 for these contracts?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : NASA는 상업용 우주정거장(CLD)을 위한 2단계 경쟁에 가까워지고 있습니다. 이 계약을 위해 헤이븐-1이나 헤이븐-2로 경쟁할 계획인가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : We have not decided because, as you know, it’s unclear yet what the requirements will be. Will they be asking for a 30-day demonstration flight? On our end it’s unclear if we want to bid that 30-day demonstration with Haven-1, or Haven-2 with two or three modules. If they ask for a 30-day mission, we have the option to offer it on Haven-1 in 2027 if we want to.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 우리는 아직 결정하지 않았습니다. 왜냐하면 아시다시피, 요구사항이 무엇이 될지 아직 불분명하기 때문입니다. 그들이 30일 시증 비행을 요구할까요? 우리 입장에서는 그 30일 시증을 헤이븐-1으로 입찰할지, 아니면 두세 개 모듈을 가진 헤이븐-2로 할지 불분명합니다. 만약 그들이 30일 임무를 요구한다면, 우리는 원한다면 2027년에 헤이븐-1으로 제공할 옵션이 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Last week a key space staffer in the US Senate, Maddy Davis, said she was “begging” for NASA to release the phase two “request for proposals” that would set the ground rules for the CLD competition. Do you feel the same way?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 지난주 미국 상원의 주요 우주 담당 스태프 매디 데이비스(Maddy Davis)는 CLD 경쟁의 기본 규칙을 정할 2단계 '제안 요청서(RFP)'를 NASA가 발표해 달라고 "간청"했다고 말했습니다. 같은 생각이신가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : Vast is dedicated to ensuring we have continuous human presence in low-Earth orbit after the ISS is retired. The date we are aiming at is end of 2030. Maddy mentioned an ISS extension. We agree, for America, if no one is ready it should be extended. But in our view, we will be ready, and we need to make sure we’re ready to start a continuous crewed mission by the end of 2030. That’s less than five years away now, right? So we definitely agree with the sentiment, and I think the full industry agrees, and I’m pretty sure Jared Isaacman also agrees that it is overdue and it’s time to make a decision and release an RFP.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 배스트는 ISS가 퇴역한 후 지구 저궤도에 인간의 지속적인 존재를 보장하는 데 전념하고 있습니다. 우리가 목표로 하는 날짜는 2030년 말입니다. 매디는 ISS 연장을 언급했습니다. 우리도 동의합니다. 미국을 위해, 아무도 준비가 안 되었다면 연장되어야 합니다. 하지만 우리의 견해로는, 우리는 준비가 될 것이며, 2030년 말까지 지속적인 유인 임무를 시작할 준비가 되어 있어야 합니다. 지금으로부터 5년도 채 남지 않았습니다. 그래서 우리는 분명히 그 정서에 동의하며, 전체 업계가 동의한다고 생각하고, 재러드 아이작맨(Jared Isaacman)도 그것이 지연되었으며 결정을 내리고 RFP를 발표할 때라고 동의할 것이라고 확신합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : What do you hope to see in that RFP when it comes to requirements?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 요구사항과 관련해 그 RFP에서 무엇을 바라시나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : We obviously can’t decide what NASA will do, and we will be competitive in whatever they decide. But there’s a few key recommendations we feel strongly about. The first one is that, as they consider whether they proceed with a demonstration mission or something else, we think they should focus on what is right for the country. What we are hearing is that they are trying to tweak the approach to do something fair to all of the bidders. And I don’t think it should matter whether people have been doing a right thing or wrong thing, and whether what’s right for the country puts somebody in a better position or not.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 우리는 분명히 NASA가 무엇을 할지 결정할 수 없으며, 그들이 무엇을 결정하든 우리는 경쟁력이 있을 것입니다. 하지만 우리가 강하게 느끼는 몇 가지 핵심 권고사항이 있습니다. 첫 번째는, 그들이 시증 임무나 다른 것을 진행할지 고려할 때, 국가에 맞는 것에 초점을 맞춰야 한다고 생각합니다. 우리가 듣기로는, 그들은 모든 입찰자에게 공정한 무언가를 하기 위해 접근법을 조정하려고 노력하고 있습니다. 그리고 사람들이 옳은 일을 해왔는지 그른 일을 해왔는지, 국가에 맞는 것이 누군가를 더 나은 위치에 놓는지 아닌지는 중요하지 않아야 한다고 생각합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second piece, obviously, is to move faster, which we just talked about. The third piece is that we think it’s really important that they require a demonstration. If you look at every human space flight program in history, none of them went straight from the program starting to a long-duration mission on a spacecraft. They all had a stepping stone, and right now none of us has proven we can have humans safely on orbit in a space station. And so in our view, they should require demonstration, and not on the eve of January 1, 2031. They should require a demonstration with crew as quickly as possible before they buy services.&lt;br/&gt;(두 번째 부분은, 분명히, 더 빠르게 움직이는 것입니다. 방금 이야기했죠. 세 번째 부분은, 우리는 그들이 시증을 요구하는 것이 정말 중요하다고 생각합니다. 역사상 모든 유인 우주 비행 프로그램을 보면, 그 어느 것도 프로그램 시작부터 우주선에서의 장기 임무로 직행한 적이 없습니다. 그들 모두 디딤돌이 있었고, 현재 우리 중 그 누구도 우주정거장에서 인간을 안전하게 궤도에 올릴 수 있다는 것을 증명하지 못했습니다. 따라서 우리의 견해로는, 그들은 시증을 요구해야 하며, 2031년 1월 1일 전야에 하는 것이 아닙니다. 그들은 서비스를 구매하기 전에 가능한 한 빨리 승무원이 참여한 시증을 요구해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : You mentioned doing the “right thing for the country.” What does that mean for NASA?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : "국가를 위한 옳은 일"을 한다고 언급하셨는데, NASA에게 그것은 무엇을 의미하나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : It means you’re focused on commercial stations being ready by 2030, so there is not a need to extend the ISS. And it means ensuring we have not just one winner, but two, in case history repeats itself, such as Boeing and SpaceX in crew transportation.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 그것은 2030년까지 상업용 정거장이 준비되도록 집중하여 ISS를 연장할 필요가 없게 하는 것을 의미합니다. 그리고 그것은 역사가 반복되는 경우(예: 보잉과 스페이스X의 승무원 수송 사례)를 대비해 단 한 명의 승자가 아닌 두 명의 승자를 보장하는 것을 의미합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars : Do you think the government has committed enough funding to make the commercial space station program a success?&lt;br/&gt;(아스 : 정부가 상업용 우주정거장 프로그램을 성공시키기에 충분한 자금을 약속했다고 생각하시나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haot : I’m a vendor, and obviously I’d like as much buffer as possible, and as much funding as possible. With the current budget we don’t think more than two winners is reasonable, but it should absolutely be two in the best interest of the country. If there was a bigger budget, obviously, three would be great. And so if you look at the CLD budget line, which is approved for next year—projected over five years for development, and you assume two winners, and then services that come later—we are confident we can be successful and profitable with two companies operating.&lt;br/&gt;(하오트 : 저는 공급자이며, 분명히 가능한 한 많은 완충 자금과 자금을 원합니다. 현재 예산으로는 두 명 이상의 승자가 나오는 것은 합리적이지 않다고 생각하지만, 국가의 최선의 이익을 위해 반드시 두 명이어야 합니다. 예산이 더 컸다면, 분명히 세 명이면 좋았을 것입니다. 따라서 내년에 승인된 CLD 예산 라인(5년간 개발에 투자되고, 두 명의 승자가 있으며, 이후 서비스가 뒤따른다고 가정할 때)을 보면, 두 기업이 운영하는 상황에서도 우리는 성공하고 수익을 낼 수 있다고 확신합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, we also need international customers, right? We need Europe. We need Japan, where we just opened a subsidiary. We need all the new emerging human spaceflight nations in the Middle East, in Europe, in Asia. And a little bit of private spaceflight. We’re not in a space tourism era, in orbit, but there are still some private individuals willing to fund a mission and do important work. With that, we get to profitability.&lt;br/&gt;(분명히, 우리는 국제 고객도 필요합니다. 유럽이 필요하고, 일본이 필요합니다(우리는 최근 일본에 자회사를 열었습니다). 중동, 유럽, 아시아의 모든 신흥 유인 우주 비행 국가들이 필요합니다. 그리고 약간의 민간 우주 비행도 필요합니다. 우리는 궤도상의 우주 관광 시대에 있는 것은 아니지만, 여전히 임무에 자금을 지원하고 중요한 일을 하려는 일부 민간 개인들이 있습니다. 그것으로 우리는 수익성을 달성합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We think a big differentiator of Vast is that we are really excited and eager to unlock the orbital economy. I’m talking about in-space semiconductor, fiber, pharmaceutical manufacturing, and so on. We think that’s our upside. We want to unlock it. But we don’t know how quickly it will happen or how big it will be. What we do know is, whoever has a platform up there with flight crew, facilities, and power will be the one unlocking it. But in our business model, if that’s delayed, we can still be profitable.&lt;br/&gt;(우리는 배스트의 큰 차별점은 우리가 정말 흥분되고 열망하며 궤도 경제를 개방하는 데 있다고 생각합니다. 저는 우주 내 반도체, 광섬유, 제약 제조 등을 말하는 것입니다. 우리는 그것이 우리의 상승 가능성이라고 생각합니다. 우리는 그것을 개방하고 싶습니다. 하지만 그것이 얼마나 빨리 일어날지, 얼마나 클지 모릅니다. 우리가 아는 것은, 그곳에 비행 승무원, 시설, 전력을 갖춘 플랫폼을 가진 자가 그것을 개방할 것이라는 점입니다. 하지만 우리의 비즈니스 모델에서는, 그것이 지연되더라도 우리는 여전히 수익을 낼 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/the-first-commercial-space-station-haven-1-is-now-undergoing-assembly-for-launch/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Vast_Haven-1_Integration_Phase-1_ISO8_Cleanroom_Spring_2026-01-15-DSC_1375-3-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:00:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sony is giving TCL control over its high-end Bravia TVs (소니, 고급형 브라비아 TV 사업권을 TCL에 넘긴다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tcl-to-gain-majority-ownership-over-sonys-bravia-tvs/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1236174910-1152x648-1768934089.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCL will own 51 percent of the high-end TVs.&lt;br/&gt;(TCL이 고급형 TV 사업의 지분 51%를 보유하게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCL is taking majority ownership of Sony’s Bravia series of TVs, the two companies announced today.&lt;br/&gt;(소니와 TCL은 오늘 공동 발표를 통해, TCL이 소니의 브라비아 TV 시리즈 사업의 지분 과반수를 인수한다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two firms said they have signed a memorandum of understanding and aim to sign binding agreements by the end of March. Pending “relevant regulatory approvals and other conditions,” the joint venture is expected to launch in April 2027.&lt;br/&gt;(양사는 양해각서(MOU)에 서명했으며, 3월 말까지 구속력 있는 계약 체결을 목표로 하고 있다. "관련 규제 당국의 승인 및 기타 조건"을 거쳐 합작 회사는 2027년 4월 출범할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a new joint venture, Huizhou, China-headquartered TCL will own 51 percent of Tokyo, Japan-headquartered Sony’s “home entertainment business,” and Sony will own 49 percent, per an announcement today, adding:&lt;br/&gt;(오늘의 발표에 따르면, 새로운 합작 회사에서 중국 후이저우에 본사를 둔 TCL은 일본 도쿄에 본사를 둔 소니의 "홈 엔터테인먼트 사업" 지분의 51%를, 소니는 49%를 각각 보유하게 된다. 발표문은 이어 다음과 같이 덧붙였다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture will operate globally, handling the full process from product development and design to manufacturing, sales, logistics, and customer service for products including televisions and home audio equipment.&lt;br/&gt;(합작 회사는 전 세계적으로 운영되며, TV 및 홈 오디오 장비를 포함한 제품의 기획, 디자인부터 제조, 판매, 물류, 고객 서비스에 이르는 전 과정을 담당할 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joint venture will continue to release TVs and home audio gadgets under the “Sony Bravia” branding; however, the TVs will rely on TCL display technology. The joint announcement suggested focuses on bigger TVs, higher-resolution displays, and “ smart features .”&lt;br/&gt;(합작 회사는 "소니 브라비아" 브랜드로 TV와 홈 오디오 기기를 계속 출시할 예정이다. 그러나 TV에는 TCL의 디스플레이 기술이 적용될 것이다. 공동 발표문은 더 큰 화면, 더 높은 해상도, 그리고 "스마트 기능"에 중점을 둘 것임을 시사했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news comes as the TV industry has struggled with decreasing margins and has become more competitive. Meanwhile, devices have become cheaper, and people are buying new TVs less frequently . Competition between Chinese companies, like TCL and Hisense, and South Korean firms, like LG and Samsung, has heated up, with Chinese companies making increasingly competitive budget and mid-range-priced TVs, and the South Korean government reportedly pushing local TV firms to work together . Numerous Japanese companies, including Toshiba and Sharp , have already exited or reduced their TV businesses.&lt;br/&gt;(이 소식은 TV 산업이 마진 감소로 어려움을 겪으며 경쟁이 더욱 치열해지는 시점에 나왔다. 한편, 기기 가격은 저렴해졌고 소비자들은 TV를 덜 자주 구매하는 추세다. TCL과 하이센스 같은 중국 기업과 LG, 삼성 같은 한국 기업 간의 경쟁은 더욱 뜨거워졌는데, 중국 기업들은 점점 더 경쟁력 있는 보급형 및 중급 가격대 TV를 선보이고 있으며, 한국 정부는 국내 TV 업체들의 협력을 촉진하고 있는 것으로 알려졌다. 도시바와 샤프를 포함한 많은 일본 기업들은 이미 TV 사업에서 철수하거나 축소한 상태다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upcoming joint venture also comes as Sony has focused less on electronics in recent years. For example, it stopped making its Vaio PCs in 2014 and quit Blu-rays last year . Meanwhile, it has been focusing on intellectual property, like anime and movies, as Bloomberg noted. The joint venture should allow Sony to focus on its more lucrative businesses and allow TCL to gain an advantage by leveraging Sony’s more high-end Bravia devices and brand.&lt;br/&gt;(이번 예정된 합작은 소니가 최근 몇 년간 전자 제품 사업에 덜 집중해 온 흐름과도 맞닿아 있다. 예를 들어, 소니는 2014년 바이오(Vaio) PC 생산을 중단했고, 지난해에는 블루레이 사업에서 철수했다. 한편, 블룸버그가 지적했듯이, 소니는 애니메이션과 영화 같은 지식 재산권(IP) 사업에 집중해 왔다. 이번 합작은 소니가 더 수익성이 높은 사업에 집중할 수 있게 해 주고, TCL은 소니의 고급형 브라비아 기기와 브랜드를 활용해 우위를 점할 수 있는 계기가 될 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tcl-to-gain-majority-ownership-over-sonys-bravia-tvs/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1236174910-1152x648-1768934089.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:58:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netflix to pay all cash for Warner Bros. to fend off Paramount hostile takeover (넷플릭스, 파라마운트 적대적 인수 견제 위해 워너브러더스 현금 전액 지급 합의)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/netflix-to-pay-all-cash-for-warner-bros-to-fend-off-paramount-hostile-takeover/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/netflix-paramount-wb-icons-1152x648-1767815429.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix and Warner seek quick shareholder vote as Paramount tries to upend deal.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트가 합병을 저지하려는 가운데, 넷플릭스와 워너가 주주 투표를 신속히 진행하려 함.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix agreed to pay all cash for Warner Bros. Discovery, amending its $72 billion deal in an attempt to fight off Paramount’s hostile takeover bid.&lt;br/&gt;(넷플릭스가 파라마운트의 적대적 인수 제안을 막기 위해, 720억 달러 규모의 워너브러더스 디스커버리 인수 계약을 수정하여 현금 전액 지급 방식으로 전환하기로 합의했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix originally agreed to buy the company with a mix of cash and stock. To sweeten the offer for shareholders, Netflix and Warner Bros. today announced that Netflix will pay all cash instead. If successful, Netflix’s purchase will include HBO Max, WB Studios, and other assets.&lt;br/&gt;(넷플릭스는 원래 현금과 주식 혼합 방식으로 회사를 인수하기로 합의했습니다. 주주들에게 제안을 더 매력적으로 만들기 위해, 넷플릭스와 워너브러더스는 오늘 넷플릭스가 대신 현금을 전액 지급할 것이라고 발표했습니다. 성사될 경우, 넷플릭스의 인수에는 HBO Max, WB 스튜디오 및 기타 자산이 포함됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price is unchanged at $27.75 per share, and Warner Bros. is targeting an April 2026 shareholder vote. The original plan was for Netflix to buy each Warner Bros. share with $23.25 in cash and $4.50 in Netflix stock.&lt;br/&gt;(주당 가격은 27.75달러로 변경되지 않았으며, 워너브러더스는 2026년 4월 주주 투표를 목표로 하고 있습니다. 원래 계획은 넷플릭스가 워너브러더스 주식 1주당 현금 23.25달러와 넷플릭스 주식 4.50달러로 매입하는 것이었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised agreement “simplifies the transaction structure,” “accelerates the path to a WBD stockholder vote,” and “provides enhanced certainty around the value WBD stockholders will receive at closing, eliminating market-based variability,” today’s press release said. Netflix plans to finance the deal with “a combination of cash on hand, available credit facilities and committed financing.”&lt;br/&gt;(수정된 합의는 "거래 구조를 단순화하고", "WBD 주주 투표로 가는 경로를 가속화하며", "마감 시 WBD 주주들이 받을 가치에 대한 변동성을 제거하여 향상된 확실성을 제공한다"고 오늘의 보도 자료는 밝혔습니다. 넷플릭스는 이 거래를 "보유 현금, 이용 가능한 신용 한도 및 확정된 자금 조달의 조합"으로 자금을 조달할 계획입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix’s pending purchase of Warner Bros. has an equity value of $72 billion and an enterprise value of $82.7 billion, which includes both equity and debt. Paramount Skydance has been trying to upend the deal with its own offer to buy Warner Bros. in a hostile takeover attempt that includes a lawsuit it filed against Warner Bros. last week.&lt;br/&gt;(넷플릭스의 워너브러더스 인수 계약은 지분 가치 720억 달러, 기업 가치(지분과 부채 포함) 827억 달러입니다. 파라마운트 스카이댄스는 지난주 워너브러더스를 상대로 제기한 소송을 포함한 적대적 인수 시도를 통해 자체 제안으로 이 거래를 저지하려 해왔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount offered $108.4 billion at $30 per share, but it’s trying to buy the entire Warner Bros. Discovery company, while Netflix’s deal is for just the streaming and movie studios divisions. The Warner Bros. board wants to complete a separate spinoff of its cable TV division, which would not be possible if Paramount’s hostile takeover succeeds. The spinoff is scheduled to be completed before the closing of the sale to Netflix, and the spun-off entity would be called Discovery Global.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트는 주당 30달러에 총 1,084억 달러를 제안했지만, 워너브러더스 디스커버리 회사 전체를 인수하려는 반면, 넷플릭스의 거래는 스트리밍 및 영화 스튜디오 부문만을 대상으로 합니다. 워너브러더스 이사회는 케이블 TV 부문의 별도 분사를 완료하려고 하는데, 파라마운트의 적대적 인수가 성공하면 불가능해집니다. 분사는 넷플릭스에 매각이 마감되기 전에 완료될 예정이며, 분사된 법인은 디스커버리 글로벌로 명명될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By transitioning to all-cash consideration, we can now deliver the incredible value of our combination with Netflix at even greater levels of certainty, while providing our stockholders the opportunity to participate in management’s strategic plans to realize the value of Discovery Global’s iconic brands and global reach,” Warner Bros. Discovery board Chairman Samuel Di Piazza Jr. said in today’s press release.&lt;br/&gt;(워너브러더스 디스커버리 이사회 사무엘 디 피아자 주니어 의장은 오늘의 보도 자료에서 "전액 현금 대가로 전환함으로써, 우리는 이제 넷플릭스와의 합병이 가져올 놀라운 가치를 더 큰 확실성으로 전달할 수 있으며, 동시에 우리 주주들에게 디스커버리 글로벌의 상징적인 브랜드와 글로벌 영향력의 가치를 실현하기 위한 경영진의 전략적 계획에 참여할 기회를 제공할 수 있다"고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount also made an all-cash offer, but the Warner Bros. board called the Paramount bid “illusory” because it requires an “extraordinary amount of debt financing” and other terms that allegedly make it less likely to be completed than a Netflix merger.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트도 전액 현금 제안을 했지만, 워너브러더스 이사회는 파라마운트의 입찰이 "엄청난 양의 부채 금융"이 필요하고 다른 조건들로 인해 넷플릭스와의 합병보다 성사 가능성이 낮다고 주장하며 "허황된" 것이라고 평가했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount “is a $14B market cap company with a ‘junk’ credit rating, negative free cash flows, significant fixed financial obligations, and a high degree of dependency on its linear business,” while Netflix has “market capitalization of approximately $400 billion, an investment grade balance sheet, an A/A3 credit rating and estimated free cash flow of more than $12 billion for 2026,” Warner Bros. told shareholders.&lt;br/&gt;(워너브러더스는 주주들에게 파라마운트는 "140억 달러 시가총액에 '정크' 신용 등급, 음의 자유현금흐름, 상당한 고정 재무 의무, 그리고 선형(전통 방송) 사업에 대한 높은 의존도를 가진 회사"인 반면, 넷플릭스는 "약 4,000억 달러의 시가총액, 투자 등급 재무 상태, A/A3 신용 등급, 그리고 2026년 기준 120억 달러 이상의 추정 자유현금흐름"을 가진다고 설명했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. and Netflix today continued to tout Netflix’s strong financial position and its ability to close the deal. “Netflix’s strong cash flow generation supports the revised all-cash transaction structure while preserving a healthy balance sheet and flexibility to capitalize on future strategic priorities,” the joint press release said.&lt;br/&gt;(워너브러더스와 넷플릭스는 오늘도 넷플릭스의 강력한 재무 상태와 거래 마감 능력을 계속 강조했습니다. 공동 보도 자료는 "넷플릭스의 강력한 현금흐름 창출 능력은 수정된 전액 현금 거래 구조를 지원하면서도 건강한 재무 상태와 미래 전략적 우선순위에 자본을 투입할 유연성을 유지합니다"라고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal explained that the new “deal structure does away with a so-called collar, a mechanism meant to protect shareholders from large swings in an acquirer’s share price between the time when a deal is announced and when it closes. If Netflix shares dipped below $97.91, Warner shareholders were to get a larger portion of Netflix shares as part of the deal. If they rose above $119.67, shareholders would have received a smaller portion.”&lt;br/&gt;(월스트리트저널은 설명하기를, 새로운 "거래 구조는 소위 '칼라'를 없앴다. 이는 거래 발표 시점부터 마감 시점까지 인수 기업 주가의 큰 변동으로부터 주주를 보호하기 위한 장치였다. 만약 넷플릭스 주가가 97.91달러 아래로 떨어지면, 워너 주주들은 거래의 일부로 더 많은 넷플릭스 주식을 받게 될 예정이었다. 만약 주가가 119.67달러 위로 올라가면, 주주들은 더 적은 주식을 받게 될 것이었다"고 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix’s stock price closed at $100.24 on December 5 and is down to about $88, partly due to investor fears that Netflix will have to pay more to complete the merger.&lt;br/&gt;(넷플릭스 주가는 12월 5일 100.24달러에 마감했으며, 현재 약 88달러까지 하락했습니다. 이는 부분적으로 투자자들이 넷플릭스가 합병을 완료하기 위해 더 많은 비용을 지불해야 할 것이라는 우려 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Paramount lawsuit against Warner Bros. alleges that the company board failed to disclose basic information that stockholders need to decide between the Paramount and Netflix bids. The lawsuit seeks details on how Warner Bros. valued the shares in its planned spinoff, and other information such as how Warner Bros. determined that the Paramount offer was too risky.&lt;br/&gt;(워너브러더스를 상대로 한 파라마운트의 소송은, 회사 이사회가 주주들이 파라마운트와 넷플릭스의 입찰 제안 사이에서 결정하는 데 필요한 기본 정보를 공개하지 않았다고 주장합니다. 이 소송은 워너브러더스가 계획된 분사에서 주식을 어떻게 평가했는지에 대한 세부 정보와, 파라마운트 제안이 너무 위험하다고 어떻게 판단했는지 등의 다른 정보를 요구합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“WBD shareholders need this information to make an informed investment decision on our offer—and importantly, Delaware law has consistently required that such information be provided to shareholders,” Paramount CEO David Ellison wrote in a letter to Warner Bros. shareholders after filing suit in Delaware Chancery Court.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트 CEO 데이비드 엘리슨은 델라웨어 주衡平法원에 소송을 제기한 후 워너브러더스 주주들에게 보낸 서신에서 "WBD 주주들은 우리의 제안에 대해 정보에 입각한 투자 결정을 내리기 위해 이 정보가 필요합니다. 그리고 중요한 것은, 델라웨어州法은 일관되게 그러한 정보가 주주들에게 제공될 것을 요구해 왔습니다"라고 썼습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount says its own analysis of Discovery Global assets values the spinoff company at $0 per share.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트는 자체적인 디스커버리 글로벌 자산 분석에 따르면 분사 회사의 가치가 주당 0달러라고 주장합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“WBD has provided increasingly novel reasons for avoiding a transaction with Paramount, but what it has never said, because it cannot, is that the Netflix transaction is financially superior to our actual offer,” Ellison wrote. Warner Bros. reportedly responded that Paramount “has yet to raise the price or address the numerous and obvious deficiencies of its offer,” and “is seeking to distract with a meritless lawsuit and attacks on a board that has delivered an unprecedented amount of shareholder value.”&lt;br/&gt;(엘리슨은 "WBD는 파라마운트와의 거래를 피하기 위해 점점 더 기이한 이유를 제시해 왔지만, 결코 말하지 않은 것은 (말할 수 없기 때문이지만) 넷플릭스 거래가 우리의 실제 제안보다 재정적으로 우월하다는 것입니다"라고 썼습니다. 보도에 따르면 워너브러더스는 파라마운트가 "아직 가격을 인상하거나 그 제안의 수많은 명백한 결점을 해결하지 못했으며", "근거 없는 소송과 전례 없는 양의 주주 가치를 창출한 이사회에 대한 공격으로 주의를 분산시키려 하고 있다"고 응답했다고 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount’s lawsuit hasn’t been an immediate success. A judge last week rejected Paramount’s request to expedite the case, saying it did not suffer “cognizable irreparable harm” from the allegedly inadequate disclosures.&lt;br/&gt;(파라마운트의 소송은 즉각적인 성공을 거두지는 못했습니다. 지난주 한 판사는 파라마운트의 사건 신속 처리 요청을 기각하며, 주장된 불충분한 공개로 인해 "인정할 만한 불가피한 손해"를 입지 않았다고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/netflix-to-pay-all-cash-for-warner-bros-to-fend-off-paramount-hostile-takeover/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/netflix-paramount-wb-icons-1152x648-1767815429.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:24:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Macaque facial gestures are more than just a reflex, study finds (마카크 원숭이의 얼굴 표정은 단순 반사 이상, 연구 결과)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/macaque-facial-gestures-are-more-than-just-a-reflex-study-finds/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2243934190-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Study is first to implant micro-electrode arrays to record neurons as they produce facial gestures.&lt;br/&gt;(얼굴 표정 생성 시 뉴런을 기록하기 위해 미세 전극 배열을 이식한 최초의 연구.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in brain-computer interfaces have made it possible to more accurately extract speech from neural signals in humans, but language is just one of the tools we use to communicate. “When my young nephew asks for ice cream before dinner and I say ‘no,’ the meaning is entirely dictated by whether the word is punctuated with a smirk or a stern frown,” says Geena Ianni, a neuroscientist at the University of Pennsylvania. That’s why in the future, she thinks, neural prostheses meant for patients with a stroke or paralysis will decode facial gestures from brain signals in the same way they decode speech.&lt;br/&gt;(뇌-컴퓨터 인터페이스의 최근 발전으로 인간의 신경 신호에서 말을 더 정확하게 추출하는 것이 가능해졌지만, 언어는 우리가 의사소통에 사용하는 도구 중 하나일 뿐입니다. 펜실베이니아 대학교의 신경과학자 지나 이아니는 "제 어린 조카가 저녁 식사 전에 아이스크림을 달라고 할 때, 제가 '안 돼'라고 말할 때 그 의미는 그 말이 능글맞은 미소와 함께 했는지 엄한 찡그림과 함께 했는지에 전적으로 달려 있습니다"라고 말합니다. 그래서 그녀는 미래에 뇌졸중이나 마비 환자를 위한 신경 보철 장치가 말을 해독하는 것과 같은 방식으로 뇌 신호에서 얼굴 표정을 해독할 것이라고 생각합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To lay a foundation for these future facial gesture decoders, Ianni and her colleagues designed an experiment to find out how neural circuitry responsible for making faces really works. “Although in recent years neuroscience got a good handle on how the brain perceives facial expressions, we know relatively little about how they are generated,” Ianni says. And it turned out that a surprisingly large part of what neuroscientists assumed about facial gestures was wrong.&lt;br/&gt;(이러한 미래의 얼굴 표정 해독기를 위한 기초를 마련하기 위해, 이아니와 그녀의 동료들은 얼굴을 만드는 데 책임이 있는 신경 회로가 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지 알아보기 위한 실험을 설계했습니다. 이아니는 "최근 몇 년간 신경과학이 얼굴 표정을 인식하는 뇌의 방식을 꽤 잘 이해하게 되었지만, 얼굴 표정이 어떻게 생성되는지에 대해서는 상대적으로 알려진 바가 적습니다"라고 말합니다. 그리고 신경과학자들이 얼굴 표정에 대해 가정했던 것의 놀라울 정도로 많은 부분이 틀렸다는 것이 밝혀졌습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, neuroscientists thought facial gestures in primates stemmed from a neat division of labor in the brain. “Case reports of patients with brain lesions suggested some brain regions were responsible for certain types of emotional expressions while other regions were responsible for volitional movements like speech,” Ianni explains. We’ve developed a clearer picture of speech by tracing the origin of these movements down to the level of individual neurons. But we’ve not done the same for facial expressions. To fill this gap, Ianni and her team designed a study using macaques—social primates that share most of their complex facial musculature with humans.&lt;br/&gt;(오랫동안 신경과학자들은 영장류의 얼굴 표정이 뇌의 깔끔한 분업에서 비롯된다고 생각했습니다. 이아니는 "뇌 병변 환자 사례 보고서에 따르면, 일부 뇌 영역은 특정 유형의 정서적 표현을 담당하는 반면 다른 영역은 말과 같은 의지적 움직임을 담당하는 것으로 보였습니다"라고 설명합니다. 우리는 이러한 움직임의 기원을 개별 뉴런 수준까지 추적함으로써 말에 대해 더 명확한 그림을 발전시켜 왔습니다. 하지만 얼굴 표정에 대해서는 같은 일을 하지 않았습니다. 이 격차를 메우기 위해 이아니와 그녀의 팀은 마카크 원숭이(인간과 대부분의 복잡한 얼굴 근육을 공유하는 사회적 영장류)를 사용한 연구를 설계했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study started by putting the macaques in an fMRI scanner to monitor their brain activity while recording their faces with a high-resolution camera. The team then exposed their participants to various stimuli: videos with other macaques making faces at them, interactive avatars, or other live macaques. “This elicited socially meaningful facial expressions that are part of the subjects’ natural repertoire,” Ianni says.&lt;br/&gt;(연구는 마카크 원숭이들을 fMRI 스캐너에 넣고 고해상도 카메라로 그들의 얼굴을 기록하면서 뇌 활동을 모니터링하는 것으로 시작했습니다. 그런 다음 팀은 참가자들에게 다양한 자극을 노출시켰습니다: 다른 마카크 원숭이들이 그들에게 얼굴을 짓는 비디오, 대화형 아바타, 또는 다른 실시간 마카크 원숭이들. 이아니는 "이것은 피험자들의 자연스러운 레퍼토리에 속하는 사회적으로 의미 있는 얼굴 표정을 유발했습니다"라고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on the video analysis, scientists identified three facial gestures they wanted to focus on: the lipsmack macaques use to signal receptivity or submission; the threat face they make when they want to challenge or chase off an adversary; and chewing, a non-social, volitional movement. Then, using the fMRI scans, the team located key brain areas involved in triggering these gestures. And when this was done, Ianni and her colleagues went deeper—quite literally.&lt;br/&gt;(비디오 분석을 바탕으로 과학자들은 집중하고 싶은 세 가지 얼굴 표정을 확인했습니다: 마카크 원숭이가 수용성이나 복종을 신호하기 위해 사용하는 입맞춤; 적수를 도전하거나 쫓아내고 싶을 때 만드는 위협 얼굴; 그리고 비사회적, 의지적 움직임인 씹기. 그런 다음 fMRI 스캔을 사용하여 팀은 이러한 표정을 유발하는 데 관여하는 주요 뇌 영역을 찾아냈습니다. 그리고 이 작업이 끝나자, 이아니와 그녀의 동료들은 더 깊이 들어갔습니다—말 그대로요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We targeted these brain areas with sub-millimeter precision for implantation of micro-electrode arrays,” Ianni explains. This, for the first time, allowed her team to simultaneously record the activity from many neurons spaced across the areas where the brain generates facial gestures. The electrodes went into the primary motor cortex, the ventral premotor cortex, the primary somatosensory cortex, and the cingulate motor cortex. When they were in, the team once again exposed the macaques to the same set of social stimuli, looking for neural signatures of the three selected facial gestures. And that’s when things took a surprising turn.&lt;br/&gt;(이아니는 "우리는 이러한 뇌 영역을 서브밀리미터 정밀도로 타겟팅하여 미세 전극 배열을 이식했습니다"라고 설명합니다. 이것은 처음으로 그녀의 팀이 뇌가 얼굴 표정을 생성하는 영역에 걸쳐 분포된 많은 뉴런의 활동을 동시에 기록할 수 있게 해주었습니다. 전극은 일차 운동 피질, 복측 운동 전 피질, 일차 체성감각 피질, 그리고 대상 운동 피질에 삽입되었습니다. 전극이 삽입된 후, 팀은 다시 한번 마카크 원숭이들에게 같은 사회적 자극 세트를 노출시켜, 선택된 세 가지 얼굴 표정의 신경적 특징을 찾았습니다. 그리고 그때 일이 놀라운 방향으로 전개되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers expected to see a clear division of responsibilities, one where the cingulate cortex governs social signals, while the motor cortex is specialized in chewing. Instead, they found that every single region was involved in every type of gesture. Whether the macaques were threatening a rival or simply enjoying a snack, all four brain areas were firing in a coordinated symphony.&lt;br/&gt;(연구자들은 책임의 명확한 분업, 즉 대상 피질이 사회적 신호를 관장하고 운동 피질은 씹기에 특화된 구조를 볼 것이라고 예상했습니다. 대신에, 그들은 모든 단일 영역이 모든 유형의 표정에 관여한다는 것을 발견했습니다. 마카크 원숭이들이 라이벌을 위협하든 단순히 간식을 즐기든, 네 개의 뇌 영역 모두가 조화로운 교향곡처럼 함께 발화하고 있었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led Ianni’s team to the question of how the brain distinguished between social gestures and chewing, since it apparently wasn’t about where the brain processed the information. The answer was in different neural codes—different ways that neurons represent and transmit information in the brain over time.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 이아니 팀에게 뇌가 사회적 표정과 씹기를 어떻게 구별하는지에 대한 질문으로 이끌었습니다. 왜냐하면 분명히 정보를 처리하는 뇌의 위치에 관한 문제가 아니었기 때문입니다. 답은 다른 신경 코드—뉴런이 시간에 따라 뇌에서 정보를 표현하고 전달하는 다른 방식—에 있었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By analyzing neural population dynamics, the team identified a temporal hierarchy across the cortex in macaques. The cingulate cortex used a static neural code. “The static means the firing pattern of neurons is persistent across both multiple repetitions of the same facial gesture and across time,” Ianni explains, and maintained their firing pattern till 0.8 seconds after that. “A single decoder which learns this pattern could be used at any timepoint or during any trial to read out the facial expression,” Ianni says.&lt;br/&gt;(신경 집단 역학을 분석함으로써, 팀은 마카크 원숭이의 피질 전체에 걸친 시간적 계층 구조를 확인했습니다. 대상 피질은 정적 신경 코드를 사용했습니다. 이아니는 "정적이란 뉴런의 발화 패턴이 같은 얼굴 표정의 여러 반복과 시간에 걸쳐 지속된다는 것을 의미합니다"라고 설명하며, 그 패턴을 그 후 0.8초까지 유지했다고 말합니다. 이아니는 "이 패턴을 학습하는 단일 디코더는 어떤 시점이나 어떤 시도 중에도 얼굴 표정을 읽어내는 데 사용될 수 있습니다"라고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firing rates in the motor and somatosensory cortex, on the other hand, looked radically different. This suggests there is a dynamic neural code defined by rapidly changing firing rate relationships amongst the neural populations.&lt;br/&gt;(반면에, 운동 피질과 체성감각 피질의 발화율은 근본적으로 달랐습니다. 이는 신경 집단들 사이에서 급격히 변화하는 발화율 관계로 정의되는 동적 신경 코드가 있음을 시사합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team thinks this means that the cingulate cortex manages the social purpose and context of the facial gesture, which is relatively stable. This may be where the brain integrates sensory cues—like the look of another monkey’s expression—with its own internal state to produce the right facial gesture for the occasion.&lt;br/&gt;(팀은 이것이 대상 피질이 상대적으로 안정적인 얼굴 표정의 사회적 목적과 맥락을 관리한다는 것을 의미한다고 생각합니다. 이것은 아마도 뇌가 감각 단서—다른 원숭이 표정의 모습과 같은—를 자신의 내부 상태와 통합하여 상황에 맞는 적절한 얼굴 표정을 생성하는 곳일 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dynamic code areas implement this expression by driving individual muscles. “They’re driving the kinematics like ‘move this lip a millimeter to the left, now a millimeter to the right,’” Ianni explains. These constant miniscule movements of muscles are necessary because facial expressions are usually dynamic—macaques’ eyelids, lips, cheeks, and ears are constantly twitching and changing their position even if the end effect looks still from a distance.&lt;br/&gt;(동적 코드 영역은 개별 근육을 구동함으로써 이 표현을 구현합니다. 이아니는 "그들은 '이 입술을 왼쪽으로 1밀리미터 움직여라, 이제 오른쪽으로 1밀리미터 움직여라'와 같은 운동학을 구동합니다"라고 설명합니다. 이러한 근육의 지속적인 미세한 움직임은 필수적입니다. 왜냐하면 얼굴 표정은 일반적으로 동적이기 때문입니다—마카크 원숭이들의 눈꺼풀, 입술, 뺨, 귀는 멀리서 보면 최종 효과가 정지해 보여도 끊임없이 떨리고 위치를 바꾸고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s just the beginning of a long journey.&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 이것은 긴 여정의 시작일 뿐입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There have been such fabulous, impressive advances in the field of assistive communication devices even since I started this project,” Ianni says, and points to neural prostheses developed by Maitreyee Wairagkar’s team Ars covered in 2025 as one of the examples. Building a similar neural prosthesis for decoding facial gestures is unlikely to happen overnight, though. We’re a rather long way away from truly restoring the ability to communicate through facial gestures to patients who lost it.&lt;br/&gt;(이아니는 "제가 이 프로젝트를 시작한 이후로도 보조 의사소통 장치 분야에서 정말 환상적이고 인상적인 발전이 있었습니다"라고 말하며, 2025년에 Ars가 다룬 마이트레예 와이라그다르크 팀이 개발한 신경 보철 장치를 예로 듭니다. 그러나 얼굴 표정을 해독하는 유사한 신경 보철 장치를 구축하는 것은 하룻밤 사이에 일어날 가능성이 낮습니다. 얼굴 표정을 통한 의사소통 능력을 잃은 환자들에게 진정으로 그 능력을 회복시키는 데는 상당히 먼 길이 남아 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ianni’s study is the first that recorded neurons producing facial gestures with multi-electrode arrays. This means we’ve only just begun to build up base science on the neural mechanism behind making faces. This is the point where neural speech decoding technology was in the late 1990s, and we still can’t make that reliable enough for regular clinical products.&lt;br/&gt;(이아니의 연구는 다중 전극 배열로 얼굴 표정을 생성하는 뉴런을 기록한 최초의 연구입니다. 이는 우리가 얼굴을 만드는 데 뒤따르는 신경 메커니즘에 대한 기초 과학을 이제 막 구축하기 시작했다는 것을 의미합니다. 이것은 1990년대 후반 신경 언어 해독 기술이 있던 지점이며, 우리는 여전히 그것을 정기적인 임상 제품에 충분히 신뢰할 수 있도록 만들지 못하고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ianni remains hopeful. “I hope our work goes towards enabling the field, even the tiniest bit, towards more naturalistic and rich communication designs that will improve lives of patients after brain injury,” she says.&lt;br/&gt;(그럼에도 불구하고, 이아니는 희망을 가지고 있습니다. 그녀는 "저는 우리의 작업이 뇌 손상 후 환자들의 삶을 개선할 더 자연스럽고 풍부한 의사소통 설계를 향해, 아주 조금이라도 이 분야를 가능하게 하는 데 기여하기를 바랍니다"라고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science: https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aea0890&lt;br/&gt;(Science: https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aea0890)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/macaque-facial-gestures-are-more-than-just-a-reflex-study-finds/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2243934190-2560x1440.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:25:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Flesh-eating flies are eating their way through Mexico, CDC warns (살을 파먹는 파리가 멕시코를 휩쓸고 있다고 CDC 경고)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/be-on-the-lookout-for-flesh-eating-flies-cdc-tells-clinicians-in-alert/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/CSIRO_ScienceImage_115_The_Tip_of_a_Screw_Worm_Fly_Larvae.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eight animal cases in Mexico’s Tamaulipas spur CDC to warn doctors of festering wounds.&lt;br/&gt;(멕시코 타마울리파스주의 동물 8건 사례가 CDC로 하여금 의사들에게 곪은 상처에 대해 경고하도록 촉발시켰다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention issued a health alert to clinicians Tuesday, warning that the savage, flesh-eating parasitic fly— the New World Screwworm —is not only approaching the Texas border, but also felling an increasing number of animals in the bordering Mexican state of Tamaulipas.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 질병통제예방센터(CDC)는 화요일 임상의들에게 보건 경보를 발령하며, 잔혹한 살을 파먹는 기생파리인 신세계사상충파리가 텍사스 주 경계에 접근하고 있을 뿐만 아니라, 인접한 멕시코 타마울리파스주에서 점점 더 많은 동물들을 쓰러뜨리고 있다고 경고했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advisory, released through the agency’s Health Alert Network, directs doctors, veterinarians, and other health workers to be on the lookout for patients with wounds teeming with ferocious maggots burrowing into their living flesh. The alert also provides guidance on what to do if any such festering wounds are encountered—namely, remove each and every maggot to prevent the patient from dying, and, under no circumstance allow any of the parasites to survive and escape.&lt;br/&gt;(CDC의 건강경보네트워크를 통해 발표된 이 권고안은 의사, 수의사 및 기타 보건 종사자들에게 살아있는 살 속으로 파고드는 사나운 구더기로 가득한 상처를 가진 환자들을 주의 깊게 살펴볼 것을 지시한다. 또한, 만약 그러한 곪은 상처를 발견하면 어떻게 해야 하는지에 대한 지침을 제공하는데, 즉 환자가 사망하는 것을 막기 위해 모든 구더기를 하나도 빠짐없이 제거하고, 어떤 경우에도 기생충이 살아남아 도망가지 않도록 해야 한다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New World Screwworm (NWS) is a fly that lays its eggs—up to 400 at a time—in the wounds, orifices, and mucus membranes of any warm-blooded animal. The eggs hatch into flesh-eating maggots, which look and act much like screws, twisting and boring into their victims while eating them alive.&lt;br/&gt;(신세계사상충파리는 따뜻한 피를 가진 모든 동물의 상처, 체공(구멍), 점막에 한 번에 최대 400개까지 알을 낳는 파리다. 알은 살을 파먹는 구더기로 부화하는데, 이 구더기는 모양과 행동이 나사와 매우 유사하여 피해자를 산 채로 먹어치우면서 비틀고 파고든다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the flies are indiscriminate killers, they’re particularly devastating to livestock and are estimated to cause hundreds of millions of dollars in damage each year. As such, the US Department of Agriculture has been leading the response to the threat, which had been held far at bay until recently. NWS used to be endemic in the US, causing heavy losses to cattle in the country. But, in the 1950s, US scientists developed a strategy to eliminate the flies by raising and releasing sterile male flies. The method exploits the fact that female flies mate only once in their 21-day lifespan. Thus, unproductive mating with a flood of sterile males can cause the population to crash.&lt;br/&gt;(이 파리들은 가리지 않고 살생을 하지만, 특히 가축에게는 파괴적이며 매년 수억 달러의 피해를 일으키는 것으로 추정된다. 이에 따라 미국 농무부는 최근까지 멀리 격리되어 있던 이 위협에 대한 대응을 주도해 왔다. NWS는 과거 미국에서 풍토병이었으며, 미국 내 소에게 막대한 손실을 초래했다. 그러나 1950년대에 미국 과학자들은 불임 수컷 파리를 대량 번식시켜 방사함으로써 파리를 근절하는 전략을 개발했다. 이 방법은 암컷 파리가 21일의 수명 동안 단 한 번만 교미한다는 사실을 이용한다. 따라서 대량의 불임 수컷과의 비생산적인 교미는 개체군을 붕괴시킬 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this strategy, screwworms were eradicated from the US around 1966 and, through coordinated efforts, cleared out from Central America in the subsequent decades. They were declared eradicated from Panama in 2006 and actively held at bay with continual sterile-fly releases along the Darién Gap, creating a biological barrier. But the barrier was breached in 2022 amid development and movement through and around the gap. Since then, the flies have quickly been marching north with the help of unregulated cattle movements.&lt;br/&gt;(이 전략으로 사상충파리는 1966년경 미국에서 근절되었고, 조정된 노력을 통해 이후 수십 년 동안 중앙아메리카에서도 퇴치되었다. 2006년에는 파나마에서 근절 선언이 되었고, 다리엔 갭을 따라 지속적인 불임파리 방사를 통해 능동적으로 격리되어 생물학적 장벽을 형성했다. 그러나 2022년 갭 주변 및 통과 지역의 개발과 이동 속에서 이 장벽이 뚫렸다. 그 이후로, 이 파리들은 규제되지 않은 소 이동의 도움으로 빠르게 북상해 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across Central America and Mexico, there have been 1,190 human cases of NWS reported and seven deaths. More than 148,000 animals have been affected.&lt;br/&gt;(중앙아메리카와 멕시코 전역에서 NWS 인체 감염 사례 1,190건과 사망 7건이 보고되었다. 148,000마리 이상의 동물이 영향을 받았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September, the USDA warned that an 8-month-old cow with an active NWS infection was found in a feedlot in the Mexican state of Nuevo León, just 70 miles from the border. The finding prompted Texas Agriculture Commissioner Sid Miller to step up warnings about the threat.&lt;br/&gt;(9월, 미국 농무부는 활성 NWS 감염을 가진 8개월 된 암소가 국경에서 불과 70마일 떨어진 멕시코 누에보레온주의 사육장에서 발견되었다고 경고했다. 이 발견은 텍사스 농업국장 시드 밀러로 하여금 이 위협에 대한 경고를 강화하도록 촉구했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ The screwworm is dangerously close ,” Miller said at the time. “It nearly wiped out our cattle industry before; we need to act forcefully now.”&lt;br/&gt;("사상충파리가 위험할 정도로 가까이 왔습니다,"라고 밀러는 당시 말했다. "이것은 이전에 우리의 소 산업을 거의 전멸시켰습니다; 우리는 지금 강력하게 행동해야 합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the USDA’s latest data , Nuevo León has seen three cases in the outbreak, with none that are currently active. But, its neighboring state, Tamaulipas, is having a flare-up, with eight animal cases considered active. The Mexican state shares a border with the southern-most portion of Texas. Mexico overall has reported 24 hospitalizations among people and 601 animal cases.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 농무부의 최신 데이터에 따르면, 누에오레온주에서는 발병 중인 3건의 사례가 있었으며, 현재 활성 상태인 사례는 없다. 그러나 인접한 타마울리파스주는 확산 중으로, 동물 사례 8건이 활성 상태로 간주된다. 이 멕시코 주는 텍사스 주의 최남단 지역과 국경을 접하고 있다. 멕시코 전체적으로는 사람들 중 24건의 입원과 601건의 동물 사례가 보고되었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the NWS has not been detected in the US, and the CDC considers the risk to people to be low.&lt;br/&gt;(현재로서는 NWS가 미국에서 발견된 바 없으며, CDC는 사람들에게 대한 위험은 낮은 것으로 간주한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“However, given the potential for geographic spread, CDC is issuing this Health Advisory to increase awareness of the outbreak and to summarize CDC recommendations for clinicians and health departments in the United States on case identification and reporting, specimen collection, diagnosis, and treatment of NWS, as well as guidance for the public,” the agency said.&lt;br/&gt;("그러나 지리적 확산 가능성을 고려하여, CDC는 이번 발병에 대한 인식을 높이고, 미국 내 임상의 및 보건 부서를 위한 NWS 사례 확인 및 보고, 검체 수집, 진단, 치료에 대한 CDC 권고사항과 대중을 위한 지침을 요약하기 위해 이 건강 권고안을 발표하고 있습니다,"라고 해당 기관은 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the agency advises being on the lookout for egg masses or fly larvae in wounds or infection sites, especially if there’s destruction of living tissue or feelings of movement. Once discovered, health care workers should report the case and promptly remove and kill all larvae and eggs, preferably by drowning in a sealed, leak-proof container of 70 percent ethanol. “Failure to kill and properly dispose of all larvae or eggs could result in the new introduction and spread of NWS in the local environment,” the CDC warns in bold. At least 10 dead larvae should then be sent to the CDC for confirmation.&lt;br/&gt;(일반적으로, CDC는 상처나 감염 부위에서 알 덩어리나 파리 유충을 주의 깊게 살펴볼 것을 권고하며, 특히 살아있는 조직의 파괴나 움직임 느낌이 있는 경우 더욱 그렇다. 발견되면, 보건 종사자는 사례를 보고하고 가능한 한 70% 에탄올이 든 밀봉되고 누출 방지된 용기에 담가 익사시켜 모든 유충과 알을 즉시 제거하고 죽여야 한다. "모든 유충이나 알을 죽이고 적절히 처리하지 못하면 지역 환경에 NWS가 새롭게 유입되고 확산될 수 있습니다,"라고 CDC는 굵은 글씨로 경고한다. 그런 다음 확인을 위해 적어도 10마리의 죽은 유충을 CDC로 보내야 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The USDA is currently releasing 100 million sterile male flies per week in Mexico to try to establish a new biological barrier.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 농무부는 현재 새로운 생물학적 장벽을 구축하기 위해 멕시코에서 주당 1억 마리의 불임 수컷 파리를 방사하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn’t the fly’s first attempt at a US comeback since the 1960s. In 2016, the flies were somehow reintroduced to the Florida Keys , where they viciously attacked Key Deer, an endangered species and the smallest of North America’s white-tailed deer. The flies were eliminated again in 2017 using the sterile fly method.&lt;br/&gt;(이것은 1960년대 이후 이 파리가 미국으로 돌아오려는 첫 번째 시도가 아니다. 2016년에 이 파리는 어떻게든 플로리다 키스에 재유입되었고, 멸종 위기 종이자 북미 흰꼬리사슴 중 가장 작은 키사슴을 잔인하게 공격했다. 2017년에 불임파리 방법을 사용하여 이 파리들은 다시 근절되었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/be-on-the-lookout-for-flesh-eating-flies-cdc-tells-clinicians-in-alert/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/11/CSIRO_ScienceImage_115_The_Tip_of_a_Screw_Worm_Fly_Larvae.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:59:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google temporarily disabled YouTube’s advanced captions without warning (구글, 경고 없이 유튜브 고급 자막 기능 일시 중단)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/google-temporarily-disabled-youtubes-advanced-captions-without-warning/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/youtube-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google says SRV3 was causing playback errors, so it has “temporarily” disabled them.&lt;br/&gt;(구글은 SRV3가 재생 오류를 일으켜 이를 "일시적으로" 비활성화했다고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTubers have been increasingly frustrated with Google’s management of the platform, with disinformation welcomed back and an aggressive push for more AI (except where Google doesn’t like it ). So it’s no surprise that creators have been up in arms over the suspicious removal of YouTube’s advanced SRV3 caption format. You don’t have to worry too much just yet—Google says this is only temporary, and it’s working on a fix for the underlying bug.&lt;br/&gt;(유튜버들은 플랫폼 관리에 대한 구글의 태도에 점점 더 좌절감을 느끼고 있습니다. 허위 정보가 다시 환영받고, 구글이 원하지 않는 곳을 제외하고는 AI 확대를 적극적으로 추진하는 상황에서, 유튜브의 고급 SRV3 자막 형식이 수상쩍게 제거된 것에 제작자들이 분노한 것은 놀라운 일이 아닙니다. 아직은 너무 걱정하지 않아도 됩니다. 구글은 이 문제가 일시적일 뿐이며, 근본적인 버그를 수정 중이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google added support for this custom subtitle format around 2018, giving creators more customization options than with traditional captions. SRV3 (also known as YTT or YouTube Timed Text) allows for custom colors, transparency, animations, fonts, and precise positioning in videos. Uploaders using this format can color-code and position captions to help separate multiple speakers, create sing-along animations, or style them to match the video.&lt;br/&gt;(구글은 2018년경 이 맞춤형 자막 형식을 지원하기 시작했으며, 이를 통해 제작자들은 기존 자막보다 더 많은 맞춤 설정 옵션을 얻었습니다. SRV3(또는 YTT, YouTube Timed Text)는 사용자 정의 색상, 투명도, 애니메이션, 글꼴 및 비디오 내 정확한 위치 지정을 허용합니다. 이 형식을 사용하는 업로더는 여러 화자를 구분하거나, 따라 부르기 애니메이션을 만들거나, 비디오와 어울리도록 스타일을 지정하기 위해 자막에 색상 코드를 적용하고 위치를 지정할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last several days, creators who’ve become accustomed to this level of control have been dismayed to see that YouTube is no longer accepting videos with this Google-created format. Many worried Google had ditched the format entirely, which could be problematic for all those previously uploaded videos.&lt;br/&gt;(지난 며칠 동안, 이 정도의 제어권에 익숙해진 제작자들은 유튜브가 더 이상 구글이 만든 이 형식의 비디오를 수락하지 않는 것을 보고 당황했습니다. 많은 이들이 구글이 형식을 완전히 포기한 것이 아닌지 걱정했으며, 이는 이전에 업로드된 모든 비디오에 문제가 될 수 있었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has now posted a brief statement and confirmed to Ars that it has not ended support for SRV3. However, all is not well. The company says it has temporarily limited the serving of SRV3 caption files because they may break playback for some users. That’s pretty vague, but it sounds like developers made a change to the platform without taking into account how it might interfere with SRV3 captions. Rather than allow those videos to be non-functional, it’s disabling most of the captions.&lt;br/&gt;(구글은 이제 간단한 성명을 게시하고 Ars에 SRV3 지원을 중단한 것이 아니라고 확인했습니다. 그러나 모든 것이 순조로운 것은 아닙니다. 회사는 SRV3 자막 파일이 일부 사용자에게 재생을 중단시킬 수 있어 해당 파일 제공을 일시적으로 제한했다고 밝혔습니다. 이는 상당히 모호한 설명이지만, 개발자들이 SRV3 자막과 어떻게 충돌할지 고려하지 않고 플랫폼에 변경을 가한 것으로 보입니다. 해당 비디오들이 작동하지 않도록 내버려두는 대신, 대부분의 자막을 비활성화하고 있는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google’s forum post says that while SRV3 is disabled, creators will not be able to upload new SRV3 captions. Videos that already have them may not show any captions until the feature is restored. However, Google notes most uploaders use other caption formats and are not affected by the playback bug.&lt;br/&gt;(구글의 포럼 게시물에 따르면, SRV3가 비활성화된 동안 제작자들은 새로운 SRV3 자막을 업로드할 수 없습니다. 이미 SRV3 자막이 있는 비디오는 기능이 복원될 때까지 자막이 표시되지 않을 수 있습니다. 그러나 구글은 대부분의 업로더가 다른 자막 형식을 사용하며 재생 버그의 영향을 받지 않는다고 언급했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Google also notes that the changes should be temporary for almost all videos. That implies some features of SRV3 may not be fully supported with whatever Google is doing on the back end. The company makes no promises about a timeline to re-enable SRV3—creators who have relied heavily on it may have to go back and re-create their captions in less capable formats or simply rely on AI-generated captions in the meantime.&lt;br/&gt;(흥미롭게도, 구글은 또한 변경 사항이 거의 모든 비디오에 대해 일시적이어야 한다고 언급했습니다. 이는 SRV3의 일부 기능이 구글이 백엔드에서 수행하는 작업과 완전히 호환되지 않을 수 있음을 시사합니다. 회사는 SRV3를 다시 활성화할 시기에 대해 어떤 약속도 하지 않았습니다. 이 기능에 크게 의존해 온 제작자들은 그동안 기능이 제한된 다른 형식으로 자막을 다시 만들어야 하거나, 단순히 AI 생성 자막에 의존해야 할 수도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether Google knew this would happen, it shouldn’t have left the community to stew about it for a week. This also suggests Google isn’t very serious about supporting its in-house CC format, which it has opted not to officially document. Creators should probably factor that into their future plans.&lt;br/&gt;(구글이 이런 일이 일어날 것을 알았든 모르든, 커뮤니티가 일주일 동안 불안에 떨게 내버려둬서는 안 됩니다. 이는 또한 구글이 공식적으로 문서화하지 않기로 선택한 자체 CC(Closed Caption) 형식 지원에 그다지 진지하지 않음을 시사합니다. 제작자들은 아마도 이를 향후 계획에 고려해야 할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/google-temporarily-disabled-youtubes-advanced-captions-without-warning/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/youtube-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:17:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Verizon starts requiring 365 days of paid service before it will unlock phones (버라이즌, 휴대폰 잠금 해제에 365일 유료 서비스 요구 시작)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-starts-requiring-365-days-of-paid-service-before-it-will-unlock-phones/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/verizon-1152x648-1752087139.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon changed prepaid brands’ policy a week after FCC waived unlocking rule.&lt;br/&gt;(FCC가 잠금 해제 규정을 면제한 지 일주일 만에 버라이즌이 선불 브랜드 정책을 변경했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon has started enforcing a 365-day lock period on phones purchased through its TracFone division, one week after the Federal Communications Commission waived a requirement that Verizon unlock handsets 60 days after they are activated on its network.&lt;br/&gt;(버라이즌은 연방통신위원회(FCC)가 버라이즌 네트워크에서 휴대폰이 활성화된 지 60일 후에 기기를 잠금 해제해야 한다는 요건을 면제한 지 일주일 만에, 트랙폰 사업부를 통해 구매한 휴대폰에 대해 365일 잠금 기간을 적용하기 시작했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon was previously required to unlock phones automatically after 60 days due to restrictions imposed on its spectrum licenses and merger conditions that helped Verizon obtain approval of its purchase of TracFone . But an update applied today to the TracFone unlocking policy said new phones will be locked for at least a year and that each customer will have to request an unlock instead of getting it automatically.&lt;br/&gt;(버라이즌은 이전에는 스펙트럼 라이선스에 부과된 제한과 트랙폰 인수를 승인받는 데 도움이 된 합병 조건으로 인해 60일 후에 휴대폰을 자동으로 잠금 해제해야 했습니다. 그러나 오늘 적용된 트랙폰 잠금 해제 정책 업데이트에 따르면, 새 휴대폰은 최소 1년 동안 잠금 상태가 유지되며, 고객은 자동 해제 대신 개별적으로 잠금 해제를 요청해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “new” TracFone policy is basically a return to the yearlong locking it imposed before Verizon bought the company in 2021. TracFone first agreed to provide unlocking in a 2015 settlement with the Obama-era FCC , which alleged that TracFone failed to comply with a commitment to unlock phones for customers enrolled in the Lifeline subsidy program. TracFone later shortened the locking period from a year to 60 days as a condition of the Verizon merger.&lt;br/&gt;(이 "새로운" 트랙폰 정책은 기본적으로 버라이즌이 2021년에 회사를 인수하기 전에 트랙폰이 시행했던 1년 잠금 정책으로의 회귀입니다. 트랙폰은 처음에 2015년 오바마 행정부 시절 FCC와의 합의에서 잠금 해제를 제공하기로 동의했는데, 당시 FCC는 트랙폰이 라이프라인 보조 프로그램에 가입한 고객을 위한 휴대폰 잠금 해제 약속을 이행하지 않았다고 주장했습니다. 트랙폰은 이후 버라이즌 합병 조건으로 잠금 기간을 1년에서 60일로 단축했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a locked phone is tied to the network of one carrier, an unlocked phone can be switched to another carrier if the device is compatible with the other carrier’s network. But the new TracFone unlocking policy is stringent, requiring customers to pay for a full year of service before they can get a phone unlocked.&lt;br/&gt;(잠긴 휴대폰은 한 통신사의 네트워크에 묶여 있는 반면, 잠금 해제된 휴대폰은 기기가 다른 통신사의 네트워크와 호환되는 경우 다른 통신사로 전환할 수 있습니다. 그러나 새로운 트랙폰 잠금 해제 정책은 엄격하여, 고객이 휴대폰 잠금을 해제하려면 1년 동안 서비스 비용을 모두 지불해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For all cellphones Activated on or after January 20, 2026, the cellphone will be unlocked upon request after 365 days of paid and active service,” the policy says. A customer who doesn’t maintain an active service plan for the whole 12 months will thus have their unlocking eligibility date delayed.&lt;br/&gt;(정책에 따르면, "2026년 1월 20일 또는 그 이후에 활성화된 모든 휴대폰은 유료 활성 서비스를 365일 이용한 후 요청 시 잠금이 해제됩니다." 전체 12개월 동안 활성 서비스 요금제를 유지하지 않는 고객은 잠금 해제 자격 날짜가 지연됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides TracFone, the change applies to prepaid brands Straight Talk, Net10 Wireless, Clearway, Total Wireless, Simple Mobile, SafeLink Wireless, and Walmart Family Mobile. Customers who bought phones before today are still eligible for unlocks after 60 days.&lt;br/&gt;(트랙폰 외에도 이 변경 사항은 선불 브랜드인 스트레이트 토크, 넷10 와이어리스, 클리어웨이, 토탈 와이어리스, 심플 모바일, 세이프링크 와이어리스, 월마트 패밀리 모바일에 적용됩니다. 오늘 이전에 휴대폰을 구매한 고객은 여전히 60일 후 잠금 해제 자격이 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As DroidLife points out , the Verizon-owned prepaid brand Visible is also requiring a year of paid service. The Visible policy updated today requires “at least 365 days of paid service” for an unlocking request. “If you stop paying for service, your progress toward the 365-day requirement pauses. It will resume once you reactivate your account and continue until you reach a total of 365 paid days of service,” the policy says.&lt;br/&gt;(DroidLife가 지적했듯이, 버라이즌이 소유한 선불 브랜드 비저블도 1년간의 유료 서비스를 요구하고 있습니다. 오늘 업데이트된 비저블 정책은 잠금 해제 요청에 "최소 365일의 유료 서비스"를 요구합니다. 정책은 "서비스 비용 지불을 중단하면 365일 요건 충족 진행이 일시 중지됩니다. 계정을 재활성화하면 진행이 재개되며, 총 365일의 유료 서비스 기간에 도달할 때까지 계속됩니다"라고 설명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unlocking policy for Verizon-branded phones has not been updated since May 2025. The policy calls for phones to be unlocked automatically after 60 days of paid service, but it will probably be changed soon because of the FCC waiver.&lt;br/&gt;(버라이즌 브랜드 휴대폰의 잠금 해제 정책은 2025년 5월 이후 업데이트되지 않았습니다. 해당 정책은 유료 서비스 60일 후 휴대폰을 자동으로 잠금 해제하도록 규정하고 있지만, FCC의 면제로 인해 곧 변경될 가능성이 높습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once updated, the primary Verizon policy will presumably match the TracFone subsidiary’s 365-day locking period, or at least require something longer than 60 days. It’s also likely to require customers to request an unlock since the FCC no longer requires Verizon to unlock phones automatically. We contacted Verizon about its plans today and will update this article if it provides a response.&lt;br/&gt;(일단 업데이트되면, 버라이즌의 주요 정책은 아마도 트랙폰 자회사의 365일 잠금 기간과 일치하거나, 최소한 60일보다는 긴 기간을 요구할 것으로 보입니다. 또한 FCC가 더 이상 버라이즌에 자동 잠금 해제를 요구하지 않기 때문에 고객이 잠금 해제를 요청하도록 할 가능성도 높습니다. 우리는 오늘 버라이즌에 향후 계획에 대해 문의했으며, 답변을 받으면 이 기사를 업데이트할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AT&amp;T’s policy allows unlocking of phones on postpaid plans after 60 days if the device has been paid in full, or after six months for phones on prepaid plans. T-Mobile’s policy allows unlocking of phones on postpaid plans after 40 days if the device has been paid in full, or after 365 days for phones on prepaid plans.&lt;br/&gt;(AT&amp;T의 정책은 기기 전액을 지불한 경우, 사후결제 요금제 휴대폰은 60일 후, 선불 요금제 휴대폰은 6개월 후 잠금 해제를 허용합니다. T-모바일의 정책은 기기 전액을 지불한 경우, 사후결제 요금제 휴대폰은 40일 후, 선불 요금제 휴대폰은 365일 후 잠금 해제를 허용합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon and FCC Chairman Brendan Carr have justified longer locking periods as a method of deterring fraud. When approving Verizon’s waiver request, the Carr FCC said the Verizon rule “required one wireless carrier to unlock their handsets well earlier than standard industry practice, thus creating an incentive for bad actors to steal those handsets for purposes of carrying out fraud and other illegal acts.”&lt;br/&gt;(버라이즌과 FCC 위원장 브렌던 카르는 긴 잠금 기간을 사기 방지 방법으로 정당화했습니다. 버라이즌의 면제 요청을 승인하면서, 카르 위원장이 이끄는 FCC는 버라이즌 규정이 "한 무선 통신사에게 업계 표준 관행보다 훨씬 이른 시점에 휴대폰 잠금을 해제하도록 요구함으로써, 불량 행위자들이 사기 및 기타 불법 행위를 목적으로 해당 휴대폰을 훔치도록 유인했다"고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer advocacy groups disputed the argument, telling the FCC that “Verizon offers no specific evidence that a longer lock period would have prevented the fraudulent acquisition of the devices it identifies,” and that Verizon is capable of detecting and responding to fraud within 60 days of a phone’s activation. Consumers and small carriers will be hurt by the decision, the groups told the FCC , saying that automatic unlocking “facilitates the resale and reuse of mobile devices, reduces e-waste, and enables low-cost carriers and MVNOs to compete on a more level playing field.”&lt;br/&gt;(소비자 옹호 단체들은 이 주장에 이의를 제기하며 FCC에 "버라이즌은 더 긴 잠금 기간이 회사가 확인한 기기의 사기성 취득을 막았을 것이라는 구체적인 증거를 제시하지 않는다"고 말했으며, 버라이즌은 휴대폰 활성화 후 60일 이내에 사기를 탐지하고 대응할 능력이 있다고 주장했습니다. 이 단체들은 FCC에 이 결정이 소비자와 소규모 통신사에게 피해를 줄 것이라고 말하며, 자동 잠금 해제가 "모바일 기기의 재판매와 재사용을 촉진하고, 전자 폐기물을 줄이며, 저비용 통신사와 MVNO가 보다 평등한 경쟁 환경에서 경쟁할 수 있도록 한다"고 덧붙였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Biden-era FCC’s leadership criticized yearlong locking periods and proposed a 60-day unlocking requirement for all carriers, the Trump FCC appears likely to write a new industry-wide standard that would be welcomed by large mobile carriers. The FCC rejected a request to limit Verizon’s locking period to 180 days, and said the Verizon waiver will stay in effect until the agency “decides on an appropriate industry-wide approach for the unlocking of handsets.”&lt;br/&gt;(바이든 행정부 시절 FCC 지도부는 1년 잠금 기간을 비판하고 모든 통신사에 대해 60일 잠금 해제 요건을 제안했지만, 트럼프 행정부 시절 FCC는 대형 이동통신사들이 환영할 업계 전반의 새로운 표준을 마련할 것으로 보입니다. FCC는 버라이즌의 잠금 기간을 180일로 제한하라는 요청을 거부했으며, 버라이즌에 대한 면제는 위원회가 "휴대폰 잠금 해제에 대한 적절한 업계 전반의 접근 방식을 결정할 때까지" 효력을 유지할 것이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/verizon-starts-requiring-365-days-of-paid-service-before-it-will-unlock-phones/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/verizon-1152x648-1752087139.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:35:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zuck stuck on Trump’s bad side: FTC appeals loss in Meta monopoly case (주크, 트럼프의 적대 세력에 갇히다: FTC, 메타 독점 소송 패소 항소)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/zuck-stuck-on-trumps-bad-side-ftc-appeals-loss-in-meta-monopoly-case/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/zuck-the-monopolist-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FTC will appeal ruling that found Meta has no monopoly in social networking.&lt;br/&gt;(FTC는 메타가 소셜 네트워킹에서 독점을 갖지 않았다는 판결에 항소할 예정입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still feeling uneasy about Meta’s acquisition of Instagram in 2012 and WhatsApp in 2014, the Federal Trade Commission will be appealing a November ruling that cleared Meta of allegations that it holds an illegal monopoly in a market dubbed “personal social networking.”&lt;br/&gt;(2012년 인스타그램 인수와 2014년 왓츠앱 인수에 대한 불안감이 여전한 연방거래위원회(FTC)는 지난 11월 '개인 소셜 네트워킹' 시장에서 메타가 불법 독점을 유지했다는 혐의를 무죄로 판결한 결정에 항소할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FTC hopes the US Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia will agree that “robust evidence at trial” showed that Meta’s acquisitions were improper. In the initial trial, the FTC sought a breakup of Meta’s apps, with Meta risking forced divestments of Instagram or WhatsApp.&lt;br/&gt;(FTC는 컬럼비아 특별구 연방항소법원이 메타의 인수가 부적절했다는 것을 보여주는 "강력한 재판 증거"에 동의하기를 바랍니다. 초기 재판에서 FTC는 메타 앱의 분리를 요구했으며, 메타는 인스타그램이나 왓츠앱의 강제 매각 위험에 처했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a press release Tuesday, the FTC confirmed that it “continues to allege” that “for over a decade Meta has illegally maintained a monopoly in personal social networking services through anticompetitive conduct—by buying the significant competitive threats it identified in Instagram and WhatsApp.”&lt;br/&gt;(화요일 보도자료에서 FTC는 "10년 이상 메타가 인스타그램과 왓츠앱에서 확인된 중요한 경쟁 위협을 인수함으로써 반경쟁적 행위를 통해 개인 소셜 네트워킹 서비스에서 불법적으로 독점을 유지해 왔다"고 "계속 주장한다"고 확인했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to press, FTC spokesperson Joe Simonson pointed out that the case against Meta originated during Donald Trump’s prior term, Reuters reported . Back then, Trump was frustrated with Facebook, claiming the company and its CEO, Mark Zuckerberg, were “anti-Trump” in 2017, the BBC reported . His frustrations only grew when Meta banned his Facebook and Instagram accounts in 2021.&lt;br/&gt;(FTC 대변인 조 시몬슨은 기자들과의 인터뷰에서 메타에 대한 소송이 도널드 트럼프의 이전 임기 동안 시작되었다고 지적했습니다. 로이터가 보도했습니다. 당시 트럼프는 페이스북에 불만을 품고 2017년 회사와 CEO 마크 주커버그가 "반트럼프 성향"이라고 주장했습니다. BBC가 보도했습니다. 그의 불만은 2021년 메타가 그의 페이스북과 인스타그램 계정을 차단했을 때 더욱 커졌습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahead of Trump’s second term, Zuckerberg has attempted to improve relations with Trump, donating $1 million to Trump’s inauguration fund in a move the BBC reported was intended to “repair his and his firm’s relationship with Trump.” Last January, Meta also paid Trump $25 million to settle lawsuits over his Facebook and Instagram suspensions, NPR reported .&lt;br/&gt;(트럼프의 두 번째 임기를 앞두고, 주커버그는 트럼프와의 관계 개선을 시도했으며, 트럼프 취임 기금에 100만 달러를 기부했습니다. BBC는 이 조치가 "그와 그의 회사와 트럼프의 관계를 수리하기 위한 것"이라고 보도했습니다. 지난 1월, 메타는 또한 트럼프의 페이스북과 인스타그램 정지 관련 소송을 해결하기 위해 트럼프에게 2500만 달러를 지불했습니다. NPR이 보도했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these moves have seemingly not affected the FTC’s resolve to undo Meta’s alleged monopoly. On Tuesday, Simonson said the Meta crackdown remained a priority because the agency believes that “Meta violated our antitrust laws when it acquired Instagram and WhatsApp,” and “consequently, American consumers have suffered from Meta’s monopoly.”&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 이러한 움직임은 메타의 주장된 독점을 해체하려는 FTC의 결의에 영향을 미치지 않은 것으로 보입니다. 화요일 시몬슨은 메타 단속이 여전히 우선 순위라고 말했는데, 이는 기관이 "메타가 인스타그램과 왓츠앱을 인수할 때 독점 금지법을 위반했다"고 믿고 있으며, "결과적으로 미국 소비자들이 메타의 독점으로 고통받고 있다"고 생각하기 때문입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Meta, the renewed fight comes at a time when most tech companies are walking tightropes to avoid any possible retaliation from Trump, not just social platforms. After defeating the FTC last fall, Meta’s chief legal officer, Jennifer Newstead, didn’t dunk on the FTC but coolly celebrated the ruling for recognizing that “Meta faces fierce competition.” In the same breath, Newstead also seemed to want to take the opportunity to remind the Trump administration that Meta was a friend.&lt;br/&gt;(메타에게 이 재개된 싸움은 대부분의 기술 회사들이 소셜 플랫폼뿐만 아니라 트럼프로부터의 가능한 보복을 피하기 위해 줄타기를 하고 있는 시기에 찾아왔습니다. 지난 가을 FTC를 상대로 승리한 후, 메타의 최고 법무 책임자 제니퍼 뉴스테드는 FTC를 비난하지 않고 "메타가 치열한 경쟁에 직면하고 있다"는 점을 인정한 판결을 냉정하게 축하했습니다. 같은 맥락에서 뉴스테드는 또한 트럼프 행정부에게 메타가 친구라는 점을 상기시키는 기회를 삼고 싶어 하는 듯했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our products are beneficial for people and businesses and exemplify American innovation and economic growth,” Newstead said. “We look forward to continuing to partner with the Administration and to invest in America.”&lt;br/&gt;("우리의 제품은 사람들과 비즈니스에 유익하며 미국 혁신과 경제 성장의 본보기입니다."라고 뉴스테드는 말했습니다. "우리는 행정부와의 협력을 지속하고 미국에 투자하기를 기대합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, this week, Meta has offered a rather neutral response to the FTC’s announcement. Asked for comment on the FTC’s decision to appeal, Meta’s spokesperson simply told Ars that James Boasberg, the US district judge who sided with Meta, got it right the first time, then repeated one of Trump’s favorite refrains from tech companies.&lt;br/&gt;(마찬가지로 이번 주 메타는 FTC의 발표에 대해 상당히 중립적인 반응을 보였습니다. FTC의 항소 결정에 대한 논평을 요청받자, 메타 대변인은 아스테크니카에 단순히 메타 편을 든 미국 지방 법원 판사 제임스 보즈버그가 처음부터 옳았다고 말한 후, 트럼프가 기술 회사들에게 자주 요구하는 말 중 하나를 반복했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The District Court’s decision to reject the FTC’s arguments is correct and recognizes the fierce competition we face,” Meta’s spokesperson said. “We will remain focused on innovating and investing in America.”&lt;br/&gt;("지방 법원이 FTC의 주장을 기각한 결정은 정확하며 우리가 직면한 치열한 경쟁을 인정합니다."라고 메타 대변인은 말했습니다. "우리는 혁신과 미국 투자에 집중할 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political tensions have remained at the center of the case, perhaps peaking after Boasberg’s ruling.&lt;br/&gt;(정치적 긴장은 이 소송의 중심에 남아 있었으며, 아마도 보즈버그 판결 이후 정점에 달했을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, Simonson criticized Boasberg, telling CNBC that “the deck was always stacked against us with Judge Boasberg, who is currently facing articles of impeachment.”&lt;br/&gt;(11월, 시몬슨은 보즈버그를 비판하며 CNBC에 "보즈버그 판사와의 판에서는 항상 우리에게 불리하게 짜여 있었다"고 말했습니다. 그는 현재 탄핵 조항에 직면해 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That push to impeach Boasberg came from Republican lawmaker Brandon Gill, who alleged the judge was abusing his power to censor conservatives, but no actions have been taken since the proposed resolution was submitted to a House committee that month. Republicans, including Trump’s attorney general Pam Bondi , have complained that Boasberg is a rogue partisan judge, but Boasberg so far has withstood their attacks while continuing to settle cases. Trump’s Truth Social tirades against the judge required a long fact-checking piece from PBS.&lt;br/&gt;(보즈버그 탄핵 추진은 공화당 의원 브랜든 길에서 비롯되었는데, 그는 판사가 보수 세력을 검열하기 위해 권력을 남용한다고 주장했지만, 해당 결의안이 그달 하원 위원회에 제출된 이후 아무런 조치도 취해지지 않았습니다. 트럼프의 법무장관 팸 본디를 포함한 공화당원들은 보즈버그가 불량한 당파적 판사라고 불평했지만, 보즈버그는 지금까지 그들의 공격을 견디며 소송을 계속 해결해 왔습니다. 트럼프의 트루스 소셜에서 판사를 향한 맹비난은 PBS의 긴 팩트체크 기사를 필요로 했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Meta case itself may be hard to win even with a judge that Republicans favor. Last year, the FTC had tried to argue that Meta faced no real competition in the personal social networking market, with only two rivals to speak of, Snapchat and an app called MeWe. But for social media users, Instagram and TikTok are interchangeable, Meta successfully argued, and that makes TikTok as much a rival as Snapchat, Boasberg agreed.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 메타 소송 자체는 공화당이 선호하는 판사가 있어도 이기기 어려울 수 있습니다. 작년에 FTC는 메타가 개인 소셜 네트워킹 시장에서 실제 경쟁이 없으며, 스냅챗과 MeWe라는 앱 두 가지만이 경쟁자라고 주장하려 했습니다. 그러나 소셜 미디어 사용자들에게 인스타그램과 틱톡은 상호 교환 가능하며, 이는 틱톡을 스냅챗만큼의 경쟁자로 만든다고 메타는 성공적으로 주장했고, 보즈버그는 이에 동의했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Boasberg was not sold on the FTC’s argument that Meta was allegedly abusing its monopoly power and harming consumers by degrading the quality of the app while increasing ad loads. Rather, he agreed with Meta that the company had added many features “continuously” improving its apps.&lt;br/&gt;(또한, 보즈버그는 메타가 독점력을 남용하고 광고 부하를 증가시키면서 앱의 품질을 저하시켜 소비자를 해친다는 FTC의 주장에 설득되지 않았습니다. 오히려 그는 메타가 앱을 "지속적으로" 개선하는 많은 기능을 추가했다는 메타의 주장에 동의했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, social media has changed so much since the days of Facebook competing for user engagement with Instagram that Boasberg emphasized that “the Court finds it impossible to believe that consumers would prefer the versions of Instagram and Facebook that existed a decade ago to the versions that exist today.”&lt;br/&gt;(더 나아가, 소셜 미디어는 페이스북이 인스타그램과 사용자 참여를 놓고 경쟁하던 시절부터 너무 많이 변화했기 때문에, 보즈버그는 "법원은 소비자들이 10년 전 존재했던 인스타그램과 페이스북 버전을 오늘날 존재하는 버전보다 선호할 것이라고 믿기 어렵다"고 강조했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the FTC revives the case, a new judge will weigh Meta’s arguments, the general thrust of which is that social networking as it was known in the early days of Facebook is dead, making the FTC’s case moot.&lt;br/&gt;(FTC가 소송을 재개함에 따라, 새로운 판사는 메타의 주장을 심사할 것입니다. 그 주장의 주요 골자는 페이스북 초기 시절 알려졌던 소셜 네트워킹은 사라졌으며, 이로 인해 FTC의 소송은 무의미하다는 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear whether a different judge will see Meta as a monopolist or if Boasberg was right to conclude that the days of grouping apps into “separate markets of social networking and social media” are over.&lt;br/&gt;(다른 판사가 메타를 독점자로 볼지, 아니면 보즈버그가 앱을 '소셜 네트워킹과 소셜 미디어의 별도 시장'으로 분류하던 시대가 끝났다고 결론지은 것이 옳았는지는 불분명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/zuck-stuck-on-trumps-bad-side-ftc-appeals-loss-in-meta-monopoly-case/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/zuck-the-monopolist-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:22:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Webb reveals a planetary nebula with phenomenal clarity, and it is spectacular (웹이 현상적인 선명도로 행성상 성운을 드러내다, 그리고 그것은 장관이다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/webb-has-given-us-with-a-stunning-new-view-of-a-well-known-planetary-nebula/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/STScI-01KCMAMZ8ZSMRTR9KKD8Y6EMRJ-2000x1440.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colors show the star’s final breath transforming into the raw ingredients for new worlds.&lt;br/&gt;(색깔들은 별의 마지막 숨결이 새로운 세계를 위한 원료로 변모하는 모습을 보여준다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Helix Nebula is one of the most well-known and commonly photographed planetary nebulae because it resembles the “ Eye of Sauron .” It is also one of the closest bright nebulae to Earth, located approximately 655 light-years from our Solar System.&lt;br/&gt;(헬릭스 성운은 "사우론의 눈"을 닮았기 때문에 가장 잘 알려지고 흔히 촬영되는 행성상 성운 중 하나이다. 또한 태양계로부터 약 655광년 떨어져 있어 지구에서 가장 가까운 밝은 성운 중 하나이기도 하다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may not know what this particular nebula looks like when reading its name, but the Hubble Space Telescope has taken some iconic images of it over the years. And almost certainly, you’ll recognize a photograph of the Helix Nebula, shown below.&lt;br/&gt;(이 특정 성운의 이름을 읽을 때 그것이 어떻게 생겼는지 모를 수도 있지만, 허블 우주 망원경은 수년간 이 성운의 몇 가지 상징적인 이미지를 촬영해왔다. 그리고 거의 확실하게, 아래에 보이는 헬릭스 성운의 사진을 알아볼 수 있을 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many objects in astronomy, planetary nebulae have a confusing name, since they are formed not by planets but by stars like our own Sun, though a little larger. Near the end of their lives, these stars shed large amounts of gas in an expanding shell that, however briefly in cosmological time, put on a grand show.&lt;br/&gt;(천문학의 많은 대상들처럼, 행성상 성운은 혼란스러운 이름을 가지고 있다. 왜냐하면 그것들은 행성에 의해 형성되는 것이 아니라 우리 태양과 비슷하지만 약간 더 큰 별들에 의해 형성되기 때문이다. 생명의 끝에 가까워지면, 이러한 별들은 팽창하는 껍질 형태로 대량의 가스를 방출하는데, 이는 우주론적 시간에서는 아주 짧지만 장관을 연출한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the James Webb Space Telescope has turned its sights on the Helix Nebula, and, oh my, does it have a story to tell. NASA released the new images of the nebula on Tuesday.&lt;br/&gt;(이제 제임스 웹 우주 망원경이 헬릭스 성운을 조사했고, 오 마이, 이야기할 것이 많다. NASA는 화요일에 이 성운의 새로운 이미지를 공개했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this image, there are vibrant pillars of gas along the inner region of the nebula’s expanding shell of gas. According to the space agency, this is what we’re seeing:&lt;br/&gt;(이 이미지에는 성운의 팽창하는 가스 껍질 내부 영역을 따라 생동감 넘치는 가스 기둥들이 있다. 우주 기관에 따르면, 이것이 우리가 보고 있는 것이다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blazing white dwarf, the leftover core of the dying star, lies right at the heart of the nebula, out of the frame of the Webb image. Its intense radiation lights up the surrounding gas, creating a rainbow of features: hot ionized gas closest to the white dwarf, cooler molecular hydrogen farther out, and protective pockets where more complex molecules can begin to form within dust clouds. This interaction is vital, as it’s the raw material from which new planets may one day form in other star systems.&lt;br/&gt;(타오르는 백색 왜성, 죽어가는 별의 남은 핵이 성운의 정확히 중심에 자리 잡고 있지만, 웹 이미지의 프레임 밖에 있다. 그 강렬한 복사선은 주변 가스를 밝히며 다양한 특징들을 만들어낸다: 백색 왜성에 가장 가까운 뜨거운 이온화된 가스, 더 멀리 떨어진 더 차가운 분자 수소, 그리고 먼지 구름 속에서 더 복잡한 분자들이 형성되기 시작할 수 있는 보호적인 주머니들. 이 상호작용은 매우 중요하다. 왜냐하면 이것이 다른 항성계에서 언젠가 새로운 행성들이 형성될 수 있는 원료가 되기 때문이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Webb’s image of the Helix Nebula, color represents the temperature and chemistry. A touch of a blue hue marks the hottest gas in this field, energized by intense ultraviolet light from the white dwarf. Farther out, the gas cools into the yellow regions where hydrogen atoms join into molecules. At the outer edges, the reddish tones trace the coolest material, where gas begins to thin and dust can take shape. Together, the colors show the star’s final breath transforming into the raw ingredients for new worlds, adding to the wealth of knowledge gained from Webb about the origin of planets.&lt;br/&gt;(웹의 헬릭스 성운 이미지에서 색깔은 온도와 화학적 구성을 나타낸다. 약간의 푸른 색조는 이 영역에서 가장 뜨거운 가스를 표시하는데, 백색 왜성의 강한 자외선에 의해 에너지를 받는다. 더 멀리 나가면, 가스는 수소 원자들이 분자로 결합하는 노란색 영역으로 식는다. 가장자리에서는 붉은색 톤이 가장 차가운 물질을 따라가며, 가스가 얇아지기 시작하고 먼지가 형성될 수 있는 곳이다. 종합하면, 색깔들은 별의 마지막 숨결이 새로운 세계를 위한 원료로 변모하는 모습을 보여주며, 웹으로부터 얻은 행성 기원에 대한 지식의 풍부함을 더한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, in a word, phenomenal.&lt;br/&gt;(한마디로, 현상적이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/webb-has-given-us-with-a-stunning-new-view-of-a-well-known-planetary-nebula/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/STScI-01KCMAMZ8ZSMRTR9KKD8Y6EMRJ-2000x1440.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:33:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>