<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:11:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How to get Doom running on a pair of earbuds</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/how-to-get-doom-running-on-a-pair-of-earbuds/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/PineBuds-Pro-4-1152x648-1769443386.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No display? No problem for the UART-to-web-server “Doombuds” project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, hackers and modders at large havemade it their missionto port classic first-person shooterDoomtopracticallyanythingwitha display. Recently, though, coderArin Sarkisanhas taken the “Can it RunDoom?” idea in an unlikely direction: wireless earbuds that aren’t designed to output graphics at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, this hack doesn’t apply to any generic set of earbuds.The “Doombuds” projectis designed specifically for thePineBuds Pro, which are unique in featuringcompletely open source firmwareanda community-maintained SDK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means Sarkisan was able tocode up a JavaScript interfacethat uses the earbuds’UART contact padsto senda heavily compressed MJPEG video streamto a web server (via a serial server). The 2.4 MB/s data stream from the UART connection can put out about 22 to 27 frames per second in this format, which is more than enough for a CPU that can only run the game at a maximum of 18 fps anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Squeezing the entirety ofDoomonto modern earbuds wasn’t an easy task, either. The 4.2MB of game data won’t quite fit on the PineBuds’ 4MB of flash memory, for instance. That means the project needed to usea 1.7MB “squashware” build ofDoom, which eliminates some animation frames and shortens some music tracks to make the game even more portable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earbuds also have just under 1MB of RAM, requiring the coding ofa new version of the gamethat optimizes away many of the bits that usually fill up a full 4MB of RAM in the standard game. “Pre-generating lookup tables, making variables const, reading const variables from flash, disabling DOOM’s caching system, removing unneeded variables… it all adds up,” Sarkisan writes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those without their own PineBuds to test this wild idea, Sarkisan has set upan interactive Twitch streamthat players can queue up to control for 45-second sessionsvia doombuds.com. It’s a great little break-time diversion, especially for people ready to marvel that a set of $70 earbuds can now run a game that required a $1,000-plus computer tower a few decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/how-to-get-doom-running-on-a-pair-of-earbuds/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:13:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Data center power outage took out TikTok first weekend under US ownership</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-glitches-caused-by-data-center-power-outage-us-joint-venture-says/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257704765-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US TikTok users experienced a wide range of errors, sparking conspiracies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok has been glitching for US users since Sunday, andTikTok’s new US ownershave finally confirmed the cause: a power outage at a US data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Since yesterday we’ve been working to restore our services following a power outage at a US data center impacting TikTok and other apps we operate,” the TikTok USDS Joint Venture posted on X on Monday morning. “We’re working with our data center partner to stabilize our service. We’re sorry for this disruption and hope to resolve it soon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DownDetectorreporttracking outages showed problems began early Sunday morning, with the majority of problems seemingly resolved by early Monday. However, The Vergereportedthat some US users continue to experience issues, including issues logging in, long delays uploading videos, generic content flooding For You pages, problems accessing comments, and other issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that the TikTok USDS Joint Venture is still working to resolve problems connected to the power outage. But their decision to remain silent while the app got buggy during the first weekend under the control of right-wing US owners hand-picked by Donald Trump sparked conspiracy theories on social media that the app had begun censoring left-leaning users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the app comes back online, users have also taken note that TikTok is collecting more of their data under US control. As Wiredreported, TikTok asked US users to agree to a new terms of service and privacy policy, which allows TikTok to potentially collect “more detailed information about its users, including precise location data.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Before this update, the app did not collect the precise, GPS-derived location data of US users,” Wired reported. “Now, if you give TikTok permission to use your phone’s location services, then the app may collect granular information about your exact whereabouts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New policies also pushed users to agree to share all their AI interactions, which allows TikTok to store their metadata and trace AI inputs back to specific accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already seeming more invasive and less reliable, for TikTok users, questions likely remain how much their favorite app might change under new ownership, as the TikTok USDS Joint Venture prepares to retrain the app’s algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has said that hewants to see the app become “100 percent MAGA,”prompting fears that “For You” pages might soon be flooded with right-wing content or that leftist content like anti-ICE criticism might be suppressed. And The Informationreportedin July that transferring millions of users over to the US-trained app is expected to cause more “technical issues.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-glitches-caused-by-data-center-power-outage-us-joint-venture-says/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:23:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The brothers meet Yoshi in Super Mario Galaxy Movie trailer</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/yoshi-joins-the-fun-in-latest-super-mario-galaxy-movie-trailer/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/mario2-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toad: “So some dinosaur just shows up and he’s now part of the group. Cool.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Universal Pictures and Illumination dropped a new trailer for the upcomingSuper Mario Galaxy Movie,and gaming fans will no doubt be delighted at the news that Yoshi, the little green dinosaur, features prominently, along with plenty of other Easter eggs for sharp-eyed fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspreviously reported, the first attempt at a Super Mario movie adaptation in 1993 was notoriously adismal failure, although it still has its ’90s-nostalgic fans. But 2023’sSuper Mario Bros. Moviewon over gaming fans who were skeptical about another adaptation—includingArs Senior Gaming Editor Kyle Orland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2023 film reintroduced Mario and Luigi, two tight-knit but struggling Brooklyn plumbers who got separated when they unexpectedly fell into the fantastical Mushroom Kingdom. Mario sought Princess Peach’s help to rescue his brother from the evil clutches of Bowser, ruler of the Dark Lands, who was keen to marry Peach and threatened to destroy the Mushroom Kingdom with a Super Star if she refused him. So Peach led Mario on a quest to recruit allies and stop Bowser for good. They succeeded, shrinking Bowser and imprisoning him in a jar. Mario and Luigi moved to the Mushroom Kingdom and continued their plumbing work there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main voice cast is returning for the sequel: Chris Pratt as Mario, Charlie Day as Luigi, Anya Taylor-Joy as Princess Peach, Jack Black as Bowser, Keegan-Michael Key as the anthropomorphic mushroom Toad, and Kevin Michael Richardson as Bowser’s advisor and informant Kamek. We’re also getting two new cast members: Brie Larson as Princess Rosalina, protector of the cosmos and the Lumas, and Benny Safdie as Bowser, Jr., Bowser’s son and heir to the throne. Directors Aaron Horvath and Michael Jelenic are also back, as is screenwriter Matthew Fogel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details on the actual plot are fuzzy, but the first trailer (released last November) focused on Bowser and Bowser Jr., who seemed intent on freeing his dad and (one assumes) taking revenge on the brothers. This latest trailer shows Mario and Luigi at the scene of a “troubled” pipe in the desert of San Kingdom, populated by the sombrero-wearing Tostarenans. When they clear away some rubble covering an opening, who should be lurking inside but Yoshi—not a monster to hit with fire flowers, but a friendly green dinosaur. Yoshi is keen to join the team, although Toad seems less than impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Super Mario Galaxy Moviehits theaters on April 1, 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/yoshi-joins-the-fun-in-latest-super-mario-galaxy-movie-trailer/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:05:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to encrypt your PC’s disk without giving the keys to Microsoft</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/how-to-encrypt-your-pcs-disk-without-giving-the-keys-to-microsoft/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/win11-pc-2023-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing recovery keys with Microsoft allows the company to unlock your disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2025, Forbesreports, investigators at the FBI served Microsoft with a warrant seeking the BitLocker encryption recovery keys for several laptops it believed held evidence of fraud in Guam’s COVID-19 unemployment assistance program. And Microsoft complied with the FBI’s request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BitLocker is the name of the full-disk encryption technology that has been part of Windows for nearly two decades. Though initially only available to owners of the Pro editions of Windows who turned it on manually,during the Windows 8 eraMicrosoft began using BitLocker to encrypt local disks automatically for all Windows 11 Home and Pro PCs that signed in with a Microsoft account. Using BitLocker in this way also uploads a recovery key for your device to Microsoft’s servers—this makes it possible to unlock your disk so you don’t lose data if something goes wrong with your system, or if you install a CPU upgrade or some other hardware change that breaks BitLocker. But it also (apparently) makes it possible for Microsoft to unlock your disk, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Microsoft rep said that the company handled “around 20” similar BitLocker recovery key requests from government authorities per year, and that these requests often fail because users haven’t stored their recovery keys on Microsoft’s servers. Microsoft and other tech companies have generallyrefused requeststo install universal encryption backdoors for law enforcement purposes, and some companies (like Apple)claimto store device encryption keys using another layer of encryption that renders the keys inaccessible to the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But storing your device’s recovery keys in someone else’s cloud can still represent a privacy and security risk, especially at a time when the US government has become more interested in targetingjournalistsand the Trump administration’s political opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to encrypt your Windows PC’s disk but you don’t want to store your recovery key with Microsoft, you do have options. We’ll recap the requirements, as well as the steps you’ll need to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin: Disk encryption is one of the handful of differences between the Home and Pro versions of Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the Home and Pro versions of Windows support disk encryption, but only the Pro versions give users full control over the process. The Home version of Windows only supports disk encryption when logged in with a Microsoft account and will only offer to store your encryption key on Microsoft’s servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the full version of BitLocker and back up your own recovery key, you’ll need to upgrade to the Pro version of Windows. Microsoft offers its own first-party upgrade optionthrough the Microsoft Store for a one-time fee of $99, but it’s also possible to bring your own product key and upgrade yourself. ThisMacworld-affiliated listingfrom StackCommerce claims to be an official Microsoft partner and is offering a Windows 11 Pro key for just $10, though your mileage with third-party key resellers may vary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However you get it, once you have a valid key, openSettings, thenSystem, thenActivation, clickupgrade your edition of Windows, clickchange product key, and then enter your Windows 11 Pro key (Windows 10 Pro keys should also work, if you already have one). Luckily, changing Windows editions doesn’t require anything more disruptive than a system restart. You won’t need to reinstall Windows, and you shouldn’t lose any of your installed apps or data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once you’ve upgraded a PC to Windows 11 Pro once, you should be able to reinstall and activate Windows 11 Pro on that system again any time you want without having to re-enter your product key. Keep the product key stored somewhere, though, just in case you do need to use it for a reinstall, or if you ever need to re-activate Windows after a hardware upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got Windows 11 Pro set up, it’s time to either encrypt or re-encrypt your disk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve signed in with a Microsoft account, your disk is likely already encrypted, and the key is likely already stored on Microsoft’s servers. If this is the case, this process will actually involve fully unencrypting and re-encrypting your drive, which can take an hour or two depending on the speed of your PC and the size of your drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to check your current encryption status and the steps to follow if you’ve already got a key backed up with Microsoft:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your disk is re-encrypted, your PC should work just as it did before. The actual encryption technology hasn’t changed at all—all we’ve done is change where the recovery key is saved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does put the burden on the user if and when it comes time to use your recovery key. You’ll have to remember where you put it and not get it mixed up with any other recovery keys you’ve stored for other PCs or old Windows installations. But for anyone concerned about Microsoft giving their device’s encryption keys to the government or anyone else with a valid subpoena, the extra hassle may be worth it in exchange for the added privacy and peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/how-to-encrypt-your-pcs-disk-without-giving-the-keys-to-microsoft/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:29:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Wildly irresponsible”: DOT’s use of AI to draft safety rules sparks concerns</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/wildly-irresponsible-dots-use-of-ai-to-draft-safety-rules-sparks-concerns/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1438737819-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staffers warn DOT’s use of Gemini to draft rules could cause injuries and deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Transportation apparently thinks it’s a good idea to use artificial intelligence to draft rules impacting the safety of airplanes, cars, and pipelines, a ProPublica investigationrevealedMonday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be a problem if DOT becomes the first agency to use AI to draft rules, ProPublica pointed out, since AI is known to confidently get things wrong and hallucinate fabricated information. Staffers fear that any failure to catch AI errors could result in flawed laws, leading to lawsuits, injuries, or even deaths in the transportation system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the DOT’s top lawyer, Gregory Zerzan, isn’t worried about that, December meeting notes revealed, because the point isn’t for AI to be perfect. It’s for AI to help speed up the rulemaking process, so that rules that take weeks or months to draft can instead be written within 30 days. According to Zerzan, DOT’s preferred tool, Google Gemini, can draft rules in under 30 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t need the perfect rule on XYZ,” Zerzan told DOT staffers at the meeting. “We don’t even need a very good rule on XYZ. We want good enough.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ProPublica spoke to experts and granted six DOT staffers anonymity to discuss their concerns about DOT’s use of Google Gemini to draft rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts who monitor AI use in government told ProPublica that DOT could save time using Gemini as a research assistant “with plenty of supervision and transparency.” For example, at a presentation, DOT staffers were told that “most of what goes into the preambles of DOT regulatory documents is just ‘word salad,’” and “Gemini can do word salad.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, staffers told ProPublica they felt “deeply skeptical” that Gemini was up to the task. They emphasized that DOT rulemaking is “intricate work” requiring sometimes decades of “expertise in the subject at hand as well as in existing statutes, regulations, and case law.” Likely unsettling staffers further, ProPublica noted that a demonstration of Gemini’s rule-drafting produced a document missing key text, which a staffer would then have to fill in. Additionally, the DOT’s move comes after a year of AI hallucinations scrambling courts, withmany lawyers finedand evenjudges admitting they can be fooledby fabricated information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any errors in the rules could have serious consequences. These rules “touch virtually every facet of transportation safety,” keeping “airplanes in the sky,” preventing “gas pipelines from exploding,” and stopping “freight trains carrying toxic chemicals from skidding off the rails,” ProPublica reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems wildly irresponsible,” one staffer said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite staffers’ concerns, DOT appears to be racing forward with the plan, ProPublica reported. The department has already used Gemini to draft a “still-unpublished Federal Aviation Administration rule, according to a DOT staffer briefed on the matter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump has urged federal agencies to adopt AI at a rapid pace, but nowhere in his orders has the president pushed for AI to draft laws, ProPublica noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Trump is “very excited” about the DOT initiative, Zerzan told staffers at the meeting, suggesting that Trump sees DOT as the “point of the spear” and expects other agencies to follow its lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At DOT, Trump likely hopes to see many rules quickly updated to modernize airways and roadways. In areporthighlighting the Office of Science and Technology Policy’s biggest “wins” in 2025, the White House credited DOT with “replacing decades-old rules with flexible, innovation-friendly frameworks,” including fast-tracking rules to allow for more automated vehicles on the roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, DOT expects that Gemini can be relied on to “handle 80 to 90 percent of the work of writing regulations,” ProPublica reported. Eventually all federal workers who rely on AI tools like Gemini to draft rules “would fall back into merely an oversight role, monitoring ‘AI-to-AI interactions,’” ProPublica reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google did not respond to Ars’ request to comment on this use case for Gemini, which could spread across government under Trump’s direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the tech giant posted ablogon Monday, pitching Gemini for government more broadly, promising federal workers that AI would help with “creative problem-solving to the most critical aspects of their work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has been competing with AI rivals for government contracts,undercuttingOpenAI and Anthropic’s $1 deals by offering a year of access to Gemini for $0.47.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DOT contract seems important to Google. In a Decemberblog, the company celebrated that DOT was “the first cabinet-level agency to fully transition its workforce away from legacy providers to Google Workspace with Gemini.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, Google suggested this move would help DOT “ensure the United States has the safest, most efficient, and modern transportation system in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately, Google encouraged other federal leaders to launch their own efforts using Gemini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are committed to supporting the DOT’s digital transformation and stand ready to help other federal leaders across the government adopt this blueprint for their own mission successes,” Google’s blog said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOT did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/wildly-irresponsible-dots-use-of-ai-to-draft-safety-rules-sparks-concerns/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:13:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple’s AirTag 2 is easier to find thanks to new chip</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-introduces-new-airtag-with-better-range-and-a-louder-speaker/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/AirTag-2-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first major upgrade since Apple introduced AirTags five years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple is introducing a new version of its AirTag tracking device—simply dubbed “the new AirTag"—and claims it offers substantial improvements thanks to a new Bluetooth chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original AirTag came out five years ago now, and it became popular in a variety of contexts. There were some problems, though—there was real concern about unwanted tracking and stalking with the devices, based on real stories of it being used for that. The company gradually introduced new features and protections against that, getting it to a much better place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version is focused on making the device more effective in general. Thanks to the inclusion of the second-generation Ultra Wideband chip (the same one found in other recently released Apple devices like the iPhone 17), Apple says the new AirTag can work with the Precision Finding feature in the Find My app to direct users to the AirTag (and whatever lost item it’s stored with or attached to) from up to 50 percent farther away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the speaker in the AirTag is now 50 percent louder, Apple says. These two things together address some user complaints that, as useful as an AirTag can be in ideal circumstances, sometimes it is frustrating trying to get things just right to find something. It won’t eliminate all edge cases, but it ought to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple used this announcement to also talk up some of the features of the AirTag, including the encryption that it says prevents anyone but the AirTag owner from using it, and an arrangement with airlines where users can temporarily give airlines the ability to use Apple’s network to find a specific AirTag to locate lost luggage and the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, the new AirTag doesn’t introduce any major new features that aren’t already offered in the previous generation—this is just an update to the device’s accuracy, volume, and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price remains unchanged, at $29 for one AirTag or $99 for a pack of four. The new model is available for order on Apple’s website now and will hit physical stores later this week.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-introduces-new-airtag-with-better-range-and-a-louder-speaker/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:18:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why has Microsoft been routing example.com traffic to a company in Japan?</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/odd-anomaly-caused-microsofts-network-to-mishandle-example-com-traffic/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/error-message-1000x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Company’s autodiscover caused users’ test credentials to be sent outside Microsoft networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Department of Bizarre Anomalies: Microsoft has suppressed an unexplained anomaly on its network that was routing traffic destined to example.com—a domain reserved for testing purposes—to a maker of electronics cables located in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under theRFC2606—an official standard maintained by the Internet Engineering Task Force—example.com isn’t obtainable by any party. Instead it resolves to IP addresses assigned to Internet Assiged Names Authority. The designation is intended to prevent third parties from being bombarded with traffic when developers, penetration testers, and others need a domain for testing or discussing technical issues. Instead of naming an Internet-routable domain, they are to choose example.com or two others, example.net and example.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output from the terminal command cURL shows that devices inside Azure and other Microsoft networks have been routing some traffic to subdomains of sei.co.jp, a domain belonging to Sumitomo Electric. Most of the resulting text is exactly what’s expected. The exception is the JSON-based response. Here’s the JSON output from Friday:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, results when adding a new account for test@example.com in Outlook looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the results show that Microsoft was routing email traffic to two sei.co.jp subdomains: imapgms.jnet.sei.co.jp and smtpgms.jnet.sei.co.jp. The behavior was the result of Microsoft’sautodiscoverservice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m admittedly not an expert in Microsoft’s internal workings, but this appears to be a simple misconfiguration,”Michael Taggart, a senior cybersecurity researcher at UCLA Health, said. “The result is that anyone who tries to set up an Outlook account on an example.com domain might accidentally send test credentials to those sei.co.jp subdomains.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked early Friday afternoon why Microsoft was doing this, a representative had no answer and asked for more time. By Monday morning, the improper routing was no longer occurring, but the representative still had no answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update:in an email sent after this post went live, the representative confirmed that Microsoft has “updated the service to no longer provide suggested server information for example.com.” As already reported here, the behavior only affected people configuring email accounts through the Outlook autoconfiguration feature. The representative added that Microsoft is investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new JSON response suggested that, as of Monday morning, Microsoft hadn’t fixed the endpoint routing traffic to the Sumitomo Electric servers. Instead, the JSON response no longer occurs. Where the output was occurring on Friday, the command now simply sits and hangs for 10 or 20 seconds and then terminates with a not found error. This behavior can be seen in the following output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It looks like they may have outright removed the endpoint that validates the email, because I’m seeing ‘not found’ errors,” saidDan Tentler, founder of Phobos Group. As denoted by ENOTFOUND, the error “suggests that [Microsoft admins] just ripped out whatever this thing was.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear how Sumitomo Electric’s domain would have found itself part of this mess. Microsoft last yearsaidthe Japanese company’s parent company, Sumitomo Corp., was deploying Microsoft 365 Copilot, but that still doesn’t explain why a subsidiary’s domain was added to Microsoft’s network configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions sent to Microsoft include: How are autodiscover records added at Microsoft; was the routing intentional; and how long has the behavior been occurring? (Tinyapps.org, whichnotedthe odd routing behavior earlier this month, said it lasted five years.) There doesn’t appear to be anything nefarious about the improper routing, and as long as people inside Microsoft’s network weren’t sending live credentials in tests, there was no danger posed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s still reason for concern. In 2024, Microsoft revealed that one of its admins had assigned administrative privileges to a test account on the company network and then forgot about it. Russia-state hackersseized on the gaffeto gain initial access to Microsoft’s system. They went on to root through the network and monitor top executives’ email for two months. The routing misconfiguration for example.com raises the question: What other possibly more severe errors lurk on the network?&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/odd-anomaly-caused-microsofts-network-to-mishandle-example-com-traffic/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:02:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Doctors face-palm as RFK Jr.’s top vaccine advisor questions need for polio shot</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/do-we-really-need-polio-shots-deep-thoughts-by-rfk-jr-advisor-get-dragged/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2235571142-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirk Milhoan’s comments come as federal vaccine policy slides to insignificance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chair of a federal vaccine advisory panel under anti-vaccine Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. made his stance clear on vaccines in a podcast last week—and that stance was so alarming that the American Medical Association was compelled to respond with a scathing statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirk Milhoan, who wasnamed chair of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practicesfor the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in December, appeared on the aptly named podcast “Why Should I Trust You.” In the hour-long interview, Milhoan made a wide range of comments that have concerned medical experts and raised eyebrows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early into the discussion, Milhoan, a pediatric cardiologist, declared, “I don’t like established science,” and that “science is what I observe.” He lambasted the evidence-based methodology that previous ACIP panels used to carefully and transparently craft vaccine policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While arguing that he was not anti-vaccine, he said he was merely focused on safety and made false claims about vaccine risks, a common trope among anti-vaccine activists. He falsely linked vaccines to allergies, asthma, and eczema and repeated a claim, without evidence, that COVID-19 vaccines killed children. When pressed by the podcast hosts, he revealed that he put the risk of vaccine side effects on the same footing as the risks from the diseases the shots prevent—despite the fact that disease risks are often orders of magnitude larger than the tiny risks from vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to pushback from the hosts, Milhoan objected to the idea that the measles and polio vaccines reduced the spread of those diseases. He went further, questioning the need for those vaccines as well as routine vaccinations, generally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think also as you look at polio, we need to not be afraid to consider that we are in a different time now than we were then,” he said, referring to the time before the first polio vaccines were developed in the 1950s. “Our sanitation is different. Our risk of disease is different. And so those all play into the evaluation of whether this is worthwhile of taking a risk for a vaccine or not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then pondered out loud what would happen if people stopped getting vaccinated. “If we take away all of the herd immunity, then does that switch, does that teeter-totter switch in a different direction?” he asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, AMA Trustee Sandra Adamson Fryhofer blasted the question. “This is not a theoretical debate—it is a dangerous step backward,” she said. “Vaccines have saved millions of lives and virtually eliminated devastating diseases like polio in the United States. There is no cure for polio. When vaccination rates fall, paralysis, lifelong disability, and death return. The science on this is settled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fryhofer also took aim at Milhoan’s repeated argument that the focus of vaccination policy should move from population-level health to individual autonomy. Moving away from routine immunizations, which include discussions between clinicians and patients, “does not increase freedom—it increases suffering,” she said, adding that the weakening of recommendations “will cost lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, Milhoan’s comments only further erode the relevance of ACIP and federal vaccine policy among the medical community and states. According toa KFF policy brief, 27 states and Washington, DC, have already announced they will not follow current CDC vaccine recommendations, whichKennedy dramatically overhauledearlier this month without even consulting the ACIP. Instead, the majority of states are relying on previous recommendations or recommendations made within states or by medical organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the American Academy of Pediatricsannounced the 2026 updateto itschildhood and adolescent vaccine schedule, which it has held up as an alternative to the CDC’s schedule and has been widely embraced by pediatricians. In the announcement, AAP noted that 12 other medical organizations have endorsed the schedule, including the AMA, the American Academy of Family Physicians, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, the Infectious Diseases Society of America, and the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AAP’s updated recommendations are largely the same as the schedule from last year, but it is significantly different from the CDC’s recommendations, which “depart from longstanding medical evidence and no longer offer the optimal way to prevent illnesses in children,” the AAP said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The AAP will continue to provide recommendations for immunizations that are rooted in science and are in the best interest of the health of infants, children and adolescents of this country,” AAP President Andrew Racine said in the announcement.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/do-we-really-need-polio-shots-deep-thoughts-by-rfk-jr-advisor-get-dragged/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:31:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI spills technical details about how its AI coding agent works</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/openai-spills-technical-details-about-how-its-ai-coding-agent-works/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/coding_robots_agents-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusually detailed post explains how OpenAI handles the Codex agent loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, OpenAI engineer Michael Bolinpublisheda detailed technical breakdown of how the company’sCodex CLIcoding agent works internally, offering developers insight into AI coding tools that can write code, run tests, and fix bugs with human supervision. It complements our articlein Decemberon how AI agents work by filling in technical details on how OpenAI implements its “agentic loop.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI coding agents are having something of a “ChatGPT moment,” where Claude Code with Opus 4.5 and Codex with GPT-5.2 have reached a new level of usefulness for rapidly coding up prototypes, interfaces, and churning out boilerplate code. The timing of OpenAI’s post details the design philosophy behind Codex just as AI agents are becoming more practical tools for everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tools aren’t perfect and remain controversial for some software developers. While OpenAI haspreviously toldArs Technica that it uses Codex as a coding tool to help develop the Codex product itself, we alsodiscovered, through hands-on experience, that these tools can be astonishingly fast at simple tasks but remain brittle beyond their training data and require human oversight for production work. The rough framework of a project tends to come fast and feels magical, but filling in the details involves tedious debugging and workarounds for limitations the agent cannot overcome on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin’s post doesn’t shy away from these engineering challenges. He discusses the inefficiency of quadratic prompt growth, performance issues caused by cache misses, and bugs the team discovered (likeMCP toolsbeing enumerated inconsistently) that they had to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of technical detail is somewhat unusual for OpenAI, which has not published similar breakdowns of how other products like ChatGPT work internally, for example (there’s a lot going on under that hood we’d like to know). But we’ve already seen how OpenAI treats Codex differently during our interview with them in December, noting that programming tasks seem ideally suited for large language models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that bothOpenAIandAnthropicopen-source their coding CLI clients on GitHub, allowing developers to examine the implementation directly, whereas they don’t do the same for ChatGPT or the Claude web interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin’s post focuses on what he calls “the agent loop,” which is the core logic that orchestrates interactions between the user, the AI model, and the software tools the model invokes to perform coding work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As wewrotein December, at the center of every AI agent is a repeating cycle. The agent takes input from the user and prepares a textual prompt for the model. The model then generates a response, which either produces a final answer for the user or requests a tool call (such as running a shell command or reading a file). If the model requests a tool call, the agent executes it, appends the output to the original prompt, and queries the model again. This process repeats until the model stops requesting tools and instead produces an assistant message for the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That looping process has to start somewhere, and Bolin’s post reveals how Codex constructs the initial prompt sent to OpenAI’s Responses API, which handles model inference. The prompt is built from several components, each with an assigned role that determines its priority: system, developer, user, or assistant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions field comes from either a user-specified configuration file or base instructions bundled with the CLI. The tools field defines what functions the model can call, including shell commands, planning tools, web search capabilities, and any custom tools provided through Model Context Protocol (MCP) servers. The input field contains a series of items that describe the sandbox permissions, optional developer instructions, environment context like the current working directory, and finally the user’s actual message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As conversations continue, each new turn includes the complete history of previous messages and tool calls. This means the prompt grows with every interaction, which has performance implications. According to the post, because Codex does not use an optional “previous_response_id” parameter that would allow the API to reference stored conversation state, every request is fully stateless (that is, it sends the entire conversation history with each API call rather than the server retrieving it from memory). Bolin says this design choice simplifies things for API providers and makes it easier to support customers who opt into “Zero Data Retention,” where OpenAI does not store user data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thequadratic growthof prompts over a conversation is inefficient, but Bolin explains that prompt caching mitigates this issue somewhat. Cache hits only work for exact prefix matches within a prompt, which means Codex must carefully avoid operations that could cause cache misses. Changing the available tools, switching models, or modifying the sandbox configuration mid-conversation can all invalidate the cache and hurt performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ever-growing prompt length is directly related to the context window, which limits how much text the AI model can process in a single inference call. Bolin writes that Codex automatically compacts conversations when token counts exceed a threshold, just as Claude Code does. Earlier versions of Codex required manual compaction via a slash command, but the current system uses a specialized API endpoint that compresses context while preserving summarized portions of the model’s “understanding” of what happened through an encrypted content item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin says that future posts in his series will cover the CLI’s architecture, tool implementation details, and Codex’s sandboxing model.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/openai-spills-technical-details-about-how-its-ai-coding-agent-works/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>