<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ArsTechnica Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text ArsTechnica articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/ArsTechnica_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 02:54:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Japan lost a 5-ton navigation satellite when it fell off a rocket during launch</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/heres-the-story-of-how-japans-h3-rocket-lost-its-cargo-and-just-kept-going/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/jaxa_h3_f8_anim1.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine: You lost your car’s cargo rack, but didn’t notice until you reached your destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re in the space business long enough, you learn there are numerous ways a rocket can fail. I’ve written my share of stories about misbehaving rockets and the extensive investigations that usually—but not always—reveal what went wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I never expected to write this story. Maybe this was a failure of my own imagination. I’m used to writing about engine malfunctions, staging issues, guidance glitches, or structural failures. Last April, Arsreported on the bizarre failureof Firefly Aerospace’s commercial Alpha rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan’s H3 rocket found a new way to fail last month, apparently eluding the imaginations of its own designers and engineers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The H3 is a relatively new vehicle, with last month’s launch marking the eighth flight of Japan’s flagship rocket. The launcher falls on the medium-to-heavy section of the lift spectrum. The eighth H3 rocket lifted off from Tanegashima Island in southern Japan on December 22, local time, carrying a roughly 5-ton navigation satellite into space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket was supposed to place the Michibiki 5 satellite into an orbit ranging more than 20,000 miles above the Earth. Everything was going well until the H3 jettisoned its payload fairing, the two-piece clamshell covering the satellite during launch, nearly four minutes into the flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials from the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency (JAXA) are starting to get a handle on what happened. Agency officials briefed the government ministry overseeing Japan’s space activities last week, and the presentation (in Japanese) wasposted on a government website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation is rich in information, with illustrations, a fault tree analysis, and a graph of in-flight measurements from sensors on the H3 rocket. It offers a treasure trove of detail and data most launch providers decline to release publicly after a rocket malfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the material is difficult to grasp for a non-Japanese speaker unfamiliar with the subtle intricacies of the H3 rocket’s design. What is clear is that something went wrong when the rocket released its payload shroud. Video beamed back from the rocket’s onboard cameras showed a shower of debris surrounding the satellite, which started wobbling and leaning in the moments after fairing separation. Sensors also detected sudden accelerations around the attachment point connecting the spacecraft with the top of the H3 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the mission, the H3 rocket was well above the thick lower layers of the atmosphere. Aerodynamic forces were not a significant factor, but the rocket continued accelerating on the power of its two hydrogen-fueled main engines. The Michibiki 5 satellite held on for a little more than a minute, when the H3’s first stage shut down and separated from the rocket’s second stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The jolt from staging dislodged the satellite from its mooring atop the rocket. Then, the second stage lit its engine and left the satellite in the dust. A rear-facing camera on the upper stage captured a fleeting view of the satellite falling back to Earth. In the briefing package, Japanese space officials wrote that Michibiki 5 fell into the Pacific Ocean in the same impact zone as the H3’s first stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever caused the satellite to break free of the rocket damaged more than its attach fitting. Telemetry data downlinked from the H3 showed a pressure drop in the second stage’s liquid hydrogen tank after separation of the payload fairing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A decrease in LH2 tank pressure was confirmed almost simultaneously,” officials wrote. A pressurization valve continued to open to restore pressure to the tank, but the pressure did not recover. “It is highly likely that the satellite mounting structure was damaged due to some factor, and as a result, the pressurization piping was damaged.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second stage engine lost 20 percent of its thrust, but it fired long enough to put the rocket into a low-altitude orbit. The rocket’s temporary recovery was likely aided by the absence of its multi-ton payload, meaning it needed a lower impulse to reach orbital velocity. The orbit was too low to sustain, and the second stage of the H3 rocket reentered the atmosphere and burned up within several hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators now have a grasp of what happened, but they are still piecing together why. JAXA presented a fault tree analysis to the Japanese science and technology ministry, showing which potential causes engineers have ruled out, and which ones remain under investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The branches of the fault tree still open include the possibility of an impact or collision between part of the payload fairing and the Michibiki 5 satellite or its mounting structure. Engineers continue to probe the possibility that residual strain energy in the connection between the satellite and the rocket was suddenly released at the moment of fairing separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket is supposed to vent pressure inside the fairing as it ascends through thinner air and into space. Measurements from the rocket indicate the pressure inside the fairing decreased as expected during the launch. Officials don’t believe this was a factor in the launch failure, but engineers are examining whether the measurements were in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rocket and satellite also carried combustible propellants, high-pressure gases, and pyrotechnics. “While no data indicating leakage of these substances has been confirmed, the possibility that they caused the abnormal acceleration cannot be ruled out at this time,” JAXA said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the probe has found no evidence that a structural problem with the satellite itself was the root cause of the failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With last month’s incident, the H3 rocket has a record of six successful launches in eight flights. The H3’s debut launch in 2023 faltered due to an ignition failure on the rocket’s second stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JAXA must complete the latest H3 failure investigation in the coming months to clear the rocket to launch the nation’s Martian Moons Exploration (MMX) mission in a narrow planetary launch window that opens in October. MMX is an exciting robotic mission to land on and retrieve samples from the Martian moon Phobos for return to Earth. MMX’s launch was previously set for 2024, but Japan’s space agency delayed it to this year due to earlier problems with the H3 rocket.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/heres-the-story-of-how-japans-h3-rocket-lost-its-cargo-and-just-kept-going/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:15:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Users flock to open source Moltbot for always-on AI, despite major risks</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/viral-ai-assistant-moltbot-rapidly-gains-popularity-but-poses-security-risks/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/clawdbot_1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The open source “Jarvis” chats via WhatsApp but requires access to your files and accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An open source AI assistant called Moltbot (formerly “Clawdbot”) recently crossed 69,000 stars onGitHubafter a month, making it one of the fastest-growing AI projects of 2026. Created by Austrian developerPeter Steinberger, the tool lets users run a personal AI assistant and control it through messaging apps they already use. While some say it feels like the AI assistant of the future, running the tool as currently designed comes with serious security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the dozens of unofficial AI bot apps that never rise above the fray, Moltbot is perhaps most notable for its proactive communication with the user. The assistant works with WhatsApp, Telegram, Slack, Discord, Google Chat, Signal, iMessage, Microsoft Teams, and other platforms. It can reach out to users with reminders, alerts, or morning briefings based on calendar events or other triggers. The project has drawn comparisons to Jarvis, the AI assistant from the Iron Man films, for its ability to actively attempt to manage tasks across a user’s digital life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we’ll tell you up front that there are plenty of drawbacks to the still-hobbyist software: While the organizing assistant code runs on a local machine, the tool effectively requires a subscription to Anthropic or OpenAI for model access (or using an API key). Users can run local AI models with the bot, but they are currently less effective at carrying out tasks than the best commercial models. Claude Opus 4.5, which is Anthropic’s flagship large language model (LLM), is a popular choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up Moltbot requires configuring a server, managing authentication, and understanding sandboxing for even a slice of security in a system that basically demands access to every facet of your digital life. Heavy use can rack up significant API costs, since agentic systems make many calls behind the scenes and use up a lot of tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve only just begun to try Moltbot ourselves (more on that soon), but we’ve seen plenty of discussions circulating in the AI community about the new assistant. The all-in approach has serious security drawbacks, since it requires access to messaging accounts, API keys, and in some configurations, shell commands. Also, an always-on agent with access to messaging channels and personal systems can quickly expand your attack surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with all the drawbacks listed above, people are still using Moltbot. MacStories editor Federico Viticci, who spent a week testing the tool,describedit as “Claude with hands,” referring to how it connects a large language model (LLM) backend with real-world capabilities like browser control, email management, and file operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s documentation describes it as a tool for users who want “a personal, single-user assistant that feels local, fast, and always-on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the project’s GitHub page, Steinberger designed the bot to retain long-term memory and execute commands directly on the user’s system, unlike current web-based chatbots from major AI labs. It’s closer toClaude CodeandCodex CLI(which also operate on local files using a cloud AI model), but with more latitude to take local actions on the user’s behalf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moltbot stores memory as Markdown files and an SQLite database on the user’s machine. It auto-generates daily notes that log interactions and uses vector search to retrieve relevant context from past conversations. The memory persists across sessions because the bot runs as a background daemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to Claude Code, which is session-based, Moltbot runs persistently (24/7) and maintains its stored memory indefinitely. It can reportedly recall what you discussed weeks ago. With Claude Code, when you close it, the conversation context is gone (unless you use CLAUDE.md files for project context).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s rapid rise has not come without complications. On Monday, AnthropicaskedSteinberger to change the project’s name due to trademark concerns (since “Clawd” sounds like “Claude”), prompting the rebrand from Clawdbot to Moltbot. “Clawdbot” was originally named after the ASCII art creature that appears when you launch Claude Code on a terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the transition enabled bad actors to hijack Steinberger’s old social media and GitHub handles,reportsThe Register. Crypto scammers launched fake tokens using the project’s name, with one reaching a $16 million market cap before crashing. Steinbergerrespondedon X: “Any project that lists me as a coin owner is a SCAM. No, I will not accept fees. You are actively damaging the project.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security researchers have alsofoundvulnerabilities in misconfigured public deployments. Bitdefender reported that exposed dashboards allowed outsiders to view configuration data, retrieve API keys, and browse full conversation histories from private chats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While there’s plenty of hype about Moltbot right now, be advised that any LLM that has access to your local machine is susceptible toprompt injectionattacks that can “trick” the AI model to share your personal data with other people or remote servers. While Moltbot offers a glimpse at what future AI assistants from major vendors might look like, it’s still experimental and not yet ready for users who aren’t comfortable trading today’s AI convenience (such as it is) for major security risks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/viral-ai-assistant-moltbot-rapidly-gains-popularity-but-poses-security-risks/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:30:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The origin story of syphilis goes back far longer than we thought</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/the-origin-story-of-syphilis-goes-back-far-longer-than-we-thought/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/02/3f05379v-e1360003011507-634x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 5,500-year-old fossil from Colombia has scientists rethinking syphilis origins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When King Charles VIII of France occupied Naples in 1495, his army of nearly 20,000 mercenaries became the ground zero of the “Great Pox,” the first massive venereal syphilis pandemic in Europe, which went on to cause up to 5 million deaths. For a long time, the siege of Naples was considered the first time syphilis entered European accounts and culture. “But the evolutionary history ofTreponema pallidum, the lineage of bacteria including the one that causes syphilis, goes way deeper in time,” says Elizabeth Nelson, an anthropologist at the Southern Methodist University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nelson and her colleagues found a 5,500-year-oldTreponema pallidumgenome in an individual excavated from a rock shelter in Colombia—a discovery that shows pathogens causing treponemal diseases like syphilis, bejel, or yaws are several millennia older than we thought. And this means we might have been thinking about the origins of syphilis in an entirely wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the French occupation of Naples did not introduce syphilis to this world, it created the perfect storm that shaped the perception of this disease and its origins for centuries to come. The first ingredient of this storm was the French army and its leader. Charles VIII invaded Naples with a vast melting pot of brigands and mercenaries from all over Europe, including the French, Swiss, Poles, and Spaniards. The king himself wasn’t exactly the epitome of morality. Chroniclers like Johannes Burckard noted his “fondness of copulation” and reported that, once he’d been with a woman, he “cared no more about her” and immediately sought another partner—a behavior eagerly mirrored by his soldiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second ingredient was the city of Naples, which back in the 15thcentury was famous as the center of luxury and sex. When the city surrendered and opened its gates, the invading army spent months on what Joseph Grünpeck, a secretary to the Holy Roman Emperor Maximillian I, described as “gluttony, debauchery, and consorting with prostitutes.” This created the ideal set of conditions for syphilis, a sexually transmitted disease, to spread massively among the armies. When the mercenaries, incapable of fighting anymore, deserted the infected army and fled to their home countries, the disease rapidly spread across Europe. These conditions also immediately defined the narrative about syphilis in terms of cultural and national blame games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Neapolitans called syphilis Morbus Gallicus, which means the French disease. The French returned the favor and called it the Neapolitan disease. The English naturally called it the French Pox, and so on. Ultimately, fingers ended up pointing at a few Spaniards from Charles VIII’s army. They allegedly served as crew members on Columbus’ ships that returned from the New World in 1493, just one year before the siege of Naples started. The syphilis was declared a “gift” Columbus brought to Europe from the Americas, a curse the New World cast upon the old one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blame game naturally assumed syphilis must have had a single place of origin, be it Naples, France, Europe, or the Americas. The 5,500-year-oldTreponema pallidumgenome discovered by Nelson and her colleagues suggests it might not have been the case at all. “I would not say our work makes popular syphilis origin stories irrelevant, but it shows there’s more ecological and evolutionary depth here,” Nelson says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discovery was, in a way, a lucky break. The team was sequencing the DNA of an individual excavated from the Tequendama I rock shelter, located in the Sabana de Bogotá, Colombia, as part of a broader research project on the population history of the Americas. The individual in question, labeled TE1-3, was an adult male hunter-gatherer who lived in Middle Holocene, roughly 5,500 years ago. “We weren’t looking for the origins of syphilis, this wasn’t the main focus of our research,” says Nasreen Broomandkhoshbacht, a geneticist at the University of Vermont and co-author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, scientists hunting for ancientTreponemagenomes look for bones with telltale signs of treponematosis like altered shins or pitted skull lesions. But the skeleton of TE1-3 showed no macroscopic signs of infection. Usually, this would make it a poor candidate for pathogen recovery. However, thanks to the sheer volume of data generated—1.5 billion fragments of genetic material—scientists could detect traces ofTreponema pallidum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the bacterial DNA making up a minuscule portion of the total sequencing data, the team succeeded in reconstructing the ancient pathogen’s genome, and right from the start it appeared a little bit special. Thetreponema pallidumlineage today comprises three subspecies responsible for syphilis, bejel, and yaws. “We noticed that the genome we recovered differed from those three much more than they differ from each other,” Broomandkhoshbacht says. That indicates the newly discovered bacterium wasn’t a direct ancestor of modern syphilis, yaws, or bejel. “It was a sister lineage that diverged from all known modern subspecies approximately 13,700 years ago in Late Pleistocene,” says Davide Bozzi, a computational biologist at the University of Lausanne and lead author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;13,700 years ago was roughly when humans first started populating South America and rapidly spread around the continent. And, based on this discovery, the bacteria of theTreponema pallidumlineage were already diverse and capable of infecting people by then. This Late Pleistocene divergence, the authors note in their study, hints at the ancient pan-human distribution. VariousTreponema pallidumsubspecies were probably our fellow travelers spreading globally with the first humans that migrated out of Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s much more we need to learn before the “Columbian” syphilis origin debate is settled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 1495 siege of Naples remains the moment syphilis etched itself into the European psyche as a new and terrifying plague, it was likely just one violent flare-up in a relationship between humans andTreponemapathogens that spans continents and millennia. What we don’t know is when and where the important turning points in this relationship took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear when and whyTreponema pallidumevolved its sexual transmission, so evidently present in the subspecies that caused the outbreak in Naples. It’s also unclear whether the 1495 pandemic was triggered by a newly imported strain or a mutation of a lineage already present in Europe. The team hopes analyzing other ancient pathogen genomes hosted by people from different places on the globe and different social contexts—hunter-gatherers, farmers, city dwellers—will answer at least some of these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, it’s hard to infer a specific pathogen’s features from ancient genomes. “With the data we have today, we can’t say anything about the virulence of this ancientTreponema pallidumsubspecies, about how the symptoms of the disease it caused looked like, or about its mode of transmission,” Bozzi says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we do know, however, is that thousands of years ago, theTreponema pallidumlineage was likely way more diverse than it is today. “In the future we’d love to look at broader ecological interactions between humans, animals, the environment, and the pathogens,” says Nelson. “We’d love to explore this diversity further.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science, 2026. DOI:10.1126/science.adw3020&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/the-origin-story-of-syphilis-goes-back-far-longer-than-we-thought/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:55:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ryzen 9850X3D review: AMD's bragging-rights gaming CPU gets more to brag about</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/review-amds-ryzen-7-9850x3d-is-a-little-faster-and-a-lot-more-power-hungry/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/IMG_7105-1152x648-1769617334.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tradeoffs for the $499 9850X3D make it hard to get excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD has released three distinct generations of its 3D V-Cache technology, which initially appeared in theRyzen 7 5800X3Din 2022. The kernel of the idea has remained the same throughout AMD’s efforts: take an existing desktop processor design and graft 64MB of additional L3 cache onto it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach disproportionately helps apps that benefit from more cache, particularly games, and the size of the boost that 3D V-Cache gives to game performance has always been enough to offset any downsides these chips have come with. And in the four years since the 5800X3D was released, AMD has steadily chipped away at those disadvantages, adding more CPU cores, improving power consumption and temperatures, and re-adding the typical Ryzen range of overclocking controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMD’s new Ryzen 7 9850X3D, which launches for $499 starting tomorrow, is the very definition of a mild upgrade. It’s the year-old Ryzen 7 9800X3D but with an extra 400 MHz of turbo boost speed. That’s it. That’s the chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is mildly interesting that the 9800X3D’s 5.6GHz boost clock is now 100 MHzhigherthan that of the Ryzen 7 9700X, the chip’s nearest non-V-Cache equivalent. It’s not nearly as interesting as an actual new chip, but it does mean AMD has closed the last major functional gap between the V-Cache and non-V-Cache Ryzen chips (the pricing gap remains; the 9700X currently retails for around $329).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means that the 9850X3D behaves more like a 9700X in other ways—differences that likely won’t matter to its target audience but which do distinguish it from being “just a faster 9800X3D.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest change AMD made to the Ryzen 9000 version of the X3D chips is that the 3D V-Cache is now stacked underneath the CPU silicon rather than on top. This has the benefit of moving the CPU cores closer to your heatsink or AIO loop, making them easier to keep cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9850X3D remains an eight-core chip based on AMD’s Zen 5 architecture. All eight of those CPU cores have access to the 3D V-Cache, unlike the 12-core and 16-core Ryzen 9 9900X3D and 9950X3D. In each of those chips, one of the CPU chiplets has access to the 3D V-Cache and one doesn’t; AMD’s chipset software is responsible for making sure apps run on the type of CPU core that will maximize the app’s performance. AMD’s software is pretty good at this, but it’s not foolproof, which can make the 9800X3D and 9850X3D more appealing and cost-effective options for PCs that will mainly be used for gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The specs in our CPU testbed are the same as they’ve been for a while. We’ll be focused on comparing the 9850X3D to its predecessors, the 5800X3D, 7800X3D, and 9800X3D, as well as the non-V-Cache 7700X and 9700X. We’ll also include numbers from the higher-end 9900X3D and 9950X3D. Intel’s side of the fence will be represented by the Core Ultra 9 285K and the last few generations of Core i9 chips, though Intel has yet to release any chips that are truly performance-competitive with the 3D V-Cache chips in gaming workloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though our testbed continues to rely on DDR5-6000, AMD’s slide deck takes the current (horrible) state of the RAM market into account. While DDR5-6000 or DDR5-6400 is generally still the performance sweet spot for all socket AM5 CPUs, AMD notes that game performance between the 9850X3D with DDR5-6000 and the same chip with DDR5-4800 can be as little as 1 to 2 percent. In other words, pair whatever RAM you can find with this chip and don’t worry about it too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice about the 9850X3D is that its multi-core performance is essentially indistinguishable from the 9800X3D. If anything, the 9800X3D seems marginally better-behaved in our Handbrake video encoding tests, which could come down to anything or nothing—maybe it’s an actual difference between the chips, maybe it’s the silicon lottery, maybe it’s something else. Overall, it’s mostly a wash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 9850X3Ddoesimprove significantly on the 9800X3D’s single-core performance, closing the gap with both the Ryzen 9900X3D and 9950X3D (both of which have regular Zen 5 cores with no 3D V-Cache) and the 9700X (which has no 3D V-Cache at all).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a world in which AMD can get this extra performance for “free” without changing anything about the architecture or manufacturing process. AMD could have been “binning” silicon lottery winners, or the reliability of the manufacturing process could have improved enough to allow AMD to hit better numbers that weren’t as consistently achievable a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it looks like AMD improved the 9850X3D’s single-core performance mainly by making it behave more like a non-X3D chip. The chip’s power consumption while gaming suggests this is more or less what’s happening—the 9850X3D’s CPU package power while gaming is some 25 or 30 W higher than the 9800X3D playing the same games, despite the single-digit-at-best performance improvement (in both our testing and AMD’s advertising).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the 9850X3D’s power consumption while gaming isn’t wildly out of step with the 9700X’s or the 9950X3D’s, it does make the tiny performance gains on display here hard to get excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is on top of the cost trade-off you’re already making when you buy an X3D-series chip. Game performance is always impressive, but you notice those benefits themostin situations where your CPU, not the GPU, is the performance bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time in a gaming PC, that’s only going to be the case when you’re trying to play games at extremely high frame rates at lower resolutions. It’s less useful when trying to play games at 4K or even 1440p, where your graphics card will be the limiter. If you’re building a system around any GPU slower than an RTX 4080 or 5080, going with a regular 9700X and putting the savings toward your GPU (or toward an eye-wateringly expensive RAM kit) will usually be a better use of funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ryzen 7 9850X3D mostly does what it says it does: It’s a mild speed bump to AMD’s best gaming processor that, in most cases, very slightly extends the company’s performance lead over Intel chips like the Core Ultra 9 285K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the vanilla 9800X3D isalmostas fast, it uses 25 or 30 W less power during gaming (which also results in temperatures that are 10 to 15 degrees Celsius cooler), and it’s $30 cheaper as of this writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who routinely runs his own Ryzen desktop chips in Eco Mode to reduce power consumption and temperatures and hit a more efficient spot on the performance-per-Watt curve, the numbers that the 9850X3D posted in our testing make it seem like an undesirable trade-off, even if you’re in the target market for a fast-as-possible, money-no-object, bragging-rights gaming PC.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/review-amds-ryzen-7-9850x3d-is-a-little-faster-and-a-lot-more-power-hungry/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 07:41:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Carolina tops Texas measles outbreak record—with no end in sight</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/sc-measles-23-schools-hit-over-550-quarantined-as-outbreak-hits-record/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257300982-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since start of the year, South Carolina’s outbreak has accelerated dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explosive measles outbreak in South Carolina has now reached789 cases, breaking Texas’s outbreak record last year of762 cases, which at the time was the largest outbreak in the US since measles was declared eliminated from the US in 2000. The country is at grave risk of losing its elimination status in the coming months due to continuous spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Texas’ outbreak last year—which spanned January to August and spread to additional states—the US saw the largest measles case total since 1991, with2,255 confirmed cases. Now, with South Carolina’s unbridled outbreak, 2026 is already looking like it will be another record year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though South Carolina’s outbreak began in October, the spread of the disease has dramatically accelerated this month, with cases jumping from 218 on December 28 to 789 on January 27.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention is reporting a national tally of416 confirmed casessince the start of the year, but the total was last updated on January 22, missing the latest cases, including the 89 South Carolina cases reported Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to South Carolina, measles cases for 2026 have been reported in Arizona, California, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Kentucky, Minnesota, North Carolina, Ohio, Oregon, Utah, Virginia, and Washington. A large outbreak of the highly infectious virus is ongoing at the border ofUtahandArizona. Collectively, the states have reported 457 cases amid the outbreak, including 66 reported in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measles is one of the most infectious viruses we know of and can linger in the airspace of a room for up to two hours after an infected person has been present. Among unvaccinated people exposed to an infectious person, up to 90 percent will become ill. Many infections are only identified when measles’ telltale rash develops, but a person can be infectious for four daysbeforethat rash develops, allowing the virus to more easily spread. People remain infectious for four days after the rash appears. In newly infected people, symptoms, which also include high fevers, typically begin 7 to 14 days after exposure, but this incubation period can be as long as 21 days, which is the length of quarantine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In itslatest update, South Carolina’s Public Health Department reported data indicating that its large case jumps will continue. In recent weeks, officials have identified 23 schools where measles has been unleashed. In 20 of the schools, unvaccinated and exposed students have been identified and quarantined, with individual schools’ quarantine totals spanning 13 to 59 students. For the remaining three schools with exposures, officials are still determining how many students need to be quarantined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State officials have also identified eight public places where measles exposures have occurred recently, including grocery stores, a US Post Office, and a skating center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, 557 students are quarantined, but additional susceptible people have likely been exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the 789 cases, 769 (97 percent) were unvaccinated or partially vaccinated or had an undocumented vaccination status. Two doses of the measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine are 97 percent effective against measles, and that protection is considered lifelong.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/sc-measles-23-schools-hit-over-550-quarantined-as-outbreak-hits-record/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:02:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Report: China approves import of high-end Nvidia AI chips after weeks of uncertainty</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/report-china-approves-import-of-high-end-nvidia-ai-chips-after-weeks-of-uncertainty/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/GettyImages-2131985696-1536x864-1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 400,000 H200 chips coming to tech giants as China tries to balance tech needs with self-reliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, China approved imports of Nvidia’s H200 artificial intelligence chips for three of its largest technology companies, Reutersreported. ByteDance, Alibaba, and Tencent received approval to purchase more than 400,000H200chips in total, marking a shift in Beijing’s stance after weeks of holding up shipments despite US export clearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move follows Beijing’s temporary halt to H200 shipments earlier this month after Washingtoncleared exportson January 13. Chinese customs authorities had told agents that the H200 chips were not permitted to enter China, Reutersreportedearlier this month, even as Chinese technology companies placed orders for more than two million of the chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The H200, Nvidia’s second most powerful AI chip after theB200, delivers roughly six times the performance of the company’sH20chip, which was previously the most capable chip Nvidia could sell to China. While Chinese companies such as Huawei now have products that rival the H20’s performance, they still lag far behind the H200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese tech giants want access to Nvidia’s higher-powered AI chips because they dramatically speed up the process of training large AI models, a computationally intensive task of feeding data through neural networks millions of times to tune their performance. More capable chips like the H200 allow companies to train larger models faster or run more AI queries (called inference) at a lower cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has made high-end AI accelerator chips a flashpoint in the ongoing AI race between Washington, DC, and Beijing, with US policymakers caught between wanting to boost sales for American semiconductor companies andfearingthat exports could help China close the gap in AI capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Nvidia wants the business because China is a huge market. The latest approvals came during Nvidia CEO Jensen Huang’s visit to China this week, according to sources who spoke with Reuters on the condition of anonymity. Other Chinese firms are now waiting for their own approvals in future rounds, though Beijing is attaching conditions to the licenses that have not yet been finalized. One source told Reuters that the license terms were too restrictive and buyers had not yet turned their approvals into actual orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval signals Beijing’s prioritization of its major Internet companies, which are spending billions of dollars to build data centers needed to develop AI services and compete with US rivals, including OpenAI. But regulators are also trying to nurture China’s domestic semiconductor industry, the South China Morning Postreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first batch was expected to go to Big Tech companies in urgent need of the GPU, according to a source who spoke with that publication. However, access for state-backed firms, including telecom operators, was expected to stay tightly restricted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beijing has previously discouraged domestic technology companies from purchasing foreign chips unless absolutely needed,according toearlier Reuters reporting. One proposal authorities discussed in the past would require each H200 purchase to be bundled with a set ratio of domestic chips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Beijing’s approval of the H200 is driven by purely strategic motives,” Alex Capri, a senior lecturer at the National University of Singapore’s business school,toldthe South China Morning Post. “Ultimately, this decision is taken to further China’s indigenous capabilities and, by extension, the competitive capabilities of China tech.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/report-china-approves-import-of-high-end-nvidia-ai-chips-after-weeks-of-uncertainty/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:21:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meta blocks links to ICE List across Facebook, Instagram, and Threads</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/meta-blocks-links-to-ice-list-across-facebook-instagram-and-threads/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/zuck-trump-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Zuckerberg’s social media platforms are assisting the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has started blocking its users from sharing links toICE List, a website that has compiled the names of what it claims areDepartment of Homeland Securityemployees, a project the creators say is designed to hold those employees accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominick Skinner, the creator of ICE List, tells WIRED that links to the website have been shared without issue on Meta’s platforms for more than six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think it’s no surprise that a company run by a man who sat behind Trump at his inauguration, and donated to the destruction of the White House, has taken a stance that helps ICE agents retain anonymity,” says Skinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asagentsfrom Border Patrol and Immigration and Customs Enforcement, which are under DHS, have continued to terrorize immigrant communities andkill US citizens, activists have sought to track and record their activity online in a bid to hold them accountable. But as well as threatening toprosecute those they claim are “doxing” ICE agents, the Trump administration haspressured tech companiesto block any efforts at crowdsourcing the location and activities of those agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE List has been operating since last June. Skinner says it is run by a core team of five people, including him, as well as hundreds of anonymous volunteers who share information about ICE agents operating in cities across the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site went viral earlier this month when it claimed to have uploaded a leaked list of 4,500 DHS employees to its site, buta WIRED analysisfound that the list relied heavily on information the employees shared publicly about themselves on sites such as LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skinner said volunteers he works with across the US first reported problems with posting links on Meta’s platforms on Monday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, WIRED verified that posting links to the site was blocked on Instagram, Facebook, and Threads. WIRED also confirmed that links can still be sent on WhatsApp, another Meta-owned product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While all the social media platforms where the link is blocked are owned by Meta, the reasons users are given for their inability to link to the ICE List website vary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When WIRED attempted to post a link on Facebook, we received a message that read: “Posts that look like spam according to our Community Guidelines are blocked on Facebook and can’t be edited.” Hours later, however, that message was updated to read: “Your content couldn’t be shared, because this link goes against our Community Standards.” The message linked to Meta’sCommunity Standards homepagerather than a specific part of those rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile on Threads, the link instantly disappeared when pasted into a new post, with a notice simply saying: “Link not allowed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Instagram, a notice appearing after an attempt to post a Story read: “We restrict certain activity to protect our community. Let us know if you think we made a mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked about the block, Meta spokesperson Andy Stone directed WIRED to the company’s policyabout sharing personally identifiable information. When WIRED pointed out that the information on the ICE List did not appear to contain any of the information listed on Meta’s policy, he said it was in relation to the policy prohibiting “content asking for personally identifiable information of others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Skinner pointed out that ICE List has been asking for tips about the identities of ICE agents for six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This story originally appeared onwired.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/meta-blocks-links-to-ice-list-across-facebook-instagram-and-threads/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:22:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Google begins rolling out Chrome’s “Auto Browse” AI agent today</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-begins-rolling-out-chromes-auto-browse-ai-agent-today/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/chrome_rollercoaster-1-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Auto Browse agent is available to AI Pro and AI Ultra subscribers, but there are some limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google began stuffing Gemini into its dominant Chrome browser several months ago, and today the AI is expanding its capabilities considerably. Google says the chatbot will be easier to access and connect to more Google services, but the biggest change is the addition of Google’s autonomous browsing agent, which it has dubbed Auto Browse. Similar to tools likeOpenAI Atlas, Auto Browse can handle tedious tasks in Chrome so you don’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newly unveiled Gemini features in Chrome are accessible from the omnipresent AI button that has been lurking at the top of the window for the last few months. Initially, that button only opened Gemini in a pop-up window, but Google now says it will default to a split-screen or “Sidepanel” view. Google confirmed the update began rolling out over the past week, so you may already have it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can still pop Gemini out into a floating window, but the split-view gives Gemini more room to breathe while manipulating a page with AI. This is also helpful when calling other apps in the Chrome implementation of Gemini. The chatbot can now access Gmail, Calendar, YouTube, Maps, Google Shopping, and Google Flights right from the Chrome window. Google technically added this feature around the middle of January, but it’s only talking about it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gemini in Chrome can now also access and edit images with Nano Banana, so you don’t have to download and re-upload them to Gemini in another location. Just open the image from the web and type in the Sidepanel with a description of the edits you want. Like in the Gemini app, you can choose between the slower but higher-quality Pro model and the faster standard one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrome’s new browsing agent (in preview) is the star of today’s show. The promise of agentic AI is one of the freedom to be lazy. Rather than filling out forms or copying information from emails, you simply task a robot with the job and relax while it goes to work. At least, that’s how it’s supposed to go. Most of the computer-use agents we’ve seen so far have been sluggish and unreliable enough to require human supervision. That kind of defeats the purpose. Now it’s Google’s turn to show us what its browsing agent can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google says Auto Browse is based on its latestGemini 3 models, with input from the company’s work on the experimental Project Mariner agent. If you’d do something with a keyboard and mouse inside your browser, Auto Browse is theoretically able to take over. It can also access the content and tabs in your browser, asking for permission when it needs sensitive data, such as your passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you launch an Auto Browse task, Chrome will open new tabs as necessary and mark them with a sparkly AI icon so you know where the robot is active. You don’t have to keep that tab in the foreground, and you can even have multiple AI tasks going at once. The AI will ping you to check in when the task is done or when it needs your input. However, there are limits on Auto Browse similar to some of the company’s more computationally intensive chatbot functions. AI Pro subscribers get 20 AI browsing tasks per day, but those paying for AI Ultra get 200 per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the AI churning in the background may be a concern—after all, generative AI can make mistakes, and you are giving it complete control over the browsing experience. Google says it has implemented a range of security and safety rules to prevent misuse. For example, if you ask Auto Browse to research and buy something, it won’t actually buy it. Instead, it will find the item (hopefully) and progress to the purchase screen before letting you pull the trigger manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to keep in mind is that Auto Browse doesn’t run locally. All content from your robotically operated tab is streamed to a cloud-based Gemini model. That means page content will be shared with Google, but the extent is not entirely clear. Google says Auto Browse is governed by the establishedGemini in Chrome policy, which says Google stores information from websites in the Gemini Apps Activity (if Keep Activity is enabled). Page content is also “logged to your Google Account temporarily.” We asked if Google would use page contents processed by Auto Browse to further train AI models, but a spokesperson declined to provide specifics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrome Auto Browse is rolling out today in preview, but it’s not exactly free. It won’t cost anything extra, but the feature is limited to AI Pro and AI Ultra subscribers. Google’s language suggests the feature may come to free users after the preview phase, but we’d expect strict usage limits.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/google/2026/01/google-begins-rolling-out-chromes-auto-browse-ai-agent-today/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:00:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I bought “Remove Before Flight” tags on eBay in 2010—it turns out they’re from Challenger</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/attached-to-tragedy-tracing-challenger-remove-before-flight-tags/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/news-012826a-lg-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is an attempt to learn more…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forty years ago, a stack of bright red tags shared a physical connection with what would become NASA’s first space shuttle disaster. The small tags, however, were collected before the ill-fated launch ofChallenger, as was instructed in bold “Remove Before Flight” lettering on the front of each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened to the tags after that is largely unknown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an attempt to learn more aboutwhere those “Remove Before Flight” tags wentafter they were detached from the space shuttle and before they arrived on my doorstep. If their history can be better documented, they can be provided to museums, educational centers, and astronautical archives for their preservation and display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin, we go back 16 years to when they were offered for sale on eBay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advertisement on the auction website was titled “Space Shuttle Remove Before Flight Flags Lot of 18.” They were listed with an opening bid of $3.99. On January 12, 2010, I paid $5.50 as the winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, my interest in the 3-inch-wide by 12-inch-long (7.6 by 30.5 cm) tags was as handouts for kids and other attendees at future events. Whether it was at an astronaut autograph convention, a space memorabilia show, a classroom visit, or a conference talk, having “swag” was a great way to foster interest in space history. At first glance, these flags seemed to be a perfect fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I didn’t pay much attention when they first arrived. The eBay listing had promoted them only as generic examples of “KSC Form 4-226 (6/77)"—the ID the Kennedy Space Center assigned to the tags. There was no mention of their being used, let alone specifying an orbiter or specific flight. If I recall correctly, the seller said his intention had been to use them on his boat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Attempts to retrieve the original listing for this article were unsuccessful. As an eBay spokesperson said, “eBay does not retain transaction records or item details dating back over a decade, and therefore we do not have any information to share with you.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was about a year later when I first noticed the ink stamps at the bottom of each tag. They were marked “ET-26” followed by a number. For example, the first tag in the clipped-together stack was stamped “ET-26-000006.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ET” refers to the External Tank. Thelargest components of the space shuttle stack, the burnt orange or brown tanks were numbered, so 26 had to be one of the earlier missions of the 30-year, 135-flight program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fact sheet prepared by Lockheed Martin provided the answer. The company operated at the Michoud Assembly Facility near New Orleans, where the external tanks were built before being barged to the Kennedy Space Center for launch. Part of the sheet listed each launch with its date and numbered external tank. As my finger traced down the page, it came to STS 61-B, 11/26/85, ET-22; STS 61-C, 1/12/86, ET-30; and then STS 51-L, 1/28/86… ET-26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, the tags had no role in the loss ofChallengeror its crew, including commander Dick Scobee; pilot Mike Smith; mission specialists Ronald McNair, Judith Resnik, and Ellison Onizuka; payload specialist Gregory Jarvis; andTeacher-in-Space Christa McAuliffe. Although the structural failure of the external tank ultimately resulted inChallengerbreaking apart, it was a compromised O-ring seal in one of the shuttle’s two solid rocket boosters that allowed hot gas to burn through, impinging the tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, although it’s still unknown when the tags and their associated ground support equipment (e.g., protective covers, caps) were removed, it was not within hours of the launch, and in many cases, it was completed well before the vehicle reached the pad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were removed later in processing at different times but definitely all done before propellant loading,” said Mike Cianilli, the former manager of NASA’sApollo, Challenger, Columbia Lessons Learned Program. “To make sure they were gone, final walkdowns and closeouts by the ground crews confirmed removal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to NASA, approximately 20 percent of ET-26 was recovered from the ocean floor after the tragedy, and like the parts of the solid rocket boosters andChallenger, they were placed into storage in two retired missile silos at the Cape Canaveral Air Force Station (today, Space Force Station). Components removed from the vehicle before the ill-fated launch that were no longer needed likely went through the normal surplus processes as overseen by the General Services Administration, said Cianilli.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the tags’ association with STS-51L was confirmed, it no longer felt right to use them as giveaways. At least, not to individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are very few items directly connected toChallenger‘s last flight that museums and other public centers can use to connect their visitors to what transpired 40 years ago. NASA has placed only onepiece ofChallengeron public display, and that is in the exhibition “Forever Remembered” at the Kennedy Space Center Visitor Complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the 50 US states, the Smithsonian, and thepresident of the United Stateswere also presented with a smallAmerican flag and a mission patchthat had been aboardChallengerat the time of the tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a more complete history of these tags would help meet the accession requirements of some museums and, if approved, provide curators with the information they need to put the tags on display.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the tags were first identified, contacts at NASA and Lockheed, among others, were unable to explain how they ended up on eBay and, ultimately, with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was 2011, and the space shuttle program was coming to its end. I was politely told that this was not the time to ask about the tags, as documents were being moved into archives and, perhaps more importantly, people were more concerned about pending layoffs. One person suggested the tags be put back in a drawer and forgotten about for another decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the years since, other “Remove Before Flight” tags from other space shuttle missions have come up for sale. Some have included evidence that the tags had passed through the surplus procedures; some did not and were offered as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were anecdotes about outgoing employees taking home mementos. Maybe someone saw these tags heading out as scrap (or worse, being tossed in the garbage) and, recognizing what they were, saved them from being lost to history. An agent with the NASA Office of Inspector General once said that dumpster diving was not prohibited, so long as the item(s) being dived for were not metal (due to recycling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recent attempts to reach people who might know anything about the specific tags have been unsuccessful, other than the few details Cianilli was able to share. An attempt to recontact the eBay seller has so far gone unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you or someone you know worked on the external tank at the time of the STS-51L tragedy, or if you’re familiar with NASA’s practices regarding installing, retrieving, and archiving or disposing of the Remove Before Flight tags, pleaseget in contact.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/attached-to-tragedy-tracing-challenger-remove-before-flight-tags/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:07:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why reviving the shuttered Anthem is turning out tougher than expected</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/why-reviving-the-shuttered-anthem-is-turning-out-tougher-than-expected/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/anthem-1152x648-1769624814.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite proof-of-concept video, EA’s Frostbite Engine servers are difficult to pick apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On January 12, EAshut down the official servers forAnthem, making Bioware’s multiplayer sci-fi adventure completely unplayable for the first time sinceits troubled 2019 launch. Last week, though, theAnthemcommunity woke up toa new videoshowing the game at least partially loading on what appears to be a simulated background server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people behind that video—and theAnthemrevival project that made it possible—told Ars they were optimistic about their efforts to coerce EA’s temperamental Frostbite engine into running the game without access to EA’s servers. That said, the team also wants to temper expectations that may have risen a bit too high in the wake of what is just a proof-of-concept video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are getting excited [about the video], and naturally people are going to get their hopes up,” project administrator Laurie told Ars. “I don’t want to be the person that’s going to have to deal with the aftermath if it turns out that we can’t actually get anywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TheAnthemrevival effort currently centers aroundThe Fort’s Forge, a Discord server where a handful of volunteer engineers and developers have gathered to pick apart the game and its unique architecture. Laurie said they initially set up the group “out of little more than spite for EA and Bioware around the time the shutdown got announced” back in July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Laurie has some experience with the community behindGundam Evolutionrevival project Side 7, they knew they’d need help from people with direct experience working on EA’s Frostbite engine games. Luckily, Laurie said they were “able to catch the eyes of people who are familiar with this line of work [without] searching too much.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those people was Ness199X, an experienced Frostbite tinkerer who told Ars he “never really played muchAnthem” before the game’s shutdown was announced. When a friend pointed out the impending death of the title, though, Ness said he was motivated to preserve the game for posterity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial efforts to examine what madeAnthemtick “came up empty,” Ness said, largely because the game uses EA’s bespoke Frostbite engine differently than other EA titles. To begin mapping out those differences, Ness released a packet logger tool in September that let contributors record their own network traffic between the client and EA’s official servers. In addition to helping with reverse-engineering work, Ness writes on the Fort’s Forge Discord that players who logged their packets should be able to fully recover their characters if and whenAnthemcomes back in playable form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By analyzing that crowdsourced packet data, Ness said the Fort’s Forge team has been able to breakAnthemdown into three essential services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early efforts to emulate the Blaze and BIGS portions of that architecture helped lead directly to last week’s proof-of-concept video. Andersson799—who says he’s been tinkering withBattlefieldand other Frostbite games since 2015—said he was quickly able to use his own loggedAnthempackets to create a “barebones anthem private server” that served as a “quick and dirty” sample that he decided to share via YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I basically made the tool to just simply reply with the packet captures that I got,” Andersson told me. That was enough to “get in to the game with player profiles loaded and everything.” And while Ness says there’s still some effort needed “to [make Blaze and BIGS] work well and smoothly in terms of quest progression, etc.,” the path forward on those portions is relatively straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the Frostbite engine and its odd client-server architecture that forms the biggest barrier to gettingAnthemup and running again without EA’s servers. “Due to how Frostbite is designed, all gameplay in a Frostbite game runs in a ‘server’ context,” Ness explained. Even in a single-player game likeMass Effect: Andromeda, he said, “the client just creates a separate server thread and pipes all the traffic internally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I feel like withAnthem, it heavily relies on online data that was stored in Bioware’s server,” Andersson added. “In my initial testing, the game couldn’t load into the level without that data.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s some hope that this crucial level data is still available and recoverable, though. Ness points out that Fort Tarsis, the game’s lobby area, already runs using offline data piped through a local “server” thread, meaning the rest of the game could theoretically be coerced to run similarly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as important, he says, “as far as we have been able to discern, all the logic for the other levels, which when the game was live ran on a remote server, also exists in the client,” Ness said. “By patching the game we can most likely enable the ability to host these in process as well. That’s what we’re exploring.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While all that local level data should be usable in theory, seemingly random differences betweenAnthemand other Frostbite games are getting in the way of loading the data in practice.Anthemacts like a standard Frostbite game “for the most part,” Ness said, but at times will show unusual behaviors that are hard to pin down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For example, when we try to load most maps, no NPCs spawn, but in some maps they do,” he said. “And we have yet to determine why. Ness has some suspicion that the odd behavior is connected to the “fairly extensive amount of player data the game keeps as part of its online RPG nature,” but adds that “to be honest we’re not entirely sure how deep the differences go, other than that the engine didn’t behave how we expected it to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ness said he’s about 75 percent confident that the team will be able to figure out how to fully leverage the Frostbite engine to power a version of the game that runs without EA’s centralized servers. If that effort succeeds, he says a playable version ofAnthemcould be back up and running in “months, or less even, depending on motivation.” But if the efforts to pick apartAnthem’s take on Frostbite hits a brick wall, Ness says “the amount of work increases fairly exponentially and I’m a lot less confident that we have the motivation for that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m fairly confident that we can get this game to be playable again, like how it is supposed to be,” Andersson said. “It’ll just take time as most of us have our own life to manage besides this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Laurie is still trying to manage expectations set by the somewhat premature posting of Andersson’s proof-of-concept video. “Please, do not expect frequent updates,” Laurie wrote in the Fort’s Forge Discord. “We had not anticipated releasing anything this early, nor should the expedience of this video’s release serve as any kind of benchmark for how fast we make progress.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laurie alsotook to Redditto publicly call the video “a really hacky thing so I want to ask people to manage their expectations just a bit. A lot of stuff clearly doesn’t work as ‘intended,’ and definitely needs at minimum, more polish.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point last week, Laurie says they had to stop accepting new members to the Fort’s Forge Discord, “mostly to prevent an influx of people in response to… news coverage.” And while people with Frostbite engine modding experience are encouraged to reach out, the small team is being cautious about growing too large, too fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re a little reluctant to add developers right now as we have no real code base to work from,” Ness said, describing their current efforts as “scratch work” maintained in separate forms by multiple people. “But once we firm that up (hopefully in the next weeks), we will look to add more [coders].”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/why-reviving-the-shuttered-anthem-is-turning-out-tougher-than-expected/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:48:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>US cyber defense chief accidentally uploaded secret government info to ChatGPT</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/us-cyber-defense-chief-accidentally-uploaded-secret-government-info-to-chatgpt/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2202418998-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress recently grilled the acting chief on mass layoffs and a failed polygraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alarming critics, the acting director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA), Madhu Gottumukkala, accidentally uploaded sensitive information to a public version of ChatGPT last summer, Politicoreported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to “four Department of Homeland Security officials with knowledge of the incident,” Gottumukkala’s uploads of sensitive CISA contracting documents triggered multiple internal cybersecurity warnings designed to “stop the theft or unintentional disclosure of government material from federal networks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gottumukkala’s uploads happened soon after he joined the agency and sought special permission to use OpenAI’s popular chatbot, which most DHS staffers are blocked from accessing, DHS confirmed to Ars. Instead, DHS staffers use approved AI-powered tools, like the agency’s DHSChat, which “are configured to prevent queries or documents input into them from leaving federal networks,” Politico reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear why Gottumukkala needed to use ChatGPT. One official told Politico that, to staffers, it seemed like Gottumukkala “forced CISA’s hand into making them give him ChatGPT, and then he abused it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information Gottumukkala reportedly leaked was not confidential but marked “for official use only.” That designation, a DHSdocumentexplained, is “used within DHS to identify unclassified information of a sensitive nature” that, if shared without authorization, “could adversely impact a person’s privacy or welfare” or impede how federal and other programs “essential to the national interest” operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s now a concern that the sensitive information could be used to answer prompts from any of ChatGPT’s 700 million active users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI did not respond to Ars’ request to comment, but Cyber Newsreportedthat experts have warned “that using public AI tools poses real risks because uploaded data can be retained, breached, or used to inform responses to other users.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources told Politico that DHS investigated the incident for potentially harming government security—which could result in administrative or disciplinary actions, DHS officials told Politico. Possible consequences could range from a formal warning or mandatory retraining to “suspension or revocation of a security clearance,” officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, CISA’s director of public affairs, Marci McCarthy, declined Ars’ request to confirm if that probe, launched in August, has concluded or remains ongoing. Instead, she seemed to emphasize that Gottumukkala’s access to ChatGPT was only temporary, while suggesting that the ChatGPT use aligned with Donald Trump’sorderto deploy AI across government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Acting Director Dr. Madhu Gottumukkala was granted permission to use ChatGPT with DHS controls in place,” McCarthy said. “This use was short-term and limited. CISA is unwavering in its commitment to harnessing AI and other cutting-edge technologies to drive government modernization and deliver” on Trump’s order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gottumukkala has not had a smooth run as acting director of the top US cyber defense agency after Trump’s pick to helm the agency, Sean Plankey, was blocked by Sen. Rick Scott (R-Fla.) “over a Coast Guard shipbuilding contract,” Politico noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS Secretary Kristi Noem chose Gottumukkala to fill in after he previously served as her chief information officer, overseeing statewide cybersecurity initiatives in South Dakota. CISA celebrated his appointment with apress releaseboasting that he had more than 24 years of experience in information technology and a “deep understanding of both the complexities and practical realities of infrastructure security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, critics “on both sides of the aisle” have questioned whether Gottumukkala knows what he’s doing at CISA, Cyberscoopreported. That includes staffers who stayed on and staffers who prematurely left the agency due to uncertainty over its future, Politico reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 65 staffers have been curiously reassigned to other parts of DHS, Cyberscoop reported, inciting Democrat fears that CISA staffers are possibly being pushed over to Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same fate almost befell Robert Costello, CISA’s chief information officer, who was reportedly involved with meetings last August probing Gottumukkala’s improper ChatGPT use and “the proper handling of for official use only material,” Politico reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, staffers alleged that Gottumukkala took steps to remove Costello from his CIO position, which he has held for the past four years. But that plan was blocked after “other political appointees at the department objected,” Politicoreported. Until others intervened to permanently thwart the reassignment, Costello was supposedly given “roughly one week” to decide if he would take another position within DHS or resign, sources told Politico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gottumukkala has denied that he sought to reassign Costello over a personal spat that Politico’s sources said sprang from “friction because Costello frequently pushed back against Gottumukkala on policy matters.” He insisted that “senior personnel decisions are made at the highest levels at the Department of Homeland Security’s Headquarters and are not made in a vacuum, independently by one individual, or on a whim.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reported move looked particularly shady, though, because Costello “is seen as one of the agency’s top remaining technical talents,” Politico reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month,Congress grilled Gottumukkalaabout mass layoffs last year that shrank CISA from about 3,400 staffers to 2,400. The steep cuts seemed to threaten national security and election integrity, lawmakers warned, and potentially have left the agency unprepared for any potential conflicts with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a hearing held by the House Homeland Security Committee, Gottumukkala said that CISA was “getting back on mission” and plans to reverse much of the damage done last year to the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, some of his responses did not inspire confidence, including a failure to forecast “how many cyber intrusions CISA expects from foreign adversaries as part of the 2026 midterm elections,” the Federal News Networkreported. In particular, Rep. Tony Gonzales (R-Texas) criticized Gottumukkala for not having “a specific number in mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, we should have that number,” Gonzales said. “It should first start by how many intrusions that we had last midterm and the midterm before that. I don’t want to wait. I don’t want us waiting until after the fact to be able to go, ‘Yeah, we got it wrong, and it turns out our adversaries influenced our election to that point.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps notably, Gottumukkala also dodged questions about reports that hefailed a polygraphwhen attempting to seek access to other “highly sensitive cyber intelligence,” Politico reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The acting director apparently blamed six career CISA staffers for requesting that he agree to the polygraph test, which the staffers said was typical protocol but Gottumukkala later claimed was misleading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failing the test isn’t necessarily damning, since anxiety or technical errors could trigger a negative result. However, Gottumukkala appears touchy about the test that he now regrets sitting for, calling the test “unsanctioned” and refusing to discuss the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that Gottumukkala felt misled after learning that he could have requested a waiver to skip the polygraph. In a letter suspending those staffers’ security clearances, CISA accused staffs of showing “deliberate or negligent failure to follow policies that protect government information.” However, staffers may not have known that he had that option, which is considered a “highly unusual loophole that may not have been readily apparent to career staff,” Politico noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staffers told Politico that Gottumukkala’s tenure has been a “nightmare"—potentially ruining the careers of longtime CISA staffers. It troubles some that it seems that Gottumukkala will remain in his post “for the foreseeable future,” while seeming to politicize the agency and bungle protocols for accessing sensitive information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Nextgov,Gottumukkala plans to right the ship with “a hiring spree in 2026 because its recent reductions have hampered some of the Trump administration’s national security goals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in November, the trade publication, Cybersecurity Dive,reportedthat Gottumukkala sent out a memo confirming the hiring spree was coming that month, while warning that CISA remains “hampered by an approximately 40 percent vacancy rate across key mission areas.” All those cuts were “spurred by the administration’s animus toward CISA over its election security work,” Cybersecurity Dive noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“CISA must immediately accelerate recruitment, workforce development, and retention initiatives to ensure mission readiness and operational continuity,” Gottumukkala told staffers at that time, then later went on to reassure Congress this month that the agency has “the required staff” to protect election integrity and national security, Cyberscoop reported.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/us-cyber-defense-chief-accidentally-uploaded-secret-government-info-to-chatgpt/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:56:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Angry Norfolk residents lose lawsuit to stop Flock license plate scanners</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/angry-norfolk-residents-lose-lawsuit-to-stop-flock-license-plate-scanners/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Flock-camera-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plaintiffs called Norfolk’s Flock camera network a “dragnet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in VirginiaruledTuesday that the City of Norfolk’s use of nearly 200 automated license plate readers (ALPRs) from Flock is constitutional and can continue, dismissing the entire case just days before a bench trial was set to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case,Schmidt v. City of Norfolk, wasoriginally filed in October 2024by two Virginians who claimed that their rights were violated when the Flock network of cameras captured their cars hundreds of times, calling the entire setup a “dragnet surveillance program.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in a51-page ruling, US District Court Judge Mark S. Davis disagreed, finding that the “…plaintiffs are unable to demonstrate that Defendants’ ALPR system is capable of tracking the whole of a person’s movements.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Davis acknowledged that while there may come a time when the use of ALPRs becomes too intrusive, “what is readily apparent to this Court is that, at least in Norfolk, Virginia, the answer is: not today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Virginia plaintiffs were represented by attorneys from the Institute of Justice, a libertarian nonprofit public interest law firmthat vowed to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decade, Flock Safety has grown to become the most sophisticated and largest ALPR vendor in America. The City of Norfolk—along with thousands of other law enforcement agencies across the country—contracts with the Atlanta-based startup, most recentlyvalued at $7.5 billion, for ALPR services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flock cameras capture not just a simple license plate number—as the tech once did a decade ago—but now can easily capture make, model, and other visual details from each car; these can be searched usingAI-powered natural language queriesthat can include phrases like “bike rack” or “tow truck.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, some jurisdictions, fromSanta Cruz, California,toCharlottesville, Virginia,have ended their contracts with Flock over concerns that the technology is too invasive and may provide information to federal immigration authorities over the objections of local policymakers. Last year,two senators expressed grave privacy concerns and wrote in a letterto the company that “abuse of Flock cameras is inevitable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his Thursday ruling, Judge Davis referenced the family tree of modern surveillance case-law, noting that a 1983 Supreme Court case (Knotts v. United States) found that there is no “reasonable expectation of privacy” when traveling on a public road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That 1983 case, which centered on a radio transmitter that enabled law enforcement to follow the movements of alleged drug traffickers driving between Minnesota and Wisconsin, has provided the legal underpinning for the use of ALPR technology in the United States over the last few decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Modern-day license plate reader systems, like Norfolk’s, are nothing like [the technology of the early 1980s],” Michael Soyfer, one of the Institute of Justice attorneys, told Ars by email. “They track the movements of virtually every driver within a city for weeks at a time. That can reveal a host of insights not captured in any single trip.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For its part, Flock Safety celebrated the ruling and wroteon its websitethat its clients may continue to use the cameras.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here, the court emphasized that LPR technology, as deployed in Norfolk, is meaningfully different from systems that enable persistent, comprehensive tracking of individuals’ movements,” the company wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When used with appropriate limitations and safeguards, LPRs do not provide an intimate portrait of a person’s life and therefore do not trigger the constitutional concerns raised by continuous surveillance,” it added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some legal scholars disagree with both the judge’s and Flock’s conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Ferguson, a law professor at George Washington University and the author of the forthcoming bookYour Data Will Be Used Against You: Policing in the Age of Self-Surveillance, told Ars by email that the judge’s ruling here is “understandably conservative and dangerous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The danger is that the same reasoning that there is no expectation of privacy in public would justify having ALPR cameras on every single street corner,” he continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Further,” he said, “looking at the technology as a mere tool, rather than a system of surveillance, misses the mark on its erosion of privacy. Think how revealing ALPRs would be outside religious institutions, gun ranges, medical clinics, addiction treatment centers, or protests.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/angry-norfolk-residents-lose-lawsuit-to-stop-flock-license-plate-scanners/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:06:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>SpaceX sends list of demands to US states giving broadband grants to Starlink</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/starlink-demands-grant-money-from-states-even-when-residents-dont-buy-service/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/starlink-snow-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX won’t make specific promises on Starlink network capacity or subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX has made a new set of demands on state governments that would ensure Starlink receives federal grant money even when residents don’t purchase Starlink broadband service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX said it will provide “all necessary equipment” to receive broadband “at no cost to subscribers requesting service,” which will apparently eliminate the up-front hardware fee for Starlink equipment. But SpaceX isn’t promising lower-than-usual monthly prices to consumers in those subsidized areas. SpaceX pledged to make broadband available for $80 or less a month, plus taxes and fees, to people with low incomes in the subsidized areas. For comparison, the normal Starlink residential prices advertised on itswebsiterange from $50 to $120 a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s demands would also guarantee that it gets paid by the government even if it doesn’t reserve “large portions” of Starlink network capacity for homes in the areas that are supposed to receive government-subsidized Internet service. Moreover, SpaceX would not be responsible for ensuring that Starlink equipment is installed correctly at each customer location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX sent a letter to state broadband offices proposing a rider with terms that it hopes will be applied to all grants it receives throughout the country. The letter was obtained and published byBroadband.ioand theBenton Institute for Broadband &amp; Society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguing that SpaceX should receive grant money regardless of whether residents purchase Starlink service, theletterto states said that grant payments should not depend on “the independent purchasing decisions of users.” SpaceX also said it will not hold “large portions of capacity fallow” to ensure that people in subsidized areas receive good service, but will instead continue its preexisting practice of “dynamically allocat[ing] capacity where needed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’sproposed contract riderwould apply to grants distributed under the US government’s Broadband Equity, Access, and Deployment (BEAD) program. BEAD was created by Congress in a 2021 law that authorized spending over $42 billion to make broadband networks available in areas without modern service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Biden administration designed the program to prioritize fiber deployments, the Trump administration threw out the previous plans. Under Trump, the National Telecommunications and Information Administration (NTIA) deemed the Biden-era plan too costly and changed the rules to make it easier for satellite services to obtain grant funding. The overhaul cut projected spending toabout $21 billion,and it’s still not clear what will happen to the other $21 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starlinksought billions in grantsafter the new rules were put in place, but states didn’t want to provide that much. So far, SpaceX isslated to receive$733.5 million to offer broadband at 472,600 locations. Amazon’s Leo satellite service (formerly Kuiper) is set to receive $311 million for 415,000 locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While not every state plan is final, it looks like satellite networks will get about 5 percent of the grant money and serve over 22 percent of locations funded by grants. Satellite companies are getting smaller payments on a per-location basis because, unlike fiber providers, they don’t have to install infrastructure at each customer’s location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concessions sought by SpaceX “would limit Starlink’s performance obligations, payment schedules, non-compliance penalties, reporting expectations, and labor and insurance standards,” wrote Drew Garner, director of policy engagement at the Benton Institute. Garner argued that SpaceX’s demands illustrate problems in how the Trump NTIA rewrote program rules to increase reliance on low-Earth orbit (LEO) satellite providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“BEAD was designed primarily to deploy terrestrial networks, which are physically located in communities, built with traditional construction methods, and are relatively easy to monitor and inspect,” Garner wrote. “But, on June 6, 2025,NTIA restructured BEADin ways that greatly increased participation by LEO providers, exacerbating the challenge of applying BEAD’s terrestrial-focused rules to LEO’s extraterrestrial networks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among other things, SpaceX is trying to “minimize states’ ability to penalize LEO grantees for defaulting or failing to comply with contract requirements,” and avoid having “to report on the use of BEAD funds or other financial information related to the grant,” Garner wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s letter said that “all requirements related to labor issues (e.g., prevailing wage and similar obligations), contractors, and procurement are inapplicable to SpaceX” because “there are no identifiable employees, contractors, or contracts being funded” to support Starlink broadband service in each state. Similarly, “there are no identifiable pieces of SpaceX infrastructure equipment (other than satellite capacity delivered from Space) being funded via BEAD,” the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear whether SpaceX will turn down grants if it doesn’t get what it wants. We asked the company for information on its plans if states refuse its terms and will update this article if we get a response. SpaceX’s proposed terms could also be applied to Amazon if states accept them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s letter said that despite the Trump administration’s changes to BEAD, “a number of issues remain that, if unaddressed, could render LEO participation in the program untenable.” SpaceX said it wants to work with states “to more fully tailor aspects of the project agreement to the reality of LEO deployment and operations now that the initial project selection and approval phase is accomplished.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space said it wants to avoid extensive negotiations over its proposed terms. But the acknowledgement that some negotiation may be necessary seems to recognize that states don’t have to comply with the demands:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward this goal, we have developed a set of terms that we intend to function as a rider to all subgrant agreements across the country. This rider is intentionally limited in scope to addressing items of critical importance, to minimize the need for negotiation, and provide clarity to both parties moving forward. Our intention is for the LEO rider to enable the state to keep its core subgrant agreement relatively uniform amongst grantees, retain state-law-specific requirements, co-locate all relevant LEO-specific material for ease of administration, and standardize agreements across states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s proposed contract rider said the firm will offer broadband plans for “a monthly cost of $80 or less before applicable taxes and fees” to households that meet the low-income eligibility guidelines used by the FCC’s Lifeline program. People who don’t qualify for low-income plans would presumably pay regular Starlink rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BEAD law requires ISPs receiving federal funds to offer at least one “low-cost broadband service option for eligible subscribers.” While the Biden administration sought low-income plans that costas little as $30 a month, the Trump administration decided that statesmay not tell ISPswhat prices to charge in their low-cost options. A Trump administration threat to shut states out of BEAD if they required low pricesdoomed a California proposalto mandate $15 monthly plans for people with low incomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX told state governments that it should receive 50 percent of grant funds when it certifies that it is capable of providing BEAD-quality service (100Mbps download and 20Mbps upload speeds) within 10 business days to any potential customer that requests it in a grant area. The rest of the money would be distributed quarterly over the 10-year period of the grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explaining why SpaceX shouldn’t be penalized if potential customers decide Starlink prices are too high, the firm wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tying payments to the independent purchasing decisions of users solely for awardees using LEO technologies, and not for any other technology, is, by definition, not technology neutral. SpaceX is already appropriately incentivized to gather customers by the opportunity to capture the monthly recurring revenue from each subscriber. SpaceX was in most instances awarded the most remote and difficult areas to serve among all other providers. SpaceX is up to the task of ensuring success in these challenging areas, however, it cannot undertake this mission without certainty of consistent payments to compensate such work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on SpaceX’s letter, it sounds like the work the company must do to ensure quality of service at BEAD-funded locations is the same work it has already done to make Starlink available across the US. Instead of dedicated capacity for government-subsidized deployments, SpaceX said it will simply factor the needs of BEAD users into its planning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With respect to capacity reservations, we have found some confusion regarding how such a reservation is made. Given the dynamic nature of the Starlink network, the reservation will not be such that SpaceX holds large portions of capacity fallow. This would be wasteful, inefficient, and does not reflect a LEO providers [sic] ability to dynamically allocate capacity where needed. Instead, SpaceX will include the capacity needs of BEAD users into its network planning efforts. These activities are multifaceted and include real time capacity allocation at the network level, launch activities, and sales efforts. As a result, there is no single “document” evidencing the reservation of capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX said it will be obvious if it does not provide sufficient service, and thus the states should not seek additional performance testing beyond what’s included in the NTIA guidelines. “If sufficient capacity was not reserved, performance testing will reveal insufficient quality of service, and this deficiency will be transparent to the state. Developing a separate, indirect measurement of the reservation itself is infeasible and unnecessary,” SpaceX said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed rider said that any network testing must “exclude subscribers who have installed CPE [consumer premise equipment] such that its view of the sky is obstructed and subscribers with damaged or malfunctioning CPE, as determined by GRANTEE.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “as determined by GRANTEE” phrase means it’s up to SpaceX to decide which subscribers should be excluded from testing. As the Benton Society says, the rider stipulates that “performance tests can only be considered if the LEO provider determines that the subscriber’s equipment is properly installed, and, notably, the LEO provider is not obligated to ensure proper installation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s proposed rider defines a “standard installation” as the mailing of equipment to a subscriber. That’s the standard process for un-subsidized areas throughout the country, and SpaceX doesn’t want to do any extra work to help set up equipment for customers in subsidized areas. However, customers may be able to purchase professional installation for an extra fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For the avoidance of doubt, the GRANTEE will not be responsible for completing a permanent installation” at each location, SpaceX’s proposed rider says. A satellite provider “may choose to offer the subscriber professional services for permanent installation of CPE at an additional fee, but such professional services shall not be considered part of the standard installation,” it says.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/starlink-demands-grant-money-from-states-even-when-residents-dont-buy-service/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:02:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Stranded boys struggle to survive in Lord of the Flies trailer</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/bbcs-lord-of-the-flies-miniseries-gets-a-trailer/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/flies1-1152x648-1769625327.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We need to think about food and shelter. We need to help each other and be good camp mates.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BBC One has adapted William Golding’s classic 1954 novelLord of the Fliesinto anew miniseriesand just dropped the first trailer. The book has been adapted for film three times since its publication and also inspired the Emmy-nominated TV seriesYellowjackets(renewed for its fourth and final season this year). This BBC miniseries apparently has the support of the Golding family and is expected to hew quite closely to the novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Spoilers for the 1954 novelbelow.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Golding was inspired to writeLord of the Fliesby a popular, pro-colonialism children’s novel calledThe Coral Island, whose central theme was the civilizing influence of British colonial efforts and Christianity on a “savage” people. Golding wanted to write a book about children on an island who “behave the way children really would behave.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;InLord of the Flies, a British airplane evacuating a group of young boys from war-torn England crashes on an isolated, uninhabited island. A boy named Ralph finds a conch shell and uses it as a horn, commanding enough respect for the boys to look to him as their chief. Initially, Ralph’s leadership helps the stranded boys establish sufficient order to survive and keep a signal fire going, thanks to the lenses in Piggy’s glasses. But that tenuous order soon begins to fray, with the community splitting into two tribes, the second led by the wilder Jack. Violence inevitably breaks out, resulting in the deaths of two of the boys. Eventually, the survivors are rescued by a British naval ship, and the boys are forced to confront the “end of innocence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lord of the Flieshas remained relevant ever since its publication as a cautionary, if cynical, tale about how social hierarchies can break down into tribal violence, although it should be noted that a real 1965 incident with stranded Tongan boys exemplified the exact opposite effect.Lord of the Fliesis a novel, not a sociological treatise. But its broad cultural influence is undeniable. Stephen King even named his fictional town of Castle Rock, Maine, after Jack’s mountain camp inLord of the Flies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winston Sawyers stars as Ralph in the BBC miniseries, with Lox Pratt playing Jack and David McKenna playing Piggy. The cast also includes Ike Talbot as Simon; Thomas Connor as Roger; Noah Flemyng as Sam; Cassius Flemyng as Eric; Cornelius Brandreth as Maurice; Tom Page-Turner as Bill;’ Rafael de Belligny as Robert; Freddie Lee-Gray as Percival; Beau Thompson as Philip; Fred Jones as Johnny;  and Lake Coleman as Boy with Birthmark. In addition, more than 20 other young boys were cast (many with no acting experience) to play the camp’s “big ‘uns” and “little ‘uns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lord of the Fliesdebuts in the UK on BBC One on February 8, 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/bbcs-lord-of-the-flies-miniseries-gets-a-trailer/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:37:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Seven things to know about how Apple’s Creator Studio subscriptions work</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/seven-things-to-know-about-how-apples-creator-studio-subscriptions-work/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/Screenshot-2026-01-28-at-4.09.33-PM-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the Mac versions of pro apps, things aren’t actually changing much (yet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’snew Creator Studio subscription bundleofficiallylaunches today, offering access to a wide range of updated professional apps for an all-or-nothing price of $13 a month or $130 a year. Teachers and students can get the same apps for $3 a month, or $30 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bundle includes either access to or enhanced features for a total of 10 Apple apps, though the base versions of several of these are available for free to all Mac and iPad owners:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When companies introduce a subscription-based model for long-standing apps with an established user base, they often shiftexclusivelyto a subscription model, offering continuous updates in return for a more consistent revenue stream. But these aren’t always popular with subscription-fatigued users, who have seen virtually all major paid software shift to a subscription model in the last 10 or 15 years, and who in recent years have had to deal with prices that arecontinuouslybeingratcheted upward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple’s subscription shift looks a little less like Adobe’s approach to Photoshop and a little more like Microsoft’s approach to Office: many of these apps, particularly the Mac versions, will remain available for free or as standalone one-time purchases from the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In lieu of running through each of these apps’ new features one by one, we’ve gathered answers to some questions about how the new subscriptions will work and how they’ll compare to the standalone versions of the apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple still offers Mac App Store versions of the following apps as one-time purchases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve already bought those apps from the Mac App Store at any point in the past, you’ll still have access to them, and they’ll be updated to the current versions at no charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mac users are generally pretty well taken care of here, current iPad users of Final Cut Pro or Logic are getting the short end of the stick. When those apps wereinitially introduced on the iPad, they cost $5 per app per month, or $50 per year per app. Those standalone subscriptions appear to have been axed with the introduction of the Creator Studio bundle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside of Apple’s all-or-nothing pricing is that the bundle is only a great value if you actually intend to use multiple apps on multiple platforms regularly. People who are already splitting their time between the Mac and the iPad and using more than one of these apps will get a lot of value for their money; anyone who just wants to run Final Cut Pro on their iPad is looking at a big price hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is “yes, the standalone versions of these apps will generally be updated in lockstep with the Creator Studio versions.” But Apple is taking slightly different approaches depending on the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the Apple Creator Studio apps are brand-new versions with new version numbers: Final Cut Pro jumpsfrom version 11 to version 12, for example, and Keynote, Pages, and Numbers (apps I still think of collectively as “iWork” despite that name beingwell over a decade out of date) are being bumped from version 14 to version 15.Apple’s Creator Studio support documentlists all of the new version numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the paid apps, these new versions will be downloaded and installed just as previous Mac App Store updates have been. The standalone Final Cut Pro, Logic Pro, Compressor, Motion, and MainStage apps have already been updated to the new version numbers, and installing any of them will pull down the latest version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the standalone version of Pixelmator Pro is still listed as the old version, 3.7.1, while the new version 4.0 requires a Creator Studio subscription. It’s not clear whether that’s going to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for Keynote, Pages, and Numbers, the iOS and iPadOS versions of the new apps will be seamlessly installed in place of the old apps. But it’s being handled slightly differently on the Mac for some reason. All three apps now have two versions listed in the app store: theold ones, set at version 14.5, andthe new ones, set at 15.1. Installing the 14.5 update, which was released today, adds a prompt when you launch the old apps, informing you that they’re out of date and that you should install the new ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can have both the standalone and Creator Studio versions of all apps installed on their devices at the same time. You’ll be able to tell both versions apart using their icons—the standalone apps keep the same icons they had before, and the Creator Studio versions get theoccasionally controversialhigh-contrast Liquid Glass-ified redesigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you can also tell the versions of the apps apart by their App Store listings. The standalone ones are just referred to by their names (i.e., “Final Cut Pro,” “Logic Pro”) while the new ones have more modern obnoxious search-optimized titles (“Final Cut Pro: Create Video,” “Logic Pro: Make Music,” “Keynote: Design Presentations”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brightest dividing line between the standalone and Creator Studio apps is for the free ones, Keynote, Pages, and Numbers. All three look the same whether you have an active subscription or not, but the free versions will prompt you to upgrade to Creator Studio any time you attempt to use “premium” features, which as of this writing includes document templates and generative AI features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Creator Studio subscription is also required to access the “Content Hub,” a library of stock images available only in the Pages, Numbers, and Keynote apps (at least for now; they should also be available in Freeform “later this year”). Apple may expand the Content Hub with video and audio content suitable for Final Cut Pro or Logic at some point in the future, but it’s not something the company is offering right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least as of this writing, the paid standalone Mac apps don’t appear to be missing any major features relative to the Creator Studio versions. There’s no way to know whether this will change except to wait and see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Apple Creator Studio subscription can be shared among up to six Apple accounts using Family Sharing, potentially defraying the cost of the subscription further. This only applies to the standard version of the subscription; education subscriptions can’t be shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple accounts attached to an active subscription can install the apps on up to 10 devices simultaneously. This is a relatively generous allotment compared toAdobe’s Creative Cloud, which just allows installation on two devices at once and only allows the apps to be used on a single system at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple outlines detailed system requirements for each app on its support pagehere. For most of the Mac apps, all you need is a Mac running macOS 15.6 Sequoia or later; the only Mac app that requires macOS 26 Tahoe is Pixelmator Pro. Most of the apps will also run on either Intel or Apple Silicon Macs, though MainStage is Apple Silicon-exclusive, and “some features” in Compressor may also require Apple Silicon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requirements for the iPad apps are a little more restrictive; you generally need to be running either iPadOS 18.6 or iPadOS 26, and both Final Cut Pro and Pixelmator Pro either want an Apple M1, an Apple A16, or an Apple A17 Pro (in other words, it will work on every iPad Apple currently sells, but older iPad hardware is more hit or miss).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple also outlines a number of usage restrictions for the generative AI features that rely on external services. Apple says that, “at a minimum,” users will be able to generate 50 images, 50 presentations of between 8 to 10 slides each, and to generate presenter notes in Keynote for 700 slides. More usage may be possible, but this depends on “the complexity of the queries, server availability, and network availability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These AI features are all based on OpenAI technology, but don’t require users to have their own OpenAI or ChatGPT account (the flip side is that if you already pay for ChatGPT, that won’t benefit you here). Apple also says that the content you use to generate images, presentations, or notes “will never be used to train intelligence models.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three major creative apps that Apple offers that haven’t been bundled into Creator Studio, and also haven’t gotten a major new update: iMovie, GarageBand, and Photomator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are extenuating circumstances that explain why these three apps haven’t been given a Creator Studio-style overhaul. The iMovie and GarageBand apps have always sort of been positioned as “lite” free-to-use versions of Final Cut Pro and Logic Pro, respectively, while Photomator is a recently acquired app that overlaps somewhat with the built-in Photos app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple has nothing to share about the future of any of the three apps. Both iMovie and Photomator received minor updates today, presumably related to maintaining compatibility with the Creator Studio apps, and GarageBand was last updated a month ago. Expect them to stick around in their current forms for at least a while.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/seven-things-to-know-about-how-apples-creator-studio-subscriptions-work/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:53:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Site catering to online criminals has been seized by the FBI</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/site-catering-to-online-criminals-has-been-seized-by-the-fbi/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/network-outage.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the last holdouts for ransomware discussions, RAMP is taken down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAMP—the predominantly Russian-language online bazaar that billed itself as the “only place ransomware allowed”—had its dark web and clear web sites seized by the FBI as the agency tries to combat the growing scourge threatening critical infrastructure and organizations around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visits to both sites on Wednesday returned pages that said the FBI had taken control of the RAMP domains, which mirrored each other. RAMP has been among the dwindling number of online crime forums to operate with impunity, following the takedown of other forums such as XSS, which saw its leader arrestedlast yearby Europol. The vacuum left RAMP as one of the leading places for people pushing ransomware and other online threats to buy, sell, or trade products and services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Federal Bureau of Investigation has seized RAMP,” a banner carrying the seals of the FBI and the Justice Department said. “This action has been taken in coordination with the United States Attorney’s Office for the Southern District of Florida and the Computer Crime and Intellectual Property Section of the Department of Justice.” The banner included a graphic that appeared on the RAMP site, before it was seized, that billed itself as the “only place ransomware allowed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RAMP was founded in 2012 and rebranded in 2021,according tosecurity firm Rapid 7. The platform served Russian, Chinese, and English speakers and counted more than 14,000 registered users, who underwent strict vetting before being accepted or paid a $500 fee for anonymous participation. The forum provided discussion groups, cyberattack tutorials, and a marketplace for malware and services. Its chief administrator said in 2024 the site earned $250,000 annually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a message posted to a rebranded XSS site, a purported RAMP member announced the shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Translated from Russian, the post read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Closure of the Ramp forum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all those concerned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regret to inform you that the police authorities have taken control of the Ramp forum. This event has destroyed years of my work building the freest forum in the world, and while I hoped this day would never come, I always knew in my heart it was possible. It’s a risk we all take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I no longer manage Ramp and will not be creating a new forum from scratch, I will continue to purchase access. My main business remains unchanged…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good luck to everyone, take care of yourselves and your loved ones,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stallman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no word of arrests or detentions of any RAMP operators or users. The seizure notice invited people to submit tips through the FBI’s IC3 portal. US authorities have yet to release a statement mentioning the takedown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DNS records show that servers resolving the RAMP domain now belong to the FBI. It’s not known if the agents now have access to user databases and other sensitive site information. If so, site users who weren’t careful may be tracked down by law enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/site-catering-to-online-criminals-has-been-seized-by-the-fbi/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:06:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tesla: 2024 was bad, 2025 was worse as profit falls 46 percent</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/2025-sees-teslas-annual-revenue-fall-for-the-first-time/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2205801667-2560x1440.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half its profit came from emissions credits as sales fell 8.6 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tesla published its financial results for 2025 this afternoon.If 2024 was a bad yearfor the electric automaker, 2025 was far worse: For the first time in Tesla’s history, revenues fell year over year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Tesla revealed its sales and production numbers for the fourth quarter of 2025, with a 16 percent decline compared to Q4 2024. Now we know the cost of those lost sales: Automotive revenues fell by 11 percent to $17.7 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happily for Tesla, double-digit growth in its energy storage business ($3.8 billion, an increase of 25 percent) and services ($3.4 billion, an increase of 18 percent) made up some of the shortfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although total revenue for the quarter fell by 3 percent, Tesla’s operating profits grew by 20 percent. But declining income from operations, which also got much more expensive, saw Tesla’s net profit plummet 61 percent, to $840 million. Without the $542 million from regulatory credits, things would have looked even bleaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selling 1,636,129 cars in 2025 generated $69.5 billion in revenue, 10 percent less than Tesla’s 2024 revenue. But storage and energy increased 27 percent year over year to $12.7 billion, and services grew by 19 percent year over year to $12.5 billion. Together, these two divisions now contribute meaningful amounts to the business, unlike just a few short years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, total revenues for 2025 only fell by 3 percent. But Tesla saw a 38 percent drop in income from operations, and its expenses went up by 23 percent. As a result, the company’s once-envied profit margin was just 4.9 percent for the year, down from 7.2 percent last year. (In 2022, Tesla had a 23.8 percent profit margin.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, its $3.8 billion net profit for the year was a reduction of 46 percent compared to 2024. Tesla blames falling sales and lower regulatory credits for its decreased revenue and falling profits, despite those regulatory credits contributing $2 billion—52 percent of its annual net profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were few specifics in the outlook section ofTesla’s presentationto its investors. It claims that this year will see volume production of its two-seat Cybercab robotaxi, the long-delayed Tesla Semi class 8 truck, and its next Megabuck energy storage system. Tesla also says it expects its investment in AI to start contributing to its annual profit, although elsewhere in the presentation, we learned that the company recently agreed to invest $2 billion into xAI, thedeepfake-andCSAM-generatingcompany owned by Tesla CEO Elon Musk.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/cars/2026/01/2025-sees-teslas-annual-revenue-fall-for-the-first-time/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:28:19 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>