<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Ars Technica Bilingual Feed</title><link>https://feeds.arstechnica.com/arstechnica/index</link><description>Ars Technica articles translated into Korean</description><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:36:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Telly’s “free” ad-based TVs make notable revenue—when they’re actually delivered (텔리의 "무료" 광고 기반 TV, 실제 배송 시 주목할 만한 수익 창출)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/652fa4f61e054d1c335ce241_Rectangle_20180_203.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LA startup said it would ship “millions” of TVs by 2024.&lt;br/&gt;(LA의 스타트업은 2024년까지 "수백만 대"의 TV를 배송할 것이라고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly , a company that accepts advertising data instead of cash for its TVs, has reportedly had a hard time getting its “free” TVs into people’s homes.&lt;br/&gt;(현금 대신 광고 데이터를 수집하는 방식으로 TV를 제공하는 회사 텔리는, 사람들의 집에 "무료" TV를 배송하는 데 어려움을 겪고 있는 것으로 알려졌습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly debuted in May 2023. Its dual-screen design can show ads, even when people aren’t watching. Although the smaller, secondary screen can be used for more helpful applications, like showing the weather or sports scores, its primary purpose is to serve as a billboard south of the 55-inch primary display. Owners cannot disable tracking or cover up the secondary screen (or they have to pay for the TV, which Telly claims is worth $1,000), and they must fill out a lengthy, detailed survey to get one.&lt;br/&gt;(텔리는 2023년 5월에 데뷔했습니다. 이중 화면 디자인으로, 사람들이 시청하지 않을 때도 광고를 표시할 수 있습니다. 더 작은 보조 화면은 날씨나 스포츠 점수와 같은 유용한 애플리케이션에 사용될 수 있지만, 주된 목적은 55인치 주 디스플레이 아래에 광고판 역할을 하는 것입니다. 소유자는 추적을 비활성화하거나 보조 화면을 가릴 수 없으며(그렇게 하려면 텔리가 1,000달러의 가치가 있다고 주장하는 TV 비용을 지불해야 함), TV를 받으려면 길고 상세한 설문조사를 작성해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it debuted its TV, Telly said it expected to ship 500,000 devices that summer. In June 2023, the startup said 250,000 people signed up to get a Telly. In a 2024 press release , Telly said that it planned to ship “millions more in 2024.”&lt;br/&gt;(TV를 출시했을 때, 텔리는 그해 여름까지 50만 대의 기기를 배송할 것으로 예상했습니다. 2023년 6월, 이 스타트업은 25만 명이 텔리 TV 신청을 했다고 밝혔습니다. 2024년 보도 자료에서 텔리는 "2024년에 수백만 대를 더 배송할 계획"이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a report from Lowpass this week, citing a “Q3 update sent to investors in November 2025,” said the startup had 35,000 TVs in people’s homes at that time. In Q2 2025, there were 28,000 Telly TVs in use, the note said, according to Lowpass.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 로우패스의 이번 주 보도에 따르면, "2025년 11월 투자자에게 발송된 3분기 업데이트"를 인용하여, 당시 스타트업이 가정에 배치된 TV는 3만5천 대에 불과했다고 합니다. 로우패스에 따르면, 해당 메모는 2025년 2분기 기준 사용 중인 텔리 TV는 2만8천 대였다고 전했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The publication reported that the investor note suggests Telly will order 100,000 TVs from supplier Foxconn and increase deliveries soon.&lt;br/&gt;(해당 매체는 투자자 메모가 텔리가 공급업체 폭스콘으로부터 10만 대의 TV를 주문하고 배송을 곧 늘릴 것임을 시사한다고 보도했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly declined to comment to Lowpass and didn’t respond to Ars Technica’s requests for comment.&lt;br/&gt;(텔리는 로우패스의 논평 요청을 거부했으며, 아스 테크니카의 논평 요청에도 응답하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what gives? Based on early registration numbers, it seems Telly has generated enough interest to ship more than 35,000 TVs.&lt;br/&gt;(그렇다면 문제는 무엇일까요? 초기 등록 수치를 기반으로 볼 때, 텔리는 3만5천 대 이상의 TV를 배송할 만큼 충분한 관심을 끌었던 것으로 보입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue seems to be poor shipping. Per the investor note that Lowpass reviewed, Telly claimed that FedEx delivered 10 percent of its shipments of Telly TVs broken. Since moving to a different company—seemingly Samsung partner RXO , based on Reddit posts —fewer Tellys are arriving broken, the company reportedly said.&lt;br/&gt;(한 가지 문제는 불량 배송으로 보입니다. 로우패스가 검토한 투자자 메모에 따르면, 텔리는 페덱스가 배송한 텔리 TV의 10%가 파손된 상태로 도착했다고 주장했습니다. 다른 회사(레딧 게시물에 따르면 삼성 파트너사 RXO로 보임)로 변경한 이후 파손된 텔리 TV 도착 수가 줄었다고 회사는 보고했다고 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Lowpass noted, dozens of online complaints claim that the free TVs, which ship directly from Telly, were broken upon arrival. The Verge also reported receiving a broken unit in September.&lt;br/&gt;(로우패스가 지적했듯이, 텔리에서 직접 배송되는 무료 TV가 도착 시 파손되었다는 수십 건의 온라인 불만이 제기되었습니다. 더 버지 또한 9월에 파손된 제품을 수령했다고 보도했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the subreddit dedicated to Telly TVs seems to show numerous other technical difficulties Telly users are experiencing. Technical complaints are common on subreddits for tech gadgets, but the forum highlights the problems Telly owners might encounter.&lt;br/&gt;(현재, 텔리 TV 전용 서브레딧에는 텔리 사용자들이 경험하는 수많은 다른 기술적 문제점들이 나타나는 것으로 보입니다. 기술 기기 서브레딧에 기술적 불만은 흔하지만, 해당 포럼은 텔리 소유자가 마주할 수 있는 문제점들을 부각시킵니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telly’s reported failure to meet its high shipment goals or even fulfill reported demand demonstrates the scaling complexities startups can face. While some companies struggle to get people interested in their product, Telly’s “free” pitch has been successful enough to lure thousands. But in its early stages, Telly has reportedly struggled with its direct-to-consumer model and smaller team compared to other TV makers.&lt;br/&gt;(텔리가 높은 배송 목표를 달성하지 못하거나 보고된 수요조차 충족시키지 못했다는 보도는 스타트업이 직면할 수 있는 확장의 복잡성을 보여줍니다. 일부 회사들은 제품에 대한 관심을 끌기 위해 고군분투하는 반면, 텔리의 "무료" 제안은 수천 명을 유치할 만큼 성공적이었습니다. 그러나 초기 단계에서 텔리는 다른 TV 제조사에 비해 직접 소비자 판매 모델과 소규모 팀으로 어려움을 겪은 것으로 알려졌습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Telly’s ad-centric business model may be starting to show its value. The investor update reportedly said Telly made $22 million in annualized revenue in Q3 2025. This could equate to about $52 in advertising revenue per Telly in use per month ($22 million divided by 35,000 TVs divided by 12 months in a year is $52.38).&lt;br/&gt;(그럼에도 불구하고, 텔리의 광고 중심 비즈니스 모델은 가치를 보이기 시작했을 수 있습니다. 투자자 업데이트에 따르면 텔리는 2025년 3분기에 연간 기준 2,200만 달러의 수익을 올렸다고 합니다. 이는 사용 중인 텔리 TV 한 대당 월 약 52달러의 광고 수익에 해당할 수 있습니다(2,200만 달러 ÷ 3만5천 대 ÷ 1년 12개월 = 52.38달러).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s notably more than what other TV companies report, as Lowpass pointed out. As a comparison to other budget TV brands that rely heavily on ads and user tracking, Roku reported an average revenue per user (ARPU) of $41.49 for 2024. Vizio, meanwhile, reported an ARPU of $37.17 in 2024.&lt;br/&gt;(로우패스가 지적했듯이, 이는 다른 TV 회사들이 보고하는 것보다 현저히 높은 수치입니다. 광고와 사용자 추적에 크게 의존하는 다른 저가 TV 브랜드와 비교해 보면, 로쿠는 2024년 사용자당 평균 수익(ARPU)이 41.49달러라고 보고했습니다. 한편, 비지오는 2024년 ARPU가 37.17달러라고 보고했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investor note reportedly said that Telly recently raised $350 million in debt funding over two rounds. The note didn’t specify when the funding occurred or how much equity Telly has raised overall.&lt;br/&gt;(투자자 메모에 따르면 텔리는 최근 두 차례에 걸쳐 총 3억5천만 달러의 부채 자금을 조달했다고 합니다. 메모는 자금 조달 시기나 텔리가 전체적으로 조달한 지분 자금 규모는 명시하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As smart TVs at every price point increasingly rely on software -integrated advertisements and user tracking to offset declining hardware margins and rising competition, Telly argues that its premise is forward-thinking, not far-fetched. Some longtime Telly users point to the sets’ decent image and audio quality but question their reliance on an (included) streaming stick to access popular apps, their default AI-avatar home screen, and repetitive ads.&lt;br/&gt;(모든 가격대의 스마트 TV가 하드웨어 마진 하락과 치열한 경쟁을 상쇄하기 위해 소프트웨어 통합 광고와 사용자 추적에 점점 더 의존함에 따라, 텔리는 자신들의 전제가 비현실적이기보다 선구적이라고 주장합니다. 오랜 텔리 사용자 중 일부는 TV의 괜찮은 화질과 음질을 지적하지만, 인기 앱 접근을 위한 (포함된) 스트리밍 스틱 의존성, 기본 AI 아바타 홈 화면, 반복적인 광고에 대해 의문을 제기합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Verge writer Emma Roth said her Telly showed her “three of the same ads in Spanish (which I don’t speak) in a row.” There’s also concern about potentially invasive uses of the TV’s integrated camera and mic.&lt;br/&gt;(더 버지의 작가 에마 로스는 자신의 텔리 TV가 "(제가 말하지 않는) 스페인어로 된 동일한 광고 세 개를 연속으로 보여줬다"고 말했습니다. 또한 TV에 내장된 카메라와 마이크의 잠재적으로 침습적인 사용에 대한 우려도 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the leaked investor report highlights, there are plenty of other challenges standing in the way of free, ad-supported TVs. Still, Telly’s early ARPU figures are notable enough to keep the idea alive.&lt;br/&gt;(유출된 투자자 보고서가 강조하듯이, 무료 광고 지원 TV의 길에는 다른 많은 도전 과제가 존재합니다. 그럼에도 불구하고, 텔리의 초기 ARPU 수치는 이 아이디어를 지속시키기에 충분히 주목할 만합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/tellys-free-ad-based-tvs-make-notable-revenue-when-theyre-actually-delivered/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/652fa4f61e054d1c335ce241_Rectangle_20180_203.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:32:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White House alters arrest photo of ICE protester, says “the memes will continue” (백악관, ICE 시위자 체포 사진 조작해 게시… "밈은 계속될 것")</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nekima-levy-white-house-manipulated-image-1152x648-1769192287.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyer calls it “outrageous that the White House would make up stories.”&lt;br/&gt;(변호사는 "백악관이 허위 이야기를 꾸며낸 것은 터무니없다"고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump White House yesterday posted a manipulated photo of Nekima Levy Armstrong, a Minnesota civil rights attorney who was arrested after protesting in a church where a pastor is allegedly also an Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) official.&lt;br/&gt;(트럼프 행정부 백악관은 어제, 이민세관단속국(ICE) 공무원이라고 알려진 목사가 있는 교회에서 시위 후 체포된 미네소타 주 민권 변호사 네키마 레비 암스트롱의 조작된 사진을 게시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noem posted what seems to be the original photo of Armstrong being led away by an officer yesterday morning. A half hour later, the official White House X account posted an altered version in which Armstrong’s face was manipulated to make it appear that she was crying.&lt;br/&gt;(커스티 노엄 국토안보부 장관은 어제 아침, 경찰관에게 끌려가는 암스트롱의 원본으로 보이는 사진을 게시했다. 반 시간 후, 백악관 공식 X 계정은 암스트롱의 얼굴을 조작해 그녀가 울고 있는 것처럼 보이게 만든 수정된 버전의 사진을 게시했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The White House shared an AI-edited photo of Nekima, depicting her in tears and scared when, in actuality, she was poised, determined, and unafraid,” NAACP President and CEO Derrick Johnson said yesterday.&lt;br/&gt;(NAACP(전국유색인종지위향상협회)의 데릭 존슨 회장 겸 최고경영자(CEO)는 어제 "백악관은 실제로는 당당하고 단호하며 두려움이 없었던 네키마를 눈물을 흘리며 겁에 질린 모습으로 묘사한 AI 편집 사진을 공유했다"고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reader-added context on X said, “This photo has been digitally altered to make Nekima Levy Armstrong appear to be in distress. The Director of DHS herself posted the unedited photo in an earlier announcement.” White House Deputy Communications Director Kaelan Dorr defended the post after criticism of the image manipulation.&lt;br/&gt;(X의 독자가 추가한 설명에는 "이 사진은 네키마 레비 암스트롱이 고통받는 것처럼 보이도록 디지털 방식으로 조작되었습니다. 국토안보부 장관 본인이 이전 발표에서 원본 사진을 게시했습니다"라고 적혀 있었다. 백악관 부대변인인 케일런 도르는 이미지 조작에 대한 비판 후 해당 게시물을 옹호했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Enforcement of the law will continue. The memes will continue. Thank you for your attention to this matter,” Dorr wrote . The White House post with the manipulated image called Levy Armstrong a “far-left agitator” who “orchestrated[ed] church riots in Minnesota.”&lt;br/&gt;(도르는 "법 집행은 계속될 것입니다. 밈도 계속될 것입니다. 이 문제에 관심을 가져주셔서 감사합니다"라고 썼다. 조작된 이미지가 담긴 백악관 게시물은 레비 암스트롱을 "미네소타에서 교회 폭동을 조장한 극좌 선동가"라고 불렀다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DHS press release about the arrest used the same image posted by Noem, without the alteration.&lt;br/&gt;(체포에 관한 국토안보부 보도 자료는 노엄 장관이 게시한 것과 동일한, 조작되지 않은 이미지를 사용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Kushner, an attorney for Levy Armstrong, said, “It is just so outrageous that the White House would make up stories about someone to try and discredit them. She was completely calm and composed and rational. There was no one crying. So this is just outrageous defamation.”&lt;br/&gt;(레비 암스트롱의 변호사인 조던 쿠슈너는 "백악관이 누군가를 비난하려고 허위 이야기를 꾸며내는 것은 정말 터무니없습니다. 그녀는 완전히 침착하고 이성적이었습니다. 울고 있는 사람은 아무도 없었습니다. 이건 그냥 터무니없는 명예훼손입니다"라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to The Associated Press , Kushner also said that the “video Levy Armstrong’s husband shot ‘dismantles what they claim’ and that the video would be released soon.”&lt;br/&gt;(AP 통신과의 인터뷰에서 쿠슈너는 또한 "레비 암스트롱의 남편이 촬영한 영상이 '그들이 주장하는 것을 무너뜨릴 것'이며, 해당 영상이 곧 공개될 예정"이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protesters disrupted services on Sunday at the Cities Church in St. Paul, chanting “ICE OUT” and “Justice for Renee Good.” The St. Paul Pioneer Press quoted Levy Armstrong as saying, “When you think about the federal government unleashing barbaric ICE agents upon our community and all the harm that they have caused, to have someone serving as a pastor who oversees these ICE agents is almost unfathomable to me.”&lt;br/&gt;(시위자들은 일요일 세인트폴 소재 시티즈 교회에서 예배를 방해하며 "ICE OUT(ICE 물러나라)"와 "르네 굿을 위한 정의"를 외쳤다. 세인트폴 파이오니어 프레스는 레비 암스트롱의 말을 인용해 "연방 정부가 우리 지역사회에 야만적인 ICE 요원을 풀어놓고 그들이 초래한 모든 피해를 생각해보면, 이러한 ICE 요원들을 감독하는 사람이 목사로 봉사한다는 것은 거의 상상하기 어렵습니다"라고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church website lists David Easterwood as one of its pastors. Protesters said this is the same David Easterwood who is listed as a defendant in a lawsuit that Minnesota Attorney General Keith Ellison filed against Noem and other federal officials. The lawsuit lists Easterwood as a defendant “in his official capacity as Acting Director, Saint Paul Field Office, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.”&lt;br/&gt;(교회 웹사이트는 데이비드 이스터우드를 목사 중 한 명으로 기재하고 있다. 시위자들은 이 사람이 미네소타 주 검찰총장 키스 엘리슨이 노엄 장관과 다른 연방 공무원들을 상대로 제기한 소송의 피고로 기재된 동일인이라고 말했다. 소송서는 이스터우드를 "미국 이민세관단속국(ICE) 세인트폴 현장 사무소 대리 소장 직책으로서" 피고로 기재하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levy Armstrong, who is also a former president of the NAACP’s Minneapolis branch, was arrested yesterday morning. Announcing the arrest, Attorney General Pam Bondi wrote , “WE DO NOT TOLERATE ATTACKS ON PLACES OF WORSHIP.” Bondi alleged that Levy Armstrong “played a key role in organizing the coordinated attack on Cities Church in St. Paul, Minnesota.”&lt;br/&gt;(NAACP 미니애폴리스 지부 전 회장이기도 한 레비 암스트롱은 어제 아침 체포되었다. 체포를 발표하며 팸 본디 검찰총장은 "우리는 예배 장소에 대한 공격을 용납하지 않습니다"라고 썼다. 본디는 레비 암스트롱이 "미네소타 주 세인트폴 소재 시티즈 교회에 대한 조직적인 공격을 계획하는 데 핵심적인 역할을 했다"고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noem said Levy Armstrong “is being charged with a federal crime under 18 USC 241,” which prohibits “conspir[ing] to injure, oppress, threaten, or intimidate any person in any State, Territory, Commonwealth, Possession, or District in the free exercise or enjoyment of any right or privilege secured to him by the Constitution or laws of the United States.”&lt;br/&gt;(노엄 장관은 레비 암스트롱이 "미국 법전 제18편 제241조에 따른 연방 범죄로 기소되고 있다"고 말했는데, 이 조항은 "어떤 사람이 미국 헌법이나 법률에 의해 보장된 권리나 특권을 자유롭게 행사하거나 향유하는 것을 방해하기 위해 공모하는 것"을 금지한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Religious freedom is the bedrock of the United States—there is no first amendment right to obstruct someone from practicing their religion,” Noem wrote.&lt;br/&gt;(노엄은 "종교의 자유는 미국의 기반입니다. 타인의 종교 실천을 방해할 제1차 수정헌법상의 권리는 없습니다"라고 썼다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul School Board member Chauntyll Allen was also arrested. Attorneys for the Cities Church issued statements supporting the arrests and saying they “are exploring all legal options to protect the church and prevent further invasions.”&lt;br/&gt;(세인트폴 교육위원회 위원인 촌틸 앨런도 체포되었다. 시티즈 교회 측 변호사들은 체포를 지지하는 성명을 발표하고 "교회를 보호하고 추가 침입을 방지하기 위해 모든 법적 옵션을 검토 중"이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal magistrate judge initially ruled that Levy Armstrong and Allen could be released, but they were still being held last night after the government “made a motion to stay the release for further review, claiming they might be flight risks,” the Pioneer Press wrote .&lt;br/&gt;(연방 치안판사는 처음에 레비 암스트롱과 앨런의 석방을 허가했지만, 정부가 "그들이 도주 위험이 있을 수 있다며 석방 유예를 위한 신청을 해 추가 검토를 요청"함에 따라 어제 밤까지도 두 사람은 구금된 상태였다고 파이오니어 프레스는 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner called the arrests a “farce” and alleged that Bondi and Noem ordered the arrests only so they could celebrate them on social media, according to the Pioneer Press. “This doesn’t happen in a legitimate prosecution,” Kushner said. “These are officials making a political decision, and purposely making a political spectacle and a political circus out of the court system for their own purposes.”&lt;br/&gt;(파이오니어 프레스에 따르면, 쿠슈너는 이 체포를 "어처구니없는 일"이라고 불렀고, 본디와 노엄이 단지 소셜미디어에서 자축하기 위해 체포를 지시했다고 주장했다. 쿠슈너는 "이것은 합법적인 기소 과정에서 일어나는 일이 아닙니다. 이들은 정치적 결정을 내리고, 자신들의 목적을 위해 법원 시스템을 정치적인 구경거리, 정치적인 서커스로 만들고 있습니다"라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kushner also “said federal agents detained one of Armstrong’s friends two days [previously], using force to tackle her in a hotel lobby, under the mistaken impression she was Armstrong,” the Pioneer Press wrote.&lt;br/&gt;(쿠슈너는 또한 "연방 요원들이 이틀 전, 암스트롱의 친구 한 명을 그녀가 암스트롱이라는 오해 아래 호텔 로비에서 제압하며 구금했다"고 파이오니어 프레스는 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marques Armstrong, Levy Armstrong’s husband, said she offered to turn herself in after the mistaken detention of her friend.&lt;br/&gt;(레비 암스트롱의 남편 마르케스 암스트롱은 그녀가 친구의 오인 구금 후 자수하겠다고 제안했다고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Initially they agreed and then a call came from up high and said, ‘No, we have to take her there (at the hotel).’ They wanted her in handcuffs,” he was quoted as saying. An “agent took photos and said it won’t go on social media. I knew it was a lie,” he also said.&lt;br/&gt;(그는 "처음에는 그들이 동의했지만, 상부에서 전화가 와서 '아니, 우리는 그녀를 (호텔에서) 데려가야 한다'고 했습니다. 그들은 그녀가 수갑을 차길 원했습니다"라고 인용되었다. 그는 또한 "요원이 사진을 찍고 소셜미디어에 올리지 않을 것이라고 말했습니다. 저는 그것이 거짓말이라는 걸 알았습니다"라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House’s posting of a manipulated version of the arrest photo could be used in Levy Armstrong’s legal defense. As the New York Times wrote , her lawyer could argue that the post was an improper extrajudicial statement that may prejudice potential jurors and that it shows the Justice Department filed charges vindictively. We contacted Kushner about the manipulated photo and case today and will update this article if he provides any comment.&lt;br/&gt;(백악관이 체포 사진의 조작된 버전을 게시한 것은 레비 암스트롱의 법적 방어에 활용될 수 있다. 뉴욕 타임스가 보도한 바와 같이, 그녀의 변호사는 해당 게시물이 잠재적 배심원들에게 편견을 줄 수 있는 부적절한 재판 외 진술이며, 이는 법무부가 보복적으로 기소했다는 것을 보여준다고 주장할 수 있다. 우리는 오늘 조작된 사진과 사건에 대해 쿠슈너 변호사에게 연락했으며, 그가 어떤 의견을 제시하면 이 기사를 업데이트할 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NAACP called for the release of Levy Armstrong, Allen, and a third arrestee, William Kelly. “Their arrests violated their constitutional rights and NAACP demands their immediate release,” the NAACP said. “Ms. Armstrong and her fellow demonstrators gathered peacefully at a church over the pastor’s alleged leadership within the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE). The protests follow the increase in ICE activity and the fatal shooting of Minneapolis resident Renee Nicole Good.”&lt;br/&gt;(NAACP는 레비 암스트롱, 앨런, 그리고 세 번째 체포자 윌리엄 켈리의 석방을 요구했다. NAACP는 "그들의 체포는 그들의 헌법적 권리를 침해했으며, NAACP는 그들의 즉각적인 석방을 요구합니다"라고 말했다. "암스트롱씨와 동료 시위자들은 목사의 미국 이민세관단속국(ICE) 내 지도력 의혹에 대해 교회에서 평화롭게 모였습니다. 이 시위는 ICE 활동 증가와 미니애폴리스 거주자 르네 니콜 굿의 치명적인 총격 사건에 따른 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department also tried to bring charges against journalist Don Lemon, but a judge rejected the charges . Lemon was at the demonstration but said he was there as a journalist and not a protester.&lt;br/&gt;(법무부는 또한 기자 돈 레몬에 대한 기소를 시도했으나, 판사가 기소를 기각했다. 레몬은 시위 현장에 있었지만 저널리스트로서 있었을 뿐 시위자가 아니라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/white-house-posts-altered-arrest-photo-to-make-it-appear-ice-critic-was-sobbing/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nekima-levy-white-house-manipulated-image-1152x648-1769192287.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:46:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask anonymous ICE critics online (DHS, 익명의 ICE 비판자들 정체 파악 시도 계속 실패)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257128839-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Community watch groups have a playbook to keep ICE away from subscriber information.&lt;br/&gt;(커뮤니티 감시 단체들은 ICE가 가입자 정보를 얻지 못하도록 막는 행동 지침을 가지고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security (DHS) has backed down from a fight to unmask the owners of Instagram and Facebook accounts monitoring Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) activity in Pennsylvania.&lt;br/&gt;(국토안보부(DHS)는 펜실베이니아에서 이민세관단속국(ICE) 활동을 감시하는 인스타그램 및 페이스북 계정 소유주의 정체를 파악하려는 싸움에서 물러섰다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the anonymous account holders, John Doe, sued to block ICE from identifying him and other critics online through summonses to Meta that he claimed infringed on core First Amendment-protected activity.&lt;br/&gt;(익명의 계정 소유주 중 한 명인 존 도(John Doe)는 메타(Meta)에 발부된 소환장을 통해 자신과 다른 온라인 비판자들을 ICE가 확인하는 것을 막기 위해 소송을 제기했다. 그는 이 조치가 수정헌법 제1조로 보호되는 핵심 활동을 침해한다고 주장했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS initially fought Doe’s motion to quash the summonses, arguing that the community watch groups endangered ICE agents by posting “pictures and videos of agents’ faces, license plates, and weapons, among other things.” This was akin to “threatening ICE agents to impede the performance of their duties,” DHS alleged. DHS’s arguments echoed DHS Secretary Kristi Noem, who has claimed that identifying ICE agents is a crime, even though Wired noted that ICE employees often post easily discoverable LinkedIn profiles.&lt;br/&gt;(DHS는 처음에는 도가 제기한 소환장 취하 신청에 맞섰다. 그들은 커뮤니티 감시 단체들이 "요원들의 얼굴, 차량 번호판, 무기 등의 사진과 동영상을 게시함으로써" ICE 요원들을 위험에 빠뜨린다고 주장했다. DHS는 이 행위가 "ICE 요원들이 직무를 수행하는 것을 방해하기 위해 그들을 위협하는 것"과 유사하다고 주장했다. DHS의 주장은 크리스티 노엄(Kristi Noem) DHS 장관의 발언과 맥을 같이한다. 그녀는 ICE 요원들을 특정하는 것이 범죄라고 주장해왔는데, 와이어드(Wired)지는 ICE 직원들이 종종 쉽게 찾을 수 있는 링크드인 프로필을 게시한다고 지적한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Doe, the agency seemed intent on testing the waters to see if it could seize authority to unmask all critics online by invoking a customs statute that allows agents to subpoena information on goods entering or leaving the US.&lt;br/&gt;(도에게는, DHS가 미국으로 들어오거나 나가는 상품에 대한 정보를 소환할 수 있도록 허용하는 관세 법률을 근거로 삼아, 온라인상의 모든 비판자들의 정체를 파악할 권한을 장악할 수 있는지 시험해보려는 의도로 보였다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, on January 16, DHS abruptly reversed course, withdrawing its summonses from Meta.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 1월 16일, DHS는 갑자기 방향을 바꿔 메타에 대한 소환장을 철회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A court filing confirmed that DHS dropped its requests for subscriber information last week, after initially demanding Doe’s “postal code, country, all email address(es) on file, date of account creation, registered telephone numbers, IP address at account signup, and logs showing IP address and date stamps for account accesses.”&lt;br/&gt;(법원 서류에 따르면, DHS는 지난주 가입자 정보 요청을 포기한 것으로 확인되었다. DHS는 처음에는 도의 "우편번호, 국가, 등록된 모든 이메일 주소, 계정 생성일, 등록된 전화번호, 계정 가입 시 IP 주소, 그리고 계정 접속 기록(IP 주소 및 날짜 스탬프 포함)"을 요구했었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filing does not explain why DHS decided to withdraw its requests.&lt;br/&gt;(해당 서류는 DHS가 요청을 철회하기로 결정한 이유에 대해서는 설명하지 않는다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, previously, DHS requested similar information from Meta about six Instagram community watch groups that shared information about ICE activity in Los Angeles and other locations. DHS withdrew those requests, too, after account holders defended their First Amendment rights and filed motions to quash their summonses, Doe’s court filing said.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 이전에도 DHS는 로스앤젤레스 및 기타 지역의 ICE 활동에 대한 정보를 공유한 6개의 인스타그램 커뮤니티 감시 단체에 대해 메타로부터 유사한 정보를 요청한 바 있다. 도의 법원 서류에 따르면, 계정 소유주들이 수정헌법 제1조 권리를 주장하고 소환장 취하 신청을 제기한 후 DHS는 그 요청들도 철회했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To defeat DHS’ summonses, Doe shared all his group’s online posts with the court. An attorney representing Doe at the American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania, Ariel Shapell, told Ars that Doe’s groups posted “pretty innocuous” content, like “information and resources about immigrant rights, due process rights, fundraising, and vigils.”&lt;br/&gt;(DHS의 소환장을 무력화하기 위해, 도는 자신의 단체가 게시한 모든 온라인 게시물을 법원에 제출했다. 펜실베이니아 미국자유시민연맹(ACLU)에서 도를 대리하는 변호사 아리엘 샤펠(Ariel Shapell)은 아스테크니카(Ars)에 도의 단체들이 "이민자 권리, 적법 절차 권리, 모금 활동, 추모 집회 등에 대한 정보와 자원"과 같은 "상당히 무해한" 콘텐츠를 게시했다고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s possible DHS caved due to lack of evidence supporting claims that Doe’s groups’ posts carried implicit threats to “assault, kidnap, or murder any federal official,” as DHS had argued . But it’s also possible that DHS keeps trying and failing to unmask ICE critics due to strong First Amendment protections working to preserve the right to post anonymously online.&lt;br/&gt;(DHS가 철회한 이유는, DHS가 주장했던 것처럼 도의 단체 게시물이 "어떤 연방 공무원을 폭행, 납치 또는 살해하려는" 암묵적 위협을 담고 있다는 주장을 뒷받침할 증거가 부족했기 때문일 수 있다. 그러나 또한, 온라인에서 익명으로 게시할 권리를 보호하는 강력한 수정헌법 제1조 보호 장치가 작용하여 DHS가 ICE 비판자들의 정체를 파악하려는 시도를 계속 실패하고 있기 때문일 수도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attempt to unmask Doe’s accounts came as criticism of ICE is mounting nationwide, and a win could have given ICE broad authority to attack that growing base of critics if DHS had dug in and its defense actually held.&lt;br/&gt;(도 계정의 정체 파악 시도는 전국적으로 ICE에 대한 비판이 고조되는 가운데 이루어졌다. 만약 DHS가 버텼고 그들의 주장이 실제로 받아들여졌다면, 승리는 ICE에게 그 증가하는 비판 세력을 공격할 수 있는 광범위한 권한을 부여했을 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses could signal that the argument the agency tried to raise— weirdly using a statute tied to the “importation/exportation of merchandise” to seize “unlimited subpoena authority” of ICE critics online—is clearly not a winning one.&lt;br/&gt;(DHS의 소환장 철회는, 해당 기관이 시도한 주장—온라인상의 ICE 비판자들에 대한 "무제한 소환 권한"을 장악하기 위해 "상품의 수입/수출"과 관련된 법률을 이상하게 사용한—이 분명히 승리할 수 없는 주장임을 시사할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment. But Meta did play a role in challenging DHS’ summonses, initially by seeking more information from the agency and then notifying account holders to provide an opportunity to quash the summonses before information was shared.&lt;br/&gt;(메타는 아스테크니카의 코멘트 요청에 즉시 응답하지 않았다. 그러나 메타는 DHS의 소환장에 도전하는 데 일정 부분 역할을 했다. 처음에는 해당 기관으로부터 더 많은 정보를 요청했고, 이후 정보가 공유되기 전에 계정 소유주들에게 소환장을 취하할 기회를 제공하도록 통지했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the playbook for community watch groups on Facebook and Instagram has been to follow Meta’s advice in order to block identifying information from being shared. But it remains unclear if Meta may have complied with DHS’s requests if account holders were not able to legally fight to quash them, perhaps leaving a vulnerable gray area for community watch groups.&lt;br/&gt;(지금까지 페이스북과 인스타그램의 커뮤니티 감시 단체들의 행동 지침은 식별 정보가 공유되는 것을 막기 위해 메타의 조언을 따르는 것이었다. 그러나 계정 소유주들이 소환장을 취하하기 위해 법적으로 싸울 수 없었다면 메타가 DHS의 요청에 응했을지 여부는 여전히 불분명하며, 이는 커뮤니티 감시 단체들에게 취약한 회색 지대를 남겨둘 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Doe and any others involved in “MontCo Community Watch,” DHS’s withdrawal of the summonses likely comes as a relief. But this wasn’t the first time DHS tried and failed to unmask online critics, so it’s just as likely that fears remain that DHS will continue trying to identify groups that are posting footage to raise awareness of ICE’s most controversial moves.&lt;br/&gt;(도와 "몽트코 커뮤니티 워치(MontCo Community Watch)"에 관여한 다른 사람들에게, DHS의 소환장 철회는 안도감으로 다가왔을 것이다. 그러나 이번이 DHS가 온라인 비판자들의 정체를 파악하려 시도하고 실패한 첫 번째 사례는 아니므로, DHS가 ICE의 가장 논란이 많은 행동에 대한 인식을 높이기 위해 영상을 게시하는 단체들을 계속 확인하려 시도할 것이라는 우려가 여전히 남아 있을 가능성도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE critics have used footage of tragic events—like Renee Good’s killing and eight other ICE shootings since September —to support calls to remove ICE from embattled communities and abolish ICE.&lt;br/&gt;(ICE 비판자들은 르네 구드(Renee Good) 살해 사건과 9월 이후 발생한 8건의 ICE 총격 사건과 같은 비극적 사건들의 영상을 사용하여, ICE를 분쟁 지역 사회에서 철수시키고 ICE를 폐지하라는 요구를 지지해왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions remain high as US citizens defend both their neighbors and their own constitutional rights. Most recently, shocking footage of ICE using a 5-year-old boy as bait to trap other family members intensified calls to defund ICE. Public backlash also raged after videos showed ICE removing a US citizen from his home in his underwear . That arrest happened while ICE was conducting a warrantless search that a whistleblower warned is becoming the new ICE norm after an internal memo said that agents can enter homes without a judicial warrant.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 시민들이 이웃과 자신의 헌법적 권리를 모두 방어하면서 긴장은 여전히 높다. 가장 최근에는, ICE가 5세 소년을 미끼로 사용하여 다른 가족 구성원들을 함정에 빠뜨린 충격적인 영상이 ICE에 대한 예산 삭감 요구를 강화시켰다. 또한 ICE가 속옷 차림의 미국 시민을 집에서 강제로 연행하는 영상이 공개된 후 공중의 반발도 격렬했다. 그 체포는 ICE가 영장 없는 수색을 진행하는 동안 발생했으며, 내부 메모에서 요원들이 사법 영장 없이 주거지에 들어갈 수 있다고 밝힌 후, 내부 고발자가 이 행위가 새로운 ICE 표준이 되어가고 있다고 경고한 바 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some politicians are starting to take up the call to diminish ICE’s power. On Thursday, the majority of House Democrats voted to defund ICE, which Politico noted was a “remarkable shift from when dozens of them voted to expand the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement authority just one year ago.” Of course, the ICE budget bill passed anyway, since Republicans control the House, but with public approval of ICE tanking , any ongoing pushback could hurt Republicans in midterms and eventually even doom ICE if momentum is sustained.&lt;br/&gt;(일부 정치인들은 ICE의 권력을 축소하라는 요구를 받아들이기 시작하고 있다. 목요일, 하원 민주당 의원들의 대다수가 ICE 예산 삭감에 투표했는데, 폴리티코(Politico)는 이는 "불과 1년 전에 수십 명의 민주당 의원들이 트럼프 행정부의 이민 단속 권한 확대에 투표했을 때와 비교하면 현저한 변화"라고 지적했다. 물론, 공화당이 하원을 장악하고 있기 때문에 ICE 예산 법안은 어쨌든 통과되었지만, ICE에 대한 공중의 지지도가 급락함에 따라, 지속되는 반발은 중간 선거에서 공화당에 타격을 줄 수 있으며, 결국 기세가 유지된다면 ICE의 운명을 결정지을 수도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/instagram-ice-critic-wins-fight-to-stay-anonymous-as-dhs-backs-down/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257128839-1024x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:10:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demand for Intel’s processors is apparently there, but the supply is not (인텔 프로세서 수요는 분명 존재하나, 공급이 따라주지 못하고 있다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/intel-core-ultra-series-3-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel is allocating more of its own production to its money-making server chips.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔은 자체 생산량을 수익성이 높은 서버 칩에 더 많이 할당하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel reported its earnings for the fourth quarter of 2025 yesterday , and the news both for the quarter and for the year was mixed: year-over-year revenue was down nearly imperceptibly, from $53.1 billion to $52.9 billion, while revenue for the quarter was down about four percent, from $14.3 billion last year to $13.7 billion this year. (That number was, nevertheless, on the high end of Intel’s guidance for the quarter, which ranged from $12.8 to $13.8 billion.)&lt;br/&gt;(인텔은 어제 2025년 4분기 실적을 발표했으며, 분기 및 연간 실적 소식은 엇갈렸다: 전년 대비 매출은 531억 달러에서 529억 달러로 거의 눈에 띄지 않게 감소했고, 분기 매출은 약 4% 하락해 지난해 143억 달러에서 올해 137억 달러를 기록했다. (그럼에도 이 수치는 인텔이 제시한 해당 분기 가이던스 범위인 128억 달러에서 138억 달러 중 상위권에 해당한다.))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diving deeper into the numbers makes it clear exactly where money is being made and lost: Intel’s data center and AI products were up 9 percent for the quarter and 5 percent for the year, while its client computing group (which sells Core processors, Arc GPUs, and other consumer products) was down 7 percent for the quarter and 3 percent for the year.&lt;br/&gt;(숫자를 자세히 들여다보면 어디서 돈을 벌고 잃는지 명확해진다: 인텔의 데이터센터 및 AI 제품 부문은 분기 기준 9%, 연간 기준 5% 성장한 반면, 클라이언트 컴퓨팅 그룹(코어 프로세서, Arc GPU 및 기타 소비자 제품 판매)은 분기 기준 7%, 연간 기준 3% 감소했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That knowledge makes it slightly easier to understand the bind that company executives talked about on Intel’s earnings call ( as transcribed by Investing.com ). In short, Intel is having trouble making (and buying) enough chips to meet demand, and it makes more sense to allocate the chips it can make to the divisions that are actually making money—which means that we could see shortages of or higher prices for consumer processors, just as Intel is gearing up to launch the promising Core Ultra Series 3 processors (codenamed Panther Lake).&lt;br/&gt;(이러한 사실은 인텔 실적 발표 컨퍼런스콜(Investing.com 필사본)에서 회사 경영진이 언급한 곤경을 이해하는 데 조금 도움이 된다. 요약하자면, 인텔은 수요를 충족할 만큼 충분한 칩을 생산(및 구매)하는 데 어려움을 겪고 있으며, 생산 가능한 칩을 실제로 수익을 내는 부서에 할당하는 것이 더 합리적이다. 이는 인텔이 유망한 코어 울트라 시리즈 3 프로세서(코드명 팬서 레이크) 출시를 준비하는 와중에 소비자용 프로세서의 공급 부족이나 가격 인상을 목격할 수 있음을 의미한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel CFO David Zinsner indicated that Intel is “prioritizing [its] internal wafer supply to data center” and having more of its consumer chips made externally. Substantial portions of the Core Ultra Series 3 processors are manufactured at Intel, after the company primarily used TSMC’s chip factories for the Core Ultra Series 2 designs.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔 CFO 데이비드 진스너는 인텔이 "데이터센터에 대한 자체 웨이퍼 공급을 우선시"하고 소비자용 칩의 외부 생산 비중을 늘리고 있다고 밝혔다. 코어 울트라 시리즈 3 프로세서의 상당 부분은 인텔에서 제조되며, 이전 코어 울트라 시리즈 2 설계에서는 주로 TSMC의 칩 공장을 활용했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can’t completely vacate the client market,” said Zinsner, but Intel is “shifting as much as we can over to data center to meet the high demand.”&lt;br/&gt;(진스너는 "클라이언트 시장을 완전히 비울 수는 없다"고 말했지만, 인텔은 "높은 수요를 충족시키기 위해 가능한 한 데이터센터로 전환하고 있다"고 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounding this is that yields for the new 18A process—that is, the number of chips in a wafer with no defects that can work as designed—are still improving. Intel CEO Lip-Bu Tan said that “while yields are in line with our internal plans, they are still below what I want them to be.”&lt;br/&gt;(이에 더해 새로운 18A 공정의 수율(즉, 설계대로 작동하는 결함 없는 칩이 웨이퍼에서 차지하는 비율)이 여전히 개선되고 있다는 점이 문제를 악화시킨다. 인텔 CEO 립부 탄은 "수율이 내부 계획에 부합하지만, 여전히 제가 원하는 수준에는 미치지 못한다"고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yields are currently improving by 7 or 8 percent every month, according to Intel. But that could be building on pretty low initial yields—reporting from last summer suggested that just 10 percent of the chips coming off of the 18A production lines were meeting Intel’s requirements at the time. Intel predicts that its supply will have ramped up enough within the next few months to help alleviate shortages.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔에 따르면, 현재 수율은 매월 7~8%씩 향상되고 있다. 하지만 이는 꽤 낮은 초기 수율을 기반으로 한 것일 수 있다. 지난여름 보도에 따르면 당시 18A 생산라인에서 나오는 칩 중 단 10%만이 인텔의 요구 사항을 충족했다. 인텔은 향후 몇 달 안에 공급이 충분히 확대되어 부족 현상을 완화하는 데 도움이 될 것으로 예측한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do believe that the first quarter is the trough,” said Zinsner. “We will improve supply in the second quarter.”&lt;br/&gt;(진스너는 "1분기가 최저점이라고 믿는다"며 "2분기에는 공급이 개선될 것"이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Intel can start making enough chips to meet its demand, it ought to help brighten the company’s earnings reports.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔이 수요를 충족할 만큼 충분한 칩을 생산하기 시작하면, 이는 회사의 실적 보고서를 밝게 만드는 데 도움이 될 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We delivered [our Q4 2025] results despite supply constraints, which meaningfully limited our ability to capture all of the strengths in our underwriting markets,” said Tan. “We are working aggressively to address this and better support our customers’ needs going forward.”&lt;br/&gt;(탄은 "공급 제약에도 불구하고 [2025년 4분기] 실적을 달성했다. 이 제약은 우리가 인수 시장의 강점을 모두 활용하는 능력을 상당히 제한했다"며 "이 문제를 해결하고 앞으로 고객의 요구를 더 잘 지원하기 위해 적극적으로 노력하고 있다"고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intel has been signaling for a while now that it was selling essentially all of the chips it could get its hands on. Intel investor relations VP John Pitzer said last month that Intel would be selling more of both its Lunar Lake and Arrow Lake Core Ultra Series 2 chips for consumers, as well as its Granite Rapids chips for data centers, if it could get more of them.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔은 한동안 손에 넣을 수 있는 모든 칩을 사실상 판매하고 있다는 신호를 보내왔다. 인텔 투자자 관계 부사장 존 피처는 지난달 인텔이 더 많은 런어 레이크 및 애로우 레이크 코어 울트라 시리즈 2 소비자용 칩과 데이터센터용 그래나이트 래피즈 칩을 확보할 수 있다면 더 많이 판매할 것이라고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Intel seeks to improve its position in the short term, the company also says that it’s still making progress on its future manufacturing nodes, including different versions of the 18A process and the upcoming 14A process. Intel is working to engage “potential external customers” who would use the 14A process to make their own chips. If these third parties decide to use Intel’s manufacturing facilities, Intel expects to know about it “starting in the second half of this year and extending into the first half of 2027,” and then it expects to build out manufacturing capacity based on the number of external customers it finds.&lt;br/&gt;(인텔이 단기적으로 입지를 개선하려는 가운데, 회사는 또한 18A 공정의 다양한 버전과 향후 14A 공정을 포함한 미래 제조 공정에서도 여전히 진전을 이루고 있다고 밝혔다. 인텔은 14A 공정을 사용해 자체 칩을 제조할 "잠재적 외부 고객"을 유치하기 위해 노력하고 있다. 이러한 제3자들이 인텔의 제조 시설을 사용하기로 결정한다면, 인텔은 "올해 하반기부터 2027년 상반기까지" 그 사실을 알게 될 것으로 예상하며, 이후 발견한 외부 고객 수에 기반해 제조 능력을 확장할 계획이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the chip design side, Intel also expects to have its first next-generation Nova Lake chips ready “at the end of 2026.” We don’t know much about Nova Lake yet, but it should be Intel’s next architecture to cover both desktop and laptop processors, while Panther Lake chips are intended mainly for laptops. At least part of the chip will also be manufactured using the 18A process.&lt;br/&gt;(칩 설계 측면에서 인텔은 또한 첫 차세대 노바 레이크 칩을 "2026년 말"에 준비할 것으로 예상한다. 노바 레이크에 대해서는 아직 많이 알려지지 않았지만, 팬서 레이크 칩이 주로 노트북용인 반면, 노바 레이크는 데스크톱과 노트북 프로세서를 모두 아우르는 인텔의 다음 아키텍처가 될 것이다. 칩의 적어도 일부는 18A 공정을 사용해 제조될 예정이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/core-ultra-series-3-launch-may-be-hampered-by-chip-shortages-says-intel/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/intel-core-ultra-series-3-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 11:48:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TR-49is interactive fiction for fans of deep research rabbit holes (TR-49: 심층 연구의 토끼굴에 빠지기 좋은 인터랙티브 픽션)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/4-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dense narrative deduction game tells a compellingly academia-tinged sci-fi tale.&lt;br/&gt;(빽빽한 서사적 추리 게임이 학문적 색채를 띤 매력적인 SF 이야기를 풀어놓는다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developer: Inkle Publisher : Inkle Platform : MacOS (reviewed), Windows, iOS Release Date: Jan. 21, 2026 ESRB Rating: N/A Price : $7 Links: iOS App Store | Steam | Official website&lt;br/&gt;(개발사: 인클(Inkle) 배급사: 인클(Inkle) 플랫폼: macOS(리뷰 기준), Windows, iOS 출시일: 2026년 1월 21일 ESRB 등급: N/A 가격: $7 링크: iOS 앱 스토어 | Steam | 공식 웹사이트)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever fallen down a Wikipedia rabbit hole or spent a pleasant evening digging through college library stacks, you know the joy of a good research puzzle. Every new source and cross-reference you find unlocks an incremental understanding of a previously unknown world, forming a piecemeal tapestry of knowledge that you can eventually look back at as a cohesive and well-known whole.&lt;br/&gt;(위키백과 토끼굴에 빠져본 적이 있거나 대학 도서관 서가를 뒤지며 즐거운 저녁을 보낸 적이 있다면, 좋은 연구 퍼즐의 즐거움을 아는 사람일 것이다. 발견하는 각각의 새로운 자료와 상호 참조는 이전에 알지 못했던 세계에 대한 점진적인 이해를 열어주며, 결국에는 응집력 있고 잘 알게 된 전체로 되돌아볼 수 있는 지식의 조각보를 형성한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49 takes this research process and operationalizes it into an engrossing and novel piece of heavily non-linear interactive fiction. Researching the myriad sources contained in the game’s mysterious computer slowly reveals a tale that’s part mystery, part sci-fi allegory, part family drama, and all-compelling alternate academic history.&lt;br/&gt;(TR-49는 이러한 연구 과정을 가져와 매력적이고 참신한, 강력한 비선형 인터랙티브 픽션으로 구현한다. 게임 속 신비로운 컴퓨터에 담긴 수많은 자료를 연구하다 보면, 미스터리이자 SF 우화이자 가족 드라마이며, 전부가 매력적인 대체 학술사인 이야기가 서서히 드러난다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entirety of TR-49 takes place from a first-person perspective as you sit in front of a kind of Steampunk-infused computer terminal. An unseen narrator asks you to operate the machine but is initially cagey about how or why or what you’re even looking for. There’s a creepy vibe to the under-explained circumstances that brought you to this situation, but the game never descends into the jump scares or horror tropes of so many other modern titles.&lt;br/&gt;(TR-49 전체는 1인칭 시점으로 진행되며, 당신은 일종의 스팀펑크 느낌이 나는 컴퓨터 터미널 앞에 앉아 있다. 보이지 않는 내레이터가 당신에게 이 기계를 작동하라고 요청하지만, 처음에는 어떻게, 왜, 심지어 무엇을 찾고 있는지에 대해 얼버무린다. 당신을 이 상황으로 이끈 설명되지 않은 상황에는 으스스한 분위기가 있지만, 게임은 결코 다른 많은 현대 타이틀들의 점프 스케어나 공포 클리셰로 전락하지 않는다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your only real form of interaction with the world of TR-49 is through a sepia-toned tube display on the left and a four-character split-flap on the right that serves as the computer’s only input. You quickly discover that entering specific sequences—each with two letters followed by two numbers, as suggested by the game’s name—brings up library catalog-style entries referring to a vast web of literary works that form the core of the game’s wider fiction.&lt;br/&gt;(TR-49 세계와 상호작용하는 유일한 실제 방법은 왼쪽의 세피아 톤 음극선관 디스플레이와 오른쪽의 컴퓨터 유일의 입력 장치인 4자리 플립 디스플레이를 통해서다. 당신은 게임 이름에서 암시하듯 두 글자 뒤에 두 숫자가 오는 특정 코드 시퀀스를 입력하면, 게임의 광활한 픽션의 핵심을 이루는 방대한 문학 작품들을 가리키는 도서관 목록 스타일의 항목이 나타난다는 것을 금방 발견하게 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the catalog contains short excerpts from each of these discovered works, it’s the additional notes added to each entry by subsequent researchers that place each title in its full context. You’ll end up poring through these research notes for clues about the existence and chronology of other authors and works. Picking out specific names and years points to the codes and titles needed to unlock even more reference pages in the computer, pushing you further down the rabbit hole. Picture something like Her Story , but replace the cinéma vérité surveillance video clips with a library card catalog.&lt;br/&gt;(목록에는 발견된 각 작품들의 짧은 발췌문이 포함되어 있지만, 후속 연구자들이 각 항목에 추가한 노트들이 각 제목을 완전한 맥락에 놓아준다. 당신은 결국 다른 작가와 작품들의 존재와 연대기에 대한 단서를 찾기 위해 이 연구 노트들을 꼼꼼히 살펴보게 될 것이다. 특정 이름과 연도를 골라내면 컴퓨터에서 더 많은 참조 페이지를 열기 위해 필요한 코드와 제목을 가리키며, 당신을 토끼굴 더 깊숙이 밀어넣는다. Her Story 같은 것을 상상해 보되, 시네마 베리테 감시 영상 클립을 도서관 카드 목록으로 대체한 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll slowly start to unravel and understand how the game world’s myriad authors are influencing each other with their cross-pollinating writings. The treatises, novels, pamphlets, and journals discussed in this database are full of academic sniping, intellectual intrigue, and interpersonal co-mingling across multiple generations of work. It all ends up circling a long-running search for a metaphysical key to life itself, which most of the authors manage to approach but never quite reach a full understanding.&lt;br/&gt;(당신은 게임 세계의 수많은 작가들이 그들의 교차 수분적인 글쓰기로 서로 어떻게 영향을 미치는지 서서히 풀어내고 이해하게 될 것이다. 이 데이터베이스에서 논의되는 논문, 소설, 팸플릿, 학술지는 학문적인 비난, 지적인 음모, 그리고 여러 세대에 걸친 작업들 사이의 대인관계적 교류로 가득하다. 이 모든 것은 결국 삶 자체에 대한 형이상학적 열쇠를 찾는 오랜 탐구를 중심으로 맴돌게 되는데, 대부분의 작가들은 접근은 하지만 결코 완전한 이해에 도달하지는 못한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you explore, you also start to learn more about the personal affairs of the researchers who collected and cataloged all this reference material and the vaguely defined temporal capabilities of the information-synthesis engine in the computer you’ve all worked on. Eventually, you’ll stumble on the existence of core commands that can unlock hidden parts of the computer or alter the massive research database itself, which becomes key to your eventual final goal.&lt;br/&gt;(탐색하면서 당신은 또한 이 모든 참고 자료를 수집하고 분류한 연구자들의 개인적 사정과, 당신이 모두 작업해 온 컴퓨터 속 정보 종합 엔진의 모호하게 정의된 시간적 능력에 대해서도 더 많이 알게 된다. 결국, 당신은 컴퓨터의 숨겨진 부분을 열거나 방대한 연구 데이터베이스 자체를 변경할 수 있는 핵심 명령어들의 존재를 우연히 발견하게 되는데, 이는 당신의 궁극적인 최종 목표에 핵심이 된다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through it all, there’s a slowly unfolding parallel narrative involving Liam, the unseen voice guiding you through the research process itself. Through occasional voice clips, Liam eventually hints at the existence of a powerful and quickly encroaching threat that wants to stop your progress by any means necessary, adding a bit of dramatic tension to your academic pursuits.&lt;br/&gt;(이 모든 과정 속에, 연구 과정 자체를 안내하는 보이지 않는 목소리, 리암(Liam)과 관련된 서서히 펼쳐지는 평행 서사가 있다. 가끔씩 나오는 음성 클립을 통해, 리암은 결국 당신의 진행을 어떤 수단을 써서라도 막으려는 강력하고 빠르게 접근하는 위협의 존재를 암시하며, 당신의 학문적 추구에 약간의 극적 긴장감을 더한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m being intentionally vague about the specifics here because I think TR-49 ‘s subtle and well-crafted sci-fi world-building is best experienced by exploring the game for yourself. There’s a real satisfaction in staring at a once impenetrably obtuse research note, recalling a bit of information from a recent cross-reference, and feeling your understanding suddenly click into place. And while the vocal performances can verge on cheesy, the writing captures the monomaniacal intensity of truly obsessive academics to a tee.&lt;br/&gt;(여기서 구체적인 내용을 의도적으로 모호하게 전달하는 것은, TR-49의 미묘하고 잘 만들어진 SF 세계 구축은 직접 게임을 탐험해 보는 것이 가장 좋다고 생각하기 때문이다. 한때 난해하게 이해되지 않았던 연구 노트를 응시하다가, 최근의 상호 참조에서 얻은 정보 조각을 떠올리고, 갑자기 이해가 맞아떨어지는 느낌을 받을 때 진정한 만족감이 있다. 그리고 성우 연기가 조금 촌스러울 수는 있지만, 글쓰기는 진정으로 집착적인 학자들의 편집증적인 강렬함을 정확하게 포착한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the game’s best features is a “Notes” sub-menu, which automatically outlines relevant facts (and potential facts) about various authors, groups, and publications as you discover them. This means you don’t have to take page after page of hand-written notes to keep track of the game’s complex connections (and potential connections), as you do in games like Blue Prince or Lorelei and the Laser Eyes . It makes for a much smoother puzzle-solving experience, even if the automatic notes sometimes pick up on things you may have missed while skimming.&lt;br/&gt;(게임의 최고의 기능 중 하나는 '노트(Notes)' 하위 메뉴로, 당신이 발견하는 다양한 작가, 단체, 출판물에 대한 관련 사실(그리고 잠재적 사실)을 자동으로 요약해 준다. 이는 Blue Prince나 Lorelei and the Laser Eyes 같은 게임들에서 하듯이 게임의 복잡한 연결(그리고 잠재적 연결)을 추적하기 위해 수기로 페이지를 넘겨가며 노트를 할 필요가 없다는 뜻이다. 이는 자동 노트가 가끔 훑어보며 놓친 것들을 포착하기도 하지만, 훨씬 더 매끄러운 퍼즐 해결 경험을 만들어준다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TR-49 also benefits from being relatively compact compared to some other narrative deduction games. A diligent investigator can reach a conclusion in four or five hours, depending on how thorough they want to be. That makes it relatively easy to keep the broad outlines of the game’s dense but parsable world in your head over a couple of evening play sessions.&lt;br/&gt;(TR-49는 또한 다른 몇몇 서사적 추리 게임들에 비해 상대적으로 간결하다는 이점이 있다. 부지런한 탐구자는 얼마나 철저하게 하고 싶은지에 따라 4~5시간 안에 결론에 도달할 수 있다. 이는 몇 차례의 저녁 플레이 세션 동안 게임의 빽빽하지만 분석 가능한 세계의 광범위한 윤곽을 머릿속에 유지하기를 상대적으로 쉽게 만든다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are bound to be some people who see TR-49 as akin to a homework simulator, with painful flashbacks to all-nighters spent desperately researching a last-minute college term paper. For anyone who knows the inherent appeal of diving deep into a previously unknown world, though, TR-49 is an engrossing work of world-building fiction presented in a truly memorable way.&lt;br/&gt;(TR-49를 마치 숙제 시뮬레이터처럼 보며, 마감 직전 대학 학기말 리포트를 필사적으로 연구하던 밤샘 작업의 고통스러운 플래시백을 경험하는 사람들도 분명 있을 것이다. 그러나 이전에 알지 못했던 세계에 깊이 빠져드는 본연의 매력을 아는 사람들에게 TR-49는 정말로 기억에 남는 방식으로 제시된 매혹적인 세계 구축 픽션이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/tr-49-is-interactive-fiction-for-fans-of-deep-research-rabbit-holes/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/4-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:52:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A weird, itchy rash is linked to the keto diet—but no one knows why (케토 다이어트와 관련된 이상한 가려운 발진—하지만 아무도 이유를 모른다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/a-weird-itchy-rash-is-linked-to-the-keto-diet-but-no-one-knows-why/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nejmicm2514242_f1-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the rash has a clear link to ketones, the underlying mechanism remains elusive.&lt;br/&gt;(이 발진이 케톤과 명확한 연관이 있지만, 근본적인 메커니즘은 여전히 불분명하다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 20-year old man in Taiwan went to a dermatology clinic for a strange rash that had developed across his shoulders and chest. The raised, red, and itchy condition had been bothering him for a full month. By this point, he had also developed patches of pigmented skin interlaced with the red rash.&lt;br/&gt;(대만의 한 20대 남성이 어깨와 가슴에 생긴 이상한 발진으로 피부과를 찾았다. 붉고 가려운 융기된 상태가 한 달 내내 그를 괴롭혔다. 이 시점에 그는 붉은 발진과 함께 색소 침착된 피부 반점도 생겼다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a case report in the New England Journal of Medicine , a skin biopsy showed swelling between his skin cells and inflammation around blood vessels, but testing came up negative for other common signs of skin conditions, leaving doctors with few leads. The doctors ultimately came to a diagnosis not by analyzing his skin further but by hearing about his diet.&lt;br/&gt;(뉴잉글랜드 저널 오브 메디신에 실린 증례 보고서에 따르면, 피부 생검 결과 피부 세포 사이의 부종과 혈관 주변의 염증이 나타났지만, 다른 일반적인 피부 질환 징후에 대한 검사는 음성이어서 의사들은 단서를 거의 찾지 못했다. 의사들은 결국 그의 피부를 더 분석하지 않고 그의 식단에 대해 듣고 진단을 내렸다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man told doctors that two months prior to his clinic appointment—a month before his rash developed—he had switched to a ketogenic diet, which is a high-fat but very low-carbohydrate eating pattern. This diet forces the body to shift from using glucose (sugar derived from carbohydrates) as an energy source to fat instead.&lt;br/&gt;(이 남성은 병원 방문 두 달 전—발진이 생기기 한 달 전—고지방이지만 탄수화물이 매우 적은 식사 패턴인 케토제닉 다이어트를 시작했다고 의사들에게 말했다. 이 식단은 신체가 에너지원으로 탄수화물에서 유래한 포도당(당) 대신 지방을 사용하도록 강제한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this happens, the body can go into ketosis. This starts with fat tissue breaking down, leading to the release of free fatty acids. These fatty acids are transported to the liver, where they’re metabolized to acetyl-CoA. Excessive amounts of this molecule gum up metabolic processes and lead to the formation of ketone bodies , primarily acetoacetate and beta-hydroxybutyrate. (A ketone is a specific chemical structure that includes a single bond to two CH3 or R groups with a double bond to an oxygen molecule.) Ketone bodies made in the liver can enter the circulatory system and be used as a source of energy for tissues around the body, particularly the brain.&lt;br/&gt;(이런 일이 발생하면 신체는 케토시스 상태에 들어갈 수 있다. 이는 지방 조직이 분해되면서 시작되어 유리 지방산이 방출된다. 이러한 지방산은 간으로 운반되어 아세틸-CoA로 대사된다. 이 분자의 과다량은 대사 과정을 방해하고 주로 아세토아세테이트와 베타-하이드록시뷰티레이트인 케톤체의 형성을 초래한다. (케톤은 두 개의 CH3 또는 R 그룹에 단일 결합을 하고 산소 분자에 이중 결합을 하는 특정 화학 구조를 포함한다.) 간에서 생성된 케톤체는 순환계로 들어가 몸 전체 조직, 특히 뇌의 에너지원으로 사용될 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ketogenic diets have clinical uses—they’ve proven useful for managing drug-resistant epilepsy and some rare genetic metabolic diseases. Studies have looked at them as possible ways to manage obesity and type 2 diabetes, and there’s interest in their use in cancer metabolism and neurodegenerative diseases, including Parkinson’s disease and Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;br/&gt;(케토제닉 다이어트는 임상적 용도가 있다—약물 내성 간질과 일부 희귀 유전성 대사 질환 관리에 유용한 것으로 입증되었다. 연구들은 비만과 제2형 당뇨병 관리의 가능한 방법으로 살펴보았으며, 파킨슨병과 알츠하이머병을 포함한 암 대사 및 신경퇴행성 질환에서의 사용에도 관심이 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, the keto diet is popular among people trying to lose weight, particularly those trying to lose visceral fat, like the man in the case study. Anecdotal reports promote the keto diet as being effective at helping people slim down relatively quickly while also improving stamina and mental clarity. But robust clinical data supporting these claims are lacking, and medical experts have raised concerns about long-term cardiovascular health, among other things.&lt;br/&gt;(그 외에도 케토 다이어트는 체중 감량을 시도하는 사람들, 특히 증례 연구의 남성처럼 내장 지방을 줄이려는 사람들 사이에서 인기가 있다. 일화적 보고들은 케토 다이어트가 비교적 빠르게 살을 빼는 데 효과적일 뿐만 아니라 체력과 정신 명료도를 향상시킨다고 홍보한다. 하지만 이러한 주장을 뒷받침하는 확실한 임상 데이터는 부족하며, 의학 전문가들은 장기적인 심혈관 건강 등에 대한 우려를 제기해 왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also clear downsides to the diet. Ketones are acidic, and if they build up too much in the blood, they can be toxic, causing ketoacidosis. This is a particular concern for people with type 1 diabetes and for people with chronic alcohol abuse. For everyone else, there’s a list of common side effects , including nausea, vomiting, constipation, diarrhea, bad breath, headache, fatigue, and dizziness. Ketogenic diets are also linked to high cholesterol and kidney stones.&lt;br/&gt;(이 식단에는 명확한 단점도 있다. 케톤은 산성이어서 혈액에 너무 많이 축적되면 독성을 일으켜 케토산증을 유발할 수 있다. 이는 제1형 당뇨병 환자와 만성 알코올 남용자에게 특히 우려된다. 다른 모든 사람들에게는 메스꺼움, 구토, 변비, 설사, 입냄새, 두통, 피로, 현기증 등 일반적인 부작용 목록이 있다. 케토제닉 다이어트는 또한 고콜레스테롤과 신장 결석과도 관련이 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s one side effect that’s well established but little known and still puzzling to doctors: the “keto rash” or prurigo pigmentosa . This rash fits the man’s case perfectly—red, raised, itchy bumps on the neck, chest, and back, with areas of hyperpigmentation also developing.&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 잘 알려져 있지만 잘 알려지지 않고 여전히 의사들을 당혹시키는 한 가지 부작용이 있다: "케토 발진" 또는 색소성 가려움증이다. 이 발진은 목, 가슴, 등에 붉고 융기된 가려운 돌기와 함께 색소 침착 부위도 발생하는 남성의 증례와 완벽히 일치한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rash was first identified in Japan in 1971, where it was mostly seen in women. While it has been consistently linked to metabolic disorders and dietary changes, experts still don’t understand what causes it. It’s seen not only in people on a keto diet but also in people with diabetes and those who have had bariatric surgery or are fasting.&lt;br/&gt;(이 발진은 1971년 일본에서 처음 확인되었으며, 주로 여성에게서 관찰되었다. 대사 장애와 식이 변화와 꾸준히 연관되어 왔지만, 전문가들은 여전히 원인을 이해하지 못한다. 케토 다이어트를 하는 사람들뿐만 아니라 당뇨병 환자, 비만 수술을 받은 사람들 또는 단식하는 사람들에게서도 관찰된다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a review this month , researchers in Saudi Arabia noted that a leading hypothesis is that the high levels of ketones in the blood trigger inflammation around blood vessels driven by a type of white blood cell called neutrophils, and this inflammation is what causes the rash, which develops in different stages.&lt;br/&gt;(이번 달에 발표된 리뷰에서 사우디아라비아 연구자들은 주요 가설로 혈액 내 높은 케톤 수치가 호중구라는 백혈구 유형에 의해 유발된 혈관 주변 염증을 촉진하며, 이 염증이 다양한 단계로 발전하는 발진을 일으킨다는 점을 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the condition remains poorly understood, effective treatments have at least been worked out. The most common treatment is to get the person out of ketosis and give them an antibiotic in the tetracycline class. Antibiotics are designed to treat bacterial infections (which this is not), but they can also dampen inflammation signals and thwart the activity of neutrophils.&lt;br/&gt;(이 질환이 여전히 잘 이해되지 않고 있지만, 효과적인 치료법은 적어도 개발되었다. 가장 일반적인 치료법은 사람을 케토시스 상태에서 벗어나게 하고 테트라사이클린 계열의 항생제를 투여하는 것이다. 항생제는 세균 감염(이 경우는 아님)을 치료하기 위해 설계되었지만, 염증 신호를 억제하고 호중구의 활동을 방해할 수도 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the man’s case, doctors gave him a two-week course of doxycycline and told him to ditch his keto diet. A week later, the rash was gone.&lt;br/&gt;(이 남성의 경우, 의사들은 그에게 2주간의 독시사이클린 치료 과정을 처방하고 케토 다이어트를 중단하라고 지시했다. 일주일 후, 발진은 사라졌다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/health/2026/01/a-weird-itchy-rash-is-linked-to-the-keto-diet-but-no-one-knows-why/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/nejmicm2514242_f1-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 03:00:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did Edison accidentally make graphene in 1879? (에디슨이 1879년에 우연히 그래핀을 만들었을까?)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/did-edison-accidentally-make-graphene-in-1879/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/edison3-1152x632.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rice University chemists replicated Thomas Edison’s seminal experiment and found a surprising byproduct.&lt;br/&gt;(라이스 대학의 화학자들이 토머스 에디슨의 획기적인 실험을 재현했을 때 놀라운 부산물을 발견했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphene is the thinnest material yet known, composed of a single layer of carbon atoms arranged in a hexagonal lattice. That structure gives it many unusual properties that hold great promise for real-world applications: batteries, super capacitors, antennas, water filters, transistors, solar cells, and touchscreens, just to name a few. The physicists who first synthesized graphene in the lab won the 2010 Nobel Prize in Physics . But 19th century inventor Thomas Edison may have unknowingly created graphene as a byproduct of his original experiments on incandescent bulbs over a century earlier, according to a new paper published in the journal ACS Nano.&lt;br/&gt;(그래핀은 현재까지 알려진 가장 얇은 물질로, 육각형 격자로 배열된 단일 층의 탄소 원자로 구성되어 있습니다. 이 구조는 그래핀에 많은 특이한 특성을 부여하며, 배터리, 슈퍼 커패시터, 안테나, 정수 필터, 트랜지스터, 태양전지, 터치스크린 등 실제 응용 분야에 큰 가능성을 지닙니다. 실험실에서 처음으로 그래핀을 합성한 물리학자들은 2010년 노벨 물리학상을 수상했습니다. 그러나 19세기 발명가 토머스 에디슨이 1세기 이상 전 백열등에 대한 초기 실험 과정에서 무심코 그래핀을 부산물로 생성했을 수 있다는 내용이 ACS Nano 저널에 발표된 새로운 논문에서 제기되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To reproduce what Thomas Edison did, with the tools and knowledge we have now, is very exciting,” said co-author James Tour , a chemist at Rice University. “Finding that he could have produced graphene inspires curiosity about what other information lies buried in historical experiments. What questions would our scientific forefathers ask if they could join us in the lab today? What questions can we answer when we revisit their work through a modern lens?”&lt;br/&gt;(라이스 대학의 화학자이자 공동 저자인 제임스 투어는 "지금 우리가 가진 도구와 지식으로 토머스 에디슨이 했던 일을 재현하는 것은 매우 흥미롭습니다"라고 말했습니다. "그가 그래핀을 생산했을 수 있다는 사실을 발견하는 것은 역사적 실험 속에 숨겨진 다른 정보들에 대한 호기심을 자아냅니다. 우리의 과학적 선구자들이 오늘날 우리와 함께 실험실에 있다면 어떤 질문을 할까요? 우리가 현대적 시각으로 그들의 작업을 재검토할 때 어떤 질문에 답할 수 있을까요?")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edison didn’t invent the concept of incandescent lamps; there were several versions predating his efforts. However, they generally had a a very short life span and required high electric current, so they weren’t well suited to Edison’s vision of large-scale commercialization. He experimented with different filament materials starting with carbonized cardboard and compressed lampblack. This, too, quickly burnt out, as did filaments made with various grasses and canes, like hemp and palmetto. Eventually Edison discovered that carbonized bamboo made for the best filament, with life spans over 1200 hours using a 110 volt power source.&lt;br/&gt;(에디슨이 백열등의 개념을 발명한 것은 아닙니다; 그의 노력 이전에도 여러 버전이 존재했습니다. 그러나 그런 등들은 일반적으로 수명이 매우 짧고 높은 전류가 필요했기 때문에, 에디슨이 구상한 대규모 상업화에는 적합하지 않았습니다. 그는 탄화된 판지와 압축된 등유 그을음으로 시작하여 다양한 필라멘트 재료를 실험했습니다. 이것도 헴프나 팔메토 같은 다양한 풀과 줄기로 만든 필라멘트와 마찬가지로 빠르게 타버렸습니다. 결국 에디슨은 탄화된 대나무가 110볼트 전원으로 1200시간 이상의 수명을 가지는 최상의 필라멘트 재료임을 발견했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucas Eddy, Tour’s  grad student at Rice, was trying to figure out ways to mass produce graphene using the smallest, easiest equipment he could manage, with materials that were both affordable and readily available. He considered such options as arc welders and natural phenomena like lightning striking trees—both of which he admitted were “complete dead ends.” Edison’s light bulb, Eddy decided, would be ideal, since unlike other early light bulbs, Edison’s version was able to achieve the critical 2000 degree C temperatures required for flash Joule heating—the best method for making so-called turbostratic graphene .&lt;br/&gt;(라이스 대학 투어 교수의 대학원생인 루카스 에디는 가능한 한 작고 쉬운 장비로, 저렴하고 쉽게 구할 수 있는 재료를 사용하여 그래핀을 대량 생산하는 방법을 알아내려고 노력하고 있었습니다. 그는 아크 용접기나 나무를 때리는 번개 같은 자연 현상과 같은 옵션을 고려했는데, 둘 다 그가 인정한 바와 같이 "완전한 막다른 길"이었습니다. 에디는 에디슨의 전구가 이상적이라고 결정했습니다. 다른 초기 전구들과 달리, 에디슨 버전은 플래시 줄 가열에 필요한 결정적인 2000°C 온도에 도달할 수 있었기 때문입니다. 이는 소위 터보스트래틱 그래핀을 만드는 최선의 방법입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plus, Eddy had access to Edison’s original 1879 patent describing the invention process. Eddy recreated Edison’s experiment, attaching light bulbs to a 110-volt power source and switching it on for 20 seconds at a time to rapidly heat the carbon-based material to between 2000 to 3000 degrees C. (Switch it on for any longer and you get graphite rather than graphene.) Then he examined the results using a modern optical microscope.&lt;br/&gt;(게다가 에디는 발명 과정을 설명하는 에디슨의 1879년 원본 특허를 접할 수 있었습니다. 에디는 에디슨의 실험을 재현하여 전구를 110볼트 전원에 연결하고 한 번에 20초 동안 스위치를 켜 탄소 기반 재료를 2000~3000°C로 급속 가열했습니다. (더 오래 켜두면 그래핀이 아닌 흑연이 됩니다.) 그런 다음 그는 현대 광학 현미경을 사용하여 결과를 조사했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His first attempt didn’t work out because the bulbs he bought turned out to use tungsten rather than carbon filaments. “You can’t fool a chemist,” said Eddy . “But I finally found a small art store in New York City selling artisan Edison-style light bulbs.” Those artisan bulbs used bamboo filaments, with diameters a mere 5 micrometers larger than Edison’s original filaments.&lt;br/&gt;(그의 첫 번째 시도는 성공하지 못했는데, 그가 구입한 전구들이 탄소 필라멘트 대신 텅스텐 필라멘트를 사용한 것으로 밝혀졌기 때문입니다. "화학자는 속일 수 없습니다"라고 에디는 말했습니다. "하지만 결국 뉴욕시의 작은 공예품 가게에서 장인이 만든 에디슨 스타일 전구를 판매하는 것을 발견했습니다." 그 공예품 전구들은 대나무 필라멘트를 사용했으며, 직경이 에디슨의 원본 필라멘트보다 단지 5마이크로미터 더 컸습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, Eddy noticed that the carbon filament turned to a “lustrous silver.” Raman spectroscopy revealed that parts of the filament had turned into turbostratic graphene. The team also took before and after images using transmission electron microscopy . Eddy and his co-authors acknowledge that this is not definitive proof that Edison produced graphene. The inventor lacked the means to detect it even if he had been aware that such a material existed. And even if one were to analyze Edison’s original bulb, any graphene would have long since turned into graphite.&lt;br/&gt;(이번에는 에디가 탄소 필라멘트가 "빛나는 은색"으로 변한 것을 발견했습니다. 라만 분광법은 필라멘트 일부가 터보스트래틱 그래핀으로 변했음을 보여주었습니다. 연구팀은 또한 투과 전자 현미경을 사용하여 전후 이미지를 촬영했습니다. 에디와 그의 공동 저자들은 이것이 에디슨이 그래핀을 생산했다는 결정적 증거는 아니라고 인정합니다. 그 발명가는 그러한 물질이 존재한다는 것을 알고 있었다 하더라도 그것을 탐지할 수단이 없었습니다. 그리고 에디슨의 원본 전구를 분석한다 하더라도, 어떤 그래핀도 오래전에 흑연으로 변했을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors concluded by noting the research potential of revisiting other early technologies using the tools of modern materials science, such as vacuum tubes, arc lamps, and early X-ray tubes. These also may have accidentally produced unusual materials or reactions that weren’t analyzed or even noticed at the time. “Innovation can emerge from reinterpreting the past with fresh tools and new questions,” they wrote. “In the case of ‘Edison graphene,’ a 140-year-old invention continues to shed light not just literally but scientifically.”&lt;br/&gt;(저자들은 진공관, 아크 램프, 초기 X-선관과 같은 다른 초기 기술들을 현대 재료 과학의 도구를 사용하여 재검토하는 연구의 잠재력을 언급하며 결론을 맺었습니다. 이것들 또한 당시에 분석되거나 심지어 인식되지 않은 특이한 물질이나 반응을 우연히 생성했을 수 있습니다. 그들은 "혁신은 새로운 도구와 새로운 질문으로 과거를 재해석함으로써 나타날 수 있습니다"라고 썼습니다. "'에디슨 그래핀'의 경우, 140년 된 발명이 문자 그대로 뿐만 아니라 과학적으로도 계속 빛을 발하고 있습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOI: ACS Nano, 2026. 10.1021/acsnano.5c12759 ( About DOIs ).&lt;br/&gt;(DOI: ACS Nano, 2026. 10.1021/acsnano.5c12759 (DOIs 정보).)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/did-edison-accidentally-make-graphene-in-1879/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/edison3-1152x632.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 09:36:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Poland’s energy grid was targeted by never-before-seen wiper malware (폴란드 에너지망, 전례 없는 와이퍼 악성코드 공격 표적)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/wiper-malware-targeted-poland-energy-grid-but-failed-to-knock-out-electricity/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/data-wiper-malware-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Destructive payload unleashed on 10-year anniversary of Russia’s attack on Ukraine’s grid.&lt;br/&gt;(러시아의 우크라이나 전력망 공격 10주년에 맞춰 파괴적 페이로드가 배포됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers on Friday said that Poland’s electric grid was targeted by wiper malware, likely unleashed by Russia state hackers, in an attempt to disrupt electricity delivery operations.&lt;br/&gt;(연구원들은 금요일, 폴란드의 전력망이 러시아 국가 해커들에 의해 전력 공급 운영을 방해하려는 시도로 와이퍼 악성코드의 표적이 되었다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cyberattack, Reuters reported , occurred during the last week of December. The news organization said it was aimed at disrupting communications between renewable installations and the power distribution operators but failed for reasons not explained.&lt;br/&gt;(로이터 통신에 따르면, 사이버 공격은 12월 마지막 주에 발생했다. 해당 언론사는 공격이 재생에너지 시설과 배전 운영자 간의 통신을 방해하기 위한 것이었으나, 설명되지 않은 이유로 실패했다고 전했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, security firm ESET said the malware responsible was a wiper, a type of malware that permanently erases code and data stored on servers with the goal of destroying operations completely. After studying the tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs) used in the attack, company researchers said the wiper was likely the work of a Russian government hacker group tracked under the name Sandworm.&lt;br/&gt;(금요일, 보안 업체 ESET은 이 공격의 원인이 된 악성코드가 와이퍼라고 밝혔다. 와이퍼는 운영을 완전히 파괴할 목적으로 서버에 저장된 코드와 데이터를 영구적으로 삭제하는 유형의 악성코드다. 공격에 사용된 전술, 기법 및 절차(TTP)를 분석한 후, 회사 연구원들은 이 와이퍼가 샌드웜(Sandworm)이라는 이름으로 추적되는 러시아 정부 해커 그룹의 소행일 가능성이 높다고 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Based on our analysis of the malware and associated TTPs, we attribute the attack to the Russia-aligned Sandworm APT with medium confidence due to a strong overlap with numerous previous Sandworm wiper activity we analyzed,” said ESET researchers. “We’re not aware of any successful disruption occurring as a result of this attack.”&lt;br/&gt;(ESET 연구원들은 "악성코드 및 관련 TTP에 대한 우리의 분석을 바탕으로, 우리가 분석한 수많은 이전 샌드웜 와이퍼 활동과의 강력한 유사성 때문에, 이 공격을 러시아와 연계된 샌드웜 APT(지속적 위협 그룹)의 소행으로 중간 정도의 확신을 가지고 귀속시킨다"고 말했다. "우리는 이 공격으로 인해 발생한 성공적인 운영 방해 사례를 알지 못한다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sandworm has a long history of destructive attacks waged on behalf of the Kremlin and aimed at adversaries. Most notable was one in Ukraine in December 2015 . It left roughly  230,000 people without electricity for about six hours during one of the coldest months of the year. The hackers used general purpose malware known as BlackEnergy to penetrate power companies’ supervisory control and data acquisition systems and, from there, activate legitimate functionality to stop electricity distribution. The incident was the first known malware-facilitated blackout.&lt;br/&gt;(샌드웜은 크렘린을 대신하여 적대국을 겨냥한 파괴적 공격을 오랜 기간 수행해 온 역사를 가지고 있다. 가장 주목할 만한 사례는 2015년 12월 우크라이나에서 발생한 공격이다. 이 공격은 한 해 가장 추운 달 중 하나에 약 6시간 동안 약 23만 명의 사람들을 전기 없이 방치했다. 해커들은 블랙에너지(BlackEnergy)로 알려진 범용 악성코드를 사용하여 발전 회사의 감시 제어 및 데이터 수집 시스템에 침투한 후, 그곳에서 합법적인 기능을 활성화하여 전력 배전을 중단시켰다. 이 사건은 악성코드가 촉진한 최초의 정전 사례로 알려져 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ESET said the attack targeting Poland occurred on the 10th anniversary of that event. The security firm provided few other details about the attack other than the malware used has been dubbed DynoWiper.&lt;br/&gt;(ESET은 폴란드를 겨냥한 이 공격이 그 사건의 10주년에 발생했다고 말했다. 해당 보안 업체는 사용된 악성코드가 다이노와이퍼(DynoWiper)로 명명되었다는 점 외에는 공격에 대한 다른 세부 사항을 거의 제공하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Custom Wipers have long been a preferred tool for Russian hackers. In 2022 , government attackers used wiper malware dubbed AcidRain to knock out 270,000 satellite modems in Ukraine in an attempt to disrupt communications. At the time, it was the seventh wiper Russia had used against since invading the neighboring country. ESET said last year that Sandworm had unleashed multiple wipers on universities and critical infrastructure in Ukraine.&lt;br/&gt;(맞춤형 와이퍼는 오랫동안 러시아 해커들이 선호하는 도구였다. 2022년, 정부 공격자들은 우크라이나에서 통신을 방해하려는 시도로 애시드레인(AcidRain)이라는 와이퍼 악성코드를 사용하여 27만 개의 위성 모뎀을 마비시켰다. 당시 이는 러시아가 이웃 국가를 침공한 이후 사용한 일곱 번째 와이퍼였다. ESET은 작년에 샌드웜이 우크라이나의 대학 및 중요 인프라에 여러 와이퍼를 배포했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known case of Russia’s use of wipers came in 2017 with the release of NotPetya. The destructive worm was intended to target only Ukraine, but quickly spread around the world and wreaked havoc as it disrupted computer operations. The event is estimated to have cost governments and businesses $10 billion , making it likely the most expensive computer intrusion in history.&lt;br/&gt;(러시아의 와이퍼 사용 사례 중 가장 잘 알려진 것은 2017년 노트페티아(NotPetya)의 출현이다. 이 파괴적인 웜은 원래 우크라이나만을 겨냥한 것이었으나, 빠르게 전 세계로 확산되어 컴퓨터 운영을 방해하며 큰 혼란을 야기했다. 이 사건으로 정부와 기업이 약 100억 달러의 손실을 입은 것으로 추정되어, 역사상 가장 비용이 많이 든 컴퓨터 침입 사건이 될 가능성이 높다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no indication how or why DynoWiper failed to take out power. It’s possible Russia planned it to do so in an attempt to send a message without provoking Polish allies. Another possibility is that cyber defenses prevented the wiper from working as intended.&lt;br/&gt;(다이노와이퍼가 전력을 차단하는 데 실패한 방법이나 이유에 대한 징후는 없다. 러시아가 폴란드의 동맹국들을 자극하지 않으면서 메시지를 전달하려는 시도로 그렇게 계획했을 가능성이 있다. 또 다른 가능성은 사이버 방어 체계가 와이퍼가 의도한 대로 작동하는 것을 막았을 수 있다는 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/security/2026/01/wiper-malware-targeted-poland-energy-grid-but-failed-to-knock-out-electricity/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/data-wiper-malware-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:08:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A decade ofStar Trek-themed fart jokes:The Greatest Generationpodcast turns 10 (스타트렉 테마의 방귀 농담 10년: '더 그레이트 제너레이션' 팟캐스트 10주년)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/a-decade-of-star-trek-themed-fart-jokes-the-greatest-generation-podcast-turns-10/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ADAM_BEN_L1560319-2560x1440-1769205903.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How two podcasters turned a Star Trek side project into a full-time career.&lt;br/&gt;(두 팟캐스터가 어떻게 스타트렉 부업 프로젝트를 본업으로 만들었는지.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A decade is a long time for a TV series; no single iteration of Star Trek has made it that far.&lt;br/&gt;(10년은 TV 시리즈 기준으로 긴 시간이다; 스타트렉의 어떤 단일 시리즈도 그렇게 오래 가지 못했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But “a Star Trek podcast by two guys just a little bit embarrassed to have a Star Trek podcast” has now passed the milestone. January 25, 2026, marks a full decade since The Greatest Generation , my favorite podcast, debuted. Like a bottle of Château Picard, the show has only improved with age. (I interviewed the guys behind the show back in 2016 when they were just getting started.)&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 "스타트렉 팟캐스트를 한다는 게 조금 부끄러운 두 남자가 하는 스타트렉 팟캐스트"는 이제 그 이정표를 넘어섰다. 2026년 1월 25일은 내가 가장 좋아하는 팟캐스트인 '더 그레이트 제너레이션'이 데뷔한 지 꼭 10년이 되는 날이다. 샤토 피카르드 와인 한 병처럼, 이 쇼는 시간이 갈수록 더 좋아졌다. (나는 2016년, 그들이 막 시작했을 때 이 쇼의 주인공들을 인터뷰한 적이 있다.))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast helped me rediscover, and appreciate more fully, Star Trek: The Next Generation— which is also my favorite TV show. The Greatest Generation continues to delight with its irreverent humor, its celebration of the most minor of characters, and its technical fascination with how a given episode was made.&lt;br/&gt;(이 팟캐스트는 내가 스타트렉: 더 넥스트 제너레이션을 재발견하고 더 충분히 감상하는 데 도움을 줬다. 그것 또한 내가 가장 좋아하는 TV 쇼다. '더 그레이트 제너레이션'은 그 불손한 유머, 가장 사소한 캐릭터들에 대한 찬사, 그리고 특정 에피소드가 어떻게 만들어졌는지에 대한 기술적 호기심으로 계속해서 즐거움을 선사한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last decade, hosts Ben Harrison and Adam Pranica have both moved to Los Angeles and become full-time podcasters. They have completed an episode-by-episode recap of all of The Next Generation, Deep Space Nine, and Voyager , and they’re now nearing the end of Enterprise. When finished, they’re threatening/promising to start over again.&lt;br/&gt;(지난 10년 동안, 호스트 벤 해리슨과 애덤 프라니카는 둘 다 로스앤젤레스로 이사하여 전업 팟캐스터가 되었다. 그들은 더 넥스트 제너레이션, 딥 스페이스 나인, 보이저의 모든 에피소드를 하나하나 리캡하는 작업을 완료했고, 현재 엔터프라이즈의 끝부분을 막 다루고 있다. 작업을 마치면, 그들은 다시 처음부터 시작하겠다고 위협/약속하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast has spawned its own (sometimes NSFW!) lexicon (a “friend of DeSoto” means a listener to and fan of The Greatest Generation ), its own recurring and hilarious segments (“Drunk Shimoda,” “Bad Bit Moment,” and “Polo? Polo? Or Pollo?”), and most importantly, its own delightful fandom. It’s the coolest and dorkiest secret club that I will ever be a part of.&lt;br/&gt;(이 팟캐스트는 자체적인 (때로는 NSFW!) 어휘("데소토의 친구"는 '더 그레이트 제너레이션'의 청취자이자 팬을 의미한다), 자체적인 반복되는 웃긴 코너("드렁크 시모다", "배드 빗 모먼트", "폴로? 폴로? 오르 폴로?"), 그리고 가장 중요한, 자체적인 즐거운 팬덤을 탄생시켰다. 그것은 내가 속한 가장 멋지고 가장 덕후 같은 비밀 클럽이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, the podcast was folded into the Maximum Fun organization. Harrison and Pranica formed their own company, Uxbridge-Shimoda LLC, that takes its name from two obscure TNG-era characters.&lt;br/&gt;(2016년, 이 팟캐스트는 맥시멈 펀 조직에 편입되었다. 해리슨과 프라니카는 그들만의 회사인 '욱스브리지-시모다 LLC'를 설립했는데, 이 이름은 TNG 시대의 두 명의 비주류 캐릭터에서 따왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the original Star Trek , the podcast even spawned its own 2017 spinoff—now called The Greatest Trek— entirely devoted to the newer series in the Star Trek universe.&lt;br/&gt;(원조 스타트렉처럼, 이 팟캐스트는 심지어 2017년 자체 스핀오프를 탄생시켰는데, 현재 '더 그레이트 트렉'이라고 불리며 스타트렉 세계관의 새로운 시리즈에만 전념하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrison and Pranica also produce two irregularly released, members-only podcasts called Santa Monica Mountains (about the 1980s and 1990s TV show Baywatch) and Factory Seconds (where they eat at various Cheesecake Factory restaurants). Last year, they also started—in conjunction with YouTube cooking star Adam Ragusea —yet another podcast, called Wholesome , which is only available to Patreon subscribers.&lt;br/&gt;(해리슨과 프라니카는 또한 불규칙적으로 발행되는 회원 전용 팟캐스트 두 개를 제작하는데, '산타 모니카 마운틴스'(1980-90년대 TV 쇼 '베이워치'에 관한)와 '팩토리 세컨즈'(그들이 다양한 치즈케이크 팩토리 레스토랑에서 식사하는)이다. 작년에는 유튜브 요리 스타 애덤 라구세아와 협력하여 '홀섬'이라는 또 다른 팟캐스트를 시작했는데, 이는 패트리온 구독자만 이용할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world replete with chaos and awfulness, I’m just here for the hang.&lt;br/&gt;(혼란과 끔찍함으로 가득 찬 세상에서, 나는 그냥 여기서 친구들과 어울리기 위해 있는 거다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This interview, which was conducted earlier this month, has been lightly edited for clarity and flow.)&lt;br/&gt;((이 인터뷰는 이번 달 초에 진행되었으며, 명확성과 흐름을 위해 약간 편집되었습니다.))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: When I first spoke to you guys back in 2016, Adam was living in Seattle. Ben, I believe you were living in New York. You guys were still working in film production. As best as I could tell, this was just a fun little side project. Who knew how long it would run? Ben : I think that us talking to you has a lot to do with it taking over our lives.&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 제가 2016년 처음 여러분과 이야기했을 때, 애덤은 시애틀에 살고 있었어요. 벤, 당신은 뉴욕에 살고 있었다고 믿어요. 여러분은 아직 영화 제작 일을 하고 있었죠. 제가 알기로는, 이건 그냥 재미있는 작은 부업 프로젝트였어요. 누가 이게 얼마나 오래 갈지 알았겠어요? 벤: 우리가 당신과 이야기한 게 우리 삶을 완전히 장악하는 데 큰 역할을 한 것 같아요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: Sorry, not sorry? I don’t know! [laughs]&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 미안해요, 안 미안해요? 모르겠네요! [웃음])&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : Your Ars article was one of the reasons we catapulted into the sort of audience we got afterward. It’s an audience that has meant we’ve been able to do the show professionally for 10 years.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 당신의 아스 테크니카 기사는 우리가 그 후 얻은 규모의 청중 속으로 도약하게 된 이유 중 하나였어요. 그 청중 덕분에 우리는 10년 동안 이 쇼를 전문적으로 할 수 있었죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben : Yeah. And when we meet people—all the time—people will say: “Oh, I’ve been listening to you guys since the beginning. Like, I was on at episode five because of that Ars Technica article.”&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 맞아요. 그리고 우리가 사람들을 만날 때면—늘 그렇듯—사람들이 이렇게 말하죠: "오, 처음부터 들었어요. 아스 테크니카 기사 때문에 에피소드 5부터 시작했죠.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: D o you feel like you are over it? It’s been a decade now. Is Greatest Gen as we know it going to continue?&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 이제 질렸다고 느끼시나요? 벌써 10년이 지났어요. 우리가 아는 그 '그레이트 젠'은 계속될 건가요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : I think the thing that’s changed is that in the beginning, it felt like a fun hobby. But when you professionalize a thing and you hire employees and you are depended on for the thing that you make in a way that you’ve never been before, it’s serious business.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 달라진 점은, 처음에는 그냥 재미있는 취미처럼 느껴졌다는 거예요. 하지만 어떤 일을 전문직으로 만들고 직원을 고용하고, 당신이 만드는 것에 대해 이전과는 다른 방식으로 의존받게 되면, 그건 진지한 사업이에요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s serious funny business, you know?&lt;br/&gt;(진지한 웃음 사업이죠, 그렇죠?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the best job I’ve ever had, but it’s also the most seriously I’ve ever taken a job because it means so much to our well-being, but also the folks who appreciate what we do.&lt;br/&gt;(이건 내가 가진 직업 중 최고지만, 동시에 내가 가장 진지하게 대했던 직업이기도 해요. 왜냐하면 이건 우리의 웰빙뿐만 아니라 우리가 하는 일을 감상하는 사람들에게도 너무나 의미 있기 때문이죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben : Yeah, one thing that Adam has said many times is we’re going to die in these chairs.&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 맞아요, 애덤이 여러 번 말한 게 하나 있는데, 우리는 이 의자에서 죽을 거라고 했어요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I think also, as we come toward the end of Enterprise and have sort of run out of the well of Old Trek, as it were, I have been thinking about [what] if I hadn’t had this show? I would still be about ready to start my next TNG rewatch.&lt;br/&gt;(그리고 또, 우리가 엔터프라이즈의 끝부분으로 가면서 일종의 '올드 트렉'의 샘물이 바닥나가고 있는 것 같아서, 나는 생각해왔어요. 만약 이 쇼가 없었다면? 나는 아직도 다음 TNG 재방송을 시작할 준비를 하고 있을 거라고요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loving Star Trek is a lot about watching it over again, you know? In the same way that I’ll put on an old rerun of The Simpsons or Seinfeld . And I love rewatching those shows. I love rewatching Star Trek .&lt;br/&gt;(스타트렉을 사랑하는 건 대부분 다시 보는 거예요, 그렇죠? 내가 심슨이나 세인펠드의 오래된 재방송을 틀어놓는 것처럼요. 나는 그 쇼들을 다시 보는 걸 좋아해요. 스타트렉을 다시 보는 걸 좋아해요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Adam and I have grown as both a comedy duo but also as observers of Star Trek and what it means on an ongoing basis. So I feel like it would be unfair for us not to go back and start painting the bridge from the beginning.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤과 나는 코미디 듀오로서 뿐만 아니라 스타트렉의 관찰자로서, 그리고 그것이 지속적으로 의미하는 바에 대해서도 성장했다고 생각해요. 그래서 우리가 돌아가서 처음부터 다리를 다시 칠하지 않는 건 불공평할 것 같아요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : I think one of the things that we’ve learned from doing the show, especially live in front of people, is that we are told by the people who enjoy this show that it’s about Star Trek, sure, but that’s not the thing that people love the most about the show.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 우리가 쇼를 하면서 배운 것 중 하나, 특히 사람들 앞에서 라이브로 할 때는, 이 쇼를 즐기는 사람들이 우리에게 말해주는 건, 이 쇼가 스타트렉에 관한 건 맞지만, 사람들이 이 쇼를 가장 사랑하는 건 그게 아니라는 거예요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I think that’s what makes a return to the beginning of it make so much sense in the way Ben’s describing. It’s about the hang and your life as it relates to a Star Trek rerun that you’re watching in that moment.&lt;br/&gt;(그리고 그게 벤이 설명하는 방식대로 처음으로 돌아가는 게 그렇게 말이 되는 이유인 것 같아요. 이건 친구들과 어울리는 거고, 그 순간 당신이 보고 있는 스타트렉 재방송과 관련된 당신의 삶에 관한 거예요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: I have watched zero minutes of Baywatch in my life. But I have listened to every single episode of the Santa Monica Mountains . I enjoy hearing you guys talk about it.&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 저는 평생 베이워치를 단 1분도 본 적이 없어요. 하지만 '산타 모니카 마운틴스'의 모든 에피소드를 다 들었어요. 여러분이 그것에 대해 이야기하는 걸 듣는 게 즐거워요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you’ve hit on a format: “Let’s talk about a thing in the way that we like to talk about it and make jokes in the way that we like to make jokes about it.” Which for me really resonates more than the format of a podcast that’s like: “Let’s get comedians to talk about a thing.”&lt;br/&gt;(여러분은 하나의 형식을 발견한 것 같아요: "우리가 좋아하는 방식으로 어떤 것에 대해 이야기하고, 우리가 좋아하는 방식으로 그것에 대해 농담을 만들어보자." 제게는 그게 "코미디언들을 불러다가 어떤 것에 대해 이야기하게 하자" 같은 형식의 팟캐스트보다 훨씬 더 공감이 가요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : Or let’s get celebrities in a room to talk about anything and have that be good enough.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 아니면 유명인들을 방에 불러다가 아무 것이나 이야기하게 하고 그걸로 충분하다고 생각하는 거죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben : The format that our shows tend to follow is something that I think just kind of was an emergent property of the way Adam and I talked to each other, much more so than it was us attempting to create a show that was our version of anything else.&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 우리 쇼들이 따르는 형식은, 애덤과 내가 서로에게 이야기하는 방식에서 자연스럽게 나타난 속성 같은 거라고 생각해요. 우리가 다른 무엇의 우리 버전이 되는 쇼를 만들려고 시도했던 것보다 훨씬 더 그렇죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t really listen to other recap podcasts. It’s kind of a funny thing, but we weren’t really inspired by any recap podcasts in particular. I guess the Flop House a little bit for me, but what they do is so different and such its own thing.&lt;br/&gt;(저는 다른 리캡 팟캐스트를 잘 안 들어요. 좀 웃긴 일이지만, 우리는 특정 리캡 팟캐스트에서 영감을 받은 건 아니에요. 제게는 '플롭 하우스'가 조금은 그렇지만, 그들이 하는 건 너무 다르고 너무 독자적인 거예요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to feel like we are connected to the universe of recap podcasts. Like when we go to add our show to a podcast service like iTunes or Apple Podcasts, you have to pick the category that you’re going to be in, and we’ve always picked comedy.&lt;br/&gt;(우리가 리캡 팟캐스트 세계와 연결되어 있다고 느끼기 어려워요. 예를 들어 우리가 아이튠즈나 애플 팟캐스트 같은 팟캐스트 서비스에 우리 쇼를 추가할 때, 속할 카테고리를 골라야 하는데, 우리는 항상 코미디를 골랐어요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Properly, I guess we probably would be in the television recap podcast section. We just never really thought of ourselves as being that. We were just doing what we wanted to do.&lt;br/&gt;(제대로라면 아마도 TV 리캡 팟캐스트 섹션에 들어가야 할 텐데요. 우리는 그렇게 생각해본 적이 없었어요. 우리는 그냥 우리가 하고 싶은 걸 했을 뿐이죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, we’re just making a show that makes us laugh. Making each other laugh has always been the primary goal of the show.  So it’s very funny to me that we’re in a category that we’ve never really aspired to be in or compared ourselves to in any way.&lt;br/&gt;(알다시피, 우리는 그냥 우리를 웃게 만드는 쇼를 만들고 있어요. 서로를 웃게 만드는 게 항상 이 쇼의 주요 목표였어요. 그래서 우리가 한 번도 열망해본 적 없거나 전혀 비교해본 적 없는 카테고리에 있다는 게 매우 웃겨요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: Any favorite moments, perhaps at live shows, that have happened to you over the last 10 years?&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 지난 10년 동안 여러분에게 일어난, 아마도 라이브 쇼에서의 좋아하는 순간이 있나요?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben : Getting to do live shows at all has been a total shock to me. When we talked to you for that first article, we barely knew what we were doing as entertainers. And I’ve taken improv classes and stuff but never really had any personal aspirations to be someone who gets up on a stage and does something. And I found that I fucking love it!&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 라이브 쇼를 할 수 있다는 자체가 저에게는 완전한 충격이었어요. 우리가 첫 기사를 위해 당신과 이야기했을 때, 우리는 엔터테이너로서 우리가 뭘 하고 있는지 거의 몰랐어요. 저는 임프로브 클래스를 듣고 그런 것도 했지만, 무대에 올라가서 무언가를 하는 사람이 되겠다는 개인적인 포부는 전혀 없었어요. 그런데 제가 그걸 정말 좋아한다는 걸 발견했어요!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love doing the show in front of an audience! And we just have had so many amazing adventures getting to go all over the country doing that.&lt;br/&gt;(저는 관객 앞에서 쇼를 하는 걸 정말 좋아해요! 그리고 우리는 전국을 돌아다니며 그걸 하면서 정말 많은 놀라운 모험을 했어요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all over the world—we’ve done the show in Canada and London now. That was a total surprise to me.&lt;br/&gt;(그리고 전 세계적으로—우리는 캐나다와 런던에서도 쇼를 했어요. 그건 저에게 완전한 놀라움이었죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like, if you grabbed me on the street 15 years ago and said, “Hey, you’re going to have a show that you get to travel around and do in front of audiences of 300 people someday!” I would have said, “Get the hell out of here! That’s not possible. That’s not something I am working toward in any way.”&lt;br/&gt;(예를 들어, 15년 전에 저를 길거리에서 붙잡고 "야, 너 언젠가 300명 관객 앞에서 여행 다니며 할 쇼를 가지게 될 거야!"라고 말했다면, 저는 "꺼져! 그건 불가능해. 그건 내가 어떤 식으로든 추구하는 게 아니야."라고 말했을 거예요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : There’s an unexpected quality to the type of—I mean, barf, right? I’m going to say the word “celebrity.” But David Letterman said that when you achieve a certain amount of notoriety, the world becomes a neighborhood to you.&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 일종의—음, 구역질 나지, 그렇죠? '유명인'이라는 단어를 말할 거예요. 하지만 데이비드 레터맨이 말했듯이, 당신이 어느 정도의 명성을 얻으면, 세상이 당신에게 이웃이 된다고요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week ago, I was at a bar with friends, and a stranger came up and told me that they really like our show and they thanked me for making it. And that is something that happens in my life in a way that I never could have anticipated at all.&lt;br/&gt;(일주일 전, 저는 친구들과 바에 있었는데, 낯선 사람이 다가와 우리 쇼를 정말 좋아한다고 말하고, 제게 그것을 만들어줘서 고맙다고 했어요. 그건 제 삶에서 전혀 예상하지 못했던 방식으로 일어나는 일이에요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s those little moments that you have with people. Those perfect interactions where it’s just like: “I like what you do and thanks for doing it.”&lt;br/&gt;(사람들과 가진 그런 작은 순간들이죠. 그냥 "당신이 하는 일 좋아해요, 해줘서 고마워요" 같은 완벽한 상호작용이요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes my life seem meaningful in a way that any previous job did not create the conditions for, you know? You do the work and you think it matters and it’s important, and largely it is in its own way, in its own ecosystem.&lt;br/&gt;(그건 제 삶을 의미 있게 느끼게 해줘요. 어떤 이전 직업도 그런 조건을 만들어주지 못했던 방식으로요, 그렇죠? 당신은 일을 하고 그게 중요하고 의미 있다고 생각하지만, 대체로 그것은 그 자체의 방식으로, 그 자체의 생태계 안에서 중요하죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to have a broad interest from folks in what you do and that it matters to them and what they do in their lives? That’s the very best part of this entire thing: knowing that the times that I can make Ben laugh are also the times that I can make 500 people laugh in a room or 25,000 people laugh on a Monday when the episode drops, you know?&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 사람들이 당신이 하는 일에 광범위한 관심을 가지고, 그게 그들에게 중요하고 그들의 삶에서 하는 일에 중요하다는 걸 아는 건? 그게 이 모든 것 중 가장 좋은 부분이에요: 제가 벤을 웃게 만들 수 있는 순간들이, 동시에 한 방에서 500명을 웃게 만들거나, 에피소드가 나오는 월요일에 25,000명을 웃게 만들 수 있는 순간이라는 걸 아는 거죠, 그렇죠?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s really powerful stuff! And it keeps me on my best behavior when I’m out in public in case an FOD is out there watching what I’m doing.&lt;br/&gt;(그건 정말 강력한 거예요! 그리고 그것은 제가 공공장소에 나갔을 때 FOD(데소토의 친구)가 저의 행동을 지켜보고 있을지도 모르니 최선의 행동을 하게 만들어요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben : Oh, yeah. You don’t want to see all the videos of Adam on Worldstar .&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 오, 맞아요. 당신은 월드스타에 있는 애덤의 모든 비디오를 보고 싶지 않을 거예요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam : Exactly. Yeah. So lock it up!&lt;br/&gt;(애덤: 정확해요. 맞아요. 그러니까 단단히 잠가요!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ars: Y ou try really hard to make the show sound great, which it does. It is well-engineered. It is well mixed. You guys put a lot of care into the production of the show.&lt;br/&gt;(아스: 여러분은 쇼가 정말 좋게 들리도록 굉장히 노력하시는데, 실제로 그렇게 들려요. 잘 설계되었고, 잘 믹싱되었어요. 여러분은 쇼 제작에 많은 신경을 쓰시네요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But also, to my knowledge, you have never missed a show’s publish date. I’m curious about how you balance all of that with whatever else is going on in your lives. Ben, you have two young kids. I know Adam has martinis to drink and golf to play.&lt;br/&gt;(하지만 또한 제가 아는 한, 여러분은 쇼의 발행 날짜를 한 번도 놓친 적이 없어요. 어떻게 그 모든 것을 삶의 다른 일들과 균형을 맞추는지 궁금해요. 벤, 당신은 어린 아이가 둘이시죠. 애덤은 마티니를 마시고 골프를 쳐야 한다는 것도 알아요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben: I think the best thing that has happened to us as a duo over the years has been all of the people who have been here to help us along the way.&lt;br/&gt;(벤: 우리 듀오로서 지난 몇 년간 우리에게 일어난 가장 좋은 일은, 길에서 우리를 도와준 모든 사람들이었다고 생각해요.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, for a while, we were working with a producer named Rob Schulte, who was really great. And we’re now very fortunate to have a full-time producer named Wynde Priddy, who is so good at anticipating things that are coming up and keeping our minds on what we need to be prepping for the future. And also taking all of the stuff off of our plate that involves the day-in, day-out of editing and producing the shows.&lt;br/&gt;(알다시피, 한동안 우리는 롭 슐테라는 프로듀서와 일했는데, 그는 정말 대단했어요. 그리고 우리는 이제 와인드 프리디라는 전임 프로)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/a-decade-of-star-trek-themed-fart-jokes-the-greatest-generation-podcast-turns-10/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/ADAM_BEN_L1560319-2560x1440-1769205903.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former astronaut on lunar spacesuits: “I don’t think they’re great right now” (전직 우주비행사가 달 우주복에 대해: "지금은 그렇게 훌륭하지 않다고 생각합니다")</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/former-astronaut-on-lunar-spacesuits-i-dont-think-theyre-great-right-now/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/jsc2025e077725-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These are just the difficulties of designing a spacesuit for the lunar environment.”&lt;br/&gt;("이것들은 단지 달 환경을 위한 우주복을 설계하는 데 따르는 어려움일 뿐입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crew members traveling to the lunar surface on NASA’s Artemis missions should be gearing up for a grind. They will wear heavier spacesuits than those worn by the Apollo astronauts, and NASA will ask them to do more than the first Moonwalkers did more than 50 years ago.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA의 아르테미스 임무로 달 표면을 향해 여행할 승무원들은 힘든 작업에 대비해야 할 것입니다. 그들은 아폴로 우주비행사들이 착용했던 것보다 더 무거운 우주복을 입게 될 것이며, NASA는 50여 년 전 첫 달 탐사자들이 했던 것보다 더 많은 일을 요구할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Moonwalking experience will amount to an “extreme physical event” for crews selected for the Artemis program’s first lunar landings, a former NASA astronaut told a panel of researchers, physicians, and engineers convened by the National Academies.&lt;br/&gt;(달 보행 경험은 아르테미스 프로그램의 첫 달 착륙 임무에 선발된 승무원들에게 "극한의 신체적 사건"이 될 것이라고 전 NASA 우주비행사가 국립과학원이 소집한 연구자, 의사, 엔지니어 패널에게 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate Rubins, who retired from the space agency last year, presented the committee with her views on the health risks for astronauts on lunar missions. She outlined the concerns NASA officials often talk about: radiation exposure, muscle and bone atrophy, reduced cardiovascular and immune function, and other adverse medical effects of spaceflight.&lt;br/&gt;(작년에 우주국을 떠난 케이트 루빈스는 위원회에 달 임무 우주비행사들의 건강 위험에 대한 자신의 견해를 제시했습니다. 그녀는 NASA 관계자들이 자주 논의하는 우려 사항들 - 방사선 노출, 근육 및 뼈 위축, 심혈관 및 면역 기능 저하, 그리고 우주 비행의 기타 부정적인 의학적 영향들 - 을 개괄했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists and astronauts have come to understand many of these effects after a quarter-century of continuous human presence on the International Space Station. But the Moon is different in a few important ways. The Moon is outside the protection of the Earth’s magnetosphere, lunar dust is pervasive, and the Moon has partial gravity, about one-sixth as strong as the pull we feel on Earth.&lt;br/&gt;(과학자들과 우주비행사들은 국제우주정거장에서 25년간 지속된 인간의 존재를 통해 이러한 영향들 중 많은 부분을 이해하게 되었습니다. 하지만 달은 몇 가지 중요한 면에서 다릅니다. 달은 지구 자기권의 보호 밖에 있으며, 달 먼지는 곳곳에 존재하고, 달은 부분 중력을 가지고 있어 지구에서 느끼는 중력의 약 1/6 수준입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these presents challenges for astronauts living and working on the lunar surface, and their effects are amplified for crew members who venture outside for spacewalks. NASA selected Axiom Space, a Houston-based company, for a $228 million fixed-price contract to develop commercial pressurized spacesuits for the Artemis III mission, slated to be the first human landing mission on the Moon since 1972.&lt;br/&gt;(이 각각은 달 표면에서 생활하고 작업하는 우주비행사들에게 도전 과제를 제시하며, 그 영향은 우주 유영을 위해 외부로 나가는 승무원들에게 더욱 증폭됩니다. NASA는 휴스턴에 기반을 둔 회사인 액시엄 스페이스를 선정하여 2028년 말까지 비행할 것으로 예정된, 1972년 이후 첫 유인 달 착륙 임무인 아르테미스 III 임무를 위한 상업용 가압 우주복 개발을 위해 2억 2800만 달러의 고정 가격 계약을 체결했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA hopes to fly the Artemis III mission by the end of 2028, but the schedule is in question. The readiness of Axiom’s spacesuits and the availability of new human-rated landers from SpaceX and Blue Origin are driving the timeline for Artemis III.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA는 2028년 말까지 아르테미스 III 임무를 비행하기를 희망하지만, 일정은 불확실합니다. 액시엄의 우주복 준비 상태와 스페이스X 및 블루 오리진의 새로운 유인 착륙선 가용성이 아르테미스 III의 타임라인을 결정짓고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubins is a veteran of two long-duration spaceflights on the International Space Station, logging 300 days in space and conducting four spacewalks totaling nearly 27 hours. She is also an accomplished microbiologist and became the first person to sequence DNA in space.&lt;br/&gt;(루빈스는 국제우주정거장에서 두 차례의 장기 우주 비행 경험을 가진 베테랑으로, 총 300일간 우주에 체류했으며 총 27시간에 가까운 4차례의 우주 유영을 수행했습니다. 그녀는 또한 뛰어난 미생물학자이며 우주에서 DNA 서열 분석을 최초로 수행한 사람이기도 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I think we have on the Moon that we don’t really have on the space station that I want people to recognize is an extreme physical stress,” Rubins said. “On the space station, most of the time you’re floating around. You’re pretty happy. It’s very relaxed. You can do exercise. Every now and then, you do an EVA (Extravehicular Activity, or spacewalk).”&lt;br/&gt;("우리가 우주정거장에는 없지만 달에는 있는, 사람들이 인식했으면 하는 것은 극한의 신체적 스트레스입니다."라고 루빈스는 말했습니다. "우주정거장에서는 대부분의 시간 동안 떠다닙니다. 꽤 행복합니다. 매우 느긋합니다. 운동을 할 수 있습니다. 가끔씩 EVA(선외 활동, 즉 우주 유영)를 합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When we get to the lunar surface, people are going to be sleep shifting,” Rubins said. “They’re barely going to get any sleep. They’re going to be in these suits for eight or nine hours. They’re going to be doing EVAs every day. The EVAs that I did on my flights, it was like doing a marathon and then doing another marathon when you were done.”&lt;br/&gt;("달 표면에 도착하면 사람들은 수면 패턴이 바뀔 것입니다."라고 루빈스는 말했습니다. "거의 잠을 잘 수 없을 것입니다. 8시간이나 9시간 동안 이 우주복을 입고 있을 것입니다. 매일 EVA를 할 것입니다. 제 비행 중에 했던 EVA는 마라톤을 한 다음, 끝나고 또 다른 마라톤을 하는 것과 같았습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubins is now a professor of computational and systems biology at the University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine. She said treks on the Moon will be “even more challenging” than her spacewalks outside the ISS.&lt;br/&gt;(루빈스는 현재 피츠버그 대학교 의과대학의 계산 및 시스템 생물학 교수입니다. 그녀는 달에서의 탐사가 ISS 외부에서의 그녀의 우주 유영보다 "훨씬 더 도전적"일 것이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Axiom spacesuit design builds on NASA’s own work developing a prototype suit to replace the agency’s decades-old Extravehicular Mobility Units (EMUs) used for spacewalks at the International Space Station (ISS). The new suits allow for greater mobility, with more flexible joints to help astronauts use their legs, crouch, and bend down—things they don’t have to do when floating outside the ISS.&lt;br/&gt;(액시엄 우주복 설계는 NASA 자체의 프로토타입 우주복 개발 작업을 기반으로 하며, 이는 국제우주정거장(ISS)에서 우주 유영에 사용되는 기관의 수십 년 된 선외 이동 장치(EMU)를 대체하기 위한 것입니다. 새로운 우주복은 더 큰 기동성을 허용하며, 더 유연한 관절로 우주비행사들이 다리를 사용하고, 쪼그려 앉고, 몸을 굽힐 수 있도록 도와줍니다. 이는 ISS 외부에서 떠다닐 때는 할 필요가 없는 동작들입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Astronauts on the Moon also must contend with gravity. Including a life-support backpack, the commercial suit weighs more than 300 pounds in Earth’s gravity, but Axiom considers the exact number proprietary. The Axiom suit is considerably heavier than the 185-pound spacesuit the Apollo astronauts wore on the Moon. NASA’s earlier prototype exploration spacesuit was estimated to weigh more than 400 pounds, according to a 2021 report by NASA’s inspector general .&lt;br/&gt;(달 위의 우주비행사들은 또한 중력과도 맞서야 합니다. 생명 유지 장치 배낭을 포함한 상업용 우주복의 무게는 지구 중력 하에서 300파운드(약 136kg) 이상이지만, 액시엄은 정확한 수치는 기밀로 간주합니다. 액시엄 우주복은 아폴로 우주비행사들이 달에서 착용했던 185파운드(약 84kg) 우주복보다 상당히 무겁습니다. NASA의 이전 프로토타입 탐사 우주복은 NASA 감찰관의 2021년 보고서에 따르면 400파운드(약 181kg) 이상으로 추정되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve definitely seen trauma from the suits, from the actual EVA suit accommodation,” said Mike Barratt, a NASA astronaut and medical doctor. “That’s everything from skin abrasions to joint pain to—no kidding—orthopedic trauma. You can potentially get a fracture of sorts. EVAs on the lunar surface with a heavily loaded suit and heavy loads that you’re either carrying or tools that you’re reacting against, that’s an issue.”&lt;br/&gt;("우리는 확실히 우주복, 실제 EVA 우주복 적응으로 인한 외상을 목격했습니다."라고 NASA 우주비행사이자 의사인 마이크 배럿이 말했습니다. "그것은 피부 찰과상부터 관절 통증, 농담이 아니라 정형외과적 외상까지 모든 것입니다. 어떤 종류의 골절을 입을 수도 있습니다. 무거운 우주복을 입고 달 표면에서 EVA를 수행하며, 운반하거나 도구를 사용하며 반작용을 받는 무거운 하중, 그것이 문제입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper, the Axiom suits for NASA’s Artemis missions are more capable than the Apollo suits. They can support longer spacewalks and provide greater redundancy, and they’re made of modern materials to enhance flexibility and crew comfort. But the new suits are heavier, and for astronauts used to spacewalks outside the ISS, walks on the Moon will be a slog, Rubins said.&lt;br/&gt;(서면상으로, NASA의 아르테미스 임무를 위한 액시엄 우주복은 아폴로 우주복보다 더 능력이 있습니다. 더 긴 우주 유영을 지원하고 더 큰 중복성을 제공하며, 유연성과 승무원 편의성을 향상시키기 위해 현대적 재료로 만들어졌습니다. 하지만 새로운 우주복은 더 무겁고, ISS 외부의 우주 유영에 익숙한 우주비행사들에게 달 보행은 힘든 고행이 될 것이라고 루빈스는 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the suits are better than Apollo, but I don’t think they are great right now,” Rubins said. “They still have a lot of flexibility issues. Bending down to pick up rocks is hard. The center of gravity is an issue. People are going to be falling over. I think when we say these suits aren’t bad, it’s because the suits have been so horrible that when we get something slightly less than horrible, we get all excited and we celebrate.”&lt;br/&gt;("저는 우주복이 아폴로보다는 낫다고 생각하지만, 지금은 그렇게 훌륭하지 않다고 생각합니다."라고 루빈스는 말했습니다. "여전히 많은 유연성 문제가 있습니다. 돌을 줍기 위해 몸을 굽히는 것은 어렵습니다. 무게 중심이 문제입니다. 사람들은 넘어질 것입니다. 우리가 이 우주복이 나쁘지 않다고 말할 때, 그것은 우주복이 너무 끔찍했기 때문에 약간 덜 끔찍한 것을 얻으면 우리가 모두 흥분하고 축하하기 때문이라고 생각합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heavier lunar suits developed for Artemis missions run counter to advice from former astronaut Harrison “Jack” Schmitt, who spent 22 hours walking on the Moon during NASA’s Apollo 17 mission in 1972.&lt;br/&gt;(아르테미스 임무를 위해 개발된 더 무거운 달 우주복은 1972년 NASA의 아폴로 17호 임무 동안 달에서 22시간 동안 보행한 전직 우주비행사 해리슨 "잭" 슈미트의 조언과 상반됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’d have that go about four times the mobility, at least four times the mobility, and half the weight,” Schmitt said in a NASA oral history interview in 2000 . “Now, one way you can… reduce the weight is carry less consumables and learn to use consumables that you have in some other vehicle, like a lunar rover. Anytime you’re on the rover, you hook into those consumables and live off of those, and then when you get off, you live off of what’s in your backpack. We, of course, just had the consumables in our backpack.”&lt;br/&gt;("저는 기동성을 적어도 네 배, 적어도 네 배로 늘리고 무게는 절반으로 줄였으면 합니다."라고 슈미트는 2000년 NASA 구술 역사 인터뷰에서 말했습니다. "자, 무게를 줄일 수 있는 한 가지 방법은... 소모품을 적게 운반하고, 달 탐사차와 같은 다른 차량에 있는 소모품을 사용하는 법을 배우는 것입니다. 탐사차에 탈 때마다, 그 소모품에 연결하여 그것들로 생활하고, 내리면 배낭에 있는 것으로 생활하는 거죠. 물론 우리는 배낭에 소모품만 가지고 있었습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA won’t have a rover on the first Artemis landing mission. That will come on a later flight. A fully pressurized vehicle for astronauts to drive across the Moon may be ready sometime in the 2030s. Until then, Moonwalkers will have to tough it out.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA는 첫 아르테미스 착륙 임무에는 탐사차를 갖지 않을 것입니다. 그것은 후속 비행에서 이루어질 것입니다. 우주비행사들이 달을 가로질러 운전할 수 있는 완전 가압 차량은 2030년대 어느 시점에 준비될 수 있습니다. 그때까지 달 보행자들은 힘겹게 견뎌내야 할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do crossfit. I do triathlons. I do marathons. I get out of a session in the pool in the NBL ( Neutral Buoyancy Laboratory ) doing the lunar suit underwater, and I just want to go home and take a nap,” Rubins told the panel. “I am absolutely spent. You’re bruised. This is an extreme physical event in a way that the space station is not.”&lt;br/&gt;("저는 크로스핏을 합니다. 철인 3종 경기를 합니다. 마라톤을 합니다. NBL(중성 부력 연구소) 수영장에서 달 우주복을 입고 수중 훈련을 한 세션을 마치고 나면, 그냥 집에 가서 낮잠을 자고 싶습니다."라고 루빈스는 패널에게 말했습니다. "저는 완전히 지쳐버립니다. 멍이 듭니다. 이것은 우주정거장과는 다른 방식의 극한의 신체적 사건입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barratt met with the same National Academies panel this week and presented a few hours before Rubins. The committee was chartered to examine how human explorers can enable scientific discovery at sites across the lunar surface. Barratt had a more favorable take on the spacesuit situation.&lt;br/&gt;(배럿은 이번 주 같은 국립과학원 패널과 만나 루빈스보다 몇 시간 앞서 발표했습니다. 위원회는 인간 탐사자들이 어떻게 달 표면 전역의 현장에서 과학적 발견을 가능하게 할 수 있는지 검토하기 위해 구성되었습니다. 배럿은 우주복 상황에 대해 더 호의적인 입장을 보였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not a commercial for Axiom. I don’t promote anyone, but their suit is getting there,” Barratt said. “We’ve got 700 hours of pressurized experience in it right now. We do a lot of tests in the NBL, and there are techniques and body conditioning that you do to help you get ready for doing things like this. Bending down in the suit is really not too bad at all.”&lt;br/&gt;("이것은 액시엄 광고가 아닙니다. 저는 누구도 홍보하지 않지만, 그들의 우주복은 거의 다 왔습니다."라고 배럿은 말했습니다. "우리는 지금 그 우주복으로 700시간의 가압 경험을 가지고 있습니다. 우리는 NBL에서 많은 테스트를 하며, 이런 일을 준비하는 데 도움이 되는 기술과 신체 컨디셔닝을 합니다. 우주복을 입고 몸을 굽히는 것은 정말 전혀 나쁘지 않습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubins and Barratt did not discuss the schedule for when Axiom’s lunar spacesuit will be ready to fly to the Moon, but the conversation illuminated the innumerable struggles of spacewalking, Moonwalking, and the training astronauts undergo to prepare for extravehicular outings.&lt;br/&gt;(루빈스와 배럿은 액시엄의 달 우주복이 언제 달로 비행할 준비가 될지에 대한 일정은 논의하지 않았지만, 대화는 우주 유영, 달 보행, 그리고 우주비행사들이 선외 활동을 준비하기 위해 겪는 무수한 고난을 조명했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spoke directly with Rubins after her discussion with the National Academies. Her last assignment at NASA was as chief of the EVA and robotics branch in the astronaut office, where she assisted in the development of the new lunar spacesuits. I asked about her experiences testing the lunar suit and her thoughts on how astronauts should prepare for Moonwalks.&lt;br/&gt;(저는 루빈스가 국립과학원과의 논의 후 그녀와 직접 이야기했습니다. 그녀의 NASA에서의 마지막 임무는 우주비행사 사무소의 EVA 및 로봇공학 부서장이었으며, 그곳에서 그녀는 새로운 달 우주복 개발을 지원했습니다. 저는 그녀에게 달 우주복 테스트 경험과 우주비행사들이 달 보행을 어떻게 준비해야 하는지에 대한 생각을 물었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The suits that we have are definitely much better than Apollo,” Rubins said in the interview. “They were just big bags of air. The joints aren’t in there, so it was harder to move. What they did have going for them was that they were much, much lighter than our current spacesuits. We have added a lot of the joints back, and that does get some mobility for us. But at the end of the day, the suits are still quite heavy.”&lt;br/&gt;("우리가 가진 우주복은 확실히 아폴로보다 훨씬 낫습니다."라고 루빈스는 인터뷰에서 말했습니다. "그것들은 그냥 큰 공기 주머니였습니다. 관절이 없어서 움직이기 더 어려웠습니다. 그들이 가진 장점은 우리 현재 우주복보다 훨씬, 훨씬 가볍다는 것이었습니다. 우리는 많은 관절을 다시 추가했고, 그것은 우리에게 어느 정도 기동성을 제공합니다. 하지만 결국, 우주복은 여전히 꽤 무겁습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can divide the weight of the suit by six to get an idea of how it might feel to carry it around on the lunar surface. While it won’t feel like 300 pounds, astronauts will still have to account for their mass and momentum.&lt;br/&gt;(우주복의 무게를 6으로 나누면 달 표면에서 그것을 들고 다니는 느낌이 어떨지 짐작할 수 있습니다. 300파운드처럼 느껴지지는 않겠지만, 우주비행사들은 여전히 자신의 질량과 운동량을 고려해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rubins explained:&lt;br/&gt;(루빈스는 설명했습니다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of kind of floating in microgravity and moving your mass around with your hands and your arms, now we’re ambulating. We’re walking with our legs. You’re going to have more strain on your knees and your hips. Your hamstrings, your calves, and your glutes are going to come more into play.&lt;br/&gt;(미세 중력에서 떠다니며 손과 팔로 질량을 움직이는 대신, 이제 우리는 걷습니다. 우리는 다리로 걷습니다. 무릎과 엉덩이에 더 많은 부담이 갈 것입니다. 햄스트링, 종아리, 엉덩이 근육이 더 많이 사용될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, overall, it may be a better fit for humans physically because if you ask somebody to do a task, I’m going to be much better at a task if I can use my legs and I’m ambulating. Then I have to pull myself along with my arms… We’re not really built to do that, but we are built to run and to go long distances. Our legs are just such a powerful force.&lt;br/&gt;(전반적으로, 신체적으로 인간에게 더 적합할 수 있다고 생각합니다. 왜냐하면 누군가에게 작업을 요청한다면, 제가 다리를 사용하고 걷는다면 그 작업을 훨씬 더 잘할 수 있기 때문입니다. 그런데 팔로 제 자신을 끌어당겨야 한다면... 우리는 그렇게 하도록 만들어지지 않았지만, 달리고 먼 거리를 가도록 만들어졌습니다. 우리 다리는 정말 강력한 힘입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think there are a lot of things lining up that are going to make the physiology easier. Then there are things that are going to be different because we’re we’re now in a partial gravity environment. We’re going to be bending, we’re going to be twisting, we’re going to be doing different things.&lt;br/&gt;(그래서 생리학적으로 더 쉬워질 많은 것들이 있다고 생각합니다. 그런데 부분 중력 환경에 있기 때문에 달라질 것들도 있습니다. 우리는 몸을 굽히고, 비틀고, 다른 일들을 하게 될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an incredibly hard engineering challenge. You have to keep a human alive in absolute vacuum, warm at temperatures that you know in the polar regions could go as far down as 40 Kelvin (minus 388° Fahrenheit). We haven’t sent humans anywhere that cold before. They are also going to be very hot. They’re going to be baking in the sunshine. You’ve got radiation. If you put all that together, that’s a huge amount of suit material just to keep the human physiology and the human body intact.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 엄청나게 어려운 공학적 도전입니다. 절대 진공 상태에서 인간을 생존하게 해야 하며, 극지방에서는 40켈빈(화씨 영하 388도)까지 떨어질 수 있는 온도에서 따뜻하게 해야 합니다. 우리는 그렇게 추운 곳에 인간을 보낸 적이 없습니다. 또한 매우 뜨거울 것입니다. 햇빛에 구워질 것입니다. 방사선도 있습니다. 이 모든 것을 합치면, 인간 생리학과 인체를 온전히 유지하기 위한 엄청난 양의 우주복 재료가 필요합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then our challenge is ‘how do you make that mobile?’ It’s very difficult to bend down and pick up a rock. You have to manage that center of gravity because you’re wearing that big life support system on your back, a big pack that has a lot of mass in it, so that brings your center of gravity higher than you’re used to on Earth and a little bit farther backward.&lt;br/&gt;(그런 다음 우리의 도전은 '어떻게 그것을 움직이게 할 것인가?'입니다. 몸을 굽혀 돌을 줍는 것은 매우 어렵습니다. 등에 큰 생명 유지 시스템, 많은 질량을 가진 큰 배낭을 메고 있기 때문에 무게 중심을 관리해야 합니다. 그래서 무게 중심이 지구에서 익숙한 것보다 높고 약간 더 뒤로 이동합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you move around, it’s like wearing a really, really heavy backpack that has mass but no weight, so it’s going to kind of tip you back. You can do some things with putting weights on the front of the suit to try to move that center of gravity forward, but it’s still higher, and it’s not exactly at your center of mass that you’re used to on the Earth. On the Earth, we have a center of our mass related to gravity, and nobody ever thinks about it, and you don’t think about it until it moves somewhere else, and then it makes all of your natural motion seem very difficult.&lt;br/&gt;(움직일 때, 질량은 있지만 무게는 없는 정말, 정말 무거운 배낭을 메고 있는 것과 같아서 뒤로 기울어지게 할 것입니다. 우주복 앞쪽에 무게를 달아 무게 중심을 앞으로 이동시키려는 시도를 할 수 있지만, 여전히 높고 지구에서 익숙한 질량 중심과 정확히 일치하지 않습니다. 지구에서는 중력과 관련된 우리 질량의 중심이 있고, 아무도 그것에 대해 생각하지 않으며, 그것이 다른 곳으로 이동할 때까지 생각하지 않다가, 그러면 모든 자연스러운 움직임이 매우 어려워 보이게 만듭니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are some of the challenges that we’re facing engineering-wise. I think the new suits, they’ve gone a long way toward addressing these, but it’s still a hard engineering challenge. And I’m not talking about any specific suit. I can’t talk about the details of the provider’s suits. This is the NASA xEMU and all the lunar suits I have tested over the years. That includes the Mark III suit , the Axiom suit. They have similar issues. So this isn’t really anything about a specific vendor. These are just the difficulties of designing a spacesuit for the lunar environment.&lt;br/&gt;(이것들이 우리가 공학적으로 직면하고 있는 일부 도전 과제들입니다. 새로운 우주복들은 이러한 문제들을 해결하는 데 큰 진전을 이루었지만, 여전히 어려운 공학적 도전입니다. 그리고 저는 특정 우주복에 대해 말하는 것이 아닙니다. 공급업체 우주복의 세부 사항에 대해 말할 수 없습니다. 이것은 NASA의 xEMU와 제가 수년 동안 테스트한 모든 달 우주복들입니다. 여기에는 Mark III 우주복, 액시엄 우주복이 포함됩니다. 그들은 비슷한 문제들을 가지고 있습니다. 그래서 이것은 특정 공급업체에 대한 것이 아닙니다. 이것들은 단지 달 환경을 위한 우주복을 설계하는 데 따르는 어려움일 뿐입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA trains astronauts for spacewalks in the Neutral Buoyancy Laboratory, an enormous pool in Houston used for simulating weightlessness. They also use a gravity-offloading device to rehearse the basics of spacewalking. The optimal test environment, short of the space environment itself, will be aboard parabolic flights, where suit developers and astronauts can get the best feel for the suit’s momentum, according to Rubins.&lt;br/&gt;(NASA는 중성 부력 연구소에서 우주비행사들을 우주 유영 훈련시킵니다. 이는 휴스턴에 있는 무중력을 시뮬레이션하는 데)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/space/2026/01/former-astronaut-on-lunar-spacesuits-i-dont-think-theyre-great-right-now/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/jsc2025e077725-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 03:00:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>EU launches formal investigation of xAI over Grok’s sexualized deepfakes (EU, 그록의 성적 딥페이크 관련 xAI에 대한 공식 조사 개시)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/eu-launches-formal-investigation-of-xai-over-groks-sexualized-deepfakes/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/xai-grok-1152x648-1752596823.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk’s company faces fines of up to 6 percent of its daily turnover.&lt;br/&gt;(일론 머스크의 회사는 일일 매출의 최대 6%에 달하는 벌금에 직면할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The EU has launched a formal investigation into Elon Musk’s xAI following a public outcry over how its Grok chatbot spread sexualized images of women and children.&lt;br/&gt;(EU는 그록(Grok) 챗봇이 여성과 아동의 성적 이미지를 유포한 방식에 대한 공중의 격렬한 반발을 받고 일론 머스크의 xAI에 대한 공식 조사를 시작했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The billionaire entrepreneur has come under scrutiny from regulators around the world this month after people began using Grok to generate deepfakes of people without consent. The images were posted on the X social network as well as the separate Grok app, both of which are run by xAI.&lt;br/&gt;(이 억만장자 기업가는 사람들이 동의 없이 개인의 딥페이크를 생성하기 위해 그록을 사용하기 시작한 후 이번 달 전 세계 규제 당국의 검토를 받고 있습니다. 해당 이미지는 xAI가 운영하는 X 소셜 네트워크와 별도의 그록 앱에 게시되었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probe, announced on Monday under the EU’s Digital Services Act, will assess if xAI tried to mitigate the risks of deploying Grok’s tools on X and the proliferation of content that “may amount to child sexual abuse material.”&lt;br/&gt;(월요일 EU 디지털 서비스법(DSA)에 따라 발표된 이 조사는 xAI가 X에 그록 도구를 배포하는 위험과 "아동 성적 학대 자료에 해당할 수 있는" 콘텐츠의 확산을 완화하려고 시도했는지 평가할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Non-consensual sexual deepfakes of women and children are a violent, unacceptable form of degradation,” the EU’s tech chief, Henna Virkkunen, said.&lt;br/&gt;(헨나 비르쿠넨 EU 기술 담당 집행위원은 "여성과 아동에 대한 비동의 성적 딥페이크는 폭력적이고 용납할 수 없는 형태의 굴욕"이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With this investigation, we will determine whether X has met its legal obligations under the DSA, or whether it treated rights of European citizens—including those of women and children—as collateral damage of its service.”&lt;br/&gt;("이번 조사를 통해 X가 DSA에 따른 법적 의무를 이행했는지, 아니면 유럽 시민의 권리—여성과 아동의 권리를 포함하여—를 서비스의 부수적 피해로 취급했는지 판단할 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the company is found to be in breach of the rules, the bloc can impose fines worth up to 6 percent of the worldwide annual turnover. An EU official said there will be no interim measures during the investigation.&lt;br/&gt;(회사가 규칙을 위반한 것으로 판명되면, EU는 전 세계 연간 매출의 최대 6%에 달하는 벌금을 부과할 수 있습니다. EU 관계자는 조사 기간 동안 임시 조치는 없을 것이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European probe comes after UK media regulator Ofcom opened a formal investigation into Grok, while Malaysia and Indonesia have banned the chatbot altogether.&lt;br/&gt;(이번 유럽의 조사는 영국 미디어 규제 기관 오프컴(Ofcom)이 그록에 대한 공식 조사를 시작한 데 이어 이루어졌으며, 말레이시아와 인도네시아는 해당 챗봇을 완전히 금지했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the backlash, xAI restricted the use of Grok to paying subscribers and said it has “implemented technological measures” to limit Grok from generating certain sexualized images.&lt;br/&gt;(반발에 직면한 xAI는 그록 사용을 유료 구독자로 제한하고, 특정 성적 이미지 생성을 그록이 제한하도록 "기술적 조치를 시행했다"고 밝혔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musk has also said “anyone using Grok to make illegal content will suffer the same consequences as if they upload illegal content.”&lt;br/&gt;(머스크는 또한 "불법 콘텐츠를 만들기 위해 그록을 사용하는 사람은 불법 콘텐츠를 업로드할 때와 동일한 결과를 겪을 것"이라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An EU official said that “with the harm that is exposed to individuals that are subject to these images, we have not been convinced so far by what mitigating measures the platform has taken to have that under control.”&lt;br/&gt;(EU 관계자는 "이러한 이미지의 대상이 되는 개인들에게 노출되는 피해를 고려할 때, 플랫폼이 그러한 상황을 통제하기 위해 취한 완화 조치에 대해 지금까지 확신을 얻지 못했습니다"라고 말했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company, which acquired Musk’s social media site X last year, has designed its AI products to have fewer content “guardrails” than competitors such as OpenAI and Google. Musk called its Grok model “maximally truth-seeking.”&lt;br/&gt;(작년 머스크의 소셜 미디어 사이트 X를 인수한 이 회사는 자사의 AI 제품이 OpenAI나 구글과 같은 경쟁사보다 콘텐츠 '안전 장치'가 적도록 설계했습니다. 머스크는 그록 모델을 "진실을 극대화하여 추구하는" 모델이라고 칭했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission fined X €120 million in December last year for breaching its regulations for transparency, providing insufficient access to data and the deceptive design of its blue ticks for verified accounts.&lt;br/&gt;(집행위원회는 지난해 12월 X에 투명성 규정 위반, 데이터에 대한 불충분한 접근 제공, 인증 계정의 블루 틱에 대한 기만적 디자인으로 1억 2천만 유로의 벌금을 부과했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fine was criticized by Musk and the US government, with the Trump administration claiming the EU was unfairly targeting American groups and infringing freedom of speech principles championed by the Maga movement.&lt;br/&gt;(이 벌금은 머스크와 미국 정부의 비판을 받았으며, 트럼프 행정부는 EU가 미국 기업을 부당하게 겨냥하고 매가(Maga) 운동이 옹호하는 표현의 자유 원칙을 침해하고 있다고 주장했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;X did not immediately reply to a request for comment.&lt;br/&gt;(X는 코멘트 요청에 즉시 답변하지 않았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© 2026 The Financial Times Ltd . All rights reserved. Not to be redistributed, copied, or modified in any way.&lt;br/&gt;(© 2026 The Financial Times Ltd. 판권 소유. 재배포, 복사 또는 어떤 방식으로든 수정할 수 없습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/eu-launches-formal-investigation-of-xai-over-groks-sexualized-deepfakes/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/xai-grok-1152x648-1752596823.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:17:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to getDoomrunning on a pair of earbuds (이어버드에서 둠(Doom) 실행하는 방법)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/how-to-get-doom-running-on-a-pair-of-earbuds/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/PineBuds-Pro-4-1152x648-1769443386.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No display? No problem for the UART-to-web-server “Doombuds” project.&lt;br/&gt;(디스플레이가 없어도 문제없는 UART-to-web-server "둠버즈(Doombuds)" 프로젝트.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, hackers and modders at large have made it their mission to port classic first-person shooter Doom to practically anything with a display . Recently, though, coder Arin Sarkisan has taken the “Can it Run Doom ?” idea in an unlikely direction: wireless earbuds that aren’t designed to output graphics at all.&lt;br/&gt;(수년간 해커와 모더들은 클래식 1인칭 슈팅 게임 '둠'을 디스플레이가 있는 거의 모든 기기에 포팅하는 것을 자신들의 사명으로 삼아왔습니다. 하지만 최근 코더 아린 사르키산(Arin Sarkisan)은 "이것도 둠을 돌릴 수 있을까?"라는 아이디어를 예상치 못한 방향으로 이끌었습니다: 그래픽 출력을 전혀 고려하지 않은 무선 이어버드에서 말이죠.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, this hack doesn’t apply to any generic set of earbuds. The “Doombuds” project is designed specifically for the PineBuds Pro , which are unique in featuring completely open source firmware and a community-maintained SDK .&lt;br/&gt;(명확히 하자면, 이 해킹은 일반적인 이어버드 세트에는 적용되지 않습니다. "둠버즈" 프로젝트는 특히 파인버즈 프로(PineBuds Pro)를 위해 설계되었으며, 이 제품은 완전한 오픈 소스 펌웨어와 커뮤니티에서 관리하는 SDK를 갖춘 독특한 특징을 가지고 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means Sarkisan was able to code up a JavaScript interface that uses the earbuds’ UART contact pads to send a heavily compressed MJPEG video stream to a web server (via a serial server). The 2.4 MB/s data stream from the UART connection can put out about 22 to 27 frames per second in this format, which is more than enough for a CPU that can only run the game at a maximum of 18 fps anyway.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 사르키산이 이어버드의 UART 접점 패드를 사용하여 고도로 압축된 MJPEG 비디오 스트림을 웹 서버(시리얼 서버를 통해)로 전송하는 JavaScript 인터페이스를 코딩할 수 있었음을 의미합니다. UART 연결의 2.4 MB/s 데이터 스트림은 이 형식으로 초당 약 22~27프레임을 출력할 수 있는데, 이는 어차피 최대 18 fps로만 게임을 실행할 수 있는 CPU에 충분한 수준입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Squeezing the entirety of Doom onto modern earbuds wasn’t an easy task, either. The 4.2MB of game data won’t quite fit on the PineBuds’ 4MB of flash memory, for instance. That means the project needed to use a 1.7MB “squashware” build of Doom , which eliminates some animation frames and shortens some music tracks to make the game even more portable.&lt;br/&gt;(둠 전체를 현대식 이어버드에 압축하는 것도 쉬운 일이 아니었습니다. 예를 들어, 4.2MB의 게임 데이터는 파인버즈의 4MB 플래시 메모리에 딱 맞지 않습니다. 이는 프로젝트가 1.7MB의 "스쿼시웨어(squashware)" 빌드 버전의 둠을 사용해야 했음을 의미하는데, 이 버전은 일부 애니메이션 프레임을 제거하고 일부 음악 트랙을 단축하여 게임을 더욱 휴대 가능하게 만듭니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The earbuds also have just under 1MB of RAM, requiring the coding of a new version of the game that optimizes away many of the bits that usually fill up a full 4MB of RAM in the standard game. “Pre-generating lookup tables, making variables const, reading const variables from flash, disabling DOOM’s caching system, removing unneeded variables… it all adds up,” Sarkisan writes.&lt;br/&gt;(또한 이어버드는 1MB 미만의 RAM만 가지고 있어, 표준 게임에서 보통 4MB의 RAM을 가득 채우는 많은 부분을 최적화하여 제거한 새로운 버전의 게임을 코딩해야 했습니다. "조회 테이블 사전 생성, 변수를 const로 만들기, const 변수를 플래시에서 읽기, 둠의 캐싱 시스템 비활성화, 불필요한 변수 제거... 이 모든 것이 합쳐졌습니다,"라고 사르키산은 설명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those without their own PineBuds to test this wild idea, Sarkisan has set up an interactive Twitch stream that players can queue up to control for 45-second sessions via doombuds.com . It’s a great little break-time diversion, especially for people ready to marvel that a set of $70 earbuds can now run a game that required a $1,000-plus computer tower a few decades ago.&lt;br/&gt;(이 기발한 아이디어를 직접 테스트할 파인버즈가 없는 사람들을 위해, 사르키산은 doombuds.com을 통해 플레이어가 대기열에 올라 45초 세션 동안 조종할 수 있는 인터랙티브 트위치 스트림을 설정했습니다. 특히 수십 년 전에는 1,000달러 이상의 컴퓨터 본체가 필요했던 게임을 이제 70달러짜리 이어버드 세트가 실행할 수 있다는 사실에 놀랄 준비가 된 사람들에게는 훌륭한 작은 휴식 시간 오락입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2026/01/how-to-get-doom-running-on-a-pair-of-earbuds/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/PineBuds-Pro-4-1152x648-1769443386.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:13:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Data center power outage took out TikTok first weekend under US ownership (미국 소유 첫 주말, 데이터센터 정전으로 틱톡 먹통)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-glitches-caused-by-data-center-power-outage-us-joint-venture-says/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257704765-1024x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US TikTok users experienced a wide range of errors, sparking conspiracies.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 틱톡 사용자들이 다양한 오류를 경험하며 음모론이 촉발됐다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok has been glitching for US users since Sunday, and TikTok’s new US owners have finally confirmed the cause: a power outage at a US data center.&lt;br/&gt;(일요일부터 미국 사용자들을 대상으로 틱톡이 오작동을 일으켰고, 틱톡의 새 미국 소유주들은 마침내 원인을 확인했다: 미국 데이터센터의 정전.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Since yesterday we’ve been working to restore our services following a power outage at a US data center impacting TikTok and other apps we operate,” the TikTok USDS Joint Venture posted on X on Monday morning. “We’re working with our data center partner to stabilize our service. We’re sorry for this disruption and hope to resolve it soon.”&lt;br/&gt;("어제부터 미국 데이터센터 정전의 영향으로 틱톡과 우리가 운영하는 다른 앱들의 서비스를 복구하기 위해 작업 중입니다,"라고 틱톡 USDS 합작회사가 월요일 아침 X에 게시했다. "우리는 데이터센터 파트너와 협력하여 서비스를 안정화하고 있습니다. 이번 불편을 사과드리며 조속히 해결하도록 하겠습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A DownDetector report tracking outages showed problems began early Sunday morning, with the majority of problems seemingly resolved by early Monday. However, The Verge reported that some US users continue to experience issues, including issues logging in, long delays uploading videos, generic content flooding For You pages, problems accessing comments, and other issues.&lt;br/&gt;(서비스 중단을 추적하는 DownDetector 보고서에 따르면 문제는 일요일 이른 아침에 시작되어 월요일 이른 아침까지 대부분 해결된 것으로 보인다. 그러나 The Verge는 일부 미국 사용자들이 여전히 로그인 문제, 동영상 업로드 지연, For You 페이지의 일반 콘텐츠 범람, 댓글 접근 문제 등 다양한 문제를 경험하고 있다고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that the TikTok USDS Joint Venture is still working to resolve problems connected to the power outage. But their decision to remain silent while the app got buggy during the first weekend under the control of right-wing US owners hand-picked by Donald Trump sparked conspiracy theories on social media that the app had begun censoring left-leaning users.&lt;br/&gt;(틱톡 USDS 합작회사가 정전과 관련된 문제를 해결하기 위해 여전히 작업 중인 것은 분명하다. 그러나 도널드 트럼프가 직접 선정한 우익 성향의 미국 소유주들의 통제 하에 첫 주말 동안 앱이 버그로 인해 불안정해졌을 때 침묵을 지키기로 한 결정은 소셜 미디어에서 앱이 좌파 성향 사용자들을 검열하기 시작했다는 음모론을 촉발시켰다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the app comes back online, users have also taken note that TikTok is collecting more of their data under US control. As Wired reported , TikTok asked US users to agree to a new terms of service and privacy policy, which allows TikTok to potentially collect “more detailed information about its users, including precise location data.”&lt;br/&gt;(앱이 다시 온라인 상태가 되면서 사용자들은 또한 틱톡이 미국 통제 하에서 더 많은 데이터를 수집하고 있음을 주목했다. Wired가 보도한 바와 같이, 틱톡은 미국 사용자들에게 새로운 이용약관과 개인정보 처리방침에 동의할 것을 요청했는데, 이는 틱톡이 "사용자들에 대한 더 상세한 정보, 정확한 위치 데이터를 포함하여" 잠재적으로 수집할 수 있도록 허용한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Before this update, the app did not collect the precise, GPS-derived location data of US users,” Wired reported. “Now, if you give TikTok permission to use your phone’s location services, then the app may collect granular information about your exact whereabouts.”&lt;br/&gt;("이번 업데이트 전에는 앱이 미국 사용자들의 정확한 GPS 기반 위치 데이터를 수집하지 않았습니다,"라고 Wired는 보도했다. "이제, 틱톡에 휴대전화 위치 서비스 사용 권한을 부여하면, 앱은 당신의 정확한 위치에 대한 세부 정보를 수집할 수 있습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New policies also pushed users to agree to share all their AI interactions, which allows TikTok to store their metadata and trace AI inputs back to specific accounts.&lt;br/&gt;(새로운 정책들은 또한 사용자들이 모든 AI 상호작용을 공유하는 데 동의하도록 유도했는데, 이는 틱톡이 그들의 메타데이터를 저장하고 AI 입력을 특정 계정으로 추적할 수 있게 한다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already seeming more invasive and less reliable, for TikTok users, questions likely remain how much their favorite app might change under new ownership, as the TikTok USDS Joint Venture prepares to retrain the app’s algorithm.&lt;br/&gt;(이미 더 침습적이고 덜 신뢰할 수 있는 것으로 보이는 틱톡에 대해, 사용자들은 틱톡 USDS 합작회사가 앱의 알고리즘을 재훈련할 준비를 하면서, 좋아하는 앱이 새 소유주 하에서 얼마나 많이 변할지에 대한 의문이 남아 있을 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has said that he wants to see the app become “100 percent MAGA,” prompting fears that “For You” pages might soon be flooded with right-wing content or that leftist content like anti-ICE criticism might be suppressed. And The Information reported in July that transferring millions of users over to the US-trained app is expected to cause more “technical issues.”&lt;br/&gt;(트럼프는 앱이 "100% MAGA(트럼프 지지)"가 되기를 원한다고 말했는데, 이는 "For You" 페이지가 곧 우익 콘텐츠로 범람하거나 ICE(이민세관단속국) 비판과 같은 좌파 콘텐츠가 억제될 수 있다는 우려를 불러일으켰다. 또한 The Information은 7월에 수백만 사용자를 미국에서 훈련된 앱으로 이전하는 것이 더 많은 "기술적 문제"를 일으킬 것으로 예상된다고 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/tiktok-glitches-caused-by-data-center-power-outage-us-joint-venture-says/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2257704765-1024x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:23:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The brothers meet Yoshi inSuper Mario Galaxy Movietrailer (슈퍼 마리오 갤럭시 영화 예고편에서 형제가 요시와 만나다)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/yoshi-joins-the-fun-in-latest-super-mario-galaxy-movie-trailer/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/mario2-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toad: “So some dinosaur just shows up and he’s now part of the group. Cool.”&lt;br/&gt;(키노피오: "그냥 공룡 하나가 나타나서 이제 우리 팀원이 됐다고? 멋지네.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Universal Pictures and Illumination dropped a new trailer for the upcoming Super Mario Galaxy Movie, and gaming fans will no doubt be delighted at the news that Yoshi, the little green dinosaur, features prominently, along with plenty of other Easter eggs for sharp-eyed fans.&lt;br/&gt;(유니버설 픽처스와 일루미네이션이 곧 개봉 예정인 슈퍼 마리오 갤럭시 영화의 새로운 예고편을 공개했으며, 게임 팬들은 작은 녹색 공룡 요시가 두드러지게 등장하고 날카로운 눈을 가진 팬들을 위한 다양한 이스터 에그가 가득하다는 소식에 분명히 기뻐할 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As previously reported , the first attempt at a Super Mario movie adaptation in 1993 was notoriously a dismal failure , although it still has its ’90s-nostalgic fans. But 2023’s Super Mario Bros. Movie won over gaming fans who were skeptical about another adaptation— including Ars Senior Gaming Editor Kyle Orland.&lt;br/&gt;(이전에 보도된 바와 같이, 1993년 최초의 슈퍼 마리오 영화 각색 시도는 악명 높게 처참한 실패로 끝났지만, 여전히 90년대 향수를 느끼는 팬들이 있습니다. 그러나 2023년 슈퍼 마리오 브라더스 영화는 또 다른 각색에 회의적이었던 게임 팬들, 아스 테크놀로지의 시니어 게임 에디터 카일 올랜드를 포함해 사로잡았습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2023 film reintroduced Mario and Luigi, two tight-knit but struggling Brooklyn plumbers who got separated when they unexpectedly fell into the fantastical Mushroom Kingdom. Mario sought Princess Peach’s help to rescue his brother from the evil clutches of Bowser, ruler of the Dark Lands, who was keen to marry Peach and threatened to destroy the Mushroom Kingdom with a Super Star if she refused him. So Peach led Mario on a quest to recruit allies and stop Bowser for good. They succeeded, shrinking Bowser and imprisoning him in a jar. Mario and Luigi moved to the Mushroom Kingdom and continued their plumbing work there.&lt;br/&gt;(2023년 영화는 긴밀하지만 어려움을 겪는 브루클린 배관공 형제 마리오와 루이지가 환상적인 버섯 왕국에 뜻밖에 떨어져 흩어지는 이야기를 다시 소개했습니다. 마리오는 다크 랜즈의 지배자 쿠파의 악랄한 손아귀에서 동생을 구출하기 위해 피치 공주의 도움을 구했습니다. 쿠파는 피치와 결혼하기를 간절히 원했고, 그녀가 거부하면 슈퍼 스타로 버섯 왕국을 파괴하겠다고 위협했습니다. 그래서 피치는 마리오를 이끌고 동맹을 모아 쿠파를 영원히 막기 위한 여정을 떠났습니다. 그들은 성공하여 쿠파를 축소시켜 병에 가두었습니다. 마리오와 루이지는 버섯 왕국으로 이사해 그곳에서 배관 작업을 계속했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main voice cast is returning for the sequel: Chris Pratt as Mario, Charlie Day as Luigi, Anya Taylor-Joy as Princess Peach, Jack Black as Bowser, Keegan-Michael Key as the anthropomorphic mushroom Toad, and Kevin Michael Richardson as Bowser’s advisor and informant Kamek. We’re also getting two new cast members: Brie Larson as Princess Rosalina, protector of the cosmos and the Lumas, and Benny Safdie as Bowser, Jr., Bowser’s son and heir to the throne. Directors Aaron Horvath and Michael Jelenic are also back, as is screenwriter Matthew Fogel.&lt;br/&gt;(주요 성우 캐스트가 속편을 위해 돌아옵니다: 크리스 프랫(마리오), 찰리 데이(루이지), 안야 테일러-조이(피치 공주), 잭 블랙(쿠파), 키건-마이클 키(의인화된 버섯 키노피오), 케빈 마이클 리처드슨(쿠파의 고문이자 정보원 카멕). 또한 두 명의 새로운 캐스트 멤버가 합류합니다: 브리 라슨(우주와 루마의 수호자 로젤리나 공주), 베니 사프디(쿠파의 아들이자 왕위 계승자 쿠파 주니어). 아론 호바스와 마이클 젤레닉 감독도 돌아왔으며, 각본가 매튜 포겔도 다시 참여합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details on the actual plot are fuzzy, but the first trailer (released last November) focused on Bowser and Bowser Jr., who seemed intent on freeing his dad and (one assumes) taking revenge on the brothers. This latest trailer shows Mario and Luigi at the scene of a “troubled” pipe in the desert of San Kingdom, populated by the sombrero-wearing Tostarenans. When they clear away some rubble covering an opening, who should be lurking inside but Yoshi—not a monster to hit with fire flowers, but a friendly green dinosaur. Yoshi is keen to join the team, although Toad seems less than impressed.&lt;br/&gt;(실제 줄거리에 대한 세부 사항은 아직 명확하지 않지만, 지난 11월 공개된 첫 번째 예고편은 아버지를 풀어주고 (추정컨대) 형제들에게 복수하려는 듯한 쿠파와 쿠파 주니어에 초점을 맞췄습니다. 이번 최신 예고편은 샌 왕국 사막의 "문제 있는" 배관 현장에 있는 마리오와 루이지를 보여줍니다. 그곳은 솜브레로를 쓴 토스타레난들이 살고 있습니다. 그들이 구멍을 덮고 있는 잔해를 치우자, 그 안에 숨어 있는 것은 다름 아닌 요시였습니다. 불꽃 꽃으로 공격해야 할 괴물이 아니라, 친근한 녹색 공룡이었죠. 요시는 팀에 합류하고 싶어 하지만, 키노피오는 그다지 감동하지 않은 듯합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Super Mario Galaxy Movie hits theaters on April 1, 2026.&lt;br/&gt;(슈퍼 마리오 갤럭시 영화는 2026년 4월 1일 극장에서 개봉됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/culture/2026/01/yoshi-joins-the-fun-in-latest-super-mario-galaxy-movie-trailer/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/mario2-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:05:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How to encrypt your PC’s disk without giving the keys to Microsoft (마이크로소프트에 키를 넘기지 않고 PC 디스크를 암호화하는 방법)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/how-to-encrypt-your-pcs-disk-without-giving-the-keys-to-microsoft/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/win11-pc-2023-1152x648.jpeg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storing recovery keys with Microsoft allows the company to unlock your disk.&lt;br/&gt;(복구 키를 마이크로소프트에 저장하면 회사가 사용자의 디스크를 잠금 해제할 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2025, Forbes reports , investigators at the FBI served Microsoft with a warrant seeking the BitLocker encryption recovery keys for several laptops it believed held evidence of fraud in Guam’s COVID-19 unemployment assistance program. And Microsoft complied with the FBI’s request.&lt;br/&gt;(2025년 초, 포브스 보도에 따르면 FBI 수사관들이 괌의 COVID-19 실업 지원 프로그램 사기 사건의 증거를 보유한 것으로 추정되는 여러 노트북의 BitLocker 암호화 복구 키를 요구하는 영장을 마이크로소프트에 발부했습니다. 그리고 마이크로소프트는 FBI의 요청에 응했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BitLocker is the name of the full-disk encryption technology that has been part of Windows for nearly two decades. Though initially only available to owners of the Pro editions of Windows who turned it on manually, during the Windows 8 era Microsoft began using BitLocker to encrypt local disks automatically for all Windows 11 Home and Pro PCs that signed in with a Microsoft account. Using BitLocker in this way also uploads a recovery key for your device to Microsoft’s servers—this makes it possible to unlock your disk so you don’t lose data if something goes wrong with your system, or if you install a CPU upgrade or some other hardware change that breaks BitLocker. But it also (apparently) makes it possible for Microsoft to unlock your disk, too.&lt;br/&gt;(BitLocker는 거의 20년 동안 Windows의 일부였던 전체 디스크 암호화 기술의 이름입니다. 처음에는 수동으로 켜는 Windows Pro 에디션 소유자만 사용할 수 있었지만, Windows 8 시대에 마이크로소프트는 Microsoft 계정으로 로그인한 모든 Windows 11 Home 및 Pro PC의 로컬 디스크를 자동으로 암호화하기 위해 BitLocker를 사용하기 시작했습니다. 이러한 방식으로 BitLocker를 사용하면 장치의 복구 키가 마이크로소프트 서버에 업로드됩니다. 이는 시스템에 문제가 발생하거나 CPU 업그레이드 또는 BitLocker를 중단시키는 다른 하드웨어 변경을 설치할 때 데이터를 잃지 않도록 디스크 잠금을 해제할 수 있게 해줍니다. 하지만 (분명히) 마이크로소프트도 사용자의 디스크를 잠금 해제할 수 있게 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Microsoft rep said that the company handled “around 20” similar BitLocker recovery key requests from government authorities per year, and that these requests often fail because users haven’t stored their recovery keys on Microsoft’s servers. Microsoft and other tech companies have generally refused requests to install universal encryption backdoors for law enforcement purposes, and some companies (like Apple) claim to store device encryption keys using another layer of encryption that renders the keys inaccessible to the company.&lt;br/&gt;(마이크로소프트 대변인은 회사가 정부 당국으로부터 연간 약 20건의 유사한 BitLocker 복구 키 요청을 처리하며, 이러한 요청은 사용자가 복구 키를 마이크로소프트 서버에 저장하지 않은 경우 종종 실패한다고 말했습니다. 마이크로소프트와 다른 기술 기업들은 일반적으로 법 집행 목적의 보편적 암호화 백도어 설치 요청을 거부해 왔으며, 일부 기업들(예: Apple)은 회사가 키에 접근할 수 없도록 하는 또 다른 암호화 계층을 사용하여 장치 암호화 키를 저장한다고 주장합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But storing your device’s recovery keys in someone else’s cloud can still represent a privacy and security risk, especially at a time when the US government has become more interested in targeting journalists and the Trump administration’s political opponents.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 사용자의 장치 복구 키를 타인의 클라우드에 저장하는 것은 여전히 프라이버시와 보안 위험을 나타낼 수 있습니다, 특히 미국 정부가 언론인과 트럼프 행정부의 정치적 반대자들을 대상으로 하는 데 더 관심을 보이는 시기에 더욱 그렇습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to encrypt your Windows PC’s disk but you don’t want to store your recovery key with Microsoft, you do have options. We’ll recap the requirements, as well as the steps you’ll need to take.&lt;br/&gt;(Windows PC의 디스크를 암호화하지만 복구 키를 마이크로소프트에 저장하고 싶지 않다면, 선택지가 있습니다. 요구 사항과 따라야 할 단계들을 요약해 보겠습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin: Disk encryption is one of the handful of differences between the Home and Pro versions of Windows.&lt;br/&gt;(시작하기 전에: 디스크 암호화는 Windows Home과 Pro 버전 간의 몇 가지 차이점 중 하나입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the Home and Pro versions of Windows support disk encryption, but only the Pro versions give users full control over the process. The Home version of Windows only supports disk encryption when logged in with a Microsoft account and will only offer to store your encryption key on Microsoft’s servers.&lt;br/&gt;(Windows Home과 Pro 버전 모두 디스크 암호화를 지원하지만, Pro 버전만 사용자에게 프로세스에 대한 완전한 제어권을 제공합니다. Windows Home 버전은 Microsoft 계정으로 로그인할 때만 디스크 암호화를 지원하며, 암호화 키를 마이크로소프트 서버에만 저장하도록 제안합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the full version of BitLocker and back up your own recovery key, you’ll need to upgrade to the Pro version of Windows. Microsoft offers its own first-party upgrade option through the Microsoft Store for a one-time fee of $99 , but it’s also possible to bring your own product key and upgrade yourself. This Macworld-affiliated listing from StackCommerce claims to be an official Microsoft partner and is offering a Windows 11 Pro key for just $10, though your mileage with third-party key resellers may vary.&lt;br/&gt;(BitLocker의 전체 버전에 접근하고 자신의 복구 키를 백업하려면 Windows Pro 버전으로 업그레이드해야 합니다. 마이크로소프트는 Microsoft Store를 통해 일회성 $99의 비용으로 자체 1자 업그레이드 옵션을 제공하지만, 자신의 제품 키를 가져와 직접 업그레이드하는 것도 가능합니다. StackCommerce의 이 Macworld 제휴 목록은 공식 마이크로소프트 파트너라고 주장하며 Windows 11 Pro 키를 단 $10에 제공하고 있지만, 타사 키 재판매업체와의 경험은 다를 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However you get it, once you have a valid key, open Settings , then System , then Activation , click upgrade your edition of Windows , click change product key , and then enter your Windows 11 Pro key (Windows 10 Pro keys should also work, if you already have one). Luckily, changing Windows editions doesn’t require anything more disruptive than a system restart. You won’t need to reinstall Windows, and you shouldn’t lose any of your installed apps or data.&lt;br/&gt;(어떻게 얻든, 유효한 키를 얻으면 설정을 열고, 시스템, 활성화를 차례로 클릭한 후 Windows 에디션 업그레이드를 클릭하고, 제품 키 변경을 클릭한 다음 Windows 11 Pro 키를 입력하세요 (이미 가지고 있다면 Windows 10 Pro 키도 작동할 것입니다). 다행히도, Windows 에디션 변경은 시스템 재시작 이상의 방해를 필요로 하지 않습니다. Windows를 재설치할 필요가 없으며, 설치된 앱이나 데이터를 잃지 않을 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once you’ve upgraded a PC to Windows 11 Pro once, you should be able to reinstall and activate Windows 11 Pro on that system again any time you want without having to re-enter your product key. Keep the product key stored somewhere, though, just in case you do need to use it for a reinstall, or if you ever need to re-activate Windows after a hardware upgrade.&lt;br/&gt;(그리고 한 번 PC를 Windows 11 Pro로 업그레이드하면, 해당 시스템에서 언제든지 Windows 11 Pro를 재설치하고 활성화할 수 있으며 제품 키를 다시 입력할 필요가 없습니다. 그러나 제품 키를 어딘가에 저장해 두세요, 재설치에 사용해야 할 경우나 하드웨어 업그레이드 후 Windows를 재활성화해야 할 경우를 대비해서입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got Windows 11 Pro set up, it’s time to either encrypt or re-encrypt your disk.&lt;br/&gt;(Windows 11 Pro를 설정한 후에는 디스크를 암호화하거나 재암호화할 시간입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve signed in with a Microsoft account, your disk is likely already encrypted, and the key is likely already stored on Microsoft’s servers. If this is the case, this process will actually involve fully unencrypting and re-encrypting your drive, which can take an hour or two depending on the speed of your PC and the size of your drive.&lt;br/&gt;(Microsoft 계정으로 로그인했다면, 디스크가 이미 암호화되었을 가능성이 높으며, 키가 이미 마이크로소프트 서버에 저장되었을 가능성이 높습니다. 이 경우, 이 프로세스는 실제로 드라이브를 완전히 암호 해제하고 재암호화하는 과정을 포함하며, PC의 속도와 드라이브 크기에 따라 한두 시간이 소요될 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to check your current encryption status and the steps to follow if you’ve already got a key backed up with Microsoft:&lt;br/&gt;(현재 암호화 상태를 확인하는 방법과 이미 마이크로소프트에 키를 백업한 경우 따라야 할 단계는 다음과 같습니다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once your disk is re-encrypted, your PC should work just as it did before. The actual encryption technology hasn’t changed at all—all we’ve done is change where the recovery key is saved.&lt;br/&gt;(디스크가 재암호화되면, PC는 이전과 동일하게 작동해야 합니다. 실제 암호화 기술은 전혀 변경되지 않았습니다. 우리가 한 모든 것은 복구 키가 저장되는 위치를 변경한 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does put the burden on the user if and when it comes time to use your recovery key. You’ll have to remember where you put it and not get it mixed up with any other recovery keys you’ve stored for other PCs or old Windows installations. But for anyone concerned about Microsoft giving their device’s encryption keys to the government or anyone else with a valid subpoena, the extra hassle may be worth it in exchange for the added privacy and peace of mind.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 복구 키를 사용해야 할 때 사용자에게 부담을 줍니다. 어디에 두었는지 기억해야 하며, 다른 PC나 이전 Windows 설치를 위해 저장한 다른 복구 키와 혼동하지 않아야 합니다. 그러나 마이크로소프트가 자신의 장치 암호화 키를 정부나 유효한 소환장을 가진 다른 누군가에게 제공하는 것을 우려하는 사람들에게는, 추가된 프라이버시와 마음의 평화를 얻기 위한 추가 번거로움이 그만한 가치가 있을 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/how-to-encrypt-your-pcs-disk-without-giving-the-keys-to-microsoft/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/win11-pc-2023-1152x648.jpeg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:29:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>“Wildly irresponsible”: DOT’s use of AI to draft safety rules sparks concerns ("극도로 무책임하다": 교통부의 안전 규칙 초안 작성에 AI 활용 논란)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/wildly-irresponsible-dots-use-of-ai-to-draft-safety-rules-sparks-concerns/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1438737819-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staffers warn DOT’s use of Gemini to draft rules could cause injuries and deaths.&lt;br/&gt;(직원들, 교통부의 Gemini를 이용한 규칙 초안 작성이 부상과 사망을 초래할 수 있다고 경고.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Transportation apparently thinks it’s a good idea to use artificial intelligence to draft rules impacting the safety of airplanes, cars, and pipelines, a ProPublica investigation revealed Monday.&lt;br/&gt;(미국 교통부가 비행기, 자동차, 파이프라인의 안전에 영향을 미치는 규칙 초안을 작성하는 데 인공지능을 사용하는 것이 좋은 생각이라고 판단하고 있는 것으로 보인다고, ProPublica의 수요일 조사 결과가 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be a problem if DOT becomes the first agency to use AI to draft rules, ProPublica pointed out, since AI is known to confidently get things wrong and hallucinate fabricated information. Staffers fear that any failure to catch AI errors could result in flawed laws, leading to lawsuits, injuries, or even deaths in the transportation system.&lt;br/&gt;(교통부가 규칙 초안 작성에 AI를 사용하는 최초의 연방 기관이 될 경우 문제가 될 수 있다고 ProPublica는 지적했는데, 이는 AI가 자신만만하게 잘못된 정보를 제공하거나 허구의 정보를 만들어내는(환각 현상) 것으로 알려져 있기 때문이다. 직원들은 AI 오류를 발견하지 못할 경우 결함이 있는 법률이 만들어져, 교통 시스템에서 소송, 부상, 심지어 사망으로 이어질 수 있다고 우려하고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the DOT’s top lawyer, Gregory Zerzan, isn’t worried about that, December meeting notes revealed, because the point isn’t for AI to be perfect. It’s for AI to help speed up the rulemaking process, so that rules that take weeks or months to draft can instead be written within 30 days. According to Zerzan, DOT’s preferred tool, Google Gemini, can draft rules in under 30 minutes.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 교통부 수석 법률고문인 Gregory Zerzan은 그 점에 대해 걱정하지 않는 것으로 12월 회의 기록이 드러냈는데, 그 이유는 AI가 완벽할 필요가 없기 때문이라고 한다. AI의 목적은 규칙 제정 과정을 가속화하여, 몇 주나 몇 달이 걸리던 규칙 초안 작성이 대신 30일 이내에 완료되도록 돕는 것이다. Zerzan에 따르면, 교통부가 선호하는 도구인 Google Gemini는 30분 이내에 규칙 초안을 작성할 수 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t need the perfect rule on XYZ,” Zerzan told DOT staffers at the meeting. “We don’t even need a very good rule on XYZ. We want good enough.”&lt;br/&gt;("우리는 XYZ에 관한 완벽한 규칙이 필요하지 않습니다."라고 Zerzan은 회의에서 교통부 직원들에게 말했다. "우리는 XYZ에 관한 아주 좋은 규칙조차 필요하지 않습니다. 우리는 '충분히 좋은' 규칙을 원합니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ProPublica spoke to experts and granted six DOT staffers anonymity to discuss their concerns about DOT’s use of Google Gemini to draft rules.&lt;br/&gt;(ProPublica는 전문가들과 인터뷰하고, 교통부 직원 6명에게 익명을 보장하여 교통부의 Google Gemini를 이용한 규칙 초안 작성에 대한 그들의 우려를 논의할 수 있게 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts who monitor AI use in government told ProPublica that DOT could save time using Gemini as a research assistant “with plenty of supervision and transparency.” For example, at a presentation, DOT staffers were told that “most of what goes into the preambles of DOT regulatory documents is just ‘word salad,’” and “Gemini can do word salad.”&lt;br/&gt;(정부의 AI 사용을 감시하는 일부 전문가들은 ProPublica에, 교통부가 Gemini를 "충분한 감독과 투명성 하에" 연구 보조원으로 사용하면 시간을 절약할 수 있다고 말했다. 예를 들어, 한 발표에서 교통부 직원들은 "교통부 규제 문서 서문에 들어가는 내용의 대부분은 그저 '말 잔치(word salad)'일 뿐"이며, "Gemini는 그런 말 잔치를 만들어낼 수 있다"는 말을 들었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, staffers told ProPublica they felt “deeply skeptical” that Gemini was up to the task. They emphasized that DOT rulemaking is “intricate work” requiring sometimes decades of “expertise in the subject at hand as well as in existing statutes, regulations, and case law.” Likely unsettling staffers further, ProPublica noted that a demonstration of Gemini’s rule-drafting produced a document missing key text, which a staffer would then have to fill in. Additionally, the DOT’s move comes after a year of AI hallucinations scrambling courts, with many lawyers fined and even judges admitting they can be fooled by fabricated information.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 직원들은 ProPublica에 Gemini가 그 임무를 수행할 수 있다는 데 "심각한 회의감"을 느낀다고 말했다. 그들은 교통부의 규칙 제정이 "복잡한 작업"으로, 때로는 해당 주제와 기존 법령, 규정, 판례법에 대한 수십 년 간의 "전문 지식"이 필요하다고 강조했다. 아마도 직원들을 더 불안하게 만든 것은, ProPublica가 지적했듯이, Gemini의 규칙 초안 작성 시연에서 핵심 텍스트가 누락된 문서가 생성되어 직원이 나중에 그 부분을 채워야 했다는 점이다. 게다가, 교통부의 이번 움직임은 AI 환각 현상이 법원을 혼란스럽게 하고 많은 변호사들이 벌금을 물며 심지어 판사들조차 허위 정보에 속을 수 있다고 인정한 지 1년 만에 나온 것이다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any errors in the rules could have serious consequences. These rules “touch virtually every facet of transportation safety,” keeping “airplanes in the sky,” preventing “gas pipelines from exploding,” and stopping “freight trains carrying toxic chemicals from skidding off the rails,” ProPublica reported.&lt;br/&gt;(규칙에 있는 어떤 오류라도 심각한 결과를 초래할 수 있다. 이 규칙들은 "비행기가 하늘을 날게 하고", "가스 파이프라인이 폭발하는 것을 막고", "유독 화학물질을 운반하는 화물 열차가 선로를 이탈하는 것을 막는" 등 "교통 안전의 거의 모든 측면에 영향을 미친다"고 ProPublica는 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems wildly irresponsible,” one staffer said.&lt;br/&gt;("극도로 무책임한 것 같습니다."라고 한 직원이 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite staffers’ concerns, DOT appears to be racing forward with the plan, ProPublica reported. The department has already used Gemini to draft a “still-unpublished Federal Aviation Administration rule, according to a DOT staffer briefed on the matter.”&lt;br/&gt;(직원들의 우려에도 불구하고, 교통부는 이 계획을 빠르게 추진하고 있는 것으로 보인다고 ProPublica는 보도했다. 해당 사안에 대해 브리핑을 받은 한 교통부 직원에 따르면, 교통부는 이미 Gemini를 사용하여 "아직 공개되지 않은 연방항공청(FAA) 규칙 초안"을 작성했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump has urged federal agencies to adopt AI at a rapid pace, but nowhere in his orders has the president pushed for AI to draft laws, ProPublica noted.&lt;br/&gt;(도널드 트럼프 대통령은 연방 기관들이 빠른 속도로 AI를 채택하도록 촉구해왔지만, 대통령의 명령 어디에도 AI로 법률을 초안 작성하도록 요구한 내용은 없다고 ProPublica는 지적했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Trump is “very excited” about the DOT initiative, Zerzan told staffers at the meeting, suggesting that Trump sees DOT as the “point of the spear” and expects other agencies to follow its lead.&lt;br/&gt;(그러나 트럼프 대통령은 교통부의 이 계획에 "매우 기뻐하고" 있다고 Zerzan은 회의에서 직원들에게 말했으며, 트럼프 대통령이 교통부를 "선봉부대(point of the spear)"로 보고 다른 기관들도 그 뒤를 따르길 기대한다고 시사했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At DOT, Trump likely hopes to see many rules quickly updated to modernize airways and roadways. In a report highlighting the Office of Science and Technology Policy’s biggest “wins” in 2025, the White House credited DOT with “replacing decades-old rules with flexible, innovation-friendly frameworks,” including fast-tracking rules to allow for more automated vehicles on the roads.&lt;br/&gt;(트럼프 대통령은 아마도 교통부에서 항공로와 도로를 현대화하기 위해 많은 규칙들이 빠르게 개정되는 것을 보기 원할 것이다. 과학기술정책실(OSTP)의 2025년 최대 '성과'를 강조한 보고서에서 백악관은 교통부가 "수십 년 된 규칙들을 유연하고 혁신 친화적인 체계로 대체한" 공로를 인정했는데, 여기에는 도로에서 더 많은 자율주행차를 허용하기 위한 규칙 신속 추진도 포함된다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, DOT expects that Gemini can be relied on to “handle 80 to 90 percent of the work of writing regulations,” ProPublica reported. Eventually all federal workers who rely on AI tools like Gemini to draft rules “would fall back into merely an oversight role, monitoring ‘AI-to-AI interactions,’” ProPublica reported.&lt;br/&gt;(현재 교통부는 Gemini가 "규정 작성 작업의 80~90%를 처리하는 데 의존할 수 있을 것"으로 기대하고 있다고 ProPublica는 보도했다. 궁극적으로 Gemini와 같은 AI 도구를 사용해 규칙을 초안 작성하는 모든 연방 공무원들은 "단지 감독 역할로 후퇴하여 'AI 대 AI 상호작용'을 모니터링하게 될 것"이라고 ProPublica는 보도했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google did not respond to Ars’ request to comment on this use case for Gemini, which could spread across government under Trump’s direction.&lt;br/&gt;(Google은 트럼프 대통령의 지시 아래 정부 전반으로 확산될 수 있는 Gemini의 이러한 사용 사례에 대한 Ars의 논평 요청에 응답하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the tech giant posted a blog on Monday, pitching Gemini for government more broadly, promising federal workers that AI would help with “creative problem-solving to the most critical aspects of their work.”&lt;br/&gt;(대신, 이 기술 거대 기업은 수요일 블로그 게시물을 통해 Gemini의 정부 활용을 더 광범위하게 홍보하며, 연방 공무원들에게 AI가 "가장 중요한 업무 측면에 대한 창의적 문제 해결"을 도울 것이라고 약속했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google has been competing with AI rivals for government contracts, undercutting OpenAI and Anthropic’s $1 deals by offering a year of access to Gemini for $0.47.&lt;br/&gt;(Google은 정부 계약을 위해 AI 경쟁사들과 경쟁해왔으며, OpenAI와 Anthropic의 1달러 계약을 깎아내리며 Gemini 1년 접속권을 0.47달러에 제공했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DOT contract seems important to Google. In a December blog , the company celebrated that DOT was “the first cabinet-level agency to fully transition its workforce away from legacy providers to Google Workspace with Gemini.”&lt;br/&gt;(교통부 계약은 Google에게 중요한 것으로 보인다. 12월 블로그에서 회사는 교통부가 "기존 제공업체에서 Google Workspace with Gemini로 인력을 완전히 전환한 최초의 장관급 기관"이 된 것을 축하했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, Google suggested this move would help DOT “ensure the United States has the safest, most efficient, and modern transportation system in the world.”&lt;br/&gt;(당시 Google은 이 조치가 교통부가 "미국이 세계에서 가장 안전하고, 효율적이며, 현대적인 교통 시스템을 갖추도록" 하는 데 도움이 될 것이라고 시사했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immediately, Google encouraged other federal leaders to launch their own efforts using Gemini.&lt;br/&gt;(Google은 즉시 다른 연방 지도자들에게도 Gemini를 사용한 자체적인 노력을 시작하도록 장려했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are committed to supporting the DOT’s digital transformation and stand ready to help other federal leaders across the government adopt this blueprint for their own mission successes,” Google’s blog said.&lt;br/&gt;("우리는 교통부의 디지털 전환을 지원할 것을 약속하며, 정부 전반의 다른 연방 지도자들이 그들 자신의 임무 성공을 위해 이 청사진을 채택하도록 돕기 위해 준비되어 있습니다."라고 Google의 블로그는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DOT did not immediately respond to Ars’ request for comment.&lt;br/&gt;(교통부는 Ars의 논평 요청에 즉시 응답하지 않았다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2026/01/wildly-irresponsible-dots-use-of-ai-to-draft-safety-rules-sparks-concerns/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-1438737819-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:13:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple’s AirTag 2 is easier to find thanks to new chip (애플 에어태그 2, 새 칩 덕분에 찾기 쉬워져)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-introduces-new-airtag-with-better-range-and-a-louder-speaker/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/AirTag-2-1152x648.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first major upgrade since Apple introduced AirTags five years ago.&lt;br/&gt;(이는 애플이 에어태그를 출시한 지 5년 만에 이루어진 첫 번째 주요 업그레이드입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple is introducing a new version of its AirTag tracking device—simply dubbed “the new AirTag"—and claims it offers substantial improvements thanks to a new Bluetooth chip.&lt;br/&gt;(애플은 새로운 버전의 에어태그 추적 장치를 선보이며, 단순히 "새로운 에어태그"라고 명명하고 새로운 블루투스 칩 덕분에 상당한 개선이 이루어졌다고 주장합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original AirTag came out five years ago now, and it became popular in a variety of contexts. There were some problems, though—there was real concern about unwanted tracking and stalking with the devices, based on real stories of it being used for that. The company gradually introduced new features and protections against that, getting it to a much better place.&lt;br/&gt;(원래 에어태그는 5년 전에 출시되었으며, 다양한 상황에서 인기를 끌었습니다. 그러나 몇 가지 문제도 있었는데, 실제로 해당 장치가 추적 및 스토킹에 사용된 사례를 바탕으로 원치 않는 추적에 대한 진정한 우려가 제기되었습니다. 회사는 점차 새로운 기능과 보호 장치를 도입하여 훨씬 더 나은 상태로 만들었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new version is focused on making the device more effective in general. Thanks to the inclusion of the second-generation Ultra Wideband chip (the same one found in other recently released Apple devices like the iPhone 17), Apple says the new AirTag can work with the Precision Finding feature in the Find My app to direct users to the AirTag (and whatever lost item it’s stored with or attached to) from up to 50 percent farther away.&lt;br/&gt;(이 새로운 버전은 일반적으로 장치의 효율성을 높이는 데 중점을 둡니다. 2세대 초광대역(UWB) 칩(아이폰 17과 같은 최근 출시된 다른 애플 기기에도 탑재된 동일한 칩)이 포함됨에 따라, 애플은 새로운 에어태그가 '나의 찾기' 앱의 정밀 찾기 기능과 함께 작동하여 사용자를 에어태그(및 에어태그가 함께 보관되거나 부착된 분실물)까지 최대 50% 더 먼 거리에서 안내할 수 있다고 설명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the speaker in the AirTag is now 50 percent louder, Apple says. These two things together address some user complaints that, as useful as an AirTag can be in ideal circumstances, sometimes it is frustrating trying to get things just right to find something. It won’t eliminate all edge cases, but it ought to help.&lt;br/&gt;(또한, 에어태그의 스피커 음량이 이제 50% 더 커졌다고 애플은 밝혔습니다. 이 두 가지 개선 사항은 에어태그가 이상적인 상황에서는 유용할 수 있지만, 때로는 무언가를 찾기 위해 조건을 맞추는 것이 좌절스러울 수 있다는 일부 사용자의 불만을 해소합니다. 모든 극단적인 경우를 없애지는 못하겠지만, 도움이 될 것입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple used this announcement to also talk up some of the features of the AirTag, including the encryption that it says prevents anyone but the AirTag owner from using it, and an arrangement with airlines where users can temporarily give airlines the ability to use Apple’s network to find a specific AirTag to locate lost luggage and the like.&lt;br/&gt;(애플은 이 발표를 통해 에어태그의 몇 가지 기능도 강조했는데, 여기에는 에어태그 소유자만이 사용할 수 있도록 방지하는 암호화와, 사용자가 항공사에 애플 네트워크를 이용해 특정 에어태그를 찾아 분실 수하물 등을 찾을 수 있는 임시 권한을 부여할 수 있는 항공사 협약이 포함됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, the new AirTag doesn’t introduce any major new features that aren’t already offered in the previous generation—this is just an update to the device’s accuracy, volume, and range.&lt;br/&gt;(명확히 말하자면, 새로운 에어태그는 이전 세대에서 이미 제공되지 않는 주요 신기능을 도입하지는 않습니다. 이는 단지 장치의 정확도, 음량 및 범위에 대한 업데이트일 뿐입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price remains unchanged, at $29 for one AirTag or $99 for a pack of four. The new model is available for order on Apple’s website now and will hit physical stores later this week.&lt;br/&gt;(가격은 변함없이, 에어태그 1개당 29달러, 4개 팩은 99달러입니다. 새로운 모델은 현재 애플 웹사이트에서 주문할 수 있으며, 이번 주 후반에 오프라인 매장에서도 판매될 예정입니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/apple-introduces-new-airtag-with-better-range-and-a-louder-speaker/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/AirTag-2-1152x648.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:18:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why has Microsoft been routing example.com traffic to a company in Japan? (마이크로소프트가 왜 example.com 트래픽을 일본 기업으로 라우팅했나?)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/odd-anomaly-caused-microsofts-network-to-mishandle-example-com-traffic/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/error-message-1000x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Company’s autodiscover caused users’ test credentials to be sent outside Microsoft networks.&lt;br/&gt;(회사의 자동 검색 기능이 사용자의 테스트 자격 증명을 마이크로소프트 네트워크 외부로 전송하게 했음.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the Department of Bizarre Anomalies: Microsoft has suppressed an unexplained anomaly on its network that was routing traffic destined to example.com—a domain reserved for testing purposes—to a maker of electronics cables located in Japan.&lt;br/&gt;(기이한 이상 현상 부서에서: 마이크로소프트는 테스트 목적으로 예약된 도메인인 example.com으로 향하는 트래픽을 일본에 위치한 전자 케이블 제조사로 라우팅하는 설명되지 않은 네트워크 이상 현상을 억제해 왔습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the RFC2606 —an official standard maintained by the Internet Engineering Task Force—example.com isn’t obtainable by any party. Instead it resolves to IP addresses assigned to Internet Assiged Names Authority. The designation is intended to prevent third parties from being bombarded with traffic when developers, penetration testers, and others need a domain for testing or discussing technical issues. Instead of naming an Internet-routable domain, they are to choose example.com or two others, example.net and example.org.&lt;br/&gt;(인터넷 엔지니어링 태스크 포스가 유지하는 공식 표준인 RFC2606에 따르면, example.com은 어떤 당사자도 획득할 수 없습니다. 대신 이 도메인은 인터넷 할당 번호 관리국에 할당된 IP 주소로 확인됩니다. 이 지정은 개발자, 침투 테스터 및 기타 사용자가 테스트나 기술 문제 논의를 위해 도메인이 필요할 때 제3자가 트래픽 폭격을 받는 것을 방지하기 위한 것입니다. 인터넷 라우팅 가능한 도메인을 지정하는 대신, 그들은 example.com 또는 다른 두 도메인인 example.net과 example.org를 선택해야 합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Output from the terminal command cURL shows that devices inside Azure and other Microsoft networks have been routing some traffic to subdomains of sei.co.jp, a domain belonging to Sumitomo Electric. Most of the resulting text is exactly what’s expected. The exception is the JSON-based response. Here’s the JSON output from Friday:&lt;br/&gt;(터미널 명령 cURL의 출력은 Azure 및 기타 마이크로소프트 네트워크 내부 장치들이 일부 트래픽을 스미토모 전기의 도메인인 sei.co.jp의 하위 도메인으로 라우팅해 왔음을 보여줍니다. 결과 텍스트 대부분은 예상대로입니다. 예외는 JSON 기반 응답입니다. 다음은 금요일의 JSON 출력입니다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, results when adding a new account for test@example.com in Outlook looked like this:&lt;br/&gt;(마찬가지로, Outlook에서 test@example.com에 대한 새 계정을 추가할 때의 결과는 다음과 같았습니다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, the results show that Microsoft was routing email traffic to two sei.co.jp subdomains: imapgms.jnet.sei.co.jp and smtpgms.jnet.sei.co.jp. The behavior was the result of Microsoft’s autodiscover service.&lt;br/&gt;(두 경우 모두, 결과는 마이크로소프트가 이메일 트래픽을 두 개의 sei.co.jp 하위 도메인인 imapgms.jnet.sei.co.jp와 smtpgms.jnet.sei.co.jp로 라우팅하고 있었음을 보여줍니다. 이 동작은 마이크로소프트의 자동 검색 서비스의 결과였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m admittedly not an expert in Microsoft’s internal workings, but this appears to be a simple misconfiguration,” Michael Taggart , a senior cybersecurity researcher at UCLA Health, said. “The result is that anyone who tries to set up an Outlook account on an example.com domain might accidentally send test credentials to those sei.co.jp subdomains.”&lt;br/&gt;(UCLA 헬스의 시니어 사이버보안 연구원인 마이클 태거트는 "저는 마이크로소프트의 내부 작동 방식에 대한 전문가는 아니지만, 이는 단순한 설정 오류로 보입니다"라고 말했습니다. "결과는 example.com 도메인에서 Outlook 계정을 설정하려는 사람이 실수로 테스트 자격 증명을 해당 sei.co.jp 하위 도메인으로 보낼 수 있다는 것입니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked early Friday afternoon why Microsoft was doing this, a representative had no answer and asked for more time. By Monday morning, the improper routing was no longer occurring, but the representative still had no answer.&lt;br/&gt;(금요일 오후 초에 마이크로소프트가 왜 이렇게 하는지 묻자, 대표자는 답변을 못하고 시간을 더 요청했습니다. 월요일 아침까지 부적절한 라우팅은 더 이상 발생하지 않았지만, 대표자는 여전히 답변을 못했습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update: in an email sent after this post went live, the representative confirmed that Microsoft has “updated the service to no longer provide suggested server information for example.com.” As already reported here, the behavior only affected people configuring email accounts through the Outlook autoconfiguration feature. The representative added that Microsoft is investigating.&lt;br/&gt;(업데이트: 이 게시물이 게시된 후 전송된 이메일에서 대표자는 마이크로소프트가 "example.com에 대한 제안된 서버 정보를 더 이상 제공하지 않도록 서비스를 업데이트했다"고 확인했습니다. 이미 여기서 보고된 바와 같이, 이 동작은 Outlook 자동 구성 기능을 통해 이메일 계정을 구성하는 사람들에게만 영향을 미쳤습니다. 대표자는 마이크로소프트가 조사 중이라고 덧붙였습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new JSON response suggested that, as of Monday morning, Microsoft hadn’t fixed the endpoint routing traffic to the Sumitomo Electric servers. Instead, the JSON response no longer occurs. Where the output was occurring on Friday, the command now simply sits and hangs for 10 or 20 seconds and then terminates with a not found error. This behavior can be seen in the following output:&lt;br/&gt;(새로운 JSON 응답은 월요일 아침 기준으로 마이크로소프트가 스미토모 전기 서버로 트래픽을 라우팅하는 엔드포인트를 수정하지 않았음을 시사했습니다. 대신, JSON 응답이 더 이상 발생하지 않습니다. 금요일에 출력이 발생했던 곳에서, 이제 명령은 단순히 10~20초간 멈춰 있다가 찾을 수 없음 오류와 함께 종료됩니다. 이 동작은 다음 출력에서 볼 수 있습니다:)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It looks like they may have outright removed the endpoint that validates the email, because I’m seeing ‘not found’ errors,” said Dan Tentler , founder of Phobos Group. As denoted by ENOTFOUND, the error “suggests that [Microsoft admins] just ripped out whatever this thing was.”&lt;br/&gt;(포보스 그룹의 설립자인 댄 텐틀러는 "이메일을 검증하는 엔드포인트를 완전히 제거한 것 같습니다. '찾을 수 없음' 오류가 보이기 때문입니다"라고 말했습니다. ENOTFOUND로 표시된 이 오류는 "[마이크로소프트 관리자들이] 이게 뭐든 간에 그냥 뜯어낸 것 같다"고 시사합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear how Sumitomo Electric’s domain would have found itself part of this mess. Microsoft last year said the Japanese company’s parent company, Sumitomo Corp., was deploying Microsoft 365 Copilot, but that still doesn’t explain why a subsidiary’s domain was added to Microsoft’s network configuration.&lt;br/&gt;(스미토모 전기의 도메인이 어떻게 이 혼란에 휘말리게 되었는지는 불분명합니다. 마이크로소프트는 작년에 일본 기업의 모회사인 스미토모 코퍼레이션이 마이크로소프트 365 코파일럿을 배포 중이라고 말했지만, 이는 여전히 자회사의 도메인이 마이크로소프트 네트워크 구성에 추가된 이유를 설명하지 못합니다.
&lt;&lt;&lt;PARAS&gt;&gt;&gt;
마이크로소프트에 보낸 질문에는 다음이 포함됩니다: 자동 검색 레코드가 마이크로소프트에서 어떻게 추가되는가; 라우팅이 의도적이었는가; 그리고 이 동작이 얼마나 오래 발생해 왔는가? (이상한 라우팅 동작을 이달 초에 지적한 Tinyapps.org는 5년간 지속되었다고 말했습니다.) 부적절한 라우팅에 대해 악의적인 것은 없는 것으로 보이며, 마이크로소프트 네트워크 내부 사람들이 테스트에서 실제 자격 증명을 보내지 않는 한 위험은 없었습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions sent to Microsoft include: How are autodiscover records added at Microsoft; was the routing intentional; and how long has the behavior been occurring? (Tinyapps.org, which noted the odd routing behavior earlier this month, said it lasted five years.) There doesn’t appear to be anything nefarious about the improper routing, and as long as people inside Microsoft’s network weren’t sending live credentials in tests, there was no danger posed.&lt;br/&gt;(여전히 우려할 이유가 있습니다. 2024년에 마이크로소프트는 자사 관리자 중 한 명이 회사 네트워크의 테스트 계정에 관리자 권한을 부여한 후 잊어버렸다고 밝혔습니다. 러시아 국가 해커들은 이 실수를 이용해 마이크로소프트 시스템에 초기 접근을 얻었습니다. 그들은 네트워크를 루팅하고 최고 경영진의 이메일을 두 달간 감시했습니다. example.com에 대한 라우팅 설정 오류는 이 질문을 제기합니다: 네트워크에 어떤 다른 더 심각한 오류가 숨어 있을까?)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2026/01/odd-anomaly-caused-microsofts-network-to-mishandle-example-com-traffic/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/error-message-1000x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:02:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Doctors face-palm as RFK Jr.’s top vaccine advisor questions need for polio shot (RFK Jr.의 백신 최고 고문이 소아마비 예방접종 필요성에 의문 제기하자 의사들 '얼굴을 감싸쥐다')</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/do-we-really-need-polio-shots-deep-thoughts-by-rfk-jr-advisor-get-dragged/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2235571142-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirk Milhoan’s comments come as federal vaccine policy slides to insignificance.&lt;br/&gt;(커크 밀호안의 발언은 연방 백신 정책이 무의미해지는 시점에 나왔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chair of a federal vaccine advisory panel under anti-vaccine Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. made his stance clear on vaccines in a podcast last week—and that stance was so alarming that the American Medical Association was compelled to respond with a scathing statement.&lt;br/&gt;(반백신 성향의 로버트 F. 케네디 주니어 보건부 장관 휘하의 연방 백신 자문 위원회 위원장이 지난주 팟캐스트에서 백신에 대한 자신의 입장을 분명히 했는데, 그 입장이 너무나 충격적이어서 미국 의학 협회가 신랄한 성명으로 응답해야 할 정도였다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirk Milhoan, who was named chair of the Advisory Committee on Immunization Practices for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in December, appeared on the aptly named podcast “ Why Should I Trust You .” In the hour-long interview, Milhoan made a wide range of comments that have concerned medical experts and raised eyebrows.&lt;br/&gt;(지난 12월 질병통제예방센터(CDC) 예방접종자문위원회(ACIP) 위원장으로 임명된 커크 밀호안은 이름이 적절한 팟캐스트 '왜 당신을 믿어야 하나요'에 출연했다. 한 시간 동안 진행된 이 인터뷰에서 밀호안은 의료 전문가들을 우려시키고 눈살을 찌푸리게 하는 다양한 발언을 했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early into the discussion, Milhoan, a pediatric cardiologist, declared, “I don’t like established science,” and that “science is what I observe.” He lambasted the evidence-based methodology that previous ACIP panels used to carefully and transparently craft vaccine policy.&lt;br/&gt;(토론 초반, 소아 심장병 전문의인 밀호안은 "저는 확립된 과학을 좋아하지 않습니다"라고 선언하며 "과학은 제가 관찰하는 것입니다"라고 말했다. 그는 이전 ACIP 위원회가 백신 정책을 신중하고 투명하게 수립하는 데 사용했던 근거 기반 방법론을 비난했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While arguing that he was not anti-vaccine, he said he was merely focused on safety and made false claims about vaccine risks, a common trope among anti-vaccine activists. He falsely linked vaccines to allergies, asthma, and eczema and repeated a claim, without evidence, that COVID-19 vaccines killed children. When pressed by the podcast hosts, he revealed that he put the risk of vaccine side effects on the same footing as the risks from the diseases the shots prevent—despite the fact that disease risks are often orders of magnitude larger than the tiny risks from vaccines.&lt;br/&gt;(그는 자신이 반백신주의자가 아니라고 주장하면서도, 단지 안전에 집중하고 있다며 백신 위험에 대한 허위 주장을 펼쳤는데, 이는 반백신 운동가들 사이에서 흔한 수법이다. 그는 백신과 알레르기, 천식, 습진을 허위로 연결지었고, 증거 없이 코로나19 백신이 어린이들을 죽였다는 주장을 반복했다. 팟캐스트 진행자들의 추궁을 받자 그는 백신 부작용 위험을 백신이 예방하는 질병 자체의 위험과 동등한 수준으로 평가한다고 밝혔는데, 사실 질병의 위험은 백신의 미미한 위험보다 종종 수십 배에서 수백 배 더 크다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to pushback from the hosts, Milhoan objected to the idea that the measles and polio vaccines reduced the spread of those diseases. He went further, questioning the need for those vaccines as well as routine vaccinations, generally.&lt;br/&gt;(진행자들의 반론에 대응하며, 밀호안은 홍역과 소아마비 백신이 해당 질병의 확산을 줄였다는 생각에 반대했다. 그는 더 나아가 그 백신들과 일반적인 정기 예방접종의 필요성 자체에 의문을 제기했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think also as you look at polio, we need to not be afraid to consider that we are in a different time now than we were then,” he said, referring to the time before the first polio vaccines were developed in the 1950s. “Our sanitation is different. Our risk of disease is different. And so those all play into the evaluation of whether this is worthwhile of taking a risk for a vaccine or not.”&lt;br/&gt;(그는 "제 생각에 소아마비를 볼 때도, 우리는 지금이 그때(1950년대 첫 소아마비 백신 개발 이전)와는 다른 시대라는 점을 두려워하지 않고 고려해야 합니다"라고 말했다. "우리의 위생 상태는 다릅니다. 우리의 질병 위험은 다릅니다. 따라서 이 모든 요소들이 백신을 맞는 위험을 감수할 가치가 있는지 평가하는 데 영향을 미칩니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then pondered out loud what would happen if people stopped getting vaccinated. “If we take away all of the herd immunity, then does that switch, does that teeter-totter switch in a different direction?” he asked.&lt;br/&gt;(그는 이어 사람들이 백신 접종을 중단하면 어떻게 될지 큰 소리로 고민했다. "만약 우리가 모든 집단 면역을 제거한다면, 그 균형이 바뀌나요? 그 시소가 다른 방향으로 기울나요?"라고 그는 물었다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, AMA Trustee Sandra Adamson Fryhofer blasted the question. “This is not a theoretical debate—it is a dangerous step backward,” she said. “Vaccines have saved millions of lives and virtually eliminated devastating diseases like polio in the United States. There is no cure for polio. When vaccination rates fall, paralysis, lifelong disability, and death return. The science on this is settled.”&lt;br/&gt;(성명에서 AMA 이사인 샌드라 애덤슨 프라이호퍼는 이 질문을 강력히 비판했다. "이것은 이론적 논쟁이 아닙니다. 위험한 후퇴입니다."라고 그녀는 말했다. "백신은 수백만 명의 생명을 구했고 미국에서 소아마비와 같은 파괴적인 질병을 사실상 근절시켰습니다. 소아마비에 대한 치료법은 없습니다. 예방접종률이 떨어지면 마비, 평생 장애, 죽음이 돌아옵니다. 이에 대한 과학적 결론은 이미 나왔습니다.")&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fryhofer also took aim at Milhoan’s repeated argument that the focus of vaccination policy should move from population-level health to individual autonomy. Moving away from routine immunizations, which include discussions between clinicians and patients, “does not increase freedom—it increases suffering,” she said, adding that the weakening of recommendations “will cost lives.”&lt;br/&gt;(프라이호퍼는 또한 밀호안이 반복적으로 주장하는, 백신 정책의 초점이 집단 수준의 건강에서 개인의 자율성으로 옮겨가야 한다는 논쟁도 공격했다. 임상의와 환자 간의 논의를 포함하는 정기 예방접종에서 벗어나는 것은 "자유를 증가시키지 않고 고통을 증가시킨다"며, 권고 사항이 약화되는 것은 "생명을 앗아갈 것"이라고 그녀는 덧붙였다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, Milhoan’s comments only further erode the relevance of ACIP and federal vaccine policy among the medical community and states. According to a KFF policy brief , 27 states and Washington, DC, have already announced they will not follow current CDC vaccine recommendations, which Kennedy dramatically overhauled earlier this month without even consulting the ACIP. Instead, the majority of states are relying on previous recommendations or recommendations made within states or by medical organizations.&lt;br/&gt;(전반적으로, 밀호안의 발언은 의료계와 주 정부 사이에서 ACIP와 연방 백신 정책의 관련성을 더욱 훼손할 뿐이다. KFF 정책 브리핑에 따르면, 27개 주와 워싱턴 DC는 이미 현재의 CDC 백신 권고 사항을 따르지 않겠다고 발표했는데, 케네디 장관은 이달 초 ACIP와 상의조차 없이 이 권고 사항을 극적으로 전면 수정했다. 대신 대다수의 주들은 이전 권고 사항이나 주 내부 또는 의학 단체가 만든 권고 사항을 따르고 있다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the American Academy of Pediatrics announced the 2026 update to its childhood and adolescent vaccine schedule , which it has held up as an alternative to the CDC’s schedule and has been widely embraced by pediatricians. In the announcement, AAP noted that 12 other medical organizations have endorsed the schedule, including the AMA, the American Academy of Family Physicians, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, the Infectious Diseases Society of America, and the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society.&lt;br/&gt;(월요일, 미국 소아과학회(AAP)는 2026년 업데이트된 소아 및 청소년 예방접종 일정을 발표했는데, 이는 CDC 일정의 대안으로 내세워져 왔으며 소아과 의사들에게 널리 받아들여지고 있다. 발표에서 AAP는 AMA, 미국 가정의학회, 미국 산부인과 의사 대학, 미국 감염병 학회, 소아 감염병 학회를 포함한 12개의 다른 의학 단체들이 이 일정을 지지했다고 밝혔다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AAP’s updated recommendations are largely the same as the schedule from last year, but it is significantly different from the CDC’s recommendations, which “depart from longstanding medical evidence and no longer offer the optimal way to prevent illnesses in children,” the AAP said.&lt;br/&gt;(AAP의 업데이트된 권고 사항은 지난해 일정과 대체로 동일하지만, CDC의 권고 사항과는 현저히 다르며, CDC 권고 사항은 "오랜 의학적 증거에서 벗어나 더 이상 어린이 질병을 예방하는 최적의 방법을 제공하지 않는다"고 AAP는 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The AAP will continue to provide recommendations for immunizations that are rooted in science and are in the best interest of the health of infants, children and adolescents of this country,” AAP President Andrew Racine said in the announcement.&lt;br/&gt;("AAP는 과학에 근거하고 이 나라 영유아, 어린이 및 청소년의 건강에 최선의 이익이 되는 예방접종 권고 사항을 계속 제공할 것입니다."라고 AAP 회장 앤드루 라신은 발표에서 말했다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/science/2026/01/do-we-really-need-polio-shots-deep-thoughts-by-rfk-jr-advisor-get-dragged/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/GettyImages-2235571142-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:31:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI spills technical details about how its AI coding agent works (OpenAI, AI 코딩 에이전트 작동 방식에 대한 기술적 세부사항 공개)</title><link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/openai-spills-technical-details-about-how-its-ai-coding-agent-works/</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/coding_robots_agents-1152x648.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unusually detailed post explains how OpenAI handles the Codex agent loop.&lt;br/&gt;(이례적으로 상세한 게시글이 OpenAI가 Codex 에이전트 루프를 어떻게 처리하는지 설명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, OpenAI engineer Michael Bolin published a detailed technical breakdown of how the company’s Codex CLI coding agent works internally, offering developers insight into AI coding tools that can write code, run tests, and fix bugs with human supervision. It complements our article in December on how AI agents work by filling in technical details on how OpenAI implements its “agentic loop.”&lt;br/&gt;(금요일, OpenAI 엔지니어 마이클 볼린이 회사의 Codex CLI 코딩 에이전트가 내부적으로 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 상세한 기술 분석을 게시하여, 개발자들에게 인간의 감독 하에 코드 작성, 테스트 실행, 버그 수정이 가능한 AI 코딩 도구에 대한 통찰력을 제공했습니다. 이는 AI 에이전트 작동 방식에 대한 우리의 12월 기사를 보완하며, OpenAI가 '에이전트 루프'를 어떻게 구현하는지에 대한 기술적 세부사항을 채워줍니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AI coding agents are having something of a “ChatGPT moment,” where Claude Code with Opus 4.5 and Codex with GPT-5.2 have reached a new level of usefulness for rapidly coding up prototypes, interfaces, and churning out boilerplate code. The timing of OpenAI’s post details the design philosophy behind Codex just as AI agents are becoming more practical tools for everyday work.&lt;br/&gt;(AI 코딩 에이전트는 일종의 'ChatGPT 순간'을 맞이하고 있으며, Opus 4.5를 탑재한 Claude Code와 GPT-5.2를 탑재한 Codex가 프로토타입, 인터페이스 신속 코딩 및 상용구 코드 생산에 있어 새로운 수준의 유용성에 도달했습니다. OpenAI의 게시글 시기는 AI 에이전트가 일상 업무를 위한 더 실용적인 도구가 되어가는 바로 그 시점에 Codex의 설계 철학을 상세히 설명합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tools aren’t perfect and remain controversial for some software developers. While OpenAI has previously told Ars Technica that it uses Codex as a coding tool to help develop the Codex product itself, we also discovered , through hands-on experience, that these tools can be astonishingly fast at simple tasks but remain brittle beyond their training data and require human oversight for production work. The rough framework of a project tends to come fast and feels magical, but filling in the details involves tedious debugging and workarounds for limitations the agent cannot overcome on its own.&lt;br/&gt;(이러한 도구들은 완벽하지 않으며 일부 소프트웨어 개발자들에게는 여전히 논란의 대상입니다. OpenAI는 이전에 Ars Technica에 Codex 제품 자체 개발을 돕는 코딩 도구로 Codex를 사용한다고 밝힌 바 있지만, 우리는 실제 경험을 통해 이러한 도구들이 간단한 작업에서는 놀라울 정도로 빠르지만, 훈련 데이터를 벗어나면 취약해지며 프로덕션 작업에는 인간의 감독이 필요하다는 점도 발견했습니다. 프로젝트의 대략적인 뼈대는 빠르게 만들어져 마법처럼 느껴지지만, 세부 사항을 채우는 작업에는 지루한 디버깅과 에이전트가 스스로 극복할 수 없는 한계를 위한 해결 방법이 필요합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin’s post doesn’t shy away from these engineering challenges. He discusses the inefficiency of quadratic prompt growth, performance issues caused by cache misses, and bugs the team discovered (like MCP tools being enumerated inconsistently) that they had to fix.&lt;br/&gt;(볼린의 게시글은 이러한 엔지니어링적 도전 과제를 피하지 않습니다. 그는 2차 프롬프트 증가의 비효율성, 캐시 미스로 인한 성능 문제, 그리고 팀이 발견하고 수정해야 했던 버그들(예: MCP 도구가 일관되지 않게 열거되는 문제)에 대해 논의합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of technical detail is somewhat unusual for OpenAI, which has not published similar breakdowns of how other products like ChatGPT work internally, for example (there’s a lot going on under that hood we’d like to know). But we’ve already seen how OpenAI treats Codex differently during our interview with them in December, noting that programming tasks seem ideally suited for large language models.&lt;br/&gt;(이 정도의 기술적 세부사항은 OpenAI에게는 다소 이례적입니다. 예를 들어, ChatGPT와 같은 다른 제품들이 내부적으로 어떻게 작동하는지에 대해서는 유사한 분석을 공개한 바 없습니다(우리가 알고 싶은 그 후드 아래에는 많은 일이 벌어지고 있죠). 하지만 우리는 이미 12월 인터뷰에서 OpenAI가 Codex를 다르게 대한다는 점을 확인했으며, 프로그래밍 작업이 대규모 언어 모델에 이상적으로 적합해 보인다고 언급한 바 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s worth noting that both OpenAI and Anthropic open-source their coding CLI clients on GitHub, allowing developers to examine the implementation directly, whereas they don’t do the same for ChatGPT or the Claude web interface.&lt;br/&gt;(OpenAI와 Anthropic 모두 GitHub에서 코딩 CLI 클라이언트를 오픈소스로 공개하여 개발자들이 구현 내용을 직접 검토할 수 있도록 하지만, ChatGPT나 Claude 웹 인터페이스에 대해서는 동일한 조치를 취하지 않는다는 점은 주목할 가치가 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin’s post focuses on what he calls “the agent loop,” which is the core logic that orchestrates interactions between the user, the AI model, and the software tools the model invokes to perform coding work.&lt;br/&gt;(볼린의 게시글은 그가 '에이전트 루프'라고 부르는, 사용자, AI 모델, 그리고 모델이 코딩 작업을 수행하기 위해 호출하는 소프트웨어 도구 간의 상호작용을 조율하는 핵심 논리에 초점을 맞춥니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we wrote in December, at the center of every AI agent is a repeating cycle. The agent takes input from the user and prepares a textual prompt for the model. The model then generates a response, which either produces a final answer for the user or requests a tool call (such as running a shell command or reading a file). If the model requests a tool call, the agent executes it, appends the output to the original prompt, and queries the model again. This process repeats until the model stops requesting tools and instead produces an assistant message for the user.&lt;br/&gt;(우리가 12월에 썼듯이, 모든 AI 에이전트의 중심에는 반복되는 사이클이 있습니다. 에이전트는 사용자로부터 입력을 받아 모델을 위한 텍스트 프롬프트를 준비합니다. 그런 다음 모델은 응답을 생성하는데, 이는 사용자에게 최종 답변을 제공하거나 도구 호출(예: 셸 명령 실행 또는 파일 읽기)을 요청합니다. 모델이 도구 호출을 요청하면, 에이전트는 이를 실행하고 출력을 원래 프롬프트에 추가한 다음 모델을 다시 쿼리합니다. 이 과정은 모델이 도구 요청을 멈추고 대신 사용자를 위한 어시스턴트 메시지를 생성할 때까지 반복됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That looping process has to start somewhere, and Bolin’s post reveals how Codex constructs the initial prompt sent to OpenAI’s Responses API, which handles model inference. The prompt is built from several components, each with an assigned role that determines its priority: system, developer, user, or assistant.&lt;br/&gt;(그 루프 과정은 어딘가에서 시작되어야 하며, 볼린의 게시글은 Codex가 모델 추론을 처리하는 OpenAI의 Responses API로 전송되는 초기 프롬프트를 어떻게 구성하는지 밝힙니다. 프롬프트는 여러 구성 요소로부터 만들어지며, 각 구성 요소에는 우선순위를 결정하는 지정된 역할(system, developer, user, 또는 assistant)이 할당됩니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions field comes from either a user-specified configuration file or base instructions bundled with the CLI. The tools field defines what functions the model can call, including shell commands, planning tools, web search capabilities, and any custom tools provided through Model Context Protocol (MCP) servers. The input field contains a series of items that describe the sandbox permissions, optional developer instructions, environment context like the current working directory, and finally the user’s actual message.&lt;br/&gt;(지시 사항 필드는 사용자가 지정한 구성 파일이나 CLI와 함께 번들로 제공되는 기본 지시 사항에서 옵니다. 도구 필드는 모델이 호출할 수 있는 함수들을 정의하며, 셸 명령, 계획 도구, 웹 검색 기능 및 Model Context Protocol(MCP) 서버를 통해 제공되는 모든 사용자 정의 도구를 포함합니다. 입력 필드는 샌드박스 권한, 선택적 개발자 지시 사항, 현재 작업 디렉토리와 같은 환경 컨텍스트, 그리고 마지막으로 사용자의 실제 메시지를 설명하는 일련의 항목들을 포함합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As conversations continue, each new turn includes the complete history of previous messages and tool calls. This means the prompt grows with every interaction, which has performance implications. According to the post, because Codex does not use an optional “previous_response_id” parameter that would allow the API to reference stored conversation state, every request is fully stateless (that is, it sends the entire conversation history with each API call rather than the server retrieving it from memory). Bolin says this design choice simplifies things for API providers and makes it easier to support customers who opt into “ Zero Data Retention ,” where OpenAI does not store user data.&lt;br/&gt;(대화가 계속됨에 따라, 각각의 새로운 턴에는 이전 메시지와 도구 호출의 전체 기록이 포함됩니다. 이는 프롬프트가 모든 상호작용마다 증가함을 의미하며, 이는 성능에 영향을 미칩니다. 해당 게시글에 따르면, Codex는 API가 저장된 대화 상태를 참조할 수 있게 해주는 선택적 'previous_response_id' 매개변수를 사용하지 않기 때문에, 모든 요청은 완전히 상태 비저장적입니다(즉, 서버가 메모리에서 검색하는 대신 각 API 호출마다 전체 대화 기록을 전송합니다). 볼린은 이 설계 선택이 API 제공자들을 위해 일을 단순화하고, OpenAI가 사용자 데이터를 저장하지 않는 '제로 데이터 보존'을 선택한 고객들을 더 쉽게 지원할 수 있게 한다고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quadratic growth of prompts over a conversation is inefficient, but Bolin explains that prompt caching mitigates this issue somewhat. Cache hits only work for exact prefix matches within a prompt, which means Codex must carefully avoid operations that could cause cache misses. Changing the available tools, switching models, or modifying the sandbox configuration mid-conversation can all invalidate the cache and hurt performance.&lt;br/&gt;(대화 중 프롬프트의 2차적 증가는 비효율적이지만, 볼린은 프롬프트 캐싱이 이 문제를 어느 정도 완화한다고 설명합니다. 캐시 히트는 프롬프트 내에서 정확한 접두사 일치에 대해서만 작동하므로, Codex는 캐시 미스를 유발할 수 있는 작업을 주의 깊게 피해야 합니다. 사용 가능한 도구 변경, 모델 전환, 또는 대화 중 샌드박스 구성 수정은 모두 캐시를 무효화하고 성능을 저하시킬 수 있습니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ever-growing prompt length is directly related to the context window, which limits how much text the AI model can process in a single inference call. Bolin writes that Codex automatically compacts conversations when token counts exceed a threshold, just as Claude Code does. Earlier versions of Codex required manual compaction via a slash command, but the current system uses a specialized API endpoint that compresses context while preserving summarized portions of the model’s “understanding” of what happened through an encrypted content item.&lt;br/&gt;(계속 증가하는 프롬프트 길이는 컨텍스트 윈도우와 직접적으로 관련되어 있으며, 이는 AI 모델이 단일 추론 호출에서 처리할 수 있는 텍스트의 양을 제한합니다. 볼린은 Codex가 토큰 수가 임계값을 초과할 때 Claude Code와 마찬가지로 자동으로 대화를 압축한다고 씁니다. Codex의 초기 버전은 슬래시 명령을 통한 수동 압축이 필요했지만, 현재 시스템은 암호화된 콘텐츠 항목을 통해 모델의 발생 상황에 대한 '이해'의 요약된 부분을 보존하면서 컨텍스트를 압축하는 특수 API 엔드포인트를 사용합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bolin says that future posts in his series will cover the CLI’s architecture, tool implementation details, and Codex’s sandboxing model.&lt;br/&gt;(볼린은 그의 시리즈의 향후 게시글에서 CLI의 아키텍처, 도구 구현 세부사항 및 Codex의 샌드박싱 모델을 다룰 것이라고 말합니다.)&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2026/01/openai-spills-technical-details-about-how-its-ai-coding-agent-works/</guid><enclosure url="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/coding_robots_agents-1152x648.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:05:17 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>