<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 14:31:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Hard Times in the Delta as Farmers Consider Letting Crops Rot</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/mississippi-delta-farmers-rice-prices.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-mississippi-farms-B1/00biz-mississippi-02-lhbq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Westerfield stood ankle deep atop 30 feet of unhusked rice, his gray T-shirt and jeans dusty with starchy powder. He sounded distressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What am I supposed to do with 2.2 million pounds of rice?” he asked, raising his voice to be heard over the noisy industrial fans drying the rice on his farm in Merigold, Miss. “I’m serious. What am I supposed to do?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a rhetorical question. Mr. Westerfield had even considered whether he should dump the grains onto a field to rot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the country, farmers are struggling. Prices for nearly every major crop are below what it costs to grow them. Much attention has been paid to Midwestern soybean growers, whose crop was at the heart of the trade war between the United States and China. But farmers in Mississippi are perhaps worse off than farmers in the rest of the country. Rice is one of their biggest crops, and almost no one is buying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things feel so hopeless that at a recent Mississippi Farm Bureau Federation meeting, a group representing farmers, participants floated the idea of a government program that would pay producers to destroy the harvested rice sitting in their bins. A similar program was put in place during the 1980s farm crisis, when the Agriculture Department paid farmers to idle land and reduce huge surpluses of crops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are making a lot of good crops, and losing money,” said Gwin Smith, the longtime owner of Rutledge Investment Company, a Mississippi agricultural land broker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mississippi Delta is a 200-mile-long pocket of fertile soil between the Mississippi and Yazoo Rivers. But farming costs are high. Most crops must be planted in a short window between spring rains and summer heat, and it is always a race in the fall to harvest and prepare fields before winter rains render them muddy and unworkable. This forces up labor costs during those periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And unlike Midwest summers, when rains provide most of the water for crops, drier Mississippi summers mean crops must be irrigated, requiring equipment and expensive fuel to power pumping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mississippi’s biggest advantage, besides good soil, is the diversity of things that can be grown. While most of the Midwest grows only corn, soybeans and wheat, Mississippi farmers can grow those crops as well as cotton and rice. Whenever one crop is selling at a premium, farmers will shift to growing more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s why Mr. Westerfield thought he was being pragmatic last spring, when he looked at $7-a-bushel rice and planted 1,000 acres more than planned on the 11,000 acres he farms with his brother-in-law and a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Westerfield’s bet on rice proved ill timed. Rice prices took a dive, with futures declining about 30 percent in the last year. India, the world’s largest producer of rice, eased export restrictions in late 2024, flooding the world with rice. Customers in Latin America, where most U.S. rice is exported, increasingly prefer the taste of varieties grown in other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value of Mississippi’s row crops, including rice, fell 9 percent from 2024 to 2025, according to the Mississippi State University Extension Service, and farm bankruptcies, though still low, are on the rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unable to get any bid on his rice this fall, Mr. Westerfield had to store it in his grain bins. That meant that he had no room for the soybeans and corn he also grew and had to send them straight from the field to the local grain elevator. When soybean prices rose by $1 per bushel in November, on expectations of China’s re-entering the soybean market, he was unable to take advantage. He had already sold all of his crop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Westerfield didn’t grow up on a farm. His father was a lawyer and his mother ran a boutique store. He went to college, but dropped out. He ran a restaurant and worked on some farms before deciding to do it full time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Growing up, all it is here in the Delta is flat as a pancake, nothing but agriculture,” he said. “I thought it was the cool thing to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most farmers identify themselves by what generation farmer they are. It is a shorthand for their connection to the land. It can also indicate an economic leg up. Sixth-generation farmers may well have inherited the land they work and a lot of the equipment they use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Westerfield is a first-generation farmer. He started working on another farm full time to learn the ropes, flipping houses and selling stuff on eBay on the side. He was able to afford to buy his first 80 acres because his father helped with the down payment. He buys whatever old machinery he can find and learns to fix it to save costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the average age of farmers inches up, and expensive land and equipment make it cost prohibitive for newcomers to enter the profession, stories like Mr. Westerfield’s are uncommon. And they will remain that way, especially if losing hundreds of thousands of dollars this year on rice pushes him too far into the red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of it makes Mr. Westerfield, a relatively young farmer at 37, wonder about the future. “Who wants to come out here and work as hard as you have to work and climb this mountain of debt you might not see the top of until the end of your life?” he asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mississippi Delta has a history as an agriculture powerhouse, though its wealth rarely flowed to those who worked the fields or the surrounding areas. At the time of the Civil War, the Delta was dominated by cotton plantations, and the legacy of slavery and Jim Crow casts a long shadow. Many farms rely on white South Africans on H-2A visas, and some have settled lawsuits accusing them of paying those laborers more than Black farmworkers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Mr. Westerfield’s farms is adjacent to a dilapidated wooden barn indistinguishable from the thousands of others dotting the area. But this is the barn where 14-year-old Emmet Till was lynched in 1955. Mr. Westerfield is in discussions with the Emmett Till Interpretive Center to sell some land to make access to the site easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Delta towns have been losing population for decades. Outside of a few sizable towns, farmland and cypress trees stretch as far as the eye can see, and little tufts of cotton that float off the back of trucks are stuck everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have a lot of old farmers in the world, and a good set of young farmers, but they haven’t done well enough to build equity or buy land,” said Mr. Smith, the land broker. “Made some good money, but they don’t have the working capital or the land equity maybe to survive this thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wayne Dulaney, 52, probably does have enough working capital and land equity to survive. But he is questioning whether trying to survive is worth it, and whether it is something he wants to pass on to his children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dulaneys have been farming in Clarksdale, in the northern Mississippi Delta, so long that some of their property abuts Dulaney Road, named for the family. His father also started a seed selling business in the 1990s, and even after it was sold, Mr. Dulaney has continued as a part-time salesman for other seed companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He farms about 4,000 acres of mostly rice and soybeans alongside his brother, working out of the old seed company offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dulaney has more than 200,000 bushels of rice, or around 9 million pounds, sitting in his bins, and had losses of around $600,000 in 2025. It is disconcerting even for somebody comfortable with agriculture’s boom-and-bust cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There have been plenty of years in there where we have had a $100,000 to $300,000 loss in a year,” he said. Usually, you make that up in the next year or two. “But we are basically on Year 4 of things being tight,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The land he works is owned by a family trust, in which he has a share. His red line is clear: He won’t put up his share as collateral for a loan to cover his losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not going to do that,” he said emphatically. “I’m not going to risk the land.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dulaney, Mr. Westerfield and other Delta farmers will benefit from the $12 billion in bailout money announced by the Trump administration. Payment rates for growers of rice and cotton are the highest under the program, an acknowledgment of how badly the crops grown in Mississippi have been hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But nobody thinks the bailout money will fundamentally change the hole farmers are in. Receiving $132 per acre of rice — the price the government has set for rice — matters little when you paid $1,000 per acre to grow it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All I am hearing everywhere about the $12b payment is the plan is way too low considering,” Mr. Smith emailed before Christmas. He added, “There are a lot of people getting out or thinking about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the World Wildlife Fund, the solution to these structural barriers to profitability is obvious, if difficult to carry out: Grow food that Americans eat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of what is farmed in Mississippi and the rest of the country isn’t food that goes on Americans’ tables. It is soybeans grown for animal feed, corn grown for ethanol, rice grown to export to Central America and so on. The fruits and vegetables that Mississippians eat are probably grown in California or in other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wildlife fund calculates that if just 3 percent of Mississippi Delta agricultural land was converted from traditional row crops into fruits, vegetables and nuts, producers would earn an additional $3.2 billion in revenue because those crops receive higher prices. Mississippi’s total agricultural production was valued at $9.5 billion in 2025, though that includes livestock and forestry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the challenges of growing those crops are enormous. Local universities don’t do research on them. The federal government doesn’t insure them. There is little processing infrastructure. The banks are leery about lending. And farmers have to find their own buyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is too much risk for Wayne Dulaney. “We could grow strawberries or whatever,” he said, “but there is nowhere to take it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, Mississippi farmers like Mr. Dulaney are looking toward 2027 and 2028, hoping things will change. Planting won’t begin for a few months, but they have already written off 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/mississippi-delta-farmers-rice-prices.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>High January Is the New Dry January</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/cannabis-thc-alcoholic-beverages.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00biz-dryjanuary-01-hjzw/00biz-dryjanuary-01-hjzw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a chilly January afternoon at a Stew Leonard’s grocery store in Paramus, N.J., prominently featured in the center of the liquor department, sit stacks of colorful boxes of hemp-infused drinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tropical punch seltzers. Pineapple mojitos. Peach-flavored ice tea. Even root beer “high” soda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The growth in the category has been explosive for us,” said Blake Leonard, a member of the third generation to run the family-owned business, and president of Stew Leonard’s Wine &amp; Spirits. The retailer has even removed pallets of beer to make way for the buzzy beverages. Three years ago, Stew Leonard’s carried fewer than 10 of these brands. Today, it offers up to 75, Ms. Leonard said, estimating that sales are 25 percent higher this January than last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, millions of Americans are practicing Dry January, giving up alcohol entirely. Others are doing Damp January, cutting back on their alcohol consumption. And still others are experimenting with Cali Sober, looking for ways to get buzzed without the booze and the next-morning hangover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For liquor manufacturers and retailers, January is a bleak month. For the last three years, alcoholic beverages not only have consistently lost ground to nonalcoholic drinks in January, but have rebounded more slowly, “signaling a sustained lifestyle shift rather than a temporary post-holiday reset,” the research firm Numerator wrote this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sales of mocktails, seltzers and teas containing tetrahydrocannabinol, or THC, have surged since their introduction a few years ago. Amid increased consumer demand and legalization of the cannabis-derived drinks, major retailers like Target, Sprouts and Circle K and national liquor stores are putting the beverages on their shelves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our THC beverages, as well as nonalcoholic drinks, are two of our highest-growth categories,” said Andrea Starr, a senior director of merchandising for THC drinks at Total Wine &amp; More, a national chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, sales of THC beverages were roughly $850 million, according to the data firm Future Markets Insight, and are expected to reach around $4 billion by 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry began to flourish after hemp, which is a variety of the cannabis plant, was legalized as part of the 2018 Farm Bill with the provision that it could have no more than 0.3 percent THC by dry weight. If it exceeds that limit, the hemp is classified as marijuana, which is still illegal at the federal level. The vast majority of THC drinks sold in retail stores are made with hemp, while some of the beverages sold in licensed dispensaries are manufactured with marijuana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States then began adopting their own rules. While 28 states, including Texas, Florida and Minnesota, allow THC-laced beverages to be sold by mainstream retailers, a handful of others, including California and Arizona, limit their sale to licensed dispensaries. In Connecticut, a 12-ounce THC beverage sold at retailers is capped at three milligrams of THC, while Tennessee has a 30-milligram limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while New York State allows liquor stores or bodegas to sell beverages with one milligram or less of THC, few brands make them at that low level. Some higher-THC drinks are available at licensed cannabis dispensaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THC and its sibling, cannabidiol, or CBD, are both produced by the cannabis plant but differ significantly in their effects on the brain. Generally, drinks made with CBD will not make you feel intoxicated, but you may feel less anxious. But you’re likely to feel something — relaxed or euphoric, or anxious and paranoid — about 20 minutes after consuming a beverage containing THC; it can also trigger a positive drug test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health experts warn that the beverages can have a significant kick and that consumers new to them should start with drinks that have small amounts of THC. Most drinks sold in retail stores have five to 10 milligrams, but some have 20 and even 60 milligrams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Almost everybody knows how they respond to a standard drink, like a gin and tonic, but people don’t necessarily know how they’re going to respond to these cannabis drinks,” said Staci Gruber, an associate professor of psychiatry at Harvard Medical School whose research focuses on the impact of cannabis on the brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like caffeine and alcohol, THC produces a response that varies from person to person, Dr. Gruber and others say. “Some people can become incredibly ill from these products,” Dr. Gruber said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manufacturers say interest in THC beverages is coming not only from early adopters like millennials and Generation Z, but from women, and particularly older women, who are trying them amid concerns about alcohol and its links to various diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Soccer parents are embracing the category, purchasing the beverages once a week,” said Sam Garfinkel, a senior vice president of commercial operations and strategy for Tilray Brands, which owns the THC brands Fizzy Jane’s and Happy Flower. “We’re also seeing these beverages popping up in retirement communities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But despite rising popularity, the drinks are at risk of disappearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New, much lower federal limits on the level of THC in hemp-derived products, including gummies and beverages, are scheduled to take effect in November, under a provision in the spending package that reopened the federal government late last year. The law’s proponents said some companies were extracting THC from legalized hemp but creating stronger products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law capped the level of THC at 0.4 milligrams per beverage. The vast majority of such drinks currently sold by retailers contain significantly higher levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With a limit of 0.4 milligrams, it’s like saying you can still buy pens, but they won’t have any ink in them,” said Christopher Lackner, the president and chief executive of the Hemp Beverage Alliance, an industry group. It worked with members of Congress on a bill, introduced in mid-January, to delay the THC limit to 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amid the uncertainty, some manufacturers are weighing their futures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally at this time of year, Justin Hopf and Matt Swanson, the co-founders of Drinkin’ Buds, would be ordering hemp seed to be planted in April in Sheboygan, Wis. They use that crop to make their THC-infused spiked lemonade, rum punch and old-fashioned cocktails, which are sold in 14 states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, they are not planting any hemp, worried that if unchanged, the new federal limit on THC beverages and other products would render their drinks illegal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our current beverage product has five or 10 milligrams per can,” Mr. Hopf said. “We wouldn’t be selling them anywhere anymore. And reformulating them would be difficult. It just wouldn’t be worth the risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/cannabis-thc-alcoholic-beverages.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:02:14 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>