<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 21:14:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Nature’s Super Feather</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/science/birds-feathers-filoplumes-cornell.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/23/multimedia/00BIRD-FEATHERS-promo-wkcq/00BIRD-FEATHERS-promo-wkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanya Gregor Rohwer slid open a drawer to display the rich pink spread wing of a roseate spoonbill, one of thousands of mounted wings at the Cornell University Museum of Vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pulled up a long flight feather to expose, at its base, a palm-tree shaped feather so minuscule it could easily be missed. For a long time, this tiny feature called a filoplume was indeed obscure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The history of research on filoplumes is not super robust. They are kind of an overlooked feather,” said Dr. Rohwer, a curator of birds and mammals at the museum. “They were considered a degenerate feather or a useless feather, a relic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No longer. Dr. Rohwer and his father, Sievert Rohwer, an influential feather researcher and curator emeritus at the Burke Museum at the University of Washington in Seattle, believe that the tiny filoplume is a key player in the monitoring and maintenance of birds’ feathers, which keep them airborne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since feathers first appeared on dinosaurs around 150 million years ago, they have been evolving. Now there are six types of feathers on a bird’s body, including filoplumes, and all are made of keratin, a dead substance like human hair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A paper published last year in the Journal of the Royal Society Interface described a feather as a masterpiece of engineering, one comprising nine orders of magnitude, from the nanoscale to the meter scale. Because the most sophisticated 3-D printers are limited to just four or five orders of magnitude, feathers have yet to be replicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no manufacturing technology that can come close to a feather,” said David Lentink, one of the paper’s authors, who studies birds to find ways to improve robots at the University of Groningen in the Netherlands. “They are unusually sophisticated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a natural material that is so light that it floats slowly to the ground, yet so strong it can protect a bird flying through wind, rain and cold for days on end. And new ones replace the old ones every few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest in bird feathers has intensified alongside the rapidly expanding uses of drones and other aircraft, with researchers looking at whether synthetic feathers would make flights more maneuverable, efficient and less noisy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes have inspired micro or hair sensors, for example, that can measure air flow, speed and direction to support a type of self-navigation called “flight by feel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplume-like sensors could help drones, which have difficulty dealing with wind gusts, make split-second adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All birds have filoplumes, even those that cannot fly. There are usually one to three per feather, and they are densest around contour or body feathers and flight feathers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes detect pressure, touch and vibration in adjacent feathers and, through highly sensitive nerve endings, called Herbst corpuscles, in their follicles, translate those mechanical cues into neuronal signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sophisticated feathers provide birds with detailed information about their plumage as they fly. They tell them to adjust their feathers to stay warm, or to release heat. They may also detect the movement of parasites,prompting the birds to preen or emit oil in that area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Bristle feathers, short and found on a bird’s head, face and neck, are also sensitive to the environment and alert birds to insects and other prey.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The birds with the most filoplumes are large, strong flying species like eagles, albatrosses and vultures. Albatrosses, which have been known to fly 6,000 miles or more without stopping, are among those who have the most — more than 9,000 have been counted on some birds. So far, red-tail hawks have the most filoplumes per feather among the birds whose feathers have been counted by researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes play other roles. The beard of a wild turkey is actually thin strands of feather called mesofiloplumes. They aren’t sensory, but ornamental, and may grow up to a foot in length. A wild turkey does have filoplumes on its bald head, though, which help it sense the world around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiskered auklets, a seabird, have large ones atop their heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those are elaborate filoplumes,” Dr. Vanya Rohwer said. “They use them for navigating down these dark nesting burrows so they are not hitting their heads.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying filoplumes and other plumage alongside his father for more than 20 years, he thought he knew how birds lost and regrew their feathers every few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was predictable, sequential and orderly,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, though, the Rohwers learned about a captive golden eagle whose tail feathers were cut experimentally for research purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That eagle replaced a cut tail feather way, way faster than an uncut feather,” the younger Dr. Rohwer said, shortening the growth period to about a year. “So birds have some mechanism to detect a feather that is not performing well.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Dr. Sievert Rohwer, said that the filoplumes, presumably, “are sensitive to vibration the feather would generate if it’s worn or not functioning as well as it should.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes intuitive sense,” the younger Dr. Rohwer said. “You are crashing through the brush capturing prey or struggling with it on the ground, a process very likely to break a feather.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Rohwers are leading curators of extended bird wings, which they have used to study filoplumes and other feathers. The elder Dr. Rohwer, 83, has amassed the world’s largest collection of bird wings, which have been spread out and mounted at the Burke Museum, with 40,000 pairs pinned open in cellophane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Vanya Rohwer, 43, is building a sizable spread wing collection of his own here at Cornell, which so far comprises around 10,000 pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full bird specimens, meanwhile, are kept in drawers, in a kind of morgue. Dr. Rohwer opened some of them on a recent tour to reveal an array of colorful plumage, including pink-and-peach-colored lilac breasted rollers and green-and-yellow bee eaters. Another drawer was filled with extinct species, including several ivory-billed woodpeckers and a passenger pigeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bird nests are another passion of the younger Dr. Rohwer’s and he studies bird eyelashes as well. In one study, he found that the use of snakeskin to line many birds’ nests significantly reduced predation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rohwer met his wife, Rachel Schlass Rohwer, when, as a budding taxidermist, she attended his class on the preparation of avian specimens. She was smitten both by Dr. Rohwer and the painstaking process of preparing birds for display in museums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Knowing these passenger pigeons once eclipsed the sky, and seeing them in these drawers with so much of their color retained, it really moved me,” Ms. Schlass Rohwer said. “Most things when they die lose color and lose so much of their narrative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The couple has taken several salvage trips to harvest surplus bird and mammal specimens from freezers at other museums for the Cornell collection. They skin and stuff the birds with cotton or spread their wings in a display, where they are available to researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Schlass Rowher, who has also studied fashion, has specialized in designing hats with ethically obtained feathers from birds who died naturally and are legal to own. It’s a violation of federal law to possess most types of bird feathers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With advances in technologies, new information is being extracted from feathers. DNA from a single feather, for instance, allows researchers to trace that bird back to its breeding population. That information is being used to create “genoscape” maps across the world for migratory birds, and to prioritize important habitats for conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filoplume, though, remains one of the least-understood feathers. “A lot remains to be discovered about their function,” Dr. Lentink said, “because it is almost impossible to study their function in living birds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bird in the lab is very different than a bird in the air, leaving avian flight largely a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes science can’t answer questions because the experiments are too hard, this is such a case,” he said. “It is hard to really prove functions of these feathers in a fully functional happy flying bird doing its normal behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/science/birds-feathers-filoplumes-cornell.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:56:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>David Rosen, 95, Dies; Video Game Visionary and Co-Founder of Sega</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/david-rosen-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/00rosen-promo-bgpz/00rosen-promo-bgpz-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maxim Ibragimov/Shutterstock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As co-founder of Sega Enterprises, David Rosen played a leading role in turning video games into a cultural touchstone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega’s games were a direct challenge to Nintendo’s dominance. Among them was Bare Knuckle II, which came to the U.S. as Streets of Rage 2 in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before long, Genesis was seemingly everywhere. But Mr. Rosen’s path to video game prominence was circuitous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supported by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He transformed his Japanese photo booth business into a gaming industry game giant that created Mortal Kombat, Sonic the Hedgehog and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Michael S. Rosenwald&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Rosen, a Brooklyn-born entrepreneur who transformed his photo booth business in Japan into Sega Enterprises, the video game giant that dominated arcades, basements and dorm rooms with blockbusters like Mortal Kombat, Sonic the Hedgehog and N.H.L. ’94, died on Dec. 25 at his home in Los Angeles. He was 95.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His death was confirmed by Annette van Duren, a spokeswoman for his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a four-decade career that began in the 1950s with coin-operated machines and culminated with the introduction of cutting-edge home gaming systems, Mr. Rosen was a visionary figure who helped shape what is now a $200 billion industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is eminently clear that computer video games are a sign of the times,” he wrote in Play Meter magazine in 1982. “And by that I mean the games are truly one of the early manifestations of an electronic revolution whose technology will personally touch, on an increasing basis, all of our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chairman of Sega’s U.S. operation in 1989, Mr. Rosen oversaw the introduction of the company’s Genesis gaming console to North America, a product that directly challenged the near-monopoly that Nintendo, its main competitor, had in American homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega marketed its system to teenagers and young adults who had played Nintendo as children, positioning Genesis as more technologically advanced, with a lineup of grittier, more intense games. In doing so, the company forged the creative and commercial blueprint that turned gaming into a cultural touchstone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 1990s, Genesis was seemingly everywhere: in commercials during the MTV Video Music Awards; on an episode of “Roseanne,” when the title character’s son, D.J., huffs off to play Genesis at a friend’s house when his parents won’t buy him a Nintendo; and in the 1996 movie “Swingers,” when Trent, played by Vince Vaughn, makes Wayne Gretzky’s head bleed in a popular hockey game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players would greet each other by shouting, “Sega!” parroting the signature ending of the company’s commercials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everything that Sega was able to do in the ’90s was built on the foundation that Rosen built,” Ken Horowitz, the author of “Playing at the Next Level: A History of American Sega Games” (2016), said in an interview. “The industry would not have become as big a thing as it is today if not for him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rosen took a circuitous path to gaming eminence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1940s, while stationed in Japan with the U.S. Air Force, he became enamored with the country’s culture, especially its art. After his discharge in 1952, he moved to New York and started a business selling portraits by Japanese painters. It wasn’t exactly a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1954, Mr. Rosen moved to Tokyo, where he noticed a booming market in photo identification cards for school and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning that shops took about three days to process photos, he thought he could shorten the wait to mere seconds by importing photo booths like the ones he had seen in American amusement parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He started a company, Rosen Enterprises, which installed hundreds of the machines around Japan — in movie theaters, restaurants and stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There were different times when people would go through school applications and whatnot, and it was not unusual at those times of the year for the lines to get into the booth to be an hour, hour and a half,” he said in an interview with the gaming journalist Steven L. Kent for the book “The Ultimate History of Video Games.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1950s, when the typical workweek in Japan shrunk from six or seven days to five and leisure time exploded, Mr. Rosen began thinking of ways to enter the entertainment market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The popular entertainment at that point in time in Japan was pachinko, dance studios, bars and cabarets,” he said in an interview with Next Generation magazine. “None of these were something I wanted to get involved in, so I thought, ‘Gee, coin-operated games.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinball machines, mechanical claws and shooting galleries had become popular arcade games in the United States but were virtually nonexistent in Japan. Mr. Rosen cut deals with U.S. distributors to import older arcade games that were gathering dust in warehouses, then installed them in the same locations as his photo booths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The games, especially the shooting ones, were an immediate hit. Before long, several Japan-based competitors emerged. The biggest was Service Games, a jukebox manufacturer that had transformed into an arcade operator. In 1965, Service Games and Rosen Enterprises merged, becoming Sega Enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newly formed company quickly released its own games, beginning with Periscope, a submarine simulator designed by Mr. Rosen, in which players fired projectiles at cardboard ships. The game was a huge hit, and Sega exported it to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1972, Atari released the video game Pong. Sega imported it to Japan. Soon, the company was making its own video games — first for arcades and eventually for its home consoles, starting with the SG-1000 in 1983.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Mr. Rosen, gaming represented an entirely new category of entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Activities such as television, movies, sporting events and records or the radio all have a valid place in our society, yet all these forms of entertainment lack an important factor in satisfying a fundamental need,” Mr. Rosen wrote in Play Meter. “That need is active participation, which is, of course, what computer video games are all about.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Rosen was born in Brooklyn on Jan. 22, 1930, to Samuel and Fay (Sacks) Rosen. His father was an importer and also owned a chocolate factory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After joining the Air Force when he was 18, Mr. Rosen was stationed throughout Asia, serving as a writer for Armed Forces Radio. He also worked in the finance office on a military base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He married Masako Fujisaki in 1954. She died last year. His family declined to provide information about his survivors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rosen stayed with Sega through several mergers. He retired in 1996 as the company was in the early stages of losing battles against Sony, which boasted the PlayStation console, and then Microsoft, with Xbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sega just didn’t have the financial resources to battle with these bigger companies, which could afford huge losses until their machines became profitable,” Mr. Horowitz said. “Sony and Microsoft just had endless supplies of cash.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega is now part of Sega Sammy Holdings Inc., a Japan-based entertainment conglomerate. In addition to making its own games, the company purchased Rovio, the developer of Angry Birds, in 2023. This year, Sega will celebrate the 35th anniversary of Sonic the Hedgehog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late in his career, Mr. Rosen marveled at how far he’d come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I was a youngster, I went to Coney Island,” he said in “The Ultimate History of Video Games.” “Like everybody else in New York City, I played the games in the penny arcades. That was really my total knowledge of the business.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/david-rosen-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:57:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber Faces Growing Pressure Over Sexual Assault Record</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/uber-scrutiny-sexual-assault.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21Biz-Uber-Ballot-01-qmfz/21Biz-Uber-Ballot-01-qmfz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A billboard in Century City, Los Angeles.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/uber-scrutiny-sexual-assault.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:03:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Anxious Japan Restarts the World’s Biggest Nuclear Plant</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/japan-nuclear-restart.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/Biz-Japan-Nuclear-01-pmlj/Biz-Japan-Nuclear-01-pmlj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan is reviving nuclear power, balancing the need for more clean energy against the lingering trauma of the 2011 Fukushima Daiichi disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/japan-nuclear-restart.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:29:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Adaptive Normalcy’ as the Trump Show Arrives at Davos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/dealbook/davos-trump-speech.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21db-trump-gfvw/21db-trump-gfvw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump is set to speak today at the World Economic Forum, an address that has generated excitement and some trepidation.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/dealbook/davos-trump-speech.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:42:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Travelers in 2026, Prices Are All Over the Map</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/prices-are-all-over-the-map.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Price-illo/21Price-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luxury travelers can expect to pay more than they did last year, while budget travelers might get a break.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/prices-are-all-over-the-map.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:44:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Getting Travel Rewards Is Getting Easier</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/loyalty-programs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Loyalty-illo/21Loyalty-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Program updates and new navigation tools help travelers negotiate the increasingly complicated universe of points.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/loyalty-programs.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:46:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Check-In, Your Face Is Increasingly Your ID</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/facial-recognition-airports.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Biometrics-illo/21Biometrics-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facial recognition at security and immigration checkpoints and gates could ease airport hassles, even as the technology raises privacy concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/facial-recognition-airports.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:47:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Do Young Travelers Want? Exclusive Experiences.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/experiences-millennials-gen-z.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Experiences-illo/21Experiences-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More millennials and Gen Z-ers are planning trips around experiences, and the industry is responding with concerts, dinners and V.I.P. events.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/experiences-millennials-gen-z.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:47:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel’s Latest Buzzword: ‘Microvacations’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/short-microvacations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Micro-vaca-illo/21Micro-vaca-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travelers short on vacation time are embarking on one- to three-day trips that take advantage of time zones and credit card points.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/short-microvacations.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:52:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mediaite Starts a Newsletter to Summarize Media Newsletters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/media/mediaite-media-newsletter.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/MEDIA-META-1-wvhp/MEDIA-META-1-wvhp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mediaite’s founder, Dan Abrams.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/media/mediaite-media-newsletter.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:57:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sports-Betting Scandals Are Ubiquitous. Whether Fans Will Care Is an Open Question.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/sports-betting-scandals-fans.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/00biz-sports-integrity-wjfv/00biz-sports-integrity-wjfv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
N.B.A. viewership was 60 percent higher compared with the year before on the night the F.B.I. held its news conference about a scandal involving figures from the Portland Trail Blazers.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/sports-betting-scandals-fans.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:55:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Job Applicants Sue A.I. Recruitment Tool Company</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/ai-hiring-tools-lawsuit-eightfold-fcra.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21Biz-AI-HIRING-gpmt/21Biz-AI-HIRING-gpmt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Erin Kistler at her Los Angeles home.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/ai-hiring-tools-lawsuit-eightfold-fcra.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:00:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>4 Takeaways from Supreme Court Hearing on Trump’s Firing of Lisa Cook</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/4-takeaways-supreme-court-fed-hearing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-takeaways-top-tcqh/21dc-takeaways-top-tcqh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Lisa Cook, a federal reserve governor, with her attorney Abbe Lowell, outside the Supreme Court on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/4-takeaways-supreme-court-fed-hearing.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:45:30 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>