<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:55:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Power Outages Could Rise as Freezing Temperatures Persist</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/energy-environment/storm-electric-grid-power-outages.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-grid-storm-mfzc/26biz-grid-storm-mfzc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As wintry conditions and frigid temperatures gripped much of the United States this weekend, the nation’s power system has avoided buckling like it has in past years. But the system continued to face severe strain early Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of thousands of residents and businesses largely in the southern parts of the country had no electricity. Most of those outages resulted from the typical challenges that accompany winter storms: snow piling up on electrical equipment and ice dangling from branches and power lines, causing them to snap. And with temperatures below freezing and demand for electricity expected to stay high, outages could very likely expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm this weekend blanketed wide parts of the nation under more than a foot of snow in some places and sheets of ice in others. Some weather models are predicting another storm, but meteorologists have cautioned that the forecast was hypothetical and should not be treated as a certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This next wave of ice that may be coming in is going to test the system even further,” said Calvin Butler, the chief executive of Exelon, which owns regulated utilities in New Jersey, Maryland, Delaware, Pennsylvania and Illinois. “All that ice, they’re just not used to it,” he said, referring to the Southeast. “We’re more used to hurricanes in the Southeast.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explosive winter storm that moved from the Southwest to the Northeast comes as electric grids struggle to manage a staggering rise in electricity demand from data centers, some of which support the development of artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first major test of the power system’s resilience during a potent winter storm in the era of huge data center expansion. In an unusual move, the Department of Energy late Sunday ordered the manager of Texas’ main electric grid, the Electric Reliability Council of Texas, to direct data centers and other facilities that consume a lot of energy to begin using backup generators in an effort to prevent blackouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other grid operators, ERCOT issued weather alerts ahead of the storm but expected conditions on the system to remain normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas experienced a widespread electric grid failure during a severe winter storm in February 2021 that killed more than 200 people. Energy companies in the state have since added more batteries, power plants and other resources, but industry experts said the state still had work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the fourth once-in-a-hundred-year winter storm in ERCOT in 25 years,” said Robert McCullough, of McCullough Research, a consulting firm in Portland, Ore. “We are forecasting poorly and preparing even worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Edison Electric Institute, a utility industry organization, is coordinating responses to the winter storm with executives of power companies across the country. That has helped utilities deploy 65,000 lineman and other workers to respond to power outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People and trucks are rolling across the country, even throughout this weather to help people,” Mr. Butler of Exelon said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/energy-environment/storm-electric-grid-power-outages.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:16:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington Post Reverses Decision on Olympics Coverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/washington-post-olympics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-wapo-olympics-1-1-qjhg/26biz-wapo-olympics-1-1-qjhg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post is reversing course on its Winter Olympics plans — again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newspaper originally intended to send more than a dozen journalists to cover the event, which has long been a major priority for The Post. Those employees were notified in a terse email on Friday, less than three weeks before the Olympics begin, that The Post would not send any of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, The Post expects to send four journalists, according to three people with knowledge of the decision. A spokeswoman for The Post confirmed the paper would be sending a small contingent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After The Post’s change of plans became public last week, admirers of the newspaper’s sports section raised objections on social media, noting the awkward timing of the decision and the effect it could have on coverage. Christine Brennan, a columnist for USA Today who was The Post’s Olympics beat writer from 1988 to 1996, wrote on X that it was a “stunning and awful development.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employees at The Post were taken by surprise, in part because the company had already made significant investments to cover the Winter Games. Flights had already been booked for the journalists’ travel to Italy, where the event is being held, and The Post had already spent roughly $80,000 for lodging.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/washington-post-olympics.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:57:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Says He Will Raise Tariffs on South Korea to 25%</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/economy/trump-tariffs-south-korea.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-tariffs-jpgm/26dc-trump-tariffs-jpgm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump on Monday said he would raise tariffs on South Korea.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/economy/trump-tariffs-south-korea.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:12:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Trump’s Shadow, India and the European Union Expand Trade Ties</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/india-europe-trade-tariffs-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/India-EU-Trade-pjbm/India-EU-Trade-pjbm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The European Council president, Antonio Costa, and the European Commission president, Ursula von der Leyen, came to India to announce a trade agreement nearly 20 years in the making.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/india-europe-trade-tariffs-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:05:03 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>