<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 09:33:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Cracks Begin to Appear at the Nation’s Biggest Banks</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/banks-earnings-goldman-sachs-jpmorgan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15BIZ-BANK-EARNINGS-fgwj/15BIZ-BANK-EARNINGS-fgwj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year, Wall Street’s dominant theme has been the so-called K-shaped economy, in which the well-to-do have powered financial activity despite lower earners’ struggles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, the nation’s largest banks reported a broadly disappointing set of quarterly earnings, marking the first stumble after a yearlong spree of rising markets and softening regulations paid off handsomely for the finance set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results at Bank of America, Citi, JPMorgan Chase and Wells Fargo all fell short of expectations and their shares fell. Troubles ranged from delayed merger deals (JPMorgan) to stubborn expenses (Citi) to questions about the efficacy of artificial intelligence tools (Bank of America). Banks that do business largely with rich individuals and corporations, such as Goldman Sachs and Morgan Stanley, fared comparatively better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from major lenders are closely watched because they contain hints about the state of the economy and ordinary American consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wells Fargo’s chief executive, Charles Scharf, said his organization had not seen a “meaningful” shift among the customer data it collects, including checking account flows, direct deposit amounts, overdraft activity and payments. Another Wells Fargo executive described “very consistent activity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wells Fargo’s quarterly results disappointed for a different reason: Lower-than-expected profits, in part because mortgage lending stayed weak in a slow housing market. The bank’s stock saw its steepest fall in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For yet another quarter, Trump administration policies loomed large. This time, the banks were asked by reporters and Wall Street analysts about President Trump’s threatened 10 percent cap on credit card interest rates. Although it’s not clear how or if Mr. Trump could unilaterally impose that ceiling, bankers mostly gave identical responses by arguing that charging lower rates would cause them to lend less to riskier borrowers with patchier credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Jeremy Barnum, JPMorgan’s chief financial officer, was candid about what a cap would mean for the bottom line. “It would obviously be bad for us,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Moynihan, Bank of America’s chief executive, kicked off 2025 by being publicly dressed down by Mr. Trump in a Davos, Switzerland, interview, and the lender’s stock lagged its rivals for much of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, Wall Street analysts repeatedly prodded Mr. Moynihan and his chief financial officer during a question-and-answer session about why the bank’s expenses (including head count) remained high despite purported efficiency improvements, as well as its relatively slow pace of growth. Mr. Moynihan eventually conceded in response: “You should expect us to get back on a streak.” Shares dropped anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks are not typically seen as on the cutting edge of technology, and Wall Street has been more eager to lend into the A.I. boom than to talk specifics about how it may change their own businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bank of America said its much-promoted “virtual financial assistant,” nicknamed Erica, was used less than before by customers in the fourth quarter. Executives attempted to argue that this was sign that the bank was doing a better job warding off questions before they even needed to be asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldman Sachs on Thursday said that it was debuting “a new operating model propelled by artificial intelligence.” A bank spokesman said that included creating a more enjoyable experience for the bank’s staff as the technology automated what he described as mundane tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are reasons for optimism on Wall Street. Investment bank traders took advantage of strong financial markets to bolster profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rise in mergers and acquisitions, exemplified by the $100 billion bidding war between Netflix and Paramount for Warner Bros. Discovery, is also a boon to Wall Street dealmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for all of this week’s angst, large bank stocks are up strongly over the past 12 months, even after this week’s stumble.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/banks-earnings-goldman-sachs-jpmorgan.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 10:15:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Biggest U.S. Crypto Company Asserts Its Power in Washington</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/coinbase-crypto-bill-clarity-act.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15biz-coinbase-kpth/15biz-coinbase-kpth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major cryptocurrency bill was headed for a committee vote in the Senate on Thursday after months of negotiations, a crucial step in the legislative process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came a social media post from the top executive of Coinbase, the largest U.S. crypto company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Coinbase unfortunately can’t support the bill as written,” Brian Armstrong, chief executive of Coinbase, posted on X Wednesday evening. “This version would be materially worse than the current status quo. We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within hours, the Senate vote was canceled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fate of a hotly contested legislative vote typically hinges on a few key lawmakers who are the moderate voices in a partisan scuffle. But what happened this week to the landmark crypto bill shows how much power Coinbase now wields in Washington, with the crypto industry newly ascendant under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, congressional staff had worked on the Clarity Act, a nearly 300-page bill designed to establish a regulatory framework for virtually every aspect of crypto, with rules the industry helped write. But at the last minute, Mr. Armstrong objected to proposed language that threatened to outlaw one of Coinbase’s products and said that the bill would assign too much authority to the Securities and Exchange Commission, the nation’s top financial regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coinbases’s decisive intervention follows years of the company’s work to build a voice in Washington. A publicly traded firm worth nearly $70 billion, Coinbase helped finance a network of PACs that spent more than $130 million to influence congressional races in 2024, aiming to elect pro-crypto legislators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The barrage of political spending sent an unmistakable message to Congress: Anyone who crosses the crypto industry could become a target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the industry’s leading firms have leverage to push for their interests. “Coinbase has played its hand very well,” said Todd Phillips, a finance expert at Georgia State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A representative for Coinbase did not offer a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 2012, Coinbase provides a marketplace for people to buy, sell and store cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ether. Anyone can log onto the app and make a purchase with a few clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t long ago, though, that the company faced a much tougher landscape in Washington. In 2023, the S.E.C. sued Coinbase for operating as an unregistered exchange, part of the Biden administration’s broad-reaching crackdown on crypto. Mr. Armstrong, who had co-founded the company, attacked the S.E.C. for “regulation by enforcement” and called for more “clarity around crypto rules.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s election in 2024 changed everything. Shortly before taking office, he and his sons started a crypto business, and Mr. Trump proclaimed that he would make the United States the “crypto capital of the planet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within weeks of Mr. Trump’s inauguration, the S.E.C. dropped its cases against Coinbase and other crypto firms. The industry pushed for legislation that would enshrine that regulatory pullback in law, preventing a future administration from reviving the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, with the administration’s support, the House passed its version of the Clarity Act, which essentially adopted the crypto industry’s concept for a new regulatory system. The bill would make it much easier for crypto firms like Coinbase to declare that digital currencies are not securities subject to the system of federal oversight designed to protect investors and markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the legislation faced hurdles in the Senate. In the fall, Senate Democrats proposed strict rules on decentralized finance, a branch of the crypto world, prompting outrage in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, banking lobbyists pushed for language to prevent crypto exchanges like Coinbase from paying interest to people who own stablecoins, a type of digital currency designed to maintain a price of $1. They argued that the exchanges would undermine banks by providing a product that competed with traditional deposit accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue soon became a sticking point for Coinbase. A ban on interest could compromise one of its revenue sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The way you compete is that you offer these types of incentive programs,” said Kara Calvert, a top policy executive at Coinbase. “It’s absolutely critical.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Senate’s most recent draft of the Clarity Act was unveiled close to midnight on Monday. Congressional staff members and crypto executives rushed to comb through it before the Senate committee meeting scheduled for Thursday, known as a markup, where senators would have a chance to introduce amendments to the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the markup fast approaching, Mr. Armstrong said that he was pulling his support, even as other crypto executives posted messages of support for the legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday night, Senator Tim Scott of South Carolina, the Republican chairman of the Senate Banking Committee, said the markup would be postponed to an unspecified date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everyone remains at the table working in good faith,” he said in a statement. “The goal is to deliver clear rules of the road that protect consumers, strengthen our national security and ensure the future of finance is built in the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharon LaFraniere contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/coinbase-crypto-bill-clarity-act.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 10:00:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Big Plan for Fannie and Freddie I.P.O. in Flux as Trump Pushes Affordability</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/fannie-and-freddie-ipo.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15biz-fannie-ipo-wvbp/15biz-fannie-ipo-wvbp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was supposed to be one of most consequential I.P.O.s in years, and President Trump wanted the nation’s biggest investment banks to hash out a plan to sell shares of the government-controlled mortgage giants Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac on a major stock exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last summer, Mr. Trump met with the chiefs of Bank of America, Citigroup, JPMorgan Chase and Goldman Sachs at the White House to discuss the initial public offering. White House officials predicted the stock offering would happen quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But six months later, the deal is still a work in progress. The government has retained a law firm, Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, to advise on the deal, but it has not appointed a major Wall Street bank to put together the offering and sell it to institutional investors, said several people briefed on the process who were not authorized to speak publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another critical decision remains outstanding: After any stock offering, will the mortgage firms be freed from government control? Fannie and Freddie were taken over by the federal government during the 2008 financial crisis to prevent their collapse and further disruption to the housing market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the firms have recovered fully from the crisis and no longer require the government’s strict monitoring of their finances, they remain a critical cog in the nation’s $12 trillion mortgage market. Some officials in the Trump administration are wary of anything that could complicate Fannie’s and Freddie’s role in the flow of credit to home buyers, said three other people briefed on the matter but not authorized to speak publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fannie and Freddie buy mortgages from banks and other lenders and package them into bonds sold to institutional investors. By buying bonds from banks, they free up capital for banks to write more loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investors in an I.P.O. may balk at the notion that the mortgage firms would essentially continue to be run by the White House via the Federal Housing Finance Agency, because what the government deems is best for the mortgage market may not always align with the interests of private shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you should know. The Times makes a careful decision any time it uses an anonymous source. The information the source supplies must be newsworthy and give readers genuine insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing pressure from voters in a midterm election year, Mr. Trump has made boosting housing affordability through lower mortgage rates a top policy goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some housing experts saw last week’s announcement that Mr. Trump had ordered Fannie and Freddie to buy up to $200 billion in mortgage-backed bonds to help drive down mortgage rates as an indication the White House no longer favored ending the government conservatorship anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Fannie and Freddie were freed from federal control, the experts added, Mr. Trump and the White House would not be able to easily direct the so-called government-sponsored entities to buy bonds or take other measures it deemed necessary to make housing more affordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It looks like the Trump team is seeing the G.S.E.’s as utilities,” said Jim Parrott, a nonresident fellow at the Urban Institute and an adviser on housing finance issues. “The more the administration comes to view them as instruments of affordability the less likely they will be to give up control of them any time soon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Parrott has long called for the federal government treat Fannie and Freddie as quasi-public utilities that can be used to make the mortgage and housing markets more affordable. He has said the Trump administration should not push ahead with a big stock offering for Fannie and Freddie until it decides the future structure of the companies and their role in the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David M. Dworkin, president of the National Housing Conference, a coalition of affordable housing providers, said any decision to end the government conservatorship needed to be done in consultation with many industry players, including bankers, homebuilders and investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is essential the approach be transparent,” said Mr. Dworkin, a former Treasury official in the Obama and first Trump administrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kush Desai, a White House spokesman, said “restoring the American Dream of homeownership after Joe Biden’s affordability disaster was a key campaign pledge for President Trump.” He added that the “administration is looking at every option to continue delivering on this pledge while protecting taxpayers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main proponents of moving swiftly with an offering have been the commerce secretary, Howard Lutnick, and the F.H.F.A. director, Bill Pulte, as well as some longtime investors in shares of Fannie and Freddie, including several hedge funds. But concern about disrupting the mortgage market is one reason the Treasury secretary, Scott Bessent, is said to have taken a much more judicious approach to any new stock offering, according to three of the people briefed on the matter. (Mr. Bessent previously said that while he favored ending the government control of Fannie and Freddie he would not do anything that would increase mortgage rates.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bessent may want to keep the status quo and not do a hasty stock offering,” said Wesley Lin, a professor of public policy at U.C.L.A. and a former policy adviser in the Obama and Biden administrations. “It’s a ‘let’s not rock the boat’ approach.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rate on the traditional 30-year mortgage currently sits at 6.06 percent, down about a percentage point from where it was a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pulte, who last fall frequently touted the stock offering on social media, has said little about the proposed deal over the past several weeks. But in a statement to The New York Times, Mr. Pulte said Mr. Trump made the right call “to not sell the companies during his first term” and that they were now worth at least $500 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mortgage rates are still relatively high compared to the decade-long low-rate environment that preceded the pandemic. But Mr. Trump and others in the administration have credited some of the recent decline to his directive that Fannie and Freddie begin buying mortgage bonds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buying mortgage bonds, in theory, can help reduce mortgage rates broadly because bond prices tend to move inversely to rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bonds marketed by Fannie and Freddie are generally considered as safe a bet as investing in Treasuries because the mortgage firms guarantee those securities in the event of default. And the federal government, which chartered both companies decades ago as public-private entities, implicitly has agreed to stand behind those mortgage guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that seemingly risk-free strategy went haywire during the financial crisis and ensuing wave of home foreclosures. Fannie and Freddie got themselves into trouble, in part, by borrowing too much money and investing in bonds backed by high-risk mortgages. To prevent both companies from collapsing, the federal government had to step in and bail them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In return for a taxpayer-funded $187 billion, the Treasury Department took equity stakes in the companies. The bailout ended up being a good deal for the government, as it helped stabilize the mortgage market, and the companies have since paid more than $300 billion in dividends to the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of a stock offering for Fannie and Freddie believe a sale of some of the government’s remaining equity would both raise tens of billions more for the Treasury and boost the valuation of the government’s remaining shares. It would also generate tens of millions in fees for the Wall Street banks, some of whom have retained the law firm Kirkland &amp; Ellis to advise them on establishing the terms for their work on the offering, said three people briefed on the matter. A stock offering also would lead to the companies having their shares re-listed on either the New York Stock Exchange or Nasdaq Stock Market, as opposed to the less prestigious over-the-counter market where the stocks have traded for the past 18 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current corporate governance of Fannie and Freddie could pose a problem because Mr. Pulte, who is the firms’ regulator, appointed himself as chair of each of their boards, and named a number of his allies as board members. Both stock exchanges require a majority of board members to be independent and have no material ties to a company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dworkin said a stock offering that “simply establishes a base line value for the government’s stake is not harmful.” But, he added, it has to be “properly structured.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/fannie-and-freddie-ipo.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:13:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>State and Federal Lawmakers Want Data Centers to Pay More for Energy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/energy-environment/data-center-energy-electricity-costs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15biz-data-center-energy-htkv/15biz-data-center-energy-htkv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governors, senators and even some tech executives increasingly agree that the companies behind data centers need to pay more for electricity and to address the strain they are causing on the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is little consensus about how much they ought to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A growing body of research suggests that the rapid growth of data centers to support the development of artificial intelligence is beginning to drive up electricity costs for residents and small businesses in some places. That has prompted Republicans and Democrats from at least a dozen states — including Florida, Oklahoma, New York and California — to propose legislation and consider other steps to protect residents from higher electricity costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Senator Chris Van Hollen of Maryland, a Democrat, introduced legislation that he said would ensure that technology companies paid their fair share of costs for upgrades to the electric grid that are needed to provide energy to data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Van Hollen’s bill cites recent analysis that indicates that by 2028, the share of all U.S. electricity used by data centers could almost double to as much as 12 percent. That, the senator asserts, will push up electricity prices for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we hope to do is create a national set of rules so that no matter where someone wants to build a data center, consumers know they are not going to get screwed with the costs,” Mr. Van Hollen said in an interview with The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology industry has responded to such proposals in a variety of ways. Executives at some companies like Microsoft have suggested that they are willing to pay more for electricity while others have said that they are already paying their fair share and have opposed efforts aimed at making them cough up more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One fundamental problem is the wide disagreement over how the costs of energy and of expanding and running the grid should be divided between individuals, ordinary businesses and large users like data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is most intense in some states, including Mr. Van Hollen’s. Maryland is part of the nation’s largest electricity market known as PJM, which serves all or parts of 13 states and the District of Columbia. PJM’s grid has the most data centers in the country, and electricity rates in its states are rising quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Shields, a spokesman for PJM, said the grid manager “is taking up many of these issues in its stakeholder process on large load additions and a decision from the PJM board is forthcoming.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent study from the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory found that data centers very likely reduced average retail electricity prices in recent years by spreading the fixed grid costs over more customers. But the study’s data ended in 2024, and the authors said it was hard to know whether this trend would continue as energy demand continued to rise sharply. The report noted a large increase in power prices last year in the Mid-Atlantic region linked to the expansion of data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electricity costs have steadily increased across the country in recent years, with the national average in October up 5 percent from a year earlier, according to data from the Energy Information Administration. A residential customer who used the typical amount of power of 1,000 kilowatt-hours paid about $180, up from $170 a year earlier. Electricity rates in three PJM states — Maryland, New Jersey and Virginia — were up 11 to 16 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to protecting consumers from higher costs, lawmakers are also trying to prevent an increase in blackouts and other grid problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Ron DeSantis of Florida has proposed a “Artificial Intelligence Bill of Rights” that would, among other things, allow local governments to prohibit construction of data centers to prevent higher electricity costs and stress on the power system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For its part, the technology industry has worked to compromise with states in some cases while fighting other proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, Amazon released a study it commissioned that concluded the tech company had more than covered its costs for power, allowing utilities to reduce rates for other customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft announced a plan on Tuesday that included promises to “pay our way to ensure our data centers don’t increase your electricity prices.” The plan also commits to minimizing water use and offering jobs and training to local residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no denying that A.I. consumes large amounts of electricity,” Brad Smith, vice chairman and president of Microsoft, said in a blog post. “While advances in technology may someday change this, today, this is the reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump praised Microsoft and said other technology companies would also address the issue. “I never want Americans to pay higher Electricity bills because of Data Centers,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Center Coalition, an industry association, said that the attention from state and federal governments highlighted the importance of the role the technology played in the 21st-century economy and that the tech industry was committed to covering its costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Data centers are committed to being responsible neighbors in the communities where they operate,” Josh Levi, president of the coalition, said in a statement. “The industry remains committed to paying its full cost of service for the energy it uses, and publications from states like Virginia and Arizona confirm we’re delivering on that commitment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech executives say artificial intelligence will make the economy much more productive. Many of them have also made commitments to use energy sources that do not emit greenhouse gases or offset emissions when they do have to use fossil fuels, the primary cause of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some climate and energy experts have expressed concerns that the expansion of data centers is leading to greater use of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/energy-environment/data-center-energy-electricity-costs.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:15:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leonard D. Jacoby, 83, Dies; Brought Legal Services to the Masses</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/leonard-d-jacoby-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00jacoby-qhmp/00jacoby-qhmp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard D. Jacoby, who as one-half of the law firm Jacoby &amp; Meyers revolutionized the legal world in the 1970s by bringing low-cost services to everyday Americans — and by winning the right to advertise those services on billboards and television — died on Monday in Manhattan. He was 83.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His stepdaughter Lindsey Schank said the death, at a hospital, was from complications of cardiac arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby and Stephen Z. Meyers, a friend from law school, started their firm in 1972 out of a single storefront in California’s San Fernando Valley. They wanted to fill a hole in the legal services industry: As they saw it, only the wealthy could afford the fees that most lawyers charged, while the very poor had access to legal aid. Those in the middle were left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They called their new firm a “legal clinic” to differentiate it from a traditional practice. It offered flat fees instead of charging by the hour. Potential clients met first with a paralegal who, if needed, could refer them to a lawyer — a process that kept costs down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacoby &amp; Meyers opened clinics in suburbs and strip malls, close to its client bases, and stayed open late and on the weekends. People came for all sorts of services, including no-fault divorces, wills and personal bankruptcies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We set out to be the Sears of the legal profession, good value for a reasonable price,” Mr. Jacoby told Los Angeles Business Journal in 1999 — and, in fact, as the firm grew, it put some of its offices in department stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partners innovated in other ways, as well. They allowed clients to pay with credit cards. They created standardized intake forms and managed the information using a centralized database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were also unabashedly populist. In terms that are ubiquitous now, but were remarkable at the time, they promised to represent their clients in the fight against corporate greed and a broken system, a message that resonated during the anti-establishment 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Bar of California banned most forms of advertising, including speaking to the press. Nevertheless, the partners invited reporters to the opening of their first location. After giving a short speech, Mr. Jacoby asked, “Who needs a lawyer?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One man shouted that he did — his car had been repossessed. After a quick consultation and a phone call, they got it back for him, charging all of $15. The story made the evening news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clients came flooding in, but the State Bar was not pleased. It moved to censure the partners, who fought back. In 1977, the California Supreme Court — and, in a separate case, the U.S. Supreme Court — ruled that banning legal advertising was unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, Jacoby &amp; Meyers ran its first print ad, in The Los Angeles Times. Within a few weeks, the firm was running ads on television. In Southern California in the late 1970s, the ads were inescapable — the firm was running up to 100 a week, each ending with the slogan “Jacoby &amp; Meyers: It’s about time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1982, Jacoby &amp; Meyers had 43 offices in California and another 18 in New York, and was seeing around 9,000 new clients a month. It was also spending about $1.9 million a year on advertising (about $7 million today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby found that even more than the law itself, he loved promoting it. He wrote the scripts for the TV ads and helped direct them, standing alongside voice actors in the studio to make sure they nailed the delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pioneering firm in a trend that brought legal services to the masses, Jacoby &amp; Meyers was omnipresent. It was even name-checked in a rap song: “Got more suits than Jacoby &amp; Meyers,” the Beastie Boys sang in “Shadrach” in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such services are taxing, low-margin work, profitable only at a high volume. Yet by the end of the 1980s, thousands of lawyers had flooded into the space that Jacoby &amp; Meyers had carved out, plastering ads for low-cost legal representation on highway billboards and in subway cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 1990s, the firm pivoted toward more lucrative areas of consumer law, including personal injury, sexual harassment and class-action suits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also reduced the number of its offices and lawyers, and in the process Mr. Jacoby came to believe that Mr. Meyers and another partner, Gail Koff, were trying to push him out. He sued, and the partners settled by effectively splitting the firm in half: Mr. Jacoby took the West Coast, while Mr. Meyers and Ms. Koff took the East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meyers died in an automobile accident in 1996.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard David Jacoby was born on March 27, 1942, in Lorain, Ohio, west of Cleveland. When he was 4, his parents, Nathan and Florence (Glasser) Jacoby, moved the family to the San Fernando Valley because Mr. Jacoby, who worked in real estate and giftware sales, had persistent health issues and thought the Southern California climate would do him good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard spent two years at the University of California, Berkeley before transferring to the University of California, Los Angeles, from which he graduated with a degree in history in 1964. He received his law degree from U.C.L.A. in 1967.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During law school, he grew close to Mr. Meyers, although they lost touch after graduation. Mr. Jacoby was working in private practice when he ran into Mr. Meyers, who was working in legal aid, at a conference in 1972. They founded their firm later that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby’s first marriage, to Barbara Rood, ended in divorce. He married Nancy Platt in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to his stepdaughter, she survives him, along with a daughter from his first marriage, Sharre Jacoby; another stepdaughter, Laurie Arent; a son from an earlier relationship, Tom Nelson; five grandchildren; and a sister, Sandra Klein. Another sister, Daryl Saunders, died in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After splitting with Mr. Meyers, Mr. Jacoby remained involved with the West Coast iteration of the firm, though he eventually sold most of his shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Len was a visionary leader who fundamentally transformed the legal industry for both the profession and the public,” Michael Akiva, a managing partner at the firm, said in a statement. “His commitment to the middle class challenged longstanding barriers and brought quality legal representation to those who previously had nowhere to turn.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/leonard-d-jacoby-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:25:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kathleen Kennedy, Lucasfilm President and ‘Star Wars’ Boss, Steps Down</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/star-wars-lucasfilm-kathleen-kennedy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/10/08/multimedia/00biz-starwars-1-kbml/00biz-starwars-1-kbml-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Kathleen Kennedy and Dave Filoni at a “Star Wars” fan convention in Japan in April.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/star-wars-lucasfilm-kathleen-kennedy.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:49:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan Strikes Trade Deal with Trump, Vows More U.S. Chip Factories</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/taiwan-trade-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16Biz-Taiwan-Trade-mhbq/16Biz-Taiwan-Trade-mhbq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Taiwan manufactures most of the world’s advanced semiconductors.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/taiwan-trade-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:43:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber’s Quest to Crack Japan Leads Through a Rural Hot-Springs Town</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/uber-japan-dara-khosrowshahi.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/Uber-Japan-Video-still-hcbp/Uber-Japan-Video-still-hcbp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ride-hailing giant’s chief executive has made a bet on how it can finally grab a bigger piece of one of the world’s largest taxi markets.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/uber-japan-dara-khosrowshahi.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:00:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Battles Over Truth Rage Online Amid Iran’s Internet Blackout</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/battles-over-truth-rage-online-amid-irans-internet-blackout.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/IRAN-DISINFO-1-mbvp/IRAN-DISINFO-1-mbvp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A frame grab from footage circulating on social media showing protesters dancing and cheering in Tehran last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/battles-over-truth-rage-online-amid-irans-internet-blackout.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>