<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:26:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Traveling This Weekend? Here’s What to Know About the Winter Storm.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/travel/winter-storm-travel-airlines.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22trav-storm-gmqf/22trav-storm-gmqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 13,000 flights have been canceled this weekend as a powerful winter storm sweeps across much of the United States, delivering freezing rain, sleet and treacherous ice and threatening the biggest snowfall in years in cities including New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The giant storm, crawling east from Texas through the South and up to the Northeast, could affect more than half of the U.S. population through the weekend, snarling air travel and coating roads in ice and snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know if you’re planning to travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 4,000 flights on Saturday were canceled across the United States as of 5:30 p.m. Eastern, and an additional 9,000 were canceled for Sunday, according to FlightAware, a flight tracking website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 80 percent of flights in and out of Dallas Fort Worth International Airport, one of the nation’s busiest, were canceled on Saturday. For the few flights still departing from that airport, the average delay was more than an hour, according to Flightradar24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every flight was canceled on Saturday at some smaller airports, including those serving Memphis, Oklahoma City and Little Rock, Ark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm is expected to drastically increase disruptions across the East Coast on Sunday. The major airports serving cities including Atlanta, New York, Toronto, Washington and Charlotte, N.C., each saw hundreds of cancellations in anticipation of the storm’s arrival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travelers who no longer want to fly this weekend can generally rebook without incurring extra costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;United Airlines, Southwest Airlines, Delta Air Lines, American Airlines, Spirit Airlines, Alaska Airlines and JetBlue are among the carriers allowing flexible rebooking if you’re traveling through dozens of cities, including Atlanta, Boston, Cleveland, Houston, New York and Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitor your flight using your airline’s app, as updates could appear there first. You can also look at websites like Flightradar24, FlightAware and the National Airspace System Status to get a sense of delays and cancellations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times travel coverage. When our writers review a destination, they do not accept free or discounted services or, in most cases, reveal that they work for The Times. We want their experience to be what you can expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, if your flight is canceled, significantly delayed or changed, airlines will rebook you (or at least try to rebook you) on another flight. If you decide not to fly, the airline owes you an automatic refund, in your original form of payment, within 20 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t expect airlines to cover your food or accommodation costs if you’re stranded; weather isn’t one of the variables, unlike staffing and maintenance, that are under their control. Travel insurance, including coverage through a credit card, may be helpful in this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amtrak has fully or partly canceled more than 75 trains across the East Coast, Midwest and South between Friday and Sunday in anticipation of the winter storm. Affected routes include the Empire Builder, which travels between Chicago and the Pacific Northwest; the Heartland Flyer, which connects Oklahoma City and Fort Worth; the Cardinal, which connects New York and Chicago via Cincinnati; and the Acela between Boston and Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those on affected trains are being offered refunds and rebooking options without extra fees, the railroad said. The number of cancellations may rise depending on how the storm develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passengers can check Amtrak’s website or app for more details on their train’s status, as well as sign up for delay alerts. Those seeking to change their reservations can contact the company’s reservation center at 1-800-USA-RAIL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Megabus, FlixBus and Greyhound are all warning of delays or cancellations. Megabus, which has suspended some routes in the Northeast on Sunday, said affected customers can get a refund or reschedule at no extra cost. Dozens of FlixBus and Greyhound buses were canceled across the Northeast on Sunday. All three companies said they would contact passengers directly via email and text if their itineraries were disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow New York Times Travel on Instagram and sign up for our Travel Dispatch newsletter to get expert tips on traveling smarter and inspiration for your next vacation. Dreaming up a future getaway or just armchair traveling? Check out our 52 Places to Go in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/travel/winter-storm-travel-airlines.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 13:31:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Automakers’ Foreign Troubles Now Extend to Canada</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/general-motors-ford-canada-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/00biz-auto-future-01-lgbf/00biz-auto-future-01-lgbf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada’s decision this month to give Chinese carmakers a toehold in the country’s car market may be an ominous development for U.S. automakers that are already struggling to stay relevant outside North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Motors and Ford Motor — the two largest U.S.-based car manufacturers — have been steadily losing customers in Asia, Europe and Latin America, as Chinese carmakers have gained ground. Now Canada plans to lower tariffs on a limited number of Chinese-made vehicles, potentially giving companies like BYD, SAIC or Geely a small but significant presence on the United States’ northern border after already building a thriving business in Mexico and much of Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they lose significant ground to Chinese companies in Canada, Mexico and other countries where they once dominated, Ford and G.M. could gradually become niche manufacturers, said Erik Gordon, a professor at the Ross School of Business at the University of Michigan. They will end up primarily making and selling large pickup trucks and sport-utility vehicles favored by many Americans but that tend to sell less well in much of the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a real danger that the market for U.S. carmakers is going to largely to be the U.S., and only that part of the U.S. market that wants big S.U.V.s and trucks,” Mr. Gordon said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of Chinese vehicles eligible for low tariffs in Canada will be small — less than 3 percent of the Canadian car market. Still, “it is very symbolic and significant to the industry,” said Lenny LaRocca, who leads the auto industry practice at the consulting firm KPMG. The U.S. automakers, he said, “are taking it very seriously.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal with China, which was announced Jan. 16 in Beijing by Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada, was the latest example of how President Trump’s policies have disrupted the U.S. auto industry. His hostile rhetoric toward Canada and 25 percent tariffs on cars imported from Canada have devastated the Canadian auto industry, which is highly intertwined with U.S. automakers and parts suppliers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year G.M. ended production of an electric van at a factory in Ingersoll, Ontario, after Republicans in Congress ended tax credits for buyers of electric vehicles, undercutting demand. G.M. is cutting a shift at a pickup factory in Oshawa, Ontario, at the end of this month. Stellantis abandoned a plan that had been subsidized by the Canadian government to produce a Jeep model at a factory in Brampton, Ontario, and moved production to Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada has had little choice but to move closer to China, said Mike Murphy, a veteran Republican political consultant and co-founder of EVs for All America, an organization that promotes electric vehicle ownership. The president’s trade policies “pushed them into a corner and the corner is Beijing,” Mr. Murphy said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese electric cars are effectively barred from the United States by 100 percent tariffs. Canada imposes roughly the same tariff, but plans to lower it to 6.1 percent for 49,000 Chinese-made cars per year. In return, China agreed to lower tariffs on Canadian canola products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the Chinese cars arriving in Canada might be Teslas made in Shanghai, where the company has a large factory. Chinese brands like BYD that are new to Canada would face a safety approval process that could take more than a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Canadian buyers might eventually get a glimpse of cars like the Xiaomi SU7, a sporty sedan that has earned grudging admiration from established Western manufacturers. The car exemplifies the styling and technology that has allowed Chinese models to sell a growing number of vehicles in Asia, Europe and Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney also announced that China would make a “considerable investment into Canada’s auto sector” within three years, suggesting that Chinese companies would ultimately manufacture cars in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans already encounter Chinese models on trips to Mexico and will soon begin to see them on visits to Canada or when Canadians drive them across the border. It may become increasingly difficult for U.S. policymakers to explain to Americans why they can’t buy the same attractively priced Chinese electric vehicles available to Canadians and Mexicans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think people like being left out of cool technology,” said Albert Gore III, executive director of the Zero Emission Transportation Association and the son of the former Democratic vice president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gore said Republican policies have undercut efforts to create an electric vehicle supply chain independent of China. Canada has significant deposits of lithium and other critical materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve pushed one of our closest allies, diplomatic and trade allies, into a deeper and more robust trade relationship with China,” Mr. Gore said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump on Saturday threatened Canada with steep tariffs if it “makes a deal with China.” There is no indication that Canada and China are in discussions about a broad trade agreement, though he may have been referring to the E.V. deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a recent visit to Detroit, Mr. Trump claimed credit for reviving the American auto industry and said that the United States did not need cars made in Canada or Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ford declined to comment on Canada’s deal with China. G.M. referred to a joint statement by the American Automotive Policy Council and the Canadian Vehicle Manufacturers’ Association, two groups that lobby on behalf of Ford, G.M., and Stellantis, which also owns Ram and Chrysler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to let in Chinese cars “has the potential to undermine Canada’s auto sector and presents risks to the future of the integrated North American auto supply chain,” the organizations’ statement said. Doug Ford, the premier of Ontario, home to many Canadian auto factories, has also objected to Mr. Carney’s agreement with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flavio Volpe, president of the Canadian Automotive Parts Manufacturers’ Association, said that the deal exposes the industry to Chinese manufacturers that sell at artificially low prices made possible by government subsidies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Chinese cars are cheaper for a reason,” he said. “All of those reasons are available only to the Chinese.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada could serve as a valuable test market for Chinese automakers, giving them an opportunity to learn about North American preferences. Canadians are fonder of small cars than Americans, while also buying lots of pickup trucks and S.U.V.s. But electric vehicles are growing in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Although E.V.s are not a big deal today, they are going to be the big deal,” said Mr. Gordon, the Michigan professor. “China is probably ahead of the U.S. in E.V. technology and ahead of the U.S. in electric vehicle manufacturing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ford and G.M. scaled back plans to develop electric vehicles after the elimination of tax credits and other clean energy incentives. Ford, for example, canceled production of the F-150 Lightning even though it was the best-selling electric pickup last year, according to estimates by Cox Automotive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s plans to cut emissions standards have also encouraged automakers to sell more gasoline pickups and S.U.V.s that earn the most profit. But those kinds of vehicles sell poorly in Asian and European countries with relatively high fuel prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. automakers say that they are aware of the threat from China and remain committed to designing electric models that can compete. Ford is developing a midsize electric pickup that the company says will sell for about $30,000 when it arrives in showrooms next year. G.M. offers an array of electric models including an electric version of the Silverado pickup truck and a $35,000 S.U.V., the Chevrolet Equinox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overseas operations of U.S. automakers have been shrinking for years. G.M. sold its Opel unit in Europe in 2017 to Peugeot, which later merged with Fiat Chrysler to become Stellantis. Sales outside of the United States, Canada and Mexico accounted for only 8 percent of G.M.’s revenue in the third quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ford remains a leading car brand in a few countries like Britain and Australia, but it has lost a lot of ground in Europe. The company had 3 percent of the European Union market last year, down from 5 percent in 2020, according to the European Automobile Manufacturers’ Association. Last year Ford closed a factory in Saarlouis, Germany, a city near the French border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese carmakers have been gaining customers in the places that Ford and G.M. are losing them. BYD tripled its share of car sales in Europe last year to almost 2 percent, surpassing Tesla, according to the manufacturers’ association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some analysts said that losing sales in foreign markets, while unappealing, might not amount to a big financial loss for U.S. automakers. That’s because it was already hard for the companies to make money in many countries because they are competing for customers against a lot of other manufacturers, including the Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the U.S. automakers’ best opportunities for growth are in new businesses like self-driving taxis or financial services, said Mr. LaRocca of KPMG. Ford provided an example last month when the company said it plans to begin manufacturing large batteries that can be used to store renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The U.S. auto market is the most profitable auto market,” he said. “Outside of the U.S. it’s very difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But industry experts say the U.S. carmakers are not moving fast enough to respond to Chinese competition. During the last decade 50 percent of the patents in automotive technology were filed by Chinese firms, according to research by Greig Mordue, a former Toyota executive who is a professor at McMaster University near Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can ignore it for a while,” Mr. Mordue said of Chinese competition, “but ultimately you will get engulfed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ian Austen contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/general-motors-ford-canada-china.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 13:27:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why the Power May Not Go Out Until After the Storm Has Passed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/energy-environment/storm-power-outages.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/business/24biz-power-outage/24biz-power-outage-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike what sometimes unfolds with hurricanes and other extreme weather events, this weekend’s winter storm may not immediately cause power outages and other electrical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy experts warned that the worst effects of the potentially catastrophic storm could come on Monday and Tuesday in areas like Texas and the Mid-Atlantic States, after snow and ice accumulate on tree branches and power lines, eventually causing them to snap and damage electrical equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The damage could be compounded by sharp increases in electricity demand at the start of the week. Peak energy usage typically occurs in the early morning and evening hours on weekdays, when consumers fire up their appliances and raise the temperature on their thermostats as they get ready for work and school, and again after they return home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just because the snow stops, that doesn’t mean the worst is over,” said Wei Du, a managing consultant for PA Consulting, which advises utilities, investors and others in the energy industry. “That’s frequently not the case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis by ICF, an energy consulting firm, shows that the main grid in Texas, which is run by Electric Reliability Council of Texas, will hit its peak demand between 5 a.m. and 8 a.m. on Monday. Across the Mid-Atlantic region, on the grid managed by PJM, which includes 13 states and the District of Columbia, demand is expected to crest from 7 a.m. to 10 a.m. on Tuesday. That’s when the system operator anticipates it will reach the highest winter demand in its history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PJM also warned customers that it may extend its winter weather alert through Jan. 30. That has prompted utilities and government officials to call on large energy users like data centers to prepare to reduce the amount of power they take from the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Definitely in the PJM system things are going to be extremely thin, and frankly we are concerned,” said George Katsigiannakis, a vice president at ICF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anticipated demand on Tuesday is almost 10 percent higher than the highest demand last winter, Mr. Katsigiannakis said. But PJM has not added many new power plants, batteries and other resources to its system. The Texas grid, by comparison, has added many new large battery storage systems and solar farms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During recent winter storms, the freezing temperatures shut down many power plants connected to the PJM and Texas grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2021, the main Texas grid experienced a huge failure that left many electricity customers without power for days. More than 200 people died in that storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, over the Christmas holidays in 2022, about a quarter of the natural gas power plants in PJM’s service area failed as snow, wind and subzero temperatures froze natural gas pipelines. Various types of power plants — fossil fuel and renewables like solar and wind — failed during both the 2021 and 2022 storms. But in PJM’s case, about 70 percent of the units were fueled by natural gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Katsigiannakis said managers of the Texas and PJM grids have tried to strengthen their systems to withstand the extreme winter weather, as neighboring energy networks in the Midwest do. Such potent winter storms had not been as common in Texas or at PJM, which extends from around the Chicago area to Virginia Beach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The powerful storm this week began making its way east from the Rocky Mountains, and is expected to drop snow, sleet and freezing rain on an area that runs from the Southwest into New England, and is home to more than 160 million people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grid managers said they have sufficient reserves to meet the anticipated demand over the weekend and next week but are preparing for a storm that is worse than expected. Depending on the actual path it takes, the wintry mix could pose challenges for multiple grid systems, straining resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a formidable arctic cold front coming our way, and it will impact our neighboring systems as much as it affects PJM,” Mike Bryson, senior vice president of operations for PJM, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Edison Electric Institute, a utility industry organization, said top executives at its member companies were coordinating responses with state and federal agencies to minimize power outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the strategy includes tamping down demand from data centers that support development of artificial intelligence. These facilities are increasingly using a larger share of the country's electricity, particularly in places like Ohio and Virginia, where forecasters are expecting snow squalls and freezing rain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, the energy secretary, Chris Wright, said the federal government was drafting orders that unused backup generators at data centers and “other major facilities” could be deployed to help prevent blackouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The orders would let grid operators force data centers to run on backup generators as a “last resort,” after all other supplies are exhausted. Data centers generally are not set up to feed energy back onto grids, but they can power their own operations from the generators, reducing the amount of electricity they draw from the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data centers must continue to operate to serve customers, but they “can maintain these operations by switching from grid power to temporarily using on-site backup generation resources that data centers maintain to serve in an emergency,” Josh Levi, president of the Data Center Coalition, an industry group, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon, the largest cloud computing company, said it was monitoring the storm closely and coordinating with grid operators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Millions of customers including hospitals, first responders and government agencies depend on Amazon’s cloud services, and our systems are built for the resilience and reliability these essential sectors require,” said Scott LaBelle, a company spokesman.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/energy-environment/storm-power-outages.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 08:31:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington Post Tears Up Plans to Cover Winter Olympics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/media/washington-post-winter-olympics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24biz-post-olympics-wzlm/24biz-post-olympics-wzlm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Winter Olympics is a quadrennial media spectacle, drawing parka-clad sportswriters, photojournalists and TV anchors from around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, a team from The Washington Post won’t be among them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kimi Yoshino, a managing editor of The Washington Post, sent a terse and unexpected email to more than a dozen of the newspaper’s journalists on Friday, notifying them that their coverage plans were abruptly being changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As we assess our priorities for 2026, we have decided not to send a contingent to the Winter Olympics,” Ms. Yoshino wrote. “We realize this decision and its timing will be disappointing to many of you, so please reach out to me if you want to talk further.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Yoshino’s email, which was reviewed by The New York Times, took journalists at The Post by surprise, since it came just two weeks before the Winter Olympics are set to kick off in Italy in early February. Many had already paid for their travel arrangements, according to two people familiar with their plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for The Washington Post had no comment on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Post’s decision not to send its journalists to cover a major sporting event with widespread global appeal breaks with years of precedent at the newspaper. Since the newspaper was purchased more than a decade ago by Amazon.com’s founder, Jeff Bezos, The Post has aggressively expanded its international presence, opening editing hubs in Seoul and London and hiring reporters to cover breaking news around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But The Post has been retrenching in recent years as losses at the paper have piled up. In 2023, The Post offered buyouts to eliminate 240 jobs amid losses of $100 million and overly rosy projections for subscriptions and advertising revenue. Last year, The Post offered another round of buyouts that were accepted by many of the paper’s marquee journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Post generally sent about 10 to 20 newsroom employees to cover the Olympics, though it typically devoted more resources to the summer games than to the winter competitions. In 2024, for example, the newspaper sent 26 journalists to cover the summer games in Paris — a peak deployment for The Post, according to one Post employee. It had secured 14 credentials for the Milano Cortina games, the person said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Post employee, the newspaper has already paid the vast majority of its expenses to cover the competition. Those include flights for the journalists, housing and office space at the Olympics site. Housing alone tallies at least $80,000, the employee said. Post management approved the outlays at each step along the way, according to the employee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Articles about the Olympics have consistently ranked among the most popular sports coverage at The Post, the employee said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/business/media/washington-post-winter-olympics.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:40:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>