<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:51:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>As Trump Promotes Economy in Iowa, Many Residents Feel Pain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump headed to Iowa on Tuesday to once again try to convince Americans that he is focused on “affordability.” He had some explaining to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa, a state whose economy is heavily reliant on farming, has been struggling under the weight of Mr. Trump’s economic policies, particularly his approach to trade. The president’s barrage of tariffs last year increased the cost of machinery and materials that many Iowan farmers rely on. The price of the metal bins used to store crops soared, along with the cost of tractors as the president’s tariffs took hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump hit China with tariffs, Beijing swiftly retaliated by halting purchases of American farm products, a move that cut off Iowa soybean exporters from their biggest buyer. That put the squeeze on the entire state’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the economy at an event in Clive, Iowa, on Tuesday, Mr. Trump defended his trade policies and told supporters that he was saving farmers money by slashing burdensome environmental regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m standing up for the workers and the farmers of our country like no other president has ever,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president added that the trade deals that he has reached have opened up international markets to American farmers, ranchers and agricultural producers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re going to see it starting to kick in now for the farmers,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many, however, the intended benefits of Mr. Trump’s policies are not kicking in soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a dire time for American farmers, particularly the Midwest soybean and corn farmers,” said Kirk Leeds, the chief executive of the Iowa Soybean Association. “The chaos, the uncertainty — right now we have so many unknowns that there’s not a lot of clarity about where we’re going.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa is of particular importance to Mr. Trump. The state helped propel his political career a decade ago, when he had a strong showing in the 2016 Republican caucuses. He won the state in all three of his general election campaigns. Perhaps more important to Mr. Trump now is that the state could prove pivotal in this year’s midterm elections, as Republicans try to retain their majority. Senator Joni Ernst, Republican of Iowa, is retiring, and the race to replace her is expected to be close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Chuck Grassley, the veteran Iowa Republican who has been critical of Mr. Trump’s tariffs, welcomed the president’s visit this week and said he would continue to work with the Trump administration to improve affordability for Iowans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump’s trade wars have in many respects been a drag on the state, which for years has lagged behind the rest of the country in economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has long been a big buyer of U.S. soybeans and other crops that are grown in Iowa. That changed last year after Mr. Trump increased tariffs on imports from China, triggering a monthslong tit-for-tat trade fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite negotiations and temporary traded truces, China continued to use farm purchases as leverage and Beijing’s refusal to buy American agricultural products for most of 2025 dealt a blow to Iowa’s soybean industry, one of the largest in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and Xi Jinping, the Chinese leader, eventually agreed in late October to a one-year truce that ended China’s boycott of farm products, including millions of tons of soybeans. The Trump administration also unveiled a $12 billion aid package for farmers, but for many farmers the relief was insufficient and too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re losing money on every bushel we produce on our two main things that we grow,” said Aaron Lehman, the president of the Iowa Farmers Union, referring to corn and soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have said that China fulfilled its initial commitment to Mr. Trump to buy 12 million metric tons of soybeans. It has also pledged to purchase 25 million metric tons per year for the next three years. The 25 million tons were in line with the 25 million to 30 million it had purchased in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said last week that he encouraged his Chinese counterpart to buy additional soybeans during a meeting on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crop receipts in Iowa were on track to fall 4 percent, or $666 million, in 2025 from last year and they are projected to hold steady this year, according to a report published last October by the Rural &amp; Farm Finance Policy Analysis Center. There were 18 farm bankruptcies in the state through last October, the highest total since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America’s rural economies have been struggling in recent years, and Iowa is no exception. Since 2021, Iowa’s economy has grown at an annual rate of about 1 percent while the United States has grown at an average annual rate of 2.5 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since retaking the White House last year, Mr. Trump and his advisers have said that the administration’s policies will usher in a new “golden age” for America. Mr. Lehman said such suggestions feel out of touch to Iowa farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The policy leaders are not understanding the situation on the ground,” Mr. Lehman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Trump administration policies have also created challenges over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Budget cuts to the Department of Agriculture and the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program, which buys food from American farmers, have been hard on Iowa’s agriculture sector, Mr. Lehman added. The lapse of Affordable Care Act subsidies is leading to higher health care costs. And immigration restrictions have made it harder for farmers to find workers in a state where the population has been shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble in the farm economy has spread to other sectors in Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Deere, the agricultural machinery company, said last September that it would cut more than 140 jobs at two plants in Iowa because of decreased demand for equipment. Case New Holland, a construction equipment manufacturer, said this week that it was cutting about 200 jobs at a plant in Burlington. Overall, the state lost 1,300 manufacturing jobs in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Orazem, an economist at Iowa State University, noted that the state’s manufacturing industries are closely tied to how farmers are faring. He said that forecasts for 2026 remain murky because of uncertainty over trade policy and whether government support for farmers will continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Restrictions on trade makes your market less lucrative,” Mr. Orazem said. “You’re getting squeezed on the demand side and getting squeezed on the supply side. That doesn’t bode well for firm profit.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:49:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Safety Board Blames F.A.A. For Multiple Failures in D.C. Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Transportation Safety Board determined that the Federal Aviation Administration had approved dangerous flight routes that allowed an Army helicopter to fly into the path of a passenger jet over the Potomac River on Jan. 29, 2025, to calamitous results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a meeting on Tuesday, the investigating board also castigated the agency for not doing enough to respond to warnings about longtime risks to safety and found a complacent culture within the air traffic control tower at Ronald Reagan National Airport that relied too heavily on pilots in the airspace being able to see and steer clear of each others’ aircraft, a practice called visual separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also determined that insufficient warnings from the air traffic controller to the pilots of the Army Black Hawk helicopter and an American Airlines passenger jet involved in the crash, and altimeters that, unbeknown to the helicopter pilots, habitually gave faulty readings of altitude, also contributed to the tragic crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long-awaited determination, which the board approved unanimously, is the culmination of a yearlong investigation that put the F.A.A. and Army under a microscope, as the board scrutinized how officials missed — or outright dismissed — risks that ultimately led to the collision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s one failure after another,” Jennifer Homendy, the board chair, told reporters during a break in the proceedings, adding: “This was 100 percent preventable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. focused the brunt of its ire on the F.A.A., determining that the route the Army Black Hawk helicopter flew along the Potomac River and the landing path of American Airlines Flight 5342 were never designed to ensure separation between aircraft — and that the dangers posed by the crisscrossing paths were never adequately reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also determined that the F.A.A. ignored repeated appeals from controllers to reduce National Airport’s traffic, even as its main runway became the single busiest in the United States. That forced controllers to routinely divert planes to a backup runway, as they did with the American Airlines flight that night, to manage congestion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.A.A. values and appreciates the N.T.S.B’s expertise and input,” said Hannah Walden, a spokeswoman for the F.A.A., in a statement. The agency has worked with the N.T.S.B. throughout the investigation, she added, “acted immediately” to put into place its initial safety recommendations and “will carefully consider” the additional recommendations it made Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy flight traffic, investigators said, routinely led controllers at the airport to direct incoming planes to the backup runway, Runway 33, putting them in proximity with helicopters. It also led controllers to rely too much on pilots themselves to “see and avoid” each other, investigators determined, noting that the practice “introduced unacceptable risk” to the airspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.T.S.B. staff members cited a culture within the F.A.A. that discouraged raising concerns about safety, describing how the agency installed, but never activated, a traffic management system that could have helped controllers handle traffic better on busy nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also concluded that the decision to put one controller in charge of both helicopter and airplane traffic on the night of the crash was not because of insufficient staffing in the tower — and that the duties should have been separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, the board did not fault the pilots of either aircraft for failing to avoid each other. It did, however, determine that the pilots of the helicopter requested visual separation too early, and probably never had the correct commercial jet in their sights. The pilots of the jet, the board added, were too busy preparing for landing to note the approach of the helicopter, which the air traffic controller had not warned them about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of striking animated visual simulations, investigators strongly suggested that the instructor pilot in the helicopter, who was evaluating a less experienced pilot on a training flight, lost sight of the passenger jet as the two aircraft approached each other. The jet came back into his view only a second or two before impact, the video indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the N.T.S.B. determined that had the controller on duty noted the danger and explicitly warned pilots that they were at risk of colliding, they likely would have had time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were not adequately prepared to do the jobs they were assigned to do,” said Brian Soper, who leads the N.T.S.B.’s air traffic control investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators also said that if either aircraft had been equipped with real-time tracking gear known as ADS-B In, the pilots might have been alerted nearly a minute before the collision of the danger, giving them ample time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the board also found that the helicopter pilots’ reliance on other equipment contributed significantly to the crash. Investigators concluded that the pilots of the Army helicopter probably thought they were flying about 100 feet lower than their actual altitude because of idiosyncrasies in the readings of altimeters on the Black Hawks that the Army knew about but never informed aviators of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They wouldn’t know it,” said Capt. Van McKenny, a helicopter investigator with the N.T.S.B. “It’s not in their manual, it’s not in the training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army also never realized that the barometric altimeters in their helicopters were giving pilots a false sense of their flying height because the service didn’t routinely collect the relevant data. Instead, the Army relied on a voluntary reporting system that was seldom used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A., investigators said, had plenty of data about the dangers to the Washington airspace, however, that the agency simply ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. questioned why on multiple occasions, the F.A.A. relaxed the restrictions on when a single controller could be assigned to manage helicopter and airplane traffic simultaneously, creating a culture of complacency that things would work out, even when controllers became overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the board excoriated the F.A.A. for downgrading National Airport’s facility rating in 2018, a measure that determines the experience level required for controllers to work there. That change, and its commensurate pay cut, made it more difficult for the tower to attract experienced personnel capable of handling Washington’s busy airspace, the N.T.S.B. staff said, especially given the city’s high cost of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This tower is essentially treated as a training facility,” Ms. Homendy said. “It is a pass-through, they can’t attract people here, which is a problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, the N.T.S.B. issued over 70 findings about the midair collision, and approved dozens of recommendations aimed at preventing similar crashes. The Trump administration and Congress will determine whether to put them into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. has already limited what aircraft can fly through the airspace surrounding National Airport. It has also reconfigured helicopter routes in the area, in response to urgent recommendations that the N.T.S.B. issued last March, and it rolled out a redesign plan it says will streamline safety monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency also has been making significant investments to modernize the country’s aging air traffic control system. A funding bill pending before the Senate would pump billions more dollars into the F.A.A. to help with hiring more controllers, but the legislation could falter amid a political standoff over funding for immigration enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. plans to publish a full report detailing the findings, causes and recommendations stemming from the crash in the weeks after Tuesday’s meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:29:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bari Weiss Urges CBS News to Think Like a ‘Start-Up’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bari Weiss, the recently hired and frequently discussed editor in chief of CBS News, began her first networkwide meeting on Tuesday by addressing the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s been a lot of noise around me taking this job,” she told hundreds of CBS staff members gathered in bureaus across the globe. “I get it. I also get why, in the face of all this tumult, you might feel uncertain or skeptical about me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bumps of Ms. Weiss’s early tenure have been heavily chronicled, including her contentious decision to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment and rocky moments on a revamped “Evening News.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, it was her turn to lay out her vision: an ambitious transformation of CBS News from a tradition-bound institution into a digitally savvy journalistic engine that meets news consumers where they are — namely, far from broadcast TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not producing a product enough people want,” she said, while dismissing day-to-day Nielsen ratings as an outmoded benchmark. “What winning looks like writ large for this company is building incredible journalism for audiences that are so much bigger than the one that we currently have,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rallying cry was intended as a reset of sorts, a chance to cut through the suspicions that Ms. Weiss, a frequent critic of the mainstream news media and founder of the independent site The Free Press, is trying to tilt CBS News into more pro-Trump territory. She urged her journalists to reel in investigative scoops (and “scoops of ideas, scoops of explanation”) and think beyond traditional TV broadcasts, referring to her ideal reporters as “dynamic Swiss Army knives capable of writing, speaking, hosting, reporting, analyzing and writing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also announced a new roster of CBS News contributors with viewpoints spanning the political spectrum. The group includes Andrew Huberman, a neurobiology expert who is a popular influencer in the so-called manosphere; Niall Ferguson, a British American historian who frequently writes for The Free Press; Casey Lewis, a Gen Alpha Substack trend-spotter; and Coleman Hughes, a Free Press contributing writer who has argued for “a colorblind society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running an organization as large and influential as CBS News is the biggest challenge of Ms. Weiss’s career. She was appointed last year by its new owner, the technology heir David Ellison, who acquired the network’s parent company, Paramount, after a contentious sale process. Shortly before the Trump administration approved the deal, Paramount paid $16 million to settle a defamation case against “60 Minutes” brought by President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, Ms. Weiss’s remarks on Tuesday echoed those of many media executives trying to steer old-line news institutions, with falling revenue and graying audiences, into the choppy waters of new media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She framed the future of CBS News in stark terms, warning employees that it would be “one hell of a fight” to keep pace in a rapidly changing business. And she told her team to be more nimble and innovative, calling CBS News “the best-capitalized media start-up in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss also warned that employees who did not subscribe to her vision may not wish to remain. “It’s a free country,” Ms. Weiss said. “I completely respect if you decide this is just not the right place at the right time for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her challenge was underscored by a lengthy question-and-answer session with employees, who asked about her decision in December to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment about a notorious prison in El Salvador where deported Venezuelan migrants were detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss said that she held the segment because she believed it required more reporting, and that the decision was hers alone. “I was not pressured by David Ellison or anyone else,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also acknowledged the fallout from her decision to pull the segment after it had been promoted by the network, noting that she was new to broadcasting and unfamiliar with “that specific logistical nightmare.” Referring to the 11th-hour nature of her decision, she said, “Nothing of that kind is ever going to happen again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Tuesday’s event concluded, Gayle King, the “CBS Mornings” anchor, spoke up to offer a rallying cry of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She thanked Ms. Weiss for presenting “a very good case for what you want this company to be,” adding that it was good for the newsroom “to hear and see that you are a real person and this is what you want and how you feel about us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ms. King was blunt about the public reaction to Ms. Weiss’s tenure so far. “People now come up to me to my face, if I’m at the airport, they go, ‘Love you guys, but I ain’t watching you anymore,’” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. King also criticized employees who were divulging details of the newsroom’s inner workings to the press, and speculated on how long it might take for her own remarks to leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss, wryly, chimed in: “I’m sure someone’s livestreaming it right now, Gayle,” she said, according to a recording of the event obtained by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:59:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Begins Assigned Seating, Scrapping a Signature Quirk</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a water-cannon salute, balloons and commemorative bag tags, Southwest Airlines on Tuesday officially retired its decades-old practice of open seating. For the first time, passengers received assigned seats, a major shift for the carrier, which also introduced a new group boarding process and premium seat options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two flights with assigned seating landed early in the day, at Chicago Midway International Airport and then at Orlando International Airport, where a plane arriving from San Juan, P.R., glided toward the jetway under two arcs of water, a salute reserved for special occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The celebration continued at the gate, which was festooned with red, blue and orange balloons. Passengers loaded up on free snacks and coffee and took selfies through heart-shaped holes in giant boarding passes. The airline handed out bag tags with the line, “I understood the assignment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southwest says the seating changes are intended to keep up with evolving customer expectations and to increase revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tony Roach, an executive vice president at the airline who was on the flight from San Juan, said that the airline had “outgrown” open seating, adding that assigned seating also reduces anxiety among travelers because they know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There were a lot of limitations with open seating in terms of what we want to do in the future,” he said. “You aren’t able to offer things inside the cabin which a lot of people want. Things like extra legroom would have been very difficult to do with an open-seating environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than 50 years, Southwest used a system of open seating: Once they had checked in, passengers received a group and a number that determined the general order of when they’d get on the plane. Then once on board, they could choose any open seat. Getting a desired seat, or sitting together, often hinged on checking in early, and there were no premium seats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was loved by some travelers, who viewed it as egalitarian and flexible, and bemoaned by others who complained that it was chaotic and stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Southwest offers three categories of seats — standard, preferred and extra legroom — and the most expensive can cost hundreds of dollars more than the cheapest fare. Boarding order now depends on the fare class, as well as whether a traveler has elite status with the airline or holds its credit card. Travelers can also pay extra to board in an earlier group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times travel coverage. When our writers review a destination, they do not accept free or discounted services or, in most cases, reveal that they work for The Times. We want their experience to be what you can expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday, the airline also ended its flexible policy for plus-size passengers, which allowed customers to ask for an extra seat at the gate, or pay for an extra seat and later receive a refund. Those passengers will now need to purchase two seats ahead of time, without a guaranteed refund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some loyal travelers expressed dismay that the airline was abandoning some of the quirks that made it different from other major U.S. carriers. In May, Southwest eliminated its popular policy of granting travelers two free checked bags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Wolf, 74, who has flown with Southwest for more than two decades, said he was enticed early on by the airline’s reputation as an industry disrupter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I liked them really well when they were young and scrappy. In the past, they seemed to have mastered the quick turnaround, they were able to get back on time after delays, they are very agile with swapping planes and all of that,” said Mr. Wolf, who was at LaGuardia Airport awaiting his flight home to Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With assigned seats and premium fares, “now it’s just like any other airline,” Mr. Wolf said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several longtime Southwest fliers also remarked that they enjoyed the unpredictability of the previous open-seating system. Aaron Schottenstein, a 35-year-old who lives in Phoenix, said he’d been dreading the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I loved the boarding, getting on in the lines, yapping with everybody while you wait there, talking about how people are trying to get like five spots closer because they might get that much better of a seat,” said Mr. Schottenstein, who was traveling from New York to Phoenix, with a connection in Kansas City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others welcomed assigned seating, saying it eliminated pain points like checking in 24 hours ahead of a flight to improve the chances of snagging a better seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love it,” said Maureen Hager, of Buffalo, who was traveling home from Orlando on Tuesday with Veronica, her adult daughter. “I hated waiting on line, trying to get there early. I don’t like waiting to get to the airport and waiting on line and the anxiety of not knowing if you got seats together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronica, however, disagreed. She called the change a “money grab.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the other way,” she said. “I like the thrill of having to check in, trying to get Group A, first round.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Jordan, the airline’s chief executive said in an interview last month that the airline was confident that customers, who he said desire these changes, would stay loyal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re now offering things that the vast majority of people want,” he said, adding, “We’ve seen no defection from the brand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Adelson contributed reporting from Orlando, Fla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow New York Times Travel on Instagram and sign up for our Travel Dispatch newsletter to get expert tips on traveling smarter and inspiration for your next vacation. Dreaming up a future getaway or just armchair traveling? Check out our 52 Places to Go in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:32:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Municipal Debt Boom Is Driving Public Projects and Tax Breaks for Investors</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/municipal-debt-market.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/business/00biz-muni-boom/00biz-muni-boom-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across America, state and local governments have been selling bonds at a record clip to finance projects like airports, roads and utilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have found a deep pool of buyers keen on realizing the tax-exemption benefits from holding this municipal debt, which also provides relatively high returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borrowing in the municipal bond market surpassed $500 billion last year, breaking the $498 billion record set in 2024. The “muni market” is now worth well over $4 trillion, roughly equivalent to the market capitalization of Nvidia, the chip maker that has soared on the artificial intelligence boom, driving stocks to record highs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People really don’t understand how big this market is and how it impacts a lot of things that everybody does every day,” said Mike Bartolotta, an executive managing director and co-head of public finance at Hilltop Securities, a firm that specializes in municipal sales. “You drive to work, you go to school, you flush the toilet, you drink water? You’re likely going to use something that’s been touched by municipal securities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bartolotta helped city leaders sell $2 billion in bonds last year to expand Dallas Fort Worth International Airport. Four hours south of Dallas along Interstate 45, Houston is also making billion-dollar renovations to the George Bush Intercontinental Airport by issuing bonds, rather than earmarking taxpayer dollars for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spreading out the costs and funding schedule for long-term projects through long-term borrowing frees up room for competing priorities in annual budgets along the way, said Vernon Lewis, director of Houston’s treasury department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason we do it this way is because it gives us a more of a cost-saving scenario,” Mr. Lewis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past two years, the issuance of municipal bonds is up 57 percent, according to Matt Fabian, the president of Municipal Market Analytics, an independent research and consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Lanouette, a Boston-based investment manager at CIBC Private Wealth, said wealthier clients were attracted to these bonds for two reasons: Their returns are generally tax-exempt, and they can produce returns, or yields, comparable to stocks’ in a middling year — and often beat the returns on federal Treasury debt, the base line of the bond market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JPMorgan Private Bank estimated at the start of 2025 that after tax advantages were factored in, yields for a typical municipal bond were over 7 percent. The yield for the benchmark 10-year Treasury note has been about 4 percent for the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump himself is among the investors piling into municipal debt. According to his latest financial disclosures, Mr. Trump bought about $100 million in municipal and corporate bonds from mid-November to late December, with a majority of the purchases from municipal bond issuers: a range of cities, school districts, utilities and hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s one of those rare moments in finance when an asset class appears to be providing a low-risk, high-reward opportunity for investors as well as cities and states looking to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The borrowing is coming out of strength,” said Susan Wachter, a professor of real estate and finance at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“State and local budgets are in good shape, and their rainy day funds are, generally, at highs,” she added — largely the downstream result of a strong economic recovery since 2020 and $350 billion in federal aid designed to refill municipal coffers after the pandemic shock. By the end of 2023, state and local governments had billions in pandemic aid left to spend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, such an accumulation of debt in such a short time has spurred some wariness among economists and money managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a little too Pollyannish to say, ‘Oh, it’s a win-win for everyone,’” said Jason Draho, the head of asset allocation for the Americas at UBS Wealth Management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say the biggest risk is a bursting of a financial bubble in artificial intelligence. From 2023 to 2025, the A.I. build-out in communities around the country has pushed up corporate valuations and economic growth. The data centers needed to power A.I. have boosted construction activity and employment, contributing at times to tens of millions of dollars in local real estate taxes and other revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But municipalities may face credit downgrades from bond rating agencies or even defaults if a bubble burst in A.I. is bad enough to prompt a downturn so severe that tax receipts from wages, commerce and property greatly decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serious defaults are not without precedent: After the Great Recession, for instance, Detroit filed for bankruptcy in 2013, the largest municipal bankruptcy in U.S. history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also more idiosyncratic risks that some investors think may get overlooked. Coastal areas, more at risk to devastating flooding, are home to almost 40 percent of the U.S. population. Last year, Standard &amp; Poor’s downgraded the outlook of California state utility issuer, Southern California Edison, from stable to negative based on prominent local threats like wildfire risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same credit assessment from S&amp;P named several Los Angeles-area issuers, with debt collectively worth tens of billions of dollars, that could also become riskier bets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, even some of the riskiest municipal borrowers seem to have been getting their act together — with the help of federal aid earlier this decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moody’s in October upgraded Illinois’s credit rating into A territory, the state’s highest mark after over two decades of budget woes and unfunded pension liabilities. That was after the state passed seven consecutive balanced budgets and expanded its rainy day fund to almost $2.4 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illinois plans to issue $2.1 billion in bonds to fund capital projects during the 2026 fiscal year, up from $1.3 billion the year prior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not long ago, Illinois was facing repeated credit downgrades, mounting unpaid bills and some of the highest borrowing costs in the country,” a spokesman for JB Pritzker, the state’s governor, said. “Today, after years of disciplined budgeting and responsible financial management, Illinois has earned 10 credit upgrades and restored investor confidence in Illinois. The state has been able to accumulate meaningful saving on interest costs, allowing taxpayer dollars to better serve the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such optimism makes it likely that municipal debt may continue to sell to high-net-worth households in high-tax states from California to Texas to New York like ice cream on a hot summer day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The muni boom is yet another aspect of the “K-shaped economy, where there’s been a divergence of wealth between the upper- and lower-income cohorts,” Mr. Lanouette of CIBC Private Wealth said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wealthier households, he added, aren’t the cohort most affected by cost-of-living concerns; they “are the ones that are looking to shield as much income from taxation as possible — so municipal bonds fit that bill.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/municipal-debt-market.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:00:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sundance Says Thank You, and Goodbye, to Park City</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/media/sundance-film-festival-park-city-boulder.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/SUNDANCE-HAWKE-04-kwfb/SUNDANCE-HAWKE-04-kwfb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actor Ethan Hawke wouldn’t be Ethan Hawke without the Sundance Film Festival. The director Cathy Yan might have given up her filmmaking dreams without it. And the producer Matthew Greenfield may not have become president of Searchlight Pictures if Sundance had not accepted his first film, “Star Maps,” into the festival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the thousands of movie industry insiders and fans make their annual pilgrimage to Park City, Utah, for the Sundance Film Festival this week, their memories about the event’s past are threatening to overwhelm the films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is because this is the last year that the event will be held in Park City, its home for 40-plus years. (Its future home is Boulder, Colo.) And because this is the first festival since the death of its founder, Robert Redford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As a generation that grew up on ‘Star Wars,’ it’s hard not to feel a disturbance in the force,” said Mr. Hawke, who first came to Sundance in 1994 as an actor in “Reality Bites.” He returned the next year with “Before Sunrise” — a movie chosen by Mr. Redford for the opening night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or as Mr. Greenfield put it: “I feel sad in a nostalgic way, but I also feel hopeful that it’s an opportunity for the next phase.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I will miss most is my youth,” the actor Ethan Hawke said about the Sundance Film Festival’s leaving Park City. “The streets are full of memories.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Redford founded Sundance in 1985 as a place to showcase new voices, and it quickly became the top festival for independent film. Along with the Sundance Institute, which started in 1981 sponsoring a host of programs to develop new filmmakers, these nonprofits have fostered a long roster of talented artists and their movies, including three of the five best directors in this year’s Oscar race and all five of the documentary features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew Greenfield, president of Searchlight Pictures, remembers his first Sundance, in 1997, delivering the print of his film “Star Maps” to the old Miners Hospital, shown here, the festival’s drop-off point for reels (before film went digital). The movie sold for $2.5 million, allowing him to pursue producing full time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, the festival has weathered the highs and lows of the business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The festival was central to Miramax’s first commercializing indie films, when the company acquired Steven Soderbergh’s “Sex, Lies, and Videotape” in 1989. Later came the advent of all-night bidding wars for movies like “Reservoir Dogs,” “Napoleon Dynamite” and “Little Miss Sunshine,” which set a Sundance record in 2006 when Fox Searchlight bought the film for $10.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The festival has also survived becoming a media circus at times, such as when Paris Hilton and Britney Spears created more attention on Main Street than the movies playing in theaters. (“Sundance is weird,” Ms. Spears said in 2003. “The movies are weird — you actually have to think about them when you watch them.”) And it overcame the financial crisis, when funding became scarce, and the pandemic, when the event was shuttered for two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way, Park City changed, too. The town became a bigger draw for skiers after it helped host the Winter Olympics in 2002, and it changed again during the pandemic, when many people moved to the snowy mountain town to escape big city living. And eventually, the festival outgrew it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The festival has ridden these ebbs and flows of the industry and either expanded to account for that or had to contract a little bit to respond to that,” said Eugene Hernandez, who was named the director of the festival in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s still a really great artistic community here,” Mr. Hernandez added, “but there’s been a transformation of the city and you observe it when you’re sitting in traffic or seeing the capacity challenges a big event brings to a place like this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eugene Hernandez, director of the Sundance Film Festival, first arrived here in 1993 as a film lover. A chance encounter on a shuttle bus with Mark Rabinowitz, a journalist, led the two (and others) to found IndieWire, an online magazine dedicated to independent film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the Sundance Film Festival has remained steady in its goals of championing new voices and being a place of discovery. This year, like most, 60 percent of its programming showcases first- or second-time directors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’ve stayed remarkably true to their mission,” said John Sloss, a lawyer turned sales agent who has played a major role in turning the festival into a marketplace for buying and selling independent films — much to Mr. Redford’s annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Clearly he was wrong,” Mr. Sloss said with a wink. “The market brought the press, it brought the buyers. We’re a commercial art form.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Sloss says Cinetic, his film management and corporate advisory firm, is synonymous with Sundance. The Deer Valley house he has rented every year was the site of many all-night bidding wars, and he was also known for hosting lively dance parties. His company is already scouting for a party venue in Boulder. “We owe it to Sundance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, much of what is heralded out of each year’s festival is the quality of the sales. A big year with lots of buyers and lots of dollar signs means the business is healthy. New talent is crowned. Impossible dreams come true. When it’s the opposite, Sundance is considered the canary in the coal mine, the harbinger of doom for a business that is constantly in a state of flux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far this year, the sales market has been slow as buyers debate what films will get moviegoers into theaters. The queer horror film “Leviticus” sold to Neon for $5 million, and a bidding war for “The Invite,” directed by and starring Olivia Wilde, is pitting most of the indie distributors against one another. Other films, like Beth de Araújo’s harrowing drama “Josephine,” starring Channing Tatum, and “Wicker,” featuring Olivia Colman and Alexander Skarsgard, are also likely to get picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Mr. Sloss, the documentary side of the business, while still challenged, has been an easier sale postpandemic, thanks to the streaming services. If the subject is commercial enough, like “Summer of Soul” or “Super/Man: The Christopher Reeve Story,” a large sale is still possible. He sold both films to streamers for $15 million each. This year, he expects “The Last First: Winter K2,” about a tragic mountaineering expedition, to sell soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Platforms understand the commercial value of documentaries, platforms really do not understand the commercial value of scripted films,” he said. “They don’t know how to market them. What’s Netflix going to do to announce a new voice that’s going to get people to watch? It’s an inherent flaw in the system.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the directors of “Little Miss Sunshine,” Valerie Faris and Jonathan Dayton, the dream situation they experienced here in Park City — fresh-faced directors, high-profile sale, nationwide promotional tour, box office grosses and the Oscar stage — feels like an impossible thing for younger generations to replicate because the movie industry is in such turmoil right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The married filmmakers Jonathan Dayton and Valerie Faris arrived in Park City in 2006 with their first feature, “Little Miss Sunshine.” The movie became a sensation, selling for a record $10.5 million and winning two Oscars. “There is no other festival like Sundance,” Ms. Faris said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I feel badly for our kids because they witnessed this storybook,” said Ms. Faris, who has children now getting into filmmaking. “We never allowed ourselves to dream that something like that could happen because the process of getting it made was so hard. But now they’ve seen that and they think it’s a real possibility.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the dream lives on for many. Ms. Yan returned to Sundance this year for her second indie feature, “The Gallerist,” a sendup of the art world starring Natalie Portman and Jenna Ortega. The film marks her return to independent filmmaking after Warner Bros. scooped her up in 2018 to direct “Birds of Prey” just months after her first movie, “Dead Pigs,” won a jury prize at the festival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The director Cathy Yan debuted her first film in the 300-seat Prospector theater (shown here, though now an event space), where audiences sat on bleachers. This year, her second indie feature debuted in the town’s largest venue, the 1,200-seat Eccles Theater. “It’s such a special place,” she said of Park City. “Yet it makes zero logical rational sense for everyone to fly in here. It also feels like we’ve outgrown it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s really nice to be back for the last Park City one,” she said. “It’s a very different experience this time, because we are no longer the kids. But it’s that same indie scramble.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, the show will go on elsewhere — a different city with a different host of challenges and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The thing about Sundance is, though it’s always been connected to the place, it’s really about the community: the filmmakers, the audiences, and how do you bring independent films to a broader audience,” said Mr. Greenfield, the president of Searchlight Pictures. “That will remain, and in some ways, being in a new place will help revitalize that.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/media/sundance-film-festival-park-city-boulder.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:02:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Watch as the Federal Reserve Meets</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/fed-interest-rates.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-fed-gtqj/27dc-fed-gtqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Reserve is expected to hold interest rates steady at its first gathering of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision on Wednesday reflects the central bank’s view that after three consecutive quarter-point reductions, which began in September, it can afford to take a bit more time to figure out its next steps. The Fed will release a new policy statement alongside its rate decision at 2 p.m. in Washington. Jerome H. Powell, the Fed chair, will hold a news conference at 2:30 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rates, which were reduced in the latter half of 2025 to a range of 3.5 percent to 3.75 percent, are now considered to be in the realm of “neutral” — meaning they are low enough to no longer be restraining the economy as much as in the past but not so low that they are revving up growth either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most officials still see a path to cut rates further this year. But the timing and magnitude of those moves are yet to be determined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is what to know about the meeting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rosier outlook: The economic backdrop has helped to bolster the Fed’s confidence that it can pause rate cuts at least for now. Just a couple of months ago, many officials harbored concern about the labor market. Those still exist but are much more muted, especially with growth expected to hold up much better than many economists had originally predicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Fed voters: The Fed’s 12-person policy committee has four new members this year. Three of those new members expressed some form of opposition to some of last year’s cuts — Neel T. Kashkari, president of the Minneapolis Fed; Beth M. Hammack, president of the Cleveland Fed; and Lorie K. Logan, president of the Dallas Fed. Anna L. Paulson, who recently became president of the Philadelphia Fed, will also be joining the Federal Open Market Committee, although she has stood apart from her regional counterparts in backing up the central bank’s reductions and emphasizing the risks posed to the labor market. Even Ms. Paulson, however, has suggested the Fed can take its time before restarting cuts, underscoring the broad consensus that Wednesday’s vote to stand pat is likely to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Committee composition: The four regional presidents, who join the Fed’s policy-setting committee on a rotating basis, will vote alongside the seven members of the board of governors and the president of the New York Fed, all of whom have a permanent seat on the committee. The composition of the committee will matter significantly for Mr. Powell’s replacement as chair when his term ends in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Escalated attacks: The meeting comes as President Trump and his administration have escalated their attacks on the central bank and its leader. Mr. Powell accused the administration this month of opening up a criminal investigation into his handling of costly renovations at the Fed’s headquarters in Washington as retaliation for not slashing rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Political independence: Wednesday’s vote also comes after Supreme Court arguments last week in a lawsuit over whether Lisa D. Cook, a Fed governor, can remain in her post after Mr. Trump tried to oust her last year. While the Supreme Court has yet to deliver a final ruling, several justices appeared wary about the Fed’s ability to operate free of political meddling if her firing was upheld. Mr. Trump has not shied away from sharing his desire to fill a majority of the seats on the Fed’s board of governors with his supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/fed-interest-rates.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:03:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fed Meeting Comes at Pivotal Moment for Central Bank’s Independence</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/fed-trump-powell-interest-rates.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/12/multimedia/28fed-meeting-politics/12dc-fed-vtwc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Jerome H. Powell, the chair of the Federal Reserve, the past month has probably felt like a political eternity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has spend much of the time under siege from President Trump, who has resorted again to name-calling in a bid force down interest rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has been subjected to a new federal investigation, the likes of which forced the notoriously cautious Fed chair to raise a rare public alarm about the future of the central bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Mr. Powell has sat in the audience of the Supreme Court while it weighed the fate of one of his colleagues — a fellow Fed governor whom Mr. Trump has tried to oust on fraud charges that have never actually been filed or prosecuted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All at once, the political forces that had gradually encircled the Fed throughout Mr. Trump’s first year back in office appeared to come to a head in the span of a few weeks, laying bare the stakes for a roughly century-old institution at the heart of the U.S. economy. And it’s in that rare context that the Fed began its two-day rate-setting meeting, which concludes Wednesday with Mr. Powell answering questions at his traditional post-meeting news conference — one that may prove livelier than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed is expected to leave borrowing costs unchanged this month, pausing a series of gradual reductions as it looks to tamp down inflation, which remains above its target. The decision is bound to anger Mr. Trump, who continues to insist that inflation has been defeated — and that affordability is a political hoax — while pining for rates as low as 1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has issued his demands while simultaneously considering successors for Mr. Powell, whose term as chair ends in May. The speculation has lasted so long, and been discussed so publicly, that it has even inspired its own betting market on prediction websites, as traders wager over the president’s periodic hints about the candidates atop his shortlist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Financial markets, at least, have not always responded well to the political chaos, the likes of which saw every living former head of the central bank express unease at one point about the fundamental threats facing the Fed. And yet Mr. Trump and his aides have remained unbowed, insisting that interest rates should be much lower than what many policymakers believe to be appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’d like to see rates go down,” Mr. Trump told reporters Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump continued the attack during a rally at Iowa, saying Mr. Powell “wants to keep rates as high as possible,” as he promised to name a replacement as chair soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Mr. Trump added: “You’ll see rates come down a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/business/economy/fed-trump-powell-interest-rates.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:04:08 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>