<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:13:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Traveling This Weekend? Here’s What to Know About the Winter Storm.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/travel/winter-storm-travel-airlines.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22trav-storm-gmqf/22trav-storm-gmqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 13,000 flights have been canceled this weekend as a powerful winter storm sweeps across much of the United States, delivering freezing rain, sleet and treacherous ice and threatening the biggest snowfall in years in cities including New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The giant storm, crawling east from Texas through the South and up to the Northeast, could affect more than half of the U.S. population through the weekend, snarling air travel and coating roads in ice and snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know if you’re planning to travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 4,000 flights on Saturday were canceled across the United States as of 5:30 p.m. Eastern, and an additional 9,000 were canceled for Sunday, according to FlightAware, a flight tracking website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 80 percent of flights in and out of Dallas Fort Worth International Airport, one of the nation’s busiest, were canceled on Saturday. For the few flights still departing from that airport, the average delay was more than an hour, according to Flightradar24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every flight was canceled on Saturday at some smaller airports, including those serving Memphis, Oklahoma City and Little Rock, Ark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm is expected to drastically increase disruptions across the East Coast on Sunday. The major airports serving cities including Atlanta, New York, Toronto, Washington and Charlotte, N.C., each saw hundreds of cancellations in anticipation of the storm’s arrival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travelers who no longer want to fly this weekend can generally rebook without incurring extra costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;United Airlines, Southwest Airlines, Delta Air Lines, American Airlines, Spirit Airlines, Alaska Airlines and JetBlue are among the carriers allowing flexible rebooking if you’re traveling through dozens of cities, including Atlanta, Boston, Cleveland, Houston, New York and Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monitor your flight using your airline’s app, as updates could appear there first. You can also look at websites like Flightradar24, FlightAware and the National Airspace System Status to get a sense of delays and cancellations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times travel coverage. When our writers review a destination, they do not accept free or discounted services or, in most cases, reveal that they work for The Times. We want their experience to be what you can expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, if your flight is canceled, significantly delayed or changed, airlines will rebook you (or at least try to rebook you) on another flight. If you decide not to fly, the airline owes you an automatic refund, in your original form of payment, within 20 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t expect airlines to cover your food or accommodation costs if you’re stranded; weather isn’t one of the variables, unlike staffing and maintenance, that are under their control. Travel insurance, including coverage through a credit card, may be helpful in this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amtrak has fully or partly canceled more than 75 trains across the East Coast, Midwest and South between Friday and Sunday in anticipation of the winter storm. Affected routes include the Empire Builder, which travels between Chicago and the Pacific Northwest; the Heartland Flyer, which connects Oklahoma City and Fort Worth; the Cardinal, which connects New York and Chicago via Cincinnati; and the Acela between Boston and Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those on affected trains are being offered refunds and rebooking options without extra fees, the railroad said. The number of cancellations may rise depending on how the storm develops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passengers can check Amtrak’s website or app for more details on their train’s status, as well as sign up for delay alerts. Those seeking to change their reservations can contact the company’s reservation center at 1-800-USA-RAIL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Megabus, FlixBus and Greyhound are all warning of delays or cancellations. Megabus, which has suspended some routes in the Northeast on Sunday, said affected customers can get a refund or reschedule at no extra cost. Dozens of FlixBus and Greyhound buses were canceled across the Northeast on Sunday. All three companies said they would contact passengers directly via email and text if their itineraries were disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow New York Times Travel on Instagram and sign up for our Travel Dispatch newsletter to get expert tips on traveling smarter and inspiration for your next vacation. Dreaming up a future getaway or just armchair traveling? Check out our 52 Places to Go in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/travel/winter-storm-travel-airlines.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 12:49:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>CEOs of Target and Minnesota’s Biggest Companies Call for ‘De-Escalation’ After Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal immigration agents outside a Target in St. Paul, Minn., on Sunday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 15:37:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Most Fox News Reporting on Minneapolis Shooting Supports Official Version</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/media/fox-news-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25biz-minnesota-fox-Pretti-kbmj/25biz-minnesota-fox-Pretti-kbmj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A handmade sign memorializes Alex Pretti, who was shot and killed by immigration agents on Saturday in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/media/fox-news-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 14:31:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Europe’s Reliance on U.S. Natural Gas Grows, So Does Trump’s Leverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A tanker waits to dock at a liquefied natural gas plant in Hammerfest, Norway, in 2024.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 20:01:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Bad Are A.I. Delusions? We Asked People Treating Them.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Julia Sheffield, a psychologist at Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville, is navigating how to treat problems caused or exacerbated by A.I. chatbots.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Hobbled the I.R.S. This C.E.O. Now Has to Make It Work.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
This year’s tax filing season could be an even more formidable challenge than usual for the Internal Revenue Service and Frank Bisignano, its chief executive.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brisk Sales at Goodwill Suggest Wary Shoppers in an Uncertain Economy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/goodwill-sales-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/00biz-goodwill-qzkw/00biz-goodwill-qzkw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Part of the appeal for Goodwill shoppers is the treasure hunt of searching the racks for hidden gems.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/goodwill-sales-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:01:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Voters See a Middle-Class Lifestyle as Drifting Out of Reach, Poll Finds</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost-mediumSquareAt3X-v4.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the affordability of education, housing, health care, having a family and retirement are driving economic anxieties, a New York Times/Siena poll found.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:02:16 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>