<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:16:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Meta Campaigns to Change Opinions on Data Centers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/19visualUploader-27018-cover/19visualUploader-27018-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advertisement began with a panning shot of Altoona, Iowa, a town of 20,000 near Des Moines. The camera moved from a diner to a farm to a high school football field. To the pluck of guitar strings, a voice-over promoted a boon for the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re bringing jobs here,” the ad said. “For us, and for our next generation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ad’s folksy vibes were not for a political candidate. They were for a data center that Meta had built in Altoona — part of an ad campaign by the Silicon Valley giant to shape a new narrative around the vast computing facilities that power artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta, OpenAI, Google, Microsoft and Amazon have embarked on a building spree in the A.I. race, investing hundreds of billions of dollars to erect data centers to develop the technology. In doing so, they have fueled an increasingly political issue, with President Trump and lawmakers across the country criticizing the computing sites for driving up energy costs and straining local water supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in November and December, Meta spent $6.4 million to run a series of ads — including the one about Altoona — in the television markets of eight state capitals such as Sacramento, Salt Lake City and Tallahassee, Fla., as well as Washington, D.C., according to data from AdImpact, an analytics firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta most likely bought the ads “with the goal of shaping policy decisions” and reaching lawmakers, said Michael Beach, the chief executive of Cross Screen Media, a marketing analytics firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other tech giants are also aiming to influence public opinion on data centers. Amazon is helping to fund a similar ad campaign in Virginia, where it operates dozens of data centers. The campaign — focused on job growth and electricity costs — began in December 2024 and is still running, backed by Virginia Connects, a nonprofit created by the Data Center Coalition, an industry trade group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Padilla, a Democratic state senator in California who proposed a bill last year to regulate rising energy costs from data centers, said such ads were a tech company tactic. “If you like sports, if you have kids, and you love America, you’ve got to love data centers, right?” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Ryan Daniels, a spokesman for Meta, did not comment on its ads but said the company paid the full costs of energy used by its data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon declined to comment. In a statement, Josh Levi, president of the Data Center Coalition, said Virginia Connects helped “inform communities and policymakers about the data center industry,” but he did not address the ad campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta operates 26 data centers in the United States and has said it will spend $600 billion to build new ones in the coming years. Last year, the company also unveiled two political action committees to back candidates at the state level who support A.I. during the midterm elections. (Meta said its spending on the ad campaign was separate from the PACs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has highlighted how data centers can bring jobs and tax revenue to places in need of economic development. It and other tech giants have hired “community affairs” workers to build local trust, according to job listings seen by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Chris Van Hollen, Democrat of Maryland, said data centers became an issue on Capitol Hill early last year when constituents started complaining en masse about rising electric bills and blamed data centers. That has made A.I. infrastructure part of the larger debate about affordability, along with things like the cost of eggs, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Mr. Van Hollen introduced a bill to regulate data center energy use. The measure is backed by other Democrats, but the issue is becoming bipartisan, he said. President Trump has recently made several statements about data centers and energy costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are the ‘HOTTEST’ Country in the World, and Number One in AI. Data Centers are key to that boom, and keeping Americans FREE and SECURE but, the big Technology Companies who build them must ‘pay their own way,’” Mr. Trump posted on social media on Jan. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diane Papan, a Democratic state assemblywoman in California, said she had seen Meta’s ads while working in Sacramento last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, she introduced a bill to require tech companies to publicize data center water use; Gov. Gavin Newsom, another Democrat, vetoed it in October. In an interview, Ms. Papan said that she was disappointed by how much the tech industry opposed the bill and that Meta and other tech companies “were not front and center to work with us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I very much worry about with this ad campaign is localities committing to this industry and then saying in 10 years, ‘What have we done to ourselves?’” Ms. Papan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta built its first data center in Altoona in 2013 and has expanded from one building there to a three-million-square-foot complex, said Chad Quick, the economic development director of Altoona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Quick, who describes Meta’s relationship with Altoona as “mutually beneficial,” said a film crew from Los Angeles had spent a week shooting scenes around town last year. After the ad aired, people from other towns called to ask whether they should welcome new data centers, too, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His response was positive. “Our experience has not been the experience that some communities have had,” Mr. Quick said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:23:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UPS Says It Is Cutting Up to 30,000 Jobs</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-ups-tlqb/27biz-ups-tlqb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS said on Tuesday that it expected to cut as many as 30,000 jobs this year as part of a continuing effort to reduce costs and shore up profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the delivery company eliminated 62,000 positions, by laying off full-time drivers, warehouse workers and managers, as well as seasonal employees. UPS said on Tuesday that it was planning the additional layoffs this year because it expected to deliver fewer packages for Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement could add to Americans’ concerns about the job market. While unemployment has risen only slightly in recent months, hiring has slowed significantly. Consumer confidence plunged this month, partly because a greater share of consumers said jobs were “hard to get,” according to the Conference Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Dykes, UPS’s chief financial officer, said this year’s job cuts would be in “operational positions,” the term UPS uses for delivery and warehouse workers. He said the reductions would occur “through attrition” and by offering “voluntary separation” to full-time drivers. UPS said last year that it wanted to wind down much of its Amazon business because it was not profitable. UPS has said Amazon was its largest customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS announced the layoffs on the same day it reported its earnings for 2025. The company had net income of $5.57 billion last year, down nearly 4 percent from $5.78 billion in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS had around half a million employees at the start of last year, some 300,000 of them members of the Teamsters union. A Teamsters spokeswoman did not respond to requests for comment on the layoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS’s leaders are restructuring the company to try to bolster profit margins in a difficult time for the delivery business. Last year, the company suffered a sharp drop in packages sent from China after President Trump imposed tariffs on lower-value shipments from the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, UPS closed 93 facilities and deployed automation in 57. Mr. Dykes said on Tuesday that the company had identified 24 more buildings for closure in the first half of the year, and that more could follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investors appear to be backing UPS’s moves to reinvigorate its business. The company’s stock is up over 35 percent from its low last year. Still, over the past year, its shares are down 18 percent, while Fedex’s stock is up 11 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an investor call on Tuesday, Carol Tomé, UPS’s chief executive, said that “2025 was a year of considerable progress for UPS.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, a UPS plane crashed in Louisville, Ky., killing three crew members and 12 people on the ground. The plane was a MD-11F jet, made by McDonnell Douglas, which Boeing acquired in the 1990s. On Tuesday, UPS said it had retired its MD-11 fleet in the fourth quarter of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:36:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bari Weiss Urges CBS News to Think Like a ‘Start-Up’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bari Weiss, the recently hired and frequently discussed editor in chief of CBS News, began her first networkwide meeting on Tuesday by addressing the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s been a lot of noise around me taking this job,” she told hundreds of CBS staff members gathered in bureaus across the globe. “I get it. I also get why, in the face of all this tumult, you might feel uncertain or skeptical about me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bumps of Ms. Weiss’s early tenure have been heavily chronicled, including her contentious decision to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment and rocky moments on a revamped “Evening News.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, it was her turn to lay out her vision: an ambitious transformation of CBS News from a tradition-bound institution into a digitally savvy journalistic engine that meets news consumers where they are — namely, far from broadcast TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not producing a product enough people want,” she said, while dismissing day-to-day Nielsen ratings as an outmoded benchmark. “What winning looks like writ large for this company is building incredible journalism for audiences that are so much bigger than the one that we currently have,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rallying cry was intended as a reset of sorts, a chance to cut through the suspicions that Ms. Weiss, a frequent critic of the mainstream news media and founder of the independent site The Free Press, is trying to tilt CBS News into more pro-Trump territory. She urged her journalists to reel in investigative scoops (and “scoops of ideas, scoops of explanation”) and think beyond traditional TV broadcasts, referring to her ideal reporters as “dynamic Swiss Army knives capable of writing, speaking, hosting, reporting, analyzing and writing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also announced a new roster of CBS News contributors with viewpoints spanning the political spectrum. The group includes Andrew Huberman, a neurobiology expert who is a popular influencer in the so-called manosphere; Niall Ferguson, a British American historian who frequently writes for The Free Press; Casey Lewis, a Gen Alpha Substack trend-spotter; and Coleman Hughes, a Free Press contributing writer who has argued for “a colorblind society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running an organization as large and influential as CBS News is the biggest challenge of Ms. Weiss’s career. She was appointed last year by its new owner, the technology heir David Ellison, who acquired the network’s parent company, Paramount, after a contentious sale process. Shortly before the Trump administration approved the deal, Paramount paid $16 million to settle a defamation case against “60 Minutes” brought by President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, Ms. Weiss’s remarks on Tuesday echoed those of many media executives trying to steer old-line news institutions, with falling revenue and graying audiences, into the choppy waters of new media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She framed the future of CBS News in stark terms, warning employees that it would be “one hell of a fight” to keep pace in a rapidly changing business. And she told her team to be more nimble and innovative, calling CBS News “the best-capitalized media start-up in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss also warned that employees who did not subscribe to her vision may not wish to remain. “It’s a free country,” Ms. Weiss said. “I completely respect if you decide this is just not the right place at the right time for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her challenge was underscored by a lengthy question-and-answer session with employees, who asked about her decision in December to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment about a notorious prison in El Salvador where deported Venezuelan migrants were detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss said that she held the segment because she believed it required more reporting, and that the decision was hers alone. “I was not pressured by David Ellison or anyone else,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also acknowledged the fallout from her decision to pull the segment after it had been promoted by the network, noting that she was new to broadcasting and unfamiliar with “that specific logistical nightmare.” Referring to the 11th-hour nature of her decision, she said, “Nothing of that kind is ever going to happen again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Tuesday’s event concluded, Gayle King, the “CBS Mornings” anchor, spoke up to offer a rallying cry of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She thanked Ms. Weiss for presenting “a very good case for what you want this company to be,” adding that it was good for the newsroom “to hear and see that you are a real person and this is what you want and how you feel about us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ms. King was blunt about the public reaction to Ms. Weiss’s tenure so far. “People now come up to me to my face, if I’m at the airport, they go, ‘Love you guys, but I ain’t watching you anymore,’” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. King also criticized employees who were divulging details of the newsroom’s inner workings to the press, and speculated on how long it might take for her own remarks to leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss, wryly, chimed in: “I’m sure someone’s livestreaming it right now, Gayle,” she said, according to a recording of the event obtained by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:59:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Begins Assigned Seating, Scrapping a Signature Quirk</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a water-cannon salute, balloons and commemorative bag tags, Southwest Airlines on Tuesday officially retired its decades-old practice of open seating. For the first time, passengers received assigned seats, a major shift for the carrier, which also introduced a new group boarding process and premium seat options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two flights with assigned seating landed early in the day, at Chicago Midway International Airport and then at Orlando International Airport, where a plane arriving from San Juan, P.R., glided toward the jetway under two arcs of water, a salute reserved for special occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The celebration continued at the gate, which was festooned with red, blue and orange balloons. Passengers loaded up on free snacks and coffee and took selfies through heart-shaped holes in giant boarding passes. The airline handed out bag tags with the line, “I understood the assignment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southwest says the seating changes are intended to keep up with evolving customer expectations and to increase revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tony Roach, an executive vice president at the airline who was on the flight from San Juan, said that the airline had “outgrown” open seating, adding that assigned seating also reduces anxiety among travelers because they know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There were a lot of limitations with open seating in terms of what we want to do in the future,” he said. “You aren’t able to offer things inside the cabin which a lot of people want. Things like extra legroom would have been very difficult to do with an open-seating environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than 50 years, Southwest used a system of open seating: Once they had checked in, passengers received a group and a number that determined the general order of when they’d get on the plane. Then once on board, they could choose any open seat. Getting a desired seat, or sitting together, often hinged on checking in early, and there were no premium seats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was loved by some travelers, who viewed it as egalitarian and flexible, and bemoaned by others who complained that it was chaotic and stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Southwest offers three categories of seats — standard, preferred and extra legroom — and the most expensive can cost hundreds of dollars more than the cheapest fare. Boarding order now depends on the fare class, as well as whether a traveler has elite status with the airline or holds its credit card. Travelers can also pay extra to board in an earlier group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times travel coverage. When our writers review a destination, they do not accept free or discounted services or, in most cases, reveal that they work for The Times. We want their experience to be what you can expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday, the airline also ended its flexible policy for plus-size passengers, which allowed customers to ask for an extra seat at the gate, or pay for an extra seat and later receive a refund. Those passengers will now need to purchase two seats ahead of time, without a guaranteed refund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some loyal travelers expressed dismay that the airline was abandoning some of the quirks that made it different from other major U.S. carriers. In May, Southwest eliminated its popular policy of granting travelers two free checked bags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Wolf, 74, who has flown with Southwest for more than two decades, said he was enticed early on by the airline’s reputation as an industry disrupter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I liked them really well when they were young and scrappy. In the past, they seemed to have mastered the quick turnaround, they were able to get back on time after delays, they are very agile with swapping planes and all of that,” said Mr. Wolf, who was at LaGuardia Airport awaiting his flight home to Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With assigned seats and premium fares, “now it’s just like any other airline,” Mr. Wolf said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several longtime Southwest fliers also remarked that they enjoyed the unpredictability of the previous open-seating system. Aaron Schottenstein, a 35-year-old who lives in Phoenix, said he’d been dreading the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I loved the boarding, getting on in the lines, yapping with everybody while you wait there, talking about how people are trying to get like five spots closer because they might get that much better of a seat,” said Mr. Schottenstein, who was traveling from New York to Phoenix, with a connection in Kansas City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others welcomed assigned seating, saying it eliminated pain points like checking in 24 hours ahead of a flight to improve the chances of snagging a better seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love it,” said Maureen Hager, of Buffalo, who was traveling home from Orlando on Tuesday with Veronica, her adult daughter. “I hated waiting on line, trying to get there early. I don’t like waiting to get to the airport and waiting on line and the anxiety of not knowing if you got seats together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronica, however, disagreed. She called the change a “money grab.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the other way,” she said. “I like the thrill of having to check in, trying to get Group A, first round.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Jordan, the airline’s chief executive said in an interview last month that the airline was confident that customers, who he said desire these changes, would stay loyal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re now offering things that the vast majority of people want,” he said, adding, “We’ve seen no defection from the brand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Adelson contributed reporting from Orlando, Fla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow New York Times Travel on Instagram and sign up for our Travel Dispatch newsletter to get expert tips on traveling smarter and inspiration for your next vacation. Dreaming up a future getaway or just armchair traveling? Check out our 52 Places to Go in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:32:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>