<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:46:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Aviation System Is Preparing for Storm-Driven Chaos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/business/airlines-travel-storm.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23biz-airlines-prep-flmb/23biz-airlines-prep-flmb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airlines and airports on Friday were preparing for widespread disruptions this weekend as a powerful storm threatened to blanket large parts of the country in ice and snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm was expected to hit much of the Southern United States on Friday, prompting some targeted flight cancellations. Delta Air Lines had proactively canceled some Friday flights in northern Texas, Oklahoma, Arkansas, Louisiana and Tennessee, but most cancellations were on the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Friday afternoon, American Airlines, which is based in Fort Worth, had canceled 19 percent of flights planned for Saturday, while Southwest Airlines, based in Dallas, had canceled 17 percent, according to FlightAware. At Dallas Fort Worth International Airport, about two in three flights scheduled for Saturday were already canceled, according to Cirium, an aviation data firm. Delta also warned of cancellations Saturday in the Midwest and South.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airlines have an easier time managing around bad weather at a single airport, but this storm is much more dangerous because of its breadth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have a storm that’s going to progress from the center of the country all the way to the East Coast and a very wide swath north to south,” said Bob Mann, an industry consultant and a former airline executive. “The area of impact and the duration of the impact is far longer than the standard weather event.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week and next are typically among the slowest of the year, according to Transportation Security Administration airport screening data. As a result, carriers may have more flexibility and resources to respond to disruptions over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Friday, many airlines had waived fees to change weekend travel, allowing customers to postpone travel from or through many major airports in the eastern half of the United States. Carriers encouraged travelers to confirm their flight status before leaving for the airport, and several airlines said they were shoring up resources to better handle the chaos expected in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delta said it expected the storm to affect about 80 cities it flies to. The airline also said it was sending experts from its hubs in colder climates to help with de-icing and baggage support in Southern airports, including those in Atlanta; Birmingham, Ala.; and Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparing to bounce back after a disruption is often as important as managing the disruption in the first place. American said in a statement that it was moving personnel and planes around to be prepared in the storm’s aftermath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re repositioning aircraft, aligning crew resources and reinforcing staffing at key airports while coordinating with our partners to help minimize disruption and set the stage for a fast, safe recovery,” the airline said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most ominous weather forecasts called for ice and a foot or more of snow in some places. In such conditions, airport runways and taxiways have to be plowed for planes to safely move about, and jets often line up to be doused in de-icing fluid to remove and prevent ice accumulation, slowing operations even at airports that are used to such conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That de-icing process is complex and expensive, especially at airports not used to severe winter conditions. But it is essential to flight safety. Even small amounts of ice can affect a jet’s aerodynamics, hindering pilots’ ability to operate various functions. For American, Chicago O’Hare International Airport is home to the airline’s biggest de-icing operation, treating planes 6,000 to 10,000 times every winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While airports in the South may not be as familiar with icy conditions, many do deal with them from time to time. Charlotte Douglas International Airport in North Carolina, a hub in American’s network, said it had a fleet of 40 snow-removal, de-icing and maintenance vehicles at the ready. In 2022, Memphis International Airport debuted a de-icing facility that cost more than $300 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At airline command centers, teams of experts work around the clock to monitor flights and help manage and resolve problems as they arise. But such work can be especially complicated because displaced planes, crews, flights or customers can have cascading effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As flights are delayed, pilots and flight attendants sometimes reach legal work limits, forcing airlines to cancel more flights or call in replacement crews. A flight attendant stranded in, say, Nashville can’t work a flight in Chicago the next day as planned. Poor conditions can also force planes to be diverted and not be available for a future flight they were scheduled for.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/business/airlines-travel-storm.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:47:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota’s Biggest Companies Call for ‘De-escalation’ of Tensions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief executives of Target, Best Buy, General Mills and Cargill were among more than 60 large Minnesota companies to issue a public letter on Sunday calling for an “immediate de-escalation of tensions” in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter marks the first time the most recognizable businesses in Minnesota have weighed in on the turmoil in Minneapolis amid the aggressive crackdown by federal immigration agents, which have sparked widespread protests throughout the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes one day after federal agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti, a nurse at the city’s Veterans Affairs hospital, while he was being restrained on a Minneapolis sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With yesterday’s tragic news, we are calling for an immediate de-escalation of tensions and for state, local and federal officials to work together to find real solutions,” the letter states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was signed by top executives of Minnesota’s largest companies and large hospital systems, including Land O’ Lakes, Hormel, U.S. Bancorp, Mayo Clinic and 3M. It also was signed by local sports teams: the Minnesota Vikings, Minnesota Timberwolves, and the Minnesota Wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is notable because many chief executives have sought to avoid weighing in on any politically charged issues during the second Trump administration. On Friday, hundreds of smaller businesses in the Minneapolis area shut their doors as they backed protests against the actions from Immigration and Customs Enforcement in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was shared by the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce, which represents more than 6,000 businesses across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, Josh Bolten, the chief executive of the Business Roundtable, an association of more than 200 chief executives of America’s leading companies, said in an emailed statement that he supported the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce’s letter. Beth Ford, the chief executive of Land O’ Lakes, sits on the Business Roundtable’s board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until Sunday, the largest companies in Minnesota had not addressed the issue, but in the Chamber of Commerce letter they said they had been in contact with federal, state and local officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The silence by big companies had been a marked contrast from their responses to the killing of George Floyd in Minneapolis in 2020. That murder helped set off a broader corporate movement to fight racism, with executives making public pledges to support diversity initiatives, donate to social justice causes and express solidarity with demonstrators at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the years since, companies have sought to avoid being caught in any political cross hairs, as the country has become more polarized. Many have said they will be more selective about the issues they tackle, sticking only to those that directly affect their business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum last week, once a hotbed for such social issues, there was hardly any public mention by executives of the unrest in Minnesota. The focus was instead on artificial intelligence, deal making and the reshaping of global alliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for some companies, the violence in Minnesota has hit particularly close to home. After immigration agents detained two employees at the Target store in Richfield, Minn., this month, clergy members gathered at the retailer’s headquarters, asking the company to keep immigration agents off its properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every C.E.O. — and I know all these C.E.O.s — they want to have a peaceful environment for their employees,” said Bill George, the former chief executive of Medtronic, whose current chief signed the letter. Mr. George is also a former board member at Target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The larger issue for C.E.O.s,” he added, is that the unrest in Minneapolis “is going to have a very negative effect on their growth, on their innovation and particularly their ability to recruit people from around the country and around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking as a group, as Minnesota executives did Sunday, could help insulate companies from individual attacks from Mr. Trump, said Jeff Sonnenfeld, a professor of leadership studies at the Yale School of Management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can take down companies individually, but when they work collectively, they have immunity,” Mr. Sonnenfeld said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executives similarly relied on the law of numbers in expressing concerns about tariffs, which organizations like the U.S. Chamber of Commerce came out in opposition to last spring. Many companies ultimately struck their own deals with the administration over tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s letter stopped short of calling for specific action nor did the corporations condemn the shooting of Mr. Pretti by the federal agents or call for immigration authorities to rein in their aggressive enforcement. The statement also did not call on protesters to change their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With polls showing voters split along party lines on whether they support President Trump’s immigration crackdown, corporations have been careful not to alienate large numbers of their customers by taking a side. They also risk angering Mr. Trump, who has publicly rebuked companies and executives he believes have crossed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter from the Minnesota companies on Sunday struck a neutral tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In this difficult moment for our community, we call for peace and focused cooperation among local, state and federal leaders to achieve a swift and durable solution that enables families, businesses, our employees, and communities across Minnesota to resume our work to build a bright and prosperous future,” the executives wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alison Taylor, a clinical associate professor of business and society at the N.Y.U. Stern business school, said she thought the companies had no choice but to say something. “They have been backed into a corner, because obviously the situation going on is starting to have commercial consequences,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Taylor added: “Is it better than doing nothing? Probably. Is it sufficient? I don’t think anyone’s going to think this is sufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:03:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Europe’s Reliance on U.S. Natural Gas Grows, So Does Trump’s Leverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Russia invaded Ukraine in 2022, it also tried to squeeze Europe by crimping natural gas flows. But increased shipments of liquid natural gas, much of it from the United States, helped ease the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, smoldering tensions between leaders in Washington and Brussels could turn Europe’s reliance on American natural gas into a similar political pressure point, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve replaced one massive dependency with another one,” said Henning Gloystein, a managing director for energy at Eurasia Group, a political risk research firm. “That looked fine three years ago, but now it doesn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to import large amounts of energy is one of Europe’s strategic weaknesses. Natural gas from Russia was a mainstay for the continent before the invasion of Ukraine. In 2019, for instance, Russian gas accounted for more than half of the European Union’s gas imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The huge volumes of Russian gas that flowed through pipelines across Ukraine and Poland and under the Baltic Sea plummeted in the wake of the assault. Prices soared, putting pressure on consumers, industries and governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States came to the rescue. Tankers loaded at U.S. terminals shipped large volumes of liquefied natural gas to European ports in the Netherlands, France and Belgium, among other destinations, helping to replace the Russian fuel and calming markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the United States had been a modest supplier of natural gas to Europe, with about 5 percent of imports in late 2019, but it has since grown, providing more than a quarter of the European Union’s gas imports in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Bruegel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, those gas flows looked heroic. Now, they are raising eyebrows. Since beginning his second term, President Trump has sought to use trade as leverage in disputes with other countries, including his recent push to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing concern in Europe is that Mr. Trump could turn the strong position that the United States has gained in the oil and gas industry into a weapon to try to coerce other countries. “Recently, people have started to realize we are probably a little bit too dependent on U.S. L.N.G.,” said Anne-Sophie Corbeau, a global research scholar in Paris for the Center on Global Energy Policy at Columbia University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has encouraged this reliance, pushing Europe to increase U.S. imports as part of the trade deal struck with the European Union last year. In 2025, L.N.G. flows from the United States to European Union countries jumped about 60 percent from the previous year, according to Bruegel, a research organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say these volumes are likely to increase. Although Europe invests in renewable energy like wind and solar power, it still requires natural gas for heating homes and manufacturing goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe is also producing less of its own fuel because its existing oil and gas fields are winding down, and countries like Britain, whose petroleum production has fallen sharply, discourage new drilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Europe is without much alternative,” said Christoph Halser, a senior analyst at Rystad Energy, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly in response to American complaints, Europe is also in the process of phasing out its purchases of Russian gas, which fell to around 12 percent of imports in 2025. Norway, which is not a European Union member, is the bloc’s largest gas supplier, accounting for around 30 percent of imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is already the world leader in L.N.G. exports, and developers are spending heavily to build facilities for chilling gas to liquid form and then shipping it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe, which is a relatively short sail from terminals on the Gulf Coast, is a logical destination for these cargoes. China, the world’s largest importer of liquefied natural gas, has largely stopped buying American fuel because of U.S. tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, a bright spot for Europe may be that a supply boom is expected in the coming years, which could bring down what have been relatively high prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in the event of increased political tensions with Europe, some analysts are skeptical that the Trump administration would take steps like reducing shipments that would be contrary to the interests of the U.S. oil and gas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That “would be a very negative market signal, and also significantly impair the competitiveness of the industry, which the administration is committed to supporting,” said David L. Goldwyn, a former U.S. energy special envoy and now president of Goldwyn Global Strategies, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry in the United States also differs markedly from Russia’s. There, the Kremlin was able to use Gazprom, the state-controlled gas monopoly, “to weaponize gas flows in 2022,” Jack Reid, a graduate economist at Oxford Economics, wrote in a recent study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States, he added, is more likely to “redirect flows than bring them to a halt.” Other analysts speculate that Washington might take measures like putting an export tax on gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, though, meddling with gas flows is likely to lead to higher costs and prices, analysts say, which would be bad news for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Import concentration” matters, said Ugne Keliauskaite, a research analyst at Bruegel. “Now Europe is more exposed to U.S.-centered disruptions.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 20:01:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brisk Sales at Goodwill Suggest Wary Shoppers in an Uncertain Economy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/goodwill-sales-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/00biz-goodwill-qzkw/00biz-goodwill-qzkw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill stores are thriving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is good news for the nonprofit organization that oversees Goodwill, the world’s largest thrift store chain. But it also signals that Americans in an uncertain economy are trying to stretch their dollars as far as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization, Goodwill Industries, said it surpassed $7 billion in revenue — a record — from its 3,400 stores in 2025, up roughly 7 percent from the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are pretty steady in almost any economic situation,” Steven C. Preston, Goodwill’s chief executive, said in an interview. “But when things are tight, we’re probably more likely to get that foot traffic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the consumer economy, holiday spending remained strong last year, and consumers are still spending on discretionary goods, even if they have to defer the costs through “buy now, pay later” plans. But a cocktail of inflation, slowing job growth and lofty bills for groceries and rent has left American households looking to eke out as much as they can with every purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a cold January day, David Collon, 48, went to a Goodwill store in northern Manhattan looking for sweatpants and sweaters. “They have a good selection, and I’m looking for a very good price at this time,” said Mr. Collon, who works as a groundskeeper. “It’s hard times. This brings down the pain of spending for clothes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill shops present a sensory overload of inventory. Shoppers go for the low prices, but also the treasure hunt of rifling through aisles of shirts and dresses for hidden gems. At the outlets that sell items lumped together in bins, some customers wait for hours for goods to be refreshed to maximize their hauls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill’s secondhand peers have also seen a boost. Savers Value Village, which operates more than 300 stores mostly in the United States and Canada, said net sales grew nearly 16 percent in its most recent quarter. The online consignment shop ThredUp said its revenue rose 34 percent last quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thrift stores are some of the only places that can offer $5 T-shirts and $15 jeans, and are shielded from tariff-related price increases because they don’t import goods manufactured abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Secondhand stores are benefiting from many of the same forces we’re seeing across the broader economy,” said Michelle Meyer, chief economist of the Mastercard Economics Institute. “Consumers are becoming far more value‑conscious.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill is a nonprofit business that relies on donations and its retail stores to fund its programs, which include career skills training, education and community programs for those in need. It also offers services for formerly incarcerated people to re-enter the work force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill collects about six billion pounds of goods per year and tries to keep as many items in circulation as possible. Items that are not sold in stores go to outlets, where they are heavily discounted and sold in bulk by the pound, or they go through partner resellers. Some products may end up in overseas markets or recycling facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executives are trying out partnerships with retailers to prompt more donations. Last year, Goodwill began a pilot project with Amazon, hosting return kiosks inside its stores so that customers can combine their drop-off errands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the slowing economy, shifting consumer trends are boosting Goodwill’s sales. Much of the growth is coming from Generation Z and millennials who see secondhand clothes not only as cheaper but also as more sustainable and fashionable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill’s annual sales are up nearly 50 percent from 2019, in part because of young shoppers like Steph Tauszik, 20, a student at the Fashion Institute of Technology in Manhattan, who was shopping for a winter coat at a Goodwill store. “It’s cheaper, and it’s good for the planet in terms of not over consuming,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s an entire shift in mind-set,” said David Eagles, Goodwill’s chief operating officer. “It’s sustainable, it’s personal, it’s local.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, young consumers are sharing their thrift hauls on TikTok and YouTube, showing off the clothes they often find from online resellers like the RealReal, Depop and Poshmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodwill, for its part, is also pushing an online auction site, which also had its biggest year ever, though it represents only a small portion of total sales. That platform sources goods exclusively from local Goodwill shops, with the proceeds of each sale going back to the affiliates that listed the item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management sees the secondhand surge as an opportunity for expansion. That means more places for Goodwill to both gather goods and sell them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, Goodwill expects to add between 50 and 100 new stores across North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m hopeful we will accelerate growth,” Mr. Eagles said, adding that 2026 “will probably be our biggest year yet — that’s our goal.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/goodwill-sales-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:02:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Elon Musk’s X Faces European Inquiry Over Sexualized A.I. Images</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/european-union-x-grok-ai-images-musk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-europe-musk1-gwcf/26biz-europe-musk1-gwcf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European Union regulators on Monday announced an investigation of Elon Musk’s social media platform X after the authorities said that it had failed to stop the spread of sexualized images generated by artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inquiry is likely to escalate a confrontation between Europe and the United States over the regulation of online content. Mr. Musk and his allies in the Trump administration have sharply criticized European Union internet regulations as an attack on free speech and American companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European authorities said that X was being investigated for possible violation of the Digital Services Act, alleging that the company had not properly addressed the “systemic risks” of integrating the A.I. chatbot Grok into its service. Starting in late December, sexually explicit images generated by Grok, including of children, flooded the service, drawing worldwide criticism from victims and regulators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Musk was facing mounting scrutiny in Europe even before this latest Grok controversy. Last month, X was fined 120 million euros, or about $140 million, for violating Digital Services Act rules around deceptive design, advertising transparency and data sharing with outside researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European authorities have another investigation underway about X’s recommender algorithm and policies for preventing the spread of illicit content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nonconsensual sexual deepfakes of women and children are a violent, unacceptable form of degradation,” Henna Virkkunen, the European Commission executive vice president who oversees enforcement of the Digital Service Act, said in a statement. “We will determine whether X has met its legal obligations under the D.S.A., or whether it treated rights of European citizens — including those of women and children — as collateral damage of its service.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Commission, the executive body for the 27-nation European Union, did not give a timeline for the investigation, but said that it had the authority to order X to make changes during the inquiry in the “absence of meaningful adjustments” to the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for X referred to a previous statement the company had made about Grok. “We remain committed to making X a safe platform for everyone and continue to have zero tolerance for any forms of child sexual exploitation, nonconsensual nudity and unwanted sexual content,” the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest investigation illustrates a growing divide between the European Union and the United States over free speech and regulation of the internet. European officials argue that the lack of safeguards on platforms like X has allowed hate speech, misogyny and violent content to flourish online. Mr. Musk and the Trump administration have said efforts to force the companies to more proactively police the services amounts to censorship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Regnier, a spokesman for the European Commission, said at a news conference on Monday that the X investigation had “nothing to do with freedom of expression or with censorship.” He said regulators had identified content spreading on X that is illegal across the continent, including antisemitism, non-consensual deepfakes and child sexual abuse material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Happy or not, compliance is not an option,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Digital Services Act, passed in 2022, requires companies to meaningfully address the spread of illegal content, the definition of which varies from country to country in the European Union. It can include material that targets individuals based on their race, ethnicity, gender, sexuality or religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European regulators said that the integration of Grok into X exposed “citizens in the E.U. to serious harm.” The British authorities are also investigating the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problems began last month. In response to simple user prompts on X, the chatbot automatically created and publicly posted manipulated photographs of real people, including children, to remove their clothes, put them in skimpy clothing or pose them in sexualized situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As criticism grew, X limited Grok’s A.I. image creation to users who paid for premium features, which reduced the number of images. X later expanded those guardrails, saying that it would no longer allow anyone to prompt Grok’s X account for “images of real people in revealing clothing such as bikinis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European Union regulators said that they would take X’s policy changes into account during the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koba Ryckewaert contributed reporting from Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/european-union-x-grok-ai-images-musk.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:16:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gold Soars Beyond $5,000 as Global Tensions Grow</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/gold-prices.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-gold-prices1-kgvw/26biz-gold-prices1-kgvw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price of gold reached a record high on Monday, surging above $5,000 an ounce, as investors sought a safe haven amid heightened geopolitical tensions and rising global risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spot gold prices jumped as high as $5,102 an ounce, after climbing 8 percent last week. Other precious metals were also rising. The price of silver topped $100 an ounce on Monday and hit $109.83, a record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. stock markets were up slightly at the start of trading on Monday ahead of a stream of company financial results expected this week, and ahead of a meeting of the Federal Reserve, which is expected to keep interest rates steady.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investors are seeking shelter from global uncertainty, including strains between the United States and the European Union over President Trump’s determination to take over Greenland, leading to fears of a renewed trade war. Tensions in Ukraine, Venezuela and the Middle East continue to simmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say gold is now on track for its best year since 1979, when prices soared during a period of runaway inflation, a weakening dollar and instability in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is comfort in holding an asset perceived as secure in a world where the global order may be shifting,” Chris Weston, the head of research at Pepperstone, a financial services company, wrote in a note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of another U.S. government shutdown has amplified Wall Street’s anxiety. Several key Democrats in Congress said they would withhold their support from a bipartisan spending bill after federal agents fatally shot a Minneapolis resident on Saturday. The standoff over the bill, which includes funding for the Department of Homeland Security, raises the likelihood of the shutdown at the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gold prices began climbing in early 2024, when the precious metal broke out of a narrow trading range and surged past $2,350 an ounce by spring. At first, the move reflected concerns about persistent inflation and growing global tensions, but it soon took on broader meaning as investors grew broadly uneasy about the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rally progressed in 2025. Central banks continued to add to their reserves, while more investors started to view gold as protection against political and financial blows. Those concerns intensified in October, when gold prices sharply jumped toward $4,000 an ounce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prices have continued to climb since then. Gold has benefited, in part, because other assets investors usually turn to for stability are looking less dependable. The U.S. dollar has weakened as the Federal Reserve lowers interest rates. The turmoil abroad has weighed on other major currencies such as the yen and the euro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rising debt and deficits have also cast doubts about U.S. creditworthiness, making Treasuries a less dependable safe haven.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/gold-prices.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:19:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Business Leaders Face a Test in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/dealbook/business-leaders-minnesota-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26db-minneapolis-kfph/26db-minneapolis-kfph-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew here. I’m back from Davos, Switzerland, just in time for a storm that has blanketed much of the East Coast, and as the latest shooting by federal agents in Minneapolis raises serious concerns throughout the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally in this space, I have raised questions about how the business community uses its voice. In recent years, that group has gone largely silent on issues deemed “too political.” But at some point, business leaders — not just those in Minneapolis — need to raise their hands. They don’t have to do it individually; they can do it collectively, as the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce has done. (More on that below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever your politics, we can all agree that federal agents shouldn’t be killing U.S. citizens except in the most dangerous circumstances. Even if you believe an officer acted in good faith or out of fear for his or her life, the frequency of these episodes suggests a systemic training failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Training” is something the business world understands intimately. If any company had failures of this magnitude twice in three weeks, any competent C.E.O. would step back — not necessarily to abandon the strategy, but at least to rethink it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will leaders who speak out against the administration face political blowback? Yes, we’ve seen it before. But some C.E.O.s have shown courage and done so anyway: Jamie Dimon, for instance, said in Davos last week, “I don’t like what I’m seeing, five grown men beating up a little old lady.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who have President Trump’s ear, who justify their public silence by being-in-the-room with the president: Are they using that proximity in private moments to tell him this needs to be fixed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is to suggest that we shouldn’t police illegal immigration or arrest people who assault others. But just as businesses do, this must be done with a process in place, in accordance with the law and with accountability. It is clearly evident from the past few weeks that we don’t have the right process in place right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outrage over the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown in Minnesota, especially over the shooting of Alex Jeffrey Pretti, the second person killed by federal agents in Minneapolis this month, has only continued to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Trump administration officials have gone on the offensive, calling Pretti, without evidence, a “domestic terrorist” and blaming Democrats and protesters for heightening tensions. But some Republican lawmakers have raised concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big questions now for businesses, both in Minnesota and nationwide, is what the economic and moral fallout might be — and whether to say anything about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some business leaders are speaking out. The C.E.O.s of more than 60 big Minnesota companies (including Target, Best Buy, 3M and Cargill) on Sunday issued a public letter, shared by the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce, calling for “an immediate de-escalation of tensions” in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The executives wrote that they had been in touch with federal, state and local officials — but didn’t call for specific action or condemn the shooting of Pretti. (Nor did they call on protesters to change their behavior.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Josh Bolten, the head of the Business Roundtable, the influential collection of national business leaders, then said in a separate statement that he supported the Minnesota letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other prominent figures have been more forceful, as Business Insider noted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Dean, the chief scientist of Google DeepMind, called the Pretti shooting “absolutely shameful,” blaming federal agents for “unnecessarily escalating, and then executing a defenseless citizen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Dyett, a senior executive at OpenAI, said that there was more outrage from tech executives over California’s proposed wealth tax “than masked ICE agents terrorizing communities and executing civilians in the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Calacanis, the investor and podcast host, wrote that “our leaders are failing us” by not defusing tensions, adding that President Trump “really needs to fire his immigration team.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s the economic fallout? Many local Minneapolis businesses had already closed on Friday, before Pretti was killed, in solidarity with protests in the Twin Cities area. But it’s unclear whether there will be more sustained pressure campaigns on businesses nationwide over their response, or lack of one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Target knows the cost of political pressure, having taken heat over its rollback of D.E.I. programs and over some Pride Month merchandise. (Some workers have skipped shifts to protest detentions of fellow employees.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a potentially bigger showdown looming. Top Democratic lawmakers vowed to oppose government funding legislation that would provide $64.4 billion for the Department of Homeland Security, including $10 billion for ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senate Republicans are examining whether to separate out the homeland security funding from the rest of the bill to avoid a partial federal shutdown this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. dollar slumps, while gold and the yen soar. The greenback hit a four-month low and gold reached a record on Monday, as traders speculated that the New York Fed and Tokyo could jointly intervene to bolster Japan’s currency and bond market. Given the highly unusual nature of such a move, analysts are forecasting more market volatility that could weaken the dollar further as the “sell America” debate continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.U. regulators announce an investigation into Elon Musk’s X. The authorities said on Monday that the social network did not do enough to prevent users from abusing the Grok chatbot to digitally disrobe images of women and children. It’s the latest legal run-in between X and the European Union over the bloc’s tough content rules, but this one could drastically escalate a clash between the Trump administration, its backers in Silicon Valley and Brussels over European digital regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed and tech earnings are in focus this week. The central bank is expected to leave interest rates unchanged at its meeting on Wednesday. But expect Jay Powell, the Fed chair, to field questions on the institution’s independence amid President Trump’s attacks. Elsewhere, investors will scrutinize the latest quarterly results from Meta and Microsoft (on Wednesday) and Apple (Thursday), over the costs of their artificial intelligence work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the fatal shootings by federal agents in Minneapolis, and the protests and vigils that came after, the fallout from President Trump’s immigration crackdown was risky for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s moves to cut university research funding and increase the price of a key employment visa have already prompted some overseas students and professionals to rethink pursuing a career in the U.S., Vivienne Walt reports. Many American business leaders fear the effects could outlast Trump, and put the country at a competitive disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re potentially losing access to the best and brightest minds from around the world who have emigrated to America, who have created just a tremendous number of jobs,” Ken Griffin, the C.E.O. of Citadel and a prominent Republican donor, said last week at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. “The majority of the A.I. start-ups are run by either immigrants or the children of immigrants,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wall Street and Big Tech are especially worried about Trump’s H-1B visa policy. The temporary permit for highly skilled workers has kick-started several American success stories, like those of Elon Musk and Sundar Pichai, Google’s C.E.O.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a new rule finalized last month, the Department of Homeland Security has lifted the application fee for an H-1B visa to $100,000, from as low as $2,000 fee, and has drastically limited how many it will approve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Chamber of Commerce sued the government in October, arguing that smaller businesses could not afford the new fee. It lost in court last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy change has already scrambled recruitment efforts. Tech companies and Wall Street firms have shifted some jobs abroad, especially to Mumbai and Bengaluru in India, hotbeds of artificial intelligence talent. The Indian government has introduced tax breaks and other incentives to attract high-skilled workers returning from the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is making India self-reliant,” Ankita Singh, an immigration lawyer in New Delhi, told DealBook. “Students who used to go to the U.S. are able to work for global employers in India.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other countries, including in Europe, hope to capitalize, too. “Europe sees this as a great opportunity to attract talent that would otherwise go to the U.S.,” Jasmijn Slootjes, a deputy director at the Migration Policy Institute, told DealBook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Travel chaos, power outages across multiple states, businesses and schools closed: Much of the U.S. has been paralyzed by a monster winter storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the deep freeze is not over yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the latest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 17 states, from New Mexico to New Hampshire, were blanketed with snow, with more than a foot of accumulation in some areas, according to preliminary figures from the National Weather Service. New York and Toronto were hit particularly hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The snow is expected to taper off in the coming hours, but more than 85 million people are under an extreme cold warning on Monday. About 830,000 homes and businesses in the U.S. are without power, mostly in the South.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airlines have canceled more than 4,000 flights on Monday, according to FlightAware. Sunday’s cancellations approached levels last seen in the early days of the coronavirus pandemic in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic cost is expected to soar. The storm could inflict up to $115 billion of damage and loss, according to AccuWeather. (Winter-related insurance losses have steadily increased in recent years.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm has slammed natural gas production in the U.S., pushing natural gas prices to above $6.20 per million British thermal units on Monday, a multiyear high. It could be a major test for data centers and other power-hungry businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the temperature dips, demand for power is expected to climb more broadly, raising the risks for more outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How have New York and its new mayor fared? The storm was seen as an early test of Zohran Mamdani’s nascent administration. So far, even critics are giving him a decent grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans are deeply pessimistic about their economic future, a new Times/Siena poll finds. Essentials of a middle class life — housing and education — have become so expensive that a majority of Americans feels they are no longer affordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conundrum was a dominant theme during the 2024 elections, and it is expected to loom over the midterms as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the report:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rising costs have shifted perceptions of America as a place of upward economic mobility dominated by a comfortable middle class. Two-thirds of voters said they now think a middle-class lifestyle is out of reach for most people, and 77 percent say it has gotten harder to achieve than a generation ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has taken notice. In recent weeks, he has announced a slew of executive orders and made a number of social media posts aimed at addressing the rising cost of living, after playing down the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s proposals carry major ramifications for the business world. Banks say a 10 percent cap on credit card interest rates, which the president called for this month, would clobber the lending industry. And he has moved to bar Wall Street investors from buying single-family homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president has also requested that Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the government-controlled finance firms, buy up to $200 billion in mortgage-backed bonds. Experts predict that could nudge 30-year mortgage rates lower, but that it would not be a panacea for many house hunters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The silver lining for corporations? There are doubts the president’s proposals will lead to legislative action. If that changes, new lobbying battles await.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shares in USA Rare Earth soared in premarket trading on a report that the Trump administration will take a 10 percent stake in the Oklahoma-based miner. (FT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SoftBank is said to have ended talks to buy Switch, a U.S. data center operator, and Merck has reportedly ended takeover discussions with Revolution Medicines. (Bloomberg, WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics, policy and regulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volkswagen says it is reconsidering plans for an Audi factory in the U.S. over concerns about President Trump’s tariffs. (Bloomberg)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hochul is poised to welcome Waymo. Mamdani may be a different story.” (Politico)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of the rest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia University has named its fourth president in three years: Jennifer Mnookin, a legal scholar who is the current chancellor at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Man Who Almost Replaced Warren Buffett” (WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d like your feedback! Please email thoughts and suggestions to dealbook@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/dealbook/business-leaders-minnesota-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 04:31:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New Videos of the Beckham Feud Are Fake. Nobody Seems to Care.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/brooklyn-beckham-victoria-feud-ai-videos-dancing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/00Beckham-AI-jqml/00Beckham-AI-jqml-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brooklyn Beckham left a few things out when he publicly cut ties with his famous family this week, but it took the internet just a few hours to concoct fake evidence to fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The eldest son of David Beckham, a former British soccer star, and Victoria Beckham, a fashion designer and former Spice Girl, blasted his parents in a series of Instagram Stories on Monday night. A key accusation: that the power duo had repeatedly tried to sabotage Brooklyn’s relationship with his wife, Nicola Peltz, the daughter of the billionaire investor Nelson Peltz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media users were enthralled by the drama, an age-old response to the spectacle of public discord in the ranks of the rich and beautiful. This time, though, the audience didn’t wait for verified evidence to be released or leaked. Instead, people took control of the narrative by using artificial intelligence to imagine what might have happened behind closed doors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brooklyn claimed, for example, that his mother “danced very inappropriately” with him at his wedding in 2022 — a situation that has not been publicly corroborated by authentic footage from the event. Into the void came a slew of realistic A.I. clips purporting to show Victoria shimmying, leaping, flailing, gyrating and recreating movie scenes from “Saturday Night Fever” and “Pulp Fiction” at the wedding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The A.I. videos and images offered an entertaining and plausible — though phony — glimpse into the Beckhams’ personal lives. Many people, their curiosity sated, did not seem to care that the content was fake. Users left comments sprinkled with laughing emojis, like “they keep getting better and better” and “the first acceptable use of A.I. I’ve ever seen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Beckhams did not respond to requests for comment. Brooklyn and Nicola admired people’s creativity, according to a person close to the couple, who was speaking anonymously because of the sensitivity of the situation. But the couple felt that A.I. renderings could not capture the reality of how poorly they say they were treated by Brooklyn’s family, the person said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are people who are hungry for a particular kind of content, and if you can create that content for them, they will eat it up,” said Kristian J. Hammond, a computer science professor and A.I. expert at Northwestern University. “Here’s a moment where, if you want to believe it, you will, and those are the moments where we have to resist.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With A.I. becoming increasingly accessible, famous people are irresistible — and easy — targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, a celebrity gets the digital treatment without his or her consent. Social media users are turning to tools with names like Nano Banana Pro to generate convincing selfies with Hollywood stars (think Leonardo DiCaprio and Kate Winslet on the “Titanic” set, or at a party with three recent “Spider-Man” actors).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resulting content is not always harmless. Such technology has also been used to undress famous people or to place them in sexual situations. After the conservative activist Charlie Kirk was assassinated, A.I.-generated musical tributes from artists with avowedly different political views — among them Adele, Eminem and Lady Gaga — surfaced on YouTube, according to the Poynter Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To many people who have been breathlessly following the Beckham feud, it is clear that the A.I. images of the family are not real (though social media users have filled comment sections with surprise at how convincing the content seems). The internet has devoured the posts, with some racking up hundreds of thousands of views. In the absence of actual footage, the A.I. renderings of Victoria and Brooklyn could become the default images of the dance, experts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Scottish digital artist known professionally as Hey Reilly used a mix of A.I. programs and Photoshop to create a series of Beckham images that has been liked more than 1.5 million times on Instagram. He wrote in an email that visualizing the wedding was “just a fundamentally funny idea” and noted that much of his work is “very obviously ridiculous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If someone thinks the aim is to fool people, they’re missing the point entirely,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Beckhams’ case, A.I. can produce whatever juicy details the public demands, even if they are inaccurate. The synthetic versions of Victoria and Nicola, many of them clad in the actual dresses they wore to the nuptials, scratch the internet’s itch for answers, and allow people to move on to their next fixation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casey Fiesler, an associate professor of information science at the University of Colorado Boulder, described the A.I. dance posts as a sort of visual fan fiction, similar to the content that is created to bridge missing scenes in books and films, to illustrate courtroom sessions or even to depict historical events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Dr. Fiesler said she was concerned about people who did not care at all whether the content was real. Disinformation researchers and fact checkers have raised alarm in recent years over a growing state of disinterest in facts, especially in a world where the White House posts manipulated images of real people, and politicians declare that the emotional impact of images is more important than their authenticity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I worry that we can get to a kind of learned helplessness in this information ecosystem where it’s like, ‘I’m never going to be able to know whether anything’s real anymore, so why bother?’” Dr. Fiesler said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If that’s the case,” she added, “then there’s an argument that even small things or things that seem frivolous are just, over time, wearing us down.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/brooklyn-beckham-victoria-feud-ai-videos-dancing.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:32:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Media Holds Its Apocalypse at Bay, for Now</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/npr-pbs-stations-funding.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/STATIONS-1-01-fzkm/STATIONS-1-01-fzkm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things looked bleak last summer for KCAW, a tiny public radio station serving the remote community of Sitka, Alaska (population 8,393).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress had just slashed $500 million in funding for public media, blowing a $187,500 hole in the station’s budget. Mariana Robertson, the station’s general manager, said she had faced a potential “doomsday” situation that included cutting staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the donations poured in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Ms. Robertson is one of many station directors across America who find themselves in unexpected territory: first, expecting the worst, but then buoyed by a flood of emergency funding that has kept their stations stable and surviving. For now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a huge success story, and we’re so grateful and thrilled,” Ms. Robertson said. “But the future is unclear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When government funding disappeared from public media last year, experts predicted dire consequences for scores of stations. According to one estimate, 78 public radio stations and 37 TV stations were at risk of going dark as a result of the cuts. President Trump recently said NPR and PBS had “closed up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But six months after the funding cuts, few public TV or radio stations have closed their doors. Many have scraped together a patchwork of funding from concerned donors, philanthropies or government grants. Others, facing insurmountable budget issues, have resorted to mergers with bigger stations to stay online. NPR and PBS have not gone anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the country’s public media system — more than 1,000 radio and TV stations, serving millions of people — remains largely intact, despite the disappearance of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is not a lot of celebrating among public media executives and supporters. Much of the angst about the long-term future remains. They point out that much of the money making up for the loss in federal funding has come from one-off donations and grants — short-term fixes — that may have managed only to defer the true financial pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not out of the woods at all,” said Tim Isgitt, chief executive of Public Media Company, a nonprofit that has stepped in to provide $30 million in emergency funding to rescue public TV and radio stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several stations teetered on the edge of insolvency when they applied for and received funding through the Public Media Bridge Fund, the program administered by Mr. Isgitt’s company. But the fund is not designed to be a long-term solution. Mr. Isgitt said it was designed to give jeopardized stations time to transition to a more sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those recipients is KWMR, a public radio station based in the coastal hamlet of Point Reyes Station, Calif. Amanda Eichstaedt, the station’s manager and executive director, scrambled to adjust for a 26 percent budget cut this summer, which she feared would result in a staff reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But listeners “really stepped up,” Ms. Eichstaedt said. They started a “25 to stay alive” campaign that aimed to patch together the quarter of the budget that had been snatched by Congress. Ultimately, they pitched in roughly $150,000, making up for the lost government money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tsunami of donations to public media stations last year resulted in an increase of roughly $300 million from the year before, with new donors growing by about 84 percent, said Michal Heiplik, president and chief executive of the Contributor Development Partnership, a firm that analyzes public media fund-raising data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other changes also helped stabilize stations: NPR and PBS reduced fees for members, some stations tapped cash reserves and others laid off employees to avoid going out of business, Mr. Heiplik said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not ready to declare a win, but the increase in community support is very encouraging,” Mr. Heiplik said. “There needs to be a lot more that is done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of Native American tribal stations, considered by many to be among the most vulnerable, received funding from the Bureau of Indian Affairs. But that funding is projected to last only through the end of this year, said Loris Taylor, the president and chief executive of Native Public Media. After that, 36 of the stations in Ms. Taylor’s network will have to fill an $11 million gap with a mix of fund-raising, emergency grants and other revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So far, none of the stations are closing their doors,” Ms. Taylor said. “They are continuing to provide service to their communities, but it’s not because the system is suddenly stable. It’s because our stations are drawing on short-term stopgaps.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option for struggling stations is combining with a more well-funded organization. That was the plan announced late last year at WPSU, a PBS and NPR station based at Pennsylvania State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university initially said the station would shut down because of financial challenges exacerbated by government defunding. Ultimately, the university’s board of trustees approved a plan to transfer WPSU’s assets to WHYY, the public media powerhouse in the Philadelphia area behind shows such as “Fresh Air.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill Marrazzo, the chief executive of WHYY, said Congress’s decision to claw back funding was forcing public media leaders to grapple with business model challenges they would have had to reckon with eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The rescission certainly accelerated the point where that kind of thinking needs to occur,” Mr. Marrazzo said. “But in my mind, as a business matter, it’s inevitable.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/media/npr-pbs-stations-funding.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:45:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Power Outages Could Rise as Freezing Temperatures Persist</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/energy-environment/storm-electric-grid-power-outages.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26biz-grid-storm-mfzc/26biz-grid-storm-mfzc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As wintry conditions and frigid temperatures gripped much of the United States this weekend, the nation’s power system has avoided buckling like it has in past years. But the system continued to face severe strain early Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of thousands of residents and businesses largely in the southern parts of the country had no electricity. Most of those outages resulted from the typical challenges that accompany winter storms: snow piling up on electrical equipment and ice dangling from branches and power lines, causing them to snap. And with temperatures below freezing and demand for electricity expected to stay high, outages could very likely expand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The storm this weekend blanketed wide parts of the nation under more than a foot of snow in some places and sheets of ice in others. Some weather models are predicting another storm, but meteorologists have cautioned that the forecast was hypothetical and should not be treated as a certainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This next wave of ice that may be coming in is going to test the system even further,” said Calvin Butler, the chief executive of Exelon, which owns regulated utilities in New Jersey, Maryland, Delaware, Pennsylvania and Illinois. “All that ice, they’re just not used to it,” he said, referring to the Southeast. “We’re more used to hurricanes in the Southeast.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explosive winter storm that moved from the Southwest to the Northeast comes as electric grids struggle to manage a staggering rise in electricity demand from data centers, some of which support the development of artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first major test of the power system’s resilience during a potent winter storm in the era of huge data center expansion. In an unusual move, the Department of Energy late Sunday ordered the manager of Texas’ main electric grid, the Electric Reliability Council of Texas, to direct data centers and other facilities that consume a lot of energy to begin using backup generators in an effort to prevent blackouts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other grid operators, ERCOT issued weather alerts ahead of the storm but expected conditions on the system to remain normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Texas experienced a widespread electric grid failure during a severe winter storm in February 2021 that killed more than 200 people. Energy companies in the state have since added more batteries, power plants and other resources, but industry experts said the state still had work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the fourth once-in-a-hundred-year winter storm in ERCOT in 25 years,” said Robert McCullough, of McCullough Research, a consulting firm in Portland, Ore. “We are forecasting poorly and preparing even worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Edison Electric Institute, a utility industry organization, is coordinating responses to the winter storm with executives of power companies across the country. That has helped utilities deploy 65,000 lineman and other workers to respond to power outages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People and trucks are rolling across the country, even throughout this weather to help people,” Mr. Butler of Exelon said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/energy-environment/storm-electric-grid-power-outages.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:56:50 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>