<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 11:20:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What to Know About Bilt’s New Rewards Program for Mortgage and Rent Payments</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/business/bilt-rent-mortgage-rewards.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/business/14bilt/14bilt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many rewards programs attract high-spending travelers with promises of access and premium status, Bilt came onto the scene in 2021 with a more basic appeal: earning rewards for paying rent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Millions signed on, and now the company is ushering homeowners into its club. Starting Feb. 7, mortgage holders can earn points on their monthly payments. Bilt is also introducing three credit cards and has recently added a rewards currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the most complicated rewards system we’ve seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our personal finance editor has the older Bilt card, and he and Ron are Bilt members. Even so, it took the three of us scores of Slack messages to sort out the details of what Bilt introduced on Wednesday. To top it off, Bilt is taking a page from lawmakers’ playbooks and capping interest rates at 10 percent on new purchases for the first year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buzz ahead of the big reveal, which the company previewed in recent weeks, had also prompted speculation. Some tech-savvy Bilt obsessives had managed to dig up the company’s plans — and rumors began flying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chatter reached Bilt’s New York headquarters, resulting in one executive’s going on Instagram to try to calm users’ concerns over possible transaction fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loyalty rewards calculations are often mind-numbing, and Bilt’s are about to reach new heights. Ankur Jain, the billionaire founder who raised about $750 million from backers including Blackstone, General Catalyst and the Vanderbilt endowment, talked to us about what’s changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we’ve learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilt made its initial splash by allowing renters to accrue points through their rent payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Bilt is different from the typical credit card rewards program in that it wants to be known as a loyalty and payments platform where you can earn points for everyday spending — even without a Bilt credit card. It also wants local merchants to see it as the most efficient way to micro-target customers on a block-by-block basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After joining as a member, you can earn points through spending at one of Bilt’s 45,000 participating partners, from neighborhood restaurants and gyms to Walgreens and Lyft. Users just need to link an existing credit or debit card, or do other things like connect their Venmo accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who have one of Bilt’s credit cards have more opportunities to earn points. More on that in a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilt deals in two forms of currency: Bilt points and Bilt cash, which is new. Starting this year, members receive $50 in Bilt cash for every 25,000 Bilt points they earn. Bilt cash comes on top of your points — one does not replace the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And customers can redeem Bilt cash within the platform’s ecosystem; $10 in Bilt cash yields a $10 credit for a Lyft ride, for example, or maybe lunch at a neighborhood restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A maximum of $100 in Bilt cash — which comes with seven pages of fine print — can carry over at the end of each year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers can generally earn points on everyday purchases using most non-Bilt-card forms of payment, and they’re largely redeemed for travel and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want to be a commerce platform for where you live, where you get all these benefits in and around your home,” said Mr. Jain, who in 2024 brought in American Express’s former chief Ken Chenault as chairman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said the company tried to make the loyalty point conversions simple for travel: 1,000 Bilt points is typically equivalent to 1,000 United Airlines miles, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the changes, renters could rack up points on their monthly rent — one point for every dollar — when they used their Bilt card for five transactions. Plenty of users took advantage, and an inside joke emerged: Renters can buy a bunch of bananas, in five transactions, and meet the minimum threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, Bilt cardholders need to reach a certain amount of spending before they can begin to earn points on housing via the card (up to one point for every $1 of on your monthly rent or mortgage).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where it gets complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a Bilt card, you receive 4 percent in Bilt cash back on everyday spend — for every $1 spent, for example, you get 4 cents in Bilt cash. And for every $30 in Bilt cash customers earn, they can redeem it for 1,000 points from their rent or mortgage payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three new cards, one named for a rare metal and another for volcanic glass. All cards earn 4 percent in Bilt cash on everyday spending, carry no foreign exchange fees and come with various sign-up bonuses and other perks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilt Palladium. With a $495 annual fee, this premium card will inevitably compete with the likes of Chase Sapphire Reserve and Capital One Venture X Rewards Credit Card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilt Obsidian. Cardholders pay a $95 annual fee and receive three points for every dollar spent on groceries (up to $25,000 per year) or dining, as well as two points on travel and one point on all other spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilt Blue. This no-annual-fee card generates one point for every dollar spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not exactly. You can get as much as one point for every dollar of mortgage, rent or monthly condo or other similar maintenance fees, but the money you spend on those things will come out of your bank account quickly. So you won’t pay interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of Bilt as a bill-paying platform in this context, where the housing payment doesn’t count against your available credit on your card. The company is hoping that points-for-mortgage-payments will be enough to pull big spenders into its larger ecosystem — and keep them out of the clutches of rival companies like Chase and American Express.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company has been doing this with rent for a few years, including printing paper checks and sending them to landlords when necessary. But doing business with any start-up has risks. As with any new payment system that you switch to — including long-established ones — it’s prudent to check that your important bills are getting paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, some Citibank customers who signed up for its Strata Elite credit card experienced big problems. A Wall Street Journal report on its troubles is harrowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jain was not dismissive of the idea that people might want to wait to see how Bilt handles its card launch. But he did note that landlords trust Bilt with their payments. And United Wholesale Mortgage doesn’t want people’s monthly payments disappearing into the ether if Bilt’s systems fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If big landlords and mortgage companies trust Bilt to help them collect payments, he said, consumers will probably trust the company with their monthly spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe. Partner merchants pay for a decent fraction of the cost of the Bilt cash. And Bilt makes money from landlords and mortgage issuers, in addition to what it generates from the usual credit-card company revenue sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, loyalty programs generally become less generous over time. Right now, Bilt is in the business of acquiring customers, fast, to try to justify and build on its $10.75 billion valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any card company and minter of loyalty currency, higher annual fees and devalued points in the future are real possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/business/bilt-rent-mortgage-rewards.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:33:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Banks Are So Worried About a 10% Credit Card Rate Cap</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/business/trump-credit-card-interest-rate-cap-banks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/14biz-creditcards-2-hglt/14biz-creditcards-2-hglt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks and lenders have been in a tizzy ever since President Trump posted on social media Friday night calling for a one-year 10 percent cap on credit card interest rates. Those fees are a major profit source for card issuers, which for decades have fought legislative attempts to curb them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the president’s call seems to be more of a wish than a mandate: There is no obvious pathway for his administration to unilaterally impose an interest cap, and Congress has shown little interest in heeding his request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bank leaders and industry lobbyists are dancing around the topic, trying to avoid publicly disparaging the president’s decree while privately insisting that it would backfire by limiting consumers’ access to credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, banks stocks have been hammered this week, particularly those with large credit card businesses like Capital One; its shares are down 7 percent since Mr. Trump’s post. Citi is down nearly 8 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If lending is less profitable, banks say, they will be forced to slash credit lines and curb their credit-card offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capping rates is “probably not a great idea,” said Jamie Dimon, the chief executive of JPMorgan Chase, which has the nation’s largest share of outstanding balances. “It’ll raise inflation expectations and probably increase rates over time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal and financial experts say a federal credit-card interest cap would almost certainly require Congress to act — and so far, there’s no sign that Republican leaders are interested in doing so. Speaker Mike Johnson threw cold water on the president’s plan, saying it could have a “negative effect on a lot of people” because credit card companies may choose to cut off lending to some consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, should the White House make a legislative push, there is some support in Congress on both sides of the aisle. Senators Bernie Sanders of Vermont and Josh Hawley of Missouri introduced a bill last year to cap fees at 10 percent for several years. Without the president’s support, the bill stalled, but it could be revived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Senator Elizabeth Warren of Massachusetts spoke about her economic vision for the Democratic Party. The president called her shortly after and discussed his desire to cap card rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I said, ‘Great, let’s get something done,’” she said Wednesday on CNBC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After calling for rate limits on the campaign trail, Mr. Trump “had not lifted a finger to try to get something through,” Ms. Warren said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump could try to force the issue with an executive order, but that would be quickly met by lawsuits from credit card companies. And the president can’t lean on the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, the federal agency that is tasked with protecting consumers but that his administration has largely gutted. Under the Dodd-Frank Act, the agency is prohibited from establishing “usury limits” — or interest rate caps — without an act of Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credit card debt in the United States now exceeds $1.21 trillion, and about 37 percent of American adults carry a credit card balance, according to data from the Federal Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Average interest rates have been trending up over the past two decades, to 22 percent in November. If those rates were brought down to 10 percent, consumers could save $100 billion a year, or about $899 per person, according to an analysis by researchers at Vanderbilt University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cap would serve a heavy blow to banks and other credit card lenders’ bottom line, analysts and researchers said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry brought in $160 billion from interest fees in 2024, according to an analysis by the consumer bureau — up more than 50 percent from the $105 billion lenders collected in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s more than financial giants made from other major profit areas like stock trading gains and commissions. Big banks collectively made $133 billion from their market trading in 2023, according to an analysis by two researchers at the Federal Reserve Bank of Boston and Harvard Business School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capital One, for example, made $22 billion in interest from its credit card business in 2024. A 10 percent cap would wipe out half of those earnings, estimated Michael Miller, an analyst at Morningstar, a financial services firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The lending model just doesn’t work in terms of mass-market credit cards at a 10 percent cap on interest rates,” Mr. Miller said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks warn that a cap would mean that they would have to cut back on the amount of credit they offered rather than lend money at a loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People will lose access to credit, like on a very, very extensive and broad basis, especially the people who need it the most, honestly,” Jeremy Barnum, the chief financial officer of JPMorgan, said on the company’s earnings call on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Santomassimo, the chief financial officer for Wells Fargo, offered a similar sentiment to reporters Wednesday morning, saying that “there would be significant negative impact of credit availability for a wide spectrum of people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some researchers point out that there are ways for the banks to issue credit cards with lower rates and still make money. In a 2025 analysis from the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, researchers concluded that marketing costs were a major factor in driving up rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Credit card banks spend an average of 1 to 2 percent of assets annually on marketing — 10 times the proportion spent by other banks,” the researchers wrote. “The largest credit card banks rank among the world’s top marketers, with budgets comparable to consumer giants like Nike and Coca-Cola.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanderbilt University suggested in an analysis that with a 10 percent cap, lenders could choose to decrease marketing budgets instead of credit lines while still making a profit. In that scenario, a reduction in credit availability would affect only the riskiest borrowers — those with a FICO score of 600 or below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banks warn that in an attempt to increase affordability for average Americans, the White House may end up denying credit to households that are struggling financially and push them to alternatives, like payday lenders, that may charge even steeper rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks are steeling for a fight should the president try to turn his call into legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five major trade groups put out a public statement last week saying they “share the president’s goal of helping Americans access more affordable credit.” But, the groups said, “evidence shows that a 10 percent interest rate cap would reduce credit availability and be devastating for millions of American families and small-business owners who rely on and value their credit cards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Banks and their lobbyists will continue to fight in public and private, said Erika Najarian, an analyst at UBS. They will warn borrowers that a cap would limit credit availability; privately, she said, they may offer Washington concessions in exchange for dropping the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said he wanted the cap to take effect on Jan. 20 — the first anniversary of the start of his second term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With less than a week to go until that deadline, no major lender has voluntarily slashed its rates. And with Congress showing no urgency to make legislative moves, industry analysts think the most likely outcome is that the president’s call will go unanswered, at least for now.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/business/trump-credit-card-interest-rate-cap-banks.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 15:33:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Biggest U.S. Crypto Company Asserts Its Power in Washington</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/coinbase-crypto-bill-clarity-act.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15biz-coinbase-kpth/15biz-coinbase-kpth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major cryptocurrency bill was headed for a committee vote in the Senate on Thursday after months of negotiations, a crucial step in the legislative process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came a social media post from the top executive of Coinbase, the largest U.S. crypto company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Coinbase unfortunately can’t support the bill as written,” Brian Armstrong, chief executive of Coinbase, posted on X Wednesday evening. “This version would be materially worse than the current status quo. We’d rather have no bill than a bad bill.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within hours, the Senate vote was canceled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fate of a hotly contested legislative vote typically hinges on a few key lawmakers who are the moderate voices in a partisan scuffle. But what happened this week to the landmark crypto bill shows how much power Coinbase now wields in Washington, with the crypto industry newly ascendant under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, congressional staff had worked on the Clarity Act, a nearly 300-page bill designed to establish a regulatory framework for virtually every aspect of crypto, with rules the industry helped write. But at the last minute, Mr. Armstrong objected to proposed language that threatened to outlaw one of Coinbase’s products and said that the bill would assign too much authority to the Securities and Exchange Commission, the nation’s top financial regulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coinbases’s decisive intervention follows years of the company’s work to build a voice in Washington. A publicly traded firm worth nearly $70 billion, Coinbase helped finance a network of PACs that spent more than $130 million to influence congressional races in 2024, aiming to elect pro-crypto legislators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The barrage of political spending sent an unmistakable message to Congress: Anyone who crosses the crypto industry could become a target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the industry’s leading firms have leverage to push for their interests. “Coinbase has played its hand very well,” said Todd Phillips, a finance expert at Georgia State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A representative for Coinbase did not offer a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 2012, Coinbase provides a marketplace for people to buy, sell and store cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Ether. Anyone can log onto the app and make a purchase with a few clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t long ago, though, that the company faced a much tougher landscape in Washington. In 2023, the S.E.C. sued Coinbase for operating as an unregistered exchange, part of the Biden administration’s broad-reaching crackdown on crypto. Mr. Armstrong, who had co-founded the company, attacked the S.E.C. for “regulation by enforcement” and called for more “clarity around crypto rules.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s election in 2024 changed everything. Shortly before taking office, he and his sons started a crypto business, and Mr. Trump proclaimed that he would make the United States the “crypto capital of the planet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within weeks of Mr. Trump’s inauguration, the S.E.C. dropped its cases against Coinbase and other crypto firms. The industry pushed for legislation that would enshrine that regulatory pullback in law, preventing a future administration from reviving the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, with the administration’s support, the House passed its version of the Clarity Act, which essentially adopted the crypto industry’s concept for a new regulatory system. The bill would make it much easier for crypto firms like Coinbase to declare that digital currencies are not securities subject to the system of federal oversight designed to protect investors and markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the legislation faced hurdles in the Senate. In the fall, Senate Democrats proposed strict rules on decentralized finance, a branch of the crypto world, prompting outrage in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, banking lobbyists pushed for language to prevent crypto exchanges like Coinbase from paying interest to people who own stablecoins, a type of digital currency designed to maintain a price of $1. They argued that the exchanges would undermine banks by providing a product that competed with traditional deposit accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue soon became a sticking point for Coinbase. A ban on interest could compromise one of its revenue sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The way you compete is that you offer these types of incentive programs,” said Kara Calvert, a top policy executive at Coinbase. “It’s absolutely critical.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Senate’s most recent draft of the Clarity Act was unveiled close to midnight on Monday. Congressional staff members and crypto executives rushed to comb through it before the Senate committee meeting scheduled for Thursday, known as a markup, where senators would have a chance to introduce amendments to the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the markup fast approaching, Mr. Armstrong said that he was pulling his support, even as other crypto executives posted messages of support for the legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday night, Senator Tim Scott of South Carolina, the Republican chairman of the Senate Banking Committee, said the markup would be postponed to an unspecified date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everyone remains at the table working in good faith,” he said in a statement. “The goal is to deliver clear rules of the road that protect consumers, strengthen our national security and ensure the future of finance is built in the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sharon LaFraniere contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/coinbase-crypto-bill-clarity-act.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:30:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>WestJet Backpedals on Economy Seats That Don’t Recline</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/travel/westjet-non-reclinable-economy-seats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16trav-westjet-seats-zbtv/16trav-westjet-seats-zbtv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
WestJet had narrowed the distance between one row of seats and the next to 28 inches from about 30 inches.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/travel/westjet-non-reclinable-economy-seats.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:25:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Edison Files Claims Against Los Angeles County and Others on Eaton Fire</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/energy-environment/southern-california-edison-eaton-fire.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16biz-edison-lawsuit-jclq/16biz-edison-lawsuit-jclq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Eaton fire killed 19 people and destroyed more than 9,400 buildings in Southern California.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/energy-environment/southern-california-edison-eaton-fire.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 15:26:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Black Women Turn to One Another as Their Career Paths Suddenly Recede</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/black-women-job-market-hiring-careers-dei.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17biz-black-women-professionals-obiekwe-lqpt/17biz-black-women-professionals-obiekwe-lqpt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Nneka Obiekwe started a chat group for Black women professionals looking for work. Within 24 hours, 500 people had joined.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/black-women-job-market-hiring-careers-dei.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:00:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Office Rents Rise, Doctors Get Creative</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/doctors-office-leasing-rent.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/00BIZ-OFFICE-AFTER-HOURS-1-bmcj/00BIZ-OFFICE-AFTER-HOURS-1-bmcj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Dr. Zarui Chopuryan, an aesthetic medicine provider, working with a patient in her office in New York, N.Y.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/doctors-office-leasing-rent.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:00:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Punched in the Face’ by a Rail Disaster, an Ohio Town Fights Its Way Back</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/east-palestine-norfolk-southern-derailment.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/08/multimedia/00biz-east-palestine-vid01-kcvq/00biz-east-palestine-vid01-kcvq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents and officials are still trying to revitalize East Palestine nearly three years after a derailment and chemical burn.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/east-palestine-norfolk-southern-derailment.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:00:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tech Firms Are Persuading Retailers to Put A.I. Everywhere</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/tech-firms-ai-retailers.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19biz-ai-retail-B1/16biz-ai-retail-tfql-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
John Furner, incoming chief executive of Walmart, left, and Sundar Pichai, Google’s leader, said at a conference in New York City this week that the two companies would use artificial intelligence to change how all businesses sold their products.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/tech-firms-ai-retailers.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:02:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Least $110,000 Worth of Pokémon Cards Stolen From New York Store</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/nyregion/pokemon-card-shop-robbery-new-york.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16xp-pokemon-wbph/16xp-pokemon-wbph-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Three robbers burst into a Pokémon card shop in Lower Manhattan on Wednesday and stole at least $110,000 worth of merchandise, the store owner said.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/nyregion/pokemon-card-shop-robbery-new-york.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:02:28 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>