<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 00:34:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Minnesota’s Biggest Companies Call for ‘De-escalation’ of Tensions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief executives of Target, Best Buy, General Mills and Cargill were among more than 60 large Minnesota companies to issue a public letter on Sunday calling for an “immediate de-escalation of tensions” in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter marks the first time the most recognizable businesses in Minnesota have weighed in on the turmoil in Minneapolis amid the aggressive crackdown by federal immigration agents, which have sparked widespread protests throughout the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes one day after federal agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti, a nurse at the city’s Veterans Affairs hospital, while he was being restrained on a Minneapolis sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With yesterday’s tragic news, we are calling for an immediate de-escalation of tensions and for state, local and federal officials to work together to find real solutions,” the letter states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was signed by top executives of Minnesota’s largest companies and large hospital systems, including Land O’ Lakes, Hormel, U.S. Bancorp, Mayo Clinic and 3M. It also was signed by local sports teams: the Minnesota Vikings, Minnesota Timberwolves, and the Minnesota Wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is notable because many chief executives have sought to avoid weighing in on any politically charged issues during the second Trump administration. On Friday, hundreds of smaller businesses in the Minneapolis area shut their doors as they backed protests against the actions from Immigration and Customs Enforcement in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was shared by the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce, which represents more than 6,000 businesses across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, Josh Bolten, the chief executive of the Business Roundtable, an association of more than 200 chief executives of America’s leading companies, said in an emailed statement that he supported the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce’s letter. Beth Ford, the chief executive of Land O’ Lakes, sits on the Business Roundtable’s board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until Sunday, the largest companies in Minnesota had not addressed the issue, but in the Chamber of Commerce letter they said they had been in contact with federal, state and local officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The silence by big companies had been a marked contrast from their responses to the killing of George Floyd in Minneapolis in 2020. That murder helped set off a broader corporate movement to fight racism, with executives making public pledges to support diversity initiatives, donate to social justice causes and express solidarity with demonstrators at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the years since, companies have sought to avoid being caught in any political cross hairs, as the country has become more polarized. Many have said they will be more selective about the issues they tackle, sticking only to those that directly affect their business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum last week, once a hotbed for such social issues, there was hardly any public mention by executives of the unrest in Minnesota. The focus was instead on artificial intelligence, deal making and the reshaping of global alliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for some companies, the violence in Minnesota has hit particularly close to home. After immigration agents detained two employees at the Target store in Richfield, Minn., this month, clergy members gathered at the retailer’s headquarters, asking the company to keep immigration agents off its properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every C.E.O. — and I know all these C.E.O.s — they want to have a peaceful environment for their employees,” said Bill George, the former chief executive of Medtronic, whose current chief signed the letter. Mr. George is also a former board member at Target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The larger issue for C.E.O.s,” he added, is that the unrest in Minneapolis “is going to have a very negative effect on their growth, on their innovation and particularly their ability to recruit people from around the country and around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking as a group, as Minnesota executives did Sunday, could help insulate companies from individual attacks from Mr. Trump, said Jeff Sonnenfeld, a professor of leadership studies at the Yale School of Management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can take down companies individually, but when they work collectively, they have immunity,” Mr. Sonnenfeld said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executives similarly relied on the law of numbers in expressing concerns about tariffs, which organizations like the U.S. Chamber of Commerce came out in opposition to last spring. Many companies ultimately struck their own deals with the administration over tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s letter stopped short of calling for specific action nor did the corporations condemn the shooting of Mr. Pretti by the federal agents or call for immigration authorities to rein in their aggressive enforcement. The statement also did not call on protesters to change their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With polls showing voters split along party lines on whether they support President Trump’s immigration crackdown, corporations have been careful not to alienate large numbers of their customers by taking a side. They also risk angering Mr. Trump, who has publicly rebuked companies and executives he believes have crossed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter from the Minnesota companies on Sunday struck a neutral tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In this difficult moment for our community, we call for peace and focused cooperation among local, state and federal leaders to achieve a swift and durable solution that enables families, businesses, our employees, and communities across Minnesota to resume our work to build a bright and prosperous future,” the executives wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alison Taylor, a clinical associate professor of business and society at the N.Y.U. Stern business school, said she thought the companies had no choice but to say something. “They have been backed into a corner, because obviously the situation going on is starting to have commercial consequences,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Taylor added: “Is it better than doing nothing? Probably. Is it sufficient? I don’t think anyone’s going to think this is sufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:53:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Europe’s Reliance on U.S. Natural Gas Grows, So Does Trump’s Leverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Russia invaded Ukraine in 2022, it also tried to squeeze Europe by crimping natural gas flows. But increased shipments of liquid natural gas, much of it from the United States, helped ease the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, smoldering tensions between leaders in Washington and Brussels could turn Europe’s reliance on American natural gas into a similar political pressure point, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve replaced one massive dependency with another one,” said Henning Gloystein, a managing director for energy at Eurasia Group, a political risk research firm. “That looked fine three years ago, but now it doesn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to import large amounts of energy is one of Europe’s strategic weaknesses. Natural gas from Russia was a mainstay for the continent before the invasion of Ukraine. In 2019, for instance, Russian gas accounted for more than half of the European Union’s gas imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The huge volumes of Russian gas that flowed through pipelines across Ukraine and Poland and under the Baltic Sea plummeted in the wake of the assault. Prices soared, putting pressure on consumers, industries and governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States came to the rescue. Tankers loaded at U.S. terminals shipped large volumes of liquefied natural gas to European ports in the Netherlands, France and Belgium, among other destinations, helping to replace the Russian fuel and calming markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the United States had been a modest supplier of natural gas to Europe, with about 5 percent of imports in late 2019, but it has since grown, providing more than a quarter of the European Union’s gas imports in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Bruegel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, those gas flows looked heroic. Now, they are raising eyebrows. Since beginning his second term, President Trump has sought to use trade as leverage in disputes with other countries, including his recent push to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing concern in Europe is that Mr. Trump could turn the strong position that the United States has gained in the oil and gas industry into a weapon to try to coerce other countries. “Recently, people have started to realize we are probably a little bit too dependent on U.S. L.N.G.,” said Anne-Sophie Corbeau, a global research scholar in Paris for the Center on Global Energy Policy at Columbia University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has encouraged this reliance, pushing Europe to increase U.S. imports as part of the trade deal struck with the European Union last year. In 2025, L.N.G. flows from the United States to European Union countries jumped about 60 percent from the previous year, according to Bruegel, a research organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say these volumes are likely to increase. Although Europe invests in renewable energy like wind and solar power, it still requires natural gas for heating homes and manufacturing goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe is also producing less of its own fuel because its existing oil and gas fields are winding down, and countries like Britain, whose petroleum production has fallen sharply, discourage new drilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Europe is without much alternative,” said Christoph Halser, a senior analyst at Rystad Energy, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly in response to American complaints, Europe is also in the process of phasing out its purchases of Russian gas, which fell to around 12 percent of imports in 2025. Norway, which is not a European Union member, is the bloc’s largest gas supplier, accounting for around 30 percent of imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is already the world leader in L.N.G. exports, and developers are spending heavily to build facilities for chilling gas to liquid form and then shipping it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe, which is a relatively short sail from terminals on the Gulf Coast, is a logical destination for these cargoes. China, the world’s largest importer of liquefied natural gas, has largely stopped buying American fuel because of U.S. tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, a bright spot for Europe may be that a supply boom is expected in the coming years, which could bring down what have been relatively high prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in the event of increased political tensions with Europe, some analysts are skeptical that the Trump administration would take steps like reducing shipments that would be contrary to the interests of the U.S. oil and gas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That “would be a very negative market signal, and also significantly impair the competitiveness of the industry, which the administration is committed to supporting,” said David L. Goldwyn, a former U.S. energy special envoy and now president of Goldwyn Global Strategies, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry in the United States also differs markedly from Russia’s. There, the Kremlin was able to use Gazprom, the state-controlled gas monopoly, “to weaponize gas flows in 2022,” Jack Reid, a graduate economist at Oxford Economics, wrote in a recent study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States, he added, is more likely to “redirect flows than bring them to a halt.” Other analysts speculate that Washington might take measures like putting an export tax on gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, though, meddling with gas flows is likely to lead to higher costs and prices, analysts say, which would be bad news for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Import concentration” matters, said Ugne Keliauskaite, a research analyst at Bruegel. “Now Europe is more exposed to U.S.-centered disruptions.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:12:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fed, Signaling Little Urgency, Prepares to Pause on Rate Cuts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-fed-mtlp/27dc-fed-mtlp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Fed, especially its chair, Jerome H. Powell, have been assailed by President Trump for not lowering interest rates fast enough.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:55:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI’s Altman and More C.E.O.s Weigh In on Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27db-altman-fjvm/27db-altman-fjvm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sam Altman, C.E.O. of OpenAI, told employees, “What’s happening with ICE is going too far.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:16:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘The Outsiders’ Musical Recoups on Broadway</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/theater/outsiders-broadway-musical-profit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27cul-outsiders-ckzt/27cul-outsiders-ckzt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The musical, which received four Tony Awards, opened in April 2024 at the Bernard B. Jacobs Theater.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/theater/outsiders-broadway-musical-profit.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:00:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>G.M. Shares Rise as Investors Are Encouraged by 2026 Prospects</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A General Motors factory in Spring Hill, Tenn. G.M. said on Tuesday it planned to introduce a more advanced version of its Super Cruise driver assistance system in 2028.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:22:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meta Campaigns to Change Opinions on Data Centers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;The tech giant has spent more than $6 million on TV ads in state capitals and Washington, with the message that data centers create jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:23:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UPS Will Cut Up to 30,000 Jobs in 2026</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-ups-tlqb/27biz-ups-tlqb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The announcement that UPS was continuing to thin its work force could add to Americans’ concerns about the job market.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:36:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bari Weiss Urges CBS News to Think Like a ‘Start-Up’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Bari Weiss was appointed editor in chief of CBS News last year.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:59:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Begins Assigned Seating, Scrapping a Signature Quirk</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Southwest Airlines commemorated the end of its longstanding open-seating policy with a celebration on Tuesday morning at Orlando International Airport.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:32:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>