<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 03:33:23 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Popularity of ‘Heated Rivalry’ Has Surprised Even TV Executives</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/10/business/media/heated-rivalry-hbo-max-popularity.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/10/multimedia/10biz-heated-rivalry-1-fmvk/10biz-heated-rivalry-1-fmvk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first season of “Heated Rivalry” on HBO Max may have ended two weeks ago, but that has done little to slow the show’s momentum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday afternoon, several dozen people, most of them quite young, gathered around the marquee for “The Tonight Show Starring Jimmy Fallon” in Midtown Manhattan, ready to shout their lungs out. The throng surprised NBC employees — a security guard likened the crowd to when Harry Styles stopped by “The Tonight Show” at the height of his popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was all to catch a glimpse of Hudson Williams, one of the stars of “Heated Rivalry,” who was in the building to appear on Mr. Fallon’s show that night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Heated Rivalry,” a steamy Canadian series about a pair of closeted gay hockey players, has become one of the television industry’s biggest surprises in recent memory. Not because it is a megahit like “Stranger Things” or “Bridgerton” or even “The White Lotus.” In fact, its viewership barely puts it among the top 15 streaming original series in the United States right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What executives didn’t expect was how it took off. The show, which was produced by a Canadian network, Crave, and licensed by HBO Max, premiered in late November to little fanfare and virtually no promotion. Yet “Heated Rivalry” quickly started to generate week-to-week jumps in viewership that are unusual in the streaming era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During its debut week on HBO Max, “Heated Rivalry” accumulated roughly 30 million streaming minutes, a figure that failed to qualify among the 50 most-watched streaming original programs, according to Luminate, a research group. By the week of Dec. 26, when the season’s sixth and final episode was released, time spent streaming the show was up more than tenfold, eclipsing 324 million minutes, Luminate said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That fast growth is “highly unusual,” said Tyler Aquilina, an analyst at Luminate, who compared it to “Baby Reindeer,” an out-of-nowhere hit for Netflix in 2024. “It is rare for a show to build in that way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casey Bloys, the head of HBO Max, who licensed “Heated Rivalry” from Crave, put it this way: “It is clearly a word-of-mouth sensation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show centers on two professional hockey stars — one a Russian, the other a Canadian — and their journey from furtive hookups to a full-blown romance. The many sex scenes have especially been a hit with viewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Heated Rivalry” was created by Jacob Tierney, who wrote and directed every episode, and was adapted from a novel by the same name. The two lead actors — Mr. Williams and Connor Storrie — were unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bloys became aware of the series only a couple of weeks before it was scheduled to premiere in Canada, he said, when a colleague asked if he would like to license it. Mr. Bloys binged it over one weekend in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I couldn’t believe it was available,” he said. “It was a very obvious yes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did not cost HBO Max much, either. The company paid only about $600,000 per episode to license it in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the “hot sex” on the show, Mr. Bloys said, he figured “Heated Rivalry” would “make some noise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But I did not anticipate that it would turn into the kind of the social phenomenon that it is,” he continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually it is Netflix that is “very good at turning these seemingly random shows into overnight sensations,” said Mr. Aquilina, the analyst. Netflix has more engagement than any subscription streaming service in the United States, and features a more powerful recommendation engine than any of its traditional Hollywood competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HBO Max has considerably less viewing time and a recommendation engine nowhere close to that. But attention grew thanks to social media platforms like TikTok, Instagram Reels and X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Heated Rivalry” has hardly slowed down. For the week of Jan. 2, the show was viewed for over 254 million minutes, its second-most-watched week, according to Luminate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, the demographics of the audience have changed. On Dec. 22, four days before the finale streamed, 53 percent of the show’s viewers were female, an HBO spokesman said. By the end of last week, roughly two-thirds of the viewers were women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show stands as a rare success story for a program that centers on gay characters. Other recent series with gay characters, including Netflix’s “Boots” or Hulu’s “Mid-Century Modern,” were canceled after a single season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bloys said that HBO Max would continue to license the show but that all creative decisions would belong to Mr. Tierney and Crave. “They clearly know what they’re doing,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the show’s stars, Mr. Williams and Mr. Storrie, are basking in their newfound fame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both actors will be presenters at the Golden Globes on Sunday night in Beverly Hills, Calif. Then Mr. Storrie will fly cross-country to appear on Seth Meyers’s late-night show on NBC on Monday. Given the unexpected crowd for Mr. Williams’s appearance on “The Tonight Show,” NBCUniversal is preparing to greatly increase security around 30 Rockefeller Plaza on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/10/business/media/heated-rivalry-hbo-max-popularity.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:19:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bird Flu Viruses Raise Mounting Concerns Among Scientists</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/10/health/bird-flu-viruses-health.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/26/multimedia/00-birdflu-02-gplw/00-birdflu-02-gplw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, the term bird flu has become synonymous with a particular virus that has devastated poultry and dairy farms over the past few years. But that virus, called H5N1, is not the only form of bird flu in circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerned scientists are keeping a close eye other types, including a fast-changing flu virus called H9N2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a study published in November, researchers in Hong Kong showed that over the last decade, this virus has acquired mutations that allow it to spread more efficiently among people and to cause more severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H9N2 is often discounted as a threat, because it causes only mild symptoms in poultry. But in people, especially children, the virus can cause more severe illness than the seasonal flu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been fewer than 200 reported cases of H9N2 in humans since 1998, but the number has been rising sharply. China reported 29 human cases of H9N2 last year, compared with 11 in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those numbers, though, are likely to be underestimates, because many infected people are never tested and the virus may spread undetected, Dr. Kelvin To, a clinical microbiologist who led the November study, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If it continues to be widely circulating in poultry, mammals and humans, it may certainly one day evolve into something very serious,” Dr. To said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers like Dr. To have long feared that the next pandemic will be caused by a flu virus, and the new report suggests that mutating H9N2 bears watching. But it is not the only one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H5N1 is “the headline stealer,” said Richard Webby, an influenza expert at St. Jude Children’s Research Hospital in Memphis. It has infected poultry and mammals worldwide, leaving behind economic devastation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, he added, “some of these other subtypes may have just as much, if not more, capacity for human infection and spread than H5N1.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September, health officials in Mexico identified the first human infection of a highly pathogenic bird flu virus called H5N2. The patient was severely ill and hospitalized, but survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in November, a resident of Washington State died of an infection with another type, H5N5, the first human known to have contracted the virus. H5N5 tends to circulate among birds along the Atlantic Coast, so its presence in the West surprised some scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, H5N1 continues to be the primary threat. The virus is reported to have infected 71 people, killing one, and has affected nearly 185 million commercial, backyard and wild birds since January 2022, when it was detected in wild aquatic birds in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since March 2024, when the first dairy cows were found to be infected, H5N1 has also been detected in 1,084 cattle herds in 19 states. The longer H5N1 persists, infecting animals and birds across the country, the greater are the chances are that it will evolve the ability to spread efficiently among people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study last year suggested that in a laboratory setting, a single mutation could tip H5N1 into a variant capable of causing a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, the Agriculture Department announced that the bird flu virus H5N1 was detected in a dairy herd in Wisconsin for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the third instance of the virus jumping from wildlife to dairy cattle this year; two other spillover events were detected early in the year in Nevada and Arizona. Each new spillover underscores the ongoing threat from the virus’s ability to jump species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, the Trump administration dismantled biosecurity work at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, gutted the White House office of pandemic preparedness, and cut support for the surveillance of pandemic threats within the United States and abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of a few announcements from the Agriculture Department early in the year, the administration has not held briefings on the threat posed by bird flu or efforts to prepare for worst-case scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Agriculture Department and Secretary Brooke Rollins have spoken about bird flu to the news media and at Cabinet meetings throughout the year, the department said in an emailed statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department’s response to bird flu “is grounded in decades of scientifically validated epidemiological practices and biosecurity protocols,” the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Health Department did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With funding cuts made in the last year by the Trump administration, many infectious disease experts say the United States is less prepared for a flu pandemic now than it was a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of animal species that H5N1 has been found to infect has increased in the last two years to dozens of mammalian species, from the mundane (raccoons and house cats) to the more exotic (vampire bats, vultures, ostriches and even an arctic fox.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the number of host species expands, “you’re setting up a scenario where you’re going to have at least more sporadic human infections,” said Dr. Nahid Bhadelia, director of the Boston University Center on Emerging Infectious Diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clinicians may incorrectly diagnose the symptoms of a novel bird flu infection, making it challenging to respond to an emerging crisis quickly enough, Dr. Bhadelia said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2024, two people, a 13-year-old Canadian girl and a Louisiana resident over 65, became seriously ill with bird flu. The girl was placed on life support because of organ failure, but she eventually recovered. Scientists still do not know how she became infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Louisiana patient, who had underlying health conditions and had interacted with infected backyard birds, died in early January. (The Washington resident who died in November of an infection with H5N5 also acquired that virus from backyard flocks.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the precautions for people remain the same: Do not touch sick or dead birds or other animals; get tested if you have flulike symptoms; and do not consume raw milk or meat or feed them to your pets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts said they worried about the commingling of bird flu and seasonal flu viruses. When two types of flu viruses infect the same animal, they can exchange genetic material and generate new subtypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The concern there is that H5N1 will pick up some genetic elements from the seasonal flu virus that makes it more able to infect and spread amongst humans,” Dr. Webby said. “So it’s clearly a risk, but luckily, we haven’t seen it yet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current flu season is shaping up to be especially severe, featuring a virus that has picked up at least seven mutations that allow it to sidestep immunity against infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commingling of people and various species at live animal markets — including in New York City — offers countless opportunities for viruses to swap mutations and gain new abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One analysis in Vietnam identified six types of bird flu viruses, including H5N1 and H9N2, circulating at live bird markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is less prepared for a flu pandemic now than it was a year ago. There are a few million doses of vaccine against H5N1 stockpiled by the federal government for use in an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr. has called the stockpiled shots “dangerous,” raising concerns about his willingness to ramp up production should more doses be needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kennedy also canceled nearly $600 million in contracts to develop a bird flu vaccine using mRNA, the technology that powered Covid shots and that is thought to be the best bet for a vaccine in a fast-moving outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you take away our capacity to rapidly respond by canceling those kinds of contracts with the very technologies that will be useful, it’s a vulnerability,” said Dr. Bhadelia, who advised the Biden administration on pandemic preparedness.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/10/health/bird-flu-viruses-health.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 05:44:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Allegiant to Buy Sun Country Airlines in $1.5 Billion Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/business/allegiant-sun-country-airlines.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/11/multimedia/11biz-allegiant-cgjh/11biz-allegiant-cgjh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allegiant Travel said on Sunday that it plans to buy Sun Country Airlines in a $1.5 billion deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of the two small, budget airlines comes as low-cost carriers have struggled with high costs and competition in recent years, putting pressure on some to seek out growth and scale through mergers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allegiant and Sun Country generally focus on providing cheap flights to people traveling for fun or to visit friends and family. Together, they expect to serve almost 175 cities in the U.S. and other nearby countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This combination is an exciting next chapter in Allegiant and Sun Country’s shared mission in providing affordable, reliable, and convenient service from underserved communities to premier leisure destinations,” Gregory C. Anderson, Allegiant’s chief executive, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allegiant said it plans to pay for the deal, which includes $400 million of Sun Country’s debt, with stock and cash. Sun Country shareholders would receive a nearly 20 percent premium for their shares, based on the stock prices of both airlines as of Friday. The combined company will be headquartered in Las Vegas, where Allegiant is based. It will maintain “a significant presence” in Minneapolis-St. Paul, where Sun Country is based, the airlines said in a news release. The airlines expect to complete the transaction in the second half of this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal is subject to regulatory approval. Airline mergers are often fraught: Integrating technology and workforces smoothly can be difficult to pull off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;News of the deal comes as discount airlines, a diverse group of companies, have struggled amid rising competition, higher costs and an increasing willingness among consumers to shell out for perks like seats with additional legroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spirit Airlines, which has filed for bankruptcy twice since late 2024, was particularly hard-hit by an oversupply of flights on important routes. A widespread engine problem also disproportionately affected Spirit’s planes and the airline faced head-to-head competition in many markets with the nation’s largest carriers, which have successfully competed against budget airlines with restrictive “basic economy” fares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spirit had tried to sell itself to JetBlue Airways, but that plan was challenged by the Justice Department under President Joseph R. Biden Jr. and blocked by a federal judge in 2024. Experts expect the Trump administration to be more permissive of such deals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Allegiant and Sun Country have avoided the worst of those problems, thanks in part to operating flights with limited competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allegiant took a big loss in 2024, but reported profits in the previous three years. It and Spirit adopted a business model focused on cutting costs about two decades ago. But Allegiant faces no competition on about 75 percent of its routes. It also earns revenue from its airline credit card and by selling travel packages including hotel rooms, ground transportation and other services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sun Country, a smaller carrier, has reported profits in each of the past few years. It primarily operates flights to and from Minneapolis-St. Paul International Airport, but the airline also earns about 20 percent of its revenue from charter flights and about 10 percent from operating cargo flights for Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, the airlines said that they would serve more than 650 routes collectively, with about 195 aircraft. Allegiant shareholders are expected to own about two-thirds of the combined company, with the remaining third owned by Sun Country shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/11/business/allegiant-sun-country-airlines.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:12:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Potential Fallout From a Legal Attack on Powell</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/dealbook/powell-federal-reserve-investigation-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12db-powell-hglv/12db-powell-hglv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew here. There are certain moments that deserve extra reflection. Today is one of them. The criminal investigation into Jay Powell, the Fed chair, ostensibly over his testimony about building renovations appears to be yet another politically motivated attack by the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nation whose success is largely tied to a belief in the rule of law, the perception that the administration is using “lawfare” to undermine the Fed’s independence is a striking example of how norms are being shattered — and how business executives have remained conspicuously silent. More details below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markets are on edge after the Trump administration made its most direct attack yet on Jay Powell, the Fed chair — and seemingly at the political independence of the central bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the battle seems unlikely to produce the drastically lower interest rates that President Trump has long demanded. It also may cast more of a pall over whoever replaces Powell, and perhaps further erode investors’ belief in the Fed’s stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest: U.S. stock futures are slightly lower this morning, after news outlets reported that Powell faces a federal criminal investigation, ostensibly related to the renovation of the Fed headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the dollar was down, while the prices of gold and silver, classic safe-haven assets, climbed to new records. The yields of various U.S. Treasury bonds, which rise when their prices go down, were up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Powell’s response, from a statement the Fed issued last night (along with a rare video message from the chair):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This new threat is not about my testimony last June or about the renovation of the Federal Reserve buildings. It is not about Congress’s oversight role; the Fed through testimony and other public disclosures made every effort to keep Congress informed about the renovation project. Those are pretexts. The threat of criminal charges is a consequence of the Federal Reserve setting interest rates based on our best assessment of what will serve the public, rather than following the preferences of the president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about whether the Fed will be able to continue to set interest rates based on evidence and economic conditions — or whether instead monetary policy will be directed by political pressure or intimidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has already taken aim at a Fed governor, Lisa Cook, whose efforts to resist being fired by Trump are expected to be heard by the Supreme Court next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump claimed that he had no advance knowledge of the Justice Department’s case. He told NBC News, “I don’t know anything about it, but he’s certainly not very good at the Fed, and he’s not very good at building buildings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On claims that the case was meant to pressure Powell into lowering interest rates, Trump added: “I wouldn’t even think of doing it that way. What should pressure him is the fact that rates are far too high.” (That said, Trump said late last month that he might sue Powell for “gross incompetence.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among those behind the case are Jeanine Pirro, who runs the U.S. attorney’s office for the District of Columbia, according to The Times, and Bill Pulte, the top housing official in the administration who also pushed for the Cook investigation, according to Bloomberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move came as something of a surprise, as Trump had appeared to back off threats to Powell after he visited the Fed construction site over the summer, suggesting that he wouldn’t seek to fire the central bank chief and wanted the renovations to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are stunned by this deeply disturbing development which came out of the blue after a period in which tensions between Trump and the Fed seemed to be contained,” Krishna Guha, a vice chairman at Evercore ISI, wrote to clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it may backfire, critics warn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several economists said Powell’s statement suggested that the Fed would be even less likely to cut interest rates at its meeting this month. The central bank was already seen as unlikely to do so, given recent economic data, but Fed futures suggest there’s just a 5 percent chance that it will do so this month and probably won’t move until June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Thom Tillis, Republican of North Carolina and a member of the Senate Banking Committee, said he would oppose the confirmation of all picks for the Fed, including the forthcoming chair nomination, until the legal matter is resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Bloomberg reports, some administration officials are worried that directly attacking Powell makes it less likely that he will leave the Fed after his term as chair expires in May — making it harder for his Trump-appointed successor to build consensus for lowering rates quickly. (Powell can stay on as a governor until early 2028.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oil prices waver as President Trump suggests he may intervene in Iran. President Trump said he was reviewing military options after the death toll from a government crackdown on protesters rose sharply, spurring concerns that Tehran could retaliate against global oil shipments. Trump also weighed in on Venezuela, saying that he was “inclined” to keep Exxon Mobil from drilling there after its C.E.O. called the country “uninvestable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countries block access to Grok over A.I.-generated sexualized images of real people. Malaysia and Indonesia barred xAI’s chatbot after global outrage over a tool that let users digitally undress women, often without their consent, or children. (On Friday, Grok began limiting access to the feature.) Separately, Google has pulled A.I. overviews for some medical queries after reports of “dangerous” mistakes in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. Discovery wins big at the Golden Globes. The media giant scored nine wins at the awards last night, the most of any company, including for the movies “One Battle After Another” and “Sinners” and the TV show “The Pitt.” The victories underscored the stakes of the takeover battle for Warner Bros. Discovery, with both of its suitors, Netflix and Paramount, catching strays during the night. (A must-read: New York magazine’s lengthy look at David Ellison, Paramount’s C.E.O., and his father, the billionaire Larry Ellison.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation into Jay Powell, the Fed chair, isn’t the only financial regulation move by the Trump administration to rattle markets this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump’s call for capping credit card interest rates at 10 percent for one year has sent banking stocks plunging. And it has another industry that had expected sunnier times in a second Trump term to instead question what other chaos it may confront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest: The stocks of big credit card issuers fell sharply in premarket trading on Monday. Shares in Capital One were down nearly 9 percent, while those in JPMorgan Chase and Citigroup were down about 3 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Trump is demanding: On Friday, Trump wrote on social media that his administration would no longer let Americans be “ripped off” by credit card companies that charge interest rates of 20 percent or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump didn’t detail how he planned to enact the policy, which would typically require congressional or regulatory action. But he told reporters on Sunday that lenders who didn’t comply by the Jan. 20 deadline would be “in violation of the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the latest sign of Trump’s focus on affordability. It’s a political issue that threatens Republicans’ electoral prospects in the midterm elections this fall as Americans worry about costs and disapprove of his handling of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 10 percent cap would save Americans about $100 billion in interest payments annually, according to a recent study from the Vanderbilt Policy Accelerator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The call for a cap aligns Trump with progressive lawmakers like Senator Bernie Sanders, independent of Vermont. Sanders, who (with Senator Josh Hawley, Republican of Missouri) released a plan in February that would cap interest rates at 10 percent for five years chided Trump about card rates on social media hours before the president released his call for a cap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wall Street is pushing back. Five industry groups argued that a 10 percent cap would “reduce credit availability” for millions of Americans and “drive consumers toward less regulated, more costly alternatives.” (Bill Ackman, the hedge fund billionaire, called the cap a “mistake” on social media in a post that was later deleted.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Profits from high interest rates drove banks to offer cards to people with poor credit, and allowed them to subsidize points and reward programs for those with good credit. The cap would most likely lead to a $27 billion cut in rewards for customers with lower credit scores, according to the Vanderbilt Policy Accelerator study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big consumer lenders including JPMorgan, Bank of America and Citigroup report quarterly earnings this week, putting their C.E.O.s on the hot seat with analysts. The move will also make the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, next week more interesting: Both Trump and many banking C.E.O.s will be in attendance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump unexpectedly cracked down on the defense industry last week, criticizing the industry and signing an executive order barring stock buybacks and dividend payouts at military contracts deemed “underperforming.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But later that day, Trump sent defense stocks soaring when he proposed increasing the U.S. defense budget to $1.5 trillion in 2027, from $1 trillion. That quickly restored confidence in the sector, which has been surging since the passage of the broad domestic policy legislation last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now one of the country’s largest venture firms, Andreessen Horowitz, is partnering with one of the biggest U.S. national security federal contractors, Booz Allen, to capitalize on the continued growth in military spending, Lauren Hirsch is first to report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the agreement, Booz Allen will help companies backed by a16z, as the venture firm is commonly known, to bring their technologies to the U.S. government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Working with governments is just very, very different than working with regular enterprise customers,” Ben Horowitz, a founder of a16z, told DealBook. “And Booz Allen has got a lot of experience in that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venture investors have been pouring money into defense and aerospace technology, investing more than $1.5 billion in the industry by March of last year, according to PitchBook data. As part of the roughly $150 billion allocated to defense and national security in the domestic policy legislation last year, the government allocated $16 billion to new weapon technologies and $25 billion to building a golden dome missile-defense system in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re trying to buy commercial technology and venture-backed technology and innovative tech much faster,” Horacio Rozanski, the C.E.O. of Booz Allen, told DealBook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partnership with Booz Allen comes after a16z said it had raised $15 billion in new capital to invest in a range of areas. That includes more than $1 billion each for funds focused on “American Dynamism” and infrastructure. The firm has backed companies like Anduril, which designs autonomous systems and weapons for government agencies and the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two firms have been working together for years. Booz Allen’s work with the software company Databricks, a gem in a16z’s portfolio, is an example of the kind of deals expected from the new partnership. Booz Allen helped deploy Databricks at federal agencies in 2018, and has since helped scale those efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Booz Allen and a16z will meet weekly to discuss new business opportunities, Rozanski said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.B.A. is reportedly preparing to pitch investors on its planned European league, set to start play as early as next year, with team valuations of up to $1 billion. (Bloomberg)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. corporate borrowers raised $95 billion in the first full week of January, the busiest week since May 2020, in anticipation for spending on takeovers and artificial intelligence. (FT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics, policy and regulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump’s ‘Superstar’ Appellate Judges Have Voted 133 to 12 in His Favor” (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Silicon Valley billionaire Peter Thiel has donated $3 million to a group opposed to California’s proposed wealth tax with lobbying money. Relatedly, the Google co-founders Larry Page and Sergey Brin are cutting some ties with the state. (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of the rest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promise of a Florida retirement is fading for the middle class, as high house prices and soaring insurance premiums make it unaffordable for many. (WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How a Puzzling 401(k) Plan Changed One Woman’s Life” (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d like your feedback! Please email thoughts and suggestions to dealbook@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/dealbook/powell-federal-reserve-investigation-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:34:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Markets Recover From Early Dip as Wall St. Assesses Fed Threat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/stock-market-dollar-trump-fed-powell.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/newsgraphics/images/icons/defaultPromoCrop.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Former Federal Reserve chiefs and Treasury officials warned of “highly negative consequences” from the Trump administration’s repeated attacks on the Federal Reserve’s independence. Even some Republicans denounced them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the moment, investors didn’t appear to believe that President Trump’s pressure campaign on the Fed will lead to immediate damage in the economy and markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest attack came late Sunday with reports that the Department of Justice was investigating the Fed’s chair, Jerome H. Powell, over comments he had made to Congress about the central bank’s renovation project on its headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell fired back publicly, suggesting in a video statement that the threat of criminal prosecution against him was driven by the Trump administration’s campaign to pressure the Fed to lower interest rates, a once rare threat on the central bank’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet investors’ reaction on Monday appeared muted, just as it was last year when President Trump tried to fire a Fed governor, Lisa D. Cook, over allegations that she had made misstatements on her mortgage document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the S&amp;P 500 opened slightly lower before recovering to trade flat. The yield, which moves inversely to price, on Treasury bonds jumped in early trading before recovering to trade little changed. There were some signs of anxiety in the markets, though. The dollar was weaker against most major currencies, and gold, a typical haven during times of worry, hit a new high, rising almost 2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some analysts and market watchers say one reason investors weren’t panicking was that the administration’s broadsides would not ultimately have much effect on monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No one seems to believe that this will push the Fed into easier near term policy,” said Ajay Rajadhyaksha, global chairman of research at Barclays. “Not a chance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has made calls for lowering interest rates a cornerstone of his economic strategy, but the Federal Reserve has been cautious about cutting rates, not wanting to reignite inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Trump were to be successful in his bid to engineer interest rates below what the economy required, Mr. Rajadhyaksha said, the effect would most likely be the opposite of what the president desired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If interest rates are lower than the economy needs, it has the effect of making money cheaper to borrow, increasing demand and driving prices higher. In other words, it would increase inflation and reduce affordability, which many voters have identified as a top challenge heading into this midterm election year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It will not help your goal, if you are the administration, of getting interest rates lower,” Mr. Rajadhyaksha said. “That is what bond investors are counting on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to investors that the Federal Reserve retains its independence, not because of a moral commitment to a certain governance structure but because history suggests that an independent central bank is more likely to set appropriate monetary policy for the economy than a politicized one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed controls the overnight interest rate it pays commercial banks on cash stored at the central bank. It also controls some other short-term lending rates. From this, investors and the market adjust interest rates throughout the economy to reflect the Fed’s new settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The issue of Fed independence is of considerable concern to the markets,” Jane Foley, a currency strategist at Rabobank, wrote in a research note. But the impact has also been limited by the view that the Fed’s policymaking committee might act as a counterbalance to a new chair who pushes for more rate cuts, she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell’s term as Fed chair ends in May, while his term as a governor runs through January 2028. In his role as governor, Mr. Powell will still have influence on the Fed’s policymaking committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investors are looking to inflation data set to be released on Tuesday for a guide on the outlook for prices. U.S. consumer prices are expected to have risen 2.7 percent in December from a year earlier, holding at the same rate as November, according to economists’ forecasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed targets a 2 percent inflation rate. The latest reading for its preferred gauge, in September, was 2.8 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The market may be too complacent,” Atakan Bakiskan, an economist at the bank Berenberg, wrote in a note on Monday. “If the Fed pursues an ultra-accommodative monetary policy despite higher inflation, the result could resemble the 1970s in a worst-case risk scenario.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/stock-market-dollar-trump-fed-powell.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 12:44:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fed Changes Course and Takes On Trump’s Political Fight</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/federal-reserve-changes-course-trump-administration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-fed-pqlh/12dc-fed-pqlh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerome H. Powell wanted to avoid a fight. That had long been his approach to handling President Trump and his relentless attacks on the Federal Reserve, which in his second term had taken on heightened intensity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between an executive order wresting more control over the Fed’s oversight of Wall Street to Mr. Trump’s attempt to oust a sitting member of the policy-setting board of governors, the Fed had stuck to a time-tested strategy: Avoid provoking the president. At times, that meant bending to meet his demands in areas like climate change and bank regulation. But Mr. Powell, the Fed chair, drew the line when it came to protecting the central bank’s autonomy to set interest rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A criminal investigation into whether Mr. Powell lied to Congress, revealed by The New York Times on Sunday, has prompted the central bank to jettison its cautious approach and fight. The battle’s outcome could determine whether the Fed remains an independent entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump is now exercising the nuclear option, so there is no longer a reason for Powell not to speak his mind,” said Maurice Obstfeld, a senior fellow at the Peterson Institute for International Economics, who was formerly the chief economist at the International Monetary Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell’s decision to push back, which came in a rare video message on Sunday evening, tees up the most challenging moment in his roughly eight years at the helm of the central bank. Mr. Powell, whose term as chair ends in May, must now decide how hard to continue fighting and whether to remain in his role as a governor, a term that is set to expire in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell and staff members at the Fed worked through the weekend after the Justice Department served the central bank with grand jury subpoenas late on Friday. What culminated was a two-minute video released Sunday evening featuring Mr. Powell bluntly calling out the administration for seeking to leverage a criminal investigation into costs related to the Fed’s renovation of its headquarters as “pretexts” to coerce the central bank into lowering borrowing costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This new threat is not about my testimony last June or about the renovation of the Federal Reserve buildings,” Mr. Powell said on Sunday. “The threat of criminal charges is a consequence of the Federal Reserve setting interest rates based on our best assessment of what will serve the public, rather than following the preferences of the president.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed has cut interest rates only gradually, reducing them by 0.75 percentage points since September to a new range of 3.5 percent to 3.75 percent. Mr. Trump has demanded rates as low as 1 percent, calling Mr. Powell a “numbskull” and a “stubborn mule” for refusing to concede.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friday’s subpoenas relate to renovations that have been taking place since 2022 at the Fed’s headquarters in Washington. The sprawling project, which is set to be completed in 2027, is $700 million over budget and is expected to cost roughly $2.5 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump seized on the renovations as a new line of attack against the central bank this summer, accusing Mr. Powell of mismanagement and taking the rare step of showing up at the construction site for a tour. Legal experts saw it as the potential groundwork to try to remove the Fed chair for “cause,” the only justification a president can use to lawfully fire an official at the central bank. Cause has typically meant gross malfeasance or a dereliction of duty while in office, although it has never been tested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell’s decision to respond directly by video reflected the explosive nature of the Justice Department’s move. Never before has a Fed chair faced a criminal investigation. It also represented a stark departure from the administration’s attacks on Mr. Powell to date, which had typically taken the form of personal insults from Mr. Trump. The president, who nominated Mr. Powell to the job during his first term, had also threatened to fire the Fed’s chair, but had not acted on it. Still, Mr. Powell had pre-emptively retained outside counsel, hiring Williams &amp; Connolly, a top litigation firm in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump instead tried to oust Lisa D. Cook, whom the Biden administration had appointed to the Fed. The president, citing allegations of mortgage fraud, said he had cause to remove her. Arguments for the case will be heard by the Supreme Court on Jan. 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell, a lawyer by training, and close advisers saw the Justice Department’s investigation as a sharp escalation in the administration’s affront against the institution that required a forceful response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump denied having knowledge of the U.S. attorney’s investigation, saying on Sunday that he did not “know anything about it, but he’s certainly not very good at the Fed, and he’s not very good at building buildings,” referring to Mr. Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, Mr. Powell had demurred from commenting directly on the president’s attacks. Instead, he spoke in favor of the importance of the Fed maintaining its longstanding independence, a protection Congress granted the central bank so that officials set rates with an aim to attain low, stable inflation and a healthy labor market, rather than to the benefit of whomever is in the White House. But that changed on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He didn’t mince words,” said Kenneth Rogoff, a professor of economics at Harvard and a former chief economist of the International Monetary Fund. “He’s tended to turn the other cheek, and he’s reached a moment where he can’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Fed seems to recognize that this administration rarely stops pressuring people and organizations to get what it wants, so anyone who won’t capitulate to that pressure ultimately needs to fight back,” added Douglas Elmendorf, a former director of the Congressional Budget Office who teaches at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell on Monday got the backing of every living former chair of the Fed, as well as multiple former Treasury secretaries who called out what they described as “prosecutorial attacks to undermine that independence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is how monetary policy is made in emerging markets with weak institutions, with highly negative consequences for inflation and the functioning of their economies more broadly,” they wrote in a joint statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Janet L. Yellen, who served as Fed chair between 2014 and 2018 and was among the statement’s signatories, said in an interview that the investigation constituted the most significant attack ever on the central bank’s independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The fact that he is willing to go that far to intimidate a Fed official suggests he’s going to stop at nothing to get his way with respect to Fed policy,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you can bring charges for no reason whatsoever against your enemies, we’re no longer living in a society governed by the rule of law.” She added: “That’s the end of Fed independence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guardrails protecting the Fed’s independence were crafted by Congress to avoid a president having undue influence over major policy decisions that have significant sway over the trajectory of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the foremost protections revolve around the seven members of the powerful board of governors. Those officials are nominated by the president and confirmed by the Senate, but they cannot be fired at will. They also serve staggered 14-year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rate decisions are voted on by a 12-person committee made up of the members the board, the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York and a rotating set of four presidents from the 12 regional banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Powell opts to stay on as a governor — something he has declined to publicly comment on — that would deny Mr. Trump the opportunity to appoint another member to the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s harder for him to go now,” Scott Alvarez, the Fed’s former general counsel, said of Mr. Powell. “If he goes now, it’s under a cloud. If they hadn’t done anything, he might have just left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president gained an unexpected vacancy in August when Adriana Kugler abruptly stepped down as governor after repeatedly violating the central bank’s trading rules. He tapped for the job one of his top economic advisers, Stephen I. Miran, who took only a temporary leave of absence from the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is also in the final stages of selecting Mr. Powell’s replacement for chair. Kevin A. Hassett, the director of the White House National Economic Council, is a top contender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appearing Monday on CNBC, Mr. Hassett said that he had “not been involved” in the Justice Department’s decision to investigate the Federal Reserve. He said that he had not been briefed on the matter, and that he would “expect” the president had not been as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressed repeatedly during the interview on the extent to which the president hoped to use the investigation to pressure the Fed to lower interest rates, Mr. Hassett at one point told CNBC: “In the fullness of time, we’ll find out whether it looks like a pretext.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Monday about the investigation, Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, took the opportunity to critcize Mr. Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do know one thing for sure, Jerome Powell is not very good at his job,” she said in an interview with Fox News. “As to whether he’s a criminal, that’s an answer the Department of Justice is going to have to find.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sign that the investigation could have an impact on the Senate confirmation process, Senator Thom Tillis, Republican of North Carolina and a member of the Banking Committee, on Sunday vowed to oppose any nominee for the Fed, including any coming chair vacancy, citing reports of subpoenas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation will also have broad implications for Ms. Cook’s case. The Supreme Court will be ruling on how much latitude a president has to remove a Fed official and the extent to which they can define what constitutes cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope the Supreme Court is watching, because it would eviscerate the independence of the Federal Reserve if the president could remove somebody on an allegation rather than on a finding of some criminal behavior,” Mr. Alvarez said. “The fact that the D.O.J. has alleged this doesn’t make it true.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kathryn Judge, a professor at Columbia Law School, added that “the Federal Reserve will not remain independent if the president feels entitled to use every tool at his disposal to harass and intimidate Fed officials.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tony Romm and Alan Rappeport contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/federal-reserve-changes-course-trump-administration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:22:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Paramount Threatens Board Fight Over Warner Bros. Discovery</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/media/paramount-warner-bros-discovery-board-fight.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12biz-wbd-hkfc/12biz-wbd-hkfc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount on Monday dialed up pressure in its hostile bid for Warner Bros. Discovery, saying that it intended to nominate directors to the Warner Bros. board to help advance the deal. Paramount also sued Warner Bros., demanding more information about how the company had decided that Netflix’s bid was superior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves were the latest in a series of increasingly aggressive actions by Paramount to buy Warner Bros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Warner board last week rebuffed Paramount’s latest $108 billion bid to acquire the company, sticking with its deal to sell a large portion of its business to Netflix for $83 billion. Paramount on Monday said it would nominate directors who would “exercise WBD’s right under the Netflix Agreement to engage on Paramount’s offer and enter into a transaction with Paramount.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount also said it would propose an amendment to the company’s bylaws that would require Warner Bros. Discovery to get shareholder approval before breaking off its cable unit as it had planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Despite six weeks and just as many press releases from Paramount Skydance, it has yet to raise the price or address the numerous and obvious deficiencies of its offer,” a spokesperson for Warner Bros. Discovery said in a statement. “Instead, Paramount Skydance is seeking to distract with a meritless lawsuit and attacks on a board that has delivered an unprecedented amount of shareholder value.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the monthslong back and forth, Paramount has accused the Warner board of running a sales process that unfairly favored Netflix. Warner Bros. Discovery has argued that Netflix’s bid is better for shareholders than Paramount’s in part because of the extensive debt it would load on the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. Discovery’s board is led by Samuel A. Di Piazza Jr., a former chief executive of PricewaterhouseCoopers. He joined the board in 2022 when AT&amp;T combined its WarnerMedia business with Discovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter to shareholders announcing the lawsuit, Paramount’s chief executive, David Ellison, said, “We are surprised by the lack of transparency on WBD’s part regarding basic financial matters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It just doesn’t add up,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the fight for Warner Bros. Discovery plays out in board rooms, it is also playing out in Washington. President Trump, who has said he would be “involved” in any deal, posted on social media Sunday an article published last month titled “Stop the Netflix Cultural Takeover” that argued against the Netflix deal.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/media/paramount-warner-bros-discovery-board-fight.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:09:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Nears Trade Deal With Taiwan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/economy/trump-taiwan-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12dc-trade-taiwan-fhkq/12dc-trade-taiwan-fhkq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration is completing a trade deal with Taiwan that would reduce tariffs on the island’s exports and commit its largest chipmaker, Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Corporation, to invest significantly more in the United States, according to three people familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement, which has been under negotiation for months, is being legally scrubbed and could be announced this month. The deal would reduce the U.S. tariff rate, to 15 percent, for goods from the island, the people said. That rate is in line with imports from Japan and South Korea, Asian allies that struck deals last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the deal, TSMC would also commit to building at least five more semiconductor facilities, or fabs, in Arizona, roughly doubling the number of plants it has in the state, one of the people said. The timeline for the investments was not immediately clear. A spokesman for TSMC declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since announcing tariffs on dozens of trading partners in April, the Trump administration has negotiated to reduce those rates in exchange for promises of investments and deals that fulfill U.S. national security priorities. South Korea and Japan have pledged hundreds of billions of dollars in investments in U.S. shipbuilding, nuclear energy, electronics and critical minerals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Taiwan, the Trump administration wanted the island to invest in more semiconductor manufacturing in the United States. Taiwan dominates global production of chips that are the brains of computers and the data centers needed for artificial intelligence. But relying on the island appears increasingly risky given Beijing’s assertion that Taiwan belongs to China and should one day be brought under Chinese control. China has done live-fire drills around the island, and officials and executives worry about the possibility of an invasion’s disrupting the global supply chains for electronics, cars and weaponry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TSMC, the world’s pre-eminent chipmaker, has completed one plant in Arizona since 2020; is completing a second, which will open in 2028; and has promised to build four more in the coming years. But as part of the U.S.-Taiwanese trade talks, it agreed to add at least five more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Office of the United States Trade Representative and the Department of Commerce did not provide comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been reporting on economics, trade and international relations for over a decade, from both China and the U.S. I aim to underpin my work with data and numbers, as well as give voice to the personal stories of people I encounter in my reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade negotiations with Taiwan have dragged on as the two sides have debated what to do about tariffs. The Trump administration has announced limited trade arrangements with countries in recent months in an effort to rework America’s trading relationships. Mr. Trump briefly introduced “reciprocal” tariffs globally in April, before pausing them and then reintroducing them in August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, importers of Taiwanese products have paid a 20 percent tariff when bringing goods into the United States. But the administration exempted semiconductors and many electronics from those tariffs, saying those sectors would be subject to separate national security tariffs issued under a legal provision known as Section 232.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration has also used the national security statute to apply tariffs to steel, aluminum, cars, copper, lumber and other goods. The Section 232 investigation into semiconductors, which is administered by the Department of Commerce, was expected last year. That has prompted speculation that the Trump administration has not pushed forward on it for fear of upsetting a trade truce with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential tariffs on chips pose a direct threat to the island and TSMC. Semiconductors account for more than a third of Taiwan’s exports, with the most valuable of those chips coming from TSMC’s network of 20-plus factories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taiwanese government had earlier concluded trade discussions with the Office of the United States Trade Representative, but continued to discuss the Section 232 tariffs and TSMC’s domestic investment plans with the Department of Commerce. Those talks only recently concluded, as TSMC bought another parcel of land in Arizona for its expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have said companies that invest domestically would not be subject to Section 232 tariffs, though it is unclear exactly how the arrangement will work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taiwanese officials declined to comment. On Dec. 26, the Taiwanese trade negotiations office said in a statement to reporters that the two sides had reached broad consensus on a trade agreement that would include the U.S. side lowering reciprocal tariffs on Taiwan and providing preferential treatment under Section 232.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the year, the two sides had been unable to conclude their trade agreement because the bulk of U.S.-Taiwan trade is in chips and the semiconductor tariffs were still evolving, the office said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amy Chang Chien contributed reporting from Taipei.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/economy/trump-taiwan-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:41:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>David Mitchell, Who Led Fight on Drug Prices, Dies at 75</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/health/david-mitchell-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/09/multimedia/00mitchell-01-mjgk/00mitchell-01-mjgk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Mitchell, a public relations executive who, after receiving a cancer diagnosis in 2010, set aside plans to retire and instead became one of the country’s leading voices in the campaign to lower prescription drug prices, died on Jan. 2 at his home in Annapolis, Md. He was 75.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His family said in a statement that the cause was multiple myeloma, a type of blood cancer he had kept at bay for 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mitchell had a master’s degree in labor relations and a 30-year career as a founding partner of GMMB, a Washington-based communications firm. But at the top of his résumé, above all that, he listed his primary occupation as “Cancer Patient, November 2010-Present.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2016, his medications were costing $300,000 a year. He was able to cover that through his insurance, but he knew that many others could not. He grew frustrated, then angry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like extortion,” he told the medical news website Stat in 2017. “It’s no different than Tony Soprano walking into a store and saying, ‘Someone may get hurt if you don’t give us the money.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He decided he was in a position to do something. He understood public relations, having spent decades leading campaigns on a wide range of public health issues, including tobacco, drunk driving and immunization awareness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2016 he founded Patients for Affordable Drugs, which he used as a vehicle to drive a nationwide effort to bring transparency and lower prices to medication. His thorough grasp of the nuances of an incredibly complex industry made him a go-to voice for news media interviews and congressional testimony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his group was far from a one-man show: It recorded tens of thousands of interviews with patients in all 50 states, and brought many of them to its hearings and rallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, Mr. Mitchell and Patients for Affordable Drugs racked up a long list of legislative accomplishments. Several states passed laws to force price transparency that were written or influenced by the group, and it is widely credited with the inclusion of an annual cap on medication prices in the Inflation Reduction Act of 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under that law, which limited drug costs for Medicare patients to $3,500 a year — and eventually to $2,000 — Mr. Mitchell saw his out-of-pocket costs go from $16,525 to just $3,308.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I want to tell the drug companies that it’s time for patients to say we’re not going to be frightened any longer by your threats not to give us drugs we need if we don’t pay prices you demand,” he told Stat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Emerson Mitchell was born on May 4, 1950, in Detroit. His father, Henry Mitchell, was a police officer and his mother, Catherine (Perri) Mitchell, was a substitute teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though his mother urged him to become a lawyer, he was unsure about college until he spent a summer on a tractor-assembly line, a hard, repetitive job that made him see the benefit of higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He enrolled as a journalism major at Wayne State University in Detroit, and completed his undergraduate studies at Michigan State University in 1977. He received his master’s degree in 1978, also from Michigan State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He spent seven years working for the United Auto Workers union, including three years as the head of its communications department, before helping to found GMMB in 1986.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm became a reliable source for projects on public health and safety topics, and Mr. Mitchell worked with clients in government agencies, major nonprofits and private industry, in the process accumulating a long list of contacts to draw on after founding Patients for Affordable Drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GMMB also taught him how the world of public advocacy worked in Washington. He saw firsthand how much money companies and corporate lobbyists poured into ostensibly independent groups, particularly when it came to health care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believed that all that money was one reason not a single patient advocacy group tackled drug prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical companies “remind me of an octopus with many, many tentacles, and at the end of each tentacle is a wad of cash,” he told the website Talking Points Memo in 2025. “Everybody relies on the money.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why he insisted that Patients for Affordable Drugs would never take industry money. Instead, he relied on a few philanthropic grants and individual donations, including tens of thousands of dollars of his own money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mitchell’s first marriage, to Rebecca Ford, ended in divorce. He married Nicole Solomon in 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His wife survives him, as do his three children from his first marriage, Nate, Claire and Ben; his son from his second marriage, Sam; one grandson; and his sisters Jocelyn Bierenkoven, Marie Mitoff and Patricia Kiekaefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mrs. Solomon-Mitchell is also a cancer survivor, and she worked closely with her husband at Patients for Affordable Drugs until last year, when he stepped back to focus on his health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mitchell said that seeing so many people fight for — and even occasionally secure — lower drug costs gave him hope, but he was also realistic about the limits of the American health care system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In the U.S. every patient should know that, contrary to propaganda from those who make money on our system, we don’t have the best health care system in the world,” he told The British Medical Journal in 2018. “We have the most expensive health care system in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/health/david-mitchell-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:41:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Top Fed Official Conveys Little Urgency for Immediate Rate Cuts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/federal-reserve-john-williams-rates.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12DC-FED-WILLIAMS-hp-pwtk/12DC-FED-WILLIAMS-hp-pwtk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A top official at the Federal Reserve on Monday conveyed little urgency to further lower interest rates, reinforcing expectations that the central bank will hold borrowing costs steady at the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John C. Williams, president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, said the central bank was “well positioned” to shore up the labor market and ensure that inflation eased back to the Fed’s 2 percent target after three quarter-point reductions last year. Interest rates stand between 3.5 percent and 3.75 percent, a range that Mr. Williams said was “closer to neutral.” That is a level that neither speeds up economic growth nor slows it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Williams, in remarks to the Council on Foreign Relations, struck an upbeat tone about the economic outlook, forecasting that the unemployment rate would stabilize around its current 4.4 percent level while growth accelerated and inflation eased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He later told reporters that he did not think there was “strong pressure one way or another to do anything” in terms of monetary policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pause at the Fed’s next meeting on Jan. 27-28 would keep the central bank at odds with President Trump, whose administration sharply ratcheted up its pressure campaign against the institution this weekend by opening a criminal investigation into Jerome H. Powell, the Fed chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extraordinary escalation from the Justice Department, which was revealed by The New York Times on Sunday, prompted a rare rebuke from Mr. Powell, who accused the administration of using legal threats to push for lower borrowing costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed’s mandate is to prioritize low, stable inflation and a healthy labor market free of political meddling. Congress granted the central bank that autonomy in order to ensure that the Fed does what is in the best interest of the economy, rather than what is best politically. Many legal experts warned that this independence was under threat in the wake of the investigation, which centers on Mr. Powell and his oversight of a $2.5 billion renovation of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Williams defended Mr. Powell in a moderated discussion hosted by the Council on Foreign Relations, saying the Fed chair is “completely dedicated” to the institution and is a man of “impeccable integrity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Williams, who is a close ally of Mr. Powell, also warned about the costs if the Fed’s independence is jeopardized. That risks “unfortunate outcomes” marked by a less stable economy and higher inflation, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Williams acknowledged to reporters that the inquiry was an escalation in what the Fed had faced so far from the administration, noting that there was a “difference between criticizing” the central bank and investigating its top official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source of tension between the president and the Fed stems from its reluctance to sharply lower borrowing costs, as Mr. Trump has demanded. Many officials have instead urged caution given uncertainty over inflation, which has remained stuck above the 2 percent target for roughly five years. The labor market, which has shown some signs of weakening, does not yet appear to be on the cusp of cracking, helping to reinforce the idea that the central bank can take its time with further cuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has instead called for interest rates as low as 1 percent, a level typically associated with a recession. The president is in the process of selecting a chair to replace Mr. Powell once his term ends in May. One concern is that Mr. Trump’s criterion that his pick must support lower rates will mean his selection will have a credibility problem from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Williams told reporters on Monday that he hoped the next chair would come in with an understanding that the central bank had a “very, very important responsibility to the American people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When we don’t get it right,” he added, “it matters a lot. When we get it right, it matters a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/federal-reserve-john-williams-rates.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:30:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Labor Secretary’s Aides Placed on Leave in Misconduct Investigation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/lori-chavez-deremer-misconduct-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/12biz-labor-aides-wpkv/12biz-labor-aides-wpkv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The secretary of labor’s chief of staff and deputy chief of staff were placed on administrative leave on Monday, as the Labor Department’s watchdog begins investigating allegations of professional misconduct involving the secretary, a person with knowledge of the matter said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move to place the two officials on leave followed a report by The New York Post on Friday that said a formal complaint had been filed against Labor Secretary Lori Chavez-DeRemer with the department’s inspector general’s office, accusing her of abusing her office and of having an affair with a subordinate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Chavez-DeRemer’s chief of staff, Jihun Han, and deputy chief of staff, Rebecca Wright, were also named in the complaint, The Post reported. Politico reported the moves to sideline Mr. Han and Ms. Wright earlier on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to The Post, the complaint accused Ms. Chavez-DeRemer of committing “travel fraud” by having Mr. Han and Ms. Wright create trips for the secretary where she could spend personal time with friends and family. The complaint also accused Ms. Chavez-DeRemer, who is married, of having an “inappropriate” relationship with a subordinate, The Post said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, The Post reported, Mr. Han and Ms. Wright knew about Ms. Chavez-DeRemer’s behavior. Both worked for Ms. Chavez-DeRemer when she served in Congress — she represented Oregon’s Fifth Congressional District for a single term, from 2023 to 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Han and Ms. Wright could not be reached for comment on Monday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on Saturday, a spokeswoman for the Labor Department’s inspector general’s office said: “It is the policy of the D.O.L. O.I.G. to neither confirm nor deny the existence or nonexistence of any O.I.G. investigation or complaint beyond what is published on our website. D.O.L. O.I.G. remains committed to rooting out fraud, waste, abuse and corruption through objective, independent oversight of the U.S. Department of Labor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspector general, the former New York congressman Anthony D’Esposito, assumed the office just last week. According to The Post, the complaint was filed in December.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/12/business/lori-chavez-deremer-misconduct-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:11:18 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>