<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:15:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Minnesota’s Biggest Companies Call for ‘De-escalation’ of Tensions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv/25biz-minnesota-ceos-target-fgbv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief executives of Target, Best Buy, General Mills and Cargill were among more than 60 large Minnesota companies to issue a public letter on Sunday calling for an “immediate de-escalation of tensions” in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter marks the first time the most recognizable businesses in Minnesota have weighed in on the turmoil in Minneapolis amid the aggressive crackdown by federal immigration agents, which have sparked widespread protests throughout the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes one day after federal agents shot and killed 37-year-old Alex Pretti, a nurse at the city’s Veterans Affairs hospital, while he was being restrained on a Minneapolis sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With yesterday’s tragic news, we are calling for an immediate de-escalation of tensions and for state, local and federal officials to work together to find real solutions,” the letter states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was signed by top executives of Minnesota’s largest companies and large hospital systems, including Land O’ Lakes, Hormel, U.S. Bancorp, Mayo Clinic and 3M. It also was signed by local sports teams: the Minnesota Vikings, Minnesota Timberwolves, and the Minnesota Wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter is notable because many chief executives have sought to avoid weighing in on any politically charged issues during the second Trump administration. On Friday, hundreds of smaller businesses in the Minneapolis area shut their doors as they backed protests against the actions from Immigration and Customs Enforcement in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter was shared by the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce, which represents more than 6,000 businesses across the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, Josh Bolten, the chief executive of the Business Roundtable, an association of more than 200 chief executives of America’s leading companies, said in an emailed statement that he supported the Minnesota Chamber of Commerce’s letter. Beth Ford, the chief executive of Land O’ Lakes, sits on the Business Roundtable’s board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until Sunday, the largest companies in Minnesota had not addressed the issue, but in the Chamber of Commerce letter they said they had been in contact with federal, state and local officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The silence by big companies had been a marked contrast from their responses to the killing of George Floyd in Minneapolis in 2020. That murder helped set off a broader corporate movement to fight racism, with executives making public pledges to support diversity initiatives, donate to social justice causes and express solidarity with demonstrators at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the years since, companies have sought to avoid being caught in any political cross hairs, as the country has become more polarized. Many have said they will be more selective about the issues they tackle, sticking only to those that directly affect their business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum last week, once a hotbed for such social issues, there was hardly any public mention by executives of the unrest in Minnesota. The focus was instead on artificial intelligence, deal making and the reshaping of global alliances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for some companies, the violence in Minnesota has hit particularly close to home. After immigration agents detained two employees at the Target store in Richfield, Minn., this month, clergy members gathered at the retailer’s headquarters, asking the company to keep immigration agents off its properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every C.E.O. — and I know all these C.E.O.s — they want to have a peaceful environment for their employees,” said Bill George, the former chief executive of Medtronic, whose current chief signed the letter. Mr. George is also a former board member at Target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The larger issue for C.E.O.s,” he added, is that the unrest in Minneapolis “is going to have a very negative effect on their growth, on their innovation and particularly their ability to recruit people from around the country and around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking as a group, as Minnesota executives did Sunday, could help insulate companies from individual attacks from Mr. Trump, said Jeff Sonnenfeld, a professor of leadership studies at the Yale School of Management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can take down companies individually, but when they work collectively, they have immunity,” Mr. Sonnenfeld said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Executives similarly relied on the law of numbers in expressing concerns about tariffs, which organizations like the U.S. Chamber of Commerce came out in opposition to last spring. Many companies ultimately struck their own deals with the administration over tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday’s letter stopped short of calling for specific action nor did the corporations condemn the shooting of Mr. Pretti by the federal agents or call for immigration authorities to rein in their aggressive enforcement. The statement also did not call on protesters to change their behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With polls showing voters split along party lines on whether they support President Trump’s immigration crackdown, corporations have been careful not to alienate large numbers of their customers by taking a side. They also risk angering Mr. Trump, who has publicly rebuked companies and executives he believes have crossed him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter from the Minnesota companies on Sunday struck a neutral tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In this difficult moment for our community, we call for peace and focused cooperation among local, state and federal leaders to achieve a swift and durable solution that enables families, businesses, our employees, and communities across Minnesota to resume our work to build a bright and prosperous future,” the executives wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alison Taylor, a clinical associate professor of business and society at the N.Y.U. Stern business school, said she thought the companies had no choice but to say something. “They have been backed into a corner, because obviously the situation going on is starting to have commercial consequences,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Taylor added: “Is it better than doing nothing? Probably. Is it sufficient? I don’t think anyone’s going to think this is sufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/business/minnesota-target-general-mills-ceo-letter.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:53:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Europe’s Reliance on U.S. Natural Gas Grows, So Does Trump’s Leverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv/26Biz-Europe-LNG-01-phlv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Russia invaded Ukraine in 2022, it also tried to squeeze Europe by crimping natural gas flows. But increased shipments of liquid natural gas, much of it from the United States, helped ease the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, smoldering tensions between leaders in Washington and Brussels could turn Europe’s reliance on American natural gas into a similar political pressure point, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve replaced one massive dependency with another one,” said Henning Gloystein, a managing director for energy at Eurasia Group, a political risk research firm. “That looked fine three years ago, but now it doesn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to import large amounts of energy is one of Europe’s strategic weaknesses. Natural gas from Russia was a mainstay for the continent before the invasion of Ukraine. In 2019, for instance, Russian gas accounted for more than half of the European Union’s gas imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The huge volumes of Russian gas that flowed through pipelines across Ukraine and Poland and under the Baltic Sea plummeted in the wake of the assault. Prices soared, putting pressure on consumers, industries and governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States came to the rescue. Tankers loaded at U.S. terminals shipped large volumes of liquefied natural gas to European ports in the Netherlands, France and Belgium, among other destinations, helping to replace the Russian fuel and calming markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the United States had been a modest supplier of natural gas to Europe, with about 5 percent of imports in late 2019, but it has since grown, providing more than a quarter of the European Union’s gas imports in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Bruegel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, those gas flows looked heroic. Now, they are raising eyebrows. Since beginning his second term, President Trump has sought to use trade as leverage in disputes with other countries, including his recent push to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growing concern in Europe is that Mr. Trump could turn the strong position that the United States has gained in the oil and gas industry into a weapon to try to coerce other countries. “Recently, people have started to realize we are probably a little bit too dependent on U.S. L.N.G.,” said Anne-Sophie Corbeau, a global research scholar in Paris for the Center on Global Energy Policy at Columbia University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has encouraged this reliance, pushing Europe to increase U.S. imports as part of the trade deal struck with the European Union last year. In 2025, L.N.G. flows from the United States to European Union countries jumped about 60 percent from the previous year, according to Bruegel, a research organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say these volumes are likely to increase. Although Europe invests in renewable energy like wind and solar power, it still requires natural gas for heating homes and manufacturing goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe is also producing less of its own fuel because its existing oil and gas fields are winding down, and countries like Britain, whose petroleum production has fallen sharply, discourage new drilling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Europe is without much alternative,” said Christoph Halser, a senior analyst at Rystad Energy, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly in response to American complaints, Europe is also in the process of phasing out its purchases of Russian gas, which fell to around 12 percent of imports in 2025. Norway, which is not a European Union member, is the bloc’s largest gas supplier, accounting for around 30 percent of imports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is already the world leader in L.N.G. exports, and developers are spending heavily to build facilities for chilling gas to liquid form and then shipping it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe, which is a relatively short sail from terminals on the Gulf Coast, is a logical destination for these cargoes. China, the world’s largest importer of liquefied natural gas, has largely stopped buying American fuel because of U.S. tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, a bright spot for Europe may be that a supply boom is expected in the coming years, which could bring down what have been relatively high prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in the event of increased political tensions with Europe, some analysts are skeptical that the Trump administration would take steps like reducing shipments that would be contrary to the interests of the U.S. oil and gas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That “would be a very negative market signal, and also significantly impair the competitiveness of the industry, which the administration is committed to supporting,” said David L. Goldwyn, a former U.S. energy special envoy and now president of Goldwyn Global Strategies, a consulting firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry in the United States also differs markedly from Russia’s. There, the Kremlin was able to use Gazprom, the state-controlled gas monopoly, “to weaponize gas flows in 2022,” Jack Reid, a graduate economist at Oxford Economics, wrote in a recent study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States, he added, is more likely to “redirect flows than bring them to a halt.” Other analysts speculate that Washington might take measures like putting an export tax on gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a minimum, though, meddling with gas flows is likely to lead to higher costs and prices, analysts say, which would be bad news for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Import concentration” matters, said Ugne Keliauskaite, a research analyst at Bruegel. “Now Europe is more exposed to U.S.-centered disruptions.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/europe-natural-gas-united-states-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:12:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Bad Are A.I. Delusions? We Asked People Treating Them.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julia Sheffield, a psychologist who specializes in treating people with delusions, is difficult to rattle. But she was unnerved last summer when patients began telling her about their conversations with A.I. chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One woman, who had no history of mental illness, asked ChatGPT for advice on a major purchase she had been fretting about. After days of the bot validating her worries, she became convinced that businesses were colluding to have her investigated by the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another patient came to believe that a romantic crush was sending her secret spiritual messages. Yet another thought he had stumbled onto a world-changing invention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the year, Dr. Sheffield had seen seven such patients at Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville. Although she is accustomed to treating people with mental instability, Dr. Sheffield was disturbed that this new technology seemed to tip people from simply having eccentric thoughts into full-on delusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like the A.I. was partnering with them in expanding or reinforcing their unusual beliefs,” Dr. Sheffield said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental health workers across the country are navigating how to treat problems caused or exacerbated by A.I. chatbots, according to more than 100 therapists and psychiatrists who told The New York Times about their experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many mentioned positive effects of the bots — like helping patients understand their diagnoses — they also said the conversations deepened their patients’ feelings of isolation or anxiety. More than 30 described cases resulting in dangerous emergencies like psychosis or suicidal thoughts. One California psychiatrist who often evaluates people in the legal system said she had seen two cases of violent crimes influenced by A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times reporters have documented more than 50 cases of psychological crises linked to chatbot conversations since last year. OpenAI, the maker of ChatGPT, is facing at least 11 personal injury or wrongful death lawsuits claiming that the chatbot caused psychological harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies behind the bots say these situations are exceedingly rare. “For a very small percentage of users in mentally fragile states there can be serious problems,” Sam Altman, the chief executive of OpenAI, said in October. The company has estimated that 0.15 percent of ChatGPT users discussed suicidal intentions over the course of a month, and 0.07 percent showed signs of psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a product with 800 million users, that translates to 1.2 million people with possible suicidal intent and 560,000 with potential psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Times has sued OpenAI, accusing it of violating copyright laws when training its models. The company has contested the lawsuit.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts said that the number of people susceptible to psychological harm, even psychosis, is far higher than the general public understands. The bots, they said, frequently pull people away from human relationships, condition them to expect agreeable responses and reinforce harmful impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A.I. could really, on a mass scale, change how many people are impacted,” said Haley Wang, a graduate student at U.C.L.A. who assesses people showing symptoms of psychosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychosis, which causes a break from reality, is most associated with schizophrenia. But as many as 3 percent of people will develop a diagnosable psychotic disorder in their lifetime, and far more are prone to delusional thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Joseph Pierre, a psychiatrist in San Francisco, said he had seen about five patients with delusional experiences involving A.I. While most had a diagnosis related to psychosis, he said, “sometimes these are very highly functioning people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For him, the idea that all chatbot-fueled delusions were going to happen anyway “just doesn’t hold water.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recently wrote in a scientific journal about a medical professional who began conversing with ChatGPT during a sleepless night. She took medication for ADHD and had a history of depression. After two nights of asking the chatbot questions about her dead brother, she became convinced that he had been communicating with her through a trail of digital footprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pierre and other experts said that a wide range of factors can combine to tip people into psychosis. These include not only genetic predisposition but also depression, lack of sleep, a history of trauma, and exposure to stimulants or cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m quite convinced that this is a real thing and that we are only seeing the tip of the iceberg,” said Dr. Soren Dinesen Ostergaard, a psychiatry researcher at Aarhus University Hospital in Denmark. In November, he published a report finding 11 cases of chatbot-associated delusions in psychiatric records from one Danish region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not unusual for new technologies to inspire delusions. But clinicians who have seen patients in the thrall of A.I. said it is an especially powerful influence because of its personal, interactive nature and authoritative tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a confidential news tip? The New York Times would like to hear from readers who want to share messages and materials with our journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the psychotic episodes spurred by chatbots can lead to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jessica Ferranti, a psychiatrist at UC Davis Health who often evaluates people in the legal system, said two of about 30 people she assessed last year in violent felony cases had delusional thoughts that were intensified by A.I. before the crimes occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both people developed messianic delusions about their own spiritual powers, Dr. Ferranti said. In one case, the bot mirrored and expanded on the psychotic thinking as the person came up with a plan to carry out a murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While delusional episodes have driven the public discourse about A.I. and mental health, the bots have other insidious effects that are far more widespread, doctors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several mental health workers who treat anxiety, depression or obsessive-compulsive disorders described A.I. either validating their clients’ worries or providing so much reassurance that patients felt reliant on chatbots to calm down — both less healthy than facing the source of the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Adam Alghalith of Mount Sinai Hospital in New York recalled a young man with depression who repeatedly shared negative thoughts with a chatbot. At first, the bot told him how to seek help. But he “just kept asking, kept pushing,” Dr. Alghalith said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safety guardrails that stop chatbots from encouraging suicide can break down when people engage the bots in extended conversations over days or weeks. Eventually, Dr. Alghalith said, the bot told the patient his thoughts of suicide were reasonable. Fortunately he had a support system and entered treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other doctors described chatbots flattering the grandiose tendencies of patients with personality disorders, or advising patients with autism to put themselves in dangerous social situations. Others said they saw patients’ interactions with chatbots as an addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quenten Visser, a therapist in Ozark, Mo., saw a 56-year-old last April who had experienced a panic attack. At first, Mr. Visser said, he thought the patient had severe anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after several therapy sessions, it became clear that the man was fixated on ChatGPT. He quit his job as a graphic designer after using ChatGPT 100 hours a week and having delusional thoughts about solving the energy crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This was this guy’s meth,” Mr. Visser said. He approached treatment as he would for any other addiction. They talked about what drove the man to use A.I.: lingering isolation from the pandemic and emotional distress he avoided by using chatbots. The man told The Times he now uses A.I. less, and makes art and works as a ride-share driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many doctors said that A.I.’s effects weren’t entirely negative. Some patients used the bots to practice techniques learned in therapy, for example, or as a nonjudgmental sounding board. Dr. Bob Lee, a psychiatry resident at a hospital in East Meadow, N.Y., even credited A.I. with saving a patient’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patient arrived at the emergency room last fall in a delusional panic about supernatural forces. He told doctors that a chatbot had identified his thoughts as symptoms of a crisis and advised him to go to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As with all new technologies, it can be used as a powerful force in both positive and negative ways,” Dr. Lee said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shannon Pagdon, a graduate student at the University of Pittsburgh who began having episodes of psychosis as a teenager and is now active in peer support networks, said A.I. can be useful to check whether her impressions line up with reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Like uploading a photo and saying, ‘Hey, do you see something in this photo?’” she explained. But, she said, she has also seen A.I. “reinforce psychotic experiences” in others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI has consulted with mental health experts to improve how ChatGPT responds to people who appear to be in a psychological crisis. The company has also formed a council with eight outside experts in psychology and human-computer interaction to advise its policy team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do we not keep people in this infinite loop of conversation with a machine?” said Munmun De Choudhury, a Georgia Tech professor and council member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although ChatGPT is by far the most used consumer chatbot, those made by Google, Anthropic and others also have millions of users. None have been able to avoid delusions and other harmful psychological effects, Dr. De Choudhury said. “I don’t think any of these companies have figured out what to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for Google said its Gemini chatbot advises users to find professional medical guidance for health-related queries. Anthropic, which makes Claude, published a blog post last month about a new feature that detects discussion of suicide or self-harm and routes users to help lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts advised therapists to ask patients about chatbot use, because its influence may not be obvious. For people trying to get their loved ones out of a delusional spiral, they advised reducing their time with the bot and making sure they get enough sleep. Insisting that the A.I. is wrong can be counterproductive if it makes the person angry or more isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sascha DuBrul, a mental health coach in Los Angeles, has seen firsthand both the good and bad of chatbot use. Last summer, Mr. DuBrul, whose work draws on his own experience with bipolar disorder, turned to ChatGPT when writing a book about psychotic episodes. After much back-and-forth, he became convinced A.I. would allow us to live “on some other level of reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With help from friends, he realized what was happening and pulled back from the bot. But he still believes mental health patients could benefit from a machine that listens infinitely — as long as it is connected to real human support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think that there’s a lot of potential there,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:54:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Says He Will Raise Tariffs on South Korea to 25%</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/economy/trump-tariffs-south-korea.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-tariffs-jpgm/26dc-trump-tariffs-jpgm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump on Monday said he would raise tariffs on South Korea.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/economy/trump-tariffs-south-korea.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:12:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Trump’s Shadow, India and the European Union Expand Trade Ties</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/india-europe-trade-tariffs-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/India-EU-Trade-pjbm/India-EU-Trade-pjbm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The European Council president, Antonio Costa, and the European Commission president, Ursula von der Leyen, came to India to announce a trade agreement nearly 20 years in the making.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/india-europe-trade-tariffs-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:05:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fed, Signaling Little Urgency, Prepares to Pause on Rate Cuts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-fed-mtlp/27dc-fed-mtlp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Fed, especially its chair, Jerome H. Powell, have been assailed by President Trump for not lowering interest rates fast enough.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:03:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>OpenAI’s Altman and More C.E.O.s Weigh In on Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27db-altman-fjvm/27db-altman-fjvm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sam Altman, C.E.O. of OpenAI, told employees, “What’s happening with ICE is going too far.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 04:44:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘The Outsiders’ Musical Recoups on Broadway</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/theater/outsiders-broadway-musical-profit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27cul-outsiders-ckzt/27cul-outsiders-ckzt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The musical, which received four Tony Awards, opened in April 2024 at the Bernard B. Jacobs Theater.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/theater/outsiders-broadway-musical-profit.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:00:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>G.M. Shares Rise as Investors Are Encouraged by 2026 Prospects</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A General Motors factory in Spring Hill, Tenn. G.M. said on Tuesday it planned to introduce a more advanced version of its Super Cruise driver assistance system in 2028.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:00:24 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>