<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:25:43 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>State and Federal Lawmakers Want Data Centers to Pay More for Energy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/energy-environment/data-center-energy-electricity-costs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15biz-data-center-energy-htkv/15biz-data-center-energy-htkv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governors, senators and even some tech executives increasingly agree that the companies behind data centers need to pay more for electricity and to address the strain they are causing on the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is little consensus about how much they ought to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A growing body of research suggests that the rapid growth of data centers to support the development of artificial intelligence is beginning to drive up electricity costs for residents and small businesses in some places. That has prompted Republicans and Democrats from at least a dozen states — including Florida, Oklahoma, New York and California — to propose legislation and consider other steps to protect residents from higher electricity costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Senator Chris Van Hollen of Maryland, a Democrat, introduced legislation that he said would ensure that technology companies paid their fair share of costs for upgrades to the electric grid that are needed to provide energy to data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Van Hollen’s bill cites recent analysis that indicates that by 2028, the share of all U.S. electricity used by data centers could almost double to as much as 12 percent. That, the senator asserts, will push up electricity prices for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we hope to do is create a national set of rules so that no matter where someone wants to build a data center, consumers know they are not going to get screwed with the costs,” Mr. Van Hollen said in an interview with The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology industry has responded to such proposals in a variety of ways. Executives at some companies like Microsoft have suggested that they are willing to pay more for electricity while others have said that they are already paying their fair share and have opposed efforts aimed at making them cough up more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One fundamental problem is the wide disagreement over how the costs of energy and of expanding and running the grid should be divided between individuals, ordinary businesses and large users like data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is most intense in some states, including Mr. Van Hollen’s. Maryland is part of the nation’s largest electricity market known as PJM, which serves all or parts of 13 states and the District of Columbia. PJM’s grid has the most data centers in the country, and electricity rates in its states are rising quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Shields, a spokesman for PJM, said the grid manager “is taking up many of these issues in its stakeholder process on large load additions and a decision from the PJM board is forthcoming.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent study from the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory found that data centers very likely reduced average retail electricity prices in recent years by spreading the fixed grid costs over more customers. But the study’s data ended in 2024, and the authors said it was hard to know whether this trend would continue as energy demand continued to rise sharply. The report noted a large increase in power prices last year in the Mid-Atlantic region linked to the expansion of data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electricity costs have steadily increased across the country in recent years, with the national average in October up 5 percent from a year earlier, according to data from the Energy Information Administration. A residential customer who used the typical amount of power of 1,000 kilowatt-hours paid about $180, up from $170 a year earlier. Electricity rates in three PJM states — Maryland, New Jersey and Virginia — were up 11 to 16 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to protecting consumers from higher costs, lawmakers are also trying to prevent an increase in blackouts and other grid problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Ron DeSantis of Florida has proposed a “Artificial Intelligence Bill of Rights” that would, among other things, allow local governments to prohibit construction of data centers to prevent higher electricity costs and stress on the power system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For its part, the technology industry has worked to compromise with states in some cases while fighting other proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, Amazon released a study it commissioned that concluded the tech company had more than covered its costs for power, allowing utilities to reduce rates for other customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft announced a plan on Tuesday that included promises to “pay our way to ensure our data centers don’t increase your electricity prices.” The plan also commits to minimizing water use and offering jobs and training to local residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no denying that A.I. consumes large amounts of electricity,” Brad Smith, vice chairman and president of Microsoft, said in a blog post. “While advances in technology may someday change this, today, this is the reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump praised Microsoft and said other technology companies would also address the issue. “I never want Americans to pay higher Electricity bills because of Data Centers,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Data Center Coalition, an industry association, said that the attention from state and federal governments highlighted the importance of the role the technology played in the 21st-century economy and that the tech industry was committed to covering its costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Data centers are committed to being responsible neighbors in the communities where they operate,” Josh Levi, president of the coalition, said in a statement. “The industry remains committed to paying its full cost of service for the energy it uses, and publications from states like Virginia and Arizona confirm we’re delivering on that commitment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech executives say artificial intelligence will make the economy much more productive. Many of them have also made commitments to use energy sources that do not emit greenhouse gases or offset emissions when they do have to use fossil fuels, the primary cause of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some climate and energy experts have expressed concerns that the expansion of data centers is leading to greater use of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/energy-environment/data-center-energy-electricity-costs.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:15:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leonard D. Jacoby, 83, Dies; Brought Legal Services to the Masses</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/leonard-d-jacoby-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00jacoby-qhmp/00jacoby-qhmp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard D. Jacoby, who as one-half of the law firm Jacoby &amp; Meyers revolutionized the legal world in the 1970s by bringing low-cost services to everyday Americans — and by winning the right to advertise those services on billboards and television — died on Monday in Manhattan. He was 83.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His stepdaughter Lindsey Schank said the death, at a hospital, was from complications of cardiac arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby and Stephen Z. Meyers, a friend from law school, started their firm in 1972 out of a single storefront in California’s San Fernando Valley. They wanted to fill a hole in the legal services industry: As they saw it, only the wealthy could afford the fees that most lawyers charged, while the very poor had access to legal aid. Those in the middle were left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They called their new firm a “legal clinic” to differentiate it from a traditional practice. It offered flat fees instead of charging by the hour. Potential clients met first with a paralegal who, if needed, could refer them to a lawyer — a process that kept costs down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jacoby &amp; Meyers opened clinics in suburbs and strip malls, close to its client bases, and stayed open late and on the weekends. People came for all sorts of services, including no-fault divorces, wills and personal bankruptcies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We set out to be the Sears of the legal profession, good value for a reasonable price,” Mr. Jacoby told Los Angeles Business Journal in 1999 — and, in fact, as the firm grew, it put some of its offices in department stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partners innovated in other ways, as well. They allowed clients to pay with credit cards. They created standardized intake forms and managed the information using a centralized database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were also unabashedly populist. In terms that are ubiquitous now, but were remarkable at the time, they promised to represent their clients in the fight against corporate greed and a broken system, a message that resonated during the anti-establishment 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Bar of California banned most forms of advertising, including speaking to the press. Nevertheless, the partners invited reporters to the opening of their first location. After giving a short speech, Mr. Jacoby asked, “Who needs a lawyer?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One man shouted that he did — his car had been repossessed. After a quick consultation and a phone call, they got it back for him, charging all of $15. The story made the evening news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clients came flooding in, but the State Bar was not pleased. It moved to censure the partners, who fought back. In 1977, the California Supreme Court — and, in a separate case, the U.S. Supreme Court — ruled that banning legal advertising was unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, Jacoby &amp; Meyers ran its first print ad, in The Los Angeles Times. Within a few weeks, the firm was running ads on television. In Southern California in the late 1970s, the ads were inescapable — the firm was running up to 100 a week, each ending with the slogan “Jacoby &amp; Meyers: It’s about time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1982, Jacoby &amp; Meyers had 43 offices in California and another 18 in New York, and was seeing around 9,000 new clients a month. It was also spending about $1.9 million a year on advertising (about $7 million today).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby found that even more than the law itself, he loved promoting it. He wrote the scripts for the TV ads and helped direct them, standing alongside voice actors in the studio to make sure they nailed the delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the pioneering firm in a trend that brought legal services to the masses, Jacoby &amp; Meyers was omnipresent. It was even name-checked in a rap song: “Got more suits than Jacoby &amp; Meyers,” the Beastie Boys sang in “Shadrach” in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such services are taxing, low-margin work, profitable only at a high volume. Yet by the end of the 1980s, thousands of lawyers had flooded into the space that Jacoby &amp; Meyers had carved out, plastering ads for low-cost legal representation on highway billboards and in subway cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 1990s, the firm pivoted toward more lucrative areas of consumer law, including personal injury, sexual harassment and class-action suits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also reduced the number of its offices and lawyers, and in the process Mr. Jacoby came to believe that Mr. Meyers and another partner, Gail Koff, were trying to push him out. He sued, and the partners settled by effectively splitting the firm in half: Mr. Jacoby took the West Coast, while Mr. Meyers and Ms. Koff took the East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Meyers died in an automobile accident in 1996.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard David Jacoby was born on March 27, 1942, in Lorain, Ohio, west of Cleveland. When he was 4, his parents, Nathan and Florence (Glasser) Jacoby, moved the family to the San Fernando Valley because Mr. Jacoby, who worked in real estate and giftware sales, had persistent health issues and thought the Southern California climate would do him good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leonard spent two years at the University of California, Berkeley before transferring to the University of California, Los Angeles, from which he graduated with a degree in history in 1964. He received his law degree from U.C.L.A. in 1967.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During law school, he grew close to Mr. Meyers, although they lost touch after graduation. Mr. Jacoby was working in private practice when he ran into Mr. Meyers, who was working in legal aid, at a conference in 1972. They founded their firm later that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jacoby’s first marriage, to Barbara Rood, ended in divorce. He married Nancy Platt in 1979.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to his stepdaughter, she survives him, along with a daughter from his first marriage, Sharre Jacoby; another stepdaughter, Laurie Arent; a son from an earlier relationship, Tom Nelson; five grandchildren; and a sister, Sandra Klein. Another sister, Daryl Saunders, died in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After splitting with Mr. Meyers, Mr. Jacoby remained involved with the West Coast iteration of the firm, though he eventually sold most of his shares.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Len was a visionary leader who fundamentally transformed the legal industry for both the profession and the public,” Michael Akiva, a managing partner at the firm, said in a statement. “His commitment to the middle class challenged longstanding barriers and brought quality legal representation to those who previously had nowhere to turn.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/leonard-d-jacoby-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:25:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan Reaches Trade Deal With Trump and Pledges More U.S. Chip Factories</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/taiwan-trade-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16Biz-Taiwan-Trade-mhbq/16Biz-Taiwan-Trade-mhbq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Taiwan manufactures most of the world’s advanced semiconductors.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/business/taiwan-trade-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:52:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uber’s Quest to Crack Japan Leads Through a Rural Hot-Springs Town</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/uber-japan-dara-khosrowshahi.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/Uber-Japan-Video-still-hcbp/Uber-Japan-Video-still-hcbp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ride-hailing giant’s chief executive has made a bet on how it can finally grab a bigger piece of one of the world’s largest taxi markets.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/uber-japan-dara-khosrowshahi.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:00:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Battles Over Truth Rage Online Amid Iran’s Internet Blackout</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/iran-internet-blackout-protests-disinformation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/IRAN-DISINFO-1-mbvp/IRAN-DISINFO-1-mbvp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A frame grab from footage circulating on social media showing protesters dancing and cheering in Tehran last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/iran-internet-blackout-protests-disinformation.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Stock Investors’ Strategy for 2026:‘Don’t Fight the White House’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/stock-market-trump-policy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/business/16biz-trump-stocks-promo/16biz-trump-stocks-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From oil drillers to credit card companies, President Trump has been a market mover this year.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/stock-market-trump-policy.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:05:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ted Sarandos Says Critics Just Misunderstand Netflix</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/media/ted-sarandos-netflix.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/12/multimedia/SARANDOS-1-01-jkqz/SARANDOS-1-01-jkqz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
“We’re going to be the buyer who keeps Warner Bros. running, releasing movies in theaters the way they always have,” said Ted Sarandos of Netflix, talking about the company’s deal for Warner Bros. Discovery’s movie and TV business.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/media/ted-sarandos-netflix.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:05:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Larry Fink, the New Mayor of Davos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/dealbook/fink-davos-wef.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16db-fink-fmgb/16db-fink-fmgb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Larry Fink, C.E.O. of BlackRock, has become a force in reshaping the agenda and participant list for the World Economic Forum.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/dealbook/fink-davos-wef.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 03:53:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What’s Next for Cuba, Now That Its Main Oil Supplier Is Gone?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/cuba-venezuela-mexico-oil-diplomacy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/16biz-strategies-pktb/16biz-strategies-pktb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A street in Havana. Cuba is reported to have less than two months of imported oil on hand.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/cuba-venezuela-mexico-oil-diplomacy.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 05:00:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Michael Saylor’s Creative Bitcoin Strategy Isn’t Working</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/michael-saylor-strategy-bitcoin.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/business/18Saylor-illo/18Saylor-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Saylor’s financial alchemy thrust an ordinary software company, Strategy, into the center of the crypto frenzy. It all worked spectacularly, until now.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/business/michael-saylor-strategy-bitcoin.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 05:00:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>