<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>‘Like a Timeshare’: Doctors Get Creative as Rents Climb</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/doctors-office-leasing-rent.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/00BIZ-OFFICE-AFTER-HOURS-1-bmcj/00BIZ-OFFICE-AFTER-HOURS-1-bmcj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jaishree Capoor was pushing her 91-year-old mother in a wheelchair along Fifth Avenue in Manhattan when a ground-level office caught her eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a private entrance, and a sign indicated that the office, in an apartment building on the corner of East 86th Street, was home to a medical practice for adolescents. On a whim, Dr. Capoor, a pediatric physiatrist who works with young people with cerebral palsy and other motor and developmental challenges, asked the office manager if any space was available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out, a consultation room had just been vacated, and Dr. Capoor sublet the space on weekends when the practice is closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangement, which started in October and costs Dr. Capoor $500 a month, means her patients don’t have to miss school and their parents don’t have to take time off from work. And because the office is near the apartment she shares with her mother and sister, Dr. Capoor can quickly get home to help care for their mother, who has severe dementia, and be back in time for her next patient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Capoor also works part time from an office in Queens and a therapy gym in Westchester County. The ad hoc arrangements give her access to patients in multiple areas while allowing her to maintain a low overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like a micropractice,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Capoor is not the only New York physician with an independent practice who is cobbling together part-time, often transient arrangements, as rents rise and renovating spaces for medical use can be prohibitively expensive. In Manhattan, asking rents average $58 per square foot for outpatient offices, according to JLL, a real estate services firm, which forecasts rising rents and declining office availability this year. And, on average, it costs $500 to $600 per square foot to make the spaces work for medical practices, said Matt Coursen, health care lead for U.S. leasing at JLL. A 2,211-square-foot space, average for an outpatient office in 2025, could end up costing over $128,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangements help doctors expand their practices without huge financial commitments. Many smaller practices have already been feeling the squeeze from bigger players like hospital groups and private equity firms, both of which have increasingly been buying up and consolidating solo practices. Nearly 80 percent of doctors nationwide work for hospitals or other corporate entities, according to a 2024 report from the Physicians Advocacy Institute. As of January 2024, 30 percent of U.S. physician practices were owned by corporations, doubling from about 15 percent in January 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Independent practice has gotten more difficult over the years,” said Hayden Rooke-Ley, a senior fellow at the Brown University School of Public Health who has done research on the corporatization and consolidation of the U.S. medical field. “Relative to large hospitals and corporate players, reimbursement for independent practice has declined and operating costs have grown, making access to capital more challenging.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rising demand for part-time, hybrid and short-term arrangements has created business opportunities for doctors who can afford to lease office space. Some are taking on the costs of making the spaces work for medical use with the intention that they’ll sublet some or all of those spaces to other physicians. Others are signing multiple leases and furnishing offices that can be booked on an as-needed basis. And more online platforms have sprung up in recent years to connect health professionals who need space with those who have it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Maria Sokolina signed a 10-year lease in 2023 for a space on West 57th Street in Manhattan for her dentistry practice. The monthly rent is $6,000, and she spent about $500,000 renovating it and installing equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help cover her expenses, Dr. Sokolina, whose primary practice is in Clifton, N.J., shares her office with two other dentists. One uses the space once a week, and the other two days a week. Another physician, Dr. Zarui Chopuryan, uses one of the rooms in the evenings to offer collagen stimulation and other cosmetic treatments, after working in palliative care at Montefiore Medical Center in the Bronx during the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m building up a practice,” said Dr. Chopuryan, who pays $1,500 a month for the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Masoud Saman, a plastic surgeon, placed an advertisement on a medical society website to rent out a spare exam room after he remodeled his office near Columbus Circle. He was looking for someone with a specialty that would complement his own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m the nose-job person here,” Dr. Saman said. “Someone who does eyelids would be a nice, symbiotic relationship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real estate brokers are typically not involved in these off-market transactions. A doctor with an office may offer a licensing agreement for a year at a time to a colleague who needs the space for three hours every Friday. “It’s like a timeshare,” said Ruth Colp-Haber, president and chief executive of Wharton Property Advisors, a real estate brokerage. (Those working out of the space part time must have their own malpractice insurance.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therapists in particular have been scrambling for space after years of remote counseling during the pandemic. Some are seeing patients, for example, in law offices after those businesses have closed for the day, said Ms. Colp-Haber, whose company works with a firm offering such an arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Glazer, a clinical psychologist in the United Kingdom, co-founded US Therapy Rooms in 2021 and now has over 3,000 listings. Many of them offer part-time options, Dr. Glazer said, including monthly packages for space once a week ($400 to $700) and even by the hour ($30 to $50).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Part-time arrangements have evolved from a niche offering to the new normal,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batya Srolovitz, a psychotherapist who started a practice in October, used the platform to find her current setup: She is now one of seven mental health professionals who occupy a suite of offices on Manhattan’s Upper West Side. Each is subletting from a therapist who holds the lease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Srolovitz sees patients there Mondays through Thursdays and recently placed an ad offering her office for use on Fridays, when she sees clients virtually, and weekends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kathleen Maher, another therapist, turned the need to rent an office for herself into a side business called TherapyHive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the pandemic, she was leasing space in a building in the Flatiron district that she had divided into 38 offices for herself and other mental health professionals. When demand for in-person sessions dwindled during Covid, she set up a website with a reservation platform and furnished some offices so they can be booked on an as-needed basis. “I must own 16 couches now,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carla Mannino, a psychotherapist and the owner of Gotham Psychotherapy, made a different kind of change during the pandemic. With landlords offering discounts on vacant spaces, she saw an opportunity to realize her dream of working in the Chrysler Building. She signed a one-year lease with Regus, a co-working company, for a corner office with a peek at one of the building’s famous gargoyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She took on more space cautiously, signing six-month leases at a time as she hired staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At any point, I could pull the plug,” Dr. Mannino said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2024, people were returning to offices and all of Regus’s space in the Chrysler Building was spoken for. But Dr. Mannino’s practice was still growing, so she added space in the nearby Chanin Building. An underground tunnel connects the two structures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We go through the tunnel all the time,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mannino now has a staff of 25, and she is paying more for rent than she would if she were to sign a lease of her own elsewhere, she said. But she loves the arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t have to worry about HVAC or Verizon,” she said. “I’m 58 years old. I don’t want to sign a 10-year lease.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/business/doctors-office-leasing-rent.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:17:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Top Editor at Axel Springer Is Ousted After Workplace Investigation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/media/axel-springer-editor-welt.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/business/18biz-axelspringer1/18biz-axelspringer1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the top editors at Axel Springer, the German media giant behind major American publications like Politico and Business Insider, left the company after an investigation into inappropriate behavior, according to three people familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation into the person, Jan Philipp Burgard, who was the editor in chief of the center-right broadsheet Welt, began this month after executives at Axel Springer received a media inquiry about Mr. Burgard’s behavior at an alcohol-filled company Christmas party in December, two of the people said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the investigation, Mr. Burgard, 41, was asked whether he had behaved inappropriately toward female employees of Axel Springer at the party, two of the people said, including whether he had kissed the employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under questioning, Mr. Burgard acknowledged that he had been drinking at the party, but said he could not recall whether the reports were true, two of the people said. After that conversation, Axel Springer told Mr. Burgard to resign, the two people said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Burgard did not respond to emails, texts or phone calls seeking comment. In a LinkedIn post last week, he said he had decided to resign after experiencing “a serious physical incident” on a flight back from vacation that required him to be treated by a doctor in midair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reached by phone on Saturday, a spokesman for Axel Springer declined to comment on personnel matters. After The Times published its article on Sunday, a spokesman for Axel Springer said in a statement that its investigation into misbehavior at the Christmas party had found no evidence to substantiate specific allegations of sexual harassment against Mr. Burgard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Burgard is being replaced by Helge Fuhst, a top editor at the German public broadcaster Ard. Mr. Fuhst will also oversee the German editions of Axel Springer’s U.S. titles, including Politico and Business Insider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Burgard was one of Axel Springer’s most prominent editors, steering its influential German broadsheet and appearing on its TV network. In 2024, he responded publicly to a controversial op-ed Welt Group had published that was written by the billionaire Elon Musk endorsing Germany’s far-right AfD party. Before he joined Axel Springer, he was the U.S. correspondent for Ard, covering the White House and traveling across America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Burgard’s exit comes as Axel Springer, a European media giant with holdings in the United States and Germany, looks to expand its influence in America. Mathias Döpfner, the influential chief executive who in effect controls the company, has been aggressively pursuing other publications in the United States in recent months, telling The Wall Street Journal in December that he was “ready to move” on major acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But questions about the conduct of Axel Springer’s top editors continue to follow the company. Five years ago, Axel Springer dismissed Julian Reichelt, who was editor of the center-right tabloid Bild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times reported in 2021 that Mr. Reichelt had a relationship with a trainee who testified during an independent legal investigation that he had summoned her in 2018 to a hotel near the office for sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Georgia Gee contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/media/axel-springer-editor-welt.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:26:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Joe Montgomery, Who Made Bicycles Lighter, Dies at 86</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/obituaries/joe-montgomery-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/18montgomery-01-lpqz-print1/18montgomery-01-lpqz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Montgomery, who founded Cannondale and transformed the cycling industry with bikes built of lightweight aluminum instead of heavier steel, sometimes walked around the company’s headquarters in Connecticut jingling coins in his pocket when the mood needed lifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You know what that is?” he would say, Murray Washburn, Cannondale’s director of product marketing, recalled in an interview. “That’s change. Change is good. We like change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an overt display of his philosophy of embracing innovation and dismissing the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Montgomery died of complications of a heart-related illness on Jan. 2 at his home in Vero Beach, Fla., his daughter, Lauren Edinger, said. He was 86.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Cannondale, which Mr. Montgomery founded in 1971 with three partners, he and his team of designers and engineers changed the build, weight and feel of upscale, high-tech bicycles. The company was among the first in the United States to mass-produce bikes with frames made of large-diameter aluminum tubes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t have a college degree, but I’ve always been a seat-of-the-pants engineer type,” Mr. Montgomery said in 1993 in an interview with The New York Times, which called Cannondale the “Lamborghini of mountain bikes” with shock-absorber systems “that are more sophisticated than some people’s first cars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company’s oft-told origin story is that Mr. Montgomery spotted a cyclist struggling up a hill in Wilton, Conn., under the weight of a heavy backpack. His idea of lightening the load was to build a trailer, known as the Bugger, that would be towed behind the bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cannondale opened its first office in a loft above a pickle factory in Wilton, in Fairfield County. Needing a phone line for the new venture, an employee, Peter Meyers, walked outside to a pay phone and placed an order. When asked what the company was called, Mr. Meyers is said to have peered at the name of a nearby neighborhood train station and said, “Cannondale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1970s, the company continued making biking accessories and apparel, tents and sleeping bags, along with dog beds for L.L. Bean. Then, in 1983, it produced its first bicycle, the ST-500, a touring model that sold for $495 (the equivalent of more than $1,600 today). It featured an oversize aluminum frame that became a Cannondale hallmark — lightweight but stiff, strong and responsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1993, The Times reported, the company was generating $100 million a year and had 800 employees worldwide. As Cannondale battled top competitors like Specialized, Trek and Giant, the company became known for numerous other innovations, including a single-legged fork, which provided a smooth ride; a carbon-fiber shell integrated with an aluminum spine; and SmartSense, a safety feature that employed lights, sensors and rear-facing radar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its first mountain bike, produced in 1984, featured a 26-inch front wheel and a 24-inch rear wheel to help the rider roll over rocks and roots. It was dismissed by some critics as cycling’s version of a mullet haircut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But by the 1990s, enhanced Cannondale mountain bikes were winning multiple medals at world championships and the Olympics. At the 1999 Tour de France, the Italian sprinter Mario Cipollini won four consecutive stages aboard a Cannondale racing bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company also experimented with one-off concepts in the 1990s, like a bike that replaced a traditional front wheel with Rollerblade wheels for maximal aerodynamics. And there was the so-called Pong bike, which was made of aluminum that was cut and shaped by a computerized process and which resembled a futuristic can opener.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Cannondale started out with a kooky streak, and they never lost it,” Zapata Espinoza, a leading cycling journalist, wrote in an appraisal of Mr. Montgomery, extolling his passion for “trying to be different.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Cannondale designed a bike that the adventurer Kevin Foster audaciously rode more than 1,500 miles along the Great Wall of China. The prototype had a seat that doubled as a tire pump and featured an automatic transmission that changed gears according to pedal pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It felt like I was putting on a tailored suit,” Mr. Foster posted in an online remembrance of Mr. Montgomery. “I was the engine, the bike, the machine.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph Stephen Montgomery was born on Dec. 11, 1939, in Coshocton, Ohio, about 110 miles south of Cleveland. His father, Edward Montgomery, was an entrepreneur who developed a process for coating cotton gloves with a rubberized compound. His mother, Frances (Bingenheimer) Montgomery, ran the family fruit farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe, too, was an inveterate tinkerer with bikes and farm equipment. He told The Times that as a boy, he built a small jeep, scavenging the transmission from a junkyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was 12 at the time, Ms. Edinger, his daughter, said in an interview, saying that her father’s ardor for barreling down a hill was overwhelmed one day by his inability to avoid crashing into the front doors of a church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think that’s how he ended up in boarding school,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Montgomery’s devotion to college ended after fits and starts — “He was just not going to do what everybody wanted him to do,” Ms. Edinger said — and, in his 20s, he found a more suitable pursuit in the Caribbean, working on the crews of racing sailboats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sturdiness of the masts gave him an appreciation for the strength-to-weight aspect of aluminum, Ms. Edinger said, as did an accident that reportedly left him and four others clinging to an overturned aluminum hull while waiting to be rescued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After stints in finance and running a bar/restaurant in New York City, Mr. Montgomery founded Cannondale. He reshaped the business with aluminum frames on the suggestion, in a letter, of an engineer, David Graham, who worked for a Connecticut company that built submarines for the Navy; Cannondale promptly hired him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website BikeRadar, to whom Mr. Washburn first told the coin-jingling story, called Mr. Montgomery “one of cycling’s greatest minds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wore jeans and sweatpants; favored conversations over emails; and opened offices in Europe and Japan but kept his manufacturing base in Bedford, Pa., which he visited twice weekly on flights aboard a corporate jet that he piloted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He regularly brought along bike shop owners to the factory to promote the Cannondale brand and make dealers feel like true partners, Dave Cote, a former graphic designer at the company, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It would be like taking batting practice at Fenway Park,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cannondale eventually became overextended and underfinanced when it ventured into the motocross motorcycle and all-terrain vehicle businesses. In 2003, it filed for bankruptcy. In “a roundabout way,” Mr. Espinoza wrote, it was Mr. Montgomery’s “confidence in himself and his employees that created the motorcycle debacle that lost him his company.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company is now owned by Pon Holdings, a Dutch conglomerate. Mr. Montgomery later founded a software company to handle billing and medical records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to his daughter, he is survived by his wife of 43 years, Celia (Congdon) Montgomery, and their sons Michael, Lucas and John. He is also survived by a son from a previous marriage that ended in divorce, Scott, who was a longtime Cannondale executive; and three grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Scott Montgomery said, “would have rather pushed the envelope on technology, and lead and crash and burn, than to be timid and afraid.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/obituaries/joe-montgomery-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:25:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Alaska Town Is Now Key to Trump’s Global Ambitions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the unimaginative eye, the view of Nome, Alaska, from Joy Baker’s well-heated S.U.V. looked like a whole lot of nothing: The early winter sun was sliding below the horizon barely four hours after it had risen, the gray water of the inner harbor had already frozen over, and the only stirring came from a flock of hearty seabirds diving for dinner just off shore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Baker has a vision that goes well beyond the subarctic calm: “More traffic, more services, more jobs. More of everything for people here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Baker is director of the Port of Nome and thus the local overseer for a $548-million-and-counting plan to expand the port, in one of America’s most remote cities on the Bering Sea. Nome is a quiet, frozen frontier town much of the year, known mostly for the Iditarod sled race, and reachable only by air except for a few summer months when the water thaws enough to allow boats through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, however, Nome’s existing dock will be turned into the country’s first deepwater Arctic port, a critical hub in President Trump’s ambitions to make the United States master of the far north and compete with other world powers for untapped natural resources and shipping corridors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president didn’t originate the decade-old plan to expand Nome’s existing port, but his Arctic ambitions, including his efforts to take over Greenland, are longstanding and widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s aspirations for Nome were made clear near the end of his first term, when Congress authorized the port expansion with administration support. Last year, the project moved from paper to procurement as the Army Corps of Engineers awarded a $399.4 million construction contract for the first phase amid an administration-wide push to treat the Arctic and critical minerals as strategic priorities. This summer, crews will start demolishing the existing port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expansion should be complete, and Nome potentially remade, by 2033.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not actually like the current administration is trying to open the Arctic —Mother Nature did that,” said Ms. Baker, a gruff South Texan who moved to Alaska in 1987 and scoffs at ever returning to what Alaskans call, not always lovingly, the Lower 48. “I just see the current administration as just capitalizing in a way that will ensure our country is more self-sufficient. That can’t be a bad thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the port expansion will be good for Nome is a big question for many of the town’s 3,700 year-round residents and an itinerant population of contractors, health workers and dog mushing fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Port expansion, and the economic growth that follows, is expected to double or even triple the population, and some in Nome worry about what could happen without a solid strategy for long-term economic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is something of a boom-and-bust town,” said Jim West Jr., a longtime civic leader whose eclectic portfolio of businesses includes a gravel company, the local taxi service and the 125-year-old Board of Trade Saloon. “We need to make sure this isn’t just another economic cycle but something with lasting benefits for our children and grandchildren.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nome’s boom began at the turn of the 20th century when prospectors immortalized as the Three Lucky Swedes found gold in nearby Anvil Creek. Their discovery briefly turned Nome into Alaska’s largest city, with more than 20,000 residents. A second kind of gold rush came in 2011, prompted by surging gold prices and consisting largely of offshore dredging, but ebbed almost as quickly as it began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the flat, treeless winter tundra around Nome is dotted with abandoned mining rigs, and the city is stuck in economic stagnation. Little is produced this close to the Arctic Circle, and everything must arrive either by plane or seasonal barge. Prices, in turn, would shock Lower 48 shoppers. On a recent visit, a gallon of gas cost $6.50, a gallon of milk went for $6.99 and one browning honeydew melon was priced at almost $12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to convince locals to stay and even harder to woo new year-round residents. The hospital and most construction companies bring in temporary workers and either build their own housing or provide housing subsidies that reduce supply and raise costs for year-round residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Civic leaders like Ms. Baker, a former Nome harbor master who came out of retirement to manage the expansion, believe the project will lead to financial sustainability. But that presumes city officials can figure out how to pay for it all. Under its deal with the state and federal governments, Nome must cover 10 percent of port construction costs and 100 percent of its own port-related infrastructure needs, such as roads, streetlights and sewer lines. The city does not know how much that will cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond Nome City Hall, optimism about the port’s effect is the cautious sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teriscovkya Smith, the principal at Nome-Beltz Middle High School, estimated that 80 percent of her students won’t go to college and hoped the expansion could bring vocational internships and quality entry-level jobs. So far, however, she hasn’t heard from anyone involved in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People who stay build careers, they buy houses, they pay property taxes,” said Ms. Smith, who fished in Alaska for 10 years before becoming a teacher. “There’s a real risk that we just waste an amazing opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, Nome voters agreed to increase the local sales tax to 6 percent to avoid cuts to services such as pothole repair as well as hours at the town recreation center. The Nome school district balanced its budget last year by taking money from a fund set aside for teacher housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing money go into the port when other services face cuts can rankle. “I see the point of this thing for some other people — for the military maybe, for big shipping companies, for cruise lines,” said Keith Reddaway, co-owner of Builders Industrial Supply, a hardware store a block from the port. “But I’m not sure I see the point for Nome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tribal members also worry about what this all could mean for the subsistence lifestyle that dominates their 15 Alaska villages of the Bering Strait region. Around Nome, 86 percent of the population identifies as Indigenous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The port expansion and a new nearby graphite mine, fast-tracked by Mr. Trump, could bring more noise, air and water pollution, damage fishing and affect migratory birds and whales. They’re scared that they will be forced to abandon their traditional homes and seasonal schedules. And they worry Nome, always a little gritty around the edges, will revert to its rougher early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Outsiders bring in drugs,” said Shirley Martin, a member of the Yup’ik nation, whose village is across the Norton Sound. “People from the villages come through all the time to see family, go to the doctor, mail packages, just eat out. Will this still be a place where we feel comfortable?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time Nome has played a part in American security. During the Cold War, the U.S. military kept Air Force bases connected in case of a Soviet attack with an antenna installation atop nearby Anvil Mountain. Today, locals call the abandoned array “Nomehenge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, with sea ice thawing and the United States, Russia and China all eyeing Arctic shipping lanes and natural resources, Nome has emerged again as one of the most strategically important places in the Northern Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expanded port won’t be a military base, but Nome is an hour’s flight from Russia. Deepening the port from 22 feet to 40 feet will allow every type of U.S. military vessel except aircraft carriers to dock in Nome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a small-town police chief, and I’ve got intelligence officers from the Navy, the Coast Guard, the Air Force coming in here to sit with me,” said William Crockett, Nome’s retiring police chief. “Something big is coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:16:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nature’s Super Feather</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/science/birds-feathers-filoplumes-cornell.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/23/multimedia/00BIRD-FEATHERS-promo-wkcq/00BIRD-FEATHERS-promo-wkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vanya Gregor Rohwer slid open a drawer to display the rich pink spread wing of a roseate spoonbill, one of thousands of mounted wings at the Cornell University Museum of Vertebrates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pulled up a long flight feather to expose, at its base, a palm-tree shaped feather so minuscule it could easily be missed. For a long time, this tiny feature called a filoplume was indeed obscure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The history of research on filoplumes is not super robust. They are kind of an overlooked feather,” said Dr. Rohwer, a curator of birds and mammals at the museum. “They were considered a degenerate feather or a useless feather, a relic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No longer. Dr. Rohwer and his father, Sievert Rohwer, an influential feather researcher and curator emeritus at the Burke Museum at the University of Washington in Seattle, believe that the tiny filoplume is a key player in the monitoring and maintenance of birds’ feathers, which keep them airborne.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since feathers first appeared on dinosaurs around 150 million years ago, they have been evolving. Now there are six types of feathers on a bird’s body, including filoplumes, and all are made of keratin, a dead substance like human hair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A paper published last year in the Journal of the Royal Society Interface described a feather as a masterpiece of engineering, one comprising nine orders of magnitude, from the nanoscale to the meter scale. Because the most sophisticated 3-D printers are limited to just four or five orders of magnitude, feathers have yet to be replicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no manufacturing technology that can come close to a feather,” said David Lentink, one of the paper’s authors, who studies birds to find ways to improve robots at the University of Groningen in the Netherlands. “They are unusually sophisticated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is a natural material that is so light that it floats slowly to the ground, yet so strong it can protect a bird flying through wind, rain and cold for days on end. And new ones replace the old ones every few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest in bird feathers has intensified alongside the rapidly expanding uses of drones and other aircraft, with researchers looking at whether synthetic feathers would make flights more maneuverable, efficient and less noisy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes have inspired micro or hair sensors, for example, that can measure air flow, speed and direction to support a type of self-navigation called “flight by feel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplume-like sensors could help drones, which have difficulty dealing with wind gusts, make split-second adjustments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All birds have filoplumes, even those that cannot fly. There are usually one to three per feather, and they are densest around contour or body feathers and flight feathers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes detect pressure, touch and vibration in adjacent feathers and, through highly sensitive nerve endings, called Herbst corpuscles, in their follicles, translate those mechanical cues into neuronal signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sophisticated feathers provide birds with detailed information about their plumage as they fly. They tell them to adjust their feathers to stay warm, or to release heat. They may also detect the movement of parasites,prompting the birds to preen or emit oil in that area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Bristle feathers, short and found on a bird’s head, face and neck, are also sensitive to the environment and alert birds to insects and other prey.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The birds with the most filoplumes are large, strong flying species like eagles, albatrosses and vultures. Albatrosses, which have been known to fly 6,000 miles or more without stopping, are among those who have the most — more than 9,000 have been counted on some birds. So far, red-tail hawks have the most filoplumes per feather among the birds whose feathers have been counted by researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Filoplumes play other roles. The beard of a wild turkey is actually thin strands of feather called mesofiloplumes. They aren’t sensory, but ornamental, and may grow up to a foot in length. A wild turkey does have filoplumes on its bald head, though, which help it sense the world around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whiskered auklets, a seabird, have large ones atop their heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those are elaborate filoplumes,” Dr. Vanya Rohwer said. “They use them for navigating down these dark nesting burrows so they are not hitting their heads.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying filoplumes and other plumage alongside his father for more than 20 years, he thought he knew how birds lost and regrew their feathers every few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was predictable, sequential and orderly,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2015, though, the Rohwers learned about a captive golden eagle whose tail feathers were cut experimentally for research purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That eagle replaced a cut tail feather way, way faster than an uncut feather,” the younger Dr. Rohwer said, shortening the growth period to about a year. “So birds have some mechanism to detect a feather that is not performing well.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Dr. Sievert Rohwer, said that the filoplumes, presumably, “are sensitive to vibration the feather would generate if it’s worn or not functioning as well as it should.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes intuitive sense,” the younger Dr. Rohwer said. “You are crashing through the brush capturing prey or struggling with it on the ground, a process very likely to break a feather.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Rohwers are leading curators of extended bird wings, which they have used to study filoplumes and other feathers. The elder Dr. Rohwer, 83, has amassed the world’s largest collection of bird wings, which have been spread out and mounted at the Burke Museum, with 40,000 pairs pinned open in cellophane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Vanya Rohwer, 43, is building a sizable spread wing collection of his own here at Cornell, which so far comprises around 10,000 pairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full bird specimens, meanwhile, are kept in drawers, in a kind of morgue. Dr. Rohwer opened some of them on a recent tour to reveal an array of colorful plumage, including pink-and-peach-colored lilac breasted rollers and green-and-yellow bee eaters. Another drawer was filled with extinct species, including several ivory-billed woodpeckers and a passenger pigeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bird nests are another passion of the younger Dr. Rohwer’s and he studies bird eyelashes as well. In one study, he found that the use of snakeskin to line many birds’ nests significantly reduced predation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Rohwer met his wife, Rachel Schlass Rohwer, when, as a budding taxidermist, she attended his class on the preparation of avian specimens. She was smitten both by Dr. Rohwer and the painstaking process of preparing birds for display in museums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Knowing these passenger pigeons once eclipsed the sky, and seeing them in these drawers with so much of their color retained, it really moved me,” Ms. Schlass Rohwer said. “Most things when they die lose color and lose so much of their narrative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The couple has taken several salvage trips to harvest surplus bird and mammal specimens from freezers at other museums for the Cornell collection. They skin and stuff the birds with cotton or spread their wings in a display, where they are available to researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Schlass Rowher, who has also studied fashion, has specialized in designing hats with ethically obtained feathers from birds who died naturally and are legal to own. It’s a violation of federal law to possess most types of bird feathers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With advances in technologies, new information is being extracted from feathers. DNA from a single feather, for instance, allows researchers to trace that bird back to its breeding population. That information is being used to create “genoscape” maps across the world for migratory birds, and to prioritize important habitats for conservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The filoplume, though, remains one of the least-understood feathers. “A lot remains to be discovered about their function,” Dr. Lentink said, “because it is almost impossible to study their function in living birds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bird in the lab is very different than a bird in the air, leaving avian flight largely a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes science can’t answer questions because the experiments are too hard, this is such a case,” he said. “It is hard to really prove functions of these feathers in a fully functional happy flying bird doing its normal behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/science/birds-feathers-filoplumes-cornell.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:51:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s First Year Could Have Lasting Economic Consequences</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/trump-first-year-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-trump-econ-pmgz/20dc-trump-econ-pmgz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the chaos along the way, President Trump’s first year back in the White House is ending with an economy that looks, by most conventional measures, much like the one he inherited. Unemployment is low, consumer spending is strong and inflation is stubbornly high but gradually improving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tariffs, Mr. Trump’s signature economic policy, haven’t set off the manufacturing renaissance he promised, but nor have they caused the surge in inflation that many forecasters feared. The stock market bobbed and weaved its way to a solid if not spectacular 16 percent gain. Analysts who began 2025 warning of the perils of uncertainty ended it by remarking on the U.S. economy’s surprising resilience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet it would be a mistake to think that Mr. Trump’s actions left the economy unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much more so than in his first four years in office, Mr. Trump has begun his second term with what amounts to an all-out assault on many of the institutions and policy paradigms that have long been seen by leaders of both major political parties as the foundations of American economic strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has sought to undermine the independence of the Federal Reserve, fired the head of the Bureau of Labor Statistics, an agency that collects key economic data, and cut funding to the universities that conduct much of the country’s cutting-edge scientific research. He has intervened in private business deals, taken stakes in private companies and threatened corporate executives who do not adequately embrace his policy priorities. He has sharply restricted immigration, questioned the value of America’s alliances and imposed punishing tariffs on friends as well as adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of those actions are being challenged in the courts, and future presidents could reverse course on at least some of the current administration’s policies. But economists from across the ideological spectrum warn that Mr. Trump is setting the country on a path that will, in the long run, leave the economy less dynamic, the financial system less stable and Americans less prosperous in the decades ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re weakening the special sauce that made America so great,” said Kimberly A. Clausing, an economist at the University of California, Los Angeles, School of Law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Clausing worked in the Treasury Department in the Biden administration. But her concerns are shared by many economists on the right, including some who have worked for Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vance Ginn, who served as chief economist in the Office of Management and Budget during Mr. Trump’s first term, praised the administration’s efforts to eliminate regulations and lower corporate taxes. But he said the benefits of those moves are outweighed by the costs of its policies on trade and immigration, its failure to rein in the federal deficit and its intervention in the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“On net, the policies have been negative for the economy,” Mr. Ginn said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects will most likely be subtle, however, showing up as a steady drip of slower growth and higher interest rates that are hard to detect in the moment. A more acute crisis, if one comes at all, might show up years or decades in the future, much too late for voters to hold Mr. Trump or his administration accountable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We know from a lot of historical experience that the sort of things he’s doing are antithetical to prosperity in the long run,” said Gregory N. Mankiw, a Harvard economist who worked in the White House under President George W. Bush. But, Mr. Mankiw added, it is impossible to know exactly when or where those consequences will be felt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More politically salient in the short run may be Mr. Trump’s failure so far to address the widespread economic dissatisfaction that helped him win the 2024 election in the first place. Mr. Trump ran for president on a promise to “end inflation” and even to bring down prices — something that economists at the time dismissed as fantasy but that connected with voters frustrated by years of big price increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once back in office, however, Mr. Trump said little about longstanding cost-of-living issues like housing and child care, and he opposed extending subsidies that made health insurance cheaper for people who buy coverage on federal health care exchanges. Instead, he focused on imposing tariffs, a policy that economists warned would lead to higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of the public shared those concerns about tariffs. Consumer sentiment rallied when Mr. Trump won the 2024 election, but cratered during the chaotic early days of his administration. For much of last year, well over half of the people responding to the University of Michigan’s long-running sentiment survey spontaneously brought up tariffs, with most of them saying they expected prices to rise as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, Americans have cited a new concern: the job market. Unemployment has risen only modestly over the past year, but hiring has slowed significantly, and Americans have become increasingly worried about their ability to find a new job if they lose their current one. That has fed into affordability concerns, as Americans, still frustrated by high prices, now also worry about losing their incomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They see young people around them struggling to find a job,” said Joanne Hsu, who directs the Michigan survey. “They see how people who are unemployed and looking for work, they see how long it takes them to find a job. So even though we don’t have mass layoffs, I think it’s unambiguously the case that it is harder to find a job now than it was just a few years ago.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s defenders argue that it will take time for his policies to bear fruit. Companies will have to adapt their strategies to a world with higher tariffs and fewer immigrant workers, then build the factories and buy the equipment to put those new plans in place, argued Oren Cass, a longtime critic of free trade who leads American Compass, a populist think tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hiring people to work in your factory is not something that you do within six months of a global economic reset,” Mr. Cass said. “You’re lucky if the company has finished developing its new strategy yet, let alone started putting shovels in the ground on anything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few economists share Mr. Cass’s optimism around Mr. Trump’s trade policies. But while tariffs dominated the conversation in 2025, many economists say they are far from the most damaging policies Mr. Trump has embraced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are much more worried about Mr. Trump’s efforts to undermine the Fed’s independence, which, if successful, could make it harder for the central bank to rein in inflation — or, in a potentially even more damaging scenario, cause investors to lose faith in the value of government-issued bonds or the dollar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are worried about yawning budget deficits — a problem that long predates Mr. Trump but that was made worse by the tax-and-spending bill he signed last year. That, too, could cause a fiscal crisis down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are worried that by defunding universities and revoking student visas, the Trump administration will make the United States a less attractive place to do scientific research — robbing the country of an advantage that has helped power its world-leading growth since World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they are worried that by using his powers to attack his enemies and reward his friends, Mr. Trump will erode the system of rules and laws that for decades have made the United States the safest place for investors to bet their money and for entrepreneurs to build their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of those concerns is likely to lead to a recession in 2026. Indeed, most forecasters expect growth to pick up this year. And the U.S. economy still has a wealth of advantages — including the absence of an obvious international alternative — that won’t disappear over night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Clausing, the U.C.L.A. economist, warned against assuming that just because Mr. Trump’s policies haven’t harmed the economy yet, they never will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The long run takes a long time to arrive, and when it comes it comes with astonishing swiftness,” she said. “I don’t know when the chickens come home to roost, but they will.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/trump-first-year-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:49:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Netflix Revamps Its Warner Bros. Bid, Seeking to Thwart Paramount</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/netflix-warner-bros-discovery-paramount-takeover.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20biz-netflix-wbd-02-qbcv/20biz-netflix-wbd-02-qbcv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix announced on Tuesday that it had modified its December offer to acquire major parts of Warner Bros. Discovery, a rejoinder to Paramount and its chief executive, David Ellison, who is also in hot pursuit of Warner Bros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, Warner Bros. Discovery agreed to sell its streaming and studios business to Netflix in an $83 billion cash-and-stock deal. On Tuesday, Netflix said it would pay that sum exclusively in cash, simplifying the deal for investors who will no longer have to account for Netflix’s fluctuating stock price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today’s revised merger agreement brings us even closer to combining two of the greatest storytelling companies in the world,” David Zaslav, the chief executive of Warner Bros. Discovery, said in a statement. Netflix’s modified offer would provide “greater financial certainty” for shareholders, added Ted Sarandos, the co-chief executive of Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move puts pressure on Paramount to further revise its own bid after Warner Bros. Discovery rejected its latest offer, saying it viewed the deal as more risky than Netflix’s. While Paramount has modified the terms of its bid, it has not increased its offer in the weeks since Warner Bros. Discovery chose Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Hollywood has been on a cliffhanger as Paramount and Netflix duked it out for control of Warner Bros. Discovery, a messy tug-of-war that could help determine the trajectory of the entertainment industry. Paramount mounted a hostile bid for Warner Bros., appealing to the company’s investors after Warner Bros. rejected a series of increasingly sweetened offers in favor of a tie-up with Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battle is now being waged among Warner Bros. shareholders, who must ultimately approve any sale, and in the hearts and minds of Hollywood’s besieged creative class, who are already reeling from decades of technological disruption and unending corporate consolidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. Discovery also said Tuesday that it was making changes to the business it was not selling to Netflix. As part of its planned deal, Warner Bros. Discovery is carving out its cable business, spinning off traditional TV channels like CNN and TNT into a separate publicly traded company. Paramount has questioned the value of that business, arguing it is, in effect, worth nothing. It has argued, in turn, that its proposal to buy all of Warner Bros. Discovery is better for shareholders than Netflix’s deal to buy only part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of the revised deal, Warner Bros. Discovery will reduce the debt that would have been on its cable business by $260 million. That change is designed to assuage shareholders who feared the cable business’s debt load would reduce investor appetite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warner Bros. Discovery also outlined how it valued its cable business, with calculations ranging from $1.33 to $6.86 a share. For shareholders, that purported value would be added to the $27.75 per share value of Netflix’s offer for the rest of Warner Bros. Discovery’s business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By detailing its analysis, Warner Bros. Discovery is trying to offer a road map for investors choosing between Netflix and Paramount, which is offering $108 billion in cash for the whole company, or $30 per share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix’s shift to an all-cash offer could hasten how quickly the deal is reviewed by regulators at the Securities and Exchange Commission, which could also expedite a vote on the deal by Warner Bros. Discovery shareholders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Paramount and Netflix are each trying to convince politicians in Washington — including President Trump — that its offer is better for Americans. Mr. Trump has said that he would be “involved” in the deal, and recently shared an editorial on social media that argued Paramount’s offer was superior. He has also offered praise for Mr. Sarandos of Netflix, calling him “a great person.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/netflix-warner-bros-discovery-paramount-takeover.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:33:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Trump Drama Hits Davos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/dealbook/trump-davos-tariffs-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20db-bessent-davos-kqmf/20db-bessent-davos-kqmf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew here. I am in Davos, Switzerland, at the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum. President Trump is expected to speak here on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mood: trepidation, for those who are being honest. I attended several events last night, where some C.E.O.s openly questioned the president, using words like “wild” and “bizarre.” Yet many of them are planning to attend a reception in his honor, with some even joking about the best way to praise him in person. “Tread lightly,” one C.E.O. said. Contrast that with a number of international politicians wringing their hands over the growing tensions about Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also on attendees’ minds: The Supreme Court could finally rule on the legality of some of Trump’s biggest tariffs as soon as Tuesday. (More on that later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there was Larry Fink’s speech at the gathering’s opening event last night. In it, the BlackRock chief and interim W.E.F. co-chair said that the forum was no longer trusted, acknowledging a longtime worry that wasn’t usually said out loud. He said he wanted to make changes, like bringing in new voices — and perhaps bringing the event to more cities. We’ve got all of the details below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The World Economic Forum is in full swing in Davos, Switzerland. Already, the U.S. delegation has made clear that it’s not particularly interested in the event’s longtime goal of improving the world through international cooperation and commerce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said he would hold a meeting to discuss what many see as his increasingly bellicose efforts to take Greenland from Denmark — but has reiterated that he still wants the semiautonomous territory. And Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent brushed aside potential European responses to Trump’s possible trade war over the island. Here’s the on-the-ground picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. show: At a news briefing on Monday at USA House, the U.S. delegation’s official hub in Davos, Bessent spoke about America’s economic strength and desire for global partners, Lauren Hirsch reports. (“America First does not mean America alone,” he said.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Bessent has also derided reports of E.U. leaders weighing 93 billion euros’ (about $109 billion) worth of tariffs on U.S. goods in response to Trump’s saber-rattling over Greenland. (“I imagine they will form the dreaded European working group first,” he quipped.) And he said on Tuesday that any European dumping of Treasury bonds “defies any logic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;USA House itself has become a symbol of this year’s forum, Hirsch adds. It’s prominent — it sports a giant painting of a bald eagle and is across from the Congress Center, the official hub for forum events — and has been packed with executives seeking to pitch the U.S. delegation. Its agenda for the week includes a live taping of the “All-In” podcast and a talk entitled, “Boardroom to Battlefield: Winning the A.I. Tempo War for Economic and National Security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tension on the streets and behind the scenes: The front page of the German newspaper Süddeutsche Zeitung, seen on the Davos Promenade by The Times’s Jordyn Holman, featured a hat bearing the phrase “Make America Go Away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over dinner, executives who last year cheered an expected surge in deal making in Trump’s second term have been debating rising geopolitical unrest. Many bankers still argue, however, that M.&amp;A. will go up this year, and that the gloomy talk is a distraction, not a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions about the future of artificial intelligence: Last year’s forum saw the escalation of an A.I. race, especially with the sudden rise of China’s DeepSeek. This year, attendees acknowledged that the sprint to embrace the technology could have serious consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satya Nadella, Microsoft’s C.E.O., said that the A.I. boom’s benefits needed to be “much more evenly spread” to avoid becoming a bubble. But he added that he believed that the technology would deliver on societal benefits like helping develop new drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk muses about buying Ryanair, the discount European airline. The Tesla C.E.O. polled his followers on X about such a move, shortly after demanding that the airline fire its longtime chief, Michael O’Leary. The feud began last week after O’Leary said he wouldn’t install Starlink satellite internet equipment on his airlines’ planes because of increased fuel costs. (The clash isn’t pretty.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links between Epstein and Goldman Sachs’s general counsel reportedly worry some executives. Years of revelations about work that Kathy Ruemmler did for the disgraced financier Jeffrey Epstein and communications between the two, as well as her having once been named as a backup executor for his will, have become concerns for unnamed figures at the bank, The Wall Street Journal reports. John Rogers, Goldman’s executive vice president, denied that he had drafted plans for Ruemmler to leave this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inflation, earnings and the future of the Fed are in focus this week. The Commerce Department is set to publish the Personal Consumption Expenditures readouts for October and November on Thursday. An earnings report to watch is Capital One’s on Thursday, with investors eager to hear about its response to President Trump’s proposed caps on credit card interest rates. Jay Powell is expected to appear at Supreme Court oral arguments on Wednesday, according to The Times, over Trump’s effort to fire the Fed governor Lisa Cook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global markets have been rocked this morning by a wide sell-off in stocks, bonds, the U.S. dollar and cryptocurrencies as global trade tensions take center stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest: S&amp;P 500 futures are down before the first U.S. trading session since President Trump threatened on Saturday new tariffs on several European countries if they impede his efforts to acquire Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s latest threats continued overnight. They have stunned many U.S. trading partners, and have revived fears of tit-for-tat retaliation — including that Brussels would prep its ominous sounding “bazooka” anti-coercion instrument — that could sock global trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several companies have been caught in the crossfire. LVMH, the French luxury goods maker, is down more than 2 percent this morning after Trump threatened to impose a 200 percent tariff on French wine, including Champagne. Why? Trump said he wanted President Emmanuel Macron of France to join his proposed “Board of Peace” for Gaza — or else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest damage is in the Treasury market as the “sell America” narrative regains momentum. The yield on a 10-year note has spiked to 4.28 percent. (Jitters in the Japanese bond market aren’t helping; the Japanese are major holders of American debt.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tariffs are again stalking the markets. The Supreme Court is expected to rule (possibly as soon as Tuesday) on the legality of Trump’s most bruising levies, which he justified under the International Emergency Economic Powers Act of 1977.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would a legal setback, which is expected by a majority of bettors on the predication market Kalshi, force Trump to hold fire?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t bet on it. If it were to lose in court, the administration would turn to a Plan B “the next day” to reinstate tariffs, Jamieson Greer, the U.S. Trade Representative, told The Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tough-talk on tariffs is spooking the markets. Many Wall Street veterans figured that the worst of the tariff fight was over. The levies risk re-accelerating inflation, an economic condition the administration is keen to avoid as it puts affordability atop its agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Fink was for years the very definition of a “Davos Man.” A longtime habitué of the World Economic Forum, Fink, the BlackRock C.E.O., publicly championed Davos-friendly topics like stakeholder capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his first speech as an interim co-chair of the W.E.F. on Monday, however, Fink took aim at the very institution he has taken the reins of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dive into what he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forum isn’t trusted outside the Davos bubble. “If we’re being honest, for many people this meeting feels out of step with the moment,” Fink said, “elites in an age of populism, an established institution in an era of deep institutional distrust.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an acknowledgment that for years Davos had been seen — by both the left and the right — as a place where business and political leaders talk to one another in isolation and deliver pronouncements that critics saw as simply enshrining the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This forum can’t remain an echo chamber,” Fink added. (That’s a topic highlighted in the latest Trust Barometer report by Edelman, the big P.R. firm.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forum shouldn’t just be about the abstract. The organization’s mission is to “improve the state of the world through public-private cooperation.” And previous forum topics have had grandiose themes like “the Fourth Industrial Revolution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, Fink suggested, it was important for participants to work on tangible accomplishments. Take, for instance, the promises and perils of artificial intelligence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If A.I. does to white-collar work what globalization did to blue-collar, we need to confront that directly. Not with abstractions about “the jobs of tomorrow,” but with a credible plan for broad participation in the gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the test: Whether capitalism can evolve to turn more people into owners of growth — instead of spectators watching it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Davos” shouldn’t just be in Davos. W.E.F. participants shouldn’t only trek to the Swiss Alps to figure out solutions to the world’s problems, Fink said. They should also go to “places where the modern world is actually built,” in locations “like Detroit and Dublin — and cities like Jakarta and Buenos Aires.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netflix fired its latest volley in the battle for control of Warner Bros. Discovery this morning, converting its $72 billion cash-and-stock takeover bid for large parts of the media company into an all-cash offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move is an effort to take away one of the most compelling aspects of Paramount’s competing bid for Warner Bros. Discovery — though the question now is whether shareholders will agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest: Netflix, which reports its quarterly earnings later on Tuesday, is still offering $27.75 a share to buy Warner Bros. Discovery’s studio and streaming businesses, but that’s now all in cash. Warner Bros. Discovery will also reduce, by $260 million, the debt that will be borne by the cable business that it plans to spin off into a separate publicly traded company, to be known as Discovery Global.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why it matters: Paramount has argued that its all-cash bid offers more certainty than Netflix’s previous cash-and-stock offer, which would have left Warner Bros. Discovery shareholders subject to the fluctuations of the streaming giant’s stock price. (Netflix shares have fallen by about a quarter since its pursuit of Warner Bros. Discovery emerged publicly.) Tuesday’s move eliminates that discrepancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s still the matter of how the bids stack up financially. Paramount is offering $30 a share for all of Warner Bros. Discovery. Netflix is buying just part of the media company, but it and Warner Bros. Discovery have contended that shareholders would also gain more from the cable spinoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paramount has argued that the spinoff is worth nothing. But on Tuesday, Warner Bros. Discovery laid out calculations for valuing the cable business, which it estimates could be worth $1.33 to $6.86 a share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Questions to keep in mind now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How realistic are Warner Bros. Discovery’s cable valuations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And will Paramount, which in recent weeks has turned to the courts to battle Netflix, finally raise its offer?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GSK agreed to buy RAPT Therapeutics, a biotech firm that is developing food-allergy treatments, for $2.2 billion. (Bloomberg)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The activist hedge fund Elliott Investment Management reportedly invested several hundred million in Stratolaunch, a hypersonic aircraft company owned by Cerberus Capital Management. (WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech and artificial intelligence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Claude Is Taking the A.I. World by Storm, and Even Non-Nerds Are Blown Away” (WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Stock Exchange’s parent company is starting a 24-hour trading platform for tokenized securities based on the blockchain. (Reuters)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of the rest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valentino Garavani, the renowned designer of royalty and celebrities who defined Italian high fashion for more than a half-century, died yesterday at 93. (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. airlines could save $580 million annually on lower fuel costs as passengers slim down with GLP-1 weight-loss drugs, according to a new study. (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d like your feedback! Please email thoughts and suggestions to dealbook@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/dealbook/trump-davos-tariffs-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:18:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Stocks and Bonds Fall on Trump’s Greenland Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/stocks-trump-greenland-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/newsgraphics/images/icons/defaultPromoCrop.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump’s intensifying standoff with European leaders over the fate of Greenland prompted a sharp response from investors Tuesday morning, with the value of U.S. stocks, dollar and government bonds all falling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S&amp;P 500 dropped over 1 percent as investors reacted to Mr. Trump’s increasing threat of higher tariffs on European allies unless they supported his plans for America to take control of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday morning’s decline was the first time the index has started the day that much lower since April amid turmoil from Mr. Trump’s initial sweeping tariff threats on nearly all of America’s trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often when stocks are roiled by geopolitical upheaval, investors flock to the safety of other U.S. assets, like the dollar or government bonds. But in a sign that investors were embracing a “sell America” trade and moving away from U.S. assets altogether, both the dollar and U.S. government debt lost value Tuesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dollar index, which pits the currency against a basket of currencies that represent America’s major trading partners, fell 0.8 percent. The dollar weakened against every currency from the group of 10 nations, which includes the euro, British pound and Norwegian Krone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yield, which moves inversely to price, on the 10-year U.S. government note rose, meaning its value declined. This yield acts as one of the most important interest rates in the world by underpinning interest rates across consumer and corporate debt. The 10-year yield rose 0.1 percentage points, to 4.3 percent, its sharpest move higher so far this year, undermining the administration’s efforts to move interest rates lower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday morning’s trading was the first chance U.S. markets had to react to Mr. Trump’s escalating threats toward Europe over the weekend with the U.S. stock market closed on Monday in honor of Martin Luther King’s Birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One bright spot in the stock market came from the rising value of defense stocks. Northrop Grumman, an aerospace and defense company, nudged higher Tuesday morning, pushing further into record territory having risen almost 20 percent already this month.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/stocks-trump-greenland-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:30:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>David Rosen, 95, Dies; Video Game Visionary and Co-Founder of Sega</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/david-rosen-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/00rosen-promo-bgpz/00rosen-promo-bgpz-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maxim Ibragimov/Shutterstock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As co-founder of Sega Enterprises, David Rosen played a leading role in turning video games into a cultural touchstone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega’s games were a direct challenge to Nintendo’s dominance. Among them was Bare Knuckle II, which came to the U.S. as Streets of Rage 2 in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before long, Genesis was seemingly everywhere. But Mr. Rosen’s path to video game prominence was circuitous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supported by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He transformed his Japanese photo booth business into a gaming industry game giant that created Mortal Kombat, Sonic the Hedgehog and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Michael S. Rosenwald&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Rosen, a Brooklyn-born entrepreneur who transformed his photo booth business in Japan into Sega Enterprises, the video game giant that dominated arcades, basements and dorm rooms with blockbusters like Mortal Kombat, Sonic the Hedgehog and N.H.L. ’94, died on Dec. 25 at his home in Los Angeles. He was 95.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His death was confirmed by Annette van Duren, a spokeswoman for his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a four-decade career that began in the 1950s with coin-operated machines and culminated with the introduction of cutting-edge home gaming systems, Mr. Rosen was a visionary figure who helped shape what is now a $200 billion industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is eminently clear that computer video games are a sign of the times,” he wrote in Play Meter magazine in 1982. “And by that I mean the games are truly one of the early manifestations of an electronic revolution whose technology will personally touch, on an increasing basis, all of our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chairman of Sega’s U.S. operation in 1989, Mr. Rosen oversaw the introduction of the company’s Genesis gaming console to North America, a product that directly challenged the near-monopoly that Nintendo, its main competitor, had in American homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega marketed its system to teenagers and young adults who had played Nintendo as children, positioning Genesis as more technologically advanced, with a lineup of grittier, more intense games. In doing so, the company forged the creative and commercial blueprint that turned gaming into a cultural touchstone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 1990s, Genesis was seemingly everywhere: in commercials during the MTV Video Music Awards; on an episode of “Roseanne,” when the title character’s son, D.J., huffs off to play Genesis at a friend’s house when his parents won’t buy him a Nintendo; and in the 1996 movie “Swingers,” when Trent, played by Vince Vaughn, makes Wayne Gretzky’s head bleed in a popular hockey game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Players would greet each other by shouting, “Sega!” parroting the signature ending of the company’s commercials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everything that Sega was able to do in the ’90s was built on the foundation that Rosen built,” Ken Horowitz, the author of “Playing at the Next Level: A History of American Sega Games” (2016), said in an interview. “The industry would not have become as big a thing as it is today if not for him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rosen took a circuitous path to gaming eminence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1940s, while stationed in Japan with the U.S. Air Force, he became enamored with the country’s culture, especially its art. After his discharge in 1952, he moved to New York and started a business selling portraits by Japanese painters. It wasn’t exactly a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1954, Mr. Rosen moved to Tokyo, where he noticed a booming market in photo identification cards for school and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After learning that shops took about three days to process photos, he thought he could shorten the wait to mere seconds by importing photo booths like the ones he had seen in American amusement parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He started a company, Rosen Enterprises, which installed hundreds of the machines around Japan — in movie theaters, restaurants and stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There were different times when people would go through school applications and whatnot, and it was not unusual at those times of the year for the lines to get into the booth to be an hour, hour and a half,” he said in an interview with the gaming journalist Steven L. Kent for the book “The Ultimate History of Video Games.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1950s, when the typical workweek in Japan shrunk from six or seven days to five and leisure time exploded, Mr. Rosen began thinking of ways to enter the entertainment market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The popular entertainment at that point in time in Japan was pachinko, dance studios, bars and cabarets,” he said in an interview with Next Generation magazine. “None of these were something I wanted to get involved in, so I thought, ‘Gee, coin-operated games.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinball machines, mechanical claws and shooting galleries had become popular arcade games in the United States but were virtually nonexistent in Japan. Mr. Rosen cut deals with U.S. distributors to import older arcade games that were gathering dust in warehouses, then installed them in the same locations as his photo booths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The games, especially the shooting ones, were an immediate hit. Before long, several Japan-based competitors emerged. The biggest was Service Games, a jukebox manufacturer that had transformed into an arcade operator. In 1965, Service Games and Rosen Enterprises merged, becoming Sega Enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newly formed company quickly released its own games, beginning with Periscope, a submarine simulator designed by Mr. Rosen, in which players fired projectiles at cardboard ships. The game was a huge hit, and Sega exported it to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1972, Atari released the video game Pong. Sega imported it to Japan. Soon, the company was making its own video games — first for arcades and eventually for its home consoles, starting with the SG-1000 in 1983.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Mr. Rosen, gaming represented an entirely new category of entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Activities such as television, movies, sporting events and records or the radio all have a valid place in our society, yet all these forms of entertainment lack an important factor in satisfying a fundamental need,” Mr. Rosen wrote in Play Meter. “That need is active participation, which is, of course, what computer video games are all about.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Rosen was born in Brooklyn on Jan. 22, 1930, to Samuel and Fay (Sacks) Rosen. His father was an importer and also owned a chocolate factory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After joining the Air Force when he was 18, Mr. Rosen was stationed throughout Asia, serving as a writer for Armed Forces Radio. He also worked in the finance office on a military base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He married Masako Fujisaki in 1954. She died last year. His family declined to provide information about his survivors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rosen stayed with Sega through several mergers. He retired in 1996 as the company was in the early stages of losing battles against Sony, which boasted the PlayStation console, and then Microsoft, with Xbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sega just didn’t have the financial resources to battle with these bigger companies, which could afford huge losses until their machines became profitable,” Mr. Horowitz said. “Sony and Microsoft just had endless supplies of cash.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sega is now part of Sega Sammy Holdings Inc., a Japan-based entertainment conglomerate. In addition to making its own games, the company purchased Rovio, the developer of Angry Birds, in 2023. This year, Sega will celebrate the 35th anniversary of Sonic the Hedgehog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late in his career, Mr. Rosen marveled at how far he’d come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I was a youngster, I went to Coney Island,” he said in “The Ultimate History of Video Games.” “Like everybody else in New York City, I played the games in the penny arcades. That was really my total knowledge of the business.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/david-rosen-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:24:05 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>