<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Business Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Business articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Business_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:42:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Fed, Signaling Little Urgency, Prepares to Pause on Rate Cuts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-fed-mtlp/27dc-fed-mtlp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Reserve is widely expected to pause interest rate cuts this week after three reductions in the final months of 2025. Less clear, however, is just how long that pause will last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fed officials, once worried about a weakening labor market, no longer appear to be in as much of a rush after bringing rates down to a range of 3.5 percent to 3.75 percent. A steadily growing economy and low layoffs have given them some comfort that they can afford to take their time with further cuts, especially as they stare down the prospects of another year of inflation well above their 2 percent target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead for the Fed is a tenuous balancing act. Policymakers do not want to jeopardize the labor market by keeping rates too high for too long, but they also want to ensure they are restraining the economy enough to stamp out any lingering price pressures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials are contending with this as the institution finds itself under attack by a White House that wants borrowing costs to be much lower. Jerome H. Powell, the Fed chair, accused the administration earlier this month of opening a criminal investigation into his handling of costly renovations at the Fed’s headquarters in Washington in retaliation for not cutting borrowing costs, a broadside that drew rare rebukes of President Trump from Republican lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesday’s vote on rates also comes after Lisa D. Cook, a Fed governor, was forced to defend her ability to remain at the Fed after Mr. Trump tried to oust her last year. While the Supreme Court has yet to deliver a final ruling, several justices at last week’s hearing appeared wary about the Fed’s ability to operate free of political meddling if her firing was upheld.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, who has not shied away from sharing his desire to fill a majority of the seats on the Fed’s board of governors with his supporters, is also close to announcing a successor for Mr. Powell when his term as chair ends in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pause in rate cuts, however long it will be, will no doubt inflame tensions between the Fed and Mr. Trump. But without more substantive signs that the labor market is deteriorating, economists do not expect the central bank to budge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s time to sit back and take a look at things,” said Peter Hooper, vice chair of research at Deutsche Bank. “We will get some further easing, but it’s not urgent at this point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed’s deliberations until now have been uniquely fraught. With each subsequent quarter-point cut last year, beginning in September, officials grew more divided about what to do about rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This culminated in December with one of the central bank’s most divisive votes in years. Two members of the 12-person policy-setting committee dissented against the cut in favor of standing pat, while four other officials registered “soft" dissents by penciling in rate forecasts that were higher than where rates ended the year. Their primary concern was inflation, which they worried was at risk of getting stuck above the 2 percent target as the full effects of Mr. Trump’s tariffs materialized and the economy remained resilient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum sat Stephen I. Miran, who joined the Fed’s board in September after Mr. Trump nominated him, and for a third-straight meeting voted in favor of a larger, half-point cut. Mr. Miran has said that his colleagues are overly concerned about inflation and are risking a recession by not cutting more aggressively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These divisions have not disappeared, but they have greatly diminished now that rates are closer to a “neutral” level that does not rev up economic growth, but does not restrain it either. That has given the central bank some breathing room, said William Dudley, who was president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York from 2009 to 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So too has the economic data, even though it is still impacted by distortions caused by last year’s government shutdown. Inflation ended last year more subdued that feared. The labor market, while sluggish, steadied last month, with the unemployment rate slipping back to 4.4 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right now, I think they’re much more comfortable than they were even six months ago,” Mr. Dudley said. “The downside risks to the labor market have lessened and the upside risks to inflation have lessened.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economists expect this relatively benign outlook to extend through much of 2026, especially with Americans expected to soon receive bigger tax refunds because of provisions in legislation Mr. Trump signed into law last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials have adopted a similarly sanguine view. John C. Williams, president of the New York Fed, told reporters earlier this month that the “economic situation today is quite favorable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He described growth as solid, and said the labor market was showing signs of stabilizing. Coupled with inflation continuing to ease, Mr. Williams said, “I feel like we’re in a good place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So long as that remain the case, it will be hard to justify more rate cuts, said Raghuram Rajan, a former governor of the Reserve Bank of India. “Inflation is still a problem,” he said. “You can’t have 3 percent inflation for this long without being worried.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That suggests that the burden of restarting cuts will likely fall on the next chair of the Fed, whose first meeting, if confirmed by the Senate in time, would be in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has said that he would not pick someone who does not support significantly lower borrowing costs, so the question is not whether that person would back more cuts but the magnitude of cuts they will push for. They would then need to convince the rest of the policy-setting committee, which is made up of all seven governors, the president of the New York Fed and a rotating group of four regional bank presidents. In an interview earlier this month, Neel T. Kashkari, who as president of the Minneapolis Fed will be a voting member this year, said the next chair is going to have to “bring forward the best arguments that he or she can and then win the votes based on the data and the analysis.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kashkari will be joined by Beth M. Hammack of the Cleveland Fed, Lorie K. Logan of the Dallas Fed and Anna Paulson of the Philadelphia Fed. All but Ms. Paulson appeared skeptical about cutting rates at some point last year, suggesting they are unlikely to support substantial reductions unless the economic backdrop dramatically shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Fed chair can influence the way things are going, but he’s not going to be able to walk in and direct the committee to do something it’s not inclined to do,” said Mr. Hooper, who worked at the Fed for nearly 30 years. “That is a power that is earned over a number of years of experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/fed-rate-decision-outlook.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:55:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘ICE Is Going Too Far’: OpenAI’s Altman Weighs In on Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27db-altman-fjvm/27db-altman-fjvm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew here. On Monday, I wrote here about the need for C.E.O.s to speak up after this weekend’s tragic shooting in Minneapolis. Credit to Sam Altman, the co-founder of OpenAI, who wrote in an internal Slack message to the company: “What’s happening with ICE is going too far. There is a big difference between deporting violent criminals and what’s happening now, and we need to get the distinction right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve got the full note. That, and much more, below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DealBook has raised the question of whether business leaders would begin to speak out against the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown after federal agents killed two Americans in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More have started doing so — including Sam Altman of OpenAI — as corporate America is forced to confront the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What’s happening with ICE is going too far,” Altman wrote in an internal Slack message to OpenAI employees, DealBook has learned. Here’s the full text of his message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the US and its values of democracy and freedom and will be supportive of the country however I can; OpenAI will too. But part of loving the country is the American duty to push back against overreach. What’s happening with ICE is going too far. There is a big difference between deporting violent criminals and what’s happening now, and we need to get the distinction right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is a very strong leader, and I hope he will rise to this moment and unite the country. I am encouraged by the last few hours of response and hope to see trust rebuilt with transparent investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a company, we aim to stick to our convictions and not get blown around by changing fashions too much. We didn’t become super woke when that was popular, we didn’t start talking about masculine corporate energy when that was popular, and we are not going to make a lot of performative statements now about safety or politics or anything else. But we are going to continue to try to figure out how to actually do the right thing as best as we can, engage with leaders and push for our values, and speak up clearly about it as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post garnered hundreds of supportive responses, including heart and “THANK YOU” emojis. In the replies, Altman said that he had spent time talking with Trump administration officials yesterday, as he had done in the fall when he was one of several San Francisco business leaders asked to help persuade Trump not to conduct a big immigration enforcement action in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His comments illustrate the fine line many executives have sought to walk in speaking out against the Trump administration. Altman has become close to the president as he pushes for A.I. policies that are friendly to the industry; Greg Brockman, a fellow OpenAI co-founder, has become a major Trump donor as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other top executives have also spoken about the shootings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Target’s incoming C.E.O., Michael Fiddelke, sent a video message to employees on Monday calling the fatal shootings “incredibly painful,” and acknowledging that it was “weighing heavily” on many of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dario Amodei, Anthropic’s C.E.O., called the events in Minnesota a “horror” in a social media post on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fissures are appearing elsewhere in Silicon Valley. Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In internal Slack messages, some workers at Palantir, a major government contractor, questioned why the tech company was working with ICE after the killing on Saturday of Alex Pretti by federal agents, Wired reported. Palantir executives reportedly defended the work with the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A public letter, known as ICEout.tech, calls on the tech industry to demand that ICE agents leave U.S. cities and to cancel contracts with the agency. It has amassed more than 800 signatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keith Rabois, a managing director at the venture capital firm Khosla Ventures, defended ICE on social media, saying that “no law enforcement has shot an innocent person” and that “illegals are committing violent crimes everyday.” Vinod Khosla, who founded the firm, publicly disavowed those comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s next: Part of the federal government could shut down by the end of the week, as Democrats seek to strip out funding for the Department of Homeland Security, which includes ICE, before approving a huge funding bill before a Friday deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comes as President Trump has shaken up the ICE operation in Minnesota, saying he will put in charge his border czar, Tom Homan, who will report directly to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump threatens to raise tariffs on South Korean goods to 25 percent. The president’s warning comes as he accuses the country’s legislature of taking too long to ratify a trade deal the countries reached last year. Separately, the European Parliament delayed a decision to unfreeze a U.S.-E.U. trade deal despite Trump walking back tariff threats tied to his efforts to acquire Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Burry, of “The Big Short” fame, bets on GameStop. Shares in the video game retailer jumped over 4 percent on Monday after Burry wrote that he was building a position in the stock, a frequent favorite of meme-stock traders. Burry backed efforts by Ryan Cohen, GameStop’s C.E.O., to turn around the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Motors reports a $3.3 billion loss after writing off E.V. investments. The automaker took a $7.2 billion accounting charge related to electric vehicles and other items, which more than erased a fourth-quarter operating profit. But its shares rose as much as 5 percent in premarket trading as the company predicted that profit this year would meet or exceed analyst estimates. Separately, sales of E.V.s surpassed those of gasoline-powered vehicles in the E.U. for the first time in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech giants have fought for years against legal broadsides by regulators and users alike over the content featured on their social networks. Starting this week, they face a new front: trials over how addictive their products are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuits are the latest effort to bring multibillion-dollar businesses like Meta, TikTok and YouTube to heel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest: Jury selection will start on Tuesday in a lawsuit against Meta, TikTok and Google’s YouTube filed by a now-20-year-old Californian, identified in court documents by the initials K.G.M. She has argued that she became addicted to social media as a child and experienced anxiety, body-image issues and depression as a result. (Snap, the parent company of Snapchat, settled with K.G.M. last week for an undisclosed amount.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prominent executives are expected to take the stand, including Mark Zuckerberg of Meta, Adam Mosseri of Instagram and Neal Mohan of YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new legal tactic against the tech titans: K.G.M.’s lawyers are drawing on the playbook used against Big Tobacco last century, and plan on citing social media features like infinite scroll and algorithmic content recommendations as intentional ways of addicting users. They also plan to cite internal documents that appear to show concern about aspects of the social networks’ design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defense: To date, companies like Meta and Google have argued that their platforms are protected by Section 230 of the Communications Decency Act of 1996, which shields websites from legal liability for content posted by users. (Worth noting: President Trump moved to narrow that protection in his first term — for his own reasons.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, the companies plan to cite Section 230 as part of their defense here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stakes: A win for K.G.M. could expose tech companies to hefty punishments — tobacco companies reached a $206 billion legal settlement in 1998 — and the threat of more lawsuits, as well as forced changes to their businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other lawsuits are on deck, including in state court in Los Angeles and federal cases brought by school districts and state attorneys general in Oakland, Calif.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our business coverage. Times journalists are not allowed to have any direct financial stake in companies they cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media companies have already been feeling heat. Australian regulators last month blocked users under 16 from social media, a model that other authorities around the world are now weighing. Officials in Britain and the E.U. have limited some features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social networks are facing pressure on other issues, too: On Monday, E.U. officials opened an investigation into Elon Musk’s X over sexualized images generated by the Grok chatbot. And some TikTok users who have accused the platform of suppressing anti-Trump videos — after a new entity that includes some allies of the president took over its U.S. operations — have flocked to an upstart rival, Upscrolled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. dollar rebounded against a basket of currencies this morning. But the greenback’s slump during President Trump’s second term continues to grip Wall Street as international investors weigh how much money to put in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, investors seek out the dollar in times of rising geopolitical uncertainty, inflation and government deficits — economic conditions that check boxes across the globe. But the U.S. Dollar Index is down nearly 10 percent in the past year, while gold and silver, other safe haven assets, are hitting records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The buck’s latest swoon may be by design. The dollar fell precipitously on Monday against the Japanese yen on reports that the U.S. Treasury and the authorities in Japan could be working together to bolster the yen and stabilize demand for Japanese bonds. The goal ostensibly would be to prevent another sell-off in Japanese debt, like the one that jolted the global bond market last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big sell-off in bonds risks driving up borrowing costs for businesses and households, a scenario that governments, including the Trump administration, are keen to avoid. The rout in Japanese bonds, and its effect on Treasury notes, prompted Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent to call his counterpart in Japan in an apparent effort to calm the markets, he said last week at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear if Washington and Tokyo have backed that up with any big dollar-yen trades. But speculation that such an extraordinary move could be on the table has become the talk of the currency markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has also heaped attention on the finances of Japan, a key U.S. ally and trading partner, under Sanae Takaichi, its new prime minister. As John Authers of Bloomberg Opinion asks in his column on Tuesday: Was the Japanese bond market swoon a blip, or the a sign of deeper instability in global markets?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what does this portend for the dollar? Over the years, Trump has shifted his position on whether he prefers a strong or a weak dollar. The latter scenario could bolster the competitiveness of American exporters, but also dent the profits of U.S. importers and drive up costs for consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dominic Bunning, the head of G10 FX Strategy at Nomura, told Bloomberg TV this morning that the dollar could slump another 5 to 10 percent. That said, he called talk that we may be glimpsing an end to dollar dominance “nonsense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market’s attention will be trained on the Magnificent Seven starting this week, with Apple, Meta, Microsoft and Tesla set to report earnings. But even as investors look to the technology giants to gauge the progress of the artificial intelligence boom, some former tech darlings are falling out of favor: software stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major software companies, including Salesforce, HubSpot and Atlassian, have seen their shares fall by 30 percent or more over the past year. The reason, Niko Gallogly reports, is the accelerating threat posed by A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D.I.Y. danger: The rapid rise of so-called vibe-coding tools like Anthropic’s Claude Code, which allow users to generate websites and apps from simple language prompts, have prompted concerns that more companies will choose to build, not buy, software. There is a “crisis of confidence” among investors about software companies’ competitive edge, Jordan Klein, an analyst at Mizuho Americas, told DealBook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even solid growth numbers haven’t eased concerns. In December, for example, Adobe reported $6.2 billion in revenue for its last fiscal quarter of 2025 — a 10 percent gain over the same period for the previous year. Adobe’s stock is down more than 10 percent since that report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the Army just awarded a $5.6 billion, 10-year contract to Salesforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some investors don’t want to “wait around to find out” how A.I. might undercut the business model of software-as-a-service companies, Klein said. Instead, many are seeking safe harbor in the companies supplying the picks and shovels for the A.I. buildout. One such winner is the computer chip memory producer Micron; its stock has risen more than 300 percent over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earnings season will be a big test. Investors will be closely attuned to what software executives say about the competitive outlook, and how conservative they are in their own earnings projections. Until they see some new bullishness from the companies, Klein predicts, investors won’t be ready to take a bet on software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major test will come Wednesday, when the business software provider ServiceNow releases its full-year 2025 results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mike Lee, Republican of Utah and the chair of the chamber’s antitrust panel, said Netflix’s proposed purchase of many Warner Bros. Discovery assets “appears likely to raise serious” competition issues. (WSJ)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goldman Sachs added several leaders from its asset management business to its management committee, including two senior private credit executives. (Bloomberg)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics, policy and regulation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Treasury Department ended contracts with Booz Allen Hamilton after a now-former contractor leaked President Trump’s tax return during his first term. (FT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republican lawmakers from Florida expressed concern about the Trump administration’s plans to sell Venezuelan oil while Delcy Rodriguez, the interim leader, retains power. (Semafor)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best of the rest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want it to be known that we are working on this”: Inside “Project Panama,” a plan by Anthropic to “destructively” scan millions of books to feed into its Claude chatbot. (WaPo)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Greenland’s Biggest Band Is Thrust Into an Uneasy Spotlight” (NYT)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’d like your feedback! Please email thoughts and suggestions to dealbook@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/dealbook/altman-openai-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:16:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>G.M. Shares Rise as Investors Are Encouraged by 2026 Prospects</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt/27biz-gm-earnings-kzvt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Motors said on Tuesday it expected a substantial rise in profits in 2026 and planned to buy back up to $6 billion worth of its own stock. The news appeared to please investors who bid up its stock price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.M. said it made $2.7 billion last year, down from $6 billion in 2024. The 2025 total was lowered by some $7.6 billion in losses the company previously reported as it pulled back on its electric vehicle strategy and lowered production of those cars. The losses in part reflected a decline in the value of factories and related investments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2026, the automaker expects to earn $10.3 billion to $11.7 billion, saying sales of high-profit gas-powered pickup trucks and large sport-utility vehicles would rise. G.M. also said it was increasing its quarterly dividend by 20 percent, to 18 cents per common share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.M. shares were up about 8 percent on Tuesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are operating in a U.S. regulatory and policy environment that is increasingly aligned with customer demand,” Mary T. Barra, G.M.’s chief executive, said on a conference call. “This allows us to onshore more production to meet strong demand for our internal-combustion vehicles.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.M.’s decision to pull back from electric vehicles came after Congress and President Trump ended a $7,500 tax credit that was available to buyers of new E.V.s, lowering demand for those models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company said it would continue to produce electric cars and trucks and expected its losses on such models to decline by $1 billion to $1.5 billion this year compared to 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While reporting its earnings, G.M. also said it planned to introduce a more advanced version of its Super Cruise driver assistance system in 2028 that would allow drivers to take their eyes off the road while traveling on highways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We believe we have everything we need to deliver a safe, reliably and highly capable system that customers will embrace,” Ms. Barra said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system will use cameras, radar and laser based sensors to detect objects on the road and signals G.M. aims to challenge Tesla and its advanced driver assist technologies. Tesla’s system, Full Self Driving (Supervised), uses only cameras and that company’s chief executive, Elon Musk, has said for years that laser-based sensors were too expensive and not necessary for safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.M. had tried to develop fully autonomous cars through its Cruise division, but announced in December 2024 that it was shutting down the operation after one of its vehicles hit and injured a pedestrian in San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2025, G.M. reported $185 billion in revenue, a decline of about 1 percent, as global vehicle sales fell about 5 percent, to 3.8 million cars and light trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The automaker also said the Trump administration’s tariffs on cars and car parts cost the company $3.1 billion in 2025, but the company was able to offset about 40 percent of that sum by moving some vehicle and component production to the United States. It said it expected tariff costs in 2026 of $3 billion to $4 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/general-motors-earnings.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:22:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Meta Campaigns to Change Opinions on Data Centers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/19visualUploader-27018-cover/19visualUploader-27018-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advertisement began with a panning shot of Altoona, Iowa, a town of 20,000 near Des Moines. The camera moved from a diner to a farm to a high school football field. To the pluck of guitar strings, a voice-over promoted a boon for the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re bringing jobs here,” the ad said. “For us, and for our next generation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ad’s folksy vibes were not for a political candidate. They were for a data center that Meta had built in Altoona — part of an ad campaign by the Silicon Valley giant to shape a new narrative around the vast computing facilities that power artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta, OpenAI, Google, Microsoft and Amazon have embarked on a building spree in the A.I. race, investing hundreds of billions of dollars to erect data centers to develop the technology. In doing so, they have fueled an increasingly political issue, with President Trump and lawmakers across the country criticizing the computing sites for driving up energy costs and straining local water supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in November and December, Meta spent $6.4 million to run a series of ads — including the one about Altoona — in the television markets of eight state capitals such as Sacramento, Salt Lake City and Tallahassee, Fla., as well as Washington, D.C., according to data from AdImpact, an analytics firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta most likely bought the ads “with the goal of shaping policy decisions” and reaching lawmakers, said Michael Beach, the chief executive of Cross Screen Media, a marketing analytics firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other tech giants are also aiming to influence public opinion on data centers. Amazon is helping to fund a similar ad campaign in Virginia, where it operates dozens of data centers. The campaign — focused on job growth and electricity costs — began in December 2024 and is still running, backed by Virginia Connects, a nonprofit created by the Data Center Coalition, an industry trade group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Padilla, a Democratic state senator in California who proposed a bill last year to regulate rising energy costs from data centers, said such ads were a tech company tactic. “If you like sports, if you have kids, and you love America, you’ve got to love data centers, right?” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Ryan Daniels, a spokesman for Meta, did not comment on its ads but said the company paid the full costs of energy used by its data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon declined to comment. In a statement, Josh Levi, president of the Data Center Coalition, said Virginia Connects helped “inform communities and policymakers about the data center industry,” but he did not address the ad campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta operates 26 data centers in the United States and has said it will spend $600 billion to build new ones in the coming years. Last year, the company also unveiled two political action committees to back candidates at the state level who support A.I. during the midterm elections. (Meta said its spending on the ad campaign was separate from the PACs.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta has highlighted how data centers can bring jobs and tax revenue to places in need of economic development. It and other tech giants have hired “community affairs” workers to build local trust, according to job listings seen by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Chris Van Hollen, Democrat of Maryland, said data centers became an issue on Capitol Hill early last year when constituents started complaining en masse about rising electric bills and blamed data centers. That has made A.I. infrastructure part of the larger debate about affordability, along with things like the cost of eggs, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Mr. Van Hollen introduced a bill to regulate data center energy use. The measure is backed by other Democrats, but the issue is becoming bipartisan, he said. President Trump has recently made several statements about data centers and energy costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are the ‘HOTTEST’ Country in the World, and Number One in AI. Data Centers are key to that boom, and keeping Americans FREE and SECURE but, the big Technology Companies who build them must ‘pay their own way,’” Mr. Trump posted on social media on Jan. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diane Papan, a Democratic state assemblywoman in California, said she had seen Meta’s ads while working in Sacramento last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, she introduced a bill to require tech companies to publicize data center water use; Gov. Gavin Newsom, another Democrat, vetoed it in October. In an interview, Ms. Papan said that she was disappointed by how much the tech industry opposed the bill and that Meta and other tech companies “were not front and center to work with us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I very much worry about with this ad campaign is localities committing to this industry and then saying in 10 years, ‘What have we done to ourselves?’” Ms. Papan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meta built its first data center in Altoona in 2013 and has expanded from one building there to a three-million-square-foot complex, said Chad Quick, the economic development director of Altoona.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Quick, who describes Meta’s relationship with Altoona as “mutually beneficial,” said a film crew from Los Angeles had spent a week shooting scenes around town last year. After the ad aired, people from other towns called to ask whether they should welcome new data centers, too, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His response was positive. “Our experience has not been the experience that some communities have had,” Mr. Quick said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/meta-data-center-ads.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:23:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>UPS Says It Is Cutting Up to 30,000 Jobs</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-ups-tlqb/27biz-ups-tlqb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS said on Tuesday that it expected to cut as many as 30,000 jobs this year as part of a continuing effort to reduce costs and shore up profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the delivery company eliminated 62,000 positions, by laying off full-time drivers, warehouse workers and managers, as well as seasonal employees. UPS said on Tuesday that it was planning the additional layoffs this year because it expected to deliver fewer packages for Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement could add to Americans’ concerns about the job market. While unemployment has risen only slightly in recent months, hiring has slowed significantly. Consumer confidence plunged this month, partly because a greater share of consumers said jobs were “hard to get,” according to the Conference Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Dykes, UPS’s chief financial officer, said this year’s job cuts would be in “operational positions,” the term UPS uses for delivery and warehouse workers. He said the reductions would occur “through attrition” and by offering “voluntary separation” to full-time drivers. UPS said last year that it wanted to wind down much of its Amazon business because it was not profitable. UPS has said Amazon was its largest customer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS announced the layoffs on the same day it reported its earnings for 2025. The company had net income of $5.57 billion last year, down nearly 4 percent from $5.78 billion in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS had around half a million employees at the start of last year, some 300,000 of them members of the Teamsters union. A Teamsters spokeswoman did not respond to requests for comment on the layoffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPS’s leaders are restructuring the company to try to bolster profit margins in a difficult time for the delivery business. Last year, the company suffered a sharp drop in packages sent from China after President Trump imposed tariffs on lower-value shipments from the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, UPS closed 93 facilities and deployed automation in 57. Mr. Dykes said on Tuesday that the company had identified 24 more buildings for closure in the first half of the year, and that more could follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investors appear to be backing UPS’s moves to reinvigorate its business. The company’s stock is up over 35 percent from its low last year. Still, over the past year, its shares are down 18 percent, while Fedex’s stock is up 11 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an investor call on Tuesday, Carol Tomé, UPS’s chief executive, said that “2025 was a year of considerable progress for UPS.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, a UPS plane crashed in Louisville, Ky., killing three crew members and 12 people on the ground. The plane was a MD-11F jet, made by McDonnell Douglas, which Boeing acquired in the 1990s. On Tuesday, UPS said it had retired its MD-11 fleet in the fourth quarter of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/ups-jobs-layoffs-2026.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:36:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bari Weiss Urges CBS News to Think Like a ‘Start-Up’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb/27biz-cbs-news-1-gkcb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bari Weiss, the recently hired and frequently discussed editor in chief of CBS News, began her first networkwide meeting on Tuesday by addressing the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s been a lot of noise around me taking this job,” she told hundreds of CBS staff members gathered in bureaus across the globe. “I get it. I also get why, in the face of all this tumult, you might feel uncertain or skeptical about me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bumps of Ms. Weiss’s early tenure have been heavily chronicled, including her contentious decision to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment and rocky moments on a revamped “Evening News.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, it was her turn to lay out her vision: an ambitious transformation of CBS News from a tradition-bound institution into a digitally savvy journalistic engine that meets news consumers where they are — namely, far from broadcast TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not producing a product enough people want,” she said, while dismissing day-to-day Nielsen ratings as an outmoded benchmark. “What winning looks like writ large for this company is building incredible journalism for audiences that are so much bigger than the one that we currently have,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rallying cry was intended as a reset of sorts, a chance to cut through the suspicions that Ms. Weiss, a frequent critic of the mainstream news media and founder of the independent site The Free Press, is trying to tilt CBS News into more pro-Trump territory. She urged her journalists to reel in investigative scoops (and “scoops of ideas, scoops of explanation”) and think beyond traditional TV broadcasts, referring to her ideal reporters as “dynamic Swiss Army knives capable of writing, speaking, hosting, reporting, analyzing and writing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also announced a new roster of CBS News contributors with viewpoints spanning the political spectrum. The group includes Andrew Huberman, a neurobiology expert who is a popular influencer in the so-called manosphere; Niall Ferguson, a British American historian who frequently writes for The Free Press; Casey Lewis, a Gen Alpha Substack trend-spotter; and Coleman Hughes, a Free Press contributing writer who has argued for “a colorblind society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running an organization as large and influential as CBS News is the biggest challenge of Ms. Weiss’s career. She was appointed last year by its new owner, the technology heir David Ellison, who acquired the network’s parent company, Paramount, after a contentious sale process. Shortly before the Trump administration approved the deal, Paramount paid $16 million to settle a defamation case against “60 Minutes” brought by President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one sense, Ms. Weiss’s remarks on Tuesday echoed those of many media executives trying to steer old-line news institutions, with falling revenue and graying audiences, into the choppy waters of new media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She framed the future of CBS News in stark terms, warning employees that it would be “one hell of a fight” to keep pace in a rapidly changing business. And she told her team to be more nimble and innovative, calling CBS News “the best-capitalized media start-up in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss also warned that employees who did not subscribe to her vision may not wish to remain. “It’s a free country,” Ms. Weiss said. “I completely respect if you decide this is just not the right place at the right time for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her challenge was underscored by a lengthy question-and-answer session with employees, who asked about her decision in December to postpone a “60 Minutes” segment about a notorious prison in El Salvador where deported Venezuelan migrants were detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss said that she held the segment because she believed it required more reporting, and that the decision was hers alone. “I was not pressured by David Ellison or anyone else,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also acknowledged the fallout from her decision to pull the segment after it had been promoted by the network, noting that she was new to broadcasting and unfamiliar with “that specific logistical nightmare.” Referring to the 11th-hour nature of her decision, she said, “Nothing of that kind is ever going to happen again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Tuesday’s event concluded, Gayle King, the “CBS Mornings” anchor, spoke up to offer a rallying cry of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She thanked Ms. Weiss for presenting “a very good case for what you want this company to be,” adding that it was good for the newsroom “to hear and see that you are a real person and this is what you want and how you feel about us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ms. King was blunt about the public reaction to Ms. Weiss’s tenure so far. “People now come up to me to my face, if I’m at the airport, they go, ‘Love you guys, but I ain’t watching you anymore,’” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. King also criticized employees who were divulging details of the newsroom’s inner workings to the press, and speculated on how long it might take for her own remarks to leak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Weiss, wryly, chimed in: “I’m sure someone’s livestreaming it right now, Gayle,” she said, according to a recording of the event obtained by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/media/bari-weiss-cbs-news-town-hall.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:59:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Begins Assigned Seating, Scrapping a Signature Quirk</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp/27trav-southwest-03-lqfp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a water-cannon salute, balloons and commemorative bag tags, Southwest Airlines on Tuesday officially retired its decades-old practice of open seating. For the first time, passengers received assigned seats, a major shift for the carrier, which also introduced a new group boarding process and premium seat options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two flights with assigned seating landed early in the day, at Chicago Midway International Airport and then at Orlando International Airport, where a plane arriving from San Juan, P.R., glided toward the jetway under two arcs of water, a salute reserved for special occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The celebration continued at the gate, which was festooned with red, blue and orange balloons. Passengers loaded up on free snacks and coffee and took selfies through heart-shaped holes in giant boarding passes. The airline handed out bag tags with the line, “I understood the assignment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southwest says the seating changes are intended to keep up with evolving customer expectations and to increase revenue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tony Roach, an executive vice president at the airline who was on the flight from San Juan, said that the airline had “outgrown” open seating, adding that assigned seating also reduces anxiety among travelers because they know what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There were a lot of limitations with open seating in terms of what we want to do in the future,” he said. “You aren’t able to offer things inside the cabin which a lot of people want. Things like extra legroom would have been very difficult to do with an open-seating environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than 50 years, Southwest used a system of open seating: Once they had checked in, passengers received a group and a number that determined the general order of when they’d get on the plane. Then once on board, they could choose any open seat. Getting a desired seat, or sitting together, often hinged on checking in early, and there were no premium seats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was loved by some travelers, who viewed it as egalitarian and flexible, and bemoaned by others who complained that it was chaotic and stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Southwest offers three categories of seats — standard, preferred and extra legroom — and the most expensive can cost hundreds of dollars more than the cheapest fare. Boarding order now depends on the fare class, as well as whether a traveler has elite status with the airline or holds its credit card. Travelers can also pay extra to board in an earlier group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times travel coverage. When our writers review a destination, they do not accept free or discounted services or, in most cases, reveal that they work for The Times. We want their experience to be what you can expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Tuesday, the airline also ended its flexible policy for plus-size passengers, which allowed customers to ask for an extra seat at the gate, or pay for an extra seat and later receive a refund. Those passengers will now need to purchase two seats ahead of time, without a guaranteed refund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some loyal travelers expressed dismay that the airline was abandoning some of the quirks that made it different from other major U.S. carriers. In May, Southwest eliminated its popular policy of granting travelers two free checked bags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larry Wolf, 74, who has flown with Southwest for more than two decades, said he was enticed early on by the airline’s reputation as an industry disrupter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I liked them really well when they were young and scrappy. In the past, they seemed to have mastered the quick turnaround, they were able to get back on time after delays, they are very agile with swapping planes and all of that,” said Mr. Wolf, who was at LaGuardia Airport awaiting his flight home to Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With assigned seats and premium fares, “now it’s just like any other airline,” Mr. Wolf said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several longtime Southwest fliers also remarked that they enjoyed the unpredictability of the previous open-seating system. Aaron Schottenstein, a 35-year-old who lives in Phoenix, said he’d been dreading the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I loved the boarding, getting on in the lines, yapping with everybody while you wait there, talking about how people are trying to get like five spots closer because they might get that much better of a seat,” said Mr. Schottenstein, who was traveling from New York to Phoenix, with a connection in Kansas City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others welcomed assigned seating, saying it eliminated pain points like checking in 24 hours ahead of a flight to improve the chances of snagging a better seat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love it,” said Maureen Hager, of Buffalo, who was traveling home from Orlando on Tuesday with Veronica, her adult daughter. “I hated waiting on line, trying to get there early. I don’t like waiting to get to the airport and waiting on line and the anxiety of not knowing if you got seats together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronica, however, disagreed. She called the change a “money grab.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the other way,” she said. “I like the thrill of having to check in, trying to get Group A, first round.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Jordan, the airline’s chief executive said in an interview last month that the airline was confident that customers, who he said desire these changes, would stay loyal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re now offering things that the vast majority of people want,” he said, adding, “We’ve seen no defection from the brand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Adelson contributed reporting from Orlando, Fla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow New York Times Travel on Instagram and sign up for our Travel Dispatch newsletter to get expert tips on traveling smarter and inspiration for your next vacation. Dreaming up a future getaway or just armchair traveling? Check out our 52 Places to Go in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/travel/southwest-airlines-assigned-seating.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:32:45 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>