<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Education Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Education articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:51:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Hey, ChatGPT: Where Should I Go to College?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/style/chatgpt-college-admissions-advice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27CHATGPT-ADMISSIONS-mjvz/27CHATGPT-ADMISSIONS-mjvz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was September, and Rosemary Davis was feeling overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her son, a high school senior interested in history and music, was beginning to apply to colleges. The admissions process had completely transformed since she was a student, and counseling at her son’s public high school in Massachusetts was “almost nonexistent,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrift in a new world of unfamiliar acronyms and exorbitant price tags, Ms. Davis, 48, a school librarian, turned to ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She began by asking the A.I. chatbot basic questions about how to fill out the Common App, a standardized application used by hundreds of U.S. colleges and universities. (For instance: What did it mean by “activity list”?) Then she requested suggestions of small liberal arts schools where her son might be competitive based on his grades and test scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her son was “horrified,” she said: “He’s like, ‘Stop, Mom.’” But she wanted to know more. She copied the list of 14 colleges he was applying to into a paid chatbot, Claude Pro, and asked it to predict where he might be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It just snowballed — I think it felt like a means of control over a process that you have no control over,” she said in January, after her son received his first acceptance, to Muhlenberg College. (Decision letters began going out in December, and most students will have heard back from every school by April.) “I don’t know if it’s accurate, but it makes me feel better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing the gantlet of applying to college, students and parents are prompting A.I. chatbots to take on a role somewhere between that of an admissions counselor and a crystal ball. One-third of high school students surveyed in 2024 by the education consulting firm Ruffalo Noel Levitz said they had used A.I. tools as part of their college planning. The most popular reason they indicated was to research schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some colleges have warned applicants against using generative A.I. to write their admissions essays for them, most have not articulated restrictions on using chatbots as a sounding board or a brainstorming tool — and students say they do not see asking a chatbot as all that different from consulting a parent or counselor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high school senior in Wisconsin applied to Purdue University at the suggestion of ChatGPT, which he had asked to compile a list of public schools with strong engineering programs. A sophomore in Connecticut regularly prompts the chatbot to estimate his chances of getting into Harvard, Yale and Princeton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior at a public school in Pittsburgh asked Microsoft Copilot to trawl her message history in order to help her brainstorm topics in response to an essay question: What do you do for fun?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In interviews, students and parents described the chatbots as reassuring, constantly available and a steal compared with private admissions consultants who can charge tens of thousands of dollars a year. But flesh-and-blood college admissions experts worry that chatbots — which frequently offer up inaccurate information and tend to flatter their users — have the potential to mislead students during a critical period in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reality is, A.I. is not going to give them good advice about what it is that an admissions officer might be looking for,” said Angel Pérez, the chief executive of the National Association for College Admission Counseling and a former counselor at a public high school in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A.I. tools might be helpful for gathering application deadlines or looking up the average G.P.A. of admitted students, he said, especially for families with limited access to a school counselor. But chatbots are a poor substitute for introspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A computer is not going to tell you what a good fit for you is,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miranda Yap was hesitant when her college admissions counselor at Punahou School, a private high school in Honolulu, suggested she use ChatGPT to help her collect information about the colleges she was considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She did not want to let the chatbot think for her, she said. Still, she said she felt immense pressure to get into a competitive school, and she wondered if the software could help. With a couple of keystrokes, it unfurled a spreadsheet of tuition costs and acceptance rates for more than a dozen schools she submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Great list!” the chatbot wrote in one response, after identifying Boston University as a “reach” school and the University of Oregon as a “safety.” It ended each message with an offer of more assistance: “I’d be happy to continue digging if needed!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Yap still leaned on her school counselor to help with granular details of her application, but she found herself turning to the chatbot for ideas and encouragement at all hours. “If it’s 11 p.m. and I’m working on my college spreadsheet, I’m not going to email my counselor and ask them about something: I’m going to talk to A.I.,” said Ms. Yap, 18, a senior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents argue that A.I. tools could improve access to college counseling for students who cannot turn to private coaches or family members with college degrees. There were an average of 376 students to every school counselor in the 2023-24 school year, according to the American School Counselor Association — well above the organization’s recommended ratio of 250-to-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College Possible, a nonprofit organization that provides free college coaching to students from low-income families, introduced an A.I. coaching service last year that it says is being used by more than 3,000 students. It answers routine questions so the organization’s human counselors can spend more time advising applicants, said Siva Kumari, College Possible’s chief executive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We definitely don’t believe that the whole thing can be done by A.I.,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although several A.I.-based start-ups promise to help students boost their chances of acceptance to selective schools, a vast majority of the students who responded to a New York Times questionnaire said they had turned to the same handful of all-purpose chatbots that others use for recipes, home-repair tips or companionship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brandon Royalty, a senior in Madison, Wis., said ChatGPT had been useful in suggesting large public colleges that were a fit for him academically and financially. It had been hard to schedule appointments with the four counselors at his public high school, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he double-checked the information the chatbot had provided, he found that it was prone to hallucinate, or fabricate real-sounding responses. “There were a couple times where it would invent some scholarship that a school offered, and then I wouldn’t find any mention of that scholarship on their website,” Mr. Royalty, 18, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he knew at least one student who had asked an A.I. tool to write a draft of a college admissions essay. Mr. Royalty wrote his essay himself, he said, but he asked ChatGPT — along with a few trusted adults — for feedback on how he could make it clearer and more concise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing so was not against any of the guidelines for the schools he was applying to, he said. Other students were less sure what was allowed and what was not: Some schools have adopted stances against A.I. use but still permit it for proofreading, while others offer no guidelines at all for prospective students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a nerve-racking period of senior year, students often turn to online forums like Reddit and College Confidential, desperate for any indication of whether they will gain admission to the schools of their choosing. Several students said they had instead asked chatbots to estimate their chances of acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’d tell me, ‘You have a shot at everything; you’re 100 percent getting into Princeton and Stanford,’” said Tanay Burman, 17, a senior at Galileo Academy of Science &amp; Technology, a public high school in San Francisco. “It’s really hard to get a realistic expectation from it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joie Jager-Hyman, a former assistant director of admissions at Dartmouth College and the founder of College Prep 360, a private admissions consulting service, said she had little confidence in chatbots’ ability to predict which students will be admitted where. She worried that the tendency of some chatbots to affirm their users’ beliefs could result in overly rosy admissions predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most selective colleges take up to two years to release admissions data for each cycle, meaning that the statistics ChatGPT relies on for its calculations may be woefully out of date, she added. “The only guess that matters is a truly educated guess,” she said. “If you’ve read thousands of applications, you have a much better sense of how people really get in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike human counselors, chatbots have no limit to how many questions they can answer about the admissions process; a nervous applicant or parent could theoretically type and scroll forever. At first, that was exciting to Tichanda Thompson, whose son, a high school junior in Memphis, plans to apply to musical theater programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To familiarize herself with the audition process, she used ChatGPT to create a spreadsheet of information about 45 schools, including columns for scholarship opportunities and the average flight cost from Memphis. (Her son, Caleb Alexander Thompson, suggested adding a column for whether there were sushi restaurants nearby.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also asked chatbots to suggest audition songs for her son in different genres: pop, contemporary, musical theater. Soon, her challenge was not a lack of data, but trying to keep herself from gathering too much of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatbots make it easy “to go deep, and deeper, and all the way,” she said. “If you don’t know when to stop, it can get a little crazy.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/style/chatgpt-college-admissions-advice.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:00:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Academic and a Dealmaker Takes on the Challenge of Running Columbia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/nyregion/columbia-president-jennifer-mnookin.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26met-columbia-president-zjhw/26met-columbia-president-zjhw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chancellor of the University of Wisconsin-Madison for the past three years, Jennifer Mnookin negotiated some tough deals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one, she forged a compromise with pro-Palestinian students on the campus of the flagship state university, persuading them to remove their encampment protesting the Gaza war. In another, she helped lead negotiations with the Republican-controlled Wisconsin Legislature, resulting in $800 million in state funding being released in exchange for ending some diversity programs in the university system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a lawyer and the daughter of a renowned legal expert in conflict resolution, Dr. Mnookin didn’t shy away from the bargaining table. She listened, made concessions and took some heat. In the end, she won not only admiration from the leadership at the University of Wisconsin, but also from the trustees at Columbia University, who just picked her as the next president of the Ivy League school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Her reputation is that she is a healer, brings people together, listens to diverse points of view and tries to find solutions that will work for everyone,” Jeh Johnson, the co-chair of Columbia’s board of trustees, said in an interview on Monday. “And given the diversity and diversity of thought at Columbia, that was a quality of general value to us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the University of Wisconsin, Columbia is facing difficult times, and a politically complicated situation, as it navigates a $200 million deal with the Trump White House that required several concessions to restore more than $400 million in research funding. Its campus remains divided over its response to Gaza war protests and has had four presidents since 2023. It also needs a leader who can bring the university together and move it forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friends and supporters of Dr. Mnookin, 58, who were interviewed on Monday said that her experience and talents make her the right person, at the right time, for that daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin has the ability to smooth tensions by “being highly consultative and very thoughtful about where the institution needs to go and having people come along to get it there,” said Joan Gabel, the chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, who during her previous job as the president of University of Minnesota became friends with Dr. Mnookin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only that, she said, “but she may be the smartest person any of us know. And given who we know in this work, it’s not an empty compliment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its December 2023 deal with the Wisconsin State Legislature, the University of Wisconsin yielded ground in some areas to secure funding for employee wage increases and to break ground for a new engineering building. In exchange, the university restructured diversity offices and positions and froze new administrative hires focused on diversity, among other changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That led to pushback from the Wisconsin Legislative Black Caucus and some students, who felt the university had sold out the interests of students and staff members of color in exchange for state funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin responded by emphasizing “an atmosphere of inclusion for everybody” on campus, a message that resonated, said Amy Bogost, the president of the Universities of Wisconsin board of regents. And then she built new programs focused on making college more affordable, regardless of race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin had said at the time that “compromise is never easy, and this compromise is far from perfect, but I continue to believe this pathway will permit us to hold onto our core values — including our firm commitments to diversity and belonging — while also allowing us to move forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Schill, a close friend and the former president of Northwestern University, said that he saw the episode as an example of her leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She will be a principled pragmatist,” he said. “She’s not an ideologue. Although she’s guided by principles, she also is a pragmatic leader and will do what is needed to protect and ensure the future of her institution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin has spent her lifetime in and around the academic world. Her father, Robert Mnookin, is a professor who served as the chair of the program on negotiation at the Harvard University Law School. In her own education, Dr. Mnookin managed a hat-trick of prestige universities, attending Harvard as an undergraduate, Yale University for law school and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology for a doctorate in the history and social study of science and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1994, she married a political theorist and professor, Joshua Foa Dienstag; the couple have two grown children, Sophia and Isaac. She has spent decades as a law professor and then academic administrator, first at the University of Virginia School of Law, and then at the University of California, Los Angeles School of Law, as a professor and dean. In 2022, she became the leader of the University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her father said he and his wife, Dale Mnookin, knew for the past few months that their daughter was under consideration for the Columbia job. “Columbia is quite a challenge,” he said, but he added that he knew Jennifer “has the values and the skills to make a contribution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I found it pretty obvious from a pretty early age that she was going to no doubt be an academic,” he said. “And I think what’s really interesting is that she has obviously developed the skills to also be a successful academic leader and administrator.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Jennifer donated a kidney to her father, which is still going strong. “It’s a really good kidney,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin’s lifetime in academia has led her to have strong relationships with many people at high levels of university leadership, which friends say will serve her well in her new position. It was also a quality that impressed Columbia’s board, Mr. Johnson, the co-chair, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Lee Isbell Jr., the chancellor of the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, served as provost under Dr. Mnookin in Madison. He said that she likes to hear from everyone before making a decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s deliberative,” he said. “She wants to understand what the possibilities are.” He said that she also cares, like a lawyer, about the details of arguments and language. “In fact, if I had to put it down to a single thing about her personality, what drives through, is that she cares about the argument and getting the argument right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher L. Eisgruber, the president of Princeton University, said that he was so glad when he heard the news of her selection that he sent an email to Columbia “expressing my extraordinary enthusiasm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope that the university comes together and supports her, because the success of any university president is critically dependent on that,” he said. Higher education, he added, needs a strong Columbia, and “she can’t do it all alone, no matter how good she is.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/nyregion/columbia-president-jennifer-mnookin.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:06:25 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>