<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Education Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Education articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:06:49 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>No Snow Day? In New York City Parks, It Felt Like One.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/weather/snow-parks-children-remote-schooling.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26winter-storm-nyc-parks-sub-bkjh/26winter-storm-nyc-parks-sub-bkjh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Children and families went sledding in Prospect Park in Brooklyn on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/weather/snow-parks-children-remote-schooling.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:09:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Academic and a Dealmaker Takes on the Challenge of Running Columbia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/nyregion/columbia-president-jennifer-mnookin.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26met-columbia-president-zjhw/26met-columbia-president-zjhw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jennifer Mnookin was dean of the University of California, Los Angeles’s law school before taking the top job at Wisconsin’s flagship public university.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/nyregion/columbia-president-jennifer-mnookin.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 23:00:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Have to Be More Than the Anti-Trump Party</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/opinion/democrats-trump-midterms-future.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27edsall-fhqw/27edsall-fhqw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment is ripe to deal a debilitating blow to Trumpism and the MAGA movement. But who can deliver it?&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/opinion/democrats-trump-midterms-future.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:03:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Columbia Selects University of Wisconsin Chancellor as Its President</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/nyregion/columbia-president-wisconsin-mnookin.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26met-columbia-presidentHFO-cqjb/26met-columbia-presidentHFO-cqjb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia University has chosen Jennifer Mnookin, the chancellor of the University of Wisconsin-Madison, as its next president, hoping to usher in a period of growth and stability after a tumultuous two years on its campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin, 58, is a legal scholar who served as the dean of the University of California, Los Angeles School of Law before arriving at Wisconsin to lead its flagship state university in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an announcement sent to the Columbia campus on Sunday night, David Greenwald and Jeh Johnson, the co-chairs of Columbia University’s board of trustees, said that Dr. Mnookin would bring to Columbia “an exceptional academic and leadership pedigree and a reputation for building trust through listening and engagement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She is known as a thoughtful consensus builder who strives for excellence in every pursuit, bringing both vision and energy to the work of institutional leadership,” they said. “She will be a remarkable leader of our great university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin said in a statement that she was “honored and thrilled to join Columbia University at this important moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I look forward to working closely with faculty, students and staff, and with both our local and global community of alumni and friends, to advance the university’s critically important mission and to ensure that its teaching and research continue to contribute meaningfully to society,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Columbia, Dr. Mnookin will find a large, complex research university that has been coping with challenges on many fronts, including cuts to its research enterprise by the Trump administration and deep divisions over how it handled a burst of student protest activity on campus after the Oct. 7, 2023, Hamas attack on Israel. At the University of Wisconsin, Dr. Mnookin also contended with student protests in 2024, charting a path that resulted in ending a student encampment while also seeking engagement with demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her own academic background is something of a top-tier trifecta. She earned a bachelor’s degree from Harvard University, a law degree from Yale University and a doctorate in the history and social study of science and technology from Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Her academic work focuses on evidence, proof and decision making in the legal system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her résumé has echoes of that of Lee Bollinger, who led Columbia between 2002 and 2023 and was a lawyer who had been president of the University of Michigan. In finding a candidate with deep roots in American academia, Columbia’s board appears to be trying to correct for its last hire, Nemat Shafik, a London economist who resigned in 2024 amid campus turmoil over the Gaza war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bollinger welcomed her appointment. “Jennifer Mnookin understands, at a deep level, what it means to lead a major research university in a complex and consequential moment,” he said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia’s campus was rocked by frequent, large demonstrations by students in favor of Palestinian self-determination, with some calling for the end of Israel as a Jewish state, using language that many Israeli and Jewish students found threatening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Shafik, who had never led an American university, struggled to balance Columbia’s free speech traditions with the pressures that came from some students, parents, donors and congressional Republicans to shut the protests down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To contain the unrest, Dr. Shafik closed the main campus in Manhattan’s Morningside Heights neighborhood to the public; it remains so to this day. In April 2024, she testified before a congressional committee about the activism, calling it unacceptable, but the political pressure did not relent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia’s student activists escalated tensions, putting up an encampment on a campus lawn. Dr. Shafik called the New York City police to make arrests, but hundreds of other students simply moved to the next lawn over. For nearly two weeks, they remained, sparking a wave of tent pro-Palestinian cities on other campuses around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When negotiations to end the encampment failed, a small group of students and outsiders took over a campus building. Dr. Shafik authorized the police to enter the building and arrest the occupiers, and the campus went into a lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With her leadership under fire on all fronts, Dr. Shafik resigned during the summer. Two interim leaders followed. Katrina Armstrong, the chief executive of Columbia’s medical school, came first, and negotiated with the Trump administration after it suspended more than $400 million in research grants because of what it called the school’s antisemitism problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She resigned following pressure from the White House, which had perceived that she was playing down the concessions that Columbia had made. The board then appointed one of its own trustees, Claire Shipman, a former television journalist, as the acting president until a permanent president could be chosen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Ms. Shipman, Columbia reached a deal in July with the White House, agreeing to pay $200 million to the federal government and $21 million to a fund to pay for claims from staff members that they experienced antisemitism. Nearly all the research grants were restored, and a tense calm returned to campus, even as anger about what critics blasted as Columbia’s capitulation persisted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Columbia searched for a new president, some faculty expressed concern that the trustees would select someone who would double down on Columbia’s growing emphasis on security over free expression. But Dr. Mnookin, based on her background, appears to be more of a moderate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she faced a pro-Palestinian encampment at the University of Wisconsin in April 2024 that had been inspired by Columbia’s, she took a dual approach. She authorized the police to dismantle the encampment, after telling the protesters to disperse multiple times. But when the demonstrators reinstated their camp, much as they did at Columbia, she became involved with negotiations and reached an agreement with students to end the encampment peacefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the most fundamental missions of a university is and must be to foster engagement and dialogue across what can often feel like intractable differences,” she told her campus community in a letter in May 2024. “As we have navigated this past week, I have endeavored to listen to the concerns of the many people we have heard from and the many perspectives that have been represented.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, Ms. Shipman, the acting president, said Dr. Mnookin’s skill as a listener who “pulls people together” was a trait that stood out about her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s able to navigate difficult political terrain, and, in fact, she isn’t afraid to dive into thorny issues,” she said. “She knows that is, in part, what universities are meant to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mnookin has also focused on affordability initiatives at Wisconsin. In addition, she launched a research initiative to invest in artificial intelligence, sustainability and human health. As of 2025, the university reclaimed a spot among the top five universities nationally for research expenditures, a milestone it had not hit in over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“During her tenure, Chancellor Jennifer Mnookin brought unbounded energy, resilience and deeply thoughtful leadership to this great university,” Jay Rothman, the president of the Universities of Wisconsin system, said in the official announcement of her new post, which she will begin on July 1.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/nyregion/columbia-president-wisconsin-mnookin.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:20:55 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>