<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Education Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Education articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:48:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Hey, ChatGPT: Where Should I Go to College?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/style/chatgpt-college-admissions-advice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27CHATGPT-ADMISSIONS-mjvz/27CHATGPT-ADMISSIONS-mjvz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was September, and Rosemary Davis was feeling overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her son, a high school senior interested in history and music, was beginning to apply to colleges. The admissions process had completely transformed since she was a student, and counseling at her son’s public high school in Massachusetts was “almost nonexistent,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adrift in a new world of unfamiliar acronyms and exorbitant price tags, Ms. Davis, 48, a school librarian, turned to ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She began by asking the A.I. chatbot basic questions about how to fill out the Common App, a standardized application used by hundreds of U.S. colleges and universities. (For instance: What did it mean by “activity list”?) Then she requested suggestions of small liberal arts schools where her son might be competitive based on his grades and test scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her son was “horrified,” she said: “He’s like, ‘Stop, Mom.’” But she wanted to know more. She copied the list of 14 colleges he was applying to into a paid chatbot, Claude Pro, and asked it to predict where he might be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It just snowballed — I think it felt like a means of control over a process that you have no control over,” she said in January, after her son received his first acceptance, to Muhlenberg College. (Decision letters began going out in December, and most students will have heard back from every school by April.) “I don’t know if it’s accurate, but it makes me feel better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing the gantlet of applying to college, students and parents are prompting A.I. chatbots to take on a role somewhere between that of an admissions counselor and a crystal ball. One-third of high school students surveyed in 2024 by the education consulting firm Ruffalo Noel Levitz said they had used A.I. tools as part of their college planning. The most popular reason they indicated was to research schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some colleges have warned applicants against using generative A.I. to write their admissions essays for them, most have not articulated restrictions on using chatbots as a sounding board or a brainstorming tool — and students say they do not see asking a chatbot as all that different from consulting a parent or counselor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high school senior in Wisconsin applied to Purdue University at the suggestion of ChatGPT, which he had asked to compile a list of public schools with strong engineering programs. A sophomore in Connecticut regularly prompts the chatbot to estimate his chances of getting into Harvard, Yale and Princeton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior at a public school in Pittsburgh asked Microsoft Copilot to trawl her message history in order to help her brainstorm topics in response to an essay question: What do you do for fun?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In interviews, students and parents described the chatbots as reassuring, constantly available and a steal compared with private admissions consultants who can charge tens of thousands of dollars a year. But flesh-and-blood college admissions experts worry that chatbots — which frequently offer up inaccurate information and tend to flatter their users — have the potential to mislead students during a critical period in their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reality is, A.I. is not going to give them good advice about what it is that an admissions officer might be looking for,” said Angel Pérez, the chief executive of the National Association for College Admission Counseling and a former counselor at a public high school in New York City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A.I. tools might be helpful for gathering application deadlines or looking up the average G.P.A. of admitted students, he said, especially for families with limited access to a school counselor. But chatbots are a poor substitute for introspection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A computer is not going to tell you what a good fit for you is,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miranda Yap was hesitant when her college admissions counselor at Punahou School, a private high school in Honolulu, suggested she use ChatGPT to help her collect information about the colleges she was considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She did not want to let the chatbot think for her, she said. Still, she said she felt immense pressure to get into a competitive school, and she wondered if the software could help. With a couple of keystrokes, it unfurled a spreadsheet of tuition costs and acceptance rates for more than a dozen schools she submitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Great list!” the chatbot wrote in one response, after identifying Boston University as a “reach” school and the University of Oregon as a “safety.” It ended each message with an offer of more assistance: “I’d be happy to continue digging if needed!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Yap still leaned on her school counselor to help with granular details of her application, but she found herself turning to the chatbot for ideas and encouragement at all hours. “If it’s 11 p.m. and I’m working on my college spreadsheet, I’m not going to email my counselor and ask them about something: I’m going to talk to A.I.,” said Ms. Yap, 18, a senior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents argue that A.I. tools could improve access to college counseling for students who cannot turn to private coaches or family members with college degrees. There were an average of 376 students to every school counselor in the 2023-24 school year, according to the American School Counselor Association — well above the organization’s recommended ratio of 250-to-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College Possible, a nonprofit organization that provides free college coaching to students from low-income families, introduced an A.I. coaching service last year that it says is being used by more than 3,000 students. It answers routine questions so the organization’s human counselors can spend more time advising applicants, said Siva Kumari, College Possible’s chief executive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We definitely don’t believe that the whole thing can be done by A.I.,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although several A.I.-based start-ups promise to help students boost their chances of acceptance to selective schools, a vast majority of the students who responded to a New York Times questionnaire said they had turned to the same handful of all-purpose chatbots that others use for recipes, home-repair tips or companionship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brandon Royalty, a senior in Madison, Wis., said ChatGPT had been useful in suggesting large public colleges that were a fit for him academically and financially. It had been hard to schedule appointments with the four counselors at his public high school, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he double-checked the information the chatbot had provided, he found that it was prone to hallucinate, or fabricate real-sounding responses. “There were a couple times where it would invent some scholarship that a school offered, and then I wouldn’t find any mention of that scholarship on their website,” Mr. Royalty, 18, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he knew at least one student who had asked an A.I. tool to write a draft of a college admissions essay. Mr. Royalty wrote his essay himself, he said, but he asked ChatGPT — along with a few trusted adults — for feedback on how he could make it clearer and more concise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing so was not against any of the guidelines for the schools he was applying to, he said. Other students were less sure what was allowed and what was not: Some schools have adopted stances against A.I. use but still permit it for proofreading, while others offer no guidelines at all for prospective students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a nerve-racking period of senior year, students often turn to online forums like Reddit and College Confidential, desperate for any indication of whether they will gain admission to the schools of their choosing. Several students said they had instead asked chatbots to estimate their chances of acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’d tell me, ‘You have a shot at everything; you’re 100 percent getting into Princeton and Stanford,’” said Tanay Burman, 17, a senior at Galileo Academy of Science &amp; Technology, a public high school in San Francisco. “It’s really hard to get a realistic expectation from it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joie Jager-Hyman, a former assistant director of admissions at Dartmouth College and the founder of College Prep 360, a private admissions consulting service, said she had little confidence in chatbots’ ability to predict which students will be admitted where. She worried that the tendency of some chatbots to affirm their users’ beliefs could result in overly rosy admissions predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most selective colleges take up to two years to release admissions data for each cycle, meaning that the statistics ChatGPT relies on for its calculations may be woefully out of date, she added. “The only guess that matters is a truly educated guess,” she said. “If you’ve read thousands of applications, you have a much better sense of how people really get in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike human counselors, chatbots have no limit to how many questions they can answer about the admissions process; a nervous applicant or parent could theoretically type and scroll forever. At first, that was exciting to Tichanda Thompson, whose son, a high school junior in Memphis, plans to apply to musical theater programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To familiarize herself with the audition process, she used ChatGPT to create a spreadsheet of information about 45 schools, including columns for scholarship opportunities and the average flight cost from Memphis. (Her son, Caleb Alexander Thompson, suggested adding a column for whether there were sushi restaurants nearby.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also asked chatbots to suggest audition songs for her son in different genres: pop, contemporary, musical theater. Soon, her challenge was not a lack of data, but trying to keep herself from gathering too much of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatbots make it easy “to go deep, and deeper, and all the way,” she said. “If you don’t know when to stop, it can get a little crazy.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/style/chatgpt-college-admissions-advice.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:06:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>When Conservative Politics Hit Cash-Starved Universities</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/opinion/conservative-campus-politics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;If college education is merely a transaction, educators — and facts — are vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/opinion/conservative-campus-politics.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:19:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Fed Rate Decisions Affect Mortgages, Credit Cards, Auto Loans and More</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/your-money/fed-rates-mortgages-credit-cards-loans.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28fed-meeting-consumer-rates-bvwq/28fed-meeting-consumer-rates-bvwq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Some home loans are closely tethered to the Federal Reserve’s decisions.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/your-money/fed-rates-mortgages-credit-cards-loans.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:07:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Maine’s Immigrant Students Stay Home as ICE Operation Ramps Up</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Educators from South Portland Middle School participate in a neighborhood watch at a bus stop in South Portland on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:54:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yale Offers Free Tuition to Families With Incomes Under $200,000</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-yale-qljh/27nat-yale-qljh-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale University said on Tuesday that attending the university would be free for newly admitted undergraduate students from families with annual incomes below $100,000, and that tuition would be waived for those earning below $200,000. The change takes effect for the class that will enroll in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move enters Yale into an arms race of elite institutions offering increasingly attractive financial aid packages to students from low- and middle-income families. At Yale, the full-price cost to attend is now more than $90,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale’s new policy essentially matches the deal offered by Harvard last year, which followed similar announcements by the University of Pennsylvania, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Princeton and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beefed-up financial aid follows the Supreme Court’s 2023 decision limiting what universities may do to recruit racially diverse student bodies. The schools hope to continue to attract diverse applicants by stepping up financial aid, since race and income are often correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort to make attendance more affordable at some of the nation’s highest-rated universities also comes at a time when public trust in higher education has declined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Kahlenberg, director of the American Identity Project at the Progressive Policy Institute, said the effort was good not just for the country but also for Yale, because it will allow students from different walks of life to attend, increasing the range of viewpoints on campus as well as the range of backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Economic diversity can bring racial diversity in a way that’s perfectly legal,” he said. “So after the Supreme Court struck down the use of race, institutions like Yale had to find different ways to get racial diversity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the new policy, which was first reported by The Wall Street Journal, Yale said that students from 80 percent of households in the United States would qualify for free tuition, and students from almost half the nation’s households would be eligible for an entirely free Yale education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the lowest-income students, the offerings at Yale, Harvard and some other schools include free housing and meal plans, allowances for travel to and from campus, medical insurance and “start-up” grants for students to use to buy books and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an announcement last August, Princeton appeared to eclipse even those generous aid packages, saying that most families with incomes up to $150,000 would pay nothing to attend and most with incomes up to $250,000 will pay no tuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, the upper limit for household income to qualify for no-cost attendance at Yale was $75,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremiah Quinlan, Yale’s dean of undergraduate admission and financial aid, said the new plan is an investment in affordability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With this announcement, we reiterate and reinforce Yale’s commitment to ensuring that cost will never be a barrier between promising students and a Yale College education,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:39:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>