<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT Education Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT Education articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/Education_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 22:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Cursive Makes a Comeback in New Jersey Schools</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/nyregion/cursive-new-jersey-schools.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20met-nj-cursive-01-glvz/20met-nj-cursive-01-glvz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a swooping P, a curling H, a slanted I and a looped L, Gov. Philip D. Murphy of New Jersey — on his last full day in office on Monday — signed into law a bill requiring that all third, fourth and fifth graders in the state learn cursive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though script is little used these days beyond checkbooks and autographs, New Jersey joins roughly two dozen other states that have inscribed similar rules in recent years, bucking a drop-off in cursive instruction that began in 2010, when the federal government removed it from the Common Core Standards for students in kindergarten through 12th grade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of cursive cite studies that link handwriting to better information retention and writing speed, and say — as Mr. Murphy did in a statement released as he signed the bill — that knowing script can help people read the original U.S. Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning cursive will provide New Jersey students with “the skills they need to read our nation’s founding documents,” as well as write checks and improve cognition, Mr. Murphy said on Monday, a day before relinquishing his office to the state’s new Democratic governor, Mikie Sherrill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requirement takes effect immediately and applies to the next full school year, according to Kevin Dehmer, the state’s education commissioner. “Ensuring that all students learn cursive handwriting reinforces not just a traditional skill, but developmental foundations that support fine motor development, literacy skills and student confidence,” Mr. Dehmer said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Gabrielle and Kurt McCann, of Lebanon, N.J., were waiting to break the news to their 9-year-old son, Atlas McCann, when he got home from school. “I think it is important that kids are able to use that refined motor skill,” Ms. McCann said in an interview shortly after a meeting where she said she had taken all her notes in longhand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Atlas, she said, was thinking, “What’s the point of having to sit here and torture myself?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hopefully in the long run, he will see it has value,” Ms. McCann said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts share Atlas’s viewpoint. “Oh, God,” Morgan Polikoff, an education professor at the University of Southern California, said when he learned of the New Jersey law. Mr. Polikoff acknowledged the studies showing the benefits of handwriting, but he pointed out that most were not specific to script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He attributed the renewed affection for the style’s curlicues and squiggles to “boomerish nostalgia,” and said he was struck by cursive’s bipartisan appeal, with states as different politically as Arkansas and California requiring its instruction. Conservatives, the professor said, promote its utility for reading old documents; liberals like it for its beauty as an art form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a very strange phenomenon, but the fact that you have states left, right and center adopting mandates that children learn cursive is not something I could have predicted,” Mr. Polikoff added. “Who hand-writes hardly anything?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renewed passion for cursive often coincides with moments of societal tumult, said Tamara Plakins Thornton, a history professor emerita at the State University of New York at Buffalo and the author of “Handwriting in America: A Cultural History.” The feminist revolution of the 1960s, for example, led to a comeback for script, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It has long been obsolete; it’s been obsolete since the typewriter came around,” Ms. Platkins Thorton said. “The fact that it is obsolete makes it all the more appealing: ‘Let’s go run back to that past.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least one New Jersey child is eager to embrace cursive instruction: A year ago, Eleanor Covucci, a kindergartner at a charter school in Jersey City, was the state’s Northeast regional winner in the National Handwriting Competition sponsored by Zaner-Bloser, a company that publishes cursive workbooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For her winning entry, Eleanor, then 5 years old, wrote “I like how there are many ways to make words” — in print as opposed to script, as was required for competitors in her age group. She still proudly wears the medal everywhere, including at the airport, her mother, Amber Covucci, said, and is already gearing up for cursive competitions, which will be more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleanor, now 6, said she was ready for the challenge. She can already write her name in cursive, she said, and even her nickname, Ellie — almost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am actually pretty good at that word,” she said. “I am sort of kind of good at cursive.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/nyregion/cursive-new-jersey-schools.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:35:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Joel Primack, Physicist Who Helped Explain the Cosmos, Dies at 80</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/science/joel-primack-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/00Primack-fvkw-print1/00Primack-fvkw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joel R. Primack, a physicist who helped explain how tiny quantum fluctuations at the birth of the universe led to the formation of galaxies, galactic clusters and even larger structures spanning the cosmos, died on Nov. 13 in Palo Alto, Calif. He was 80.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause was pancreatic cancer, said his wife, Nancy Ellen Abrams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a professor of physics and astrophysics at the University of California, Santa Cruz, Dr. Primack was a key contributor to a landmark paper, published in the journal Nature in 1984, that laid out how the universe came to look like it does today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even at the time the paper came out, astrophysicists had already realized that ordinary matter — the particles that make up stars, gas clouds, planets, people — could account for only a small fraction of the mass in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the outer parts of galaxies seemed to be spinning too fast, there had to be more mass that could not be observed — what scientists called dark matter — to exert the gravitational pull to keep the stars from flying apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists did not know what dark matter could be — and decades later, they still do not. But Dr. Primack, along with two colleagues at Santa Cruz, George Blumenthal and Sandra Faber, and Martin Rees, at the University of Cambridge in England, figured out key properties of dark matter that were essential for producing what is observed in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That became part of this whole foundation that we’ve been using now for years,” said Saul Perlmutter, an astrophysicist at the University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper published in Nature provided a coherent story of how the universe evolved over billions of years after the Big Bang. During a brief moment of rapid expansion known as cosmic inflation, which occurred immediately after the birth of the universe, tiny quantum fluctuations produced a bit of lumpiness in the universe. The regions that were ever so slightly denser grew into clumps of dark matter, and the gravity of the dark matter pulled clouds of ordinary matter that then collapsed into galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this model to work, the dark matter had to be “cold,” consisting of larger particles that moved relatively slowly, Dr. Primack and his colleagues calculated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was really pretty simple pencil and paper,” Dr. Faber recalled. “That’s all that we had available.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Dr. Primack was listed third among the four authors, a ranking that usually indicates a smaller role, Dr. Faber said that “he actually conceived and directed the whole thing and wrote 90 percent of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Think of him as the orchestra director who sort of got us all together,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harnessing the power of supercomputers, Dr. Primack and others provided much more detail in subsequent work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numerical simulations “allowed us to make specific predictions” about the structure of the dark matter concentrations, how they grew and how they merged and grew together, said James Bullock, who was a graduate student of Dr. Primack’s in the 1990s and is now an astrophysicist at the University of Southern California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those predictions, he added, could then be compared with astronomical observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Primack also played an influential role in the world of science policy. When he was a graduate student at Stanford, his thesis adviser was Sidney Drell, who was continually flying to Washington to make recommendations to President Lyndon B. Johnson on military technology and national security matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an oral history interview with the American Institute of Physics, Dr. Primack recalled: “I would keep asking Sid, ‘How come this stupid Vietnam War is going on? You’re meeting with the president frequently, serving on his science advisory committee. Can’t you tell him how dumb this war is?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he did not receive much of an answer — Dr. Drell said the discussions were classified — but Dr. Primack nonetheless was inspired to undertake similar efforts. He and other Stanford students decided to organize workshops on political and social issues; one was on how the federal government could do a better job of managing science and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, a group based in Washington, began offering a fellowship for scientists and engineers to advise members of Congress on policy. The program, which began in 1973, continues today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frank von Hippel, a theoretical physicist who wrote about science policy with Dr. Primack in the 1970s, said scientists in that era were increasingly “open to rethinking their relationship with their larger responsibility for science and society, saying when things were nonsense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Joel was part of that, a leader of that,” Dr. von Hippel said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joel Robert Primack, the eldest of three siblings, was born on July 14, 1945, in Santa Barbara, Calif., and grew up in Butte, Mont., and Granada Hills, Calif. His father, Roy, was a district manager for a chain of shoe stores, and his mother, Loretta (Zabarsky) Primack, oversaw the home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the American Institute of Physics interview, he described his parents as “not particularly intellectual,” but said that they had encouraged his interests in science. He graduated from Princeton with a bachelor’s degree in physics as valedictorian of the class of 1966, completed his doctorate at Stanford in 1970 and received a postdoctoral fellowship at Harvard before joining Santa Cruz as a professor in 1973.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He began his career studying particle physics — the tiniest bits of matter — but eventually grew bored of it and pivoted to astrophysics as new data offered the possibility of answering fundamental questions about the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With his wife, a philosopher, Dr. Primack taught a course at Santa Cruz called “Cosmology and Culture” and wrote a book, “The View From the Center of the Universe” (2006), which explored the place of humans in the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to his wife, whom he married in 1977, Dr. Primack is survived by a daughter, Samara Bay; and a grandson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He retired from teaching in 2014, taking emeritus status, but his cosmological research continued. In recent years, Dr. Primack worked on the structure of early galaxies and why they were in the shape of what he called “cosmic pickles” instead of spheres or discs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images from the Hubble Space Telescope, which was launched in 1990, first suggested that unexpected elongated shape, and dark matter again provided an explanation. Dark matter is distributed along filaments in weblike structures spanning the cosmos. Thus, clouds of gas were attracted along the filaments, producing the “pickle” shapes. (Other astrophysicists have described them as bananas, cigars or surfboards.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And as the gas rotates, the stars form primarily in the pickle,” Dr. Primack said in an interview in 2020. As he predicted, the James Webb Space Telescope, launched the next year, has seen these early galaxies in greater detail.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/science/joel-primack-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:42:56 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>