<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:30:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How We Photographed an ICE Confrontation in MinneapolisHow We Photographed an ICE Confrontation in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010643550/how-we-photographed-an-ice-confrontation-in-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/arts/minneapolis-protest-escalation_thumbnail/minneapolis-protest-escalation_thumbnail-facebookJumbo.png?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Our visual journalists David Guttenfelder and Todd Heisler describe a dramatic incident in which federal agents dragged a woman out of her car in Minneapolis near where Renee Nicole Good had been killed days before.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010643550/how-we-photographed-an-ice-confrontation-in-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 03:00:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ICE’s No. 2 Official Leaves to Run for the House in Ohio</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/pol-sheahan-zgbl/pol-sheahan-zgbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a moment when President Trump’s immigration crackdown has inflamed political tensions, one of the top enforcers of his effort to deport undocumented immigrants is leaving his administration to run for Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madison D. Sheahan, 28, the deputy director of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, announced on Thursday that she would enter the Republican primary race to oppose Representative Marcy Kaptur, a 22-term Democrat who represents a northwest Ohio district that Mr. Trump won in the last two presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her announcement video, Ms. Sheahan called herself “a Trump conservative” and focused on her work helping carry out the president’s deportation agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In less than one year at ICE, I’ve stopped more illegal immigration than Marcy Kaptur has in her 43 years in Washington,” Ms. Sheahan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How top of mind Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown remains for voters come November will be one of the biggest question of the midterm elections. Polling so far suggests that while Americans generally favor tighter immigration policies, they believe Mr. Trump is going too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CNN survey released Wednesday found that 51 percent of Americans said ICE enforcement actions were making cities less safe, compared with 31 percent who perceived an increase in safety. The fatal shooting of a Minneapolis woman by an ICE officer has touched off nationwide protests and renewed calls from some liberal Democrats to abolish the agency and impeach Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kaptur, 79, was first elected to represent the Toledo area in northwest Ohio in 1982, and she coasted to re-election every two years before Ohio Republicans redrew what had been a safe Democratic district into a competitive one before the 2022 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, she won by less than a percentage point against Derek Merrin, who at the time served in the Ohio legislature. On the same ballot, Mr. Trump carried the district by seven points against Vice President Kamala Harris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Merrin announced another challenge to Ms. Kaptur in June. Several other Republicans have entered the primary, including Josh Williams, a state representative from Toledo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before coming to Washington, Ms. Sheahan worked as a political aide to Ms. Noem when she was South Dakota’s governor and as secretary of the Louisiana Department of Wildlife and Fisheries. Ms. Noem praised Ms. Sheahan as a “terrific leader” in a statement to Fox News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats professed confidence that Ms. Kaptur would prevail, but they steered clear of addressing Ms. Sheahan’s immigration enforcement credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Voters are tired of the self-dealing corruption and culture of lawlessness they’ve seen over the last year,” said Kegan Zimmermann, Ms. Kaptur’s campaign manager. “They want a leader focused on affordability and real results, and Marcy Kaptur consistently works across the aisle to deliver both.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan’s departure from the agency comes as the Trump administration carries out an immigration enforcement blitz in Minnesota, which ICE has called its “largest operation to date.” Roughly 3,000 federal agents and officers are being deployed to the Minneapolis region as part of the effort, which administration officials have said is meant to crack down on illegal immigration and fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operation has led to clashes between protesters and law enforcement officers. Local officials in Minneapolis have urged immigration officers to leave the city, saying their efforts have sowed chaos. Trump administration officials have pledged that federal agents will remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan has repeatedly defended the agency’s enforcement operations, saying they are necessary to remove people in the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is taking the stand and making sure that we’re enforcing the law as it’s written with the support of Secretary Noem leading the way to make sure we get these dangerous criminals removed from our community,” Ms. Sheahan said in an interview with Fox News in September.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:47:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arkansas Rescinds Choice of Law School Dean Over Transgender Stance</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a week after naming a new dean, the University of Arkansas Law School withdrew the appointment, saying on Wednesday that the decision was based on “feedback from key external stakeholders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appointee, Emily Suski, a legal scholar at the University of South Carolina, had been selected after a lengthy public search, and the university’s provost, Indrajeet Chaubey, praised her work on medical partnerships to help low-income children when the choice was announced on Jan. 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback that derailed the appointment, members of the state legislature said, was related to her signature on an amicus brief filed with the Supreme Court last year in support of transgender student athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders of Arkansas supported the decision to withdraw the offer, according to her spokesman, Sam Dubke. “Governor Sanders appreciates the University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, for reaching the common sense decision on this matter in the best interest of students,” Mr. Dubke said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief that Ms. Suski signed was filed in a case that was argued this week before the Supreme Court. Dan Sullivan, an Arkansas state senator, said the views expressed in the brief were inconsistent with Arkansas law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you look at some of her opinions to the Supreme Court and amicus briefs, I think she has not reflected the laws of the state of Arkansas,” said Mr. Sullivan, a Republican from Jonesboro who applauded the decision to rescind the offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkansas was the first state to ban gender-affirming medical care for minors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode is an example of how politics has increasingly been influencing university decisions about faculty hiring, which were once the exclusive purview of academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of the nation’s highly charged political environment has been felt primarily in the selection of university presidents, including an episode last year at the University of Florida. The school’s board chose Santa Ono, a former president of the University of Michigan, who was criticized by conservatives for his past support of diversity initiatives. The board’s decision was overruled by a statewide board of political appointees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But political pressures are also influencing searches for deans and even professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, universities have begun to treat job searches, which were once fairly public, as carefully guarded secrets, in order to avoid putting prospective hires in awkward positions if they are rejected. At Arkansas, however, the search for a new law school dean was conducted publicly, with four top candidates making presentations in open meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Arkansas, which had issued a statement Wednesday saying that its offer to Ms. Suski had been withdrawn, said Thursday it had no additional statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski, currently an associate dean at the University of South Carolina, issued a written statement on Thursday saying she was “disappointed and hurt by the university’s decision to rescind my contract.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been informed that the decision was not in any way a reflection of my qualifications to serve as dean,” she wrote, “but rather the result of influence from external individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski’s résumé includes work as a staff attorney for the Legal Aid Justice Center in Charlottesville, Va. Her teaching and legal expertise have been focused on health, poverty and education law, including Title IX, a federal civil rights law that bans sex-based discrimination in education programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amicus brief that she signed along with 16 other legal scholars made a narrowly focused argument on the question of whether the sex assigned at birth should be the sole determining factor in decisions about which sports teams students can compete on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief argued that the case before the Supreme Court should be sent back to the lower courts for further review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Democratic state representative in Arkansas, Nicole Clowney, said in a telephone interview that the offer to Ms. Suski was rescinded after a few state legislators and one executive-branch official became aware that Ms. Suski had signed the brief, and then threatened the university’s funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Clowney, who represents Fayetteville and teaches at the law school, said she saw the decision as a free-speech issue, and added that Ms. Suski was eminently qualified for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker of the state House of Representatives, Brian Evans, a Republican, issued a statement saying his office was not involved in the decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski had been offered a five-year contract with total annual compensation of $350,000, according to documents reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its announcement Wednesday, the law school praised Ms. Suski, but said it had “decided to go in a different direction.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:37:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pentagon Will ‘Refocus’ Military Publication Stars and Stripes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/us/politics/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon on Thursday said it planned to commandeer Stars and Stripes, a government-funded newspaper that covers the military, and align it with official department messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will modernize its operations, refocus its content away from woke distractions that syphon morale, and adapt it to serve a new generation of service members,” Sean Parnell, the chief Pentagon spokesman, wrote in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It will focus on warfighting, weapons systems, fitness, lethality, survivability, and ALL THINGS MILITARY. No more repurposed DC gossip columns; no more Associated Press reprints.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon’s intervention would be a stark departure from historical precedent at the publication, which describes itself as the “U.S. military’s independent news source.” The organization has long prized its latitude to make editorial decisions free from external interference, including from the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stars and Stripes, often referred to as Stripes, has been published continuously since World War II, with daily papers for U.S. military troops overseas and up-to-the-minute news on stripes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement on its website describes its “core values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A news organization must not just cover the news but uncover it. It must follow the story wherever it leads, without allowing preconceived ideas to filter the search for facts or replace the discipline of verification.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon turned down a request to interview Mr. Parnell about the changes. In response to questions, a press official referred to Mr. Parnell’s statement on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Max D. Lederer Jr., the publisher of Stripes, said he knew nothing about the Pentagon’s directive for the publication until after Mr. Parnell’s announcement Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Stripes’ tradition of operating without any meddling from the military, editor in chief Erik Slavin said, “I wouldn’t have taken this job otherwise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Reid, a former editor in chief of Stripes, said, “You have to think small-town newspaper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The mayor may object to a story, but there was no prior censorship and no direction as to what should and should not be covered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reid, 78, who left the publication last year, said that Stripes saw fit to cover the panoply of controversies that have cropped up over the years in the U.S. military, including debates about the role of women, transgender people, and instances of racism and sexism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That might be what they described as woke,” said Mr. Reid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Daily Wire, a conservative outlet, reported that under the new plan, half of the material in Stripes will be generated by the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a directive “would definitely change the character and nature of what we’re presenting to the audience,” said Mr. Lederer. That said, the leadership of Stripes is working with little in the way of formal information about the future of its publication. In addition to receiving no advance notification about Thursday’s announcement, there are no meetings scheduled to discuss it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have the Daily Wire to go on right now — I’ll leave it at that,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the Pentagon’s hostility toward “repurposed DC gossip columns,” Mr. Lederer said, “We don’t carry any gossip columns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Controversy engulfed the publication in President Trump’s first term, when the Pentagon tried to cut its $15.5 million in funding. Mr. Trump came to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The United States of America will NOT be cutting funding to @starsandstripes magazine under my watch,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media. “It will continue to be a wonderful source of information to our Great Military!” Stripes draws its budget in part from federal funding and in part from other, traditional revenue streams for newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post on Wednesday reported that applicants for employment at Stripes faced questions about how they would support Mr. Trump’s policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, the Pentagon introduced a set of binding restrictions that apply to journalists who receive press credentials to report from the military complex. Dozens of journalists with major media outlets surrendered their press badges instead of signing the policy. Department officials subsequently heralded the arrival of a newly credentialed press corps, one populated by pro-Trump commentators and influencers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stripes didn’t have to agonize over whether to sign on to the restrictions because it is not an external media organization. However, it reviewed the restrictions and voluntarily pulled its reporter from the Pentagon hallways. “When we reviewed that, we saw problematic areas like most news organizations affiliated with the Pentagon at the time,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:00:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens to Invoke the Insurrection Act and Send Troops to Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-trump-minnesota-cjlf/15dc-trump-minnesota-cjlf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Donald J. Trump in the Oval Office on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:34:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>N.S.A. Nominee Promises to Protect Elections From Foreign Interference</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-nsa-cyber-command-nominee.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15trump-news-nsa-topart-zfvw/15trump-news-nsa-topart-zfvw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Lt. Gen. Francis L. Donovan, left, and Lt. Gen. Joshua M. Rudd testified in front of the Senate Armed Services Committee on Capitol Hill on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-nsa-cyber-command-nominee.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:35:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New York Sues Former C.E.O. of Covid Vaccine Maker Over Insider Trading</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/emergent-biosolutions-ceo-insider-trading-covid-vaccine.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-emergent-Kramer-vqtk/15xp-emergent-Kramer-vqtk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Robert G. Kramer, former chief of Emergent BioSolutions, appearing before a House subcommittee by video in 2021.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/emergent-biosolutions-ceo-insider-trading-covid-vaccine.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:39:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Proposes Restricting Deportation of Student Activists</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-protester-deportations-trump-khalil.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-speech-hmqt/15dc-speech-hmqt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mahmoud Khalil speaking in Manhattan last August. Earlier on Thursday, a federal appeals court ruled that he was improperly ordered released by a Federal District Court judge last year. Academic groups have raised alarms over the government’s efforts to deport him.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-protester-deportations-trump-khalil.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:18:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Was Renee Good Obligated to Comply With an ICE Agent’s Orders?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/renee-good-ice-agent-comply-legal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-ice-agent-justification-bmjp/15minneapolis-shooting-ice-agent-justification-bmjp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial for Renee Good. She was shot after beginning to drive away from an ICE agent who told her to get out of her car.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/renee-good-ice-agent-comply-legal.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:35:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Did the White House and Denmark Agree to on Greenland? It Depends Whom You Ask.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/white-house-greenland-meeting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-greenland-kqlv/15dc-greenland-kqlv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A Danish military vessel sailing near the old harbor of Nuuk, Greenland’s capital, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/white-house-greenland-meeting.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 00:05:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Couple Says ICE Agents Gassed Them as They Drove With 6 Children</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-couple-ice-tear-gas-6-children.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-father-teargas-khgl/15minneapolis-shooting-father-teargas-khgl-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal agents, like these outside a federal building on Thursday, have frequently used tear gas on Minneapolis streets.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-couple-ice-tear-gas-6-children.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:14:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>California’s Pacific Coast Highway Fully Reopens After Three Years</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/pacific-coast-highway-reopened.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/06/17/multimedia/15xp-highway-promo-copy/15xp-highway-promo-copy-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The famed highway reopened this week after consecutive landslides shuttered two sections of the road in Big Sur and forced major repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/pacific-coast-highway-reopened.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:10:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Senator Kyrsten Sinema Accused of Affair With Member of Security Team</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/kyrsten-sinema-affair-lawsuit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-sinema-bcpm/15dc-sinema-bcpm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Former Senator Kyrsten Sinema at the Capitol last month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/kyrsten-sinema-affair-lawsuit.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:12:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Lawsuit Seeking California Voter Data Is Dismissed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/california-voter-roll-lawsuit-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-california-hfqj/15xp-california-hfqj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Voting in Los Angeles last year. A federal judge dismissed a lawsuit on Thursday that the Justice Department had filed against California last year demanding access to voter data.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/california-voter-roll-lawsuit-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:17:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Says It Erred in Deporting Student Traveling for Thanksgiving</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-deportation-student-traveling-thanksgiving.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/08/multimedia/15trump-news-student-deported/15trump-news-student-deported-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Any Lucía López Belloza’s high school graduation in Texas. She was detained and later deported in late November while trying to surprise her family with a visit.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-deportation-student-traveling-thanksgiving.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 04:10:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emergency Call Transcripts Record a Crisis Unfolding in Real Time</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/911-calls-minneapolis-ice-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-records-pvtj/15minneapolis-shooting-records-pvtj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
After the shooting, a caller pleaded: “Send an ambulance please. Ambulance, please.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/911-calls-minneapolis-ice-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:13:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Happened to London Breed, the Former San Francisco Mayor?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/london-breed-san-francisco-mayor-job.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/00nat-sf-breed-pjvz/00nat-sf-breed-pjvz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
London Breed, the former mayor of San Francisco, is still adjusting to life beyond City Hall a year after she left office.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/london-breed-san-francisco-mayor-job.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:00:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Renee Good Was Concerned About ICE, a Lawyer Says, but Wasn’t Following Agents</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/renee-good-minneapolis-ice-lawyer-interview.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15nat-good-lawyer-topper-wjpf/15nat-good-lawyer-topper-wjpf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial for Renee Good near where she was fatally shot in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/renee-good-minneapolis-ice-lawyer-interview.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:04:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virginia Poised to Redraw House Maps That Could Set Democrats Up for a Win</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/virginia-house-democrats-congressional-maps.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16nat-va-redistricting-wgvm/16nat-va-redistricting-wgvm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Virginia State Capitol in Richmond, Va.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/virginia-house-democrats-congressional-maps.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 01:05:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Store to Close as Sales Falter, With No Election Battles Ahead</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-store-closing-philadelphia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15trump-news-trump-store-01-vjkp/15trump-news-trump-store-01-vjkp-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mike Domanico, the owner of a store that sells Trump merchandise in Bensalem, Pa., said it was time to close its doors.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-store-closing-philadelphia.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 02:30:05 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>