<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:43:23 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Once Again, Federal Officials Exclude Minnesota From Investigation of a Fatal Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the second time in three weeks, local and state authorities in Minnesota say they have been impeded from investigating how federal agents shot and killed someone, cutting off access to crucial evidence and basic facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, Minnesota officials said they sought to have their Bureau of Criminal Apprehension, which typically takes the lead in police shootings, work in partnership with the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the Department of Homeland Security has blocked local investigators from reviewing evidence gathered following the fatal shootings of Renee Good and Alex Jeffrey Pretti, both Minneapolis residents and U.S. citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal authorities shut down an early effort to collaboratively investigate the agent who killed Ms. Good and said that they would handle any investigation into the killing of Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re in uncharted territory here,” said Drew Evans, the superintendent of the B.C.A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, in the chaotic hours after federal agents killed Mr. Pretti, state officials resorted to a pair of highly unconventional moves in a bid to gain access to the scene and evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They obtained a judicial search warrant granting them access to the sidewalk where Mr. Pretti, 37, was shot multiple times after a confrontation with Border Patrol agents. And they sought and received an emergency court order from a federal judge who barred federal officials from destroying evidence from the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late Saturday, a federal judge in Minnesota issued a temporary restraining order barring federal officials “from destroying or altering evidence related to the fatal shooting involving federal officers” earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, a day after the shooting, local officials remained shut out of the investigation — lacking facts as basic as the identity of the federal agents who shot Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standoff over the investigations into both killings — which were each documented in videos shot from multiple angles — was a break from the typical cooperation seen between state and federal authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What you have now is a sense that immigration agents are able to operate with impunity because there is no accountability and no prospect of accountability for these horrific acts,” said Vanita Gupta, who served as associate attorney general in the Biden administration. “That is an incredibly dangerous place for this country to be in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Mr. Pretti on Saturday morning happened amid escalating tensions over the federal government’s deployment of thousands of immigration agents to Minnesota, which began late last year. The Trump administration has called the operation — which has been met with strong local resistance — a necessary intervention to round up criminals who are in the country illegally. It has also cited concerns about fraud in safety net programs in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far this month, federal agents involved in the immigration operation, called Metro Surge, have shot three people, including Ms. Good, a 37-year-old mother of three who was killed in her S.U.V. on Jan. 7 as she appeared to be steering away from federal agents during a tense confrontation. A federal agent also shot, but did not kill, a Venezuelan man on Jan. 14.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fatal shootings by federal agents in the line of duty are rare. As investigators review evidence, they seek to answer a basic question: whether an agent had a “reasonable belief” that the person who was shot posed “an imminent danger of death or serious physical injury to the agent or another person.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials from the Department of Justice’s Office of Civil Rights and experts at the F.B.I. generally play a leading role in making that determination, which dictates whether a prosecution is warranted. Separately, federal law enforcement agencies typically conduct an administrative review to establish whether an agent followed their training and protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joint investigations involving federal and state agencies often involve a degree of tension, said J. Thomas Manger, the former chief of the United States Capitol Police, who previously led two large police departments in suburban Washington, D.C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But it would always be a very cooperative effort where people communicate,” said Mr. Manger, who has been involved in many use-of-force investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Good was killed, as protesters took to the streets, top officials at the U.S. attorney’s office in Minneapolis set out to launch an investigation into the shooting in partnership with the Minnesota Bureau of Criminal Apprehension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph H. Thompson, a career federal prosecutor who was running the office the day Ms. Good was killed, called on the Department of Homeland Security to halt immigration enforcement operations while the F.B.I. and state investigators began gathering evidence, according to an email he sent to colleagues that morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, shortly after Mr. Thompson set out to launch a conventional review of Ms. Good’s killing, senior officials in the Trump administration overruled him on two fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They sent immigration agents back into the streets of Minneapolis that same day and they barred the B.C.A. from the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior Trump administration officials were quick to claim that the agent who shot Ms. Good, Jonathan Ross, acted properly. They also labeled Ms. Good — who along with her partner, Becca, had been among the hundreds of Minneapolis residents who have protested immigration raids — a domestic terrorist. A similar refrain was put forward by federal officials on Saturday with regard to Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days after the shooting of Ms. Good, the Justice Department pushed for a criminal investigation into her partner, Becca, focusing on links to groups of civilians that have documented and challenged the work of immigration agents. Mr. Thompson and five fellow career prosecutors resigned in protest on Jan. 13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracee Mergen, a supervisor at the F.B.I. field office in Minneapolis who had sought to investigate the shooting, also resigned after supervisors opted not to investigate the case as a civil rights matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, said in a statement that an investigation into the killing of Mr. Pretti was underway. But he and other senior administration officials have provided virtually no details about what that review would entail and they have sought to cast blame on civilians and local Democratic leaders who have been protesting the immigration operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Department of Justice will continue to hold those breaking federal law accountable, including those who harass and violently attack law enforcement in the name of protest,” Mr. Blanche said in a statement on social media that was paired with one in which President Trump implied, without evidence, that Mr. Pretti posed a threat to agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota called the ongoing immigration crackdown a “campaign of organized brutality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Minnesota’s justice system will have the last word,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department has launched a criminal investigation into the manner in which Mr. Walz, Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis and other local officials have pushed back on immigration operations in their state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among those the Justice Department is investigating are Attorney General Keith Ellison of Minnesota and Mary Moriarty, the elected prosecutor in Hennepin County, which includes Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Mr. Ellison and Ms. Moriarty are resorting to highly unusual means to investigate whether the killings of Ms. Good and Mr. Pretti warrant filing criminal charges against the federal agents involved. Ms. Moriarty’s office has established online portals where people can submit videos and other forms of evidence related to both killings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Federal agents are not above the law, and Alex Pretti is certainly not beneath it,” Mr. Ellison said. “A full, impartial and transparent investigation into his fatal shooting at the hands of D.H.S. agents is nonnegotiable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the name of the agent who killed Ms. Good quickly came to light, it has still not been released by federal authorities. State officials said they have not learned the identities of the agents who shot Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond their lack of such basic facts and evidence that is normally analyzed in use-of-force cases, local prosecutors face formidable procedural challenges. Even if a federal agent were to be charged in one of the shootings, the supremacy clause of the U.S. Constitution gives federal officials the ability to move the case to federal court.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 19:46:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How the Trump Administration Rushed to Judgment in Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting-response.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-response-ltpb/25dc-response-ltpb-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow live updates on the aftermath of the Minneapolis shooting and the political fallout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after federal agents shot and killed a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident on Saturday, senior members of the Trump administration were ready with their conclusions about what had happened and who was to blame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Miller, President Trump’s homeland security adviser, called the victim, Alex Pretti, who was filming Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis, a “domestic terrorist.” Gregory Bovino, the official in charge of Border Patrol operations, said Mr. Pretti was out to “massacre law enforcement.” The Department of Homeland Security said an agent had fired “defensive shots” because he was “fearing for his life and the lives and safety of fellow officers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as videos emerged that contradicted the government’s account, the Trump administration was in a race to control the narrative around the killing of Mr. Pretti, a registered nurse with no criminal record who was pinned down when immigration agents opened fire and killed him. The rush to blame Mr. Pretti and exonerate the immigration agents — even while officials were still gathering the facts — deviates entirely from the way law enforcement investigations are normally carried out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it also underscores what has become a pattern by Mr. Trump and top administration officials to justify an increasingly violent crackdown: immediately going on the offensive and demonizing the victim, often distorting the facts in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Mr. Trump said Democrats were to blame for the killings, not federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His reasoning, which he laid out on social media, was that Democrats were not cooperating with the ICE operation in Minneapolis, which has created “dangerous circumstances for EVERYONE involved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Altman, a former Customs and Border Protection official who served in the Trump and Biden administrations, said presidents often tried to find political advantage in moments of crisis. But he said it undermined public confidence in the investigation process to make snap judgments about motive and blame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Altman, who oversaw internal investigations into use of force, said there were well-established procedures for such cases, including timelines for notifying Congress and the public. “Those measures are designed to promote transparency and accountability,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after Mr. Pretti was shot, officials at D.H.S. and the White House were in contact about how to respond to the incident, according to a person familiar with the communications who asked for anonymity to describe internal procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The officials sought information from the ground in Minneapolis and worked with lawyers to prepare the statement issued by D.H.S. Some details were removed before the statement was published because they were still working to get a more complete picture of what happened, the person familiar with the process said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the statement claimed that Mr. Pretti “approached” officers with handgun and the “armed suspect violently resisted” when officials tried to disarm him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos of the encounter show Mr. Pretti, who had a permit to carry a firearm, stepping between a woman and an agent who was pepper spraying her. Mr. Pretti is then hit with pepper spray before a group of agents pile on to him, restraining and disarming him before the barrage of gunfire. Videos show that he never drew his weapon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, labeled Mr. Pretti a “domestic terrorist,” saying that was just “the facts” of the case and claiming to know his motive: “to inflict maximum damage on individuals and to kill law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same day D.H.S. issued its statement, Mr. Miller and Mr. Bovino, the key architects of Mr. Trump’s aggressive immigration crackdown, showed little restraint. Their social media posts are not subject to review, and their public comments are rarely carefully worded. In November, a federal judge found that Mr. Bovino had lied multiple times about federal agents’ use of force during immigration enforcement operations in Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The killing of Mr. Pretti — and the administration’s handling of the case — has drawn criticism from across the political spectrum. Democrats assailed the Trump administration and quickly signaled that they would oppose legislation to fund large parts of the government because it included $10 billion for ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major gun rights activists and groups, typically allies of Mr. Trump’s, also denounced his administration for suggesting that Mr. Pretti’s killing might have been justified because he was carrying a pistol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bill Essayli, a federal prosecutor in Los Angeles, wrote on social media, “If you approach law enforcement with a gun, there is a high likelihood they will be legally justified in shooting you.” Gun Owners of America, one of the country’s largest gun advocacy groups, said in a post on social media that it condemned Mr. Essayli’s “untoward comments.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Republicans in Congress also raised concerns about the shooting, a reflection of fears within the party of how backlash to the administration’s aggressive tactics could damage their political prospects in the midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The credibility of ICE and D.H.S. are at stake,” said Senator Bill Cassidy, Republican of Louisiana, who also called for a “full joint federal and state investigation” into Mr. Pretti’s death. “We can trust the American people with the truth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A poll from The New York Times and Siena University, conducted after the killing of Renee Good, the 37-year-old woman who was shot in Minneapolis by an ICE officer this month, found that roughly half of voters supported Mr. Trump’s deportations and his handling of the border with Mexico, but a sizable majority believed that ICE had gone too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just 36 percent of voters said they approved of the way ICE was handling its job, according to the poll, while 63 percent disapproved — including 70 percent of independent voters. And 61 percent of voters said ICE had “gone too far” in their tactics, including nearly one in five Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday morning, even some senior Trump administration officials appeared to try to tone down some of the language. Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, dodged questions on NBC’s “Meet the Press” about whether Mr. Pretti was “brandishing a gun,” as Ms. Noem had said on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do not know, and nobody else knows, either,” Mr. Blanche said. “That’s why we’re doing an investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Bovino gave little ground in an interview on CNN, arguing that the border patrol agents were the “victims” and that Mr. Pretti had “injected himself into that law enforcement situation with a weapon.” Still, when pressed for evidence, Mr. Bovino had little to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The facts are going to come to light as to what exactly happened with an investigation,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Berzon contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting-response.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:59:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Killing Prompts Only a Defiant Response From Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/minneapolis-killing-trump-defiant-response.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-trump-gkzp/25dc-trump-gkzp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hours after a man was brought to his knees and fatally shot by Border Patrol officers in Minneapolis on Saturday, President Trump was in the Oval Office, where an aide, Natalie Harp, sat close by with a laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with input from aides who called throughout the day by phone, the two pumped out several presidential social media posts that blamed local law enforcement officials and the victim for the killing and accused Minnesota officials of covering up an unrelated fraud scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also spoke with Stephen Miller, his deputy chief of staff, who called the victim — Alex Pretti, a U.S. citizen and I.C.U. nurse who had been using his cellphone to record immigration agents on the street and was carrying a licensed handgun — a “would-be assassin.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, Mr. Trump posted a photo of an agent whose hand was bleeding after a different encounter, and a photo of a fingertip in a jar. The president wrote no additional commentary, but a few hours later, Attorney General Pam Bondi, who also spoke with Mr. Trump throughout the day, wrote that federal prosecutors would charge a suspect in the finger biting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When that work was done, Mr. Trump went over to the residence to attend a screening of a documentary that the first lady has produced about herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The killing of Mr. Pretti, the second fatal shooting of a protester in Minneapolis by federal agents this month, came amid an increasingly militarized deportation campaign directed by Mr. Trump and his aides, and after years in which the president has excused violence by his allies, characterized opponents as traitors and terrorists and threatened to invoke the Insurrection Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If, as many Democrats say, the death was a consequence of Mr. Trump’s embrace of extreme measures to reverse the tide of immigration, the nature of his response was also in keeping with a pattern of reflexively attacking his critics and insulating himself from dissenting voices. Even as some Republicans voiced concern about the conduct of the federal agents and as Democrats demanded accountability, his instinct was not just to evade responsibility but also to assign blame to his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with The Wall Street Journal on Sunday, Mr. Trump seemed to show some willingness for an investigation, if only after he and his aides had already made clear their view of who was at fault. “We’re looking, we’re reviewing everything and will come out with a determination,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the White House has repeatedly asserted that the problem is not that federal agents are killing protesters. It is that liberals, encouraged and backed by elected Democrats in Minnesota, are seeking to impede a deportation push that in the name of targeting criminals has swept up children, citizens, longtime neighbors and refugees who are in the United States legally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Mr. Trump posted that the blame rested with “Democrat run Sanctuary Cities and States” that he said “are REFUSING to cooperate with ICE, and they are actually encouraging Leftwing agitators to unlawfully obstruct their operations to arrest the Worst of the Worst People.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In doing so, Mr. Trump said, “Democrats are putting Illegal Alien Criminals over Taxpaying, Law-Abiding Citizens and they have created dangerous circumstances for EVERYONE involved. Tragically, two American citizens have lost their lives as a result of this Democrat ensued chaos.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Trump’s first term, there were one or two voices in the mix who sometimes curbed his instincts to punch back or crack down on any opposition to his political agenda. In his second term, though, Mr. Trump has built around himself a wall of advisers who reinforce and celebrate his instincts to demonize opponents and escalate a conflict rather than prevent one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at a moment when the scene in Minneapolis is a result of the hard-line policies and pugilistic politics that brought him twice to the White House, Mr. Trump is only encouraged to double down and blame others for not making it easier for thousands of masked agents to enact a military-style occupation of an American city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has long dismissed protests against his administration as the work of professional and paid agitators. After the killing of George Floyd by police officers in Minneapolis in 2020, Mr. Trump addressed the nation and said that the voices of “peaceful protesters” had been drowned out by “professional anarchists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly six years later and faced with growing protests and outrage over the violent outcome of his policies, Mr. Trump and his advisers are describing protesters as domestic terrorists who have impeded efforts of federal agents to arrest immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have also suggested, as they have during other moments of unrest, that protesters have been funded or organized by movements like antifa. In September, Mr. Trump signed an executive order declaring antifa a “domestic terrorist organization” — a designation that does not exist under U.S. law. Anti-fascism is a broad political ideology rather than a specific organization, and the United States does not have a domestic terrorism law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have targeted Minneapolis protesters using laws that do exist on the books, including one that bars using or threatening force and physical obstruction to interfere or intimidate someone worshiping at a religious institution. Last week, three people were arrested for interrupting a church service to protest a pastor’s apparent work as an Immigration and Customs Enforcement official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump has not ruled out the idea that lawful behavior can warrant punishment. When Renee Good, a 37-year-old mother, was shot three times at close range by federal agents as she drove away in her S.U.V., the president suggested that being “very disrespectful to law enforcement” had contributed, in part, to her death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confronted with reports of violence and killing, Mr. Trump has not allowed for the possibility that the operation in Minneapolis had gone too far. Instead, he suggested that ICE agents would continue to do their work with his complete support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re going to make mistakes sometimes,” Mr. Trump said last week. “ICE is going to be too rough with somebody or, you know — they deal with rough people. Are they going to make a mistake? Sometimes it can happen. We feel terribly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four days later, Mr. Pretti was shot dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the killings in Minnesota, Mr. Trump was being challenged about whether he is living in a bubble and out of touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With midterm elections coming this year, Mr. Trump and his fellow Republicans are under political pressure from American voters who are signaling that they are not better off than they were before he was elected to another term and do not see the same progress he trumpets in bringing down inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the White House can be a lavish, glossy bubble. On Saturday evening, the East Room documentary event was attended by Queen Rania of Jordan; the boxer Mike Tyson; the self-help author Tony Robbins; Erika Kirk, the chief executive of Turning Point USA; and Andy Jassy, the chief executive of Amazon, the movie’s distributor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The evening was defined by extraordinary warmth, grace and a palpable sense of love,” said Marc Beckman, an adviser to Melania Trump who called the event “an atmosphere as moving as it was unforgettable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on Sunday, before posting his attack on Democrats, which included a call for Democratic leaders in Minnesota to turn over to federal authorities any immigrants who are in the country illegally and are in prison, Mr. Trump took to his social media account to attack a lawsuit filed by a preservation group that has opposed the changes he has made to the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m building, on top of everything else that I am doing, one of the greatest and most beautiful Ballrooms anywhere in the World,” the president said in a 450-word post. “The so-called ‘preservationists,’ who get their money from the most unusual of places, should not be allowed to stop this desperately needed addition to our GREAT White House,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/minneapolis-killing-trump-defiant-response.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:18:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alex Pretti’s Friends and Family Denounce ‘Sickening Lies’ About His Life</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-01-hmvf/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-01-hmvf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was a calm presence amid hospital chaos. A mentor who taught kindness and patience to younger friends and colleagues. A singer with a knack for dancing. A bicyclist who treasured the beauty of Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weekend, the family, co-workers and friends of Alex Pretti, who was killed by immigration agents in a confrontation after he was apparently filming them, remembered his life, even as the circumstances of his death were debated on the national stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They shared photos of the Alex they knew: a smiling, bearded Mr. Pretti in the powder-blue scrubs he wore at his job as an intensive-care nurse at the Veterans Affairs hospital, an outdoors lover posing with his mountain bike on a wooded trail and a student wearing a green cap and gown as he sang a solo at his high school graduation in Green Bay, Wis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they denounced what they saw as smear campaigns in the aftermath of Mr. Pretti’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within hours of the killing by federal agents on a Minneapolis street, Trump administration officials labeled Mr. Pretti a “would-be assassin” and asserted, with no evidence, that he had committed an act of “domestic terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through their own shock and grief, people who knew him struggled to rise above the lies and insults, they said, to describe who he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rory Shefchek, a friend from high school who now lives in Madison, Wis., said that he hoped that Mr. Pretti would be remembered as the person he knew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a helpful, kind guy,” Mr. Shefchek said. “He was a confident, diligent and respectful person throughout his life. I hope that Alex’s story can catalyze change, as someone who believed in doing the right thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the cellphone footage of Mr. Pretti’s death that has circulated widely in the news and on social media, Mr. Shefchek said, “We have all seen the video and our eyes don’t lie.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dimitri Drekonja, a colleague of Mr. Pretti’s at the VA hospital, was shaken when he heard that an immigration agent had killed a civilian in Minneapolis. It was awful, he said, even before he learned that the civilian was his friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a happy guy,” Dr. Drekonja said. “When you asked him to do something, it would be done and it would be done right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, who was 37, was on the front lines of the Covid-19 pandemic, and was always eager to help whoever needed an extra hand. He was the kind of nurse patients remembered, colleagues said, and he was a beloved mentor to nurses stepping into the intimidating environment of the intensive care unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an ICU nurse, he was accustomed to people in crisis, said Elissa Todd, a colleague and friend. He was also trained in de-escalation, she noted. Ms. Todd said it was painful to see his last moments knowing personally how calmly Mr. Pretti was able to manage the chaos and stress that came with his job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whatever conversation was being had, I cannot imagine he’s someone who would have made it worse,” she said, referring to his interaction with immigration agents in the minutes before he died. “He would have been someone who was being reasonable and thinking clearly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She paused, before saying “I can’t imagine what their last dialogue was, but I will say that he’s uniquely qualified to handle it with integrity and grace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota said on Sunday that he had spoken with Mr. Pretti’s parents, who live in Colorado. Mr. Walz said he was trying to channel their desire to tell the world who Mr. Pretti really was, a person who lived “a life of generosity” according to his family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Someone who went to work to care for veterans, someone who was a valued co-worker, someone who relished and lived in this state in a big way, whether it was outdoor activities or being down there on the street as a First Amendment witness to what ICE is doing to this state,” Mr. Walz said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we cannot all agree that the smearing of an American citizen and besmirching everything they stood for and asking us not to believe what we saw,” he added, “I don’t know what else to tell you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti’s family said in a statement on Saturday that they were heartbroken, but also “very angry.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti’s parents, Susan and Michael Pretti, in a statement reported by The Associated Press and CNN, called their son “a kindhearted soul who cared deeply for his family and friends and also the American veterans whom he cared for as an ICU nurse at the Minneapolis VA hospital.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Alex wanted to make a difference in this world,” the statement said. “Unfortunately he will not be with us to see his impact.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family denounced the Trump administration’s response to the shooting, which included the accusation that Mr. Pretti had confronted immigration agents with the intent “to perpetuate violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal officials have noted that Mr. Pretti had a gun with him during the confrontation, though he was licensed to carry the firearm and had not drawn the weapon. Videos show that Mr. Pretti was holding a phone, rather than his gun. An agent had disarmed Mr. Pretti just before he was shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues knew he was a gun owner, although he didn’t speak of it often, except in occasional conversations about gun reform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The sickening lies told about our son by the administration are reprehensible and disgusting,” the Pretti family statement said. “Please get the truth out about our son. He was a good man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Mr. Pretti’s apartment building on Saturday evening, neighbors on his block came together for a small gathering, lighting candles in the brutally cold Minnesota air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As word of Mr. Pretti’s death spread among friends in Wisconsin, where he grew up, they swapped memories from decades ago — of Mr. Pretti dancing in the show choir in a tuxedo and performing in a production of “Guys and Dolls.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JD Atkins, 36, remembers when he got his first big role in a play and Mr. Pretti calmed his nerves and offered to run lines together. It was not uncommon for younger students to see Mr. Pretti as a role model, he said, and Mr. Atkins credited him for influencing his career as a high school theater director and playwright near Milwaukee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We just really wanted to be like him, because he was cool without trying,” Mr. Atkins said. “And as an adult I realize, it’s because he was kind to everybody.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another classmate, Kevin McGillivray, recalled that Mr. Pretti seemed to exude a sense of justice even when it came to petty school interactions. Upperclassmen tended to pick on younger students, but Mr. Pretti never joined his peers. Mr. McGillivray said he and others looked up to Mr. Pretti as an older brother figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He would step up and say something to them and encourage them to reconsider what they’re doing,” Mr. McGillivray, 35, said. “The feeling that I have when I remember him is just a deep sense of safety and confidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Heather Zielinski saw the video of a federal agent shooting a man on Saturday, she knew she recognized the person. It took her a minute to realize it was her friend of more than 10 years, Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I saw him get wrestled down to the ground, and I saw his feet just go limp, and my heart sank into my stomach,” she said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Zielinski doesn’t think he would want to be known as a martyr. She thinks he would like to be remembered as a guy who enjoyed riding his bike, as someone who loved his family and as a person who cared about health care, science and research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She described him as strait-laced, someone who got good grades in school and cared deeply about his job. He loved being outdoors, she said, and took a mountain biking trip to Utah and Colorado over the summer before competing in a cycling relay race in Milwaukee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a really good friend, and a really good man,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Healy contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:03:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Private Jet With 8 People Aboard Crashes at Maine Airport, F.A.A. Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bangor-maine-airport-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25xp-crash-2/25xp-crash-2-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency crews were responding to the crash of a private jet, with eight people on board, on Sunday evening at Bangor International Airport in Maine, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Aviation Administration said in a statement that the plane, a Bombardier Challenger 600, crashed as it was taking off from the airport at around 7:45 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unclear whether there were any fatalities or injuries among the eight people that the F.A.A. reported were on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. and the National Transportation Safety Board will investigate, the F.A.A. said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airport remained closed on Sunday as emergency crews responded to the crash, Aimee Thibodeau, a spokeswoman for Bangor International Airport, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement did not provide details about the crash, but residents were advised to stay away from the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are unable to provide any additional information at this time,” Ms. Thibodeau said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major winter storm was pummeling the eastern United States on Sunday, forcing the cancellation of thousands of flights nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a developing story.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bangor-maine-airport-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:53:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Storm Dumps a Foot of Snow in About a Third of U.S. States</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/snow-totals.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-snow-totals-vqgt/25winter-storm-snow-totals-vqgt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend’s gigantic snowstorm dumped a foot or more of snow in at least 17 states from New Mexico to New Hampshire, according to preliminary figures from the National Weather Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonito Lake, N.M., received 31 inches, the most in the United States this weekend, the agency said. East of the Mississippi, the highest totals were recorded in western Pennsylvania, where 20 inches had fallen near Clintonville, about 60 miles north of Pittsburgh, as of 8:30 p.m. Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figures are a mix of unofficial and official measurements and are subject to verification, the Weather Service said. As of Sunday night, these were the highest totals in the other 15 states that received at least a foot of snow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crested Butte, Colo.: 23 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New City, N.Y.: 17.6 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastford, Conn.: 18 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Branchville, N.J.: 17 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zanesville, Ohio: 16.9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis, W.Va.: 16.6 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cranston, R.I.: 16.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newton, N.H.: 16 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holland, Mass.: 16 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbus, Ind.: 14.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredericktown, Mo.: 14.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oblong, Ill.: 14.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plaistow, N.H.: 14 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sayre, Okla.: 14 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witts Springs, Ark.: 12 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine other states and the District of Columbia did not quite reach a foot of snow but received substantial amounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cedar Grove, Va.: 11.8 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarksburg, Md.: 11.8 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarendon, Texas: 10.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hebron, Ky.: 10.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyersburg, Tenn.: 10 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bouplon Corner, Vt.: 10 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olsburg, Kan.: 9.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auburn, Maine: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilmington, Del.: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington, D.C.: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/snow-totals.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:40:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ice Storm Leaves Thousands Without Power in a Mississippi County</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-storm-mississippi-oxford.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-mississippi-jbth/25winter-storm-mississippi-jbth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freezing rain from a severe winter storm led to tens of thousands of power outages in a Mississippi county over the weekend, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 20,000 out of about 35,000 homes in Lafayette County had no power on Sunday night as a result of an ice storm and high winds, said Beau Moore, an emergency management officer there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area around Oxford, Miss., was especially hard hit. The National Weather Service received reports of nearly an inch of accumulated ice after freezing rain hit that area late Saturday, said Phil Baker, a meteorologist in the agency’s Memphis office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Robyn Tannehill of Oxford said in an update posted to social media said that trees had fallen under the weight of ice and that power lines were down across the city of 26,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Things went downhill quickly,” Mr. Baker said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperatures were expected to drop to 7 degrees Fahrenheit overnight, he added, and the main concern was the safety of people dealing with the cold without power. Officials opened warming centers to accommodate as many residents without heat as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheriff Joey East of Lafayette County said in a text message on Sunday night that conditions were “probably worse or as bad” as they were after a 1994 storm that left some in the region without power for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tate Reeves of Mississippi said at a news conference that approximately 47 counties in the state had been impacted by the storm. State officials had requested generators and other supplies from the Federal Emergency Management Agency under a federal emergency declaration for the state signed by President Trump, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The weather is probably going to get worse before it gets better,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 150,000 electricity customers across Mississippi had no power as of early Monday morning, according to the site poweroutage.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Mississippi, which is in Oxford, will be closed on Monday and Tuesday, and local public school districts will be closed all week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Moore said that Lafayette County expected to see more downed trees, and that this could take down additional power lines. The county has hired private companies to help clear the roads, but he estimated that power outages would continue for at least another 48 hours. It could be another week before the county’s main roads are safe enough for travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Blinder contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-storm-mississippi-oxford.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 23:23:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Bad Are A.I. Delusions? We Asked People Treating Them.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julia Sheffield, a psychologist who specializes in treating people with delusions, is difficult to rattle. But she was unnerved last summer when patients began telling her about their conversations with A.I. chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One woman, who had no history of mental illness, asked ChatGPT for advice on a major purchase she had been fretting about. After days of the bot validating her worries, she became convinced that businesses were colluding to have her investigated by the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another patient came to believe that a romantic crush was sending her secret spiritual messages. Yet another thought he had stumbled onto a world-changing invention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the year, Dr. Sheffield had seen seven such patients at Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville. Although she is accustomed to treating people with mental instability, Dr. Sheffield was disturbed that this new technology seemed to tip people from simply having eccentric thoughts into full-on delusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like the A.I. was partnering with them in expanding or reinforcing their unusual beliefs,” Dr. Sheffield said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental health workers across the country are navigating how to treat problems caused or exacerbated by A.I. chatbots, according to more than 100 therapists and psychiatrists who told The New York Times about their experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many mentioned positive effects of the bots — like helping patients understand their diagnoses — they also said the conversations deepened their patients’ feelings of isolation or anxiety. More than 30 described cases resulting in dangerous emergencies like psychosis or suicidal thoughts. One California psychiatrist who often evaluates people in the legal system said she had seen two cases of violent crimes influenced by A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times reporters have documented more than 50 cases of psychological crises linked to chatbot conversations since last year. OpenAI, the maker of ChatGPT, is facing at least 11 personal injury or wrongful death lawsuits claiming that the chatbot caused psychological harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies behind the bots say these situations are exceedingly rare. “For a very small percentage of users in mentally fragile states there can be serious problems,” Sam Altman, the chief executive of OpenAI, said in October. The company has estimated that 0.15 percent of ChatGPT users discussed suicidal intentions over the course of a month, and 0.07 percent showed signs of psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a product with 800 million users, that translates to 1.2 million people with possible suicidal intent and 560,000 with potential psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Times has sued OpenAI, accusing it of violating copyright laws when training its models. The company has contested the lawsuit.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts said that the number of people susceptible to psychological harm, even psychosis, is far higher than the general public understands. The bots, they said, frequently pull people away from human relationships, condition them to expect agreeable responses and reinforce harmful impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A.I. could really, on a mass scale, change how many people are impacted,” said Haley Wang, a graduate student at U.C.L.A. who assesses people showing symptoms of psychosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychosis, which causes a break from reality, is most associated with schizophrenia. But as many as 3 percent of people will develop a diagnosable psychotic disorder in their lifetime, and far more are prone to delusional thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Joseph Pierre, a psychiatrist in San Francisco, said he had seen about five patients with delusional experiences involving A.I. While most had a diagnosis related to psychosis, he said, “sometimes these are very highly functioning people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For him, the idea that all chatbot-fueled delusions were going to happen anyway “just doesn’t hold water.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recently wrote in a scientific journal about a medical professional who began conversing with ChatGPT during a sleepless night. She took medication for ADHD and had a history of depression. After two nights of asking the chatbot questions about her dead brother, she became convinced that he had been communicating with her through a trail of digital footprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pierre and other experts said that a wide range of factors can combine to tip people into psychosis. These include not only genetic predisposition but also depression, lack of sleep, a history of trauma, and exposure to stimulants or cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m quite convinced that this is a real thing and that we are only seeing the tip of the iceberg,” said Dr. Soren Dinesen Ostergaard, a psychiatry researcher at Aarhus University Hospital in Denmark. In November, he published a report finding 11 cases of chatbot-associated delusions in psychiatric records from one Danish region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not unusual for new technologies to inspire delusions. But clinicians who have seen patients in the thrall of A.I. said it is an especially powerful influence because of its personal, interactive nature and authoritative tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a confidential news tip? The New York Times would like to hear from readers who want to share messages and materials with our journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the psychotic episodes spurred by chatbots can lead to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jessica Ferranti, a psychiatrist at UC Davis Health who often evaluates people in the legal system, said two of about 30 people she assessed last year in violent felony cases had delusional thoughts that were intensified by A.I. before the crimes occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both people developed messianic delusions about their own spiritual powers, Dr. Ferranti said. In one case, the bot mirrored and expanded on the psychotic thinking as the person came up with a plan to carry out a murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While delusional episodes have driven the public discourse about A.I. and mental health, the bots have other insidious effects that are far more widespread, doctors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several mental health workers who treat anxiety, depression or obsessive-compulsive disorders described A.I. either validating their clients’ worries or providing so much reassurance that patients felt reliant on chatbots to calm down — both less healthy than facing the source of the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Adam Alghalith of Mount Sinai Hospital in New York recalled a young man with depression who repeatedly shared negative thoughts with a chatbot. At first, the bot told him how to seek help. But he “just kept asking, kept pushing,” Dr. Alghalith said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safety guardrails that stop chatbots from encouraging suicide can break down when people engage the bots in extended conversations over days or weeks. Eventually, Dr. Alghalith said, the bot told the patient his thoughts of suicide were reasonable. Fortunately he had a support system and entered treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other doctors described chatbots flattering the grandiose tendencies of patients with personality disorders, or advising patients with autism to put themselves in dangerous social situations. Others said they saw patients’ interactions with chatbots as an addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quenten Visser, a therapist in Ozark, Mo., saw a 56-year-old last April who had experienced a panic attack. At first, Mr. Visser said, he thought the patient had severe anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after several therapy sessions, it became clear that the man was fixated on ChatGPT. He quit his job as a graphic designer after using ChatGPT 100 hours a week and having delusional thoughts about solving the energy crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This was this guy’s meth,” Mr. Visser said. He approached treatment as he would for any other addiction. They talked about what drove the man to use A.I.: lingering isolation from the pandemic and emotional distress he avoided by using chatbots. The man told The Times he now uses A.I. less, and makes art and works as a ride-share driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many doctors said that A.I.’s effects weren’t entirely negative. Some patients used the bots to practice techniques learned in therapy, for example, or as a nonjudgmental sounding board. Dr. Bob Lee, a psychiatry resident at a hospital in East Meadow, N.Y., even credited A.I. with saving a patient’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patient arrived at the emergency room last fall in a delusional panic about supernatural forces. He told doctors that a chatbot had identified his thoughts as symptoms of a crisis and advised him to go to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As with all new technologies, it can be used as a powerful force in both positive and negative ways,” Dr. Lee said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shannon Pagdon, a graduate student at the University of Pittsburgh who began having episodes of psychosis as a teenager and is now active in peer support networks, said A.I. can be useful to check whether her impressions line up with reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Like uploading a photo and saying, ‘Hey, do you see something in this photo?’” she explained. But, she said, she has also seen A.I. “reinforce psychotic experiences” in others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI has consulted with mental health experts to improve how ChatGPT responds to people who appear to be in a psychological crisis. The company has also formed a council with eight outside experts in psychology and human-computer interaction to advise its policy team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do we not keep people in this infinite loop of conversation with a machine?” said Munmun De Choudhury, a Georgia Tech professor and council member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although ChatGPT is by far the most used consumer chatbot, those made by Google, Anthropic and others also have millions of users. None have been able to avoid delusions and other harmful psychological effects, Dr. De Choudhury said. “I don’t think any of these companies have figured out what to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for Google said its Gemini chatbot advises users to find professional medical guidance for health-related queries. Anthropic, which makes Claude, published a blog post last month about a new feature that detects discussion of suicide or self-harm and routes users to help lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts advised therapists to ask patients about chatbot use, because its influence may not be obvious. For people trying to get their loved ones out of a delusional spiral, they advised reducing their time with the bot and making sure they get enough sleep. Insisting that the A.I. is wrong can be counterproductive if it makes the person angry or more isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sascha DuBrul, a mental health coach in Los Angeles, has seen firsthand both the good and bad of chatbot use. Last summer, Mr. DuBrul, whose work draws on his own experience with bipolar disorder, turned to ChatGPT when writing a book about psychotic episodes. After much back-and-forth, he became convinced A.I. would allow us to live “on some other level of reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With help from friends, he realized what was happening and pulled back from the bot. But he still believes mental health patients could benefit from a machine that listens infinitely — as long as it is connected to real human support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think that there’s a lot of potential there,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Far from Minneapolis, Memphis Remains Under a Different Federal Crackdown</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving through Memphis, it is hard not to feel the presence of the federal task force that has patrolled the city since September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cars are often stopped on the side of the road, surrounded by clusters of law enforcement agents and a mix of patrol and unmarked cars. National Guard troops in camouflage stand patrol outside stores and restaurants. Some of the main business strips seem emptier, even for a chilly stretch of January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis has been experiencing a show of force similar to those in cities like Minneapolis, where the Trump administration has sent hundreds of agents to enforce its immigration crackdown. But unlike in Minneapolis, where tensions have boiled over into frequent and at times violent confrontations this month, the task force in Memphis has focused broadly on fighting crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And support from Republican state leaders — and to an extent, from the city’s Democratic mayor, Paul Young — has kept things to an uneasy simmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To proponents of the operation, it has been a shining example of the administration’s aggressive approach to law enforcement, with city police officers, state troopers and federal agents collaborating as a single force. After U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents shot and killed Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday, Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, noted that Mayor Young of Memphis had “worked with us and our federal law enforcement officers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared with Minneapolis, she said, the Memphis operation was having “a very different result because of the leadership in place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis, with about 610,000 residents, saw 195 homicides from last January to this January, according to data analysis from the F.B.I., compared with 251 in the same 2024 time frame. It is still one of the highest rates in the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I see it as an extraordinarily successful solution to a chronic violent crime problem in Memphis that’s motivated by greed and evil,” said Michael Dunavant, who was sworn as U.S. attorney for the Western District of Tennessee in October. “We’re finally, actually enforcing the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those who are uncomfortable with the task force’s presence also say that the federal operation — “the occupation,” as some have branded it — has harmed some of the city’s most vulnerable residents while very likely doing little to reduce crime in the long term. Many poor people of color, they say, are avoiding their usual routines for fear of being pulled over or arrested. The majority Black city has a long history of the police using excessive force and racially profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve been the brunt of a lot of stuff considering how much that we produce culturally, economically, for the state, for this country,” said Chris Collier, who volunteers at Gaisman Park in the Berclair neighborhood. “For them to take this approach here, it just seems a whole lot more than totally necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no set end date for the Memphis Safe Task Force, which began its work in late September after President Trump signed an executive order dispatching employees of more than a dozen agencies to the city. Agents from the F.B.I. and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms are among those frequently on the streets. To date, the task force has made more than 6,300 arrests, conducted more than 68,000 traffic stops and recovered 1,532 firearms, according to city data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of the arrests were for nonviolent offenses, according to the data — even though the task force says its focus is violent crime. Still, crime rates, which had already been declining, have dropped even more since Oct. 1: Murder and sexual assault are down nearly 42 percent, while aggravated assault is down about 35 percent, according to city data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis residents broadly acknowledge that crime, which was already dropping, has decreased even more since the task force started its work. At the same time, there has been an uptick in the number of residents renewing vehicle registrations and drivers licenses, to avoid getting pulled over and penalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While immigration enforcement is not a stated focus of the task force, residents and local officials say that immigration arrests are quietly happening in tandem with the crime crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph Richman, 48, who commutes from Forrest City, Ark., about 45 miles away, to work as a painter in Memphis, said the task force’s presence has left many people with “kind of a mixed feeling”: hope that it will help address crime, but also fear of profiling and mistreatment by task force members, given the city’s history of discriminatory policing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really think that they need to be prayed for,” he added of the agents, just minutes after a group of agents made an arrest along the diverse, commercial stretch of Summer Avenue and drove away. “Sometimes they can make bad decisions pursuing good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent shot Renee Good, an American citizen, on a Minneapolis street in early January, some Memphis residents expressed concern that something similar could happen in their city. Ms. Good was killed on the anniversary of the death of Tyre Nichols, who died in 2023 after a traffic stop with Memphis police officers turned violent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Court documents show that many of the task force’s arrests have come after traffic stops, with officials citing a broken taillight or overly tinted window among the reasons for stopping a driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You ain’t speeding, you ain’t doing nothing, they just looking for excuses,” said Billy Walker, 67, who said he is set to go to court in the coming weeks for two traffic infractions — one for having a clear cover over his license plate, the other for turning at a red light. Mr. Walker, who said he felt both infractions were unfair, added, “Quit messing with people that’s trying to go to work here every day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared with other cities, where clashes between federal agents and protesters are far more common and Democratic governors have been vocal in their opposition, backlash in Memphis has been far more muted. Clusters of activists have rallied behind a “Free the 901” campaign — a reference to the city’s area code — documenting law enforcement activity and pressuring elected leaders to oppose the surge of agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a sprawling city where neighborhoods are spread out and many residents are struggling to make ends meet, protesting can be risky or just impractical. Some residents have resorted to staying home. One woman, in a neighborhood where immigrants live, recounted how her free Zumba class that usually draws a few dozen people had dropped to single digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic elected officials have had to make difficult calculations about how to react when Tennessee’s Republican governor and conservative supermajority in the legislature have outsize control over the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Lee Harris, a Democrat, of surrounding Shelby County, has joined a lawsuit seeking to end the National Guard deployment, which is set to having a hearing in March. But Mayor Young of Memphis has won plaudits from Republicans for working with the task force, even as he has voiced frustration about the Guard’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Young and his office did not immediately respond to questions about Ms. Noem’s comments on Memphis. But in an interview that took place before the two shootings in Minnesota, Mr. Young stressed that he believed “we’ve made the decisions that are in the best interest of the most people in our city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I knew my options were different than other mayors in the country,” he said, referring to the fact that his state is governed by Republicans aligned with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the federal agents patrolling Memphis, he added: “I have power to influence their work. And that’s the power that I’m exercising, the influence of the work and their focus each and every day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pointed to the number of open warrants the task force had pursued as part of its work, as well as the broader emphasis on violent crime, rather than immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citizens looking to blunt the task force’s impact have focused on raising money to cover bail for people arrested on minor offenses, delivering food to immigrants afraid to leave their homes or offering rides for those afraid to drive. They’ve also encouraged other residents to support only businesses that have publicly disowned the task force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re fighting from just a small corner,” said Rob Brown, the owner of Da Sammich Spot in the Orange Mound neighborhood, whose business fell off when the task force first arrived. But after a video went viral of Mr. Brown asking National Guard troops standing outside his business to leave after hours, he has sold out of loaded fries, sandwiches and fried fruit pies almost every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want crime running rampant,” he added. Still, he said, law enforcement officers should not “treat people like nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of task force arrests has strained the legal system and made overcrowding at the Shelby County Jail, a long-running problem, even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dunavant’s office in the Western District of Tennessee said that from Oct. 1 to Dec. 31, 141 people were charged under 111 indictments, compared with 37 people and 35 indictments over the same period in 2024. This month, the Pentagon dispatched 20 military lawyers from across the country to help with the caseload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The infrastructure has not been prepared,” said Lee Gerald, a defense lawyer who is representing a man accused of trying to run away from officers after he ran a red light and could not provide proof of citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At some point, the task force is going to leave,” he added, “and the problems persist.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Hobbled the I.R.S. This C.E.O. Now Has to Make It Work.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gathering of former leaders of the Internal Revenue Service this past fall was not meant to be anything special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had come to a private room in a Washington steakhouse to meet with the newest steward of the agency and discuss the challenges of running one of the most pilloried, and yet essential, parts of the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all its apparent mundanity, much about the meeting was atypical. For starters, the target for the group’s wisdom, Frank Bisignano, was not the commissioner of the I.R.S. He was its chief executive officer, a newly created role that Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent had asked him to fill in addition to his duties as the Senate-confirmed commissioner of the Social Security Administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there was the state of the I.R.S. Before Mr. Bisignano agreed to run it part time last October, the I.R.S. had spun through a chaotic carousel of seven leaders in 2025. Roughly 25,000 I.R.S. employees, a quarter of the work force, had left under President Trump. Congress was pursuing deep cuts to the I.R.S. budget, just weeks after Republicans passed into law a slew of complex new tax cuts that the agency would be responsible for administering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just the fact that Mr. Bisignano had called for the dinner encouraged the group of former I.R.S. commissioners, who had served in both Republican and Democratic administrations. After months of turmoil at the I.R.S., the opportunity to trade notes with Mr. Bisignano, once one of the highest paid executives in the country, seemed refreshingly normal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We came away, every single one of us, thinking, ‘This guy is competent, he is for real,’” Fred Goldberg, who led the I.R.S. under President George H.W. Bush, said at a recent tax conference. “He understands what needs to be done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the top of Mr. Bisignano’s list is having a smooth tax filing season. The annual tax season is always a critical period for the I.R.S. More than 140 million tax returns — many simple, some complicated — pour into the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Americans expect a refund, and they want it quickly. For poor Americans, their tax refund, padded by credits that return cash to people even if they did not owe any income tax, is often the single largest payment they receive in a year. Delays can mean skipped meals and missed bills. The margin for error is small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year’s filing season, which began on Monday, could be an even more formidable challenge than usual for the I.R.S. and Mr. Bisignano. Taxpayers may have difficulty parsing the fine print of the new tax cuts. Mr. Trump’s promise of “no tax on overtime,” for example, is in fact just a partial tax break that applies to a portion of certain federally mandated overtime wages. Rules like that could fuel a rush of additional questions for the I.R.S. during the 10-week filing season, which the agency will have to handle with its significantly smaller staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano, in an interview, said the I.R.S. was prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The job is to deliver the best results we have ever seen, and I haven’t seen anything in the way of executing that mission, with the technology crowd we have, with the operations crowd we have, with the legal staff we have,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano, the former chief executive of a payment processing company, will have to execute the filing season while also overseeing another large agency, the Social Security Administration. He works at the I.R.S. roughly two days a week, commuting from his home in New Jersey to Washington in his private plane, according to five people familiar with his schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I run two large organizations,” Mr. Bisignano said. “I don’t divide my time. On any given day, for example at 11:15 today, I will have an S.S.A. call, and at 12:30 I will have an I.R.S. call. They’re just two big divisions I run.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano, a onetime lieutenant to Jamie Dimon, JPMorgan’s chief executive, has quickly won some fans at the I.R.S., where there’s respect for his experience at large financial services companies and relief at the stability he appears to bring to the agency. The last commissioner of the I.R.S., Billy Long, was a former Republican congressman who had never run a major organization. He lasted less than two months last year. (Mr. Long did not attend the gathering of former I.R.S. leaders, according to three people familiar with the meeting.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hope among some current and former I.R.S. officials is that Mr. Bisignano represents a shift away from the Trump administration’s attempted demolition of the federal government last year and toward a more functional and professional equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Republicans are now counting on the federal government’s successful operation to help deliver political wins. Mr. Trump has promised Americans record tax refunds this year as a result of his tax law, and the G.O.P. hopes the cash payments can buoy Americans’ views of the economy before this year’s midterm election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The administration needs to be very, very careful about what they’re promising about refunds because they don’t have the staffing to quickly resolve these issues and get people their refunds,” said Nina Olson, who previously led taxpayer advocacy efforts at the I.R.S. “There’s nothing worse than promising people something and then not giving it to them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bessent, who is also the acting commissioner of the I.R.S., said in a statement that previous infusions of workers and money to the agency had made it “a bloated, inefficient and technologically unprepared entity that wasn’t serving the American people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times would like to hear about your experience as a federal worker under the second Trump administration. We may reach out about your submission, but we will not publish any part of your response without contacting you first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Under my leadership, along with Frank Bisignano, we are bringing this organization into the 21st century while providing greater collections, customer service and privacy,” Mr. Bessent said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if Mr. Bisignano can deliver a painless tax filing season, the outlook for the I.R.S. remains uncertain. Democrats have questioned the legality of Mr. Bisignano’s leadership of the I.R.S. without Senate confirmation. Mr. Trump has continued to shake things up, most recently in November, when he at the last minute pulled his nominee for I.R.S. chief counsel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m here for the foreseeable future, and the support of both the president and the secretary has made it possible to execute in both the jobs,” Mr. Bisignano said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Bisignano was first approached about leading the Social Security Administration in 2024, he told lawmakers that he had to Google basic details about the position. While his father had spent his career working for the federal government, Mr. Bisignano dedicated his professional life to the private sector, where he earned a reputation as a “Mr. Fix-It.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the chief administrative officer of Citigroup, Mr. Bisignano led the relocation of 16,000 staff members from Lower Manhattan on Sept. 11, 2001. Mr. Bisignano has said his work near ground zero that day later gave him throat cancer, changing the sound of his voice. He went on to JPMorgan, rising to become its co-chief operating officer, before leaving to run First Data, a payments company then owned by the private equity giant KKR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano led an aggressive turnaround of KKR’s investment in First Data, with a public offering in 2015. The company was later merged with another payments firm, Fiserv, which Mr. Bisignano then led as chief executive officer until joining the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, Senate Republicans confirmed Mr. Bisignano to run Social Security, where he inherited an agency in disarray. Elon Musk, the architect of the so-called Department of Government Efficiency, had spent the first few months of the Trump administration fanning falsehoods about widespread fraud in Social Security, a line of criticism that Mr. Trump adopted. The agency lost much of its staff, and, at one point, the interim chief threatened to shut down key operations during a legal standoff over DOGE access to the agency’s records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after starting at Social Security, Mr. Bisignano told The New York Times that the agency would be “a fact-based, rule-based organization that can count.” So far, he has had a comparatively calm tenure. He shifted resources toward reducing call wait times and made sure the agency’s website was up and running 24/7, rather than regularly going dark for service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under him, the Social Security Administration has also taken down some public metrics of its performance. Current and former agency staff members warn that focusing a smaller work force on reducing phone wait times could create backlogs in other areas, eventually causing a new set of problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano said the agency, with better technology systems, would be able to do more with less. “Head count is not the only metric to look at when you run these businesses with a technological presence,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Mr. Bisignano’s reputation on Wall Street has been dented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an earnings call last October, Mr. Bisignano’s replacement at Fiserv, Mike Lyons, said that the company had not invested enough in long-term growth under Mr. Bisignano and that it would not meet its previous financial forecasts. That prompted a plunge in a stock that had been dropping for much of the year; Fiserv’s stock is down nearly 70 percent over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a temptation to underinvest,” said Brett Horn, an analyst at Morningstar. “You can pull back on spending, margins go up and everybody’s happy. But eventually that hits growth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps Mr. Bisignano’s first accomplishment at the I.R.S. has been beginning this year’s filing season on the normal timeline. Mr. Long, the previous commissioner, suggested over the summer that filing season could start several weeks late. Mr. Trump fired him soon after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just days before filing season, Mr. Bisignano announced a reorganization of the agency’s leadership, one that redirected more people to report to him directly, according to a memo he sent to I.R.S. staff that was viewed by The Times. He will directly oversee all of the agency’s compliance work, an unusual arrangement, splitting the portfolio with Jarod Koopman, a longtime I.R.S. special agent who has been simultaneously assigned to lead the agency’s criminal division.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bisignano replaced the retiring I.R.S. criminal chief with Mr. Koopman instead of Gary Shapley, the I.R.S. agent who became a minor celebrity among conservatives after he testified publicly that the criminal investigation into Hunter Biden’s taxes had been slow walked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Shapley, who was briefly the acting I.R.S. commissioner in the spring, repeatedly told colleagues that he would be the I.R.S. criminal chief starting in 2026, answering questions about his plans for the job in an interview with CBS News in November. While Mr. Shapley told CBS that he would be apolitical, current and former I.R.S. officials worried that Mr. Shapley intended to change internal I.R.S. procedures to more easily pursue investigations of liberal individuals and organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Shapley will serve as the deputy chief of criminal investigations and remain on the senior leadership staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The recent reorganization was decided by the C.E.O., but was discussed with the team, and we are all on board to continue to improve the I.R.S. experience for all Americans,” Mr. Shapley said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the criminal investigations group has been pulled into the Trump administration’s broader political agenda. Some of its agents, typically focused on complex financial crimes, have had to spend time patrolling the streets in Washington, D.C., and Memphis alongside other federal law enforcement agencies as part of Mr. Trump’s crackdown on crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That diversion could eventually blunt the agency’s ability to pursue investigations into tax crimes, part of a broader anticipated enforcement drop-off at the I.R.S. caused by the staffing losses and budget cuts. But any decline in revenue caused by weaker I.R.S. enforcement would marginally widen the deficit over years. A mess during the tax filing season would be an immediate problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a huge amount at stake here,” Terry Lemons, the former I.R.S. communications chief who now works at Frost Law, said of filing season. “If you’re a leader of the I.R.S., this is the one area where you cannot fail.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Voters See a Middle-Class Lifestyle as Drifting Out of Reach, Poll Finds</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost-facebookJumbo-v4.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans are deeply pessimistic about their economic future, driven by financial anxiety among all but the oldest Americans and by a widespread belief that a middle-class lifestyle is out of reach for most people, a New York Times/Siena poll found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a majority of people said that they could afford basics like rent, gas and groceries, most said they worry about the costs, and there was a pronounced sense that it has become more difficult, if not nearly impossible, to get ahead in America today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Majorities of voters said they do not feel confident in their ability to pay for housing, retirement and health care, all traditional staples of a middle-class lifestyle. Separately, more than half said housing and education are now so expensive that both have become unaffordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those rising costs have shifted perceptions of America as a place of upward economic mobility dominated by a comfortable middle class. Two-thirds of voters said they now think a middle-class lifestyle is out of reach for most people, and 77 percent say it has gotten harder to achieve than a generation ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic worries persist across geographic, gender and racial lines. The only voters who seem less stressed economically are those over age 65, who express far fewer concerns about costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken together, the findings illustrate how economic anxieties, feelings of insecurity and a bleak outlook for the future have continued to weigh on most voters despite a booming stock market and resilient consumer spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such cost-of-living concerns have emerged as a major issue in the midterm elections and a notable weakness for President Trump, as he works to push his agenda through Washington. Fifty-one percent of voters said that Mr. Trump’s policies had made life less affordable for most Americans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prominent Democratic candidates in marquee races embraced a message focused on “affordability” to sweep to victory in the elections last year. Already, the party has made the issue a centerpiece of its midterm campaign, attacking the Trump administration over the costs of housing, health care, groceries, child care and other household expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the survey indicates that the issue is not lost for Republicans. Americans were divided on whom to blame most for the nation’s economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirty-one percent said Mr. Trump was responsible for the biggest challenges facing the U.S. economy, while 35 percent said it was former President Joseph R. Biden Jr., and 33 percent said neither president was responsible. Independent voters were equally likely to place blame with Mr. Biden and Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The polling also offered hints that the current economic mood, while dour, may be slightly brighter than it was at the end of Mr. Biden’s term. Thirty-one percent of voters think the economy is better off than it was a year ago, an improvement over the 21 percent who said the same in April 2025. Twenty-nine percent rated the economy as “excellent” or “good,” a seven percentage point increase from the fall of 2024. But 70 percent still describe the economy as fair or poor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 60 percent of voters said they worry about affording the very basics — rent, gas, routine bills and groceries — and 11 percent said they could not afford them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan June, an engineer from St. Louis, said he can afford basic expenses and save some for retirement but has little “level of buffer” for emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even though I make more than my parents have, I struggle more than my parents ever did,” said Mr. June, 41, a father of three young daughters with a net annual household income of about $160,000. “For the amount of work that we’ve put in, it really seems much more difficult than it should be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inflation, while far down from the highs after the pandemic, continues to nag at households in the form of stubbornly high utility and food prices. Housing costs and rents, typically the biggest slice of a household budget, have soared above what many families can stomach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a small fraction of voters — 14 percent — feel they are actually getting ahead financially. Even many people making more than $200,000 a year, a household income in the upper ranges of American families, expressed concerns about their long-term economic stability and the cost of health care. Ten percent of voters making more than $200,000 a year said they did not think they could afford the cost of retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the economic pessimism tracks along generational lines. Younger Americans expressed far more financial anxieties and a bleaker view of their economic futures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Half of voters under 45 described themselves as generally worse off financially than their parents were at their age, and just 10 percent feel they are getting ahead financially. A majority of those voters say the cost of having a family has become unaffordable. And as traditional pensions disappear and Social Security faces a financing shortfall, 75 percent of voters under 65 say they cannot afford the cost of retirement or feel insecure about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voters over age 65 consistently expressed far less anxiety about costs. When asked what they worry about affording, 24 percent said “nothing.” Nearly 60 percent of older voters described themselves as “holding steady” financially, while 40 percent of voters under 30 said they were “falling behind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older voters likely don’t face the same economic pressures as younger generations. Most receive health care through Medicare, bought homes in a far cheaper market and, with grown children, do not face record high costs of child care and education. But 26 percent said they worried about affording medical and health care costs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly two-thirds of voters over 65 said they can afford the life they feel like they should be able to afford, while a whopping 75 percent of voters under 30 said they cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times/Siena poll&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan. 12-17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on a New York Times/Siena poll of 1,625 registered voters nationwide conducted Jan. 12 to 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gray segment is for voters who did not respond or said they didn’t know. Question wording and response categories have been condensed. Respondents were asked if they could afford the life they felt like they should be able to afford. Those who said they could not currently afford it were then asked if they thought it was within reach or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martín González Gómez/The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael McCarthy, a retired high school computer drafting teacher from outside of Buffalo, N.Y., described himself as doing better financially in his retirement than his parents in theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My wife and I were both teachers, so we both had decent incomes and we saved,” said Mr. McCarthy, 77. “I don’t want to buy a vineyard, so that’s out. I don’t need a yacht. So that’s out. If I want something, I buy it. But I don’t have a lot of wants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing topped the list as the biggest financial concern for most voters under 65, including more than half of voters under 30 who said it was the thing they worry most about affording.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While 70 percent of older voters said that they already have the home they’d like to own, more than half of voters under 30 said such a home was “out of reach.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For young voters, the anxieties span the political spectrum. Majorities of young Republicans and Democrats said housing and education costs had become unaffordable and that they did not feel secure in being able to afford retirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasen Millspaw, 21, an Amazon delivery driver from Ogden, Utah, said that his grandmother had told him that decades ago even people earning minimum wage could save and afford a reasonable place to live. While he now earns more than three times the minimum wage, he said, “I still have to live with other people in order to just pay rent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Millspaw added: “It’s harder to be middle class nowadays.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the key things to know about this poll from The New York Times and Siena University:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• The survey was conducted among 1,625 registered voters nationwide from Jan. 12 to 17, 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• This poll was conducted in English and Spanish, by telephone using live interviewers and by text message. Overall, 98 percent of respondents were contacted on their cellphone. You can see the exact questions that were asked and the order in which they were asked here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• Voters are selected for the survey from a list of registered voters. The list contains information on the demographic characteristics of every registered voter, allowing us to make sure we reach the right number of voters of each party, race and region. For this poll, interviewers placed more than 188,000 calls or texts to more than 86,000 voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• To further ensure that the results reflect the entire voting population, not just those willing to take a poll, we give more weight to respondents from demographic groups that are underrepresented among survey respondents, like people without a college degree. You can see more information about the characteristics of respondents and the weighted sample at the bottom of the results and methodology page, under “Composition of the Sample.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• The margin of sampling error among registered voters is about plus or minus 2.8 percentage points. In theory, this means that the results should reflect the views of the overall population most of the time, though many other challenges create additional sources of error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see full results and a detailed methodology here. If you want to read more about how and why we conduct our polls, you can see answers to frequently asked questions and submit your own questions here.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:02:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota Claims the ICE Surge Is Illegal. A Judge Will Hear Arguments on Monday.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-lawsuit-ice-surge-hearing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-minnesota-courtfight-plbw/25nat-minnesota-courtfight-plbw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in Minnesota will consider an extraordinary legal question on Monday: Can a deployment of federal law enforcement officers be so dangerous and so intrusive that it violates a state’s sovereignty under the 10th Amendment?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the state of Minnesota, along with the cities of Minneapolis and St. Paul, have claimed that the Trump administration’s surge of some 3,000 immigration agents to the state has crossed the line into an unconstitutional and illegal occupation. They have asked a judge to temporarily halt the surge, which has led to three shootings, thousands of arrests and tense protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has dismissed the state’s legal theory, saying in court filings that it “would constitute an unprecedented act of judicial overreach” to expel federal officers from Minnesota. They have argued that Operation Metro Surge, as the administration has named its Minnesota campaign, is fully legal, and that it is up to the federal government to decide when and how to enforce federal laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spotlight on Monday’s hearing in U.S. District Court in Minneapolis intensified over the weekend after federal agents shot and killed Alex Pretti, a local resident and nurse who appeared to be filming agents on the south side of Minneapolis. Federal officials said that Mr. Pretti, a U.S. citizen, had endangered agents. They accused him of engaging in “domestic terrorism” and noted that he was in possession of a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times contradict portions of the Department of Homeland Security’s account of the shooting. Minneapolis officials said Mr. Pretti, who is seen in the videos holding a cellphone, was licensed to legally carry a gun, and a witness who gave a sworn statement in court disputed the federal account of the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter to the judge on Saturday night, hours after the shooting, lawyers for the state and the cities reiterated their calls for an immediate pause of the surge that began late last year, writing that “the situation is grave.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This cannot continue,” they wrote. “We need the court to act to stop this surge before yet another resident dies because of Operation Metro Surge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit, filed two weeks ago, argues that the surge in immigration enforcement in Minnesota is motivated by a “desire to punish political opponents and score partisan points.” The state and local governments told the judge that the deployment had panicked residents, endangered public safety and infringed on their ability to carry out basic government functions. Local law enforcement is overburdened, they said, and schools have been disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case was filed days after the fatal shooting of Renee Good by a federal agent in Minneapolis. It does not seek an end to all immigration enforcement in Minnesota, but asks the judge to order a return to pre-surge levels of agents. It also asks for restrictions on the actions of agents who remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Defendants’ actions appear designed to provoke community outrage, sow fear, and inflict emotional distress, and they are interfering with the ability of state and local officials to protect and care for their residents,” the lawsuit said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the state and cities have asked Judge Kate M. Menendez to temporarily block Operation Metro Surge and to immediately impose restrictions on the actions of remaining immigration agents. But Judge Menendez, who was nominated to the bench by President Joseph R. Biden Jr., declined to rule on that timetable during a hearing earlier this month, saying that the Trump administration needed time to respond to the case in writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since that hearing, federal agents have been involved in two more shootings in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the Trump administration have described the state and local governments’ claims as a fundamental misreading of the 10th Amendment, which gives powers not reserved for the federal government to the states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “10th Amendment and related claims have not a shred of legal support,” they said in a brief filed with the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration’s lawyers described Operation Metro Surge as a lawful campaign that had resulted in the arrests of people convicted of serious crimes and had made Minnesota safer. They said the president was acting within his authority and delivering on a campaign promise to crack down on illegal immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump campaigned and won election on a promise to enforce immigration laws enacted by Congress,” the federal government’s lawyers said. “For the last year, D.H.S. has delivered on that promise by surging resources to the removal of aliens who entered this country illegally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez is scheduled to hear arguments on whether to grant a temporary restraining order or preliminary injunction at the courthouse in downtown Minneapolis on Monday morning. She could rule at any time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During an earlier hearing, the judge noted that there was limited case law for a state challenging a federal law enforcement deployment on 10th Amendment grounds. Other Democratic-led states have challenged Mr. Trump’s deployment of National Guard members or federal troops during immigration enforcement campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred Smith Jr., a Stanford law professor, said Minnesota’s lawsuit “makes novel claims,” but that the “central government is doing novel things, and so there’s not a lot of precedent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ruling in favor of Minnesota, Mr. Smith said, could “open up a door to kind of a new area of 10th Amendment jurisprudence, where the federal government in the future would have to be mindful about acting in ways that unduly interfered with states’ ability to carry out their own laws.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same day that Minnesota officials sued, Illinois officials filed their own 10th Amendment case asking another judge to block U.S. Customs and Border Protection “from conducting civil immigration enforcement” in the state without “express congressional authorization.” An order has yet to be issued in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez is also presiding over a case filed by Minnesota protesters who accused immigration agents of systematically violating their rights. She issued a preliminary injunction in that case, but that ruling was stayed by an appellate court after the Trump administration appealed.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-lawsuit-ice-surge-hearing.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:02:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Crisis of Confidence for ICE and Border Patrol as Clashes Escalate</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26DC-DHS-ANGER-oscar-tfwz/26DC-DHS-ANGER-oscar-tfwz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oscar Hagelsieb spent nearly 25 years as an immigration officer and special agent, proud of his work enforcing federal laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But watching the chaos unfolding in Minneapolis, and the fatal shooting of a U.S. citizen there on Saturday, Mr. Hagelsieb said he felt anger and despair at how the Trump administration was deploying his former agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re not addressing the problem by throwing a 500-pound gorilla into these inner cities,” said Mr. Hagelsieb, 52, who said he voted three times for President Trump and retired from the Department of Homeland Security in 2023. “It’s completely unfair to the agents who have been put in this position.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re causing chaos, and unfortunately it’s costing lives,” he added. “There’s only so much they can handle before bad things start to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hagelsieb’s comments reflect a growing sense of fear, frustration and disillusionment among some current and former immigration officials at the department, which is leading Mr. Trump’s push to arrest and deport millions of people. In interviews with The New York Times, more than 20 of them expressed anxieties that the administration was sending federal agents into situations in Minneapolis and other major cities that were increasingly dangerous both for them and civilians they encountered. They said that long hours, arrest quotas and public vitriol were taking a significant toll on morale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many also worried that the fallout would irreparably damage how the public perceived the two main homeland security agencies involved in Mr. Trump’s crackdown, Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the U.S. Border Patrol, hurting long-term recruitment and retention. Several said they worried that Democrats would draw on voter outrage to shut down ICE, which has been the most publicly visible arm of the immigration operation, if they returned to power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some also criticized the more aggressive tactics being used by the Border Patrol, as well as the combative approach of one of its leaders, Gregory Bovino. Mr. Bovino has often used the phrase “turn and burn” to describe Border Patrol operations, a reference to actions like smashing windshields, using explosives to blow down the doors of homes and engaging in car chases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gil Kerlikowske, who during the Obama administration led Customs and Border Protection, which includes the Border Patrol, said most Border Patrol agents did not have experience “policing an urban environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kerlikowske also said many of the tactics he had seen being used in Minneapolis and other cities, like shooting people with pepper ball rounds and spraying chemical agents at nonviolent protesters, were “far outside standard practices in law enforcement.” And he said his conversations with current Border Patrol employees reflected a grim situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Morale is in the dumpster,” he said. “Many of the agents will be very happy to go back to the job they were trained for on the border.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to know how widespread any sense of discontent is among ICE and Border Patrol agents on the ground in Minneapolis or other cities. Many have been seen arguing with protesters and appear to be supporting one another during confrontations. Paul Perez, the chief of the Border Patrol union, told The Times that morale remained “high” and that there were plenty of volunteers for Mr. Trump’s immigration operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Agents are concerned about being doxxed, having their families and themselves put at risk,” Mr. Perez said. “But I don’t think anybody’s afraid to do the mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, blamed Democrats for the violence and chaos in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody, including President Trump, wants to see people get shot or hurt,” Ms. Leavitt said in a statement. “That’s exactly why Governor Walz and Mayor Frey need to allow local police to work with federal law enforcement to remove illegal alien criminals, murderers and pedophiles from Minnesota,” she added, referring to Tim Walz of Minnesota and Jacob Frey of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump on Sunday posted on social media asking Democratic leaders to “formally cooperate with the Trump Administration” rather than “resist and stoke the flames of Division, Chaos, and Violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Homeland Security Department did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the Trump administration has rapidly grown both ICE and the Border Patrol, thanks to an infusion of billions of dollars from Congress that has financed an intense recruitment drive. Many homeland security hiring ads feature military-style imagery, like officers wearing tactical gear and driving combat vehicles. They refer to immigration as an “invasion” and immigrants as “enemies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times spoke with current and former officials in the hours after federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday shot and killed Alex Pretti, an intensive care nurse who was filming them, the second fatal shooting of a civilian there this month. Many described the deaths of Mr. Pretti and the other American citizen, Renee Good, as points of no return in the relationship between homeland security and members of the public. Most of those who spoke to The Times did so on the condition of anonymity, fearing retribution from the Trump administration if they spoke openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the current and former ICE officials who spoke with The Times said they supported enforcing the nation’s immigration laws. Many said they believed that President Joseph R. Biden Jr.’s border policies had contributed to the current crisis. They also criticized many blue cities and states for not cooperating more with federal immigration authorities, for instance by restricting their ability to make arrests of undocumented immigrants at jails and prisons, moves that they said were safer than picking people up on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most said they were unhappy with the sharp language from top White House and Homeland Security officials, especially their quick rush to conclude that agents were blameless and Mr. Pretti was at fault, before a full investigation had taken place. One current Homeland Security agent said he had “always given the benefit of the doubt to the government in these situations” but he no longer believed “any of the statements they put out anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many also said that Mr. Trump’s mass-arrest campaign was proving counterproductive. In part, they said, that was because many federal agents were not thoroughly trained in dealing with hostile crowds, a growing concern as organized groups of protesters have sought to monitor homeland security activities, filming them on the street, following their agents’ cars and blowing whistles to disrupt their operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We lost all trust,” one current ICE official said. “I’m not sure I can see how we exist three years from now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most ICE agents do not receive specialized training in crowd control, according to a 2021 report by the Government Accountability Office. Neither do agents at the F.B.I.; the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives; and the U.S. Marshals Service, the report found. Thousands of law enforcement officers from those agencies have also been assigned to the immigration crackdown. Border Patrol agents do receive more extensive training in crowd control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal tactics for making immigration arrests have also changed substantially, current and former officials said. In previous administrations, ICE tried to take a more targeted approach. That could involve carrying out several days of surveillance before approaching a suspect, trying to identify the safest place to make an arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the administration’s demand for as many as 3,000 arrests per day has significantly reduced the time available for that kind of careful preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a social media post on Sunday, Tim Quinn, a former senior official at C.B.P. who left the agency last year, criticized the White House’s “reckless push for deportation numbers,” saying that it was “putting the public and law enforcement at great risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, agents have been told to cast a far wider net, questioning people they encounter about their immigration status, which has made many of their operations resemble indiscriminate street sweeps. That has led to concerns about racial profiling, inciting anger in many communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m Hispanic, I look Hispanic,” Mr. Hagelsieb said. “I would be highly upset if someone came and asked me if I was illegal because I’m Hispanic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deborah Fleischaker, who was the assistant director for policy for ICE during the Biden administration, said the agency had previously conducted immigration enforcement in a “careful, thoughtful, targeted way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, she said, agents would plan extensively to minimize the risk to themselves, their targets and the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“None of that appears to be happening anymore,” Ms. Fleischaker said. Referring to the current operation in Minneapolis and other cities, she added, “This isn’t what they were trained to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Mitnick, who served as the top attorney at the Department of Homeland Security in the first Trump administration, wrote on social media that he was “enraged and embarrassed by DHS’s lawlessness, fascism, and cruelty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump, the Border Patrol has also played a sweeping role in enforcing immigration laws within the nation’s interior. There are fewer constitutional protections at the border than there are inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency has sent hundreds of agents to Minneapolis; Los Angeles; Washington, D.C.; Portland, Ore.; and Memphis, the main targets of Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown. Several current and former homeland security officials said they believed that the Border Patrol was not prepared to operate this extensively within cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol’s more aggressive tactics have led to behind-the-scenes conflicts with ICE, according to current and former federal officials. Two former ICE officials said the public was blaming ICE for Border Patrol’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump has sent thousands of federal agents into Minneapolis, making it the nation’s largest-ever immigration enforcement operation, public opinion has shifted decisively against ICE. Just 36 percent of voters said they approved of the way ICE was handling its job, while 63 percent disapproved, according to a Times/Siena University poll. Fueled by the outrage, Senate Democrats have signaled that they may be willing to partly shut down the government over the Homeland Security Department’s funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One former ICE official questioned whether many Americans would want to work in federal law enforcement after seeing the clashes in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Hagelsieb, one particular worry is the number of ICE special agents taken off of complex criminal investigations to instead track down undocumented immigrants, many of whom have not been convicted of crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Times investigation last year found that agents at Homeland Security Investigations, which is part of ICE and is where Mr. Hagelsieb worked, had been reassigned from cases involving sex crimes against children, drug smuggling and terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like a local police department pulling a homicide investigator to conduct an operation against jaywalkers,” Mr. Hagelsieb said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Flavelle and Michael H. Keller contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:25:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Our Photographer Describes the Scene After the Pretti ShootingOur Photographer Describes the Scene After the Pretti Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010667387/our-photographer-describes-pretti-shooting-scene.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/arts/guttenfelder-thumb/guttenfelder-thumb-facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
David Guttenfelder, a Times photographer based in Minneapolis, describes what he saw at the scene where Alex Jeffrey Pretti had been killed by federal agents.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010667387/our-photographer-describes-pretti-shooting-scene.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:00:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The ‘R-Word’ Returns, Dismaying Those Who Fought to Oust It</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/r-word-slur-disability.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/r-word-01-jvfh/r-word-01-jvfh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late last month, a woman posted a photograph on social media of a purple hat she had knitted, while a black-and-white dog lounged on the carpet a few feet away. The cozy scene was accompanied by a single sentence: “This hat is an hour behind schedule thanks to influencer retards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proud knitter, Harmeet K. Dhillon, is also the assistant attorney general overseeing the Justice Department’s Civil Rights Division. Her purview includes protecting the rights of people with intellectual disabilities by ensuring compliance with the Americans With Disabilities Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades now, the “R-word” has been regarded as a slur against people with intellectual disabilities — a word to be avoided. Yet it has had a striking resurgence, in part because people in high-profile positions of power and influence have chosen to resurrect it, often with an air of defiance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The word ‘retarded’ is back,” the popular podcaster Joe Rogan declared in April, describing its return as “one of the great culture victories.” He did not respond to requests for elaboration, but there is abundant evidence to support his muscular declaration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past three months, the musician Kid Rock donned a face mask while appearing on a program streaming on Fox Nation and said he was dressing up as a “retard” for Halloween. (He was also wearing a Jesus trucker cap.) The Fox News personality Greg Gutfeld coupled the word with a schoolyard taunt to mock mayors who oppose President Trump, and Elon Musk used it on his social media platform to insult a critic. The word has recently been uttered on the podcasts of the white nationalist Nick Fuentes and the right-wing commentators Derek Hunter, Steven Crowder and Tim Pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of a hurtful word still considered taboo is emblematic of the provocative language that courses through the manosphere sector of social media these days — almost gleefully transgressive language often adopted in messaging from the White House. Diplomacy is out and mockery in, whether by displaying plaques that insult former presidents, depicting Mr. Trump spraying excrement on protesters from a military jet — or using the “R-word” to question the intelligence of a political opponent, as Mr. Trump did in a Truth Social post on Thanksgiving Day, in which he called Minnesota’s Democratic governor, Tim Walz, “seriously retarded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked later whether he stood by that statement, Mr. Trump said, “Absolutely,” because he thought there was something wrong with the governor. For her part, Ms. Dhillon did not answer questions about her use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word’s proliferation has alarmed many advocates and people with disabilities who thought it had long since been removed from circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The drumbeat and use of this word has been like nothing I’ve seen in a very long time,” said Katy Neas, the chief executive of the Arc of the United States, a disability rights organization. She called its use by the Justice Department’s civil rights chief “simply mind-blowing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word’s return raises an obvious question: Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why decide to resurrect a term well known to offend a community that has been historically marginalized, so much so that its usage prompted public-awareness campaigns and wholesale changes to nomenclature?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think there’s a perception of power, of ‘I am powerful, therefore I can use this language; I am powerful, and therefore I can diminish others,’” Ms. Neas said. She added: “It’s language used by bullies to bully.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Amy Hewitt, the director of the Institute on Community Integration at the University of Minnesota, the word’s return reflects a divisiveness defining the United States of 2026, in which a sizable part of the population believes that “many people are a drain on our society, on our progress, on what makes us great.” She pointed in particular to the Trump administration’s dismantling of diversity, equity and inclusion efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not just about race and ethnicity, it’s also about disability,” she said. “This is why the R-word is completely acceptable to them. It’s ‘us versus them.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of the word has skyrocketed on X, Mr. Musk’s social media platform. In 2020, it appeared on the platform, then known as Twitter, just over 2,000 times a day, according to a recent study by two Montclair State University researchers. That number is now over 46,000 times a day — a more than 2,000 percent increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers, Bond Benton, a communications professor, and Daniela Peterka-Benton, a justice studies professor, said the word’s use rose after Mr. Musk bought the platform in late 2022, and then spiked when he included it in an X post in January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this Musk-induced growth was a blip when compared with what followed in the week after Mr. Trump’s disparagement of Mr. Walz in late November. Use of the word increased by more than 200 percent, with more than 1.1 million posts on X employing the word. Most of them, the study’s authors noted, conveyed enthusiastic endorsement of the term’s apparent restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Musk influences a lot of people, especially in the manosphere, so we had a hunch that the platform was going to have more use of the term,” Dr. Benton said. “Then when Trump used it, it was like a nuclear bomb.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defenders of the word’s use say that it is intended in part to clap back at political correctness, “wokeness” and perceived infringements of the right to free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are so many words in the English language that have been driven out of use because we’ve been told that they’re politically incorrect,” Mark Meckler, a right-wing activist and self-described “free speech warrior,” said in his podcast last month. “Well, that’s just cultural Marxism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So this has now come back into common use, and I’m actually glad it has, because it just shows we’ve been recapturing language from the woke left,” said Mr. Meckler, who, in adding that he did not mean to insult “mentally handicapped” people, used another term that disability advocates say is outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who defend the word’s use often contend that it is meant as a synonym for “stupid” or “slow,” and not as a reference to people with intellectual disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not really like anybody wants to make fun of people who are slow, when it comes to brain development,” the conservative commentator Megyn Kelly said on her podcast last month. “It’s that they’re sick and tired of being told what they can and cannot say.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No one’s trying to actually say something negative about that community,” Ms. Kelly added. “They’re trying to say something about the person they’re targeting — that they’re kind of slow.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But many people with intellectual disabilities and their advocates consider this distinction to be disingenuous, if not a complete cop-out. The word, they say, continues to wound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helena Donato-Sapp, 16, of Long Beach, Calif., is a junior in high school with several learning disabilities. Last semester, while walking through campus at lunchtime, she heard a classmate call a friend the R-word, and was taken aback by a word she associates with shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes me feel bad and confused that people still use it,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terminology for people with intellectual disabilities has evolved over generations, with words like “idiot,” “imbecile,” “feebleminded” and “moron” having their moment before being phased out for reasons of imprecision or hurtfulness, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What united them, though, was an implied sense of otherness that, among other effects, gave oxygen to the pseudoscience of eugenics in the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1950s, “mental retardation” had become the socially acceptable medical term of choice, but it, too, devolved into a pejorative. The phrase became part of what linguistics experts refer to as a “euphemism treadmill,” in which a word that begins as acceptable develops into a slur through negative use, leading to eventual replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As people with intellectual disabilities began more and more to speak up for themselves, they made their dislike of the R-word clear. The consensus was “that it’s mean, hurtful, harassing,” Dr. Hewitt said. “It’s personally offensive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rejection of the term gradually took hold. In 1992, for example, the Association for Retarded Citizens of the United States changed its name to what it is called today: the Arc of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Neas, its chief executive, said that advocates, including those with intellectual disabilities, argued that words mattered. “The words had to be fully inclusive, and not in any way include language that separates or denigrates people,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the 2009 Special Olympics in Idaho, youth advocates — galvanized in part by repeated use of the word in the film “Tropic Thunder” — sparked a global movement called Spread the Word to End the Word. Disability advocates called out anyone who used the word, including President Barack Obama’s chief of staff, Rahm Emanuel, who subsequently apologized and agreed to sign a pledge to end the use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most significant rejection of the term came in 2010, when Mr. Obama signed “Rosa’s Law” — named after a young girl with Down syndrome — replacing “mental retardation” with “intellectual disability” in federal legislation and policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among those present for the signing ceremony was Jill Eglé, a disability advocate who, a year earlier, had been a driving force in having the word eliminated at the state level in Virginia. The cause was personal; as a child growing up in Virginia, she had been declared “mildly mentally retarded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had a hard time because I was made fun of, laughed at,” Ms. Eglé, 49, recalled. “I didn’t have a boyfriend, always ridiculed and always, you know, just was the odd one out. No boy ever asked me to the prom and stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They all called me retarded, and I tried to be nice, but it wasn’t the way it should be,” she said. “And it was hurtful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next decade, the sustained efforts to remove the word from the vocabulary seemed to succeed, with students and teachers reporting a marked decline in its use. By 2019, the Special Olympics considered the matter settled, and began shifting the focus of its public awareness campaign to a larger message of inclusivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really felt like we had made so much progress,” said Andrea Cahn, vice president of Unified Champion Schools, the Special Olympics umbrella program that oversaw the campaign. “The use of the word really seemed to have been diminished.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it came back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Olympics saw a spike in alerts from athletes and people with intellectual disabilities about an increased use of the word. Ms. Cahn said the thrust of many messages was: “Can you do something? Can you make them stop?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocates say it isn’t surprising that the word is being heard more frequently. “You’ve got the president of the United States using that word,” Dr. Hewitt said. “So why are we surprised?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole LeBlanc, 40, of Silver Spring, Md., an advocate who has autism and an intellectual disability, said she had noticed how the word had returned as a common, everyday insult. Hearing it, she said, she feels the sting of stigma — even when it isn’t directed at her or another person with a disability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes me want to run, hide and curl up into a ball,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitty Bennett contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/r-word-slur-disability.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:10:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Is Sending Tom Homan, His Border Czar, to Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/homan-minnesota-ice-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-homan-zwgf/26minneapolis-ice-homan-zwgf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said he was sending Tom Homan, his border czar, to Minnesota to run immigration enforcement operations in the state on Monday, two days after a man was fatally shot there by Department of Homeland Security officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to send Mr. Homan, a longtime veteran of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, came amid increased criticism of the D.H.S. operation in the state and its rushed response to the shooting of the man, Alex Pretti, who was pinned down by agents when he was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am sending Tom Homan to Minnesota tonight,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media on Monday. “He has not been involved in that area, but knows and likes many of the people there. Tom is tough but fair, and will report directly to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, detailed Mr. Homan’s mandate in the state in her own post. “Tom Homan will be managing ICE Operations on the ground in Minnesota to continue arresting the worst of the worst criminal illegal aliens,” she wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Homan has extensive ties at ICE. He led the agency’s deportation wing during the Obama administration, saying at the time that he supported its efforts to target serious criminals in the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later, he was tapped to be the agency’s acting director during the first Trump administration. Mr. Homan, along with two other senior leaders, recommended a policy that led to the separation of families along the border in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As border czar, Mr. Homan has taken on a communications role. He often appears on television or holds gaggles with reporters outside the White House, spreading the message of the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown and offering public defenses of its tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running the operations on the ground has mostly been the responsibility of Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, along with other agency leaders. including Gregory Bovino, who has overseen Border Patrol operations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem praised the decision to send Mr. Homan to Minnesota in a social media post. “This is good news for peace, safety, and accountability in Minneapolis,” she wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/homan-minnesota-ice-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:17:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nigella Lawson Joins ‘The Great British Baking Show’ as a Judge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/nigella-lawson-great-british-bake-off.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26xp-bakeoff1/26xp-bakeoff1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Great British Baking Show” announced a new judge on Monday: Nigella Lawson, the British author and cooking personality, after the departure of Prue Leith from the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m uncharacteristically rather lost for words right now!” Ms. Lawson said in a statement announcing her appointment, calling the show a “national treasure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series, known as “The Great British Bake Off” in Britain, developed into one of the most popular shows on British television after its debut in 2010. In 2016, the show’s producer, Love Productions, decided to leave the BBC for Channel 4, a rival network, prompting a judge, Mary Berry, and two of the show’s hosts, Sue Perkins and Mel Giedroyc, to depart. Ms. Leith replaced Ms. Berry in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson said it was “daunting” to be following in the footsteps of Ms. Leith and Mary Berry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Leith, 86, said this month that she was stepping away after nine seasons and more than 400 challenges on the show. Ms. Lawson joins Paul Hollywood, another judge who remained with the show after it left the BBC, and the presenters Noel Fielding and Alison Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the signature tent that serves as the show’s set, bakers compete in challenges for the judges and presenters, pushing the boundaries of baking with unconventional creations. The show has been credited with changing the way Britain viewed the cultural range and offerings of baking, and for inspiring home bakers encouraged by the diverse roster of contestants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson, 66, who was a columnist for The New York Times in the early 2000s, has long been a star of culinary culture, with best-selling cookbooks and television appearances, in a career that has spanned decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “How to Eat,” the cookbook that helped kick off her culinary career, was published in 1998, it featured ingredients that were not popular at the time, including avocado, pomegranate and quinoa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Ms. Lawson demonstrated a recipe from her cookbook “Cook, Eat, Repeat” on her BBC television show of the same name that included a dish of cauliflower and banana peels, an ingredient traditionally used in Bengali cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I certainly didn’t expect newspaper headlines about it!” she told The Times in 2021. “It’s hard to overcome the cultural assumptions about what is and is not edible, and to start eating what we have customarily regarded as waste.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson recently celebrated 25 years of her classic baking book, “How to Be a Domestic Goddess.” Ian Katz, the chief content officer at Channel 4, said her addition to the show was “the marriage of two great British icons.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/nigella-lawson-great-british-bake-off.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:01:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>They ‘Had Done Everything Right.’ ICE Detained Them Anyway.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-minnesota-refugees.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00dc-refugees-hfzw/00dc-refugees-hfzw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selamawit Mehari, an Eritrean single mother of three, was starting her day when federal agents showed up at her apartment in St. Paul, Minn., on a recent morning. As her 13-year-old son wailed and her older daughter produced paperwork proving her mother was in the United States lawfully, the agents shackled Ms. Mehari and took her away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They didn’t explain anything,” recalled her daughter, Yosan, 21, who described the encounter to The New York Times. “We didn’t understand. We had done everything right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, chained at the wrists, waist and ankles, Ms. Mehari, 38, was shuffling up the steps of a plane bound for Texas, tears streaming down her face in the frigid wind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 100 refugees with no criminal record from about a dozen countries have been arrested in Minnesota by immigration agents in recent weeks and flown to detention centers in Texas for interviews, according to lawyers, family members and faith leaders. At least some, including Ms. Mehari, were eventually released in Texas, leaving them to find their own way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrests, which began this month and are continuing, have sown panic among refugees in Minnesota, where thousands of agents are conducting a sweeping operation as President Trump intensifies his national immigration crackdown. Over the weekend, U.S. Border Patrol officers fatally shot a Minneapolis protester in the second killing of a demonstrator at the hands of immigration agents this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being approved for resettlement in the United States, refugees often wait years in camps and undergo extensive vetting by the Department of Homeland Security and other federal agencies. They arrive on flights coordinated with the U.S. government. The process is radically different from that of asylum seekers who have shown up at the border and been allowed to remain in the United States only if they win their cases in immigration court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration had announced early this month that it would “re-examine thousands of refugee cases through new background checks.” Officials said they would focus on people who had arrived in the United States in recent years and were yet to obtain green cards, or legal permanent residency, starting with 5,600 refugees in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement, by U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services, did not say that refugees would be rounded up and jailed for the review to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dragnet has swept up refugees from Africa, Asia, Latin America and the Middle East, according to lawyers and leaders of resettlement agencies that are government-funded to assist refugees in the United States. It has included Karen people from Myanmar, a persecuted Christian minority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to questions from The Times about the detentions, a spokesman for Citizenship and Immigration Services, Matthew Tragesser, said in a statement that the agency “is verifying the merits of all refugee applications and ensuring no issues were overlooked.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is determined during the rescreening that a refugee poses a national security or public safety concern, or committed fraud, that person will face deportation proceedings, Mr. Tragesser said, and if the refugee passes, he or she “may be granted a green card.” Mr. Tragesser did not explain why the refugees were being flown to Texas for the interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering sanctuary to the displaced has long been a bedrock of U.S. policy, garnering bipartisan support. Refugees are typically fleeing war or persecution, without the possibility of ever returning to their home country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has sought to drastically cut back legal immigration in addition to purging the country of those here unlawfully. He has halted all refugee admissions except a small group including white Afrikaners from South Africa. The president has fixated on Minnesota’s Somalis, most of whom are refugees, after revelations that some individuals were involved in a multimillion-dollar social-services fraud scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All refugees, once admitted to the United States, must apply for a green card within one year, but some fail to do so — sometimes because they cannot afford it or have challenges with red tape. Those who miss the deadline retain their refugee status, and in the past were not subject to arrest or threatened with deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has never been a systematic effort to re-examine refugees,” said Barbara Strack, a former senior refugee official who served under Republican and Democratic administrations. ”There was a recognition that refugees had been highly vetted overseas before they were admitted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In rare instances, she said, refugee status might have been re-examined if evidence-based leads raised suspicions of fraud in the application process or criminal or national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Saturday, a group of refugees represented by two immigrant-rights advocacy organizations and a private law firm filed a federal class-action lawsuit in Minnesota challenging the arrest and imprisonment of refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit said that the refugees had not been charged with crimes or with any violations of immigration statutes, and that the government was using the operation to “trigger a mass termination of refugee status” and to make refugees vulnerable to deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This goal represents an egregious and unlawful betrayal of the promise made to refugees, pursuant to the Refugee Act of 1980 to offer safety, stability and a path to a safe home,” the suit said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times has reviewed court records of three refugees swept up in the arrest operation in recent weeks who were not part of the suit. In one, a Somali refugee was arrested outside his workplace in Minnesota on Jan. 14. Lawyers obtained a court order blocking his movement from Minnesota. The next day, he told his family he had been moved to El Paso. The court later ordered the government to return him to Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another man, from Moldova, was arrested in Minneapolis and moved to Texas on Jan. 16. He was a refugee who entered the United States in 2023 and had applied for a green card. A federal court judge ordered his release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court found that the man had “submitted ample evidence in support of his refugee status and his pending adjustment application.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Accordingly,” the court said, “there is no lawful basis for petitioner’s detention, and the court orders his immediate release.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases reviewed by The Times, the refugees had applied for green cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some refugees have been released after hourslong interviews in Texas, often with only the shirts on their backs, their documents still with Immigration and Customs Enforcement in St. Paul. Family and friends have scrambled to buy them bus and plane tickets home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walid Ali, 19, also from Eritrea, was arrested outside his home in St. Paul on Jan. 13 and transferred to a holding facility where ICE is processing the refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They took my wallet, my phone, my social, driver’s license, everything,” said Mr. Ali, who arrived in the United States as an unaccompanied refugee minor in 2023. Friends and relatives paid for a flight back from Houston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ali said that he protested when his belongings were confiscated, and that agents responded by pushing him to the ground, kneeling on him and beating him. His uncle, who is a nurse, said he had made an appointment at a clinic to check his nephew’s neck, shoulders and back, as well as to have his ribs X-rayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not the American way, to grab people from the street and violate their rights, hit them,” said the uncle, Sal Gimiy, 51.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resettlement groups said the unpredictability of the tactics employed has amplified the fear rippling through refugee communities. While agents sometimes seek specific people, other times they seem to strike at random. They have knocked on doors and arrested an adult or an entire family, and have picked up people from grocery stores and city streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are hearing from a lot of families about their immense fear and confusion about what is happening,” said Rebekah Phillips, the executive director of Arrive Ministries, a local resettlement agency. “They are afraid to send kids to school, attend work. They don’t know if they will be detained, or redetained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refugees are often being questioned without the chance to prepare or to contact a lawyer, according to advocates and resettlement agencies. The groups were aware of refugees who have been released but many remain detained, they said, and did not know whether any had been deported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The refugees who have been detained described being subjected to a jarring and bewildering process. Ms. Mehari, who works at the Minneapolis airport packing meals for airlines, spent five days in custody, first in St. Paul and then in Houston. Along the way, she was given conflicting information about her fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her children did not hear from her until late in the afternoon on Jan. 13, the day she was arrested, when she was permitted to make a call from an ICE facility in St. Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I kept telling my mother not to sign anything,” her daughter, Yosan, recalled. Her mother had already applied for a green card, and Yosan suggested authorities could check her files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with The Times, Ms. Mehari said she was told at the facility that she would be transferred to Texas and then deported to Eritrea. Do you want to take your kids with you, an officer asked, according to her recollection. “No, no, no,” she responded, insisting she had a friend who could care for the 13- and 14-year-old, who was not home when she was detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a call to that friend shortly after, an officer explained that Ms. Mehari had been detained because she had not adjusted her status and her case would be reassessed, the friend, Elsa Zerai, said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari, who has been living in the United States since 2023, was baffled, she said. To work at the airport, she wears a badge that whisks her through security checkpoints for her shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival in Texas on Jan. 14, she said she was issued prison garb and rubber slippers, and locked in a frigid room with other women. There were mattresses on the floor and thin metallic sheets to huddle under. She said she lost track of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari clung to her Christian faith. “God, help us,” she prayed. “What will become of me, my children?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, she was escorted to an interview room, where an immigration official questioned her for three hours with an interpreter on the line translating into Tigrinya. He asked about her history, her fears of returning to her homeland and her reasons for seeking refuge in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were familiar questions — ones she had answered when she was screened to come to the United States, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she was returned to the cell, Ms. Mehari had no idea if she had passed or failed. She was allowed one brief call home during which she wept before the line was cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, one day, she was abruptly ordered to change back into her street clothes. It was Saturday, Jan. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari was released alongside several other men and women, all refugees. “I screamed: ‘I’m free! I’m free,” Ms. Mehari recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without money and identification, they had to make it home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yosan sent an acquaintance in Houston $255 to buy a plane ticket for her mother, and she sent screenshots of her mother’s immigration papers to his phone to show airport security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that day, the family learned that her green card had been approved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Sunday,Ms. Mehari still did not have her documents or her favorite gold chain, which the authorities confiscated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caroline Yang contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-minnesota-refugees.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:09:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Parts of Minneapolis Carry On, but Talk of Killings Is Everywhere</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-shootings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-nat-minn-talk-qwkf/25minneapolis-ice-nat-minn-talk-qwkf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A crowd of dozens cheered when the final buzzer sounded at the U.S. Pond Hockey Championships on Sunday, an event that had drawn teams from 20 states to a frozen lake in a city that remained in the throes of a contentious immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hockey players and fans bundled up to their eyes chatted around the empty rinks, or filtered back to their cars hauling oversized duffel bags. Just a day earlier in Minneapolis, several miles across town, the streets had been littered with tear gas canisters and crowd control munitions, after a second fatal shooting by federal law enforcement agents touched off a wave of unrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even at the hockey tournament, removed from the conflicts that have left pockets of the Twin Cities resembling war zones, the clashes were at the top of everyone’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are trying to get out there as much as I think they can, yet still feeling scared, and I think still feeling really helpless,” said Mark Holloway, 48, of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As escalating clashes between federal agents and residents continue to rattle Minneapolis, life elsewhere in the city — in its parks, its downtown core, its quiet neighborhoods — has continued. But several people who spoke to The New York Times across Minneapolis over the weekend said that the issue had overshadowed daily life, if only as an undercurrent of fear, and was a constant subject of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Holloway was among the spectators heading to the parking lot as the hockey tournament wrapped up on the shores of Lake Nokomis on the city’s south side. He said the immigration sweep had directly touched his family and his community. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents had shown up on the grounds of his son’s high school, he said, and his neighbors who feared they could be profiled as immigrants based on their appearance had started carrying passports for fear of being detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a 48-year-old white guy,” Mr. Holloway said, his breath turning to vapor in the subzero temperatures. “And I don’t feel really safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several visitors to the city — who had flown in from as far as Colorado, Utah and Texas — said that recent events had been top of mind for them when they arrived. But their trips, so far, had been largely without disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing around a fire pit beside the rinks, Nate Jackson, 40, and Casey Donovan, 39, visiting hockey players from Texas, said they had arrived in Minneapolis expecting to find a city in chaos. So far, though, they hadn’t seen any signs of unrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching from afar, the two men said that though they supported law enforcement, they felt the conflicts were unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think it’s all parties involved, on that one,” Mr. Donovan said. “There’s not a single person to point a finger at.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Cooler heads could prevail, but it just seems like that’s not even an option,” Mr. Jackson added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they left the event, many attendees drove past the intersection of Cedar Avenue and East Minnehaha Parkway, where protesters held signs denouncing ICE. Kyle Ness, 56, of Minneapolis, was among them. He said he had been protesting on and off for some time, but was compelled to be even more involved in the demonstrations after federal agents shot and killed a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident, Alex Pretti, on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The collateral damage that’s coming from their extreme anger toward people exercising their rights, like in the case of Alex — that’s what really got me mad,” Mr. Ness said of the federal agents in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impacts of the immigration crackdown resonated even more deeply in the Cedar-Riverside neighborhood, known by locals as Little Mogadishu for its high concentration of residents of Somalian heritage. Few pedestrians were out early Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Afrik Grocery African Market, the co-manager Mohamed Ahmed said the crackdown had left his store quieter than ever, as his customers were afraid to go out shopping. Even the suppliers who kept his shelves stocked were affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The suppliers don’t have drivers,” said Mr. Ahmed, a native of Somalia who said he had lived in Minneapolis for more than 20 years. His shelf that usually holds injera, a staple of Ethiopian cuisine, sat empty on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Minneapolis’s downtown core later Saturday afternoon, protesters toted signs as they dispersed through the quiet streets. On the floor of the city’s convention center, visitors toured lavishly outfitted pontoons on display at the Minneapolis boat show. Khaleel Thompson, 26, stood by the doors waiting to meet a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Thompson said he had steered clear of the protests, knowing how quickly things could escalate, and had not followed events in the city very closely. Aside from glimpses of the demonstrations, he had not felt the impacts of the immigration enforcement operation on his daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the deaths of Renee Good, the 37-year-old woman killed by an ICE agent in Minneapolis earlier this month, and Mr. Pretti on Saturday, he felt it would best if the agents left Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those people didn’t have to die,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-shootings.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:21:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonstrators Enter Hotel Vestibule, Setting Off a Fracas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/demonstrators-hotel-ice-confrontation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-hotel-agents-qhjk/26minneapolis-ice-hotel-agents-qhjk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What began as a noise demonstration outside of a Home2Suites by Hilton hotel near the University of Minnesota became heated on Sunday night as protesters were met with dozens of federal agents and tear gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 8 p.m., after about an hour of peaceful protesting, some began vandalizing the building with messages like “ICE OUT” as others hurled objects at the windows. As people began entering the hotel vestibule, two employees and a single Minneapolis police officer tried to calm the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hotel guests, many in masks like those worn by federal immigration agents, began gathering in the lobby. Two men pushed vending machines to block the glass front doors. By 9 p.m., many of the protesters had left, and about 50 protesters remained on the street in front of the hotel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, the Minnesota Police Department said that as the protesters became disorderly, police officers and officers from assisting agencies “began moving in to surround the crowd, give dispersal orders and prepare for mass arrests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal forces arrived without warning, the Police Department said, and deployed tear gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two dozen armed federal agents entered the hotel around 10 p.m. They left about an hour later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis police officers did not fire any chemical munitions, according to the statement, and federal officials refused help from the Police Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two men were detained by the police and released, the department said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/demonstrators-hotel-ice-confrontation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:33:05 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>