<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 04:39:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>After Renee Good’s Killing, Some Conservatives Scorn Liberal Women</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/white-women-conservatives.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16nat-awful-1-wpcm/16nat-awful-1-wpcm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A makeshift memorial near the site where Renee Good was shot and killed in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/white-women-conservatives.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 06:32:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Trump Veto Leaves Republicans in Colorado Parched and Bewildered</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/colorado-water-trump-veto.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17nat-colo-water-ed-1-wkbj/17nat-colo-water-ed-1-wkbj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Ed Brown can’t consume water that comes out of the tap at his house because it is contaminated with unsafe levels of radium and uranium. He fills jugs of drinking water at Rocky Ford Food Market in Rocky Ford, Colo.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/colorado-water-trump-veto.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 09:01:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The People of Minneapolis vs. ICE: A Street-Level View</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/minneapolis-protests-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17nat-minneapolis-scene-top-maybe-qbmk/17nat-minneapolis-scene-top-maybe-qbmk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal agents detained a man along Lake Street in Minneapolis on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/minneapolis-protests-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:52:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Announces New Tariffs on Some European Countries in Greenland Standoff</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/trump-eu-tariffs-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17dc-tariffs-greenland-topart-ctfl/17dc-tariffs-greenland-topart-ctfl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump said the new tariff would increase to 25 percent on June 1 if his demands were not met.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/trump-eu-tariffs-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:56:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Conservative Influencer Chased From Minneapolis Streets by Counterprotesters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/minneapolis-protests-immigration-fraud.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17nat-minn-protest-fzjw/17nat-minn-protest-fzjw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small protest organized by a conservative influencer in downtown Minneapolis on Saturday was quickly overwhelmed by a liberal counterprotest, as both sides scuffled and exchanged taunts for hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The influencer, Jake Lang, who was among the pardoned Jan. 6 rioters, was eventually chased into the lobby of a hotel by a throng of counterprotesters who threw water balloons at him when outside temperatures hovered around 10 degrees, prompting police officers to respond. Mr. Lang was seen with a trickle of blood on the back of his head before disappearing into the hotel. It was unclear how he suffered the injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counterprotest, led by The People’s Action Coalition Against Trump, vastly outnumbered the people gathered by Mr. Lang for his March Against Minnesota Fraud. Mr. Lang had vowed to burn a Quran and march through a neighborhood with a heavy Somali population, but apparently did not follow through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators who had gathered in opposition to Mr. Lang also denounced Immigration and Customs Enforcement, holding signs that read “ICE Out of Minnesota.” They blasted music from the Disney musical “Frozen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis police officers and Hennepin County sheriff’s deputies amassed in downtown Minneapolis in large numbers to monitor the protests, which drew hundreds of attendees by early afternoon and lasted for close to two hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Anderson, 42, stood in the cold for hours, frozen droplets clinging to his beard. He said he was there to protest fraud and illegal immigration and had traveled from his home in Forest Lake, a town about 30 minutes outside Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have nothing against immigration as long as it’s legal,” he said, adding that his fiancée is a legal immigrant from Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests capped a tumultuous 10 days in Minneapolis, after an immigration agent shot and killed Renee Good, 37, on Jan. 7. Since then, thousands of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents have fanned out around the Twin Cities, arresting people for immigration violations, interrogating U.S. citizens and deploying tear gas and pepper balls in residential neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lang’s protest opposing fraud was directed at a wide-ranging investigation into Minnesota’s social services programs. Most of the people charged in the scheme so far have been of Somali origin. A preliminary assessment suggests that billions in taxpayer funds spent on programs intended to help low-income people since 2018 was most likely stolen, federal prosecutors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lang could not immediately be reached for comment after he left the protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, a federal judge restricted the actions of immigration agents toward protesters in the state, ordering agents not to retaliate against people “engaging in peaceful and unobstructive protest activity,” and to refrain from using pepper spray or other “crowd dispersal tools” in retaliation for protected speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge also said agents could not stop or detain protesters in vehicles who were not “forcibly obstructing or interfering” with agents.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/minneapolis-protests-immigration-fraud.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 12:39:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shooting at Historic New Orleans Restaurant Leaves One Dead, Several Wounded</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/shooting-at-historic-new-orleans-restaurant-leaves-one-dead-several-wounded.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17nat-nola-shooting-updatetopart-cpbv/17nat-nola-shooting-updatetopart-cpbv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four people were shot on Friday night, and one was killed, at a historic restaurant in New Orleans during the city’s busy Mardi Gras season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site of the shooting, Dooky Chase’s, is a fixture in the city’s Treme neighborhood and a nationally known culinary landmark with deep ties to its Black community. Civil rights leaders convened at the restaurant for decades, and in more recent years, Presidents George W. Bush and Barack Obama each dined there while in office. It was long headed by Leah Chase, a member of New Orleans restaurateur royalty who died in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authorities said the restaurant itself was not the target of the shooting, which took place around 8 p.m. on Friday. Rather, the gunman pursued a person into the establishment, fired several shots that struck bystanders and then fled the scene. One person was killed, and the police continue to search for the gunman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The person who was the target simply ran into the restaurant, where he collapsed, and unfortunately the perpetrator continued to shoot, so innocent bystanders who were patrons were actually hit,” the New Orleans police superintendent, Anne Kirkpatrick, said at a news conference on Friday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About an hour after the shooting, yellow police tape was draped from Dooky Chase’s front door, across two lanes of the adjacent Orleans Avenue and into the median. Roughly a dozen police cars blocked off part of the street. The surrounding residential neighborhood was hushed while reporters and bystanders huddled in the cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the attack, the shooter initially left the scene but briefly returned before fleeing again, Ms. Kirkpatrick said. The authorities are now asking local residents to check their doorbell cameras and to come forward with any information that could aid the search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Saturday afternoon, the authorities were offering a $5,000 reward for information leading to the capture of the shooter The Times-Picayune/NOLA.com reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“During the 85 years that this restaurant has been established here, there’s never been any kind of incident like this,” Mayor Helena Moreno told reporters at the news conference. “This was a very targeted event toward one person.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Treme neighborhood is a bastion of Black and Créole culture, and was the setting of an HBO television series created by David Simon and Eric Overmyer. The restaurant is within walking distance of the city’s French Quarter, where Bourbon Street — the site of an attack that killed 14 people a year ago — was busy with tourists on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting occurred less than two weeks into Mardi Gras season, the city’s biggest tourist draw of the year, which will continue through Feb. 17. National Guard troops remain deployed in the city, a month after President Trump sent federal agents to sweep New Orleans in an immigration enforcement crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/shooting-at-historic-new-orleans-restaurant-leaves-one-dead-several-wounded.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:46:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>These Are the 12 States Vying to Kick Off Democrats’ 2028 Contest</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/2028-democratic-primary-states-iowa-south-carolina-nevada-new-hampshire.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18pol-dems-2028-fgwv/18pol-dems-2028-fgwv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa Democrats said they would fix the problems that torpedoed their last competitive presidential caucus. Nevada Democrats pointed to their state’s large population of politically crucial Latino voters. And Delaware Democrats said their small state was easy to drive across.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats in 12 states have applied to kick off the party’s 2028 presidential primary contest, pushing arguments about race, geography, size, diversity, the rural-urban divide and their relative status as battlegrounds, according to copies of hundreds of pages of application materials reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Democratic National Committee, which will decide the order, has said that one state from each of four regions will hold nominating contests in the so-called early window, the month before Super Tuesday. A bonus fifth state could also be selected. State parties in these places applied:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;West: Nevada and New Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South: Georgia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Midwest: Illinois, Iowa and Michigan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;East: New Hampshire and Delaware&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some state parties — including in Iowa, New Hampshire, South Carolina, Nevada and North Carolina — wrote in their applications that they hoped to be placed at the very front of the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications ranged in length. North Carolina’s was a crisp nine pages, while Iowa’s stretched for 120 pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there were some subtle regional digs: Delaware Democrats took aim at New Hampshire, arguing that their small state had grown faster and was more racially diverse than the heavily white Granite State, the longtime home of the first-in-the-nation primary election. New Hampshire Democrats seemed aware they would face such criticism, arguing that their state was growing more diverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several state parties included letters of support from influential figures and groups, including Planned Parenthood and local business organizations. Two states — Michigan and Illinois — offered support from their governors, Gretchen Whitmer and JB Pritzker, who are seen as potential 2028 presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Ken Burns, the award-winning documentary filmmaker, jumped into the fray with a letter offering his support for New Hampshire, where he has lived for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rules and Bylaws Committee of the D.N.C. had set a deadline of Friday for states to apply. The panel’s members are set to meet this month in Puerto Rico to discuss the applicants. Here are the highlights of the pitches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats in Nevada made a case that their state would be the best proving ground for a tough general election because it would force presidential primary candidates to appeal to Latino voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We cannot afford to have overwhelmingly college-educated, white, or less competitive states kick off the process of selecting our party’s nominee,” they wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevada has competition from New Mexico, whose Democrats argued that their state is cheap and racially diverse, with large numbers of Latino and Native American voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state has also bucked national trends, its Democrats wrote. While most rural states with lower percentages of college-educated voters have become more Republican, New Mexico has remained deeply blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“New Mexico provides the Democratic Party with a low-cost, high-value test of general-election readiness,” state Democrats wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Carolina, which former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. moved to the first position for the 2024 election, is vying to keep that coveted slot. Democrats there called the state “a proven, disciplined, and consequential first test of presidential candidates” and pointed to its large numbers of Black voters and Black women in particular, “who are among the most consistent and influential voters in Democratic general elections nationwide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The knock on South Carolina has been that the state is too Republican to hold such a central role in elevating the next Democratic presidential nominee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Carolina suggested that it was central to the Democratic Party’s future nationwide, noting that partisan gerrymandering of congressional lines in the battleground state before the 2024 election helped give Republicans their current narrow House majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Putting North Carolina first isn’t just a 2 year strategy,” the party wrote. “It’s a 20 year strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One hurdle is that Republican lawmakers in North Carolina would need to approve shifting the primary date. Democratic officials wrote that their conversations with Republicans had been “limited” but that there had been “positive indications.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Georgia would also need Republican approval. Democrats there made a different argument about the viability of moving the primary date: “Georgia Democrats are confident that Georgia will elect a Democratic Governor and Secretary of State,” they wrote of the 2026 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennessee’s plea was more about transforming the solidly red state to make it more blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“On its face, Tennessee would seem like an odd choice,” state Democrats wrote. Yet an early spot “could and would be the single most impactful and organic data investment in our state voter file ever.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Virginia positioned itself as a racially diverse testing ground for candidates and a state that knows how to hold elections — since it does so every year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Virginia is never ‘spinning up’ an election apparatus. We are always operating,” state Democrats wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa, which had held its caucuses first for 50 years until 2024, argued that its should not be excluded because of its disastrous 2020 caucuses, when a technology meltdown and widespread errors put in question the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state Democratic Party, it wrote in its application, “will report the total number of presidential preferences from caucus-goers and not require extensive math from precinct chairs. Additionally, we will not use any kind of phone application for reporting results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illinois Democrats tried to downplay their state’s solidly blue status, noting that a Republican won an election for governor of the state as recently as 2014. “​​There is a common misconception that Illinois can be taken for granted,” they wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michigan, which moved into the first month of voting in 2024, is hoping to stay there. Unlike Iowa or Illinois, the state is a perennial battleground. In its pitch, it argued that no other state could “lay claim to playing as significant a role in a winning national coalition for Democrats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Hampshire, which held the first-in-the-nation primary election for roughly a century, argued that it remained uniquely suited for the role despite its lack of racial diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“New Hampshire should go first not simply because of tradition,” state Democrats wrote. “There is no other state that better meets the efficiency, rigorousness, and fairness criteria needed in our presidential nominating process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state party also wrote that the state is cheap, accessible and small, served by a single television station that reaches nearly all voters, and that candidates there must test their mettle with retail campaigning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one other Eastern state applied. Delaware was explicit about drawing demographic contrasts with New Hampshire, pointing to its “substantially larger Black population,” “greater racial and ethnic diversity overall” and “higher share of women voters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaware also bragged that its small size made stumping easy. “Driving the entire length of the state takes about two hours,” state Democrats wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/2028-democratic-primary-states-iowa-south-carolina-nevada-new-hampshire.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:43:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virginia’s New Governor Moves Swiftly to Overhaul State University Boards</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/spanberger-virginia-uva-board.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17nat-UVA-board-pkwl/17nat-UVA-board-pkwl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Abigail Spanberger of Virginia lost no time on Saturday in altering the tenor of the board that controls the University of Virginia, appointing 10 new members to the 17-member body within hours of being inaugurated. She also acted to revamp the boards of two other state schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before, she had asked five board members at the University of Virginia, all appointees of her Republican predecessor, Gov. Glenn Youngkin, to step aside. The swift change in university leadership followed more than a year of partisan acrimony over the university’s direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservative members of the school’s board, in alliance with the Trump administration, had moved successfully last summer to remove James E. Ryan from the university presidency, largely because of his support for diversity initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, the Youngkin-appointed board prompted strong objections from the university’s faculty by signing an agreement with the Trump administration to eliminate diversity programs, which the government had argued were illegally discriminatory, and to follow the administration’s prescriptions for university admissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the objections of Ms. Spanberger, who had asked for a delay, the board rushed to replace Mr. Ryan before she was inaugurated, giving Scott C. Beardsley, the dean of the university’s business school, a five-year contract to serve as president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By forcing the resignations of the five members, who included the board’s chair, vice-chair, and a donor who had given $100 million, Ms. Spanberger, an alumna of the university, gained influence over the university much faster than new governors usually do. Ordinarily, governors have the opportunity to appoint just four new members in each year of their four-year terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Sheridan, a lawyer who served as the university’s rector, or board chair, offered a parting note of concern in her letter of resignation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have come to believe,” she wrote in the letter, which was made public on Saturday, “that our efforts to do what is right for U.Va. have become paralyzed through purposeful political warfare that is dangerous to the university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were already five vacancies on the board before the resignations because Democrats in the state legislature had refused to approve some of Mr. Youngkin’s appointees. The new governor, consequently, had 10 slots she could fill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new members include Carlos Brown, a utility executive; Peter Grant, a private equity executive who once led a successful fund-raising campaign for the university; and Victoria Harker, a former publishing and broadcast executive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Mr. Brown and Ms. Harker have previously served on the board, which is known as the Board of Visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Spanberger also announced the appointment on Saturday of new board members at George Mason University and the Virginia Military Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At George Mason, the state’s largest public university, the Trump administration had worked with Youngkin-appointed board members in an unsuccessful attempt to oust the university’s president, Gregory N. Washington, a champion of diversity programs. Ms. Spanberger appointed 12 new members to the school’s board on Saturday, including Tom Davis, a former Republican congressman who had previously served.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the chairman of the George Mason board, Charles Stimson, a Heritage Foundation official, had submitted his resignation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Virginia Military Institute, where conservatives on the board declined last year to renew the appointment of the school’s leader, Maj. Gen. Cedric T. Wins, Ms. Spanberger appointed five new members, including Ralph Northam, a former Democratic governor of the state.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/us/politics/spanberger-virginia-uva-board.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:56:31 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>