<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:11:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Administration Social Media Posts Echo White Supremacist Messaging</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-altright-bczq/26nat-altright-bczq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The posts have referred to neo-Nazi literature, ethnic cleansing and QAnon conspiracies, mused about deporting nearly a third of the U.S. population, and promoted lyrics from an anthem bellowed by the far-right militants of the Proud Boys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their authors are not on society’s fringe. They are in the offices of the White House and the departments of Homeland Security and Labor, using official government accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some people, the administration’s posts sound patriotic. Others might sense at most a faint dog whistle to extremists. Some posts may just look odd. But those well-versed in the abstruse codes of right-wing extremism hear klaxons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, the White House and the Department of Homeland Security jointly posted a recruitment ad for Immigration and Customs Enforcement on Instagram, Facebook and X, overlaid with the words “WE’LL HAVE OUR HOME AGAIN.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s also the name of a song, written by members of a self-described “pro-White fraternal order,” that has been embraced by the Proud Boys and other white-nationalist groups. Hundreds of explicitly neo-Nazi and white-supremacist accounts have shared the song on Telegram, an encrypted messaging app, since 2020. The white supremacist who killed three Black people at a Jacksonville, Fla., dollar store in 2023 included lyrics from the song in his writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are two types of people to whom these messages will quickly look familiar,” Oren Segal, a vice president for counterextremism at the Anti-Defamation League, said of the panoply of postings, “white supremacists, and those who study white supremacists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Homeland Security spokeswoman, Tricia McLaughlin, said that if the ICE recruiting post were actually about the song, it “would be a problem” and “morally repugnant.” But, she said, the post had no relation to the white-supremacist anthem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are plenty of references to those words in books and poems,” she said, adding that she was “in charge of everything” posted on the department’s social media accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when the post was opened on Instagram’s mobile app, audio from the chorus of the song played in the background. After a reporter pointed this out, Ms. McLaughlin said The Times was participating in a left-wing conspiracy theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m telling you it’s not there,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than 40 minutes after the interview on Thursday, the Instagram post — including audio from the song — disappeared from social media. Posts on X and Facebook, which did not include an audio component, are still visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was The Times, Ms. McLaughlin said, that was “mainstreaming racism” by tying the agency’s post to the white nationalist anthem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Hanania, a political scientist who once wrote for white-nationalist publications under a pseudonym before moderating his views, said such accusations were part of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They do everything up to the line; it’s kind of clever,” he said. “‘We’ll Have Our Home Again’ is a white-nationalist song.” He added that to his knowledge, no other groups would use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past month, government agencies have made dozens more social-media posts that include iconography associated with far-right extremist groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As President Trump escalated his campaign to seize control of Greenland this month, the White House’s X account posted an image of a crossroads, with a sun-drenched White House on the left and Russia and China to the right. The caption read, “Which way, Greenland man?” Last year, an ICE recruitment post on Homeland Security’s X account asked, “Which way, American man?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slogans echo the title of a 1978 book — “Which Way Western Man?” — that white-supremacist groups treat “as foundational,” said Robert Futrell, a sociologist at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas. The book claims that Jewish people are plotting to destroy Western civilization, that Adolf Hitler was right and that violence against Jews is justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, the Labor Department posted a noir-style image with the words “TRUST THE PLAN.” That’s also a central catchphrase of QAnon, an internet conspiracy theory that falsely claims the world is run by a cabal of Satan-worshiping pedophiles, and that Mr. Trump has been chosen to sunder it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On New Year’s Eve, the White House’s X account posted a photo of Mr. Trump alongside the word “remigration.” That is a decades-old European concept centered on the expulsion of nonwhite people and immigrants deemed “unassimilated,” said Wendy Via, co-founder of the Global Project Against Hate and Extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tens of thousands of Germans protested the concept two years ago after the country’s far-right Alternative für Deutschland party secretly met with neo-Nazis to discuss plans to implement it. (More than a dozen AfD politicians have reposted Mr. Trump’s “remigration” photo on X.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month, the Labor Department posted a video captioned “One Homeland. One People. One Heritage.” That phrase resembled a German slogan used by Nazis during World War II, “Ein Volk, Ein Reich, Ein Führer,” or “One People, One Realm, One Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Labor did not respond to multiple requests for comment, but Abigail Jackson, a White House spokeswoman, dismissed any connections between the government posts and extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems that the mainstream media has become a meme of their own: the deranged leftist who claims everything they dislike must be Nazi propaganda,” she said, adding, “Get a grip.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who study the online right said one or two posts might be coincidental. But “when you add it all together,” said William Braniff, director of the Polarization and Extremism Research and Innovation Lab at American University, “it’s much harder to dismiss.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other experts were equally certain the apparent allusions were not an accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people used to be in the dark corners of the internet,” said Jessie Daniels, a sociologist at Hunter College who has studied online extremism for 30 years. “Now, they are holding public office.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the draw of the posts could be their potentially secret codes and numerological clues, especially in the recruitment images. They appear to be an appeal to “a very specific segment” of Americans, young men who live online and are disaffected by what they see as unwanted changes in American life, said Peter Simi, a Chapman University sociologist who studies extremist groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shirin Sinnar, a Stanford law professor who studies the legal treatment of political violence, said “they are plainly trying to recruit a segment of the population that’s moved by this rhetoric.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, Mr. Trump and his campaign have dealt with and rejected accusations that officials in the Trump inner circle were surreptitiously appealing to racists and antisemites. A Twitter post by the candidate in 2016 depicting Hillary Clinton beside a Jewish star, before piles of money, had previously appeared on a message board known for antisemitism and white supremacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s final campaign commercial that year featured grainy images of George Soros, the liberal American financier; Janet L. Yellen, then the chairwoman of the Federal Reserve; and Lloyd C. Blankfein, then the chairman of Goldman Sachs — all of them Jewish — as Mr. Trump warned darkly about the “global special interests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s just a straight line between these ideas and the modern Trump administration,” Mr. Hanania said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration is “mobilizing these people and having them flood Twitter and create this environment that they’re winning,” he said. “The fact that the media and liberals react so strongly to this is kind of a badge of honor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Greer, a right-wing podcaster and writer who considers himself part of the “online right” that these posts are ostensibly targeting, is not so sure of the administration’s motivation. Some on the Internet-obsessed right think the posts “are meant to bamboozle them into liking Trump,” he said. For his part, he added, even though some of the posts go “too far with what the normal, not-so-online MAGA base may be for,” he now thinks they reflect the broader trend of politicians “taking this more irreverent tone and using memes from the right and left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We accept it as more a normal part of politics,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Republican leaders vehemently denounce antisemitism, and the Trump administration has put pressure on universities and other parts of American society to protect Jews from hate speech and attacks. But in recent months, some members of the party have openly wrestled with whether to reject some Trump supporters who have made antisemitic, bigoted or extremist remarks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked in December whether far-right extremists and conspiracy theorists should be embraced as part of the Trump coalition, Vice President JD Vance declined to rule them out. In contrast, Mr. Trump said of antisemites in an interview this month with The Times, “I think we don’t need them,” emphasizing, “I think we don’t like them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, most of the social media posts remain, despite the scrutiny over possible allusions to extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read by Evan Gorelick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio produced by Adrienne Hurst.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:24:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An American Street</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/us/nat-minn-oneimage-promo/nat-minn-oneimage-promo-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In One Image An American Street By David Guttenfelder and Thomas Gibbons-Neff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In south Minneapolis, snow and ice still blanketed Nicollet Avenue when federal agents fanned out and started tackling heckling protesters on Saturday, about a block away from where Alex Pretti was shot and killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Shame!” the protesters yelled. “Why did you murder another one of our neighbors?” they said. The agents charged, launching gas canisters, yelling at the protesters. “Get back!” “Get out of the street!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agents grabbed a protester who had only a painter’s mask covering his mouth and little else to protect himself from the gas. He gasped, choking for air as he was cuffed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing in front of him was a federal agent armed with a grenade launcher, used here for launching tear gas or smoke. The agent also carried a Glock handgun with two spare magazines, a stun gun and a spare magazine for an AR-15-style rifle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detritus left behind tells the story of deep-winter protests in subzero weather: a warm hat, a shirt, Kirkland chewy bars and hand warmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nestled in the snow were two grenades for tear gas and smoke. Without traditional policing tactics, federal agents rely on these tools to push back protesters and onlookers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another federal agent is seen with his grenade launcher almost at his shoulder. His equipment is not uniform. His outfit — including the patch on his helmet, Nike shoes and his vest’s camouflage pattern — mirrors a distinct look promoted by military influencers selling products to newer generations eager to define themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supported by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In One Image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By David Guttenfelder and Thomas Gibbons-Neff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the Minneapolis area appears normal. There are no signs of unrest. But an aggressive immigration crackdown by heavily armed federal agents has led to clashes with a population that largely rejects their presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two centuries ago, Nicollet Avenue was a military route, connecting St. Anthony Falls to Fort Snelling. Over the weekend, it became the stage for a violent confrontation between protesters and the government’s military-like law enforcement operation in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vigil for Mr. Pretti was held on Saturday night about a block from where this photograph was taken. Nicollet Avenue is quiet now, but the city remains in a defensive crouch, unsure where the next battle will erupt.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:11:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Trump Promotes Economy in Iowa, Many Residents Feel Pain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump headed to Iowa on Tuesday to once again try to convince Americans that he is focused on “affordability.” He had some explaining to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa, a state whose economy is heavily reliant on farming, has been struggling under the weight of Mr. Trump’s economic policies, particularly his approach to trade. The president’s barrage of tariffs last year increased the cost of machinery and materials that many Iowan farmers rely on. The price of the metal bins used to store crops soared, along with the cost of tractors as the president’s tariffs took hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump hit China with tariffs, Beijing swiftly retaliated by halting purchases of American farm products, a move that cut off Iowa soybean exporters from their biggest buyer. That put the squeeze on the entire state’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the economy at an event in Clive, Iowa, on Tuesday, Mr. Trump defended his trade policies and told supporters that he was saving farmers money by slashing burdensome environmental regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m standing up for the workers and the farmers of our country like no other president has ever,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president added that the trade deals that he has reached have opened up international markets to American farmers, ranchers and agricultural producers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re going to see it starting to kick in now for the farmers,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many, however, the intended benefits of Mr. Trump’s policies are not kicking in soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a dire time for American farmers, particularly the Midwest soybean and corn farmers,” said Kirk Leeds, the chief executive of the Iowa Soybean Association. “The chaos, the uncertainty — right now we have so many unknowns that there’s not a lot of clarity about where we’re going.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa is of particular importance to Mr. Trump. The state helped propel his political career a decade ago, when he had a strong showing in the 2016 Republican caucuses. He won the state in all three of his general election campaigns. Perhaps more important to Mr. Trump now is that the state could prove pivotal in this year’s midterm elections, as Republicans try to retain their majority. Senator Joni Ernst, Republican of Iowa, is retiring, and the race to replace her is expected to be close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Chuck Grassley, the veteran Iowa Republican who has been critical of Mr. Trump’s tariffs, welcomed the president’s visit this week and said he would continue to work with the Trump administration to improve affordability for Iowans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump’s trade wars have in many respects been a drag on the state, which for years has lagged behind the rest of the country in economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has long been a big buyer of U.S. soybeans and other crops that are grown in Iowa. That changed last year after Mr. Trump increased tariffs on imports from China, triggering a monthslong tit-for-tat trade fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite negotiations and temporary traded truces, China continued to use farm purchases as leverage and Beijing’s refusal to buy American agricultural products for most of 2025 dealt a blow to Iowa’s soybean industry, one of the largest in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and Xi Jinping, the Chinese leader, eventually agreed in late October to a one-year truce that ended China’s boycott of farm products, including millions of tons of soybeans. The Trump administration also unveiled a $12 billion aid package for farmers, but for many farmers the relief was insufficient and too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re losing money on every bushel we produce on our two main things that we grow,” said Aaron Lehman, the president of the Iowa Farmers Union, referring to corn and soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have said that China fulfilled its initial commitment to Mr. Trump to buy 12 million metric tons of soybeans. It has also pledged to purchase 25 million metric tons per year for the next three years. The 25 million tons were in line with the 25 million to 30 million it had purchased in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said last week that he encouraged his Chinese counterpart to buy additional soybeans during a meeting on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crop receipts in Iowa were on track to fall 4 percent, or $666 million, in 2025 from last year and they are projected to hold steady this year, according to a report published last October by the Rural &amp; Farm Finance Policy Analysis Center. There were 18 farm bankruptcies in the state through last October, the highest total since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America’s rural economies have been struggling in recent years, and Iowa is no exception. Since 2021, Iowa’s economy has grown at an annual rate of about 1 percent while the United States has grown at an average annual rate of 2.5 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since retaking the White House last year, Mr. Trump and his advisers have said that the administration’s policies will usher in a new “golden age” for America. Mr. Lehman said such suggestions feel out of touch to Iowa farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The policy leaders are not understanding the situation on the ground,” Mr. Lehman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Trump administration policies have also created challenges over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Budget cuts to the Department of Agriculture and the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program, which buys food from American farmers, have been hard on Iowa’s agriculture sector, Mr. Lehman added. The lapse of Affordable Care Act subsidies is leading to higher health care costs. And immigration restrictions have made it harder for farmers to find workers in a state where the population has been shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble in the farm economy has spread to other sectors in Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Deere, the agricultural machinery company, said last September that it would cut more than 140 jobs at two plants in Iowa because of decreased demand for equipment. Case New Holland, a construction equipment manufacturer, said this week that it was cutting about 200 jobs at a plant in Burlington. Overall, the state lost 1,300 manufacturing jobs in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Orazem, an economist at Iowa State University, noted that the state’s manufacturing industries are closely tied to how farmers are faring. He said that forecasts for 2026 remain murky because of uncertainty over trade policy and whether government support for farmers will continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Restrictions on trade makes your market less lucrative,” Mr. Orazem said. “You’re getting squeezed on the demand side and getting squeezed on the supply side. That doesn’t bode well for firm profit.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:49:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Safety Board Blames F.A.A. For Multiple Failures in D.C. Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Transportation Safety Board determined that the Federal Aviation Administration had approved dangerous flight routes that allowed an Army helicopter to fly into the path of a passenger jet over the Potomac River on Jan. 29, 2025, to calamitous results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a meeting on Tuesday, the investigating board also castigated the agency for not doing enough to respond to warnings about longtime risks to safety and found a complacent culture within the air traffic control tower at Ronald Reagan National Airport that relied too heavily on pilots in the airspace being able to see and steer clear of each others’ aircraft, a practice called visual separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also determined that insufficient warnings from the air traffic controller to the pilots of the Army Black Hawk helicopter and an American Airlines passenger jet involved in the crash, and altimeters that, unbeknown to the helicopter pilots, habitually gave faulty readings of altitude, also contributed to the tragic crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long-awaited determination, which the board approved unanimously, is the culmination of a yearlong investigation that put the F.A.A. and Army under a microscope, as the board scrutinized how officials missed — or outright dismissed — risks that ultimately led to the collision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s one failure after another,” Jennifer Homendy, the board chair, told reporters during a break in the proceedings, adding: “This was 100 percent preventable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. focused the brunt of its ire on the F.A.A., determining that the route the Army Black Hawk helicopter flew along the Potomac River and the landing path of American Airlines Flight 5342 were never designed to ensure separation between aircraft — and that the dangers posed by the crisscrossing paths were never adequately reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also determined that the F.A.A. ignored repeated appeals from controllers to reduce National Airport’s traffic, even as its main runway became the single busiest in the United States. That forced controllers to routinely divert planes to a backup runway, as they did with the American Airlines flight that night, to manage congestion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.A.A. values and appreciates the N.T.S.B’s expertise and input,” said Hannah Walden, a spokeswoman for the F.A.A., in a statement. The agency has worked with the N.T.S.B. throughout the investigation, she added, “acted immediately” to put into place its initial safety recommendations and “will carefully consider” the additional recommendations it made Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy flight traffic, investigators said, routinely led controllers at the airport to direct incoming planes to the backup runway, Runway 33, putting them in proximity with helicopters. It also led controllers to rely too much on pilots themselves to “see and avoid” each other, investigators determined, noting that the practice “introduced unacceptable risk” to the airspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.T.S.B. staff members cited a culture within the F.A.A. that discouraged raising concerns about safety, describing how the agency installed, but never activated, a traffic management system that could have helped controllers handle traffic better on busy nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also concluded that the decision to put one controller in charge of both helicopter and airplane traffic on the night of the crash was not because of insufficient staffing in the tower — and that the duties should have been separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, the board did not fault the pilots of either aircraft for failing to avoid each other. It did, however, determine that the pilots of the helicopter requested visual separation too early, and probably never had the correct commercial jet in their sights. The pilots of the jet, the board added, were too busy preparing for landing to note the approach of the helicopter, which the air traffic controller had not warned them about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of striking animated visual simulations, investigators strongly suggested that the instructor pilot in the helicopter, who was evaluating a less experienced pilot on a training flight, lost sight of the passenger jet as the two aircraft approached each other. The jet came back into his view only a second or two before impact, the video indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the N.T.S.B. determined that had the controller on duty noted the danger and explicitly warned pilots that they were at risk of colliding, they likely would have had time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were not adequately prepared to do the jobs they were assigned to do,” said Brian Soper, who leads the N.T.S.B.’s air traffic control investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators also said that if either aircraft had been equipped with real-time tracking gear known as ADS-B In, the pilots might have been alerted nearly a minute before the collision of the danger, giving them ample time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the board also found that the helicopter pilots’ reliance on other equipment contributed significantly to the crash. Investigators concluded that the pilots of the Army helicopter probably thought they were flying about 100 feet lower than their actual altitude because of idiosyncrasies in the readings of altimeters on the Black Hawks that the Army knew about but never informed aviators of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They wouldn’t know it,” said Capt. Van McKenny, a helicopter investigator with the N.T.S.B. “It’s not in their manual, it’s not in the training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army also never realized that the barometric altimeters in their helicopters were giving pilots a false sense of their flying height because the service didn’t routinely collect the relevant data. Instead, the Army relied on a voluntary reporting system that was seldom used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A., investigators said, had plenty of data about the dangers to the Washington airspace, however, that the agency simply ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. questioned why on multiple occasions, the F.A.A. relaxed the restrictions on when a single controller could be assigned to manage helicopter and airplane traffic simultaneously, creating a culture of complacency that things would work out, even when controllers became overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the board excoriated the F.A.A. for downgrading National Airport’s facility rating in 2018, a measure that determines the experience level required for controllers to work there. That change, and its commensurate pay cut, made it more difficult for the tower to attract experienced personnel capable of handling Washington’s busy airspace, the N.T.S.B. staff said, especially given the city’s high cost of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This tower is essentially treated as a training facility,” Ms. Homendy said. “It is a pass-through, they can’t attract people here, which is a problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, the N.T.S.B. issued over 70 findings about the midair collision, and approved dozens of recommendations aimed at preventing similar crashes. The Trump administration and Congress will determine whether to put them into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. has already limited what aircraft can fly through the airspace surrounding National Airport. It has also reconfigured helicopter routes in the area, in response to urgent recommendations that the N.T.S.B. issued last March, and it rolled out a redesign plan it says will streamline safety monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency also has been making significant investments to modernize the country’s aging air traffic control system. A funding bill pending before the Senate would pump billions more dollars into the F.A.A. to help with hiring more controllers, but the legislation could falter amid a political standoff over funding for immigration enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. plans to publish a full report detailing the findings, causes and recommendations stemming from the crash in the weeks after Tuesday’s meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:29:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Population Growth Slows Sharply as Immigration Numbers Plunge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-census-fjcl/27nat-census-fjcl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States population grew last year at one of the slowest rates in its history, according to new numbers released on Tuesday by the Census Bureau. The immigration numbers plunged by more than 50 percent from the previous year, under the aggressive anti-immigration policies of President Trump. And the birthrate continued its nearly two-decade long decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nation’s population increased by about 1.8 million over the year, and stood at almost 342 million on July 1, the estimates say. That is a growth rate of about 0.5 percent, the lowest since 2021, when the Covid-19 pandemic caused deaths to soar and borders to close, shutting the door to international migration. That year saw the slowest growth since the nation’s founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new census estimates measure changes in the population from June 30, 2024, to July 1, 2025, capturing the last months of the Biden administration, when it tightened border policies, and the early months of the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over that time, net immigration added almost 1.3 million people to the U.S. population. That number is considerably lower than that of 2024, when, under President Joseph R. Biden Jr., immigration reached a record high of just over 2.7 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump continues his term, immigration is expected to drop even further. If current trends continue, it will fall to about 321,000 for the year ending on June 30, according to a Census Bureau news release. That would be lower than during the pandemic year, when net international migration dropped to 376,000, one of the lowest points in modern history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The basic goal here was to stop people coming over the border illegally and being released, and to ramp up interior enforcement to actually remove people,” Simon Hankinson, a senior research fellow at the conservative Heritage Foundation, said of Mr. Trump’s immigration policy. “This is an indicator that much of the strategy is working.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has pledged to bring down levels of illegal immigration through a border shutdown and mass deportations. But although net immigration has declined substantially, it has still not reached the point where more people are leaving the country than arriving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country’s attention has been focused on raids and deportations, those actions accounted for relatively little of the overall decline in net immigration of about 1.5 million. The Census Bureau does not break down what caused the drop, but a New York Times analysis found that about 230,000 people were deported from the United States over the entirety of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That suggests that deportations are not directly responsible for most of the decline in net immigration numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The border shutdown was a major part of the decline. Other factors that contributed to the drop include the increased difficulty of getting visas and foreign citizens who chose not to come to the United States, or to leave on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was expecting that the decline would be bigger than we’re seeing here,” said William Frey, chief demographer at the left-leaning Brookings Institution. “This is still over a million people coming in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though several estimates have been made of the change in the immigrant population since President Trump came into office, the estimates by the Census Bureau on Tuesday are the first gold-standard set of federal figures to be made public. They attempt to account for both legal and illegal immigration, as well as deportations and voluntary departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The federal government’s population numbers are a measure of a nation’s demographic health, and take account of births and deaths as well as immigration, emigration and deportation. The country needs a large enough population of young workers and taxpayers to finance care for the nation’s older residents, whose numbers are swelling as the Baby Boom generation retires. Growth that is too rapid can also present problems, taxing resources and driving up the cost of housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sharp drop in the birthrate also contributed to the slowdown in population growth. The birthrate has been falling since the Great Recession in 2008, and new births outpaced deaths by only about 518,000 in the latest period. That is higher than during the peak of the Covid pandemic, when deaths were soaring, but it is still extremely low by historical standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What has been carrying the United States through this decade has been immigration,” said Kenneth Johnson, a demographer at the University of New Hampshire. “My question is, what will happen to the population if we go to negative immigration?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He noted that in the decade from 2010 to 2020, immigration made up about 40 percent of the overall population growth, while births supplied about 60 percent. But since 2020, as the birthrate has declined, immigration has taken up a larger and larger share, and now accounts for around 80 percent of overall growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Lowering immigration at a time when our birthrate is falling is a recipe for lower growth for our economy and weaker international competition,” said Julia Gelatt, an associate director at the Migration Policy Institute, a research center in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While demographers expected the latest estimates to show a decline in the rate of population growth — the question was simply by how much — some of the changes seen at the state level were a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Midwest was the only region where every state grew in population over the year: For the first time in a decade, more people in the United States moved to the region than left it. Ohio and Michigan both gained population arriving from other states, after seeing residents leave in earlier years. South Carolina was the country’s fastest growing state, followed by Idaho, North Carolina and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, immigration has fueled population growth in the states, and the reduction has dragged it down. There were sharp drops in Texas, New York, Florida and California. The drop in California contributed to an outright decline in population for that state, one of five states to run in the red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Census Bureau estimates are derived from government records, like birth and death certificates and data on immigration and refugees. This year, the bureau also included new sources of information, including government data from Mexico, to get a more accurate count of the number of people leaving the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some demographers have praised these changes and said they will contribute to a more accurate count, they have also cautioned that immigration is difficult to track precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:38:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment Commission Chair Recasts Workplace Discrimination in Trump’s Image</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, a 9,000-word essay about white male millennials shot across the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, a ticket scalper and frustrated screenwriter, marshaled interviews and data to describe how the professional trajectories of members of his generation had been crushed by what he called the institutionalization of diversity, equity and inclusion mandates, a “profound shift in how power and prestige were distributed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vice President JD Vance reposted the piece, saying it “describes the evil of DEI and its consequences.” Elon Musk responded, calling D.E.I. “a great wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essay also caught the attention of Andrea Lucas, the chair of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, the agency, born of the Civil Rights Act, that enforces laws against employment discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are you a white male who has experienced discrimination at work based on your race or sex? You may have a claim to recover money under federal civil rights laws,” Ms. Lucas said in a video posted on Dec. 17 on social media. From her desk at E.E.O.C. headquarters, she referred viewers to the commission’s primer on “D.E.I.-related discrimination.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, which recalled the television commercials of personal injury law firms, generated volleys of shock, outrage and gratitude online. To Ms. Lucas, 40, it was an urgent public service announcement, central to her mission as an agent of President Trump’s executive authority and part of a robust response to what she described as the excesses of the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, she said she was determined to undo the consequences of five years of “aggressive focus by D.E.I. activists” that reserved the protections of the country’s civil rights infrastructure for certain groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the agency is the tip of the spear for implementing a really ambitious civil rights agenda,” Ms. Lucas said. “I think that that mission is to restore a focus on equality as opposed to equity. It’s going back to the concept of equal treatment as opposed to equal outcomes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics of Ms. Lucas, including former commissioners of the E.E.O.C., say she is distorting the intent of the Civil Rights Act, paying lip service to equal treatment while using her position to write MAGA grievances into federal law. They noted that as she has solicited complaints from white men — historically a small share of complainants to the E.E.O.C. — the commission has dismissed cases that would defend transgender employees and job applicants with criminal records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlotte Burrows, Ms. Lucas’s predecessor as chair, who was fired by Mr. Trump last January, said, “Federal civil rights laws protect everyone, and the E.E.O.C. has a duty to engage in fair and evenhanded law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She and others said Ms. Lucas’s message in the December video was that white Americans would receive preferential consideration under the Trump administration. “That’s the opposite of equal opportunity,” Ms. Burrows said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her first year, Ms. Lucas has taken steps to undo the work of her predecessors, particularly regarding contentious issues like gender. Her work is likely to accelerate now that the commission has three members, required for a quorum, with a 2-to-1 Republican majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a meeting on Jan. 22, the commission voted — over the objections of the sole Democrat — to rescind guidance for employers about workplace harassment. Issued in 2024 after 10 years of debate, the guidance detailed prohibitions against harassment, including on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She has closed the door of the E.E.O.C. to groups that are disfavored by the president,” said Josh Boxerman, who handles civil rights work at the National Employment Law Project, a workers rights group. “That is extraordinary. And it is radical and harmful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody who wants to sue a private employer under civil rights law must file a complaint with the commission. The E.E.O.C. received more than 88,000 such complaints in 2024, the last year for which data is publicly available. The commission is legally mandated to look into all of them, but only a sliver develop into full investigations. The commission, and particularly the chair, has great discretion over what cases to pursue, particularly because staff and resources are stretched thin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the commission “saw our work as protecting the rights, often, of the most vulnerable workers, who really needed the government’s help,” said Jenny Yang, who worked at the E.E.O.C. from 2013 to 2018, including three years as chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we are seeing now is a real politicization of the priorities of the agency, and a disregard for the law,” Ms. Yang said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas joined the commission in 2020, when its work was being complicated by the Covid-19 pandemic and the racial reckoning that followed the murder of George Floyd. The commission, along with employers across the country, grappled with vaccine mandates, diversity and inclusion practices, questions about gender-specific bathrooms and charges of deep-seated racism across entire industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That period of time, primarily during the Biden administration, but even heading into it, was a period of a wave of discrimination that was motivated or framed as D.E.I.,” Ms. Lucas said. “Everyone collectively lost their minds for a period of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backlash followed, a sentiment Mr. Trump harnessed in the 2024 election. Among his first moves after returning to office last January was issuing executive orders that dismantled D.E.I. programs in the federal government. On Jan. 20, 2025, he nominated Ms. Lucas to serve as the E.E.O.C.’s acting chair. A week later, he fired two of the Democratic commissioners, Ms. Burrows and Jocelyn Samuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Samuels filed a lawsuit challenging her firing, which is on hold while the Supreme Court considers a similar case at the Federal Trade Commission, another independent agency Mr. Trump has sought to bring under the reach of executive authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission and the Justice Department, Ms. Samuels said, are neglecting their legal duty to protect workers equally, adding that Ms. Lucas is making changes that are procedurally suspect and damaging to workers who bear the greatest burden of discrimination in America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It has been heartbreaking and infuriating, in equal measure,” Ms. Samuels said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of 2025, Ms. Lucas was the interim head of an agency that had only one other member, Kalpana Kotagal, a Democrat, lacking the quorum required to pursue major rule changes or litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas worked around those constraints. In March, she wrote to 20 law firms seeking details about their D.E.I. practices. The commission worked with the Justice Department and the Department of Labor in a campaign to root out “national-origin discrimination,” such as apparent preferences for foreign skilled workers holding H-1B visas over American workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a little bit of a backwater. But Andrea has done an effective job of making the E.E.O.C., and the chair of the E.E.O.C., an important policymaking position,” said Jason C. Schwartz, a co-chair of the labor and employment group at the law firm Gibson Dunn, where he worked with Ms. Lucas. He called her “really smart, really strong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission also took action against universities, including reaching an agreement in which Columbia University would pay $21 million to resolve complaints of civil rights violations against its Jewish employees after the Israel-Hamas war started in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Pennsylvania rebuked the E.E.O.C. in a court filing this month, refusing to supply information about its Jewish employees in connection with an investigation into antisemitism at the university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, Mr. Trump issued an executive order taking aim at a pillar of civil rights law: disparate-impact liability, a legal principle holding that an employment practice is discriminatory if it creates unequal outcomes among different groups, even unintentionally. Mr. Trump directed government agencies to stop enforcing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move, denounced by civil rights and employment groups, had swift consequences at the commission. Within weeks, it moved to dismiss a civil rights lawsuit it had brought a year earlier against Sheetz, the convenience store chain, over its practice of screening out applicants with criminal convictions. The commission had previously found that the practice disproportionately affected applicants of color and violated the Civil Rights Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last October, the E.E.O.C. moved to dismiss seven cases it had brought in 2024 on behalf of transgender and gender-nonconforming people, in accordance with a new agency policy that it would not enforce workplace harassment claims brought on the basis of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her Senate confirmation hearing in June, Ms. Lucas was clear about her priorities: pursuing cases related to religious and national-origin discrimination, rooting out D.E.I. initiatives and ending what she sees as the improper elevation of “gender identity” over biological sex. She disavowed statements she had made referring to the E.E.O.C. as an independent agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been very clear: The agency is not an independent agency,” she said in the interview. “It’s an executive branch agency. The will of the people elected the president, and I’m going to execute it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Senate’s confirmation in October of Brittany Bull Panuccio, a Republican nominated by Mr. Trump to the E.E.O.C., the commission’s work is likely to accelerate in volume and ambition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are very concerned that it will continue that path of wide-ranging rescissions and rollbacks of hard-won and thoughtfully considered worker protections,” said Mr. Boxerman of the National Employment Law Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She has made it clear that longstanding agency policy, judicial precedent — these things matter less than fulfilling the Trump agenda,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas sees her role as an expression of Mr. Trump’s executive authority, but it is also clear that she has given a lot of thought to issues of fairness and justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If your answer to solve prior discrimination is present discrimination, I think that’s a really ugly view of the world,” Ms. Lucas said in the interview. “That’s not the vision that I want for my children. It’s not the vision that I think goes back to the concept of people being created equal. And I just really fundamentally disagree with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Historically, Republicans have been very uncomfortable to talk about race, uncomfortable to deal with this issue,” Ms. Lucas said. “But from my perspective, we have to deal with these topics.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:49:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yale Offers Free Tuition to Families With Incomes Under $200,000</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-yale-qljh/27nat-yale-qljh-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale University said on Tuesday that attending the university would be free for newly admitted undergraduate students from families with annual incomes below $100,000, and that tuition would be waived for those earning below $200,000. The change takes effect for the class that will enroll in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move enters Yale into an arms race of elite institutions offering increasingly attractive financial aid packages to students from low- and middle-income families. At Yale, the full-price cost to attend is now more than $90,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale’s new policy essentially matches the deal offered by Harvard last year, which followed similar announcements by the University of Pennsylvania, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Princeton and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beefed-up financial aid follows the Supreme Court’s 2023 decision limiting what universities may do to recruit racially diverse student bodies. The schools hope to continue to attract diverse applicants by stepping up financial aid, since race and income are often correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort to make attendance more affordable at some of the nation’s highest-rated universities also comes at a time when public trust in higher education has declined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Kahlenberg, director of the American Identity Project at the Progressive Policy Institute, said the effort was good not just for the country but also for Yale, because it will allow students from different walks of life to attend, increasing the range of viewpoints on campus as well as the range of backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Economic diversity can bring racial diversity in a way that’s perfectly legal,” he said. “So after the Supreme Court struck down the use of race, institutions like Yale had to find different ways to get racial diversity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the new policy, which was first reported by The Wall Street Journal, Yale said that students from 80 percent of households in the United States would qualify for free tuition, and students from almost half the nation’s households would be eligible for an entirely free Yale education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the lowest-income students, the offerings at Yale, Harvard and some other schools include free housing and meal plans, allowances for travel to and from campus, medical insurance and “start-up” grants for students to use to buy books and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an announcement last August, Princeton appeared to eclipse even those generous aid packages, saying that most families with incomes up to $150,000 would pay nothing to attend and most with incomes up to $250,000 will pay no tuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, the upper limit for household income to qualify for no-cost attendance at Yale was $75,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremiah Quinlan, Yale’s dean of undergraduate admission and financial aid, said the new plan is an investment in affordability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With this announcement, we reiterate and reinforce Yale’s commitment to ensuring that cost will never be a barrier between promising students and a Yale College education,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:50:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Breaking Silence, Eleanor Holmes Norton Announces Retirement</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-norton-vphw/27trump-news-norton-vphw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton, who has served for three decades as Washington, D.C.’s nonvoting representative in Congress, on Tuesday announced she planned to retire at the end of her term, pivoting after months of insisting she had no intention of stepping aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to my constituents for choosing and trusting me to fight for you in Congress 18 times,” she said in a statement. “I will leave this institution knowing that I have given you everything I have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 88-year-old Democrat is the oldest person serving in the House. Once a forceful voice for the nation’s capital, she had retreated from her congressional duties in recent years amid signs of mental and physical decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she had repeatedly swatted away the suggestion that she might leave Congress, including as recently as this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, even after her campaign filed a termination notice for her re-election, her office declined to confirm that Ms. Norton planned to retire and she issued no statement, raising questions about whether she had approved the move — or even knew about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Norton, a civil-rights leader and former law professor who entered Congress in 1991, earned the moniker of D.C.’s “warrior on the Hill,” after decades of fighting for statehood for the district.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in recent years her voice has diminished on Capitol Hill. She has said little since President Trump’s return to office, even as Republicans wielded their trifecta of power to increase federal control over the city she represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The privilege of public service is inseparable from the responsibility to recognize when it’s time to lift up the next generation of leaders,” Ms. Norton said in her statement on Tuesday. “For D.C., that time has come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her exit will mark the end of a strained final chapter of her congressional career in which Ms. Norton often appeared confused on Capitol Hill, but steadfastly refused to consider ending her long political career. She had become a symbol of the gerontocracy gripping Washington, sitting silent in committee meetings and saying little to push back on Republicans’ legislative attacks on the district and the deployment of the National Guard to police the city’s streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former top staff member, Trent Holbrook, and several members of the D.C. Council had already announced plans to run for her seat even before Ms. Norton announced she was stepping down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Democrats praised her for decades of work fighting for the rights of D.C. voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Eleanor fought with deep patriotism for the people of the District of Columbia, honoring the history and promise of Washington while never wavering in her demand for justice,” former Speaker Nancy Pelosi, Democrat of California, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Congressional Black Caucus said in a statement that Ms. Norton had been “a guiding force for our members for decades, sharing her wisdom and expertise and helping to shape generations of leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Muriel E. Bowser of Washington said in a statement on Sunday that the congresswoman’s work “embodies the unwavering resolve of a city that refuses to yield in its fight for equal representation.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:26:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Immigration, the G.O.P. Finds Itself in a Shocking Place: On Defense</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two killings by federal agents on the icy streets of Minneapolis have suddenly turned the politics of immigration upside down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans, led by a president who rose to power with promises to build a Southern border wall and carry out mass deportations, are now trying to dodge an issue that polls had long shown to be a strength for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats, who have for years tried to change the political subject to health care or abortion rights, are now racing to talk about immigration and harness their voters’ rage over the fatal shootings in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift could be fleeting. American politics has rarely felt so unsettled and unpredictable, with President Trump just as responsive to television coverage as to on-the-ground realities. On Monday, he shook up the leadership of his immigration crackdown in Minnesota and seemed inclined to try to calm tensions, at least for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime, both parties are adjusting on the fly as a midterm election year they thought would center on the cost of living abruptly seems far more focused on immigration and federal power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Illinois and New Mexico, Democratic candidates this week began running advertisements highlighting their opposition to federal immigration operations. Others in Maine and New Jersey have upended their campaign messaging, long directed at high costs, to address their voters’ anger about deportations. The party’s primary candidates for Senate spoke forcefully against Mr. Trump’s immigration policies during recent debates in Texas and Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic members of Congress including Senator Raphael Warnock of Georgia and Representative Ro Khanna of California have braved snowstorms and subzero temperatures to fly to Minneapolis and meet — and be seen — with activists on the ground. Others have led rallies against Immigration and Customs Enforcement in their home states. And Senate Democrats have quickly grown an appetite for again shutting down the federal government over funding for Mr. Trump’s Department of Homeland Security, which includes ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top Republican leaders and many candidates in tough races have struggled for a response to the chaos in Minnesota. Speaker Mike Johnson has still not issued a statement, while Senator John Thune, the majority leader, praised Mr. Trump’s shake-up in Minnesota as a positive step for “turning down the temperature.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, a parade of other politicians in the party have expressed concerns about the killings and the aggressiveness of federal immigration authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Madel, a Republican candidate for governor of Minnesota governor, called the federal immigration operation “a disaster” as he dropped out on Monday. Representative Glenn Grothman, from next-door Wisconsin, suggested that the latest shooting by a federal agent was “murder.” Even Gov. Greg Abbott of Texas, known for his hard-line immigration approach, suggested that the White House should “recalibrate” its strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Immigration enforcement used to be a strong point for Republicans,” said Adam Jentleson, the president of the Searchlight Institute, a moderate Democratic think tank, who two weeks ago released a memo warning Democrats to avoid the phrase “Abolish ICE.” “Republicans thought that there was no version of enforcement that people would reject, and they were wrong about that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The political risks for Republicans in battleground states and districts have become clear, with polls showing voters souring on Mr. Trump’s immigration tactics. A New York Times/Siena poll released last week — conducted before the latest shooting in Minnesota — showed that while roughly half of voters supported his deportations, a sizable majority believed that ICE had gone too far, including a remarkable 71 percent of politically crucial independent voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even if the administration is telling the truth, the perception is immediately colored against ICE because of how much fear and anxiety has piled up,” said Preya Samsundar, a Republican strategist in Minneapolis. “If this continues to go on, it could cause some issues with the gains we have been able to make as a party.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats say their change in focus is being driven by fury from their voters, who want to know what their representatives will do to try to stop Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In every conversation, it is brought up,” said Tahesha Way, a Democratic former lieutenant governor of New Jersey who is running in a special election to the U.S. House next week. “People not only see what’s going on nationally in Minnesota — they’re living in fear as to what is happening on the ground here in New Jersey.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wave of Democratic outrage could force another government shutdown at the end of the week. Key Senate Democrats have promised to oppose bipartisan legislation to fund a broad swath of the government because it includes billions of dollars for the Department of Homeland Security and ICE. Several suggested they were open to eventually including such funding, but they demanded more guardrails to “rein in the abuses of ICE,” as Senator Chuck Schumer, the minority leader, put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How Americans might respond to another shutdown is one uncertain factor in the ever-changing political calculus. And Republicans have hardly given up their tough-on-immigration stance: In television ads broadcast this year, there have been more than twice as many Republican ads highlighting such positions than Democratic spots criticizing ICE tactics, according to data from AdImpact, a media tracking firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Democrats warn that voters broadly have not rejected the overall goal of combating illegal immigration that helped twice elect Mr. Trump to the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a topic that Democrats have an imperative to engage on, but they still need to do it the right way,” said Molly Murphy, a Democratic pollster who worked in 2024 for the campaigns of President Joseph R. Biden Jr. and Vice President Kamala Harris. “Voters believe a secure border is important and that Trump’s tactics are not doing that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the two killings in Minnesota made the state the focus of the nation’s attention, ICE operations in other states have pushed immigration and deportation issues to the forefront of local politics. Maine’s Senate race, one of the country’s most competitive, and its contest for governor have become dominated by the government’s deportation push in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the name of the ICE effort in Maine — Operation Catch of the Day — has infuriated some officials and voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a grotesque name,” said Shenna Bellows, the Maine secretary of state and Democrat who is running for governor. “People are not fish.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:29:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Man Is Wounded After Exchanging Fire With Border Patrol in Arizona</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2024/03/11/multimedia/27xp-border/11budget-border-btpv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Arizona man was in critical condition after exchanging gunfire with a U.S. Border Patrol agent and shooting at a federal helicopter on Tuesday in Arizona near the Mexican border, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol agents were working to apprehend a male suspect in an “active alien smuggling matter” when he shot at a federal helicopter, Heith Janke, the special agent in charge of the F.B.I.’s Phoenix field office, said during a news conference late Tuesday afternoon. Federal agents returned fire and shot the suspect, Mr. Janke said. No federal agents were injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams from the Santa Rita Fire District of Green Valley, Ariz., and American Medical Response, which provides emergency medical services, were dispatched to the reported shooting around milepost 15 on West Arivaca Road, just after 7:30 a.m., the fire district said in an emailed statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crews found “one patient in custody and in critical condition,” and provided medical care before the patient was airlifted to a regional trauma center, the fire district said. The federal agent involved in the shooting also rendered aid for the man, Mr. Janke said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man, Patrick Gary Schlegel, 34, of Sahuarita, Ariz., was transported to the hospital and underwent surgery, Mr. Janke said. He is recovering but remains in serious condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schlegel has a significant criminal history, including an active federal arrest warrant, and is in federal custody, Mr. Janke said. He is expected to be charged with assault on a federal officer, alien smuggling and being a felon in possession of a firearm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let me be clear: Any assault on law enforcement officers will not be tolerated,” he said. “The F.B.I. will continue to vigorously investigate those who harm or threaten to do harm to those who wear the badge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal agents had seen the vehicle that Mr. Schlegel was driving before 7 a.m. with other passengers. When agents tried to stop the vehicle, which was believed to be involved in human smuggling, “everybody fled, the vehicle fled,” Sheriff Chris Nanos of Pima County said during the news conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the morning, an agent saw the vehicle again and made a second traffic stop in the area of Arivaca Road, he said. The driver fled, Sheriff Nanos said, and the Border Patrol agent gave chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pima County Sheriff’s Department said it was working with the F.B.I. and the U.S. Customs and Border Protection, which oversees the Border Patrol, on the case. The department said the F.B.I. had asked it to lead the investigation into the use of force involving the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a news release, the department said it “will thoroughly examine all aspects of the incident, however, these investigations are complex and require time.” It appears that the Border Patrol agent who shot Mr. Schlegel acted lawfully, Sheriff Nanos said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Border Patrol and its parent agency, Customs and Border Protection, did not immediately respond to requests for comment on the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arivaca Road is about 25 miles from the international border and about 20 miles from the center of Arivaca, an unincorporated community in Arizona. The region and its checkpoints have been a focus of border enforcement for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Customs and Border Protection said a Border Patrol agent “was involved in a use-of-force incident while investigating a human smuggling event” near the Santa Cruz and Pima Counties line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, a shooting by a Border Patrol agent wounded one person near Arivaca, one of two shootings in a week that capped a string of drug seizures by the patrol, The Arizona Daily Star reported that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrutiny of the nation’s immigration debate has been heightened in recent months with the Trump administration crackdown turning violent in Minneapolis, including the fatal shootings of two people by federal officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitty Bennett contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:08:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok Blames Technical Problems After Users Claimed It Blocked ICE Posts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok said on Tuesday that its app was facing technical problems after users accused the service of suppressing posts related to Immigration and Customs Enforcement following the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok’s U.S. operations said in a statement on Monday that a power outage at an American data center had impeded users from uploading new videos. It said that some videos also inaccurately showed that they had zero views or likes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some TikTok users, including the comedian Megan Stalter, have accused the app of blocking them from posting videos about ICE or limiting the reach of those videos. State Senator Scott Wiener, Democrat of California, who is running for Congress, said on X that he had posted about legislation that would allow lawsuits against ICE agents. Mr. Wiener said the post was “sitting at zero views, and I’m not the only person this is happening to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an early test for the app after its Chinese parent company, ByteDance, last week spun off its U.S. operations into a new joint venture controlled by non-Chinese investors. Those investors include firms close to President Trump, like the cloud computing giant Oracle and the Emirati investment firm MGX. The investors’ association with Mr. Trump had raised concerns among some TikTok users that the new venture would slant the app’s content in a more conservative direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for TikTok said on Tuesday that the new U.S. entity had not updated its algorithm since the joint venture was announced. As part of the agreement to spin out the new venture, TikTok’s U.S. operation is planning to retrain the content recommendation algorithm that it will be licensing from ByteDance. The creation of the U.S. TikTok was aimed at addressing longstanding national security concerns about ByteDance’s ties to China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Senator Chris Murphy, Democrat of Connecticut, re-shared a post on X from before Mr. Pretti was killed that accused TikTok of “censoring” content critical of Mr. Trump and ICE. “I know it’s hard to track all the threats to democracy out there right now, but this is at the top of the list,” Mr. Murphy wrote in his post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for the app said in an email that it was “inaccurate to report that this is anything but the technical issues we’ve transparently confirmed.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Senator Warnock Says ‘Soul of Our Nation Is at Stake’ During Visit to Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Raphael Warnock, Democrat of Georgia, visited the site of Alex Pretti’s killing late Tuesday morning in South Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As I stand where Alex Pretti lost his life, in a real sense, I feel like I’m standing on holy ground,” he said. “And the blood spilled on this ground reminds us we’re in a moral moment in our country, and the soul of our nation is at stake here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before addressing the media, Mr. Warnock, the senior pastor at the Atlanta church where the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. once preached, stood in silence at the edge of a memorial to Mr. Pretti. The memorial had sprouted around the place where he was shot and killed by federal agents on Saturday. While in Minneapolis, the senator planned to meet with local faith leaders who serve the people reeling from the recent killings of Mr. Pretti and Renee Good, a Minneapolis woman fatally shot by an agent earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before the senator’s arrival, the site had been attracting mourners. People brought bouquets to add to the dozens already placed along the sidewalk. A couple of votive candles still flickered in the bitter cold, amid others that had burned out. Mr. Pretti’s framed picture had been placed in a wreath, beneath a folded American flag and a few dozen pine cones arranged to spell his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Warnock said that when he returned to Washington, he would push to block funding for Immigration and Customs Enforcement in the Senate and bring federal immigration officials before Congress to answer for “the mayhem and death we’re seeing on our streets” from the Trump administration’s aggressive deportation crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m going to use all the levers that I have available to me as a member of the Senate to hold these officials accountable,” Mr. Warnock said. “You’ll see me drag them in front of Congress, ask them the tough questions and hold them accountable.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:00:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Texas Moves to Curtail Visas for Skilled Foreign Workers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Greg Abbott of Texas on Tuesday abruptly blocked state agencies and public universities from using skilled foreign worker visas in hiring, as conservative state leaders and the Trump administration seek to curtail the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Abbott, in a letter to state agencies, ordered an investigation into agencies and universities that sponsored foreign job applicants for what are known as H-1B visas, which are issued to nonimmigrant workers in a range of specialty fields. Texas is among the top states for such visas, along with California, New York and New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Gov. Ron DeSantis of Florida argued for limiting H-1B visas at his state’s universities, and this week, a Florida Board of Governors committee will consider pausing such hiring until early 2027. Mr. Abbott proposed the same time frame, freezing hiring until after the State Legislature meets next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves by Florida and Texas align with the Trump administration’s “America first” agenda. The administration in September imposed a $100,000 fee on new H-1B petitions, arguing that employers had used the program to keep wages low, hurting American workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Abbott, who is running for re-election in November for a fourth term, has taken steps throughout President Trump’s second term to adopt and expand many of the policies coming out of Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Abbott’s move on H-1B visas was immediately embraced by the state Republican Party, which called it “a great first step in the fight to protect Texas jobs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some in higher education have pushed back against efforts to limit visas. Todd Wolfson, the president of the American Association of University Professors, called the move “partisan interference in students’ right to learn” that would “lower the quality and diminish the value of education and research at Texas universities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 12,000 H-1B visas were approved in Texas in the 2025 fiscal year, according to an analysis of government data by the National Foundation for American Policy, a nonpartisan research group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Higher education advocates say that H-1B visa holders fill critical teaching and research positions in specialized areas. Some university leaders have also appealed to the Trump administration’s rhetoric about merit, arguing that hiring the best candidate for the job sometimes means an H-1B worker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 40,600 faculty members working in the United States hold an H-1B visa, according to an estimate from the College and University Professional Association for Human Resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lynn Pasquerella, president of the American Association of Colleges and Universities, said the political uncertainty created by Mr. Abbott’s move discourages global talent from choosing American schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reductions in hiring could weaken research output, slow innovation and make Texas institutions less competitive nationally,” she said in an email, adding that Mr. Abbott’s move was “another example of government overreach.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Abbott directed the state agencies and universities to provide the state’s work force commission with detailed information about the visas that have already been issued, including the country of origin of the recipients, the jobs for which each visa holder was hired and documents showing efforts to provide qualified Texans with a chance to apply for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Evidence suggests that bad actors have exploited this program by failing to make good-faith efforts to recruit qualified U.S. workers before seeking to use foreign labor,” Mr. Abbott said in his letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His office referred to recent news reports but did not provide examples of companies that the governor believed were exploiting the program. In recent days, a video posted by a reporter with BlazeTV and Texas Scorecard, a hard-line conservative news site widely read in the Texas Capitol, claimed to show H-1B visa violations around Dallas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brian Harrison, a Republican member of the Texas House and a vocal critic of the state’s large public universities, argued last week that the state government was “one of the biggest users/abusers of H-1B.” On Tuesday, he said he welcomed Mr. Abbott’s move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the nonsense that has been happening at the hands of supposed Republicans here in the Texas government for far too long,” Mr. Harrison said in a podcast interview with Steve Bannon, a former Trump adviser, on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:47:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Temporarily Blocks Deportation of 5-Year-Old Detained in Minneapolis Suburb</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-liam1/27minneapolis-ice-liam1-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge on Monday temporarily blocked the deportation of a 5-year-old boy and his father who were arrested in a Minneapolis suburb in an operation that further stirred the outrage over the Trump administration’s deportation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boy, Liam Conejo Ramos, and his father, Adrian Conejo Arias, were arrested last week in Columbia Heights, Minn., shortly after the father had picked the boy up from school, according to school district officials. They were quickly taken to an immigration detention center outside San Antonio, where they remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his order, Judge Fred Biery of the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Texas told the federal government that it could not move the boy or his father out of his court’s jurisdiction while they challenged their detention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detention of the boy and his father by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents became a flashpoint in the Twin Cities, where anger has continued to grow over the surge of federal agents in the region. The image of Liam, wearing a Spider-Man backpack and a large winter hat as he was detained by federal agents, quickly became emblematic of the harsh effects of the government’s tactics in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly what happened during the arrest remains in dispute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials with the Columbia Heights Public School District, where Liam is a prekindergarten student, accused the federal government of using the boy as bait at his home to try to lure other family members out of the house. They said he was one of four students in the district who had recently been detained by the immigration authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Department of Homeland Security officials said that Mr. Conejo Arias had fled from agents, leaving Liam behind, and that Liam’s mother had “refused to accept custody” of him. They said Mr. Conejo Arias had told agents that he wanted Liam to remain with him. They also said that agents had not targeted or arrested the child, though they said he was being held with his father at an immigration detention center in Dilley, Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricia McLaughlin, a Homeland Security Department spokeswoman, maintained on Tuesday that Mr. Conejo Arias, who is from Ecuador, had entered the country illegally in December 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lawyer for the father and son disputed that in court documents, saying that the pair had entered legally at a border crossing in Brownsville, Texas. The lawyer, Jennifer Scarborough, said they had followed the government’s guidelines for asylum seekers and argued that the government had violated the rights of the father and his son by detaining them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The order from Judge Biery, who was appointed by President Bill Clinton, was brief and did not delve into the details of the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a news conference at the Minnesota State Capitol in St. Paul on Tuesday, school district officials and lawmakers decried the impact that immigration arrests were having on students. Of the four students arrested in Columbia Heights, two were detained on their way to school, said Mary Granlund, who chairs the Board of Education there. Another student was getting ready for school when there was a knock on the door from immigration agents, Ms. Granlund said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Granlund and others said the district, which has about 3,400 students, was in a crisis, with students staying home from school, children crying in classrooms and teachers not being able to give answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Children ask, ‘Can they take us?’ We don’t know what to tell them,” said Peg Nelson, a teacher in Columbia Heights. “Every day we wonder: How long is this sustainable?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sarah Mervosh contributed reporting from St. Paul, Minn., and Edgar Sandoval from San Antonio.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:40:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Push to Impeach and Investigate Noem</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top three House Democrats on Tuesday came out in support of an effort to impeach Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, part of a growing chorus in the party calling for Ms. Noem’s ouster after federal immigration agents shot and killed two people in Minneapolis this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a joint statement, Representatives Hakeem Jeffries of New York, Katherine Clark of Massachusetts and Pete Aguilar of California called for “dramatic changes” at the Homeland Security Department and accused officials of carrying out a violent “killing spree.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kristi Noem should be fired immediately, or we will commence impeachment proceedings in the House of Representatives,” they wrote. “We can do this the easy way or the hard way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 150 congressional Democrats have now joined the bid to impeach Ms. Noem. The effort would need Republican support to move forward, and, so far, no G.O.P. lawmaker has called for the secretary’s removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the leadership’s statement was a strong indication that Democrats would move to impeach Ms. Noem if they won the majority in the midterm elections, and that many of them, across the ideological spectrum, are prepared to campaign on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Jamie Raskin of Maryland, the top Democrat on the Judiciary Committee, suggested that the party would begin preparing for eventual impeachment proceedings, with or without Republican support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, he said that he and other leading Democrats would start “a complete oversight and impeachment inquiry into all potential constitutional crimes committed by Secretary Noem” if Republicans failed to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, 162 House Democrats — about three-quarters of the total caucus — have backed a resolution to impeach Ms. Noem, according to a spokeswoman for Representative Robin Kelly, who introduced the resolution earlier this month. That is 51 more than had signed on as cosponsors to Ms. Kelly’s measure as of Friday, the last day the House met for legislative business and the day before Mr. Pretti was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jeffries, Ms. Clark and Mr. Aguilar have yet to sign on as co-sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though many Senate Democrats have called for Ms. Noem to resign or be fired, a smaller number in that chamber have called for her to be impeached. They include Senators Jacky Rosen of Nevada, Peter Welch of Vermont, and Ed Markey and Elizabeth Warren of Massachusetts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kristi Noem should resign,” Ms. Warren said in a video posted on social media platforms. “And if she doesn’t, Congress should impeach her and remove her from office.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:38:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virginia Judge Blocks Democrats’ Efforts to Redraw Congressional Maps</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/virginia-court-ruling-redistricting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27-nat-virginia-redistricting-jzhc/27-nat-virginia-redistricting-jzhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A state judge in Virginia issued an order on Tuesday blocking the Democratic-led legislature from drawing new district maps for the 2026 congressional elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling, which found that Democratic lawmakers had not followed state law on redistricting, could be a major setback to the party’s attempt to counter President Trump’s push for the drawing of favorable new districts in Republican-held states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic leaders, who had been anticipating a legal fight, immediately said that they would appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This jockeying over congressional maps began in Texas last year, at the president’s urging, as he sought to ensure that Republicans would maintain their very slim majority in the House in the midterm elections this fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Texas launched the first salvo of partisan gerrymandering, North Carolina and Missouri, both states with Republican legislatures, have also adopted new maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The counter-effort in some Democratic-held states, including Virginia and California, was more complicated, requiring constitutional amendments required to allow the legislatures to redraw congressional districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voters in California approved such an amendment in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Virginia, a new constitutional amendment must be voted on by the legislature twice, before and after an “intervening” statewide election, and then put to voters in a referendum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last October, Democratic leaders in the General Assembly announced they were calling the legislature back to Richmond as part of an ongoing special session, which had been first called by the governor in 2024 to consider budget matters. Democrats then introduced the topic of the session: a resolution that would allow the legislature to draw new maps in time for the 2026 midterms. It was passed on a party-line vote, less than week before Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Democrats passed the resolution for the required second time and this week, the legislature was holding votes to schedule the referendum for April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the ruling on Tuesday, by Judge Jack S. Hurley Jr. of Tazewell County Circuit Court in southwest Virginia, has, for now, thrown the redistricting effort into question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans had raised objections as soon as the resolution was introduced. They argued that the vote was too late to count for the required “intervening” election, given that hundreds of thousands of people had already been to the polls in early voting. They also pointed to an old Virginia law requiring proposed amendments be “posted at the front door of every Courthouse” at least three months before a statewide election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats had responded to some of these arguments in debates about the bill on the floor of the legislature. They argued that last November’s election was the required “intervening election.” They also said that the law requiring the posting of amendments on courthouse doors was outdated and obsolete and that was why a state commission had recommended that it be deleted from the legal code last year. Lawyers for the Democrats argued in court that blocking the amendment would be a violation of the separation of powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Hurley sided with the Republicans on nearly all of their arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, State Senator Ryan McDougle and Delegate Terry Kilgore, both Republicans and plaintiffs in the lawsuit, said the case was “about process, fairness, and the simple principle that you cannot change the Constitution by ignoring the Constitution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic leaders said they would continue “to move forward and put this matter directly to the voters. Republicans who can’t win at the ballot box are abusing the legal process in an attempt to sow confusion and block Virginians from voting.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/virginia-court-ruling-redistricting.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:25:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>City Prosecutors Join Forces to Bring Charges Against Federal Agents</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28nat-prosecutors-gczj/28nat-prosecutors-gczj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine progressive prosecutors from cities around the country are launching a coalition to assist in prosecuting federal law enforcement officers who violate state laws, one of the prosecutors, Larry Krasner in Philadelphia, said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization, which is called the Project for the Fight Against Federal Overreach, will also include Mary Moriarty, the elected prosecutor in Minneapolis. Its acronym, F.A.F.O., references a slang term for negative consequences, and its formation was spurred by “growing concerns about warrantless entries, unlawful detentions, and coercive enforcement tactics by federal agents,” according to a news release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The handling of potentially criminal actions by federal agents has become a major issue in Minneapolis after two protesters, both U.S. citizens, were killed there this month by Department of Homeland Security officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Bureau of Investigation said it would not investigate the first killing, of Renee Good, a 37-year-old mother of three. She was killed in her S.U.V. on Jan. 7 as she appeared to be steering away from federal agents during a tense confrontation. Trump administration officials said that the officer who shot Ms. Good had been under attack and was acting in self-defense, and state investigators have been blocked from accessing evidence related to the episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a second resident was killed — Alex Pretti, a Veteran Affairs nurse who was also 37 — federal officials initially appeared to use the same playbook. They blocked state investigators from the scene and declined to provide basic facts, like the identity of the agents involved. In both instances, bystander video contradicted key elements of the Trump administration’s account of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing a wave of criticism, President Trump on Tuesday promised a “very honorable and honest investigation” into Mr. Pretti’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As videos and reports of ICE officers acting with aggressive force have flooded the country, a small but growing number of law enforcement officials have warned that they would arrest and prosecute federal officials who break their laws. One of the first to do so was the district attorney in San Francisco, Brooke Jenkins, after the president threatened to send National Guard troops there last October. In Minneapolis, protesters have demanded that the local police arrest ICE officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, John Choi, the top prosecutor in Ramsey County, which includes St. Paul, said his office was investigating reports of crimes by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials say that ICE officers are making cities safer by removing criminals from the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, the F.B.I. and the Department of Justice’s Office of Civil Rights determine whether the use of deadly force by a federal agent was justified. State prosecutors also have the power to investigate and prosecute state crimes like murder, and they have often done so in cooperation with the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that cooperation has broken down as Trump administration officials have denied that the federal agents committed any wrongdoing and accused Minnesota leaders of thwarting their immigration enforcement efforts and allowing fraud in federally funded programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After local officials were blocked from the investigations, Ms. Moriarty, the elected prosecutor for Hennepin County, resorted to opening a web portal to allow the public to submit evidence like cellphone videos. She has said that she expects to have enough evidence to decide whether to pursue charges in the two killings. Her office is also investigating a third incident in which a Venezuelan man was shot in the leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecuting any police officer raises significant obstacles, since officers are authorized to use deadly force when they reasonably perceive a serious threat. The Constitution’s supremacy clause gives federal agents additional protection, though they do not have absolute immunity, as Vice President JD Vance initially claimed. They can ask for a federal court to shield them from prosecution if their actions were authorized under federal law, and if they can show that they did “no more than what was necessary and proper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Krasner said the new organization would provide “mutual support” to prosecutors who are “up against the might of the federal government.” So far, nine prosecutors from around the country have signed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are a very substantial tool against what I consider to be a pretty clear attempt to normalize fascism and to overthrow democracy in the United States,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other locations whose elected prosecutors are participating include Austin; Dallas; Pima County in Arizona, which includes Tucson; and several cities in Virginia: Fairfax, Falls Church and Arlington, Portsmouth and Norfolk.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:50:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>President Visits Iowa, Trying to Shift Focus to the Economy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-los-angeles-fires-rebuilding</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-la-thmp/27trump-news-la-thmp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Over the weekend, the president demanded that local officials expedite rebuilding permits and ordered an audit of federal funds. But he was silent on the region’s stalled request for $34 billion in federal aid.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-los-angeles-fires-rebuilding</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:25:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Republicans Shift Tone After Killings, Criticizing Trump’s Immigration Push</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/republicans-shift-tone-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-memo-wkmg/27dc-memo-wkmg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demands for independent investigations. Scheduled oversight hearings. Overtures for proposed concessions to avert a government shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti by a federal agent in Minneapolis, Republicans in Congress have starkly shifted their tone on the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown, offering some of the strongest and most pointed criticism of the administration since the start of President Trump’s second term and conceding that something must change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti’s killing over the weekend had drawn notable pushback from a small but significant group of G.O.P. lawmakers even before Mr. Trump switched rhetorical gears, distancing himself from his administration’s smears of Mr. Pretti and installing a new commander to oversee his deportation push in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for a much broader group of Republicans who have been reluctant to challenge Mr. Trump or even gently criticize him, the president’s messaging pivot appeared to have provided license to air grave concerns about what happened in Minneapolis and the backlash it had generated among much of the American public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift could be temporary and may be more of a matter of style over substance. It was not clear whether it would yield any immediate action by Republicans, who have largely ceded their power to Mr. Trump and who still solidly back his immigration policy. They have balked at Democrats’ demands to drop funding for the Department of Homeland Security bill from a spending package needed to avert a government shutdown on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, Republicans have toned down the hyperpartisan language typical in the run-up to a shutdown. Senator John Thune, Republican of South Dakota and the majority leader, signaled openness on Tuesday to negotiating with Democrats on policy changes that might draw their votes for the homeland security spending measure, as he called for a full and impartial investigation into Mr. Pretti’s killing, which he described as “an inflection point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all reflected a worry among congressional Republicans, shared by the president, that voters are souring on the immigration crackdown as they see a federal agency acting far beyond the limits of a police force — and that the party may pay a political price for it in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after months of standing on the sidelines as Democrats and municipal and state leaders railed against the tactics of Immigration and Customs Enforcement and other border agencies, Republicans have moved quickly this week to put the agency and Mr. Trump’s policy under scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Representative Andrew Garbarino, the New York Republican who leads the House Homeland Security Committee, announced that top administration immigration officials would testify before the panel on Feb. 10 after Mr. Garbarino called for their appearance immediately after Mr. Pretti’s killing on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Transparency and communication are needed to turn the temperature down,” Mr. Garbarino said in setting the date for the hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Rand Paul, the Kentucky Republican who heads his chamber’s homeland security panel, announced a similar session on Feb. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another sign of Republican unease with the immigration push, Representative Mark Amodei of Nevada, who leads the spending panel responsible for the Homeland Security Department’s funding, criticized Secretary Kristi Noem’s response to the shootings in an interview with The Nevada Independent. He said a “pivot” in immigration enforcement tactics was necessary “because regardless of what side of immigration enforcement you’re on, we are not in a good place right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Thom Tillis, the North Carolina Republican who has announced his retirement, went further on Tuesday, becoming the first in his party to call for Ms. Noem’s firing. “What she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” he said at the Capitol, adding, “She needs to go.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the House, Representatives Brian Fitzpatrick, Republican of Pennsylvania, and Tom Suozzi, Democrat of New York, leaders of the Problem Solvers Caucus, wrote to Mr. Trump asking for a meeting to discuss a broad immigration overhaul, because his border successes “are now being overshadowed by the interior enforcement that has given rise to a growing rejection by the public.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those actions followed calls by several Senate Republicans — some of whom have never previously questioned the administration’s actions — for an independent investigation into the killings in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top Republicans are also taking a different approach to the intensifying clash with Senate Democrats over funding for the Department of Homeland Security as a partial government shutdown looms at the end of the week. Democrats are demanding tough new limits on federal immigration agents or they will oppose homeland security funding that is part of a six-bill spending package set for an initial vote on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than immediately accusing Democrats of acting irresponsibly and putting government services at risk, Republican leaders have taken a softer approach and have said they hope a resolution can be reached in talks between Democrats and the White House. It is a stark contrast from the last shutdown, when Republicans refused to even enter into negotiations on Democrats’ key demand, extending health care subsidies, until they agreed to end the shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the question is, ‘What is it the Democrats want?’” Mr. Thune said as the Senate returned on Tuesday. “And if they can define that, then we should figure out if there’s a way to actually achieve it, or come to some agreement, if you will, to negotiate whatever their demands are.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added, “Obviously this is an inflection point, an opportunity to evaluate and to really assess the policies and the procedures” of the Trump administration in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all Republicans are dialing it down. In a statement on Tuesday posted on X, the members of the far-right House Freedom Caucus urged Mr. Trump to keep the immigration pressure on, illustrating how difficult it could be to secure House approval of any changes won by Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We support @POTUS doing whatever is necessary to keep American streets safe from rapists, murderers, and pedophiles here illegally,” the Freedom Caucus statement said. “If Democrat-run Sanctuary Cities continue enabling Communist agitators assaulting ICE and federal law enforcement, then it is time to invoke the Insurrection Act to maintain law and order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Senate Republicans took a similar stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Four months ago, Democrats shut down the government in an attempt to give illegal aliens free health care,” Senator Marsha Blackburn, Republican of Tennessee, wrote on X. “Now, they want to shut down the government to stop illegal aliens from being deported. Do Democrats work for the American people or illegal aliens?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Thune’s comments suggested that Senate leaders were still hopeful for a resolution that could avoid a shutdown. Whether the more measured approach would result in real action that could change the administration’s tactics or avoid a partial government shutdown at the end of the week remained an open question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Senate Republicans said Democrats should cut a deal with Mr. Trump for whatever policy changes they wanted to see in exchange for voting for the spending package, Senator Chuck Schumer, Democrat of New York and the minority leader, threw cold water on that idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The fix should come from Congress,” Mr. Schumer said on Tuesday as he again called for Mr. Thune to break off the homeland security funding measure and allow the Senate to approve funding for the rest of the government while lawmakers negotiated new restrictions on immigration enforcement. “The public can’t trust the administration to do the right thing on its own. The Republicans and Democrats must work together to make that happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schumer also made it clear that he was not impressed with a tonal shift by Republicans and the president and that he wanted immediate results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What ICE is doing is state-sanctioned thuggery and it must be stopped,” he said. “ICE must leave Minnesota today. Not tomorrow, not next week, but today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catie Edmondson, Megan Mineiro and Michael Gold contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/republicans-shift-tone-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:32:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Suggests He Will ‘De-Escalate’ in Minneapolis, Without Offering Details</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-trump-fbpk/27dc-trump-fbpk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said on Tuesday that “we’re going to de-escalate a little bit” when it comes to his immigration crackdown in Minneapolis, the latest indication that the mounting backlash to the fatal shooting of a protester Saturday had prompted him to try to shift perceptions of the administration’s approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump did not specify what tactics being used by federal immigration agents would change, if any. And he continued to blame Alex Pretti, the intensive care unit nurse shot by Border Patrol agents, for legally carrying a gun with a permit — comments that risked angering gun rights supporters in his base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can’t walk in with guns,” Mr. Trump told reporters as he departed the White House for a speech in Iowa about the economy. “You can’t do that,” he added, before calling Mr. Pretti’s death “a very unfortunate incident.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president also acknowledged the aggressive tactics of Gregory Bovino, the Border Patrol official known for his confrontational style who was pulled out of Minneapolis. In an interview with Fox News, Mr. Trump described him as “a pretty out there kind of guy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In some cases it’s good,” the president said. “Maybe it’s not good here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallout from Mr. Pretti’s killing on a frozen Minneapolis street Saturday shadowed the president’s attempts to focus on the economy during a speech to supporters in Clive, Iowa, an event meant to serve as a kickoff for his broader campaign to bolster Republicans in the midterm elections. Outside the Horizon Events Center before the appearance, thousands of protesters blew whistles, beat drums and chanted “ICE out now!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During his address, Mr. Trump did not mention the shooting. But he kept up his hard-edge attacks on immigrants, lines that got the loudest cheers of the night. At one point, he raised the specter of immigrants who may “blow up our shopping centers, blow up our farms, kill people.” He also falsely portrayed the vast majority of those detained by ICE in Minnesota and elsewhere as hardened criminals, asserting that once those people were removed, crime would be nearly eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Capitol Hill Tuesday, the top three House Democrats came out in support of an effort to impeach Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary — part of a growing chorus in the party calling for her ouster after the deaths of two protesters in Minneapolis in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans were also critical. Senator Thom Tillis of North Carolina, who is retiring at the end of his term, told reporters that Ms. Noem should be fired, and called her actions “amateurish.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lisa Murkowski of Alaska struck a similar note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have a secretary right now who needs to be accountable to the chaos and some of the tragedy that we have seen,” Ms. Murkowski told reporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the day, reflecting the competing pressures he was under from aides who wanted to stay the course and from Republicans who joined the criticism of the administration’s tactics, Mr. Trump kept hedging his comments. During the Fox News interview, he insisted: “I don’t think this is a pullback.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the president also said that “we’re going to de-escalate a little bit.” He noted that he had dispatched his border czar, Tom Homan, to take over the operation in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also told reporters that he did not believe Mr. Pretti was a potential “assassin,” the term used by his close aide, Stephen Miller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Pretti’s killing, the president has repeatedly questioned why the protester was carrying a gun as he was observing Border Patrol agents conducting an operation. (Mr. Trump has not made similar comments about incidents in which his supporters have carried weapons, including during the Jan. 6, 2021, attack on the U.S. Capitol.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar rhetoric in recent days by top administration officials has drawn condemnation from gun rights groups, including the National Rifle Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump insisted Tuesday that he was awaiting a “very honorable and honest investigation” into the shooting. That investigation is being conducted by the Department of Homeland Security, which oversees the agents who were involved in Mr. Pretti’s shooting. Ms. Noem was also among the first and most insistent to declare that Mr. Pretti had violent motives, saying he had arrived on the scene with the intention to “inflict maximum damage on individuals and to kill law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No evidence has emerged to support that assertion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details that have emerged in court filings so far indicate that the Department of Homeland Security probe is limited to a “use of force” review, rather than a broader inquiry that would examine whether the agents should face criminal charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arriving in Iowa, Mr. Trump tried to change the topic, appearing at a rally where he was surrounded by supporters holding signs that said “Lower Prices.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Incomes are up, prices are down, our economy is roaring,” the president declared. “Our workers are thriving and our country is winning again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has frequently claimed that prices are declining, though federal statistics show that the inflation rate — while slowing from several years ago — is hovering around 2.7 percent. He claimed that he had inherited “the highest inflation rate in the history of our country,” though that statement was false — something he seemed to acknowledge almost immediately, correcting himself to say it was the highest in “48 years.” (In fact, the highest was more than a century ago, at the end of World War I, when the inflation rate hit 23 percent.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans in Congress, also eager to turn the conversation away from the fatal shooting in Minneapolis, spent much of the day Tuesday seeking to remind voters who would soon file tax returns about the tax cuts their party had pushed through Congress in their marquee domestic policy bill last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaker Mike Johnson, who as of Tuesday afternoon had not put out a statement responding to Mr. Pretti’s death, took to social media proclaiming: “MORE MONEY IS BEING RETURNED TO YOU.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s what happens when Republicans are in charge and we put AMERICANS first,” Mr. Johnson wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Charles E. Grassley of Iowa, the senior-most Republican in the chamber, delivered a triumphal speech from the Senate floor, saying: “This year taxpayers can expect to see some of the largest tax refunds in history.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That, of course, is thanks to our enactment of the legislation called the Working Families Tax Act,” Mr. Grassley said, referring to the legislation that Mr. Trump had insisted on calling the “Big Beautiful Bill.” Republicans have since rebranded that law after polling showed that voters had a negative opinion of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Catie Edmondson, Michael Gold, Chris Cameron and Ann Klein.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:53:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota Leaders Meet With White House Border Czar</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-walz-frey-homan-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/newsgraphics/images/icons/defaultPromoCrop.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota and Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis held separate meetings on Tuesday with President Trump’s border czar, Tom Homan, a day after he was dispatched by the president to direct ICE operations in the state in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti was the second Minneapolis resident in the past three weeks to be killed, and the third to be shot, by federal agents engaged in the administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Homan’s meetings with the governor and mayor came amid Mr. Trump’s struggles to contain the fallout over the killing and his administration’s false accusations about Mr. Pretti, a Veterans Affairs nurse who was shot repeatedly by agents in South Minneapolis on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Walz’s office said in a statement that he and Mr. Homan had met in St. Paul on Tuesday and that the two had agreed to continue working toward the state’s goals: a swift reduction in federal forces on the ground, impartial investigations into Minneapolis shootings involving federal agents and “an end to the campaign of retribution against Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Frey said in a series of social media posts that he and his police chief, Brian O’Hara, had also spoken with Mr. Homan on Tuesday, calling their meeting “productive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I reiterated that my main ask is for Operation Metro Surge to end as quickly as possible,” Mr. Frey said, referring to the Trump administration’s immigration enforcement campaign in Minneapolis, during which some 3,000 federal agents have flooded Minnesota, making thousands of arrests and prompting mass protests, street confrontations and widespread fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Frey said he had made clear that Minneapolis would continue to prohibit city employees, including police officers, from enforcing federal immigration law, but he added that city leaders would “stay in conversation with Mr. Homan and his team.” Mr. Walz’s office said in its statement that the Minnesota Department of Public Safety would be the state’s primary liaison to Mr. Homan. The president has said Mr. Homan will report directly to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commenting on the meetings on social media, Mr. Homan said that he met with Mr. Walz and Mr. Frey to talk about the need to support law enforcement officers and get criminals off the streets. “While we don’t agree on everything, these meetings were a productive starting point and I look forward to more conversations with key stakeholders in the days ahead,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts to reach Mr. Homan for additional comment were unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks with Mr. Homan came one day after Mr. Trump said he’d had “very good” calls with Mr. Walz and Mr. Frey. Later on Monday, he met for nearly two hours in the Oval Office with Kristi Noem, the Homeland Security secretary, and her top aide, Corey Lewandowski, according to two people briefed on the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s decision to send Mr. Homan to Minnesota is part of a shake-up that, according to two federal officials, will include Gregory Bovino, who has led the Border Patrol’s operations in Minneapolis, leaving the city. Mr Bovino’s aggressive tactics in major American cities have made him a face of the White House’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino is “a pretty out there kind of guy,” Mr. Trump said in a Fox News interview on Tuesday. “In some cases it’s good, maybe it’s not good here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same interview, Mr. Trump described Mr. Homan, a longtime immigration enforcement official who played a central role in implementing the Trump administration’s family separation policy during the president’s first term, as a “tough guy” who nevertheless got along well with governors and mayors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashley Ahn and Hamed Aleaziz contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-walz-frey-homan-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:22:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Did the Trump Administration Silence Bovino on Social Media?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/bovino-minnesota-social-media-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-bovino-social-media-qzpm/27dc-bovino-social-media-qzpm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is one sure sign that the Trump administration understands it is in trouble with the public this week: They didn’t just recall Gregory Bovino from Minnesota. They silenced him on social media, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the unacquainted, Mr. Bovino is the great-coat-wearing border patrol “commander-at-large” who led the operation in Minneapolis and became the face of the mayhem. It was a role he leaned into online, posting prolifically from his X account, @CMDROpAtLargeCA, right up until Monday morning, when the account appeared to go dormant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Convicted sexual predator arrested!” read his last post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to bar Mr. Bovino from his account was made not by the White House but by his higher-ups at U.S. Customs and Border Protection, according to an official at the Department of Homeland Security. A different U.S. official insisted that Mr. Bovino would eventually regain access to his social media account, once he’s back at his previous post in California, overseeing part of the border there. Both asked for anonymity because they were not allowed to speak to the media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the taming of CMDROpAtLargeCA offered a glimpse into an administration in damage control mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is one thing to be demoted. It is another thing entirely to lose your social media megaphone. In this administration, there may be no worse fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump rules by social media and it’s difficult to be a power player in his court if you’re not power posting, too. To lose one’s account is to lose the ability to brag about all the righteous work one does for him. It means losing the ability to tar one’s common enemy. How is one supposed to build a profile within the MAGA universe if one cannot post?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino, 55, seemed to understand all of this. He used his X account to mix it up with journalists, lawmakers, critics, fans, Stephen King — whoever. CMDROpAtLargeCA became an expression of the persona he crafted for himself, every bit as important as the coat and the haircut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino could be blasé about the bloodshed on American streets. “Pipe down with the feigned outrage,” he wrote to Democratic representative Seth Moulton of Massachusetts, who posted a video condemning the killing of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis. When Senator Mark Kelly, Democrat of Arizona, posted about Mr. Pretti’s death, Mr. Bovino replied: “You were there? Typical arm chair quarterback.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it became clear that Mr. Bovino would be the one to take the fall, it was somehow surprising that he would be suspended from social media. There was really nothing about his behavior online that wasn’t perfectly in keeping with how his superiors behave online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, is a social media warrior. Vice President JD Vance has been crashing out online about Minneapolis all week. Stephen Miller, the architect of the administration’s immigration policies, called Mr. Pretti a “would-be assassin” in a post on X. These officials have posted things that are in direct contradiction to what the president and his press secretary are now saying about the violence in Minneapolis, and yet, this does not seem to have hurt them at work. Mr. Miller was traveling with the president aboard Air Force One to Iowa Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to imagine what was off-kilter about the way Mr. Bovino was using social media. After all, the White House, the Department of Homeland Security, the Labor Department and other sectors of this administration have spent the year posting references to neo-Nazi literature, QAnon conspiracy theories and white-supremacist song lyrics on official government accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A White House official declined to comment about Mr. Bovino’s social media account Tuesday.His social media suspension has raised a collective eyebrow on the right, as social media censorship has long been one of most animating causes for members of the president’s political base. One of the main consequences of Mr. Trump’s actions on Jan. 6, 2021, was that he was kicked off social media platforms. He started his own platform, Truth Social, which is a key part of how he governs today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several prominent posters with connections to the administration preferred not to comment about the silencing of Mr. Bovino when asked about it on Tuesday. One who did want to comment was Steve Bannon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Silencing Commander Bovino is a terrible idea,” he wrote in a text message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What might Laura Loomer think? It was only a few years ago that she had been banned by so many platforms that, she once said, she had to go to therapy because of the “PTSD I have developed as a result of being silenced.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, she functions as a combination mouthpiece and loyalty enforcer for the Trump administration. So maybe it shouldn’t have come as a surprise that she didn’t seem too concerned about Mr. Bovino being shut up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So from what I was told by the White House when I asked about this is that he’s going to have another social media account, but for the El Centro sector,” she said, referring to the part of California to which Mr. Bovino has been reassigned. “It’s not that he’s being shut down or silenced.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another power poster in the Trump orbit is Katie Miller, the former administration aide who is married to Stephen Miller. Ms. Miller said she hadn’t been paying attention to the commotion around Mr. Bovino’s suspension and therefore couldn’t be sure if it was true. “I don’t follow him even,” she said. She said she didn’t know what he had or had not been posting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My algo doesn’t show him, unfortunately,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now neither does yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Hamed Aleaziz&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/bovino-minnesota-social-media-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:29:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens to Pull U.S. Help From Iraq if Former Leader Returns</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iraq-al-maliki.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-iraq-lgwk/27trump-news-iraq-lgwk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump on Tuesday warned that the United States would “no longer help Iraq” if Nuri Kamal al-Maliki returned as Iraq’s prime minister, a new intervention in another country’s politics that came after Washington signaled it would seek to limit Iranian influence in Iraq’s next government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just over the last few days, Mr. Trump has threatened Canada over doing business with China and vowed to raise tariffs on South Korea because of delays in fulfilling a trade deal with the United States. Last week, Mr. Trump walked back a pledge to raise tariffs on European countries that were resisting his efforts to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Iraq, where Prime Minister Mohammed Shia al-Sudani fell short of a decisive victory in elections last November, is far more vulnerable to American threats. The United States controls Iraq’s oil revenues because they flow through the New York Federal Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No Iraqi prime minister is viable if the Americans say, ‘We’re going to hate this guy from Minute 1,’” said Michael Knights, an Iraq specialist at Horizon Engage, a strategic consulting firm in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Maliki was nominated to the prime minister post by the main Shiite Muslim bloc in the Iraqi Parliament on Saturday. He was backed by the United States when he first became prime minister in 2006 but was blamed in his second term, from 2010 to 2014, for sectarian policies that fueled the rise of the Islamic State, a Sunni extremist group. Iraq, like Iran, is a majority Shiite nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Last time Maliki was in power, the Country descended into poverty and total chaos,” Mr. Trump posted on his Truth Social platform on Tuesday. “Because of his insane policies and ideologies, if elected, the United States of America will no longer help Iraq and, if we are not there to help, Iraq has ZERO chance of Success, Prosperity, or Freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s broadside against Mr. Maliki came after months of building U.S. pressure against Iranian influence in Iraq. Iraq’s leaders have long had to walk a tightrope between the United States on one hand and Iran, their powerful neighbor, on the other. Iran has ties to many leading figures in Iraq’s Shiite majority, including Mr. Maliki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A government controlled by Iran cannot successfully put Iraq’s own interests first,” the State Department said after Secretary of State Marco Rubio spoke with Mr. Sudani, the current prime minister of Iraq, in a phone call on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump did not mention Iran in his Truth Social post, leaving his exact motivations unclear. Mr. Knights said that while Mr. Maliki empowered Iran-linked militias in his second term as prime minister, his actions in recent years did not stand out as particularly pro-Iranian compared with other major Shiite figures in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Representative Joe Wilson, Republican of South Carolina, reinforced the administration’s anti-Iran message in a social media post a few hours after Mr. Trump’s missive on Tuesday. He said that Iraq needed to “fully disarm and dismantle all Iranian aligned militia groups” within 12 months and remove Iranian advisers, operatives and agents from the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Iranian influence in Iraq will no longer be tolerated,” Mr. Wilson wrote. “The era in which outside actors imposed prime ministers on Iraq is over.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iraq-al-maliki.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:51:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>D.H.S. Review Does Not Say Pretti Brandished Gun, As Noem Claimed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pretti-shooting-minneapolis-dhs-report.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-DHS-report1-ckpq/27minneapolis-ice-DHS-report1-ckpq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A preliminary review by U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s internal watchdog office found that Alex Pretti was shot by two federal officers after resisting arrest, but did not indicate that he brandished a weapon during the encounter, according to an email sent to Congress and reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The review makes no mention of the Department of Homeland Security’s earlier claims that Mr. Pretti, a U.S. citizen, “wanted to do maximum damage and massacre law enforcement.” Shortly after the shooting, Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, claimed that Mr. Pretti had been “brandishing” a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials had provided no evidence to back up the claim, which was contradicted by witness videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial review by C.B.P., which deployed more than 1,000 officers and agents to support the enforcement operation in Minnesota, represents the first official written assessment of Saturday’s shooting since administration officials rushed to blame Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These notifications reflect standard Customs and Border Protection protocol and are issued in accordance with existing procedures,” Hilton Beckham, a C.B.P. spokeswoman, said in a statement. “They provide an initial outline of an event that took place and do not convey any definitive conclusion or investigative findings. They are factual reports — not analytical judgments — and are provided to inform Congress and to promote transparency.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The review was done by C.B.P.’s Office of Professional Responsibility, which normally conducts internal misconduct investigations following shootings, and was distributed to members of Congress on Tuesday, as required by law. It presents a detailed timeline of the events based on body camera footage and agency documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At approximately 9 a.m. on Saturday, a federal officer was confronted by two female civilians blowing whistles, according to the review. Although the officer ordered them to move out of the road, they did not move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The officer then “pushed them both away,” and one of the women ran to Mr. Pretti, the review said. After the officer attempted to move them out of the road and they did not move, the officer deployed pepper spray at them, according to the review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti then resisted attempts by C.B.P. officers to take him into custody, prompting a struggle, the review said. A Border Patrol agent multiple times yelled, “He’s got a gun!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About five seconds later, a Border Patrol agent fired his Glock 19, and a C.B.P. officer also fired his Glock 47 at Mr. Pretti, according to the review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New York Times analysis of video footage from the scene found that officers fired 10 shots, including six after Mr. Pretti was lying motionless on the ground. Mr. Pretti had been disarmed before he was shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government review said that after the shooting, a Border Patrol agent “advised he had possession of Pretti’s firearm” and “subsequently cleared and secured Pretti’s firearm in his vehicle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At approximately 9:02 a.m., C.B.P. personnel cut Mr. Pretti’s clothing and provided medical aid to him by placing chest seals on his wounds, according to the review. About three minutes later, local emergency medical services arrived at the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti was placed in an ambulance and transported to Hennepin County Medical Center before medical personnel pronounced him dead at approximately 9:32 a.m., the review said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, President Trump faulted Mr. Pretti, who had a firearms permit, for bringing a gun to protest the enforcement operation. It is legal to openly carry a weapon in Minnesota. Still, Mr. Trump promised a “very honorable and honest investigation” into his killing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C.B.P.’s Office of Professional Responsibility has a large investigative program to look into officer-involved shootings and other potential officer misconduct. Basic incident reports like the one distributed on Tuesday are required to be released within 72 hours of an officer shooting. But those are often followed by investigations from internal staff members, typically alongside F.B.I. officials conducting a review to see if criminal charges are warranted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The review says instead that Homeland Security Investigations, an arm of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, is investigating the incident while O.P.R. reviews those findings. The decision to have Homeland Security Investigations take the lead has provoked some consternation from former O.P.R. leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on LinkedIn posted Tuesday morning, Daniel Altman and Matthew Klein, two former officials at the watchdog office who left the department last year, called on the administration to allow O.P.R. to do an internal review and the F.B.I. to conduct a criminal investigation into whether the officers violated civil rights laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said that Homeland Security Investigations “does not have the mandate or expertise to conduct civil-rights use-of-force investigations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Altman and Mr. Klein were also critical of the initial rush to judgment by administration officials and called for more transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Public confidence has already been damaged,” they wrote. “Transparency — through disciplined, sequenced release of investigative findings — allows the public to judge the results for themselves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Gold contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pretti-shooting-minneapolis-dhs-report.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:53:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Demonizes ICE Detainees in Minnesota as ‘Vicious’ Criminals</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-speech-minnesota-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-trump-speech-wpbv/27minneapolis-ice-trump-speech-wpbv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking in Iowa on Tuesday at a rally billed as an address on the economy, President Trump veered near the end into a tirade in which he vilified the thousands of people arrested by ICE in Minnesota, falsely describing them as “hardened, vicious, horrible criminals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raising the specter of immigrants who may “blow up our shopping centers, blow up our farms, kill people,” Mr. Trump asserted while speaking near Des Moines that “2 percent of the population causes 90 percent of the crime.” He added, “So when you start decimating that 2 percent, boom,” miming a falling gesture with one finger as he spoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, most of the immigrants that ICE has arrested in city crackdowns since Mr. Trump took office have no criminal record. In Washington, which Mr. Trump characterized in his speech as a “horrible,” crime-ridden city before his recent show of force, only 2 percent of those arrested by ICE had been convicted of a violent crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tim Hogan, a spokesman for the Democratic National Committee, criticized Mr. Trump’s rhetoric toward detained migrants as dangerous, saying that voters will hold him accountable in November’s midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At a time when our entire nation is reeling from multiple tragedies in Minnesota, Donald Trump continues to pour gasoline on the fire,” Mr. Hogan said, adding “He knows damn well that his lies sow chaos, but he does it anyway.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dark turn in Mr. Trump’s language came amid a growing outcry against his administration’s show of force in Minnesota. After suggesting to Fox News earlier on Tuesday that he might “de-escalate” the crackdown, he then pushed back on the idea that any change in approach in Minnesota was a retreat, attacking anti-ICE demonstrators as “paid insurrectionists” and “paid agitators.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He returned to that language in his speech. Mr. Trump was heckled throughout the address and outside the rally venue by people he described as “lunatics.” A crowd lined up for blocks along the president’s motorcade route, blowing whistles, beating drums and chanting “ICE out now!” A woman attending the rally screamed, “Release the files,” presumably referring to the Epstein files, and was being escorted out. A young man was dragged out by security officers for heckling the president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They get paid,” Mr. Trump said as the man was removed. “These are all paid agitators, that’s all they are. They get paid to go and — they don’t even know when they interview them. ‘Why are you here? I don’t know.’ They have no idea. They’re paid insurrectionists, really, in some cases. They’re sickos.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Mr. Trump’s sidetrack, he had delivered an unusually focused hourlong speech, campaigning for the midterms and seeking to counter criticism of his tariffs and the rising cost of goods. In recent months, when Mr. Trump has been frustrated by continuing criticism over the state of the economy, he has vacillated between blaming immigrants for the country’s economic woes and assuring his supporters that life has been better than ever under his administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump repeated many of his false claims about the economy on Tuesday. He falsely said that he had eliminated taxes on Social Security, when he has not. He said that his administration had collected $600 billion in tariff revenue, when in reality the sum is $287 billion. And he claimed that prices for groceries and pharmaceutical drugs were falling, but the reverse is true: Drug prices are still rising and prices for groceries are now rising faster than during any month since October 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-speech-minnesota-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:02:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Representative Ilhan Omar Is Attacked at Town Hall in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a town hall with Representative Ilhan Omar in Minneapolis on Tuesday evening, a man rushed the lectern and appeared to spray her with a strong-smelling liquid before he was tackled by security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man, who had been seated directly in front of the lectern in the front row, suddenly jumped up as Ms. Omar was speaking and ran toward the podium. He used a syringe to spray her shirt with a substance that smelled strongly of vinegar. As he stumbled backward and pointed at her, a security officer tackled him to the ground, handcuffed him and removed him from the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gasps were audible through the crowd, as well as cries of “Oh my God, oh my God.” Some attendees yelled out, “He sprayed something!” A woman in the crowd appeared near tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minneapolis Police said the man, whom they later identified as Anthony J. Kazmierczak, 55, was arrested and booked into jail on suspicion of assault. A forensics squad was called to analyze the scene, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar, a Democrat who represents part of Minneapolis and has been a frequent target of President Trump, held the town hall in her district of Minneapolis to address the ongoing ICE operations in the city. Hours before, Mr. Trump criticized Ms. Omar at a rally in Iowa and repeated inflammatory remarks about her birth country, Somalia. He said immigrants “have to show that they can love our country. They have to be proud, not like Ilhan Omar.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assault occurred just after she said: “We must abolish ICE for good. And D.H.S. Secretary Kristi Noem must resign or face impeachment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her comment mirrored calls by Democratic lawmakers for Ms. Noem, the homeland security secretary, to step down or face impeachment after federal immigration agents shot and killed two people in Minneapolis this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar, visibly shaken after the assault, insisted to her staff and security that she would continue. She asked for a napkin and told them: “Just give me 10 minutes. I beg you. Please don’t let them have the show.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar then turned the crowd. “Here’s the reality that people like this ugly man don’t understand,” she said. “We are Minnesota strong, and we will stay resilient in the face of whatever they might throw at us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone in the crowd later thanked Ms. Omar for staying and continuing after the assault, which had shaken not only her but the entire room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I learned at a young age you don’t give in to threats,” Ms. Omar said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About an hour after the town hall, Ms. Omar posted on social media that she was OK and grateful to her constituents for rallying behind her after the assault. “I’m a survivor so this small agitator isn’t going to intimidate me from doing my work,” she said. “I don’t let bullies win.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Capitol Police, which investigates threats against lawmakers, said in a statement that the attack on Ms. Omar was “unacceptable” and would be met with “swift justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are now working with our federal partners to see this man faces the most serious charges possible to deter this kind of violence in our society,” the agency said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As video of the encounter quickly circulated on social media, some officials condemned the assault. Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis denounced the attack, saying on X that “this kind of behavior will not be tolerated in our city,” and that “violence and intimidation have no place in Minneapolis,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Nancy Mace, a South Carolina Republican who has often been at odds with Ms. Omar, said she was “deeply disturbed” by the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Regardless of how vehemently I disagree with her rhetoric — and I do — no elected official should face physical attacks,” she said in a social media post. “This is not who we are.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Bogel-Burroughs contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:40:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Noem’s Handling of Shooting Put Her in Trump’s Penalty Box, but Just Briefly</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/noem-trump-minnesota-shooting-fallout.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-noem-gzwq/27dc-noem-gzwq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his second term, President Trump has been extremely reluctant to fire or even publicly rebuke his aides. So it was no small thing on Monday when he unmistakably gave Kristi Noem, his homeland security secretary, a serious knuckle rapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing an intense and increasingly bipartisan fusillade of criticism over the killing of a protester in Minneapolis and how Ms. Noem and other officials sought to portray the victim as a “domestic terrorist,” Mr. Trump removed the official running the deportation campaign in Minnesota and replaced him with an aide reporting directly to him, effectively cutting Ms. Noem out of the chain of command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked later about Ms. Noem’s characterization of the victim, Alex Pretti, the White House press secretary, Karoline Leavitt, declined to defend it, distinctly distancing Mr. Trump from her remarks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s apparent displeasure with the handling of the situation in Minnesota was quickly mirrored in conservative media. A New York Post front page called Ms. Noem “Iced Barbie.” On Fox News, a morning host argued that she should be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But her time in Mr. Trump’s penalty box was measured in hours. By Monday night, she was in the Oval Office, meeting with Mr. Trump. By Tuesday the president was telling reporters that her job was safe and that the media should focus more on her role in shutting down illegal immigration into the country, not the chaotic scenes coming out of Minnesota in which agents who report to her have twice shot and killed American citizens protesting their presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think she’s doing a very good job,” Mr. Trump said. “The border is totally secure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the episode was the latest in a year in which her high-profile efforts on behalf of Mr. Trump’s aggressive drive to shut off illegal immigration and deport millions of people have drawn intense criticism and caused heartburn for the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Thom Tillis of North Carolina, a Republican retiring at the end of his term, told reporters at the Capitol on Tuesday that Ms. Noem’s actions had been “amateurish” and that she should be fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What she’s done in Minnesota should be disqualifying,” Mr. Tillis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials at the Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has frustrated Mr. Trump with some of the department’s tactics, like work-site raids that harmed businesses, including one on a Hyundai factory, according to people familiar with the matter. She has angered Republican senators with her handling of grants from the Federal Emergency Management Agency. And her propensity for flashy, self-promotional displays has generated some backlash among the rank and file of her agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some members of Immigration and Customs Enforcement disliked what they perceived as Ms. Noem’s theatricality, according to three former agency officials who were granted anonymity to speak frankly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They objected to photo ops that showed her in field gear accompanying agents on immigration operations, accusing her of cosplaying, such as an episode in Phoenix in which her bulletproof vest appeared to be improperly secured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one ICE field office, agents used disparaging nicknames for Ms. Noem that played on her self-promotion, such as “ICE Barbie,” one of the people said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some inside the agency believe that leading immigration enforcement is part of a broader effort on her part to run for president in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Ms. Noem’s choice of aides has drawn scrutiny, particularly her reliance on Corey Lewandowski, the onetime Trump political adviser who is a constant presence at her side and was among those in the Oval Office with her on Monday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside ICE, there have been high levels of distrust of both Mr. Lewandowski and Madison Sheahan, who was installed as deputy director last year. Ms. Sheahan was previously a political aide of Ms. Noem’s. Some officials at ICE believed that Ms. Sheahan was relaying what was happening at the agency to Mr. Lewandowski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond those concerns, there have been more practical issues. Agency officials have been frustrated with being forced to get Ms. Noem’s approval for every contract worth $100,000 or above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At ICE, according to one official, that made it more difficult to spend the extra money received from the domestic policy bill signed into law last year by Mr. Trump, especially as the White House presses for huge expansions of detention capacity for the deportation drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official said that even existing contracts had expired as they waited for approval, forcing the agency to pay late fees to companies it contracts with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also frustration at the level of power she gave Gregory Bovino, the Border Patrol official who had been the public face of the deportation campaign in Minneapolis before being removed by Mr. Trump on Monday. Ms. Noem had installed him to run deportation operations across the country, and, according to three U.S. officials, he reported to Ms. Noem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to remove him from Minnesota, said one official, helps with returning the agency to a more normal chain of command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem’s approach to the job has caused bipartisan pushback — both to her tactics on the immigration crackdown and also to her handling of the department’s intelligence analysts — who have been directed to focus more on immigration than other security issues — and the downsizing of FEMA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the raid on a Hyundai facility in Georgia in early September, in which agents detained hundreds of South Korean citizens on hand to help build a new battery plant, Mr. Trump told his top immigration officials to use a more targeted approach when it came to his deportation campaign, according to a senior White House official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump told the officials to “focus on the criminals,” rather than to target work sites like Home Depots, restaurants, hotels and farms. Mr. Trump has told his aides they need to be conscious of the business community when it comes to their mass deportation campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Hyundai raid, people familiar with the episode said, he told a group of senior officials, including Ms. Noem, to “use your heads.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem’s push to downsize FEMA has also raised alarm among leaders of disaster-prone communities, including Republicans, about the nation’s readiness for emergencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem has said cuts to FEMA’s staffing and spending are needed to make the agency less bloated and Washington-centric, and to allow states and communities to lead disaster response, but she has faced blowback for the impacts those changes may have on communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Carolina’s Republican senators repeatedly held up votes on homeland security nominees in the fall until FEMA approved delayed aid for parts of western North Carolina still recovering from Hurricane Helene in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Republican senators were among a group of lawmakers that gathered privately with FEMA veterans this month to raise questions about the ways a FEMA overhaul could affect their constituents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Bill Cassidy, Republican of Louisiana, said on Monday that he had appealed both to FEMA and to Russell T. Vought, the White House budget director, about delays in disaster recovery funds to his home state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem’s partisanship has prompted pushback on Capitol Hill from Democrats, more than 160 of whom have signed on to an effort to impeach Ms. Noem. The articles of impeachment, filed by Representative Robin Kelly of Illinois, accuse her of obstruction of Congress, violation of public trust and self-dealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impeachment push will go nowhere while Republicans control the House. But House Democratic leaders said they would keep up the pressure if Mr. Trump refused to fire her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can do this the easy way or the hard way,” said Representatives Hakeem Jeffries of New York, Katherine M. Clark of Massachusetts and Pete Aguilar of California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erica L. Green, Catie Edmondson, Nicholas Nehamas and Scott Dance contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/noem-trump-minnesota-shooting-fallout.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:57:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Restore Minnesota House to Even Split Amid Immigration Turmoil</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minnesota-house-special-elections.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-minnesota-election-1-hfzj/27nat-minnesota-election-1-hfzj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats won two vacant seats in the Minnesota House of Representatives on Tuesday, The Associated Press said, restoring that chamber to an even partisan split amid upheaval in the state over the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results were not unexpected. The districts are heavily Democratic, and in one of the races, the Democratic nominee was the only candidate on the ballot. Shelley Buck, a former president of the Prairie Island Indian Community’s Tribal Council, won one of the seats, and Meg Luger-Nikolai, a lawyer, won the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seats, one in St. Paul and another in suburban St. Paul, became vacant after the Democrats who previously held them were elected to other offices in November. Assuming there are no other changes before Ms. Buck and Ms. Luger-Nikolai are sworn in, their elections will leave the Minnesota House with 67 Republicans and 67 Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats hold a slim majority in the Minnesota State Senate, and the state’s governor, Tim Walz, is a Democrat. While the results on Tuesday denied Republicans an outright House majority, Democrats will still not be able to enact their policy agenda without Republican support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elections played out at an extraordinarily tense time in Minnesota. Federal immigration agents have flooded into the state in recent weeks, making thousands of arrests, clashing with protesters and fatally shooting two U.S. citizens. Alex Pretti, an intensive-care nurse at a Veterans Affairs hospital, was killed by federal agents on Saturday, and Renee Good, a poet and a mother of three, was killed by an agent earlier this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local and state officials have repeatedly criticized the tactics of immigration agents and have filed a lawsuit claiming the surge of federal agents is unconstitutional. The Trump administration has criticized Minnesota Democrats for not cooperating more with immigration enforcement, as well as for a fraud scheme in state social service programs that played out on their watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Minnesota Senate subcommittee is scheduled to hold a hearing on Thursday about the impact of the federal immigration enforcement campaign. State lawmakers from across the country are also expected to visit the state this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several legislative seats in Minnesota have been contested in special elections since the start of 2025 after the resignations and deaths of lawmakers, including State Representative Melissa Hortman, a Democrat who was fatally shot in June in what the authorities called an act of political violence.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minnesota-house-special-elections.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:11:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tails of the City: San Francisco’s Latest Animal Sensation Is a Mountain Lion</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/mountain-lion-san-francisco.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-mountain-lion-ghqf/27nat-mountain-lion-ghqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cellphones around San Francisco buzzed late Monday night with a very unusual alert: A young mountain lion had been spotted prowling around Pacific Heights, the upscale northern neighborhood dotted with mansions and lush parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you see it, slowly back away,” the alert read, adding that it would also be wise to call 911.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents swapped texts and scared-face emojis. Local media outlets posted videos showing the mountain lion walking past Muni bus stops. Another mountain lion had been captured in San Francisco in 2021 after climbing a tree, but any other cougars in town since then had kept a low profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city that famously has more dogs than children, that counts flocks of wild parrots, packs of coyotes and docks filled with sea lions among its residents, went to bed not knowing just how its latest bizarre animal story line would play out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of the night, at about 1:30 a.m., Animal Care and Control officers scouring the neighborhood spotted the mountain lion on California Street and called police. Patrol cars pulled up, and officers saw the creature leap over a tall fence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon further inspection, it appeared that the frightened animal had wedged himself in a narrow gap between two apartment buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By early morning, dozens of officials from the San Francisco Zoo, the San Francisco Police Department, the San Francisco Fire Department, San Francisco Animal Care and Control and the California Department of Fish and Wildlife were on the scene — and one of them was inside the apartment of Jessica Fajardo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Fajardo, a 35-year-old tech worker, said it was strange to see an animal control official in her apartment at dawn, but her husband had encountered the officer while out walking the couple’s dog and had invited her up to the sixth-floor apartment for a better look at the mountain lion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She came up, she went out onto the fire escape and shone a flashlight around,” Ms. Fajardo recounted in an interview. “I’ve seen a lot of coyotes and have gotten used to cohabitating with them, but definitely a mountain lion is next level.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, the morning got stranger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials shut down a section of California Street. Others peered at the puma from nearby rooftops trying to figure out how to get it out of its tiny hiding place. The city sent another cellphone alert that the mountain lion had been located and a nearby school went into lockdown, said Lt. Mariano Elias, a spokesman for the San Francisco Fire Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The saga was just the latest in a long string of San Francisco animal happenings. Earlier this month, thousands of people attended the funeral of Claude, the albino alligator who had delighted crowds at the California Academy of Sciences for 17 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days before that, the city was abuzz about the news that a coyote had swum across the bay to Alcatraz Island, the site of a notorious former federal prison known as the Rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late last year, Kit Kat, a beloved bodega cat, was struck and killed by a Waymo self-driving taxi, which started the city debating the merits of such vehicles. Just after that, a newly appointed member of the Board of Supervisors had to resign after it was revealed that she had left her pet shop in horrific condition, with animal corpses in the freezer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, a record 2,000 sea lions swamped the docks at Pier 39 with a deafening chorus of “Arf! Arf! Arf!” And the San Francisco Zoo has had a string of can-you-believe-it happenings — including a kidnapped lemur in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“San Franciscans do love their animals,” said Cassandra Costello, the San Francisco Zoo’s interim co-chief executive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Animals are a great distraction from everyday life, so a mountain lion walking on city streets is something that really mesmerizes the public,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back at the mountain lion’s hiding spot, a state official was able to shoot a tranquilizer dart from above to render it motionless. Then a veterinarian from the local zoo shot two more darts from the side and ensured the animal was fully unconscious by prodding it with a pole and getting no response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crew was then able to pull the mountain lion into the garden and place it on an orange tarp for a medical exam. It appeared healthy, and an ear tag identified him as a male just under 2 years old who had grown up in a woodsy area about 50 miles south of the city. Young mountain lions often leave their families around that age, but it is not known exactly how or why he ventured all the way to the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As all this was happening, neighbors watched in awe — and with hope that the cat would survive the ordeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chloe Safier said neighbors had been joking that they should turn the side yard into a petting zoo with a sign reading “Home of the Mountain Lion.” One neighbor, she said, was playing Wordle while watching and had plugged in L-I-O-N-S as her starting word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“More than anything, I wanted this little cub to get home to his family,” Ms. Safier said, noting that the capture had made her late to a work meeting, but that her colleagues understood “the mountain lion situation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After officials determined the mountain lion was healthy, but fully zonked out and temporarily harmless, they put a mask on him, strapped his legs together and loaded all 77 pounds of him into a metal cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan, officials said, was to release him back into his native South Bay habitat and hope that when it came to visiting San Francisco, once was enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the mountain lion captured, Ms. Safier was ready to relax. She took her baby boy to a nearby park — and there, by the playground, was a coyote.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/mountain-lion-san-francisco.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:11:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At the Center of the ICE Uproar, a Familiar Figure: Corey Lewandowski</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/corey-lewandowski-noem-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/us/politics/27pol-lewandowski/27pol-lewandowski-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Day 1, he was Donald Trump’s pit bull.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corey Lewandowski was a hard-charging political operative who worked for a group backed by the Koch brothers when Mr. Trump put him in charge of a nascent White House campaign with only a handful of staff members in 2015. Untested at the presidential level, he led with a simple mantra: “Let Trump be Trump.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an attack-and-never-apologize style that mirrored his boss’s, Mr. Lewandowski could almost always count on Mr. Trump’s eventual support over the next decade, as he ping-ponged from government to lobbying and back again with several scandals in his wake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now back as a top adviser to Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, he finds himself at the center of the uproar over the immigration crackdown in Minnesota, where two American citizens have been killed by federal agents in the past month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lewandowski and Ms. Noem met with Mr. Trump on Monday for nearly two hours as the administration faced intense pressure, including from Republicans, to ease up federal immigration agents’ aggressive tactics in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump did not suggest that either Ms. Noem’s or Mr. Lewandowski’s jobs were at risk, according to people briefed on the meeting, but speculation has swirled about their future amid signs of Republican unease with Ms. Noem’s combative, camera-heavy approach to immigration enforcement. Democrats and a few Republicans have called for investigations into the Minnesota operation that could potentially draw in Mr. Lewandowski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He looms as a significant figure inside the Department of Homeland Security, where he has been serving as a “special government employee” despite questions about whether he has exceeded the limit of 130 days a year for such workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem’s decision to empower Mr. Lewandowski has frustrated some in the agency and at Immigration and Customs Enforcement, which is part of the homeland security department. One D.H.S. official, speaking on the condition of anonymity because they were not authorized to speak publicly, said that Mr. Lewandowski was known as someone willing to fire anyone perceived as getting in his way. At times, this official said, he has mused about which officials were stalling certain priorities and whether they should be fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.S. official said that directions at ICE were coming from Mr. Lewandowski and that nothing got done at the agency without his blessing. At times, this person said, Mr. Lewandowski yelled at ICE leaders as the pressure to meet Mr. Trump’s mass deportation goals increased last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lewandowski has also been present at pivotal moments for Ms. Noem and the department, including speeches and controversial episodes. He was at the news conference in Los Angeles last year when Senator Alex Padilla, a Democrat from California, was forcibly removed and handcuffed after he tried to talk to Ms. Noem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lewandowski did not respond to a text message seeking comment. A spokeswoman for the Department of Homeland Security did not respond to requests for comment about Mr. Lewandowski, but she pointed to what she called “ICE’s remarkable results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Mr. Lewandowski would again find himself in the center of things was no surprise to Republicans who have watched his cat-with-nine-lives political career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Corey has shown that he is the ultimate loyalist,” said Stephanie Grisham, who worked on Mr. Trump’s 2016 campaign and served as White House press secretary during his first term but became an outspoken critic after the Jan. 6, 2021, riot at the Capitol. “I’ve never seen him back away or even slightly criticize the president in any way, and that’s pretty much all you have to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in Mr. Trump’s first bid, Mr. Lewandowski attracted criticism that he was not up to the task to make the New York businessman’s bare-bones campaign compete with well-funded opponents like former Gov. Jeb Bush of Florida and Senator Ted Cruz of Texas. After a narrow loss to Mr. Cruz in Iowa, Mr. Lewandowski faced mounting doubts about the campaign’s strategy in New Hampshire — his home state — but Mr. Trump, of course, ended up sweeping to victory there and then won South Carolina and Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lewandowski further endeared himself to his boss by regularly berating reporters, leaving menacing late-night voice mail messages and threatening to put them in the “doghouse” for critical coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his antipathy toward the news media took a darker turn in March 2016, when he grabbed a reporter for Breitbart News, Michelle Fields, who posted a picture of bruising on her arm. He was charged with battery but the charges were later dropped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode would be an early preview of how both Mr. Trump and Mr. Lewandowski tended to respond to controversy. At first, they denied the accusations and suggested Ms. Fields was lying, with Mr. Lewandowski calling her “delusional.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after video emerged of Mr. Lewandowski grabbing Ms. Fields, the two men continued to dispute what happened. “If you look at her, in my book and according to a lot of people, she’s grabbing at me, and he’s acting as an intermediary and trying to block her from doing that,” Mr. Trump said at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked whether he might fire Mr. Lewandowski over the incident, Mr. Trump was blunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t discard people,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Grisham, the former Trump press secretary, said that Mr. Lewandowski “knew to kind of disappear from sight for a while.” She said, “That’s all you really have to do is get out of his line of sight for a while and wait for somebody else to mess up,” adding, “and then you can kind of get back in there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June 2016, however, Mr. Trump did fire Mr. Lewandowski as campaign manager, with Republicans worried about their presumptive nominee’s weak operation against what seemed like a formidable opponent in Hillary Clinton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Lewandowski did not go far, quickly earning a CNN contract and becoming one of Mr. Trump’s chief defenders on cable news. He was paid $20,000 by the Trump campaign in August, two months after he was fired, for “strategy consulting,” according to campaign finance records. In the final weeks of the campaign, he was seen on Mr. Trump’s plane and at his rallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump’s victory, Mr. Lewandowski opened a lobbying shop in Washington, where he served as an informal adviser to the president and wrote a book about his time with him titled “Let Trump Be Trump.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also courted new controversies. In December 2017, a pop singer, Joy Villa, accused him of slapping her twice on the buttocks at a party in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, though, he maintained access to the president. The same month, Mr. Lewandowski was in the Oval Office, lashing out at some of Mr. Trump’s top advisers and criticizing the Republican National Committee, all in defense of the president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in 2021, a Republican donor accused Mr. Lewandowski of making unwanted sexual advances and touching her inappropriately at a dinner in Las Vegas, saying he had grown aggressive and thrown a drink at her when she made clear she was rebuffing him. He was soon removed from his role overseeing a super PAC backing Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump aides insisted at the time that this episode was different, and that Mr. Trump would distance himself from Mr. Lewandowski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But during the 2024 campaign, Mr. Lewandowski was back in the fold, hired as an adviser to the Trump campaign with vague responsibilities. Aides suggested that Mr. Trump found comfort in Mr. Lewandowski’s presence — no matter his history, his volatility or his penchant for controversy — because he was an original believer that Mr. Trump could become president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just like him,” Mr. Trump told Olivia Nuzzi of New York magazine in 2024. “Corey’s a character.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tyler Pager contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/corey-lewandowski-noem-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:26:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>