<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 08:48:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Cyberattack in Venezuela Demonstrated Precision of U.S. Capabilities</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/cyberattack-venezuela-military.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-cyber-lwtm/15dc-cyber-lwtm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cyberattack that plunged Venezuela’s capital into darkness this month demonstrated the Pentagon’s ability not just to turn off the lights, but also to allow them to be turned back on, according to U.S. officials briefed on the operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jan. 3 operation was one of the most public displays of offensive U.S. cyber-capabilities in recent years. It showed that at least with a country like Venezuela, whose military does not have sophisticated defenses against cyberattacks, the United States could use cyberweapons with powerful and precise effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military also used cyberweapons to interfere with air defense radar, according to people briefed on the matter, who discussed sensitive details of the operation on the condition of anonymity. (Venezuela’s most powerful radar was not functional, however.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning off the power in Caracas and interfering with radar allowed U.S. military helicopters to move into the country undetected on their mission to capture Nicolás Maduro, the Venezuelan president who has now been brought to the United States to face drug charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senators on the Armed Services Committee are set to ask questions about the Venezuela operation at the confirmation hearing on Thursday of Lt. Gen. Joshua M. Rudd, President Trump’s nominee to lead the U.S. Cyber Command and the National Security Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Rudd, a longtime special operation forces commander, is currently the deputy head of the Indo-Pacific Command. If confirmed, he would lead an agency and command that have had a number of senior officials forced out by Laura Loomer, the far-right conspiracy theorist and Trump ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you should know. The Times makes a careful decision any time it uses an anonymous source. The information the source supplies must be newsworthy and give readers genuine insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump fired Gen. Tim Haugh, the former head of the Cyber Command and the N.S.A., in April after Ms. Loomer noted that he had been appointed by the previous administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers received classified briefings on the cyberoperations this week, but General Rudd’s confirmation hearing will be their first opportunity to pose questions in public about the raid as well as the Trump administration’s plans for more aggressive cyberoperations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a news conference hours after the raid that captured Mr. Maduro, Mr. Trump made reference to the cyberoperation, though he did not explicitly say what it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was dark, the lights of Caracas were largely turned off due to a certain expertise that we have, it was dark, and it was deadly,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on Wednesday, a spokeswoman for the U.S. Cyber Command said the organization “was proud to support Operation Absolute Resolve,” as the mission was named. She added that the command was equipped to execute orders of the president at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attack caused most of Caracas’s residents to lose their power for a few minutes, though some neighborhoods near the military base where Mr. Maduro was captured were left without electricity for up to 36 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts have long worried that a cyberattack on the power grid could cause widespread collateral damage, particularly if hospitals or trauma centers lost power while trying to treat badly injured people. But that did not happen in Caracas, in large measure because the power was restored quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, after years of blackouts, Caracas was better prepared for a power outage. Most hospitals in the city have installed backup generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medical workers said there were no known fatalities during the cyberattack in areas that depend on constant power, such as maternity wards or intensive care units. Because the attack happened in the early hours, most people were asleep and were mostly unaffected by the blackout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the Maduro government accused the United States of conducting a cyberattack on a hydropower plant that plunged much of the country into darkness for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power failures caused sporadic outbursts of looting and unrest, bringing the government close to collapse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The electric war announced and led by the US imperialism against our people will be defeated,” Mr. Maduro wrote on social media in March 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the first Trump administration was trying to push Mr. Maduro from power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mike Pompeo, then the secretary of state, denied any U.S. involvement in the power failure, blaming it instead on Cuban engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Maduro’s government never provided evidence for the cyberattack, and electrical experts said the blackout could have been caused by poor maintenance and underinvestment. A union official at the state electricity company said at the time that the blackout was caused by a brush fire under a power line, which destabilized the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, in the following years, Venezuelan officials increasingly pointed to a U.S. plot behind frequent industrial incidents in the country, without providing evidence. Rumors of U.S.-directed saboteurs only increased in the tense month before Mr. Maduro was captured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Sella contributed reporting from Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/cyberattack-venezuela-military.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:21:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Releases Health Plan but It’s Short on Specifics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-health-care-plan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-trump-health-care-zcjp/15dc-trump-health-care-zcjp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under pressure to address affordability issues in the country, President Trump on Thursday released his long-awaited health care plan, urging Congress to pass measures that would codify steps his administration has already taken to try to lower drug costs and providing what a White House official called “broad direction” to back health savings accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan was short on specific details and left much of the direction for how to finalize it up to Congress. It amounted to a few paragraphs on a webpage, released with a video of Mr. Trump promoting what he called “the great health care plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan rejects efforts to extend the enhanced Affordable Care Act benefits that expired at the end of the year and have been the subject of intense debate on Capitol Hill. Mr. Trump briefly considered supporting an extension of those insurance subsidies, but has since backed away. Congress is continuing to consider options for extending the funding, though prospects for passage seem dim, and the enrollment period for insurance concludes today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lisa Murkowski, Republican of Alaska and part of a group of senators trying to reinstate the subsidies, said the talks would be continuing. “I’m not giving up,” she said on Thursday. Still, she acknowledged that any plan would struggle to move forward without White House support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, Mr. Trump’s plan calls for redirecting insurance subsidies into individual health savings accounts, which people could use to purchase health care services directly. Lawmakers have been discussing a few similar proposals, with varying details about the magnitude of the funding and how the money could be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such plan came up for a vote on the Senate floor last month, and Senate Republicans did not have the 60 votes necessary to advance past a filibuster. It would have replaced the expiring subsidies by putting similar amounts into health savings accounts for consumers who chose high deductible insurance plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal would require insurance companies to provide more transparency on the prices they pay medical providers and their profit margins, though both sets of data are already required of the industry to some degree. Mr. Trump has long believed that improving the transparency of health care prices will drive down costs, though evidence for that contention is limited, and some economists believe publishing health care prices could actually help raise them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also calls for a requirement that would force insurance companies to prominently post the frequency with which they deny care. And it calls for more regulation of pharmacy benefit managers — giant middlemen companies like CVS Caremark and Express Scripts that manage prescription drug benefits for Americans with health insurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal builds on another longstanding health care priority of the president’s — lowering prescription drug prices. It asks Congress to codify voluntary deals Mr. Trump has already made with drug companies. Those deals cover 16 of the 17 major drugmakers to which the president sent letters last summer demanding lower prices. The last holdout, Regeneron, said it is still in talks with the administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deals seek to align some U.S. drug prices with the lower levels in European countries, a long-sought goal of Mr. Trump’s. Drugmakers agreed to offer those lower international prices to state Medicaid programs, which cover lower-income Americans and already pay the lowest prices in the United States for drugs. They also pledged to introduce new drugs in the United States at prices comparable to what they ask European countries to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the companies committed to setting up websites to sell some of their drugs directly to American patients, without going through insurance; a site to help patients navigate those company websites, TrumpRx.gov, is expected to become operational later this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects of those pricing deals are likely to be limited, at least in the short term, because they do not cut the prices that drugmakers currently offer to employers, private insurers and other government programs. Nor do they address the high out-of-pocket drug costs for most American patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president is responding to the many people who are talking to him about the problems in health care,” said Dr. Mehmet Oz, the administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, adding: “People are complaining about drug prices. We have a framework for addressing that. They complain about insurance premiums in general, not just in the A.C.A. They are complaining about the lack of accountability of big insurance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he described the proposals, Dr. Oz referred to the document as both a “framework” and a “plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a beautiful framework, and that’s why — it’s a health care plan that I think we can celebrate when we’re done.” he said. “That’s what makes it great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bipartisan group of Senators is continuing to negotiate on legislation to extend Obamacare subsidies, but congressional leaders seem uninterested. Republicans passed major Medicaid cuts as part of their major tax and domestic policy legislation this summer. But there has been little appetite among congressional leaders for another major health care bill.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-health-care-plan.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:16:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ICE’s No. 2 Official Leaves to Run for the House in Ohio</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/pol-sheahan-zgbl/pol-sheahan-zgbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a moment when President Trump’s immigration crackdown has inflamed political tensions, one of the top enforcers of his effort to deport undocumented immigrants is leaving his administration to run for Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madison D. Sheahan, 28, the deputy director of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, announced on Thursday that she would enter the Republican primary race to oppose Representative Marcy Kaptur, a 22-term Democrat who represents a northwest Ohio district that Mr. Trump won in the last two presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her announcement video, Ms. Sheahan called herself “a Trump conservative” and focused on her work helping carry out the president’s deportation agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In less than one year at ICE, I’ve stopped more illegal immigration than Marcy Kaptur has in her 43 years in Washington,” Ms. Sheahan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How top of mind Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown remains for voters come November will be one of the biggest question of the midterm elections. Polling so far suggests that while Americans generally favor tighter immigration policies, they believe Mr. Trump is going too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CNN survey released Wednesday found that 51 percent of Americans said ICE enforcement actions were making cities less safe, compared with 31 percent who perceived an increase in safety. The fatal shooting of a Minneapolis woman by an ICE officer has touched off nationwide protests and renewed calls from some liberal Democrats to abolish the agency and impeach Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kaptur, 79, was first elected to represent the Toledo area in northwest Ohio in 1982, and she coasted to re-election every two years before Ohio Republicans redrew what had been a safe Democratic district into a competitive one before the 2022 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, she won by less than a percentage point against Derek Merrin, who at the time served in the Ohio legislature. On the same ballot, Mr. Trump carried the district by seven points against Vice President Kamala Harris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Merrin announced another challenge to Ms. Kaptur in June. Several other Republicans have entered the primary, including Josh Williams, a state representative from Toledo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before coming to Washington, Ms. Sheahan worked as a political aide to Ms. Noem when she was South Dakota’s governor and as secretary of the Louisiana Department of Wildlife and Fisheries. Ms. Noem praised Ms. Sheahan as a “terrific leader” in a statement to Fox News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats professed confidence that Ms. Kaptur would prevail, but they steered clear of addressing Ms. Sheahan’s immigration enforcement credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Voters are tired of the self-dealing corruption and culture of lawlessness they’ve seen over the last year,” said Kegan Zimmermann, Ms. Kaptur’s campaign manager. “They want a leader focused on affordability and real results, and Marcy Kaptur consistently works across the aisle to deliver both.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan’s departure from the agency comes as the Trump administration carries out an immigration enforcement blitz in Minnesota, which ICE has called its “largest operation to date.” Roughly 3,000 federal agents and officers are being deployed to the Minneapolis region as part of the effort, which administration officials have said is meant to crack down on illegal immigration and fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operation has led to clashes between protesters and law enforcement officers. Local officials in Minneapolis have urged immigration officers to leave the city, saying their efforts have sowed chaos. Trump administration officials have pledged that federal agents will remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan has repeatedly defended the agency’s enforcement operations, saying they are necessary to remove people in the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is taking the stand and making sure that we’re enforcing the law as it’s written with the support of Secretary Noem leading the way to make sure we get these dangerous criminals removed from our community,” Ms. Sheahan said in an interview with Fox News in September.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:47:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Runaway Emu Leads Florida Corporal in 45-Minute Police Chase</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/runaway-emu-florida-video.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/arts/_-_high/_-_high-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day that Cpl. Thomas Keisler reports to work at the sheriff’s office in St. Johns County, Fla., there is a chance he’ll come face to face with an animal on the road. In his 25 years of working in a county with farmland and rural areas, he’s seen officers encounter horses, goats, pigs, cows, turkeys and ducks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But last Friday brought a new creature to his patch: a runaway emu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporal was sent to wrangle one bobbing along a county road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s certainly different than coming across a horse or a cow because it was literally like trying to restrain a miniature velociraptor,” Corporal Keisler said in a phone interview on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he got the call about the loose bird, he underestimated what it would take to get the situation under control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agricultural deputies usually respond to that type of call, he said, but they were in training when the emu went on the road. “I figured I can handle something like this oversized turkey,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How hard could it be, after all, to grab a large and flightless bird? According to body-camera footage, which was released by the sheriff’s office on Wednesday, considerably harder than expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler and the emu, named Tina, would ultimately spend about 45 minutes together. The footage shows only about two minutes of their entanglement, which appears mutually frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, Tina walks at an unhurried pace along the county road as the corporal tries to get her to come toward him. Corporal Keisler even sounds upbeat, but as the video continues, the occasional deep sigh is audible. Tina just keeps sauntering away. At one point, Corporal Keisler has his hands on Tina. She runs away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An emu like Tina, who had escaped from a farm, is not so easy to catch. Though emus can’t fly with their tiny, useless wings, they have powerful legs and will use their heavy feet to strike, according to the San Diego Zoo Wildlife Alliance. Emus are the second-largest bird in the world, after ostriches, and can be from 4.9 to 6.2 feet tall and weigh from 66 to 121 pounds. Adult female emus are larger and heavier than males.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler said that his past experience with animals had proved to be pretty useless in apprehending Tina. “We don’t get emu combat training and restraining for some reason, or I’ve never had that,” he said. “Maybe I missed that day of training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of their battle, Corporal Keisler put handcuffs on Tina’s legs because she had ripped holes in his uniform and he needed to stop her from kicking him. “That was really the only option that I had because she had cornered herself in an area that was going to be very difficult to bring her out,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, Tina’s owner knew her bird was on the loose and was able to meet the corporal and the bird under arrest. The sheriff’s office did not say where the bird is usually housed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tina calmed down immediately when she was reunited with her owner, the corporal said. “The owner brought her some food, and it was the most gentle creature I’ve seen,” he said, “but it’s not what it showed me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler was happy that the owner was there, too, and said of Tina, “I think we were both kind of over each other at that point.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/runaway-emu-florida-video.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:58:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Verizon Offers $20 Credit to Users Affected by Outage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/verizon-outage-issues-credit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-verizon-lzmf/15xp-verizon-lzmf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon said on Thursday that it would credit $20 to customers affected by the widespread outage that disrupted cellular and data service for over six hours on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage began to draw widespread attention around 12:30 p.m. Eastern and persisted into the evening. Phones on the network displayed “SOS” in the status bar where the cellular antenna icon typically appears. A feature that allows users to make calls over Wi-Fi also appeared to be down. Some customers complained online that their service was briefly restored, only to lose it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage reached a peak of more than 170,000 concurrent reports of disrupted service early Wednesday afternoon, according to Downdetector, an outage-tracking site. Verizon, with 146.1 million subscribers in the United States, is the country’s largest mobile carrier and one of the biggest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday afternoon, Christina Moon Ashraf, a Verizon spokeswoman, blamed “a software issue” for the disruption, adding that the company was conducting a full review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday, we did not meet the standard of excellence our customers expect and that we expect of ourselves,” Ms. Moon Ashraf said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said that affected customers could log into the myVerizon app to accept a $20 account credit and that they would be notified by text message when the credit was available. That covers, on average, multiple days of service, she said, adding that business customers would be contacted directly about their credits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This credit isn’t meant to make up for what happened,” Ms. Moon Ashraf said. “No credit really can. But it’s a way of acknowledging our customers’ time and showing that this matters to us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’s website said Thursday that customers still encountering problems with their service should restart their devices to reconnect to the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the outage was most likely wider than reported by websites that track disruptions to communications and utility services, according to Lee W. McKnight, an associate professor in the School of Information Studies at Syracuse University, who researches wireless grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage left customers frustrated from coast to coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim Garrity, a civil rights lawyer in Tallahassee, Fla., said he was questioning witnesses in an employment discrimination case on Wednesday when he lost service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I use my iPhone frequently to quickly search for information bearing on the witnesses’ answers while the examination is in progress,” he said. “The disruption severely interfered with my ability to conduct examinations throughout the day, and further prevented me from speaking with my client.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said other lawyers in his office who reported the same difficulties were unable to reach clients and, in one case, unable to participate in a video court hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nichole Gantshar, who lives in North Carolina but works for a theater in California, said that working remotely meant “my phone is my life.” She said she was able to do most of her work by using Wi-Fi, but once she stopped receiving texts, she could not do anything that required two-factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Many of my daily tasks were completely stopped,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the $20 credit, she said that it was “a nice, but hollow, gesture and it doesn’t make up for the poor communications.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“More important to me as a customer, I want to know what happened, what they are going to do to prevent this in the future, and how they are going to improve communications with customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/verizon-outage-issues-credit.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:32:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nick Reiner Was in a Mental Health Conservatorship in 2020</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/nick-reiner-conservatorship-schizophrenia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/16/multimedia/15nat-reiner-mental-health/16reiner-promo-7pm-ctzq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Reiner, who has been charged with the murder of his parents, Rob Reiner and Michele Singer Reiner, was placed into a yearlong mental health conservatorship in 2020, according to two people with knowledge of the legal arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A clerk with the Los Angeles Superior Court said the conservatorship ended in 2021. Steven Baer, a licensed fiduciary who was appointed as the conservator for Mr. Reiner, said mental illness “is an epidemic that is widely misunderstood and this is a horrible tragedy.” Both people declined to provide further details about the arrangement, citing confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revelation of the conservatorship underscores the severity of the mental health challenges Mr. Reiner faced in recent years, issues that are likely to be central to his legal defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Reiner, the director of movies such as “This Is Spinal Tap” and “The Princess Bride,” and his wife were found stabbed to death in their Los Angeles home on Dec. 14. If Nick Reiner were convicted of two counts of first-degree murder, he could be sentenced to life in prison without parole or the death penalty. He is being represented by a public defender and has not entered a plea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner, 32, has a serious mental illness and had struggled in the weeks before his arrest with a change in his medication, two other people familiar with his health told The New York Times on the condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive medical information. One of those people said he had been diagnosed at different times with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The medication Mr. Reiner had been taking was effective, the other person said, but side effects led him to switch to a new medication about a month before his parents were killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Los Angeles County public defender’s office declined to comment, as did a representative for the district attorney’s office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Mr. Reiner, who had battled drug addiction starting in his teenage years, had been in a conservatorship indicates that a judge determined he had a “grave disability,” meaning he was unable to provide for his basic personal needs for food, clothing or shelter as a result of a mental health disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have to be pretty severe to be placed on a mental health conservatorship in California,” said Lee Blumen, a lawyer with expertise in such cases. “Of all the people who come into this system, a very small group of people actually get placed on conservatorship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner was put under what is known as an L.P.S. conservatorship, based on a 1967 law — the Lanterman-Petris-Short Act — that established a new process for involuntary psychiatric treatment in California. It is distinct from the system that is commonly used to take over medical and financial decision-making for people with dementia or a developmental disability; that system drew significant scrutiny for its use in controlling the affairs of the pop star Britney Spears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L.P.S. conservatorships typically originate from an involuntary psychiatric hospitalization and are initiated by a doctor. In Los Angeles County, officials from the Office of the Public Guardian then assess whether a conservatorship is warranted and make their case to a judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system allows a professional conservator or a person close to the patient, such as a family member, to make decisions about medical treatment, including psychiatric medications. It lasts one year, after which the conservator has the opportunity to try to renew it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear why Mr. Reiner’s conservatorship did not last beyond one year. The county’s Department of Mental Health, which oversees the public guardian’s office, declined to comment or provide any documentation from the legal proceedings, citing patient confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner had long struggled with drug addiction and spoken about it publicly, co-writing a 2016 movie that was directed by his father and was loosely based on the family’s experience with his heroin and cocaine use. He had been in drug treatment about 18 times as a teenager, circling through residential facilities across the country and sometimes experiencing homelessness amid conflict with his parents about returning to rehab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has alluded to broader behavioral health issues, saying in an interview alongside his father that “it was more than drugs — it’s really always about more than that.” But he and his family have not spoken publicly about his psychiatric diagnosis or treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schizophrenia is a severe brain disorder characterized by abnormal thinking, often involving delusions, paranoia or hallucinations. Schizoaffective disorder combines symptoms of schizophrenia with mood episodes, which can be manic or depressive. Both disorders are usually managed with a combination of medications and therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most antipsychotic medications work by blocking receptors for the neurotransmitter dopamine, which affects functions like motivation, reward, mood, attention and sleep. In most patients, they can reduce symptoms like hallucinations and paranoia to a manageable level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they have serious side effects including weight gain, which contributes to a high rate of cardiac disease and early death among people with psychotic illnesses. Many patients stop taking the medications, saying that they leave them sluggish and unmotivated. Researchers have found that as many as half of patients do not take antipsychotic drugs as prescribed, often leading to relapse and hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking generally, any switch in medication for a disorder like schizophrenia is best undertaken over several weeks, said Dr. Demian Rose, a professor of psychiatry and behavioral sciences at the University of California, San Francisco. A slow “cross taper” helps ensure that the new medication is effective and that the old medication is not withdrawn too quickly, he said, adding that discontinuing an antipsychotic medication after long use can induce withdrawal symptoms like insomnia, agitation and restlessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner is being held at the Twin Towers Correctional Facility, a county jail in downtown Los Angeles. When his previous lawyer, Alan Jackson, left the case last week for reasons he did not provide, he told reporters that “pursuant to the law in California, Nick Reiner is not guilty of murder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments indicated that Mr. Jackson may have been preparing a defense centered on mental health. It is unclear whether Mr. Reiner’s current counsel, a public defender, will take a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan J. Hochman, the Los Angeles County district attorney, told reporters this month that he was confident a jury would ultimately convict Mr. Reiner for the “brutal murders of his parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the mental health issues at play, Mr. Reiner’s counsel will have to assess whether he is competent to understand the court proceedings or help with his own defense. Questioning his competency would initiate a process that involves medical examinations and culminates in a decision by a judge or jury. It can take months or years of medical treatment and court proceedings for a defendant to be found competent to stand trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Reiner is deemed competent, he can seek to prove at trial that he is not guilty by reason of insanity. In such cases, the defense must convince a jury that mental health problems made the defendant unable to understand past actions and incapable of distinguishing right from wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But winning acquittals in such cases is rare, said John Kip Cornwell, a law professor at Seton Hall who has expertise in criminal cases involving mental health issues. It can be challenging, he said, to prove that someone, even when experiencing psychosis and paranoia, did not have some understanding that killing a person was wrong. Juries can also be unwilling to let violent crimes go unpunished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Jurors want, instinctively, for justice to be served,” Professor Cornwell said, “and they’re uncomfortable letting someone be found ‘not guilty’ when an innocent victim was killed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If jurors reach a verdict of not guilty by reason of insanity, it means they decided the defendant committed a crime but cannot be held legally responsible. The defendant would typically be confined in a state-run psychiatric hospital and can eventually petition the court for release. That requires convincing a judge that the person does not pose a danger to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn Hubler contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/nick-reiner-conservatorship-schizophrenia.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:59:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did a Supreme Court Loss Embolden Trump on the Insurrection Act?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-insurrection-act.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-insurrection-assess-lfck/15dc-insurrection-assess-lfck-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Brett M. Kavanaugh sometimes says the quiet part out loud. He did that last month when the Supreme Court refused to let President Trump deploy National Guard troops in Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision was a rare loss for the administration at the court, and it seemed to prompt Mr. Trump to abandon his efforts to deploy troops in Illinois, Oregon and California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Justice Kavanaugh, in a footnote in a concurring opinion, suggested that the ruling could be a speed bump on the road to greater presidential power. He pointed to the possibility of Mr. Trump invoking a different law, the Insurrection Act, to send more conventional military troops to American cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a month later, Mr. Trump suggested he might do exactly that in response to violence and protests in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the corrupt politicians of Minnesota don’t obey the law and stop the professional agitators and insurrectionists from attacking the Patriots of I.C.E., who are only trying to do their job, I will institute the INSURRECTION ACT, which many Presidents have done before me,” he wrote on Thursday on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his own social media post hours earlier, Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, had called the opposition to immigration raids in the state a “Minnesota insurrection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has long floated the possibility of invoking the act, and he did not need a sentence in a footnote to give him any ideas. But Justice Kavanaugh’s statement did make plain that the Supreme Court’s action in blocking one kind of deployment could set the stage for other, more aggressive ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump relied on a different law to order National Guard troops to cities last summer, an obscure measure adopted in 1903 and 1908 that said deployments were allowed for three reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One, concerning foreign invasions, plainly did not apply to the events in Illinois. The second permissible reason for deploying the Guard was if a rebellion was underway, or if there was danger of one. That is a stretch, and the majority did not cite it, much less discuss it. The court’s order focused on the third reason: the president’s right to deploy the National Guard if he is unable to execute laws “with regular forces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five justices joined the unsigned majority opinion, which rejected the Trump administration’s position that “regular forces” referred to civilian law enforcement like Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents. Instead, the majority said, the term referred to the military. Since there had been no showing that those forces would be unable to execute the laws, the administration lost — at least for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh voted with the majority but did not sign its opinion, and accepted only part of its reasoning. Such a “concurrence in the judgment” is unusual in cases decided on the court’s emergency docket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking for himself, Justice Kavanaugh surveyed the legal landscape and said what the majority had left unstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As I read it,” he wrote, “the court’s opinion does not address the president’s authority under the Insurrection Act.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam LiptakSupreme Court reporter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I try to make the Supreme Court accessible to readers. I strive to distill and translate complex legal materials into accessible prose, while presenting fairly the arguments of both sides and remaining alert to the political context and practical consequences of the court’s work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Insurrection Act, a set of laws adopted in the nation’s first century, authorizes the president to use the National Guard or more traditional armed forces to quell widespread public unrest. It seems to give him substantial leeway in determining when circumstances warrant invoking it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law repeatedly says the president can use force “as he considers necessary,” for instance. And a leading precedent, Martin v. Mott, from 1827, said that “the authority to decide whether the exigency has arisen belongs exclusively to the president.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If lawfully invoked, the Insurrection Act would also seem to satisfy the Posse Comitatus Act, a bedrock 1878 law that prohibits the use of the military for law enforcement unless authorized by Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Insurrection Act has been invoked throughout the nation’s history, typically at the request of local officials. It was last used in 1992, following riots in Los Angeles in the wake of the acquittals of four white police officers accused of beating Rodney King, a Black motorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military has also been deployed under the act to address labor disputes, conflicts with Native Americans, looting after natural disasters, and to enforce court orders in the civil rights era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should Mr. Trump invoke the Insurrection Act to send troops to Minneapolis or other cities over the objections of local officials, there will certainly be court challenges, and the Supreme Court may well have another chance to consider what Justice Neil M. Gorsuch in his dissent in the Illinois case called a fraught and grave question: “When, if ever, may the federal government deploy the professional military for domestic law enforcement purposes consistent with the Constitution?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh’s concurring opinion, on the other hand, said the Constitution itself may provide a source of presidential power to deploy troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The court’s opinion does not address or purport to disturb the president’s long-asserted Article II authority to use the U.S. military (as distinct from the National Guard) to protect federal personnel and property and thereby ensure the execution of federal law,” Justice Kavanaugh wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He cited with approval an essay in October by Jack Goldsmith, a law professor at Harvard and an authority on executive power. The essay’s title: “President Trump Holds the Legal Cards on the Use of the Military in the Domestic Sphere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh all but suggested that the challengers’ victory in the Illinois case was Pyrrhic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One apparent ramification of the court’s opinion is that it could cause the president to use the U.S. military more than the National Guard to protect federal personnel and property in the United States,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Goldsmith, for his part, wrote that litigation over any invocation of the Insurrection Act was inevitable, and that the Trump administration, against all odds, may find a way to lose it. But, he wrote, that will not be easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every single word of the Insurrection Act will be intensely contested in court should the president invoke it,” Professor Goldsmith wrote. “And given the administration’s tendency to blunder, to bully, to overstep and to develop factual predicates inadequately, not to mention the president’s always-legally unhelpful social media activity, litigation might be tough and victory for the administration in every instance cannot be assumed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after the Illinois decision landed, Professor Goldsmith wrote in a blog post that the Supreme Court had closed one door and opened another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday’s defeat,” he wrote, “could provide ‘cover’ for the Trump administration to go the Insurrection Act route.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-insurrection-act.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:01:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minneapolis Schools Allow Students to Learn Online Amid ICE Fears</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-schools-online-learning-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-reporter-update18-mhcq/15minneapolis-shooting-reporter-update18-mhcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several of Minnesota’s largest school districts, including those of Minneapolis and St. Paul, are offering students the option to learn remotely amid a federal immigration crackdown that has left many families on edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Minneapolis, where 37-year-old Renee Good was fatally shot by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent last week, students will have the option to learn online until Feb. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The school district in St. Paul said it would offer an online option starting next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Over the past several days, I have received hundreds of messages about offering a temporary virtual learning option for students who do not feel comfortable coming to school right now,” said St. Paul’s schools superintendent, Stacie Stanley, in a video message on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul’s school district, the state’s second largest, is home to a significant immigrant population. Many students speak Spanish, Hmong, Somali or another foreign language at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About half of Spanish-speaking students in St. Paul and a quarter of Somali-speaking students were absent from school last Friday, as tensions escalated in the aftermath of Ms. Good’s death, according to district data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis Public Schools declined to make attendance data available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration launched an immigration enforcement operation in the Twin Cities, primarily focused on Somali immigrants, in December, and last week, ICE announced it was amping up its presence in the Minneapolis area in its “largest operation to date.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials have said that ICE does not target or raid schools, though the administration has rescinded Biden-era guidance that limited immigration enforcement activities in or near “sensitive” locations, such as schools, churches and hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research has shown that immigration raids can lead to increased student absences, hurting student achievement and opportunities to learn, even when they do not occur on school grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation in the Minneapolis area has been especially tense since Ms. Good was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol agents clashed with protesters outside a Minneapolis high school last week, hours after the shooting. In Robbinsdale, a northwest suburb, school officials said that ICE agents detained a parent at a bus stop on Wednesday morning while the parent was dropping a child off for school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Fridley, a district of about 2,700 students north of Minneapolis, roughly a third of students have been absent so far this week, according to the superintendent, Brenda Lewis. The district has a significant Hispanic and Somali population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Students are terrified to come to school,” Dr. Lewis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The district is planning to offer an online option starting next week.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-schools-online-learning-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:48:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arkansas Rescinds Choice of Law School Dean Over Transgender Stance</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a week after naming a new dean, the University of Arkansas Law School withdrew the appointment, saying on Wednesday that the decision was based on “feedback from key external stakeholders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appointee, Emily Suski, a legal scholar at the University of South Carolina, had been selected after a lengthy public search, and the university’s provost, Indrajeet Chaubey, praised her work on medical partnerships to help low-income children when the choice was announced on Jan. 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback that derailed the appointment, members of the state legislature said, was related to her signature on an amicus brief filed with the Supreme Court last year in support of transgender student athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders of Arkansas supported the decision to withdraw the offer, according to her spokesman, Sam Dubke. “Governor Sanders appreciates the University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, for reaching the common sense decision on this matter in the best interest of students,” Mr. Dubke said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief that Ms. Suski signed was filed in a case that was argued this week before the Supreme Court. Dan Sullivan, an Arkansas state senator, said the views expressed in the brief were inconsistent with Arkansas law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you look at some of her opinions to the Supreme Court and amicus briefs, I think she has not reflected the laws of the state of Arkansas,” said Mr. Sullivan, a Republican from Jonesboro who applauded the decision to rescind the offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkansas was the first state to ban gender-affirming medical care for minors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode is an example of how politics has increasingly been influencing university decisions about faculty hiring, which were once the exclusive purview of academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of the nation’s highly charged political environment has been felt primarily in the selection of university presidents, including an episode last year at the University of Florida. The school’s board chose Santa Ono, a former president of the University of Michigan, who was criticized by conservatives for his past support of diversity initiatives. The board’s decision was overruled by a statewide board of political appointees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But political pressures are also influencing searches for deans and even professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, universities have begun to treat job searches, which were once fairly public, as carefully guarded secrets, in order to avoid putting prospective hires in awkward positions if they are rejected. At Arkansas, however, the search for a new law school dean was conducted publicly, with four top candidates making presentations in open meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Arkansas, which had issued a statement Wednesday saying that its offer to Ms. Suski had been withdrawn, said Thursday it had no additional statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski, currently an associate dean at the University of South Carolina, issued a written statement on Thursday saying she was “disappointed and hurt by the university’s decision to rescind my contract.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been informed that the decision was not in any way a reflection of my qualifications to serve as dean,” she wrote, “but rather the result of influence from external individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski’s résumé includes work as a staff attorney for the Legal Aid Justice Center in Charlottesville, Va. Her teaching and legal expertise have been focused on health, poverty and education law, including Title IX, a federal civil rights law that bans sex-based discrimination in education programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amicus brief that she signed along with 16 other legal scholars made a narrowly focused argument on the question of whether the sex assigned at birth should be the sole determining factor in decisions about which sports teams students can compete on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief argued that the case before the Supreme Court should be sent back to the lower courts for further review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Democratic state representative in Arkansas, Nicole Clowney, said in a telephone interview that the offer to Ms. Suski was rescinded after a few state legislators and one executive-branch official became aware that Ms. Suski had signed the brief, and then threatened the university’s funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Clowney, who represents Fayetteville and teaches at the law school, said she saw the decision as a free-speech issue, and added that Ms. Suski was eminently qualified for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker of the state House of Representatives, Brian Evans, a Republican, issued a statement saying his office was not involved in the decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski had been offered a five-year contract with total annual compensation of $350,000, according to documents reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its announcement Wednesday, the law school praised Ms. Suski, but said it had “decided to go in a different direction.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:37:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pentagon Will ‘Refocus’ Military Publication Stars and Stripes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/us/politics/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon on Thursday said it planned to commandeer Stars and Stripes, a government-funded newspaper that covers the military, and align it with official department messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will modernize its operations, refocus its content away from woke distractions that syphon morale, and adapt it to serve a new generation of service members,” Sean Parnell, the chief Pentagon spokesman, wrote in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It will focus on warfighting, weapons systems, fitness, lethality, survivability, and ALL THINGS MILITARY. No more repurposed DC gossip columns; no more Associated Press reprints.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon’s intervention would be a stark departure from historical precedent at the publication, which describes itself as the “U.S. military’s independent news source.” The organization has long prized its latitude to make editorial decisions free from external interference, including from the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stars and Stripes, often referred to as Stripes, has been published continuously since World War II, with daily papers for U.S. military troops overseas and up-to-the-minute news on stripes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement on its website describes its “core values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A news organization must not just cover the news but uncover it. It must follow the story wherever it leads, without allowing preconceived ideas to filter the search for facts or replace the discipline of verification.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon turned down a request to interview Mr. Parnell about the changes. In response to questions, a press official referred to Mr. Parnell’s statement on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Max D. Lederer Jr., the publisher of Stripes, said he knew nothing about the Pentagon’s directive for the publication until after Mr. Parnell’s announcement Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Stripes’ tradition of operating without any meddling from the military, editor in chief Erik Slavin said, “I wouldn’t have taken this job otherwise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Reid, a former editor in chief of Stripes, said, “You have to think small-town newspaper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The mayor may object to a story, but there was no prior censorship and no direction as to what should and should not be covered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reid, 78, who left the publication last year, said that Stripes saw fit to cover the panoply of controversies that have cropped up over the years in the U.S. military, including debates about the role of women, transgender people, and instances of racism and sexism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That might be what they described as woke,” said Mr. Reid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Daily Wire, a conservative outlet, reported that under the new plan, half of the material in Stripes will be generated by the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a directive “would definitely change the character and nature of what we’re presenting to the audience,” said Mr. Lederer. That said, the leadership of Stripes is working with little in the way of formal information about the future of its publication. In addition to receiving no advance notification about Thursday’s announcement, there are no meetings scheduled to discuss it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have the Daily Wire to go on right now — I’ll leave it at that,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the Pentagon’s hostility toward “repurposed DC gossip columns,” Mr. Lederer said, “We don’t carry any gossip columns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Controversy engulfed the publication in President Trump’s first term, when the Pentagon tried to cut its $15.5 million in funding. Mr. Trump came to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The United States of America will NOT be cutting funding to @starsandstripes magazine under my watch,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media. “It will continue to be a wonderful source of information to our Great Military!” Stripes draws its budget in part from federal funding and in part from other, traditional revenue streams for newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post on Wednesday reported that applicants for employment at Stripes faced questions about how they would support Mr. Trump’s policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, the Pentagon introduced a set of binding restrictions that apply to journalists who receive press credentials to report from the military complex. Dozens of journalists with major media outlets surrendered their press badges instead of signing the policy. Department officials subsequently heralded the arrival of a newly credentialed press corps, one populated by pro-Trump commentators and influencers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stripes didn’t have to agonize over whether to sign on to the restrictions because it is not an external media organization. However, it reviewed the restrictions and voluntarily pulled its reporter from the Pentagon hallways. “When we reviewed that, we saw problematic areas like most news organizations affiliated with the Pentagon at the time,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:00:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Forces Seize Sixth Oil Tanker Linked to Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/oil-tanker-seized-venezuela.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15trump-news-tanker1-jvtq/15trump-news-tanker1-jvtq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
An image from video released by the U.S. military showing the oil tanker Galileo, previously named Veronica, in the Caribbean on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/oil-tanker-seized-venezuela.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:26:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens to Invoke the Insurrection Act and Send Troops to Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-trump-minnesota-cjlf/15dc-trump-minnesota-cjlf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Donald J. Trump in the Oval Office on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-insurrection-act-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:34:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>N.S.A. Nominee Promises to Protect Elections From Foreign Interference</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-nsa-cyber-command-nominee.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15trump-news-nsa-topart-zfvw/15trump-news-nsa-topart-zfvw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Lt. Gen. Francis L. Donovan, left, and Lt. Gen. Joshua M. Rudd testified in front of the Senate Armed Services Committee on Capitol Hill on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-nsa-cyber-command-nominee.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:35:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New York Sues Former C.E.O. of Covid Vaccine Maker Over Insider Trading</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/emergent-biosolutions-ceo-insider-trading-covid-vaccine.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-emergent-Kramer-vqtk/15xp-emergent-Kramer-vqtk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Robert G. Kramer, former chief of Emergent BioSolutions, appearing before a House subcommittee by video in 2021.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/emergent-biosolutions-ceo-insider-trading-covid-vaccine.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:39:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Proposes Restricting Deportation of Student Activists</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-protester-deportations-trump-khalil.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-speech-hmqt/15dc-speech-hmqt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mahmoud Khalil speaking in Manhattan last August. Earlier on Thursday, a federal appeals court ruled that he was improperly ordered released by a Federal District Court judge last year. Academic groups have raised alarms over the government’s efforts to deport him.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-protester-deportations-trump-khalil.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:18:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Was Renee Good Obligated to Comply With an ICE Agent’s Orders?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/renee-good-ice-agent-comply-legal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-ice-agent-justification-bmjp/15minneapolis-shooting-ice-agent-justification-bmjp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial for Renee Good. She was shot after beginning to drive away from an ICE agent who told her to get out of her car.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/renee-good-ice-agent-comply-legal.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 18:35:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Did the White House and Denmark Agree to on Greenland? Depends Whom You Ask.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/white-house-greenland-meeting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-greenland-kqlv/15dc-greenland-kqlv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A Danish military vessel sailing near the old harbor of Nuuk, Greenland’s capital, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/white-house-greenland-meeting.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:48:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Couple Says ICE Agents Gassed Them as They Drove With 6 Children</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-couple-ice-tear-gas-6-children.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-father-teargas-khgl/15minneapolis-shooting-father-teargas-khgl-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal agents, like these outside a federal building on Thursday, have frequently used tear gas on Minneapolis streets.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-couple-ice-tear-gas-6-children.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:14:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>California’s Pacific Coast Highway Fully Reopens After Three Years</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/pacific-coast-highway-reopened.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/06/17/multimedia/15xp-highway-promo-copy/15xp-highway-promo-copy-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The famed highway reopened this week after consecutive landslides shuttered two sections of the road in Big Sur and forced major repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/pacific-coast-highway-reopened.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:10:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Senator Kyrsten Sinema Accused of Affair With Member of Security Team</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/kyrsten-sinema-affair-lawsuit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-sinema-bcpm/15dc-sinema-bcpm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Former Senator Kyrsten Sinema at the Capitol last month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/kyrsten-sinema-affair-lawsuit.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:12:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Lawsuit Seeking California Voter Data Is Dismissed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/california-voter-roll-lawsuit-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-california-hfqj/15xp-california-hfqj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Voting in Los Angeles last year. A federal judge dismissed a lawsuit on Thursday that the Justice Department had filed against California last year demanding access to voter data.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/california-voter-roll-lawsuit-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:17:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Says It Erred in Deporting Student Traveling for Thanksgiving</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-deportation-student-traveling-thanksgiving.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/08/multimedia/15trump-news-student-deported/15trump-news-student-deported-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Any Lucía López Belloza’s high school graduation in Texas. She was detained and later deported in late November while trying to surprise her family with a visit.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-deportation-student-traveling-thanksgiving.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 19:46:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Emergency Call Transcripts Record a Crisis Unfolding in Real Time</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/911-calls-minneapolis-ice-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-records-pvtj/15minneapolis-shooting-records-pvtj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
After the shooting, a caller pleaded: “Send an ambulance please. Ambulance, please.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/911-calls-minneapolis-ice-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:10:11 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>