<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 21:27:30 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>In Court Filings, Witnesses Describe Fatal Minneapolis Shooting of Alex Pretti</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor who lives near the scene where Alex Jeffrey Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday described in a sworn court filing how agents initially hesitated and asked for proof of a medical license when the doctor tried to approach and render aid. And a person who said they were standing near Mr. Pretti disputed the Department of Homeland Security’s account of that incident in another sworn court filing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Mr. Pretti, 37, renewed protests and clashes with law enforcement in a city where tensions over aggressive federal immigration action are high. Video footage of the encounter appeared to contradict parts of the federal government’s narrative of what happened, and the latest court filings raised further questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor, whose name was redacted from the publicly available version of the court filing, described themselves as a pediatrician and said they had witnessed parts of the encounter from a nearby apartment. Though their view was from a distance, they described seeing a man being shoved to the ground and then shot several times. After the gunfire, they described going outside, telling an agent that they were a physician and asking to check the person who had been shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor said they were initially turned down, but eventually allowed to go to the person after being patted down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Normally, I would not have been so persistent,” the doctor said in their statement, “but as a physician, I felt a professional and moral obligation to help this man, especially since none of the agents were helping him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor described checking for a pulse, finding none, and then beginning C.P.R. The man appeared to have been shot several times, the doctor said. Shortly after he started C.P.R., emergency medical personnel arrived and took over, the doctor said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the shooting, the doctor described returning home as protests intensified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was sobbing and shaking uncontrollably,” they said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once tear gas began seeping into their apartment from the street below, they said they got in a car and drove to a friend’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am not sure when I will return to my apartment,” the doctor wrote. “I do not feel safe in my city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after agents shot Mr. Pretti on Saturday morning, federal officials claimed that he had endangered agents with a gun he was carrying, and some later accused him of “domestic terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times appear to contradict portions of the Department of Homeland Security’s account of the shooting, and the Minneapolis police chief, Brian O’Hara, said that Mr. Pretti was believed to be licensed to legally carry a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another person who said they witnessed the shooting also submitted a sworn statement in court on Saturday. Like the doctor’s statement, it was filed as part of a lawsuit challenging federal agents’ interactions with protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have read the statement from D.H.S. about what happened and it is wrong,” said that person, who described themselves as a children’s entertainer specializing in face painting. “The man did not approach the agents with a gun. He approached them with a camera. He was just trying to help a woman get up and they took him to the ground.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That witness described hearing whistles — which Minneapolis residents have used to alert people to the presence of immigration agents — and going toward the noise to observe and record on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person said they walked toward an area where someone was being thrown to the ground and then started filming. When an agent asked them to move back, the witness said, they slowly did so. Another man who was in the street and who was also recording remained there and continued filming, the witness said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The man stayed in the street, filming as the other observers I mentioned earlier were being forced backward by another ICE agent threatening them with pepper spray,” the witness statement said. “The man went closer to support them as they got threatened, just with his camera out. I didn’t see him reach for or hold a gun.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person was thrown to the ground by an agent, the witness said, and pepper spray was used. The man who had been filming — almost certainly Mr. Pretti, though no name was used in the court filing — tried to help the person who had fallen, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The agents pulled the man on the ground,” the statement said, adding that the witness was perhaps five feet away. “I didn’t see him touch any of them — he wasn’t even turned toward them. It didn’t look like he was trying to resist, just trying to help the woman up. I didn’t see him with a gun. They threw him to the ground. Four or five agents had him on the ground and they just started shooting him. They shot him so many times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court filing said that a video taken by the witness was also filed with the court, but that footage was not immediately accessible through an online court records system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to a request for comment about the witness statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those sworn statements were filed as part of a lawsuit backed by the American Civil Liberties Union of Minnesota that accused federal agents of repeatedly violating protesters’ rights during a recent surge of immigration enforcement. The federal judge hearing that case issued an injunction earlier this month that imposed restrictions on agents. The Trump administration appealed, and an appellate court issued an administrative stay this week that blocked the injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, lawyers for the protesters filed an emergency motion that asked the appellate court to allow the injunction to go back into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:46:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rep. Maxwell Alejandro Frost Is Assaulted at Sundance Film Festival</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/maxwell-alejandro-frost-assaulted-sundance-festival.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25xp-frost-qkhc/25xp-frost-qkhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Maxwell Alejandro Frost, Democrat of Florida, was hit in the face by a man who told the lawmaker that he would be deported at the Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah, over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attacker “told me that Trump was going to deport me before he punched me in the face,” Mr. Frost said in a social media post on Saturday. “He was heard screaming racist remarks as he drunkenly ran off.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Park City police said they responded to reports of an assault just after midnight on Saturday at the High West Saloon, a whiskey distillery and bar where a private party was being held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danielle Snelson, a community outreach lieutenant with the Park City Police Department, identified the assailant as Christian Young in an email Saturday night. Mr. Young “assaulted Florida Congressman Maxwell Frost and a female who was attending the private event,” Ms. Snelson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Young had “unlawfully” entered the event after being turned away because he did not have an invitation, according to Ms. Snelson. The police did not offer a possible motive for Mr. Young’s entry or assault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police arrested Mr. Young and booked him into the Summit County Jail on charges of aggravated burglary and two counts of simple assault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Frost’s family moved from Cuba to Florida in the early 1960s, part of a wave of hundreds of thousands of Cuban refugees who were flown to the United States, according to his campaign website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elected in 2022 at the age of 25, Mr. Frost became the first member of Generation Z to win a seat in Congress. He represents District 10, an area in Central Florida that includes much of Orlando.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Hakeem Jeffries, Democrat of New York, was one of several politicians who expressed their shock over the attack on social media. “Hate and political violence has no place in our country,” Mr. Jeffries said in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am okay. Thank you for all the well wishes. We are in scary times,” Mr. Frost said in a later post on his personal X account. “Please stay safe and do not let these people silence you. Onwards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A representative from Sundance Film Festival did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Variety, the festival organizers said in a statement that they “strongly condemn last night’s assault and abhor any form of violence, harassment, and hate speech.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/maxwell-alejandro-frost-assaulted-sundance-festival.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:13:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Pushes A.I. Data Centers, but the G.O.P. Is Cool to One in Alabama</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-ai.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-bessemer-promo1-bhvm/25dc-bessemer-promo1-bhvm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenneth E. Gulley, the mayor of Bessemer, Ala., confesses to some befuddlement as to why the people in his community would oppose the construction of a $14.5 billion artificial intelligence data center in a woodland just outside of town. “A data center is probably the most unintrusive thing,” Mr. Gulley said in his office one morning earlier this month. “You know, it’s like a big computer sitting in your backyard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several residents whose backyards may soon adjoin a digital facility the size of 18 Walmarts freely acknowledge their displeasure. “This is as pristine a forest that you’ll find in the foothills of the Appalachian Mountains,” said Ron Morgan, a diesel machinist and retired military veteran, who drove a reporter through the dense timberland behind his house in an all-terrain vehicle. “And if they have their way, all this will be gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Morgan’s sentiments are echoed by his neighbor Marshall Killingsworth, who bought his own land 58 years ago and now fears that the hoot owls in his backyard will no longer serenade him at night. Also fretful is Ronnie Buchanan, a retired rubber plant manager whose family has lived adjacent to the proposed site since 1979. “If that data center takes in all the water everyone says it will, it’s going to flood my land,” Mr. Buchanan said. “I’ll have to move.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seemingly overnight explosion in A.I. usage by American businesses and individuals has spawned a corresponding proliferation of facilities to store and manage all that digital information. As it stands, around 5,400 data centers currently exist in the United States. By 2030 they are expected to multiply by almost 50 percent. In a social media post on Jan. 12, President Trump expressed his view that “Data Centers are key” to America’s pre-eminence over China in the A.I. arms race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the president’s cheerleading of A.I. — codified in an executive order last month in which he declared that the administration will “sustain and enhance the United States’ global A.I. dominance” — has not spurred equal fervor for the data center in Bessemer among Republican political leaders in Alabama. Senator Tommy Tuberville and the state’s governor, Kay Ivey, have not issued statements celebrating the project, and they did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alabama’s other senator, Katie Britt, also a Republican, said in a statement that she hoped that the facility would not raise utility costs. “I remain motivated to ensure that ratepayers are not footing the bill for data center buildouts,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Terri A. Sewell, an Alabama Democrat whose district includes Bessemer and who also declined a request for comment, said during a House hearing last year that some of her Bessemer constituents were “voicing their deep concern” about the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gulley, the city’s mayor, expressed weary exasperation. “It’s the largest single project in the state of Alabama’s history,” he said. “I would have liked to have heard more from those other individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as multibillion-dollar economic projects go, A.I. data centers lack ribbon-cutting allure. Their warehouse-like appearance and the continuous 50-decibel whir of their server fans do not project neighborliness. Any local tax revenues they might bring in are, to some extent, often offset by abatements that states like Alabama have put in place to attract such businesses to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their work forces tend to be small, requiring a highly skilled labor pool most likely drawn from elsewhere. “You can’t spin them as big job creators,” said Michael Hicks, an economics professor at Ball State University in Muncie, Ind., who has written extensively about data centers. “And beyond that, after all the tax incentives are offered, the local effects of these data centers are so vanishingly small, there’s no discernible economic benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data centers also pose risks. Cooling their servers requires enormous amounts of water, potentially straining the local supply and driving up utility costs in the process. “In the short run, at least, growing demand for energy by A.I. and the development of data centers will increase household and business costs of electricity,” Mr. Hicks said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while data center operators often pledge to rely on clean energy, a study published last year by the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy at the University of Michigan, in partnership with the Michigan Environmental Justice Coalition, concluded that such goals are “often delayed or abandoned altogether, resulting in the direct commissioning of new fossil fuel power plants to keep these facilities online.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resulting air pollution from such emissions was found by a Harvard Business Review study last year to cause “significant respiratory-related health consequences that are estimated to cost up to $20 billion per year in the United States by 2028.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bessemer (population 25,100) might be expected to welcome a $14.5 billion economic investment with open arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a steel boomtown and manufacturer of Pullman railroad cars, the self-described “Marvel City” lost its economic moorings with the gradual decline of the domestic steel industry. Today, much of downtown Bessemer remains boarded up. The majority-Black city’s poverty rate of 31 percent was three times that of the nation as a whole in 2024, according to the most recent data available, the same year that the state took over the city’s failing public school system to address its academic and financial woes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early last year, TPA Group, an Atlanta-based real estate development firm, convened a secret meeting with several state and local officials in a conference room of the Bessemer Public Library. Everyone in attendance was required to sign a nondisclosure agreement that would remain in force until public zoning hearings took place months later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to three attendees, TPA unveiled a slide presentation of what it called Project Marvel. The firm, which declined repeated requests to be interviewed for this story, had already built at least one data center in Georgia, and a second Georgia facility was in the works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm was now setting its sights on 675 woodland acres about five miles from Bessemer, in an unincorporated area of Jefferson County. The land had previously been annexed by the city for a landfill project, but the project was scuttled by local opposition. The acreage had ample access to electrical power, as well as water from the Warrior River Water Authority, which pumps its water from the Black Warrior River.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The land’s Mississippi-based owner was willing to sell the 675 acres for what TPA said would be a 100-acre data center campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local officials said that TPA’s representatives at the meeting told them the data center would generate 990 construction jobs and 330 full-time jobs, and bring the Bessemer school district roughly $25 million in annual tax revenue. The officials said TPA also assured them that the project would not damage any wetlands or threaten any endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City and county officials interviewed for this story said that they independently verified TPA’s economic claims. But such estimates pertaining to data centers have been disputed. In TPA’s home state, Georgia, a government audit last month found that the data centers there had produced less than one-third the jobs and economic value that had originally been projected. Mr. Hicks, the Ball State professor, said that the projected job gains from the Bessemer data center struck him as “wildly high” and estimated that such a center would more likely “have 40 workers on a shift, so perhaps 120 to 160 overall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, said Aaron Killings Jr., Bessemer’s city attorney, who attended the meeting, “it was just no question about whether we should proceed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But questions did arise from the area’s residents once they learned about the rezoning plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We tried talking to the mayor and other city officials,” said David Havron, an accountant whose property lies about 200 yards from the site. “They told us they had signed NDAs and couldn’t reveal anything.” Mr. Havron and other residents enlisted two Birmingham, Ala.-based groups, the Alabama Rivers Alliance and the Southern Environmental Law Center, to help them organize opposition to the data center. A third group, the Center for Biological Diversity, petitioned the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service to classify the Birmingham darter, a fish newly discovered in one of the land’s creeks, as an endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Bessemer city officials remained confident that Project Marvel would be widely viewed as a winner for the community. “We can’t allow just a few people to impede the progress and the work that is going to take place here, because it’s going to have such an incredible impact,” said Michael Turner, the superintendent of Bessemer’s public school system, which stands to reap millions in tax revenue from the data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rude awakening greeted Project Marvel at one of the first public hearings in June. The audience chairs were filled with residents wearing red T-shirts to indicate their opposition to the data center. Representatives of the Birmingham environmental groups were also present. “The city and TPA did not anticipate this amount of resistance,” Mr. Killings said. “We just got caught off guard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The residents who were interviewed for this story said Project Marvel’s proponents seemed dismissive of their concerns, including what they see as a threat to the area’s wildlife. During one hearing in June, a TPA representative, Brad Kaaber, said, “There are no bald eagles out there,” which prompted Chester W. Porter, a Bessemer City Council member and a data center supporter, to suggest that all claims of protected or exotic species on the acreage amounted to hyperbole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So Bigfoot is not out there, correct?” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unamused, Mr. Havron, who had come to the meeting prepared to raise environmental concerns, stepped up to the public microphone and held up a photograph of a bald eagle in one of his pine trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who favored the data center maintained that many of the concerns expressed by opponents lacked a factual foundation. Jefferson Traywick, the Jefferson County economic development adviser, acknowledged that some of the concerns were valid. “There are worries about excessive noise and light that I would consider legitimate,” he said in an interview. “But then you get into people telling me that A.I. is the mark of the devil, or that it’s going to create more storms over Birmingham, or that it’s going to emit brain cancer-causing pollutants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Traywick was referring in part to a 70-year-old Bessemer woman who challenged the City Council at one of the meetings, saying, “You can’t say it won’t cause cancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Nov. 18, the Bessemer City Council voted, 5 to 2, to rezone the land for a data center. But by then there was another roadblock. It turned out that a highway extension that had been in the works for decades would be routed through the same acreage where the data center would be built. TPA, unaware that the land was already spoken for, announced this month that it would buy an adjacent 900 acres of land so that the two endeavors could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, moving the data center will mean a new zoning application, which will also mean a second round of noisy hearings. “There’s going to be a lot more public disclosure in this second phase,” Mr. Killings, the city attorney, said in an interview. “We know we’re not going to make everybody happy. But this time around, we’re going to put it all out there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Porter, the City Council’s most vocal defender of the data center, said that he hoped for less hand-wringing from his Bessemer neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I mean, we’re in the 21st century,” he said. “A.I. is here.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-ai.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:02:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>New York City Schools Announce Remote Learning Day in Response to Storm</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/nyc-school-closure-remote-learning-storm.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-nyc-schools-qtcp/25winter-storm-nyc-schools-qtcp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Snow began to accumulate in Queens on Sunday morning. Mayor Zohran Mamdani had said last week that he would not call for a snow day in city schools.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/nyc-school-closure-remote-learning-storm.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 08:55:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>G.O.P. Senator Cassidy Calls for Investigation of Fatal Minnesota Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bill-cassidy-minneapolis-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-cassidy-qvtf/25minneapolis-ice-cassidy-qvtf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Bill Cassidy, the Louisiana Republican who is facing a primary challenger backed by President Trump, called for a “full joint federal and state investigation” into the fatal shooting of a Minneapolis resident by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy on Saturday night became the most prominent congressional Republican to condemn what was unfolding in Minneapolis, in a statement that called the fatal shooting of Alex Jeffrey Pretti “incredibly disturbing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The credibility of ICE and D.H.S. are at stake,” Mr. Cassidy said. “There must be a full joint federal and state investigation. We can trust the American people with the truth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is at odds with the approach of the Trump administration, which said the Department of Homeland Security would lead the investigation into the shooting and initially blocked Minnesota authorities from examining the scene of the shooting, according to a state official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Democrats in Congress have expressed outrage about the shooting and quickly said they could not support a spending deal to fund the Department of Homeland Security, most congressional Republicans, away from Washington for the weekend, have stayed quiet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy’s comments were all the more striking because he is fighting for his political career amid accusations that he has been insufficiently supportive of Mr. Trump. The president has backed a primary challenger to Mr. Cassidy, who voted for an impeachment conviction of the president after the Jan. 6 Capitol riot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another Republican senator, Susan Collins of Maine, has also called for an investigation into the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Andrew Garbarino of New York, the Republican chairman of the Homeland Security Committee, said in a statement on Saturday night that he had requested testimony from the heads of ICE, Customs and Border Protection, and U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Garbarino did not mention Minneapolis in his statement, but said: “I take my oversight duties for the department seriously, and Congress has an important responsibility to ensure the safety of law enforcement and the people they serve and protect.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bill-cassidy-minneapolis-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 12:03:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Museums From Texas to Massachusetts Close for Storm, but Broadway Shows Go On</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/museums-broadway-storm-closed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-museum-closings-sub-jctf/25winter-storm-museum-closings-sub-jctf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Museums, theaters and concert halls from Texas to Massachusetts shut their doors on Sunday as a powerful winter storm marched eastward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least five of New York’s largest museums were closed on Sunday, when the brunt of the storm was expected to hit the region, including the Frick Collection, the Guggenheim, the Whitney, the Brooklyn Museum and the Studio Museum in Harlem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of Natural History remained open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday morning, two Broadways shows in New York — “Aladdin” and “The Lion King” — had paused performances until Tuesday. And while a handful of Off Broadway shows, including “Heathers: The Musical,” “The Monsters” and “Anna Christie,” also canceled shows, the Broadway League, which represents theater owners, producers and other professionals, said on Saturday that most productions would continue as planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Philharmonic rescheduled a show conducted by Gustavo Dudamel at Radio City Music Hall for Tuesday, and the Beacon Theater rescheduled a performance by the comedians Seth Meyers and John Oliver for next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Texas, where tens of thousands of customers had lost power, officials at the Dallas Museum of Art said their institution would be closed for the entire weekend. Similar announcements were made by the Mint Museum Randolph in Charlotte, N.C.; the Columbia Museum of Art in South Carolina; the Carnegie museums in Pittsburgh; and the Philadelphia Museum of Art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smithsonian, which has locations in Washington and New York, said all of its museums, research centers and the National Zoo would be closed on Sunday and Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, the Field Museum in Chicago closed because of extreme cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zachary Small contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/museums-broadway-storm-closed.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 11:10:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Trump, the Truth in Minneapolis Is What He Says It Is</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-truth-minneapolis-shootings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-assess-Trumplaptop-vbft/25dc-assess-Trumplaptop-vbft-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump has found that putting out a story line early and repeating it often can convince a sizable share of the public that does not credit contrary evidence.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-truth-minneapolis-shootings.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:16:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Eleanor Holmes Norton Files to End Re-election Campaign</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-re-election-campaign.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-Norton-gpvb/25dc-Norton-gpvb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The campaign of Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton of Washington, D.C., the 88-year-old Democrat, filed paperwork to officially end her campaign for re-election.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-re-election-campaign.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:58:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Family of Alex Pretti, the Man Shot in Minnesota, Says They Are Heartbroken and Angry</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-family-statement.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-family-statement-pzjh/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-family-statement-pzjh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial at the site where Alex Jeffrey Pretti, a nurse and Minneapolis resident, was killed by federal agents.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-family-statement.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 11:14:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Government Again Excludes Minnesota From Investigation of Fatal Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Minnesota officials said they aimed to have their Bureau of Criminal Apprehension, which typically takes the lead in police shootings, work the investigation, either concurrently or in partnership with the federal government.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 11:24:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>While many churches canceled Sunday services, some carried on for a hardy few.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/winter-storm-snow-ice/churches</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-churches-fjbh/25winter-storm-churches-fjbh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The winter storm warning covered a range from New Mexico to Maine.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/winter-storm-snow-ice/churches</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 11:52:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minneapolis Live Updates: Demands for Investigation Grow as Trump Officials Blame Victim</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/deputy-attorney-general-takes-a-measured-tone-after-trump-officials-call-the-shooting-victim-a-terrorist</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-sunday-shows-gczp/25minneapolis-ice-sunday-shows-gczp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Other senior officials in the Trump administration continued to cast blame on the man shot by federal agents.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/deputy-attorney-general-takes-a-measured-tone-after-trump-officials-call-the-shooting-victim-a-terrorist</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 11:58:53 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>