<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:44:43 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How Bad Are A.I. Delusions? We Asked People Treating Them.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julia Sheffield, a psychologist who specializes in treating people with delusions, is difficult to rattle. But she was unnerved last summer when patients began telling her about their conversations with A.I. chatbots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One woman, who had no history of mental illness, asked ChatGPT for advice on a major purchase she had been fretting about. After days of the bot validating her worries, she became convinced that businesses were colluding to have her investigated by the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another patient came to believe that a romantic crush was sending her secret spiritual messages. Yet another thought he had stumbled onto a world-changing invention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the year, Dr. Sheffield had seen seven such patients at Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville. Although she is accustomed to treating people with mental instability, Dr. Sheffield was disturbed that this new technology seemed to tip people from simply having eccentric thoughts into full-on delusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like the A.I. was partnering with them in expanding or reinforcing their unusual beliefs,” Dr. Sheffield said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mental health workers across the country are navigating how to treat problems caused or exacerbated by A.I. chatbots, according to more than 100 therapists and psychiatrists who told The New York Times about their experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many mentioned positive effects of the bots — like helping patients understand their diagnoses — they also said the conversations deepened their patients’ feelings of isolation or anxiety. More than 30 described cases resulting in dangerous emergencies like psychosis or suicidal thoughts. One California psychiatrist who often evaluates people in the legal system said she had seen two cases of violent crimes influenced by A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Times reporters have documented more than 50 cases of psychological crises linked to chatbot conversations since last year. OpenAI, the maker of ChatGPT, is facing at least 11 personal injury or wrongful death lawsuits claiming that the chatbot caused psychological harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies behind the bots say these situations are exceedingly rare. “For a very small percentage of users in mentally fragile states there can be serious problems,” Sam Altman, the chief executive of OpenAI, said in October. The company has estimated that 0.15 percent of ChatGPT users discussed suicidal intentions over the course of a month, and 0.07 percent showed signs of psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a product with 800 million users, that translates to 1.2 million people with possible suicidal intent and 560,000 with potential psychosis or mania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Times has sued OpenAI, accusing it of violating copyright laws when training its models. The company has contested the lawsuit.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts said that the number of people susceptible to psychological harm, even psychosis, is far higher than the general public understands. The bots, they said, frequently pull people away from human relationships, condition them to expect agreeable responses and reinforce harmful impulses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A.I. could really, on a mass scale, change how many people are impacted,” said Haley Wang, a graduate student at U.C.L.A. who assesses people showing symptoms of psychosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychosis, which causes a break from reality, is most associated with schizophrenia. But as many as 3 percent of people will develop a diagnosable psychotic disorder in their lifetime, and far more are prone to delusional thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Joseph Pierre, a psychiatrist in San Francisco, said he had seen about five patients with delusional experiences involving A.I. While most had a diagnosis related to psychosis, he said, “sometimes these are very highly functioning people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For him, the idea that all chatbot-fueled delusions were going to happen anyway “just doesn’t hold water.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He recently wrote in a scientific journal about a medical professional who began conversing with ChatGPT during a sleepless night. She took medication for ADHD and had a history of depression. After two nights of asking the chatbot questions about her dead brother, she became convinced that he had been communicating with her through a trail of digital footprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pierre and other experts said that a wide range of factors can combine to tip people into psychosis. These include not only genetic predisposition but also depression, lack of sleep, a history of trauma, and exposure to stimulants or cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m quite convinced that this is a real thing and that we are only seeing the tip of the iceberg,” said Dr. Soren Dinesen Ostergaard, a psychiatry researcher at Aarhus University Hospital in Denmark. In November, he published a report finding 11 cases of chatbot-associated delusions in psychiatric records from one Danish region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not unusual for new technologies to inspire delusions. But clinicians who have seen patients in the thrall of A.I. said it is an especially powerful influence because of its personal, interactive nature and authoritative tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a confidential news tip? The New York Times would like to hear from readers who want to share messages and materials with our journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the psychotic episodes spurred by chatbots can lead to violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jessica Ferranti, a psychiatrist at UC Davis Health who often evaluates people in the legal system, said two of about 30 people she assessed last year in violent felony cases had delusional thoughts that were intensified by A.I. before the crimes occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both people developed messianic delusions about their own spiritual powers, Dr. Ferranti said. In one case, the bot mirrored and expanded on the psychotic thinking as the person came up with a plan to carry out a murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While delusional episodes have driven the public discourse about A.I. and mental health, the bots have other insidious effects that are far more widespread, doctors said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several mental health workers who treat anxiety, depression or obsessive-compulsive disorders described A.I. either validating their clients’ worries or providing so much reassurance that patients felt reliant on chatbots to calm down — both less healthy than facing the source of the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Adam Alghalith of Mount Sinai Hospital in New York recalled a young man with depression who repeatedly shared negative thoughts with a chatbot. At first, the bot told him how to seek help. But he “just kept asking, kept pushing,” Dr. Alghalith said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safety guardrails that stop chatbots from encouraging suicide can break down when people engage the bots in extended conversations over days or weeks. Eventually, Dr. Alghalith said, the bot told the patient his thoughts of suicide were reasonable. Fortunately he had a support system and entered treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other doctors described chatbots flattering the grandiose tendencies of patients with personality disorders, or advising patients with autism to put themselves in dangerous social situations. Others said they saw patients’ interactions with chatbots as an addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quenten Visser, a therapist in Ozark, Mo., saw a 56-year-old last April who had experienced a panic attack. At first, Mr. Visser said, he thought the patient had severe anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after several therapy sessions, it became clear that the man was fixated on ChatGPT. He quit his job as a graphic designer after using ChatGPT 100 hours a week and having delusional thoughts about solving the energy crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This was this guy’s meth,” Mr. Visser said. He approached treatment as he would for any other addiction. They talked about what drove the man to use A.I.: lingering isolation from the pandemic and emotional distress he avoided by using chatbots. The man told The Times he now uses A.I. less, and makes art and works as a ride-share driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many doctors said that A.I.’s effects weren’t entirely negative. Some patients used the bots to practice techniques learned in therapy, for example, or as a nonjudgmental sounding board. Dr. Bob Lee, a psychiatry resident at a hospital in East Meadow, N.Y., even credited A.I. with saving a patient’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patient arrived at the emergency room last fall in a delusional panic about supernatural forces. He told doctors that a chatbot had identified his thoughts as symptoms of a crisis and advised him to go to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As with all new technologies, it can be used as a powerful force in both positive and negative ways,” Dr. Lee said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shannon Pagdon, a graduate student at the University of Pittsburgh who began having episodes of psychosis as a teenager and is now active in peer support networks, said A.I. can be useful to check whether her impressions line up with reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Like uploading a photo and saying, ‘Hey, do you see something in this photo?’” she explained. But, she said, she has also seen A.I. “reinforce psychotic experiences” in others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAI has consulted with mental health experts to improve how ChatGPT responds to people who appear to be in a psychological crisis. The company has also formed a council with eight outside experts in psychology and human-computer interaction to advise its policy team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do we not keep people in this infinite loop of conversation with a machine?” said Munmun De Choudhury, a Georgia Tech professor and council member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although ChatGPT is by far the most used consumer chatbot, those made by Google, Anthropic and others also have millions of users. None have been able to avoid delusions and other harmful psychological effects, Dr. De Choudhury said. “I don’t think any of these companies have figured out what to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for Google said its Gemini chatbot advises users to find professional medical guidance for health-related queries. Anthropic, which makes Claude, published a blog post last month about a new feature that detects discussion of suicide or self-harm and routes users to help lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts advised therapists to ask patients about chatbot use, because its influence may not be obvious. For people trying to get their loved ones out of a delusional spiral, they advised reducing their time with the bot and making sure they get enough sleep. Insisting that the A.I. is wrong can be counterproductive if it makes the person angry or more isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sascha DuBrul, a mental health coach in Los Angeles, has seen firsthand both the good and bad of chatbot use. Last summer, Mr. DuBrul, whose work draws on his own experience with bipolar disorder, turned to ChatGPT when writing a book about psychotic episodes. After much back-and-forth, he became convinced A.I. would allow us to live “on some other level of reality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With help from friends, he realized what was happening and pulled back from the bot. But he still believes mental health patients could benefit from a machine that listens infinitely — as long as it is connected to real human support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think that there’s a lot of potential there,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:54:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Far from Minneapolis, Memphis Remains Under a Different Federal Crackdown</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving through Memphis, it is hard not to feel the presence of the federal task force that has patrolled the city since September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cars are often stopped on the side of the road, surrounded by clusters of law enforcement agents and a mix of patrol and unmarked cars. National Guard troops in camouflage stand patrol outside stores and restaurants. Some of the main business strips seem emptier, even for a chilly stretch of January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis has been experiencing a show of force similar to those in cities like Minneapolis, where the Trump administration has sent hundreds of agents to enforce its immigration crackdown. But unlike in Minneapolis, where tensions have boiled over into frequent and at times violent confrontations this month, the task force in Memphis has focused broadly on fighting crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And support from Republican state leaders — and to an extent, from the city’s Democratic mayor, Paul Young — has kept things to an uneasy simmer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To proponents of the operation, it has been a shining example of the administration’s aggressive approach to law enforcement, with city police officers, state troopers and federal agents collaborating as a single force. After U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents shot and killed Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday, Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, noted that Mayor Young of Memphis had “worked with us and our federal law enforcement officers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared with Minneapolis, she said, the Memphis operation was having “a very different result because of the leadership in place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis, with about 610,000 residents, saw 195 homicides from last January to this January, according to data analysis from the F.B.I., compared with 251 in the same 2024 time frame. It is still one of the highest rates in the nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I see it as an extraordinarily successful solution to a chronic violent crime problem in Memphis that’s motivated by greed and evil,” said Michael Dunavant, who was sworn as U.S. attorney for the Western District of Tennessee in October. “We’re finally, actually enforcing the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those who are uncomfortable with the task force’s presence also say that the federal operation — “the occupation,” as some have branded it — has harmed some of the city’s most vulnerable residents while very likely doing little to reduce crime in the long term. Many poor people of color, they say, are avoiding their usual routines for fear of being pulled over or arrested. The majority Black city has a long history of the police using excessive force and racially profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve been the brunt of a lot of stuff considering how much that we produce culturally, economically, for the state, for this country,” said Chris Collier, who volunteers at Gaisman Park in the Berclair neighborhood. “For them to take this approach here, it just seems a whole lot more than totally necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no set end date for the Memphis Safe Task Force, which began its work in late September after President Trump signed an executive order dispatching employees of more than a dozen agencies to the city. Agents from the F.B.I. and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms are among those frequently on the streets. To date, the task force has made more than 6,300 arrests, conducted more than 68,000 traffic stops and recovered 1,532 firearms, according to city data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of the arrests were for nonviolent offenses, according to the data — even though the task force says its focus is violent crime. Still, crime rates, which had already been declining, have dropped even more since Oct. 1: Murder and sexual assault are down nearly 42 percent, while aggravated assault is down about 35 percent, according to city data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memphis residents broadly acknowledge that crime, which was already dropping, has decreased even more since the task force started its work. At the same time, there has been an uptick in the number of residents renewing vehicle registrations and drivers licenses, to avoid getting pulled over and penalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While immigration enforcement is not a stated focus of the task force, residents and local officials say that immigration arrests are quietly happening in tandem with the crime crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joseph Richman, 48, who commutes from Forrest City, Ark., about 45 miles away, to work as a painter in Memphis, said the task force’s presence has left many people with “kind of a mixed feeling”: hope that it will help address crime, but also fear of profiling and mistreatment by task force members, given the city’s history of discriminatory policing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really think that they need to be prayed for,” he added of the agents, just minutes after a group of agents made an arrest along the diverse, commercial stretch of Summer Avenue and drove away. “Sometimes they can make bad decisions pursuing good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent shot Renee Good, an American citizen, on a Minneapolis street in early January, some Memphis residents expressed concern that something similar could happen in their city. Ms. Good was killed on the anniversary of the death of Tyre Nichols, who died in 2023 after a traffic stop with Memphis police officers turned violent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Court documents show that many of the task force’s arrests have come after traffic stops, with officials citing a broken taillight or overly tinted window among the reasons for stopping a driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You ain’t speeding, you ain’t doing nothing, they just looking for excuses,” said Billy Walker, 67, who said he is set to go to court in the coming weeks for two traffic infractions — one for having a clear cover over his license plate, the other for turning at a red light. Mr. Walker, who said he felt both infractions were unfair, added, “Quit messing with people that’s trying to go to work here every day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared with other cities, where clashes between federal agents and protesters are far more common and Democratic governors have been vocal in their opposition, backlash in Memphis has been far more muted. Clusters of activists have rallied behind a “Free the 901” campaign — a reference to the city’s area code — documenting law enforcement activity and pressuring elected leaders to oppose the surge of agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a sprawling city where neighborhoods are spread out and many residents are struggling to make ends meet, protesting can be risky or just impractical. Some residents have resorted to staying home. One woman, in a neighborhood where immigrants live, recounted how her free Zumba class that usually draws a few dozen people had dropped to single digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic elected officials have had to make difficult calculations about how to react when Tennessee’s Republican governor and conservative supermajority in the legislature have outsize control over the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Lee Harris, a Democrat, of surrounding Shelby County, has joined a lawsuit seeking to end the National Guard deployment, which is set to having a hearing in March. But Mayor Young of Memphis has won plaudits from Republicans for working with the task force, even as he has voiced frustration about the Guard’s presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Young and his office did not immediately respond to questions about Ms. Noem’s comments on Memphis. But in an interview that took place before the two shootings in Minnesota, Mr. Young stressed that he believed “we’ve made the decisions that are in the best interest of the most people in our city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I knew my options were different than other mayors in the country,” he said, referring to the fact that his state is governed by Republicans aligned with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the federal agents patrolling Memphis, he added: “I have power to influence their work. And that’s the power that I’m exercising, the influence of the work and their focus each and every day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He pointed to the number of open warrants the task force had pursued as part of its work, as well as the broader emphasis on violent crime, rather than immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citizens looking to blunt the task force’s impact have focused on raising money to cover bail for people arrested on minor offenses, delivering food to immigrants afraid to leave their homes or offering rides for those afraid to drive. They’ve also encouraged other residents to support only businesses that have publicly disowned the task force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re fighting from just a small corner,” said Rob Brown, the owner of Da Sammich Spot in the Orange Mound neighborhood, whose business fell off when the task force first arrived. But after a video went viral of Mr. Brown asking National Guard troops standing outside his business to leave after hours, he has sold out of loaded fries, sandwiches and fried fruit pies almost every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t want crime running rampant,” he added. Still, he said, law enforcement officers should not “treat people like nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer number of task force arrests has strained the legal system and made overcrowding at the Shelby County Jail, a long-running problem, even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Dunavant’s office in the Western District of Tennessee said that from Oct. 1 to Dec. 31, 141 people were charged under 111 indictments, compared with 37 people and 35 indictments over the same period in 2024. This month, the Pentagon dispatched 20 military lawyers from across the country to help with the caseload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The infrastructure has not been prepared,” said Lee Gerald, a defense lawyer who is representing a man accused of trying to run away from officers after he ran a red light and could not provide proof of citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At some point, the task force is going to leave,” he added, “and the problems persist.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:53:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Crisis of Confidence for ICE and Border Patrol as Clashes Escalate</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26DC-DHS-ANGER-oscar-tfwz/26DC-DHS-ANGER-oscar-tfwz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oscar Hagelsieb spent nearly 25 years as an immigration officer and special agent, proud of his work enforcing federal laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But watching the chaos unfolding in Minneapolis, and the fatal shooting of a U.S. citizen there on Saturday, Mr. Hagelsieb said he felt anger and despair at how the Trump administration was deploying his former agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re not addressing the problem by throwing a 500-pound gorilla into these inner cities,” said Mr. Hagelsieb, 52, who said he voted three times for President Trump and retired from the Department of Homeland Security in 2023. “It’s completely unfair to the agents who have been put in this position.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re causing chaos, and unfortunately it’s costing lives,” he added. “There’s only so much they can handle before bad things start to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hagelsieb’s comments reflect a growing sense of fear, frustration and disillusionment among some current and former immigration officials at the department, which is leading Mr. Trump’s push to arrest and deport millions of people. In interviews with The New York Times, more than 20 of them expressed anxieties that the administration was sending federal agents into situations in Minneapolis and other major cities that were increasingly dangerous both for them and civilians they encountered. They said that long hours, arrest quotas and public vitriol were taking a significant toll on morale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many also worried that the fallout would irreparably damage how the public perceived the two main homeland security agencies involved in Mr. Trump’s crackdown, Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the U.S. Border Patrol, hurting long-term recruitment and retention. Several said they worried that Democrats would draw on voter outrage to shut down ICE, which has been the most publicly visible arm of the immigration operation, if they returned to power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some also criticized the more aggressive tactics being used by the Border Patrol, as well as the combative approach of one of its leaders, Gregory Bovino. Mr. Bovino has often used the phrase “turn and burn” to describe Border Patrol operations, a reference to actions like smashing windshields, using explosives to blow down the doors of homes and engaging in car chases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gil Kerlikowske, who during the Obama administration led Customs and Border Protection, which includes the Border Patrol, said most Border Patrol agents did not have experience “policing an urban environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kerlikowske also said many of the tactics he had seen being used in Minneapolis and other cities, like shooting people with pepper ball rounds and spraying chemical agents at nonviolent protesters, were “far outside standard practices in law enforcement.” And he said his conversations with current Border Patrol employees reflected a grim situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Morale is in the dumpster,” he said. “Many of the agents will be very happy to go back to the job they were trained for on the border.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to know how widespread any sense of discontent is among ICE and Border Patrol agents on the ground in Minneapolis or other cities. Many have been seen arguing with protesters and appear to be supporting one another during confrontations. Paul Perez, the chief of the Border Patrol union, told The Times that morale remained “high” and that there were plenty of volunteers for Mr. Trump’s immigration operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Agents are concerned about being doxxed, having their families and themselves put at risk,” Mr. Perez said. “But I don’t think anybody’s afraid to do the mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, blamed Democrats for the violence and chaos in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody, including President Trump, wants to see people get shot or hurt,” Ms. Leavitt said in a statement. “That’s exactly why Governor Walz and Mayor Frey need to allow local police to work with federal law enforcement to remove illegal alien criminals, murderers and pedophiles from Minnesota,” she added, referring to Tim Walz of Minnesota and Jacob Frey of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump on Sunday posted on social media asking Democratic leaders to “formally cooperate with the Trump Administration” rather than “resist and stoke the flames of Division, Chaos, and Violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Homeland Security Department did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the Trump administration has rapidly grown both ICE and the Border Patrol, thanks to an infusion of billions of dollars from Congress that has financed an intense recruitment drive. Many homeland security hiring ads feature military-style imagery, like officers wearing tactical gear and driving combat vehicles. They refer to immigration as an “invasion” and immigrants as “enemies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times spoke with current and former officials in the hours after federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday shot and killed Alex Pretti, an intensive care nurse who was filming them, the second fatal shooting of a civilian there this month. Many described the deaths of Mr. Pretti and the other American citizen, Renee Good, as points of no return in the relationship between homeland security and members of the public. Most of those who spoke to The Times did so on the condition of anonymity, fearing retribution from the Trump administration if they spoke openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the current and former ICE officials who spoke with The Times said they supported enforcing the nation’s immigration laws. Many said they believed that President Joseph R. Biden Jr.’s border policies had contributed to the current crisis. They also criticized many blue cities and states for not cooperating more with federal immigration authorities, for instance by restricting their ability to make arrests of undocumented immigrants at jails and prisons, moves that they said were safer than picking people up on the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most said they were unhappy with the sharp language from top White House and Homeland Security officials, especially their quick rush to conclude that agents were blameless and Mr. Pretti was at fault, before a full investigation had taken place. One current Homeland Security agent said he had “always given the benefit of the doubt to the government in these situations” but he no longer believed “any of the statements they put out anymore.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many also said that Mr. Trump’s mass-arrest campaign was proving counterproductive. In part, they said, that was because many federal agents were not thoroughly trained in dealing with hostile crowds, a growing concern as organized groups of protesters have sought to monitor homeland security activities, filming them on the street, following their agents’ cars and blowing whistles to disrupt their operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We lost all trust,” one current ICE official said. “I’m not sure I can see how we exist three years from now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most ICE agents do not receive specialized training in crowd control, according to a 2021 report by the Government Accountability Office. Neither do agents at the F.B.I.; the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives; and the U.S. Marshals Service, the report found. Thousands of law enforcement officers from those agencies have also been assigned to the immigration crackdown. Border Patrol agents do receive more extensive training in crowd control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal tactics for making immigration arrests have also changed substantially, current and former officials said. In previous administrations, ICE tried to take a more targeted approach. That could involve carrying out several days of surveillance before approaching a suspect, trying to identify the safest place to make an arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the administration’s demand for as many as 3,000 arrests per day has significantly reduced the time available for that kind of careful preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a social media post on Sunday, Tim Quinn, a former senior official at C.B.P. who left the agency last year, criticized the White House’s “reckless push for deportation numbers,” saying that it was “putting the public and law enforcement at great risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, agents have been told to cast a far wider net, questioning people they encounter about their immigration status, which has made many of their operations resemble indiscriminate street sweeps. That has led to concerns about racial profiling, inciting anger in many communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m Hispanic, I look Hispanic,” Mr. Hagelsieb said. “I would be highly upset if someone came and asked me if I was illegal because I’m Hispanic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deborah Fleischaker, who was the assistant director for policy for ICE during the Biden administration, said the agency had previously conducted immigration enforcement in a “careful, thoughtful, targeted way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, she said, agents would plan extensively to minimize the risk to themselves, their targets and the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“None of that appears to be happening anymore,” Ms. Fleischaker said. Referring to the current operation in Minneapolis and other cities, she added, “This isn’t what they were trained to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Mitnick, who served as the top attorney at the Department of Homeland Security in the first Trump administration, wrote on social media that he was “enraged and embarrassed by DHS’s lawlessness, fascism, and cruelty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump, the Border Patrol has also played a sweeping role in enforcing immigration laws within the nation’s interior. There are fewer constitutional protections at the border than there are inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency has sent hundreds of agents to Minneapolis; Los Angeles; Washington, D.C.; Portland, Ore.; and Memphis, the main targets of Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown. Several current and former homeland security officials said they believed that the Border Patrol was not prepared to operate this extensively within cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol’s more aggressive tactics have led to behind-the-scenes conflicts with ICE, according to current and former federal officials. Two former ICE officials said the public was blaming ICE for Border Patrol’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump has sent thousands of federal agents into Minneapolis, making it the nation’s largest-ever immigration enforcement operation, public opinion has shifted decisively against ICE. Just 36 percent of voters said they approved of the way ICE was handling its job, while 63 percent disapproved, according to a Times/Siena University poll. Fueled by the outrage, Senate Democrats have signaled that they may be willing to partly shut down the government over the Homeland Security Department’s funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One former ICE official questioned whether many Americans would want to work in federal law enforcement after seeing the clashes in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Hagelsieb, one particular worry is the number of ICE special agents taken off of complex criminal investigations to instead track down undocumented immigrants, many of whom have not been convicted of crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Times investigation last year found that agents at Homeland Security Investigations, which is part of ICE and is where Mr. Hagelsieb worked, had been reassigned from cases involving sex crimes against children, drug smuggling and terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like a local police department pulling a homicide investigator to conduct an operation against jaywalkers,” Mr. Hagelsieb said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Flavelle and Michael H. Keller contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:22:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Our Photographer Describes the Scene After the Pretti ShootingOur Photographer Describes the Scene After the Pretti Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010667387/our-photographer-describes-pretti-shooting-scene.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/arts/guttenfelder-thumb/guttenfelder-thumb-facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
David Guttenfelder, a Times photographer based in Minneapolis, describes what he saw at the scene where Alex Jeffrey Pretti had been killed by federal agents.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010667387/our-photographer-describes-pretti-shooting-scene.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:38:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The ‘R-Word’ Returns, Dismaying Those Who Fought to Oust It</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/r-word-slur-disability.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/r-word-01-jvfh/r-word-01-jvfh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late last month, a woman posted a photograph on social media of a purple hat she had knitted, while a black-and-white dog lounged on the carpet a few feet away. The cozy scene was accompanied by a single sentence: “This hat is an hour behind schedule thanks to influencer retards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proud knitter, Harmeet K. Dhillon, is also the assistant attorney general overseeing the Justice Department’s Civil Rights Division. Her purview includes protecting the rights of people with intellectual disabilities by ensuring compliance with the Americans With Disabilities Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades now, the “R-word” has been regarded as a slur against people with intellectual disabilities — a word to be avoided. Yet it has had a striking resurgence, in part because people in high-profile positions of power and influence have chosen to resurrect it, often with an air of defiance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The word ‘retarded’ is back,” the popular podcaster Joe Rogan declared in April, describing its return as “one of the great culture victories.” He did not respond to requests for elaboration, but there is abundant evidence to support his muscular declaration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past three months, the musician Kid Rock donned a face mask while appearing on a program streaming on Fox Nation and said he was dressing up as a “retard” for Halloween. (He was also wearing a Jesus trucker cap.) The Fox News personality Greg Gutfeld coupled the word with a schoolyard taunt to mock mayors who oppose President Trump, and Elon Musk used it on his social media platform to insult a critic. The word has recently been uttered on the podcasts of the white nationalist Nick Fuentes and the right-wing commentators Derek Hunter, Steven Crowder and Tim Pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of a hurtful word still considered taboo is emblematic of the provocative language that courses through the manosphere sector of social media these days — almost gleefully transgressive language often adopted in messaging from the White House. Diplomacy is out and mockery in, whether by displaying plaques that insult former presidents, depicting Mr. Trump spraying excrement on protesters from a military jet — or using the “R-word” to question the intelligence of a political opponent, as Mr. Trump did in a Truth Social post on Thanksgiving Day, in which he called Minnesota’s Democratic governor, Tim Walz, “seriously retarded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked later whether he stood by that statement, Mr. Trump said, “Absolutely,” because he thought there was something wrong with the governor. For her part, Ms. Dhillon did not answer questions about her use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word’s proliferation has alarmed many advocates and people with disabilities who thought it had long since been removed from circulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The drumbeat and use of this word has been like nothing I’ve seen in a very long time,” said Katy Neas, the chief executive of the Arc of the United States, a disability rights organization. She called its use by the Justice Department’s civil rights chief “simply mind-blowing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word’s return raises an obvious question: Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why decide to resurrect a term well known to offend a community that has been historically marginalized, so much so that its usage prompted public-awareness campaigns and wholesale changes to nomenclature?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think there’s a perception of power, of ‘I am powerful, therefore I can use this language; I am powerful, and therefore I can diminish others,’” Ms. Neas said. She added: “It’s language used by bullies to bully.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Amy Hewitt, the director of the Institute on Community Integration at the University of Minnesota, the word’s return reflects a divisiveness defining the United States of 2026, in which a sizable part of the population believes that “many people are a drain on our society, on our progress, on what makes us great.” She pointed in particular to the Trump administration’s dismantling of diversity, equity and inclusion efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not just about race and ethnicity, it’s also about disability,” she said. “This is why the R-word is completely acceptable to them. It’s ‘us versus them.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use of the word has skyrocketed on X, Mr. Musk’s social media platform. In 2020, it appeared on the platform, then known as Twitter, just over 2,000 times a day, according to a recent study by two Montclair State University researchers. That number is now over 46,000 times a day — a more than 2,000 percent increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The researchers, Bond Benton, a communications professor, and Daniela Peterka-Benton, a justice studies professor, said the word’s use rose after Mr. Musk bought the platform in late 2022, and then spiked when he included it in an X post in January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this Musk-induced growth was a blip when compared with what followed in the week after Mr. Trump’s disparagement of Mr. Walz in late November. Use of the word increased by more than 200 percent, with more than 1.1 million posts on X employing the word. Most of them, the study’s authors noted, conveyed enthusiastic endorsement of the term’s apparent restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Musk influences a lot of people, especially in the manosphere, so we had a hunch that the platform was going to have more use of the term,” Dr. Benton said. “Then when Trump used it, it was like a nuclear bomb.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defenders of the word’s use say that it is intended in part to clap back at political correctness, “wokeness” and perceived infringements of the right to free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are so many words in the English language that have been driven out of use because we’ve been told that they’re politically incorrect,” Mark Meckler, a right-wing activist and self-described “free speech warrior,” said in his podcast last month. “Well, that’s just cultural Marxism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So this has now come back into common use, and I’m actually glad it has, because it just shows we’ve been recapturing language from the woke left,” said Mr. Meckler, who, in adding that he did not mean to insult “mentally handicapped” people, used another term that disability advocates say is outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who defend the word’s use often contend that it is meant as a synonym for “stupid” or “slow,” and not as a reference to people with intellectual disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not really like anybody wants to make fun of people who are slow, when it comes to brain development,” the conservative commentator Megyn Kelly said on her podcast last month. “It’s that they’re sick and tired of being told what they can and cannot say.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No one’s trying to actually say something negative about that community,” Ms. Kelly added. “They’re trying to say something about the person they’re targeting — that they’re kind of slow.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But many people with intellectual disabilities and their advocates consider this distinction to be disingenuous, if not a complete cop-out. The word, they say, continues to wound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helena Donato-Sapp, 16, of Long Beach, Calif., is a junior in high school with several learning disabilities. Last semester, while walking through campus at lunchtime, she heard a classmate call a friend the R-word, and was taken aback by a word she associates with shame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes me feel bad and confused that people still use it,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terminology for people with intellectual disabilities has evolved over generations, with words like “idiot,” “imbecile,” “feebleminded” and “moron” having their moment before being phased out for reasons of imprecision or hurtfulness, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What united them, though, was an implied sense of otherness that, among other effects, gave oxygen to the pseudoscience of eugenics in the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1950s, “mental retardation” had become the socially acceptable medical term of choice, but it, too, devolved into a pejorative. The phrase became part of what linguistics experts refer to as a “euphemism treadmill,” in which a word that begins as acceptable develops into a slur through negative use, leading to eventual replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As people with intellectual disabilities began more and more to speak up for themselves, they made their dislike of the R-word clear. The consensus was “that it’s mean, hurtful, harassing,” Dr. Hewitt said. “It’s personally offensive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rejection of the term gradually took hold. In 1992, for example, the Association for Retarded Citizens of the United States changed its name to what it is called today: the Arc of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Neas, its chief executive, said that advocates, including those with intellectual disabilities, argued that words mattered. “The words had to be fully inclusive, and not in any way include language that separates or denigrates people,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the 2009 Special Olympics in Idaho, youth advocates — galvanized in part by repeated use of the word in the film “Tropic Thunder” — sparked a global movement called Spread the Word to End the Word. Disability advocates called out anyone who used the word, including President Barack Obama’s chief of staff, Rahm Emanuel, who subsequently apologized and agreed to sign a pledge to end the use of the word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most significant rejection of the term came in 2010, when Mr. Obama signed “Rosa’s Law” — named after a young girl with Down syndrome — replacing “mental retardation” with “intellectual disability” in federal legislation and policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among those present for the signing ceremony was Jill Eglé, a disability advocate who, a year earlier, had been a driving force in having the word eliminated at the state level in Virginia. The cause was personal; as a child growing up in Virginia, she had been declared “mildly mentally retarded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I had a hard time because I was made fun of, laughed at,” Ms. Eglé, 49, recalled. “I didn’t have a boyfriend, always ridiculed and always, you know, just was the odd one out. No boy ever asked me to the prom and stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They all called me retarded, and I tried to be nice, but it wasn’t the way it should be,” she said. “And it was hurtful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next decade, the sustained efforts to remove the word from the vocabulary seemed to succeed, with students and teachers reporting a marked decline in its use. By 2019, the Special Olympics considered the matter settled, and began shifting the focus of its public awareness campaign to a larger message of inclusivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really felt like we had made so much progress,” said Andrea Cahn, vice president of Unified Champion Schools, the Special Olympics umbrella program that oversaw the campaign. “The use of the word really seemed to have been diminished.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it came back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Olympics saw a spike in alerts from athletes and people with intellectual disabilities about an increased use of the word. Ms. Cahn said the thrust of many messages was: “Can you do something? Can you make them stop?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocates say it isn’t surprising that the word is being heard more frequently. “You’ve got the president of the United States using that word,” Dr. Hewitt said. “So why are we surprised?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicole LeBlanc, 40, of Silver Spring, Md., an advocate who has autism and an intellectual disability, said she had noticed how the word had returned as a common, everyday insult. Hearing it, she said, she feels the sting of stigma — even when it isn’t directed at her or another person with a disability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It makes me want to run, hide and curl up into a ball,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitty Bennett contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/r-word-slur-disability.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:10:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Is Sending Tom Homan, His Border Czar, to Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/homan-minnesota-ice-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-homan-zwgf/26minneapolis-ice-homan-zwgf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said he was sending Tom Homan, his border czar, to Minnesota to run immigration enforcement operations in the state on Monday, two days after a man was fatally shot there by Department of Homeland Security officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to send Mr. Homan, a longtime veteran of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, came amid increased criticism of the D.H.S. operation in the state and its rushed response to the shooting of the man, Alex Pretti, who was pinned down by agents when he was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am sending Tom Homan to Minnesota tonight,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media on Monday. “He has not been involved in that area, but knows and likes many of the people there. Tom is tough but fair, and will report directly to me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, detailed Mr. Homan’s mandate in the state in her own post. “Tom Homan will be managing ICE Operations on the ground in Minnesota to continue arresting the worst of the worst criminal illegal aliens,” she wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Homan has extensive ties at ICE. He led the agency’s deportation wing during the Obama administration, saying at the time that he supported its efforts to target serious criminals in the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Years later, he was tapped to be the agency’s acting director during the first Trump administration. Mr. Homan, along with two other senior leaders, recommended a policy that led to the separation of families along the border in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As border czar, Mr. Homan has taken on a communications role. He often appears on television or holds gaggles with reporters outside the White House, spreading the message of the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown and offering public defenses of its tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running the operations on the ground has mostly been the responsibility of Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, along with other agency leaders. including Gregory Bovino, who has overseen Border Patrol operations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem praised the decision to send Mr. Homan to Minnesota in a social media post. “This is good news for peace, safety, and accountability in Minneapolis,” she wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/homan-minnesota-ice-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:17:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nigella Lawson Joins ‘The Great British Baking Show’ as a Judge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/nigella-lawson-great-british-bake-off.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26xp-bakeoff1/26xp-bakeoff1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Great British Baking Show” announced a new judge on Monday: Nigella Lawson, the British author and cooking personality, after the departure of Prue Leith from the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m uncharacteristically rather lost for words right now!” Ms. Lawson said in a statement announcing her appointment, calling the show a “national treasure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series, known as “The Great British Bake Off” in Britain, developed into one of the most popular shows on British television after its debut in 2010. In 2016, the show’s producer, Love Productions, decided to leave the BBC for Channel 4, a rival network, prompting a judge, Mary Berry, and two of the show’s hosts, Sue Perkins and Mel Giedroyc, to depart. Ms. Leith replaced Ms. Berry in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson said it was “daunting” to be following in the footsteps of Ms. Leith and Mary Berry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Leith, 86, said this month that she was stepping away after nine seasons and more than 400 challenges on the show. Ms. Lawson joins Paul Hollywood, another judge who remained with the show after it left the BBC, and the presenters Noel Fielding and Alison Hammond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the signature tent that serves as the show’s set, bakers compete in challenges for the judges and presenters, pushing the boundaries of baking with unconventional creations. The show has been credited with changing the way Britain viewed the cultural range and offerings of baking, and for inspiring home bakers encouraged by the diverse roster of contestants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson, 66, who was a columnist for The New York Times in the early 2000s, has long been a star of culinary culture, with best-selling cookbooks and television appearances, in a career that has spanned decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “How to Eat,” the cookbook that helped kick off her culinary career, was published in 1998, it featured ingredients that were not popular at the time, including avocado, pomegranate and quinoa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Ms. Lawson demonstrated a recipe from her cookbook “Cook, Eat, Repeat” on her BBC television show of the same name that included a dish of cauliflower and banana peels, an ingredient traditionally used in Bengali cuisine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I certainly didn’t expect newspaper headlines about it!” she told The Times in 2021. “It’s hard to overcome the cultural assumptions about what is and is not edible, and to start eating what we have customarily regarded as waste.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lawson recently celebrated 25 years of her classic baking book, “How to Be a Domestic Goddess.” Ian Katz, the chief content officer at Channel 4, said her addition to the show was “the marriage of two great British icons.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/nigella-lawson-great-british-bake-off.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:01:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>They ‘Had Done Everything Right.’ ICE Detained Them Anyway.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-minnesota-refugees.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00dc-refugees-hfzw/00dc-refugees-hfzw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Selamawit Mehari, an Eritrean single mother of three, was starting her day when federal agents showed up at her apartment in St. Paul, Minn., on a recent morning. As her 13-year-old son wailed and her older daughter produced paperwork proving her mother was in the United States lawfully, the agents shackled Ms. Mehari and took her away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They didn’t explain anything,” recalled her daughter, Yosan, 21, who described the encounter to The New York Times. “We didn’t understand. We had done everything right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, chained at the wrists, waist and ankles, Ms. Mehari, 38, was shuffling up the steps of a plane bound for Texas, tears streaming down her face in the frigid wind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 100 refugees with no criminal record from about a dozen countries have been arrested in Minnesota by immigration agents in recent weeks and flown to detention centers in Texas for interviews, according to lawyers, family members and faith leaders. At least some, including Ms. Mehari, were eventually released in Texas, leaving them to find their own way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrests, which began this month and are continuing, have sown panic among refugees in Minnesota, where thousands of agents are conducting a sweeping operation as President Trump intensifies his national immigration crackdown. Over the weekend, U.S. Border Patrol officers fatally shot a Minneapolis protester in the second killing of a demonstrator at the hands of immigration agents this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being approved for resettlement in the United States, refugees often wait years in camps and undergo extensive vetting by the Department of Homeland Security and other federal agencies. They arrive on flights coordinated with the U.S. government. The process is radically different from that of asylum seekers who have shown up at the border and been allowed to remain in the United States only if they win their cases in immigration court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration had announced early this month that it would “re-examine thousands of refugee cases through new background checks.” Officials said they would focus on people who had arrived in the United States in recent years and were yet to obtain green cards, or legal permanent residency, starting with 5,600 refugees in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement, by U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services, did not say that refugees would be rounded up and jailed for the review to take place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dragnet has swept up refugees from Africa, Asia, Latin America and the Middle East, according to lawyers and leaders of resettlement agencies that are government-funded to assist refugees in the United States. It has included Karen people from Myanmar, a persecuted Christian minority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to questions from The Times about the detentions, a spokesman for Citizenship and Immigration Services, Matthew Tragesser, said in a statement that the agency “is verifying the merits of all refugee applications and ensuring no issues were overlooked.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is determined during the rescreening that a refugee poses a national security or public safety concern, or committed fraud, that person will face deportation proceedings, Mr. Tragesser said, and if the refugee passes, he or she “may be granted a green card.” Mr. Tragesser did not explain why the refugees were being flown to Texas for the interviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Offering sanctuary to the displaced has long been a bedrock of U.S. policy, garnering bipartisan support. Refugees are typically fleeing war or persecution, without the possibility of ever returning to their home country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has sought to drastically cut back legal immigration in addition to purging the country of those here unlawfully. He has halted all refugee admissions except a small group including white Afrikaners from South Africa. The president has fixated on Minnesota’s Somalis, most of whom are refugees, after revelations that some individuals were involved in a multimillion-dollar social-services fraud scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All refugees, once admitted to the United States, must apply for a green card within one year, but some fail to do so — sometimes because they cannot afford it or have challenges with red tape. Those who miss the deadline retain their refugee status, and in the past were not subject to arrest or threatened with deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has never been a systematic effort to re-examine refugees,” said Barbara Strack, a former senior refugee official who served under Republican and Democratic administrations. ”There was a recognition that refugees had been highly vetted overseas before they were admitted.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In rare instances, she said, refugee status might have been re-examined if evidence-based leads raised suspicions of fraud in the application process or criminal or national security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Saturday, a group of refugees represented by two immigrant-rights advocacy organizations and a private law firm filed a federal class-action lawsuit in Minnesota challenging the arrest and imprisonment of refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit said that the refugees had not been charged with crimes or with any violations of immigration statutes, and that the government was using the operation to “trigger a mass termination of refugee status” and to make refugees vulnerable to deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This goal represents an egregious and unlawful betrayal of the promise made to refugees, pursuant to the Refugee Act of 1980 to offer safety, stability and a path to a safe home,” the suit said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times has reviewed court records of three refugees swept up in the arrest operation in recent weeks who were not part of the suit. In one, a Somali refugee was arrested outside his workplace in Minnesota on Jan. 14. Lawyers obtained a court order blocking his movement from Minnesota. The next day, he told his family he had been moved to El Paso. The court later ordered the government to return him to Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another man, from Moldova, was arrested in Minneapolis and moved to Texas on Jan. 16. He was a refugee who entered the United States in 2023 and had applied for a green card. A federal court judge ordered his release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court found that the man had “submitted ample evidence in support of his refugee status and his pending adjustment application.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Accordingly,” the court said, “there is no lawful basis for petitioner’s detention, and the court orders his immediate release.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all cases reviewed by The Times, the refugees had applied for green cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some refugees have been released after hourslong interviews in Texas, often with only the shirts on their backs, their documents still with Immigration and Customs Enforcement in St. Paul. Family and friends have scrambled to buy them bus and plane tickets home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walid Ali, 19, also from Eritrea, was arrested outside his home in St. Paul on Jan. 13 and transferred to a holding facility where ICE is processing the refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They took my wallet, my phone, my social, driver’s license, everything,” said Mr. Ali, who arrived in the United States as an unaccompanied refugee minor in 2023. Friends and relatives paid for a flight back from Houston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ali said that he protested when his belongings were confiscated, and that agents responded by pushing him to the ground, kneeling on him and beating him. His uncle, who is a nurse, said he had made an appointment at a clinic to check his nephew’s neck, shoulders and back, as well as to have his ribs X-rayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not the American way, to grab people from the street and violate their rights, hit them,” said the uncle, Sal Gimiy, 51.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resettlement groups said the unpredictability of the tactics employed has amplified the fear rippling through refugee communities. While agents sometimes seek specific people, other times they seem to strike at random. They have knocked on doors and arrested an adult or an entire family, and have picked up people from grocery stores and city streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are hearing from a lot of families about their immense fear and confusion about what is happening,” said Rebekah Phillips, the executive director of Arrive Ministries, a local resettlement agency. “They are afraid to send kids to school, attend work. They don’t know if they will be detained, or redetained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refugees are often being questioned without the chance to prepare or to contact a lawyer, according to advocates and resettlement agencies. The groups were aware of refugees who have been released but many remain detained, they said, and did not know whether any had been deported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The refugees who have been detained described being subjected to a jarring and bewildering process. Ms. Mehari, who works at the Minneapolis airport packing meals for airlines, spent five days in custody, first in St. Paul and then in Houston. Along the way, she was given conflicting information about her fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her children did not hear from her until late in the afternoon on Jan. 13, the day she was arrested, when she was permitted to make a call from an ICE facility in St. Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I kept telling my mother not to sign anything,” her daughter, Yosan, recalled. Her mother had already applied for a green card, and Yosan suggested authorities could check her files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with The Times, Ms. Mehari said she was told at the facility that she would be transferred to Texas and then deported to Eritrea. Do you want to take your kids with you, an officer asked, according to her recollection. “No, no, no,” she responded, insisting she had a friend who could care for the 13- and 14-year-old, who was not home when she was detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a call to that friend shortly after, an officer explained that Ms. Mehari had been detained because she had not adjusted her status and her case would be reassessed, the friend, Elsa Zerai, said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari, who has been living in the United States since 2023, was baffled, she said. To work at the airport, she wears a badge that whisks her through security checkpoints for her shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival in Texas on Jan. 14, she said she was issued prison garb and rubber slippers, and locked in a frigid room with other women. There were mattresses on the floor and thin metallic sheets to huddle under. She said she lost track of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari clung to her Christian faith. “God, help us,” she prayed. “What will become of me, my children?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, she was escorted to an interview room, where an immigration official questioned her for three hours with an interpreter on the line translating into Tigrinya. He asked about her history, her fears of returning to her homeland and her reasons for seeking refuge in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were familiar questions — ones she had answered when she was screened to come to the United States, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she was returned to the cell, Ms. Mehari had no idea if she had passed or failed. She was allowed one brief call home during which she wept before the line was cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, one day, she was abruptly ordered to change back into her street clothes. It was Saturday, Jan. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Mehari was released alongside several other men and women, all refugees. “I screamed: ‘I’m free! I’m free,” Ms. Mehari recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without money and identification, they had to make it home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yosan sent an acquaintance in Houston $255 to buy a plane ticket for her mother, and she sent screenshots of her mother’s immigration papers to his phone to show airport security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that day, the family learned that her green card had been approved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Sunday,Ms. Mehari still did not have her documents or her favorite gold chain, which the authorities confiscated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caroline Yang contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-minnesota-refugees.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 10:26:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Parts of Minneapolis Carry On, but Talk of Killings Is Everywhere</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-shootings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-nat-minn-talk-qwkf/25minneapolis-ice-nat-minn-talk-qwkf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A crowd of dozens cheered when the final buzzer sounded at the U.S. Pond Hockey Championships on Sunday, an event that had drawn teams from 20 states to a frozen lake in a city that remained in the throes of a contentious immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hockey players and fans bundled up to their eyes chatted around the empty rinks, or filtered back to their cars hauling oversized duffel bags. Just a day earlier in Minneapolis, several miles across town, the streets had been littered with tear gas canisters and crowd control munitions, after a second fatal shooting by federal law enforcement agents touched off a wave of unrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even at the hockey tournament, removed from the conflicts that have left pockets of the Twin Cities resembling war zones, the clashes were at the top of everyone’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are trying to get out there as much as I think they can, yet still feeling scared, and I think still feeling really helpless,” said Mark Holloway, 48, of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As escalating clashes between federal agents and residents continue to rattle Minneapolis, life elsewhere in the city — in its parks, its downtown core, its quiet neighborhoods — has continued. But several people who spoke to The New York Times across Minneapolis over the weekend said that the issue had overshadowed daily life, if only as an undercurrent of fear, and was a constant subject of conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Holloway was among the spectators heading to the parking lot as the hockey tournament wrapped up on the shores of Lake Nokomis on the city’s south side. He said the immigration sweep had directly touched his family and his community. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents had shown up on the grounds of his son’s high school, he said, and his neighbors who feared they could be profiled as immigrants based on their appearance had started carrying passports for fear of being detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a 48-year-old white guy,” Mr. Holloway said, his breath turning to vapor in the subzero temperatures. “And I don’t feel really safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several visitors to the city — who had flown in from as far as Colorado, Utah and Texas — said that recent events had been top of mind for them when they arrived. But their trips, so far, had been largely without disruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing around a fire pit beside the rinks, Nate Jackson, 40, and Casey Donovan, 39, visiting hockey players from Texas, said they had arrived in Minneapolis expecting to find a city in chaos. So far, though, they hadn’t seen any signs of unrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching from afar, the two men said that though they supported law enforcement, they felt the conflicts were unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think it’s all parties involved, on that one,” Mr. Donovan said. “There’s not a single person to point a finger at.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Cooler heads could prevail, but it just seems like that’s not even an option,” Mr. Jackson added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they left the event, many attendees drove past the intersection of Cedar Avenue and East Minnehaha Parkway, where protesters held signs denouncing ICE. Kyle Ness, 56, of Minneapolis, was among them. He said he had been protesting on and off for some time, but was compelled to be even more involved in the demonstrations after federal agents shot and killed a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident, Alex Pretti, on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The collateral damage that’s coming from their extreme anger toward people exercising their rights, like in the case of Alex — that’s what really got me mad,” Mr. Ness said of the federal agents in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impacts of the immigration crackdown resonated even more deeply in the Cedar-Riverside neighborhood, known by locals as Little Mogadishu for its high concentration of residents of Somalian heritage. Few pedestrians were out early Sunday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Afrik Grocery African Market, the co-manager Mohamed Ahmed said the crackdown had left his store quieter than ever, as his customers were afraid to go out shopping. Even the suppliers who kept his shelves stocked were affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The suppliers don’t have drivers,” said Mr. Ahmed, a native of Somalia who said he had lived in Minneapolis for more than 20 years. His shelf that usually holds injera, a staple of Ethiopian cuisine, sat empty on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Minneapolis’s downtown core later Saturday afternoon, protesters toted signs as they dispersed through the quiet streets. On the floor of the city’s convention center, visitors toured lavishly outfitted pontoons on display at the Minneapolis boat show. Khaleel Thompson, 26, stood by the doors waiting to meet a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Thompson said he had steered clear of the protests, knowing how quickly things could escalate, and had not followed events in the city very closely. Aside from glimpses of the demonstrations, he had not felt the impacts of the immigration enforcement operation on his daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the deaths of Renee Good, the 37-year-old woman killed by an ICE agent in Minneapolis earlier this month, and Mr. Pretti on Saturday, he felt it would best if the agents left Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those people didn’t have to die,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-shootings.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:21:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonstrators Enter Hotel Vestibule, Setting Off a Fracas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-protests-minneapolis-hotel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-hotel-agents-qhjk/26minneapolis-ice-hotel-agents-qhjk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What began as a noise demonstration outside of a Home2Suites by Hilton hotel near the University of Minnesota became heated on Sunday night as protesters were met with dozens of federal agents and tear gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 8 p.m., after about an hour of peaceful protesting, some began vandalizing the building with messages like “ICE OUT” as others hurled objects at the windows. As people began entering the hotel vestibule, two employees and a single Minneapolis police officer tried to calm the scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hotel guests, many in masks like those worn by federal immigration agents, began gathering in the lobby. Two men pushed vending machines to block the glass front doors. By 9 p.m., many of the protesters had left, and about 50 protesters remained on the street in front of the hotel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, the Minnesota Police Department said that as the protesters became disorderly, police officers and officers from assisting agencies “began moving in to surround the crowd, give dispersal orders and prepare for mass arrests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal forces arrived without warning, the Police Department said, and deployed tear gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two dozen armed federal agents entered the hotel around 10 p.m. They left about an hour later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis police officers did not fire any chemical munitions, according to the statement, and federal officials refused help from the Police Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two men were detained by the police and released, the department said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-protests-minneapolis-hotel.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:33:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Is the Trump Administration Demanding Minnesota’s Voter Rolls?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minnesota-trump-voter-rolls.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/us/politics/pol-minnesota-voter-rolls/pol-minnesota-voter-rolls-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After federal immigration agents shot and killed an American citizen in Minneapolis for the second time this month, Attorney General Pam Bondi sent a letter to Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota that outlined what she described as three “simple steps” to “bring back law and order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her final step, however, seemed to have little to do with immigration or the state’s fraud scandal, the stated reasons for the federal government’s presence in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Third, allow the Civil Rights Division of the Department of Justice to access voter rolls to confirm that Minnesota’s voter registration practices comply with federal law,” she wrote. Minnesota’s secretary of state, Steve Simon, a Democrat, swiftly rejected the demand, calling it an “outrageous attempt to coerce Minnesota into giving the federal government private data on millions of U.S. citizens in violation of state and federal law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Bondi’s request was part of a nearly yearlong fight in which the Trump administration has sought voters’ private data from states across the country. Numerous states, including Minnesota, have not complied, and the Justice Department has sued them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at what is happening and the concerns over privacy and elections that have arisen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every state has a public version of its voter roll that includes basic information like first and last names. Some of these rolls include addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the complete, unredacted voter file includes personal identifying information, like driver’s license numbers and Social Security numbers. This list is kept private and is maintained by top election officials in each state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, no one can obtain it through public records requests — not even the Justice Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Bondi has said that the Trump administration is trying to keep elections secure. But President Trump and his allies — who tried to overturn the 2020 election and continue to deny its legitimacy — have long pushed unsubstantiated claims about undocumented immigrants voting illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And last year, the Justice Department began to try to build the largest set of national voter roll data it has ever collected, raising concerns that the data could be used to cast doubt on future election results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it’s highly unusual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department has taken aggressive steps in the past to try to root out voter fraud, including during former President George W. Bush’s administration. But the idea of the federal government obtaining states’ private voter information was long seen as an overreach, because the Constitution dictates that elections are run mainly by individual states, not the administration in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 11, all of them at least partly run by Republicans, according to data from the Brennan Center for Justice, a voting rights and democracy group. Some other states, largely Republican-led ones, have provided their voter data to a separate but related program in the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But roughly half of the country’s states, most of them led by Democrats, have rejected the requests. The Justice Department has sued at least 24 states and territories, including Minnesota, to force them to turn over their voter data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some states, including Minnesota, have laws that prevent the transfer of private information. Others have expressed worries about how the Justice Department will keep the enormous troves of private information secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for many election officials and voting rights experts, the main concern is that the Justice Department’s effort is led by Trump allies who long falsely denied that former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. won the 2020 election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These data can be manipulated to support false claims about ineligible voting and justify efforts to thwart free and fair elections,” Wendy Weiser, who directs the Democracy Program at the Brennan Center, wrote on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minnesota secretary of state, Mr. Simon, said this possibility was on his mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Though I’m not necessarily predicting direct federal interference with elections, I am planning for it,” he said in an interview, “and it would be irresponsible to not do that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is still being litigated, but some legal experts have pointed to the Constitution’s language that the “times, places and manner” of elections are governed by the states, and that only Congress — not the president — can make or change election laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, a federal judge in California dismissed the Justice Department’s lawsuit against California seeking to obtain its full voter roll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The taking of democracy does not occur in one fell swoop; it is chipped away piece-by-piece until there is nothing left,” wrote Judge David O. Carter, an appointee of former President Bill Clinton. “The erosion of privacy and rolling back of voting rights is a decision for open and public debate within the legislative branch, not the executive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Election officials also say that any national voter roll within the Justice Department would probably be rife with errors because each state’s voter file is updated every day, changing as voters move away or die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If any state were to provide a voter list, and the list against which the federal government or anyone else is checking it is out of date, you’re going to have a lot of falsely identified ineligible voters,” Mr. Simon said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minnesota-trump-voter-rolls.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:03:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice Dept. Drops Charges Accusing Person of Assaulting an Officer</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/justice-dept-drops-charges-assault-officer.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-dismissal-protest-wqvm/26minneapolis-ice-dismissal-protest-wqvm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors dropped assault charges on Monday against a man accused of ramming his vehicle into federal agents during an immigration operation outside a Mexican restaurant in Minnesota this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dismissal of the charges against the man, Jose Espinoza-Espinoza, came at a five-minute hearing in Federal District Court in Minnesota where prosecutors did not present any witnesses to establish probable cause that an assault had been committed. The dismissal appeared to be the first time that the Justice Department has backed away from pursuing an assault case against a federal agent in Minnesota since the Trump administration ramped up an immigration crackdown in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have repeatedly asserted that federal agents in Minnesota have come under constant attack as they carry out the White House’s aggressive deportation efforts. Those claims have grown in frequency and volume after immigration officers fatally shot two people, Renee Good and Alex Pretti, in Minneapolis in recent weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Espinoza-Espinoza was taken into custody on Jan. 16 after prosecutors said that several federal agents approached him in his Mazda outside a Mexican restaurant in Virginia, Minn., and he “rapidly accelerated.” Court papers say that Mr. Espinoza-Espinoza injured the finger of one of the agents and drove into the vehicle of another, causing it to leak coolant fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the agents removed Mr. Espinoza-Espinoza from his car, he resisted arrest by trying to avoid being handcuffed, according to the court papers. He later told investigators that he was from Guatemala and was in the United States illegally, raising the possibility that he could now be deported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Magistrate Judge Leo I. Brisbois, who oversaw the case, consented to the government’s request to dismiss the charges and ordered Mr. Espinoza-Espinoza to be released from criminal custody.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/justice-dept-drops-charges-assault-officer.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:21:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White House Wobbles, Distancing Trump From Initial Response to Minnesota Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-nurse-shooting-video.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-new-gpqc/26dc-trump-new-gpqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with broad outcry over the killing of a protester on Saturday in Minneapolis, the White House on Monday tried to distance President Trump from the response of his most senior officials, who had immediately characterized the man fatally shot by federal agents as a “domestic terrorist” who was “brandishing” a gun, before video evidence undercut their charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, notably did not defend the rhetoric of White House officials, including Stephen Miller, the deputy chief of staff, and Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, who were the most vocal in spreading false accusations against the victim, Alex Pretti. Mr. Pretti was shot roughly 10 times by immigration agents after he was apparently filming them with his camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was licensed to carry a gun in Minnesota, but video from several angles shows he never pulled one, and his hands were visible as he was shot in the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White House officials clearly understood that the killing, the second of an American citizen protesting the presence of Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Minneapolis, posed one of the gravest political threats to Mr. Trump since his inauguration just a little over a year ago. Yet they seemed frozen in place, unwilling to walk back the statements by Mr. Miller and Ms. Noem, which were widely repeated throughout the administration, while sending Ms. Leavitt out to insist that “we will let the facts lead and we will let the facts play out in this investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They provided no evidence to back up the statements by the two officials, who have become the face of Mr. Trump’s efforts to deport undocumented immigrants. And while Ms. Leavitt would not contradict the two officials, she insisted to reporters that “nobody in the White House, including President Trump, wants to see people getting hurt or killed in America’s streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also declined to defend the attacks on Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This has obviously been a very fluid and fast-moving situation throughout the weekend,” Ms. Leavitt said. “As for President Trump, whom I speak for, he has said that he wants to let the investigation continue and let the facts lead in this case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For two days, the White House has struggled to contain the fallout from the killing. Democrats have been withering in their criticism of the administration’s actions, and Republicans have begun joining calls for a fair investigation into the killing. Even the National Rifle Association, long an ally of Republican administrations, has defended Mr. Pretti, who had a concealed-carry permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bipartisan pushback on Capitol Hill now risks another government shutdown as lawmakers threaten to withhold funding for ICE after the killing of Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Mr. Trump dispatched his border chief, Tom Homan, to oversee the immigration enforcement operation in Minneapolis and backed off his attacks on Minnesota’s governor after a phone call with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Homan takes over that job, it was not clear what would become of Gregory Bovino, the official in charge of Mr. Trump’s Border Patrol operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Leavitt did not directly answer a question about whether Mr. Bovino would remain in Minneapolis after Mr. Homan’s arrival. She called Mr. Bovino “a great professional” who “is going to very much continue to lead Customs and Border Patrol throughout and across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his latest pivot, Mr. Trump moved from castigating Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota as a cause of the violence in Minneapolis and declared that, in a call, they “seemed to be on a similar wavelength.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said on social media that Mr. Walz was “happy that Tom Homan was going to Minnesota.” Mr. Trump announced earlier in the day that Mr. Homan would be his personal representative overseeing ICE operations in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a sharp contrast from his weekend pronunciations, in which the president blamed Mr. Walz and other Minnesota Democrats for Mr. Pretti’s death. Those remarks echoed his comments after the fatal shooting by federal agents of a Minneapolis woman, Renee Good, this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he hailed operations in Washington and other cities as a “tremendous success,” Mr. Trump said crime in Minnesota was “way down.” He added, “Both Governor Walz and I want to make it better!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Mr. Walz’s office described the call as “productive” and said the two men had discussed broader issues that have been at the center of the state’s complaints about the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the governor’s office, Mr. Walz told Mr. Trump that impartial investigations into the two killings were needed, and he called for a reduction in the number of federal agents in Minnesota. Mr. Trump agreed to ensure a fair investigation and to look into reducing the number of agents, the governor’s office said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even as Mr. Trump tried to mend fences with Mr. Walz, Ms. Leavitt continued the administration’s previous strategy of arguing that the governor and Democrats in Minnesota bore the blame for the chaos. “This tragedy occurred as a result of a deliberate and hostile resistance by Democrat leaders in Minnesota for weeks,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration’s reaction to the killing of Mr. Pretti was similar to its initial approach the killing of Ms. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, administration officials rushed to attack the victims and defend the ICE agents before an investigation had taken place. After video emerged raising serious questions about the cause for both killings, White House officials changed their tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Mr. Trump said the killing of Ms. Good was a “tragedy” about which he “felt terribly,” adding that the immigration agents he had deployed were sometimes “going to make a mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change in tone was stark for the president, who said he had been told that Ms. Good’s father was a strong Trump supporter. No longer did the administration suggest she was a domestic terrorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You know, when the woman was shot, I felt terribly about it,” he said. “And I understand both sides of it.” He called the shooting “a horrible thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hours after Mr. Pretti’s killing, Mr. Trump referred to him as a “gunman” in a social media post. But after video emerged showing that Mr. Pretti carried a cellphone, and that agents took his legally carried gun from him before shooting him, the White House had a different message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody here at the White House, including the president of the United States, wants to see Americans hurt or killed and losing their lives in American streets,” Ms. Leavitt said on Monday. “And we mourn for the parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ernesto Londoño contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-nurse-shooting-video.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:38:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrat Who Voted for D.H.S. Funding Suggests He Now Regrets It</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/democrats-ice-funding-vote-dhs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-democrats-Suozzi-cjpf/26minneapolis-ice-democrats-Suozzi-cjpf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Tom Suozzi of New York, one of seven Democrats who broke from their party last week to provide the votes to pass a bill to fund the Homeland Security Department, told his constituents on Monday that he had “failed” in doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an email sent by his re-election campaign, Mr. Suozzi, who represents a politically competitive district on Long Island, suggested that he was hearing outrage from his community about the vote and had come to regret it. He said that he fell short by not taking into account the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I failed to view the D.H.S. funding vote as a referendum on the illegal and immoral conduct of ICE in Minneapolis,” Mr. Suozzi wrote. “I hear the anger from many of my constituents, and I take responsibility for that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Suozzi’s statement came two days after a federal agent shot and killed Alex Jeffrey Pretti, 37, an intensive care nurse, in Minneapolis. It was the second fatal shooting of a United States citizen there this month, after an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent killed Renee Good, 37.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Good’s death, many Democrats in Congress refused to advance legislation that provided funding for ICE, saying no money should go to the agency without imposing severe restrictions on its tactics. But Mr. Suozzi and six other Democrats crossed party lines to pass it, in a 220 to 207 vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their backing was vital because given Republicans’ tiny margin of control, they would otherwise have lacked the votes to approve the funding bill. And while a solid contingent of Senate Democrats had been expected to follow suit and allow the measure to clear Congress this week as part of a larger spending package, they reversed course after Mr. Pretti’s shooting and are now vowing not to do so, even if it means shutting down the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Mr. Suozzi went the furthest to distance himself from his vote, other Democrats who voted for the spending bill tried to downplay funding ICE and focus attention elsewhere. In a video on social media, Representative Vicente Gonzalez of Texas said that he voted for the spending bill “not to fund ICE,” but to secure funding for the Federal Emergency Management Agency, the Coast Guard and other agencies covered by the measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While we hold ICE and every other federal agency accountable, let’s do it thoughtfully, smartly,” Mr. Gonzalez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Laura Gillen of New York, who also represents a swing district on Long Island, did not address her vote on Sunday but called for the impeachment of Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, joining dozens of Democrats who have demanded her removal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a statement on Monday, Ms. Gillen, one of the most politically vulnerable House Democrats, said that her vote on the spending bill was necessary to “fund essential disaster-relief and local and national security efforts,” and argued that the bill imposed “important guardrails for ICE, including body cameras and increased de-escalation training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Marie Gluesenkamp Perez of Washington on Sunday called the shooting “un-American” and called on Ms. Noem to step down, but she did not mention her backing for funding the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other Democrats who joined Republicans to pass the spending bill were Representatives Henry Cuellar of Texas, Jared Golden of Maine and Don Davis of North Carolina, whose offices did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/democrats-ice-funding-vote-dhs.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:28:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Foreign Policy, Trump’s Fans Give Him the Benefit of the Doubt</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-supporters-foreign-policy-greenland-iran.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-maga-greenland-TOP-gckb/26dc-maga-greenland-TOP-gckb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When President Trump bombed Iran last summer, Nathaniel Cheevers, 24, thought: “Yup, that’s exactly why I hired you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Trump has veered from the way diplomacy is typically conducted, Mr. Cheevers saw him as doing “the most American thing a president can do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for taking over Greenland, “the idea that we shouldn’t expand our borders is kind of ridiculous,” he said. “That’s how we made the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s foreign policy whirlwind of recent months has bewildered many, including Republicans who wish he were spending more time fixing problems closer to home. His grab for Greenland and his attacks on Venezuela, Nigeria, Iran and beyond have confounded those who thought “America First” would mean fewer foreign interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for now, Mr. Trump’s supporters appear largely to be giving him the benefit of the doubt when it comes to foreign policy. Where critics see bluster, they see the “art of the deal.” Where even some Republicans see an abandonment of the postwar rules and alliances that made America prosperous, Mr. Trump’s fans laud a president reviving the spirit of Theodore Roosevelt. And while Mr. Trump may appear to be contradicting his campaign rhetoric opposing military adventures, the president’s mantra of “peace through strength” still resonates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, Mr. Trump’s foreign policy may yet prove a political liability, and polls show that independent voters are deeply skeptical of it. For now, Mr. Trump’s military moves have been quick and have not cost American lives, meaning that public opinion could sour further if a future intervention is more painful. And Mr. Trump’s latest foreign policy decisions are being made against the background of growing anger over his administration’s actions in Minnesota, a furor that could drown out any successes he tries to point to abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the blowback from his base about his overseas interventions has been limited. Mr. Trump appeared to back down from his demand for taking over Greenland last week, but the framework of a deal he says he reached with NATO over the Danish-owned island remained unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump’s base has a phobia or a distaste or an objection to endless wars,” said Douglas Wilson, an evangelical pastor in Moscow, Idaho, who has emerged as one of the president’s most prominent defenders on the ultraconservative Christian right. “But they don’t have an objection to flexing militarily.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polls show concern about the economy and a widespread view that Mr. Trump is not focusing on the right priorities. But they also show Republicans to be largely on board with his aggressive foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Marist poll conducted Jan. 12 and 13 found that most Republicans favored the United States’ taking military action in Venezuela, Iran, Mexico, Cuba and even, at 57 percent, Greenland. A Quinnipiac poll conducted Jan. 8 to 12 showed only 23 percent of Republicans supporting the use of force to take Greenland, but 67 percent supporting attempts to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Washington, even conservatives who favor restraint in foreign policy have found things to like in Mr. Trump’s global hyperactivity of the last few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curt Mills, executive director of The American Conservative, a magazine founded by the 1990s right-wing presidential candidate Patrick J. Buchanan, called Mr. Trump’s attack on Venezuela “foolhardy.” Attacking Iran to support protesters, he said in an interview, would seem jarring when the administration is “currently trying to suppress protest in Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But finding a peaceful way to annex Greenland, he said, “is the most sympathetic thing the government has proposed doing on foreign policy in nearly a century.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The European argument that this could unravel NATO — what a bonus,” Mr. Mills said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interviews in Moscow, Idaho, last week showed that Mr. Trump’s supporters were inclined to trust the president’s foreign policy, even if they sometimes struggled to explain it. Brandon Mitchell, the area’s representative in the Idaho House of Representatives, endorsed Mr. Trump’s interest in Greenland, even though “I kind of don’t know where he’s at on that and why.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of things that he does that I kind of questioned and then I’m like, ‘But that worked,’” said Mr. Mitchell, a Republican who operates Jiffy Lube shops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In downtown Moscow — the second syllable is “coe,” not “cow” — America’s divisions are palpable on every corner. Gay pride flags are displayed at businesses aligned with the liberal community revolving around the main campus of the University of Idaho in town. And then there are the buildings associated with Pastor Wilson, one of America’s best-known Christian nationalists; Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth is part of his denomination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watched closely by security guards, Nick Solheim, a rising political operative who had flown in from Washington, gave a speech at Pastor Wilson’s New Saint Andrews College urging the students to join him in the fight against their “enemies.” He highlighted Mr. Trump’s campaign message about “an end to endless wars,” and attacked “Republican elites” like Senator Lindsey Graham of South Carolina for teaming up with “establishment hawks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Solheim, 28, said nothing about Mr. Trump’s own military interventions, instead praising his trade deals and mass deportations. In addition to cofounding a group, American Moment, that aims to train the next generation of Republican aides, Mr. Solheim has mused about buying Greenland since at least 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, he described Mr. Trump’s pursuit of Greenland as having “spiritual” significance, because “our nation has stagnated in a certain sense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We haven’t been to the moon since, what, the ’70s or ’80s,” he said. “We haven’t explored new territory. We haven’t conquered anything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the young men in Mr. Solheim’s audience was Jacob Gartrell, 19, president of the University of Idaho chapter of Turning Point USA, the right-wing group founded by Charlie Kirk. Mr. Gartrell said he appreciated Mr. Trump’s attacks on “drug boats” near Venezuela because each bombing was saving hundreds of lives, echoing the president’s contention about the strikes. (He said he was speaking only for himself, not his group.) But he had issues with other aspects of Mr. Trump’s foreign policy, because he believed that the United States already had too many foreigners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we were to take over both Venezuela and Greenland,” he said, their residents could “just hop on a plane and come to America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has not talked about annexing Venezuela, but has promised to “run” the country indefinitely. Still, Mr. Gartrell’s concern highlighted the contradictory impulses of Trump supporters who want their leaders to turn inward but also to project strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Florian Justwan, a political science professor at the University of Idaho, said there were early indications in his own, unpublished survey research of the seeming foreign-policy contradictions in Mr. Trump’s base: core supporters of Mr. Trump appear both more likely than other Republicans to say that the United States should concentrate more on its own problems, and more likely to favor military action in places like Greenland and Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Justwan said that Mr. Trump’s populist approach to foreign policy — like sharing private texts from world leaders — still appeared to resonate with his base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s about anti-elitism,” he said. “It’s about doing what’s right for the in-group.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, after the campus Turning Point USA meeting last Friday night, Ben Coons, 22, said it was “really cool” that Mr. Trump was making “people respect us when we feed them and take care of them.” He said that last summer he’d visited Denmark, where they “pooh-pooh America all day long.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was also some unease. Pastor Wilson, the far-right Christian leader, said that acquiring Greenland was a “good, noble goal,” as long as it was done “peaceably.” Striking Venezuela was “defensible” because “what you had was a drug cartel that had seized control of a government.” But airstrikes for changing the government in Iran would not be, because “what’s the American foreign policy interest in doing this with naked military power?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of the Venezuela mission, he warned, “invites a spirit of hubris.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thus far, Trump is living a charmed life in foreign policy,” Pastor Wilson said. “So take risks when you need to, but don’t resort to it first thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastor Wilson has said that his flock makes up some 10 percent of Moscow’s increasingly polarized population of around 25,000 people. At the town’s Unitarian Universalist church, the Rev. Elizabeth Stevens said she believed there was no longer a single Trump supporter in her congregation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastor Stevens said parents of adolescents had told her they worried “that we are going to slide into World War III and their kids are going to get called up and put at risk.” She pointed to Mr. Trump’s renaming the Defense Department the Department of War and the administration’s turn against U.S. allies, international law and the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A lot of people are making comparisons to heading into World War II, and this time we’re on the wrong side,” Pastor Stevens said. “There’s a lot of fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-supporters-foreign-policy-greenland-iran.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:40:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Asks Pointed Questions, but Does Not Rule, in Hearing Seeking Block to ICE Surge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-hearing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-gun-fplk/26minneapolis-ice-gun-fplk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in Minnesota asked a lawyer for the Trump administration on Monday whether the surge of federal officers to the state was really just about immigration enforcement, or whether it might also be motivated by political retribution and coercion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the judge, Kate M. Menendez of the Federal District Court, also had pointed questions about the state government’s request that she issue a sweeping order blocking the surge of agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota, along with the cities of Minneapolis and St. Paul, filed a lawsuit two weeks ago claiming that the Trump administration’s campaign, called Operation Metro Surge, violates state sovereignty under the 10th Amendment and should be blocked. The surge has brought some 3,000 federal agents to Minnesota, resulting in thousands of arrests, three shootings and tense protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez, who was nominated to the bench by former President Joseph R. Biden Jr., did not rule from the bench on Monday and did not provide a timeline for issuing a written decision. She indicated that she would move quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If I had a burner in front of the front burner, this would be on it,” the judge said as the hearing ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some takeaways from the hearing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For two weeks, lawyers for the state and the cities have pressed Judge Menendez to immediately issue a temporary restraining order blocking the surge. But the judge has moved more slowly, giving the Trump administration time to reply to the lawsuit in writing, and then scheduling oral arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since her first hearing on the case, federal agents have shot two people in Minneapolis, including the nonfatal shooting of a Venezuelan man accused of resisting arrest and the killing on Saturday of Alex Pretti, a U.S. citizen and nurse. An earlier fatal shooting, of Renee Good, also a U.S. citizen, took place days before the suit was filed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lindsey Middlecamp, a lawyer for the state, reiterated the call for swift action on Monday, asking the judge to stop what she called an “invasion” of federal agents. She called on the judge to “issue a temporary restraining order today. Not tomorrow. Not next week. Today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sara Lathrop, a lawyer for the city of Minneapolis, said on Monday that the events over the weekend showed that the “situation is absolutely untenable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Brantley Mayers, a lawyer for the Trump administration, described the request for an order blocking the surge as “a pretty staggering remedy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez said in court that “I think it goes without saying that we are in shockingly unusual times.” But she pressed lawyers for the state to explain when, in its view, the federal government deploying federal agents to enforce federal law could become a constitutional affront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How do I decide when a law enforcement response crosses the line from a legitimate law enforcement response to a response that violates the 10th Amendment?” the judge asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state has not sought an end to all immigration enforcement in Minnesota, only a return to the levels seen before the surge. But its lawyers were reluctant to provide a specific number of agents or amount of enforcement that they believed tipped the scales into unconstitutional behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is so far beyond the pale of legality,” said one of the state’s lawyers, Brian Carter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge also expressed some concern about the sweeping nature of the lawsuit, and asked whether some of the claims of unconstitutional behavior might be better addressed through separate, more focused lawsuits, like one she is hearing on agents’ actions toward protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems that part of the solution for this set of wrongs that you describe is to bring cases about those wrongs,” Judge Menendez said, “rather than to say all of these things together means the federal government has to leave the state of Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mayers, the federal government’s lawyer, argued that immigration agents were “here enforcing federal law” and were acting within their authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He noted that Congress had passed immigration laws and that President Trump had campaigned on a promise to crack down on illegal immigration. Judge Menendez said that might be true broadly, but that the surge of thousands of “troops to the state of Minnesota has not been vetted in any democratic forge, so to speak.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mayers said the administration had found that Minnesota officials were not doing enough to help with immigration enforcement, and that more federal enforcement was needed “to address the law enforcement vacuum.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mayers argued that was not allowable for a state “to use the 10th Amendment as both a sword and a shield.” His point was that Minnesota officials were choosing not to cooperate with aspects of federal immigration enforcement, and then also objecting when the federal government decided to devote more resources to that issue in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez noted that the state of Minnesota “has one set of values” around immigration enforcement, and the Trump administration has another. She told a lawyer for the state that “we’re at risk of asking me to decide who’s right there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State and city officials claimed that the motives for Operation Metro Surge reached beyond immigration enforcement and were part of a broader campaign of payback against the president’s perceived political enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carter said that “it is personal animosity, it is retribution” that was motivating the Trump administration’s campaign in Minnesota. He also accused the administration of trying to strong-arm the state into changing its policies on immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The federal government is attempting to bend the state’s will to its own,” Mr. Carter said, “and that is not allowed under the Constitution.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez referred to a social media post by President Trump that mentioned Minnesota and said “THE DAY OF RECKONING &amp; RETRIBUTION IS COMING!” She also asked repeatedly about a letter sent over the weekend by Attorney General Pam Bondi to Gov. Tim Walz that outlined several policy demands for the state related to immigration enforcement, welfare programs and a request to hand over voter rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Middlecamp, a lawyer for the state, had referred to Ms. Bondi’s letter as “a ransom note.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pressed on those issues, Mr. Mayers, the federal government’s lawyer, insisted the operation was about enforcing immigration laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is nothing to back up this claim that we’re here for another reason,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While other states have brought 10th Amendment lawsuits against the federal government over the years, lawyers for both sides struggled to find direct parallels for the claims being made in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carter said that “this situation is unprecedented in the 250-year history of our country.” He claimed the deployment of immigration agents — which he called “essentially an army” — was intended to “basically stir the pot with conduct that is pervasive and includes widespread illegal violent conduct.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mayers countered that it was well within the president’s rights to deploy federal law enforcement agents within the country as he saw fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fred Smith Jr., a Stanford law professor, said in an interview that Minnesota’s lawsuit “makes novel claims,” but that the “central government is doing novel things, and so there’s not a lot of precedent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ruling in favor of Minnesota, Mr. Smith said, could “open up a door to kind of a new area of 10th Amendment jurisprudence, where the federal government in the future would have to be mindful about acting in ways that unduly interfered with states’ ability to carry out their own laws.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same day that Minnesota officials sued, Illinois officials filed their own 10th Amendment case asking another judge to block U.S. Customs and Border Protection “from conducting civil immigration enforcement” in the state without “express congressional authorization.” An order has yet to be issued in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ernesto Londoño and Bernard Mokam contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-ice-hearing.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:11:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under Biden Administration, Justice Dept. Began Examining Ilhan Omar’s Finances</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ilhan-omar-investigation-finances.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-omar-photo-ctpq/26dc-omar-photo-ctpq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department under the Biden administration opened an investigation into Representative Ilhan Omar, Democrat of Minnesota, in 2024 to scrutinize her finances, campaign spending and interactions with a foreign citizen, according to people with knowledge of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inquiry, initiated by the U.S. attorney’s office in Washington and the department’s public integrity unit in June of that year, appears to have stalled for lack of evidence, according to one of the people who requested anonymity to discuss internal department matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation was thrust into the public spotlight on Monday, when President Trump blindsided department officials by posting about it on Truth Social, singling out Ms. Omar. It was part of a rambling statement announcing a shake-up of the team overseeing immigration raids in Ms. Omar’s Minneapolis district that misspelled her name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The DOJ and Congress are looking at ‘Congresswoman’ Illhan Omar, who left Somalia with NOTHING, and is now reportedly worth more than 44 Million Dollars,” he wrote. “Time will tell all.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear how Mr. Trump arrived at the $44 million figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar, a Somali-born refugee who emigrated to the United States when she was 12, has repeatedly denied any wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sorry, Trump, your support is collapsing and you’re panicking,” she wrote on social media on Monday. “Right on cue, you’re deflecting from your failures with lies and conspiracy theories about me. Years of ‘investigations’ have found nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publicly announcing criminal investigations against political opponents has been a feature of the Trump’s administration’s approach to federal law enforcement. It violates the Justice Department’s standards of practice and can jeopardize future prosecutions by giving defense lawyers an opening to claim that investigations and prosecutions are malicious and unjustified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ugly personal attacks against Ms. Omar have been a staple of Mr. Trump’s speeches since her election to Congress in 2018, when she and Representative Rashida Tlaib, Democrat of Michigan, made history as the first two Muslim women elected to Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar’s sharp criticism of Israel, her repetition of antisemitic tropes and her comparison of U.S. actions to those of Hamas have elicited bipartisan criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But few people have demonized her more than Mr. Trump, who has veered into racist and xenophobic vitriol, in the view of Ms. Omar and other critics of the president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 2020 election, Mr. Trump would often goad his supporters to chant “send her back” to Somalia. Ms. Omar, who has not bristled from fighting back against the president, appears to still be a fixation of his.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump recently called her “garbage” at a cabinet meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, House Republicans have threatened to open their own investigation into Ms. Omar, an apparent effort to tie her to the Minnesota fraud scandal that has revealed evidence that some members of the Somali community set up companies that billed state agencies for social services that were never provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative James R. Comer of Kentucky, the Republican chairman of the House Oversight Committee, has vowed to subpoena Ms. Omar’s husband. His venture capital firm made millions over the past few years, according to Ms. Omar’s financial disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No evidence has yet been produced showing that Ms. Omar was connected to the fraud scheme. A spokeswoman for Ms. Omar said her office had received no official inquiries from the Oversight Committee or the Justice Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Comer is still seeking to raise ethical questions about how Ms. Omar’s husband has been able to accumulate his wealth and he has promised an update on a potential investigation soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar has been under intense pressure since her community became a main target of the Trump administration’s crackdown on immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think we’re in for a lot of pain as Americans during this presidency,” she said in an interview with The New York Times in December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a desire to purify the country from any brown and Black people,” Ms. Omar said. “A lot of their policies and rhetoric seems to be rooted in white supremacy.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ilhan-omar-investigation-finances.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:47:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Embrace a Shutdown Fight They Wanted to Avoid</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/democrats-shutdown-ice-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26DC-ASSESS-top-pljf/26DC-ASSESS-top-pljf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after federal agents carrying out President Trump’s immigration crackdown shot an unarmed woman in her car and handcuffed a preschooler this month, a solid bloc of Democrats in the Senate had appeared ready to swallow their outrage and vote to fund the Homeland Security Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But following the shocking fatal shooting in Minneapolis over the weekend, Democrats have pivoted sharply, and are confident they are now on solid political ground as they draw a hard line against approving any money for the agency that has executed chaotic and violent operations across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the imminent prospect of a second crippling government shutdown in less than three months and the potential for a backlash, Democrats say they believe they have public opinion on their side as many Americans have recoiled from videos of the shooting of Alex Pretti and the earlier death of Renee Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are insisting that Republicans abandon efforts this week to include a spending bill for the Department of Homeland Security in a package of measures needed to keep federal agencies funded past Friday, at least until new controls on its agents are put in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also have little choice. Their political base has made it clear it would revolt if Democrats went ahead and passed the funding in the wake of the fatal shootings by government agents. Democrats do not want to risk such blowback from their strongest supporters as the midterms loom and the party sees a strong chance for gains in both the House and Senate. And they see the shootings as an abomination that demands a strong response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In my 15 years in the United States Senate, I have never seen our caucus more unified or fired up with outrage and energy to stop these absolutely abhorrent, brutal tactics that exemplify a police state, not the greatest democracy in the world,” Senator Richard Blumenthal, Democrat of Connecticut, said Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t supposed to be this way. Just days ago, Senate Democrats were clearing the way for the final spending bills of the fiscal year to be approved, a rare achievement in recent years. They lacked the appetite for another shutdown, particularly after they came out of last year’s believing they had put Republicans on defense over health care policy. It looked like the spending fights were about to be wrapped up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the shooting death of Mr. Pretti after he was apparently disarmed has upended the Capitol as Democrats dig in and urge Senator John Thune, the South Dakota Republican and majority leader, to break off the homeland security money from five other spending measures so most of the government could be funded past the Jan. 30 deadline despite the outcry over the shootings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Leader Thune puts those five bills on the floor this week, we can pass them right away,” Senator Chuck Schumer, the New York Democrat and minority leader, said in a statement on Monday. “If not, Republicans will again be responsible for another government shutdown.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the Democrats who broke with their party last fall to bring the last shutdown to an end have said that they would oppose the homeland security spending legislation without significant changes. They have made their position known to Republicans who might have seen them as a potential path around Mr. Schumer. Republicans would need at least seven Democrats to join them in advancing the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reform is urgently needed at the Department of Homeland Security, and their dishonest response to the death of a U.S. citizen only underscores that,” Senator Jeanne Shaheen of New Hampshire, one of the Democrats who brokered the deal to end last fall’s shutdown, said Monday. “I will vote against D.H.S.’s funding until additional reforms are in place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, Republicans insist they will push ahead with all six bills as a package, putting themselves on a collision course with Democrats and raising the risk that much of the government will shut down after midnight Friday. Senator Susan Collins, the Maine Republican who leads the Appropriations Committee, on Monday urged lawmakers to avoid that outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope we can come together in a constructive way to get this done and to ensure that we do not lurch into a dangerous and detrimental government shutdown,” she said during a brief Senate session Monday, even as she acknowledged that Mr. Pretti’s “tragic death” had increased scrutiny on the homeland security bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though some Republicans have expressed serious reservations about the events in Minneapolis, they will be reluctant to give in to Democratic demands since it could be interpreted as an admission that the Trump administration has acted improperly. The majority also never wants to be dictated to by the minority, whatever the circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Democrats have hardened their position, Senate Republicans have suggested a deal could be struck between the White House and Democrats, but Democratic officials said on Monday that no progress toward such an agreement had been made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Senate conservatives have made it clear they do not want Mr. Thune to grant any concessions to Democrats and that Republicans should be ready to make sure the blame for a shutdown falls on Democrats if they hold out against a package of spending bills they were about to approve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll oppose any effort to defund DHS,” Senator Mike Lee, Republican of Utah, wrote on X. “Every Republican should.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are incentives for Republicans to reach some accommodation with Democrats in addition to sparing the government another prolonged disruption. Fears are mounting within the party that the immigration crackdown in Minnesota and elsewhere is backfiring with voters, potentially neutralizing what Republicans see as one of their strongest political issues. Republican lawmakers in both the House and Senate also have invested significant time and effort in writing the spending bills that contain their priorities, and they don’t want to see them die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But working out any solution before Friday absent some significant retreat by either party will prove difficult. Even if there were an agreement, the House is out for the week and would need to approve any revisions in the package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats are still determining their precise demands for new restrictions on immigration agents. But possibilities they are discussing include requirements around judicial arrest warrants, elimination of quotas for arrests, visible identification on agents, an end to indiscriminate sweeps and a clear course of action to hold officers legally accountable for wrongdoing. Mr. Schumer described the framework to his colleagues on a Sunday conference call as “restrict, reform and restrain.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The showdown carries significant political risks for Democrats. They are threatening to again shut down a wide swath of the government and potentially disrupt services such as airport security and the Federal Emergency Management Agency as the nation deals with winter storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2018, Democrats forced the government to shut down as they tried to win legal protections for hundreds of thousands of so-called Dreamers, undocumented immigrants brought into the country as children. But they backed down just three days in when they determined that they lacked popular support for the tactic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though immigration policy is part of this dispute, Democrats see it as a dramatically different situation in which the public is squarely behind them. They say they are willing to take the heat to win new limits on the federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have no choice,” Mr. Blumenthal said, “given the strength of our determination to impose some restraints and reforms on an out-of-control agency.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/democrats-shutdown-ice-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:38:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alex Pretti Shooting in Minneapolis Went Wrong From the Start, Experts Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/alex-pretti-shooting-federal-agents-force.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25nat-minn-agents-bjhz/25nat-minn-agents-bjhz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In the moments leading up to the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis, federal agents had acted in ways that raised serious questions among policing experts.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/alex-pretti-shooting-federal-agents-force.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:43:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Killings in Minneapolis Invert Usual Dynamic Over Policing the Police</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-killings-federal-state-police.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-states01-photo-kjfl/26dc-states01-photo-kjfl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Protesters in Minneapolis gather near where Alex Pretti was killed. It is rare for state and local police to try to investigate federal law enforcement officials.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-killings-federal-state-police.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:24:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The G.O.P. tees up its spending package in Congress, leading to a shutdown showdown.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/26/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/gop-tees-up-spending-package-leading-to-shutdown-showdown</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-spend-Collins-gwhb/26minneapolis-spend-Collins-gwhb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Senator Susan Collins, Republican of Maine, and chairwoman of the Appropriations Committee, speaks to reporters, at the U.S. Capitol earlier this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/26/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/gop-tees-up-spending-package-leading-to-shutdown-showdown</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:34:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Border Patrol Official Gregory Bovino Is Set to Leave Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/greg-bovino-border-patrol-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-bovino-jzmt/26minneapolis-ice-bovino-jzmt-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
U.S. Border Patrol official Gregory Bovino and other U.S. Border Patrol agents earlier this month in Minneapolis, Minnesota.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/greg-bovino-border-patrol-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:55:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Investigation Into Shooting of Pretti Appears Limited</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/pretti-minneapolis-shooting-dhs-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-dhs-investigate-photo-cgwh/26dc-dhs-investigate-photo-cgwh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration appeared to acknowledge on Monday that its investigation into the killing of a Veterans Affairs nurse, Alex Pretti, by federal agents this weekend was limited to a “use of force” review meant to establish whether government employees had violated training standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a move, disclosed in court filings, would represent a much narrower inquiry focused on tactics and conduct than one that would examine whether federal agents should face criminal charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the administration’s efforts to block a judge from ordering it to preserve evidence, Mark Zito, who leads the Homeland Security Investigations office in St. Paul, Minnesota, provided the court with a sworn statement that noted that his agency, which belongs to the Department of Homeland Security, is investigating the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“H.S.I. is the lead investigatory entity reviewing the use-of-force encounter at issue in this case,” Mr. Zito’s declaration said. “H.S.I. agents tasked with this investigation are required to preserve all evidence collected, including physical evidence collected by other federal agencies, which are then properly transferred to the custody of H.S.I.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota state officials have sought a court order to preserve evidence for their own investigation of the killing of Mr. Pretti, who was repeatedly shot by Border Patrol agents on Saturday. The Trump administration is fighting such an order, claiming that it is already preserving the relevant evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critical terms in Mr. Zito’s statement are “use of force” and “reviewing.” Among federal law enforcement agencies, a use of force review is focused on whether law enforcement personnel followed agency rules and regulations and where and when to use force, and how much force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is distinct from a criminal investigation. F.B.I. agents could, for example, investigate to determine if Mr. Pretti’s civil rights were violated by federal agents acting under color of law, a crime that carries the possibility of a death sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. could also investigate whether Mr. Pretti assaulted or impeded a federal law enforcement officer, although there is limited practical use to such an investigation, given that Mr. Pretti is dead and cannot be charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no indication yet that the F.B.I. is doing either. Whatever the Trump administration investigates, their determinations may not be the last word, since there is no statute of limitations on murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An F.B.I. spokesman declined to comment. A D.H.S. spokeswoman did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Court filings suggest that, so far, the F.B.I.’s involvement is limited to assisting the Department of Homeland Security in its use-of-force review. F.B.I. agents arrived quickly on the scene of Mr. Pretti’s killing and secured his weapon and his phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. has since turned over Mr. Pretti’s phone to Immigration and Customs Enforcement, but not his gun, according to Mr. Zito’s sworn statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.B.I. has not altered or destroyed the collected evidence,” an unidentified F.B.I. agent declared in a sworn statement to the court. It also added that the evidence is secure in the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis office and that no one there “has conducted any analysis, examinations, or interpretations of the collected evidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement does not say whether other F.B.I. personnel, such as forensic experts at their lab in Quantico, Virginia, have examined any evidence, or a digital copy of Mr. Pretti’s phone data. “The F.B.I. will continue to preserve the collected evidence in accordance with the F.B.I.’s policies and procedures for evidence retention,” it noted. “In no event will any collected evidence be destroyed before resolution of this investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately, some of the Border Patrol agents at the scene of the killing were wearing body cameras, and that footage has been retained, according to court filings. Many Border Patrol agents do not wear body cameras, so it is unclear how much footage there may be, or how much can be gleaned from it.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/pretti-minneapolis-shooting-dhs-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:23:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Minneapolis Means for the Country and Its Politics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-protests-midterm-politics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/newsletter-1-gjqf/newsletter-1-gjqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young asylum-seeking family, terrified to go outside or even to look out of the window. Parents of elementary schoolers, struggling to explain to their children why their Latino classmates were staying home. Another fatal shooting of a U.S. citizen by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the painful and extraordinary scenes my colleagues in Minneapolis are documenting during the federal immigration crackdown there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a fast-moving, fluid and unpredictable situation, as the sudden move to reassign Greg Bovino shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But increasingly, one thing seems clear: The country is now paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moderate Democratic lawmakers have called for Kristi Noem, who leads the Department of Homeland Security, to step aside or to be impeached. At least some Republicans have broken with the Trump administration in expressing grave concerns or, in some cases, urging a full independent investigation into the fatal shooting on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Former Presidents Barack Obama and Bill Clinton, who rarely weigh in on the day-to-day moves of the Trump administration, cast the moment as an inflection point for the country, with core American values and freedoms under real threat. And over a weekend when many Americans were snowed in, plenty of people around the country who don’t usually post about politics took to social media to talk about Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sense of all of this, I turned to my colleague Charles Homans, who just wrote a deeply reported piece capturing how the Trump administration’s immigration operations are stoking fear and chaos across Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s well worth reading in full. In the meantime, here’s our conversation, edited and condensed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Glueck: In your story, you mentioned that many of the people pushing back aren’t what we might usually think of as activists. Who are they, and how would you describe them politically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Homans: I was struck by what a broad cross-section of Minneapolis liberals and progressives I saw participating in one way or another in the resistance to the federal deployment. The Twin Cities are overwhelmingly Democratic and have a real culture of political engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But participation is not the same as activism. Most of these people were not in the streets in 2020 after the murder of George Floyd, for instance, and a lot of them were very ambivalent about the aftermath of his killing in the city. What you are seeing now is a much broader kind of engagement, where even people who are not attending protests or following federal immigration agents with their phones are doing little things through their schools and churches, or with local businesses, to stand in the way of the federal operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: You also wrote about the parents — particularly those with kids attending schools with larger Latino populations, it sounded like — whose “latent politics had been supercharged by a very parental mix of fear and fury.” What does that look like in practice? Is this a newly engaged political demographic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: In Minneapolis, I think these are people who were pretty politically engaged to begin with. One big question I have, which is a good subject for further reporting, is whether this is the same farther out into the exurbs, where you start getting into constituencies who are more politically mixed and maybe less political in general, but confronting similar circumstances. The raids have happened there, too. They’ve just been less well-documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: Watching from New York, at least, the events in Minneapolis seem to have broken through with parts of the public in a way I’m not sure I’ve seen in the second Trump administration. Is that your sense, too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: It does feel that way. You always want to be careful about over-interpreting these moments in the moment itself. But even before the first fatal shooting by a federal agent in Minneapolis this month, polls had shown approval of Immigration and Customs Enforcement’s tactics really tanking, especially among independents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans have contradictory and ambivalent views about immigration, and what should be done to control it. The administration’s tactics and messaging have forced voters to think harder about that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly the biggest factor here is the video that Minnesotans have been gathering. There’s the footage of the shootings themselves, and the administration’s false or misleading accounts of what happened — which have been easy to see through even for people who are not especially engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: How does this moment in Minneapolis compare with the protests there after the murder of George Floyd?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: I asked a lot of people in Minneapolis about that, and the consensus, which I think is true, was that they are extremely different. The George Floyd protests, riots and ensuing debate about defunding or reorganizing the Minneapolis Police Department produced a deep division within the Twin Cities’ Democratic majority that was never really healed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But pretty much none of these people disagree about the federal deployment. And amid all of the fury and alarm of the present moment, there is a very palpable sense of relief among a lot of these people that they are on common ground, at least for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: You mentioned the Defund the Police movement, something Democratic leaders came to see as a huge political liability nationally. Is there any concern among Democrats you talked to that scenes of unrest, or pushes to abolish ICE, could backfire for them politically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: Minneapolis’s mayor, Jacob Frey, has clearly been trying to keep the Minneapolis Police Department out of the mix as much as possible. And for now, the balance of violence in the footage coming out of the city lies clearly on the side of the federal agents, who have shot and killed two people in the midst of what has been extremely angry but overwhelmingly nonviolent resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does seem that so far, this has kept a lot of the ghosts of 2020 at bay. What is clear on the street in Minneapolis is that this is really a tightrope walk, and I think it is much more so since the second fatal shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: Anything I didn’t ask you about on the political front that you think is important for people to understand about Minneapolis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: I wrote about this in another piece this month, but I do think that Minnesota’s particular political history, of which the state’s liberals are very proud, is very relevant to how Minneapolitans see what they are doing now, and the stakes of what they are doing. They see themselves as fighting for a civic ideal that is directly under attack by the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A curious demand stuck out in Attorney General Pam Bondi’s letter to Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota over the weekend laying out what must happen to restore “law and order” to the state: Hand over your voter rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Nick Corasaniti, who covers voting rights and elections, explains why the Trump administration is seeking voters’ private data from states across the country, and the concerns surrounding the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Number&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the percentage of American voters who believe a middle-class lifestyle is out of reach for most people, a New York Times/Siena poll found. It reflects the nation’s pessimistic mood as another midterm election year kicks off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;QUOTE OF THE DAy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s Oscar Hagelsieb, a retired immigration officer and special agent. He voted three times for President Trump but is now feeling anger and despair about the administration’s deployment of his former agency: “It’s completely unfair to the agents who have been put in this position.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ONE LAST THING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For newly elected mayors, major weather events can pose tough tests of leadership. So far, my colleagues Sally Goldenberg and Dana Rubinstein write, Mayor Zohran Mamdani of New York City has seemed to clear early hurdles with his handling of the snowstorm this weekend. But Gov. Kathy Hochul — his political pal, at least for now — had some feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thanks for helping out our neighbors,” she wrote on social media in response to a video Mamdani shared that showed him trying to help a car stuck in the snow. “But put on a hat!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Homans and Taylor Robinson contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-protests-midterm-politics.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:08:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Year Past a Fatal Crash, Concerns About Safety at Reagan Airport Continue</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/reagan-national-airport-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/dc-airspace-promo-hbwv/dc-airspace-promo-hbwv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One year after two seemingly routine flights above Washington, D.C., ended in a deadly midair collision, some efforts to make the airspace significantly safer have faltered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the crash, the Federal Aviation Administration, which controls the airspace, has asked airlines to modify their schedules to reduce the number of flights per hour at Ronald Reagan National Airport until the facility can handle a more normal tempo. The agency has also closed the air route that an Army helicopter was traversing when it collided with a passenger jet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But control tower staffing is not much higher than it was at the time of the crash, according to F.A.A. figures. And morale within the tower remains low, according to two people who have spent time there recently, raising concerns about readiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other steps that crash victims’ families had hoped would help protect fliers in the Washington skies seem to be languishing amid congressional inaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An air safety bill that recently passed the Senate faces opposition in the House, threatening its viability. And despite years of concerns by the F.A.A. and some lawmakers about congestion in the airspace around National Airport, there has been no meaningful discussion of permanently removing flight routes in and out of the airport to reduce the load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision occurred Jan. 29, 2025, when an Army Black Hawk flew into American Airlines Flight 5342, which was on its way to land at National Airport from Wichita, Kan. Everyone aboard both aircraft died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, the U.S. government admitted liability for the collision. As part of a civil suit brought by the family of one of the victims, the Justice Department said that the Army pilots flying a Black Hawk helicopter that night failed to maintain separation from the jet. Officials also acknowledged that the controller did not provide proper instructions, but denied that the lapse was the cause of the crash for the purpose of monetary damages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An F.A.A. spokeswoman, Hannah Walden, said that the agency has taken steps to increase safety since the tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Sean Duffy was confirmed as transportation secretary, “he and the F.A.A. have taken decisive steps to correct past failures, strengthen accountability, and modernize” the national airspace, Ms. Walden said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are acting proactively to mitigate risks,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, the National Transportation Safety Board, the independent government agency that has been investigating the crash, will share its findings on the cause of the collision and the circumstances around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. will also share recommendations for ways to improve safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The safety board fast-tracked its report to help bring closure to a frightening and impactful aviation crash, the nation’s deadliest in 24 years. The Army said it will work with the board to support “lasting improvements” in aviation safety, and the F.A.A. said it will “diligently consider” the board’s additional advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to some who lost loved ones in the crash, the fixes that have been made since last January have been too gradual, and too reactive, to be satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doug Lane, a Barrington, R.I., man who lost his wife, Christine, and 16-year-old son, Spencer, in the plane crash, said in an interview that, in his view, the F.A.A. has not been proactive about its own role as a safety agent. It instead looks to Congress for direction, he said, when crises happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m kind of willing to forgive for things that happened before Jan. 29, 2025,” he said. “But I think the way that people react after that means a lot to me. And I’ve really gotten the sense that they have made no effort to learn from this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Airport tower had been a troubled workplace before the crash, struggling with chronic understaffing and safety lapses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, conditions have improved at the tower, said two people who have spent time there recently who were not authorized to speak publicly, but morale has still not bounced back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Walden said the F.A.A. conducts “regular wellness checks” at the facility to talk to the team there and listen to “any concerns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, the tower employs 22 of the 30 controllers it is approved for, according to the F.A.A., an improvement over the 19 controllers it had at the time of the collision, but not by much. The F.A.A. noted that controllers there are currently working with eight trainees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before staffing got to its current levels, there was a wave of departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some controllers who were working on Jan. 29 went on leave immediately, people who were familiar with the matter told The New York Times at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times would like to hear about your experience as a federal worker under the second Trump administration. We may reach out about your submission, but we will not publish any part of your response without contacting you first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others, including senior managers, were relocated to different facilities in the aftermath of the crash, N.T.S.B. hearings revealed. The senior-most position in the tower, air traffic manager, has been occupied by three people within the past year. Still other management positions have gone unfilled, at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Jarvis, an F.A.A. contractor who worked in the tower for years until his retirement in October, said he was bothered by the fact that certain management jobs had remained vacant in recent years and that others were occupied by people who had no knowledge of Washington’s skies, a sign that the agency has not always prioritized the facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.A.A. and the public consider D.C.A. a gem,” said Mr. Jarvis, using a shorthand for the D.C. airport. “We have not treated it like a gem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, some controllers struggled psychologically in the aftermath of the crash, according to N.T.S.B. officials and others who spent time in the tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the weeks and months after Jan. 29, N.T.S.B. investigators who were interviewing controllers sometimes found them highly distressed, said Jennifer Homendy, the N.T.S.B. chair. Some cried during conversations. One was spotted sleeping at their workstation, she said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About two months after the crash, two investigators who had gone to the tower to conduct additional interviews were made aware of an altercation that had just occurred: one controller had punched another controller after a verbal argument that had grown heated, Ms. Homendy said. The aggressor was arrested by airport police, according to a Virginia court summons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By that point, “our air traffic control team was really concerned about the well-being of the controllers in the tower,” Ms. Homendy said. She called the acting administrator at the F.A.A. as well as the president of the National Air Traffic Controllers Association and contacts on Capitol Hill to ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. declined to comment on the altercation or the call from Ms. Homendy. The agency noted that it has brought in four controllers from other sites to augment staffing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan National Airport has in some ways been a victim of its own popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decades ago, it was established as the short-haul complement to the nearby Dulles International Airport, whose sprawling footprint and longer runways could more easily accommodate longer-haul flights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But National Airport’s convenient location made it irresistible to many Washingtonians, including elected officials, who travel in and out often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, a series of congressional waivers have allowed airlines to add new and longer routes to the airport’s roster, adding to controller workload and to airspace congestion. In 2024, five new round-trip routes were added despite F.A.A. concerns about the strains those flights could add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last January’s midair collision came on the heels of a banner year for travel. National Airport set a record for the number of commercial passengers handled. The tower’s controllers had also been busy handling frequent military, medical evacuation and local law enforcement helicopters that passed through, often on very short notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the crash, the F.A.A. initially reduced the number of hourly flights into National Airport from 36 to 26, but the number is now back up to 30. It also reduced helicopter traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figures kept by the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority, which operates National Airport and Dulles, show that between January and October of 2024, 21.9 million passengers traveled through National Airport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the same period in 2025, the figure was 20.9 million, a 4.6 percent drop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, family members of the crash victims say they know of no significant efforts on Capitol Hill to permanently reduce flights, even though many believe that airport congestion remains a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some lawmakers agree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I remain extremely concerned by the amount of air traffic in and out of D.C.A.,” said Senator Tim Kaine, the Virginia Democrat, in an emailed statement. “This is some of the most complex and crowded airspace in the country, and every additional flight that is crammed into it stretches an already overburdened runway and air traffic control work force.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kaine said he wants to work on removing routes from National Airport as soon as the N.T.S.B. and Army release their investigative findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some victims’ families and N.T.S.B. officials say one of the most frustrating policy debates since the crash has been the back-and-forth over a cockpit system that allows aircraft to broadcast their locations and whether those should be mandatory to be used on military training flights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That broadcasting system, which is a fixture on all commercial planes and the majority of military helicopters, provides real-time information to other pilots and controllers on an aircraft’s location in the skies, allowing others to track and avoid hitting it. But the Army, citing the need for confidentiality in case it is flying to secure locations, has long had a waiver on the system’s use, including for training flights, the type of flight that was occurring on Jan. 29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of the crash, the F.A.A. ruled that the Army must use the system, even for training flights. But the mandate was unwound late last year in the annual defense spending bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Senate last month passed an aviation safety bill that would revert to requiring the broadcasting system be turned on, along with a passel of other new aviation-safety measures that would secure skies in Washington and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Representative Sam Graves, the Missouri Republican who leads the House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee, has called the bill “emotional” and has said he won’t support it as written, effectively relegating it to a back burner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, he said in a statement to The Times that he was waiting to see the N.T.S.B. findings before “considering the best way forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.T.S.B. officials and relatives of people who died in the collision have bemoaned the setbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a text to The Times, Sheri Lilley, the stepmother of Sam Lilley, the first officer of the American Airlines flight, noted that the N.T.S.B. began recommending the broadcast system be activated 17 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If those recommendations had been heeded at that time, this tragedy would not have happened,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julie Tate, Kitty Bennett and Minho Kim contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/reagan-national-airport-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:33:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>F.A.A. Rolls Out Agency Overhaul for Improving Air Safety</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/faa-overhaul-safety-modernization.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-faa-cjtp/26dc-faa-cjtp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Aviation Administration is overhauling its internal structure to modernize and increase safety, its leaders announced on Monday, in a shake-up intended to make the agency more responsive at a time of heightened focus on improving the security of air travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A.’s new organizational chart will concentrate safety oversight functions in a new, single office instead of leaving them spread among several divisions. The agency will also open an airspace modernization office to support its efforts toward a new air traffic control system, and create a division focused solely on drones, air taxis and other advanced aircraft. The new structure also consolidates many of the agency’s administrative functions, including finance, human resources and information technology, in a single office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy and the F.A.A. administrator, Bryan Bedford, announced the new structure on Monday, just ahead of the first anniversary of a midair collision outside Ronald Reagan National Airport that killed 67 people and prompted a public outcry for improved aviation safety. Many of the changes were mandated by Congress in 2024, as part of a bill authorizing the F.A.A.’s activities for the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With these critical organizational changes, the F.A.A. can streamline the bureaucracy, encourage innovation and deliver a new air traffic control system,” Mr. Duffy said in a statement, adding that safety would be enhanced along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new plan also calls for some F.A.A. offices, including the new one responsible for drones and other advanced aviation technologies, answering to the agency’s deputy administrator, Chris Rocheleau, instead of directly to Mr. Bedford. Mr. Duffy’s and Mr. Bedford’s announcement said that no layoffs were expected as part of the restructuring.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/faa-overhaul-safety-modernization.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:31:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shootings Pose a Hard Question for the Right: Who’s a Conservative, Really?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-shooting-trump-ice-gop.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-Reversal-ftcw/26minneapolis-ice-Reversal-ftcw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Randy Fine, a hard-right Republican from Florida, has regularly warned about the perils of federal government overreach during his decade-long career in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a state legislator, he described federal Covid-19 vaccination mandates as “tyrannical.” As a member of Congress, he supported the elimination of the Department of Education, stating, “Federal bureaucrats shouldn’t dictate how our kids are taught.” In a 2022 social media post, Mr. Fine, memorably and menacingly, addressed President Joseph R. Biden Jr. over gun control, telling him, “try to take our guns and you’ll learn why the Second Amendment was written in the first place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this weekend, Mr. Fine took to X.com to voice his approval that federal immigration officers in Minneapolis had killed Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old nurse whose filming of immigration officers on Saturday morning turned into a confrontation. The officers shot Mr. Pretti at least 10 times after one of them had removed a holstered gun that he was legally authorized to carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An armed seditionist attacked federal law enforcement today as they were rounding up foreign invaders in Minneapolis,” Mr. Fine wrote on Saturday, without evidence that Mr. Pretti had been there to attack anyone. “The insurrectionist was put down. Well done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American conservatives have a long history of supporting gun rights and states’ rights, as well as calling for firm restraint on the federal government. And they have criticized the excessive use of federal power in a number of bloody confrontations with recalcitrant citizens, including a white separatist family in Ruby Ridge, Idaho, in 1992, and the Branch Davidians cult the following year in Waco, Texas, both by agents from the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the case of the Minneapolis deployment, the Trump administration and some allies like Mr. Fine have taken positions that seem to contradict some of the bedrock principles of conservatism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deployment, called Operation Metro Surge, would seem like the definition of big-government action. Gov. Tim Walz and Mayor Jacob Frey, both Democrats, vehemently oppose federal intervention, as do many residents of largely liberal Minneapolis. Agents, wearing masks to hide their identities, have forced their way into homes without warrants. They have detained citizens and legal immigrants. And then, there are the killings of Mr. Pretti and Renee Good, the mother of three shot on Jan. 7 while driving her S.U.V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, many Republicans see Mr. Trump’s effort as a fundamentally conservative strategy — an effort to to rid the United States of all illegal immigrants, which they say upholds the rule of law and maintains national sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incongruity has set off a roiling series of debates about the very nature of conservatism, often within the sphere of conservatism itself, even as Mr. Trump softened his position on Monday and said that he was sending Tom Homan, his border czar, to Minneapolis and that Mr. Homan would work more closely with local officials. Mayor Frey said in a statement late Monday that some federal agents would leave the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a phone interview on Monday, Representative Fine argued that there was no disconnect between his support for Operation Metro Surge and his broader belief that the federal government should be reined in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not at all,” he said. “The most fundamental responsibility of the federal government is to secure the border and to protect Americans. ICE is rounding up foreign invaders who have been instructed to leave the country and have refused.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other Republicans are voicing concerns. Former Vice President Mike Pence wrote on social media on Monday that the images of the shooting of Mr. Pretti were “deeply troubling,” adding that “a full and transparent investigation of this officer involved shooting must take place immediately.” Senators Ted Cruz, of Texas, and Jerry Moran, of Kansas, also called for an investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our Constitution provides citizens protection from the government,” Mr. Moran wrote. “We have a right to free speech, to peaceably assemble and to bear arms. We also expect government to protect us from lawless behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview this week, Erick Erickson, the conservative pundit and radio host from Georgia, said he supports the administration’s mass deportation goals. But he said he was “uncomfortable” with the recently disclosed guidance drafted by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement officials stating that deportation officers are allowed to enter homes to arrest people without judicial warrants. And he described Mr. Trump’s recent threat to invoke the Insurrection Act and send troops to Minnesota as “overkill” and “too provocative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Erickson said that the current disagreements over the Minnesota surge are part of a broader debate about shifting definitions of conservatism in the Trump era, as the president has embraced once-taboo ideas like the imposition of tariffs and government investment in private companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Erickson was among a number of conservatives who took issue over the weekend with assertions by Trump officials and allies who criticized Mr. Pretti for bringing a gun to a protest. Among them was Scott Bessent, the Treasury secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been to a protest,” Mr. Bessent said in an interview with ABC’s Jonathan Karl. “Guess what? I didn’t bring a gun. I brought a billboard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bessent is wrong,” Mr. Erickson wrote on X.com “I know plenty of people who participate in political events, including protests, and have their guns. It is their right. While we can say the man should not have gotten in an altercation with agents, merely exercising his 2A right with his 1A right is irrelevant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Stitt, the Republican governor of Oklahoma and the chair of the National Governors Association, told CNN on Sunday that while Mr. Trump’s promise to close the border was popular, the killings of Mr. Pretti and Ms. Good were “causing deep concerns over federal tactics and accountability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also suggested that the federal response was violating the principle that the political will of states should not be overrun by an overzealous federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We believe in federalism and state rights,” Mr. Still said. “And nobody likes feds coming into their state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s threat to invoke the Insurrection Act earlier this month has also become a delicate issue among Republicans, especially those vying for their party’s nomination in the upcoming Minnesota governor’s race. Earlier this month, The Minnesota Star Tribune reported that “several” G.O.P. candidates “would not explicitly say whether they would support President Donald Trump deploying the military to Minnesota to tamp down protests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One exception was Mike Lindell, the pro-Trump conspiracy theorist, MyPillow chief executive and Minnesota native. He said he would support “whatever it takes” to stop what he considered to be unlawful protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side was Chris Madel, a Minneapolis lawyer who said he would not support invocation of the Insurrection Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Madel dropped out of the governor’s race on Monday and leveled harsh words against some fellow Republicans. “I cannot support the national Republicans stated retribution on the citizens of our state, nor can I count myself a member of a party that would do so,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most pointed criticism of the surge has, perhaps unsurprisingly, come from libertarians, many of whom have repeatedly chafed at Trump policies not deemed sufficiently in line with their small-government ethos. Walter Olson, a senior fellow at the Cato Institute, the libertarian think tank, has noted that protesters in Minnesota have been “repeatedly attacked” while filming or nonviolently protesting the enforcement actions, “in what looks very much like a practice that is being tolerated by policy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even among libertarians, there is disagreement. Angela McArdle, a former chair of the Libertarian Party, argued this weekend that the nation was in crisis mode and that now was not a time for libertarians to stick so strictly to their ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The threat of mass migration is civilizational,” Ms. McArdle wrote on X on Sunday, adding: “It sucks that ICE shoots people sometimes. If we don’t deport illegal aliens and stop Democrat fraud, we will be Canada in less than 10 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-shooting-trump-ice-gop.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:07:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Takes Another Stake in Rare Earth Sector</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-rare-earth-howard-lutnick.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-invest-lzpf/26dc-trump-invest-lzpf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration announced on Monday that it had agreed to extend up to $277 million in direct funding and up to $1.3 billion in loans to USA Rare Earth Inc., a mining and manufacturing group, to help develop its supply chain for rare earth metals and magnets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal adds to the administration’s growing portfolio of equity stakes in private companies, and it would help expand domestic production of a critical input for cars, robots, semiconductors, drones and other products. China, which dominates the production of rare earth minerals and magnets, began clamping down on its export last year, and companies have struggled to find other sources of supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commerce Department, which arranged the financing through a semiconductor investment program set up during the Biden administration, said it had signed a nonbinding letter of intent to provide the funding, subject to further due diligence and approvals. The deal will give the Commerce Department approximately 16 million shares in the company, as well as a warrant to acquire another 17.6 million shares, the department said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Lutnick, the secretary of commerce, said in a statement that the company’s project was essential to “restoring U.S. critical mineral independence.” The investment “ensures our supply chains are resilient and no longer reliant on foreign nations,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the company also announced that it had raised $1.5 billion through a consortium of private investors. For that transaction, Cantor Fitzgerald, a Wall Street firm formerly headed by Mr. Lutnick, acted as the lead placement agent, the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overlap between the Trump administration and Cantor Fitzgerald has recently been under scrutiny by Democratic lawmakers and others, after revelations by The New York Times that the Wall Street firm profited off several projects that Mr. Lutnick promoted in his official role as commerce secretary. Mr. Lutnick has divested from Cantor Fitzgerald, but the firm is now led by two of his sons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Weisman, the co-president of Public Citizen, a government ethics watchdog group that has been critical of the Trump administration, described the ties as concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The fact that the deal is brokered by the Wall Street firm formerly run by the Commerce Secretary — and now headed by his sons — is reason to worry that the public interest is being subordinated, yet again, to the profit seeking of Trump cronies,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A commerce department official said that the CHIPS office worked directly with USA Rare Earth on the government deal, with no involvement from Cantor Fitzgerald. Cantor Fitzgerald declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has now announced deals to take equity stakes in at least 10 private companies, in an unusual strategy for a Republican administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the deals involve the metals and mining sector, which the government has been trying to build up to ensure strategic independence from China. But the administration has also taken stake, or the option to acquire it, in the chipmaker Intel, the nuclear firm Westinghouse and U.S. Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While critics say the practice risks distorting the private market, the Trump administration has argued that the deals give American taxpayers more benefits when companies succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funding announced on Monday is expected to support two projects, a mine anticipated to begin commercial production in Texas in 2028, and a manufacturing project in Oklahoma. USA Rare Earths would be the only company in the United States that would mine minerals containing rare earths, extract rare earth oxides, convert them to metals and turn that into the feedstock for magnets, the Commerce Department said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-rare-earth-howard-lutnick.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:26:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chris Madel Ends Run for Minnesota Governor, Citing Immigration Crackdown</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/chris-madel-minnesota-governor-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-Madel-vwgl-copy/26minneapolis-Madel-vwgl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Chris Madel said the immigration crackdown in Minneapolis “has departed so far from the stated goals that it is simply a disaster.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/chris-madel-minnesota-governor-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:28:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Holds 2-Hour Meeting With Noem Amid Backlash to Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, at the White House earlier this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 19:30:02 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>