<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Congress Is Spurning Many of Trump’s Proposed Spending Cuts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/politics/congress-trump-spending-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/14dc-spend-top-jwlk/14dc-spend-top-jwlk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congress is quietly rejecting almost all of the deepest cuts to federal programs that President Trump requested for this year, turning back his efforts to slash funding for foreign aid, global health programs, scientific research, the arts and more in a bipartisan repudiation of his spending plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest rejection of his budget blueprint came on Wednesday, after the House voted 341 to 79 to pass a pair of bills to fund the State and Treasury Departments, as well as other foreign aid programs, providing money for agencies that Mr. Trump had proposed eliminating entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All told, while lawmakers have agreed to make modest trims to a number of programs that Mr. Trump has wanted to eviscerate — and to zero out some others — the spending bills that they are now moving through Congress reflect the political reality that any funding measure must be bipartisan in order to avoid a Democratic filibuster in the Senate and become law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These are bills that reject the devastating cuts Trump demanded in his deeply unserious budget he sent to Congress about a year ago,” said Senator Patty Murray of Washington, the top Democrat on the Appropriations Committee. “When just about every secretary came before our Appropriations Committee to advocate for those Trump funding cuts, I made clear to them I planned to rip up his budget and write a new one — and that is exactly what we are doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a striking pivot just months after the partisan clash last fall that led to the longest government shutdown in history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers are now in the process of negotiating and approving a series of spending bills before a Jan. 30 shutdown deadline. Appropriators in both the House and the Senate have come to bipartisan agreements on eight of the 12 bills that fund the government. The Senate was racing to clear three measures that passed the House last week with money for the Commerce and Justice Departments, as well as for environmental programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even some programs that have long been despised by conservatives are instead set to sustain only modest cuts, including Voice of America, the National Endowment for Democracy and the National Endowment for the Arts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The legislation to fund the State Department and other foreign assistance programs alone provides over $19 billion more than Mr. Trump’s request — though it would constitute a cut of $9 billion below current levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voice of America, the federal news network the Trump administration has sought to dismantle, is set to receive about $653 million, half a billion more than what Mr. Trump requested to “support the orderly shutdown” of the agency. Lawmakers had previously provided $867 million to the broadcaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a long history of international aid being viewed as an effective tool on a bipartisan basis, and I think that this bill re-establishes that bipartisan foundation,” said Senator Brian Schatz of Hawaii, the top Democrat on the subcommittee overseeing funding for the State Department and foreign aid programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;House and Senate negotiators also rejected a proposal advanced by the White House to cancel $16.5 billion in previously approved funding for the Internal Revenue Service that Democrats included in 2022 in their sprawling climate and domestic policy law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they endorsed keeping scientific funding levels at the National Science Foundation and at NASA essentially flat, making only slight trims rather than the major cuts the White House had proposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways, the spending bills confirm the worst fears of conservatives on Capitol Hill, who have worried that even with a Republican governing trifecta, they would be unable to enact the kind of major spending cuts they have long agitated for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those lawmakers had argued that the unilateral actions taken by the Department of Government Efficiency early last year to cancel congressionally appropriated programs were necessary to bypass the bipartisan agreements that typically fuel spending legislation and bring about the steep reductions to programs Republicans have long targeted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Endowment for Democracy, said Representative Eric Burlison, Republican of Missouri, is “a program that Elon Musk, while leading DOGE, said publicly was a scam; that it was rife with corruption and an evil organization that should be dissolved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump and his administration attempted to do that, and yet here we are trying to fund it,” Mr. Burlison said. The House rejected an amendment to eliminate funding for the nonprofit in a 291-to-127 vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Democrats also are unhappy with the emerging spending package, believing that their party should use the leverage it has in the appropriations process to try to rein in U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement and the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown. That could still emerge as a sticking point to a final agreement; the bill to fund the Department of Homeland Security is among the toughest to negotiate and has yet to be agreed upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But overall, the bipartisan consensus around the spending measures is strong. Republican leaders who helped negotiate them championed the trims in the spending bills, arguing that the overall reduction in funding compared with last year’s levels constituted a major win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they noted that the bills represented a return to the practice of writing and passing individual spending bills, rather than lumping all 12 together into a behemoth package, or enacting an emergency stopgap measure to keep funding flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Difficulty is what separates serious legislating from political convenience,” said Representative Tom Cole, Republican of Oklahoma and the chairman of the Appropriations Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the administration ultimately spends the money that lawmakers appropriate is still an unanswered question. Russell T. Vought, the White House budget director, has made clear that he believes the president has the authority to disregard congressional directives in order to spend less money than lawmakers approved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And members of Congress omitted language they had considered including in the legislation aimed at limiting Mr. Trump’s ability to circumvent them. For instance, lawmakers ultimately jettisoned language that senators had tucked into the bill to fund the Commerce and Justice Departments that would have required administration officials to notify lawmakers 30 days before canceling federal contracts or enacting mass layoffs of federal employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That provision also would have restricted agencies’ ability to use funds approved for one purpose for another, a maneuver known as “reprogramming.” Some Democrats argued such measures were futile and potentially unnecessary since Mr. Trump would be less likely to unilaterally cancel spending approved by Republicans that he had signed into law himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they’re going to violate the underlying statute, then passing a new statute that says they have to abide by the old one is silliness,” Mr. Schatz said. “I also think that it’s a little harder for them to send rescissions packages, and to do great violence to the agencies, if this is a bill passed by Republicans in Congress and signed by the Republican president.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/politics/congress-trump-spending-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:37:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>3 More Lawmakers in Video Say Federal Prosecutors Are Investigating Them</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/politics/crow-goodlander-houlahan-trump-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/14dc-video-mlwg/14dc-video-mlwg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three more Democratic lawmakers said on Wednesday that they were being investigated for their participation in a video urging military service members to resist illegal orders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representatives Jason Crow of Colorado, Maggie Goodlander of New Hampshire and Chrissy Houlahan of Pennsylvania all reported that they had received inquiries from Jeanine Pirro, the U.S. attorney for the District of Columbia and a longtime ally of President Trump, requesting an interview with them or their private counsel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disclosures follow a similar one this week by Senator Elissa Slotkin of Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and other administration officials have described the video, which restates a fundamental principle of military law, as “seditious.” But it is unclear what possible crime the lawmakers are believed to have committed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigations are the latest escalation in a campaign by Mr. Trump and his allies to exact retribution on those he views as enemies. They also add to a growing list of high-profile targets who have clashed with Mr. Trump and are now being investigated by Ms. Pirro’s office, including the Federal Reserve chair, Jerome H. Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for Ms. Pirro’s office on Wednesday declined to confirm or deny any investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Slotkin, who organized the video, served three tours in Iraq with the C.I.A. The other five members who appeared in the video, which was released in November, all served in the U.S. military. All six lawmakers also said they had received an inquiry from the F.B.I.’s counterterrorism division late last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Crow, who served as an Army Ranger and led troops in combat, accused Mr. Trump in a video post to social media of “using his political cronies in the Department of Justice to continue to threaten and intimidate us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Houlahan, an Air Force veteran, said on social media that she and her colleagues were being targeted because they had said something that Mr. Trump and Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth “didn’t want anyone to hear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This investigation is ridiculous on any day but especially so on a day the President is considering launching airstrikes against Iran in retaliation for their crack down on free speech,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Goodlander, in a social media post, called the Trump administration’s response “sad and telling.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These threats will not deter, distract, intimidate, or silence me,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a video released on Wednesday, Ms. Slotkin disparaged the investigation and Mr. Trump’s attacks on her and her colleagues as “legal intimidation and physical intimidation meant to get you to shut up.” But she vowed that they would not work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right now, speaking out against the abuse of power is the most patriotic thing we can do,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Mr. Hegseth announced that the military had started administrative actions against Senator Mark Kelly, Democrat of Arizona and a retired Navy captain, who also participated in the video. The proceedings could result in a reduction in his rank and military pension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a retired naval officer, Mr. Kelly, who flew 39 combat missions as a naval aviator and four spaceflights as an astronaut, is subject to the Uniform Code of Military Justice and therefore can be recalled to active duty and disciplined. The other Democratic lawmakers in the video did not serve long enough to retire and do not receive a pension or fall under military law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a lawsuit filed on Monday, Mr. Kelly called the Pentagon’s efforts to punish him “unlawful and unconstitutional” and asked a federal judge to block them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Megan Mineiro and Devlin Barrett contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/politics/crow-goodlander-houlahan-trump-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 04:16:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Agent Shoots Man in Minneapolis, Prompting Tense Protests</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/minneapolis-federal-agent-shooting-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/14nat-shooting-promo-2-qvph/14nat-shooting-promo-2-qvph-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal agent shot and injured a man in Minneapolis on Wednesday evening, federal officials said, an incident that touched off hours of clashes between protesters and law enforcement officers and that came just one week after an immigration agent killed a woman in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricia McLaughlin, a spokeswoman for the Department of Homeland Security, said in a statement that federal agents were trying to arrest a man from Venezuela who was in the country illegally in a “targeted traffic stop” at around 6:50 p.m. She said that he fled from agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the officer caught up to him, Ms. McLaughlin said he “began to resist and violently assault the officer.” She said two people came out of a nearby building and, along with the man being sought, attacked the officer with a snow shovel and a broom handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The officer feared for his life and fired shots, striking the man whom agents were seeking in the leg, Ms. McLaughlin said. The agent and the man who was shot were in the hospital, she added, and the other two people she accused of attacking the agent were in custody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The federal government’s narrative could not immediately be verified. City officials said the person who was shot had “apparent non-life-threatening injuries.” The agent’s condition was not immediately clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis residents have protested repeatedly in the week since an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent fatally shot an American woman, Renee Nicole Good, on the south side of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City officials said the latest shooting occurred on the city’s north side, in the 600 block of 24th Avenue North. At a news conference, Brian O’Hara, the city’s police chief, said his understanding was that a 911 call appeared to have been made from a house. He said the caller reported that the man was running from immigration agents and was driving toward the residence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neighbors said they saw federal agents ordering people inside the house to come out with their hands up, and that several people, including children, walked out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Jacob Frey said after the shooting that “there’s still a lot that we don’t know” but that “this is not sustainable.” He reiterated his call for ICE to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is an impossible situation that our city is presently being put in,” Mr. Frey said. “And at the same time, we are trying to find a way forward to keep people safe, to protect our neighbors, to maintain order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As word of the latest shooting spread, at least 200 protesters gathered near the apparent scene on Wednesday night. A group of them yelled at Minneapolis police officers who had blocked the street to traffic, telling the local officers that the federal agents should be arrested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief O’Hara said the crowd at the scene was “engaging in unlawful acts.” He and the mayor urged people to leave the area near the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They have thrown fireworks at police officers and at multiple times, gas has been deployed,” Chief O’Hara said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several heavily armed Border Patrol agents arrived in a large, military-style vehicle outside of the crime scene tape. Protesters swarmed the vehicle and yelled and threw snowballs at agents who had gotten out. The agents eventually retreated, and as they left, they fired at least two canisters of gas that made a loud bang and made it difficult for some to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few minutes later, at least two ICE agents arrived in an unmarked S.U.V. and sprayed chemical agents in the faces of protesters who approached them, causing one protester to say that he could not see. At one point, a protester fired several fireworks toward retreating ICE agents and their cars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chemical agents were used against protesters, and two people were detained and later released. Protesters damaged an unmarked vehicle with police lights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Minneapolis police officer who identified himself as a supervisor to several protesters told them he did not know exactly what happened. “It’s not like they’re talking to us,” he said, referring to the federal agents on scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal Bureau of Prisons officers were seen carrying out crowd-control duties alongside state troopers. Chief O’Hara said he had asked the Minnesota Bureau of Criminal Apprehension to investigate the shooting, and its agents were also at the scene. That agency was excluded from the F.B.I. inquiry into Ms. Good’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 3,000 federal immigration agents have flooded the Minneapolis area in recent weeks, angering residents and local officials. The Trump administration has defended the deployment as necessary to cracking down on illegal immigration and rooting out fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly before the latest shooting was reported on Wednesday night, Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota gave a speech that called on the Trump administration to “end this occupation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, referred to a “Minnesota insurrection” in a social media post after the shooting and accused Mr. Walz and Mr. Frey, both Democrats, of making the situation worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liish Kozlowski, a Democratic state representative, said that Minnesotans should be “enraged” by the report of another ICE-related shooting, adding that “we’ve been raising alarms that they are not here for public safety or for fraud or for the well-being of anybody, but to hunt and harm us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julie Bosman, Orlando Mayorquín and Pooja Salhotra contributed reporting. Georgia Gee contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/14/us/minneapolis-federal-agent-shooting-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:55:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Universities Surge in Global Rankings as U.S. Schools Slip</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/harvard-global-ranking-chinese-universities-trump-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/02/multimedia/00nat-harvard-global-02-ghkt/00nat-harvard-global-02-ghkt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until recently, Harvard was the most productive research university in the world, according to a global ranking that looks at academic publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That position may be teetering, the most recent evidence of a troubling trend for American academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard recently dropped to No. 3 on the ranking. The schools racing up the list are not Harvard’s American peers, but Chinese universities that have been steadily climbing in rankings that emphasize the volume and quality of research they produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reordering comes as the Trump administration has been slashing research funding to American schools that depend heavily on the federal government to pay for scientific endeavors. President Trump’s policies did not start the American universities’ relative decline, which began years ago, but they could accelerate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a big shift coming, a bit of a new world order in global dominance of higher education and research,” said Phil Baty, chief global affairs officer for Times Higher Education, a British organization unconnected to The New York Times that produces one of the better-known world rankings of universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educators and experts say the shift is a problem not just for American universities, but also for the nation as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a risk of the trend continuing, and potential decline,” Mr. Baty said. “I use the word ‘decline’ very carefully. It’s not as if U.S. schools are getting demonstrably worse, it’s just the global competition: Other nations are making more rapid progress.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look back to the early 2000s, and a global university ranking based on scientific output, such as published journal articles, would be very different. Seven American schools would be among the top 10, led by Harvard University at No. 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one Chinese school, Zhejiang University, would even make the top 25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Zhejiang is ranked first on that list, the Leiden Rankings, from the Centre for Science and Technology Studies at Leiden University in the Netherlands. Seven other Chinese schools are in the top 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard produces significantly more research now than it did two decades ago, but it has nonetheless fallen to third. And it is the only American university still near the top of the list. Harvard is still first in the Leiden rankings for highly-cited scientific publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue at top American universities is not falling production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six prominent American schools that would have been in the top 10 in the first decade of the 2000s — the University of Michigan, the University of California, Los Angeles, Johns Hopkins, the University of Washington-Seattle, the University of Pennsylvania, and Stanford University — are producing more research than they did two decades ago, according to the Leiden tallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But production by the Chinese schools has risen far more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Mark Neijssel, director of services for the Centre for Science and Technology Studies, the Leiden rankings take into account papers and citations contained in the Web of Science, a database set of academic publications which is owned by Clarivate, a data and analytics company. Thousands of academic journals are represented in the databases, many of which are highly specialized, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global university rankings generally have not attracted much popular attention in the United States. Even so, some experienced academics are seeing the growth in research production from China that the rankings reflect, and are warning that America is falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rafael Reif, a former president of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said on a podcast last year that “the number of papers and the quality of the papers coming from China are outstanding” and are “dwarfing what we’re doing in the U.S.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institutions in other countries around the world, by contrast, are watching the global rankings, seeing them as a measure both of academic prowess and of their progress in overtaking the United States. Zhejiang University displays its rankings prominently on its web page, and lists among the milestones in its history when it broke into the top 100 globally in 2017. Chinese state media has celebrated the ranking rise of the country’s universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The center at Leiden has begun producing an alternative ranking that is based on a different academic database, called OpenAlex. Harvard is No. 1 in that ranking, but the trend is the same: 12 of the next 13 schools on the alternative list are Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“China is really building a lot of research capacity,” Mr. Neijssel said. At the same time, he said, Chinese researchers are putting more emphasis on publishing in English-language journals that are more widely read — and cited — around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Xi Jinping, in a speech in 2024, praised his country’s advances in fields such as quantum technology and space science. He cited a breakthrough by researchers at Tianjin Institute of Industrial Biotechnology, who developed a method to synthesize starch from carbon dioxide in the lab, which could possibly lead to industries making food from the air, without needing acres of plants dependent on land, irrigation and harvesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other ranking systems that are weighted toward scientific output reflect a similar shift toward Chinese institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard is No. 1 globally in the University Ranking by Academic Performance, compiled by the Informatics Institute of Middle East Technical University in Ankara, Turkey. But Stanford University was the only other U.S. school in the top 10, which includes four Chinese universities. Another ranking, the Nature Index, placed Harvard first, followed by 10 Chinese schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard and other leading U.S. universities face a fresh set of stressors from the Trump administration’s cuts to science grants, as well as from travel bans and an anti-immigration crackdown that has swept up international students and academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of international students arriving in the U.S. in August 2025 was 19 percent lower than the year before, a trend that could further hurt the prestige and rankings of American schools if the world’s best minds choose to study and work elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has been pouring billions of dollars into its universities and aggressively working to make them attractive to foreign researchers. In the fall, China began offering a visa specifically for graduates of top universities in science and technology to travel to China to study or do business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“China has a boatload of money in higher education that it didn’t have 20 years ago,” said Alex Usher, president of Higher Education Strategy Associates, a Toronto education consulting company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Xi has made the reasons for the country’s investments explicit, arguing that a nation’s global power depends on its scientific dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The scientific and technological revolution is intertwined with the game between superpowers,” he said in a speech in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump’s administration has taken the opposite tack, aiming to cut billions of dollars in research grants for U.S. universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump officials have argued that the cuts are meant to eliminate waste and reorient research away from themes of diversity and other topics that they see as too political.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration did not respond to a request for comment for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A White House spokeswoman, Liz Huston, has said in the past that “the best science can’t thrive in institutions that have abandoned merit, free inquiry, and the pursuit of truth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University leaders in the United States warned throughout 2025 that reductions in federal research grants could have devastating effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard established a web page to catalog the types of scientific and medical research that would be interrupted by grant cuts. The American Association of University Professors and several legal allies filed suit to contest some of the cuts. The group’s president, Todd Wolfson, warned that research cuts would “stunt the development of the next generation of scientists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge has ordered the federal government to resume funding for Harvard, after the Trump administration cut off billions of dollars in research funds in the spring. The administration has said it would curtail future grants to the school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Harvard spokesman declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prestige and global standing of many other U.S. universities are also in jeopardy. Fewer and smaller federal grants means less research, and by extension, potentially fewer discoveries to be written up and published in academic articles and papers, which will affect how schools fare in future rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research universities make it part of their mission to pursue discoveries and develop new knowledge. Faculty members are often under pressure to produce results, summed up in the phrase “publish or perish.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schools that do not aspire to produce reams of academic research papers, such as many liberal arts colleges, would not figure on production-based rankings. Mr. Neijssel said the Leiden rankings “do not pretend to say anything” about the quality of teaching at a university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top U.S. schools have fared much better in ranking systems whose criteria are broader than just academic output. Some give weight to factors such as a school’s reputation, finances, and how badly students want to enroll, as reflected in its application acceptance rate. Some even take into account the number of Nobel Prize winners on the faculty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These broader rankings may be slower to change, experts say, though they still show signs of the erosion of American supremacy in higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2026, and for the 10th year in a row, Times Higher Education in Britain ranked Oxford University the No. 1 university in the world. The rest of the organization’s top five included the same schools as last year: M.I.T., Princeton, the University of Cambridge, and then Harvard, tied with Stanford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American schools held seven of the top 10 spots in the 2026 ranking. But farther down the list, American universities are slipping. Sixty-two U.S. schools were ranked lower than last year, while only 19 rose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, two prominent Beijing schools — Peking University and Tsinghua University — were ranked 42nd and 47th in Times Higher Education’s list. Now they are just below the top 10: Tsinghua was ranked 12th, and Peking 13th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six schools in Hong Kong are now in the top 200; South Korea placed four in the top 100.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some foreign schools have risen, some well-known American schools have slipped. Duke University, for instance, was ranked 20th in 2021, and now is ranked 28th. Over that same time span, Emory University dropped to 102nd from 85th. Ten years ago, Notre Dame ranked 108th; now it is No. 194.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pressures that could reduce Harvard’s research output, like federal grant reductions and cuts to the school’s Ph.D. programs, are unlikely to show up immediately in rankings, said Mr. Usher, the higher education consultant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re looking at how many articles end up in ‘Nature’ or ‘Science’ from that institution, that is based on research that started four or five years ago,” he said. “There is a pretty serious time lag. I wouldn’t expect that to have a big impact in the next few years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While China is thriving in disciplines like chemistry and environmental sciences, the United States and Europe remain dominant in others, like general biology and medical sciences. And a study has suggested that Chinese researchers have been boosting their citation rankings by citing one another more often than western researchers tend to cite other westerners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University rankings are an old phenomenon, dating back to the early 20th Century, according to Alan Ruby, senior fellow and director of global engagement at the Graduate School of Education at the University of Pennsylvania.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students often use rankings to help them decide where to apply, and academics use them as guides to where to work and conduct research, he said. Some governments use them in doling out research money, and some employers see them as a tool for quickly sorting large numbers of entry-level job candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re trying to attract the best talent in the world, be it students or researchers or faculty, you want to have that signaling power of, ‘We’re a highly ranked institution,’ ” Mr. Ruby said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond marketing, rankings matter because the quality of universities matter, according to Paul Musgrave, a professor of government at Georgetown University’s campus in Doha, Qatar. It can be difficult to draw a direct line between good universities and national power, he said, but “on the other hand, we all know that when the Germans wrecked their universities in the 1930s it probably hurt them in a lot of ways.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/harvard-global-ranking-chinese-universities-trump-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 03:24:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge to Weigh Next Steps in Student Activist Deportations Case</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-activist-deportations-judge.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-deport-qhpw/15dc-deport-qhpw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in Boston last September issued a landmark ruling that the Trump administration deliberately chilled the speech of international students with a string of targeted arrests intended to “strike fear” in demonstrators and academics critical of Israel’s conduct in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Judge William G. Young will decide what should be done about that violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, he did not order the Trump administration to correct course right away, but asked the government and the academic organizations who sued to return to argue over how he could intervene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his ruling, Judge Young, who is 85 and has served as a federal judge for over 40 years, described the case as “perhaps the most important” of his career. Academic organizations that sued argued that the attempted deportations of a few prominent student activists — and broader threats by President Trump and Secretary of State Marco Rubio — had a silencing effect across academia and chilled speech about the war in Gaza and other contentious issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a two-week trial, lawyers for the groups examined the cases of five prominent student activists: Mahmoud Khalil, Rumeysa Ozturk, Mohsen Mahdawi, Badar Khan Suri and Yunseo Chung. Though the students were in the United States legally, the administration accused them of undermining U.S. foreign policy interests through their activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, they were held for months, and federal officials attempted to deport them. The students successfully challenged their deportations in separate, individual lawsuits, and those who were detained were eventually ordered released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central question before Judge Young last year was whether Mr. Trump’s policies had suppressed academic speech on campus more broadly. In an extraordinary 161-page opinion, Judge Young found that they had. He upbraided the Trump administration and the president himself for cultivating what he cast as a climate of fear and repression, concluding that noncitizens had an equal First Amendment right to free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal scholars said that deciding on a remedy was likely to be a harder task for Judge Young than excoriating the administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael Kagan, a law professor and the director of the University of Nevada, Las Vegas Immigration Clinic, said that Judge Young could focus on stopping the implementation of the executive orders and Department of Homeland Security policies that had authorized the wave of student arrests last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he said it would be challenging for Judge Young to craft a remedy that would predict and pre-empt other ways the administration may try to pursue noncitizen academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is all pretty dicey territory for the court to navigate in terms of solving the problem,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The groups behind the lawsuit have argued for broad relief that would prohibit the administration from pursuing any part of what they describe as an “enforcement policy” of revoking green cards and student visas based on anti-Israel or pro-Palestinian speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The government’s unconstitutional actions have made many noncitizen students and faculty fearful of speaking out on issues that are important to them,” said Ramya Krishnan, a senior staff attorney at the Knight First Amendment Institute, which helped represent the academic organizations. “We want the court to grant relief that addresses that fear — starting with an order that expressly prohibits the government from pursuing its policy of deporting people based on constitutionally protected speech.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some legal scholars speculated that following his blunt ruling, Judge Young could opt for a narrower solution, to avoid overstepping in ways that could be questioned on appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One thing I could imagine is that the judge, having made that rather substantial departure from the norm, would get cautious at the remedy stage, and not purport to tell the government in too stark or precise terms what to do,” said Gregory P. Magarian, a law professor at Washington University in St. Louis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Magarian said that Judge Young may want to avoid taking steps that would endanger his underlying landmark ruling on the First Amendment rights of noncitizens, which by itself was a major breakthrough for groups promoting freedom of speech on campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration has argued throughout the case that the court lacks the authority to interfere in the Trump administration’s foreign policy priorities, or curtail the “investigative and enforcement” power of agencies it tasked with reviewing the conduct of noncitizens and visa holders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In filings, it has argued that threatening language from Mr. Rubio and other cabinet officials about investigating critics of Israel was also protected speech the court should not police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Young on Thursday will also consider requests from a variety of news organizations, including The New York Times, that he agree to unseal some evidence presented during the trial last year. The documents appeared to include details about how top officials justified arresting students and attempting to strip them of their visas or legal status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the trial, witnesses for the government described parts of the process through which the State Department and the Department of Homeland Security identified student leaders to target. They testified that they had relied in part on lists published by an anonymously run site that shared the personal details of academics it deemed hostile to Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other evidence Judge Young relied on to reach his decision, including memos and dossiers passed between the agencies authorizing the arrests of the five students, have remained sealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Young provisionally agreed to keep certain documents private at the government’s request during the trial last year, citing caution over revealing confidential details about immigration enforcement. But he referred to many of them in his opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/student-activist-deportations-judge.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:14:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Leading Prediction Firms Share a Commonality: Donald Trump Jr.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/donald-trump-jr-prediction-markets.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/us/politics/00DC-Trumppredictions/00DC-Trumppredictions-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The companies running online prediction markets, where ordinary people bet on real-world events, can count on intense interest in what President Trump might have up his sleeve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traders this month are wagering millions on whether the president will take over Greenland, whom he will nominate to lead the Federal Reserve and whether the government will shut down again. Less than two weeks ago, someone netted an eye-popping $410,000 payout betting that Venezuela’s leader, Nicolás Maduro, would lose power by the end of the month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the intersection of the prediction market industry and Trump world is Donald Trump Jr., the president’s eldest son. He is both an investor in and an unpaid adviser to Polymarket, and a paid adviser to Kalshi, the two biggest prediction markets. And he is a director of the Trump family’s social media company, which recently announced it would start its own platform called Truth Predict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The various hats worn by Donald Trump Jr. are an example of the ethical questions raised by Trump family business ventures during the president’s second term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts see dual concerns: Prediction markets are federally regulated, and the Commodity Futures Trading Commission last year backed away from enforcement efforts against both Polymarket and Kalshi. That has created questions about whether regulators could have been swayed by simply knowing the interests of the president’s son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethics experts say the younger Mr. Trump’s frequent proximity to the president, along with his advisers, their staff members and their cohorts, also naturally prompts suspicions even if he neither knows nor shares any information that could influence the markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ann Skeet, the senior director of leadership ethics at the Markkula Center for Applied Ethics in Santa Clara, Calif., said that “it’s problematic to have the president’s son in the mix” because he could be among a small group of people who actually know the answers to specific White House questions that people are betting on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew Surabian, a spokesman for Donald Trump Jr., said his only involvement with prediction markets is to advise Kalshi and Polymarket on marketing strategies and to back Polymarket financially. He said that Mr. Trump does not trade on their platforms and that he never interacts with the federal government on behalf of any company he has invested in or advises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump Jr. is a lifelong investor and entrepreneur with ventures in cryptocurrency, real estate, drones and the distribution of pharmaceutical drugs, Mr. Surabian said, and he operates like any other businessman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The idea that Don, who has never worked in the government in his life, should cease working in the private sector and providing for his five children, just because his dad was elected president, is an absurd premise,” Mr. Surabian said in a statement. “The only conflict of interest that exists here is between the network of left-wing activists and their ideological allies in the media who keep using lies and baseless innuendo to smear Don.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s involvement in prediction markets underscores how thoroughly the president’s family is enmeshed in businesses that are subject to federal government oversight. The Trump administration has taken a distinctly friendlier regulatory approach toward prediction market platforms compared with the Biden administration. That dovetails with its pullback in enforcement against the cryptocurrency industry, which has been a hugely lucrative new field for the Trump family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also shows how eager companies are to have a Trump ally in their corner: Polymarket and Kalshi are neck-and-neck competitors, yet Mr. Trump is an adviser to both. Since President Trump’s election, at least seven other companies have announced that his son is either an adviser, a board member or a director.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prediction markets are exploding in popularity, offering what are typically yes-or-no questions on topics including sports, the Oscars, foreign events and the price of silver. Together, Kalshi and Polymarket, a crypto-based platform, took in nearly $50 billion in trades last year, according to an analysis by Piper Sandler, an investment bank. Some research suggests that the online markets give better real-time signals than surveys or polls because they are more nimble and people are putting their money where their mouths are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traders are publicly anonymous, but Tre Upshaw, whose start-up company Polysights monitors Polymarket’s platform, said some wagers suggested bettors had inside knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Upshaw said the trader who made a killing betting on the ouster of Venezuela’s leader this month, for example, bet a total of about $34,000 against very long odds. That person used a brand-new crypto account and wagered most of the funds just hours before news of Mr. Maduro’s capture broke. Mr. Upshaw said that some trades about whether the president would pardon Changpeng Zhao, the billionaire founder of the cryptocurrency exchange Binance, before he did so also stood out to him as suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kalshi’s website states that people who have inside information or who can influence the outcome of an event are prohibited from betting on it. The company said in a statement that it forbids bets by government officials and checks trades against a database of “politically exposed people.” Shayne Coplan, Polymarket’s founder, has said his firm abides by all legal rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commodity Futures Trading Commission is supposed to police insider trading on prediction markets, but experts say the law is so vague that it is virtually impossible to enforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s very difficult for the platforms themselves to prevent this or the C.F.T.C. to prohibit it,” said Timothy G. Massad, who led the agency under President Barack Obama. Some operators argue that the prediction markets actually benefit from traders who are in the know because it makes for more accurate odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Biden administration, the trading commission tried to limit the scope of prediction markets and forced exchanges to register with the agency. But last February, Caroline D. Pham, the acting chair at the time, said that the agency had unfairly constrained “an important new frontier in harnessing the power of markets” and that it needed to back off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The current commission interpretations regarding event contracts are a sinkhole of legal uncertainty and an inappropriate constraint on the new administration,” said Ms. Pham, who had served as a commissioner during the Biden administration and took over the agency temporarily under Mr. Trump. She resigned last month when Michael S. Selig, appointed by Mr. Trump as chairman, was confirmed by the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Kalshi and Polymarket have benefited from the agency’s lighter touch. Once targets of enforcement efforts, both companies’ chief executives are now on the trading commission’s innovation council, which was created to help shape policy on prediction markets, cryptocurrency and other issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2023, the agency banned Kalshi from offering trades about the outcome of congressional elections, arguing that such activity would undermine state gambling bans, spread misinformation and threaten the public’s trust in elections. Kalshi sued the agency and won in federal court in late 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal appeals court refused to temporarily halt the trading while the commission appealed, saying that the regulators had failed to prove that irreparable harm would result if it did not step in. But the court said in its October 2024 opinion that “the question on the merits is close and difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week before Mr. Trump’s inauguration, Kalshi said it had hired the president’s son as a strategic adviser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four months later, the trading commission dropped its appeal of the election betting ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, the company said the president’s son had nothing to do with the end of the case. “Donald Trump Jr. does not engage with government officials on Kalshi’s behalf,” it said. “We have never asked him, nor has he ever intervened in court cases for us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polymarket’s dealings with the trading commission date to 2022, when it agreed to pay a $1.4 million fine for failing to register as an online trading platform. The firm was ordered to block U.S. users on its platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Polymarket took in a surge of bets about the 2024 presidential election, the F.B.I. raided the apartment of Mr. Coplan, seizing his phone and other electronic devices. The trading commission also investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, Polymarket announced that both the Justice Department and the commission had closed their inquiries. “After cooperating and engaging, we’ve been cleared of any wrongdoing,” Mr. Coplan said on social media. “Justice prevailed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August, Polymarket announced that 1789 Capital, a venture capital outfit in which Donald Trump Jr. is a partner, had invested in the firm and that he would be a member of its advisory board. Asked what role the president’s son played, Mr. Coplan told “60 Minutes” in November that he needed help navigating the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If I have people who believe in what I do, who understand how politics works and can help me,” he said, then “there’s nothing wrong about that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A week after the firm announced its new adviser, the trading commission issued a ruling that helped clear away obstacles to Polymarket’s serving U.S. traders. The agency issued another favorable ruling in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approvals followed Polymarket’s decision in July to buy a company that was already licensed by the trading commission as an exchange. Polymarket’s U.S. operation is now in testing mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth Predict, a new product of Trump Media &amp; Technology Group, may be close behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, Donald Trump Jr. earned $813,000, mostly in stock, as one of the firm’s directors. That was the equivalent of nearly a quarter of the firm’s annual revenue, according to filings with the Securities and Exchange Commission. He is also the sole trustee of his father’s trust, overseeing the president’s majority stake in the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shannon Devine, a spokeswoman for the firm, said last year that “Donald Trump Jr. is highly engaged in the board’s work, as well as T.M.T.G.’s operations and strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Surabian said Mr. Trump was not involved in the decision to create “Truth Predict,” announced in October. He said that it was not a board-level resolution and that Donald Trump Jr. was not a part of the company’s day-to-day operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump Media said Crypto.com, its partner in various crypto ventures, would help run the operation. The platform will allow users of Truth Social, where the president routinely posts about official business and politics, to trade on topics including sports, inflation, interest rates, and gold and oil prices, it said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also on the menu: political elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julie Tate contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/donald-trump-jr-prediction-markets.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 01:02:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>One State, Two Very Different Views of Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minnesota-minneapolis-shooting-ice-renee-good.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15nat-minnesota-view-top-hfmj/15nat-minnesota-view-top-hfmj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regulars file into Ye Olde Pickle Factory in Nisswa, Minn., before 10 a.m. most days, taking their seats at the bar. Chili pepper lights hang from the ceiling, and neon beer signs glow against wood-paneled walls. A television flickers on. “The Price Is Right” is about to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have been doing this since the mid-1980s, gathering in this small, dim room, waiting for someone on the game show to spin exactly $1 on the big wheel. When that happens, everyone receives a token for a free drink. Lately, they had been in a lull. No one had hit the dollar in weeks — until Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nisswa is a town of about 2,000 people in the Brainerd Lakes Area, a popular summer vacation destination about 150 miles north of Minneapolis. Most of the regulars on hand this morning say they prefer not to go the city anymore. Not since the summer of 2020, when George Floyd was murdered by a police officer and the city erupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Minneapolis is in the news again. An Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent shot and killed a woman, Renee Good, during an immigration operation last week, and demonstrators are back on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did the regulars make of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Good’s death was tragic, they said. Horrific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they also said that she had asked for trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You obey the law officer,” a man in a veteran’s ball cap said, “and question it later.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the divide, in a single sentence. In Minneapolis, protesters saw an innocent woman killed by a federal agent and took to the streets. At “the Pickle,” the regulars saw a woman who should have complied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In bars, cafes and coffee shops across rural Minnesota, the same conversations were unfolding. Ms. Good’s death had become a mirror, reflecting back a fracture that had been deepening for years — not just in their state, but across the country, wherever rural areas chafe against the political power of big cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deb Lund and Connie Jenson, both in their early 70s, sat at the bar. A Busch Light cooler nearby read “Welcome Hunters!” A patron had brought smoked salmon to share, and someone passed a Tupperware container down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area, like most of rural Minnesota, votes solidly Republican. It was not always this way. For decades, rural Minnesota was home to moderate Democrats who would vote for candidates from their own party who aligned with their views. The rightward shift was catalyzed by the rise of Donald J. Trump. Now the regulars at the Pickle say that what everyone in the region seems to agree on is that life there is safer and quieter than in the Twin Cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the regulars avoid Minneapolis if they can. They see the city as dangerous, out of control and something to flee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t even want to go there,” Ms. Jenson said of Minneapolis. “Not anymore. Not since the George Floyd riots.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lund used to live in Crystal, a Minneapolis suburb. “I worked my butt off to get up here,” she said, “and there’s no way I’m going back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regulars once bristled when Gov. Tim Walz, a Democrat, referred to rural Minnesota as “the land of rocks and cows.” Now they call themselves “rocks and cows” with a kind of pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a hopeless feeling,” Ms. Jenson said, “that most everything is controlled by the city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a term for what Ms. Lund and Ms. Jenson are expressing. Christopher Federico, a professor of political science and psychology at the University of Minnesota, calls it “rural consciousness” — a sense that living in a rural area comes with consequences: less political power, fewer resources, less respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One thing we find is that individuals who are high in rural consciousness feel misunderstood by people living in nonrural areas,” Professor Federico said. “To some extent, there’s evidence they feel shortchanged.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing uniquely Minnesotan about this. The same fault line runs through Illinois, California, New York — anywhere a major metropolis dominates state politics, as it is in Minnesota by the Twin Cities. Rural citizens have become more conservative and more Republican across the country. But in Minnesota, the shift has been particularly pronounced. Today, less populated areas of the state vote Republican by a margin of roughly two to one, according to Tim Lindberg, an associate professor of political science at the University of Minnesota, Morris, who studies rural politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sense of alienation is not new. But in recent years it has become tightly bound to Republican partisanship — a shift accelerated by conservative media and political leaders who frame cities as dangerous and lawless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Pickle, neither Ms. Lund nor Ms. Jenson had seen President Trump’s recent social media post calling for “a day of reckoning and retribution” in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the reckoning part,” Ms. Jenson said when told of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for retribution, she had a target in mind: the allegations of fraud in Minnesota’s child care and nutrition programs that federal prosecutors have been investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protesters filling the streets of Minneapolis after Ms. Good was killed? Mr. Jenson wondered aloud about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Do you think they’re paid?” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But elsewhere in rural Minnesota, the shooting had unsettled even some conservatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Pine City, about 75 miles north of Minneapolis, Trever DePoppe, 23, helps manage a pro shop that screens jerseys for local sports teams. He considers himself a Republican. He supports ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is also troubled by the killing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think the shooting was necessarily 100 percent justified,” Mr. DePoppe said. “I can see both sides of it. Obviously when you drive into someone that has a gun pointed, that’s probably not the smartest idea. But at the same time, why do you have a gun pulled in that situation? And then to walk away on your body cam and be using foul language toward the person?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think it’s great to start to get some of the illegal immigrants out of the state,” he added. “I think it’s bad how they are going about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. DePoppe had never seen an ICE agent in town. He said many residents see the Twin Cities — also known as “the Cities” in these parts — as almost another world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Until something happens up here, it’s not a problem for anyone up here,” he said. “A lot of people don’t watch the news anymore because all you see is the stuff that happens in the Cities. It’s depressing, traumatizing. It’s things that we don’t think about until it happens up here, but down in the Cities it happens every day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary Kay Brautigan, 74, a retired local real estate agent and a member of a local liberal activist group called the Blue Brigade, has a different view. She said she had been haunted by Ms. Good’s last words, captured on video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I can’t sleep at night because of that sound bite in my head,” she said. “‘Dude, we’re not trying to hurt you.’ That’s how we feel — dudes, we’re not trying to hurt you when we are out there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Minnesota is under attack right now,” she added. “Seriously under attack. And I don’t know what the defense is other than to keep standing for what we believe in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nancy Mach, 79, another Blue Brigade member, who is a retired dean of student affairs at a local community college, said navigating the divide in a small town required care. In Pine City, she sees the same people every day — including friends she plays trivia with on Thursday nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re fun, you know,” she said. “It’s just that you have to avoid the political piece, which is too bad, because we’re not going to learn from others by avoiding it. But it’s the only way we can exist right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back at the Pickle, Lani Thompsen knows that delicate dance well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Thompsen has been tending bar there for 40 years. She has lived in Nisswa since she was 10. The regulars recently threw her an anniversary party. She is a lifelong Democrat; they are, by and large, Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She calls them family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a mutual respect,” Ms. Thompsen said. “They don’t talk real bad when I’m around, and I choose not to fight with them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before ICE arrived in the state, she said, her customers talked about what they were making for dinner, where the fish were biting or how Connie’s quilts were coming along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are people who take care of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A customer brings smoked salmon for others to share. The regulars throw their Democratic bartender a party. They organize gatherings for National Soup Day, the Fall Fling and National Pickle Day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Jenson and her husband leave for lunch every day, Ms. Thompsen said. But they often return near the end of her shift to say goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attention turned to the television. The contestants were about to spin the wheel for the Showcase Showdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One hundred fifty miles to the south, protesters were following ICE vehicles through the streets of Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minnesota-minneapolis-shooting-ice-renee-good.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 08:28:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cyberattack in Venezuela Demonstrated Precision of U.S. Capabilities</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/cyberattack-venezuela-military.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-cyber-lwtm/15dc-cyber-lwtm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cyberattack that plunged Venezuela’s capital into darkness this month demonstrated the Pentagon’s ability not just to turn off the lights, but also to allow them to be turned back on, according to U.S. officials briefed on the operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jan. 3 operation was one of the most public displays of offensive U.S. cyber-capabilities in recent years. It showed that at least with a country like Venezuela, whose military does not have sophisticated defenses against cyberattacks, the United States could use cyberweapons with powerful and precise effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military also used cyberweapons to interfere with air defense radar, according to people briefed on the matter, who discussed sensitive details of the operation on the condition of anonymity. (Venezuela’s most powerful radar was not functional, however.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning off the power in Caracas and interfering with radar allowed U.S. military helicopters to move into the country undetected on their mission to capture Nicolás Maduro, the Venezuelan president who has now been brought to the United States to face drug charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senators on the Armed Services Committee are set to ask questions about the Venezuela operation at the confirmation hearing on Thursday of Lt. Gen. Joshua M. Rudd, President Trump’s nominee to lead the U.S. Cyber Command and the National Security Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Rudd, a longtime special operation forces commander, is currently the deputy head of the Indo-Pacific Command. If confirmed, he would lead an agency and command that have had a number of senior officials forced out by Laura Loomer, the far-right conspiracy theorist and Trump ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you should know. The Times makes a careful decision any time it uses an anonymous source. The information the source supplies must be newsworthy and give readers genuine insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump fired Gen. Tim Haugh, the former head of the Cyber Command and the N.S.A., in April after Ms. Loomer noted that he had been appointed by the previous administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers received classified briefings on the cyberoperations this week, but General Rudd’s confirmation hearing will be their first opportunity to pose questions in public about the raid as well as the Trump administration’s plans for more aggressive cyberoperations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a news conference hours after the raid that captured Mr. Maduro, Mr. Trump made reference to the cyberoperation, though he did not explicitly say what it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was dark, the lights of Caracas were largely turned off due to a certain expertise that we have, it was dark, and it was deadly,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on Wednesday, a spokeswoman for the U.S. Cyber Command said the organization “was proud to support Operation Absolute Resolve,” as the mission was named. She added that the command was equipped to execute orders of the president at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attack caused most of Caracas’s residents to lose their power for a few minutes, though some neighborhoods near the military base where Mr. Maduro was captured were left without electricity for up to 36 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts have long worried that a cyberattack on the power grid could cause widespread collateral damage, particularly if hospitals or trauma centers lost power while trying to treat badly injured people. But that did not happen in Caracas, in large measure because the power was restored quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, after years of blackouts, Caracas was better prepared for a power outage. Most hospitals in the city have installed backup generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medical workers said there were no known fatalities during the cyberattack in areas that depend on constant power, such as maternity wards or intensive care units. Because the attack happened in the early hours, most people were asleep and were mostly unaffected by the blackout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the Maduro government accused the United States of conducting a cyberattack on a hydropower plant that plunged much of the country into darkness for a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power failures caused sporadic outbursts of looting and unrest, bringing the government close to collapse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The electric war announced and led by the US imperialism against our people will be defeated,” Mr. Maduro wrote on social media in March 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the first Trump administration was trying to push Mr. Maduro from power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mike Pompeo, then the secretary of state, denied any U.S. involvement in the power failure, blaming it instead on Cuban engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Maduro’s government never provided evidence for the cyberattack, and electrical experts said the blackout could have been caused by poor maintenance and underinvestment. A union official at the state electricity company said at the time that the blackout was caused by a brush fire under a power line, which destabilized the grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, in the following years, Venezuelan officials increasingly pointed to a U.S. plot behind frequent industrial incidents in the country, without providing evidence. Rumors of U.S.-directed saboteurs only increased in the tense month before Mr. Maduro was captured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Sella contributed reporting from Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/cyberattack-venezuela-military.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:21:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How We Photographed an ICE Confrontation in MinneapolisHow We Photographed an ICE Confrontation in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010643550/how-we-photographed-an-ice-confrontation-in-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/arts/minneapolis-protest-escalation_thumbnail/minneapolis-protest-escalation_thumbnail-facebookJumbo.png?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Our visual journalists David Guttenfelder and Todd Heisler describe a dramatic incident in which federal agents dragged a woman out of her car in Minneapolis near where Renee Nicole Good had been killed days before.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010643550/how-we-photographed-an-ice-confrontation-in-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 07:45:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Abolish ICE? It’s a Slogan Some Democratic Critics of ICE Would Abolish.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/democrats-abolish-ice-slogan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/pol-ice-vtzh/pol-ice-vtzh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatal shooting of a 37-year-old woman in Minneapolis by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent last week outraged many Democratic officials, who have watched with increasing alarm and anger as federal officers have swooped into cities across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State and local officials in Minnesota and Illinois are suing the Trump administration to try to block the raids, which have sown chaos in their cities. Democratic members of Congress are demanding more oversight over ICE and its tactics, and some are trying to tie their demands to budget talks. A group of House Democrats have called for impeaching Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some Democrats running for Congress in blue districts around the country have revived a phrase from the first Trump administration: “Abolish ICE.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a slogan that many Democrats had hoped to retire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immigration has arguably been the most vexing issue for Democrats in the Trump era. The Biden administration’s missteps on the issue — underestimating the scale of migration that their policies would allow and failing to anticipate the political backlash — helped pave the way for President Trump’s election to a second term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as the crisis in Minneapolis grows and Democrats struggle to effectively rein in tactics that they see as overly aggressive and possibly illegal, some Democrats worry that calls to eliminate the agency are an unwelcome distraction from more pragmatic approaches. They fear that the “Abolish ICE” slogan will age as poorly as “Defund the Police” did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Clearly ICE is an absolute problem — they’re out of control, moving way too fast,” said Senator Ruben Gallego, Democrat of Arizona. But Mr. Gallego, who has criticized other members of his party for kowtowing to the left, said that resuming “Abolish ICE” calls would hurt the cause. “The last thing we need to do, again, is to make the same mistake when it comes to ‘Defund the Police’ rhetoric. That ended up not actually helping communicate what people wanted. People want a slimmed-down ICE that is truly focused on security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, polls have suggested that support for the Trump administration’s immigration policies has been falling, with a majority now saying that the administration is doing “too much” on deportations. A CNN poll released Wednesday found that 51 percent of Americans believed that ICE enforcement actions were making cities less safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Democrats believe they have an opportunity to reframe the debate about the administration’s enforcement tactics by casting it as overreach in need of oversight. The shooting of Renee Nicole Good in Minneapolis last week refocused national attention on the raids, particularly on the masked federal agents who have moved to expel people who are in the country without legal status even if they do not have criminal backgrounds, questioned American citizens on the streets and clashed with protesters in chaotic scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats grew increasingly concerned after another shooting in Minneapolis on Wednesday evening, where officials said that a federal agent had shot and injured a man at a traffic stop. And they were alarmed by President Trump’s threat on Thursday morning to invoke the Insurrection Act to quell protests there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment has uncovered a still-simmering tension within the party: Some Democrats are eager to take an even more forceful stance against the administration’s tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micah Lasher, who is running in a crowded primary to represent a congressional district in Manhattan, posted “Abolish ICE” on X last week and argued in an interview that it was time to do away with the agency, which was established in 2003 as part of the newly created Department of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ICE has become the embodiment of a thugocracy and a growing number of Americans, regardless of where they fall on the ideological spectrum, feel that this is an entity that should be dismantled,” said Mr. Lasher, a state lawmaker who worked in the administrations of Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg and Gov. Kathy Hochul. He described ICE as a “completely unchecked, almost militia-like, organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Shri Thanedar, a Democrat from Michigan, plans to introduce the “Abolish ICE Act” in the House to dismantle the agency. In Chicago, Patty Garcia has made abolishing it a central part of her campaign for Congress, and on a lighter note the city’s mayor, Brandon Johnson, recently voiced his support to officially name a city snowplow “Abolish ICE.” That drew the ire of Gregory Bovino, the Border Patrol chief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some Democrats caution that calling for the outright elimination of ICE is a trap that will only help Republicans. Third Way, a centrist Washington-based think tank, released a memo Tuesday urging Democrats not to take up the ‘abolish’ mantel, warning that “when the debate sinks into polarizing slogans that read as anti-law or anti-safety, space for practical reform disappears.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every call to abolish ICE risks squandering one of the clearest opportunities in years to secure meaningful reform of immigration enforcement — while handing Republicans exactly the fight they want,” the authors wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a spokesman for the National Republican Congressional Committee seemed to relish the idea that more Democrats were embracing the term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The radical ‘Abolish ICE’ crusade from far-left Democrats seemed like a relic of the past, but it’s the brand-new litmus test for Democrats who are barely hanging on and begging on their knees to get approval from their socialist base,” the spokesman, Mike Marinella, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats have taken a number of different approaches on the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Robin Kelly, a Democrat from Illinois, has introduced articles of impeachment against Secretary Noem, whom she has called incompetent and a disgrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I definitely know there needs to be a lot of reform, if not complete abolishment,” she said. “I’ve met a lot of people who said they voted for him and they didn’t think this was going to be the result. They thought, yes, murderers and rapists off the street, but I think people feel like he’s overreaching, and going too far.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some Democrats believe that the only way to meaningfully change the agency is by eliminating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ICE is acting like a rogue agency, it doesn’t follow American norms and the fact that they basically have impunity in the law is even crazier — they’re just this force of power,” said Representative Mark Pocan, a Democrat from Wisconsin who supported the earliest calls to abolish ICE. “I think the public is actually leading us to a place where they’re saying this is not America, this is not acceptable. I think that sentiment is significantly different from when I introduced this in the first Trump administration.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even some Republicans have begun to publicly caution against the kind of headline-grabbing tactics used in many of the enforcement operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ICE needs to concentrate on what the president promised, which was deportation of the bad hombres,” said Representative Maria Elvira Salazar, a Republican who represents Miami. “The overwhelming majority of the illegal population is not that and they have been here for a long time working.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Salazar has warned that the administration’s approach puts the gains Republicans have made with Latino voters at serious risk. She has introduced a bill to allow millions of undocumented immigrants to adjust their legal status and in some cases become citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t want the Hispanic community, my community, to believe or to think that the G.O.P. doesn’t love them,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats in Congress are debating whether they should try to hold up funding for the agency at the end of this month as they try to force changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The agency needs to change and it’s going to take a long time for it to regain the trust of the American people,” said Representative Betty McCollum, a Democrat from Minnesota who faulted ICE for detaining American citizens and profiling people during raids. “We want law enforcement to conduct their jobs in the right way.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/democrats-abolish-ice-slogan.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:07:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under Trump, a Shift Toward ‘Absolute Immunity’ for ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-ice-immunity.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/14dc-icetraining-01-lwgz/14dc-icetraining-01-lwgz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions to Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents explain in clear terms how to defuse dangerous encounters: Use “minimal force” when trying to remove people from cars. Issue commands in “professional,” “firm,” “courteous” voices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“First step in arresting an occupant of a vehicle is NOT to reach in and grab him, unless there are specific circumstances requiring that action,” reads one internal ICE document providing legal guidance for uses of force during vehicle stops. It was reviewed by The New York Times, along with other training materials. ICE officials will thoroughly investigate any encounter, but “deadly force” is allowed only when agents believe lives are in danger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatal shooting of Renee Good last week by an ICE agent in Minneapolis — and the quick reaction by Trump administration officials to declare the agent a hero and Ms. Good a villain — has put a new focus on whether federal agents enforcing President Trump’s deportation drive have been properly prepared for confrontations on city streets. The response of Mr. Trump and his top lieutenants to the killing has also underscored how they have embraced what is supposed to be a last resort under the written standards: using lethal force in self-defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than encourage agents to de-escalate combustible encounters, as the agency guidelines emphasize, Mr. Trump and his lieutenants have provided tacit approval for more aggressive tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several weeks before the shooting, a top ICE official told officers to take “decisive action” if threatened. Immediately after, Mr. Trump and other administration officials said Ms. Good had tried to run the agent over, although a Times video analysis found that she appeared to have turned her vehicle away from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That guy is protected by absolute immunity,” Vice President JD Vance said last week of the ICE agent who killed Ms. Good, 37. “He was doing his job.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, the Homeland Security Department reiterated that sentiment to its agents, posting a clip on social media of Stephen Miller, a White House deputy chief of staff, saying, “You have immunity to perform your duties, and no one — no city official, no state official, no illegal alien, no leftist agitator or domestic insurrectionist — can prevent you from fulfilling your legal obligations and duties.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions in Minneapolis have boiled over in the days since Ms. Good’s death. On Wednesday night, a federal agent in the city shot and wounded a man who was attacking him, officials said. The episode led to hours of clashes between protesters and law enforcement officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abigail Jackson, a White House spokeswoman, said ICE agents were using appropriate tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The entire Trump administration stands behind our heroic ICE officers who are conducting themselves with the utmost professionalism and integrity, while making American communities safer,” Ms. Jackson said in a statement. “It is not an ‘aggressive tactic’ to defend yourself from an individual using their car as a deadly weapon — ICE officers have a right to self-defense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricia McLaughlin, a homeland security spokeswoman, said that “ICE law enforcement officers are trained to use the minimum amount of force necessary to resolve dangerous situations to prioritize the safety of the public and our officers” and are “highly trained in de-escalation tactics.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minneapolis shooting has also revealed the risks of Mr. Trump’s decision to send ICE on large-scale sweeps through cities, a move that has thrust agents into confrontations with hostile crowds. Most ICE agents are not trained to handle crowd control, according to a 2021 report by the Government Accountability Office. That is in part because ICE has historically focused on targeted arrests that attract less attention and rarely put its officers in conflict with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the agency is rapidly expanding its ranks, already more than doubling its number of law enforcement personnel, after an infusion of $75 billion in new funding over four years. It has expedited its training programs to accommodate the new recruits, including reducing training on how to handle vehicle stops, according to a former official at the federal government’s law enforcement academy who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss internal homeland security policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. McLaughlin said there had been no reduction in training on vehicle stops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal officers do not have “absolute” immunity from prosecution, although the U.S. Constitution makes it difficult for states to prosecute them for actions taken while on duty. They can also face federal charges. But that is unlikely to happen in the Minneapolis case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sign of the administration’s priorities, the Justice Department has decided to investigate Ms. Good’s widow and groups that monitor and protest immigration agents, rather than open a civil rights inquiry into whether the actions of the ICE agent, Jonathan Ross, were legal. In a statement, Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, said there was “no basis for a criminal civil rights investigation” into the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times would like to hear about your experience as a federal worker under the second Trump administration. We may reach out about your submission, but we will not publish any part of your response without contacting you first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have said ICE will conduct an internal investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has shown no signs of ordering ICE to back off, raising the possibility of further conflicts between agents and protesters. “FEAR NOT, GREAT PEOPLE OF MINNESOTA, THE DAY OF RECKONING &amp; RETRIBUTION IS COMING!” he wrote on social media on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Shuchart, a senior ICE official in the Biden administration, said the message from Trump administration officials to agents was to “disregard their years or decades of training” and “disregard what lawyers have told them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times reviewed internal homeland security documents that included training materials, use-of-force guidelines, legal guidance prepared by ICE lawyers and firearms policies. The training materials are from 2025, while the guidelines on use of force were published in 2023 and remain current.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documents spotlight the importance of techniques intended to avoid heated confrontations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When feasible, authorized officers must employ tactics to de-escalate by the use of communication or other techniques during an encounter to stabilize, slow or reduce the intensity of a potentially violent situation,” one document states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documents also describe a “use-of-force continuum” that officers may follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The continuum begins with officers being present on the scene with a “professional, courteous demeanor.” It progresses to issuing verbal commands. Officers may then deploy “soft techniques” like the use of “touch pressure points” or “chemical agents,” and then “hard techniques” such as “strikes with a hand, arm, foot, leg, head or the whole body” or the use of “impact weapons.” The final step is deadly force, including firearms, “strangulation techniques” and “edged weapons.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When officers use force, they must be offered “psychological first aid services” as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The materials make clear that officers are entitled to escalate the use of force as quickly as they see fit and can use lethal measures if there is “an imminent danger of serious bodily injury or death to the officer or to another person.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Ms. Good’s case, the question of whether Mr. Ross was in danger has been a point of contention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos show federal agents quickly approaching the maroon S.U.V. that she had stopped in the street on Jan. 7, partially blocking the road. One of the agents cursed as he demanded that Ms. Good get out of the car before almost immediately trying to open the driver’s side door, reaching through the open window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Good drove her car forward, Mr. Ross, who had been walking in front of her vehicle and recording video on his cellphone, shot and killed her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ross is an experienced ICE officer who served as a firearms instructor for the agency’s field office in St. Paul, Minn., and also received extra training as a member of its tactical team. Tactical team members typically receive crowd-control training. In court records, he described serving in the Iraq war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he and the ICE agents involved in the shooting of Ms. Good may not have followed some aspects of their training, documents and interviews suggest. ICE officers are generally advised not to stand in front of or behind stopped vehicles to avoid being run over, according to three former senior agency officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customs and Border Protection, which like ICE is part of the Homeland Security Department, tells agents to “avoid standing directly in front of or behind a subject vehicle,” according to a use-of-force policy posted on its website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lawyer for Mr. Ross did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While opportunities for oversight have been rare under the Trump administration, the department’s inspector general’s office said in an online notice that it was conducting an audit of ICE’s hiring and training processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the office has started an audit of how ICE investigates “allegations of excessive use of force” and disciplines officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That audit began this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Berzon, Alicia Parlapiano and Ruth Igielnik contributed reporting. Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-ice-immunity.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 06:56:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Releases Health Plan but It’s Short on Specifics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-health-care-plan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-trump-health-care-zcjp/15dc-trump-health-care-zcjp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under pressure to address affordability issues in the country, President Trump on Thursday released his long-awaited health care plan, urging Congress to pass measures that would codify steps his administration has already taken to try to lower drug costs and providing what a White House official called “broad direction” to back health savings accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan was short on specific details and left much of the direction for how to finalize it up to Congress. It amounted to a few paragraphs on a webpage, released with a video of Mr. Trump promoting what he called “the great health care plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan rejects efforts to extend the enhanced Affordable Care Act benefits that expired at the end of the year and have been the subject of intense debate on Capitol Hill. Mr. Trump briefly considered supporting an extension of those insurance subsidies, but has since backed away. Congress is continuing to consider options for extending the funding, though prospects for passage seem dim, and the enrollment period for insurance concludes today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lisa Murkowski, Republican of Alaska and part of a group of senators trying to reinstate the subsidies, said the talks would be continuing. “I’m not giving up,” she said on Thursday. Still, she acknowledged that any plan would struggle to move forward without White House support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, Mr. Trump’s plan calls for redirecting insurance subsidies into individual health savings accounts, which people could use to purchase health care services directly. Lawmakers have been discussing a few similar proposals, with varying details about the magnitude of the funding and how the money could be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One such plan came up for a vote on the Senate floor last month, and Senate Republicans did not have the 60 votes necessary to advance past a filibuster. It would have replaced the expiring subsidies by putting similar amounts into health savings accounts for consumers who chose high deductible insurance plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal would require insurance companies to provide more transparency on the prices they pay medical providers and their profit margins, though both sets of data are already required of the industry to some degree. Mr. Trump has long believed that improving the transparency of health care prices will drive down costs, though evidence for that contention is limited, and some economists believe publishing health care prices could actually help raise them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also calls for a requirement that would force insurance companies to prominently post the frequency with which they deny care. And it calls for more regulation of pharmacy benefit managers — giant middlemen companies like CVS Caremark and Express Scripts that manage prescription drug benefits for Americans with health insurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal builds on another longstanding health care priority of the president’s — lowering prescription drug prices. It asks Congress to codify voluntary deals Mr. Trump has already made with drug companies. Those deals cover 16 of the 17 major drugmakers to which the president sent letters last summer demanding lower prices. The last holdout, Regeneron, said it is still in talks with the administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deals seek to align some U.S. drug prices with the lower levels in European countries, a long-sought goal of Mr. Trump’s. Drugmakers agreed to offer those lower international prices to state Medicaid programs, which cover lower-income Americans and already pay the lowest prices in the United States for drugs. They also pledged to introduce new drugs in the United States at prices comparable to what they ask European countries to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the companies committed to setting up websites to sell some of their drugs directly to American patients, without going through insurance; a site to help patients navigate those company websites, TrumpRx.gov, is expected to become operational later this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effects of those pricing deals are likely to be limited, at least in the short term, because they do not cut the prices that drugmakers currently offer to employers, private insurers and other government programs. Nor do they address the high out-of-pocket drug costs for most American patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president is responding to the many people who are talking to him about the problems in health care,” said Dr. Mehmet Oz, the administrator of the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services, adding: “People are complaining about drug prices. We have a framework for addressing that. They complain about insurance premiums in general, not just in the A.C.A. They are complaining about the lack of accountability of big insurance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he described the proposals, Dr. Oz referred to the document as both a “framework” and a “plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a beautiful framework, and that’s why — it’s a health care plan that I think we can celebrate when we’re done.” he said. “That’s what makes it great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bipartisan group of Senators is continuing to negotiate on legislation to extend Obamacare subsidies, but congressional leaders seem uninterested. Republicans passed major Medicaid cuts as part of their major tax and domestic policy legislation this summer. But there has been little appetite among congressional leaders for another major health care bill.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-health-care-plan.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:06:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ICE’s No. 2 Official Leaves to Run for the House in Ohio</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/pol-sheahan-zgbl/pol-sheahan-zgbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a moment when President Trump’s immigration crackdown has inflamed political tensions, one of the top enforcers of his effort to deport undocumented immigrants is leaving his administration to run for Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madison D. Sheahan, 28, the deputy director of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, announced on Thursday that she would enter the Republican primary race to oppose Representative Marcy Kaptur, a 22-term Democrat who represents a northwest Ohio district that Mr. Trump won in the last two presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her announcement video, Ms. Sheahan called herself “a Trump conservative” and focused on her work helping carry out the president’s deportation agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In less than one year at ICE, I’ve stopped more illegal immigration than Marcy Kaptur has in her 43 years in Washington,” Ms. Sheahan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How top of mind Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown remains for voters come November will be one of the biggest question of the midterm elections. Polling so far suggests that while Americans generally favor tighter immigration policies, they believe Mr. Trump is going too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A CNN survey released Wednesday found that 51 percent of Americans said ICE enforcement actions were making cities less safe, compared with 31 percent who perceived an increase in safety. The fatal shooting of a Minneapolis woman by an ICE officer has touched off nationwide protests and renewed calls from some liberal Democrats to abolish the agency and impeach Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kaptur, 79, was first elected to represent the Toledo area in northwest Ohio in 1982, and she coasted to re-election every two years before Ohio Republicans redrew what had been a safe Democratic district into a competitive one before the 2022 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, she won by less than a percentage point against Derek Merrin, who at the time served in the Ohio legislature. On the same ballot, Mr. Trump carried the district by seven points against Vice President Kamala Harris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Merrin announced another challenge to Ms. Kaptur in June. Several other Republicans have entered the primary, including Josh Williams, a state representative from Toledo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before coming to Washington, Ms. Sheahan worked as a political aide to Ms. Noem when she was South Dakota’s governor and as secretary of the Louisiana Department of Wildlife and Fisheries. Ms. Noem praised Ms. Sheahan as a “terrific leader” in a statement to Fox News.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats professed confidence that Ms. Kaptur would prevail, but they steered clear of addressing Ms. Sheahan’s immigration enforcement credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Voters are tired of the self-dealing corruption and culture of lawlessness they’ve seen over the last year,” said Kegan Zimmermann, Ms. Kaptur’s campaign manager. “They want a leader focused on affordability and real results, and Marcy Kaptur consistently works across the aisle to deliver both.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan’s departure from the agency comes as the Trump administration carries out an immigration enforcement blitz in Minnesota, which ICE has called its “largest operation to date.” Roughly 3,000 federal agents and officers are being deployed to the Minneapolis region as part of the effort, which administration officials have said is meant to crack down on illegal immigration and fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The operation has led to clashes between protesters and law enforcement officers. Local officials in Minneapolis have urged immigration officers to leave the city, saying their efforts have sowed chaos. Trump administration officials have pledged that federal agents will remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheahan has repeatedly defended the agency’s enforcement operations, saying they are necessary to remove people in the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is taking the stand and making sure that we’re enforcing the law as it’s written with the support of Secretary Noem leading the way to make sure we get these dangerous criminals removed from our community,” Ms. Sheahan said in an interview with Fox News in September.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/madison-sheahan-ice-ohio-house-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:07:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Runaway Emu Leads Florida Corporal in 45-Minute Police Chase</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/runaway-emu-florida-video.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/arts/_-_high/_-_high-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each day that Cpl. Thomas Keisler reports to work at the sheriff’s office in St. Johns County, Fla., there is a chance he’ll come face to face with an animal on the road. In his 25 years of working in a county with farmland and rural areas, he’s seen officers encounter horses, goats, pigs, cows, turkeys and ducks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But last Friday brought a new creature to his patch: a runaway emu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporal was sent to wrangle one bobbing along a county road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s certainly different than coming across a horse or a cow because it was literally like trying to restrain a miniature velociraptor,” Corporal Keisler said in a phone interview on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he got the call about the loose bird, he underestimated what it would take to get the situation under control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agricultural deputies usually respond to that type of call, he said, but they were in training when the emu went on the road. “I figured I can handle something like this oversized turkey,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How hard could it be, after all, to grab a large and flightless bird? According to body-camera footage, which was released by the sheriff’s office on Wednesday, considerably harder than expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler and the emu, named Tina, would ultimately spend about 45 minutes together. The footage shows only about two minutes of their entanglement, which appears mutually frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, Tina walks at an unhurried pace along the county road as the corporal tries to get her to come toward him. Corporal Keisler even sounds upbeat, but as the video continues, the occasional deep sigh is audible. Tina just keeps sauntering away. At one point, Corporal Keisler has his hands on Tina. She runs away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An emu like Tina, who had escaped from a farm, is not so easy to catch. Though emus can’t fly with their tiny, useless wings, they have powerful legs and will use their heavy feet to strike, according to the San Diego Zoo Wildlife Alliance. Emus are the second-largest bird in the world, after ostriches, and can be from 4.9 to 6.2 feet tall and weigh from 66 to 121 pounds. Adult female emus are larger and heavier than males.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler said that his past experience with animals had proved to be pretty useless in apprehending Tina. “We don’t get emu combat training and restraining for some reason, or I’ve never had that,” he said. “Maybe I missed that day of training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toward the end of their battle, Corporal Keisler put handcuffs on Tina’s legs because she had ripped holes in his uniform and he needed to stop her from kicking him. “That was really the only option that I had because she had cornered herself in an area that was going to be very difficult to bring her out,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, Tina’s owner knew her bird was on the loose and was able to meet the corporal and the bird under arrest. The sheriff’s office did not say where the bird is usually housed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tina calmed down immediately when she was reunited with her owner, the corporal said. “The owner brought her some food, and it was the most gentle creature I’ve seen,” he said, “but it’s not what it showed me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporal Keisler was happy that the owner was there, too, and said of Tina, “I think we were both kind of over each other at that point.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/runaway-emu-florida-video.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:58:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Verizon Offers $20 Credit to Users Affected by Outage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/verizon-outage-issues-credit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-verizon-lzmf/15xp-verizon-lzmf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon said on Thursday that it would credit $20 to customers affected by the widespread outage that disrupted cellular and data service for over six hours on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage began to draw widespread attention around 12:30 p.m. Eastern and persisted into the evening. Phones on the network displayed “SOS” in the status bar where the cellular antenna icon typically appears. A feature that allows users to make calls over Wi-Fi also appeared to be down. Some customers complained online that their service was briefly restored, only to lose it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage reached a peak of more than 170,000 concurrent reports of disrupted service early Wednesday afternoon, according to Downdetector, an outage-tracking site. Verizon, with 146.1 million subscribers in the United States, is the country’s largest mobile carrier and one of the biggest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday afternoon, Christina Moon Ashraf, a Verizon spokeswoman, blamed “a software issue” for the disruption, adding that the company was conducting a full review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday, we did not meet the standard of excellence our customers expect and that we expect of ourselves,” Ms. Moon Ashraf said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said that affected customers could log into the myVerizon app to accept a $20 account credit and that they would be notified by text message when the credit was available. That covers, on average, multiple days of service, she said, adding that business customers would be contacted directly about their credits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This credit isn’t meant to make up for what happened,” Ms. Moon Ashraf said. “No credit really can. But it’s a way of acknowledging our customers’ time and showing that this matters to us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verizon’s website said Thursday that customers still encountering problems with their service should restart their devices to reconnect to the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the outage was most likely wider than reported by websites that track disruptions to communications and utility services, according to Lee W. McKnight, an associate professor in the School of Information Studies at Syracuse University, who researches wireless grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outage left customers frustrated from coast to coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim Garrity, a civil rights lawyer in Tallahassee, Fla., said he was questioning witnesses in an employment discrimination case on Wednesday when he lost service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I use my iPhone frequently to quickly search for information bearing on the witnesses’ answers while the examination is in progress,” he said. “The disruption severely interfered with my ability to conduct examinations throughout the day, and further prevented me from speaking with my client.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said other lawyers in his office who reported the same difficulties were unable to reach clients and, in one case, unable to participate in a video court hearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nichole Gantshar, who lives in North Carolina but works for a theater in California, said that working remotely meant “my phone is my life.” She said she was able to do most of her work by using Wi-Fi, but once she stopped receiving texts, she could not do anything that required two-factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Many of my daily tasks were completely stopped,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the $20 credit, she said that it was “a nice, but hollow, gesture and it doesn’t make up for the poor communications.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“More important to me as a customer, I want to know what happened, what they are going to do to prevent this in the future, and how they are going to improve communications with customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/verizon-outage-issues-credit.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:32:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nick Reiner Was in a Mental Health Conservatorship in 2020</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/nick-reiner-conservatorship-schizophrenia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/16/multimedia/15nat-reiner-mental-health/16reiner-promo-7pm-ctzq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Reiner, who has been charged with the murder of his parents, Rob Reiner and Michele Singer Reiner, was placed into a yearlong mental health conservatorship in 2020, according to two people with knowledge of the legal arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A clerk with the Los Angeles Superior Court said the conservatorship ended in 2021. Steven Baer, a licensed fiduciary who was appointed as the conservator for Mr. Reiner, said mental illness “is an epidemic that is widely misunderstood and this is a horrible tragedy.” Both people declined to provide further details about the arrangement, citing confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revelation of the conservatorship underscores the severity of the mental health challenges Mr. Reiner faced in recent years, issues that are likely to be central to his legal defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Reiner, the director of movies such as “This Is Spinal Tap” and “The Princess Bride,” and his wife were found stabbed to death in their Los Angeles home on Dec. 14. If Nick Reiner were convicted of two counts of first-degree murder, he could be sentenced to life in prison without parole or the death penalty. He is being represented by a public defender and has not entered a plea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner, 32, has a serious mental illness and had struggled in the weeks before his arrest with a change in his medication, two other people familiar with his health told The New York Times on the condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive medical information. One of those people said he had been diagnosed at different times with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The medication Mr. Reiner had been taking was effective, the other person said, but side effects led him to switch to a new medication about a month before his parents were killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Los Angeles County public defender’s office declined to comment, as did a representative for the district attorney’s office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Mr. Reiner, who had battled drug addiction starting in his teenage years, had been in a conservatorship indicates that a judge determined he had a “grave disability,” meaning he was unable to provide for his basic personal needs for food, clothing or shelter as a result of a mental health disorder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have to be pretty severe to be placed on a mental health conservatorship in California,” said Lee Blumen, a lawyer with expertise in such cases. “Of all the people who come into this system, a very small group of people actually get placed on conservatorship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner was put under what is known as an L.P.S. conservatorship, based on a 1967 law — the Lanterman-Petris-Short Act — that established a new process for involuntary psychiatric treatment in California. It is distinct from the system that is commonly used to take over medical and financial decision-making for people with dementia or a developmental disability; that system drew significant scrutiny for its use in controlling the affairs of the pop star Britney Spears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L.P.S. conservatorships typically originate from an involuntary psychiatric hospitalization and are initiated by a doctor. In Los Angeles County, officials from the Office of the Public Guardian then assess whether a conservatorship is warranted and make their case to a judge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system allows a professional conservator or a person close to the patient, such as a family member, to make decisions about medical treatment, including psychiatric medications. It lasts one year, after which the conservator has the opportunity to try to renew it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear why Mr. Reiner’s conservatorship did not last beyond one year. The county’s Department of Mental Health, which oversees the public guardian’s office, declined to comment or provide any documentation from the legal proceedings, citing patient confidentiality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner had long struggled with drug addiction and spoken about it publicly, co-writing a 2016 movie that was directed by his father and was loosely based on the family’s experience with his heroin and cocaine use. He had been in drug treatment about 18 times as a teenager, circling through residential facilities across the country and sometimes experiencing homelessness amid conflict with his parents about returning to rehab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has alluded to broader behavioral health issues, saying in an interview alongside his father that “it was more than drugs — it’s really always about more than that.” But he and his family have not spoken publicly about his psychiatric diagnosis or treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schizophrenia is a severe brain disorder characterized by abnormal thinking, often involving delusions, paranoia or hallucinations. Schizoaffective disorder combines symptoms of schizophrenia with mood episodes, which can be manic or depressive. Both disorders are usually managed with a combination of medications and therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most antipsychotic medications work by blocking receptors for the neurotransmitter dopamine, which affects functions like motivation, reward, mood, attention and sleep. In most patients, they can reduce symptoms like hallucinations and paranoia to a manageable level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they have serious side effects including weight gain, which contributes to a high rate of cardiac disease and early death among people with psychotic illnesses. Many patients stop taking the medications, saying that they leave them sluggish and unmotivated. Researchers have found that as many as half of patients do not take antipsychotic drugs as prescribed, often leading to relapse and hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking generally, any switch in medication for a disorder like schizophrenia is best undertaken over several weeks, said Dr. Demian Rose, a professor of psychiatry and behavioral sciences at the University of California, San Francisco. A slow “cross taper” helps ensure that the new medication is effective and that the old medication is not withdrawn too quickly, he said, adding that discontinuing an antipsychotic medication after long use can induce withdrawal symptoms like insomnia, agitation and restlessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reiner is being held at the Twin Towers Correctional Facility, a county jail in downtown Los Angeles. When his previous lawyer, Alan Jackson, left the case last week for reasons he did not provide, he told reporters that “pursuant to the law in California, Nick Reiner is not guilty of murder.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments indicated that Mr. Jackson may have been preparing a defense centered on mental health. It is unclear whether Mr. Reiner’s current counsel, a public defender, will take a similar approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nathan J. Hochman, the Los Angeles County district attorney, told reporters this month that he was confident a jury would ultimately convict Mr. Reiner for the “brutal murders of his parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering the mental health issues at play, Mr. Reiner’s counsel will have to assess whether he is competent to understand the court proceedings or help with his own defense. Questioning his competency would initiate a process that involves medical examinations and culminates in a decision by a judge or jury. It can take months or years of medical treatment and court proceedings for a defendant to be found competent to stand trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Reiner is deemed competent, he can seek to prove at trial that he is not guilty by reason of insanity. In such cases, the defense must convince a jury that mental health problems made the defendant unable to understand past actions and incapable of distinguishing right from wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But winning acquittals in such cases is rare, said John Kip Cornwell, a law professor at Seton Hall who has expertise in criminal cases involving mental health issues. It can be challenging, he said, to prove that someone, even when experiencing psychosis and paranoia, did not have some understanding that killing a person was wrong. Juries can also be unwilling to let violent crimes go unpunished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Jurors want, instinctively, for justice to be served,” Professor Cornwell said, “and they’re uncomfortable letting someone be found ‘not guilty’ when an innocent victim was killed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If jurors reach a verdict of not guilty by reason of insanity, it means they decided the defendant committed a crime but cannot be held legally responsible. The defendant would typically be confined in a state-run psychiatric hospital and can eventually petition the court for release. That requires convincing a judge that the person does not pose a danger to the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shawn Hubler contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/nick-reiner-conservatorship-schizophrenia.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:43:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did a Supreme Court Loss Embolden Trump on the Insurrection Act?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-insurrection-act.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-insurrection-assess-lfck/15dc-insurrection-assess-lfck-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Brett M. Kavanaugh sometimes says the quiet part out loud. He did that last month when the Supreme Court refused to let President Trump deploy National Guard troops in Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision was a rare loss for the administration at the court, and it seemed to prompt Mr. Trump to abandon his efforts to deploy troops in Illinois, Oregon and California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Justice Kavanaugh, in a footnote in a concurring opinion, suggested that the ruling could be a speed bump on the road to greater presidential power. He pointed to the possibility of Mr. Trump invoking a different law, the Insurrection Act, to send more conventional military troops to American cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a month later, Mr. Trump suggested he might do exactly that in response to violence and protests in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the corrupt politicians of Minnesota don’t obey the law and stop the professional agitators and insurrectionists from attacking the Patriots of I.C.E., who are only trying to do their job, I will institute the INSURRECTION ACT, which many Presidents have done before me,” he wrote on Thursday on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his own social media post hours earlier, Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, had called the opposition to immigration raids in the state a “Minnesota insurrection.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has long floated the possibility of invoking the act, and he did not need a sentence in a footnote to give him any ideas. But Justice Kavanaugh’s statement did make plain that the Supreme Court’s action in blocking one kind of deployment could set the stage for other, more aggressive ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump relied on a different law to order National Guard troops to cities last summer, an obscure measure adopted in 1903 and 1908 that said deployments were allowed for three reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One, concerning foreign invasions, plainly did not apply to the events in Illinois. The second permissible reason for deploying the Guard was if a rebellion was underway, or if there was danger of one. That is a stretch, and the majority did not cite it, much less discuss it. The court’s order focused on the third reason: the president’s right to deploy the National Guard if he is unable to execute laws “with regular forces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five justices joined the unsigned majority opinion, which rejected the Trump administration’s position that “regular forces” referred to civilian law enforcement like Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents. Instead, the majority said, the term referred to the military. Since there had been no showing that those forces would be unable to execute the laws, the administration lost — at least for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh voted with the majority but did not sign its opinion, and accepted only part of its reasoning. Such a “concurrence in the judgment” is unusual in cases decided on the court’s emergency docket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking for himself, Justice Kavanaugh surveyed the legal landscape and said what the majority had left unstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As I read it,” he wrote, “the court’s opinion does not address the president’s authority under the Insurrection Act.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam LiptakSupreme Court reporter&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I try to make the Supreme Court accessible to readers. I strive to distill and translate complex legal materials into accessible prose, while presenting fairly the arguments of both sides and remaining alert to the political context and practical consequences of the court’s work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Insurrection Act, a set of laws adopted in the nation’s first century, authorizes the president to use the National Guard or more traditional armed forces to quell widespread public unrest. It seems to give him substantial leeway in determining when circumstances warrant invoking it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law repeatedly says the president can use force “as he considers necessary,” for instance. And a leading precedent, Martin v. Mott, from 1827, said that “the authority to decide whether the exigency has arisen belongs exclusively to the president.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If lawfully invoked, the Insurrection Act would also seem to satisfy the Posse Comitatus Act, a bedrock 1878 law that prohibits the use of the military for law enforcement unless authorized by Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Insurrection Act has been invoked throughout the nation’s history, typically at the request of local officials. It was last used in 1992, following riots in Los Angeles in the wake of the acquittals of four white police officers accused of beating Rodney King, a Black motorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military has also been deployed under the act to address labor disputes, conflicts with Native Americans, looting after natural disasters, and to enforce court orders in the civil rights era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should Mr. Trump invoke the Insurrection Act to send troops to Minneapolis or other cities over the objections of local officials, there will certainly be court challenges, and the Supreme Court may well have another chance to consider what Justice Neil M. Gorsuch in his dissent in the Illinois case called a fraught and grave question: “When, if ever, may the federal government deploy the professional military for domestic law enforcement purposes consistent with the Constitution?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh’s concurring opinion, on the other hand, said the Constitution itself may provide a source of presidential power to deploy troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The court’s opinion does not address or purport to disturb the president’s long-asserted Article II authority to use the U.S. military (as distinct from the National Guard) to protect federal personnel and property and thereby ensure the execution of federal law,” Justice Kavanaugh wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He cited with approval an essay in October by Jack Goldsmith, a law professor at Harvard and an authority on executive power. The essay’s title: “President Trump Holds the Legal Cards on the Use of the Military in the Domestic Sphere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Kavanaugh all but suggested that the challengers’ victory in the Illinois case was Pyrrhic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One apparent ramification of the court’s opinion is that it could cause the president to use the U.S. military more than the National Guard to protect federal personnel and property in the United States,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Goldsmith, for his part, wrote that litigation over any invocation of the Insurrection Act was inevitable, and that the Trump administration, against all odds, may find a way to lose it. But, he wrote, that will not be easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every single word of the Insurrection Act will be intensely contested in court should the president invoke it,” Professor Goldsmith wrote. “And given the administration’s tendency to blunder, to bully, to overstep and to develop factual predicates inadequately, not to mention the president’s always-legally unhelpful social media activity, litigation might be tough and victory for the administration in every instance cannot be assumed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after the Illinois decision landed, Professor Goldsmith wrote in a blog post that the Supreme Court had closed one door and opened another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yesterday’s defeat,” he wrote, “could provide ‘cover’ for the Trump administration to go the Insurrection Act route.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-insurrection-act.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:01:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minneapolis Schools Allow Students to Learn Online Amid ICE Fears</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-schools-online-learning-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15minneapolis-shooting-reporter-update18-mhcq/15minneapolis-shooting-reporter-update18-mhcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several of Minnesota’s largest school districts, including those of Minneapolis and St. Paul, are offering students the option to learn remotely amid a federal immigration crackdown that has left many families on edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Minneapolis, where 37-year-old Renee Good was fatally shot by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent last week, students will have the option to learn online until Feb. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The school district in St. Paul said it would offer an online option starting next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Over the past several days, I have received hundreds of messages about offering a temporary virtual learning option for students who do not feel comfortable coming to school right now,” said St. Paul’s schools superintendent, Stacie Stanley, in a video message on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Paul’s school district, the state’s second largest, is home to a significant immigrant population. Many students speak Spanish, Hmong, Somali or another foreign language at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About half of Spanish-speaking students in St. Paul and a quarter of Somali-speaking students were absent from school last Friday, as tensions escalated in the aftermath of Ms. Good’s death, according to district data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minneapolis Public Schools declined to make attendance data available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration launched an immigration enforcement operation in the Twin Cities, primarily focused on Somali immigrants, in December, and last week, ICE announced it was amping up its presence in the Minneapolis area in its “largest operation to date.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials have said that ICE does not target or raid schools, though the administration has rescinded Biden-era guidance that limited immigration enforcement activities in or near “sensitive” locations, such as schools, churches and hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research has shown that immigration raids can lead to increased student absences, hurting student achievement and opportunities to learn, even when they do not occur on school grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation in the Minneapolis area has been especially tense since Ms. Good was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol agents clashed with protesters outside a Minneapolis high school last week, hours after the shooting. In Robbinsdale, a northwest suburb, school officials said that ICE agents detained a parent at a bus stop on Wednesday morning while the parent was dropping a child off for school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Fridley, a district of about 2,700 students north of Minneapolis, roughly a third of students have been absent so far this week, according to the superintendent, Brenda Lewis. The district has a significant Hispanic and Somali population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Students are terrified to come to school,” Dr. Lewis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The district is planning to offer an online option starting next week.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/minneapolis-schools-online-learning-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:48:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Arkansas Rescinds Choice of Law School Dean Over Transgender Stance</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw/15nat-arkansas-law-gkbw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a week after naming a new dean, the University of Arkansas Law School withdrew the appointment, saying on Wednesday that the decision was based on “feedback from key external stakeholders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appointee, Emily Suski, a legal scholar at the University of South Carolina, had been selected after a lengthy public search, and the university’s provost, Indrajeet Chaubey, praised her work on medical partnerships to help low-income children when the choice was announced on Jan. 9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback that derailed the appointment, members of the state legislature said, was related to her signature on an amicus brief filed with the Supreme Court last year in support of transgender student athletes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Sarah Huckabee Sanders of Arkansas supported the decision to withdraw the offer, according to her spokesman, Sam Dubke. “Governor Sanders appreciates the University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, for reaching the common sense decision on this matter in the best interest of students,” Mr. Dubke said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief that Ms. Suski signed was filed in a case that was argued this week before the Supreme Court. Dan Sullivan, an Arkansas state senator, said the views expressed in the brief were inconsistent with Arkansas law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you look at some of her opinions to the Supreme Court and amicus briefs, I think she has not reflected the laws of the state of Arkansas,” said Mr. Sullivan, a Republican from Jonesboro who applauded the decision to rescind the offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arkansas was the first state to ban gender-affirming medical care for minors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episode is an example of how politics has increasingly been influencing university decisions about faculty hiring, which were once the exclusive purview of academics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of the nation’s highly charged political environment has been felt primarily in the selection of university presidents, including an episode last year at the University of Florida. The school’s board chose Santa Ono, a former president of the University of Michigan, who was criticized by conservatives for his past support of diversity initiatives. The board’s decision was overruled by a statewide board of political appointees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But political pressures are also influencing searches for deans and even professors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, universities have begun to treat job searches, which were once fairly public, as carefully guarded secrets, in order to avoid putting prospective hires in awkward positions if they are rejected. At Arkansas, however, the search for a new law school dean was conducted publicly, with four top candidates making presentations in open meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Arkansas, which had issued a statement Wednesday saying that its offer to Ms. Suski had been withdrawn, said Thursday it had no additional statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski, currently an associate dean at the University of South Carolina, issued a written statement on Thursday saying she was “disappointed and hurt by the university’s decision to rescind my contract.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have been informed that the decision was not in any way a reflection of my qualifications to serve as dean,” she wrote, “but rather the result of influence from external individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski’s résumé includes work as a staff attorney for the Legal Aid Justice Center in Charlottesville, Va. Her teaching and legal expertise have been focused on health, poverty and education law, including Title IX, a federal civil rights law that bans sex-based discrimination in education programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amicus brief that she signed along with 16 other legal scholars made a narrowly focused argument on the question of whether the sex assigned at birth should be the sole determining factor in decisions about which sports teams students can compete on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brief argued that the case before the Supreme Court should be sent back to the lower courts for further review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Democratic state representative in Arkansas, Nicole Clowney, said in a telephone interview that the offer to Ms. Suski was rescinded after a few state legislators and one executive-branch official became aware that Ms. Suski had signed the brief, and then threatened the university’s funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Clowney, who represents Fayetteville and teaches at the law school, said she saw the decision as a free-speech issue, and added that Ms. Suski was eminently qualified for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker of the state House of Representatives, Brian Evans, a Republican, issued a statement saying his office was not involved in the decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Suski had been offered a five-year contract with total annual compensation of $350,000, according to documents reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its announcement Wednesday, the law school praised Ms. Suski, but said it had “decided to go in a different direction.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/university-of-arkansas-dean-emily-suski-transgender.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:44:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pentagon Will ‘Refocus’ Military Publication Stars and Stripes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/us/politics/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart/15trump-news-starsandstripes-topart-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon on Thursday said it planned to commandeer Stars and Stripes, a government-funded newspaper that covers the military, and align it with official department messaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will modernize its operations, refocus its content away from woke distractions that syphon morale, and adapt it to serve a new generation of service members,” Sean Parnell, the chief Pentagon spokesman, wrote in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It will focus on warfighting, weapons systems, fitness, lethality, survivability, and ALL THINGS MILITARY. No more repurposed DC gossip columns; no more Associated Press reprints.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon’s intervention would be a stark departure from historical precedent at the publication, which describes itself as the “U.S. military’s independent news source.” The organization has long prized its latitude to make editorial decisions free from external interference, including from the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stars and Stripes, often referred to as Stripes, has been published continuously since World War II, with daily papers for U.S. military troops overseas and up-to-the-minute news on stripes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A statement on its website describes its “core values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A news organization must not just cover the news but uncover it. It must follow the story wherever it leads, without allowing preconceived ideas to filter the search for facts or replace the discipline of verification.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pentagon turned down a request to interview Mr. Parnell about the changes. In response to questions, a press official referred to Mr. Parnell’s statement on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Max D. Lederer Jr., the publisher of Stripes, said he knew nothing about the Pentagon’s directive for the publication until after Mr. Parnell’s announcement Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of Stripes’ tradition of operating without any meddling from the military, editor in chief Erik Slavin said, “I wouldn’t have taken this job otherwise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Reid, a former editor in chief of Stripes, said, “You have to think small-town newspaper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The mayor may object to a story, but there was no prior censorship and no direction as to what should and should not be covered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Reid, 78, who left the publication last year, said that Stripes saw fit to cover the panoply of controversies that have cropped up over the years in the U.S. military, including debates about the role of women, transgender people, and instances of racism and sexism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That might be what they described as woke,” said Mr. Reid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Daily Wire, a conservative outlet, reported that under the new plan, half of the material in Stripes will be generated by the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a directive “would definitely change the character and nature of what we’re presenting to the audience,” said Mr. Lederer. That said, the leadership of Stripes is working with little in the way of formal information about the future of its publication. In addition to receiving no advance notification about Thursday’s announcement, there are no meetings scheduled to discuss it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have the Daily Wire to go on right now — I’ll leave it at that,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the Pentagon’s hostility toward “repurposed DC gossip columns,” Mr. Lederer said, “We don’t carry any gossip columns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Controversy engulfed the publication in President Trump’s first term, when the Pentagon tried to cut its $15.5 million in funding. Mr. Trump came to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The United States of America will NOT be cutting funding to @starsandstripes magazine under my watch,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media. “It will continue to be a wonderful source of information to our Great Military!” Stripes draws its budget in part from federal funding and in part from other, traditional revenue streams for newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Washington Post on Wednesday reported that applicants for employment at Stripes faced questions about how they would support Mr. Trump’s policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, the Pentagon introduced a set of binding restrictions that apply to journalists who receive press credentials to report from the military complex. Dozens of journalists with major media outlets surrendered their press badges instead of signing the policy. Department officials subsequently heralded the arrival of a newly credentialed press corps, one populated by pro-Trump commentators and influencers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stripes didn’t have to agonize over whether to sign on to the restrictions because it is not an external media organization. However, it reviewed the restrictions and voluntarily pulled its reporter from the Pentagon hallways. “When we reviewed that, we saw problematic areas like most news organizations affiliated with the Pentagon at the time,” said Mr. Slavin.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/stars-and-stripes-pentagon.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:48:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Forces Seize Sixth Oil Tanker Linked to Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/us-forces-seize-sixth-oil-tanker-linked-to-venezuela.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15trump-news-tanker1-jvtq/15trump-news-tanker1-jvtq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Coast Guard said on Thursday that it had taken control of a tanker that was operating in defiance of the Trump administration’s partial blockade on sanctioned vessels transporting oil from Venezuela, the sixth ship intercepted since December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tanker, originally called the Veronica, was “boarded and seized” in the Caribbean Sea, according to a social media post from the Coast Guard. The post included a video of armed U.S. forces sliding down ropes onto the tanker’s deck from a helicopter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. authorities obtained a warrant to seize the vessel based on its history carrying Iranian oil, which prosecutors maintained was sold to finance terrorism, according to an American official briefed on the seizure and granted anonymity to discuss a sensitive operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Veronica had officially registered as a Russian-flagged vessel last week and had been renamed the Galileo, possibly in an effort to avoid being seized by the United States. The ship also had recently claimed to be registered in Guyana, raising questions about whether it was operating under a valid flag, according to the official. The impounding of the ship could raise tensions with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has sought to take control of Venezuela’s oil industry since the U.S. military captured its leader, Nicolás Maduro, and brought him to the United States to face criminal charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. government has started to broker the sale of as many as 50 million barrels of Venezuelan oil under an agreement with Venezuela’s interim government. Officials say selling the crude will prevent Venezuela’s oil industry from collapsing and stabilize its government and economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Veronica was among the vessels that left Venezuelan waters en masse after Mr. Maduro’s capture on Jan. 3. The ship was not carrying oil at the time, according to data from TankerTrackers.com and Kpler, two companies that track global oil shipments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States sanctioned the ship in 2022 after Russia’s full-scale invasion of Ukraine, and it had previously transported Iranian oil on at least 15 voyages, according to the same companies. Ukraine sanctioned the vessel as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same year, the tanker, then sailing under the name Lana, was detained by Greek authorities while carrying Iranian oil after officials linked it to a Russian entity under European Union sanctions. Although its ownership was later found to have shifted to a different company, Greece held the vessel for more than two months while the United States tried to seize its cargo, prompting Iran to seize two Greek tankers in retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an effort to pressure Mr. Maduro, U.S. forces began seizing oil tankers in the Caribbean in December, including one ship that eluded the Coast Guard and sailed far into the North Atlantic before being captured. It unsuccessfully claimed Russian protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American officials have said they plan to keep commandeering tankers that operate without U.S. permission. The ships are part of a so-called ghost fleet that transport oil from Venezuela, Russia or Iran despite sanctions from the United States and other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As we’ve now demonstrated through multiple boardings, there is no outrunning or escaping American justice — period,” Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem said on social media on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Noem said the pre-dawn operation had been carried out by Coast Guard “tactical teams.” That term could refer to one of two Coast Guard units: the Maritime Security Response Teams, or MSRT, or the Tactical Law Enforcement Teams, or TACLET. Both receive training in what the service calls “high-speed tactics” for boarding noncompliant ships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. Southern Command, which controls military operations in Latin America and the Caribbean, said in a social media post that Marines and sailors from the aircraft carrier U.S.S. Gerald R. Ford had also participated in the mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The International Maritime Organization issues an IMO number, a permanent identification number, that remains associated with a vessel throughout its lifetime unlike a ship’s name, which can change frequently. The ship in this article is the Galileo (9256860, previously known as Pegas, Lana and Veronica).&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/us-forces-seize-sixth-oil-tanker-linked-to-venezuela.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:55:48 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>