<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:34:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Struck Again by Hatred, a Mississippi Temple Says There Is More to Its Story</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/mississippi-beth-israel-temple-judaism.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-mississippi-synagogue-zmjw/20nat-mississippi-synagogue-zmjw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arsonist started the fire in the library, investigators said, incinerating shelves of prayer books and destroying two Torahs. The flames and smoke then spread rapidly through Beth Israel, the oldest synagogue in Mississippi, reaching the congregation’s Tree of Life display, with its ever-growing foliage of brass leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaves were engraved with messages celebrating bar and bat mitzvahs, weddings and the memories of family members and friends who had died. Some simply contained words of gratitude from one congregant to another — a way, as one put it, to recognize someone for “being a mensch.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tree was a prominent manifestation of what Beth Israel has been for more than a century: a refuge, a nucleus of fellowship for Jews in a part of the world where they are a tiny minority that could be overlooked and misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the tree was lost and, for the time being, so was that refuge, as the damage to the building was severe enough to displace the congregation indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s our history right there,” said Michele Schipper, who has worshiped at Beth Israel for some 40 years and could trace her family’s story through the leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attack on Jan. 10 — carried out, investigators said, by a 19-year-old driven by his hatred of Jewish people — has exposed once again the pernicious threat of antisemitism, as attacks and other incidents have increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the aftermath of the fire has been a heartening reminder of something else: The congregation might be small — with just over 140 families — but its members are not alone. They have one another. They also have a kinship with the broader community that has been forged over generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of Christian churches have offered help, including space to worship until the temple is restored. One church was returning a favor: When a group splintered off from a Baptist congregation in the mid-1960s, wanting one that wasn’t segregated, Beth Israel let members use its old temple until they could find a permanent home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not feeling like ‘us against them,’” said Rachel Myers, a leader in the congregation and longtime member. “It’s feeling like ‘all of us against him.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, a civic event originally planned as a sort of pep rally for the city became a vigil for Beth Israel. “In Jackson, we should know better,” Mayor John A. Horhn said as he led the crowd in prayer. “Lord, make our city a place where everyone can worship freely and live without fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate-fueled perpetrators had targeted the synagogue once before. The Ku Klux Klan bombed it in 1967, just months after the congregation finished building the synagogue, in retaliation for its rabbi’s speaking out in favor of racial integration. Then, as now, congregants were forced to reconcile the warmth and camaraderie that defined so much of their experience living in Jackson with a flash of darkness that threatened to eclipse it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s frustration and there’s sadness and there’s anger,” Zach Shemper, the congregation’s president, said. “Being resilient means you acknowledge those feelings, and then you think about the next step.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The congregation dates to 1860, when a group of Jews in Jackson bought land for a cemetery. Next came a simple wooden house of worship, which burned down in 1874. A local newspaper appealed for donations to help “our Jewish neighbors” build the synagogue — one of the earliest signs of the congregation’s becoming part of the city’s social fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From early on, Beth Israel’s leaders were deliberate about connecting with the community around them. That’s why the temple was built in 1967 on Old Canton Road, a strip lined with Christian churches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think that’s a coincidence,” said Stuart Rockoff, the executive director of the Mississippi Humanities Council, who has studied the history of Jews in the South. He is also a member of Beth Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mississippi has one of the smallest Jewish populations in the country, according to the Jewish Virtual Library: fewer than 3,000 people, in a state of nearly three million. It is a deeply Christian place where 100-foot crosses loom over interstate highways, business meetings sometimes begin with prayers offered “in Jesus’ name,” and one of the first questions that new acquaintances ask is, “Where do you go to church?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have to work hard in places like Jackson, Mississippi, to maintain your Judaism,” said Ms. Schipper, a Jackson native and the chief executive of the Goldring/Woldenberg Institute of Southern Jewish Life. It was housed at Beth Israel and was also displaced by the fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members have often had to be ambassadors for their faith and culture. “That’s part of your job, whether you like it or not,” Dr. Rockoff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One tradition is opening their doors to the community every year for the Beth Israel Bazaar, at which matzo ball soup and corned beef are served. When the tradition returned last year for the first time since the pandemic, the temple’s “kugel krewe” made 60 pounds of the noodle variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, the outreach has succeeded. When the “where do you go to church” question comes up, Dr. Rockoff said, “Beth Israel is an acceptable answer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some congregants said that as fears of antisemitism intensified in recent years, they believed their community had a measure of insulation from the worst of it — an assumption that held even immediately after the fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That morning, Ms. Myers and a few other congregants were reviewing security camera footage to send to the fire marshal when a hooded figure suddenly appeared in the frame. She gasped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suspect, who faces federal and state arson charges, was turned into the F.B.I. by his father after he admitted to setting the fire, telling his father that he had “finally got them,” according to an affidavit. He later told investigators that he specifically sought out the temple because of its “Jewish ties,” they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really thought it was an electrical fire,” Ms. Myers said. “That, I think, says a lot about how I’ve been living my Jewish life here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, before the bombing, many Beth Israel members were wary, if not outright opposed, when Rabbi Perry Nussbaum, a Canadian new to the South, visited imprisoned civil rights activists and pushed for an integrated association for the city’s clergy, whom he invited to meet at the temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as the broader Jewish American community took pride in its involvement in the civil rights movement, many Jews in the South kept their distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One explanation was “wanting to keep themselves and their families and livelihoods safe and not make too many waves,” said Rabbi Debra Kassoff, a congregant and community organizer. She learned soon after moving to Mississippi about this history and how it is still being wrestled with, as descendants of that generation balance empathy for the situation they were in and regret that they did not do more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the bombing, white and Black ministers organized a “walk of penance” on Old Canton Road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Penance was an interesting way of framing it,” Dr. Rockoff said, “almost apologizing for the culture that had led to that sort of violence.” A couple months later, the K.K.K. attacked again, setting off explosives at Rabbi Nussbaum’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many larger American cities, Judaism is reflected in a constellation of synagogues and organizations serving different denominations, movements, geographic roots, ethnic and racial histories and political ideologies. In Jackson, a city of about 140,000, they all have to fit in Beth Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everyone recognized that we want to have a place where we can bring our Jewish selves,” Rabbi Kassoff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t mean to make it sound completely idyllic,” she added. “There are disagreements. There are resentments. There are people who stop turning up from time to time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she and others believe that navigating those differences has made the congregation stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening, the congregation’s members gathered again for services for the first time since the attack. They were in someone else’s house of worship, borrowing space from the Baptist church that had once borrowed it from them. No one knew when they could return home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, they were together, and for now, that was enough.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/mississippi-beth-israel-temple-judaism.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:32:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada’s Prime Minister Says There Has Been a ‘Rupture’ in the World Order</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/carney-davos-speech-world-economic-forum.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-HFO-carney-topart-wmbt/20trump-news-HFO-carney-topart-wmbt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada did not mention the United States or President Trump by name in a speech on at the World Economic Forum on Tuesday, but it was clear where he placed the blame for what he called a “rupture” in the world order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will talk today about the breaking of the world order, the end of a pleasant fiction and the beginning of a brutal reality where the geopolitics of the great powers is not subject to any constraint,” said Mr. Carney, who used a mixture of French and English in his address in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we are reminded that we live in an era of great power rivalry,” he said. “That the rules-based order is fading. That the strong do what they can, and the weak suffer what they must.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added, “Let me be direct: We are in the midst of a rupture, not a transition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney, who received a standing ovation, spoke not long after Mr. Trump posted an A.I. image on social media that included a map of American flags superimposed over both Canada and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney, a former investment executive who has served as the governor of Canada and England’s central banks was on familiar ground in Davos. His office estimated that he has attended the global gathering about 30 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday he arrived at a conference in turmoil over the rapidly growing rift between Europe and the United States because of Mr. Trump’s effort to make Greenland, which is controlled by Denmark, an American territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s hostility toward European allies over Greenland, which has included tariff threats, has led many Canadians to fear that he may act on his hope of annexing Canada as the 51st State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland, like the United States, is a neighbor of Canada. Canada and Denmark are members of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and have long been involved in military exercises in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Carney and his cabinet ministers have repeatedly denounced Mr. Trump’s plan, Canada has not joined European countries in sending troops to the island in a gesture of support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech on Tuesday, Mr. Carney said that Canada’s commitment to an article in the NATO treaty that views an attack on any member as an attack on all members was “unwavering.” That article was not written with the consideration that one member would be attacking another. It is also not clear that all NATO members would respond militarily to an attack on another member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada and the United States have a joint command for North American air defense. This week aircraft from both countries are at an American air base in Greenland as part of a regular training exercise that the joint air command said had been approved by Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech Mr. Carney called on medium-size countries like Canada to band together to offset the power of the United States, China and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The middle powers must act together because if you are not at the table, we’re are on the menu,” he said. “Great powers can afford now to go it alone.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/carney-davos-speech-world-economic-forum.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:34:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In U.S. Attorney Standoff, Judges in Virginia Seek to Fill Top Prosecutor Job</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/virginia-us-attorney-halligan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/dc-halligan-lwkb/dc-halligan-lwkb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal judges in the Eastern District of Virginia are seeking applicants to become the U.S. attorney there, signaling that President Trump’s handpicked choice, Lindsey Halligan, has run out of time as the top prosecutor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public request is the latest move in a monthslong standoff between the Trump administration and the judges who sit in that district. The dispute has potential consequences for federal prosecutors around the country because the administration has used a similar personnel maneuver to install others into U.S. attorney positions in Nevada, California, New York and New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, a judge ruled that Ms. Halligan’s appointment was invalid, stating that Mr. Trump and Attorney General Pam Bondi had not followed the law in selecting U.S. attorneys. In September, Mr. Trump forced out Ms. Halligan’s predecessor to install her instead, despite her lack of prosecutorial experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Halligan quickly indicted two of the president’s foes, the former F.B.I. director, James B. Comey, and Letitia James, the New York attorney general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those indictments were thrown out of court in November after a federal judge determined Ms. Halligan’s appointment was unlawful. Since that ruling, some judges in the district have expressed concern and frustration that Ms. Halligan continues to claim she is the U.S. attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a new order, the court noted that Ms. Halligan’s appointment, even if it were valid, expires Tuesday, suggesting once again that the judges expect her to step aside. The court system separately asked for “expressions of interest” from any lawyers interested in being appointed to serve as an interim U.S. attorney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Justice Department did not immediately comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal law allows for the judges in a district without a Senate-confirmed U.S. attorney to select a temporary replacement, and the court’s moves Tuesday suggest it plans to go forward with doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the court did appoint a new U.S. attorney, it is likely that the president would simply fire that person and put his own choice — possibly Ms. Halligan — back in the job.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/virginia-us-attorney-halligan.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:07:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prosecutors Subpoena Minnesota Democrats as Part of Federal Inquiry</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/subpoena-minnesota-democrats-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/dc-minnesota-tzqh/dc-minnesota-tzqh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors issued subpoenas on Tuesday to at least five Democratic officials in Minnesota, ramping up the Justice Department’s investigation into their response to the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown in the state, according to two people familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subpoenas sought documents from Gov. Tim Walz, Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis and Mayor Kaohly Her of St. Paul related to their policies on immigration enforcement efforts in the state. Two Minnesota prosecutors, Keith Ellison, the state attorney general, and Mary Moriarty, the Hennepin County attorney, were also sent similar subpoenas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subpoenas, all of which were formally served on the officials’ offices, represent a significant expansion of the inquiry into Minnesota leaders that was disclosed late Friday. The investigation was initially said to have focused on Mr. Frey and Mr. Walz, who have both criticized the crackdown. But it now appears that prosecutors will also scrutinize other public officials, including Mr. Ellison and Ms. Moriarty, who could open their own inquiries into the fatal shooting in Minneapolis this month of a 37-year-old woman, Renee Good, by a federal immigration agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the subpoenas did not cite a specific criminal statute, the inquiry as a whole was said to center on whether elected officials in Minnesota had conspired to impede the thousands of federal agents who have been in the state since last month looking for undocumented immigrants. But the investigation is likely to run up against stiff pushback for examining political speech and conduct that is traditionally protected by the First Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Ms. Good, an unarmed mother of three, has led to sustained protests against federal agents in Minneapolis. In the immediate aftermath of Ms. Good’s death, Mr. Frey used an expletive to demand that agents leave the city. Mr. Walz has also sharply criticized the agents’ conduct, asking residents to monitor their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Department leaders, in turn, have vowed to arrest anyone impeding the agents’ mission. Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, recently accused Mr. Frey and Mr. Walz of “encouraging violence against law enforcement” and referred to their actions as “terrorism.” But there is no evidence that either man has incited violence — let alone engaged in acts of terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation into the elected Democrats comes as the Justice Department has all but announced that it will not bring charges against Jonathan Ross, the agent who killed Ms. Good. Instead, the department has signaled that it intends to scrutinize possible connections between Ms. Good and her partner, Becca Good, and left-wing protesters in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That decision led to the resignation last week of six prosecutors in the U.S. attorney’s office in Minneapolis. Among those who quit was Joseph H. Thompson, the office’s second in command, who oversaw a sprawling fraud investigation that President Trump and his allies have repeatedly used to criticize Democratic leaders in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal investigators have refused to cooperate with state and local officials like Mr. Ellison and Ms. Moriarty, who have the power to open their own inquiries into Ms. Good’s killing. But the subpoenas they received could further complicate their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Trump administration has started enlisting prosecutors and agents from other states to travel to Minnesota to assist in pursuing criminal cases against protesters they claim have impeded the activities of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents. Over the weekend, Attorney General Pam Bondi pressed U.S. attorneys in Midwestern states to provide personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten federal prosecutors from Michigan have been assigned to work in Minnesota for the time being, according to people familiar with the matter. Additional prosecutors are expected to arrive in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have repeatedly said that ICE agents have been under sustained assault from protesters. But prosecutors have only filed a handful of criminal cases related to the protests since Ms. Good was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department needs additional personnel in part because so many senior prosecutors left the Minneapolis office rather than follow orders from the department’s leaders to conduct a criminal investigation into Ms. Good. The office already faced a significant staff shortage because many prosecutors had left last year as the Trump administration offered buyouts and encouraged prosecutors to quit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try to address the shortage, Justice Department leaders plan to draw staff from six states: Michigan, South Dakota, North Dakota, Iowa, Nebraska and Wisconsin, according to people familiar with the matter and internal department communications.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/subpoena-minnesota-democrats-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:23:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pentagon Hasn’t Been Asked to Plan Greenland Invasion Amid Trump Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/pentagon-greenland-invasion-plans.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-pentagon-greenland-mlpb/20trump-news-pentagon-greenland-mlpb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Nuuk, Greenland, on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/pentagon-greenland-invasion-plans.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 23:24:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>JD Vance and Second Lady Usha Vance Are Expecting Their 4th Child</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/jd-usha-vance-baby-pregnant.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-vance-child-htmf/20trump-news-vance-child-htmf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Vice President JD Vance and his wife, Usha Vance, at the White House in November.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/jd-usha-vance-baby-pregnant.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 17:32:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>DOGE Employees Shared Social Security Data, Court Filing Shows</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/doge-employees-social-security-data.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-ssa-doge-ltmb/20dc-ssa-doge-ltmb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Social Security Administration does not know what data was shared on the server, the Justice Department said.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/doge-employees-social-security-data.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 16:15:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Timothy Busfield Ordered Released From Jail Ahead of Sex Abuse Trial</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/timothy-busfield-charges-release.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20cul-busfield-hearing-gwcf/20cul-busfield-hearing-gwcf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The actor and director Timothy Busfield in 2020. He turned himself into the authorities in Albuquerque last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/timothy-busfield-charges-release.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:27:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>ChongLy Scott Thao, Hmong Immigrant and U.S. Citizen, Arrested by ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/chongly-scott-thao-ice-arrest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/nat-minn-hmong-1-fmkq/nat-minn-hmong-1-fmkq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
ChongLy Scott Thao, a Hmong immigrant and naturalized U.S. citizen, looked out the window of his home as several vehicles with federal agents idled in the street after he was able to return home in St. Paul, Minn.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/chongly-scott-thao-ice-arrest.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:28:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Calls Renee Good Killing a ‘Tragedy’ and Says ICE Agents Will Make Mistakes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-renee-good-ice-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-minneapolis-good-wgvb/20trump-news-minneapolis-good-wgvb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial for Renee Good at the site of her killing.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-renee-good-ice-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:38:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘God Is Very Proud’: Trump Marks Anniversary With a Victory Lap</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-anniversary-briefing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-trump-top-cpkv/20dc-trump-top-cpkv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump tossed aside a 31-page list of his accomplishments during a briefing at the White House on Tuesday but still had plenty to say about the first year of his second term.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-anniversary-briefing.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 18:26:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>House Foreign Affairs Members Call for Machado to Govern Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/house-foreign-affairs-machado-venezuela.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-machado-capitol-hill1-bfth/20trump-news-machado-capitol-hill1-bfth-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
María Corina Machado, the Venezuelan opposition leader, on Capitol Hill on Tuesday, meeting with members of the House Foreign Affairs Committee.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/house-foreign-affairs-machado-venezuela.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 16:45:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Miami Beach Nightclub Is Condemned for Playing Kanye West’s Song ‘Heil Hitler’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/tate-brothers-miami-heil-hitler-kanye-west.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-miamibeach-maps/20xp-miamibeach-maps-mediumSquareAt3X.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Members of the Tate Brothers entourage were seen giving the Nazi salute at the Vendôme night club in Miami Beach on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/tate-brothers-miami-heil-hitler-kanye-west.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 17:25:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Court Record, Official Describes Assault Before ICE Agent Shot Man in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/ice-shooting-minneapolis-charges.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-minnesota-shooting-1-cptq/20nat-minnesota-shooting-1-cptq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal agents near the scene where a man was shot by an agent in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/ice-shooting-minneapolis-charges.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 18:51:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Force One Turns Back With Trump After Electrical Issue</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/air-force-one-trump-turn-around.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21vid-trump-af1-cover/21vid-trump-af1-cover-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane was heading for Switzerland when it turned back for Joint Base Andrews. A White House official said there had been a minor electrical issue.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/air-force-one-trump-turn-around.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 23:52:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuban Immigrant Was Killed in ICE Custody, Family Says in Legal Filing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/cuban-immigrant-death-ice-custody.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-ice-death-1-kmfb/20nat-ice-death-1-kmfb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Camp East Montana, an Immigration and Customs Enforcement detention facility in El Paso.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/cuban-immigrant-death-ice-custody.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 20:28:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Investigations and a Billion-Dollar ‘Shakedown’: How Trump Targeted Higher Education</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-higher-education-2025.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/30/multimedia/00DC-TRUMP-EDUCATION-fhlq/00DC-TRUMP-EDUCATION-fhlq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The president managed to chisel away at the independence of the nation’s top universities by pairing investigations with pre-emptive strikes on federal funding for schools.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-higher-education-2025.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 04:29:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court Considers Trump’s Attempt to Fire Fed Governor Lisa Cook</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-fed-cook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-scotus-hlzq/21dc-scotus-hlzq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Lisa Cook, a Federal Reserve governor, speaking in Washington in November.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/supreme-court-trump-fed-cook.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:05:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NATO brass meet for ‘frank’ talks amid the Greenland feud.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/21/us/trump-davos-greenland-news/nato-brass-meet-for-frank-talks-amid-the-greenland-feud</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21trump-news-nato-chiefs-btjm/21trump-news-nato-chiefs-btjm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Adm. Giuseppe Cavo Dragone, the Italian chair of NATO’s military committee, speaking last year.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/21/us/trump-davos-greenland-news/nato-brass-meet-for-frank-talks-amid-the-greenland-feud</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:05:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court to Weigh Trump’s Bid to Fire Lisa CookSupreme Court to Weigh Trump’s Bid to Fire Lisa Cook</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010651242/supreme-court-to-weigh-trumps-bid-to-fire-lisa-cook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/arts/Colby-Smith-Thumbnail/Colby-Smith-Thumbnail-facebookJumbo.png?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Supreme Court is hearing oral arguments on Wednesday in the case of Lisa Cook, the Federal Reserve governor whom President Trump is trying to fire. Our reporter Colby Smith describes the importance of Cook’s case for the independence of the central bank.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010651242/supreme-court-to-weigh-trumps-bid-to-fire-lisa-cook.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:20:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greenland Shouldn’t Overshadow Ukraine, NATO Chief Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/greenland-ukraine-nato-rutte.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21trump-news-davos-ukraine-hlpk/21trump-news-davos-ukraine-hlpk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mark Rutte, the secretary general of NATO, cautioned about complacency on Ukraine.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/greenland-ukraine-nato-rutte.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:26:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Michele Tafoya Announces Senate Run in Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/michele-tafoya-senate-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/19/multimedia/00pol-tafoya-wfqp/00pol-tafoya-wfqp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Michele Tafoya joins a fledgling Republican primary field in the race to replace Senator Tina Smith, a Democrat who is retiring.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/michele-tafoya-senate-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 04:41:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Brief From Every Living Former Fed Chair Could Sway the Justices</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/fed-governors-lisa-cook.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2017/03/14/upshot/21scotus-cook-fed-amicus/21scotus-cook-fed-amicus-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Former chairs of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve including Alan Greenspan, left, and Janet Yellen, signed the amicus brief.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/fed-governors-lisa-cook.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:11:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s retribution efforts have struggled with mortgage cases.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/21/us/supreme-court-fed-lisa-cook/trumps-retribution-efforts-have-struggled-with-mortgage-cases</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21scotus-cook-fed-indict-topart-vkpw/21scotus-cook-fed-indict-topart-vkpw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Bill Pulte, the director of the Federal Housing Finance Agency, has targeted several rivals of President Trump with investigations into their mortgages.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/21/us/supreme-court-fed-lisa-cook/trumps-retribution-efforts-have-struggled-with-mortgage-cases</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:22:47 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>