<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:58:53 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>White House Wobbles, Distancing Trump From Initial Response to Minnesota Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-nurse-shooting-video.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-new-gpqc/26dc-trump-new-gpqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with broad outcry over the killing of a protester on Saturday in Minneapolis, the White House on Monday tried to distance President Trump from the response of his most senior officials, who had immediately characterized the man fatally shot by federal agents as a “domestic terrorist” who was “brandishing” a gun, before video evidence undercut their charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, notably did not defend the rhetoric of White House officials, including Stephen Miller, the deputy chief of staff, and Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, who were the most vocal in spreading false accusations against the victim, Alex Pretti. Mr. Pretti was shot roughly 10 times by immigration agents after he was apparently filming them with his camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was licensed to carry a gun in Minnesota, but video from several angles shows he never pulled one, and his hands were visible as he was shot in the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White House officials clearly understood that the killing, the second of an American citizen protesting the presence of Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Minneapolis, posed one of the gravest political threats to Mr. Trump since his inauguration just a little over a year ago. Yet they seemed frozen in place, unwilling to walk back the statements by Mr. Miller and Ms. Noem, which were widely repeated throughout the administration, while sending Ms. Leavitt out to insist that “we will let the facts lead and we will let the facts play out in this investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They provided no evidence to back up the statements by the two officials, who have become the face of Mr. Trump’s efforts to deport undocumented immigrants. And while Ms. Leavitt would not contradict the two officials, she insisted to reporters that “nobody in the White House, including President Trump, wants to see people getting hurt or killed in America’s streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also declined to defend the attacks on Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This has obviously been a very fluid and fast-moving situation throughout the weekend,” Ms. Leavitt said. “As for President Trump, whom I speak for, he has said that he wants to let the investigation continue and let the facts lead in this case.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For two days, the White House has struggled to contain the fallout from the killing. Democrats have been withering in their criticism of the administration’s actions, and Republicans have begun joining calls for a fair investigation into the killing. Even the National Rifle Association, long an ally of Republican administrations, has defended Mr. Pretti, who had a concealed-carry permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bipartisan pushback on Capitol Hill now risks another government shutdown as lawmakers threaten to withhold funding for ICE after the killing of Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Mr. Trump dispatched his border chief, Tom Homan, to oversee the immigration enforcement operation in Minneapolis and backed off his attacks on Minnesota’s governor after a phone call with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Homan takes over that job, it was not clear what would become of Gregory Bovino, the official in charge of Mr. Trump’s Border Patrol operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Leavitt did not directly answer a question about whether Mr. Bovino would remain in Minneapolis after Mr. Homan’s arrival. She called Mr. Bovino “a great professional” who “is going to very much continue to lead Customs and Border Patrol throughout and across the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his latest pivot, Mr. Trump moved from castigating Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota as a cause of the violence in Minneapolis and declared that, in a call, they “seemed to be on a similar wavelength.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said on social media that Mr. Walz was “happy that Tom Homan was going to Minnesota.” Mr. Trump announced earlier in the day that Mr. Homan would be his personal representative overseeing ICE operations in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a sharp contrast from his weekend pronunciations, in which the president blamed Mr. Walz and other Minnesota Democrats for Mr. Pretti’s death. Those remarks echoed his comments after the fatal shooting by federal agents of a Minneapolis woman, Renee Good, this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he hailed operations in Washington and other cities as a “tremendous success,” Mr. Trump said crime in Minnesota was “way down.” He added, “Both Governor Walz and I want to make it better!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Mr. Walz’s office described the call as “productive” and said the two men had discussed broader issues that have been at the center of the state’s complaints about the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the governor’s office, Mr. Walz told Mr. Trump that impartial investigations into the two killings were needed, and he called for a reduction in the number of federal agents in Minnesota. Mr. Trump agreed to ensure a fair investigation and to look into reducing the number of agents, the governor’s office said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even as Mr. Trump tried to mend fences with Mr. Walz, Ms. Leavitt continued the administration’s previous strategy of arguing that the governor and Democrats in Minnesota bore the blame for the chaos. “This tragedy occurred as a result of a deliberate and hostile resistance by Democrat leaders in Minnesota for weeks,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration’s reaction to the killing of Mr. Pretti was similar to its initial approach the killing of Ms. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, administration officials rushed to attack the victims and defend the ICE agents before an investigation had taken place. After video emerged raising serious questions about the cause for both killings, White House officials changed their tone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Mr. Trump said the killing of Ms. Good was a “tragedy” about which he “felt terribly,” adding that the immigration agents he had deployed were sometimes “going to make a mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change in tone was stark for the president, who said he had been told that Ms. Good’s father was a strong Trump supporter. No longer did the administration suggest she was a domestic terrorist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You know, when the woman was shot, I felt terribly about it,” he said. “And I understand both sides of it.” He called the shooting “a horrible thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hours after Mr. Pretti’s killing, Mr. Trump referred to him as a “gunman” in a social media post. But after video emerged showing that Mr. Pretti carried a cellphone, and that agents took his legally carried gun from him before shooting him, the White House had a different message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody here at the White House, including the president of the United States, wants to see Americans hurt or killed and losing their lives in American streets,” Ms. Leavitt said on Monday. “And we mourn for the parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ernesto Londoño contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-nurse-shooting-video.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 22:08:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Killings in Minneapolis Invert Usual Dynamic Over Policing the Police</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-killings-federal-state-police.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-states01-photo-kjfl/26dc-states01-photo-kjfl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Protesters in Minneapolis gather near where Alex Pretti was killed. It is rare for state and local police to try to investigate federal law enforcement officials.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-killings-federal-state-police.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:25:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Investigation Into Shooting of Pretti Appears Limited</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/pretti-minneapolis-shooting-dhs-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-dhs-investigate-photo-cgwh/26dc-dhs-investigate-photo-cgwh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration appeared to acknowledge on Monday that its investigation into the killing of a Veterans Affairs nurse, Alex Pretti, by federal agents this weekend was limited to a “use of force” review meant to establish whether government employees had violated training standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a move, disclosed in court filings, would represent a much narrower inquiry focused on tactics and conduct than one that would examine whether federal agents should face criminal charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the administration’s efforts to block a judge from ordering it to preserve evidence, Mark Zito, who leads the Homeland Security Investigations office in St. Paul, Minnesota, provided the court with a sworn statement that noted that his agency, which belongs to the Department of Homeland Security, is investigating the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“H.S.I. is the lead investigatory entity reviewing the use-of-force encounter at issue in this case,” Mr. Zito’s declaration said. “H.S.I. agents tasked with this investigation are required to preserve all evidence collected, including physical evidence collected by other federal agencies, which are then properly transferred to the custody of H.S.I.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota state officials have sought a court order to preserve evidence for their own investigation of the killing of Mr. Pretti, who was repeatedly shot by Border Patrol agents on Saturday. The Trump administration is fighting such an order, claiming that it is already preserving the relevant evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critical terms in Mr. Zito’s statement are “use of force” and “reviewing.” Among federal law enforcement agencies, a use of force review is focused on whether law enforcement personnel followed agency rules and regulations and where and when to use force, and how much force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is distinct from a criminal investigation. F.B.I. agents could, for example, investigate to determine if Mr. Pretti’s civil rights were violated by federal agents acting under color of law, a crime that carries the possibility of a death sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. could also investigate whether Mr. Pretti assaulted or impeded a federal law enforcement officer, although there is limited practical use to such an investigation, given that Mr. Pretti is dead and cannot be charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no indication yet that the F.B.I. is doing either. Whatever the Trump administration investigates, their determinations may not be the last word, since there is no statute of limitations on murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An F.B.I. spokesman declined to comment. A D.H.S. spokeswoman did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Court filings suggest that, so far, the F.B.I.’s involvement is limited to assisting the Department of Homeland Security in its use-of-force review. F.B.I. agents arrived quickly on the scene of Mr. Pretti’s killing and secured his weapon and his phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. has since turned over Mr. Pretti’s phone to Immigration and Customs Enforcement, but not his gun, according to Mr. Zito’s sworn statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.B.I. has not altered or destroyed the collected evidence,” an unidentified F.B.I. agent declared in a sworn statement to the court. It also added that the evidence is secure in the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis office and that no one there “has conducted any analysis, examinations, or interpretations of the collected evidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement does not say whether other F.B.I. personnel, such as forensic experts at their lab in Quantico, Virginia, have examined any evidence, or a digital copy of Mr. Pretti’s phone data. “The F.B.I. will continue to preserve the collected evidence in accordance with the F.B.I.’s policies and procedures for evidence retention,” it noted. “In no event will any collected evidence be destroyed before resolution of this investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately, some of the Border Patrol agents at the scene of the killing were wearing body cameras, and that footage has been retained, according to court filings. Many Border Patrol agents do not wear body cameras, so it is unclear how much footage there may be, or how much can be gleaned from it.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/pretti-minneapolis-shooting-dhs-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:23:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Minneapolis Means for the Country and Its Politics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-protests-midterm-politics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/newsletter-1-gjqf/newsletter-1-gjqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A young asylum-seeking family, terrified to go outside or even to look out of the window. Parents of elementary schoolers, struggling to explain to their children why their Latino classmates were staying home. Another fatal shooting of a U.S. citizen by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the painful and extraordinary scenes my colleagues in Minneapolis are documenting during the federal immigration crackdown there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a fast-moving, fluid and unpredictable situation, as the sudden move to reassign Greg Bovino shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But increasingly, one thing seems clear: The country is now paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moderate Democratic lawmakers have called for Kristi Noem, who leads the Department of Homeland Security, to step aside or to be impeached. At least some Republicans have broken with the Trump administration in expressing grave concerns or, in some cases, urging a full independent investigation into the fatal shooting on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Former Presidents Barack Obama and Bill Clinton, who rarely weigh in on the day-to-day moves of the Trump administration, cast the moment as an inflection point for the country, with core American values and freedoms under real threat. And over a weekend when many Americans were snowed in, plenty of people around the country who don’t usually post about politics took to social media to talk about Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sense of all of this, I turned to my colleague Charles Homans, who just wrote a deeply reported piece capturing how the Trump administration’s immigration operations are stoking fear and chaos across Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s well worth reading in full. In the meantime, here’s our conversation, edited and condensed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Glueck: In your story, you mentioned that many of the people pushing back aren’t what we might usually think of as activists. Who are they, and how would you describe them politically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Homans: I was struck by what a broad cross-section of Minneapolis liberals and progressives I saw participating in one way or another in the resistance to the federal deployment. The Twin Cities are overwhelmingly Democratic and have a real culture of political engagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But participation is not the same as activism. Most of these people were not in the streets in 2020 after the murder of George Floyd, for instance, and a lot of them were very ambivalent about the aftermath of his killing in the city. What you are seeing now is a much broader kind of engagement, where even people who are not attending protests or following federal immigration agents with their phones are doing little things through their schools and churches, or with local businesses, to stand in the way of the federal operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: You also wrote about the parents — particularly those with kids attending schools with larger Latino populations, it sounded like — whose “latent politics had been supercharged by a very parental mix of fear and fury.” What does that look like in practice? Is this a newly engaged political demographic?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: In Minneapolis, I think these are people who were pretty politically engaged to begin with. One big question I have, which is a good subject for further reporting, is whether this is the same farther out into the exurbs, where you start getting into constituencies who are more politically mixed and maybe less political in general, but confronting similar circumstances. The raids have happened there, too. They’ve just been less well-documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: Watching from New York, at least, the events in Minneapolis seem to have broken through with parts of the public in a way I’m not sure I’ve seen in the second Trump administration. Is that your sense, too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: It does feel that way. You always want to be careful about over-interpreting these moments in the moment itself. But even before the first fatal shooting by a federal agent in Minneapolis this month, polls had shown approval of Immigration and Customs Enforcement’s tactics really tanking, especially among independents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Americans have contradictory and ambivalent views about immigration, and what should be done to control it. The administration’s tactics and messaging have forced voters to think harder about that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly the biggest factor here is the video that Minnesotans have been gathering. There’s the footage of the shootings themselves, and the administration’s false or misleading accounts of what happened — which have been easy to see through even for people who are not especially engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: How does this moment in Minneapolis compare with the protests there after the murder of George Floyd?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: I asked a lot of people in Minneapolis about that, and the consensus, which I think is true, was that they are extremely different. The George Floyd protests, riots and ensuing debate about defunding or reorganizing the Minneapolis Police Department produced a deep division within the Twin Cities’ Democratic majority that was never really healed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But pretty much none of these people disagree about the federal deployment. And amid all of the fury and alarm of the present moment, there is a very palpable sense of relief among a lot of these people that they are on common ground, at least for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: You mentioned the Defund the Police movement, something Democratic leaders came to see as a huge political liability nationally. Is there any concern among Democrats you talked to that scenes of unrest, or pushes to abolish ICE, could backfire for them politically?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: Minneapolis’s mayor, Jacob Frey, has clearly been trying to keep the Minneapolis Police Department out of the mix as much as possible. And for now, the balance of violence in the footage coming out of the city lies clearly on the side of the federal agents, who have shot and killed two people in the midst of what has been extremely angry but overwhelmingly nonviolent resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does seem that so far, this has kept a lot of the ghosts of 2020 at bay. What is clear on the street in Minneapolis is that this is really a tightrope walk, and I think it is much more so since the second fatal shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KG: Anything I didn’t ask you about on the political front that you think is important for people to understand about Minneapolis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CH: I wrote about this in another piece this month, but I do think that Minnesota’s particular political history, of which the state’s liberals are very proud, is very relevant to how Minneapolitans see what they are doing now, and the stakes of what they are doing. They see themselves as fighting for a civic ideal that is directly under attack by the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A curious demand stuck out in Attorney General Pam Bondi’s letter to Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota over the weekend laying out what must happen to restore “law and order” to the state: Hand over your voter rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My colleague Nick Corasaniti, who covers voting rights and elections, explains why the Trump administration is seeking voters’ private data from states across the country, and the concerns surrounding the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Number&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the percentage of American voters who believe a middle-class lifestyle is out of reach for most people, a New York Times/Siena poll found. It reflects the nation’s pessimistic mood as another midterm election year kicks off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;QUOTE OF THE DAy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s Oscar Hagelsieb, a retired immigration officer and special agent. He voted three times for President Trump but is now feeling anger and despair about the administration’s deployment of his former agency: “It’s completely unfair to the agents who have been put in this position.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ONE LAST THING&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For newly elected mayors, major weather events can pose tough tests of leadership. So far, my colleagues Sally Goldenberg and Dana Rubinstein write, Mayor Zohran Mamdani of New York City has seemed to clear early hurdles with his handling of the snowstorm this weekend. But Gov. Kathy Hochul — his political pal, at least for now — had some feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thanks for helping out our neighbors,” she wrote on social media in response to a video Mamdani shared that showed him trying to help a car stuck in the snow. “But put on a hat!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Homans and Taylor Robinson contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-protests-midterm-politics.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 22:29:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Shootings Pose a Hard Question for the Right: Who’s a Conservative, Really?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-shooting-trump-ice-gop.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-Reversal-ftcw/26minneapolis-ice-Reversal-ftcw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Randy Fine, a hard-right Republican from Florida, has regularly warned about the perils of federal government overreach during his decade-long career in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a state legislator, he described federal Covid-19 vaccination mandates as “tyrannical.” As a member of Congress, he supported the elimination of the Department of Education, stating, “Federal bureaucrats shouldn’t dictate how our kids are taught.” In a 2022 social media post, Mr. Fine, memorably and menacingly, addressed President Joseph R. Biden Jr. over gun control, telling him, “try to take our guns and you’ll learn why the Second Amendment was written in the first place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this weekend, Mr. Fine took to X.com to voice his approval that federal immigration officers in Minneapolis had killed Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old nurse whose filming of immigration officers on Saturday morning turned into a confrontation. The officers shot Mr. Pretti at least 10 times after one of them had removed a holstered gun that he was legally authorized to carry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An armed seditionist attacked federal law enforcement today as they were rounding up foreign invaders in Minneapolis,” Mr. Fine wrote on Saturday, without evidence that Mr. Pretti had been there to attack anyone. “The insurrectionist was put down. Well done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American conservatives have a long history of supporting gun rights and states’ rights, as well as calling for firm restraint on the federal government. And they have criticized the excessive use of federal power in a number of bloody confrontations with recalcitrant citizens, including a white separatist family in Ruby Ridge, Idaho, in 1992, and the Branch Davidians cult the following year in Waco, Texas, both by agents from the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the case of the Minneapolis deployment, the Trump administration and some allies like Mr. Fine have taken positions that seem to contradict some of the bedrock principles of conservatism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deployment, called Operation Metro Surge, would seem like the definition of big-government action. Gov. Tim Walz and Mayor Jacob Frey, both Democrats, vehemently oppose federal intervention, as do many residents of largely liberal Minneapolis. Agents, wearing masks to hide their identities, have forced their way into homes without warrants. They have detained citizens and legal immigrants. And then, there are the killings of Mr. Pretti and Renee Good, the mother of three shot on Jan. 7 while driving her S.U.V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, many Republicans see Mr. Trump’s effort as a fundamentally conservative strategy — an effort to to rid the United States of all illegal immigrants, which they say upholds the rule of law and maintains national sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incongruity has set off a roiling series of debates about the very nature of conservatism, often within the sphere of conservatism itself, even as Mr. Trump softened his position on Monday and said that he was sending Tom Homan, his border czar, to Minneapolis and that Mr. Homan would work more closely with local officials. Mayor Frey said in a statement late Monday that some federal agents would leave the next day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a phone interview on Monday, Representative Fine argued that there was no disconnect between his support for Operation Metro Surge and his broader belief that the federal government should be reined in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not at all,” he said. “The most fundamental responsibility of the federal government is to secure the border and to protect Americans. ICE is rounding up foreign invaders who have been instructed to leave the country and have refused.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But other Republicans are voicing concerns. Former Vice President Mike Pence wrote on social media on Monday that the images of the shooting of Mr. Pretti were “deeply troubling,” adding that “a full and transparent investigation of this officer involved shooting must take place immediately.” Senators Ted Cruz, of Texas, and Jerry Moran, of Kansas, also called for an investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our Constitution provides citizens protection from the government,” Mr. Moran wrote. “We have a right to free speech, to peaceably assemble and to bear arms. We also expect government to protect us from lawless behavior.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview this week, Erick Erickson, the conservative pundit and radio host from Georgia, said he supports the administration’s mass deportation goals. But he said he was “uncomfortable” with the recently disclosed guidance drafted by U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement officials stating that deportation officers are allowed to enter homes to arrest people without judicial warrants. And he described Mr. Trump’s recent threat to invoke the Insurrection Act and send troops to Minnesota as “overkill” and “too provocative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Erickson said that the current disagreements over the Minnesota surge are part of a broader debate about shifting definitions of conservatism in the Trump era, as the president has embraced once-taboo ideas like the imposition of tariffs and government investment in private companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Erickson was among a number of conservatives who took issue over the weekend with assertions by Trump officials and allies who criticized Mr. Pretti for bringing a gun to a protest. Among them was Scott Bessent, the Treasury secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been to a protest,” Mr. Bessent said in an interview with ABC’s Jonathan Karl. “Guess what? I didn’t bring a gun. I brought a billboard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bessent is wrong,” Mr. Erickson wrote on X.com “I know plenty of people who participate in political events, including protests, and have their guns. It is their right. While we can say the man should not have gotten in an altercation with agents, merely exercising his 2A right with his 1A right is irrelevant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Stitt, the Republican governor of Oklahoma and the chair of the National Governors Association, told CNN on Sunday that while Mr. Trump’s promise to close the border was popular, the killings of Mr. Pretti and Ms. Good were “causing deep concerns over federal tactics and accountability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also suggested that the federal response was violating the principle that the political will of states should not be overrun by an overzealous federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We believe in federalism and state rights,” Mr. Still said. “And nobody likes feds coming into their state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s threat to invoke the Insurrection Act earlier this month has also become a delicate issue among Republicans, especially those vying for their party’s nomination in the upcoming Minnesota governor’s race. Earlier this month, The Minnesota Star Tribune reported that “several” G.O.P. candidates “would not explicitly say whether they would support President Donald Trump deploying the military to Minnesota to tamp down protests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One exception was Mike Lindell, the pro-Trump conspiracy theorist, MyPillow chief executive and Minnesota native. He said he would support “whatever it takes” to stop what he considered to be unlawful protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other side was Chris Madel, a Minneapolis lawyer who said he would not support invocation of the Insurrection Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Madel dropped out of the governor’s race on Monday and leveled harsh words against some fellow Republicans. “I cannot support the national Republicans stated retribution on the citizens of our state, nor can I count myself a member of a party that would do so,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most pointed criticism of the surge has, perhaps unsurprisingly, come from libertarians, many of whom have repeatedly chafed at Trump policies not deemed sufficiently in line with their small-government ethos. Walter Olson, a senior fellow at the Cato Institute, the libertarian think tank, has noted that protesters in Minnesota have been “repeatedly attacked” while filming or nonviolently protesting the enforcement actions, “in what looks very much like a practice that is being tolerated by policy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even among libertarians, there is disagreement. Angela McArdle, a former chair of the Libertarian Party, argued this weekend that the nation was in crisis mode and that now was not a time for libertarians to stick so strictly to their ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The threat of mass migration is civilizational,” Ms. McArdle wrote on X on Sunday, adding: “It sucks that ICE shoots people sometimes. If we don’t deport illegal aliens and stop Democrat fraud, we will be Canada in less than 10 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/minneapolis-shooting-trump-ice-gop.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:07:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Takes Another Stake in Rare Earth Sector</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-rare-earth-howard-lutnick.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-trump-invest-lzpf/26dc-trump-invest-lzpf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration announced on Monday that it had agreed to extend up to $277 million in direct funding and up to $1.3 billion in loans to USA Rare Earth Inc., a mining and manufacturing group, to help develop its supply chain for rare earth metals and magnets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal adds to the administration’s growing portfolio of equity stakes in private companies, and it would help expand domestic production of a critical input for cars, robots, semiconductors, drones and other products. China, which dominates the production of rare earth minerals and magnets, began clamping down on its export last year, and companies have struggled to find other sources of supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commerce Department, which arranged the financing through a semiconductor investment program set up during the Biden administration, said it had signed a nonbinding letter of intent to provide the funding, subject to further due diligence and approvals. The deal will give the Commerce Department approximately 16 million shares in the company, as well as a warrant to acquire another 17.6 million shares, the department said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Lutnick, the secretary of commerce, said in a statement that the company’s project was essential to “restoring U.S. critical mineral independence.” The investment “ensures our supply chains are resilient and no longer reliant on foreign nations,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the company also announced that it had raised $1.5 billion through a consortium of private investors. For that transaction, Cantor Fitzgerald, a Wall Street firm formerly headed by Mr. Lutnick, acted as the lead placement agent, the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overlap between the Trump administration and Cantor Fitzgerald has recently been under scrutiny by Democratic lawmakers and others, after revelations by The New York Times that the Wall Street firm profited off several projects that Mr. Lutnick promoted in his official role as commerce secretary. Mr. Lutnick has divested from Cantor Fitzgerald, but the firm is now led by two of his sons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Weisman, the co-president of Public Citizen, a government ethics watchdog group that has been critical of the Trump administration, described the ties as concerning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The fact that the deal is brokered by the Wall Street firm formerly run by the Commerce Secretary — and now headed by his sons — is reason to worry that the public interest is being subordinated, yet again, to the profit seeking of Trump cronies,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A commerce department official said that the CHIPS office worked directly with USA Rare Earth on the government deal, with no involvement from Cantor Fitzgerald. Cantor Fitzgerald declined to comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has now announced deals to take equity stakes in at least 10 private companies, in an unusual strategy for a Republican administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the deals involve the metals and mining sector, which the government has been trying to build up to ensure strategic independence from China. But the administration has also taken stake, or the option to acquire it, in the chipmaker Intel, the nuclear firm Westinghouse and U.S. Steel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While critics say the practice risks distorting the private market, the Trump administration has argued that the deals give American taxpayers more benefits when companies succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funding announced on Monday is expected to support two projects, a mine anticipated to begin commercial production in Texas in 2028, and a manufacturing project in Oklahoma. USA Rare Earths would be the only company in the United States that would mine minerals containing rare earths, extract rare earth oxides, convert them to metals and turn that into the feedstock for magnets, the Commerce Department said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-rare-earth-howard-lutnick.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 18:26:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Holds 2-Hour Meeting With Noem Amid Backlash to Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, at the White House earlier this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:41:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Donations, Trump Administration Revoked Rule Requiring More Nursing Home Staff</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Starting in early August, nursing home executives began making donations that would eventually total nearly $4.8 million to MAGA Inc., a super PAC devoted to President Trump and run by his allies.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:23:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Social Media Posts Echo White Supremacist Messaging</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-altright-bczq/26nat-altright-bczq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In the past month, government agencies have made dozens more social-media posts that include iconography associated with far-right extremist groups.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:41:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Maine’s Immigrant Students Stay Home as ICE Operation Ramps Up</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Educators from South Portland Middle School participate in a neighborhood watch at a bus stop in South Portland on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:02:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Photo Shows ICE Agents Deploying at Minneapolis Protest After Alex Pretti Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/us/nat-minn-oneimage-promo/nat-minn-oneimage-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violence in Minneapolis in the Wake of Alex Pretti’s Killing&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:03:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Trump Heads to Iowa to Trumpet Economy, Many Residents Feel Pain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-iowaecon-fgqz/27dc-iowaecon-fgqz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Iowa, a state that is heavily focused on farming, has been struggling under the weight of President Trump’s economic policies.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 04:01:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Transportation Safety Board Set to Declare Cause of Midair Collision</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/transportation-safety-board-set-to-declare-cause-of-midair-collision.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jennifer Homendy, the National Transportation Safety Board chairwoman, speaking after the crash at Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport last year. The board plans to publish a full report on the crash.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/transportation-safety-board-set-to-declare-cause-of-midair-collision.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:12:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Alex Pretti’s Killing, A Divided America Wonders What’s Next</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial formed at the spot where Alex Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:46:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alexander Vindman, of Trump Impeachment Fame, Runs for Senate in Florida</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Alexander Vindman testifying before Congress in 2019.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:07:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Investigators Review Body Camera Video Related to Killing of Alex Pretti</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/body-cam-video-alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-body-cam-gqmk/27minneapolis-ice-body-cam-gqmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal investigators are reviewing body camera footage related to the killing of Alex Pretti, the 37-year-old nurse who was fatally shot in Minneapolis on Saturday by federal agents involved in President Trump’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is body camera footage from multiple angles, which investigators are currently reviewing,” the Department of Homeland Security said in a statement to The New York Times on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage could shed new light on the killing of Mr. Pretti, who was an intensive-care nurse at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis. Administration officials quickly branded Mr. Pretti as a “domestic terrorist” after he was killed, even as videos of the encounter contradicted their narrative and D.H.S.’s account of the events leading up to the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Pretti was killed, the Hennepin County Attorney’s Office and Minnesota’s Bureau of Criminal Apprehension filed a lawsuit against several federal agencies and officials, including D.H.S. and Immigration and Customs Enforcement, to prevent the destruction of evidence related to the killing. A federal judge in Minnesota on Saturday issued a temporary restraining order barring federal officials from destroying evidence related to the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a memo filed Monday opposing the temporary restraining order, D.H.S. and other government agencies said that “the evidence is being preserved; nothing has been destroyed or altered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence is being stored in a secure evidence room at the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis field office, according to the memo. The document also stated that “CBP has preserved all relevant body-worn camera footage from the incident and will do so for 75 years,” referring to Customs and Border Protection, which includes U.S. Border Patrol, one of the two main homeland security agencies involved in the immigration crackdown, alongside ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times contradict D.H.S.’s account of Mr. Pretti’s killing. The department said the episode began after a man “approached US Border Patrol officers with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun” and they tried to disarm him. Footage shows Mr. Pretti was holding a phone, not a gun, before agents pulled him to the ground and shot him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamed Aleaziz contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/body-cam-video-alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:55:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A History of the Department of Homeland Security, the Agency Overseeing ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-timeline/26minneapolis-ice-timeline-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President George W. Bush signing the legislation that officially created the Homeland Security Department in 2002.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:06:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Orders ICE Chief to Appear in Court Over Potential Contempt</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
ICE’s acting director, Todd Lyons, was ordered to personally explain the agency’s actions to a federal judge.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:10:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>She’s the Face of Trump’s Aviation Safety Board, and She’s a Democrat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jennifer Homendy, the chairwoman of the National Transportation Safety Board, reconvening a hearing in July on the midair collision above Washington.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:35:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Florida Republican Says Immigration Crackdown Has ‘Gone Too Far’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/florida-republican-says-immigration-crackdown-has-gone-too-far.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/us/00nat-miami-senator/00nat-miami-senator-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Florida State Sen. Ileana Garcia sees herself as a truth-teller within her party. The killing of Alex Pretti by Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis, she said, was “abhorrent.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/florida-republican-says-immigration-crackdown-has-gone-too-far.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:14:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Population Growth Slows Sharply as Immigration Plunges</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-census-fjcl/27nat-census-fjcl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Population growth in Florida slowed markedly last year, according to new census estimates.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:32:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Andrea Lucas, EEOC Chair, Recasts Workplace Discrimination in Trump’s Image</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Andrea Lucas, the chair of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, said she was determined to undo the consequences of an “aggressive focus by D.E.I. activists.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:41:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yale Offers Free Tuition to Families With Incomes Under $200,000</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-yale-qljh/27nat-yale-qljh-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Yale University campus in New Haven, Conn.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:52:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mark Carney Rejects Suggestions That He Walked Back His Davos Speech to Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada dismissed Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent’s suggestion that he had retracted his assertion that President Trump had created an irrevocable “rupture” to the world order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian leader spoke to reporters in Ottawa on Tuesday, the day after Mr. Bessent said on Fox News that he was in the Oval Office while Mr. Carney “was very aggressively walking back some of the unfortunate remarks” he had made at the World Economic Forum in Davos during a telephone call with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that speech, Mr. Carney, though he did not specifically name Mr. Trump was clear in his intent, calling on the world’s middle powers to stop accommodating the United States just “to go along to get along,” and to instead band together to counter its political and economic power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Tuesday if he had rescinded any of his remarks while speaking with Mr. Trump, Mr. Carney said “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To be absolutely clear, and I said this to the president, I meant what I said in Davos,” Mr. Carney told reporters, referring to the Swiss ski resort town where the gathering of billionaires, investors, executives and politicians was held last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “It was clear. It was a broader set of issues, and Canada was the first country to understand the change in U.S. trade policy that he initiated, and we’re responding to that.” Mr. Carney added that during their conversation on Monday, the president had “understood’’ Canada’s position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week Mr. Carney warned other middle powers that they faced potential danger if they do not stand up for their own interests and push back against Mr. Trump’s aggressive economic moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His remarks received an unusual standing ovation and were widely praised around the world and stood in stark contrast to Mr. Trump’s long and rambling address at Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of Mr. Carney’s speech, Mr. Trump revoked his invitation to Canada for membership on his Gaza “Board of Peace,” though Mr. Carney had not fully committed to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney arrived in Switzerland after striking a trade deal with China that will allow a small number of Chinese electric vehicles to enter Canada at a low tariff rate. During the Biden administration, Canada joined the United States and imposed a 100 percent tariff on Chinese E.V.s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, Mr. Trump seemed to bless Mr. Carney’s agreement with China, saying, “That’s OK, that’s what he should be doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But later, on social media, he threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canadian exports “If Canada makes a deal with China.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney has repeatedly said that Canada has no plan to seek a broader free trade deal with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I explained to him our arrangement with China,” Mr. Carney said of his conversation with Mr. Trump on Tuesday. “I explained to him what we’re doing: 12 new deals on four continents in six months — he was impressed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday Canada and India released a joint statement about expanding trade in Canadian oil and natural gas. Mr. Carney is scheduled to travel to India next month to meet Prime Minister Narendra Modi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday Mr. Carney suggested that Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threat was a negotiating tactic ahead of a review of the free trade agreement between Canada, the United States and Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president is a strong negotiator and I think some of these comments and positioning should be viewed in the broader context of that,” Mr. Carney said at a news conference.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:54:25 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>