<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:58:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>An Alaska Town Is Now Key to Trump’s Global Ambitions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the unimaginative eye, the view of Nome, Alaska, from Joy Baker’s well-heated S.U.V. looked like a whole lot of nothing: The early winter sun was sliding below the horizon barely four hours after it had risen, the gray water of the inner harbor had already frozen over, and the only stirring came from a flock of hearty seabirds diving for dinner just off shore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Baker has a vision that goes well beyond the subarctic calm: “More traffic, more services, more jobs. More of everything for people here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Baker is director of the Port of Nome and thus the local overseer for a $548-million-and-counting plan to expand the port, in one of America’s most remote cities on the Bering Sea. Nome is a quiet, frozen frontier town much of the year, known mostly for the Iditarod sled race, and reachable only by air except for a few summer months when the water thaws enough to allow boats through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, however, Nome’s existing dock will be turned into the country’s first deepwater Arctic port, a critical hub in President Trump’s ambitions to make the United States master of the far north and compete with other world powers for untapped natural resources and shipping corridors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president didn’t originate the decade-old plan to expand Nome’s existing port, but his Arctic ambitions, including his efforts to take over Greenland, are longstanding and widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s aspirations for Nome were made clear near the end of his first term, when Congress authorized the port expansion with administration support. Last year, the project moved from paper to procurement as the Army Corps of Engineers awarded a $399.4 million construction contract for the first phase amid an administration-wide push to treat the Arctic and critical minerals as strategic priorities. This summer, crews will start demolishing the existing port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expansion should be complete, and Nome potentially remade, by 2033.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not actually like the current administration is trying to open the Arctic —Mother Nature did that,” said Ms. Baker, a gruff South Texan who moved to Alaska in 1987 and scoffs at ever returning to what Alaskans call, not always lovingly, the Lower 48. “I just see the current administration as just capitalizing in a way that will ensure our country is more self-sufficient. That can’t be a bad thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the port expansion will be good for Nome is a big question for many of the town’s 3,700 year-round residents and an itinerant population of contractors, health workers and dog mushing fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Port expansion, and the economic growth that follows, is expected to double or even triple the population, and some in Nome worry about what could happen without a solid strategy for long-term economic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is something of a boom-and-bust town,” said Jim West Jr., a longtime civic leader whose eclectic portfolio of businesses includes a gravel company, the local taxi service and the 125-year-old Board of Trade Saloon. “We need to make sure this isn’t just another economic cycle but something with lasting benefits for our children and grandchildren.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nome’s boom began at the turn of the 20th century when prospectors immortalized as the Three Lucky Swedes found gold in nearby Anvil Creek. Their discovery briefly turned Nome into Alaska’s largest city, with more than 20,000 residents. A second kind of gold rush came in 2011, prompted by surging gold prices and consisting largely of offshore dredging, but ebbed almost as quickly as it began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the flat, treeless winter tundra around Nome is dotted with abandoned mining rigs, and the city is stuck in economic stagnation. Little is produced this close to the Arctic Circle, and everything must arrive either by plane or seasonal barge. Prices, in turn, would shock Lower 48 shoppers. On a recent visit, a gallon of gas cost $6.50, a gallon of milk went for $6.99 and one browning honeydew melon was priced at almost $12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to convince locals to stay and even harder to woo new year-round residents. The hospital and most construction companies bring in temporary workers and either build their own housing or provide housing subsidies that reduce supply and raise costs for year-round residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Civic leaders like Ms. Baker, a former Nome harbor master who came out of retirement to manage the expansion, believe the project will lead to financial sustainability. But that presumes city officials can figure out how to pay for it all. Under its deal with the state and federal governments, Nome must cover 10 percent of port construction costs and 100 percent of its own port-related infrastructure needs, such as roads, streetlights and sewer lines. The city does not know how much that will cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond Nome City Hall, optimism about the port’s effect is the cautious sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teriscovkya Smith, the principal at Nome-Beltz Middle High School, estimated that 80 percent of her students won’t go to college and hoped the expansion could bring vocational internships and quality entry-level jobs. So far, however, she hasn’t heard from anyone involved in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People who stay build careers, they buy houses, they pay property taxes,” said Ms. Smith, who fished in Alaska for 10 years before becoming a teacher. “There’s a real risk that we just waste an amazing opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, Nome voters agreed to increase the local sales tax to 6 percent to avoid cuts to services such as pothole repair as well as hours at the town recreation center. The Nome school district balanced its budget last year by taking money from a fund set aside for teacher housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing money go into the port when other services face cuts can rankle. “I see the point of this thing for some other people — for the military maybe, for big shipping companies, for cruise lines,” said Keith Reddaway, co-owner of Builders Industrial Supply, a hardware store a block from the port. “But I’m not sure I see the point for Nome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tribal members also worry about what this all could mean for the subsistence lifestyle that dominates their 15 Alaska villages of the Bering Strait region. Around Nome, 86 percent of the population identifies as Indigenous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The port expansion and a new nearby graphite mine, fast-tracked by Mr. Trump, could bring more noise, air and water pollution, damage fishing and affect migratory birds and whales. They’re scared that they will be forced to abandon their traditional homes and seasonal schedules. And they worry Nome, always a little gritty around the edges, will revert to its rougher early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Outsiders bring in drugs,” said Shirley Martin, a member of the Yup’ik nation, whose village is across the Norton Sound. “People from the villages come through all the time to see family, go to the doctor, mail packages, just eat out. Will this still be a place where we feel comfortable?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time Nome has played a part in American security. During the Cold War, the U.S. military kept Air Force bases connected in case of a Soviet attack with an antenna installation atop nearby Anvil Mountain. Today, locals call the abandoned array “Nomehenge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, with sea ice thawing and the United States, Russia and China all eyeing Arctic shipping lanes and natural resources, Nome has emerged again as one of the most strategically important places in the Northern Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expanded port won’t be a military base, but Nome is an hour’s flight from Russia. Deepening the port from 22 feet to 40 feet will allow every type of U.S. military vessel except aircraft carriers to dock in Nome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a small-town police chief, and I’ve got intelligence officers from the Navy, the Coast Guard, the Air Force coming in here to sit with me,” said William Crockett, Nome’s retiring police chief. “Something big is coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:16:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Yosemite, Rangers Are Scarce and Visitors Have Gone Wild</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/yosemite-national-park-california-staffing-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-california-promo-jltc/00nat-50states-california-promo-jltc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, visitors to Yosemite National Park have been greeted by green- and khaki-clad rangers, who collect fees and guard the park’s entrance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on a chilly morning in December, there were no rangers at the park gates. Tourists descended into the majestic wilderness for free, confused by their apparent good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, ranger sightings were too rare last year, according to park regulars and advocates. Visitors were far less supervised than they normally were, which had led to the wrong kind of wildness — littering, cliff jumping, drone-flying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Yosemite under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, Mr. Trump has upended the agency that oversees Yosemite, the National Park Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has presided over a 25 percent drop in permanent staff across the park service, through a combination of Department of Government Efficiency layoffs, as well as buyouts and retirements, according to the National Parks Conservation Association, a nonprofit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has overhauled fee structures and reservation systems. It has ended free entry on Juneteenth and Martin Luther King’s Birthday, while granting free park admission on Mr. Trump’s birthday, which coincides with Flag Day. And this year, his face is on the annual park pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of the Interior, which administers the National Park Service, declined to comment on staffing numbers or operations at Yosemite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yosemite National Park continues to operate safely and serve millions of visitors each year,” the agency said in a statement, adding, “Interpretive offerings may vary throughout the year, but the park continues to provide a wide range of educational, recreational and stewardship opportunities for visitors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But according to interviews with park employees and environmentalists, the cuts at Yosemite, one of the country’s most visited national parks, have meant there aren’t always enough rangers to staff entrance booths or educate visitors on caring for the park. Amid the shortage, scientists working in the parks have cleaned the public toilets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s really disheartening to see the direction we’re going,” said Mark Ruggiero, a retired Yosemite ranger who still does part-time work in the park. “It’s trying times. Nobody is really sure what’s going to happen next.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, tourists have been coming to Yosemite in droves, with 2025 becoming one of its busiest summers in recent years. October was unusually packed because the park was left open and free during the federal government shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisabeth Barton, a co-owner of a company that offers guided tours of Yosemite’s attractions, said her business had benefited from the crowds. But she has also noticed more visitors driving the wrong way down one-way roads, parking on sensitive meadows and BASE jumping off cliffs, which is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing the park really struggling to support the number of visitors that are coming in,” said Ms. Barton, 46. “I struggle to see the long game here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the vistas of Yosemite, with alpine lakes and meadows bathed in golden light, that helped inspire the creation of the entire national park system. President Abraham Lincoln in 1864 made the Yosemite Valley federally protected land designated for public use. That act paved the way for the eventual creation of the national park system, and Yosemite became the country’s third national park in 1890.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The park, the size of Rhode Island, is home to Half Dome and El Capitan, perhaps the most iconic rock faces in the country. It also has one of the tallest waterfalls in the United States, where, on that recent morning, a rainbow was visible at the base as it crashed into granite boulders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a walk around the park in December, Yosemite seemed the same as it had for decades. A father from Southern California was waiting at sunset for his son to propose to his girlfriend, so he could surprise them after. A tourist from the Czech Republic visiting several national parks marveled at how one country could contain so much beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grace Shiyatta said she was passing through a pine forest to meet her friends for a picnic to celebrate her 60th birthday. In their 20s, she and her friends had visited Yosemite every year, renting a big house to cross-country ski. It was a natural choice to return for her big birthday celebration, said Ms. Shiyatta, who lives in Sacramento.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What would I rather do than hang out in Yosemite?” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she and other tourists also said they had been puzzled that the park hadn’t collected their entrance fees. And a climber said that he had just scaled Half Dome without the required permit, which is intended to prevent deaths and injuries on the exposed rock face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Barton and her co-owner, Bryant Burnette, who have been giving private tours of the park for years, think visitors have become particularly unruly because there haven’t been enough staff members around to teach them the importance of caring for the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No wonder people are throwing trash and flying drones,” said Mr. Burnette, 36, who, as he walked, picked up tissues and wrappers that had been discarded on the valley floor. “I can’t be mad at them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Yosemite was home to some of the most public displays of federal employee anger toward the Trump administration. In February, shortly after an abrupt firing of 1,000 park service employees, a group of frustrated staffers hung a distress flag off El Capitan, which still rises more than 3,000 feet above the base of Yosemite Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Park supporters fear the long-term impact, especially with the loss of employees who plan for Yosemite’s preservation, including scientists who study endangered species or wildfire mitigation, and infrastructure experts who plan to move buildings out of flood plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, employees are keeping the park running day to day, but that isn’t enough — and it can’t last forever, said Don Neubacher, who was superintendent of Yosemite from 2010 to 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not like you’re talking about some city park,” he said. “You’re talking about nature’s greatest gifts — it’s a dire time.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/yosemite-national-park-california-staffing-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:19:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>When Trump Took a Whack at the C.D.C., Atlanta Lost Something, Too</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cdc-atlanta-trump-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-georgia-fbcl/00nat-50states-georgia-fbcl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Atlanta is a city full of public servants who no longer serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of them had held jobs at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. But last year, the Trump administration slashed the agency in waves of firings. Public health programs were shrunk or shuttered. Top medical experts have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasoned epidemiologists and other staff members are working in yoga studios, walking neighbors’ dogs and job hunting — although cuts to other government agencies and cutbacks at health-related nonprofits have made the job hunt difficult for many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jennifer McQuiston, 54, thought she had a few more years of working at the C.D.C., fighting some of the world’s most dangerous health threats at the National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases. But she took early retirement, concerned that the agency had strayed too far from its commitment to science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days Dr. McQuiston, who has a veterinary degree, is working at an animal shelter and spending time riding her horse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was my calling,” she said. “I don’t mourn the loss at this moment, because I don’t believe the agency is the same agency I worked in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways, the C.D.C. is still trundling along. Government employees still come and go from the agency’s main campus near Emory University. And to the C.D.C.’s detractors, the Trump administration is simply forcing much-needed change to an agency that lost trust during the Covid pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The C.D.C. was broken for a long time,” Andrew Nixon, a spokesman with the Department of Health and Human Services, said in a statement. Reform was needed, he said, to combat a “culture of groupthink and mission creep” at the agency that had undermined public confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But civic leaders, scientists and public health advocates are increasingly worried about stories like Dr. McQuiston’s — and their effect not only on the C.D.C., but also on Atlanta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the decades, the disease-fighting work of the C.D.C. has helped define the Southern city’s sense of moral purpose, alongside its rich civil rights legacy. It has helped Atlanta realize its ambitions to be a city with global impact, alongside its famously busy international airport. The C.D.C. is also at the center of a regional life sciences sector that employs nearly 200,000 people and generates billions of dollars in economic activity yearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some fear that the C.D.C. is on “life support,” as three former agency leaders declared in November, no longer trusted by the broader medical community and no longer able to attract some of the brightest minds in the life sciences to Atlanta. An Axios/Ipsos poll in October found that 62 percent of Americans trust health information from the C.D.C., down from 88 percent in March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ve had a lot of different kinds of institutions benefit from the focus on public heath,” said Doug Shipman, the former president of the Atlanta City Council. “Does that now stall? To me, that’s the fundamental question.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in Atlanta in 1946 as the Communicable Disease Center, the agency grew out of the fight to keep U.S. troops at Southern military bases safe from malaria. It would eventually expand its remit to fight all communicable diseases, as well as other health risks like smoking, gun violence prevention and bioterror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atlanta would soon become home to other major institutions with a health focus — the Carter Center, the Task Force for Global Health, the American Cancer Society and CARE, the global nonprofit that seeks to eradicate poverty and expand health services in some of the poorest parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the earnest C.D.C. employee became a kind of Atlanta archetype, alongside aspiring rappers and C-suite strivers. The disease fighters have lent their own flavors — civic-mindedness, scientific rigor — to the metropolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the agency was buffeted by the Covid-19 pandemic and public distrust over its handling of the crisis. After an external review pointed out that its response had been sluggish and muddled, even its leadership acknowledged that it needed to be reformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Trump’s second inauguration, the changes to the agency have been chaotic. Agency officials did not respond to a request for details about the extent of the staff reductions. But an article in November in the medical journal The Lancet by Debra Houry, Daniel Jernigan and Demetre Daskalakis — former C.D.C. leaders who resigned in protest over Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr.’s vision for the agency — states that the number of staff members had been reduced to fewer than 10,000 employees in October from roughly 13,500 employees at the beginning of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writers argued that the cuts had left the nation unprepared to handle viruses like Zika and mpox, unable to properly keep track of diseases like Creutzfeldt-Jakob and chronic wasting disease, and understaffed in sectors that keep tabs on basic national health data. The authors said the C.D.C.’s malaria staff in Africa had been eliminated, “undermining decades of progress.” Other cuts, they wrote, threatened to “reverse decades of progress in ending the H.I.V. epidemic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Elizabeth Soda, a Stanford-trained physician and epidemiologist, left the C.D.C. in September after working there for a decade. Among other things, Dr. Soda, an infectious disease specialist, helped to develop health screening for immigrants and refugees entering the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She knew little about Atlanta when she arrived, but she and her husband settled in and started their family. She thought she had found her dream job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She watched the Trump administration with concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She had tried to give the new secretary of Health and Human Services, Mr. Kennedy, a chance, but was sorely disappointed. “He lacks expertise, he believes damaging theories about well-proven science — and this guy’s in charge of our health?” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She had also begun to feel unsafe. In August, a gunman fired dozens of rounds at the C.D.C. headquarters. Dr. Soda had left the campus a half-hour earlier, but her office was four doors down from one of the holes a bullet left in a window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After her husband, also a scientist, won an appointment in Italy, they moved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling that she abandoned the agency gnaws at her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We go through massive, real guilt moments,” Dr. Soda, 47, said in a telephone interview late last year. “That’s one of the hardest things being here, to be honest, is knowing what we’ve left behind, who we’ve left behind — family, friends, our country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a modicum of hope that Atlanta will help steer the C.D.C. — or whatever government entity follows in its wake — back on a more trustworthy path. Some of that optimism is rooted in the belief that public health officials know how to solve problems in the midst of chaos. Some of it is rooted in the vast public health expertise that still resides in Atlanta’s nonprofits and educational institutions, including Emory, Georgia Tech, Georgia State and the Morehouse School of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These institutions allow Atlanta’s Chamber of Commerce to plausibly boast that the city is the “public health capital of the world.” Many of those groups have been absorbing as many former C.D.C. workers as they can. The hope is that they will continue to incubate the values of the old C.D.C. and lead a comeback in the public health sphere when and if Mr. Kennedy’s influence wanes, said Terry Pechacek, a former C.D.C. scientist and emeritus professor of public health at Georgia State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The future rebound, which may be a generation away, will come out of that core,” Dr. Pechacek said. “The core is not dead.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cdc-atlanta-trump-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:12:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Idaho City Has New Refugees: White South Africans</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/twin-falls-idaho-afrikaners-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/00Nat-50states-Idaho-fgmj/00Nat-50states-Idaho-fgmj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, refugees have been part of the rhythm of Twin Falls, a small city in southern Idaho. Displaced from the world’s most troubled corners — places like Bosnia, the Democratic Republic of Congo and Myanmar — these new residents have worked to rebuild their lives, finding jobs in factories, singing in church choirs and loading up their carts in supermarkets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a story that is as old as the nation itself: A town prospers with the support of newcomers, who are grateful to be there. There have been some ugly tensions in the past, but refugees in Twin Falls have helped turn the area into a dairy industry juggernaut. They have rehabbed homes and filled classrooms. The town’s children play together in parks, schoolyards and sports fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No matter where you come from, there is opportunity to achieve the American dream in Twin Falls, clichéd as that may sound,” said Shawn Barigar, the city’s director of economic development. “The refugee population, tiny as it may be, is a component that is important to our prosperity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But refugee resettlement is now getting an overhaul, as part of the Trump administration’s upending of the immigration system. President Trump, who was elected in part because of his anti-immigration views, has said that refugees pose security risks, strain public coffers and undermine American values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his first day in the White House, Mr. Trump suspended the U.S. refugee program. A few weeks later, his administration announced it would make an exception and admit just one group: Afrikaners, or white South Africans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, the administration established new targets for the refugee program, and said it would allow only 7,500 refugees for the coming year — the lowest number in the program’s history. (Former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. set the ceiling at 125,000 for 2024.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And an overwhelming majority of them, the administration said, would be Afrikaners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means Twin Falls, which had typically received 200 to 350 refugees a year, would be in for an adjustment. As it is, since May, a total of 37 refugees, all Afrikaners, have resettled in Twin Falls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for the city’s future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idaho has for decades been a leader in resettling refugees, with a robust brigade of volunteers and employers in Boise and Twin Falls to welcome and integrate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the resettlement program, refugees face extensive vetting before being cleared to enter the United States, often waiting years abroad. On arrival, they are assisted by nonprofit contractors, such as the U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants in Twin Falls, which secure temporary housing, enroll children in school and provide cash for initial expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just benevolence. Refugees are vital to businesses here in Idaho’s Magic Valley, which has emerged as an agribusiness powerhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economy around Twin Falls is anchored by the world’s biggest yogurt factory, Chobani. But there are also major companies like Clif Bar and outposts of global companies like Glanbia Nutritionals, a milk processor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And down the line is a vast network of dairy farms, cheese and whey producers, potato and beef plants and food-science labs, which Hamdi Ulukaya, Chobani’s founder, has called “the Silicon Valley of food innovation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The labor market is tight, with unemployment hovering around 3.5 percent. “We have a desperate shortage of people at all levels in this area,” said Daragh Maccabee, the chief executive of Idaho Milk Products, which, like many companies in the area, is in the midst of major expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The refugee program has been a source of motivated, qualified talent,” Mr. Maccabee said. “I fear the impact of losing that valuable source for the economy and the community.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning, Nijaz Heric, a safety supervisor at Idaho Milk, patrolled the high-tech dairy processing plant with a practiced eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, Mr. Heric and his family were among the first Muslim Bosnians resettled in Twin Falls, fleeing war and ethnic cleansing. He had no money, no English, only the hope of starting over. His first job was making cheese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I tried to explain with my hands that I wanted a job,” he recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2000s, persecuted minority groups from Myanmar and Bhutan arrived, followed by people displaced by wars in Africa and the Middle East, often after languishing for years in refugee camps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low cost of living coupled with good wages enabled many refugees to vault into the middle class. Often, their children, raised in the United States, became college students and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything has gone smoothly. In 2016, during Mr. Trump’s first presidential campaign, Twin Falls found itself besieged. Far-right outlets, including Breitbart, seized and distorted a story about a sex abuse case involving teenagers. The outlets falsely claimed that a little girl had been gang raped at knife point by Syrian refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police officials tried to debunk the reports, declaring that the crime was not gang rape and that the perpetrators were juveniles who were not Syrian and did not wield a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But outside militia groups descended on the town. Some people threatened city officials and demanded an end to refugee resettlement, asserting that “all refugees must be criminals,” recalled Matthew Hicks, the police chief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As hostility intensified, city officials formed civic groups to introduce refugees to residents. That helped ease the tension. And so did the passing of the news cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the tensions come from above. In December, Samuel Nzapalaha sat in the living room of his four-bedroom house, his family by his side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He bought that house for $385,000 two years ago, putting $50,000 down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was one marker of his success in Twin Falls after arriving in 2016 with his wife, Josephine Mirindi, and their five children. The family had fled armed conflict in the Democratic Republic of Congo. At first, Mr. Nzapalaha worked two jobs, at a cheese maker and the local refugee agency, while attending a local college. Within a year, the couple could afford their first house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nzapalaha now works as a case manager at an addiction recovery center. His wife works at Chobani labeling yogurt cups, earning $23 an hour. Their children are working or attending college or high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their story, he said, stands in stark contrast to the president’s portrayal of refugees as ruining America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We work hard; we buy things; we are contributing,’’ Mr. Nzapalaha said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for opening the door to Afrikaners, he described them as “so-called refugees.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, Twin Falls received nine of the first 59 Afrikaners admitted in 2025 to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have been quiet, with neighbors shrugging their shoulders and saying they do not really know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a middle-class subdivision, one Afrikaner couple stood in June on the lawn outside their home. The wife praised President Trump before her husband said they did not want to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether more Afrikaners, beyond those who have already arrived, are resettling in Twin Falls is unclear. The political climate is tense, and many in Twin Falls were reluctant to talk, including those at nonprofit agencies that assist refugees and companies that depend on them for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Chobani, which has been a vocal champion of refugees, did not reply to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a handful of South Africans cannot meet the labor demands of these companies. A $500 million expansion of the Chobani plant, tied to its acquisition of La Colombe Coffee in 2023, is expected to come online in 2026. Idaho Milk Products plans to open an ice cream factory this year as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we don’t let refugees in, we’ll stagnate,” said Jim Jones, the former Republican attorney general of Idaho, who has publicly criticized the Trump administration’s refugee policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Refugees are in dairies, maintenance, everywhere,” said Mr. Jones, who was born and raised in the area. “They do hard work that locals think are beneath them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/twin-falls-idaho-afrikaners-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:59:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Columbia University’s Strained Peace: Fewer Protests and Sealed Gates</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/columbia-university-protests-culture-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-50states-NY-flqp/00nat-50states-NY-flqp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a frigid evening in December, hundreds of bundled up Columbia students gathered on the university’s main campus — not to shout political slogans, but to mingle at an annual holiday  celebration. The campus trees were lit up, the university gave out free hot chocolate, and a cappella groups sang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a sign of the times, the campus’s imposing iron gates, historically open to the public, were closed. The Low Library steps, a frequent site for student protests, were blocked off. Police cars and additional barricades ringed the area outside of the gates, to control any other demonstrations that might happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gates to Columbia’s main campus in Manhattan swung shut more than two years ago to control volatile protests over the war in Gaza. There was a days-long encampment, a building takeover and arrests by police. Now, entry is permitted only to those who hold Columbia identification and their approved guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closure does provide extra security for students and faculty, a benefit underscored after the mass shooting at Brown in December. But its main purpose has been to limit the potential for protests and unrest, including since the Trump administration has used the full force of his office to bend universities to his will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia was once known as America’s “activist Ivy,” in part because of its hands-off policy for demonstrations, a legacy of 1968 antiwar protests that led to an aggressive police response. The images from that time left an indelible mark not only on Columbia, but on New York’s protest culture more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the relative quiet at the university — despite its history of uprisings, even within a boisterous anti-Trump New York — is partly a measure of the White House’s success in taming unrest at Columbia and other universities around the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I feel like it’s very disheartening,” said Gabriela Ruiz, a freshman attending the tree lighting with her roommates. “I think protest has become a bad word. The concept of encampment has become a bad word.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the country, President Trump has used executive orders, civil rights investigations and the withdrawal of research funds to try to tamp down protests that he accused of antisemitism, and to reshape universities that he accused of being captured by leftist orthodoxy. Leadership, faculty power, diversity programs and the minutiae of grant proposals are all up for scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia was President Trump’s first high-profile university target, followed by Harvard, Brown, Northwestern and others. In July, Columbia settled with the Trump administration, paying $221 million to settle civil rights claims against the university for allegedly failing to protect students from antisemitic harassment. Harvard has not settled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some at Columbia, the new, quieter campus culture is a relief, especially for those who found the protests offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natan Rosenbaum, an Orthodox Jewish senior at Columbia, recalled how in December 2023, the annual lighting celebration was disrupted by a large group of pro-Palestinian protesters who held up signs that said “Joy is Canceled” and chanted slogans like “There’s no room for celebration, end Israeli occupation.” This year, a smaller group of protesters briefly interrupted the event, before moving to rally outside the Columbia gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not saying I was in favor of withholding the funding, but yeah, I think things are entirely more pleasant now,” he said. “The protests were not a kind presence. And their rhetoric was many times very ugly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other students and faculty members say the strained campus peace has cut unacceptably at Columbia’s identity and made the school an example of capitulation to government overreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Political advocacy has just been tamped down to a remarkable degree,” said Michael Thaddeus, a mathematics professor and vice president of Columbia’s American Association of University Professors chapter. In the fall, he navigated the tighter rules on demonstrations while organizing an event for academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can try to spin it in a positive way by saying, well, the campus has calmed down and people can get back to doing their important work,” he said. “But my view is that protest and dissent are part of the essential work of a university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in 2025, several pro-Palestinian protests caught the attention of the new Trump administration. In January, a modern Israel history class was disrupted. In early March, there was a Barnard sit-in, with Mahmoud Khalil, then a little-known graduate student and Palestinian activist, acting as a negotiator between demonstrators and administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 7, the White House announced it was withholding $400 million in federal grants. The next day, Immigration and Customs Enforcement officers arrested Mr. Khalil in the lobby of his Columbia-owned apartment building and detained him for 104 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia administrators did not mention him by name for months. To this day, Mr. Khalil said, Columbia has not reached out directly to him or offered support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Columbia is no longer an educational institution,” said Mr. Khalil, who is out of detention but still fighting deportation. “It has pretty much become an institution of oppression for the right wing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Columbia spokeswoman said that the university had been “in regular contact with Mr. Khalil through his lawyers since March” and had granted his family’s request to extend their housing lease for months because of their difficult circumstances. Mr. Khalil and seven other students are suing Columbia and the Trump administration over their treatment as pro-Palestinian activists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of its pledges to the Trump administration, Columbia gave arrest powers to some of its public safety officers, a major change at the university. Other new rules include: Demonstrations inside academic buildings are no longer allowed. Columbia’s unwieldy campus Senate, made up of mostly faculty and created in the aftermath of the 1968 protests to encourage democratic decision-making, has had its authority over disciplining student protesters taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Events must go through multiple layers of approval, which on a practical level, reduces their frequency. On some days, extra notice is required for security reasons. When there are protests, they often happen outside the campus, where fewer rules apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students have gotten the message that certain kinds of protesting could lead to serious consequences. But that doesn’t mean that they all agree with Columbia’s decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of simmering contempt, I’d say,” said Stella Dougherty, 21, a junior studying information science. “You get the sense that a lot of people wish they could say things or demonstrate in ways that they feel like they can’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others see the new rules as an acceptable compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were a university in crisis,” said Brian Cohen, the executive director of the campus Hillel chapter. “What we saw was the interruption of admissions tours, storming of academic buildings, assaulting public safety officers, disrupting classes, destroying property. That’s not activism in my book — it’s intimidation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last large pro-Palestinian demonstration happened in May, when dozens of masked protesters stormed into Columbia’s Butler Library to occupy its main reading room. Campus security prevented students from leaving without showing their identification. Eventually, the police were called in. Over 70 students were disciplined, the majority with multiyear suspensions, according to Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This academic year has been relatively quiet so far. Pro-Palestinian student activists, who say that even cultural celebrations are subject to the new restrictions, are regrouping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pilot to reopen the campus was delayed by new security concerns, including worries about federal immigration police having access to campus, Claire Shipman, the acting university president, told students this fall. In one change, people who live nearby can now apply for campus access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We understand the desire to return to an open campus, and the university evaluates campus access protocols on an ongoing basis,” said Samantha Slater, a spokeswoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Khalil said he did not expect Columbia to open its gates anytime soon. He was denied permission to go to a November film screening at the university’s journalism school because of what Columbia said were security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The I.D. checks, he said, are “a sign that we are watching you.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/columbia-university-protests-culture-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:58:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Tennessee Dean Had ‘Zero Sympathy’ for Charlie Kirk. She Was Fired.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/middle-tennessee-state-university-dean-fired-charlie-kirk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-50states-tennessee-01-zbpj/00nat-50states-tennessee-01-zbpj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the conservative political activist Charlie Kirk was assassinated in September, Laura Sosh-Lightsy fired off a late-night post on Facebook: “Looks like ol’ Charlie spoke his fate into existence. Hate begets hate. ZERO sympathy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comment was harsh, and so was the pushback. Within hours, she was fired from her job as a dean at Middle Tennessee State University, about an hour southeast of Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a stunning turnabout for Ms. Sosh-Lightsy, whose work responsibilities included overseeing conduct and often navigating free-speech questions within the university community. Should a student be punished for using a slur? Can someone be removed from class over derogatory language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She now finds herself a central figure in a debate over appropriate sanctions for speech — and an example of how much the contours of the free-speech debate have changed in the last year under President Trump, especially in red states like Tennessee. Ms. Sosh-Lightsy is just one of scores of people across the country who have been fired, suspended or called to step aside for things they said about Mr. Kirk or his assassination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An online campaign, encouraged by some members of the Trump administration, other high-ranking lawmakers and prominent right-wing figures, tried to swiftly single out anyone who made disparaging, callous or celebratory comments after the assassination. Professors, health care workers, lawyers and journalists, restaurant workers and airline employees have all faced consequences for their statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For champions of Mr. Kirk’s far-right agenda, those comments seemed indicative of a liberal intolerance and orthodoxy that helped whip up the conditions for Mr. Kirk’s killing. But it was also a sign of how many conservatives had reversed course on their condemnation of what they call cancel culture and instead embarked on a sweeping campaign, especially in Republican-dominated places like Tennessee, to penalize opposing viewpoints and political expression they found to be offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have the shock of murder combined with partisan division and vitriol, and that’s a potent combination,” said Will Creeley, the legal director at the nonpartisan Foundation for Individual Rights and Expression, which is now representing two other Tennesseans penalized for their online posts about Mr. Kirk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In those moments, people don’t give a damn about the First Amendment,” he added. “And they just want to see the people who don’t feel like they do shut up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sosh-Lightsy, 54, has also sued, charging a violation of her First Amendment rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her lawsuit, she argued that a Facebook post outside working hours on her private page — where she had a disclaimer saying views may not reflect that of her employer — did not disrupt university operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook had long been an outlet for her, where she shared memes, humor and lengthy political commentary. The posts, she said, had never come up at work, even though she had allowed some colleagues to view them. And having grown up in a conservative, rural area of Kentucky, she knew some relatives and others did not agree with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After she heard about Mr. Kirk’s assassination, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy recalled his comments after the 2023 shooting at a private Nashville Christian school: “I think it’s worth to have a cost of, unfortunately, some gun deaths every single year so that we can have the Second Amendment to protect our other God-given rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m like, this is so ironic that this man was shot at a school and he said, ‘this is just part of it,’” she said. At night, home from work, frustrated with the outpouring of grief, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, “I made the post, and I probably could have said it better. I didn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her sympathy, she later said, was with his family and those who witnessed the killing. And in a follow-up post, she tried to clarify that she did not support violence. But screenshots began to circulate online, slowly fueling an outcry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 9:33 p.m. in Tennessee, Senator Marsha Blackburn, a Republican, called on X for Ms. Sosh-Lightsy’s removal, adding that she should be “ashamed.” Minutes later, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy was told to expect a call from the university president, Dr. Sidney A. McPhee. By the end of the night he had called and fired her, news that was promoted across social media and in an alert on the university’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments were “inappropriate and callous,” Dr. McPhee said in a statement at the time, and “undermined the university’s credibility and reputation.” Hundreds of comments — many from people who identified themselves as alumni or parents of current students — flooded the posts, thanking the school for its action. (A spokesman for the school declined to comment, citing the ongoing lawsuit. The school has not yet filed a response in court.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservatives have suffered similar consequences for things they said online, especially in 2020, and successfully brought some free-speech cases. Last year, a federal jury awarded a Nashville firefighter about $1.8 million after the local government demoted him for Facebook comments critical of the Black Lives Matter movement and pandemic mask mandates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are conflicting feelings, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, when people send her reports that some people penalized for their online posts related to Mr. Kirk have won initial court cases, resulting in reinstatements or monetary awards, including a reported $500,000 settlement in Tennessee. There is some hope for what she sees as a fair outcome, she said, but still frustration that her case is unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next few days, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, threatening and critical messages poured in, prompting her to temporarily leave her home. A lesser penalty — being put on leave, losing her responsibilities related to student conduct — could be understood, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she maintains that she had done nothing egregious, let alone anything to warrant her immediate firing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If I’m wrong, and this speech is not protected, then I have never understood what the Constitution means and I have never understood what it protects,” Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said. “Either I haven’t understood it or we are on the edge of completely changing what it means.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some friends and longtime work references have distanced themselves publicly and privately. Others who disagree with the extent of Ms. Sosh-Lightsy’s punishment have still declined to say so publicly, wary of retribution for even the slightest association with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve never been one to back down in the face of injustice or inequity,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she has since struggled to find a job. Grocery stores, public school systems and other workplaces have rejected her. She is living primarily off the payout from her unused time off, and is looking to sell her car in the coming weeks. She can no longer send money home to help her mother with her bills, and is worried about slipping back into the poverty she grew up in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand the sentiment that people have — that you did this, you said this awful thing — but I can almost guarantee you that if you put it into an example in their own life, they would say that the extent that I’m being held accountable is excessive,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She continues to post on Facebook, now, she said, with a hint of caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/middle-tennessee-state-university-dean-fired-charlie-kirk.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:32:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>To Their Shock, Cubans in Florida Are Being Deported in Record Numbers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cubans-florida-deportations-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-50states-florida-01-mlft/19nat-50states-florida-01-mlft-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heidy Sánchez took her 17-month-old daughter to a routine check-in last April with Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Tampa, Fla. During the appointment, federal authorities told her that she was being detained and that her husband should pick up their daughter, who was still breastfeeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days later, Ms. Sánchez, 44, who worked as a home health aide, was deported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sánchez’s story quickly spread across social media, in part because she is Cuban, a group that had long been treated differently than other immigrants, even when they entered the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has changed under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has repatriated more than 1,600 Cubans in 2025, according to the Cuban government. That is about double the number of Cubans who were repatriated in 2024. And in the years that Mr. Trump has been president, he has sent more Cubans back than his three predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those numbers are greater for Cubans who were deported by land into Mexico. Some of them had been in the United States for decades and built families and businesses, but were removed because of an old criminal conviction — say, from Miami’s infamous cocaine cowboys days in the late 1970s and early 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere has the shock of treating Cubans like other migrants been felt more than in Florida, which was shaped in modern times by exiles of the 1959 Cuban Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Families, businesses and communities that once felt removed from or immune to immigration enforcement now must face it head-on. Some Floridians worry that these deportations could stain the state’s proud Cuban identity, turning older immigrants against newer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump, many other countries saw similar increases in repatriation. The difference is that Cubans had not previously been targeted as aggressively for removal. Regular deportation flights to Cuba began in January 2017, under President Barack Obama, paused during the coronavirus pandemic and restarted in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Cubans have also been detained for weeks or months in a facility in the Florida Everglades known as “Alligator Alcatraz.” At another nearby detention facility, Cuban detainees protested last June by writing “SOS Cuba” on their shirts and spelling out “SOS” with their bodies in the recreation yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal immigration has also been all but cut out. Mr. Trump enacted a travel ban on 19 countries, including Cuba, and ended a family reunification program. U.S. officials are rejecting visa applications, which can take years to complete. Last month, the Trump administration paused all Cuban immigration cases, including pending naturalization, residency and asylum applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s the most sweeping rollback of Cuban migration channels since the Cold War,” said María José Espinosa, the executive director of the Center for Engagement and Advocacy in the Americas, a nonprofit strategy organization based in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polls suggest that most Cuban American registered voters, who tend to be Republican, continue to support Mr. Trump, said Michael J. Bustamante, an associate history professor and director of Cuban studies at the University of Miami who studies Cuban American political culture. But he said that he had noticed “a growing amount of unease” throughout the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a senator, Secretary of State Marco Rubio, the Trump administration’s most prominent Cuban American, often criticized Cuban immigrants who received government benefits like food stamps and Medicaid, and frequently returned to the island. Over the summer, Mr. Rubio said in a video commemorating huge anti-Communist protests in 2021 that many Cubans had found it “easier” to “abandon” the island than stay and fight the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immigration enforcement in South Florida has not involved a mass federal operation, as in Los Angeles or Chicago, and previous administrations had made changes that started to erode Cubans’ immigration privileges. Still, Mr. Trump’s anti-immigration campaign has shaken some Cubans unused to feeling at risk in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am scared of everything,” said Javier González, a 36-year-old salesman in the heavily Cuban city of Hialeah, northwest of Miami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González and his family crossed the United States-Mexico border in February 2022, fleeing what he described as a threat to his life in Cuba, where he was a political dissident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González and his wife, like hundreds of thousands of recent Cubans migrants, were released under what is known as conditional parole. That does not allow them to apply for residency under the Cuban Adjustment Act, a law that Congress passed in 1966, and leaves them vulnerable to deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. González and his wife legally obtained Social Security numbers, work permits and driver’s licenses. He applied for political asylum and has a pending court date in 2028. He found work as an HVAC technician. Mr. Trump’s campaign promise to deport criminals seemed sound to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then early last year, ICE officers, during regular check-ins in South Florida, started detaining Cubans with conditional parole. Now, to avoid immigration sweeps, Mr. González said he avoided unnecessary car rides and local Hispanic supermarkets. He cannot fathom the repression he might face in Cuba were he to return as a former dissident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes I tell myself, ‘Why do you have to feel as if you were a criminal when you are an upstanding person?’” Mr. González said. But, he added, “They can grab you and do whatever they want.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some older Cuban American immigrants are angry over the turnabout in circumstances. Alicia Peláez, 78, arrived in the United States as an unaccompanied minor in 1960, under Operation Pedro Pan, a secret program run by the Catholic Church with help from the State Department that resettled some 14,000 young Cubans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were welcomed into the country,” said Ms. Peláez, who is a registered Republican, but has not voted that way in recent elections. “Now, it’s the complete opposite.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sánchez, who was separated from her baby and husband, remains in Havana, with a pending visa interview that will determine whether she can apply for a waiver to return to Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She came to the United States through the border, presented herself to request asylum, and waited in Mexico. But she missed a hearing because of safety reasons, which resulted in a deportation order and nine months of detention. In the end, she was released in the United States because Cuba at the time did not accept her repatriation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in Florida, Ms. Sánchez studied and became a nursing assistant. She met and married her husband, an American citizen, who petitioned for her residency. She underwent fertility treatments and had their daughter. Three months before her deportation, they had bought a house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being returned to Cuba, Ms. Sánchez said she was so upset that she had to see a psychiatrist. Her daughter, in Tampa, was no longer her cheery self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She didn’t laugh anymore, which really worried us,” Ms. Sánchez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her husband and daughter visited Ms. Sánchez over Christmas, which lifted their spirits, she said. But she did not know how she would handle more months of separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her daughter, she said, “is our joy, our happiness, our life.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cubans-florida-deportations-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:47:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens 200 Percent Tariffs on French Wine</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-france-wine-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-champagne-bgcz/20xp-champagne-bgcz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump threatened on Monday to impose 200 percent tariffs on French wine, including Champagne, if President Emmanuel Macron of France declined to join his proposed “Board of Peace” for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France was among the countries the Trump administration invited last week to join the body, which Mr. Trump has said he plans to lead to oversee the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas and supervise the rebuilding of Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics said the board could undermine the United Nations, which Mr. Trump has accused of liberal bias and waste. A senior French official said on Monday that France did not intend to join, citing concerns that the board’s charter raised serious questions about respecting the role of the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Monday about France’s refusal to join, Mr. Trump threatened to impose steep tariffs on some of the country’s best-known exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said he would impose the tariffs if France took what he described as a hostile stance, suggesting that the pressure would push Mr. Macron to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has increasingly used trade threats as a tool of diplomacy and a way to achieve his broader foreign policy goals. On Saturday, he demanded a deal to buy Greenland, warning that he would otherwise impose 10 percent tariffs on a group of European countries, which he said could later rise to 25 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, Annie Genevard, France’s minister of agriculture, described Mr. Trump’s comments as a form of “blackmail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s shocking because it’s brutal, it’s done to force compliance,” Ms. Genevard told the French television station TF1, describing it as a threat aimed at not only France but also other countries who have been invited to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reactions across France on Tuesday were angry, with many calling for a firm European response. Nathalie Loiseau, a member of the European Parliament and a former minister for European affairs, said on France Inter public radio that “positive parenting” is over with Mr. Trump and that “today is the time for firmness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Either we assert ourselves,” she said, “or we fade into history.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Macron raised the possibility that Europe could use its anti-coercion instrument — often called the “trade bazooka” — against the United States, which he said seemed “crazy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do regret that, but this is a consequence of just unpredictability and useless aggressivity,” Macron said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump announced his “Board of Peace” on Friday, and his administration later sent letters inviting countries to participate. The body’s charter suggests that Mr. Trump envisions it playing a role in a range of global conflicts, not only the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countries invited to join include close American allies such as Canada, Britain and Saudi Arabia, as well as countries with which the United State has had strained relations, including Russia and Belarus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, only a handful of leaders, including the pro-Trump Argentine president, Javier Milei, and Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary, have said they would join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time Mr. Trump has threatened France with steep tariffs. In March last year, he threatened to impose 200 percent tariffs on European wine, including Champagne, as part of a rapidly escalating trade war between the United States and the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump did not follow through on that threat. Even so, the episode rattled French Champagne producers, for whom the United States is the largest foreign market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Tuesday, Mr. Trump shared on Truth Social a screenshot of a message he received from Mr. Macron in which the French president offered to organize a Group of 7 meeting on Thursday afternoon after the World Economic Forum in Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron also offered to have dinner with Mr. Trump on Thursday, and told Mr. Trump that the two were aligned on Syria, while expressing confusion about the U.S. position on Greenland. Mr. Macron’s office confirmed the veracity of the message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ségolène Le Stradic and Ana Castelain contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-france-wine-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:56:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Suicides Were Frequent at the Golden Gate Bridge. Not Anymore.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/golden-gate-bridge-suicides.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20NAT-BRIDGE-SUICIDES-top-kvqg/20NAT-BRIDGE-SUICIDES-top-kvqg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Gate Bridge, the iconic span that hangs between San Francisco Bay and the Pacific Ocean, has been the site of more than 2,000 confirmed suicide leaps since its completion in 1937. The true death toll is certainly higher, since not all jumps are witnessed and not all bodies are recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2006, at least 34 people jumped to their deaths by crossing the four-foot rail and plunging more than 200 feet into the strait below. It was also the year that Paul Muller and two others with family members who had jumped from the bridge decided to do something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That something slowly evolved into a complicated, miles-long series of stainless-steel nets — a “suicide deterrent system” — now strung on both sides of the bridge. It is out of sight to the millions of people who cross the bridge every year, but plainly visible to anyone standing at the rail, looking down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, there had been an average of 30 suicides at the bridge each year. In 2024, as the final pieces of the net were installed and tweaks were made, there were eight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2025, the first full year with the nets in place, there were four, and none between June and December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That annual total is surely among the fewest ever recorded at the bridge, and seven months might be the longest stretch without a suicide at the bridge, though early records are sparse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The last seven months there were zero, so the results couldn’t be better,” Mr. Muller said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Muller was disheartened to learn that there has been one suicide early in 2026. But the goal all along was to save lives, and to eventually undo the dark magnetism of the bridge as a place to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denis Mulligan oversees the bridge operations as general manager of the Golden Gate Bridge, Highway and Transportation District. His office at the south end of the bridge overlooks the steady flow of cars, pedestrians and bikes that cross between San Francisco and Marin County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late 2023, as the installation of the nets was nearing completion, Mr. Mulligan said it would take a year or two of data collection to assess the impact of the nets on the death toll outside his window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in 2026, Mr. Mulligan considered the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The assessment is that the net is working as intended,” Mr. Mulligan said. “We’re trying to reduce the number of deaths. That’s what government should do, is protect the public. We were candid up front that nothing’s 100 percent, but that we think this is a worthwhile endeavor and good for the community. And we think a lot of people are alive today because of the project.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mulligan also oversees a vast electronic surveillance system and a team of on-bridge officers whose responsibilities include identifying and stopping those who are considering a leap. Last year, there were 94 successful interventions, about half as many as the average before the nets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nets” is a misnomer; they are taut, marine-grade stainless steel cables about 20 feet below the public walkways on both sides of the bridge. The idea is that anyone who jumps into the net will be injured enough, or at least shaken enough, to keep them from crawling out and intentionally falling the rest of the way to the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Mulligan, wary of attracting copycat attempts, declined to explain how those who have died by suicide the past two years have circumvented the nets. He also declined to say how many people have jumped into them and been rescued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the immeasurable number might be those who came to the bridge, spotted the nets and decided that suicide there was no longer possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1937, 10 weeks after the bridge opened, a 47-year-old World War I veteran reportedly said, “This is as far as I go,” and jumped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His was the first known suicide. Others followed. In 1939, the California Highway Patrol recommended that the four-foot rails be raised. For decades, decision makers ducked behind aesthetic concerns, costs and effectiveness. The death toll, loosely tracked, reached 500, then 1,000, and kept growing every week or two, on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frustrated by the inertia, Mr. Muller, Dave Hull and Patrick Hines founded the nonprofit Bridge Rail Foundation in 2006, with the hope of raising, finally, the height of the rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The overriding concept to the Golden Gate Bridge story is restricting easy access to lethal means,” Muller said. “It’s a way to reduce suicides that John and Jane Q. Public can do. You don’t need a lot of complex psychiatric training to, say, simply lock up the guns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or to make leaping into the ocean more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support grew slowly. Growing numbers of grieving families, mental health professionals, even coroners pleaded for something to be done. Eventually, the idea that took hold was borrowed from a solution used in Bern, Switzerland: nets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Debates raged, approvals came, construction bids opened and costs rose. There were legal squabbles with contractors. Construction began in 2018, meaning it took longer to install the nets than the four-plus years it took to build the bridge itself. What was once estimated to cost $76 million ended up costing $224 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics have long wondered if steering the suicidal away from the Golden Gate Bridge merely sends them elsewhere to take their own life. Net proponents do not think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 1978 study by Richard Seiden, at the University of California, Berkeley, tracked 515 people who, between 1937 and 1971, went to the Golden Gate Bridge intending to jump but had been persuaded not to. It found that 94 percent were still alive or had died of natural causes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Suicidal behavior is crisis-oriented and acute in nature,” Mr. Seiden concluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden Gate Bridge has long been a unique draw for the suicidal, some even coming from other states and countries. At the edge of the ocean, on one of the world’s most famous structures, it was a way to die somewhere both beautiful and notable. Death was almost certain. (Most jumpers are killed on impact, but those who survive usually drown.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And access was simple, with parking lots on both ends and public sidewalks along a short rail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The bridge has exerted a siren’s call for so long for some suicidal people that it might be hard for them to believe that it’s no longer the case,” said John Bateson, a longtime director of a suicide prevention center in the Bay Area and author of “The Final Leap: Suicide on the Golden Gate Bridge.” He writes a monthly newsletter for the Bridge Rail Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That might all explain why, while the number of suicides in 2025 were about one-seventh the pre-net average, interventions only dropped in half. People are still showing up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The more people who know that the barrier is in place will be discouraged for even thinking about the Golden Gate Bridge as a suicide destination,” Mr. Bateson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bridge Rail Foundation remains active, despite the successful completion of its original goal. It fields calls from officials around the world looking to reduce suicides from other bridges or high places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That might be the incalculable legacy of the work, beyond the raw number of lives saved at the Golden Gate Bridge. If one of the world’s most famous and deadliest bridges can prevent all but a few suicides, other places can probably do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s certainly the hope,” Mr. Bateson said. “From the outset, all of us have recognized that whatever happens on the Golden Gate Bridge is going to serve as a model for others.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are having thoughts of suicide, call or text 988 to reach the 988 Suicide and Crisis Lifeline or go to SpeakingOfSuicide.com/resources for a list of additional resources.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/golden-gate-bridge-suicides.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:01:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court to Hear Case Testing Limits of Hawaii Gun Law</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/supreme-court-hawaii-gun-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-scotus-hawaii-top-pwvq/20dc-scotus-hawaii-top-pwvq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can a Hawaii gun owner bring a concealed handgun to the grocery store? How about to a beachside restaurant, or when pulling into the parking lot of a coffee shop?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court on Tuesday will consider where exactly Hawaiians can carry weapons, hearing arguments in a key Second Amendment challenge to a state law banning concealed firearms on private property without advance permission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dispute over Hawaii’s gun restrictions has set up a clash between two rights championed by many of the court’s conservatives — robust private property protections and an expansive view of the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case, Wolford v. Lopez, could also provide the justices with a chance to clarify a new standard they set in a 2022 Second Amendment case, New York State Rifle &amp; Pistol Association v. Bruen. In its ruling, the court laid out a new test that required gun laws to be consistent with the country’s “history and tradition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That test has created chaos in lower courts, as judges have sorted through new challenges to gun laws — some on the books for years — to determine if historical records have provided analogies to modern-day gun regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2022 case, Justice Clarence Thomas, joined by the court’s other conservative justices, struck down a New York gun regulation and ruled that Americans had wide latitude to carry guns for self-defense outside their homes, in keeping with U.S. tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bruen case was the first time in more than a decade that the court had considered a major Second Amendment challenge, and was the first such case accepted by the conservative supermajority that took the bench in 2020. It immediately set off a scramble among states, including Hawaii and California, prompting a flurry of legislation. Some Democratic-led states moved to pass local gun restrictions in light of the new standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hawaii case is one of at least two Second Amendment cases the justices will hear this term that wrestle with how to apply the 2022 test. In March, the justices will consider another case, U.S. v. Hemani, that focuses on a challenge to a federal law that bans gun possession by people who use or are addicted to illegal drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hawaii lawmakers in 2023 revisited the state’s gun laws and swiftly passed restrictions on concealed carrying of handguns. The law banned concealed weapons in so-called sensitive places — schools, parks, playgrounds, beaches and restaurants that serve alcohol. It also imposed criminal penalties for carrying a concealed weapon onto private property without permission. Violators face potential criminal misdemeanor charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law required property owners to give explicit consent to carrying weapons, either by “unambiguous written or verbal authorization” or by the “posting of clear and conspicuous signage.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anne E. Lopez, Hawaii’s attorney general, wrote in a brief to the court that the law was an effort “to vindicate both the right to bear arms and property owners’ undisputed right to choose whether to permit armed entry onto their property.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hawaii has long had some of the country’s most restrictive gun laws, and is known for rarely granting concealed-carry permits. In court filings, officials traced their gun laws to the state’s unique history: its former traditions as a kingdom. They pointed to an 1833 law in place during the reign of King Kamehameha III that prohibited “any person or persons” from possessing deadly weapons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A coalition of Hawaii gun owners challenged the law. The group included a Maui realtor, Jason Wolford, and his wife, Alison, a nurse; Atom Kasprzycki, an architect; and the Hawaii Firearms Coalition, a gun rights group. They claimed that they had a “credible fear of arrest and prosecution” if they took their guns to places in Maui that they frequented, such as local restaurants, parks and beaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through their lawyer, Alan Alexander Beck, the plaintiffs declined to comment. In an interview, Mr. Beck said that “this law right now effectively eviscerates the ability to carry a firearm for self-defense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re taking a walk by yourself on an isolated beach, you may want to be able to defend yourself,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal trial court temporarily paused most of the new law’s provisions as the case moved through the courts, including the part requiring permission to carry weapons on private property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a panel of judges on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit overturned portions of the lower court’s ruling, clearing the way for Hawaii’s law to go into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judges drew parallels to the time of the country’s founding, and to Reconstruction following the Civil War — periods around when the Second and Fourteenth Amendments were ratified. They found that there were rules in those times that banned guns in establishments that sold alcohol and at some social gatherings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challengers then asked the Supreme Court to weigh in. They were soon joined by the Trump administration, which argued that Hawaii’s law violated the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a brief in support of the challengers, Trump administration lawyers argued that “because most property owners do not post signs either allowing or forbidding guns,” the state law “functions as a near-complete ban on public carry.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawyers also claimed that the law meant that anyone carrying a handgun for self-defense in ordinary places — a mall, gas station, convenience store, supermarket, restaurant, coffee shop or parking lot — “commits a crime.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case has prompted a raft of impassioned amicus briefs on both sides of the issue. Gun rights advocacy groups have asserted that Hawaii has been trying to get around the court’s Second Amendment rulings. Supporters of Hawaii’s law have argued that striking it down would clear the way for more gun violence.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/supreme-court-hawaii-gun-law.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:16:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Volunteers in Minnesota Deliver Groceries So Immigrants Can Hide at Home</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/minnesota-groceries-church-volunteer-ice-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-minn-food-1-fqvc/19nat-minn-food-1-fqvc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergio Amezcua arrived at the house carrying two boxes filled with groceries, but the man inside was afraid to come to the door. A blue sedan parked outside seemed suspicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t come out,” Mr. Amezcua, speaking in Spanish, told the man by phone. “Let me check the car first.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The car was empty, and Mr. Amezcua saw no signs of federal agents in the area. So the man appeared at the door, expressing gratitude for the food, and Mr. Amezcua, a pastor, prayed over him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As thousands of federal agents have flooded streets in the Minneapolis-St. Paul area to round up and deport undocumented immigrants, Mr. Amezcua, 46, has mobilized his church and organized free grocery deliveries to help people stay safely inside their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An effort that started with a couple of hundred deliveries a week quickly swelled into a vast operation involving thousands of volunteers, who have signed up at the church to pack boxes with donated grocery items and make deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Amezcua said that, so far, the church had received almost 25,000 requests for grocery deliveries through an online request form. Since the program started, he said, there have been 14,000 deliveries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Amezcua’s church, Dios Habla Hoy in south Minneapolis, offers services in English and Spanish to roughly 500 members. It organized a similar effort during the height of the Covid-19 pandemic, but that was smaller in scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To us, as Latinos in Minnesota, this is worse than Covid,” he said of the enforcement surge. “This is a bigger pandemic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our community is traumatized,” he added. “People that are born here are traumatized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Falling snow and freezing temperatures on Friday afternoon seemed to do little to slow the busy scene in the church’s parking lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A steady stream of volunteer drivers rolled into the lot, where their cars were loaded with grocery boxes that had been stacked on shipping pallets. Other people arrived to drop off donations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the church lobby, dozens of volunteers filled cardboard boxes with chicken, milk, fruit, paper towels, potatoes, flowers and, in some cases, hygiene products. A human chain snaked out the church doors to move the boxes to the staging area in the parking lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More volunteers crammed into the church sanctuary, waiting in lines to sign up to make deliveries. Some had their children in tow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Amezcua said that volunteers were vetted to make sure they had driver’s licenses and to try to prevent infiltration by federal agents. Once they are registered, volunteers are given an orientation on how to make deliveries and what to do if they encounter the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Germaine Grueneberg, a Minneapolis resident, was standing in line at the volunteer sign-up on Friday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the desperation is palpable right now, and we need to do something,” Ms. Grueneberg said. “I’m lucky enough to have the privilege of a comfortable home, being able to buy my own food and go out and feel somewhat safe, for the most part, and it’s about time that we support our neighbors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molly Kenny, a recent retiree, started volunteering last month to make deliveries, and she eventually took on a bigger role helping Mr. Amezcua run the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re literally building this as we go, and every day is a little bit different, so it really requires all of us to be super fluid and patient,” Ms. Kenny said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the food is packed off-site and supplied to the church by food bank organizations. Some of it is packed at the church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need is greater than the church can meet, Mr. Amezcua said, so he is focusing on expanding the effort and hopes to open up more food delivery hubs in other parts of the city. With no end to the Immigration and Customs Enforcement operation in sight, he said, the organizers are preparing for a long haul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pastor’s cellphone has been buzzing relentlessly since the federal surge began. He gets texts and calls from his staff about people showing up at the church to donate money or help out — and, just as often, he said, from church members alerting him about close calls with ICE or seeking information about sightings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the pastor was out making deliveries on Friday, a church member called him for help getting his car registration renewed because he was afraid to go to the Department of Driver and Vehicle Services office to do it in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Amezcua, who immigrated to the United States from the state of Sinaloa in Mexico, described himself as a conservative and said that when he first heard that ICE was coming to Minneapolis, he was not concerned. Agents would target people with criminal records, he thought, and then they would be gone after a couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the firsthand accounts he started hearing from community members about ICE’s aggressive tactics and its apparent targeting of nonwhite people changed his view, he said. Businesses, especially those serving or employing immigrants, have been decimated, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is literally racism in the name of patriotism — and a conservative guy is telling you that,” he said. “I feel betrayed by Donald Trump.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials have denied that agents target people based on their race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions have run high around the city, he said. Community observers patrol the streets and stand near businesses, keeping watch for any unmarked vehicle that might be carrying federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pastor, who drives a lifted pickup truck with tinted windows, said he himself had been mistaken for a federal agent while on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is where they showed me the finger,” he said, as he drove by a shopping center filled with Latino businesses on Friday. “They thought I was an ICE agent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when he drove back to the church grounds and saw two women peering into his truck from a stopped car, he got out to reassure them that he was the church’s pastor.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/minnesota-groceries-church-volunteer-ice-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Falsehoods Fueled Trump’s First Year Back in Office</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-falsehoods-fact-check-first-year.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/us/politics/dc-fact-check-2/dc-fact-check-2-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first year of his second term, President Trump has cited an arsenal of falsehoods, baseless claims and distortions to justify significant policy changes on the economy, immigration and deployments of the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His case for ushering in a turnaround rests on inaccurate superlatives (the “worst inflation” ever under his predecessor and the “best numbers” now under his presidency), mathematically impossible figures (a “600 percent” decline in drug prices) and evidence-free assertions (the decimation of maritime drug smuggling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a fact-check of some of the falsehoods that fueled Mr. Trump’s first year back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is exaggerated. Mr. Trump has long overstated the unauthorized migration under his predecessor and has wrongly portrayed most migrants as criminals. Likewise, contrary to his claims, most migrants deported in his first year back in office had no criminal convictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the 25 million figure is more than double than most credible estimates of unauthorized migration under the Biden administration. (And also a few million more than Mr. Trump’s own estimates of 21 million from July.) Mr. Trump has also not provided any evidence of his repeated assertion that “many” of those migrants were criminals and “some of the worst people on earth.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the 2021 to 2024 fiscal years, officials recorded roughly 11 million “encounters” of unauthorized migrants at borders and ports of entry, including about seven million at the southwestern border with Mexico. More than a quarter of the migrants were repeat offenders. Republican lawmakers have estimated that about 2.2 million more unauthorized migrants evaded detection during this time. And a March report from the Center for Migration Studies, a think tank that supports lower levels of immigration, estimated that 11.5 million to 12.5 million migrants — both legal and illegal — settled in the United States under the Biden administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most migrants detained by Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Mr. Trump’s first year had no criminal convictions. In late November, of the 65,000 people in detention, about 26 percent had a criminal conviction, 26 percent had pending charges and 47 percent had immigration violations, according to data compiled by the Transactional Records Access Clearinghouse, a nonprofit at Syracuse University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New York Times analysis of ICE arrests and detentions from Jan. 20 to Oct. 15 of last year found that just 7 percent of those arrested nationwide had a violent conviction. Thirty-seven percent had a previous conviction, with driving under the influence and traffic violations as the most common offenses. A third had no criminal charges at all. And in locales where ICE has conducted high-profile operations — Los Angeles, Chicago, Washington, D.C., and across Massachusetts — more than half had no charges at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the Trump administration has deported about 622,000 people since Jan. 20, 2025. Even if one assumed that all of them had criminal convictions, that would amount to about 2.5 percent of Mr. Trump’s own 25 million figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Was said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;False. Most metrics do not support Mr. Trump’s claim of transforming the economy from the “worst” to the “best.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inflation was 3 percent in January 2025, when Mr. Trump took office. That was far from the “worst” recorded — inflation was much higher in the 1980s, when it topped 14 percent. The rate declined slightly to 2.7 percent in December, the most recent month with available data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unemployment grew to 4.4 percent in December 2025, up from 4 percent that January. For comparison, unemployment surged to 14.8 percent in April 2020 during the coronavirus pandemic, and it was 6.4 percent in January 2021, the last month of Mr. Trump’s first term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nominal median wage growth, too, fell to 3.7 by December 2025 from 4.2 percent in January of that year. After adjusting for inflation, real hourly earnings grew at 1.1 percent in both December 2024 and December 2025, while real weekly earnings grew to 1.1 percent in December 2025 from 0.5 percent in December 2024. None of those figures were historically high or historically low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gross domestic product did increase to a robust 4.3 percent in the third quarter of 2025, compared with 1.9 percent in the last quarter of 2024. In comparison, the economy grew at a faster clip in the third quarter of 2023 at 4.7 percent and contracted in the first quarter of 2025 by 0.6 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A White House official cited two less commonly cited economic measures — the Federal Reserve’s industrial production index and its count of shipments of manufacturing orders — hitting record highs under Mr. Trump. But those measures rose slightly from January, when Mr. Trump took office, not from record lows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Was said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lacks evidence. Mr. Trump has long argued, falsely, that the Gilded Age was the most prosperous era in American history because of tariffs. In his prime-time address on the economy, he claimed to have reproduced that prosperity with his tariffs responsible for companies “building factories and plants at levels we haven’t seen” and convincing drug giants to lower the cost of prescription medicines by “400, 500 and even 600 percent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, his $18 trillion figure is almost double than the White House’s own tally of investments ($9.6 trillion). While it is possible that the pledges will result in economic gains, those effects have yet to come to fruition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The $9.6 trillion also includes broad pledges and previously announced projects. And more than half of that amount comes from informal pledges from foreign countries to invest in the United States that experts warn may be unrealistic. For example, Qatar and the United Arab Emirates each pledged more than $1 trillion in investments, which is more than their gross domestic products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so far, there is little evidence that Mr. Trump’s tariffs have ushered in a manufacturing renaissance, job and wage growth, or a decline in drug prices. Economists have said that the sustained economic growth in the United States was in spite of tariffs, not because of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector shed 63,000 jobs from January 2025 to December 2025. Construction spending in manufacturing has also declined. Economic activity in the sector in general contracted for 10 consecutive months in 2025, according to a longstanding survey by the Institute for Supply Management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s claim that his tariffs brought a decline of 400 to 600 percent in drug prices is not mathematically possible. A 100 percent decline would mean that the product is free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Consumer Price Index for prescription drugs rose by 2 percent from December 2024 to December 2025. Several independent research firms that track drug prices reported that pharmaceutical companies have raised the prices of hundreds of prescription drugs in the new year, with a median hike of 4 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that Mr. Trump has announced deals with several drug manufacturers to reduce the prices of some medicines. But the deals do not address the high cost of most drugs. And Mr. Trump’s tariffs may, on the contrary, raise the prices of drugs manufactured abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Was said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lacks evidence. Mr. Trump has authorized a series of military strikes against boats and the capture of the ousted president of Venezuela based on the faulty premise that its government was flooding the United States with deadly drugs. His contention that the strikes successfully decimated maritime drug trafficking is unsupported and unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary mode of trafficking drugs directly to the United States from Venezuela is by air, according to the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime. Major maritime routes for trafficking cocaine to the United States largely departed from Colombia, Ecuador and Central American countries, traveling through the Eastern Pacific Ocean (which Venezuela does not border). A 2020 report from the Drug Enforcement Administration noted that just 8 percent of documented cocaine was smuggled through the Caribbean corridor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House cited data from Customs and Border Protection showing that officials with the agency’s Air and Marine Operations in the United States seized a record amount of drugs in July — more than 220,000 pounds — and that number has since fallen to 2,000 pounds in December. But of that figure of 220,000 pounds, more than 200,000 pounds was of marijuana and it is unclear where those interdictions took place. Moreover, C.B.P. is not the only agency that seizes drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the strikes occurred, the Coast Guard continued to conduct other maritime drug enforcement operations. For example, the Coast Guard reported seizing nearly 20,000 pounds of cocaine across 10 days in November as part of Operation Pacific Viper. The Coast Guard also announced on Thursday the seizure of more than 2,200 pounds of cocaine in a 45-day patrol in the Caribbean and eastern Pacific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremy McDermott and Steven Dudley, the co-founders of InSight Crime, a Latin America crime and security think tank, wrote in a recent post that while the military strikes had likely disrupted some drug routes, the campaign had not halted trafficking altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This has not stopped the flow of drugs; it simply forced traffickers to use different routes and modus operandi,” they wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Was said&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is misleading. Mr. Trump has justified deploying National Guard troops to Democratic-led cities by overstating their crime rates, and then overstating the impact of those deployments. After the Supreme Court ruled in December that he could not deploy the Guard over the objections of local officials in Illinois, Mr. Trump instead asserted his authority to deploy more conventional troops to American cities — an authority, he argued misleadingly, that most other presidents had exercised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s claims about the National Guard’s effect on crime in Portland, Ore., were particularly inaccurate, as the Guard barely had a presence in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late September, after protests over immigration enforcement in Portland, Mr. Trump announced he would deploy the Guard to the city. Local officials challenged the deployment in court almost immediately. Emails released in court showed — and a Justice Department lawyer acknowledged — that about seven to 10 members of Oregon’s National Guard were briefly sent to an ICE building in downtown Portland from about 11:30 in the morning on Oct. 4 and left sometime at night, after a judge barred the deployment in the afternoon. After the Supreme Court ruling in December, Mr. Trump abandoned his efforts to deploy the Guard to Portland, Chicago and Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House cited a decline in crime from September, when Mr. Trump announced the deployment, to November. But even before the announcement and the half-day deployment of a handful of troops in October, crime in Portland had been falling, with homicides already declining by more than 50 percent in the first half of 2025 and violent crime down by 17 percent. Last year, the local police recorded 4,000 to 5,200 monthly offenses from January to November, the month with the most recent data available. The greatest number of offenses were recorded in October, the month with the brief appearance of National Guard troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s contention that half his predecessors have invoked the Insurrection Act of 1807, which gives the president broad authority to mobilize troops domestically under certain conditions, is overstated and leaves out critical context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the 1790s, 17 presidents have used or invoked the Insurrection Act a total of 30 times, according to a timeline compiled by the Brennan Center for Justice. That’s about 38 percent of all presidents. Most invocations — 19 instances — occurred before 1900. Many of the invocations in the last century occurred during the Civil Rights era. For example, President Dwight D. Eisenhower invoked the act after the governor of Arkansas deployed the state’s National Guard to stop nine Black students from enrolling at a high school in Little Rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most recently, President George H.W. Bush invoked the act twice, not 22 times as Mr. Trump said, in 1989 to quell looting after a hurricane in the Virgin Islands and in 1992 to quell unrest after the police beating of Rodney King. Mr. Bush invoked the act at the request of the California governor. In contrast, local officials in Democratic-led cities and states have resisted Mr. Trump’s deployment of troops.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-falsehoods-fact-check-first-year.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:19:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Calls U.K. Deal on Indian Ocean Islands ‘Great Stupidity,’ in Blow to Starmer</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-uk-chagos-islands-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-chagos-qcmk/20trump-news-chagos-qcmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump on Tuesday accused Britain of “an act of great stupidity” for agreeing to end British sovereignty over the Chagos Islands in the Indian Ocean, in a blow to Prime Minister Keir Starmer’s attempts to cultivate the president’s favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incendiary comments reversed the Trump administration’s previous policy over the Chagos Islands, a remote archipelago that Britain held since the colonial era and that houses a strategically important U.S.-British military base on Diego Garcia, the largest island in the chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, Mr. Starmer’s government agreed to relinquish control of the islands to Mauritius after years of negotiations, following a ruling by the United Nations’ highest court that found Britain had acted unlawfully by detaching the archipelago from Mauritius in 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of the deal, the United States and Britain could continue to operate the military base on Diego Garcia for an initial period of 99 years. At the time Secretary of State Marco Rubio praised the deal and said that Mr. Trump had “expressed his support for this monumental achievement,” which “reflects the enduring strength of the US-UK relationship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a post on Truth Social on Tuesday morning, Mr. Trump abruptly reversed that position and argued that the decision strengthened the case for the United States to acquire Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Shockingly, our ‘brilliant’ NATO Ally, the United Kingdom, is currently planning to give away the Island of Diego Garcia, the site of a vital U.S. Military Base, to Mauritius, and to do so FOR NO REASON WHATSOEVER,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “The UK giving away extremely important land is an act of GREAT STUPIDITY, and is another in a very long line of National Security reasons why Greenland has to be acquired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s comments are an embarrassment for Mr. Starmer, who has courted the president assiduously, and the comments were immediately seized on by the prime minister’s domestic political adversaries. Nigel Farage, a longtime ally of Mr. Trump and the leader of the right wing populist Reform U.K. party, wrote on social media, “Thank goodness Trump has vetoed the surrender of the Chagos islands.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking in Parliament on Tuesday, Stephen Doughty, a minister in Britain’s foreign office, said the government would “never compromise on our national security.” He added: “The agreement we have struck is vital for protecting our national security and that of our allies in guaranteeing the long term future of a base that is crucially important for the U.K. and the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than a day before Mr. Trump made his comments, Mr. Starmer gave a speech in Downing Street calling for calm discussion with the United States over Greenland and the threat of American tariffs. Like other countries in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, Britain has expressed its support for the right of Greenlanders to decide their own destiny.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-uk-chagos-islands-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:30:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Make America Go Away’ Caps Surge in Popularity as Trump Eyes Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/make-america-go-away-hats-greenland-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-hats-vjth/20trump-news-hats-vjth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bright red baseball caps reading “Make America Go Away” have surged in popularity among Danes and Greenlanders, who have adopted them as a symbol of resistance to President Trump’s push to acquire Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hats, which mock the “Make America Great Again” hats worn by Mr. Trump and his supporters, have become a conspicuous presence at recent protests, including demonstrations this weekend in Copenhagen and Nuuk, Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danish writing on the hats, “Nu det Nuuk,” uses “Nuuk,” Greenland’s capital to play on an expression that roughly means “enough is enough.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cap was designed last summer by Jesper Tonnesen, a Copenhagen vintage shop owner who was overwhelmed by global politics and the coarsening tone of international debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I felt powerless,” he said. “I wanted to do something — even if it was small.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, only a few of the hats sold in his shop. But last week, after an image of the hat began circulating online, demand skyrocketed. Within a matter of hours, Mr. Tonnesen’s stock had sold out, and orders outpaced what he could produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hat resonates with people, Mr. Tonnesen said, because it allows them to register dissent without adopting overly confrontational language. Humor, he added, makes it possible to signal opposition while inviting conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can laugh and still send a message,” he said. “It’s lightness in something very heavy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Tonnesen said he had also produced hats aimed at international audiences, including one bearing the slogan “Already Great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump, who this weekend linked his efforts to not winning the Nobel Peace Prize, doubled down Tuesday morning on his desire to acquire the island, a semiautonomous territory of Denmark, as European leaders gathered at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/make-america-go-away-hats-greenland-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:28:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bessent Attended a Supreme Court Argument. Now He’s Telling Powell Not to.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/bessent-powell-supreme-court-fed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-bessent-klgf/20dc-bessent-klgf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said on Tuesday that it is a mistake for Jerome H. Powell, the Federal Reserve chair, to attend oral arguments at the Supreme Court this week over whether President Trump has the authority to remove Lisa D. Cook, a governor at the central bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to CNBC on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Bessent said that Mr. Powell’s decision to attend the arguments on Wednesday risked further politicizing the Fed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you’re trying not to politicize the Fed, for the Fed chair to be sitting there trying to put his thumb on the scale is a real mistake,” Mr. Bessent said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Bessent is offering advice to Mr. Powell that he did not heed personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Supreme Court heard arguments in November over Mr. Trump’s authority to use a 1977 emergency law to impose tariffs on scores of countries, Mr. Bessent was in attendance. He sat in the front row of the gallery with Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick and the U.S. trade representative, Jamieson Greer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Treasury secretary told Fox News before the arguments that he wanted to be there and have a “ringside seat.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also considered attending the arguments last year but ultimately decided against it to avoid becoming a distraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Mr. Powell and the Federal Reserve as an institution are co-defendants in the case that the Supreme Court will be hearing. Mr. Bessent is not a defendant in the case on presidential tariff powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell is also not the first Fed chair to attend a Supreme Court argument. Paul A. Volcker attended in 1985 in the case of Governors of the Federal Reserve System v. Dimension Financial Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Mr. Bessent and Mr. Trump have made clear that the outcome of the tariff case will be pivotal to the administration’s economic agenda. They have warned that if the court rules against them, it will create chaos by forcing the government to refund billions of dollars of tariff revenue to businesses and weaken the president’s ability to negotiate with trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Powell will attend the arguments on the heels of his own confrontation with the administration, which he directly called out in an extraordinary video message last week after the Justice Department sent the central bank grand jury subpoenas seeking information about a $2.5 billion renovation project of the Fed’s headquarters in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview in Davos, Mr. Bessent said that he valued the independence of the Federal Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes, of course,” he told The New York Times. “I talk about it all the time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked about the criminal investigation into Mr. Powell and Mr. Trump’s attempts to fire Ms. Cook, Mr. Bessent said, “There still needs to be accountability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Cook, who has been a Fed governor since 2022, sued after Mr. Trump tried to oust her in August, arguing that the law that established the Fed allowed presidents to dismiss members only “for cause.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration has accused Ms. Cook of mortgage fraud. She has not been charged with wrongdoing, and denies the allegations, which relate to loan documents she signed before joining the Fed. The Supreme Court ruled in October that Ms. Cook could stay in her post while her lawsuit played out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter S. Goodman contributed reporting from Davos, Switzerland. Colby Smith contributed reporting from New York.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/bessent-powell-supreme-court-fed.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:37:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Struck Again by Hatred, a Mississippi Temple Says There Is More to Its Story</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/mississippi-beth-israel-temple-judaism.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-mississippi-synagogue-zmjw/20nat-mississippi-synagogue-zmjw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arsonist started the fire in the library, investigators said, incinerating shelves of prayer books and destroying two Torahs. The flames and smoke then spread rapidly through Beth Israel, the oldest synagogue in Mississippi, reaching the congregation’s Tree of Life display, with its ever-growing foliage of brass leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaves were engraved with messages celebrating bar and bat mitzvahs, weddings and the memories of family members and friends who had died. Some simply contained words of gratitude from one congregant to another — a way, as one put it, to recognize someone for “being a mensch.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tree was a prominent manifestation of what Beth Israel has been for more than a century: a refuge, a nucleus of fellowship for Jews in a part of the world where they are a tiny minority that could be overlooked and misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the tree was lost and, for the time being, so was that refuge, as the damage to the building was severe enough to displace the congregation indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s our history right there,” said Michele Schipper, who has worshiped at Beth Israel for some 40 years and could trace her family’s story through the leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attack on Jan. 10 — carried out, investigators said, by a 19-year-old driven by his hatred of Jewish people — has exposed once again the pernicious threat of antisemitism, as attacks and other incidents have increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the aftermath of the fire has been a heartening reminder of something else: The congregation might be small — with just over 140 families — but its members are not alone. They have one another. They also have a kinship with the broader community that has been forged over generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of Christian churches have offered help, including space to worship until the temple is restored. One church was returning a favor: When a group splintered off from a Baptist congregation in the mid-1960s, wanting one that wasn’t segregated, Beth Israel let members use its old temple until they could find a permanent home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not feeling like ‘us against them,’” said Rachel Myers, a leader in the congregation and longtime member. “It’s feeling like ‘all of us against him.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, a civic event originally planned as a sort of pep rally for the city became a vigil for Beth Israel. “In Jackson, we should know better,” Mayor John A. Horhn said as he led the crowd in prayer. “Lord, make our city a place where everyone can worship freely and live without fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate-fueled perpetrators had targeted the synagogue once before. The Ku Klux Klan bombed it in 1967, just months after the congregation finished building the synagogue, in retaliation for its rabbi’s speaking out in favor of racial integration. Then, as now, congregants were forced to reconcile the warmth and camaraderie that defined so much of their experience living in Jackson with a flash of darkness that threatened to eclipse it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s frustration and there’s sadness and there’s anger,” Zach Shemper, the congregation’s president, said. “Being resilient means you acknowledge those feelings, and then you think about the next step.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The congregation dates to 1860, when a group of Jews in Jackson bought land for a cemetery. Next came a simple wooden house of worship, which burned down in 1874. A local newspaper appealed for donations to help “our Jewish neighbors” build the synagogue — one of the earliest signs of the congregation’s becoming part of the city’s social fabric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From early on, Beth Israel’s leaders were deliberate about connecting with the community around them. That’s why the temple was built in 1967 on Old Canton Road, a strip lined with Christian churches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think that’s a coincidence,” said Stuart Rockoff, the executive director of the Mississippi Humanities Council, who has studied the history of Jews in the South. He is also a member of Beth Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mississippi has one of the smallest Jewish populations in the country, according to the Jewish Virtual Library: fewer than 3,000 people, in a state of nearly three million. It is a deeply Christian place where 100-foot crosses loom over interstate highways, business meetings sometimes begin with prayers offered “in Jesus’ name,” and one of the first questions that new acquaintances ask is, “Where do you go to church?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have to work hard in places like Jackson, Mississippi, to maintain your Judaism,” said Ms. Schipper, a Jackson native and the chief executive of the Goldring/Woldenberg Institute of Southern Jewish Life. It was housed at Beth Israel and was also displaced by the fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members have often had to be ambassadors for their faith and culture. “That’s part of your job, whether you like it or not,” Dr. Rockoff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One tradition is opening their doors to the community every year for the Beth Israel Bazaar, at which matzo ball soup and corned beef are served. When the tradition returned last year for the first time since the pandemic, the temple’s “kugel krewe” made 60 pounds of the noodle variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, the outreach has succeeded. When the “where do you go to church” question comes up, Dr. Rockoff said, “Beth Israel is an acceptable answer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some congregants said that as fears of antisemitism intensified in recent years, they believed their community had a measure of insulation from the worst of it — an assumption that held even immediately after the fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That morning, Ms. Myers and a few other congregants were reviewing security camera footage to send to the fire marshal when a hooded figure suddenly appeared in the frame. She gasped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suspect, who faces federal and state arson charges, was turned into the F.B.I. by his father after he admitted to setting the fire, telling his father that he had “finally got them,” according to an affidavit. He later told investigators that he specifically sought out the temple because of its “Jewish ties,” they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I really thought it was an electrical fire,” Ms. Myers said. “That, I think, says a lot about how I’ve been living my Jewish life here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, before the bombing, many Beth Israel members were wary, if not outright opposed, when Rabbi Perry Nussbaum, a Canadian new to the South, visited imprisoned civil rights activists and pushed for an integrated association for the city’s clergy, whom he invited to meet at the temple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as the broader Jewish American community took pride in its involvement in the civil rights movement, many Jews in the South kept their distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One explanation was “wanting to keep themselves and their families and livelihoods safe and not make too many waves,” said Rabbi Debra Kassoff, a congregant and community organizer. She learned soon after moving to Mississippi about this history and how it is still being wrestled with, as descendants of that generation balance empathy for the situation they were in and regret that they did not do more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the bombing, white and Black ministers organized a “walk of penance” on Old Canton Road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Penance was an interesting way of framing it,” Dr. Rockoff said, “almost apologizing for the culture that had led to that sort of violence.” A couple months later, the K.K.K. attacked again, setting off explosives at Rabbi Nussbaum’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many larger American cities, Judaism is reflected in a constellation of synagogues and organizations serving different denominations, movements, geographic roots, ethnic and racial histories and political ideologies. In Jackson, a city of about 140,000, they all have to fit in Beth Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everyone recognized that we want to have a place where we can bring our Jewish selves,” Rabbi Kassoff said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t mean to make it sound completely idyllic,” she added. “There are disagreements. There are resentments. There are people who stop turning up from time to time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she and others believe that navigating those differences has made the congregation stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening, the congregation’s members gathered again for services for the first time since the attack. They were in someone else’s house of worship, borrowing space from the Baptist church that had once borrowed it from them. No one knew when they could return home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, they were together, and for now, that was enough.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/mississippi-beth-israel-temple-judaism.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:57:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada’s Prime Minister Says There Has Been a ‘Rupture’ in the World Order</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/carney-davos-speech-world-economic-forum.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-HFO-carney-topart-wmbt/20trump-news-HFO-carney-topart-wmbt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada did not mention the United States or President Trump by name in a speech on at the World Economic Forum on Tuesday, but it was clear where he placed the blame for what he called a “rupture” in the world order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will talk today about the breaking of the world order, the end of a pleasant fiction and the beginning of a brutal reality where the geopolitics of the great powers is not subject to any constraint,” said Mr. Carney, who used a mixture of French and English in his address in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we are reminded that we live in an era of great power rivalry,” he said. “That the rules-based order is fading. That the strong do what they can, and the weak suffer what they must.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added, “Let me be direct: We are in the midst of a rupture, not a transition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney, who received a standing ovation, spoke not long after Mr. Trump posted an A.I. image on social media that included a map of American flags superimposed over both Canada and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney, a former investment executive who has served as the governor of Canada and England’s central banks was on familiar ground in Davos. His office estimated that he has attended the global gathering about 30 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday he arrived at a conference in turmoil over the rapidly growing rift between Europe and the United States because of Mr. Trump’s effort to make Greenland, which is controlled by Denmark, an American territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s hostility toward European allies over Greenland, which has included tariff threats, has led many Canadians to fear that he may act on his hope of annexing Canada as the 51st State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland, like the United States, is a neighbor of Canada. Canada and Denmark are members of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and have long been involved in military exercises in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Carney and his cabinet ministers have repeatedly denounced Mr. Trump’s plan, Canada has not joined European countries in sending troops to the island in a gesture of support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech on Tuesday, Mr. Carney said that Canada’s commitment to an article in the NATO treaty that views an attack on any member as an attack on all members was “unwavering.” That article was not written with the consideration that one member would be attacking another. It is also not clear that all NATO members would respond militarily to an attack on another member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada and the United States have a joint command for North American air defense. This week aircraft from both countries are at an American air base in Greenland as part of a regular training exercise that the joint air command said had been approved by Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech Mr. Carney called on medium-size countries like Canada to band together to offset the power of the United States, China and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The middle powers must act together because if you are not at the table, we’re are on the menu,” he said. “Great powers can afford now to go it alone.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/carney-davos-speech-world-economic-forum.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:32:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Swan Seeks Mate: Must Like Cold Lake and Small Flock</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/swan-mates-fundraiser-troy-illinois.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18xp-swans1/18xp-swans1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started with a sad black swan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The swan, who had recently lost his mate, would not move away from a vending machine at Tri-Township Park in Troy, Ill. The swan stared at his reflection below the Dr Pepper dispensers, thinking it showed his mate, park officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The swan needed a new partner, but the parks department would not be able to budget for new swans until April, said Sandy Pensoneau, the office manager at the Tri-Township Park District. So the agency decided to raise money to get a new match for the black swan, and for a white swan who had also just lost his mate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Park regulars had been clamoring for a response, Ms. Pensoneau said. “The people that walk the park every day, they’re like, ‘Hey, you guys need to do something. This is sad,’” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, the department posted a flyer on social media that asked the public to donate money to help the swans “find companionship again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want to help them feel safe, calm, and at home again by purchasing two new companion swans — and we need our community’s help to make that happen,” the flyer said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parks department has since raised $4,000, Ms. Pensoneau said in an interview on Tuesday morning. The bulk of the money was donated in the first 36 hours after the fund-raiser opened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new female black swan was purchased from a local family farm for $1,000 and is getting used to its new home at the park. Ms. Pensoneau said the two black swans are following each other everywhere. “I think they think they like each other,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black swans are monogamous, often staying with the same mate for life, according to Animal Diversity Web, a database maintained by the University of Michigan. They have been known to live for 40 years in the wild.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The white swan is a mute swan, which do not pair for life, but are monogamous for at least a season, according to Animal Diversity Web. The longest they are known to live in the wild is 19 years, and in captivity, 30 to 40 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two male swans who lost their mates have lived at the park in Troy, about 20 miles northeast of St. Louis, for about four or five years, Ms. Pensoneau said. The Tri-Township Park has more than a dozen soccer fields and baseball fields, as well as a lake where the swans and some ducks and geese live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two female swans passed away about three or four weeks ago, Ms. Pensoneau said. The white female swan had gotten caught in the lake’s ice over a weekend, and an unknown animal appeared to have attacked the black female swan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the black swan was matched with a new companion, KMOV, a local news station, reported that park regulars were giving it space. “He’s grumpy,” said Dustin Hayden, a park visitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parks department had also put a sign on the vending machine: “Swan thinks he sees his mate in reflection. He will be ok!!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The park’s white swan had a different response to its new solitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It flies off for a little bit and then comes back, flies off for a bit. I think it’s just looking for a mate,” Ms. Pensoneau said. “That’s why he keeps leaving for like a week at a time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, the white swan will be able to stop making these trips soon. The parks department has raised enough money to buy a new white female swan, which costs about $2,000. Ms. Pensoneau expects the department will purchase it this week. Once all four swans are living in the park, there will be a public vote to name them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Pensoneau thought only a few people might donate to the fund-raiser. “We are just absolutely amazed and thankful that the community has come together and wanted to help this cause,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/swan-mates-fundraiser-troy-illinois.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:25:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About California’s Proposed Tax on Billionaires</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/california-billionaires-wealth-tax.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-wealth-tax-explainer-ckwv/00nat-wealth-tax-explainer-ckwv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the final days of 2025, some of California’s wealthiest residents began cutting ties with the state by buying new homes and relocating business offices to Nevada, Texas or Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason? The possibility of a new tax on California billionaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the proposal faces political and legal hurdles, the itinerant billionaires were taking no chances. The proposal has set off a feverish debate in California, as well as a lot of confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know about California’s potential new tax on billionaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large labor union representing health care workers drafted an initiative called the “2026 Billionaire Tax Act” and is currently gathering signatures in hopes of putting it on the November ballot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization, Service Employees International Union-United Healthcare Workers West, largely represents employees at private hospitals, including cooks and janitors. Within California, the union is known for its aggressive use of the ballot initiative process to pressure health care companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voters may be familiar with the organization because it placed measures on three past ballots that would have placed new requirements on dialysis clinics, whose workers it wanted to unionize. None of those measures passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, supporters must gather nearly 900,000 valid signatures from California voters to place it on the ballot. In California, groups that have enough money can often qualify their measures by paying signature gatherers until they get enough petitions signed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, a majority of voters would have to approve it. If that happens, opponents would most likely file lawsuits immediately that would challenge its legality, so the tax would have to survive court challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative would require Californians with a net worth beyond $1.1 billion to pay a one-time tax equal to 5 percent of their assets, while those worth between $1 billion and $1.1 billion would pay a smaller percentage. It would apply retroactively to anyone who was living in California as of Jan. 1, 2026, and taxpayers could spread their payments across five years starting in 2027.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The union figures that California is home to approximately 200 billionaires who would have to pay the tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The state would be required to spend 90 percent of the new revenues on health care, with the rest devoted to food assistance and education. The health care workers union argues that the tax is necessary to make up for federal cuts to Medicaid, Affordable Care Act subsidies and food assistance that President Trump signed into law last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California’s nonpartisan legislative analyst and the governor’s Department of Finance estimated in a joint review that the tax would deliver tens of billions of dollars in one-time money for the state, but that it could lead to hundreds of millions or more in continuing losses from billionaires leaving California to avoid the tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the union behind the measure, Senator Bernie Sanders, Independent of Vermont, has endorsed the proposal. Representative Ro Khanna, Democrat of California, also backs it but said he would like to see provisions that allow start-up founders to defer the tax if their companies are not yet profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Gavin Newsom said this month that he had been working behind the scenes to try to stop the proposal and vowed to defeat it if it made the ballot. The governor said the mere introduction of the initiative was already hurting California by driving some billionaires to relocate, taking their tax dollars with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Business leaders have begun contributing money to oppose the measure. Peter Thiel, a venture capitalist and chairman of Palantir, has given $3 million to one effort. Ron Conway, a major tech investor, has donated $100,000 to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Sacks, a venture capitalist appointed by President Trump to guide policy on artificial intelligence and cryptocurrency, has been criticizing the billionaire tax proposal on social media and on the podcast he hosts with other Silicon Valley investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, other labor unions in California have remained quiet and may not support the ballot measure in the end. There are disagreements over how the tax is structured, as well as whether it is the right move politically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supporters could wage a compelling campaign that taps into voters’ economic anxieties and frustration about wealth inequality. They would most likely highlight the cuts to the health care system that are looming from the federal law Mr. Trump signed last year, and argue that hospitals could close without the billionaire tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voters are often leery of tax increases. But because very few voters would be required to pay the billionaire tax, most may be inclined to pass it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Newsom has already committed to killing the tax, and he holds considerable weight in California government. He is hoping to derail the proposal before it ever qualifies for the ballot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to reach the ballot, however, opponents would wage a fierce and costly campaign to fight the wealth tax. Billionaires could find allies in other labor unions that would not benefit from the tax and emphasize that it could decrease long-term funding for schools, universities and other popular services. They could argue that it would damage California’s start-up economy and diminish the state’s global standing as the cradle of technological innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opponents could also try to qualify rival measures for the same ballot. That could make it harder for proponents to get enough signatures or have the effect of confusing voters and prompting them to vote “no.” Opponents have already drafted a handful of initiatives that could undermine the billionaire tax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also possible that the union could fail to collect enough signatures. More than a dozen initiative efforts have paid petitioners asking voters for signatures at the moment, and some campaigns are paying more than the union has. Most other efforts aiming for the November ballot began collecting signatures earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the union has qualified measures before, it spent $1.9 million gathering signatures in 2018 for an initiative that called for a new tax on millionaires to pay for health care. The proposal never made it onto the ballot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California law gives initiative backers a window to negotiate with lawmakers at the State Capitol before the ballot is finalized. It’s not uncommon for groups to collect signatures as a way to build political leverage. Proponents are sometimes willing to pull their measures off the ballot if they can strike a satisfactory deal with lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The union backing the billionaire tax has said it is fully committed to the ballot route, but it has a history of using initiatives as leverage in its negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, it struck a deal with Mr. Newsom and legislative Democrats to pass a statewide $25 per hour minimum wage for health care workers after backing similar initiatives in various cities. In 2016, the union sponsored a statewide initiative to raise California’s minimum wage, but withdrew it from the ballot after then-Gov. Jerry Brown signed legislation increasing the wage to $15 an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/california-billionaires-wealth-tax.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:26:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump-Backed Challenger Enters Race to Unseat Senator Bill Cassidy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/julia-letlow-trump-louisiana-senate-bill-cassidy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/us/politics/pol-letlow-louisiana2/pol-letlow-louisiana2-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Julia Letlow of Louisiana said on Tuesday that she was officially running for Senate, challenging Senator Bill Cassidy in a Republican primary contest days after President Trump said he would back her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“RUN JULIA RUN!!!” Mr. Trump wrote in a social media post on Saturday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Letlow made her announcement at a breakfast of business leaders on Tuesday, according to a report in the Greater Baton Rouge Business Report, and she later posted a video online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am grateful for the courageous leadership of our president,” she said. “I’ve witnessed firsthand how President Trump is taking on the swamp and delivering for the American people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy said in a statement that Ms. Letlow had called him to share the news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She said she respected me and that I had done a good job,” he said. “I will continue to do a good job when I win re-election. I am a conservative who wakes up every morning thinking about how to make Louisiana and the United States a better place to live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Letlow entered Congress in 2021 after her husband died from the coronavirus weeks after he won a congressional race in 2020. She ran in a special election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy already faces several other primary challengers, including John Fleming, the Louisiana treasurer and a former congressman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy has been an occasional critic of Mr. Trump, but he most notably voted to convict the president in his second impeachment trial five years ago. Years after Mr. Trump pushed during the 2022 midterm elections to excise House Republicans who voted to impeach him, he is now trying to punish Mr. Cassidy in the first election the senator has faced voters since his impeachment trial vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Letlow made an oblique reference to this in her kickoff video, saying, “We shouldn’t have to wonder how our senator will vote when the pressure’s on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has for months privately mulled backing Ms. Letlow. The New York Times reported over the weekend that Mr. Trump first met with her in March 2025 and said that he would support her but that he would lie low to avoid a repeat of the president’s clashes with Mitt Romney, a former senator who routinely and publicly clashed with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cassidy, a physician, had made some attempts to make amends with Mr. Trump, most notably voting last year to confirm Robert F. Kennedy Jr. as health secretary, despite the senator’s advocacy for vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary election is on May 16. Mr. Cassidy had $9.5 million in his campaign accounts as of October, while Ms. Letlow had $2.3 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Letlow’s candidacy sets off the second major challenge of a sitting Republican senator from the right this year. In Texas, Senator John Cornyn is in a three-way race with Ken Paxton, the state attorney general, and Representative Wesley Hunt.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/julia-letlow-trump-louisiana-senate-bill-cassidy.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:39:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greenland’s Leader Says He Cannot Rule Out an American Attack</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-denmark-supplies-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-denmark-topart-wpmb/20trump-news-denmark-topart-wpmb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States was “not likely” to use military force against Greenland but it cannot be completely ruled out, Greenland’s prime minister, Jens-Frederik Nielsen, said on Tuesday, as President Trump repeated his threat to seize control of the semiautonomous Danish territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nielsen appeared at a news conference in the capital of Nuuk beside a former prime minister, Mute B. Egede, who said that territorial officials were reviewing their civil preparedness strategies. Those preparations could include asking all households to have five days of food supplies, Mr. Egede said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We must be prepared for all the things that may happen,” said Mr. Egede, who is now a member of Greenland’s parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both officials reiterated that Greenland — as part of the Danish kingdom — is part of NATO and warned that any escalation would have consequences beyond its shores. They also condemned Mr. Trump’s threats on social media, which Mr. Nielsen called “disrespectful.” He said Greenland would respond through formal channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, there has been no official call for Greenlanders to stock up on essential household supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar messages from governments in the Nordic region have been issued to address rising threats in recent years. In late 2024, Sweden, Finland, Denmark and Norway updated their advice for citizens preparing to survive war and other crises. At the time, their main concern was Russian aggression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s insistence that the United States will take action regarding Greenland “whether they like it or not” has upended the longstanding international order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. president, emboldened since the American military captured the Venezuelan president in a raid, has ramped up his rhetoric on Greenland, threatening to impose tariffs on longstanding European allies to force negotiations to take control of the massive island. The result has been that Greenland is afraid, Denmark is angry and Europe is standing in opposition to Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mette Frederiksen, the Danish prime minister, on Tuesday remained in Copenhagen to address Denmark’s parliament instead of attending the start of the annual meeting of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. She said neither Danes nor Greenlanders had wished to become “the center of a conflict between the United States and Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours after Mr. Trump ratcheted up his feud with European leaders, Ms. Frederiksen described his actions as a threat to Danish territory and Greenland’s right to self-determination. She warned that neither the United States nor Denmark would benefit from a trade war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“On both sides, a trade war will cost jobs,” she said, a day before Mr. Trump was expected to attend the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. “On both sides, it will harm the economy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly said control of Greenland is a matter of U.S. national security. On Monday, Denmark sent a small contingent of about 100 soldiers to western Greenland, along with the Danish army chief, Peter Boysen, the Danish state broadcaster reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts have said Denmark’s move to increase its military presence in Greenland seemed to be part of an effort to show Mr. Trump that the country was taking his concerns about security seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For their part, Greenland’s leaders have repeated their position that their island is not for sale and they do not want to be part of the United States. Mr. Nielsen, Greenland’s prime minister, said that if Greenlanders had to choose, they would rather stay aligned with Denmark, their former colonizer.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-denmark-supplies-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:34:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In U.S. Attorney Standoff, Judges in Virginia Seek to Fill Top Prosecutor Job</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/virginia-us-attorney-halligan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/dc-halligan-lwkb/dc-halligan-lwkb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal judges in the Eastern District of Virginia are seeking applicants to become the U.S. attorney there, signaling that President Trump’s handpicked choice, Lindsey Halligan, has run out of time as the top prosecutor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The public request is the latest move in a monthslong standoff between the Trump administration and the judges who sit in that district. The dispute has potential consequences for federal prosecutors around the country because the administration has used a similar personnel maneuver to install others into U.S. attorney positions in Nevada, California, New York and New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, a judge ruled that Ms. Halligan’s appointment was invalid, stating that Mr. Trump and Attorney General Pam Bondi had not followed the law in selecting U.S. attorneys. In September, Mr. Trump forced out Ms. Halligan’s predecessor to install her instead, despite her lack of prosecutorial experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Halligan quickly indicted two of the president’s foes, the former F.B.I. director, James B. Comey, and Letitia James, the New York attorney general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those indictments were thrown out of court in November after a federal judge determined Ms. Halligan’s appointment was unlawful. Since that ruling, some judges in the district have expressed concern and frustration that Ms. Halligan continues to claim she is the U.S. attorney for the Eastern District of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a new order, the court noted that Ms. Halligan’s appointment, even if it were valid, expires Tuesday, suggesting once again that the judges expect her to step aside. The court system separately asked for “expressions of interest” from any lawyers interested in being appointed to serve as an interim U.S. attorney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Justice Department did not immediately comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal law allows for the judges in a district without a Senate-confirmed U.S. attorney to select a temporary replacement, and the court’s moves Tuesday suggest it plans to go forward with doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the court did appoint a new U.S. attorney, it is likely that the president would simply fire that person and put his own choice — possibly Ms. Halligan — back in the job.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/virginia-us-attorney-halligan.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:33:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>One Year In, Searching for a Strategy Behind Trump’s Unpredictability</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-one-year-unpredicatability.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/us/politics/20DC-TRUMP-TEAR-TOP-new/20DC-TRUMP-TEAR-TOP-new-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One year and a seemingly infinite number of news cycles ago, Donald J. Trump returned to Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city was drunk with expectation and dread that first weekend leading into his inauguration. Trump supporters palled around town in pedicabs blaring “Y.M.C.A.” Plutocrats partied on yachts in the Potomac. Tech billionaires sat cheek to jowl in the Capitol Rotunda, licking their lips. Democrats looked in a daze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president who had been left for political dead was regenerated, bigger and bolder than ever, back inside the building that a mob of his supporters attacked four years earlier. The world tried to wrap its head around the thought — the reality — of a second Trump presidency. What would it be like this time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official photograph of Mr. Trump printed inside the programs that day was a startling image that thrilled some and terrified others. Bathed in eerie light from below, high-powered strobes reflected in his eyes, he glared out from the portrait and into the future he was about to conjure for us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordinarily, by the one-year point in a presidency, it is possible to connect certain dots so that a coherent picture begins to come into focus, showing us where a president is taking the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, there is conspicuousness — Mr. Trump seems to be everywhere, in everything — but there is little consistency or predictability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been the great truth of Trump II so far, and anyone who has spent time in Washington this past year has experienced it in some way big or small. European leaders. Republican allies. Military commanders. Media executives. Financiers. Oilmen. Journalists trying to make sense of the daily machinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these people have any idea what tomorrow holds. It doesn’t seem knowable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a business forum in Qatar last month, Donald Trump Jr. said that “what’s good about my father, and what’s unique about my father, is you don’t know what he’s going to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The son called the father “the most unpredictable person, probably in the history of politics.” He wouldn’t get any argument there from anyone in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president’s supporters sent him back to this place to disrupt. They see his ability to keep everyone guessing as one of his supreme strengths, a strategy unto itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But one year since his return to power, this question has only deepened: Is there a strategy behind all this terrific unpredictability — or does it reflect the absence of one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tariffs come on. Tariffs come off. Tariffs come on again, but only partially. Tariffs come off again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration spent the last six months trying to hash out a trade deal with the European Union. That deal blew up spectacularly this weekend after Mr. Trump suddenly decided to threaten eight European nations with new tariffs until they agree to sell Greenland to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very same European heads of state now being threatened by Mr. Trump had spent the year making pilgrimages to Washington, separately and then all together in August, to endear themselves to him. Oftentimes, it seemed to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that August confab, Mr. Trump talked about how much he admired everyone gathered at his table. He said that Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain was “my friend.” President Emmanuel Macron of France had “been with me from the beginning.” The NATO secretary general? “Doing a fantastic job.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe, on that day, Mr. Trump really did feel that way. But so what? These days, the Europeans are conducting military exercises in Greenland amid Mr. Trump’s increasingly menacing designs on the icy land mass in the North Atlantic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president spent half the year bullying Canada until Canada’s new prime minister went to the White House. “I love Canada,” Mr. Trump claimed at that meeting. Asked then what “concession” he wanted from Canada, he said only “friendship.” But how can the Canadians be sure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can anyone be sure of anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning last week, Mr. Trump announced that he was close to invoking the Insurrection Act of 1807 to send troops into Minnesota to put down the protests that had broken out after an ICE agent shot and killed a woman there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very next morning, this extraordinary development was off. As he traipsed across the South Lawn of the White House to make his way down to Palm Beach, Fla., for the weekend, Mr. Trump casually declared that there was no need for the Insurrection Act. Preparing for the possibility that Mr. Trump might change his mind again, the Pentagon told 1,500 active-duty troops to ready for a possible deployment to Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most illuminating things Mr. Trump said this year was that it was important for the United States to actually own Greenland “because that’s what I feel is psychologically needed for success.” Psychologically important for him, or for the United States, he was asked? “Psychologically important for me,” he answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His psychology is his doctrine. Foreign policy, the economy, domestic politics — all plans and policies in Washington now come filtered through the overmastering prism of this “unpredictable” psyche.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is the capo dei capi of chaos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So many events this year have been so absurd, so abrupt, or so operatic that they have contributed to a general atmosphere of destabilization — of entropy and caprice and expediency — in the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember Elon Musk? He was such a central character for the first half of the year, lording over cabinet meetings, giving news conferences while standing beside the Resolute Desk, until one day his time in Washington was over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He showed up to the West Wing for his last day of work with a black eye (which he blamed on his toddler). Mr. Trump gave him an oversize novelty key to the White House and sent him on his way. A few days later, the two men got into a nasty fight in which the mogul accused the president of covering up Jeffrey Epstein’s crimes and the president threatened to use the power of the government to destroy the mogul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was the public to make of any of this? The two are said to be friends again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One morning in October, everybody in Washington woke up and, poof, the East Wing was gone. The president had insisted his plans for a White House ballroom would pay “total respect to the existing building.” Well, the building doesn’t exist anymore. All that’s left of the East Wing is a pile of mud that’s been dumped in the middle of a public golf course in the Potomac. Cranes currently encircle the White House, and the plans for the ballroom keep changing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president seized control of the Kennedy Center and put a crew of right-wing political operatives in charge of it. Ticket sales plummeted. He decided to host the Kennedy Center Honors himself. Ratings plummeted. His name was put on the front of the building. The Washington National Opera departed. He has declared the institution saved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presidential mood swings play themselves out in televised cabinet meetings that can go from dark and stormy to sunny and funny over the course of an hour. The morning after he single-handedly provoked this weekend’s diplomatic uproar, as European leaders hurriedly convened an emergency meeting in Brussels, Mr. Trump directed his motorcade to … a furniture store in Palm Beach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;White House officials did not respond to an inquiry asking what sort of furniture he was looking to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On balance, there has been no balance. Only imbalance. Sometimes, a measure of imbalance is what’s needed to shake up sclerotic institutions, relationships, old ways of thinking — and that is what Mr. Trump’s supporters sent him back here to do one year ago to the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a lot of what’s happened since last January has left much of Washington and the world with what seems like a strange new variety of American vertigo.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-one-year-unpredicatability.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:15:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens New Trade War as Court Weighs Whether to Check Him</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-tariffs-supreme-court.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-tariffs-jgbq/20dc-tariffs-jgbq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court could soon curtail President Trump’s ability to swiftly impose tariffs on allies and adversaries around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that hasn’t slowed down Mr. Trump, who has issued a series of new, belligerent threats against European countries in recent days that have threatened to start another trade war with some of America’s closest allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to reporters on Monday, Mr. Trump casually threatened a 200 percent tariff on French wine and champagne, unless Emmanuel Macron, the president of France, chose to join a “board of peace” Mr. Trump set up last year for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll put a 200 percent tariff on his wines and champagnes, and he’ll join, but he doesn’t have to join,” Mr. Trump told reporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threat came just days after Mr. Trump said that eight European countries would be hit with escalating tariffs unless they agreed to sell the Danish territory of Greenland to the United States. The regional bloc has staunchly resisted that demand, describing it as destabilizing for global peace, as some countries have started to explore retaliatory measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal experts said that Mr. Trump would most likely issue the new tariffs using the same emergency law that he has used to target imports from nearly every country during his second term. That law, the International Emergency Economic Powers Act, is under scrutiny at the Supreme Court, after small businesses and states sued on grounds that Mr. Trump had overstepped his authorities to tax imports from nearly every U.S. trading partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Hillman, a professor at Georgetown University Law Center, said that Mr. Trump had abused the law to declare “anything he wants” — from Brazil’s prosecution of Jair Bolsonaro, a political ally of Mr. Trump’s, to the president’s desire to take over Greenland — “to somehow be an unusual and extraordinary threat to U.S. security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He is attempting to turn a limited sanctions statute into a broad mandate to do anything,” Ms. Hillman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know if the Supreme Court justices have already made up their minds in the IEEPA case, but I would hope that if they have not, that this further abuse of IEEPA would reinforce the need for the court to step in and declare that IEEPA cannot be used in this way,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By midday Tuesday, Mr. Trump’s newest ultimatum appeared to trouble financial markets around the world, as investors braced for the possibility of a trans-Atlantic, tit-for-tat dispute that could harm both sides. Yields on U.S. bonds spiked, the S&amp;P 500 dropped over 1 percent and the Vix volatility index, known as Wall Street’s fear gauge, rose to its highest since November. The administration largely shrugged off the turbulence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Bessent, the Treasury secretary, attributed the market gyrations instead to hiccups in the Japanese bond market. Speaking at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Bessent told European leaders to “sit back, take a deep breath, do not retaliate” and await Mr. Trump’s arrival at Davos this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Trump proceeds with his tariffs — and Europe responds — growth in U.S. economic output could fall by half a percentage point next year, according to a report released Monday by Oxford Economics. Some experts questioned whether the president’s threats might ever achieve their intended result, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tariffs are typically not a great tool for getting governments to do what you want, but they’re particularly ill-suited for something like this, where you already have tariffs in place,” said Scott Lincicome, the vice president of general economics at the Cato Institute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “It beggars belief that a 10 percent tax that’s mainly borne by Americans is going to somehow cause all of Europe to cave on something as serious as this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other legal experts questioned how much the Supreme Court decision would actually curtail the president’s power. The nation’s justices have been weighing the president’s use of IEEPA, a 1977 law, to swiftly raise and lower tariffs on a variety of trading partners over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some analysts described Mr. Trump’s threat of tariffs over Greenland as his most outlandish and unconventional use of the statute to date. But the president has relied on the emergency law to impose tariffs for a variety of reasons, including trying to reduce trade deficits, stopping inflows of illegal drugs and addressing other international situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court could decide to revoke some or all of those tariffs — or it could decide to allow the president’s approach. Mr. Trump could then impose steep duties by other means — and his aides have indicated they are exploring options to do so — but none would allow the president to raise or lower tariffs so flexibly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan Majerus, a partner at King and Spalding, said he would be “surprised” if the Supreme Court held that the emergency law could never authorize tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the administration believes it will retain the authority to use this law at least in some situations dovetailing with national security interests,” Mr. Majerus said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-tariffs-supreme-court.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:13:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prosecutors Subpoena Minnesota Democrats as Part of Federal Inquiry</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/subpoena-minnesota-democrats-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/dc-minnesota-tzqh/dc-minnesota-tzqh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal prosecutors issued subpoenas on Tuesday to at least five Democratic officials in Minnesota, ramping up the Justice Department’s investigation into their response to the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown in the state, according to two people familiar with the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subpoenas sought documents from Gov. Tim Walz, Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis and Mayor Kaohly Her of St. Paul related to their policies on immigration enforcement efforts in the state. Two Minnesota prosecutors, Keith Ellison, the state attorney general, and Mary Moriarty, the Hennepin County attorney, were also sent similar subpoenas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subpoenas, all of which were formally served on the officials’ offices, represent a significant expansion of the inquiry into Minnesota leaders that was disclosed late Friday. The investigation was initially said to have focused on Mr. Frey and Mr. Walz, who have both criticized the crackdown. But it now appears that prosecutors will also scrutinize other public officials, including Mr. Ellison and Ms. Moriarty, who could open their own inquiries into the fatal shooting in Minneapolis this month of a 37-year-old woman, Renee Good, by a federal immigration agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the subpoenas did not cite a specific criminal statute, the inquiry as a whole was said to center on whether elected officials in Minnesota had conspired to impede the thousands of federal agents who have been in the state since last month looking for undocumented immigrants. But the investigation is likely to run up against stiff pushback for examining political speech and conduct that is traditionally protected by the First Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Ms. Good, an unarmed mother of three, has led to sustained protests against federal agents in Minneapolis. In the immediate aftermath of Ms. Good’s death, Mr. Frey used an expletive to demand that agents leave the city. Mr. Walz has also sharply criticized the agents’ conduct, asking residents to monitor their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice Department leaders, in turn, have vowed to arrest anyone impeding the agents’ mission. Todd Blanche, the deputy attorney general, recently accused Mr. Frey and Mr. Walz of “encouraging violence against law enforcement” and referred to their actions as “terrorism.” But there is no evidence that either man has incited violence — let alone engaged in acts of terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigation into the elected Democrats comes as the Justice Department has all but announced that it will not bring charges against Jonathan Ross, the agent who killed Ms. Good. Instead, the department has signaled that it intends to scrutinize possible connections between Ms. Good and her partner, Becca Good, and left-wing protesters in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That decision led to the resignation last week of six prosecutors in the U.S. attorney’s office in Minneapolis. Among those who quit was Joseph H. Thompson, the office’s second in command, who oversaw a sprawling fraud investigation that President Trump and his allies have repeatedly used to criticize Democratic leaders in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal investigators have refused to cooperate with state and local officials like Mr. Ellison and Ms. Moriarty, who have the power to open their own inquiries into Ms. Good’s killing. But the subpoenas they received could further complicate their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Trump administration has started enlisting prosecutors and agents from other states to travel to Minnesota to assist in pursuing criminal cases against protesters they claim have impeded the activities of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents. Over the weekend, Attorney General Pam Bondi pressed U.S. attorneys in Midwestern states to provide personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten federal prosecutors from Michigan have been assigned to work in Minnesota for the time being, according to people familiar with the matter. Additional prosecutors are expected to arrive in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have repeatedly said that ICE agents have been under sustained assault from protesters. But prosecutors have only filed a handful of criminal cases related to the protests since Ms. Good was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department needs additional personnel in part because so many senior prosecutors left the Minneapolis office rather than follow orders from the department’s leaders to conduct a criminal investigation into Ms. Good. The office already faced a significant staff shortage because many prosecutors had left last year as the Trump administration offered buyouts and encouraged prosecutors to quit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To try to address the shortage, Justice Department leaders plan to draw staff from six states: Michigan, South Dakota, North Dakota, Iowa, Nebraska and Wisconsin, according to people familiar with the matter and internal department communications.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/subpoena-minnesota-democrats-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:56:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota Police Leaders Criticize Federal Tactics in ICE Surge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/ice-minnesota-police-axel-henry.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-minnesota-placeholder-tlzm/20nat-minnesota-placeholder-tlzm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three top Minnesota police officials on Tuesday criticized the tactics that federal agents have used during their immigration crackdown and described a region where residents, including those with legal status, were scared to venture outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of the officials said they knew of United States citizens, including a police officer and city workers, who had been stopped and questioned by immigration agents. And they expressed concern that the Trump administration’s surge of some 3,000 federal agents to Minnesota was undermining residents’ trust in law enforcement and disrupting daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Can we find a way to make sure that we can do these things without scaring the hell out of our community members and freaking everyone out?” Chief Axel Henry of the St. Paul Police Department asked at a news conference. He added that many people in his city “are scared to death” and “afraid to go outside.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately provide a statement in response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news conference, which also included Sheriff Dawanna S. Witt of Hennepin County and Chief Mark Bruley of the Brooklyn Park police, revealed escalating tensions between federal officials and Minnesota law enforcement leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security has repeatedly criticized state and local policies that limit coordination with immigration agents. On Tuesday, the Justice Department issued subpoenas to at least five Democratic officials in Minnesota — including Gov. Tim Walz, Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis and Mayor Kaohly Her of St. Paul — related to their policies on immigration enforcement efforts in the state, according to two people familiar with the matter. Mr. Walz dismissed the investigation in a statement as a “partisan distraction.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Minnesotans are more concerned with safety and peace than baseless legal tactics aimed at intimidating public servants standing shoulder to shoulder with their community,” the governor said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elected leaders in Minnesota have repeatedly called on Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents to leave the state, and a lawsuit filed by the state and the cities of Minneapolis and St. Paul claims that the surge is unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has defended its work in Minnesota as necessary to crack down on illegal immigration and root out fraud in state social service programs. In a court filing on Monday, the administration said that more than 3,000 people who were in the country illegally had been arrested during the campaign. Many of those people, federal officials said, had been convicted of serious crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in their news conference, the local police officials criticized what they described as heavy-handed tactics from federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We demand more from our federal government — more professionalism, more accountability, more humanity,” said Sheriff Witt, who said she was especially concerned about claims of racial profiling by federal agents. “We demand lawful policing that respects human dignity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devlin Barrett, Alan Feuer and Glenn Thrush contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/ice-minnesota-police-axel-henry.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:59:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Penn Calls Government’s Demand for Lists of Jewish Staff ‘Disconcerting’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/university-of-pennsylvania-trump-jewish-staff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-penn-lhzj/20nat-penn-lhzj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Pennsylvania on Tuesday condemned Trump administration investigators for seeking records about Jewish employees, saying in a federal court filing that the request was “disconcerting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The university and the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission have been at odds for months over an investigation into antisemitism at Penn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions roared into public view in November, when the Trump administration sued the university because it had “refused to comply” with a subpoena that sought information about employees who brought complaints about antisemitic discrimination and those who are members of Jewish groups on campus, among other people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demand prompted a campus uproar, and in a blistering response on Tuesday, Penn described the request as an “extraordinary and unconstitutional demand.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The E.E.O.C. insists that Penn produce this information without the consent — and indeed, over the objections — of the employees impacted while entirely disregarding the frightening and well-documented history of governmental entities that undertook efforts to identify and assemble information regarding persons of Jewish ancestry,” the university said in a filing in Federal District Court in Philadelphia. “The government’s demand implicates Penn’s substantial interest in protecting its employees’ privacy, safety and First Amendment rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Penn declined to comment beyond its 163-page filing on Tuesday. In its filing, the university said that the E.E.O.C.’s request had “alarmed” members of the university’s Jewish community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The E.E.O.C., which previously said it was seeking information that could be relevant to its “investigation of potential unlawful employment practices, namely religious, national origin and race-based harassment,” did not immediately respond to a request for comment, nor did the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Liz Huston, a White House spokeswoman, said the administration would “always aggressively enforce the law” and that the university “should comply with the straightforward subpoena and demonstrate their commitment to safeguarding their students.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its submission on Tuesday, Penn said it had told the commission in September that it was willing to send notices to all employees “informing them of the agency’s desire to hear about any experiences of antisemitism, together with instructions about how to contact the E.E.O.C. directly.” Within hours, according to the court filing, the E.E.O.C. told Penn it would seek to enforce its subpoena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission has a Jan. 27 deadline to respond to Penn’s filing.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/university-of-pennsylvania-trump-jewish-staff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:48:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Comer Rejects Clinton Interview on Epstein, Setting Up Contempt Vote</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/comer-clinton-interview-epstein.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-clintons-cbqp/20dc-clintons-cbqp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negotiations between Representative James R. Comer of Kentucky, the Republican chairman of the Oversight Committee, and Bill and Hillary Clinton over their refusal to testify in his panel’s Jeffrey Epstein investigation broke down on Tuesday, hours before a scheduled vote to hold the couple in contempt of Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Comer refused an offer to interview the former president under oath in his New York office, rejecting terms he said were untenable and vowing to go forward with the vote as planned on Wednesday. That would be the first step in a process that could potentially lead to the Clintons’ criminal prosecution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The breakdown came after days of delicate negotiations between a top aide to Mr. Comer and lawyers for the couple over the conditions under which Mr. Clinton would sit for the interview, as the couple sought a compromise that could spare them a contempt vote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clintons have remained adamant that they would not appear at a formal deposition with the committee, accusing Mr. Comer of pursuing a politically driven process “literally designed to result in our imprisonment” and promising to fight the chairman on the issue for as long as it takes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes, their lawyers had been negotiating directly with Mark Marin, Mr. Comer’s staff director, seeking a deal that could result in the lifting of the subpoenas his panel has issued to both Clintons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their latest offer, according to people familiar with the matter, was an interview under oath in Mr. Clinton’s New York office with Mr. Comer and Representative Robert Garcia of California, the ranking Democrat on the committee, both of whom would be accompanied by a staff member taking notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a statement, Mr. Comer said the offer was unreasonable because it did not include an official transcript of the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the people involved in the matter on behalf of the Clintons said they had never ruled out a transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Clinton has repeatedly called for the Justice Department to release any files from its Epstein investigation that pertain to him. He was acquainted with the disgraced financier who died in prison in 2019 — an association the former president described in his memoir — but never visited his private island and cut off contact with him two decades ago. Mr. Clinton took four international trips on Mr. Epstein’s private jet in 2002 and 2003, according to flight logs, and an undated photograph of Mr. Clinton and Mr. Epstein signed by the former president was part of a batch of images released by House Democrats last month highlighting Mr. Epstein’s ties to powerful men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clintons have noted in previous letters from their lawyers that they are being held to a different standard than the seven or eight former law enforcement officials Mr. Comer had also subpoenaed and then excused from testifying before the committee. Like those officials, the Clintons submitted sworn legal statements to Mr. Comer detailing everything they had to offer on the Epstein matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Mr. Comer refusing to back down, the Clintons have recently beefed up their legal team, adding Ashley Callen, the co-chairwoman of the congressional investigations practice at Jenner &amp; Block and a Republican lawyer who previously worked as general counsel for Speaker Mike Johnson. They have also brought in Cheryl Mills, a longtime Clinton aide who defended Mr. Clinton in his 1999 impeachment trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in negotiations that stretched over the holiday weekend, Ms. Callen, working with Mr. Marin, offered up Mr. Clinton for a face-to-face interview with Mr. Comer. Such an interview, she noted, would have been the first time in history that a former president sat for in-person testimony, under oath, to assist with a congressional investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In discussions on Jan. 16 regarding the “parameters” of the proposed interview with Mr. Clinton, Ms. Callen and the Clintons’ legal team told Mr. Comer’s aide that the former president would agree to discuss subjects within the committee’s legislative scope, meaning the Epstein investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days later, the Clintons offered “further accommodations” to address concerns about limits on who could question Mr. Clinton, according to a letter to Mr. Comer dated Jan. 20 that was obtained by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Comer ultimately rejected the proposal, insisting that the Clintons appear in front of the entire House Oversight Committee for questioning and that there be no limits on the subjects its members could ask about. He argued that the Clintons’ offer fell “far outside the normal and well-established operating procedures of the committee when it conducts compulsory depositions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Clintons’ latest demands make clear they believe their last name entitles them to special treatment,” Mr. Comer said. “The absence of an official transcript is an indefensible demand that is insulting to the American people who demand answers about Epstein’s crimes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added that testimony from Mrs. Clinton was equally necessary to his investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Comer’s relentless efforts to force the Clintons to testify are in keeping with his approach to his panel’s Epstein inquiry. He has sought to deflect focus from President Trump’s ties to the convicted sex offender, and instead spotlight prominent Democrats who once associated with Mr. Epstein and his longtime companion, Ghislaine Maxwell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kimberly Hamm, a partner at Morrison Foerster who previously served as general counsel to former Speaker Kevin McCarthy, a Republican, said that Mr. Comer appeared to have closed a legitimate avenue for gaining information for his inquiry, adding that there should be a “heightened standard” when it comes to a subpoena of a former president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s an accommodation process when you’re talking about a president or a former president,” Ms. Hamm said. “Contempt is punitive; it’s not about enforcement. If you want to get the information, agreeing to accommodations is one way of getting it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Hamm said the steps the Clintons had offered to the committee so far “seem like a way to get some information, if that’s the goal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Jan. 20 letter, obtained by The Times, Ms. Callen and the Clintons’ legal team wrote that Mr. Comer had insisted on a format “that would allow members of the committee to harass our clients, and indicated you would proceed with plans to hold our clients in contempt if they did not agree.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Callen said that Mr. Comer had refused to allow questions to be limited to topics within the scope of the investigation, claiming that limitations on staff questions would not “allow the committee to appropriately further its investigation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And then you stopped negotiating altogether,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Comer on Wednesday is expected to proceed with the vote in his committee to hold both Clintons in contempt of Congress, which, if successful, would send the matter to the House floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The action puts Democrats in a difficult position: There would be little political upside to casting a vote that appeared to protect the Clintons from testifying. Should a contempt citation pass the House, it would be up to the Justice Department to prosecute the matter, in which penalties include a fine of up to $100,000 and imprisonment for as long as a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Clintons have now sent five legal letters to Mr. Comer, seeking to outline how they have bent over backward to offer transparency on the Epstein issue and how Mr. Comer’s efforts to bring them in before the committee amount to harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Jim Comer claiming to be looking for the truth about Epstein is as honest as O.J. looking for the real killer,” said Philippe Reines, a longtime Clinton aide who has been helping them navigate the issue with Mr. Comer. “Everyone knew O.J. was protecting himself. Everyone knows who Jim Comer is protecting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the most recent letter sent on Jan. 20, the Clintons’ lawyers stated that it was the committee that had made unreasonable demands of the Clintons, and that the committee’s entire approach bore “no resemblance to its well-established historical procedures for seeking and obtaining information procedures that dictate substance over form.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as they did in an eight-page legal letter they sent to the committee last week, they again argued that the subpoenas from Mr. Comer’s committee were “invalid and legally unenforceable.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/comer-clinton-interview-epstein.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:16:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Macron Vows France Will Not Capitulate to Bullying From Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/macron-france-trump-world-economic-forum.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-macron-trump-topart-tcvl/20trump-news-macron-trump-topart-tcvl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Emmanuel Macron of France said on Tuesday that France would not capitulate to bullying and attempts to undermine European sovereignty after President Trump threatened to impose new tariffs on a bloc of European nations until Denmark agrees to sell Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are reaching a time of instability and imbalances,” Mr. Macron said in his remarks at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. He added that the answer was “more cooperation,” not a system that accepts “the law of the strongest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade decisions by the United States that undermine European exports and demand “maximum concessions,” Mr. Macron said, are aimed to “weaken and subordinate Europe.” He added that the “endless accumulation of new tariffs” was “unacceptable,” particularly when used as “leverage against territorial sovereignty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France is one of eight nations Mr. Trump has threatened will be hit with an additional 10 percent tariff on exports to the United States beginning on Feb. 1 if those countries do not drop their opposition to the U.S. acquisition of Greenland from Denmark. That rate would increase to 25 percent on June 1 if they stand firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark and Greenland, which is a semiautonomous Danish territory, have said they are not interested in handing Greenland over to the United States. The dispute has threatened the NATO alliance, as President Trump has raised the possibility of seizing Greenland by force if Denmark does not agree to cede it to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European leaders have so far reacted with unified outrage to Mr. Trump’s coercive measures on Greenland, a massive Arctic island the president has argued the United States must control to check Chinese and Russian influence. European leaders are considering striking back with their own trade measures through a tool known as the anti-coercion instrument, which could be used to impose limitations on big American technology companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech on Tuesday, Mr. Macron echoed previous calls for invoking those limitations. But he also advocated more broadly a shift to an effective and cooperative form of multilateralism, urging a collective effort to work against the weakening of international institutions intended to keep global power balanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We do prefer respect to bullies,” Mr. Macron said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/macron-france-trump-world-economic-forum.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:45:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Replica of Trump’s Birthday Message to Epstein Appears on National Mall</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-epstein-birthday-card-national-mall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-card-vlfq/20xp-card-vlfq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large replica of a sexually suggestive birthday message to Jeffrey Epstein, featuring a drawing of a naked woman’s torso and what appears to be President Trump’s signature, was placed on the National Mall in Washington overnight on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appearance of the 10-foot-tall installation near the United States Capitol was timed to coincide with what would have been Mr. Epstein’s 73rd birthday on Tuesday. Mr. Epstein, a convicted sex offender and disgraced financier, was 66 when he died in prison in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One side of the mock card has the greeting “Happy Birthday To A ‘Terrific Guy!’” — an apparent reference to a description of Mr. Epstein that Mr. Trump gave to New York magazine in 2002. The other side features the rendering of the female torso with “Donald” written below her waist and the cryptic message: “may every day be another wonderful secret.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The display was the latest installation by an anonymous group of artists known as the Secret Handshake, which has been putting a spotlight on the relationship between the president and Mr. Epstein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on Tuesday, a White House spokeswoman criticized the display, while saying Democrats in Congress solicited funds from Mr. Epstein. “Kudos to these Trump Deranged Liberals for constantly inventing new ways to light Democrat donor money on fire by spreading fake news,” the spokeswoman, Abigail Jackson, said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly insisted that he did not create or sign the drawing, which the House Oversight Committee released in September and was originally included in a book that was presented to Mr. Epstein for his 50th birthday in 2003. It was among documents turned over by Mr. Epstein’s estate to the committee, which had subpoenaed them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A portion of the permit for the display, issued by the National Park Service, says that the “birthday card,” measuring 12 feet by 10 feet, would be installed on the National Mall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the site, a sign invites visitors to write a message to the administration, to “celebrate the birthday of President Donald Trump’s ‘closest friend,’ Jeffrey Epstein, with a larger-than-life tribute to their intimate correspondence.” The message was placed near mock boxes brimming with redacted files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Secret Handshake said in a statement on Monday that the display had a permit to remain in place until Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Park Service and the Interior Department did not respond to requests for comment on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same group claimed responsibility for another Epstein-themed installation at the National Mall in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, bronze-colored statues of Mr. Trump and Mr. Epstein, frolicking and holding hands, were placed on the Mall, with an inscription that read “Best Friends Forever.” It was briefly removed for not being in compliance with a permit and was reinstalled in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has downplayed his ties to Mr. Epstein, while coming under increased public scrutiny after the Justice Department failed to release all the files in the Epstein case by Dec. 19, a deadline set by Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-epstein-birthday-card-national-mall.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:20:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>White Students Hurt by L.A. Desegregation Policy, Lawsuit Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/los-angeles-schools-desegregation-lawsuit.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20nat-lausd-lawsuit-mclz/20nat-lausd-lawsuit-mclz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A decades-old policy meant to combat the harms of school segregation in Los Angeles was challenged in federal court on Tuesday by a conservative group that says the policy discriminates against white students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy dates back to the 1970s, when the Los Angeles school district, the nation’s second-largest, was under a court order to desegregate and improve conditions for students of color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policy offers smaller class sizes and other benefits to students at schools whose enrollment is predominantly Hispanic, Black or Asian — a majority of the district’s schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs argue that students at schools with more white students receive “inferior treatment and calculated disadvantages,” according to the lawsuit, which was filed Tuesday by the 1776 Project Foundation, a group that opposes racial preferences in education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the most blatant example of racial discrimination by a major school district in this country,” said Ryan James Girdusky, a conservative political consultant and the group’s founder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Los Angeles school district said officials were reviewing the lawsuit, but did not immediately provide a comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit is the latest effort to roll back race-based policies in education, including court-ordered desegregation remedies, in a fast-shifting legal landscape remade by the Trump administration and the Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Los Angeles school district remains among the most segregated in the country, with wide test score gaps between racial groups, well short of the ideals that motivated a 1963 desegregation lawsuit and the lengthy legal battle that followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many other districts, Los Angeles never truly integrated its schools. A short-lived mandatory busing program ended in the early 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nationally, many school desegregation efforts faded long before the Trump presidency. U.S. school segregation has increased since the early 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the politics around civil rights have shifted significantly under President Trump. Federal officials have backed away from enforcing efforts to help Black students and other groups that historically faced discrimination, and instead prioritized investigating what they see as unfair treatment of white students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2023 Supreme Court decision outlawing race-based affirmative action in college admissions has galvanized conservative groups and the Trump administration, which has pushed to apply the ruling beyond college admissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are living through an era of racial revanchism,” said Justin Driver, a professor at Yale Law School who wrote a book about the affirmative action decision. He said the Trump administration and others have often interpreted the ruling beyond the scope of the decision itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Los Angeles, the 1963 lawsuit led to series of remedies. In addition to the busing program, “racially isolated minority” schools that could not be desegregated were designated to receive certain supports, said Mark Rosenbaum, a lawyer with Public Counsel in Los Angeles, who represented plaintiffs toward the end of the desegregation case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That included setting a maximum teacher-student ratio for the schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schools eventually became known as “predominantly Hispanic, Black, Asian or other non-Anglo,” Mr. Rosenbaum said. Schools qualify if they have a resident population that is more than 70 percent nonwhite, according to the district’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That takes in the vast majority of public schools in Los Angeles, whose student enrollment today is more than 70 percent Hispanic, 7 percent Black and 3 percent Asian. About 10 percent of students are non-Hispanic white.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 600 schools in the district qualify, according to the lawsuit, while fewer than 100 do not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qualifying schools have student-to-teacher ratios of no more than 25 to 1, compared with nonqualifying schools, where the ratio may be as high as 34 to 1, according to the lawsuit. Students at qualifying schools also receive extra points when applying to the district’s selective magnet schools, the lawsuit says.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t think the court order is relevant anymore to the present day, and it is currently inflicting present day harms,” said Aiden Buzzetti, president of the 1776 Project Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group has argued that students of Middle Eastern descent, classified as white by the school district, miss out on benefits, and so do students of color who attend whiter schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courts have often been more receptive to efforts to help students on the basis of family income rather than race. In 2024, Los Angeles recast a program meant to lift scores for Black students to include other factors, after a federal civil rights complaint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Racially segregated schools are associated with wider gaps in student achievement, but research has shown that these academic differences can be entirely explained by differences in school poverty. In other words, segregation is harmful because it concentrates Black and Hispanic students in high-poverty environments, often with less access to qualified teachers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Segregation is not just by race — it is by race, by class, by teacher experience, by curriculum,” said Gary Orfield, co-director of the Civil Rights Project at the University of California, Los Angeles, who served as an expert witness for the judge in the 1963 school desegregation case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Referring to the broader political movement to view remedies for historical racial discrimination as discriminatory against white Americans, he said, “For those of us who have worked in civil rights for the last 50 years, this is the ultimate degradation of the whole principle of civil rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/los-angeles-schools-desegregation-lawsuit.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:46:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Some Republicans Begin to Echo Trump’s Case to Acquire Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/republicans-trump-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-gop-greenland-lfmv/20trump-news-gop-greenland-lfmv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small but growing group of Republicans in Congress is expressing openness to President Trump’s increasingly explicit push to acquire Greenland, along with his desire to punish European allies who resist the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days since Mr. Trump began musing openly about taking over the semiautonomous island territory, which is currently controlled by Denmark, many Republican lawmakers have issued vocal warnings against a push to annex Greenland, arguing that it would dangerously divide the United States’ closest allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with the president stepping up his threats and showing no sign of backing down, Republicans across the ideological spectrum are increasingly finding ways to defend or justify his threats — or embrace them altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During an address to Britain’s Parliament in London on Tuesday, Speaker Mike Johnson, Republican of Louisiana, said he had spoken “at length” with Mr. Trump and framed his visit as an effort to “encourage our friends and help to calm the waters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Johnson, the first American House speaker to address Britain’s Parliament, did not mention Greenland by name or address the issue directly during his speech, which sought to emphasize the strength of the U.S.-U.K. relationship. But the speaker, who has marched in lock-step with Mr. Trump on almost every issue, implicitly backed the president’s argument that the territory is vital to the national security of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also urged British lawmakers and other allies in Europe to support the president’s efforts to maintain “strategic strongholds around the world,” citing threats from China and Russia and singling out the Arctic, as Mr. Trump has in recent weeks, as an area of focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While we can have thoughtful debate among our friends about how best to counter these threats,” Mr. Johnson said, “we all certainly agree they must be countered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, he has dismissed the idea that the administration would make good on the threats to seize Greenland by force. Last week, Mr. Trump told reporters that he would acquire the island “the easy way” or “the hard way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t anticipate any kind of military intervention,” Mr. Johnson said during an interview with Nigel Farage, a prominent right wing member of Parliament, on Monday. In a series of appearances in British media, Mr. Johnson said that Mr. Trump’s provocations on social media were simply the “certain manner in which he goes about doing things,” but the speaker said that he did not always consider the president’s public remarks a literal reflection of his aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We take him seriously, not always literally,” Mr. Johnson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Republicans, including some who have at times parted way with the president, have taken a similar position. Representative Mike Lawler, Republican of New York, said that there was “broad bipartisan opposition in Congress to any use of force in relation to Greenland.” But during an interview on CNN on Tuesday, he said that he supported acquiring the territory as a way to counter “the malign influence of Russia and China” and characterized Mr. Trump’s threats and social media provocations as merely a way to “spur conversation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some G.O.P. lawmakers have aligned themselves more squarely with Mr. Trump’s ambition of taking Greenland by force if necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Eric Schmitt, Republican of Missouri, a Trump loyalist, argued over the weekend that the United States was uniquely capable of defending Greenland and criticized European governments as too weak to do so themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of reasons that the United States has a very important interest in making sure that Greenland is protected,” Mr. Schmitt said during an appearance on Fox News. “Europe can’t protect it, the Danes can’t protect it. That’s just an obvious fact at this point. And so it is in the strategic interest of the United States of America to pursue this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Senator Ted Cruz, Republican of Texas, commended Mr. Trump for targeting the territory, saying on Fox News’s “Sunday Morning Futures With Maria Bartiromo”: “I believe it is overwhelmingly in America’s national interest to acquire Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, a number of Republicans have criticized Mr. Trump’s aggression toward Greenland as misguided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Thom Tillis, Republican of North Carolina, speaking on the Senate floor last Wednesday, called the idea that the United States would take the territory “absurd,” and suggested the president was being given bad advice. A push to take over Greenland, he said in a social media post on Saturday, would be “bad for America, bad for American businesses, and bad for America’s allies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s great for Putin, Xi and other adversaries who want to see NATO divided,” Mr. Tillis added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Republicans, including Representatives Blake Moore of Utah and Don Bacon of Nebraska, warned that threatening Greenland amounted to threatening the core of the NATO alliance itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Stop the stupid ‘we want Greenland BS,’” Mr. Bacon wrote in a post on social media in early January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the message is that ‘we need Greenland,’ the truth is that we already have access to everything we could need from Greenland,” Mr. Moore said in a joint statement with Representative Steny Hoyer, Democrat of Maryland. “If we want to deploy more forces or build additional missile defense infrastructure in Greenland, Denmark has given us a green light to do so. Our ally has always accommodated us. Threatening to annex Greenland needlessly undermines that cooperation for no gain.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/republicans-trump-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:51:10 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>