<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:30:04 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>As Trump Focuses Abroad, G.O.P. Toils to Hone Election Message</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/gop-election-message-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24DC-REPUBS-top-vmfw/24DC-REPUBS-top-vmfw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Don Bacon, a Nebraska Republican, isn’t running for re-election this year. But he wishes that President Trump would spend more time promoting his economic record as his party wages an uphill fight to maintain control of Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He should be talking that for the first time in five years, we have wages climbing faster than inflation,” Mr. Bacon said of the president. “That should be in every speech. We have 4.3 percent G.D.P. growth. That should be in every speech. That’s a great number.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, most of Mr. Trump’s attention in recent months — and nearly all of his public message — has been on international affairs and divisive moves at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has initiated military action in Venezuela, pushed aggressively to acquire Greenland, warned Iran against killing protesters, threatened retaliatory tariffs that could drive up prices in the United States and relentlessly bemoaned the fact that he was not awarded a Nobel Peace Prize. At the same time, he is leading an increasingly aggressive immigration crackdown that has in recent weeks led to the shooting of an unarmed 37-year-old woman by a U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent and the detention of a preschooler in Minnesota. On Saturday, federal agents shot and killed a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident who Homeland Security officials said was carrying a handgun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has all left voters who will determine the course of the final two years of his presidency believing that his attention has been misplaced, a grim dynamic for Republicans in Congress who must face re-election in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New York Times/Siena poll conducted this month found that a large majority of Americans believe Mr. Trump has focused on the wrong priorities, as they point to their own economic worries. And while they back his immigration policies overall, a sizable majority also said that Immigration and Customs Enforcement had gone too far with tactics that have sown chaos across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president will not be on the ballot this fall, but Republican lawmakers in the House and Senate who will be have a steep challenge: The survey gave Democrats a five-percentage-point edge over Republicans when it came to congressional candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With anxiety about the coming election rising among Republicans on Capitol Hill, Susie Wiles, the White House chief of staff, made a point of telling members of the news media accompanying Mr. Trump on his trip to Davos, Switzerland, this week that he would soon begin making more trips around the United States to sell his domestic achievements. She said cabinet officials would also increase their visibility around the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the president himself conceded last week that he had failed to communicate effectively about his economic record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not getting — maybe I have bad public relations people — but we’re not getting it across,” Mr. Trump told reporters this week during a rambling news conference celebrating the anniversary of the start of his second term. Later, he said: “I think we’ve done a much better job than we’re able to promote.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top Republicans concede privately that Mr. Trump’s emphasis on international affairs — along with the economic and social unrest prompted by his policies — are significant obstacles they will have to overcome in the coming months as they try to defy the historic trend of the president’s party losing seats in midterm elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers facing tough races say they will need to steer around the president and run on their own records, leaning in to the economic bright spots that Mr. Trump has sometimes overshadowed with his unpredictable moves and extreme statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m always running my own race and my voters will weigh in irrespective of who the president is,” said Representative Kevin Kiley, a California Republican whose current district was sliced up by Democrats working to counter a nationwide redistricting push by Mr. Trump, leaving him searching for a new political base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When it comes to affordability, we’ve seen progress with energy and gas prices,” Mr. Kiley said. “But that is not in any way to look past the real struggles that people are having and the fact that there’s still a lot more we need to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He and other Republicans who are considered vulnerable say they understand that Mr. Trump has duties and responsibilities beyond looking out for the election prospects of Republicans on Capitol Hill, and that he is capable of educating voters on both the domestic and foreign policy accomplishments of his administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president’s time has to be spent on those things which, if not for the president, wouldn’t happen,” said Representative Darrell Issa, another California Republican whose re-election bid has been made more difficult by the new House map in the state. “When you look at the domestic agenda, is a speech in Minneapolis the most important thing or is striving to fix the problems that have cost the blood and treasure of America for generations?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans also say that they expect to reap a political benefit as Americans enter tax season and realize what Republicans predict will be significant savings from the extension of tax cuts that their party pushed through as part of last year’s sweeping domestic policy law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When people file their taxes, obviously they are going to see a large tax cut and that’s going to have a very positive impact on their situation and their outlook,” said Representative Mike Lawler, Republican of New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether voters will attribute any tax savings to Republicans remains to be seen. The Times poll found that Americans overall did not support the tax cuts, which disproportionately benefit the wealthiest Americans, and that a significant number of Republicans polled — 18 percent — had not even heard about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans are well aware of the sales job they need to do to on the tax cuts and have stepped up efforts to drive the impact home with voters. Senator John Thune, the South Dakota Republican and majority leader, hits the topic regularly. He and a group of Senate Republican leaders and candidates traveled to Texas earlier this month to boast both of the tax policy and new border security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republican strategists say lawmakers will need to hone their own message and not rely on the president, who tends to go his own way despite the dangers posed to him by the loss of the House or Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump is going to do what Trump is going to do,” said John Feehery, a former senior Republican congressional communications aide. “Congressional Republicans have to be highly disciplined on their own messaging, taking credit for their joint accomplishments while attacking the Democrats for being loony. Trump’s ratings aren’t great, but they are much better than the Democrats’.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Democrats appear gleeful at the prospect of capitalizing on the disaffection with Mr. Trump and making the case that Republicans in Congress have put their loyalty to him above their concern for voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This week, the Republican focus has been on Greenland, Jack Smith and Bill and Hillary Clinton,” Representative Hakeem Jeffries, the New York Democrat and minority leader, said on Thursday, referring to a politically charged hearing with Mr. Smith, the special prosecutor in a case against Mr. Trump related to the 2020 election, and possible contempt charges against the former first couple. “That’s their focus this week, not driving down the high cost of living for everyday Americans.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/gop-election-message-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:56:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minneapolis Live Updates: Man Killed by Federal Agents Was Holding a Phone, Not a Gun</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/authorities-in-minneapolis-respond-to-reports-of-shooting-involving-federal-agents</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-promo-0430/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
At least two people have been shot by agents in Minneapolis this month, including Renee Good, 37, who was killed in her car.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/authorities-in-minneapolis-respond-to-reports-of-shooting-involving-federal-agents</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 17:24:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Videos Show Moments in Which Agents Killed a Man in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/video/24vi-minn-shooting/24vi-minn-shooting-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times appear to contradict the Department of Homeland Security’s account of the fatal shooting of Alex Jeffrey Pretti, 37, by federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security said the episode began after a man “approached US Border Patrol officers with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun” and they tried to disarm him. The statement did not specify whether the gun was in the man’s hands or merely on his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage shows Mr. Pretti was clearly holding a phone, not a gun, before the agents took him to the ground and shot him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what the videos show, according to a Times analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small group of protesters stands in the street, speaking to a federal agent as whistles sound. Mr. Pretti appears to be filming the scene with his phone and directing traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agent begins shoving the demonstrators, and squirts pepper spray at their faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment, Mr. Pretti has both hands clearly visible. One is holding his phone, while he holds the other up to protect himself from pepper spray. He moves to help one of the protesters who was sprayed, as other agents approach and pull him from behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several agents tussle with Mr. Pretti before bringing him to his knees. He appears to resist as the agents grab his legs, push down on his back and strike him repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage shows an agent approaching with empty hands and grabbing at Mr. Pretti as the others hold him down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About eight seconds after he is pinned, agents yell that he has a gun, indicating that they may not have known he was armed until he was on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same agent who approached with empty hands pulls a gun from among the group that appears to match the profile of a firearm DHS said belonged to Mr. Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agents appear to have him under their control, with his arms pinned near his head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the gun emerges from the melee, another agent aims his own firearm at Mr. Pretti’s back and appears to fire one shot at close range. He then appears to continue firing at Mr. Pretti, who collapses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third agent unholsters a weapon. Both agents appear to fire additional shots into Mr. Pretti as he lies motionless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, at least 10 shots appear to have been fired within five seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Gibbons-Neff and McKinnon de Kuyper contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-federal-agents-video.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 13:28:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Millions of Gallons of Raw Sewage Spill Into the Potomac River</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/potomac-river-untreated-sewage-spill.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24xp-sewage-bvgk/24xp-sewage-bvgk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crews worked on Saturday to reroute millions of gallons of untreated sewage from spilling into the Potomac River days after the collapse of a major sewer line and as one of the most severe winter storms to hit the Washington region in years approached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collapse happened on Monday in a section of the Potomac Interceptor, which carries up to 60 million gallons of wastewater each day from parts of Maryland and Virginia to a pumping station in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Lisle, a spokesman with DC Water, a water and sewer utility company serving Washington, said in an email on Saturday afternoon that the company estimated that 40 million gallons of untreated sewage a day had spilled into the river since the rupture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of the break was not yet known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DC Water is working with several agencies, including the Environmental Protection Agency and the D.C. Department of Energy and Environment, to address potential ecological impacts, Mr. Lisle said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crews were installing high-powered pumps to divert wastewater around the damaged section of the Potomac Interceptor along Clara Barton Parkway in Montgomery County, Md., near the Potomac River and the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historic Park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials said the temporary bypass was intended to limit additional overflows while repairs were made, even as snow and ice expected with an approaching storm threatened to complicate repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DC Water has warned the public to stay away from the area during repairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is important to note that DC Water’s drinking water system is separate from the wastewater system and is not affected by the overflow,” officials said in a news release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The utility was repairing deteriorating sections of the Potomac Interceptor, which was built in the 1960s, when the rupture occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The break did not happen at one of those targeted sections, Mr. Lisle said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forecasters expect eight inches of snow across the metro area, with the possibility of up to 10 inches, starting on Sunday. Wind chills as low as 10 below zero are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cold weather, along with the snow, could make the repairs difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are planning to work through the weather as long as it is safe for the crews,” Mr. Lisle said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/potomac-river-untreated-sewage-spill.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:27:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump and Federal Officials Try to Blame Minnesota Authorities and Slain Man</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-Trump-topart-hqmk/24minneapolis-ice-Trump-topart-hqmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump moved swiftly on Saturday to try to shift the blame for another shooting death in Minneapolis away from the federal agents involved in the incident, claiming instead that it was the result of inflammatory rhetoric by local officials and the victim himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of Mr. Trump’s administration also quickly labeled the man, who Minneapolis police said was 37 and an American citizen, as a “domestic terrorist” and would-be assassin hours after the morning shooting, before all the facts were known or an investigation could take place. Videos taken by bystanders appeared to contradict the account of federal officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a pair of social media posts, Mr. Trump accused local politicians, including Gov. Tim Walz and Jacob Frey, the mayor of Minneapolis, of “inciting Insurrection” in an attempt to divert attention from an unrelated fraud scandal. He called Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents “patriots” who were left unassisted by the local police as they seek to detain what Mr. Trump described as violent immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they were still there, you would see something far worse than you are witnessing today!” the president wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also shared a photo of a firearm that federal officials claim belonged to the man who was killed. The police in Minneapolis said the man, whom law enforcement officials identified as Alex Jeffrey Pretti, had a firearms permit. It is legal to openly carry a weapon in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security said the episode began when a man approached Border Patrol agents “with a 9 mm semiautomatic handgun” and they tried to disarm him. But footage from the scene verified by The New York Times shows that the man was holding a phone in his hand when federal agents took him to the ground and shot him. A Times analysis found that at least 10 shots were fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.S. official said the Department of Homeland Security would investigate the shooting, with the help of the F.B.I. The Justice Department’s civil rights division, which has historically investigated shootings involving federal law enforcement officials, is not expected to be involved, said two senior law enforcement officials, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss internal decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite that, top Department of Homeland Security leaders weighed in on the shooting Saturday with assertions of what had occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Bovino, the Border Patrol official in charge of agents in Minnesota, claimed that the man was attempting to murder agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This looks like a situation where an individual wanted to do maximum damage and massacre law enforcement,” Mr. Bovino said at a news conference on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defiant and angry response by the president and members of his administration further inflamed tensions in a city that has for weeks been racked by conflicts between protesters and government agents sent there to enforce the president’s crackdown on immigrants. Increasingly, U.S. citizens have taken to the streets to protest what many have described as a military-style occupation of an American city in which federal agents are using aggressive and violent tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting further deepened a calcifying rift between federal officials and their counterparts in Minnesota, where local and state officials said they have been given sparse information about the actions of federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the shooting, Stephen Miller, the White House deputy chief of staff, posted messages on social media claiming the man was seeking to murder federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A would-be assassin tried to murder federal law enforcement and the official Democrat account sides with the terrorists,” Mr. Miller said. Earlier, he responded to a social media post from Senator Amy Klobuchar, Democrat of Minnesota, that criticized the administration’s crackdown in her state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A domestic terrorist tried to assassinate federal law enforcement and this is your response?” he wrote. “You and the state’s entire Democrat leadership team have been flaming the flames of insurrection for the singular purpose of stopping the deportation of illegals who invaded the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem echoed the idea that Mr. Pretti was a domestic terrorist in a news conference on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This looks like a situation where an individual arrived at the scene to inflict maximum damage on individuals and to kill law enforcement,” she said, despite no known evidence of his intent. She called her assertion of “domestic terrorism” just “the facts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatal shooting Saturday came a little over two weeks after Renee Good, a 37-year-old woman, was shot three times while she was driving in her S.U.V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hours after she was shot and killed, Ms. Good was also labeled a “domestic terrorist” by members of the Trump administration, as officials moved quickly to exonerate the ICE official who shot her before an investigation could determine what had occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A supervisor in the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis field office resigned after bureau leadership in Washington pressured her to discontinue a civil rights inquiry into Jonathan Ross, the immigration officer who shot Ms. Good, The Times reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and top officials were following a similar playbook in their response to the shooting of Mr. Pretti on Saturday, even as videos emerged that challenged their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, angry Minnesota officials demanded that Department of Homeland Security officials leave the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How many more residents, how many more Americans, need to die or get badly hurt for this operation to end?” Mr. Frey said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media and in a later news conference, Mr. Walz said he had spoken with Susie Wiles, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, after the shooting. He had argued for state officials to lead the investigation. He accused “the most powerful people in the federal government” of “spinning stories and putting up pictures.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of immigration agents, Mr. Walz added: “They killed a man, created chaos, pushed down protesters, threw gas indiscriminately and then left the scene and then we’re left to clean up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glenn Thrush contributed reporting from Washington, and Mitch Smith from Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:43:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Vow Not to Fund ICE After Shooting, Imperiling Spending Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/democrats-congress-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-congress/13TRUMP-NEWS-WARNER-print-lpkc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bipartisan legislation to fund a broad swath of the government and avert a shutdown at the end of the week appeared to be in grave danger on Saturday, as key Senate Democrats vowed to oppose it after federal agents shot and killed a Minneapolis resident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapidly escalating opposition to the measure, which includes $64.4 billion for the Department of Homeland Security, including $10 billion for ICE, amplified the likelihood of a partial government shutdown at the end of the month. The legislation requires the support of Democrats to muster the 60 votes needed to avoid a filibuster and advance in the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Senate Democrats will not provide the votes to proceed to the appropriations bill if the D.H.S. funding bill is included,” Senator Chuck Schumer, Democrat of New York and the minority leader, said in a statement, calling what is unfolding in Minnesota “appalling” and “unacceptable in any American city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the depth of Democratic outrage, Senate Republicans immediately began examining whether they could separate the homeland security funding from the rest of the package and preserve the bulk of what had been a bipartisan deal to fund a large chunk of the government. The measure also funds the Pentagon and State Department, as well as health, education, labor and transportation programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m exploring all options,” said Senator Susan Collins, the Maine Republican who is the chairwoman of the Appropriations Committee, adding that she had been in touch with Senator John Thune, the South Dakota Republican and majority leader. “We have five other bills that are really vital, and I’m relatively confident they would pass.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A planned vote on the package next week had already promised to pose an agonizing dilemma for many Democrats. They have been eager to avoid another shutdown but have grown increasingly infuriated by the scenes of chaos and violence coming out of Minnesota and facing intense pressure not to fund ICE. Some had already announced they would not support the package as a result, but a substantial bloc had been expected to swallow their reservations and back it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hours after the killing on Saturday, a flood of Democrats who had previously been seen as likely to support the deal declared that they simply could not do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Trump administration and Kristi Noem are putting undertrained, combative federal agents on the streets with no accountability,” Senator Catherine Cortez Masto, Democrat of Nevada, said in a statement announcing her opposition. “They are oppressing Americans and are at odds with local law enforcement. This is clearly not about keeping Americans safe. It’s brutalizing U.S. citizens and law-abiding immigrants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mark Warner, Democrat of Virginia, wrote on social media: “I cannot and will not vote to fund D.H.S. while this administration continues these violent federal takeovers of our cities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spending measure that senators are set to take up includes six bills to fund the government that Democrats and Republicans negotiated, and that the House already passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The House considered the homeland security portion separately, given the depth of Democratic opposition, and all but seven House Democrats voted against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measure rejects President Trump’s request for an $840 million increase in funding for ICE, instead leaving it roughly the same as the previous year, when the agency was operating off funds provided in a stopgap measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While other departments and agencies would most likely shutter if Senate Democrats filibuster the spending package, ICE could potentially tap the $75 billion Republicans allocated to it in their marquee domestic policy bill. That legislation largely contained tax cuts and spending reductions for programs including Medicaid and food assistance, but also included $190 billion for the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During negotiations on the homeland security bill, Republicans rejected a series of proposals by Democrats to rein in ICE, including barring funds from being used to to detain or deport U.S. citizens. Democrats succeeded in winning the addition of $20 million for purchasing body cameras for ICE agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also won the inclusion of a provision to reduce funding for Ms. Noem’s office by $29.5 million and require the secretary to pay for any travel on government aircraft — in this case private jets the Coast Guard bought — out of the budget for her own office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Collins, who called for an investigation into the shooting, noted that the spending measure also includes some new guardrails on ICE, included money for de-escalation training and added authority for the agency’s inspector general to investigate disputed accounts of ICE activities. Those provisions would be lost if Congress ended up not approving the new bill, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a number of Senate Democrats said on Saturday that those measures fell far short of what was necessary in the current moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am voting against funding for D.H.S. until and unless more controls are put in place to hold ICE accountable,” said Senator Brian Schatz of Hawaii, a member of the Appropriations Committee. “These repeated incidents of violence across the country are unlawful, needlessly escalatory and making all of us less safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schumer also said he would vote no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Democrats sought common sense reforms in the Department of Homeland Security spending bill, but because of Republicans’ refusal to stand up to President Trump, the D.H.S. bill is woefully inadequate to rein in the abuses of ICE,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/democrats-congress-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 18:47:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Scenes From the Winter Storm</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/winter-storm-snow-photos-videos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-storm-visuals-01-wpgj/24nat-storm-visuals-01-wpgj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tens of millions of Americans faced a weekend of snow, ice and brutally cold temperatures as a winter storm that formed in the Rockies drove eastward across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Airlines canceling hundreds of flights, consumers hurried to lay in food and supplies, and officials warned that there could be widespread power outages.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/winter-storm-snow-photos-videos.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:04:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What We Know About a Second Fatal Shooting by Federal Agents in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/second-ice-shooting-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday fatally shot a 37-year-old man, the second person to be shot and killed in the city during a ramped-up immigration enforcement effort by the Trump administration, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two other people have been shot by federal law enforcement agents in Minneapolis this month — one in the leg and another, Renee Good, 37, in the head, killing her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Good’s death on Jan. 7, protests have taken place in the city, raising tensions with federal agents. State and local officials have called for federal agents to leave the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we know:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a news conference Greg Bovino, the official in charge of President Trump’s Border Patrol operations, said agents were conducting a “targeted operation” searching for a man accused of domestic assault and other charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person who was shot was not the target of the operation, Mr. Bovino said. He said the episode began after a man with a handgun approached Border Patrol agents and they tried to disarm him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino and Kristi Noem, secretary of the Department of Homeland Security, said the man wanted to hurt law enforcement officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino said the agent who fired has been with the Border Patrol for eight years. He did not publicly identify the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief Brian O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said investigators believed that at least two agents fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video on social media verified by The New York Times shows several agents tussling with the man before bringing him to his knees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man appears to resist as agents grab his legs, push down on his back and strike him repeatedly. This video does not show what led to the episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage shows an agent approaching and grabbing at the man as other agents hold him down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agent appears to pull a gun from out of the scrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, another agent unholsters his firearm. That agent aims at the man’s back and appears to fire one shot at close range. He then appears to continue firing at the man, who collapses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two agents appear to fire at the man as he is motionless on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, at least 10 shots appear to have been fired within five seconds, according to the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage of the encounter shows the man was holding a phone in his hand, not a gun, when federal agents took him to the ground and shot him. There was no evidence that the man who was fatally shot opened fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities did not publicly identify the man who was killed but colleagues and a senior law enforcement official identified the man as Alex Jeffrey Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A colleague, Dimitri Drekonja, said Mr. Pretti worked in the intensive-care unit at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said at a news conference that the person who was shot was a 37-year-old man who lived in Minneapolis and was an American citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man had no criminal record and had a permit to carry a gun, Chief O’Hara said. Minnesota law allows citizens with a permit to carry handguns in public without concealment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief O’Hara said he asked the Minnesota Bureau of Criminal Apprehension to lead the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drew Evans, the superintendent of the bureau, said at a news conference that the Department of Homeland Security had blocked state agents from the scene of the shooting on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being denied access, the bureau is talking with witnesses and seeking video, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal authorities said the Department of Homeland Security would lead the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary Moriarty, the prosecutor in Hennepin County, which includes Minneapolis, said that the “scene must be secured by local law enforcement for preservation of evidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota officials have been blocked by federal agencies from getting access to evidence and pursuing an investigation of Ms. Good’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota has authorized the deployment of the National Guard amid concerns of escalating violence. National Guard members will wear neon vests to distinguish them from federal immigration agents, state officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/second-ice-shooting-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:47:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alex Jeffrey Pretti Knew He Wanted to Help Others</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-jeffrey-pretti-was-an-icu-nurse-at-the-va-hospital.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-victim-topart-fhlp/24minneapolis-ice-victim-topart-fhlp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man fatally shot by Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis was Alex Jeffrey Pretti, a U.S. citizen with no criminal record, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, who was 37, was a registered nurse who worked in the intensive-care unit at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis, according to interviews and public records, and lived in an apartment in Minneapolis a short drive away from where he was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had a firearms permit, required by state law in Minnesota to carry a handgun, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues and acquaintances of Mr. Pretti were stunned by his death, recalling a friendly neighbor and hardworking professional who was devoted to his patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dimitri Drekonja said that the two had worked together for years. Mr. Pretti was capable, competent and friendly, he said, the kind of person who cared deeply about his work and his patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a really great colleague and a really great friend,” he said. “The default look on his face was a smile.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two chatted regularly about mountain biking, one of Mr. Pretti’s passions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Family members of Mr. Pretti declined to comment on Saturday. Michael Pretti, Mr. Pretti’s father, told The Associated Press that he had warned his son to be careful in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We had this discussion with him two weeks ago or so, you know, that go ahead and protest, but do not engage, do not do anything stupid, basically,” Michael Pretti said. “And he said he knows that. He knew that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti received a bachelor’s degree from the University of Minnesota in 2011, a spokeswoman said. He graduated from a high school in Green Bay, Wis., in 2006, and was listed on the honor roll in a local newspaper. His parents now live in Colorado, and his former spouse lives in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A next-door neighbor, Jeanne Wiener, said she believed Mr. Pretti lived alone with his dog, but saw him walking frequently, and would speak with him several times a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing in her home, Ms. Wiener said she was shocked to hear of his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We talk over the fence all the time,” she said. “He’s the sweetest, kindest, most unoffensive, most nonviolent person you’d ever want to meet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruth Anway, who worked with Mr. Pretti, described him as a passionate colleague and kindhearted friend with a sharp sense of humor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Anway, a nurse, said she first met Mr. Pretti around 2014 when he was a research assistant at the hospital. She said she had encouraged him to pursue nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He really thrived in that environment,” she said in a phone interview on Saturday. “He wanted to be helpful, to help humanity and have a career that was a force of good in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his free time, she said, Mr. Pretti loved to bike the trails around Minneapolis, and spent time with his dog, Joule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Anway said Mr. Pretti followed the news closely and cared deeply about social justice and fighting for fairness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not surprised he was out there protesting and observing,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aasma Shaukat, a physician at the V.A. who worked with Mr. Pretti, said she had hired him to his first job in the research department at the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, then fresh from college and in his early 20s, had come to her with no medical training, but a deep drive, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was your typical struggling young person with a lot of ambition, but no direction yet,” she said. “But he knew he wanted to help people in some way or another.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti spent the next few years working for Dr. Shaukat, assisting on medical studies and enrolling patients — while delivering pizzas at night to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time they spoke, Mr. Pretti had been working extra shifts as a nurse, saving up to buy a home and a new car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was happy, and I was happy for him because his life was just starting,” she said. “This feels so senseless and just so wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-jeffrey-pretti-was-an-icu-nurse-at-the-va-hospital.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:38:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Appeals Court Rejects Justice Dept. Push for Arrest Warrant for Don Lemon</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/don-lemon-arrest-warrant.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24dc-minnesota-courts-fcmb/24dc-minnesota-courts-fcmb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal appeals court on Friday turned down an extraordinary request from the Justice Department to force a judge to issue arrest warrants for Don Lemon, the journalist, and four other people in connection with a church protest in Minneapolis last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department’s unusual petition, which was unsealed on Saturday along with other documents arising from the case, was a remarkably aggressive attempt by the Trump administration to strong-arm judges into doing its bidding. It prompted an equally remarkable pushback from the conservative chief federal judge in Minnesota, who called the petition “frivolous” and categorically rejected the administration’s efforts to depict its need for the warrants as what he described as a “national security emergency.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dispute also shows the boundary-pushing lengths to which Trump administration officials are willing to go in their efforts to crack down on what they see as criticism of the president’s aggressive immigration measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fight over the warrants began Tuesday evening, when federal prosecutors presented a criminal complaint to Magistrate Judge Douglas L. Micko in the Federal District Court in Minneapolis, seeking the arrest of eight people in connection with the disruption of a church service in neighboring St. Paul, Minn., just days before. The protest was held because the pastor of the church apparently also works as a U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After considering the complaint, Judge Micko found there was probable cause to issue warrants for three of the suspects — Nekima Levy Armstrong, Chauntyll Louisa Allen and William Kelly — all of whom were ultimately taken into custody on Thursday. But he refused to approve warrants for the other five people, including Mr. Lemon, who had been working as an independent reporter, and his producer, the unsealed court papers said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately, the U.S. attorney in Minnesota, Daniel N. Rosen, who was appointed by President Trump last year, notified the district’s chief judge, Patrick J. Schiltz, that he wanted another judge to review Judge Micko’s decision — a highly unusual move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, Judge Schiltz wrote in a letter to the appeals court, if the government is unsatisfied with a magistrate’s refusal to sign warrants, it can either “improve” its affidavit making the request and present it again, or it can set aside its criminal complaint and try a different way to charge the suspects: by seeking a grand jury indictment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is important to emphasize that what the U.S. attorney requested is unheard-of in our district or, as best as I can tell, any other district in the Eighth Circuit,” wrote Judge Schiltz, a staunch Republican appointed by President George W. Bush. “I have surveyed all of our judges — some of whom have been judges in our district for over 40 years — and no one can remember the government asking a district judge to review a magistrate judge’s denial of an arrest warrant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Judge Schiltz wrote, three of the people whose warrants were denied had not been charged with committing any violence, but at worst had been accused of “yelling horrible things at the members of the church.” He added there was no evidence that Mr. Lemon or his producer had engaged “in any criminal behavior or conspired to do so.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, Judge Schiltz sought to take a measured path in response to the request by Mr. Rosen, a longtime commercial litigator who had little experience in prosecuting criminal cases when he took over as U.S. attorney in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noting that the request was “unprecedented” and had prompted “strong and differing views” from his fellow judges, Judge Schiltz told Mr. Rosen that he would not decide what to do about the warrants until he had discussed the issue at a meeting with his colleagues scheduled for this past Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the meeting was postponed because of security concerns arising from Vice President JD Vance’s visit to Minneapolis this week. And Judge Schiltz informed Mr. Rosen that he would make a decision about the warrants after the next meeting, scheduled for Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of waiting, however, the Justice Department filed a direct request on Friday to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit, which sits over Judge Schiltz, seeking an order directing a judge in the lower court to sign the complaint and immediately issue arrest warrants for the five remaining suspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The warrants were “urgently needed,” department officials wrote, “to protect the public safety from concrete, credible threats of criminal activity this weekend.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rosen echoed those concerns in an email to Judge Schiltz the day before the petition was sent to the appeals court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Copycat raiders of places of worship are an immediate danger as we approach Saturday and Sunday,” he wrote, “and the Department of Justice has determined that deterrence of such raiders is essential to protecting the safety of worshipers nationwide.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Judge Schiltz rejected the idea that there was an emergency in his correspondence with Mr. Rosen and with the appeals court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do not believe that the applications present an actual emergency,” he told Mr. Rosen. “You have already arrested Ms. Levy Armstrong and Ms. Allen, and those arrests are receiving international publicity. That should provide plenty of deterrence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I doubt very much,” the judge went on, “that anyone who is still contemplating raiding a church will change his mind if three or four more demonstrators are arrested.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a three-judge panel of the Eighth Circuit denied Mr. Rosen’s emergency request, it did so in a single-page order that gave little reason for the decision. It is unclear what the Justice Department may do next to try to obtain the warrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department has clashed with federal judges several times over immigration issues. Those fights have come in cases involving the deportation of scores of Venezuelan immigrants under a wartime statute called the Alien Enemies Act and in proceedings focused on Kilmar Armando Abrego Garcia, an immigrant who was wrongfully deported to El Salvador last year and then brought back to face criminal charges.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/don-lemon-arrest-warrant.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 13:24:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Dolly Plowton’ Debuts in Snowy Nashville</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/dolly-plowton-debuts-in-snowy-nashville.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-nashville-snow-01-zwhm/24nat-nashville-snow-01-zwhm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A father, with his two children each carrying a sled, stopped to wave from the sidewalk. A boy with a snowball in hand ran across his yard to see it go by. As chunks of snow flew off the road, a bundled-up pair of walkers whooped in appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an occasional honk for well-wishers, Dolly Plowton — a snazzy new snowplow adorned with purple and pink snowflakes — was making its Nashville debut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I get a lot of waves, a lot of hurrahs,” said Greg Bergstresser, 23, who spent much of his 12-hour shift on Saturday behind the wheel of the snowplow, driving through West Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to how well the South deals with snow and ice, the question is not necessarily one of individual fortitude. The region is accustomed to meteorological and natural calamity: hurricanes, tornadoes, sweltering humidity, even invasive flora and fauna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the South struggles with low temperatures and snow-slickened roads, it is often more of a matter of infrastructure and inexperience. Southerners resort to staying home during winter storms in part because they know that, in a region that does not see snow and ice very often, even a couple of inches can snarl roads and ravage the power grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The addition of Dolly Plowton and four other new snowplows in Nashville illustrates how some Southern cities have been trying to shore up their little-used winter infrastructure. It also reflects the migration of many people to the region from colder parts of the country, who bring assumptions about how a city should respond to snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a different mentality, and, as we’ve had different people move in here from outside of this area, the expectation has been different” from that of lifelong residents, said Philip Jones, the deputy director of Nashville’s transportation department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this weekend’s snowstorm, he added, “has been the talk of the town.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jones and others on his staff concede that, while they loved snow days as children, they are more serious now as adults working 12-hour weekend shifts to deal with the storm. The main concern in the city was not so much the accumulating snow as the possible buildup of ice through days of below-freezing temperatures; ice is a far more potent threat to power lines, roads and other city infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tennessee Department of Transportation reported responding to dozens of traffic incidents on Saturday as snow began to fall across the state. But many motorists heeded warnings to stay off the roads: In parts of Nashville, the snowplows encountered a fraction of the usual traffic as they pushed slowly up and down the streets, passing an occasional jogger, dog walker or sledding child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has not been cheap to build up the city’s fleet, which now numbers 45 plows. The five new trucks cost about $350,000 apiece. The city spent another $200,000 on a driver training simulator, which is essentially an arcade console surrounded by screens that can be programmed to simulate ice, road or pedestrian conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new plows are bigger than the city’s older ones, which has taken some getting used to. This is the first full year that the plows are equipped with iPads that display routes digitally, rather than drivers having to depend on paper maps and their memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are about 603 additional miles of roads to be cleared by city plows this winter, compared with in past years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We got the equipment, we got the guys — get to it, let’s get to it,” said William Shelton, 37, who usually cuts trees for the city, but who spent part of Friday using a snowplow to spray streets with brine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll keep driving ol’ Dolly,” he added, though the machine had just 1,200 miles on the odometer so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with Dolly Plowton, four other new snowplows in the newly expanded fleet were given names and paint job designs by public school students in Nashville: Music City Plow, Blizzard of Oz, Snowella and Frosty the Snow Plow. (Never mind that some students were hoping the new plows wouldn’t entirely clear away the snow-day magic.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Cane Ridge High School in Antioch, the class discussion about plow names began with a simple question: What is a snowplow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t have snow, like, all the time, where you would have a huge fleet of trucks,” said Larissa Ottinger, who teaches the class that came up with the Dolly Plowton moniker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her students, she said, “wouldn’t have necessarily seen” one of the vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to naming the plows, it was an easy decision to draw inspiration from one of Tennessee’s most beloved icons, according to Courtney Hester, 16, who said she happened to be wearing a Dolly Parton shirt that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ottinger said on Friday that her class was eagerly anticipating seeing their plow and its signature purple and pink snowflakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll definitely be out looking,” said Jordan Rizzo, 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the city hopes the new plows will help keep winter mayhem to a minimum this weekend, the message to its residents remains the same: Please stay home.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/dolly-plowton-debuts-in-snowy-nashville.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:37:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Over a Thousand Protesters in New York Denounce ICE After Latest Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/nyc-ice-protest-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-NYC-protests-hqlp/24minneapolis-ice-NYC-protests-hqlp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a powerful winter storm approaching New York City and temperatures in the teens, more than a thousand demonstrators rallied on short notice at Union Square late Saturday afternoon to protest the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t know I could be enraged more than I already was,” said Alli Malafronte, 61, a retired nurse who lives in Manhattan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signs held in the frigid air read “Justice for Alex” in honor of Alex Jeffrey Pretti, 37, a registered nurse shot and killed by ICE agents in Minneapolis earlier on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Say it once, say it twice, we will not put up with ICE,” the crowd chanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One sign was held by Indigo Moore, 27, a school administrator who lives in Manhattan. She was horrified by online videos of Mr. Pretti’s shooting. Ms. Moore said she had been to Union Square on Friday for a similarly frigid protest against the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At this rate I’m getting pretty angry,” she said, “and that’s what’s keeping me warm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attendees expressed a mix of anguished resignation and outraged optimism about what effect the demonstration might have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ella Devi, 18, a Parsons University student who lives in Manhattan and who had campaigned for Mayor Zohran Mamdani in Union Square last year, the turnout was a sign that a political movement for change was gaining force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope it puts pressure on electeds to abolish ICE,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Fowler, a psychiatric nurse practitioner who lives in Manhattan, said the protest served less as a portent of a good future than as a place to mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not angry, I’m hurt,” Ms. Fowler said, adding that Mr. Pretti reminded her of her seven kids, four of whom are veterans. “This is America and I love America,” she said, referring to the scene around her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Fowler’s sign read “Protesting ICE Is Not a Crime!” Other signs read, “Stop ICE Terror,” “ICE Is Trump’s Gestapo” and “No Kings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manny Vasquez, 21, a service industry worker from Queens, held a giant sign featuring the face of Hakeem Jeffries, the Democratic House leader, and the words: “Abolish ICE Jeffries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I saw the news I was like, ‘Lemme go outside again,” to protest, he said. “And I hate the cold. No amount of money is worth it to me to be in this cold — that’s how much I want to be here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re facing something we’ve never faced in our country before — this level of lawlessness from a federal law enforcement agency,” said Zack Weinstein, a Manhattan resident over 60 who works as a filmmaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After massing at Union Square, the protesters started marching. They blocked traffic as they headed west to Sixth Avenue, north to 23rd Street and east toward Madison Square Park. The protesters then turned south and hundreds eventually rallied outside 26 Federal Plaza, ICE’s headquarters in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before joining the march, Sam Dixon, a 30-year-old art director, held a sign with an expletive telling ICE to go away. He had made it after seeing video of Mr. Pretti’s shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You see the horrors all the time and you feel so helpless,” he said. “You want action to be taken against ICE and this administration.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/nyc-ice-protest-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:50:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Running for U.S. Senate in Texas Call for Overhaul of ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/texas-debate-senate-jasmine-crockett-james-talarico-democrats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-texas-debate-qzjw/24nat-texas-debate-qzjw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top two Democratic candidates for U.S. Senate in Texas showcased their disagreements over political tactics and style on Saturday, in the first debate of a primary race that has drawn national interest as an early test of the party’s direction in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The candidates — Jasmine Crockett and James Talarico — directed their sharpest words of the debate, which took place just a few hours after a 37-year-old man was fatally shot by federal agents in Minnesota, not at each other but at the Trump administration, and the aggressive tactics of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents on American streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s time to tear down this secret police force,” said Mr. Talarico, a state representative whose progressive Christian faith has attracted attention. “We need to prosecute agents who have abused their power. We have to haul these masked men before Congress so the world can see their faces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett, an outspoken U.S. Representative with a national following, said that immigration agents were “turning us into Nazi Germany” with tactics that included going door to door and “going after people because of their accent or the color of their skin.” She added that “we absolutely have to clean house.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two candidates are young, social-media savvy politicians who largely agree on matters of policy, like increasing taxes on billionaires and opposing foreign policy adventurism by President Trump. So the race has focused instead on their differing approaches to how to win in Texas, where no Democrat has won a race for a statewide office in three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underscoring the importance of that difference, the debate, which was held by the Texas AFL-CIO on a stage outside Austin, began with the subject of electability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will do the edgy things, the things that the political consultants will never tell you to do,” said Ms. Crockett, who occasionally struggled to fit her responses to questions into the allotted time. “It’s not about who sounds as clean as possible. It is about tapping into the rawness of this moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett, 44, a former defense lawyer, is betting that her willingness to spar with Republicans in the House and her ability to attract attention online will bring new voters to the polls, and that she will be able to persuade Democrats to turn out who might otherwise have stayed home. She has only been in the race for a month, but she already has greater name recognition among Democrats than her opponent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a point Ms. Crockett made herself, in remarks that approached criticism of Mr. Talarico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s not as known right now, because I have engaged in these fights,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Mr. Talarico, 36, a seminarian and former middle school teacher, has been campaigning not only to court Democrats, but also to reach middle-of-the-road voters and Republicans who have been turned off by the Trump administration. He spent much of the debate stressing his alliance with Ms. Crockett on issues, while attacking “billionaires,” whom he said were ruining politics and making life unaffordable for Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not writing off any voter or any community,” Mr. Talarico said. “We will not win this race in November with the same old politics of division. Billionaires want us looking left and right at each other, so we’re not looking up at them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early voting in the Texas primaries begins Feb. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats see an opportunity in Texas this year, which is why the argument within the party about who would offer the best chance of victory against a Republican candidate has been so acute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times, supporters of Mr. Talarico and Ms. Crockett have argued with each other online. But the candidates know that whoever wins the March 3 primary will need their rival’s supporters as well as their own in order to win what will probably be a close general election race in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of what gives Democrats hope is that there has been even greater internal strife among Republicans during their primary campaign. Senator John Cornyn has been trading bruising attacks with his main challenger, Attorney General Ken Paxton, as well as with a third candidate in the race, U.S. Representative Wesley Hunt. Their primary is likely to go to a runoff, extending the G.O.P. intramural fight to the end of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In November, we have a moral imperative to win,” Mr. Talarico said in his closing remarks on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett similarly closed by citing the high stakes she saw in both the election and the political fights to come in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whoever goes to the United States Senate is going to have to be ready for real war,” she said, referencing a recent death threat she had received and the killing of two people by federal agents in Minnesota. “I am here to tell you that it is life or death.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/texas-debate-senate-jasmine-crockett-james-talarico-democrats.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:14:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gun Activists Bridle at Suggestion That Pistol Justified Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-second-amendment.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-second-amendment-zkqj/24minneapolis-ice-second-amendment-zkqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some high-profile gun rights activists and groups bristled on Saturday at government officials’ claims that federal agents may have been justified in killing a Minneapolis man during a protest because he was carrying a pistol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right to bear arms in public has been a mainstay of the gun rights movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, a Los Angeles federal prosecutor, Bill Essayli, became a magnet for outrage when he wrote on social media that “If you approach law enforcement with a gun, there is a high likelihood they will be legally justified in shooting you. Don’t do it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun Owners of America, one of the country’s largest gun advocacy groups, said in its own posting that it condemned his “untoward comments.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group said that “federal agents are not ‘highly likely’ to be ‘legally justified’ in ‘shooting’ concealed carry licensees who approach while lawfully carrying a firearm. The Second Amendment protects Americans’ right to bear arms while protesting — a right the federal government must not infringe upon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gun group also accused “the Left” of “antagonizing” immigration agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange could point to political fissures between the gun rights movement and President Trump, who is generally seen as an ally. And it already is sparking debate within a movement that has long warned against government overreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Rifle Association referred to federal agents as “jackbooted government thugs” in a 1995 mailer. But in a statement Saturday night, the N.R.A. put blame for the shooting on Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota and other “radical progressive politicians.” It said their “calls to dangerously interject oneself into legitimate law-enforcement activities have ended in violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As there is with any officer-involved shooting, there will be a robust and comprehensive investigation that takes place to determine if the use of force was justified,” the group added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a separate post, the N.R.A. called Mr. Essayli’s comments “dangerous and wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Responsible public voices should be awaiting a full investigation, not making generalizations and demonizing law-abiding citizens,” it said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video footage shows that Alex Jeffrey Pretti, an intensive care nurse at a Veterans Affairs hospital, stepped between a woman and an agent pepper spraying her, and then was sprayed himself. He appeared to hold a phone in one hand and nothing in the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As agents restrained him, one appeared to take his pistol, videos show, and then agents opened fire, killing him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief Brian O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said that Mr. Pretti was an American citizen with no known criminal record, and had a firearms permit allowing him to carry a gun openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We the people have a right to bear arms in public,” Cam Edwards, a prominent gun rights activist and radio host, said in a social media post. “I’ve encountered countless police while I’ve been armed, and never been shot. The presence of a firearm, by itself, is not an indicator of a criminal intent or a threat to law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Bovino, a top Border Patrol official leading the crackdown in Minneapolis, said at a news conference on Saturday that Mr. Pretti “had two loaded magazines,” and appeared to want to do “maximum damage and massacre law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No evidence has been produced to back up that claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dana Loesch, a former spokeswoman of the National Rifle Association, highlighted Mr. Bovino’s comments, saying in a social media post that “statements like this don’t help. What he has or didn’t have isn’t the issue. What he was doing, with or without it, is the issue. Did he draw on agents? Reach for it? Was it on him?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Fernandez, an Orlando, Fla., firearms instructor and founder of Equality In Arms Defensive Training, also took issue with Mr. Bovino. Mr. Fernandez said the official had falsely characterized Mr. Pretti as “a crazed assailant launching himself at C.B.P. officers, pistol drawn and firing with the intent to slaughter as many of them as possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said that the heavy-handed tactics of federal agents have left people on both sides of the political spectrum “living in fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “How can they not be when this is what we are seeing?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has argued strongly for the right to carry guns. A Justice Department suit filed in December against the U.S. Virgin Islands over its gun permitting process, for example, noted that “law-abiding citizens” have “a fundamental right to ‘carry handguns publicly for self-defense.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Levine, who runs an online gun rights advocacy company called A Better Way 2A, said that “what happened in Minneapolis shows that ICE will treat the mere presence of a legal firearm as justification for lethal force. Carrying a gun is not a crime, yet it was readily used as proof of dangerous intent once Alex Pretti was dead and unable to contest that narrative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danielle L. Campbell, who helped found Protect Peace, a community outreach group for gun owners in Central and Southern Florida, said she was shocked after watching video of the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m willing to wait for more facts to come out,” she said. “What I will say is carrying a concealed weapon legally shouldn’t be a death sentence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike McIntire contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-second-amendment.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 19:58:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Court Filings, Witnesses Describe Fatal Minneapolis Shooting of Alex Pretti</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor who lives near the scene where Alex Jeffrey Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday described in a sworn court filing how agents initially hesitated and asked for proof of a medical license when the doctor tried to approach and render aid. And a person who said they were standing near Mr. Pretti disputed the Department of Homeland Security’s account of that incident in another sworn court filing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Mr. Pretti, 37, renewed protests and clashes with law enforcement in a city where tensions over aggressive federal immigration action are high. Video footage of the encounter appeared to contradict parts of the federal government’s narrative of what happened, and the latest court filings raised further questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor, whose name was redacted from the publicly available version of the court filing, described themselves as a pediatrician and said they had witnessed parts of the encounter from a nearby apartment. Though their view was from a distance, they described seeing a man being shoved to the ground and then shot several times. After the gunfire, they described going outside, telling an agent that they were a physician and asking to check the person who had been shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor said they were initially turned down, but eventually allowed to go to the person after being patted down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Normally, I would not have been so persistent,” the doctor said in their statement, “but as a physician, I felt a professional and moral obligation to help this man, especially since none of the agents were helping him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor described checking for a pulse, finding none, and then beginning C.P.R. The man appeared to have been shot several times, the doctor said. Shortly after he started C.P.R., emergency medical personnel arrived and took over, the doctor said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the shooting, the doctor described returning home as protests intensified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was sobbing and shaking uncontrollably,” they said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once tear gas began seeping into their apartment from the street below, they said they got in a car and drove to a friend’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am not sure when I will return to my apartment,” the doctor wrote. “I do not feel safe in my city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after agents shot Mr. Pretti on Saturday morning, federal officials claimed that he had endangered agents with a gun he was carrying, and some later accused him of “domestic terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times appear to contradict portions of the Department of Homeland Security’s account of the shooting, and the Minneapolis police chief, Brian O’Hara, said that Mr. Pretti was believed to be licensed to legally carry a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another person who said they witnessed the shooting also submitted a sworn statement in court on Saturday. Like the doctor’s statement, it was filed as part of a lawsuit challenging federal agents’ interactions with protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have read the statement from D.H.S. about what happened and it is wrong,” said that person, who described themselves as a children’s entertainer specializing in face painting. “The man did not approach the agents with a gun. He approached them with a camera. He was just trying to help a woman get up and they took him to the ground.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That witness described hearing whistles — which Minneapolis residents have used to alert people to the presence of immigration agents — and going toward the noise to observe and record on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person said they walked toward an area where someone was being thrown to the ground and then started filming. When an agent asked them to move back, the witness said, they slowly did so. Another man who was in the street and who was also recording remained there and continued filming, the witness said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The man stayed in the street, filming as the other observers I mentioned earlier were being forced backward by another ICE agent threatening them with pepper spray,” the witness statement said. “The man went closer to support them as they got threatened, just with his camera out. I didn’t see him reach for or hold a gun.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person was thrown to the ground by an agent, the witness said, and pepper spray was used. The man who had been filming — almost certainly Mr. Pretti, though no name was used in the court filing — tried to help the person who had fallen, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The agents pulled the man on the ground,” the statement said, adding that the witness was perhaps five feet away. “I didn’t see him touch any of them — he wasn’t even turned toward them. It didn’t look like he was trying to resist, just trying to help the woman up. I didn’t see him with a gun. They threw him to the ground. Four or five agents had him on the ground and they just started shooting him. They shot him so many times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court filing said that a video taken by the witness was also filed with the court, but that footage was not immediately accessible through an online court records system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to a request for comment about the witness statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those sworn statements were filed as part of a lawsuit backed by the American Civil Liberties Union of Minnesota that accused federal agents of repeatedly violating protesters’ rights during a recent surge of immigration enforcement. The federal judge hearing that case issued an injunction earlier this month that imposed restrictions on agents. The Trump administration appealed, and an appellate court issued an administrative stay this week that blocked the injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, lawyers for the protesters filed an emergency motion that asked the appellate court to allow the injunction to go back into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 19:41:39 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>