<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 14:30:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Minneapolis Live Updates: Man Killed by Federal Agents Was Holding a Phone, Not a Gun</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/authorities-in-minneapolis-respond-to-reports-of-shooting-involving-federal-agents</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-promo-0430/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
At least two people have been shot by agents in Minneapolis this month, including Renee Good, 37, who was killed in her car.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/us/minneapolis-shooting-ice/authorities-in-minneapolis-respond-to-reports-of-shooting-involving-federal-agents</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 17:24:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump and Federal Officials Try to Blame Minnesota Authorities and Slain Man</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-Trump-topart-hqmk/24minneapolis-ice-Trump-topart-hqmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump moved swiftly on Saturday to try to shift the blame for another shooting death in Minneapolis away from the federal agents involved in the incident, claiming instead that it was the result of inflammatory rhetoric by local officials and the victim himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of Mr. Trump’s administration also quickly labeled the man, who Minneapolis police said was 37 and an American citizen, as a “domestic terrorist” and would-be assassin hours after the morning shooting, before all the facts were known or an investigation could take place. Videos taken by bystanders appeared to contradict the account of federal officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a pair of social media posts, Mr. Trump accused local politicians, including Gov. Tim Walz and Jacob Frey, the mayor of Minneapolis, of “inciting Insurrection” in an attempt to divert attention from an unrelated fraud scandal. He called Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents “patriots” who were left unassisted by the local police as they seek to detain what Mr. Trump described as violent immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they were still there, you would see something far worse than you are witnessing today!” the president wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also shared a photo of a firearm that federal officials claim belonged to the man who was killed. The police in Minneapolis said the man, whom law enforcement officials identified as Alex Jeffrey Pretti, had a firearms permit. It is legal to openly carry a weapon in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security said the episode began when a man approached Border Patrol agents “with a 9 mm semiautomatic handgun” and they tried to disarm him. But footage from the scene verified by The New York Times shows that the man was holding a phone in his hand when federal agents took him to the ground and shot him. A Times analysis found that at least 10 shots were fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.S. official said the Department of Homeland Security would investigate the shooting, with the help of the F.B.I. The Justice Department’s civil rights division, which has historically investigated shootings involving federal law enforcement officials, is not expected to be involved, said two senior law enforcement officials, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss internal decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite that, top Department of Homeland Security leaders weighed in on the shooting Saturday with assertions of what had occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Bovino, the Border Patrol official in charge of agents in Minnesota, claimed that the man was attempting to murder agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This looks like a situation where an individual wanted to do maximum damage and massacre law enforcement,” Mr. Bovino said at a news conference on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defiant and angry response by the president and members of his administration further inflamed tensions in a city that has for weeks been racked by conflicts between protesters and government agents sent there to enforce the president’s crackdown on immigrants. Increasingly, U.S. citizens have taken to the streets to protest what many have described as a military-style occupation of an American city in which federal agents are using aggressive and violent tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting further deepened a calcifying rift between federal officials and their counterparts in Minnesota, where local and state officials said they have been given sparse information about the actions of federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the shooting, Stephen Miller, the White House deputy chief of staff, posted messages on social media claiming the man was seeking to murder federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A would-be assassin tried to murder federal law enforcement and the official Democrat account sides with the terrorists,” Mr. Miller said. Earlier, he responded to a social media post from Senator Amy Klobuchar, Democrat of Minnesota, that criticized the administration’s crackdown in her state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A domestic terrorist tried to assassinate federal law enforcement and this is your response?” he wrote. “You and the state’s entire Democrat leadership team have been flaming the flames of insurrection for the singular purpose of stopping the deportation of illegals who invaded the country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem echoed the idea that Mr. Pretti was a domestic terrorist in a news conference on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This looks like a situation where an individual arrived at the scene to inflict maximum damage on individuals and to kill law enforcement,” she said, despite no known evidence of his intent. She called her assertion of “domestic terrorism” just “the facts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fatal shooting Saturday came a little over two weeks after Renee Good, a 37-year-old woman, was shot three times while she was driving in her S.U.V.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the hours after she was shot and killed, Ms. Good was also labeled a “domestic terrorist” by members of the Trump administration, as officials moved quickly to exonerate the ICE official who shot her before an investigation could determine what had occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A supervisor in the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis field office resigned after bureau leadership in Washington pressured her to discontinue a civil rights inquiry into Jonathan Ross, the immigration officer who shot Ms. Good, The Times reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and top officials were following a similar playbook in their response to the shooting of Mr. Pretti on Saturday, even as videos emerged that challenged their accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, angry Minnesota officials demanded that Department of Homeland Security officials leave the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How many more residents, how many more Americans, need to die or get badly hurt for this operation to end?” Mr. Frey said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media and in a later news conference, Mr. Walz said he had spoken with Susie Wiles, Mr. Trump’s chief of staff, after the shooting. He had argued for state officials to lead the investigation. He accused “the most powerful people in the federal government” of “spinning stories and putting up pictures.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of immigration agents, Mr. Walz added: “They killed a man, created chaos, pushed down protesters, threw gas indiscriminately and then left the scene and then we’re left to clean up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glenn Thrush contributed reporting from Washington, and Mitch Smith from Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:43:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Vow Not to Fund ICE After Shooting, Imperiling Spending Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/democrats-congress-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-congress/13TRUMP-NEWS-WARNER-print-lpkc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bipartisan legislation to fund a broad swath of the government and avert a shutdown at the end of the week appeared to be in grave danger on Saturday, as key Senate Democrats vowed to oppose it after federal agents shot and killed a Minneapolis resident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapidly escalating opposition to the measure, which includes $64.4 billion for the Department of Homeland Security, including $10 billion for ICE, amplified the likelihood of a partial government shutdown at the end of the month. The legislation requires the support of Democrats to muster the 60 votes needed to avoid a filibuster and advance in the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Senate Democrats will not provide the votes to proceed to the appropriations bill if the D.H.S. funding bill is included,” Senator Chuck Schumer, Democrat of New York and the minority leader, said in a statement, calling what is unfolding in Minnesota “appalling” and “unacceptable in any American city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the depth of Democratic outrage, Senate Republicans immediately began examining whether they could separate the homeland security funding from the rest of the package and preserve the bulk of what had been a bipartisan deal to fund a large chunk of the government. The measure also funds the Pentagon and State Department, as well as health, education, labor and transportation programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m exploring all options,” said Senator Susan Collins, the Maine Republican who is the chairwoman of the Appropriations Committee, adding that she had been in touch with Senator John Thune, the South Dakota Republican and majority leader. “We have five other bills that are really vital, and I’m relatively confident they would pass.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A planned vote on the package next week had already promised to pose an agonizing dilemma for many Democrats. They have been eager to avoid another shutdown but have grown increasingly infuriated by the scenes of chaos and violence coming out of Minnesota and facing intense pressure not to fund ICE. Some had already announced they would not support the package as a result, but a substantial bloc had been expected to swallow their reservations and back it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hours after the killing on Saturday, a flood of Democrats who had previously been seen as likely to support the deal declared that they simply could not do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Trump administration and Kristi Noem are putting undertrained, combative federal agents on the streets with no accountability,” Senator Catherine Cortez Masto, Democrat of Nevada, said in a statement announcing her opposition. “They are oppressing Americans and are at odds with local law enforcement. This is clearly not about keeping Americans safe. It’s brutalizing U.S. citizens and law-abiding immigrants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mark Warner, Democrat of Virginia, wrote on social media: “I cannot and will not vote to fund D.H.S. while this administration continues these violent federal takeovers of our cities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spending measure that senators are set to take up includes six bills to fund the government that Democrats and Republicans negotiated, and that the House already passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The House considered the homeland security portion separately, given the depth of Democratic opposition, and all but seven House Democrats voted against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The measure rejects President Trump’s request for an $840 million increase in funding for ICE, instead leaving it roughly the same as the previous year, when the agency was operating off funds provided in a stopgap measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While other departments and agencies would most likely shutter if Senate Democrats filibuster the spending package, ICE could potentially tap the $75 billion Republicans allocated to it in their marquee domestic policy bill. That legislation largely contained tax cuts and spending reductions for programs including Medicaid and food assistance, but also included $190 billion for the Department of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During negotiations on the homeland security bill, Republicans rejected a series of proposals by Democrats to rein in ICE, including barring funds from being used to to detain or deport U.S. citizens. Democrats succeeded in winning the addition of $20 million for purchasing body cameras for ICE agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also won the inclusion of a provision to reduce funding for Ms. Noem’s office by $29.5 million and require the secretary to pay for any travel on government aircraft — in this case private jets the Coast Guard bought — out of the budget for her own office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Collins, who called for an investigation into the shooting, noted that the spending measure also includes some new guardrails on ICE, included money for de-escalation training and added authority for the agency’s inspector general to investigate disputed accounts of ICE activities. Those provisions would be lost if Congress ended up not approving the new bill, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a number of Senate Democrats said on Saturday that those measures fell far short of what was necessary in the current moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am voting against funding for D.H.S. until and unless more controls are put in place to hold ICE accountable,” said Senator Brian Schatz of Hawaii, a member of the Appropriations Committee. “These repeated incidents of violence across the country are unlawful, needlessly escalatory and making all of us less safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schumer also said he would vote no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Democrats sought common sense reforms in the Department of Homeland Security spending bill, but because of Republicans’ refusal to stand up to President Trump, the D.H.S. bill is woefully inadequate to rein in the abuses of ICE,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/democrats-congress-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 18:47:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What We Know About a Second Fatal Shooting by Federal Agents in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/second-ice-shooting-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc/24xp-wwk-minnesota-tzlc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday fatally shot a 37-year-old man, the second person to be shot and killed in the city during a ramped-up immigration enforcement effort by the Trump administration, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two other people have been shot by federal law enforcement agents in Minneapolis this month — one in the leg and another, Renee Good, 37, in the head, killing her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ms. Good’s death on Jan. 7, protests have taken place in the city, raising tensions with federal agents. State and local officials have called for federal agents to leave the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we know:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking at a news conference Greg Bovino, the official in charge of President Trump’s Border Patrol operations, said agents were conducting a “targeted operation” searching for a man accused of domestic assault and other charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person who was shot was not the target of the operation, Mr. Bovino said. He said the episode began after a man with a handgun approached Border Patrol agents and they tried to disarm him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino and Kristi Noem, secretary of the Department of Homeland Security, said the man wanted to hurt law enforcement officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bovino said the agent who fired has been with the Border Patrol for eight years. He did not publicly identify the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief Brian O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said investigators believed that at least two agents fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video on social media verified by The New York Times shows several agents tussling with the man before bringing him to his knees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man appears to resist as agents grab his legs, push down on his back and strike him repeatedly. This video does not show what led to the episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage shows an agent approaching and grabbing at the man as other agents hold him down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An agent appears to pull a gun from out of the scrum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simultaneously, another agent unholsters his firearm. That agent aims at the man’s back and appears to fire one shot at close range. He then appears to continue firing at the man, who collapses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two agents appear to fire at the man as he is motionless on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, at least 10 shots appear to have been fired within five seconds, according to the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage of the encounter shows the man was holding a phone in his hand, not a gun, when federal agents took him to the ground and shot him. There was no evidence that the man who was fatally shot opened fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities did not publicly identify the man who was killed but colleagues and a senior law enforcement official identified the man as Alex Jeffrey Pretti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A colleague, Dimitri Drekonja, said Mr. Pretti worked in the intensive-care unit at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said at a news conference that the person who was shot was a 37-year-old man who lived in Minneapolis and was an American citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man had no criminal record and had a permit to carry a gun, Chief O’Hara said. Minnesota law allows citizens with a permit to carry handguns in public without concealment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief O’Hara said he asked the Minnesota Bureau of Criminal Apprehension to lead the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drew Evans, the superintendent of the bureau, said at a news conference that the Department of Homeland Security had blocked state agents from the scene of the shooting on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being denied access, the bureau is talking with witnesses and seeking video, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal authorities said the Department of Homeland Security would lead the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mary Moriarty, the prosecutor in Hennepin County, which includes Minneapolis, said that the “scene must be secured by local law enforcement for preservation of evidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minnesota officials have been blocked by federal agencies from getting access to evidence and pursuing an investigation of Ms. Good’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota has authorized the deployment of the National Guard amid concerns of escalating violence. National Guard members will wear neon vests to distinguish them from federal immigration agents, state officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/second-ice-shooting-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:33:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alex Jeffrey Pretti Knew He Wanted to Help Others</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-jeffrey-pretti-was-an-icu-nurse-at-the-va-hospital.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-victim-topart-fhlp/24minneapolis-ice-victim-topart-fhlp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man fatally shot by Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis was Alex Jeffrey Pretti, a U.S. citizen with no criminal record, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, who was 37, was a registered nurse who worked in the intensive-care unit at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis, according to interviews and public records, and lived in an apartment in Minneapolis a short drive away from where he was killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had a firearms permit, required by state law in Minnesota to carry a handgun, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues and acquaintances of Mr. Pretti were stunned by his death, recalling a friendly neighbor and hardworking professional who was devoted to his patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dimitri Drekonja said that the two had worked together for years. Mr. Pretti was capable, competent and friendly, he said, the kind of person who cared deeply about his work and his patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a really great colleague and a really great friend,” he said. “The default look on his face was a smile.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two chatted regularly about mountain biking, one of Mr. Pretti’s passions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Family members of Mr. Pretti declined to comment on Saturday. Michael Pretti, Mr. Pretti’s father, told The Associated Press that he had warned his son to be careful in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We had this discussion with him two weeks ago or so, you know, that go ahead and protest, but do not engage, do not do anything stupid, basically,” Michael Pretti said. “And he said he knows that. He knew that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti received a bachelor’s degree from the University of Minnesota in 2011, a spokeswoman said. He graduated from a high school in Green Bay, Wis., in 2006, and was listed on the honor roll in a local newspaper. His parents now live in Colorado, and his former spouse lives in California.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A next-door neighbor, Jeanne Wiener, said she believed Mr. Pretti lived alone with his dog, but saw him walking frequently, and would speak with him several times a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing in her home, Ms. Wiener said she was shocked to hear of his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We talk over the fence all the time,” she said. “He’s the sweetest, kindest, most unoffensive, most nonviolent person you’d ever want to meet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruth Anway, who worked with Mr. Pretti, described him as a passionate colleague and kindhearted friend with a sharp sense of humor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Anway, a nurse, said she first met Mr. Pretti around 2014 when he was a research assistant at the hospital. She said she had encouraged him to pursue nursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He really thrived in that environment,” she said in a phone interview on Saturday. “He wanted to be helpful, to help humanity and have a career that was a force of good in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his free time, she said, Mr. Pretti loved to bike the trails around Minneapolis, and spent time with his dog, Joule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Anway said Mr. Pretti followed the news closely and cared deeply about social justice and fighting for fairness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not surprised he was out there protesting and observing,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aasma Shaukat, a physician at the V.A. who worked with Mr. Pretti, said she had hired him to his first job in the research department at the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, then fresh from college and in his early 20s, had come to her with no medical training, but a deep drive, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was your typical struggling young person with a lot of ambition, but no direction yet,” she said. “But he knew he wanted to help people in some way or another.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti spent the next few years working for Dr. Shaukat, assisting on medical studies and enrolling patients — while delivering pizzas at night to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time they spoke, Mr. Pretti had been working extra shifts as a nurse, saving up to buy a home and a new car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was happy, and I was happy for him because his life was just starting,” she said. “This feels so senseless and just so wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/alex-jeffrey-pretti-was-an-icu-nurse-at-the-va-hospital.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:38:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Dolly Plowton’ Debuts in Snowy Nashville</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/dolly-plowton-debuts-in-snowy-nashville.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-nashville-snow-01-zwhm/24nat-nashville-snow-01-zwhm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A father, with his two children each carrying a sled, stopped to wave from the sidewalk. A boy with a snowball in hand ran across his yard to see it go by. As chunks of snow flew off the road, a bundled-up pair of walkers whooped in appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an occasional honk for well-wishers, Dolly Plowton — a snazzy new snowplow adorned with purple and pink snowflakes — was making its Nashville debut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I get a lot of waves, a lot of hurrahs,” said Greg Bergstresser, 23, who spent much of his 12-hour shift on Saturday behind the wheel of the snowplow, driving through West Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to how well the South deals with snow and ice, the question is not necessarily one of individual fortitude. The region is accustomed to meteorological and natural calamity: hurricanes, tornadoes, sweltering humidity, even invasive flora and fauna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the South struggles with low temperatures and snow-slickened roads, it is often more of a matter of infrastructure and inexperience. Southerners resort to staying home during winter storms in part because they know that, in a region that does not see snow and ice very often, even a couple of inches can snarl roads and ravage the power grid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The addition of Dolly Plowton and four other new snowplows in Nashville illustrates how some Southern cities have been trying to shore up their little-used winter infrastructure. It also reflects the migration of many people to the region from colder parts of the country, who bring assumptions about how a city should respond to snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a different mentality, and, as we’ve had different people move in here from outside of this area, the expectation has been different” from that of lifelong residents, said Philip Jones, the deputy director of Nashville’s transportation department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this weekend’s snowstorm, he added, “has been the talk of the town.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jones and others on his staff concede that, while they loved snow days as children, they are more serious now as adults working 12-hour weekend shifts to deal with the storm. The main concern in the city was not so much the accumulating snow as the possible buildup of ice through days of below-freezing temperatures; ice is a far more potent threat to power lines, roads and other city infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tennessee Department of Transportation reported responding to dozens of traffic incidents on Saturday as snow began to fall across the state. But many motorists heeded warnings to stay off the roads: In parts of Nashville, the snowplows encountered a fraction of the usual traffic as they pushed slowly up and down the streets, passing an occasional jogger, dog walker or sledding child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has not been cheap to build up the city’s fleet, which now numbers 45 plows. The five new trucks cost about $350,000 apiece. The city spent another $200,000 on a driver training simulator, which is essentially an arcade console surrounded by screens that can be programmed to simulate ice, road or pedestrian conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new plows are bigger than the city’s older ones, which has taken some getting used to. This is the first full year that the plows are equipped with iPads that display routes digitally, rather than drivers having to depend on paper maps and their memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are about 603 additional miles of roads to be cleared by city plows this winter, compared with in past years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We got the equipment, we got the guys — get to it, let’s get to it,” said William Shelton, 37, who usually cuts trees for the city, but who spent part of Friday using a snowplow to spray streets with brine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll keep driving ol’ Dolly,” he added, though the machine had just 1,200 miles on the odometer so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with Dolly Plowton, four other new snowplows in the newly expanded fleet were given names and paint job designs by public school students in Nashville: Music City Plow, Blizzard of Oz, Snowella and Frosty the Snow Plow. (Never mind that some students were hoping the new plows wouldn’t entirely clear away the snow-day magic.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Cane Ridge High School in Antioch, the class discussion about plow names began with a simple question: What is a snowplow?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We don’t have snow, like, all the time, where you would have a huge fleet of trucks,” said Larissa Ottinger, who teaches the class that came up with the Dolly Plowton moniker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her students, she said, “wouldn’t have necessarily seen” one of the vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to naming the plows, it was an easy decision to draw inspiration from one of Tennessee’s most beloved icons, according to Courtney Hester, 16, who said she happened to be wearing a Dolly Parton shirt that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ottinger said on Friday that her class was eagerly anticipating seeing their plow and its signature purple and pink snowflakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll definitely be out looking,” said Jordan Rizzo, 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the city hopes the new plows will help keep winter mayhem to a minimum this weekend, the message to its residents remains the same: Please stay home.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/dolly-plowton-debuts-in-snowy-nashville.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:37:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Over a Thousand Protesters in New York Denounce ICE After Latest Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/nyc-ice-protest-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-NYC-protests-hqlp/24minneapolis-ice-NYC-protests-hqlp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a powerful winter storm approaching New York City and temperatures in the teens, more than a thousand demonstrators rallied on short notice at Union Square late Saturday afternoon to protest the U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t know I could be enraged more than I already was,” said Alli Malafronte, 61, a retired nurse who lives in Manhattan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Signs held in the frigid air read “Justice for Alex” in honor of Alex Jeffrey Pretti, 37, a registered nurse shot and killed by ICE agents in Minneapolis earlier on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Say it once, say it twice, we will not put up with ICE,” the crowd chanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One sign was held by Indigo Moore, 27, a school administrator who lives in Manhattan. She was horrified by online videos of Mr. Pretti’s shooting. Ms. Moore said she had been to Union Square on Friday for a similarly frigid protest against the Trump administration’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At this rate I’m getting pretty angry,” she said, “and that’s what’s keeping me warm.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attendees expressed a mix of anguished resignation and outraged optimism about what effect the demonstration might have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ella Devi, 18, a Parsons University student who lives in Manhattan and who had campaigned for Mayor Zohran Mamdani in Union Square last year, the turnout was a sign that a political movement for change was gaining force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope it puts pressure on electeds to abolish ICE,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Fowler, a psychiatric nurse practitioner who lives in Manhattan, said the protest served less as a portent of a good future than as a place to mourn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not angry, I’m hurt,” Ms. Fowler said, adding that Mr. Pretti reminded her of her seven kids, four of whom are veterans. “This is America and I love America,” she said, referring to the scene around her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Fowler’s sign read “Protesting ICE Is Not a Crime!” Other signs read, “Stop ICE Terror,” “ICE Is Trump’s Gestapo” and “No Kings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manny Vasquez, 21, a service industry worker from Queens, held a giant sign featuring the face of Hakeem Jeffries, the Democratic House leader, and the words: “Abolish ICE Jeffries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When I saw the news I was like, ‘Lemme go outside again,” to protest, he said. “And I hate the cold. No amount of money is worth it to me to be in this cold — that’s how much I want to be here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re facing something we’ve never faced in our country before — this level of lawlessness from a federal law enforcement agency,” said Zack Weinstein, a Manhattan resident over 60 who works as a filmmaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After massing at Union Square, the protesters started marching. They blocked traffic as they headed west to Sixth Avenue, north to 23rd Street and east toward Madison Square Park. The protesters then turned south and hundreds eventually rallied outside 26 Federal Plaza, ICE’s headquarters in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before joining the march, Sam Dixon, a 30-year-old art director, held a sign with an expletive telling ICE to go away. He had made it after seeing video of Mr. Pretti’s shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You see the horrors all the time and you feel so helpless,” he said. “You want action to be taken against ICE and this administration.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/nyc-ice-protest-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:50:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Running for U.S. Senate in Texas Call for Overhaul of ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/texas-debate-senate-jasmine-crockett-james-talarico-democrats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-texas-debate-qzjw/24nat-texas-debate-qzjw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top two Democratic candidates for U.S. Senate in Texas showcased their disagreements over political tactics and style on Saturday, in the first debate of a primary race that has drawn national interest as an early test of the party’s direction in 2026.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The candidates — Jasmine Crockett and James Talarico — directed their sharpest words of the debate, which took place just a few hours after a 37-year-old man was fatally shot by federal agents in Minnesota, not at each other but at the Trump administration, and the aggressive tactics of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents on American streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s time to tear down this secret police force,” said Mr. Talarico, a state representative whose progressive Christian faith has attracted attention. “We need to prosecute agents who have abused their power. We have to haul these masked men before Congress so the world can see their faces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett, an outspoken U.S. Representative with a national following, said that immigration agents were “turning us into Nazi Germany” with tactics that included going door to door and “going after people because of their accent or the color of their skin.” She added that “we absolutely have to clean house.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two candidates are young, social-media savvy politicians who largely agree on matters of policy, like increasing taxes on billionaires and opposing foreign policy adventurism by President Trump. So the race has focused instead on their differing approaches to how to win in Texas, where no Democrat has won a race for a statewide office in three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underscoring the importance of that difference, the debate, which was held by the Texas AFL-CIO on a stage outside Austin, began with the subject of electability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will do the edgy things, the things that the political consultants will never tell you to do,” said Ms. Crockett, who occasionally struggled to fit her responses to questions into the allotted time. “It’s not about who sounds as clean as possible. It is about tapping into the rawness of this moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett, 44, a former defense lawyer, is betting that her willingness to spar with Republicans in the House and her ability to attract attention online will bring new voters to the polls, and that she will be able to persuade Democrats to turn out who might otherwise have stayed home. She has only been in the race for a month, but she already has greater name recognition among Democrats than her opponent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a point Ms. Crockett made herself, in remarks that approached criticism of Mr. Talarico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s not as known right now, because I have engaged in these fights,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, Mr. Talarico, 36, a seminarian and former middle school teacher, has been campaigning not only to court Democrats, but also to reach middle-of-the-road voters and Republicans who have been turned off by the Trump administration. He spent much of the debate stressing his alliance with Ms. Crockett on issues, while attacking “billionaires,” whom he said were ruining politics and making life unaffordable for Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not writing off any voter or any community,” Mr. Talarico said. “We will not win this race in November with the same old politics of division. Billionaires want us looking left and right at each other, so we’re not looking up at them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early voting in the Texas primaries begins Feb. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats see an opportunity in Texas this year, which is why the argument within the party about who would offer the best chance of victory against a Republican candidate has been so acute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times, supporters of Mr. Talarico and Ms. Crockett have argued with each other online. But the candidates know that whoever wins the March 3 primary will need their rival’s supporters as well as their own in order to win what will probably be a close general election race in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of what gives Democrats hope is that there has been even greater internal strife among Republicans during their primary campaign. Senator John Cornyn has been trading bruising attacks with his main challenger, Attorney General Ken Paxton, as well as with a third candidate in the race, U.S. Representative Wesley Hunt. Their primary is likely to go to a runoff, extending the G.O.P. intramural fight to the end of May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In November, we have a moral imperative to win,” Mr. Talarico said in his closing remarks on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Crockett similarly closed by citing the high stakes she saw in both the election and the political fights to come in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whoever goes to the United States Senate is going to have to be ready for real war,” she said, referencing a recent death threat she had received and the killing of two people by federal agents in Minnesota. “I am here to tell you that it is life or death.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/texas-debate-senate-jasmine-crockett-james-talarico-democrats.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:14:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gun Activists Bridle at Suggestion That Pistol Justified Killing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-second-amendment.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-second-amendment-zkqj/24minneapolis-ice-second-amendment-zkqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some high-profile gun rights activists and groups bristled on Saturday at government officials’ claims that federal agents may have been justified in killing a Minneapolis man during a protest because he was carrying a pistol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right to bear arms in public has been a mainstay of the gun rights movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, a Los Angeles federal prosecutor, Bill Essayli, became a magnet for outrage when he wrote on social media that “If you approach law enforcement with a gun, there is a high likelihood they will be legally justified in shooting you. Don’t do it!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun Owners of America, one of the country’s largest gun advocacy groups, said in its own posting that it condemned his “untoward comments.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group said that “federal agents are not ‘highly likely’ to be ‘legally justified’ in ‘shooting’ concealed carry licensees who approach while lawfully carrying a firearm. The Second Amendment protects Americans’ right to bear arms while protesting — a right the federal government must not infringe upon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gun group also accused “the Left” of “antagonizing” immigration agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exchange could point to political fissures between the gun rights movement and President Trump, who is generally seen as an ally. And it already is sparking debate within a movement that has long warned against government overreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Rifle Association referred to federal agents as “jackbooted government thugs” in a 1995 mailer. But in a statement Saturday night, the N.R.A. put blame for the shooting on Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota and other “radical progressive politicians.” It said their “calls to dangerously interject oneself into legitimate law-enforcement activities have ended in violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As there is with any officer-involved shooting, there will be a robust and comprehensive investigation that takes place to determine if the use of force was justified,” the group added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a separate post, the N.R.A. called Mr. Essayli’s comments “dangerous and wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Responsible public voices should be awaiting a full investigation, not making generalizations and demonizing law-abiding citizens,” it said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video footage shows that Alex Jeffrey Pretti, an intensive care nurse at a Veterans Affairs hospital, stepped between a woman and an agent pepper spraying her, and then was sprayed himself. He appeared to hold a phone in one hand and nothing in the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As agents restrained him, one appeared to take his pistol, videos show, and then agents opened fire, killing him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief Brian O’Hara of the Minneapolis police said that Mr. Pretti was an American citizen with no known criminal record, and had a firearms permit allowing him to carry a gun openly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We the people have a right to bear arms in public,” Cam Edwards, a prominent gun rights activist and radio host, said in a social media post. “I’ve encountered countless police while I’ve been armed, and never been shot. The presence of a firearm, by itself, is not an indicator of a criminal intent or a threat to law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregory Bovino, a top Border Patrol official leading the crackdown in Minneapolis, said at a news conference on Saturday that Mr. Pretti “had two loaded magazines,” and appeared to want to do “maximum damage and massacre law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No evidence has been produced to back up that claim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dana Loesch, a former spokeswoman of the National Rifle Association, highlighted Mr. Bovino’s comments, saying in a social media post that “statements like this don’t help. What he has or didn’t have isn’t the issue. What he was doing, with or without it, is the issue. Did he draw on agents? Reach for it? Was it on him?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Fernandez, an Orlando, Fla., firearms instructor and founder of Equality In Arms Defensive Training, also took issue with Mr. Bovino. Mr. Fernandez said the official had falsely characterized Mr. Pretti as “a crazed assailant launching himself at C.B.P. officers, pistol drawn and firing with the intent to slaughter as many of them as possible.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said that the heavy-handed tactics of federal agents have left people on both sides of the political spectrum “living in fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “How can they not be when this is what we are seeing?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has argued strongly for the right to carry guns. A Justice Department suit filed in December against the U.S. Virgin Islands over its gun permitting process, for example, noted that “law-abiding citizens” have “a fundamental right to ‘carry handguns publicly for self-defense.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Levine, who runs an online gun rights advocacy company called A Better Way 2A, said that “what happened in Minneapolis shows that ICE will treat the mere presence of a legal firearm as justification for lethal force. Carrying a gun is not a crime, yet it was readily used as proof of dangerous intent once Alex Pretti was dead and unable to contest that narrative.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danielle L. Campbell, who helped found Protect Peace, a community outreach group for gun owners in Central and Southern Florida, said she was shocked after watching video of the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m willing to wait for more facts to come out,” she said. “What I will say is carrying a concealed weapon legally shouldn’t be a death sentence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike McIntire contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-second-amendment.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 19:58:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Court Filings, Witnesses Describe Fatal Minneapolis Shooting of Alex Pretti</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements/24minneapolis-ice-swornstatements-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor who lives near the scene where Alex Jeffrey Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents in Minneapolis on Saturday described in a sworn court filing how agents initially hesitated and asked for proof of a medical license when the doctor tried to approach and render aid. And a person who said they were standing near Mr. Pretti disputed the Department of Homeland Security’s account of that incident in another sworn court filing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shooting of Mr. Pretti, 37, renewed protests and clashes with law enforcement in a city where tensions over aggressive federal immigration action are high. Video footage of the encounter appeared to contradict parts of the federal government’s narrative of what happened, and the latest court filings raised further questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor, whose name was redacted from the publicly available version of the court filing, described themselves as a pediatrician and said they had witnessed parts of the encounter from a nearby apartment. Though their view was from a distance, they described seeing a man being shoved to the ground and then shot several times. After the gunfire, they described going outside, telling an agent that they were a physician and asking to check the person who had been shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor said they were initially turned down, but eventually allowed to go to the person after being patted down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Normally, I would not have been so persistent,” the doctor said in their statement, “but as a physician, I felt a professional and moral obligation to help this man, especially since none of the agents were helping him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The doctor described checking for a pulse, finding none, and then beginning C.P.R. The man appeared to have been shot several times, the doctor said. Shortly after he started C.P.R., emergency medical personnel arrived and took over, the doctor said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the shooting, the doctor described returning home as protests intensified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was sobbing and shaking uncontrollably,” they said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once tear gas began seeping into their apartment from the street below, they said they got in a car and drove to a friend’s home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am not sure when I will return to my apartment,” the doctor wrote. “I do not feel safe in my city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost immediately after agents shot Mr. Pretti on Saturday morning, federal officials claimed that he had endangered agents with a gun he was carrying, and some later accused him of “domestic terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times appear to contradict portions of the Department of Homeland Security’s account of the shooting, and the Minneapolis police chief, Brian O’Hara, said that Mr. Pretti was believed to be licensed to legally carry a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another person who said they witnessed the shooting also submitted a sworn statement in court on Saturday. Like the doctor’s statement, it was filed as part of a lawsuit challenging federal agents’ interactions with protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have read the statement from D.H.S. about what happened and it is wrong,” said that person, who described themselves as a children’s entertainer specializing in face painting. “The man did not approach the agents with a gun. He approached them with a camera. He was just trying to help a woman get up and they took him to the ground.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That witness described hearing whistles — which Minneapolis residents have used to alert people to the presence of immigration agents — and going toward the noise to observe and record on Saturday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person said they walked toward an area where someone was being thrown to the ground and then started filming. When an agent asked them to move back, the witness said, they slowly did so. Another man who was in the street and who was also recording remained there and continued filming, the witness said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The man stayed in the street, filming as the other observers I mentioned earlier were being forced backward by another ICE agent threatening them with pepper spray,” the witness statement said. “The man went closer to support them as they got threatened, just with his camera out. I didn’t see him reach for or hold a gun.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person was thrown to the ground by an agent, the witness said, and pepper spray was used. The man who had been filming — almost certainly Mr. Pretti, though no name was used in the court filing — tried to help the person who had fallen, the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The agents pulled the man on the ground,” the statement said, adding that the witness was perhaps five feet away. “I didn’t see him touch any of them — he wasn’t even turned toward them. It didn’t look like he was trying to resist, just trying to help the woman up. I didn’t see him with a gun. They threw him to the ground. Four or five agents had him on the ground and they just started shooting him. They shot him so many times.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court filing said that a video taken by the witness was also filed with the court, but that footage was not immediately accessible through an online court records system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security did not immediately respond to a request for comment about the witness statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those sworn statements were filed as part of a lawsuit backed by the American Civil Liberties Union of Minnesota that accused federal agents of repeatedly violating protesters’ rights during a recent surge of immigration enforcement. The federal judge hearing that case issued an injunction earlier this month that imposed restrictions on agents. The Trump administration appealed, and an appellate court issued an administrative stay this week that blocked the injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, lawyers for the protesters filed an emergency motion that asked the appellate court to allow the injunction to go back into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/witnesses-alex-pretti-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 04:47:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rep. Maxwell Alejandro Frost Is Assaulted at Sundance Film Festival</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/maxwell-alejandro-frost-assaulted-sundance-festival.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25xp-frost-qkhc/25xp-frost-qkhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Maxwell Alejandro Frost, Democrat of Florida, was hit in the face by a man who told the lawmaker that he would be deported at the Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah, over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attacker “told me that Trump was going to deport me before he punched me in the face,” Mr. Frost said in a social media post on Saturday. “He was heard screaming racist remarks as he drunkenly ran off.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Park City police said they responded to reports of an assault just after midnight on Saturday at the High West Saloon, a whiskey distillery and bar where a private party was being held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danielle Snelson, a community outreach lieutenant with the Park City Police Department, identified the assailant as Christian Young in an email Saturday night. Mr. Young “assaulted Florida Congressman Maxwell Frost and a female who was attending the private event,” Ms. Snelson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Young had “unlawfully” entered the event after being turned away because he did not have an invitation, according to Ms. Snelson. The police did not offer a possible motive for Mr. Young’s entry or assault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police arrested Mr. Young and booked him into the Summit County Jail on charges of aggravated burglary and two counts of simple assault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Frost’s family moved from Cuba to Florida in the early 1960s, part of a wave of hundreds of thousands of Cuban refugees who were flown to the United States, according to his campaign website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elected in 2022 at the age of 25, Mr. Frost became the first member of Generation Z to win a seat in Congress. He represents District 10, an area in Central Florida that includes much of Orlando.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Hakeem Jeffries, Democrat of New York, was one of several politicians who expressed their shock over the attack on social media. “Hate and political violence has no place in our country,” Mr. Jeffries said in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am okay. Thank you for all the well wishes. We are in scary times,” Mr. Frost said in a later post on his personal X account. “Please stay safe and do not let these people silence you. Onwards.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A representative from Sundance Film Festival did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Variety, the festival organizers said in a statement that they “strongly condemn last night’s assault and abhor any form of violence, harassment, and hate speech.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/maxwell-alejandro-frost-assaulted-sundance-festival.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:13:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Pushes A.I. Data Centers, but the G.O.P. Is Cool to One in Alabama</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-ai.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-bessemer-promo1-bhvm/25dc-bessemer-promo1-bhvm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kenneth E. Gulley, the mayor of Bessemer, Ala., confesses to some befuddlement as to why the people in his community would oppose the construction of a $14.5 billion artificial intelligence data center in a woodland just outside of town. “A data center is probably the most unintrusive thing,” Mr. Gulley said in his office one morning earlier this month. “You know, it’s like a big computer sitting in your backyard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several residents whose backyards may soon adjoin a digital facility the size of 18 Walmarts freely acknowledge their displeasure. “This is as pristine a forest that you’ll find in the foothills of the Appalachian Mountains,” said Ron Morgan, a diesel machinist and retired military veteran, who drove a reporter through the dense timberland behind his house in an all-terrain vehicle. “And if they have their way, all this will be gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Morgan’s sentiments are echoed by his neighbor Marshall Killingsworth, who bought his own land 58 years ago and now fears that the hoot owls in his backyard will no longer serenade him at night. Also fretful is Ronnie Buchanan, a retired rubber plant manager whose family has lived adjacent to the proposed site since 1979. “If that data center takes in all the water everyone says it will, it’s going to flood my land,” Mr. Buchanan said. “I’ll have to move.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seemingly overnight explosion in A.I. usage by American businesses and individuals has spawned a corresponding proliferation of facilities to store and manage all that digital information. As it stands, around 5,400 data centers currently exist in the United States. By 2030 they are expected to multiply by almost 50 percent. In a social media post on Jan. 12, President Trump expressed his view that “Data Centers are key” to America’s pre-eminence over China in the A.I. arms race.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the president’s cheerleading of A.I. — codified in an executive order last month in which he declared that the administration will “sustain and enhance the United States’ global A.I. dominance” — has not spurred equal fervor for the data center in Bessemer among Republican political leaders in Alabama. Senator Tommy Tuberville and the state’s governor, Kay Ivey, have not issued statements celebrating the project, and they did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alabama’s other senator, Katie Britt, also a Republican, said in a statement that she hoped that the facility would not raise utility costs. “I remain motivated to ensure that ratepayers are not footing the bill for data center buildouts,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Terri A. Sewell, an Alabama Democrat whose district includes Bessemer and who also declined a request for comment, said during a House hearing last year that some of her Bessemer constituents were “voicing their deep concern” about the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gulley, the city’s mayor, expressed weary exasperation. “It’s the largest single project in the state of Alabama’s history,” he said. “I would have liked to have heard more from those other individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as multibillion-dollar economic projects go, A.I. data centers lack ribbon-cutting allure. Their warehouse-like appearance and the continuous 50-decibel whir of their server fans do not project neighborliness. Any local tax revenues they might bring in are, to some extent, often offset by abatements that states like Alabama have put in place to attract such businesses to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their work forces tend to be small, requiring a highly skilled labor pool most likely drawn from elsewhere. “You can’t spin them as big job creators,” said Michael Hicks, an economics professor at Ball State University in Muncie, Ind., who has written extensively about data centers. “And beyond that, after all the tax incentives are offered, the local effects of these data centers are so vanishingly small, there’s no discernible economic benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data centers also pose risks. Cooling their servers requires enormous amounts of water, potentially straining the local supply and driving up utility costs in the process. “In the short run, at least, growing demand for energy by A.I. and the development of data centers will increase household and business costs of electricity,” Mr. Hicks said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while data center operators often pledge to rely on clean energy, a study published last year by the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy at the University of Michigan, in partnership with the Michigan Environmental Justice Coalition, concluded that such goals are “often delayed or abandoned altogether, resulting in the direct commissioning of new fossil fuel power plants to keep these facilities online.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resulting air pollution from such emissions was found by a Harvard Business Review study last year to cause “significant respiratory-related health consequences that are estimated to cost up to $20 billion per year in the United States by 2028.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bessemer (population 25,100) might be expected to welcome a $14.5 billion economic investment with open arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a steel boomtown and manufacturer of Pullman railroad cars, the self-described “Marvel City” lost its economic moorings with the gradual decline of the domestic steel industry. Today, much of downtown Bessemer remains boarded up. The majority-Black city’s poverty rate of 31 percent was three times that of the nation as a whole in 2024, according to the most recent data available, the same year that the state took over the city’s failing public school system to address its academic and financial woes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early last year, TPA Group, an Atlanta-based real estate development firm, convened a secret meeting with several state and local officials in a conference room of the Bessemer Public Library. Everyone in attendance was required to sign a nondisclosure agreement that would remain in force until public zoning hearings took place months later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to three attendees, TPA unveiled a slide presentation of what it called Project Marvel. The firm, which declined repeated requests to be interviewed for this story, had already built at least one data center in Georgia, and a second Georgia facility was in the works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm was now setting its sights on 675 woodland acres about five miles from Bessemer, in an unincorporated area of Jefferson County. The land had previously been annexed by the city for a landfill project, but the project was scuttled by local opposition. The acreage had ample access to electrical power, as well as water from the Warrior River Water Authority, which pumps its water from the Black Warrior River.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The land’s Mississippi-based owner was willing to sell the 675 acres for what TPA said would be a 100-acre data center campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local officials said that TPA’s representatives at the meeting told them the data center would generate 990 construction jobs and 330 full-time jobs, and bring the Bessemer school district roughly $25 million in annual tax revenue. The officials said TPA also assured them that the project would not damage any wetlands or threaten any endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;City and county officials interviewed for this story said that they independently verified TPA’s economic claims. But such estimates pertaining to data centers have been disputed. In TPA’s home state, Georgia, a government audit last month found that the data centers there had produced less than one-third the jobs and economic value that had originally been projected. Mr. Hicks, the Ball State professor, said that the projected job gains from the Bessemer data center struck him as “wildly high” and estimated that such a center would more likely “have 40 workers on a shift, so perhaps 120 to 160 overall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, said Aaron Killings Jr., Bessemer’s city attorney, who attended the meeting, “it was just no question about whether we should proceed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But questions did arise from the area’s residents once they learned about the rezoning plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We tried talking to the mayor and other city officials,” said David Havron, an accountant whose property lies about 200 yards from the site. “They told us they had signed NDAs and couldn’t reveal anything.” Mr. Havron and other residents enlisted two Birmingham, Ala.-based groups, the Alabama Rivers Alliance and the Southern Environmental Law Center, to help them organize opposition to the data center. A third group, the Center for Biological Diversity, petitioned the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service to classify the Birmingham darter, a fish newly discovered in one of the land’s creeks, as an endangered species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Bessemer city officials remained confident that Project Marvel would be widely viewed as a winner for the community. “We can’t allow just a few people to impede the progress and the work that is going to take place here, because it’s going to have such an incredible impact,” said Michael Turner, the superintendent of Bessemer’s public school system, which stands to reap millions in tax revenue from the data center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A rude awakening greeted Project Marvel at one of the first public hearings in June. The audience chairs were filled with residents wearing red T-shirts to indicate their opposition to the data center. Representatives of the Birmingham environmental groups were also present. “The city and TPA did not anticipate this amount of resistance,” Mr. Killings said. “We just got caught off guard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The residents who were interviewed for this story said Project Marvel’s proponents seemed dismissive of their concerns, including what they see as a threat to the area’s wildlife. During one hearing in June, a TPA representative, Brad Kaaber, said, “There are no bald eagles out there,” which prompted Chester W. Porter, a Bessemer City Council member and a data center supporter, to suggest that all claims of protected or exotic species on the acreage amounted to hyperbole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So Bigfoot is not out there, correct?” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unamused, Mr. Havron, who had come to the meeting prepared to raise environmental concerns, stepped up to the public microphone and held up a photograph of a bald eagle in one of his pine trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who favored the data center maintained that many of the concerns expressed by opponents lacked a factual foundation. Jefferson Traywick, the Jefferson County economic development adviser, acknowledged that some of the concerns were valid. “There are worries about excessive noise and light that I would consider legitimate,” he said in an interview. “But then you get into people telling me that A.I. is the mark of the devil, or that it’s going to create more storms over Birmingham, or that it’s going to emit brain cancer-causing pollutants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Traywick was referring in part to a 70-year-old Bessemer woman who challenged the City Council at one of the meetings, saying, “You can’t say it won’t cause cancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Nov. 18, the Bessemer City Council voted, 5 to 2, to rezone the land for a data center. But by then there was another roadblock. It turned out that a highway extension that had been in the works for decades would be routed through the same acreage where the data center would be built. TPA, unaware that the land was already spoken for, announced this month that it would buy an adjacent 900 acres of land so that the two endeavors could coexist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, moving the data center will mean a new zoning application, which will also mean a second round of noisy hearings. “There’s going to be a lot more public disclosure in this second phase,” Mr. Killings, the city attorney, said in an interview. “We know we’re not going to make everybody happy. But this time around, we’re going to put it all out there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Porter, the City Council’s most vocal defender of the data center, said that he hoped for less hand-wringing from his Bessemer neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I mean, we’re in the 21st century,” he said. “A.I. is here.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-ai.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:02:20 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>