<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:24:41 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Read the Texts Between Trump and Norway’s Prime Minister About Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-norway-prime-minister-texts-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-news-trump-norway-text-messages-whkl/19trump-news-trump-norway-text-messages-whkl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a text message over the weekend, President Trump told Jonas Gahr Store, Norway’s prime minister, that since being denied the Nobel Peace Prize, he no longer felt obliged to “think purely of Peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Store had contacted Mr. Trump to discuss global security, signing his message “Alex and Jonas,” a reference to the Finnish president, Alexander Stubb. The Norwegian prime minister’s office provided the full exchange to The New York Times. Read it below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text message from Mr. Store to Mr. Trump on Sunday, Jan. 18, 3:48 p.m.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Mr President, dear Donald – on the contact across the Atlantic – on Greenland, Gaza, Ukraine – and your tariff announcement yesterday. You know our position on these issues. But we believe we all should work to take this down and de-escalate – so much is happening around us where we need to stand together. We are proposing a call with you later today – with both of us or separately – give us a hint of what you prefer! Best – Alex and Jonas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text message from Mr. Trump to Mr. Store on Sunday, Jan. 18, at 4:15 p.m.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Jonas: Considering your Country decided not to give me the Nobel Peace Prize for having stopped 8 Wars PLUS, I no longer feel an obligation to think purely of Peace, although it will always be predominant, but can now think about what is good and proper for the United States of America. Denmark cannot protect that land from Russia or China, and why do they have a ‘right of ownership’ anyway? There are no written documents, it’s only that a boat landed there hundreds of years ago, but we had boats landing there, also. I have done more for NATO than any other person since its founding, and now, NATO should do something for the United States. The World is not secure unless we have Complete and Total Control of Greenland. Thank you! President DJT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the full article about the leaders’ exchange here.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-norway-prime-minister-texts-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:07:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Protest at Minnesota Church Service Adds to Tensions Over ICE Tactics</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/minnesota-church-protest-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-minnesota-ice-1-qpfl/19nat-minnesota-ice-1-qpfl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protesters interrupted a Sunday church service in St. Paul, Minn., over a pastor’s apparent work as an Immigration and Customs Enforcement official, escalating tensions between Minnesota residents and the Trump administration after an immigration agent shot and killed a woman in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos posted on social media show protesters chanting at the Cities Church — including calls for “ICE out” — and bringing the service to a halt. Congregants are seen moving to leave the church as the chants continue and worship music begins to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of people across Minnesota continued throughout the holiday weekend to protest the surge of immigration agents to their state, at rallies and marches and at annual celebrations honoring the life and legacy of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We need to show up for our community and neighbors, because no one is coming to save us,” said Vivian Stroh, 38, who joined a caravan of cars driving to an event at Saint Paul College. “We will keep each other safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the event, hosted by Black Lives Matter Minnesota and other local organizations, cheers went up when the incident at Cities Church was mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church protest over the weekend was organized by Nekima Levy Armstrong, a civil rights lawyer. She said she wanted to draw attention to a church leader, David Easterwood, who also appears to be the acting director of ICE’s field office for enforcement and removal operations in St. Paul, and who is named in a lawsuit challenging aggressive enforcement tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church, Mr. Easterwood and Jonathan Parnell, the lead pastor leading service on Sunday, did not immediately respond to calls or requests for comment. It was unclear whether Mr. Easterwood was present in the church during the protest on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department said it was investigating the event, with officials pointing to a 1994 law that bars using or threatening force and physical obstruction to interfere or intimidate someone worshiping at a religious institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attorney General Pam Bondi, who said she spoke with a pastor at the church late Sunday, said “attacks against law enforcement and the intimidation of Christians are being met with the full force of federal law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has moved to aggressively investigate and curb protests against immigration enforcement in Minnesota. Anger flared in the Minneapolis-St. Paul area this month after Jonathan Ross, an immigration agent, shot and killed Renee Good, a Minneapolis woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been clashes between federal agents and protesters, though a judge recently imposed restrictions on the agents’ actions. And the federal authorities have begun criminal investigations into Gov. Tim Walz and Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis, both Democrats who have been sharply critical of the immigration enforcement surge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement acknowledging Monday’s holiday, Mr. Walz invoked the civil rights icon’s emphasis on nonviolent protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today serves as a stark reminder of the legacy of Dr. King and his contributions to social justice, nonviolence, and freedom,” he said. “As we grapple today with unjust actions of the federal government, we are guided by Dr. King’s teachings of resilience and peaceful protest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keith Ellison, the Minnesota attorney general, joined protesters outside the Bishop Henry Whipple Federal Building, just outside Minneapolis, on Monday,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody is doing a use-of-force death investigation for Renee Good at this moment,” Mr. Ellison, a Democrat, said in an interview. “And in this country, no matter what your subjective opinion might be, everyone’s death should be investigated when they lose their life at the hands of the state.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the unrest in the Twin Cities prompted at least two St. Paul hotels to stop accepting bookings and close down on Sunday, citing “elevated safety and security concerns.” Guests were offered refunds or help in obtaining accommodations at other hotels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Levy Armstrong, the church protest organizer, said that in the lawsuit filed earlier this month against ICE’s tactics, she saw that Mr. Easterwood was named as a defendant for overseeing “a racial profiling campaign of massive scale and with devastating consequences,” and connected him with the church. She compared Mr. Easterwood’s appearance in an October news conference alongside Homeland Security Secretary Kristi Noem with a sermon he delivered at the church that was posted to YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Levy Armstrong said she circulated her plan for interrupting the service on social media as a way to raise awareness among the congregation of Mr. Easterwood’s involvement in the immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To have someone in the role of a pastor also being in that role as an overseer is unconscionable,” she said. She said that Jesus “called out religious leaders for their hypocrisy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s part of our duty as Christians,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Parnell, speaking to the former CNN anchor Don Lemon during the Sunday protest, said it was “shameful to interrupt a public gathering of Christians in worship.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Ezell, president of the North American Mission Board of the Southern Baptist Convention, to which the church belongs, said in a statement that “what occurred was not protest; it was lawless harassment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elsewhere in the city, mourners on Monday were continuing to mark Ms. Good’s death, adding signs and flowers to heaps of flags and trinkets that were covered in ice overnight at the intersection near where she was shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rick Kelley, 47, said he traveled to Minneapolis from Cleveland on Sunday to join the protests, and made the memorial his first stop Monday morning. It felt meaningful, he said, particularly given the celebrations of Dr. King’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We read about struggles in the past, but clearly, struggles are ongoing in many ways, and so is organizing,” Mr. Kelley said, warming his hands by a small fire crackling near the memorial. “It seems resonant, especially today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sonia A. Rao and Mitch Smith contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/minnesota-church-protest-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:57:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Wintry Weather Leads to 100-Vehicle Pileup on Interstate in Michigan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/michigan-interstate-traffic-pileup.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19xp-pileup/19xp-pileup-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With conditions treacherous on a highway in Michigan on Monday after a blast of lake-effect snow, more than 100 vehicles slipped and crashed into one another in a chain-reaction pileup, with some sliding off the interstate entirely, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous injuries were reported, but no deaths, according to the Michigan State Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pileup, set off around 10:20 a.m., forced the closure of Interstate 196 in both directions between Hudsonville and Zeeland, just southwest of Grand Rapids and about 10 miles east of Lake Michigan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highway reopened about 6 p.m., after emergency crews worked for nearly eight hours to clear the vehicles, including about three dozen semitrailer trucks that had jackknifed, said Shanon Banner, the communications director for the Michigan State Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buses from nearby cities and area schools were taking stranded motorists from the scene to Hudsonville High School. Some were arranging to be picked up once at the school, according to the Ottawa County Sheriff’s Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were reports of poor visibility and blowing snow on Interstate 196, whipped up by a winter storm system moving across the country over the holiday weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Weather Service in Grand Rapids, Mich., said on Monday afternoon that “heavy lake-effect and lake-enhanced snow will persist downwind of the Great Lakes and produce some whiteout conditions that could cause difficult travel conditions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, a winter storm delivered a chilly blast to the Southeast, bringing an unusual but short-lived dose of snow as far south as Florida and Georgia before traveling up the East Coast and into New England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forecasters warned Monday that freezing temperatures would linger in the eastern half of the country, with freeze warnings in effect for portions of southern Georgia and northern Florida into Tuesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said that arctic air moving over the Great Lakes would lead to another round of heavy lake-effect snow for the area over the next few days. Accumulations of up to four inches were expected overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/michigan-interstate-traffic-pileup.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:38:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Indiana Judge and His Wife Are Shot at Their Suburban Home</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/indiana-judge-and-wife-shot.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/us/19nat-judge-shot-1/19nat-judge-shot-1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Indiana judge and his wife were shot at their home on Sunday, prompting concerns for the safety of the state’s judiciary after recent increases in threats and violence against public officials nationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police in Lafayette, Ind., said on Monday that they were investigating the shootings of the judge, Steven P. Meyer of Tippecanoe County Superior Court, and his wife, Kimberly Meyer. Both were in stable condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Meyer, 66, recently announced plans to retire at the end of the year. In 12 years on the bench, he has presided over a number of high-profile cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shootings prompted a statement from Loretta H. Rush, the chief justice of the Indiana Supreme Court, urging judges to remain vigilant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I worry about the safety of all our judges,” Chief Justice Rush wrote. “As you work to peacefully resolve more than one million cases a year, you must not only feel safe, you must also be safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public servants have become increasingly worried about their personal safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year alone, the Pennsylvania governor’s residence was set on fire while Gov. Josh Shapiro, a Democrat, and his family were asleep inside; the Republican Party’s headquarters in New Mexico were firebombed; and a Democratic state representative in Minnesota, Melissa Hortman, and her husband were assassinated in their home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lafayette Police Department released few details about the shootings of the Meyers. The police said that they were called to the couple’s home at about 2 p.m. on Sunday. They found that Judge Meyer had been shot in the arm, and that Ms. Meyer had sustained an injury to her hip, the police said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a police dispatch from Sunday, a caller had notified the police that a man had come to the couple’s door, claimed he had found their dog, and then shot through the door before fleeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police recovered shell casings at the scene, in a residential neighborhood about 10 minutes from Purdue University’s campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several cases overseen by Judge Meyer, who has run for office as a Democrat and previously served on the Lafayette City Council, had been the subject of news reports in the state. In July, for example, he sentenced a father to 24 years in prison for leaving a gun unattended in his apartment; his 5-year-old son had found the gun and fatally shot his 1-year-old brother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement on Monday, Ms. Meyer thanked the Police Department, medical personnel and the community for their support.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/indiana-judge-and-wife-shot.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:38:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Alabama Pastor Credits Trump for Putting ‘Christ’ Back in Christmas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/pastor-travis-johnson-evangelicalism-alabama.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00nat-50states-alabama-lckp/00nat-50states-alabama-lckp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pastor Travis Johnson sees signs everywhere that the country is better off today than it was when President Trump took office a year ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take, for example, the signs at car dealerships and banks around his home city, Mobile, Ala., in December urging people to “Put the CHRIST back in Christmas.” Only a few years ago, Mr. Johnson said, secular businesses might have shied away from that message even here in deep-red Alabama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Freedom is back in style,” he said over lunch with his wife and son at a favorite oyster house in Mobile. “Christmas is Christmas.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Johnson leads Pathway Church, a growing evangelical congregation where most people take for granted that Mr. Trump is on their side. Many conservative Christians, especially in states like Alabama, feel that their faith is finally ascendant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The church uses the motto “We exist for God and our city.” But these days, the pastor is often traveling beyond his own city. In 2025, he prayed in the Oval Office, sang hymns in the Roosevelt Room, attended an Easter dinner with Mr. Trump in the Blue Room, and posed in the Rose Garden after the president signed an executive order establishing a commission on religious liberty. On New Year’s Eve, he was in Palm Beach, Fla., with a group of pastors, reassuring the prime minister of Israel that evangelicals stand with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Johnson’s expanded church and social circle reflect how Mr. Trump has radically reshaped the contours of the American evangelical elite. With the help of the televangelist Paula White-Cain, his longtime personal pastor, Mr. Trump has courted a new class of pastors and evangelists like Mr. Johnson, who support him without question. Mr. Trump promised them direct access to the White House, and he has delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In pulpits around the country, soft-edged conservatism is out, replaced by a punchier style advanced by Trump associates like Charlie Kirk, who urged pastors to embrace being perceived as offensive in defense of truth, and dismissed the notion of the separation of church and state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Johnson’s time at Pathway Church in Mobile has overlapped almost exactly with the Trump era. Since arriving from Florida in October 2016, he has leaned into the new political moment, joining Evangelicals for Trump and forging connections with other pastors around the country who supported the new president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His work continued locally, too. In June 2023, Mr. Johnson was invited to deliver a prayer to open a City Council meeting where the agenda included discussion of a drag show in a public park. He delivered a six-minute prayer asking God to protect children “from ideologies that have zeroed in on them at their youngest and most innocent ages,” drawing criticism from groups alarmed by the eroding wall between church and state. At the same time, he began a sermon series titled “Awake, Not Woke” in which he lambasted the city’s Pride Month celebrations. In August, under pressure from a wider coalition of pastors, the city’s mayor discontinued the city’s L.G.B.T.Q. liaison positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Mr. Johnson refers to the backlash to his City Council prayer as a “cancellation,” the Trump era has been good for his career. Pathway now has five locations, three in the Mobile area, one in Mississippi and one in Cambodia, where Mr. Johnson has been active in a Christian humanitarian organization since the early 2000s. His first book, “[Un]Embarrassed of Jesus” will be published by a Christian publisher in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pastor sees it as a responsibility to be active on social media — X, TikTok, Instagram, Facebook, YouTube, BeReal — and reaches quickly for his phone to share photos and videos of his trips in Washington and overseas. In one recent photo, he and other pastors gaze at the ceiling of the Lincoln Bedroom as Mr. Trump points out a chandelier awkwardly connected to an air vent. The president planned to fix it, Mr. Johnson said, comparing him favorably to a general contractor. He guessed that the president knows his name, though he wasn’t sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country has come a long way since 2015, as Mr. Johnson sees it. He recalled that summer, when the White House facade was illuminated in rainbow-colored lights to celebrate the Supreme Court ruling that legalized same-sex marriage. It remains a touchstone moment for many social conservatives, who speak about it as a kind of desecration of a national monument, proof in lights that their values no longer reigned at the highest levels of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Suddenly everything that was good is now bad, and things that are bad are good,” Mr. Johnson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked if he had ever said anything negative publicly about Mr. Trump, Mr. Johnson paused for several seconds. “I doubt it,” he concluded. After reflecting more, he offered one potential area for improvement: The evangelist Franklin Graham, he said, is working to get the president to stop cursing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Sunday before Christmas at Pathway, trees and wreaths twinkled in the lobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first service that morning, Mr. Johnson baptized two people, celebrating the chance to “take people public with their faith.” There was a rock-tinged version of “Hark, the Herald Angels Sing” and a recap of the church’s involvement in a baseball game for young people with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it was time to preach. The pastor opened with a story about a troublesome tree he had cut down on his property, only to have small shoots grow out of the leveled stump. The lesson was that hope is never lost, that God always has a plan, that faith rewards. “When you’re down to nothing,” Mr. Johnson said, “God is up to something.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many church members seemed to have only a hazy sense of Mr. Johnson’s activities in Washington. For Keeli Wall, it was surreal to think about her pastor spending time at the White House. Ms. Wall, a nurse, started attending Pathway a few years ago, after her son began participating in a youth group. It’s a positive sign that a “man of God” like Mr. Johnson has influence in Washington, she said. “I don’t believe religion and government should be separate.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/pastor-travis-johnson-evangelicalism-alabama.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:40:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Alaska Town Is Now Key to Trump’s Global Ambitions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk/00nat-50states-alaska-qmfk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the unimaginative eye, the view of Nome, Alaska, from Joy Baker’s well-heated S.U.V. looked like a whole lot of nothing: The early winter sun was sliding below the horizon barely four hours after it had risen, the gray water of the inner harbor had already frozen over, and the only stirring came from a flock of hearty seabirds diving for dinner just off shore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Baker has a vision that goes well beyond the subarctic calm: “More traffic, more services, more jobs. More of everything for people here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Baker is director of the Port of Nome and thus the local overseer for a $548-million-and-counting plan to expand the port, in one of America’s most remote cities on the Bering Sea. Nome is a quiet, frozen frontier town much of the year, known mostly for the Iditarod sled race, and reachable only by air except for a few summer months when the water thaws enough to allow boats through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, however, Nome’s existing dock will be turned into the country’s first deepwater Arctic port, a critical hub in President Trump’s ambitions to make the United States master of the far north and compete with other world powers for untapped natural resources and shipping corridors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president didn’t originate the decade-old plan to expand Nome’s existing port, but his Arctic ambitions, including his efforts to take over Greenland, are longstanding and widely known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s aspirations for Nome were made clear near the end of his first term, when Congress authorized the port expansion with administration support. Last year, the project moved from paper to procurement as the Army Corps of Engineers awarded a $399.4 million construction contract for the first phase amid an administration-wide push to treat the Arctic and critical minerals as strategic priorities. This summer, crews will start demolishing the existing port.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expansion should be complete, and Nome potentially remade, by 2033.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not actually like the current administration is trying to open the Arctic —Mother Nature did that,” said Ms. Baker, a gruff South Texan who moved to Alaska in 1987 and scoffs at ever returning to what Alaskans call, not always lovingly, the Lower 48. “I just see the current administration as just capitalizing in a way that will ensure our country is more self-sufficient. That can’t be a bad thing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether the port expansion will be good for Nome is a big question for many of the town’s 3,700 year-round residents and an itinerant population of contractors, health workers and dog mushing fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Port expansion, and the economic growth that follows, is expected to double or even triple the population, and some in Nome worry about what could happen without a solid strategy for long-term economic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is something of a boom-and-bust town,” said Jim West Jr., a longtime civic leader whose eclectic portfolio of businesses includes a gravel company, the local taxi service and the 125-year-old Board of Trade Saloon. “We need to make sure this isn’t just another economic cycle but something with lasting benefits for our children and grandchildren.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nome’s boom began at the turn of the 20th century when prospectors immortalized as the Three Lucky Swedes found gold in nearby Anvil Creek. Their discovery briefly turned Nome into Alaska’s largest city, with more than 20,000 residents. A second kind of gold rush came in 2011, prompted by surging gold prices and consisting largely of offshore dredging, but ebbed almost as quickly as it began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the flat, treeless winter tundra around Nome is dotted with abandoned mining rigs, and the city is stuck in economic stagnation. Little is produced this close to the Arctic Circle, and everything must arrive either by plane or seasonal barge. Prices, in turn, would shock Lower 48 shoppers. On a recent visit, a gallon of gas cost $6.50, a gallon of milk went for $6.99 and one browning honeydew melon was priced at almost $12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to convince locals to stay and even harder to woo new year-round residents. The hospital and most construction companies bring in temporary workers and either build their own housing or provide housing subsidies that reduce supply and raise costs for year-round residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Civic leaders like Ms. Baker, a former Nome harbor master who came out of retirement to manage the expansion, believe the project will lead to financial sustainability. But that presumes city officials can figure out how to pay for it all. Under its deal with the state and federal governments, Nome must cover 10 percent of port construction costs and 100 percent of its own port-related infrastructure needs, such as roads, streetlights and sewer lines. The city does not know how much that will cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond Nome City Hall, optimism about the port’s effect is the cautious sort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teriscovkya Smith, the principal at Nome-Beltz Middle High School, estimated that 80 percent of her students won’t go to college and hoped the expansion could bring vocational internships and quality entry-level jobs. So far, however, she hasn’t heard from anyone involved in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People who stay build careers, they buy houses, they pay property taxes,” said Ms. Smith, who fished in Alaska for 10 years before becoming a teacher. “There’s a real risk that we just waste an amazing opportunity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, Nome voters agreed to increase the local sales tax to 6 percent to avoid cuts to services such as pothole repair as well as hours at the town recreation center. The Nome school district balanced its budget last year by taking money from a fund set aside for teacher housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing money go into the port when other services face cuts can rankle. “I see the point of this thing for some other people — for the military maybe, for big shipping companies, for cruise lines,” said Keith Reddaway, co-owner of Builders Industrial Supply, a hardware store a block from the port. “But I’m not sure I see the point for Nome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tribal members also worry about what this all could mean for the subsistence lifestyle that dominates their 15 Alaska villages of the Bering Strait region. Around Nome, 86 percent of the population identifies as Indigenous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The port expansion and a new nearby graphite mine, fast-tracked by Mr. Trump, could bring more noise, air and water pollution, damage fishing and affect migratory birds and whales. They’re scared that they will be forced to abandon their traditional homes and seasonal schedules. And they worry Nome, always a little gritty around the edges, will revert to its rougher early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Outsiders bring in drugs,” said Shirley Martin, a member of the Yup’ik nation, whose village is across the Norton Sound. “People from the villages come through all the time to see family, go to the doctor, mail packages, just eat out. Will this still be a place where we feel comfortable?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time Nome has played a part in American security. During the Cold War, the U.S. military kept Air Force bases connected in case of a Soviet attack with an antenna installation atop nearby Anvil Mountain. Today, locals call the abandoned array “Nomehenge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, with sea ice thawing and the United States, Russia and China all eyeing Arctic shipping lanes and natural resources, Nome has emerged again as one of the most strategically important places in the Northern Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expanded port won’t be a military base, but Nome is an hour’s flight from Russia. Deepening the port from 22 feet to 40 feet will allow every type of U.S. military vessel except aircraft carriers to dock in Nome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a small-town police chief, and I’ve got intelligence officers from the Navy, the Coast Guard, the Air Force coming in here to sit with me,” said William Crockett, Nome’s retiring police chief. “Something big is coming.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/nome-alaska-arctic-port-trump-ambitions.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:41:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Yosemite, Rangers Are Scarce and Visitors Have Gone Wild</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/yosemite-national-park-california-staffing-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-california-promo-jltc/00nat-50states-california-promo-jltc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, visitors to Yosemite National Park have been greeted by green- and khaki-clad rangers, who collect fees and guard the park’s entrance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on a chilly morning in December, there were no rangers at the park gates. Tourists descended into the majestic wilderness for free, confused by their apparent good fortune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, ranger sightings were too rare last year, according to park regulars and advocates. Visitors were far less supervised than they normally were, which had led to the wrong kind of wildness — littering, cliff jumping, drone-flying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Yosemite under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, Mr. Trump has upended the agency that oversees Yosemite, the National Park Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has presided over a 25 percent drop in permanent staff across the park service, through a combination of Department of Government Efficiency layoffs, as well as buyouts and retirements, according to the National Parks Conservation Association, a nonprofit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has overhauled fee structures and reservation systems. It has ended free entry on Juneteenth and Martin Luther King’s Birthday, while granting free park admission on Mr. Trump’s birthday, which coincides with Flag Day. And this year, his face is on the annual park pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Department of the Interior, which administers the National Park Service, declined to comment on staffing numbers or operations at Yosemite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yosemite National Park continues to operate safely and serve millions of visitors each year,” the agency said in a statement, adding, “Interpretive offerings may vary throughout the year, but the park continues to provide a wide range of educational, recreational and stewardship opportunities for visitors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But according to interviews with park employees and environmentalists, the cuts at Yosemite, one of the country’s most visited national parks, have meant there aren’t always enough rangers to staff entrance booths or educate visitors on caring for the park. Amid the shortage, scientists working in the parks have cleaned the public toilets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s really disheartening to see the direction we’re going,” said Mark Ruggiero, a retired Yosemite ranger who still does part-time work in the park. “It’s trying times. Nobody is really sure what’s going to happen next.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, tourists have been coming to Yosemite in droves, with 2025 becoming one of its busiest summers in recent years. October was unusually packed because the park was left open and free during the federal government shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elisabeth Barton, a co-owner of a company that offers guided tours of Yosemite’s attractions, said her business had benefited from the crowds. But she has also noticed more visitors driving the wrong way down one-way roads, parking on sensitive meadows and BASE jumping off cliffs, which is not allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re seeing the park really struggling to support the number of visitors that are coming in,” said Ms. Barton, 46. “I struggle to see the long game here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the vistas of Yosemite, with alpine lakes and meadows bathed in golden light, that helped inspire the creation of the entire national park system. President Abraham Lincoln in 1864 made the Yosemite Valley federally protected land designated for public use. That act paved the way for the eventual creation of the national park system, and Yosemite became the country’s third national park in 1890.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The park, the size of Rhode Island, is home to Half Dome and El Capitan, perhaps the most iconic rock faces in the country. It also has one of the tallest waterfalls in the United States, where, on that recent morning, a rainbow was visible at the base as it crashed into granite boulders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a walk around the park in December, Yosemite seemed the same as it had for decades. A father from Southern California was waiting at sunset for his son to propose to his girlfriend, so he could surprise them after. A tourist from the Czech Republic visiting several national parks marveled at how one country could contain so much beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grace Shiyatta said she was passing through a pine forest to meet her friends for a picnic to celebrate her 60th birthday. In their 20s, she and her friends had visited Yosemite every year, renting a big house to cross-country ski. It was a natural choice to return for her big birthday celebration, said Ms. Shiyatta, who lives in Sacramento.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What would I rather do than hang out in Yosemite?” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she and other tourists also said they had been puzzled that the park hadn’t collected their entrance fees. And a climber said that he had just scaled Half Dome without the required permit, which is intended to prevent deaths and injuries on the exposed rock face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Barton and her co-owner, Bryant Burnette, who have been giving private tours of the park for years, think visitors have become particularly unruly because there haven’t been enough staff members around to teach them the importance of caring for the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No wonder people are throwing trash and flying drones,” said Mr. Burnette, 36, who, as he walked, picked up tissues and wrappers that had been discarded on the valley floor. “I can’t be mad at them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Yosemite was home to some of the most public displays of federal employee anger toward the Trump administration. In February, shortly after an abrupt firing of 1,000 park service employees, a group of frustrated staffers hung a distress flag off El Capitan, which still rises more than 3,000 feet above the base of Yosemite Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Park supporters fear the long-term impact, especially with the loss of employees who plan for Yosemite’s preservation, including scientists who study endangered species or wildfire mitigation, and infrastructure experts who plan to move buildings out of flood plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, employees are keeping the park running day to day, but that isn’t enough — and it can’t last forever, said Don Neubacher, who was superintendent of Yosemite from 2010 to 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not like you’re talking about some city park,” he said. “You’re talking about nature’s greatest gifts — it’s a dire time.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/yosemite-national-park-california-staffing-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:41:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>When Trump Took a Whack at the C.D.C., Atlanta Lost Something, Too</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cdc-atlanta-trump-cuts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-georgia-fbcl/00nat-50states-georgia-fbcl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, Atlanta is a city full of public servants who no longer serve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of them had held jobs at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. But last year, the Trump administration slashed the agency in waves of firings. Public health programs were shrunk or shuttered. Top medical experts have resigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasoned epidemiologists and other staff members are working in yoga studios, walking neighbors’ dogs and job hunting — although cuts to other government agencies and cutbacks at health-related nonprofits have made the job hunt difficult for many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jennifer McQuiston, 54, thought she had a few more years of working at the C.D.C., fighting some of the world’s most dangerous health threats at the National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases. But she took early retirement, concerned that the agency had strayed too far from its commitment to science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days Dr. McQuiston, who has a veterinary degree, is working at an animal shelter and spending time riding her horse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was my calling,” she said. “I don’t mourn the loss at this moment, because I don’t believe the agency is the same agency I worked in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some ways, the C.D.C. is still trundling along. Government employees still come and go from the agency’s main campus near Emory University. And to the C.D.C.’s detractors, the Trump administration is simply forcing much-needed change to an agency that lost trust during the Covid pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The C.D.C. was broken for a long time,” Andrew Nixon, a spokesman with the Department of Health and Human Services, said in a statement. Reform was needed, he said, to combat a “culture of groupthink and mission creep” at the agency that had undermined public confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But civic leaders, scientists and public health advocates are increasingly worried about stories like Dr. McQuiston’s — and their effect not only on the C.D.C., but also on Atlanta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the decades, the disease-fighting work of the C.D.C. has helped define the Southern city’s sense of moral purpose, alongside its rich civil rights legacy. It has helped Atlanta realize its ambitions to be a city with global impact, alongside its famously busy international airport. The C.D.C. is also at the center of a regional life sciences sector that employs nearly 200,000 people and generates billions of dollars in economic activity yearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some fear that the C.D.C. is on “life support,” as three former agency leaders declared in November, no longer trusted by the broader medical community and no longer able to attract some of the brightest minds in the life sciences to Atlanta. An Axios/Ipsos poll in October found that 62 percent of Americans trust health information from the C.D.C., down from 88 percent in March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’ve had a lot of different kinds of institutions benefit from the focus on public heath,” said Doug Shipman, the former president of the Atlanta City Council. “Does that now stall? To me, that’s the fundamental question.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in Atlanta in 1946 as the Communicable Disease Center, the agency grew out of the fight to keep U.S. troops at Southern military bases safe from malaria. It would eventually expand its remit to fight all communicable diseases, as well as other health risks like smoking, gun violence prevention and bioterror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atlanta would soon become home to other major institutions with a health focus — the Carter Center, the Task Force for Global Health, the American Cancer Society and CARE, the global nonprofit that seeks to eradicate poverty and expand health services in some of the poorest parts of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, the earnest C.D.C. employee became a kind of Atlanta archetype, alongside aspiring rappers and C-suite strivers. The disease fighters have lent their own flavors — civic-mindedness, scientific rigor — to the metropolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the agency was buffeted by the Covid-19 pandemic and public distrust over its handling of the crisis. After an external review pointed out that its response had been sluggish and muddled, even its leadership acknowledged that it needed to be reformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Trump’s second inauguration, the changes to the agency have been chaotic. Agency officials did not respond to a request for details about the extent of the staff reductions. But an article in November in the medical journal The Lancet by Debra Houry, Daniel Jernigan and Demetre Daskalakis — former C.D.C. leaders who resigned in protest over Health Secretary Robert F. Kennedy Jr.’s vision for the agency — states that the number of staff members had been reduced to fewer than 10,000 employees in October from roughly 13,500 employees at the beginning of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writers argued that the cuts had left the nation unprepared to handle viruses like Zika and mpox, unable to properly keep track of diseases like Creutzfeldt-Jakob and chronic wasting disease, and understaffed in sectors that keep tabs on basic national health data. The authors said the C.D.C.’s malaria staff in Africa had been eliminated, “undermining decades of progress.” Other cuts, they wrote, threatened to “reverse decades of progress in ending the H.I.V. epidemic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Elizabeth Soda, a Stanford-trained physician and epidemiologist, left the C.D.C. in September after working there for a decade. Among other things, Dr. Soda, an infectious disease specialist, helped to develop health screening for immigrants and refugees entering the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She knew little about Atlanta when she arrived, but she and her husband settled in and started their family. She thought she had found her dream job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She watched the Trump administration with concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She had tried to give the new secretary of Health and Human Services, Mr. Kennedy, a chance, but was sorely disappointed. “He lacks expertise, he believes damaging theories about well-proven science — and this guy’s in charge of our health?” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She had also begun to feel unsafe. In August, a gunman fired dozens of rounds at the C.D.C. headquarters. Dr. Soda had left the campus a half-hour earlier, but her office was four doors down from one of the holes a bullet left in a window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After her husband, also a scientist, won an appointment in Italy, they moved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeling that she abandoned the agency gnaws at her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We go through massive, real guilt moments,” Dr. Soda, 47, said in a telephone interview late last year. “That’s one of the hardest things being here, to be honest, is knowing what we’ve left behind, who we’ve left behind — family, friends, our country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a modicum of hope that Atlanta will help steer the C.D.C. — or whatever government entity follows in its wake — back on a more trustworthy path. Some of that optimism is rooted in the belief that public health officials know how to solve problems in the midst of chaos. Some of it is rooted in the vast public health expertise that still resides in Atlanta’s nonprofits and educational institutions, including Emory, Georgia Tech, Georgia State and the Morehouse School of Medicine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These institutions allow Atlanta’s Chamber of Commerce to plausibly boast that the city is the “public health capital of the world.” Many of those groups have been absorbing as many former C.D.C. workers as they can. The hope is that they will continue to incubate the values of the old C.D.C. and lead a comeback in the public health sphere when and if Mr. Kennedy’s influence wanes, said Terry Pechacek, a former C.D.C. scientist and emeritus professor of public health at Georgia State University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The future rebound, which may be a generation away, will come out of that core,” Dr. Pechacek said. “The core is not dead.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cdc-atlanta-trump-cuts.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:41:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Idaho City Has New Refugees: White South Africans</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/twin-falls-idaho-afrikaners-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/00Nat-50states-Idaho-fgmj/00Nat-50states-Idaho-fgmj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, refugees have been part of the rhythm of Twin Falls, a small city in southern Idaho. Displaced from the world’s most troubled corners — places like Bosnia, the Democratic Republic of Congo and Myanmar — these new residents have worked to rebuild their lives, finding jobs in factories, singing in church choirs and loading up their carts in supermarkets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a story that is as old as the nation itself: A town prospers with the support of newcomers, who are grateful to be there. There have been some ugly tensions in the past, but refugees in Twin Falls have helped turn the area into a dairy industry juggernaut. They have rehabbed homes and filled classrooms. The town’s children play together in parks, schoolyards and sports fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No matter where you come from, there is opportunity to achieve the American dream in Twin Falls, clichéd as that may sound,” said Shawn Barigar, the city’s director of economic development. “The refugee population, tiny as it may be, is a component that is important to our prosperity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But refugee resettlement is now getting an overhaul, as part of the Trump administration’s upending of the immigration system. President Trump, who was elected in part because of his anti-immigration views, has said that refugees pose security risks, strain public coffers and undermine American values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On his first day in the White House, Mr. Trump suspended the U.S. refugee program. A few weeks later, his administration announced it would make an exception and admit just one group: Afrikaners, or white South Africans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, the administration established new targets for the refugee program, and said it would allow only 7,500 refugees for the coming year — the lowest number in the program’s history. (Former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. set the ceiling at 125,000 for 2024.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And an overwhelming majority of them, the administration said, would be Afrikaners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means Twin Falls, which had typically received 200 to 350 refugees a year, would be in for an adjustment. As it is, since May, a total of 37 refugees, all Afrikaners, have resettled in Twin Falls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for the city’s future?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idaho has for decades been a leader in resettling refugees, with a robust brigade of volunteers and employers in Boise and Twin Falls to welcome and integrate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the resettlement program, refugees face extensive vetting before being cleared to enter the United States, often waiting years abroad. On arrival, they are assisted by nonprofit contractors, such as the U.S. Committee for Refugees and Immigrants in Twin Falls, which secure temporary housing, enroll children in school and provide cash for initial expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just benevolence. Refugees are vital to businesses here in Idaho’s Magic Valley, which has emerged as an agribusiness powerhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economy around Twin Falls is anchored by the world’s biggest yogurt factory, Chobani. But there are also major companies like Clif Bar and outposts of global companies like Glanbia Nutritionals, a milk processor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And down the line is a vast network of dairy farms, cheese and whey producers, potato and beef plants and food-science labs, which Hamdi Ulukaya, Chobani’s founder, has called “the Silicon Valley of food innovation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The labor market is tight, with unemployment hovering around 3.5 percent. “We have a desperate shortage of people at all levels in this area,” said Daragh Maccabee, the chief executive of Idaho Milk Products, which, like many companies in the area, is in the midst of major expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The refugee program has been a source of motivated, qualified talent,” Mr. Maccabee said. “I fear the impact of losing that valuable source for the economy and the community.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning, Nijaz Heric, a safety supervisor at Idaho Milk, patrolled the high-tech dairy processing plant with a practiced eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1990s, Mr. Heric and his family were among the first Muslim Bosnians resettled in Twin Falls, fleeing war and ethnic cleansing. He had no money, no English, only the hope of starting over. His first job was making cheese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I tried to explain with my hands that I wanted a job,” he recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2000s, persecuted minority groups from Myanmar and Bhutan arrived, followed by people displaced by wars in Africa and the Middle East, often after languishing for years in refugee camps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low cost of living coupled with good wages enabled many refugees to vault into the middle class. Often, their children, raised in the United States, became college students and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not everything has gone smoothly. In 2016, during Mr. Trump’s first presidential campaign, Twin Falls found itself besieged. Far-right outlets, including Breitbart, seized and distorted a story about a sex abuse case involving teenagers. The outlets falsely claimed that a little girl had been gang raped at knife point by Syrian refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Police officials tried to debunk the reports, declaring that the crime was not gang rape and that the perpetrators were juveniles who were not Syrian and did not wield a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But outside militia groups descended on the town. Some people threatened city officials and demanded an end to refugee resettlement, asserting that “all refugees must be criminals,” recalled Matthew Hicks, the police chief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As hostility intensified, city officials formed civic groups to introduce refugees to residents. That helped ease the tension. And so did the passing of the news cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the tensions come from above. In December, Samuel Nzapalaha sat in the living room of his four-bedroom house, his family by his side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He bought that house for $385,000 two years ago, putting $50,000 down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was one marker of his success in Twin Falls after arriving in 2016 with his wife, Josephine Mirindi, and their five children. The family had fled armed conflict in the Democratic Republic of Congo. At first, Mr. Nzapalaha worked two jobs, at a cheese maker and the local refugee agency, while attending a local college. Within a year, the couple could afford their first house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nzapalaha now works as a case manager at an addiction recovery center. His wife works at Chobani labeling yogurt cups, earning $23 an hour. Their children are working or attending college or high school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their story, he said, stands in stark contrast to the president’s portrayal of refugees as ruining America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We work hard; we buy things; we are contributing,’’ Mr. Nzapalaha said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for opening the door to Afrikaners, he described them as “so-called refugees.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, Twin Falls received nine of the first 59 Afrikaners admitted in 2025 to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have been quiet, with neighbors shrugging their shoulders and saying they do not really know them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a middle-class subdivision, one Afrikaner couple stood in June on the lawn outside their home. The wife praised President Trump before her husband said they did not want to talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether more Afrikaners, beyond those who have already arrived, are resettling in Twin Falls is unclear. The political climate is tense, and many in Twin Falls were reluctant to talk, including those at nonprofit agencies that assist refugees and companies that depend on them for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Chobani, which has been a vocal champion of refugees, did not reply to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a handful of South Africans cannot meet the labor demands of these companies. A $500 million expansion of the Chobani plant, tied to its acquisition of La Colombe Coffee in 2023, is expected to come online in 2026. Idaho Milk Products plans to open an ice cream factory this year as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we don’t let refugees in, we’ll stagnate,” said Jim Jones, the former Republican attorney general of Idaho, who has publicly criticized the Trump administration’s refugee policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Refugees are in dairies, maintenance, everywhere,” said Mr. Jones, who was born and raised in the area. “They do hard work that locals think are beneath them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/twin-falls-idaho-afrikaners-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:41:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Columbia University’s Strained Peace: Fewer Protests and Sealed Gates</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/columbia-university-protests-culture-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-50states-NY-flqp/00nat-50states-NY-flqp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a frigid evening in December, hundreds of bundled up Columbia students gathered on the university’s main campus — not to shout political slogans, but to mingle at an annual holiday  celebration. The campus trees were lit up, the university gave out free hot chocolate, and a cappella groups sang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a sign of the times, the campus’s imposing iron gates, historically open to the public, were closed. The Low Library steps, a frequent site for student protests, were blocked off. Police cars and additional barricades ringed the area outside of the gates, to control any other demonstrations that might happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gates to Columbia’s main campus in Manhattan swung shut more than two years ago to control volatile protests over the war in Gaza. There was a days-long encampment, a building takeover and arrests by police. Now, entry is permitted only to those who hold Columbia identification and their approved guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closure does provide extra security for students and faculty, a benefit underscored after the mass shooting at Brown in December. But its main purpose has been to limit the potential for protests and unrest, including since the Trump administration has used the full force of his office to bend universities to his will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia was once known as America’s “activist Ivy,” in part because of its hands-off policy for demonstrations, a legacy of 1968 antiwar protests that led to an aggressive police response. The images from that time left an indelible mark not only on Columbia, but on New York’s protest culture more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the relative quiet at the university — despite its history of uprisings, even within a boisterous anti-Trump New York — is partly a measure of the White House’s success in taming unrest at Columbia and other universities around the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I feel like it’s very disheartening,” said Gabriela Ruiz, a freshman attending the tree lighting with her roommates. “I think protest has become a bad word. The concept of encampment has become a bad word.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the country, President Trump has used executive orders, civil rights investigations and the withdrawal of research funds to try to tamp down protests that he accused of antisemitism, and to reshape universities that he accused of being captured by leftist orthodoxy. Leadership, faculty power, diversity programs and the minutiae of grant proposals are all up for scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia was President Trump’s first high-profile university target, followed by Harvard, Brown, Northwestern and others. In July, Columbia settled with the Trump administration, paying $221 million to settle civil rights claims against the university for allegedly failing to protect students from antisemitic harassment. Harvard has not settled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some at Columbia, the new, quieter campus culture is a relief, especially for those who found the protests offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natan Rosenbaum, an Orthodox Jewish senior at Columbia, recalled how in December 2023, the annual lighting celebration was disrupted by a large group of pro-Palestinian protesters who held up signs that said “Joy is Canceled” and chanted slogans like “There’s no room for celebration, end Israeli occupation.” This year, a smaller group of protesters briefly interrupted the event, before moving to rally outside the Columbia gates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not saying I was in favor of withholding the funding, but yeah, I think things are entirely more pleasant now,” he said. “The protests were not a kind presence. And their rhetoric was many times very ugly.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other students and faculty members say the strained campus peace has cut unacceptably at Columbia’s identity and made the school an example of capitulation to government overreach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Political advocacy has just been tamped down to a remarkable degree,” said Michael Thaddeus, a mathematics professor and vice president of Columbia’s American Association of University Professors chapter. In the fall, he navigated the tighter rules on demonstrations while organizing an event for academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can try to spin it in a positive way by saying, well, the campus has calmed down and people can get back to doing their important work,” he said. “But my view is that protest and dissent are part of the essential work of a university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in 2025, several pro-Palestinian protests caught the attention of the new Trump administration. In January, a modern Israel history class was disrupted. In early March, there was a Barnard sit-in, with Mahmoud Khalil, then a little-known graduate student and Palestinian activist, acting as a negotiator between demonstrators and administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On March 7, the White House announced it was withholding $400 million in federal grants. The next day, Immigration and Customs Enforcement officers arrested Mr. Khalil in the lobby of his Columbia-owned apartment building and detained him for 104 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbia administrators did not mention him by name for months. To this day, Mr. Khalil said, Columbia has not reached out directly to him or offered support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Columbia is no longer an educational institution,” said Mr. Khalil, who is out of detention but still fighting deportation. “It has pretty much become an institution of oppression for the right wing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Columbia spokeswoman said that the university had been “in regular contact with Mr. Khalil through his lawyers since March” and had granted his family’s request to extend their housing lease for months because of their difficult circumstances. Mr. Khalil and seven other students are suing Columbia and the Trump administration over their treatment as pro-Palestinian activists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of its pledges to the Trump administration, Columbia gave arrest powers to some of its public safety officers, a major change at the university. Other new rules include: Demonstrations inside academic buildings are no longer allowed. Columbia’s unwieldy campus Senate, made up of mostly faculty and created in the aftermath of the 1968 protests to encourage democratic decision-making, has had its authority over disciplining student protesters taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Events must go through multiple layers of approval, which on a practical level, reduces their frequency. On some days, extra notice is required for security reasons. When there are protests, they often happen outside the campus, where fewer rules apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students have gotten the message that certain kinds of protesting could lead to serious consequences. But that doesn’t mean that they all agree with Columbia’s decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of simmering contempt, I’d say,” said Stella Dougherty, 21, a junior studying information science. “You get the sense that a lot of people wish they could say things or demonstrate in ways that they feel like they can’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others see the new rules as an acceptable compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were a university in crisis,” said Brian Cohen, the executive director of the campus Hillel chapter. “What we saw was the interruption of admissions tours, storming of academic buildings, assaulting public safety officers, disrupting classes, destroying property. That’s not activism in my book — it’s intimidation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last large pro-Palestinian demonstration happened in May, when dozens of masked protesters stormed into Columbia’s Butler Library to occupy its main reading room. Campus security prevented students from leaving without showing their identification. Eventually, the police were called in. Over 70 students were disciplined, the majority with multiyear suspensions, according to Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This academic year has been relatively quiet so far. Pro-Palestinian student activists, who say that even cultural celebrations are subject to the new restrictions, are regrouping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A pilot to reopen the campus was delayed by new security concerns, including worries about federal immigration police having access to campus, Claire Shipman, the acting university president, told students this fall. In one change, people who live nearby can now apply for campus access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We understand the desire to return to an open campus, and the university evaluates campus access protocols on an ongoing basis,” said Samantha Slater, a spokeswoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Khalil said he did not expect Columbia to open its gates anytime soon. He was denied permission to go to a November film screening at the university’s journalism school because of what Columbia said were security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The I.D. checks, he said, are “a sign that we are watching you.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/columbia-university-protests-culture-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:58:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Tennessee Dean Had ‘Zero Sympathy’ for Charlie Kirk. She Was Fired.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/middle-tennessee-state-university-dean-fired-charlie-kirk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-50states-tennessee-01-zbpj/00nat-50states-tennessee-01-zbpj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the conservative political activist Charlie Kirk was assassinated in September, Laura Sosh-Lightsy fired off a late-night post on Facebook: “Looks like ol’ Charlie spoke his fate into existence. Hate begets hate. ZERO sympathy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comment was harsh, and so was the pushback. Within hours, she was fired from her job as a dean at Middle Tennessee State University, about an hour southeast of Nashville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a stunning turnabout for Ms. Sosh-Lightsy, whose work responsibilities included overseeing conduct and often navigating free-speech questions within the university community. Should a student be punished for using a slur? Can someone be removed from class over derogatory language?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She now finds herself a central figure in a debate over appropriate sanctions for speech — and an example of how much the contours of the free-speech debate have changed in the last year under President Trump, especially in red states like Tennessee. Ms. Sosh-Lightsy is just one of scores of people across the country who have been fired, suspended or called to step aside for things they said about Mr. Kirk or his assassination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An online campaign, encouraged by some members of the Trump administration, other high-ranking lawmakers and prominent right-wing figures, tried to swiftly single out anyone who made disparaging, callous or celebratory comments after the assassination. Professors, health care workers, lawyers and journalists, restaurant workers and airline employees have all faced consequences for their statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For champions of Mr. Kirk’s far-right agenda, those comments seemed indicative of a liberal intolerance and orthodoxy that helped whip up the conditions for Mr. Kirk’s killing. But it was also a sign of how many conservatives had reversed course on their condemnation of what they call cancel culture and instead embarked on a sweeping campaign, especially in Republican-dominated places like Tennessee, to penalize opposing viewpoints and political expression they found to be offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You have the shock of murder combined with partisan division and vitriol, and that’s a potent combination,” said Will Creeley, the legal director at the nonpartisan Foundation for Individual Rights and Expression, which is now representing two other Tennesseans penalized for their online posts about Mr. Kirk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In those moments, people don’t give a damn about the First Amendment,” he added. “And they just want to see the people who don’t feel like they do shut up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sosh-Lightsy, 54, has also sued, charging a violation of her First Amendment rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her lawsuit, she argued that a Facebook post outside working hours on her private page — where she had a disclaimer saying views may not reflect that of her employer — did not disrupt university operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook had long been an outlet for her, where she shared memes, humor and lengthy political commentary. The posts, she said, had never come up at work, even though she had allowed some colleagues to view them. And having grown up in a conservative, rural area of Kentucky, she knew some relatives and others did not agree with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After she heard about Mr. Kirk’s assassination, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy recalled his comments after the 2023 shooting at a private Nashville Christian school: “I think it’s worth to have a cost of, unfortunately, some gun deaths every single year so that we can have the Second Amendment to protect our other God-given rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m like, this is so ironic that this man was shot at a school and he said, ‘this is just part of it,’” she said. At night, home from work, frustrated with the outpouring of grief, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, “I made the post, and I probably could have said it better. I didn’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her sympathy, she later said, was with his family and those who witnessed the killing. And in a follow-up post, she tried to clarify that she did not support violence. But screenshots began to circulate online, slowly fueling an outcry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 9:33 p.m. in Tennessee, Senator Marsha Blackburn, a Republican, called on X for Ms. Sosh-Lightsy’s removal, adding that she should be “ashamed.” Minutes later, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy was told to expect a call from the university president, Dr. Sidney A. McPhee. By the end of the night he had called and fired her, news that was promoted across social media and in an alert on the university’s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments were “inappropriate and callous,” Dr. McPhee said in a statement at the time, and “undermined the university’s credibility and reputation.” Hundreds of comments — many from people who identified themselves as alumni or parents of current students — flooded the posts, thanking the school for its action. (A spokesman for the school declined to comment, citing the ongoing lawsuit. The school has not yet filed a response in court.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservatives have suffered similar consequences for things they said online, especially in 2020, and successfully brought some free-speech cases. Last year, a federal jury awarded a Nashville firefighter about $1.8 million after the local government demoted him for Facebook comments critical of the Black Lives Matter movement and pandemic mask mandates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are conflicting feelings, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, when people send her reports that some people penalized for their online posts related to Mr. Kirk have won initial court cases, resulting in reinstatements or monetary awards, including a reported $500,000 settlement in Tennessee. There is some hope for what she sees as a fair outcome, she said, but still frustration that her case is unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next few days, Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said, threatening and critical messages poured in, prompting her to temporarily leave her home. A lesser penalty — being put on leave, losing her responsibilities related to student conduct — could be understood, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she maintains that she had done nothing egregious, let alone anything to warrant her immediate firing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If I’m wrong, and this speech is not protected, then I have never understood what the Constitution means and I have never understood what it protects,” Ms. Sosh-Lightsy said. “Either I haven’t understood it or we are on the edge of completely changing what it means.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some friends and longtime work references have distanced themselves publicly and privately. Others who disagree with the extent of Ms. Sosh-Lightsy’s punishment have still declined to say so publicly, wary of retribution for even the slightest association with her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve never been one to back down in the face of injustice or inequity,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she has since struggled to find a job. Grocery stores, public school systems and other workplaces have rejected her. She is living primarily off the payout from her unused time off, and is looking to sell her car in the coming weeks. She can no longer send money home to help her mother with her bills, and is worried about slipping back into the poverty she grew up in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand the sentiment that people have — that you did this, you said this awful thing — but I can almost guarantee you that if you put it into an example in their own life, they would say that the extent that I’m being held accountable is excessive,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She continues to post on Facebook, now, she said, with a hint of caution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kirsten Noyes contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/middle-tennessee-state-university-dean-fired-charlie-kirk.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:32:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Trump Shut the Border, a Texas Shelter for Migrants Emptied</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/sister-norma-pimentel-shelter-texas.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/00NAT-50states-texas-01-lmfh/00NAT-50states-texas-01-lmfh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For as long as Sister Norma Pimentel can remember, the shelter she runs in the border city of McAllen, Texas, has been crowded with thousands of migrants fleeing natural disasters, violence, authoritarian governments and poverty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But ever since President Trump retook the White House and embarked on aggressive immigration enforcement that has all but sealed the U.S. border with Mexico, her shelter, steps away from a bus station, looks quiet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have not seen a single migrant in months,” Sister Pimentel said last month. “We are completely empty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She pointed to a vacant kitchen, a deserted children’s play area and a bare floor that less than two years ago was filled with makeshift beds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the height of the migrant surge during President Joseph R. Biden Jr.’s administration, shelters along the border quickly became overwhelmed by the flood of migrants, some having received up to 1,000 people a day. At Sister Pimentel’s shelter, the Humanitarian Respite Center, the emptiness was so palpable recently that the voices of the workers and volunteers and a Christmas song echoed throughout the desolate rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The migrant slowdown is happening from Texas to California. The number of individuals seeking to cross the Southwest border has dwindled to an average of 245 a day from a peak of about 10,000 to 12,000 encounters a day during Mr. Biden’s administration, according to government data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sister Pimentel is well known globally for migrant advocacy and was included in Time magazine’s 100 Most Influential People in 2020. Her shelter became an epicenter of the immigration debate, and received some backlash for its work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The question back then was that some people viewed Catholic Charities as inviting people to come over,” said Javier Villalobos, the mayor of McAllen, a registered Republican. “That’s not necessarily true, but some people viewed it this way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With no migrants to house, the staff and volunteers at Sister Pimentel’s shelter have pivoted to help residents of McAllen, one of the poorest cities in America, with a population of about 150,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Villalobos said that he would rather see local organizations help the local population than take in migrants. “It’s not within our parameters to be dealing with immigration issues,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the shelter sometimes offers three meals a day, a change of clothes and assistance in finding government resources to about 50 to 60 people a day, in McAllen. The shelter largely relies on donations. It runs an educational program for low-income pregnant women. (As part of a larger immigration crackdown, the federal government has paused funding for the organization pending a review. Catholic Charities said it was cooperating with federal officials.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leo Wolf, 64, said that knowing the place offered food and a place to shower had given him a sense of comfort. “The migrants are no longer coming,” Mr. Wolf said. “But there are a lot of people like me locally who need their help. I hope this place never goes away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sister Pimentel said that the center’s mission had been to offer assistance to anyone who needs it. But in recent years, the migration crisis led an avalanche of families, many of them with young children, to border cities, overwhelming not just shelters, but hospitals, local police departments and other local resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those days, the U.S. Border Patrol processed migrants, most of whom were seeking asylum and released them at the shelter, where they stayed until they got their bearings to reach their destination inland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You never know when the situation is going to change — nothing is forever,” Sister Pimentel said. “But for now, this is the new normal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word about the shelter’s new focus has spread in McAllen, where a majority of the population is Latino.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paloma Garcia, 48, said she now got most of her meals at the shelter. Ms. Garcia said that since she was laid off as a cleaner a few months ago, she has struggled to find a new job and a place to live. She said she used to sleep in her car, until it was towed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They have been a lifesaver,” Ms. Garcia said of the shelter, adding, “I’m glad that they stayed open and now help people like me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing a few feet away, Eduardo Hendricks-Castillo, 60, nodded in agreement as he accepted a sandwich from a volunteer. He said he also had been homeless, until he recently secured housing through a government program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I heard they were aiding people like me and so I came over,” he said. “I don’t know what I would do about food if they weren’t around.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her office, Sister Pimentel keeps a copy of a portrait she painted in 2015 of a young Honduran mother and her son, during a time when many migrants were coming across the border. She recalled only the boy’s name, Tomasito, which became the title for the portrait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said she was haunted by their empty stares. She gave the painting to Pope Francis during a visit to New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I told him to keep it in his church so that he thinks of migrants like them when he prays every day,” she said. “This painting reminds us that migrants will always need our help.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/sister-norma-pimentel-shelter-texas.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 18:27:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At a Seattle Port Rocked by Tariffs, There Were 70 Jobs for 600 Workers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/seattle-dock-workers-tariffs-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-washington-zlqv/00nat-50states-washington-zlqv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On many mornings, Sarah Esch’s job as a dispatcher for dockworkers at the Port of Seattle boils down to a question of simple, frustrating math.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No ships came in last night, so we have maybe 70 jobs today for 600 workers,” Ms. Esch said before dawn on a recent Monday, eyeing the whiteboard used to track available shifts. “Those numbers aren’t great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dock workers in Seattle, like those in other ports up and down the West Coast, do the hard work of bringing Asian imports like electronics and auto parts off boats to make their way to consumers across the West and Midwest. They also load grain, seafood and other American exports onto ships for the return trip overseas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are used to uncertainty and shifting economic tides, but nothing since the Great Recession of 2008 compares to what these workers with the International Longshore and Warehouse Union have experienced in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump frames tariffs as an all-purpose tool and long-term strategy: a way to force other nations to rethink their own trade policies and prod U.S. manufacturers to bring blue-collar jobs back from foreign markets. Any short term pain, the president has argued, is a small price to pay for long-term global economic realignment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But at this port, and others, the broad tariffs have meant economic uncertainty for veteran workers and put what was once a stable blue-collar career increasingly out of reach for many younger longshoremen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People just can’t afford this,” Ms. Esch said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Longshoremen operate within a system based almost entirely on seniority and showing up. In Seattle, longshoremen rise through three employment ranks with hourly rates, which can start around $40 an hour, and rise to as much as $63 an hour for the most experienced and specially trained workers. People who work nights and weekends earn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entry-level workers are known as “casuals.” They don’t have benefits and aren’t guaranteed work. The second rung on the ladder, known as B-level, comes with health care benefits, the beginning of a pension plan and a guaranteed 32 hours of pay each week. Finally, after five years as what workers commonly call “B men,” dock workers rise to the top, A-level, which guarantees 40 hours of pay a week, full benefits, the right to vote for union hall officers and an ample retirement plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Once you get to A-level, there’s no better career,” said Gina Dobson, 49, an A-level worker with I.L.W.U. Local 19. “But we all tell the casuals, ‘Don’t quit your day job.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some union members can also pass down their “books,” essentially their union registration card, to their children if they die — meaning they start as B men. This perk helps explain why longshoring is such a legacy business: At the Local 19 union hall, third- or even fourth-generation dock workers are common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The pay, the benefits, the pension,” Ms. Esch said. “Once you’re in, it’s hard to find another profession that offers this kind of security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took her seven years to rise from casual to B man. She grew up in Colorado and came west to study theater at the University of Puget Sound in nearby Tacoma. She fell into port work while serving drinks at a bar frequented by longshoremen, who encouraged her to try the docks as a more stable way to make a living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She fell in love with the work — the easy camaraderie, being outside by the water beneath the Seattle skyline, never knowing what a day might bring, the “greasy, dirty sweaty” parts of the job — enough to push through those early lean years. She found free housing through a generous union member and worked second jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now at 48, she is a dispatcher. Elected by their fellow union members, dispatchers spend their days inside a fishbowl-like office, tracking jobs and doling out assignments. Their technology is decidedly old school: A wall-length whiteboard lists arriving ships. Workers log in using wooden pegs. Ms. Esch and other dispatchers hand write assignments with carbon paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through November, the total number of shipping containers that passed through the ports in Seattle and Tacoma was down almost 4 percent from 2024. That figure may not seem so bad, but it is skewed by an unusual spike in imports during the first quarter of 2025, as shipping companies rushed goods into the United States ahead of potential tariffs. Since August, the monthly drop in traffic has been in the double digits compared to 2024. There was no pre-Christmas rush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When China is sending fewer goods into the United States, that hurts. And when other countries aren’t buying soybeans from farmers in the Midwest, we feel that too,” said Sam Cho, a Port of Seattle commissioner. “We’re feeling it all right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This winter, most days bring barely enough jobs for A-level longshoremen. Despite their guaranteed wages, many are losing chances at overtime or higher pay for specialized work, like crane operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, it all sucks,” said Antonio Cappiello, 37, a longshoreman who is an A-level worker. “You just can’t predict from week to week or month to month what your take-home will be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Local 19 union hall, A- and B-level workers wait for assignments in adjoining upstairs rooms just outside the dispatch office, where they can watch Ms. Esch and her colleagues work the list of available shifts. Casuals wait downstairs, in a room near a parking lot. Ms. Esch usually radios down the bad news. Even within this blue-collar world, where most longshoremen wear the same unofficial uniform of weathered baseball caps or beanies, union sweatshirts and work boots, the gap between the haves and have-nots widens with every spasm of the global economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For newcomers, Ms. Esch’s now-regular announcement that there is “no work for casuals today” means careers may end before they truly begin. Old-timers talk about making it from casual to A-man in less than a decade during boom times when there were more than enough hours to go around. Now there is simply not enough work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s just an everyday disappointment right now,” said Matt Mirante, 31, who has been a casual for seven and a half years and, over the past three months, worked just seven shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has cousins and other relatives working upstairs, but sometimes considers quitting to focus on this other job, a junk removal business that earns him enough to afford a place of his own to live. He worries about walking away too soon. “I’ve spent so much time already,” Mr. Mirante said. “How could I give that up?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abegail Contreras has been a casual for seven years. At 41, she lives with her mother, works several other jobs and shows up almost every morning and evening hoping for shifts. She has picked up four over the last month. “I’ve wanted to be a longshoreman since I was a kid,” she said, adding, “I can see what kind of life it will mean once I make it upstairs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When — or if.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the union hall, the worries extend beyond the tariffs, and when politics comes up, there is less anger at the president and more frustration at the broad, existential decay of America’s shipping economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workers speak with fear about the Port of Rotterdam, in the Netherlands, among the most automated shipping terminals in the world, and the automation experiments taking place 1,100 miles south in Long Beach, Calif. They know how little longshoremen earn in Mexico and South America, and they track everything President Trump says about tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some good news: Improvements at the Seattle port have driven a surge in cruise ship traffic, bringing plentiful work during the summer months. Mr. Cappiello said he had stopped planning summer vacations because “even at A-level, you have to work when there’s work.” But cruise ship hours do not help casuals build up hours for advancing upstairs, and bills come due year-round.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Esch is not sure she would recommend the work she loves to another generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just don’t know what the future looks like,” she said. “Is there one?”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/seattle-dock-workers-tariffs-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:42:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Trump Made Life Difficult for International Students and Wisconsin</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/uw-madison-international-students-visas-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-wisconsin-fvqz/00nat-50states-wisconsin-fvqz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first signs of trouble came last spring, when the Trump administration abruptly moved to deport scores of international students, including a handful at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University officials were alarmed, well aware that around 8,000 students, 15 percent of its enrollment, were from abroad. And they worried that the looming deportations might spook prospective international students, said Frances Vavrus, the dean of the international division at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within weeks, she said, they were running tabletop exercises to game out the repercussions of a significant drop in international students — including for the university’s financials. International undergraduates tend to pay full tuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visa cancellations were eventually reversed. But for the rest of the summer, a team met every week to monitor the situation and plan for worst-case scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many universities across the country, the last year has been an exercise in crisis management, as the Trump administration has taken steps to overhaul higher education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials have had to handle visa restrictions, social media vetting procedures and travel bans from certain countries. Because of federal research funding cuts, universities have been forced to limit admission for graduate students, including those from abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A chill has settled over the University of Wisconsin-Madison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last fall, the number of new international undergraduates fell by 25 percent compared to the previous year. The number of new international graduate students also fell, declining by more than 27 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, universities around the country reported a 17 percent decrease in new international student enrollments last fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International programs began decades ago as a way to open up cultural exchange. Now, international students are a key to keeping universities solvent and competitive in science and technology research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many universities have relied especially on students from China. They make up the largest share of international pupils at the University of Wisconsin-Madison and, until recently, in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uncertainty over visas nearly drove Sidi Liu, 23, to accept a Ph.D. offer at a university in Switzerland last spring, instead of attending the University of Wisconsin. In the end, Ms. Liu, who grew up in China, decided to take the risk. Wisconsin had a stronger program in her area of research, understanding the movement of polar icebergs, a crucial issue for shipping lanes in the Arctic Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Liu is enjoying life in Wisconsin. She has tried fried cheese curds and joined a Chinese musical club, and was excited to go to a Badgers football game. But she is also taking it year by year. She still gets nervous passing through passport control at the airport, and she has made a backup plan with her supervisor in case her funding falls through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s almost like a mind-set of gambling,” Ms. Liu said. “Currently, I’m still winning, but I can’t foresee the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has sent confusing messages about his ultimate intentions. He has suggested that international students take up coveted slots at universities that could go to American citizens. His administration has sought to deport students for reasons ranging from pro-Palestinian activism to minor traffic violations. And he has said that some Chinese students may be security risks if they are involved in academic espionage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, he has acknowledged that cutting half of the international students would “destroy our entire university and college system.” And he has also suggested that the United States could double its enrollment of Chinese students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if Mr. Trump were to ease up on his restrictions, there is no guarantee that international students, and Chinese students in particular, will continue to choose the United States. The number of Chinese students in America had been steadily declining since its peak in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reality is that China’s best and the brightest are not coming but leaving,” said Yingyi Ma, a professor of sociology at Syracuse University who researches education and migration in the United States and China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers have shown that public research universities around the country have turned to full-paying international students to make up for state funding cuts. At more than 50 American universities, international students make up at least 10 percent of the undergraduate class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Wisconsin began to ramp up that enrollment after the double whammy of the 2008 financial crisis and Gov. Scott Walker’s decision in 2015 to freeze tuition and cut educational spending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By last year, international students made up around 10 percent of the undergraduate class, paying nearly 3.5 times as much — or about $30,000 more — in tuition and fees per year compared to in-state students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judie Zhang, a sophomore majoring in psychology and neuroscience, saw an education in America as a longer-term financial investment and a way to circumvent China’s pressure cooker education system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She hopes to stay in the United States. But the restrictions and uncertainty weigh on her. For now, she has chosen not to go home to see her family, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Wisconsin officials have emphasized that despite the drop in new, incoming international students, the overall decline was only 6 percent. And, they said, more international students are on campus today than a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were able to weather that storm,” Ms. Vavrus, the university dean, said in an interview. But the university announced in June a budget cut of 5 percent, citing among various “uncertainties and concerning headwinds” the potential decline in international student enrollment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And officials are under no illusion that they are out of the woods. Ms. Vavrus said she believed that starting in the spring, the team could be meeting again more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extended decline could ripple out beyond the campus. International students at the University of Wisconsin-Madison contributed almost $400 million to the local economy, according to a 2024 report from the Association of International Educators, a nonprofit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could also cause lasting damage to a significant pipeline of scientific and technological talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karu Sankaralingam, a computer science professor at the university, said that about five years ago, he stopped taking on graduate students from China, even though they were among the best in his area of research, which focuses on efficient chip design for artificial intelligence. With the growing geopolitical sensitivities around chips, it had become too much of a risk, he reasoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Mr. Sankaralingam is holding off on recruiting new graduate students altogether, in line with guidance issued last year by university officials. He increasingly worries about being cut off long term from the global talent pool. In 2024, 57 percent of computer science doctoral graduates at American colleges were on temporary visas, according to an annual survey from the National Science Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are intentionally hamstringing ourselves,” Mr. Sankaralingam said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many international students, America may still be the top choice, but it is not the only choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Junda Li, 29, who grew up in China, is now finishing his doctorate in political science at Wisconsin, where he studies industrial policy between the United States and China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he contemplates his next career move, he is keeping a mental ledger of pros and cons. In Mr. Li’s mind, the advantages of going back to China are a less competitive job market, better Chinese food and proximity to his family. The pros of staying are a more vibrant academic environment and better pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is still hoping to keep his options open. But especially after the recent visa restrictions, Mr. Li said, “going back to China is an easier path.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/uw-madison-international-students-visas-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:42:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>To Their Shock, Cubans in Florida Are Being Deported in Record Numbers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cubans-florida-deportations-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-50states-florida-01-mlft/19nat-50states-florida-01-mlft-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heidy Sánchez took her 17-month-old daughter to a routine check-in last April with Immigration and Customs Enforcement in Tampa, Fla. During the appointment, federal authorities told her that she was being detained and that her husband should pick up their daughter, who was still breastfeeding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days later, Ms. Sánchez, 44, who worked as a home health aide, was deported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sánchez’s story quickly spread across social media, in part because she is Cuban, a group that had long been treated differently than other immigrants, even when they entered the country illegally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has changed under President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has repatriated more than 1,600 Cubans in 2025, according to the Cuban government. That is about double the number of Cubans who were repatriated in 2024. And in the years that Mr. Trump has been president, he has sent more Cubans back than his three predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those numbers are greater for Cubans who were deported by land into Mexico. Some of them had been in the United States for decades and built families and businesses, but were removed because of an old criminal conviction — say, from Miami’s infamous cocaine cowboys days in the late 1970s and early 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere has the shock of treating Cubans like other migrants been felt more than in Florida, which was shaped in modern times by exiles of the 1959 Cuban Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Families, businesses and communities that once felt removed from or immune to immigration enforcement now must face it head-on. Some Floridians worry that these deportations could stain the state’s proud Cuban identity, turning older immigrants against newer ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump, many other countries saw similar increases in repatriation. The difference is that Cubans had not previously been targeted as aggressively for removal. Regular deportation flights to Cuba began in January 2017, under President Barack Obama, paused during the coronavirus pandemic and restarted in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Cubans have also been detained for weeks or months in a facility in the Florida Everglades known as “Alligator Alcatraz.” At another nearby detention facility, Cuban detainees protested last June by writing “SOS Cuba” on their shirts and spelling out “SOS” with their bodies in the recreation yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal immigration has also been all but cut out. Mr. Trump enacted a travel ban on 19 countries, including Cuba, and ended a family reunification program. U.S. officials are rejecting visa applications, which can take years to complete. Last month, the Trump administration paused all Cuban immigration cases, including pending naturalization, residency and asylum applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s the most sweeping rollback of Cuban migration channels since the Cold War,” said María José Espinosa, the executive director of the Center for Engagement and Advocacy in the Americas, a nonprofit strategy organization based in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polls suggest that most Cuban American registered voters, who tend to be Republican, continue to support Mr. Trump, said Michael J. Bustamante, an associate history professor and director of Cuban studies at the University of Miami who studies Cuban American political culture. But he said that he had noticed “a growing amount of unease” throughout the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a senator, Secretary of State Marco Rubio, the Trump administration’s most prominent Cuban American, often criticized Cuban immigrants who received government benefits like food stamps and Medicaid, and frequently returned to the island. Over the summer, Mr. Rubio said in a video commemorating huge anti-Communist protests in 2021 that many Cubans had found it “easier” to “abandon” the island than stay and fight the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immigration enforcement in South Florida has not involved a mass federal operation, as in Los Angeles or Chicago, and previous administrations had made changes that started to erode Cubans’ immigration privileges. Still, Mr. Trump’s anti-immigration campaign has shaken some Cubans unused to feeling at risk in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am scared of everything,” said Javier González, a 36-year-old salesman in the heavily Cuban city of Hialeah, northwest of Miami.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González and his family crossed the United States-Mexico border in February 2022, fleeing what he described as a threat to his life in Cuba, where he was a political dissident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González and his wife, like hundreds of thousands of recent Cubans migrants, were released under what is known as conditional parole. That does not allow them to apply for residency under the Cuban Adjustment Act, a law that Congress passed in 1966, and leaves them vulnerable to deportation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. González and his wife legally obtained Social Security numbers, work permits and driver’s licenses. He applied for political asylum and has a pending court date in 2028. He found work as an HVAC technician. Mr. Trump’s campaign promise to deport criminals seemed sound to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then early last year, ICE officers, during regular check-ins in South Florida, started detaining Cubans with conditional parole. Now, to avoid immigration sweeps, Mr. González said he avoided unnecessary car rides and local Hispanic supermarkets. He cannot fathom the repression he might face in Cuba were he to return as a former dissident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sometimes I tell myself, ‘Why do you have to feel as if you were a criminal when you are an upstanding person?’” Mr. González said. But, he added, “They can grab you and do whatever they want.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some older Cuban American immigrants are angry over the turnabout in circumstances. Alicia Peláez, 78, arrived in the United States as an unaccompanied minor in 1960, under Operation Pedro Pan, a secret program run by the Catholic Church with help from the State Department that resettled some 14,000 young Cubans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We were welcomed into the country,” said Ms. Peláez, who is a registered Republican, but has not voted that way in recent elections. “Now, it’s the complete opposite.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sánchez, who was separated from her baby and husband, remains in Havana, with a pending visa interview that will determine whether she can apply for a waiver to return to Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She came to the United States through the border, presented herself to request asylum, and waited in Mexico. But she missed a hearing because of safety reasons, which resulted in a deportation order and nine months of detention. In the end, she was released in the United States because Cuba at the time did not accept her repatriation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in Florida, Ms. Sánchez studied and became a nursing assistant. She met and married her husband, an American citizen, who petitioned for her residency. She underwent fertility treatments and had their daughter. Three months before her deportation, they had bought a house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being returned to Cuba, Ms. Sánchez said she was so upset that she had to see a psychiatrist. Her daughter, in Tampa, was no longer her cheery self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She didn’t laugh anymore, which really worried us,” Ms. Sánchez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her husband and daughter visited Ms. Sánchez over Christmas, which lifted their spirits, she said. But she did not know how she would handle more months of separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her daughter, she said, “is our joy, our happiness, our life.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/cubans-florida-deportations-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:47:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Vermont Town Was a Foodie Mecca for Canadians. Until Trump’s Threats.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/greensboro-vermont-canada-tariffs-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/00nat-50states-vermont-pzwh/00nat-50states-vermont-pzwh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the looks of it, Willey’s Store, with its rambling maze of rooms and modest white clapboard profile, is not the kind of place to expect a binational meeting of the minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this store in Greensboro, in the northernmost part of Vermont, has long attracted customers from Canada who trek there on a quest for their favorite cheeses from nearby Jasper Hill Farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoulder to shoulder, on a creaking wooden floor worn smooth by 125 years of foot traffic, Canadians and Americans reach eagerly for coveted blocks of Withersbrook Blue, a recent winner at the World Cheese Awards, and rounds of creamy Harbison, its woodsy notes derived from its spruce-bark wrapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To these seekers, the border between the two countries scarcely mattered: The cheese was the thing. Its cachet helped make the store, and the town, a destination, lending this remote and rural place an international appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This cheese has such a cult following, people bring their coolers and stock up,” said Christina Hernandez, the store’s general manager. “They’ll spend a few hundred dollars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since President Trump took office, though, Greensboro, with about 800 residents, has been stung by a collapse in traffic from Canada. Spooked by his threats to make their country the “51st state,” angered by his claims of rampant cross-border drug smuggling and shocked by hefty new tariffs on some of their goods, Canadians have cut back, or suspended, their cross-border travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Willey’s Store, overall sales declined by 33 percent last year, including a $14,000 drop for Jasper Hill cheese, for reasons that included the loss of Canadian business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at Hill Farmstead, an award-winning brewery that is another major draw for visitors to Greensboro, things have been no better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since last January, Hill Farmstead has sustained a 25 percent to 30 percent hit to its business that is “directly attributable” to damaged relations with Canada under the Trump administration, said Bob Montgomery, director of brand quality at the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our region has always struggled for an economic engine, and Canadian traffic has been essential,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other small towns in the sparsely populated region, one of the most economically fragile in New England, Greensboro depends on tourists from up north to help fill its lodges, restaurants and shops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But “the impact is not just economic,” Mr. Montgomery said. In Greensboro, people have grieved two losses: the Canadian customers who help to keep small businesses afloat, and the uncomplicated relationship they long took for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The damage done is measurable,” Mr. Montgomery said. “It may take a generation to get back to what it was.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the antagonism began last February and March, Mr. Montgomery said, “we saw traffic nosedive within a week.” Border crossings into Vermont from Canada declined 30 percent in 2025, compared with 2024, while credit card spending by Canadian visitors fell by half, according to state data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Canadians say they don’t want to boost the U.S. economy. Others feel a new sense of danger at the border, more typically associated with the southern border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among them was Emilie Laferriere, a Montrealer who used to visit Vermont often with her wife, an American who grew up there. The couple spent time with family members and camped in Vermont parks every summer. But Ms. Laferriere stayed away after Mr. Trump took office. A visit in December, to celebrate a late Thanksgiving with the in-laws, was the first in Vermont all year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In part, there was a reluctance to spend money in a country where leaders had been so aggressively antagonistic toward Canada. But there was also a feeling of risk in the United States, both as a Canadian and as an openly gay woman who is half Asian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The current opinion in Canada is, the U.S. is a scary place, so don’t go there,” Ms. Laferriere said, savoring a glass of beer by a window with a sweeping view of snowy pines. “I don’t want to support the policies. And I’m not sure if it’s safe or not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support for Mr. Trump is low in Vermont, a famously liberal state that Vice President Kamala Harris won in 2024 by 30 percentage points. In Greensboro, 376 voters cast ballots for Ms. Harris, 75 percent of the total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just to the north, where Vermont meets Canada, Mr. Trump won every border town, a complicating factor in the way the region thinks and talks about his toll on the local economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Northern Vermont has challenges that predate Mr. Trump’s return to the presidency. Its young people have long fled south to cities with more opportunities, making local jobs hard to fill. At the same time, its housing crisis has worsened dramatically since 2020, when a pandemic-driven surge in out-of-state buyers inflated real estate prices, squeezing out local families and potential workers at Hill Farmstead, Jasper Hill Farm and other businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layered on top of existing obstacles, the loss of Canadian business has been an especially harsh blow for Jasper Hill Farm. The small cheese maker, founded 22 years ago by two brothers, was rapidly expanding sales of its cheese in Canada when the sudden split between the two countries stopped its growth cold, said Mateo Kehler, a co-founder and the head cheesemaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had already taken a decade to find a way into the Canadian market, where the government closely guards the supply of products, but persistence had begun to pay off, Mr. Kehler said. The farm was on track to make $500,000 in annual Canadian sales, and its owners had believed sales could soon reach seven figures. The collapse of U.S.-Canadian relations abruptly upended that progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In February, it just ended,” Mr. Kehler said. “As in, zero cases ordered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adding to its losses, the business has had to pay tens of thousands of dollars in tariffs on specialized cheese-making equipment it imported last year from Canada and Switzerland. Some replacement parts have doubled in price, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The health of his business matters deeply to the region: Jasper Hill Farm employs 80 people and supplements the milk supply from its own cows with milk it buys from local dairy farmers. It pays them nearly twice the commodity price, a carefully calibrated effort to help support farmers who are also neighbors, in a state that lost hundreds of dairy farms in the last decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tremors from the Canadian shake-up have also been felt at other small Greensboro businesses. At Highland Lodge, a historic inn with cabins on 130 acres, Canadian guests canceled reservations last year, some citing U.S. policies, an innkeeper, Elsa Schultz, said in an email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is evidence that some Canadians are coming back. On a weekday in December, bartenders in the Hill Farmstead taproom estimated that as many as a third of the customers were Canadian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brewery’s managers said they understood why many others were continuing to stay away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve made it abundantly clear that we support their decisions, from a fundamental philosophical place,” Mr. Montgomery said. “And that we hope to see them when they feel they can return.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/greensboro-vermont-canada-tariffs-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:42:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Colorado, the Options for Ari, a Transgender Teen, Begin to Disappear</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/colorado-transgender-treatments-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00nat-50states-colorado-jfqk/00nat-50states-colorado-jfqk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been two years since Ari Cohen, 16, began taking hormone therapy to coax his female body into closer alignment with his long-held masculine sense of self.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During treatment at Children’s Hospital Colorado on the outskirts of Denver, Ari’s voice has deepened, so much that he has been known to laugh out loud at the booming sound. He has gained muscle. His breasts stopped growing. The anxiety of not quite looking or sounding like a boy, even though in his mind he had always been one, lifted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the way I am now,’’ he said in a recent interview. “It’s nice.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had taken years for Ari to persuade his parents to take him to a gender clinic. But the new year brings a new anxiety for Ari, as well as for thousands of other transgender teenagers in the United States: What if they can no longer receive medical treatment for gender dysphoria in this country?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last year, the Trump administration has moved to upend gender transition treatment for minors. Many families living in Republican-led states had already faced bans on such treatment, but federal agencies in 2025 used an array of pressure tactics to try to end treatments for minors in every state, red and blue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ari lives in Colorado, one of the two dozen states where it is legal to provide the care, and received treatment from the increasingly rare hospital still offering it. But over the course of the year, his family, too, was sent scrambling for Plans B, C, and D. And by the beginning of this year, it became clear that those plans might need to be put into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his 2024 election campaign, President Trump tapped into — and stoked — a broad cultural discomfort with the growing number of young people identifying as transgender, vowing to “stop the transgender lunacy,” especially when it came to medical treatment for minors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once in office, he quickly signed an executive order that vowed the government would not “fund, sponsor, promote, assist, or support the so-called ‘transition’ of a child from one sex to another.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in February, the Trump administration urged the Supreme Court to uphold a Tennessee law banning transgender medication for minors, and, by extension, other bans in more than 20 states. The court did that in June, prompting many families to move or travel to receive care, including to Ari’s hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most major U.S. medical groups have endorsed medical treatments as effective in relieving the distress young people can experience when their gender identity conflicts with their sex. That treatment can include puberty blockers, hormone therapies and, in rare cases, mastectomies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But an influential report commissioned by the British government found that the risks and benefits have not been well studied. And some European countries have restricted gender treatments in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration took its own stance in May, when the Department of Health and Human Services issued a report prioritizing psychotherapy for gender dysphoria treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other federal agencies also began to act against medical treatment for minors. In June, the F.B.I. called on the public to report hospitals and doctors who are performing mastectomies on minors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission held a hearing in July on potentially unfair or deceptive trade practices in the field, featuring several young people and parents who say they were misled by the medical establishment into embracing gender treatments, and regretted their decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same month, the Justice Department issued subpoenas to more than 20 doctors and hospitals, including Children’s Hospital Colorado, demanding confidential records of gender treatments that it suggested could be linked to fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Ari’s hospital, along with several other institutions, sued. But high-profile clinics in Boston, Washington D.C., Los Angeles and Pittsburgh started shutting down, telling patients they were trying to avoid government sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, a week before Christmas, Mr. Trump’s health secretary, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., made it all but impossible for Children’s Hospital Colorado to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kennedy announced that the agency would effectively bar all Medicaid and Medicare funding to hospitals that continued to provide gender medicine to minors. Two weeks later, Mr. Kennedy’s agency indicated that it would investigate several hospitals, including Ari’s, for failing to meet the standards of its report recommending psychotherapy.In the first week of January, the hospital informed Ari and his family that it was suspending care for patients under the age of 18 — “beginning today.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk of losing federal health care funding was too great, the hospital said in a statement: “As a safety net hospital system, nearly half of our patients are covered by Medicaid. This loss of funding would critically impair our ability to provide care for the multitudes of children who depend on us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics of youth gender medicine — including some health professionals, parents and young people who regret their own treatment — have applauded the closings. They say the shutdowns will protect many children from long-term side effects that can include infertility. About 10,000 minors between age 10 and 17 have been receiving gender treatment, according to a federal government estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threat to withhold Medicaid and Medicare funds, said Dr. Stanley Goldfarb, chairman of Do No Harm, an anti-transgender advocacy group, “marks a major step toward delivering a crippling blow to the child transgender industry.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For his part, Ari has started calculating whether he can adjust his testosterone dosage to make his existing prescriptions last until he turns 18, which is more than a year away. He has worries, especially over the possibility of uneven consequences. Vocal changes are typically permanent. But he might get a period and return to a softer, more feminine physique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m afraid of basically turning back into a female-presenting person,’’ Ari said. “And I don’t even know what that will look like, so I’m afraid of that too.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ari’s mother, Erin Roosa, is worried about the harassment that can come from “not passing” as male. She is looking into other options, just as she has all year. When Children’s Hospital Colorado suspended care, she already had a backup provider lined up nearby, in Boulder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that is no guarantee that Ari’s care will last, since legal experts say that any provider receiving federal funds could be affected by the Trump administration’s new policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Roosa is looking into the legality of purchasing hormones outside the United States. Other parents, especially those with younger children being treated with puberty blockers, are considering leaving the country. Another option, albeit an expensive one, may be providers that take only private insurance or direct payments, and do not accept Medicare and Medicaid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Roosa, like many parents of transgender teenagers, feels the Trump administration is attacking her family for political advantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Apparently,” she said, “I can’t be given the responsibility to take care of my own child.’’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Litigation is continuing. Colorado is among 19 states now suing the U.S. Health Department, arguing that Mr. Kennedy does not have the legal authority to declare a new standard of care and punish providers who do not adhere to it. The department has agreed not to take action against any provider as the litigation proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hearing is scheduled for March 19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Ari, who turns 18 in 2027, that buys him some time.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/colorado-transgender-treatments-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:41:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Allows Policy Restricting Lawmakers’ Access to ICE Facilities</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/ice-detention-lawmakers-oversight.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/14/multimedia/00dc-immig-top-fchp/00dc-immig-top-fchp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge in Washington declined on Monday to immediately block the Department of Homeland Security from requiring lawmakers to provide seven days’ notice before they try to visit and inspect immigration detention facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without finding that the policy itself was legal, Judge Jia M. Cobb of the Federal District Court for the District of Columbia wrote that the group of lawmakers who sued to halt it would need to revise their lawsuit in a way that directly addressed the Trump administration’s latest rationale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Cobb had blocked an essentially identical policy by the agency in December, citing a provision of the appropriations law that funds the department and requires facilities to be open to congressional oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Homeland Security had reinitiated the policy earlier this month, claiming that funds set aside in the One Big Beautiful Bill Act, President Trump’s signature domestic policy law, were enough to fund the detention facilities rather than the appropriations legislation cited by Judge Cobb, allowing them to skirt the requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling followed an emergency hearing last week, in which lawyers for Democratic members of Congress argued the funding switch amounted to a dubious legal sleight of hand intended to bypass the judge’s order. It came after the government had already invoked the policy to deny Representatives Angie Craig, Ilhan Omar and Kelly Morrison, all Minnesota Democrats, entry to a detention center in Minneapolis on Jan. 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a brief, four-page order, Judge Cobb wrote that the lawmakers would need to revise their complaint. She stressed that the decision on Monday hinged on technical changes the Trump administration had made to put the policy back in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision also landed amid a surge in opposition to federal immigration operations in Minnesota, where daily clashes between residents and the more than 3,000 federal officers deployed there have put a spotlight on the Trump administration’s eagerness to use overwhelming force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump mused about invoking the Insurrection Act to deploy the military for domestic law enforcement in Minneapolis, though he later backed off. And the White House has rallied to the defense of an agent who shot and killed an unarmed woman in Minneapolis, while increasingly supporting the use of deadly force despite internal guidance at ICE that urges restraint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Wednesday’s hearing, Amber Richer, a lawyer from the Justice Department, told Judge Cobb that ICE had effectively freed itself of requirements in the appropriations law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Richer pointed to a sworn statement by a senior D.H.S. financial officer who explained that the agency was able to use a surge of funding in the president’s bill to cover operations at detention centers instead. The availability of those funds, she argued, circumvented requirements in the law that annually funded ICE. That legislation prohibits money authorized by Congress from being used to deny lawmakers or members of their staff access to conduct oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the hearing, Judge Cobb said that without more evidence that the government had completely changed funding streams, the reinstated policy appeared to violate her previous order that members of Congress be allowed to visit detention centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think taking steps to exclude members of Congress from facilities is the subject of my order,” Judge Cobb said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hearing on Wednesday came in a lawsuit brought by a group of Democratic lawmakers who had previously been turned away while trying to visit detention facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christine Coogle, a lawyer from the legal advocacy group Democracy Forward who is representing the members of Congress, told the judge that the government had set out to revive “the same exact policy” as before while deflecting detailed questions about the funds it was using. She said she believed the administration was “trying to make a game” out of using the new funds “to paper over” a violation of the judge’s order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just think that defendants cannot win that game, because appropriations are not a game — they are the law,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Coogle raised a number of examples that she said showed that the government could not claim to have fully abandoned funding from Congress. She cited salaries for top department officials and licenses for Microsoft software in use at ICE facilities, which were all already covered with money appropriated by Congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also pointed to news media reports about overcrowding at ICE facilities and a surge in detentions that had already contributed to the deaths of at least four people so far in 2026 as reasons the unannounced inspections by members of Congress were necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/ice-detention-lawmakers-oversight.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:04:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Asks Judge to Reject Minnesota’s Call to Block ICE Surge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/minnesota-ice-lawsuit-trump-administration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-minnesota-lawsuit-1-tgjf/19nat-minnesota-lawsuit-1-tgjf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Justice Department asked a federal judge on Monday to allow a surge of immigration agents in Minnesota to continue despite a lawsuit filed by state and local officials claiming that the deployment is unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the state and the cities of Minneapolis and St. Paul say in the suit that the operation violates Minnesota’s sovereignty under the 10th Amendment. It says that the federal government’s “actions appear designed to provoke community outrage, sow fear and inflict emotional distress, and they are interfering with the ability of state and local officials to protect and care for their residents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Trump administration said on Monday that the state and local governments’ position was an “absurdity” that “would render the supremacy of federal law an afterthought to local preferences.” An injunction blocking the operation “would constitute an unprecedented act of judicial overreach,” they added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plaintiffs filed the suit last week. Judge Kate M. Menendez made no rulings in a hearing on Wednesday; the state had pressed her to immediately block the deployment of some 3,000 federal agents to Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ICE campaign, which the Trump administration has named Operation Metro Surge, has led to more than 3,000 arrests, repeated clashes with protesters and two shootings. The administration has described the effort as necessary to crack down on illegal immigration and to root out fraud in state social service programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez, who was nominated by President Joseph R. Biden Jr., said during the hearing last week that the Trump administration needed time to reply to the lawsuit. She said another hearing on the issue was possible, perhaps as soon as this Friday, though one has not been scheduled yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Democratic-led states targeted in immigration enforcement campaigns have challenged President Trump’s use of the military in such efforts, but questioning the executive branch’s authority to deploy law enforcement officers appears to be a new strategy. Mr. Trump has threatened to invoke the Insurrection Act to send federal troops to Minnesota, but he has not yet done so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawyers for the administration said in their written filing on Monday that “Minnesota wants a veto over federal law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The 10th Amendment does not afford an ejectment action for states who are dissatisfied with the federal government’s enforcement of federal law,” the administration’s response said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the same day that Minnesota filed its lawsuit, Illinois sued the Trump administration and asked a judge to halt civil immigration enforcement in the state without “express congressional authorization.” No ruling has been entered in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minnesota lawsuit is playing out against the backdrop of large protests, highly visible patrols by Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents and mounting hostility between Republicans in the federal government and the top Democrats in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ICE agent fatally shot Renee Good, a U.S. citizen, on a Minneapolis street on Jan. 7, an encounter that federal and local officials have described in sharply contrasting terms. Last week, another agent shot and injured a man who officials said was in the country illegally. They said that the man had assaulted an agent with a shovel or a broom while resisting arrest in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the Justice Department was said to have opened a criminal investigation into whether Gov. Tim Walz of Minnesota and Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis had conspired to impede federal agents. Mr. Walz and Mr. Frey, both Democrats, described the inquiry as a weaponization of law enforcement power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Menendez, of the U.S. District Court for the District of Minnesota, is also hearing a separate lawsuit that challenges the actions of immigration agents toward protesters. She entered a preliminary injunction in that case on Friday, imposing restrictions on how agents interact with demonstrators. Lawyers for the Trump administration said on Monday that they would appeal that injunction.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/minnesota-ice-lawsuit-trump-administration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:00:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A City on Edge: Protesters Clash in MinneapolisA City on Edge: Protesters Clash in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010652966/protesters-clash-ice-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/arts/19vid-pro-ice-minneapolis-COVER/19vid-pro-ice-minneapolis-COVER-facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jake Lang, a prominent right-wing activist, held a small pro-ICE rally in Minneapolis on Saturday. Within minutes, counterprotesters closed in and the confrontation turned violent.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010652966/protesters-clash-ice-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:32:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Issues M.L.K. Day Proclamation After Criticism</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-mlk-day-proclamation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-news-MLK-Day2-plmw/19trump-news-MLK-Day2-plmw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump proclaimed Martin Luther King Jr. Day on Monday evening, after he was criticized by civil rights activists for breaking from tradition by failing to recognize Dr. King’s legacy or attending commemorations of the holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, presidents issued statements about Dr. King even before the federal holiday. Toward the end of Mr. Trump’s first term in 2021, when M.L.K. Day fell on Jan. 18, his proclamation was issued on Jan. 15, Dr. King’s birthday. Last year, President Joe Biden issued a proclamation on Jan. 17, days before the holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each year, the United States celebrates Dr. King’s legacy with a federal holiday on the third Monday of January. Dr. King played an instrumental role in the civil rights movement, which called for an end to racial segregation and discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presidents usually attend parades and commemorative services held in his honor. The federal holiday was created in 1983 by legislation signed by President Ronald Reagan, 15 years after Dr. King was assassinated. President Bill Clinton signed legislation in 1994 designating it as a day of service to encourage Americans to volunteer in their communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump did not attend M.L.K. Day events on Monday, spending the holiday at his Mar-a-Lago estate in Florida. In the proclamation, Mr. Trump said he had honored Dr. King last year by declassifying documents related to his assassination. Several noted historians said at the time, however, that there was little of note in these documents and most of Dr. King’s family had opposed their release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dr. King’s extraordinary resolve stands as an enduring testament to the unstoppable fire of freedom and, tragically, ultimately cost him his life,” Mr. Trump said in the proclamation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today, we honor the brave men and women who remain steadfast in their commitment to law, order, liberty, and justice for all. We renew our resolve to honor our heritage, reclaim our freedom, and recommit to the truth that America is, was, and forever will be a great Nation,” the proclamation said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of a proclamation for most of Monday was criticized by civil rights groups, including the N.A.A.C.P.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a social media post on Monday, Bernice King, Dr. King’s daughter, called on Americans to remember her father by, among other things, “amplifying and advocating for the end of state-sanctioned and facilitated violence against Black and Brown immigrants and against people, period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s M.L.K. Day proclamation was not shared by the White House or the president on their social media accounts, which have posted throughout the day about immigration enforcement actions and the college football championship in Miami, which Mr. Trump was attending on Monday night.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-mlk-day-proclamation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 19:20:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens 200% Tariffs on Wine if France Declines to Join Gaza Board of Peace</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-france-wine-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-champagne-bgcz/20xp-champagne-bgcz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump threatened on Monday to impose 200 percent tariffs on French wine.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-france-wine-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:22:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Suicides Were Frequent at the Golden Gate Bridge. Not Anymore.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/golden-gate-bridge-suicides.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20NAT-BRIDGE-SUICIDES-top-kvqg/20NAT-BRIDGE-SUICIDES-top-kvqg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A system of stainless steel cables was installed on both sides of the bridge.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/golden-gate-bridge-suicides.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:01:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court to Hear Case Testing Limits of Hawaii Gun Law</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/supreme-court-hawaii-gun-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-scotus-hawaii-top-pwvq/20dc-scotus-hawaii-top-pwvq-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Atom Kasprzycki, left, and Jason Wolford are part of a group of Hawaii gun owners challenging the law, which requires gun owners to get the explicit consent of a property owner before carrying a concealed weapon.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/supreme-court-hawaii-gun-law.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Volunteers in Minnesota Deliver Groceries So Immigrants Can Hide at Home</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/minnesota-groceries-church-volunteer-ice-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19nat-minn-food-1-fqvc/19nat-minn-food-1-fqvc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sergio Amezcua, a pastor at Dios Habla Hoy in south Minneapolis, organized the effort by his church to help fearful immigrants remain at home.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/minnesota-groceries-church-volunteer-ice-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fact-Checking Trump’s Misleading Claims After One Year Back in Office</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-falsehoods-fact-check-first-year.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/us/politics/dc-fact-check-2/dc-fact-check-2-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president has justified many significant moves of his second term with inaccurate claims and overstated boasts.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-falsehoods-fact-check-first-year.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 05:19:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Calls Britain’s Chagos Deal ‘Act of Great Stupidity,’ in Blow to Starmer</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-uk-chagos-islands-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-chagos-qcmk/20trump-news-chagos-qcmk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Diego Garcia, the largest island in the Chagos Archipelago, is the site of a major military base used by Britain and the United States.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-uk-chagos-islands-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:53:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Make America Go Away’ Caps Surge in Popularity as Trump Eyes Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/make-america-go-away-hats-greenland-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-hats-vjth/20trump-news-hats-vjth-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The anti-Trump hats, developed by a store owner in Copenhagen, have captured a mood.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/make-america-go-away-hats-greenland-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:03:08 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>