<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:09:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Republicans Struggle to Respond to Shooting, Reflecting Political Peril</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/bill-cassidy-minneapolis-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-cassidy-qvtf/25minneapolis-ice-cassidy-qvtf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Senator Bill Cassidy has faced accusations that he is not sufficiently supportive of President Trump.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/bill-cassidy-minneapolis-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 04:37:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Museums From Texas to Massachusetts Close for Storm, but Broadway Shows Go On</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/museums-broadway-storm-closed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-museum-closings-sub-jctf/25winter-storm-museum-closings-sub-jctf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Museums, theaters and concert halls from Texas to Massachusetts shut their doors on Sunday as a powerful winter storm marched eastward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least five of New York’s largest museums were closed on Sunday, when the brunt of the storm was expected to hit the region, including the Frick Collection, the Guggenheim, the Whitney, the Brooklyn Museum and the Studio Museum in Harlem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of Natural History remained open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday morning, two Broadways shows in New York — “Aladdin” and “The Lion King” — had paused performances until Tuesday. And while a handful of Off Broadway shows, including “Heathers: The Musical,” “The Monsters” and “Anna Christie,” also canceled shows, the Broadway League, which represents theater owners, producers and other professionals, said on Saturday that most productions would continue as planned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Philharmonic rescheduled a show conducted by Gustavo Dudamel at Radio City Music Hall for Tuesday, and the Beacon Theater rescheduled a performance by the comedians Seth Meyers and John Oliver for next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Texas, where tens of thousands of customers had lost power, officials at the Dallas Museum of Art said their institution would be closed for the entire weekend. Similar announcements were made by the Mint Museum Randolph in Charlotte, N.C.; the Columbia Museum of Art in South Carolina; the Carnegie museums in Pittsburgh; and the Philadelphia Museum of Art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Smithsonian, which has locations in Washington and New York, said all of its museums, research centers and the National Zoo would be closed on Sunday and Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, the Field Museum in Chicago closed because of extreme cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zachary Small contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/museums-broadway-storm-closed.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 14:32:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Trump, the Truth in Minneapolis Is What He Says It Is</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-truth-minneapolis-shootings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-assess-Trumplaptop-vbft/25dc-assess-Trumplaptop-vbft-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump has found that putting out a story line early and repeating it often can convince a sizable share of the public that does not credit contrary evidence.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-truth-minneapolis-shootings.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 15:38:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Government Again Excludes Minnesota From Investigation of Fatal Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl/25nat-minnesota-investigation-mcvl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Minnesota officials said they aimed to have their Bureau of Criminal Apprehension, which typically takes the lead in police shootings, work the investigation, either concurrently or in partnership with the federal government.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/federal-exclude-minnesota-shooting-investigations.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 19:46:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Broadway, frustration mounts as curtains rise amid the snowfall.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/winter-storm-snow-ice/broadway-winter-storm-closures</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-broadway-kzpv/25winter-storm-broadway-kzpv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Most Broadway theaters on Sunday kept the lights on, exasperating some performers and theatergoers.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/25/us/winter-storm-snow-ice/broadway-winter-storm-closures</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 16:30:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>False Posts and Altered Images Distort Views of Minnesota Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/minnesota-shooting-false-posts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-misinfo-vkfm/25minneapolis-ice-misinfo-vkfm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across social media, pro-Trump influencers and others muddled the evidence of the killing of a nurse in Minneapolis on Saturday with social media posts that included misdirection and fabricated content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While verified videos and witnesses showed how federal immigration agents tackled and shot Alex Pretti, 37, the posts tried to warp the events, including in ways intended to support the Trump administration’s claims that Mr. Pretti was at fault for his own death. Some posts smeared him or portrayed him as a radical activist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Sortor, a pro-Trump influencer with 1.4 million followers on X, incorrectly identified Mr. Pretti, a U.S. citizen, as an unauthorized immigrant. Jack Posobiec, a Trump loyalist with 3.3 million followers on X, falsely described Mr. Pretti as having “run up on police” and drawn a gun — claims that other users on X corrected in an appended note. Photos of different men — dressed in drag or shirtless at a street festival — were wrongly identified as Mr. Pretti and shared widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Posobiec, Mr. Sortor and the White House did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chaotic scene was captured on video from several angles, yet that shaky footage added to debate online, where it was rapidly interpreted and scrutinized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authenticated footage shows Mr. Pretti, who had no known criminal record and had a permit to carry a concealed firearm, stepping in front of a woman being pepper-sprayed by an agent before being restrained himself. One agent removed Mr. Pretti’s pistol, which he had not drawn, and then another shot him repeatedly in the back. Witnesses corroborated the details in the videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flurry of online activity echoed the broader political narratives that emerged after the shooting. Top Trump administration officials have repeatedly lodged unsubstantiated accusations of domestic terrorism against Mr. Pretti, who was pinned down and had been disarmed when agents opened fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some conservative accounts pushed back against the Trump administration’s narrative. Responding to the Trump administration’s suggestion that Mr. Pretti wanted to “massacre” law enforcement, Tim Pool, a right-wing podcaster, wrote on X that Mr. Pretti “clearly was not intending to massacre ICE.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, many social media users repeated the Trump administration’s representation of events. Others posted images of the scene misleadingly altered with artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One image, for example, was edited to depict Mr. Pretti pointing a gun at an agent, though he was actually holding a phone. Another was altered with Gemini, Google’s A.I. tool, supposedly to enhance and sharpen it to reveal key details about the scene. The altered image included obvious errors, including changes to Mr. Pretti’s face. It also removed a gun from the agent’s hand, fueling more debate on social media over what had happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A widely circulated image on social media was edited using A.I., introducing errors and other changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real image from a video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image edited by A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GENERATED BY A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real image from a video&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image edited with A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GENERATED BY A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/minnesota-shooting-false-posts.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 16:27:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How the Trump Administration Rushed to Judgment in Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting-response.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-response-ltpb/25dc-response-ltpb-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The rush to blame Mr. Pretti and exonerate the immigration agents deviated entirely from the way law enforcement investigations were normally carried out.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-administration-minneapolis-shooting-response.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 16:53:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Killing Prompts Only a Defiant Response From Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/minneapolis-killing-trump-defiant-response.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25dc-trump-gkzp/25dc-trump-gkzp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump said on social media on Sunday that the blame for recent unrest lay, in part, with “Democrat run Sanctuary Cities and States.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/minneapolis-killing-trump-defiant-response.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 16:35:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alex Pretti’s Friends and Family Denounce ‘Sickening Lies’ About His Life</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-01-hmvf/25minneapolis-ice-pretti-01-hmvf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Alex Pretti’s friends and family said he was calm and generous with others.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 22:15:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Blames Democrats for ‘Tragic’ Deaths as Agents Clash With Protesters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-blames-democrats-minneapolis-killings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25minneapolis-ice-trump-social-zhmk/25minneapolis-ice-trump-social-zhmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said in a series of social media posts on Sunday that two American citizens had “tragically” lost their lives amid his administration’s immigration crackdown in Minneapolis, but he blamed Democratic leaders for the deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Democrat run Sanctuary Cities and States are REFUSING to cooperate with ICE, and they are actually encouraging Leftwing Agitators to unlawfully obstruct their operations to arrest the Worst of the Worst People!” he wrote. “By doing this, Democrats are putting Illegal Alien Criminals over Taxpaying, Law-Abiding Citizens, and they have created dangerous circumstances for EVERYONE involved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The posts apparently referred to the deaths this month of Renee Good and Alex Pretti, two U.S. citizens and Minneapolis residents who were shot and killed by federal immigration agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top Trump administration officials immediately and without evidence accused each of the shooting victims of “domestic terrorism” and said they were seeking to harm federal agents. In both cases, video footage from the scene contradicted the Trump administration’s version of events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, in the posts, also called on officials in Democratic-led cities and states to work with immigration authorities by turning over undocumented immigrants who are in state prisons and local jails, and said that Congress should pass legislation to “END Sanctuary Cities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He drew a contrast with Republican-led states, including Texas, Florida and Louisiana, where he said that immigration operations had not been met with the same level of opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The killing of Mr. Pretti on Saturday has prompted a growing number of Republicans to express concerns about what happened and to call for an independent investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti had been legally carrying a gun but was disarmed and pinned on the ground when he was shot, according to videos. Gun rights groups, including the National Rifle Association, have also pushed back on claims by federal officials that Mr. Pretti did not have a Second Amendment right to carry a firearm simply because he was protesting or observing federal agents’ actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also on Sunday, Mr. Trump told The Wall Street Journal that his administration was “reviewing everything” about Mr. Pretti’s death, and that agents would leave the city “at some point,” although he did not give a time frame.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/politics/trump-blames-democrats-minneapolis-killings.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 16:49:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Private Jet With 8 People Aboard Crashes at Maine Airport, F.A.A. Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bangor-maine-airport-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25xp-crash-2/25xp-crash-2-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency crews were responding to the crash of a private jet, with eight people on board, on Sunday evening at Bangor International Airport in Maine, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Aviation Administration said in a statement that the plane, a Bombardier Challenger 600, crashed as it was taking off from the airport at around 7:45 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unclear whether there were any fatalities or injuries among the eight people that the F.A.A. reported were on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. and the National Transportation Safety Board will investigate, the F.A.A. said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airport remained closed on Sunday as emergency crews responded to the crash, Aimee Thibodeau, a spokeswoman for Bangor International Airport, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement did not provide details about the crash, but residents were advised to stay away from the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are unable to provide any additional information at this time,” Ms. Thibodeau said in the statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major winter storm was pummeling the eastern United States on Sunday, forcing the cancellation of thousands of flights nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a developing story.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/bangor-maine-airport-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 18:18:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Storm Dumps a Foot of Snow in About a Third of U.S. States</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/snow-totals.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-snow-totals-vqgt/25winter-storm-snow-totals-vqgt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend’s gigantic snowstorm dumped a foot or more of snow in at least 17 states from New Mexico to New Hampshire, according to preliminary figures from the National Weather Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonito Lake, N.M., received 31 inches, the most in the United States this weekend, the agency said. East of the Mississippi, the highest totals were recorded in western Pennsylvania, where 20 inches had fallen near Clintonville, about 60 miles north of Pittsburgh, as of 8:30 p.m. Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figures are a mix of unofficial and official measurements and are subject to verification, the Weather Service said. As of Sunday night, these were the highest totals in the other 15 states that received at least a foot of snow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crested Butte, Colo.: 23 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New City, N.Y.: 17.6 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastford, Conn.: 18 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Branchville, N.J.: 17 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zanesville, Ohio: 16.9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davis, W.Va.: 16.6 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cranston, R.I.: 16.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newton, N.H.: 16 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holland, Mass.: 16 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Columbus, Ind.: 14.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fredericktown, Mo.: 14.5 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oblong, Ill.: 14.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plaistow, N.H.: 14 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sayre, Okla.: 14 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witts Springs, Ark.: 12 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine other states and the District of Columbia did not quite reach a foot of snow but received substantial amounts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cedar Grove, Va.: 11.8 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarksburg, Md.: 11.8 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarendon, Texas: 10.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hebron, Ky.: 10.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyersburg, Tenn.: 10 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bouplon Corner, Vt.: 10 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olsburg, Kan.: 9.2 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Auburn, Maine: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilmington, Del.: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington, D.C.: 9 inches&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/us/snow-totals.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:00:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ice Storm Leaves Thousands Without Power in a Mississippi County</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-storm-mississippi-oxford.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-mississippi-jbth/25winter-storm-mississippi-jbth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freezing rain from a severe winter storm led to tens of thousands of power outages in a Mississippi county over the weekend, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 20,000 out of about 35,000 homes in Lafayette County had no power on Sunday night as a result of an ice storm and high winds, said Beau Moore, an emergency management officer there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area around Oxford, Miss., was especially hard hit. The National Weather Service received reports of nearly an inch of accumulated ice after freezing rain hit that area late Saturday, said Phil Baker, a meteorologist in the agency’s Memphis office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Robyn Tannehill of Oxford said in an update posted to social media said that trees had fallen under the weight of ice and that power lines were down across the city of 26,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Things went downhill quickly,” Mr. Baker said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperatures were expected to drop to 7 degrees Fahrenheit overnight, he added, and the main concern was the safety of people dealing with the cold without power. Officials opened warming centers to accommodate as many residents without heat as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheriff Joey East of Lafayette County said in a text message on Sunday night that conditions were “probably worse or as bad” as they were after a 1994 storm that left some in the region without power for weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tate Reeves of Mississippi said at a news conference that approximately 47 counties in the state had been impacted by the storm. State officials had requested generators and other supplies from the Federal Emergency Management Agency under a federal emergency declaration for the state signed by President Trump, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The weather is probably going to get worse before it gets better,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 150,000 electricity customers across Mississippi had no power as of early Monday morning, according to the site poweroutage.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Mississippi, which is in Oxford, will be closed on Monday and Tuesday, and local public school districts will be closed all week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Moore said that Lafayette County expected to see more downed trees, and that this could take down additional power lines. The county has hired private companies to help clear the roads, but he estimated that power outages would continue for at least another 48 hours. It could be another week before the county’s main roads are safe enough for travel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alan Blinder contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/ice-storm-mississippi-oxford.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 23:23:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Bad Are A.I. Delusions? We Asked People Treating Them.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq/00inv-therapists-ai-02-gjvq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Julia Sheffield, a psychologist at Vanderbilt University Medical Center in Nashville, is navigating how to treat problems caused or exacerbated by A.I. chatbots.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/chatgpt-delusions-psychosis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Memphis, Federal Crime Task Force Keeps Residents on Edge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm/25nat-memphis-feds-01-pvjm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Cars are often stopped on the side of the road in Memphis, surrounded by clusters of law enforcement agents and a mix of patrol and unmarked cars.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/memphis-crime-federal-agents-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Hobbled the I.R.S. This C.E.O. Now Has to Make It Work.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh/00dc-taxman-01-fcjh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
This year’s tax filing season could be an even more formidable challenge than usual for the Internal Revenue Service and Frank Bisignano, its chief executive.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-irs-taxes-bisignano.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:00:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Voters See a Middle-Class Lifestyle as Drifting Out of Reach, Poll Finds</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost/2026-01-22-national-poll-graphics-affordability-cost-mediumSquareAt3X-v4.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the affordability of education, housing, health care, having a family and retirement are driving economic anxieties, a New York Times/Siena poll found.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/affordability-poll.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:02:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Court Will Hear Minnesota Claims That Immigration Surge is Illegal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-lawsuit-ice-surge-hearing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-minnesota-courtfight-plbw/25nat-minnesota-courtfight-plbw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal agents confronted people in Minneapolis on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/minnesota-lawsuit-ice-surge-hearing.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 01:02:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Crisis of Confidence for ICE and Border Patrol as Clashes Escalate</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-dhs-anger-mctl/26dc-dhs-anger-mctl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Some current and former immigration officials expressed anxieties that the Trump administration was sending agents into situations that were increasingly dangerous both for them and civilians.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/ice-border-patrol-trust.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 03:45:07 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>