<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:29:19 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>After Donations, Trump Administration Revoked Rule Requiring More Nursing Home Staff</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nursing home industry was on a roll last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had just won a 10-year moratorium on a rule initiated during President Joseph R. Biden Jr.’s administration to require increased staffing levels in an effort to reduce neglect among residents, which had led to injuries and deadly infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, some in the industry, warning that the rule would have substantially increased costs, wanted to make it go away permanently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So nursing home executives turned to a tool that has proved successful in getting President Trump’s attention: money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting in early August, the industry began making donations that over the course of weeks would eventually total nearly $4.8 million to MAGA Inc., a super PAC devoted to Mr. Trump and run by his allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that same month, a handful of nursing home executives who had given the biggest donations joined industry lobbyists at Mr. Trump’s golf club in suburban Washington to plead their case, according to campaign finance filings and people familiar with the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over light lunch fare, the contingent “urged the president to formally repeal the harmful minimum staffing mandate, which would have surely forced providers throughout the country to close their doors to new residents — or possibly close their doors altogether,” Bill Weisberg, the founder and chief executive of Saber Healthcare Group, recounted in a text message to The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than one month after the lunch meeting, Trump administration lawyers quietly stopped defending the pending staffing rule in court against challenges from the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete victory came a couple of months after that, when the White House approved a full revocation. The Department of Health and Human Services announced the repeal in a statement that echoed industry talking points, which have emphasized the industry’s difficulty in hiring enough staff, especially in rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves outraged groups representing patients. They argued that the rule was necessary to protect millions of American seniors — a demographic that helped power Mr. Trump’s return to the White House last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Residents are not getting the care they need,” said Lori Smetanka, executive director of the National Consumer Voice for Quality Long-Term Care. “They’re dying from a lack of care.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By one estimate, the staffing rule could have saved 13,000 lives of nursing home residents per year. It set off a tense debate over whether the industry, still recovering from the Covid-19 pandemic, could have found the funds to attract the staff needed to meet the new requirements. Research has suggested that the industry relies on a warren of corporations to conceal profits — profits that could have been used to improve care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the rule was never enacted, it is impossible to say who is right. But even nonpartisan government analysts expected that state and federal governments would have kicked in an additional $22 billion over 10 years to help the industry boost staffing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In written statements to The Times, the White House and H.H.S. defended the repeal. Kush Desai, a White House spokesman, called the move a “common-sense, anti-red tape policy decision,” and said it had nothing to do with any special interest influence campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only special interest guiding President Trump’s decision-making is the best interest of the American people,” Mr. Desai said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no evidence linking the decision to scrap the rule to the nursing home industry’s donations or its lobbying of Mr. Trump. And the rule was already facing uncertain prospects before the August meeting. Mr. Trump had signed a bill in July that included the 10-year delay; behind the scenes, other parts of his administration were preparing to back away from the rule in the days before the lunch meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the industry’s fund-raising for MAGA Inc. highlights the eagerness of corporate America to curry favor with a president who has repeatedly used the levers of government to reward donors and allies — and to punish critics. Mr. Trump has remained keenly interested in fund-raising, keeping close tabs on who has donated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies that are heavily regulated by the government or reliant on it for contracts have donated millions to groups and causes favored by Mr. Trump since his return to the White House, while hiring lobbyists and consultants in his orbit. Corporate donors have received remarkable access to plead their cases directly to the president of the United States, to a degree seldom seen with other modern administrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fund-raising for super PACs is something of a departure for well-established national trade groups that seek support from both parties, like the American Health Care Association, which has represented the nursing home industry’s interests in Washington for more than 75 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The association’s president and chief executive attended the lunch meeting alongside Brian Ballard, a top Trump fund-raiser whose lobbying firm represents the association and also registered to lobby for Mr. Weisberg’s company six weeks after the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Reeves, a spokeswoman for the American Health Care Association, said in a statement that the group “appreciated the opportunity to speak with the president directly and foster an open dialogue with the administration.” But she emphasized the association’s nonpartisanship and denied that the lunch focused on either the staffing rule or possible Medicaid cuts — another threat that Mr. Weisberg, who is on the association’s board, said was discussed at the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Reeves said “our meeting with the president was primarily about how we could focus on more meaningful ways to advance quality and prepare for the care needs of our nation’s aging population.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, studies have linked insufficient staffing levels to poor care in the nation’s 15,000 nursing homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspection reports have repeatedly faulted facilities for leaving residents lying in their own feces, suffering severe bedsores and falls, contracting infections or ending up in a hospital for preventable reasons. Some nursing homes overuse psychotropic medications to pacify residents because they do not have enough workers to attend to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tinamarie Scicchitano said she saw the effects of understaffing firsthand when her mother, Madeline Tardiolo, developed a pressure wound in 2022 while living her final days at an Arizona nursing home, a scenario that experts say is often the result of having too few staff members to regularly reposition immobilized patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Scicchitano said it was an indignity for her mother, who had filled their home with warm cookies and family friends, but never lost the sharp wit she got growing up in prewar Brooklyn. The family has sued over Ms. Tardiolo’s 2022 death in the nursing home, appending a gruesome photo of the black wound that spread across her back and claiming that neglect and insufficient staffing levels contributed to her death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lawsuit, filed in 2023, is ongoing. The Ensign Group, the publicly traded nursing home chain that owns the facility, did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Scicchitano said the repeal of the staffing rule boded poorly for other families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m deeply concerned that they will not staff these facilities appropriately because the patients are suffering, and my mom is living proof of what had happened,” Ms. Scicchitano said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ensign Group reported $3 billion in revenue in 2022 — an increase of more than 15 percent from the previous year. Barry Port, the company’s chief executive, emerged as a leading opponent of the staffing rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his State of the Union address in 2022, Mr. Biden criticized declining quality and increasing costs at nursing homes. “That ends on my watch,” Mr. Biden said, promising to “make sure your loved ones get the care they deserve and that they expect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Medicare officials unveiled a proposal requiring facilities to have enough staff members to provide at least three and a half hours of care to each patient each day. There was also a new requirement for a registered nurse to be on-site at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patients’ rights groups pushed to raise the staffing minimum, eventually citing a 2024 report from a nonprofit group that found that more than 60 percent of nursing home profits were hidden in a maze of transactions among related corporations. The report, by the National Bureau of Economic Research, showed that if those funds were spent on staff, nearly 76 percent of facilities could meet the new standard for 24-hour registered nurse coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Elizabeth Warren, Democrat of Massachusetts, wrote a letter pressing the Ensign Group on its opposition to the rule even as it offered multimillion-dollar executive pay and dividends to shareholders. She cited the nonprofit’s report as “evidence that nursing homes can afford to meet higher staffing standards, but are simply unwilling to do so.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, R. Tamara Konetzka, a University of Chicago economist who studies long-term care, said pressing the staffing rule would have been a high-stakes way to test the notion that nursing homes could find the money, if it resulted in facilities accepting fewer patients or closing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To me, that’s a really dangerous game,” said Dr. Konetzka, whose research has been supported by government grants under Democratic and Republican administrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American Health Care Association, which counts Mr. Port and Mr. Weisberg among the members on its board of governors, claimed that the proposal established “impossible standards” that 95 percent of nursing homes did not meet. The association warned that the cost of complying could put some nursing homes out of business and estimated that it could displace as many as 290,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Biden administration finalized the rule in April 2024, the association sued to block its implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some in the industry came to see Mr. Trump’s campaign as their best hope. His first administration had pushed to remove what he described as burdensome regulations on health care providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within six weeks of the Biden administration’s finalizing the staffing rule, Mr. Weisberg and several other nursing home executives donated as much as $250,000 each to Mr. Trump’s campaign, according to campaign finance filings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Weisberg told The Times this month that “the Biden administration spent four years doing its best to attack us, vilify us and regulate us into nonexistence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industry had reason for optimism when, during his confirmation hearing to be health secretary last January, Robert F. Kennedy Jr. echoed the industry’s claim that the rule was not feasible given the industry’s challenges finding enough staff. Though its intent was “noble,” he said, in practice it would be a “disaster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the administration continued defending the proposed rule in court, including taking steps to appeal rulings that were going in favor of the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Port called the trade group’s lobbying “enormously efficient and effective” during an earnings call in April. “I personally met with leadership in both the House and the Senate,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June, the association mobilized about 750 nursing home staff members to converge on Washington and attend about 450 meetings with lawmakers to tell them about the importance of Medicaid funding for long-term care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocacy seemed to pay dividends in July, when Mr. Trump signed into law the spending bill that included the 10-year moratorium on the staffing rule and exempted nursing homes from a Medicaid cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the victory, the industry continued courting Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 40 corporate entities associated with nursing homes across the country gave to MAGA Inc. in August through mid-September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the donations were arriving and the lunch meeting approached, the Trump administration was taking steps to scrap the rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five days before the meeting, a Trump appointee at the Justice Department recommended the administration drop its legal defense of the rule in an internal email that was described to The Times. The day before the meeting, Medicare officials inside of H.H.S., who were also lobbied by the industry, sent a request to the White House to formally repeal the rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lunch meeting was attended by the executives whose companies made the largest donations to MAGA Inc., including $750,000 each from a subsidiary of the Ensign Group (on whose behalf Mr. Port attended), a company associated with Saber Healthcare (Mr. Weisberg attended) and PruittHealth Corporation, which owns nursing homes in the Southeast and sent an executive to the meeting. Another $600,000 came from entities associated with the Alabama-based nursing home company NHS Management; its chief executive, Norman Estes, also attended the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Estes declined to comment. Mr. Port and his company did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PruittHealth said in a statement that “we fully support the Trump administration and all policymakers who advocate for the well-being of our patients and caregivers.” It added that it has highlighted “work force shortages and rising patient acuity” to policymakers, and said that one meeting “does not determine federal policy, nor does it reflect the full scope of our longstanding advocacy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the meeting, Mr. Trump was accompanied by his lead fund-raiser, Meredith O’Rourke, who raises money for MAGA Inc. and who regularly briefs the president about who has donated to the various groups and projects he favors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Weisberg said they were eager to lobby the president against cuts to Medicaid reimbursements and the staffing rule, indicating that the combination could have “crippled our ability to provide care to the country’s aging population.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They thanked Mr. Trump for the Medicaid carve-out in the tax and spending bill signed into law the month before, according to Mr. Weisberg, and urged him to repeal the staffing rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump left the group with the impression that he understood and was sympathetic to their concerns, Mr. Weisberg suggested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He wants to see our industry survive as he values the population we serve,” Mr. Weisberg said, indicating that Mr. Trump was more knowledgeable and thoughtful than he might appear from afar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About a month after the lunch meeting, the Justice Department dropped its effort to appeal rulings favoring the industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chad Gilmartin, a Justice Department spokesman, said in a statement that the decision came after consultation with Medicare officials and “had absolutely nothing to do with the fund-raiser.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily G. Hilliard, a spokeswoman for the health department, said in a statement that the rule “disproportionally burdened facilities, especially those serving rural and tribal communities and jeopardized patient’s access to care.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next month, Clifton J. Porter II, the industry association’s president and chief executive, took a victory lap when the nursing home industry convened in Las Vegas for an annual convention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I forget the artist, but I like the song, ‘All we do is win, win, win no matter what,’” he said on a podcast during the convention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month later, the White House finalized the repeal, putting the old rules back in place. These require a registered nurse to be on-site for at least eight hours per day and for staffing to be sufficient to meet patients’ needs without requiring minimum numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Kennedy announced the move at a cabinet meeting in early December, he claimed that the rule was going to “destroy the nursing home industry” in rural and Native American communities. By revoking it, he boasted, the Trump administration had saved the federal government $25 billion, though a spokeswoman from a federal budget office told The Times that the figure was $22 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those are some of the things that we’re doing because of your leadership, President Trump,” Mr. Kennedy said. “Thank you so much, and Merry Christmas to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:23:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Administration Social Media Posts Echo White Supremacist Messaging</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-altright-bczq/26nat-altright-bczq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The posts have referred to neo-Nazi literature, ethnic cleansing and QAnon conspiracies, mused about deporting nearly a third of the U.S. population, and promoted lyrics from an anthem bellowed by the far-right militants of the Proud Boys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their authors are not on society’s fringe. They are in the offices of the White House and the departments of Homeland Security and Labor, using official government accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some people, the administration’s posts sound patriotic. Others might sense at most a faint dog whistle to extremists. Some posts may just look odd. But those well-versed in the abstruse codes of right-wing extremism hear klaxons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, the White House and the Department of Homeland Security jointly posted a recruitment ad for Immigration and Customs Enforcement on Instagram, Facebook and X, overlaid with the words “WE’LL HAVE OUR HOME AGAIN.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s also the name of a song, written by members of a self-described “pro-White fraternal order,” that has been embraced by the Proud Boys and other white-nationalist groups. Hundreds of explicitly neo-Nazi and white-supremacist accounts have shared the song on Telegram, an encrypted messaging app, since 2020. The white supremacist who killed three Black people at a Jacksonville, Fla., dollar store in 2023 included lyrics from the song in his writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are two types of people to whom these messages will quickly look familiar,” Oren Segal, a vice president for counterextremism at the Anti-Defamation League, said of the panoply of postings, “white supremacists, and those who study white supremacists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Homeland Security spokeswoman, Tricia McLaughlin, said that if the ICE recruiting post were actually about the song, it “would be a problem” and “morally repugnant.” But, she said, the post had no relation to the white-supremacist anthem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are plenty of references to those words in books and poems,” she said, adding that she was “in charge of everything” posted on the department’s social media accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when the post was opened on Instagram’s mobile app, audio from the chorus of the song played in the background. After a reporter pointed this out, Ms. McLaughlin said The Times was participating in a left-wing conspiracy theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m telling you it’s not there,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than 40 minutes after the interview on Thursday, the Instagram post — including audio from the song — disappeared from social media. Posts on X and Facebook, which did not include an audio component, are still visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was The Times, Ms. McLaughlin said, that was “mainstreaming racism” by tying the agency’s post to the white nationalist anthem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Hanania, a political scientist who once wrote for white-nationalist publications under a pseudonym before moderating his views, said such accusations were part of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They do everything up to the line; it’s kind of clever,” he said. “‘We’ll Have Our Home Again’ is a white-nationalist song.” He added that to his knowledge, no other groups would use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past month, government agencies have made dozens more social-media posts that include iconography associated with far-right extremist groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As President Trump escalated his campaign to seize control of Greenland this month, the White House’s X account posted an image of a crossroads, with a sun-drenched White House on the left and Russia and China to the right. The caption read, “Which way, Greenland man?” Last year, an ICE recruitment post on Homeland Security’s X account asked, “Which way, American man?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slogans echo the title of a 1978 book — “Which Way Western Man?” — that white-supremacist groups treat “as foundational,” said Robert Futrell, a sociologist at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas. The book claims that Jewish people are plotting to destroy Western civilization, that Adolf Hitler was right and that violence against Jews is justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, the Labor Department posted a noir-style image with the words “TRUST THE PLAN.” That’s also a central catchphrase of QAnon, an internet conspiracy theory that falsely claims the world is run by a cabal of Satan-worshiping pedophiles, and that Mr. Trump has been chosen to sunder it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On New Year’s Eve, the White House’s X account posted a photo of Mr. Trump alongside the word “remigration.” That is a decades-old European concept centered on the expulsion of nonwhite people and immigrants deemed “unassimilated,” said Wendy Via, co-founder of the Global Project Against Hate and Extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tens of thousands of Germans protested the concept two years ago after the country’s far-right Alternative für Deutschland party secretly met with neo-Nazis to discuss plans to implement it. (More than a dozen AfD politicians have reposted Mr. Trump’s “remigration” photo on X.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this month, the Labor Department posted a video captioned “One Homeland. One People. One Heritage.” That phrase resembled a German slogan used by Nazis during World War II, “Ein Volk, Ein Reich, Ein Führer,” or “One People, One Realm, One Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Labor did not respond to multiple requests for comment, but Abigail Jackson, a White House spokeswoman, dismissed any connections between the government posts and extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It seems that the mainstream media has become a meme of their own: the deranged leftist who claims everything they dislike must be Nazi propaganda,” she said, adding, “Get a grip.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who study the online right said one or two posts might be coincidental. But “when you add it all together,” said William Braniff, director of the Polarization and Extremism Research and Innovation Lab at American University, “it’s much harder to dismiss.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other experts were equally certain the apparent allusions were not an accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people used to be in the dark corners of the internet,” said Jessie Daniels, a sociologist at Hunter College who has studied online extremism for 30 years. “Now, they are holding public office.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the draw of the posts could be their potentially secret codes and numerological clues, especially in the recruitment images. They appear to be an appeal to “a very specific segment” of Americans, young men who live online and are disaffected by what they see as unwanted changes in American life, said Peter Simi, a Chapman University sociologist who studies extremist groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shirin Sinnar, a Stanford law professor who studies the legal treatment of political violence, said “they are plainly trying to recruit a segment of the population that’s moved by this rhetoric.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, Mr. Trump and his campaign have dealt with and rejected accusations that officials in the Trump inner circle were surreptitiously appealing to racists and antisemites. A Twitter post by the candidate in 2016 depicting Hillary Clinton beside a Jewish star, before piles of money, had previously appeared on a message board known for antisemitism and white supremacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s final campaign commercial that year featured grainy images of George Soros, the liberal American financier; Janet L. Yellen, then the chairwoman of the Federal Reserve; and Lloyd C. Blankfein, then the chairman of Goldman Sachs — all of them Jewish — as Mr. Trump warned darkly about the “global special interests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s just a straight line between these ideas and the modern Trump administration,” Mr. Hanania said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration is “mobilizing these people and having them flood Twitter and create this environment that they’re winning,” he said. “The fact that the media and liberals react so strongly to this is kind of a badge of honor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott Greer, a right-wing podcaster and writer who considers himself part of the “online right” that these posts are ostensibly targeting, is not so sure of the administration’s motivation. Some on the Internet-obsessed right think the posts “are meant to bamboozle them into liking Trump,” he said. For his part, he added, even though some of the posts go “too far with what the normal, not-so-online MAGA base may be for,” he now thinks they reflect the broader trend of politicians “taking this more irreverent tone and using memes from the right and left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We accept it as more a normal part of politics,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Republican leaders vehemently denounce antisemitism, and the Trump administration has put pressure on universities and other parts of American society to protect Jews from hate speech and attacks. But in recent months, some members of the party have openly wrestled with whether to reject some Trump supporters who have made antisemitic, bigoted or extremist remarks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked in December whether far-right extremists and conspiracy theorists should be embraced as part of the Trump coalition, Vice President JD Vance declined to rule them out. In contrast, Mr. Trump said of antisemites in an interview this month with The Times, “I think we don’t need them,” emphasizing, “I think we don’t like them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, most of the social media posts remain, despite the scrutiny over possible allusions to extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read by Evan Gorelick&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audio produced by Adrienne Hurst.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:24:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An American Street</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/us/nat-minn-oneimage-promo/nat-minn-oneimage-promo-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In One Image An American Street By David Guttenfelder and Thomas Gibbons-Neff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In south Minneapolis, snow and ice still blanketed Nicollet Avenue when federal agents fanned out and started tackling heckling protesters on Saturday, about a block away from where Alex Pretti was shot and killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Shame!” the protesters yelled. “Why did you murder another one of our neighbors?” they said. The agents charged, launching gas canisters, yelling at the protesters. “Get back!” “Get out of the street!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agents grabbed a protester who had only a painter’s mask covering his mouth and little else to protect himself from the gas. He gasped, choking for air as he was cuffed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standing in front of him was a federal agent armed with a grenade launcher, used here for launching tear gas or smoke. The agent also carried a Glock handgun with two spare magazines, a stun gun and a spare magazine for an AR-15-style rifle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detritus left behind tells the story of deep-winter protests in subzero weather: a warm hat, a shirt, Kirkland chewy bars and hand warmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nestled in the snow were two grenades for tear gas and smoke. Without traditional policing tactics, federal agents rely on these tools to push back protesters and onlookers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another federal agent is seen with his grenade launcher almost at his shoulder. His equipment is not uniform. His outfit — including the patch on his helmet, Nike shoes and his vest’s camouflage pattern — mirrors a distinct look promoted by military influencers selling products to newer generations eager to define themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supported by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In One Image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By David Guttenfelder and Thomas Gibbons-Neff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the Minneapolis area appears normal. There are no signs of unrest. But an aggressive immigration crackdown by heavily armed federal agents has led to clashes with a population that largely rejects their presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two centuries ago, Nicollet Avenue was a military route, connecting St. Anthony Falls to Fort Snelling. Over the weekend, it became the stage for a violent confrontation between protesters and the government’s military-like law enforcement operation in the wake of the killing of Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old Minneapolis resident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vigil for Mr. Pretti was held on Saturday night about a block from where this photograph was taken. Nicollet Avenue is quiet now, but the city remains in a defensive crouch, unsure where the next battle will erupt.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:11:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Trump Promotes Economy in Iowa, Many Residents Feel Pain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj/27dc-iowa-econ-ctqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump headed to Iowa on Tuesday to once again try to convince Americans that he is focused on “affordability.” He had some explaining to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa, a state whose economy is heavily reliant on farming, has been struggling under the weight of Mr. Trump’s economic policies, particularly his approach to trade. The president’s barrage of tariffs last year increased the cost of machinery and materials that many Iowan farmers rely on. The price of the metal bins used to store crops soared, along with the cost of tractors as the president’s tariffs took hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump hit China with tariffs, Beijing swiftly retaliated by halting purchases of American farm products, a move that cut off Iowa soybean exporters from their biggest buyer. That put the squeeze on the entire state’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking about the economy at an event in Clive, Iowa, on Tuesday, Mr. Trump defended his trade policies and told supporters that he was saving farmers money by slashing burdensome environmental regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m standing up for the workers and the farmers of our country like no other president has ever,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president added that the trade deals that he has reached have opened up international markets to American farmers, ranchers and agricultural producers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re going to see it starting to kick in now for the farmers,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many, however, the intended benefits of Mr. Trump’s policies are not kicking in soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a dire time for American farmers, particularly the Midwest soybean and corn farmers,” said Kirk Leeds, the chief executive of the Iowa Soybean Association. “The chaos, the uncertainty — right now we have so many unknowns that there’s not a lot of clarity about where we’re going.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iowa is of particular importance to Mr. Trump. The state helped propel his political career a decade ago, when he had a strong showing in the 2016 Republican caucuses. He won the state in all three of his general election campaigns. Perhaps more important to Mr. Trump now is that the state could prove pivotal in this year’s midterm elections, as Republicans try to retain their majority. Senator Joni Ernst, Republican of Iowa, is retiring, and the race to replace her is expected to be close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Chuck Grassley, the veteran Iowa Republican who has been critical of Mr. Trump’s tariffs, welcomed the president’s visit this week and said he would continue to work with the Trump administration to improve affordability for Iowans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump’s trade wars have in many respects been a drag on the state, which for years has lagged behind the rest of the country in economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has long been a big buyer of U.S. soybeans and other crops that are grown in Iowa. That changed last year after Mr. Trump increased tariffs on imports from China, triggering a monthslong tit-for-tat trade fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite negotiations and temporary traded truces, China continued to use farm purchases as leverage and Beijing’s refusal to buy American agricultural products for most of 2025 dealt a blow to Iowa’s soybean industry, one of the largest in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and Xi Jinping, the Chinese leader, eventually agreed in late October to a one-year truce that ended China’s boycott of farm products, including millions of tons of soybeans. The Trump administration also unveiled a $12 billion aid package for farmers, but for many farmers the relief was insufficient and too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re losing money on every bushel we produce on our two main things that we grow,” said Aaron Lehman, the president of the Iowa Farmers Union, referring to corn and soybeans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administration officials have said that China fulfilled its initial commitment to Mr. Trump to buy 12 million metric tons of soybeans. It has also pledged to purchase 25 million metric tons per year for the next three years. The 25 million tons were in line with the 25 million to 30 million it had purchased in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said last week that he encouraged his Chinese counterpart to buy additional soybeans during a meeting on the sidelines of the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crop receipts in Iowa were on track to fall 4 percent, or $666 million, in 2025 from last year and they are projected to hold steady this year, according to a report published last October by the Rural &amp; Farm Finance Policy Analysis Center. There were 18 farm bankruptcies in the state through last October, the highest total since 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America’s rural economies have been struggling in recent years, and Iowa is no exception. Since 2021, Iowa’s economy has grown at an annual rate of about 1 percent while the United States has grown at an average annual rate of 2.5 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since retaking the White House last year, Mr. Trump and his advisers have said that the administration’s policies will usher in a new “golden age” for America. Mr. Lehman said such suggestions feel out of touch to Iowa farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The policy leaders are not understanding the situation on the ground,” Mr. Lehman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Trump administration policies have also created challenges over the last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Budget cuts to the Department of Agriculture and the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program, which buys food from American farmers, have been hard on Iowa’s agriculture sector, Mr. Lehman added. The lapse of Affordable Care Act subsidies is leading to higher health care costs. And immigration restrictions have made it harder for farmers to find workers in a state where the population has been shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble in the farm economy has spread to other sectors in Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Deere, the agricultural machinery company, said last September that it would cut more than 140 jobs at two plants in Iowa because of decreased demand for equipment. Case New Holland, a construction equipment manufacturer, said this week that it was cutting about 200 jobs at a plant in Burlington. Overall, the state lost 1,300 manufacturing jobs in 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Orazem, an economist at Iowa State University, noted that the state’s manufacturing industries are closely tied to how farmers are faring. He said that forecasts for 2026 remain murky because of uncertainty over trade policy and whether government support for farmers will continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Restrictions on trade makes your market less lucrative,” Mr. Orazem said. “You’re getting squeezed on the demand side and getting squeezed on the supply side. That doesn’t bode well for firm profit.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:49:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Safety Board Blames F.A.A. For Multiple Failures in D.C. Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Transportation Safety Board determined that the Federal Aviation Administration had approved dangerous flight routes that allowed an Army helicopter to fly into the path of a passenger jet over the Potomac River on Jan. 29, 2025, to calamitous results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a meeting on Tuesday, the investigating board also castigated the agency for not doing enough to respond to warnings about longtime risks to safety and found a complacent culture within the air traffic control tower at Ronald Reagan National Airport that relied too heavily on pilots in the airspace being able to see and steer clear of each others’ aircraft, a practice called visual separation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also determined that insufficient warnings from the air traffic controller to the pilots of the Army Black Hawk helicopter and an American Airlines passenger jet involved in the crash, and altimeters that, unbeknown to the helicopter pilots, habitually gave faulty readings of altitude, also contributed to the tragic crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long-awaited determination, which the board approved unanimously, is the culmination of a yearlong investigation that put the F.A.A. and Army under a microscope, as the board scrutinized how officials missed — or outright dismissed — risks that ultimately led to the collision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s one failure after another,” Jennifer Homendy, the board chair, told reporters during a break in the proceedings, adding: “This was 100 percent preventable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. focused the brunt of its ire on the F.A.A., determining that the route the Army Black Hawk helicopter flew along the Potomac River and the landing path of American Airlines Flight 5342 were never designed to ensure separation between aircraft — and that the dangers posed by the crisscrossing paths were never adequately reviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also determined that the F.A.A. ignored repeated appeals from controllers to reduce National Airport’s traffic, even as its main runway became the single busiest in the United States. That forced controllers to routinely divert planes to a backup runway, as they did with the American Airlines flight that night, to manage congestion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The F.A.A. values and appreciates the N.T.S.B’s expertise and input,” said Hannah Walden, a spokeswoman for the F.A.A., in a statement. The agency has worked with the N.T.S.B. throughout the investigation, she added, “acted immediately” to put into place its initial safety recommendations and “will carefully consider” the additional recommendations it made Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavy flight traffic, investigators said, routinely led controllers at the airport to direct incoming planes to the backup runway, Runway 33, putting them in proximity with helicopters. It also led controllers to rely too much on pilots themselves to “see and avoid” each other, investigators determined, noting that the practice “introduced unacceptable risk” to the airspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N.T.S.B. staff members cited a culture within the F.A.A. that discouraged raising concerns about safety, describing how the agency installed, but never activated, a traffic management system that could have helped controllers handle traffic better on busy nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board also concluded that the decision to put one controller in charge of both helicopter and airplane traffic on the night of the crash was not because of insufficient staffing in the tower — and that the duties should have been separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notably, the board did not fault the pilots of either aircraft for failing to avoid each other. It did, however, determine that the pilots of the helicopter requested visual separation too early, and probably never had the correct commercial jet in their sights. The pilots of the jet, the board added, were too busy preparing for landing to note the approach of the helicopter, which the air traffic controller had not warned them about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of striking animated visual simulations, investigators strongly suggested that the instructor pilot in the helicopter, who was evaluating a less experienced pilot on a training flight, lost sight of the passenger jet as the two aircraft approached each other. The jet came back into his view only a second or two before impact, the video indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the N.T.S.B. determined that had the controller on duty noted the danger and explicitly warned pilots that they were at risk of colliding, they likely would have had time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were not adequately prepared to do the jobs they were assigned to do,” said Brian Soper, who leads the N.T.S.B.’s air traffic control investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators also said that if either aircraft had been equipped with real-time tracking gear known as ADS-B In, the pilots might have been alerted nearly a minute before the collision of the danger, giving them ample time to avoid each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the board also found that the helicopter pilots’ reliance on other equipment contributed significantly to the crash. Investigators concluded that the pilots of the Army helicopter probably thought they were flying about 100 feet lower than their actual altitude because of idiosyncrasies in the readings of altimeters on the Black Hawks that the Army knew about but never informed aviators of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They wouldn’t know it,” said Capt. Van McKenny, a helicopter investigator with the N.T.S.B. “It’s not in their manual, it’s not in the training.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Army also never realized that the barometric altimeters in their helicopters were giving pilots a false sense of their flying height because the service didn’t routinely collect the relevant data. Instead, the Army relied on a voluntary reporting system that was seldom used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A., investigators said, had plenty of data about the dangers to the Washington airspace, however, that the agency simply ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. questioned why on multiple occasions, the F.A.A. relaxed the restrictions on when a single controller could be assigned to manage helicopter and airplane traffic simultaneously, creating a culture of complacency that things would work out, even when controllers became overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the board excoriated the F.A.A. for downgrading National Airport’s facility rating in 2018, a measure that determines the experience level required for controllers to work there. That change, and its commensurate pay cut, made it more difficult for the tower to attract experienced personnel capable of handling Washington’s busy airspace, the N.T.S.B. staff said, especially given the city’s high cost of living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This tower is essentially treated as a training facility,” Ms. Homendy said. “It is a pass-through, they can’t attract people here, which is a problem.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, the N.T.S.B. issued over 70 findings about the midair collision, and approved dozens of recommendations aimed at preventing similar crashes. The Trump administration and Congress will determine whether to put them into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.A.A. has already limited what aircraft can fly through the airspace surrounding National Airport. It has also reconfigured helicopter routes in the area, in response to urgent recommendations that the N.T.S.B. issued last March, and it rolled out a redesign plan it says will streamline safety monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency also has been making significant investments to modernize the country’s aging air traffic control system. A funding bill pending before the Senate would pump billions more dollars into the F.A.A. to help with hiring more controllers, but the legislation could falter amid a political standoff over funding for immigration enforcement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The N.T.S.B. plans to publish a full report detailing the findings, causes and recommendations stemming from the crash in the weeks after Tuesday’s meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:25:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Shocked Nation Watches Minneapolis Killings: ‘Something Needs to Change’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wintry whiteout that swept across half the United States over the weekend could not erase what the country had just seen unfold in Minneapolis. No amount of snow could block out the images: furious protesters clashing with masked officers, clouds of tear gas wafting through neighborhoods — and for the second time in three weeks, video of an American citizen being shot dead by a federal agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the second time in three weeks, the Trump administration’s account of a deadly shooting contradicted what many in the country believe they saw. Federal officials described both victims as “domestic terrorists” intent on harming federal agents; critics of the administration, and many others, said such a description was belied by the video evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scenes from the violent unrest in Minneapolis played on a loop throughout the weekend, overshadowing the extreme weather and two N.F.L. playoff games. The images conveyed the unmistakable sense of consequence, of a watershed moment, prompting reflections about what the nation stands for, and where it is heading. Minneapolis seemed close, no matter where one lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Georgia, a high school teacher anticipated the questions his students would ask about the latest shooting death. In Indiana, broadcasts of the violence dampened a 97th birthday celebration. In Iowa, a married couple, on an outing with their autistic son, disagreed about what had happened, while in Wisconsin, a supporter of President Trump marveled at what she considered the stupidity of some protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in Rhode Island, a snowbound student at Brown University cried when he saw the video from Saturday of immigration officers pepper-spraying Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old registered nurse, wrestling him to the cold Minneapolis ground, and shooting him to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t get any sleep last night,” the student, Jack DiPrimio, 23, said on Sunday. “The video was just replaying over and over again in my head.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend’s turn of events in Minnesota began with a campaign promise. Since returning to office a year ago, President Trump has sought to make good on his vow to rid the country of undocumented immigrants he describes as criminals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agents for U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement have carried out sweeps in a succession of Democratic-controlled cities, all the while being dogged by protesters. Critics have denounced the operations as cruel, often unconstitutional, fraught with mistaken or improper detentions — even un-American.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, ICE turned to the Minneapolis-St. Paul area with a focus on its large Somali community. The Trump administration has blamed an ongoing fraud scandal in Minnesota, involving billions of dollars in federal funding, on the state’s Somali immigrants, whom Mr. Trump demonized as “garbage” in comments widely denounced as bigoted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, on Jan. 7, an ICE agent fired three times into an S.U.V. as it was pulling away from a confrontation, killing the 37-year-old driver, Renee Good. Federal officials have maintained that the agent acted in self-defense, while state and local officials have disputed that account of the fatal moment, which was filmed from several angles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions continued to escalate all month, with furious protests, arrests and the shooting and wounding of a Venezuelan man by an immigration officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then: Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pretti, a nurse at a Veterans Affairs hospital with no criminal record, was using his cellphone to record a protest when he stepped between a woman and an immigration agent who was pepper spraying her. As he, too, was hit with pepper spray, several agents threw him to the ground and, in the ensuing scrum, saw that he had a gun, which he never drew and was legally carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They opened fire, in a brutal scene that was witnessed, recorded and quickly shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the inclement weather brought much of the country to a standstill, many people could not help but see the disturbing video, hear the Trump administration’s rushed justifications — including the unsubstantiated claim by Gregory Bovino, a senior Border Patrol official, that Mr. Pretti had been out to “massacre law enforcement” — and ruminate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Crown Point, Ind., more than a dozen family members gathered Saturday night to celebrate the 97th birthday of Jerry Weber. But they found themselves glued to the television and the disturbing reports from Minnesota, including another shooting death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s kind of like living in your own world and living in a second world at the same time,” said Mr. Weber’s son, Gerry Weber, a civil rights attorney. “We drove through a snowstorm to get to our family’s house and celebrate dad’s birthday, and then we’re back to the television, watching America fall apart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Weber had flown in from the Atlanta area, where Ray Brown, 40, who teaches advanced-placement U.S. history at Northview High School, in Johns Creek, Ga., was also trying to process what was happening in Minnesota — and how he would respond to questions from his students about the constitutionality, and propriety, of the government’s actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The teacher said that he tries to give his students, many of whom are from immigrant families, the space to question why certain federal departments exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m going to have to present a very diplomatic view,” Mr. Brown said. “Which is revolting to hear myself say, because I think that taking a life is wrong, no matter what.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many frozen corners, people expressed admiration for the protesters in Minneapolis, as well as a resolve to follow their lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In south-central Pennsylvania, Brandie Kessler, a communications professional, spent Saturday night at the home of her in-laws just outside of Harrisburg. After arriving, she made a mordant comment to her mother-in-law as they sat in the living room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I said, kind of sarcastically, ‘I guess I need to prepare my own obituary in case there’s something that happens at a demonstration here,’” Ms. Kessler, 42, recalled. “In case I go out to peacefully protest — which I am completely entitled to do — and I’m gunned down.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday morning, with snow blanketing the rolling landscape outside, Ms. Kessler felt frustrated, even disoriented, by what was happening, and not just in Minnesota. The polarization. The violence. The deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don't know everything there is to know about what happened in Minneapolis,” Ms. Kessler said, her voice breaking. “But I know what I saw. I don’t know how someone could watch the same thing and say everything is OK.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sandi Lipinski, a sales director in Waukesha, Wis., was not suggesting that everything was OK, but after going to church and running a few errands on Sunday, she shared a decidedly different view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said she supported President Trump’s efforts to detain and deport undocumented immigrants. And she expressed little sympathy for protesters who are following ICE agents around and sometimes taunting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They are going to carry guns and use cars as weapons, then they run the risk of getting killed,” Ms. Lipinski, 62, said. “That’s just stupidity. They should stay home or go to work or go to school and stay out of the street and let everybody do their own jobs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other stunning developments unfolded last week, including the Trump administration’s resolve to acquire Greenland. But the crisis in Minnesota seemed to dominate the nation’s collective thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Waterville, Maine, Nancy Smith sat behind the counter of her store, Smitty’s Book Cellar, and thought about Minnesota — and the similar ICE operation that started last week in her own state. “I don’t want the same things to happen here,” Ms. Smith, 55, said. “I don’t want the same things to happen anywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Atlanta, Jamie Christy, a 30-year-old lawyer who heads her neighborhood’s Young Republican chapter, did not see the video of Mr. Pretti’s shooting until taking a lunch break on Sunday. Soon she was replaying it again and again, at full and partial speed, to see what could have necessitated the use of deadly force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s completely unjustified,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at an upscale mall in West Des Moines, Iowa, where the temperature was in the single digits, a married couple, Jennifer Stitz and Don Caves, finished their food-court meal on Sunday evening while trying to find common ground on Minnesota and the country. Mr. Caves’s 18-year-old son, Carsten, sat nearby, playing a game on a tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Caves, a high school Bible teacher, and Ms. Stitz, an accountant, both voted for Mr. Trump in 2024. But as they discussed the shooting deaths in Minneapolis, their viewpoints diverged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Caves, 62, said that the shootings were “absolutely terrible,” but he maintained that Ms. Good and Mr. Pretti had put themselves in harm’s way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just don’t understand why people would interfere in other people doing their job, especially law enforcement,” Mr. Caves said. “Get out of their way. They’ve got guns.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he supported peaceful protest, but added: "Don’t get in the way between point A and point B, the good guys going and getting the bad guys. And that’s the situation that our officers have been facing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Stitz, 54, listened quietly — and then disagreed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said she was troubled by both deaths in Minneapolis. Mr. Pretti, she said, had “every right” to carry a gun, and ICE agents could have simply let Ms. Good drive away and then trace her through her license plate. Both victims, she said, had the right to protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not China or a communist country where, you know, you get killed for protesting,” Ms. Stitz said. She added: “Something needs to change, is what I feel.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mall was closing. The couple gathered up their leftover food and, with Mr. Caves’s son, headed out into the night’s unforgiving cold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David C. Adams contributed reporting from Miami; Curt Anderson from St. Petersburg, Fla., Murray Carpenter from Belfast, Maine; Sydney Cromwell from Waterville, Maine; Kristi Eaton from Tulsa, Abigail Geiger from Carlisle, Pa.; Sean Keenan from Atlanta; Ann Hinga Klein from West Des Moines, Iowa; Tom Li from Providence; Eduardo Medina from Durham, N.C.; Alessandro Marazzi Sassoon from Atlanta; Jamie McGee from Nashville and Dan Simmons from Milwaukee.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:46:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alexander Vindman, of Trump Impeachment Fame, Runs for Senate in Florida</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexander S. Vindman, a retired Army lieutenant colonel who was a top witness in President Trump’s first impeachment trial, announced on Tuesday that he was running for Senate in Mr. Trump’s adopted home state of Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vindman brings fresh star power to the race as he seeks the Democratic nomination to run against Senator Ashley Moody, a Republican who was appointed to replace Marco Rubio after he became secretary of state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In announcing his bid, Mr. Vindman also became one of the first Democrats to release a campaign video with footage of the recent shooting of Alex Pretti in Minnesota, a nurse who was killed by a federal agent. The kickoff video also includes the shooting of Renee Good earlier in the month by an Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today our country is in chaos,” Mr. Vindman says in the video as clips of those shootings play and gunfire rings out. “Thug militias attacking citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Florida has increasingly trended away from Democrats, but Mr. Vindman gives the party a figure with a national following. He remains a long shot in a state that Mr. Trump won by 13 percentage points in 2024 and that has become increasingly Republican in the Trump era. The expense of campaigning in such a large state has been prohibitive for Democrats in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vindman first drew liberal attention in 2019, when he testified before Congress about the now-infamous call between Mr. Trump and President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine that led to the American leader’s impeachment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the exchange, Mr. Trump pressured Mr. Zelensky to investigate his rivals, including the Biden family. Mr. Vindman was on the call as a National Security Council aide, and he later testified that he had been alarmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vindman’s candidacy is likely to be an unwelcome reminder for Mr. Trump of his first impeachment. The president has tried to erase that episode from memory. The Smithsonian’s National Portrait Gallery recently removed wall text that referred to his two impeachments. Last year, Mr. Trump announced that he was firing the director of the gallery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Mr. Trump fired Mr. Vindman after the Senate acquitted the president. Mr. Vindman later sued Trump officials, accusing them of retaliation and intimidation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This president unleashed a reign of terror and retribution, not just against me and my family, but against all of us,” Mr. Vindman says in his rollout video, which begins with Wolf Blitzer of CNN announcing Mr. Vindman’s firing roughly six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The last time you saw me was here,” Mr. Vindman says, with an image of him raising his right hand to testify while in his Army dress uniform, “swearing an oath to tell the truth about a president who broke his.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Moody, who served previously as the Florida attorney general, was appointed to the Senate last year by Gov. Ron DeSantis to fill Mr. Rubio’s vacancy. She has drawn other Democratic challengers, including State Representative Angie Nixon of Jacksonville; Jennifer Jenkins, a former school board member who won her seat after defeating a right-wing incumbent in Republican-leaning Brevard County; and Hector Mujica, a Venezuelan American who used to work for Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vindman first floated running for Senate last spring, saying he did not see Florida as “too far gone by any means” for a Democrat to win. He has worked with the organization VoteVets, which recruits and supports Democratic veterans running for office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first Trump administration, Mr. Vindman’s twin brother, Eugene Vindman, was also removed by Mr. Trump from his role as a lawyer for the National Security Council after the impeachment fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eugene Vindman won a hotly contested congressional race in Northern Virginia in 2024 and became a favorite of grass-roots Democratic donors. Federal Election Commission records show that Mr. Vindman raised the third-most money into his House campaign account of anyone running for the House — finishing behind only Speaker Mike Johnson and Representative Hakeem Jeffries, the minority leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sizable haul suggests that small donors might also be eager to back his brother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patricia Mazzei contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:07:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Homeland Security’s Shifting Mission Over the Past Quarter-Century</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-timeline/26minneapolis-ice-timeline-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Trump administration, the Department of Homeland Security functions in part as the president’s arm for conducting the immigration enforcement operations that he made a key campaign promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when the agency was founded in the early 2000s after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, the mission was largely focused on coordinating a national strategy to prevent terrorism in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The new department will analyze threats, will guard our borders and airports, protect our critical infrastructure and coordinate the response of our nation for future emergencies,” former President George W. Bush said in a 2002 speech before he signed the bill that officially enacted the agency. “The Department of Homeland Security will focus the full resources of the American government on the safety of the American people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know about the creation of the Department of Homeland Security, the agency central to President Trump’s agenda on immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Days after the Sept. 11 terrorist attacks, Mr. Bush announced in a nationwide address that he was creating a new cabinet-level position reporting directly to him called the Office of Homeland Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its first leader was Tom Ridge, the former governor of Pennsylvania who was a close political ally and trusted friend of the president, but had no experience in the executive branch, counterterrorism or intelligence. His job was to “oversee and coordinate a comprehensive national strategy to safeguard our country against terrorists and respond to any attacks that may come,” Mr. Bush said in a speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ridge was also tasked with coordinating the efforts of other agency leaders — as many as 46 at the time — to gather intelligence that could prevent another terrorist attack, to protect borders and systems inside the country and to respond immediately if there was another targeted assault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some back-and-forth with congressional committees in the summer of 2002 to finalize the agency through the Homeland Security Act, Mr. Bush’s original vision for the office and the agencies under it was scaled back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall of the same year, Congress finalized the act and Mr. Bush signed it into law soon after, officially creating the Department of Homeland Security. It was considered Washington’s biggest transformation in 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-two federal departments were moved under the agency, including those overseeing the U.S. border, transportation security, emergency preparations and threat analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A priority for the department at the time was securing borders to prevent terrorist attacks, which made immigration a matter of national security, according to the 2002 proposal by the Bush administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Homeland Security Act also dissolved the Immigration and Naturalization Service and moved the agency’s functions to three separate ones under the new Department of Homeland Security: the U.S. Citizenship and Immigration Services, U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement and U.S. Customs and Border Protection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Trump took office in 2017, he quickly made immigration enforcement a priority of his first term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration directed the Department of Homeland Security to prioritize immigration enforcement through several executive orders, including building a wall to protect the border, deporting more undocumented immigrants and limiting travel to certain countries. He also added additional resources to the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mr. Trump’s second term, beginning in 2025, the administration has sought to arrest and deport people living in the United States illegally. It secured an extraordinary injection of funding to help pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president has targeted sanctuary cities led by Democrats in targeted enforcement operations, and Kristi Noem, the secretary of the Department of Homeland Security, has sent thousands of agents from C.B.P., ICE and other offices under her to make arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has also removed temporary protected status for some immigrants, instituted travel bans similar to his first term and has challenged birthright citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:06:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Orders ICE Chief to Appear in Court Over Potential Contempt</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a remarkable display of frustration, the chief federal judge in Minnesota ordered the head of U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement to appear in court on Friday to explain why he should not be held in contempt for violating court orders arising from the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a brief ruling issued late Monday, the judge, Patrick J. Schiltz, of Federal District Court in Minnesota, said he recognized that ordering ICE’s acting director, Todd Lyons, to personally defend himself in court was “an extraordinary step.” But Judge Schiltz, who was appointed by President George W. Bush, said it was necessary because “the extent of ICE’s violation of court orders is likewise extraordinary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Schiltz wrote that he had been “extremely patient” with the agency even though it had sent thousands of agents to the state as part of President Trump’s immigration crackdown, but did so without preparing for the legal challenges and lawsuits that “were sure to result.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He concluded, “The court’s patience is at an end.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Judge Schiltz’s irritation with the administration was palpable, he left Mr. Lyons a way out of his court summons. The judge said he would cancel the hearing if ICE quickly released an immigrant whom he said had been wrongly detained by agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Schiltz’s decision to summon Mr. Lyons came as the federal courts in Minnesota have been deluged by legal cases filed by immigrants swept up in the administration’s dragnet. Some of the immigrants have sought to avoid being shipped out of the state by federal agents, while others have complained about being sent to places like Texas and forced to find their own way home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge’s order stemmed from the case of Juan Hugo Tobay Robles, an Ecuadorean man who entered the United States illegally nearly 30 years ago and has been in custody after immigration agents detained him on Jan. 6, according to court papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 14, Judge Schiltz ordered ICE to allow Mr. Tobay Robles to challenge his detention at a hearing within a week or release him from custody altogether. As part of the ruling, the judge determined that ICE was holding Mr. Tobay Robles under an improper reading of federal law — one of hundreds of such cases that have unfolded in courts across the country in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday night, Judge Schiltz wrote that ICE had failed to obey his instructions, noting that Mr. Tobay Robles had not yet had a hearing but remained in custody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is one of dozens of court orders with which respondents have failed to comply in recent weeks,” the judge wrote without specifying other examples. “The practical consequence of respondents’ failure to comply has almost always been significant hardship to aliens (many of whom have lawfully lived and worked in the United States for years and done absolutely nothing wrong.)”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Schiltz, who once clerked for Justice Antonin Scalia, is an unlikely critic of the White House. But his summons of Mr. Lyons was his second clash with the Trump administration in less than a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, he expressed exasperation about an extraordinary request from the Justice Department to have him reverse another judge’s decision and personally issue arrest warrants for the journalist Don Lemon and four other people in connection with a protest at a church service in St. Paul this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a letter to the appeals court that sits over him, Judge Schiltz called the request by department lawyers “frivolous” and “unprecedented,” categorically rejecting their assertion that the warrants for Mr. Lemon and the others were needed on an emergency basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Judge Schiltz’s loss of patience with the administration comes at a particularly fraught moment for the Justice Department, which has been called upon to defend the government in other significant cases in the Minnesota federal courts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One judge in Minneapolis, Kate M. Menendez, held a hearing on Monday to consider whether the administration’s surge of some 3,000 immigration agents to the state had effectively become an unconstitutional occupation. Lawyers for the state and for the cities of St. Paul and Minneapolis have asked Judge Menendez to temporarily halt the surge, but she has not yet issued her decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a separate case, a federal judge in St. Paul heard arguments on Monday about whether to extend a preliminary order he issued over the weekend forcing the Department of Homeland Security to preserve evidence arising from the fatal shooting on Saturday of Alex Pretti, an intensive care nurse.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:10:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>She’s the Face of Trump’s Aviation Safety Board, and She’s a Democrat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg-facebookJumbo-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the National Transportation Safety Board meets on Tuesday to make an official determination about what caused a midair collision last year near Washington, D.C., that killed 67 people, its outspoken chairwoman is stepping back into a spotlight that she never fully left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Homendy, the chair, has been an unusually public crusader for changes to the aviation system in the year since her agency began probing why a military helicopter and a commercial jet collided near Ronald Reagan National Airport. A rare Democrat running a federal agency under President Trump, she has used her bully pulpit to lend support to — or dish out scathing criticism of — government initiatives and legislation concerning aviation safety. And she has offered effusive praise for the Trump administration’s efforts to make improvements — even when doing so has rankled peers and members of her own party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Homendy has retained her post atop a federal oversight agency at a time when many investigators and inspectors general, including a member of the N.T.S.B., were fired by the Trump administration. She has the rare distinction of having earned the trust not just of Republicans, but of President Trump himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The White House maintains the utmost confidence in Jennifer Homendy, who is playing a key role in ensuring that Americans can have peace of mind each time they board a flight or train,” Kush Desai, a White House spokesman, said in a statement this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting on Tuesday is the culmination of an investigation that could be legacy-defining for Ms. Homendy, 54, who was a lobbyist and longtime congressional staff member before she joined the investigative agency in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadliest U.S. aviation accident in a generation created a rare appetite for action, as lawmakers and administration officials proposed changes, including to flight routes and rules governing the use of advanced aircraft tracking technology. That the board was able to wrap up the probe in about a year is a testament to how much urgency surrounded it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, when investigators settle on a probable cause of the accident and issue recommendations, Ms. Homendy’s penchant for aggressive advocacy will once again be on display. But her style is not just for the dais: It’s a reflection of her contention that the N.T.S.B. has to be more visible around Washington if members want decision makers to heed their advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You need to be proactive — and I felt that we were reactive for so many years,” she said during an interview in her Washington office last week. “We have such an important role in safety that it needed to be elevated.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between her duties overseeing a large investigative docket and the agency’s administrative operations, Ms. Homendy spends a sizable chunk of every day on the phone. She reaches out to heads of the Department of Transportation and its subagencies, White House officials and lawmakers, frequently offering briefings to get people up to speed on the N.T.S.B.’s dealings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not waiting for them to call me,” she said. “They need information to do their job, and what I don’t want them to have is the wrong information, what they might be reading in something or on social media.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agency has a mandate to investigate transportation incidents, including all civil aviation accidents in the United States, but no regulatory authority. It can only make recommendations to Congress and the president. The board is designed to be nonpartisan, with no more than three of its five members belonging to the same political party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Homendy’s focus on outreach is informed by an early career in lobbying, followed by nearly 15 years working for the House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee’s subpanel on railroads. During that time, she would often wonder why N.T.S.B. officials were such a rare presence around Congress. When the Trump administration selected her for the board, she vowed to do things differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within months of joining, Ms. Homendy began campaigning for full implementation of positive train control, an automated system to prevent rail accidents. When she became chair in 2021, she sought to imbue the entire agency with a sense of responsibility to educate outsiders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t the smoothest transition. Some N.T.S.B. employees bristled at the added demands and worried that they were distracting from investigative work, according to current and former employees who spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of exposing individuals to retaliation. They pointed to significant attrition among retirement-eligible staff since Ms. Homendy became chair, a period that overlapped with the aftermath of the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But under Ms. Homendy’s leadership, the agency also expanded its budget by nearly a quarter and reduced a punishing backlog of cases. The board also managed to avoid crippling austerity measures imposed on other parts of the government — things Ms. Homendy attributes to having cultivated advocates throughout Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That development of those relationships over time, I believe, has created a lot of trust back and forth,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Ms. Homendy’s habit of responding positively to any lawmaker’s request for a briefing yielded a particularly valuable connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a Norfolk Southern freight train carrying hazardous materials derailed in East Palestine, Ohio, releasing toxic gases and forcing an evacuation of the area, she and a staff member pulled a wagon full of materials from the N.T.S.B.’s public docket through the halls of the Capitol to brief the staff of the state’s junior senator. When that senator, JD Vance, was later selected to be Mr. Trump’s vice president, she suddenly had advocates in the president’s immediate orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representatives for Mr. Vance did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A similar overture kicked off her partnership with Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy. The night of the Washington collision was the second time Ms. Homendy recalls offering to help Mr. Duffy, who had been confirmed as secretary only the afternoon before. Within days, she was shepherding him around wreckage and rescue operations at the crash site. A few months later, she appeared alongside him as he unveiled plans to upgrade the nation’s air traffic control system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, Mr. Duffy described Ms. Homendy’s leadership as “remarkable.” Last week, Ms. Homendy described Mr. Duffy as “the most engaged secretary on safety and with this agency in the entire time I have served as chair of the N.T.S.B.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But her apparent closeness with administration officials and other Republicans has also prompted concerns among some N.T.S.B. employees and Democratic staffers that she could risk politicizing the traditionally nonpartisan agency, even as some of the same people applaud her commitment to advancing safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, without directly warning the rest of the board, she took the rare step of calling an emergency news conference to demand changes to an annual defense bill that was pending before Congress, warning that it would make the skies over Reagan National Airport less safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In July, Ms. Homendy appeared alongside Ted Cruz, a Republican senator from Texas and the chairman of the Senate committee overseeing transportation, at a news conference to tout aviation safety legislation that no Democrats had endorsed yet. And last fall, she promoted John DeLeeuw, Mr. Trump’s pick to replace the N.T.S.B. member whom he fired last year and who is suing to get his job back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say such moves are expedient and reveal her political savvy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s done a masterful job of dealing with multiple political pressures,” Alan Diehl, an aviation safety consultant said in an interview, adding that “if she were not to do that, she would probably be replaced, almost certainly — and that would be a very bad thing for aviation safety.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Homendy disputes the suggestion that politics are on her mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t care if you’re the president, United States vice president, a secretary, you know, an intern,” she added. “If you’re for safety, I don’t care who you are. I will meet with you. I will work with you.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:35:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Latinas for Trump’ Co-Founder Warns Immigration Will Cost G.O.P. the Midterms</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ileana-garcia-trump-immigration-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/us/00nat-miami-senator/00nat-miami-senator-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration’s immigration crackdown over the last year has gone from uncomfortable to untenable for Ileana Garcia, a Republican state senator in Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Transportation Security Administration officer at the Tallahassee airport overheard her speaking Spanish and asked whether Ms. Garcia, who was born in Miami, was an American citizen. She worried for the first time that Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents might stop her son, a young adult, because he looks Hispanic. Constituents have asked her for help finding immigrant relatives arrested by ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garcia, 56, has had enough. The Republican Party is in trouble, she said in an interview, predicting that it will lose this year’s midterm elections if the White House does not soon reconsider its harsh immigration enforcement tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We should not be afraid as a party to speak up, to course correct,” she said. That was before Saturday, when Border Patrol agents shot and killed Alex Pretti, a 37-year-old I.C.U. nurse who was protesting in Minneapolis, and federal officials sought to portray him as a “domestic terrorist.” Ms. Garcia said she was “dumbfounded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s gone too far,” she said. “What happened Saturday was abhorrent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a little-known state senator in a state that no longer appears to be a political battleground thinks might seem of little consequence. But Ms. Garcia, who is Cuban American, was once such a true believer in President Trump that she went all-in on his 2016 campaign, leaving her career in Spanish-language media to co-found “Latinas for Trump,” a national organization that drew attention at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She then moved to Washington to work for Mr. Trump’s first administration, in the public affairs office of the Department of Homeland Security, which enforces immigration laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, Mr. Trump was focused on closing the U.S.-Mexico border and building a border wall, both policies she supported. Now he has gone much further, Ms. Garcia said. She blamed Stephen Miller, the president’s deputy chief of staff for policy and homeland security adviser, for tactics that include yanking people out of cars and trying to remove children who crossed the border on their own from foster care homes and deport them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do think that he will lose the midterms because of Stephen Miller,” she said of Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not respond to a request for comment on Monday about Ms. Garcia’s assertion but pointed to remarks by Karoline Leavitt, the press secretary, about Mr. Pretti’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nobody in the White House, including President Trump, wants to see people getting hurt or killed in America’s streets,” she said, claiming that the killing “occurred as a result of a deliberate and hostile resistance by Democrat leaders in Minnesota.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garcia said she knew Mr. Miller during the president’s first term and did not like him then, either. But he had less power than he does now, she said. Was she blaming Mr. Miller for the administration’s immigration policies but absolving Mr. Trump?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not absolving him,” Ms. Garcia said. “I’m not justifying the things that we’re seeing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, she was quick to add, “There’s no perfect administration.” She remembered being a guest at Mr. Trump’s Mar-a-Lago estate in Palm Beach in late 2023 and talking to him about immigrants who were brought into the country illegally as children, known as Dreamers. She found Mr. Trump receptive to the argument that they should be allowed to stay, and she still likes him, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garcia’s blunt criticism is unusual even among Florida’s Hispanic lawmakers. Representative María Elvira Salazar, one of Miami’s three Cuban American Republicans in Congress, has disagreed with the Trump administration on immigration and other policies, but her comments have tended to be more conciliatory than Ms. Garcia’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, Ms. Garcia voted for an immigration enforcement bill in the Legislature that created a new state board of immigration enforcement. But she opposed another bill that made it a state crime for unauthorized immigrants to enter Florida and ended a policy allowing Florida residents who had been brought into the country illegally as children to pay in-state tuition at public universities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most people will come in and whisper in my ear, ‘Aren’t you afraid they’re going to primary you?’” said Ms. Garcia, who is up for re-election this year. “No, I’m not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m afraid of someone stopping my son,” she added. “That’s what I’m afraid of.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garcia has been speaking out for months in social media posts and statements to local news outlets. She received death threats in June after condemning the Trump administration’s mass deportations as “unacceptable and inhumane.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She discussed her unease over lunch last month in Coral Gables, an upscale Miami suburb in her district, which stretches across central Miami-Dade County to Miami Beach, and again by phone in mid-January. Miami voters elected their first Democratic mayor in nearly 30 years in December, and Ms. Garcia agreed with those who credited Eileen Higgins’ resounding victory in part to voters’ disgust over the immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Republicans stayed home — I wonder why?” Ms. Garcia said. “I think they’re embarrassed. I think that they feel that they might have gotten the wool pulled over their eyes. And this was their way of pushing back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Garcia is well aware of critics who say that Republicans like her should have foreseen the second Trump administration’s aggressive immigration tactics. She thought the White House would focus on limiting border crossings, vetting new immigrants and removing criminals, all of which she supports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has been especially offended by the deportations of Cubans who had committed nonviolent criminal offenses but had been in the country for decades and of Venezuelans and other immigrants from politically unstable countries who had been granted temporary permission to live and work in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go after people like that “doesn’t make sense,” Ms. Garcia said, adding that it has wreaked havoc on families and communities and is “inhumane.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has been disappointed not only with regards to immigration. The Trump administration, she said, is also “gaslighting” Americans on the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In 2016 to 2020, the rhetoric matched the reality,” she added. “The economy was good. People were working. People were happy. But now, they are saying the economy is better. I am sorry, respectfully: I shop for my parents, and I count coupons.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She sees herself as a truth-teller within her party. Too many of her fellow Republicans are scared to say how they feel, a self-censorship that frightens her. “It’s almost like the stories that my mother would tell me of what she lived in Cuba, and we’re seeing it here,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She rejected any suggestion that she could afford to speak out because redistricting has made Florida legislative elections less competitive than they once were. (She won her first election in 2020 by a mere 32 votes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know if anybody is really safe anymore, at least in Miami-Dade County,” she said. “There are so many mixed feelings.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she started criticizing the Trump administration last year, she said, a man she knows told her that she had gone too far. “‘I can’t believe you jumped over to the dark side,’” she recounted him saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has since heard back from the same man, she said. This time, he told her she was right.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ileana-garcia-trump-immigration-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:03:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Population Growth Slows Sharply as Immigration Numbers Plunge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-census-fjcl/27nat-census-fjcl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States population grew last year at one of the slowest rates in its history, according to new numbers released on Tuesday by the Census Bureau. The immigration numbers plunged by more than 50 percent from the previous year, under the aggressive anti-immigration policies of President Trump. And the birthrate continued its nearly two-decade long decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nation’s population increased by about 1.8 million over the year, and stood at almost 342 million on July 1, the estimates say. That is a growth rate of about 0.5 percent, the lowest since 2021, when the Covid-19 pandemic caused deaths to soar and borders to close, shutting the door to international migration. That year saw the slowest growth since the nation’s founding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new census estimates measure changes in the population from June 30, 2024, to July 1, 2025, capturing the last months of the Biden administration, when it tightened border policies, and the early months of the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over that time, net immigration added almost 1.3 million people to the U.S. population. That number is considerably lower than that of 2024, when, under President Joseph R. Biden Jr., immigration reached a record high of just over 2.7 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump continues his term, immigration is expected to drop even further. If current trends continue, it will fall to about 321,000 for the year ending on June 30, according to a Census Bureau news release. That would be lower than during the pandemic year, when net international migration dropped to 376,000, one of the lowest points in modern history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The basic goal here was to stop people coming over the border illegally and being released, and to ramp up interior enforcement to actually remove people,” Simon Hankinson, a senior research fellow at the conservative Heritage Foundation, said of Mr. Trump’s immigration policy. “This is an indicator that much of the strategy is working.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has pledged to bring down levels of illegal immigration through a border shutdown and mass deportations. But although net immigration has declined substantially, it has still not reached the point where more people are leaving the country than arriving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country’s attention has been focused on raids and deportations, those actions accounted for relatively little of the overall decline in net immigration of about 1.5 million. The Census Bureau does not break down what caused the drop, but a New York Times analysis found that about 230,000 people were deported from the United States over the entirety of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That suggests that deportations are not directly responsible for most of the decline in net immigration numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The border shutdown was a major part of the decline. Other factors that contributed to the drop include the increased difficulty of getting visas and foreign citizens who chose not to come to the United States, or to leave on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was expecting that the decline would be bigger than we’re seeing here,” said William Frey, chief demographer at the left-leaning Brookings Institution. “This is still over a million people coming in.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though several estimates have been made of the change in the immigrant population since President Trump came into office, the estimates by the Census Bureau on Tuesday are the first gold-standard set of federal figures to be made public. They attempt to account for both legal and illegal immigration, as well as deportations and voluntary departures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The federal government’s population numbers are a measure of a nation’s demographic health, and take account of births and deaths as well as immigration, emigration and deportation. The country needs a large enough population of young workers and taxpayers to finance care for the nation’s older residents, whose numbers are swelling as the Baby Boom generation retires. Growth that is too rapid can also present problems, taxing resources and driving up the cost of housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sharp drop in the birthrate also contributed to the slowdown in population growth. The birthrate has been falling since the Great Recession in 2008, and new births outpaced deaths by only about 518,000 in the latest period. That is higher than during the peak of the Covid pandemic, when deaths were soaring, but it is still extremely low by historical standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What has been carrying the United States through this decade has been immigration,” said Kenneth Johnson, a demographer at the University of New Hampshire. “My question is, what will happen to the population if we go to negative immigration?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He noted that in the decade from 2010 to 2020, immigration made up about 40 percent of the overall population growth, while births supplied about 60 percent. But since 2020, as the birthrate has declined, immigration has taken up a larger and larger share, and now accounts for around 80 percent of overall growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Lowering immigration at a time when our birthrate is falling is a recipe for lower growth for our economy and weaker international competition,” said Julia Gelatt, an associate director at the Migration Policy Institute, a research center in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While demographers expected the latest estimates to show a decline in the rate of population growth — the question was simply by how much — some of the changes seen at the state level were a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Midwest was the only region where every state grew in population over the year: For the first time in a decade, more people in the United States moved to the region than left it. Ohio and Michigan both gained population arriving from other states, after seeing residents leave in earlier years. South Carolina was the country’s fastest growing state, followed by Idaho, North Carolina and Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, immigration has fueled population growth in the states, and the reduction has dragged it down. There were sharp drops in Texas, New York, Florida and California. The drop in California contributed to an outright decline in population for that state, one of five states to run in the red.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Census Bureau estimates are derived from government records, like birth and death certificates and data on immigration and refugees. This year, the bureau also included new sources of information, including government data from Mexico, to get a more accurate count of the number of people leaving the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some demographers have praised these changes and said they will contribute to a more accurate count, they have also cautioned that immigration is difficult to track precisely.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:38:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment Commission Chair Recasts Workplace Discrimination in Trump’s Image</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, a 9,000-word essay about white male millennials shot across the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, a ticket scalper and frustrated screenwriter, marshaled interviews and data to describe how the professional trajectories of members of his generation had been crushed by what he called the institutionalization of diversity, equity and inclusion mandates, a “profound shift in how power and prestige were distributed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vice President JD Vance reposted the piece, saying it “describes the evil of DEI and its consequences.” Elon Musk responded, calling D.E.I. “a great wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essay also caught the attention of Andrea Lucas, the chair of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, the agency, born of the Civil Rights Act, that enforces laws against employment discrimination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are you a white male who has experienced discrimination at work based on your race or sex? You may have a claim to recover money under federal civil rights laws,” Ms. Lucas said in a video posted on Dec. 17 on social media. From her desk at E.E.O.C. headquarters, she referred viewers to the commission’s primer on “D.E.I.-related discrimination.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, which recalled the television commercials of personal injury law firms, generated volleys of shock, outrage and gratitude online. To Ms. Lucas, 40, it was an urgent public service announcement, central to her mission as an agent of President Trump’s executive authority and part of a robust response to what she described as the excesses of the left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview, she said she was determined to undo the consequences of five years of “aggressive focus by D.E.I. activists” that reserved the protections of the country’s civil rights infrastructure for certain groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think the agency is the tip of the spear for implementing a really ambitious civil rights agenda,” Ms. Lucas said. “I think that that mission is to restore a focus on equality as opposed to equity. It’s going back to the concept of equal treatment as opposed to equal outcomes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics of Ms. Lucas, including former commissioners of the E.E.O.C., say she is distorting the intent of the Civil Rights Act, paying lip service to equal treatment while using her position to write MAGA grievances into federal law. They noted that as she has solicited complaints from white men — historically a small share of complainants to the E.E.O.C. — the commission has dismissed cases that would defend transgender employees and job applicants with criminal records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charlotte Burrows, Ms. Lucas’s predecessor as chair, who was fired by Mr. Trump last January, said, “Federal civil rights laws protect everyone, and the E.E.O.C. has a duty to engage in fair and evenhanded law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She and others said Ms. Lucas’s message in the December video was that white Americans would receive preferential consideration under the Trump administration. “That’s the opposite of equal opportunity,” Ms. Burrows said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her first year, Ms. Lucas has taken steps to undo the work of her predecessors, particularly regarding contentious issues like gender. Her work is likely to accelerate now that the commission has three members, required for a quorum, with a 2-to-1 Republican majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a meeting on Jan. 22, the commission voted — over the objections of the sole Democrat — to rescind guidance for employers about workplace harassment. Issued in 2024 after 10 years of debate, the guidance detailed prohibitions against harassment, including on the basis of sexual orientation and gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She has closed the door of the E.E.O.C. to groups that are disfavored by the president,” said Josh Boxerman, who handles civil rights work at the National Employment Law Project, a workers rights group. “That is extraordinary. And it is radical and harmful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody who wants to sue a private employer under civil rights law must file a complaint with the commission. The E.E.O.C. received more than 88,000 such complaints in 2024, the last year for which data is publicly available. The commission is legally mandated to look into all of them, but only a sliver develop into full investigations. The commission, and particularly the chair, has great discretion over what cases to pursue, particularly because staff and resources are stretched thin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, the commission “saw our work as protecting the rights, often, of the most vulnerable workers, who really needed the government’s help,” said Jenny Yang, who worked at the E.E.O.C. from 2013 to 2018, including three years as chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we are seeing now is a real politicization of the priorities of the agency, and a disregard for the law,” Ms. Yang said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas joined the commission in 2020, when its work was being complicated by the Covid-19 pandemic and the racial reckoning that followed the murder of George Floyd. The commission, along with employers across the country, grappled with vaccine mandates, diversity and inclusion practices, questions about gender-specific bathrooms and charges of deep-seated racism across entire industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That period of time, primarily during the Biden administration, but even heading into it, was a period of a wave of discrimination that was motivated or framed as D.E.I.,” Ms. Lucas said. “Everyone collectively lost their minds for a period of time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backlash followed, a sentiment Mr. Trump harnessed in the 2024 election. Among his first moves after returning to office last January was issuing executive orders that dismantled D.E.I. programs in the federal government. On Jan. 20, 2025, he nominated Ms. Lucas to serve as the E.E.O.C.’s acting chair. A week later, he fired two of the Democratic commissioners, Ms. Burrows and Jocelyn Samuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Samuels filed a lawsuit challenging her firing, which is on hold while the Supreme Court considers a similar case at the Federal Trade Commission, another independent agency Mr. Trump has sought to bring under the reach of executive authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission and the Justice Department, Ms. Samuels said, are neglecting their legal duty to protect workers equally, adding that Ms. Lucas is making changes that are procedurally suspect and damaging to workers who bear the greatest burden of discrimination in America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It has been heartbreaking and infuriating, in equal measure,” Ms. Samuels said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of 2025, Ms. Lucas was the interim head of an agency that had only one other member, Kalpana Kotagal, a Democrat, lacking the quorum required to pursue major rule changes or litigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas worked around those constraints. In March, she wrote to 20 law firms seeking details about their D.E.I. practices. The commission worked with the Justice Department and the Department of Labor in a campaign to root out “national-origin discrimination,” such as apparent preferences for foreign skilled workers holding H-1B visas over American workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a little bit of a backwater. But Andrea has done an effective job of making the E.E.O.C., and the chair of the E.E.O.C., an important policymaking position,” said Jason C. Schwartz, a co-chair of the labor and employment group at the law firm Gibson Dunn, where he worked with Ms. Lucas. He called her “really smart, really strong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commission also took action against universities, including reaching an agreement in which Columbia University would pay $21 million to resolve complaints of civil rights violations against its Jewish employees after the Israel-Hamas war started in 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Pennsylvania rebuked the E.E.O.C. in a court filing this month, refusing to supply information about its Jewish employees in connection with an investigation into antisemitism at the university.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April, Mr. Trump issued an executive order taking aim at a pillar of civil rights law: disparate-impact liability, a legal principle holding that an employment practice is discriminatory if it creates unequal outcomes among different groups, even unintentionally. Mr. Trump directed government agencies to stop enforcing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move, denounced by civil rights and employment groups, had swift consequences at the commission. Within weeks, it moved to dismiss a civil rights lawsuit it had brought a year earlier against Sheetz, the convenience store chain, over its practice of screening out applicants with criminal convictions. The commission had previously found that the practice disproportionately affected applicants of color and violated the Civil Rights Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last October, the E.E.O.C. moved to dismiss seven cases it had brought in 2024 on behalf of transgender and gender-nonconforming people, in accordance with a new agency policy that it would not enforce workplace harassment claims brought on the basis of gender identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her Senate confirmation hearing in June, Ms. Lucas was clear about her priorities: pursuing cases related to religious and national-origin discrimination, rooting out D.E.I. initiatives and ending what she sees as the improper elevation of “gender identity” over biological sex. She disavowed statements she had made referring to the E.E.O.C. as an independent agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been very clear: The agency is not an independent agency,” she said in the interview. “It’s an executive branch agency. The will of the people elected the president, and I’m going to execute it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Senate’s confirmation in October of Brittany Bull Panuccio, a Republican nominated by Mr. Trump to the E.E.O.C., the commission’s work is likely to accelerate in volume and ambition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are very concerned that it will continue that path of wide-ranging rescissions and rollbacks of hard-won and thoughtfully considered worker protections,” said Mr. Boxerman of the National Employment Law Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She has made it clear that longstanding agency policy, judicial precedent — these things matter less than fulfilling the Trump agenda,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Lucas sees her role as an expression of Mr. Trump’s executive authority, but it is also clear that she has given a lot of thought to issues of fairness and justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If your answer to solve prior discrimination is present discrimination, I think that’s a really ugly view of the world,” Ms. Lucas said in the interview. “That’s not the vision that I want for my children. It’s not the vision that I think goes back to the concept of people being created equal. And I just really fundamentally disagree with it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Historically, Republicans have been very uncomfortable to talk about race, uncomfortable to deal with this issue,” Ms. Lucas said. “But from my perspective, we have to deal with these topics.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:49:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yale Offers Free Tuition to Families With Incomes Under $200,000</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-yale-qljh/27nat-yale-qljh-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale University said on Tuesday that attending the university would be free for newly admitted undergraduate students from families with annual incomes below $100,000, and that tuition would be waived for those earning below $200,000. The change takes effect for the class that will enroll in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move enters Yale into an arms race of elite institutions offering increasingly attractive financial aid packages to students from low- and middle-income families. At Yale, the full-price cost to attend is now more than $90,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yale’s new policy essentially matches the deal offered by Harvard last year, which followed similar announcements by the University of Pennsylvania, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Princeton and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beefed-up financial aid follows the Supreme Court’s 2023 decision limiting what universities may do to recruit racially diverse student bodies. The schools hope to continue to attract diverse applicants by stepping up financial aid, since race and income are often correlated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort to make attendance more affordable at some of the nation’s highest-rated universities also comes at a time when public trust in higher education has declined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Kahlenberg, director of the American Identity Project at the Progressive Policy Institute, said the effort was good not just for the country but also for Yale, because it will allow students from different walks of life to attend, increasing the range of viewpoints on campus as well as the range of backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Economic diversity can bring racial diversity in a way that’s perfectly legal,” he said. “So after the Supreme Court struck down the use of race, institutions like Yale had to find different ways to get racial diversity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the new policy, which was first reported by The Wall Street Journal, Yale said that students from 80 percent of households in the United States would qualify for free tuition, and students from almost half the nation’s households would be eligible for an entirely free Yale education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the lowest-income students, the offerings at Yale, Harvard and some other schools include free housing and meal plans, allowances for travel to and from campus, medical insurance and “start-up” grants for students to use to buy books and supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an announcement last August, Princeton appeared to eclipse even those generous aid packages, saying that most families with incomes up to $150,000 would pay nothing to attend and most with incomes up to $250,000 will pay no tuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, the upper limit for household income to qualify for no-cost attendance at Yale was $75,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeremiah Quinlan, Yale’s dean of undergraduate admission and financial aid, said the new plan is an investment in affordability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With this announcement, we reiterate and reinforce Yale’s commitment to ensuring that cost will never be a barrier between promising students and a Yale College education,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:50:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mark Carney Rejects Suggestions That He Walked Back His Davos Speech to Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada dismissed Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent’s suggestion that he had retracted his assertion that President Trump had created an irrevocable “rupture” to the world order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian leader spoke to reporters in Ottawa on Tuesday, the day after Mr. Bessent said on Fox News that he was in the Oval Office while Mr. Carney “was very aggressively walking back some of the unfortunate remarks” he had made at the World Economic Forum in Davos during a telephone call with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that speech, Mr. Carney, though he did not specifically name Mr. Trump was clear in his intent, calling on the world’s middle powers to stop accommodating the United States just “to go along to get along,” and to instead band together to counter its political and economic power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Tuesday if he had rescinded any of his remarks while speaking with Mr. Trump, Mr. Carney said “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To be absolutely clear, and I said this to the president, I meant what I said in Davos,” Mr. Carney told reporters, referring to the Swiss ski resort town where the gathering of billionaires, investors, executives and politicians was held last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “It was clear. It was a broader set of issues, and Canada was the first country to understand the change in U.S. trade policy that he initiated, and we’re responding to that.” Mr. Carney added that during their conversation on Monday, the president had “understood’’ Canada’s position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week Mr. Carney warned other middle powers that they faced potential danger if they do not stand up for their own interests and push back against Mr. Trump’s aggressive economic moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His remarks received an unusual standing ovation and were widely praised around the world and stood in stark contrast to Mr. Trump’s long and rambling address at Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of Mr. Carney’s speech, Mr. Trump revoked his invitation to Canada for membership on his Gaza “Board of Peace,” though Mr. Carney had not fully committed to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney arrived in Switzerland after striking a trade deal with China that will allow a small number of Chinese electric vehicles to enter Canada at a low tariff rate. During the Biden administration, Canada joined the United States and imposed a 100 percent tariff on Chinese E.V.s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, Mr. Trump seemed to bless Mr. Carney’s agreement with China, saying, “That’s OK, that’s what he should be doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But later, on social media, he threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canadian exports “If Canada makes a deal with China.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney has repeatedly said that Canada has no plan to seek a broader free trade deal with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I explained to him our arrangement with China,” Mr. Carney said of his conversation with Mr. Trump on Tuesday. “I explained to him what we’re doing: 12 new deals on four continents in six months — he was impressed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday Canada and India released a joint statement about expanding trade in Canadian oil and natural gas. Mr. Carney is scheduled to travel to India next month to meet Prime Minister Narendra Modi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday Mr. Carney suggested that Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threat was a negotiating tactic ahead of a review of the free trade agreement between Canada, the United States and Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president is a strong negotiator and I think some of these comments and positioning should be viewed in the broader context of that,” Mr. Carney said at a news conference.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:54:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Breaking Silence, Eleanor Holmes Norton Announces Retirement</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-norton-vphw/27trump-news-norton-vphw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton, who has served for three decades as Washington, D.C.’s nonvoting representative in Congress, on Tuesday announced she planned to retire at the end of her term, pivoting after months of insisting she had no intention of stepping aside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Thank you to my constituents for choosing and trusting me to fight for you in Congress 18 times,” she said in a statement. “I will leave this institution knowing that I have given you everything I have.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 88-year-old Democrat is the oldest person serving in the House. Once a forceful voice for the nation’s capital, she had retreated from her congressional duties in recent years amid signs of mental and physical decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she had repeatedly swatted away the suggestion that she might leave Congress, including as recently as this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, even after her campaign filed a termination notice for her re-election, her office declined to confirm that Ms. Norton planned to retire and she issued no statement, raising questions about whether she had approved the move — or even knew about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Norton, a civil-rights leader and former law professor who entered Congress in 1991, earned the moniker of D.C.’s “warrior on the Hill,” after decades of fighting for statehood for the district.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in recent years her voice has diminished on Capitol Hill. She has said little since President Trump’s return to office, even as Republicans wielded their trifecta of power to increase federal control over the city she represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The privilege of public service is inseparable from the responsibility to recognize when it’s time to lift up the next generation of leaders,” Ms. Norton said in her statement on Tuesday. “For D.C., that time has come.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her exit will mark the end of a strained final chapter of her congressional career in which Ms. Norton often appeared confused on Capitol Hill, but steadfastly refused to consider ending her long political career. She had become a symbol of the gerontocracy gripping Washington, sitting silent in committee meetings and saying little to push back on Republicans’ legislative attacks on the district and the deployment of the National Guard to police the city’s streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former top staff member, Trent Holbrook, and several members of the D.C. Council had already announced plans to run for her seat even before Ms. Norton announced she was stepping down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Democrats praised her for decades of work fighting for the rights of D.C. voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Eleanor fought with deep patriotism for the people of the District of Columbia, honoring the history and promise of Washington while never wavering in her demand for justice,” former Speaker Nancy Pelosi, Democrat of California, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Congressional Black Caucus said in a statement that Ms. Norton had been “a guiding force for our members for decades, sharing her wisdom and expertise and helping to shape generations of leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mayor Muriel E. Bowser of Washington said in a statement on Sunday that the congresswoman’s work “embodies the unwavering resolve of a city that refuses to yield in its fight for equal representation.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:26:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Immigration, the G.O.P. Finds Itself in a Shocking Place: On Defense</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two killings by federal agents on the icy streets of Minneapolis have suddenly turned the politics of immigration upside down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Republicans, led by a president who rose to power with promises to build a Southern border wall and carry out mass deportations, are now trying to dodge an issue that polls had long shown to be a strength for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats, who have for years tried to change the political subject to health care or abortion rights, are now racing to talk about immigration and harness their voters’ rage over the fatal shootings in Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift could be fleeting. American politics has rarely felt so unsettled and unpredictable, with President Trump just as responsive to television coverage as to on-the-ground realities. On Monday, he shook up the leadership of his immigration crackdown in Minnesota and seemed inclined to try to calm tensions, at least for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the meantime, both parties are adjusting on the fly as a midterm election year they thought would center on the cost of living abruptly seems far more focused on immigration and federal power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Illinois and New Mexico, Democratic candidates this week began running advertisements highlighting their opposition to federal immigration operations. Others in Maine and New Jersey have upended their campaign messaging, long directed at high costs, to address their voters’ anger about deportations. The party’s primary candidates for Senate spoke forcefully against Mr. Trump’s immigration policies during recent debates in Texas and Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic members of Congress including Senator Raphael Warnock of Georgia and Representative Ro Khanna of California have braved snowstorms and subzero temperatures to fly to Minneapolis and meet — and be seen — with activists on the ground. Others have led rallies against Immigration and Customs Enforcement in their home states. And Senate Democrats have quickly grown an appetite for again shutting down the federal government over funding for Mr. Trump’s Department of Homeland Security, which includes ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top Republican leaders and many candidates in tough races have struggled for a response to the chaos in Minnesota. Speaker Mike Johnson has still not issued a statement, while Senator John Thune, the majority leader, praised Mr. Trump’s shake-up in Minnesota as a positive step for “turning down the temperature.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, a parade of other politicians in the party have expressed concerns about the killings and the aggressiveness of federal immigration authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Madel, a Republican candidate for governor of Minnesota governor, called the federal immigration operation “a disaster” as he dropped out on Monday. Representative Glenn Grothman, from next-door Wisconsin, suggested that the latest shooting by a federal agent was “murder.” Even Gov. Greg Abbott of Texas, known for his hard-line immigration approach, suggested that the White House should “recalibrate” its strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Immigration enforcement used to be a strong point for Republicans,” said Adam Jentleson, the president of the Searchlight Institute, a moderate Democratic think tank, who two weeks ago released a memo warning Democrats to avoid the phrase “Abolish ICE.” “Republicans thought that there was no version of enforcement that people would reject, and they were wrong about that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The political risks for Republicans in battleground states and districts have become clear, with polls showing voters souring on Mr. Trump’s immigration tactics. A New York Times/Siena poll released last week — conducted before the latest shooting in Minnesota — showed that while roughly half of voters supported his deportations, a sizable majority believed that ICE had gone too far, including a remarkable 71 percent of politically crucial independent voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Even if the administration is telling the truth, the perception is immediately colored against ICE because of how much fear and anxiety has piled up,” said Preya Samsundar, a Republican strategist in Minneapolis. “If this continues to go on, it could cause some issues with the gains we have been able to make as a party.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats say their change in focus is being driven by fury from their voters, who want to know what their representatives will do to try to stop Mr. Trump’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In every conversation, it is brought up,” said Tahesha Way, a Democratic former lieutenant governor of New Jersey who is running in a special election to the U.S. House next week. “People not only see what’s going on nationally in Minnesota — they’re living in fear as to what is happening on the ground here in New Jersey.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wave of Democratic outrage could force another government shutdown at the end of the week. Key Senate Democrats have promised to oppose bipartisan legislation to fund a broad swath of the government because it includes billions of dollars for the Department of Homeland Security and ICE. Several suggested they were open to eventually including such funding, but they demanded more guardrails to “rein in the abuses of ICE,” as Senator Chuck Schumer, the minority leader, put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How Americans might respond to another shutdown is one uncertain factor in the ever-changing political calculus. And Republicans have hardly given up their tough-on-immigration stance: In television ads broadcast this year, there have been more than twice as many Republican ads highlighting such positions than Democratic spots criticizing ICE tactics, according to data from AdImpact, a media tracking firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Democrats warn that voters broadly have not rejected the overall goal of combating illegal immigration that helped twice elect Mr. Trump to the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a topic that Democrats have an imperative to engage on, but they still need to do it the right way,” said Molly Murphy, a Democratic pollster who worked in 2024 for the campaigns of President Joseph R. Biden Jr. and Vice President Kamala Harris. “Voters believe a secure border is important and that Trump’s tactics are not doing that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the two killings in Minnesota made the state the focus of the nation’s attention, ICE operations in other states have pushed immigration and deportation issues to the forefront of local politics. Maine’s Senate race, one of the country’s most competitive, and its contest for governor have become dominated by the government’s deportation push in the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even the name of the ICE effort in Maine — Operation Catch of the Day — has infuriated some officials and voters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a grotesque name,” said Shenna Bellows, the Maine secretary of state and Democrat who is running for governor. “People are not fish.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:29:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Man Is Wounded After Exchanging Fire With Border Patrol in Arizona</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2024/03/11/multimedia/27xp-border/11budget-border-btpv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Arizona man was in critical condition after exchanging gunfire with a U.S. Border Patrol agent and shooting at a federal helicopter on Tuesday in Arizona near the Mexican border, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Border Patrol agents were working to apprehend a male suspect in an “active alien smuggling matter” when he shot at a federal helicopter, Heith Janke, the special agent in charge of the F.B.I.’s Phoenix field office, said during a news conference late Tuesday afternoon. Federal agents returned fire and shot the suspect, Mr. Janke said. No federal agents were injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teams from the Santa Rita Fire District of Green Valley, Ariz., and American Medical Response, which provides emergency medical services, were dispatched to the reported shooting around milepost 15 on West Arivaca Road, just after 7:30 a.m., the fire district said in an emailed statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crews found “one patient in custody and in critical condition,” and provided medical care before the patient was airlifted to a regional trauma center, the fire district said. The federal agent involved in the shooting also rendered aid for the man, Mr. Janke said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man, Patrick Gary Schlegel, 34, of Sahuarita, Ariz., was transported to the hospital and underwent surgery, Mr. Janke said. He is recovering but remains in serious condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Schlegel has a significant criminal history, including an active federal arrest warrant, and is in federal custody, Mr. Janke said. He is expected to be charged with assault on a federal officer, alien smuggling and being a felon in possession of a firearm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let me be clear: Any assault on law enforcement officers will not be tolerated,” he said. “The F.B.I. will continue to vigorously investigate those who harm or threaten to do harm to those who wear the badge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal agents had seen the vehicle that Mr. Schlegel was driving before 7 a.m. with other passengers. When agents tried to stop the vehicle, which was believed to be involved in human smuggling, “everybody fled, the vehicle fled,” Sheriff Chris Nanos of Pima County said during the news conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in the morning, an agent saw the vehicle again and made a second traffic stop in the area of Arivaca Road, he said. The driver fled, Sheriff Nanos said, and the Border Patrol agent gave chase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pima County Sheriff’s Department said it was working with the F.B.I. and the U.S. Customs and Border Protection, which oversees the Border Patrol, on the case. The department said the F.B.I. had asked it to lead the investigation into the use of force involving the agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a news release, the department said it “will thoroughly examine all aspects of the incident, however, these investigations are complex and require time.” It appears that the Border Patrol agent who shot Mr. Schlegel acted lawfully, Sheriff Nanos said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Border Patrol and its parent agency, Customs and Border Protection, did not immediately respond to requests for comment on the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arivaca Road is about 25 miles from the international border and about 20 miles from the center of Arivaca, an unincorporated community in Arizona. The region and its checkpoints have been a focus of border enforcement for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Customs and Border Protection said a Border Patrol agent “was involved in a use-of-force incident while investigating a human smuggling event” near the Santa Cruz and Pima Counties line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2003, a shooting by a Border Patrol agent wounded one person near Arivaca, one of two shootings in a week that capped a string of drug seizures by the patrol, The Arizona Daily Star reported that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scrutiny of the nation’s immigration debate has been heightened in recent months with the Trump administration crackdown turning violent in Minneapolis, including the fatal shootings of two people by federal officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitty Bennett contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:08:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok Blames Technical Problems After Users Claimed It Blocked ICE Posts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
TikTok’s U.S. entity said in a statement on Monday that a power outage at an American data center had impeded users from uploading new videos.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Senator Warnock Says ‘Soul of Our Nation Is at Stake’ During Visit to Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Senator Raphael Warnock, Democrat of Georgia, on Tuesday at the site where federal agents shot and killed Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:00:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Texas Moves to Curtail H-1B Visas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gov. Greg Abbott has sought to expand on policies coming out of the Trump administration.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:47:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Temporarily Blocks Deportation of 5-Year-Old Detained by ICE in Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-liam1/27minneapolis-ice-Liam-jvht-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A protester holding an artwork of Liam Conejo Ramos in Portland, Maine, last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:40:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Push to Impeach DHS Secretary Kristi Noem After Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
From left, Representatives Pete Aguilar, Democrat of California and the Democratic Caucus chair; Hakeem Jeffries, Democrat of New York and the minority leader; and Katherine Clark, Democrat of Massachusetts and the minority whip, at a news conference in Washington this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:38:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Virginia Judge Blocks Democrats’ Efforts to Redraw Congressional Maps</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/virginia-court-ruling-redistricting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27-nat-virginia-redistricting-jzhc/27-nat-virginia-redistricting-jzhc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Virginia General Assembly convened earlier this month for a new session that included a vote on redistricting and an address by the state’s new Democratic governor, Abigail Spanberger, who greeted legislators, below, as she entered the chamber.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/virginia-court-ruling-redistricting.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:25:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>City Prosecutors Join Forces to Bring Charges Against Federal Agents</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28nat-prosecutors-gczj/28nat-prosecutors-gczj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine progressive prosecutors say they will work together to charge federal agents accused of wrongdoing, but they will face significant legal obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:50:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Issues Order, but No Funds, to Push Faster Rebuilding After L.A. Fires</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-los-angeles-fires-rebuilding</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-la-thmp/27trump-news-la-thmp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump’s executive order on the rebuilding of Los Angeles communities after last year’s wildfires calls for an audit of federal fire assistance that California received immediately after the disaster.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-los-angeles-fires-rebuilding</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:25:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Republicans Shift Tone After Killings, Criticizing Trump’s Immigration Push</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/republicans-shift-tone-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-memo-wkmg/27dc-memo-wkmg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Republicans in Congress have starkly shifted their tone on the Trump administration’s aggressive immigration crackdown, conceding that something must change.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/republicans-shift-tone-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:32:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Suggests He Will ‘De-Escalate’ in Minneapolis, Without Offering Details</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-trump-fbpk/27dc-trump-fbpk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump speaking at the White House before leaving for Iowa on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-minneapolis-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:53:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Minnesota Leaders Meet With White House Border Czar</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-walz-frey-homan-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;Gov. Tim Walz and the mayor of Minneapolis, Jacob Frey, met separately with the Trump aide Tom Homan on Tuesday. All three described the discussions as a productive starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-walz-frey-homan-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:22:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Did the Trump Administration Silence Bovino on Social Media?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/bovino-minnesota-social-media-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-bovino-social-media-qzpm/27dc-bovino-social-media-qzpm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gregory Bovino speaking in Minneapolis last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/bovino-minnesota-social-media-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:29:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens to Pull U.S. Help From Iraq if Former Leader Returns</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iraq-al-maliki.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-iraq-lgwk/27trump-news-iraq-lgwk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, a former prime minister of Iraq, at a polling station in Baghdad in November.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iraq-al-maliki.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:51:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>D.H.S. Review Does Not Say Pretti Brandished Gun, As Noem Claimed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pretti-shooting-minneapolis-dhs-report.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-DHS-report1-ckpq/27minneapolis-ice-DHS-report1-ckpq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A makeshift memorial at the site where Alex Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents during an immigration enforcement operation.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pretti-shooting-minneapolis-dhs-report.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:53:12 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Trump speaks in Iowa, a few thousand demonstrators protest Pretti’s killing.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-iowa-speech-ice-protests</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-iowa-protest-top-fhjp/27trump-news-iowa-protest-top-fhjp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Demonstrators gathered across the street from the Horizon Event Center where President Trump delivered remarks on the economy in Clive, Iowa, on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/27/us/trump-news/trump-iowa-speech-ice-protests</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:35:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Demonizes ICE Detainees in Minnesota as ‘Vicious’ Criminals</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-speech-minnesota-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-trump-speech-wpbv/27minneapolis-ice-trump-speech-wpbv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump at the Horizon Events Center in Clive, Iowa, on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-speech-minnesota-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:02:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Man Rushes Ilhan Omar at Minneapolis Town Hall and Sprays Her</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A man rushed toward Representative Ilhan Omar, Democrat of Minnesota, and sprayed liquid on her on Tuesday night in Minneapolis. Security officials tackled him.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:40:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Noem’s Handling of Shooting Put Her in Trump’s Penalty Box, but Just Briefly</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/noem-trump-minnesota-shooting-fallout.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-noem-gzwq/27dc-noem-gzwq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The fatal shooting in Minnesota over the weekend was the latest episode in which high-profile efforts by Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, on behalf of President Trump’s policies have drawn intense criticism.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/noem-trump-minnesota-shooting-fallout.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:57:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Restore Minnesota House to Even Split Amid Immigration Turmoil</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minnesota-house-special-elections.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-minnesota-election-1-hfzj/27nat-minnesota-election-1-hfzj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Minnesota House of Representatives at the Capitol in St. Paul.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minnesota-house-special-elections.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:11:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Tails of the City: San Francisco’s Latest Animal Sensation Is a Mountain Lion</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/mountain-lion-san-francisco.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;The 2-year-old male was safely captured after he got stuck between two apartment buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/mountain-lion-san-francisco.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:11:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Corey Lewandowski, a Familiar Trumpworld Figure, Is at the Center of the ICE Uproar</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/corey-lewandowski-noem-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/us/politics/27pol-lewandowski/27pol-lewandowski-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Corey Lewandowski and Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, met with President Trump on Monday for nearly two hours as the administration faced intense pressure to ease up federal immigration agents’ aggressive tactics in Minnesota.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/corey-lewandowski-noem-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:26:57 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>