<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:16:12 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>TikTok Blames Technical Problems After Users Claimed It Blocked ICE Posts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok said on Tuesday that its app was facing technical problems after users accused the service of suppressing posts related to Immigration and Customs Enforcement following the shooting of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TikTok’s U.S. operations said in a statement on Monday that a power outage at an American data center had impeded users from uploading new videos. It said that some videos also inaccurately showed that they had zero views or likes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some TikTok users, including the comedian Megan Stalter, have accused the app of blocking them from posting videos about ICE or limiting the reach of those videos. State Senator Scott Wiener, Democrat of California, who is running for Congress, said on X that he had posted about legislation that would allow lawsuits against ICE agents. Mr. Wiener said the post was “sitting at zero views, and I’m not the only person this is happening to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an early test for the app after its Chinese parent company, ByteDance, last week spun off its U.S. operations into a new joint venture controlled by non-Chinese investors. Those investors include firms close to President Trump, like the cloud computing giant Oracle and the Emirati investment firm MGX. The investors’ association with Mr. Trump had raised concerns among some TikTok users that the new venture would slant the app’s content in a more conservative direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for TikTok said on Tuesday that the new U.S. entity had not updated its algorithm since the joint venture was announced. As part of the agreement to spin out the new venture, TikTok’s U.S. operation is planning to retrain the content recommendation algorithm that it will be licensing from ByteDance. The creation of the U.S. TikTok was aimed at addressing longstanding national security concerns about ByteDance’s ties to China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Senator Chris Murphy, Democrat of Connecticut, re-shared a post on X from before Mr. Pretti was killed that accused TikTok of “censoring” content critical of Mr. Trump and ICE. “I know it’s hard to track all the threats to democracy out there right now, but this is at the top of the list,” Mr. Murphy wrote in his post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for the app said in an email that it was “inaccurate to report that this is anything but the technical issues we’ve transparently confirmed.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 09:40:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>City Prosecutors Join Forces to Bring Charges Against Federal Agents</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28nat-prosecutors-gczj/28nat-prosecutors-gczj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nine progressive prosecutors from cities around the country are launching a coalition to assist in prosecuting federal law enforcement officers who violate state laws, one of the prosecutors, Larry Krasner in Philadelphia, said on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization, which is called the Project for the Fight Against Federal Overreach, will also include Mary Moriarty, the elected prosecutor in Minneapolis. Its acronym, F.A.F.O., references a slang term for negative consequences, and its formation was spurred by “growing concerns about warrantless entries, unlawful detentions, and coercive enforcement tactics by federal agents,” according to a news release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The handling of potentially criminal actions by federal agents has become a major issue in Minneapolis after two protesters, both U.S. citizens, were killed there this month by Department of Homeland Security officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Federal Bureau of Investigation said it would not investigate the first killing, of Renee Good, a 37-year-old mother of three. She was killed in her S.U.V. on Jan. 7 as she appeared to be steering away from federal agents during a tense confrontation. Trump administration officials said that the officer who shot Ms. Good had been under attack and was acting in self-defense, and state investigators have been blocked from accessing evidence related to the episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a second resident was killed — Alex Pretti, a Veteran Affairs nurse who was also 37 — federal officials initially appeared to use the same playbook. They blocked state investigators from the scene and declined to provide basic facts, like the identity of the agents involved. In both instances, bystander video contradicted key elements of the Trump administration’s account of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facing a wave of criticism, President Trump on Tuesday promised a “very honorable and honest investigation” into Mr. Pretti’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As videos and reports of ICE officers acting with aggressive force have flooded the country, a small but growing number of law enforcement officials have warned that they would arrest and prosecute federal officials who break their laws. One of the first to do so was the district attorney in San Francisco, Brooke Jenkins, after the president threatened to send National Guard troops there last October. In Minneapolis, protesters have demanded that the local police arrest ICE officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, John Choi, the top prosecutor in Ramsey County, which includes St. Paul, said his office was investigating reports of crimes by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump administration officials say that ICE officers are making cities safer by removing criminals from the streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, the F.B.I. and the Department of Justice’s Office of Civil Rights determine whether the use of deadly force by a federal agent was justified. State prosecutors also have the power to investigate and prosecute state crimes like murder, and they have often done so in cooperation with the federal government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that cooperation has broken down as Trump administration officials have denied that the federal agents committed any wrongdoing and accused Minnesota leaders of thwarting their immigration enforcement efforts and allowing fraud in federally funded programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After local officials were blocked from the investigations, Ms. Moriarty, the elected prosecutor for Hennepin County, resorted to opening a web portal to allow the public to submit evidence like cellphone videos. She has said that she expects to have enough evidence to decide whether to pursue charges in the two killings. Her office is also investigating a third incident in which a Venezuelan man was shot in the leg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecuting any police officer raises significant obstacles, since officers are authorized to use deadly force when they reasonably perceive a serious threat. The Constitution’s supremacy clause gives federal agents additional protection, though they do not have absolute immunity, as Vice President JD Vance initially claimed. They can ask for a federal court to shield them from prosecution if their actions were authorized under federal law, and if they can show that they did “no more than what was necessary and proper.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Krasner said the new organization would provide “mutual support” to prosecutors who are “up against the might of the federal government.” So far, nine prosecutors from around the country have signed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are a very substantial tool against what I consider to be a pretty clear attempt to normalize fascism and to overthrow democracy in the United States,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other locations whose elected prosecutors are participating include Austin; Dallas; Pima County in Arizona, which includes Tucson; and several cities in Virginia: Fairfax, Falls Church and Arlington, Portsmouth and Norfolk.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/prosecutors-charges-against-federal-agents.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:23:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Representative Ilhan Omar Is Attacked at Town Hall in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf/27minneapolis-ice-Omarattack-vpkf-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a town hall with Representative Ilhan Omar in Minneapolis on Tuesday evening, a man rushed the lectern and appeared to spray her with a strong-smelling liquid before he was tackled by security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man, who had been seated directly in front of the lectern in the front row, suddenly jumped up as Ms. Omar was speaking and ran toward the podium. He used a syringe to spray her shirt with a substance that smelled strongly of vinegar. As he stumbled backward and pointed at her, a security officer tackled him to the ground, handcuffed him and removed him from the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gasps were audible through the crowd, as well as cries of “Oh my God, oh my God.” Some attendees yelled out, “He sprayed something!” A woman in the crowd appeared near tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Minneapolis Police said the man, whom they later identified as Anthony J. Kazmierczak, 55, was arrested and booked into jail on suspicion of assault. A forensics squad was called to analyze the scene, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar, a Democrat who represents part of Minneapolis and has been a frequent target of President Trump, held the town hall in her district of Minneapolis to address the ongoing ICE operations in the city. Hours before, Mr. Trump criticized Ms. Omar at a rally in Iowa and repeated inflammatory remarks about her birth country, Somalia. He said immigrants “have to show that they can love our country. They have to be proud, not like Ilhan Omar.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assault occurred just after she said: “We must abolish ICE for good. And D.H.S. Secretary Kristi Noem must resign or face impeachment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her comment mirrored calls by Democratic lawmakers for Ms. Noem, the homeland security secretary, to step down or face impeachment after federal immigration agents shot and killed two people in Minneapolis this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar, visibly shaken after the assault, insisted to her staff and security that she would continue. She asked for a napkin and told them: “Just give me 10 minutes. I beg you. Please don’t let them have the show.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Omar then turned the crowd. “Here’s the reality that people like this ugly man don’t understand,” she said. “We are Minnesota strong, and we will stay resilient in the face of whatever they might throw at us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone in the crowd later thanked Ms. Omar for staying and continuing after the assault, which had shaken not only her but the entire room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I learned at a young age you don’t give in to threats,” Ms. Omar said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About an hour after the town hall, Ms. Omar posted on social media that she was OK and grateful to her constituents for rallying behind her after the assault. “I’m a survivor so this small agitator isn’t going to intimidate me from doing my work,” she said. “I don’t let bullies win.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Capitol Police, which investigates threats against lawmakers, said in a statement that the attack on Ms. Omar was “unacceptable” and would be met with “swift justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are now working with our federal partners to see this man faces the most serious charges possible to deter this kind of violence in our society,” the agency said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As video of the encounter quickly circulated on social media, some officials condemned the assault. Mayor Jacob Frey of Minneapolis denounced the attack, saying on X that “this kind of behavior will not be tolerated in our city,” and that “violence and intimidation have no place in Minneapolis,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representative Nancy Mace, a South Carolina Republican who has often been at odds with Ms. Omar, said she was “deeply disturbed” by the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Regardless of how vehemently I disagree with her rhetoric — and I do — no elected official should face physical attacks,” she said in a social media post. “This is not who we are.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Bogel-Burroughs contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ilhan-omar-town-hall-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:59:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Loose Rules Let State Police Hand Out Lax Penalties for Serious Misconduct</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/new-york-state-police-discipline.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20lif-ny-state-police-02-fvlj/20lif-ny-state-police-02-fvlj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigator with the New York State Police helped get a friend’s traffic tickets reduced “in exchange” for her sexually explicit photos, according to a disciplinary letter from 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another stunned a combative suspect with his Taser in 2020 and held down the trigger for 33 seconds, twice the amount of time widely considered dangerous and potentially fatal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some officers with the agency neglected their duties; others had sex while on duty. Some used their badges to elicit favors; others to settle personal scores. Some failed to call for medical aid when needed; others lied in police reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circumstances of any case of officer misconduct vary. Still, most large police agencies in New York State thoroughly outline steps to be taken in their investigative processes and have explicit disciplinary guidelines that recommend specific punishments — in some cases, even firing — for these types of offenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the State Police, New York’s second-biggest law enforcement agency, has no such formal disciplinary guidelines. How a misconduct complaint is investigated, and any resulting discipline, is discretionary. All of these officers remained on the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times and New York Focus, a nonprofit newsroom, obtained through records requests thousands of State Police disciplinary files dating back to 1998. For the most part, the files do not include cases of officers committing crimes, which are generally investigated by prosecutors. But they do include confirmed cases of misconduct handled by the agency itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An examination of agency files from 2014 to 2024 revealed a far weaker disciplinary system than those used in other large departments in New York. It is one that has routed complaints of flagrant wrongdoing to low-levels of scrutiny, and that has addressed abuses of power and derelictions of duty with lax punishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cases were investigated by an internal affairs office, but without formal guidelines, discipline was applied inconsistently. One trooper who had sex while on duty, for example, received an eight-day suspension without pay. Two years earlier he had been caught taking a photo of his genitalia while in uniform. But two others who also had sex while on duty, records show, got suspensions of 45 and 90 days without pay, even though they had relatively cleaner disciplinary records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other cases — those that the office decided could be handled at a lower level — were addressed with a conversation between trooper and supervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And despite repeated calls for reform, the State Police’s disciplinary system remained largely unchanged for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Police declined multiple requests for interviews with agency leadership. Beau Duffy, a director of public information with the State Police, wrote in a statement that “allegations involving serious misconduct are thoroughly investigated” and that the agency began developing a formal disciplinary model in 2025. It is not yet complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The circumstances and facts revealed during an investigation can vary widely” and influence possible discipline, Mr. Duffy wrote, adding that “past precedent, and an employee’s previous history” also play a role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, a representative for Gov. Kathy Hochul of New York wrote that “this Administration fully investigates any claims of wrongdoing” and supports Steven G. James, who took over the State Police as superintendent in 2024. The representative declined to comment on actions of past administrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suat Cubukcu, a professor of criminal justice at Towson University who studies discipline in large law enforcement agencies, including those in New York, said that weak disciplinary systems and inconsistencies in punishments could lead to more bad behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People see that their colleagues aren’t being punished,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With more than 5,200 officers across roughly 200 stations, the State Police has a reputation for investigative work; troopers are often brought in to aid local law enforcement in serious cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But disciplinary files from the agency’s 11 regional troops, many of which had never before been reviewed by journalists, revealed a lack of scrutiny when the department policed its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internal affairs office, called the Professional Standards Bureau, independently investigates “serious or complex” allegations of officer misconduct, per the agency’s website, but generally assigns those of a “routine nature” to the commanders of troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commanders resolve these cases with troopers, who waive their union representation. Following a conversation with the trooper, commanders must write a letter summarizing their findings, and, if they feel it is warranted, issue a suspension not exceeding five days, or a loss of five or fewer vacation days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process was designed so that commanders could handle minor complaints, like lost equipment or cursing on the job. But without formal disciplinary guidelines, the bureau’s determination of which complaints are serious — and which are minor — is subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This includes the case of the trooper who stunned a suspect and “inadvertently held the trigger” of his Taser for 33 seconds, per a disciplinary letter. The trooper’s commander found his actions were “excessive” and summed up the “informal inquiry” in the one-page letter: “We discussed the importance of attention to detail,” wrote the commander. “Handling a Taser requires your complete attention.” The trooper lost one vacation day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mac Muir, a former investigator for New York City’s Civilian Complaint Review Board, an independent agency that investigates allegations of police misconduct by members of the New York Police Department, questioned the State Police’s handling of the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Show me a large police department that doesn’t require more than a supervisory review for a 33 second Taser deployment,” said Mr. Muir, who also supervised disciplinary investigations in Oakland, Calif. “I’ve literally never heard of that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also criticized the report for lacking an interview transcript, which is not required in troop-level investigations. “Without a recorded statement, there’s no meaningful way to hold the officer accountable,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a more robust disciplinary record, the complete context of the case is unclear. But in the New York Police Department, the state’s largest agency, disciplinary policy would suggest that an officer who used excessive force with a stun gun face termination or, at minimum, a 10-day penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns about how complaints at the State Police are designated, and who looks into them, are not new. In 1997, a special prosecutor appointed to investigate troopers who tampered with evidence in multiple cases criticized the State Police for resolving complaints of serious misconduct at the troop level, recommending that such cases be investigated by the standards bureau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Moran, a law professor at the University of St. Thomas School of Law who studies police accountability, called it “troubling” that some cases she viewed as serious were investigated at the troop level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When you see such a large agency that doesn’t even have a systematic way of deciding when discipline is appropriate and at what level,” she said, “it suggests a lack of attention to the issue of accountability entirely.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, a trooper responding to a “shots-fired” call missed a loaded revolver in a suspect’s pocket, allowing the suspect to bring the weapon into the police station. Ten months later, his commander talked to him and issued a disciplinary letter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That year, another trooper responded “telephonically” to a larceny call at a Lowe’s store, interviewing employees over the phone while he and his sergeant ate breakfast. After conversations with their commander five months later, the trooper lost two vacation days; the sergeant lost three, according to records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a separate incident two months later, records show, the same sergeant was caught adding false information to a police report. He lost four vacation days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Duffy said he could not comment on previous leadership, adding that the bureau currently does “not assign cases involving serious misconduct to troop level.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, the agency faced public scrutiny when the Times Union reported that some high-ranking agency leaders had used their police credentials to access exclusive areas of the Ryder Cup, a golf tournament on Long Island, two months earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after the article was published, the agency’s superintendent wrote in a statement that it had learned of the allegations the week prior and was turning the case over to the state inspector general. Many involved in the incident, including the first deputy superintendent in charge of agency discipline, have since resigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement, a representative for the troopers’ union wrote that the scandal exemplified a “two-tiered system, in which rank-and-file Troopers are held to stricter standards than those in leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the weeks following the 2020 murder of George Floyd by a Minneapolis police officer, the New York Legislature passed a number of police reform laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the State Police was one of a handful of multicounty agencies excluded from most of the changes, and it unsuccessfully fought in court one of the few that did apply: the repeal of a 1976 law that kept officer disciplinary records secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Police Department made most of its files public in 2021. But despite a court order, the State Police has yet to make its entire body of misconduct files public. WKBW, a Buffalo TV station, reported on some records obtained from a local district attorney about state troopers in their area in 2022. The thousands of State Police files obtained by The Times and New York Focus came through records requests of county district attorneys’ offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They say it’s too burdensome to identify all the files,” said Cory Morris, an attorney on Long Island who in 2021 sued for the disciplinary files of troopers across three counties. He continues to fight the agency for prompt access to the records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well then, how much misconduct is there?” he asked in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, former Gov. Andrew M. Cuomo signed an order requiring hundreds of police agencies to submit police reform plans to the state. The Legislature passed a law requiring police agencies to report to the attorney general repeated allegations of misconduct against an officer over a two-year period. Neither requirement applied to the State Police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al Taylor, a state assemblyman and author of the bill, said in an interview that he thought the agency faced oversight from the state inspector general’s office. That office investigates waste, fraud and abuse — exploiting overtime, for example — but it does not routinely investigate allegations of law enforcement misconduct, like excessive force. There is no regulation or statute requiring the State Police to report repeated allegations of misconduct to the inspector general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s worth taking a look at it again,” Mr. Taylor said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its most recent reports, from 2020 and 2022, the state inspector general’s office criticized the State Police for its disciplinary practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discipline “was extremely lenient and lacked transparency,” the inspector general wrote in a 2020 report about an off-duty officer’s car crash of a federally leased vehicle. The agency lacked policies “to ensure consistency and transparency in the classification of violations,” the inspector general wrote, “as well as the assignment of discipline.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the 2022 report, the Professional Standards Bureau began sharing cases it investigates in monthly meetings with the inspector general’s office, according to Mr. Duffy, the agency representative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in not yet making the bulk of its misconduct files available to the public, many complaints — and how they were handled — remain concealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some instances, records obtained by The Times and New York Focus show, state troopers evaded public scrutiny — even, in one case, when an officer from another agency faced significant criticism over the same incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2021 a police officer in the village of Monticello ended a traffic pursuit by firing his stun gun at a motorcyclist through the passenger-side window. The motorcyclist sustained serious injuries. The officer was suspended, and he resigned in the face of public scrutiny and a disciplinary investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was not widely reported was that a State Police trooper was riding in the passenger seat. The trooper, records revealed, failed to render aid to the motorcyclist, or call an ambulance. He turned off his body camera, and didn’t report the use of force, a disciplinary letter later noted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Monticello officer was criminally charged for impeding an investigation and lost his certification to be a police officer in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following an investigation by the standards bureau, the trooper was suspended without pay for three days. He remains on the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sarah Cohen contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was reported in partnership with Big Local News at Stanford University, and with support from MuckRock, the Fund for Investigative Journalism and the Data-Driven Reporting Project.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/new-york-state-police-discipline.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How the Online SAT May Be Vulnerable to Cheating</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/how-the-online-sat-may-be-vulnerable-to-cheating.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-sat-cheating-cfvl/26nat-sat-cheating-cfvl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, after nearly a century of testing on paper, the College Board rolled out a new digital SAT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students who had long relied on No. 2 pencils to take the exam would instead use their laptops. One advantage, the College Board said, was a reduced chance of cheating, in part because delivering the test online meant the questions would vary for each student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, however, worries are growing that the College Board’s security isn’t fail safe. Fueling the concerns are what appear to be copies of recently administered digital SAT questions that have been posted on the internet — on social media sites as well as websites primarily housed in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SAT leaks dominated the conversation in November at an international education conference in Seville, Spain, according to Angel B. Peréz, the head of the National Association for College Admission Counseling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was the talk of cocktail parties at the international high school conference,” Dr. Peréz said in an interview. “I had a few counselors come up to me to say, ‘we are very concerned.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The College Board was alerted to the cheating efforts by an SAT tutor, according to emails obtained by The New York Times. “This is not a matter of one compromised form. It is a multiyear breach of active test material, accessible on a global scale,” the tutor wrote to the College Board in November, according to the emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutor, who works with students at a prestigious European boarding school, asked the Times not to be identified, fearing harm to his students and school. But after reviewing leaked questions, he said he concluded that at least some of them were authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A near-identical version began circulating on the Internet months before it was decommissioned by the College Board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The function g is defined by g(z) = |x|a - 14, where a &lt; 0. What is the product of g(15a) and g(7a)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SAT is administered seven to eight times a year, and the College Board says its network includes 1,700 testing sites in 187 countries. Students take the test at an SAT-approved site, but they are permitted to use their own laptops. While some colleges, including the Ivy League, made standardized admissions tests optional during the pandemic, many top schools have since reinstated a requirement that applicants submit a standardized test score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the sites — bluebook.plus, an apparent knockoff of the official College Board platform, Bluebook, used to administer the actual test — posts what it says are practice tests that students can pay to access. But some of the questions appear to be real, possibly providing questions that ultimately may appear on a student’s actual exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, bluebook.plus, which appears from domain name searches to be based in China, had 875,000 visitors, according to an analysis by the web traffic site Similarweb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bluebook.plus site did not respond to an emailed request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concerns about the security of the digital SAT follow breaches involving other digital tests, including the Law School Admissions Test and Graduate Record Examination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The College Board said in written statements that SAT cheating is rare, affecting only a fraction of 1 percent of its test scores, and noted that overall test scores have remained steady after the transition to digital tests. “However, some students will always be tempted to cheat on high-stakes assessment, and bad actors are persistent. We stay hypervigilant,” it wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The College Board also acknowledged that, “in certain international markets, bad actors have long made concerted efforts to access and share test content (as well as fabricate content) in order to take advantage of anxious students and parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization has taken steps to make cheating on the digital test more difficult. The exam is adaptive, meaning that test-takers who perform well early in the exam receive harder questions as they go along. And the College Board says the tests are drawn from a pool of “several hundred thousand” test items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to having human proctors present during testing, the SAT’s Bluebook platform requires that other apps on a student’s computer be turned off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the organization acknowledged that it was aware of “screenshots that purport to have been taken while testing is in progress” as well as “hardware and software-based efforts to evade our security system.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A variety of coding and SAT “prep” websites discuss ways to bypass Bluebook security. One way is to use a plug-in that seems like a mouse, but is, in fact, a video capture device. Another is a program called a “sandbox, an isolated virtual environment that can work without detection within a computer. Users in various forums, as well as advertisements, also discuss the remote takeover of a student’s computer by an off-site proxy test taker, operating much like an office IT expert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test experts caution that many of these ads are scams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheating on standardized tests is not new. In the Varsity Blues college admissions scheme, wealthy parents paid test site administrators to allow others to take tests for their children, give them answers or change answers after testing was complete. Other SAT leaks over the years have included the theft of paper tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rob Franek, editor in chief of Princeton Review, a publishing and test preparation company, said there has been cheating “since these tests were invented,” adding, “certainly, the digital versions were not spared.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allegations of SAT cheating follow breaches in digital LSAT and GRE tests used by dozens of prestigious law and graduate programs to screen applicants. In those cases, the tests were taken remotely, not in test centers like the SAT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several graduate business schools, including those at the Ohio State University and the University of Minnesota, rescinded admissions offers in 2024 following allegations of GRE cheating by students in Ghana and Nigeria who had taken the tests at home, according to the online publication Poets &amp; Quants, which writes about business schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August, the Law School Admission Council, which administers the LSAT, suspended testing in China, the only place that tests were administered remotely. (The SAT is no longer administered in China because of government restrictions in that country. Instead, students travel to Hong Kong, Macau, or South Korea to take the test.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In announcing the LSAT suspension, Susan L. Krinsky, executive vice president of the organization, sounded an alarm about the growth of test cheating. Her organization, she said, had become “increasingly concerned about organized efforts by individuals and companies in mainland China to promote test misconduct.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added: “This type of activity is not limited to the LSAT; these enterprises purport to offer cheating services for virtually every standardized test.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LSAT cheating was exposed when a Chinese law student in the United States raised alarms after seeing cheating services advertised on RedNote, a Chinese social media platform. The student, using the pseudonym “Travis,” later discussed LSAT security problems on a podcast hosted by Mike Spivey, an LSAT admissions consultant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Schoenig, a former head of security for the ACT, the second-largest undergraduate admissions test, said the web is filled with ads from companies selling hardware and software, purportedly to help students cheat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Some are scams,” she wrote in an email. But, she added, “The reality is that no system is foolproof.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Schoenig, now chief executive of Cornerstone Strategies, an industry consultant, described efforts to ensure test security and the counter-efforts by cheaters as “always a bit of a cat-and-mouse game.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that students are permitted to use their own laptops is one weak link that several experts flagged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is evidence that digital test security problems are spreading beyond standardized admissions tests, with companies operating online that offer to take college exams for students, for a fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cornell Law School has notified students that it is investigating a testing breach during a contracts exam in December. The school learned of the problem because a paid test taker — intending to advertise his services — posted screen shots of the exam online shortly after gaining remote access to a student’s laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for Cornell confirmed that its law school had investigated an “isolated incident of alleged testing misconduct,” adding that the school would not comment on disciplinary cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The content of the SAT exam is not public, but the tutor who notified the College Board said he was able to authenticate some of the questions students flagged to him. One way was to compare old SAT questions that were retired last year, which the College Board has since published online, with questions posted earlier on cheating sites when those retired questions were still being used on the SAT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, an advanced math question, part of a March 2025 international exam that was posted online and shared with the European tutor by a student, was virtually identical to a question the College Board removed from its question bank in August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When presented with the similarities, the College Board said it would not comment on any test content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, metadata showed that questions were posted online almost instantaneously after the test — creating the possibility of “time zone cheating,” in which test takers in a later time zone can gain access to the test questions before their test begins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Test questions also have been sold on Telegram, a Dubai-based platform, and posted on Scribd, a subscription digital repository of data. Students have also circulated questions among themselves on Google docs, the European tutor said. Many of the tests have been removed from Scribd, apparently at the College Board’s request. A spokesman for Scribd, based in San Francisco, said the company responds to valid requests to remove copyrighted material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the College Board has been unable to fight bluebook.plus, according to an email exchange with the College Board that the tutor shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We did go through the legal process to request a takedown, but as is often the case with international sites, we didn’t get a response,” wrote a College Board security official, Michael Thiel, responding to the tutor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Thiel added: “Some of what’s posted may be real, some isn’t, but none of these sites have all the SAT questions.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/how-the-online-sat-may-be-vulnerable-to-cheating.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 07:51:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How We Tracked Down Thousands of Police Misconduct Files</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/how-we-tracked-down-thousands-of-police-misconduct-files.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28lif-foil-sidebar-bqhv/28lif-foil-sidebar-bqhv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent the past two and a half years requesting and reviewing more than 10,000 misconduct files from New York State’s roughly 500 police agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work has been as tedious as it probably sounds. But it has also contributed to a new era of transparency around policing. These files, many of which had never been reviewed, reveal the systems through which police departments have addressed negligence and misconduct committed by their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work started in 2023, when I filed a request with the Orange County District Attorney’s Office for its “Brady files,” or records about police officers’ potential credibility issues. I assumed I would receive a few files about a handful of officers with known disciplinary histories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the office sent me more than 1,600 pages of files pertaining to misconduct by hundreds of officers in the county and the surrounding area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to get most of these records is relatively new. Starting in 1976, New York State, by law, kept most police personnel records secret. But when the law was repealed in 2020, many departments began making their records available. Others resisted the change, demanding large payments to do the work of pulling the files, providing lengthy timelines or ignoring requests altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the immediate aftermath of the law’s repeal, the Democrat and Chronicle in Rochester filed records requests with every police department in the state. The news organization received huge troves of records, but it also received a number of denials from police departments, a few of which it took to court. From the files it obtained, the organization published an investigation, “Driving Force,” that documented the toll of hundreds of car crashes by on-duty police officers around the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran into similar walls. I filed administrative appeals to challenge almost all the denials, citing a growing body of case law requiring the prompt release of these records. In a few instances, I sued to force agencies to comply. (The New York Times, where I worked as a reporter in the Local Investigations Fellowship, a program that helps local reporters produce investigative work about their communities, continues to represent me in a suit against the Erie County Sheriff’s Office.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I stumbled upon a loophole: Though some police departments were denying or delaying reporters’ requests for records, they were required to share files with their county district attorney’s office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One police chief in Orange County, for example, said in response to my request that there were “no records” of discipline in his department. But records provided by his county district attorney’s office told a different story: An officer in the department had written a confidential letter to members of the village board about accusations of sexual misconduct against the chief, which he denied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I filed requests with every county district attorney’s office in the state. Not every office replied, and I would often try again (and again). In counties that did, I used the records from the district attorney to ask for records from local police departments. Many departments released records after they learned that their local district attorney had already provided me with a few. In total, I filed more than 800 requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In New York, records requests are governed by the Freedom of Information Law, leading some to refer to these requests as “FOIL requests.” Anyone can file a request with a government agency under this law for access to existing records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other states, New York does not confine records requests to state residents. And though agencies most often receive requests from lawyers or journalists, they are generally barred from considering a requester’s job title or motivation while deciding whether to grant access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agencies can withhold information that falls within specific privacy exemptions, such as the disclosure of confidential informants, law enforcement techniques or material that would pose an invasion of privacy. In most instances, a requester can ask an agency to redact certain information while still turning over some portions of the text, but some agencies are pushing back in court. Almost all of the files I received were redacted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote about the contents of the files for New York Focus, a nonprofit newsroom, before joining The Times’s fellowship. I wrote about officers who evaded criminal charges despite driving drunk, an officer who failed to properly investigate a child sexual abuse case and most recently, how the State Police department sometimes handed out lax punishments for officer misconduct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After every article, readers emailed me asking how they could get records for officers in their communities. My process was mind-numbing at times, and I wouldn’t recommend it to everyone. But filing records requests is something the public has a right to do.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/how-we-tracked-down-thousands-of-police-misconduct-files.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:00:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Minneapolis Rages, Legislators Move to Restrict ICE in Their States</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/minneapolis-ice-states.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25nat-ice-legislatures-kzjc/25nat-ice-legislatures-kzjc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the deaths of two American citizens in Minneapolis at the hands of federal agents, Democratic legislators across the country, aided by libertarian groups, are redoubling their efforts to restrict and challenge federal immigration tactics in their states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Colorado bill that was introduced in mid-January would enable individuals to sue federal law enforcement officials for civil rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Delaware, a bill similar to one that was filed in New York last spring would prevent commercial airlines from receiving jet fuel tax exemptions if they transport people detained by Immigration and Customs Enforcement without warrants and due process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in the wake of the killing on Saturday of Alex Pretti in Minneapolis, a California lawmaker said he would sponsor two bills, one to require that any shooting by ICE agents be subject to an independent state investigation, and another to bar ICE from using state properties as a staging area for federal operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the second Trump administration embarked on its large-scale deportation effort, Democratic-leaning states have proposed — and passed, in some instances — countermeasures, such as banning masked or unidentified law enforcement officers. Last month, a dozen legislators from seven states announced that they would coordinate legislation in 2026 to complement the litigation already being used by Democratic attorneys general to challenge immigration policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the killings of both Mr. Pretti and Renee Good, a resident protesting ICE’s presence in the Twin Cities, those endeavors have gained more urgency, according to lawmakers and immigration rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I do think that we are starting to see legislators who, last session, were afraid of being a thorn in the side of an ascendant Trump administration — they were so afraid of poking the bear,” said Naureen Shah, who leads the American Civil Liberties Union’s immigration and advocacy work. “The tide is now turning, and maybe they feel that they’ve got nothing to lose.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abigail Jackson, a White House spokeswoman, questioned the motives of all those state-level Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Democrats don’t care about the rule of law,” she said. “If they did, they would support the president’s law-and-order agenda, which includes enforcing federal immigration law. Instead, Democrats are openly undermining the rule of law to protect criminal illegal aliens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some states that are controlled by Republicans have gone the opposite direction. A new bill in the South Carolina legislature would mandate that all county sheriffs enter into formal agreements to work with ICE. Tennessee Republicans want government agencies to check the legal status of all residents as a condition of receiving public assistance, and also to verify the immigration status of elementary and secondary school students, despite a decade-old Supreme Court ruling that forbade it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With most state legislatures back in session, patterns are emerging out of the dozens of bills that are active or being discussed, said Gaby Goldstein, the founder of State Futures, which organizes progressive lawmakers nationally and tracks legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many are related to rule-of-law concerns and civil rights protections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Colorado proposal, for instance, mirrors ones in California, Washington, Wisconsin and elsewhere that seek to establish a private right of action, which would give individuals or organizations the ability to file civil lawsuits for constitutional violations in state court, rather than on the federal courts, said State Senator Mike Weissman, the bill’s primary sponsor and a lawyer by trade. He represents the Denver suburb of Aurora, which Mr. Trump has said has been “taken over” by Venezuelan gangs. His bill would take aim at civil immigration enforcement, he said, “not police officers doing ordinary work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the legislation would apply to ICE and other branches of the Department of Homeland Security, he emphasized that the bill focuses on conduct that would violate constitutional rights rather than on employees of any particular branch of government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I mean, to use a crazy example, if Trump starts mobilizing park service employees to go crack heads and violate the Fourth Amendment, they’re going to find themselves answerable as well,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has been working with the Institute for Justice, a libertarian group that has long battled against federal overreach. One of its cases involves a construction worker in Alabama of Mexican descent who, despite being a U.S. citizen and showing his REAL ID, was detained twice by masked agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under current legal standards, Anya Bidwell, a senior attorney for the Institute for Justice, said individuals find it hard to sue state and local officials, and all but impossible to sue federal ones, who have broader immunity. And with the Supreme Court and Congress showing no appetite to step in, she said it is incumbent upon a state to “protect its own citizens.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Power works in a way that once you have it, you try to accumulate more and more and more of it,” she said. “And it’s really important to be able to fight back and to be able to enforce the rights that are guaranteed to us as individuals. That really shouldn’t be a partisan issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sensibility is also guiding State Senator Anthony Broadman, a first-term Democrat who represents a swing district in Bend, Ore., and is trying to appeal to conservatives who might remember when they were the ones outraged by federal recklessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oregonians, Mr. Broadman said, still remember the armed sieges in Ruby Ridge, Idaho, and in the Malheur National Wildlife Refuge in eastern Oregon, he said, “where conservatives have been harmed by the federal government.” So he hopes to introduce a bill similar to the one in Colorado that would apply to federal constitutional violations, but would not be limited to immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s not just liberals and immigrants who get hurt by the United States, when they violate people’s rights,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other targets of state-level Democratic bills include banning agreements that delegate some federal immigration powers to state and municipal law enforcement agencies (Hawaii, Massachusetts, Vermont) and banning masked or unidentified law enforcement officers (Maryland, Arizona, Virginia).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bill in Washington would limit the ability of federal immigrant agents to enter child care centers, health care facilities and election sites without a warrant or court order. And in Maryland, one lawmaker wants to prevent ICE agents who were recruited by the Trump administration from later working for any state law enforcement agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democrats are also hoping to gain more traction on bills introduced last year that would use fiscal tools to clamp down on immigration tactics, such as by restricting public contracting with companies that work with ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lawmakers in Maryland and New York have proposed that if the federal government withholds money that the state is owed, in defiance of court decisions, then they would place liens on federally owned properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has already begun to fight back. The Department of Justice sued Illinois in December after the Democratic governor, JB Pritzker, signed a law making it easier for state residents to sue immigration agents. Federal lawyers argued that the law placed the agents in physical harm and at financial risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One state whose legislature is not scheduled to meet until Feb. 17 is Minnesota. But already, legislators are hammering out bills in response to Ms. Good’s death, such as prohibiting or limiting ICE agents from entering sensitive places such as hospitals, schools and group homes, said State Senator Erin Murphy, the chamber’s top Democrat, a nurse by training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another proposal — which she believes has not been introduced elsewhere — would require that federal agents operating in Minnesota meet the same kind of training requirements now in place for local law enforcement — including providing first aid. ICE agents appeared to reject offers to aid Ms. Good after she was shot, including from a man who identified himself as a doctor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no Republican co-sponsors yet for any of the proposed bills. But Ms. Murphy did note that Representative Marion Rarick, who represents a reliably Republican district about 45 minutes northwest of Minneapolis, had posted on Facebook that “ICE must stop racial profiling and violating civil rights as has been experienced and documented by LAW ENFORCEMENT. Full stop. No excuses. Just stop.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laurel Rosenhall contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/minneapolis-ice-states.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:02:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Height of Close-Combat Weaponry Is on This Woman’s Doorstep</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ice-agent-weapons-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/00nat-minn-gun-fjzw/00nat-minn-gun-fjzw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images of the immigration crackdowns in Minneapolis and across the United States have been likened to those from the country’s wars in Iraq and Afghanistan. The helmets, camouflage and tactical gear all look straight from the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere is that more apparent than in a single photo taken on Jan. 11 by John Locher of The Associated Press. It captures a line of federal agents on the doorstep of a woman’s home, rifles in hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon closer inspection, the agents’ equipment tells its own story. Their gear is the physical manifestation of decades of war, fine-tuned and perfected for close-quarters killing over myriad operations in faraway lands but now wielded in broad daylight in American cities. This type of equipment is often reserved for SWAT and hostage rescue units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppressor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppressor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppressors, like the ones on the end of these rifles, have migrated from soldiers to law enforcement officers and civilians. They have proliferated because of the added safety benefits of reducing brain trauma and hearing damage when shooting indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The production of firearm suppressors, or silencers, climbed by more than 9,000 percent from 2000 to 2021, according to data from the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives. The suppressor highlighted above is made by HUXWRX Safety Co. In recent years, the company was awarded a multimillion-dollar contract to supply the F.B.I. with its suppressors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAWL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAWL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just behind the muzzle toward the front of the rifle are two modular advanced weapons lasers, commonly referred to as MAWLs, made by B.E. Meyers &amp; Co., Inc. The laser is considered top of its class and is described in the company’s literature as “the superior solution for any low light/no light combat environment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Iraq and Afghanistan and elsewhere, the U.S. military’s dominance on the battlefield was aided by advanced night-vision equipment and thermal-imaging technology. Troops used infrared aiming lasers that evolved from clunky-looking boxes on the end of their rifles to streamlined and ergonomic tools that cost more than $3,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M-LOK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M-LOK&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two of the rifles have modernized black rails mounted around their barrels, which allow accessories to attach more easily. These are Daniel Defense MFR M-LOK rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the M4 — the military equivalent of the AR-15 — U.S. Special Operations Command has championed the M-LOK, or modular lock, for its lighter weight and sturdiness when securing devices like lasers, flashlights and grips. Daniel Defense receivers and barrels are used across the U.S. military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DUMP POUCHES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DUMP POUCHES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also pictured in the photos is a smattering of tactical gear plucked from the battlefield. The tan and camouflage “dump pouches” on the agents’ belts are used to store expended ammunition magazines (though they often just hold snacks and water bottles).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAGWELL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MAGWELL&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clasped on one agent’s weapon is a rifle combat magwell, a piece of plastic that helps widen the aperture for an ammunition magazine so the firearm is easier to reload when adrenaline overpowers fine-motor skills during a firefight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civilian standing in the doorway, at the receiving end of a swarm of well-armed federal agents, was Teyana Gibson Brown. Her husband, Garrison Gibson, who is from Liberia, was arrested during the raid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a video taken from inside the house and posted on Instagram and other social media sites, Ms. Brown yells for the agents to put down their guns. “There’s kids in this house,” Ms. Brown said. “Show the warrant first.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal judge ordered Mr. Gibson’s release four days later, ruling that the agents violated his Fourth Amendment rights against unlawful search and seizure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annotations by James Thomas and Gray Beltran. Video production by Jackeline Luna and Zach Wasser.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ice-agent-weapons-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:02:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ecuador Objects After ICE Agent Tries to Enter Minneapolis Consulate</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ice-ecuador-consulate-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28minneapolis-ice-ecuador-consulate-cmlh/28minneapolis-ice-ecuador-consulate-cmlh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecuador’s foreign ministry said it lodged a formal diplomatic protest with the United States after a U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agent attempted to enter the country’s consulate in Minneapolis without permission on Tuesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employees of the consulate stopped the agent from entering, the Ecuadorean foreign ministry said in a statement Tuesday night. Under the Vienna Conventions, to which the United States is a party, foreign consular buildings are off-limits to law enforcement from the host country without authorization from consular officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incident comes amid an aggressive federal immigration crackdown in Minnesota that has prompted an outpouring of anger in the state and across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video footage verified by The New York Times shows a member of staff rushing to an entrance to the consulate, where an agent appears to have opened the door. The employee can be heard saying, “This is the Ecuadorean consulate, you’re not allowed to enter.” The agent responds by saying, “If you touch me, I’ll grab you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consulate, in Northeast Minneapolis, has a clearly marked facade emblazoned with Ecuador’s national seal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ecuadorean foreign ministry said it had lodged its complaint with the American Embassy in Ecuador “so that acts of this nature don’t happen again.” The Department of Homeland Security did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incident comes a week after ICE agents detained 5-year-old Liam Conejo Ramos outside of his school building in Minneapolis. A photograph of the incident — Liam detained, in a bright blue bunny hat and a Spiderman backpack — sent waves of outrage through the Twin Cities area and across the country. Liam came to America with his father from Ecuador in 2024, and both were pursuing legal asylum claims.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ice-ecuador-consulate-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:45:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nervous Allies and Fox News: How Trump Realized He Had a Big Problem in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-minnesota-noem-bovino-homan-miller.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-trump-minnesota-top-cpqh/27dc-trump-minnesota-top-cpqh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump has honed a survival tactic over many years facing criticism in the public eye.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-minnesota-noem-bovino-homan-miller.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:33:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>To Combat Fake Water Filters, GE Appliances Opens Own U.S. Factory</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ge-appliances-water-filters-factory.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28biz-fake-ge-filters-fwpc/28biz-fake-ge-filters-fwpc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A GE plant in Louisville, Ky., in 2014. GE Appliances is opening a factory in the city to make water filters for its refrigerators.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ge-appliances-water-filters-factory.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:00:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump threatens Iran again and calls for negotiations on a nuclear deal.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/28/us/trump-news/trump-threatens-iran-again-and-calls-for-negotiations-on-a-nuclear-deal</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28trump-news-iran-lzjg/28trump-news-iran-lzjg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A billboard in Tehran depicts strikes on an American aircraft carrier.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/28/us/trump-news/trump-threatens-iran-again-and-calls-for-negotiations-on-a-nuclear-deal</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:10:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Who Is Ilhan Omar, the Lawmaker Attacked in Minnesota?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ilhan-omar-who-is-minnesota-sprayed-attack.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28minneapolis-ice-who-is-omar-pgjv/28minneapolis-ice-who-is-omar-pgjv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Ilhan Omar
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/ilhan-omar-who-is-minnesota-sprayed-attack.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:57:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Miller Suggests Federal Agents May Have Diverted From ‘Protocol’ Before Pretti Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/stephen-miller-alex-pretti-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28minneapolis-ice-miller-vzcw/28minneapolis-ice-miller-vzcw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Miller, a top aide to President Trump, has suggested that federal agents “may not have been following” protocol before the fatal shooting of Alex Pretti, after days in which he and other Trump administration officials portrayed the shooting as justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Miller said in a statement that the White House had provided “clear guidance” to the Department of Homeland Security that federal agents deployed to Minnesota as part of the administration’s immigration crackdown be used to protect “arrest teams” from people he described as “disruptors.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are evaluating why the CBP team may not have been following that protocol,” Mr. Miller said in the statement, referring to agents from U.S. Customs and Border Protection, a law enforcement agency under the department. The statement was provided to The New York Times on Wednesday by a White House spokesperson and was reported earlier by CNN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Miller did not elaborate, his comments came as the Trump administration faces escalating blowback for Mr. Pretti’s killing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the shooting, Mr. Miller, the highly influential deputy White House chief of staff, characterized the 37-year-old Minneapolis resident in a social media post as a “domestic terrorist” and an “assassin” who had “tried to murder federal agents,” without providing evidence. He accused Democratic leaders who had condemned the killing of inciting insurrection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Trump administration officials offered similar accounts. The homeland security secretary, Kristi Noem, claimed that Mr. Pretti had brandished a gun and appeared intent on inflicting “maximum damage on individuals and to kill law enforcement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New York Times analysis of videos of the shooting contradicted those accounts. The analysis shows that Mr. Pretti was holding a phone — not a gun — when federal agents pinned him to the ground before shooting him. A preliminary review by U.S. Customs and Border Protection’s internal watchdog office also did not say that Mr. Pretti had brandished a gun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his statement on Wednesday, Mr. Miller said the Homeland Security Department’s initial assessment of the killing of Mr. Pretti was “based on reports from CBP on the ground.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration’s comments about the killing of Mr. Pretti, who worked as a nurse in the intensive-care unit at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis, have stirred widespread public anger and prompted more protests in the city over the aggressive federal immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump told Fox News on Tuesday that he might “de-escalate” the campaign but later, at a rally in Iowa, made incendiary remarks that falsely described thousands of people arrested by Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents in Minnesota as “hardened, vicious, horrible criminals” and anti-ICE demonstrators as “paid insurrectionists.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and his aides have made similar justifications for the killing of Renee Good, the 37-year-old Minneapolis woman fatally shot on Jan. 7. by the ICE agent Jonathan Ross, who the president said had acted in self-defense. Local and state officials in Minnesota have contested those accounts. A New York Times analysis of that shooting shows no indication that Mr. Ross had been run over.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/stephen-miller-alex-pretti-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:46:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did Trump Really Change His Mind on Minnesota?Did Trump Really Change His Mind on Minnesota?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010671666/did-trump-really-change-his-mind-on-minnesota.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/arts/Tyler-ICE/Tyler-ICE-facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Our White House reporter Tyler Pager describes how while President Trump appeared to soften his tone on Minnesota after seeing outrage over the killing of Alex Pretti, the crackdown continues on the ground.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010671666/did-trump-really-change-his-mind-on-minnesota.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:19:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Battlefield Tech Was Used in MinneapolisHow Battlefield Tech Was Used in Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010669560/how-battlefield-tech-was-used-in-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/arts/ICE-weapons-thumb/ICE-weapons-thumb-facebookJumbo-v3.png?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Our reporter Thomas Gibbons-Neff, who deployed twice to Afghanistan as a Marine and later was our Kabul bureau chief, looks at the battlefield technology used for an immigration arrest at a home in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010669560/how-battlefield-tech-was-used-in-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:46:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens Iran With ‘Massive Armada’ and Presses a Set of Demands</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-iran-armada.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28DC-PREXY-hmkc/28DC-PREXY-hmkc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The USS Abraham Lincoln in 2024. The aircraft carrier group is currently stationed in striking distance of targets in Iran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-iran-armada.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:50:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>F.B.I. Agents Search Georgia Election Center</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/fbi-search-election-center-georgia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28dc-fbi2-zhjc/28dc-fbi2-zhjc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Votes are counted in November 2024 at the election hub and operations center in Fulton County in Union City, Ga.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/fbi-search-election-center-georgia.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:19:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Officials’ Use of ‘Domestic Terrorist’ in Minnesota Shootings Doesn’t Match Legal Reality</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/trump-minnesota-protesters-domestic-terrorists.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/00met-domestic-terrorism-explainer-01-jcbq/00met-domestic-terrorism-explainer-01-jcbq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Vice President JD Vance characterized the actions of Renee Good, one of the two demonstrators killed this month, as “classic terrorism.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/trump-minnesota-protesters-domestic-terrorists.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:58:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Minneapolis’s Native Americans, a New Fight Echoes a Bitter History</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/minneapolis-native-americans.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/XXnative-1-vtpg/XXnative-1-vtpg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sophie Watso, of the Mdewakanton Dakota tribe, was arrested in a dispute with federal agents in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/minneapolis-native-americans.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:04:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. allies in the Middle East have been pressing for weeks to prevent a conflict with Iran.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/28/us/trump-news/iran-us-allies-trump</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28trump-news-live-Lincoln/28trump-news-live-Lincoln-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The USS Abraham Lincoln, a Nimitz-class nuclear-powered aircraft carrier in San Diego last year. The USS Abraham Lincoln is part of what President Trump has descried as an armada poised to strike near Iran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/28/us/trump-news/iran-us-allies-trump</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:50:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Federal Officers Who Fired at Pretti Placed on Leave</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/federal-officers-pretti-leave.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/28minneapolis-ice-agents-leave-topart/28minneapolis-ice-agents-leave-topart-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Federal officers and protesters faced off in Minneapolis on Saturday, shortly after agents shot and killed Alex Pretti, a Minneapolis man, that morning.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/federal-officers-pretti-leave.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:07:07 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>