<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT US Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT US articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/US_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 23:12:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Trump Holds 2-Hour Meeting With Noem Amid Backlash to Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg/26minneapolis-ice-noem-hqcg-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Kristi Noem, the homeland security secretary, at the White House earlier this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/noem-trump-meeting-minneapolis-ice.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:41:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Donations, Trump Administration Revoked Rule Requiring More Nursing Home Staff</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg/DC-TRUMP-NURSING-1-cjzg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Starting in early August, nursing home executives began making donations that would eventually total nearly $4.8 million to MAGA Inc., a super PAC devoted to President Trump and run by his allies.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/after-donations-trump-administration-revoked-rule-requiring-more-nursing-home-staff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:23:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Administration Social Media Posts Echo White Supremacist Messaging</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-altright-bczq/26nat-altright-bczq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In the past month, government agencies have made dozens more social-media posts that include iconography associated with far-right extremist groups.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/white-supremacy-trump-administration-social-media.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:24:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Maine’s Immigrant Students Stay Home as ICE Operation Ramps Up</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc/24nat-maine-schools-tglk-zhbc-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Educators from South Portland Middle School participate in a neighborhood watch at a bus stop in South Portland on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/maine-ice-immigrant-students.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:02:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Photo Shows ICE Agents Deploying at Minneapolis Protest After Alex Pretti Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/us/nat-minn-oneimage-promo/nat-minn-oneimage-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violence in Minneapolis in the Wake of Alex Pretti’s Killing&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/minneapolis-nicollet-avenue-alex-pretti.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:11:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Trump Heads to Iowa to Trumpet Economy, Many Residents Feel Pain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-iowaecon-fgqz/27dc-iowaecon-fgqz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Iowa, a state that is heavily focused on farming, has been struggling under the weight of President Trump’s economic policies.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trump-iowa-farms-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:00:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Safety Board Heaps Blame on F.A.A. Over Potomac Plane-Helicopter Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh/27dc-dca-crash-kbgh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jennifer Homendy, the National Transportation Safety Board chairwoman, speaking after the crash at Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport last year. The board plans to publish a full report on the crash.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/dca-plane-collision-faa.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:26:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Alex Pretti’s Killing, A Divided America Wonders What’s Next</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj/26nat-minn-mood-top-qfmj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial formed at the spot where Alex Pretti was shot and killed by federal agents in Minneapolis.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/alex-pretti-shooting-minneapolis-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:46:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Alexander Vindman, of Trump Impeachment Fame, Runs for Senate in Florida</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt/27po-florida-senate2-bgvt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Alexander Vindman testifying before Congress in 2019.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/alexander-vindman-trump-impeachment-florida-senate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:07:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Investigators Review Body Camera Video Related to Killing of Alex Pretti</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/body-cam-video-alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-body-cam-gqmk/27minneapolis-ice-body-cam-gqmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Federal investigators are reviewing body camera footage related to the killing of Alex Pretti, the 37-year-old nurse who was fatally shot in Minneapolis on Saturday by federal agents involved in President Trump’s immigration crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is body camera footage from multiple angles, which investigators are currently reviewing,” the Department of Homeland Security said in a statement to The New York Times on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footage could shed new light on the killing of Mr. Pretti, who was an intensive-care nurse at the Veterans Affairs hospital in Minneapolis. Administration officials quickly branded Mr. Pretti as a “domestic terrorist” after he was killed, even as videos of the encounter contradicted their narrative and D.H.S.’s account of the events leading up to the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Pretti was killed, the Hennepin County Attorney’s Office and Minnesota’s Bureau of Criminal Apprehension filed a lawsuit against several federal agencies and officials, including D.H.S. and Immigration and Customs Enforcement, to prevent the destruction of evidence related to the killing. A federal judge in Minnesota on Saturday issued a temporary restraining order barring federal officials from destroying evidence related to the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a memo filed Monday opposing the temporary restraining order, D.H.S. and other government agencies said that “the evidence is being preserved; nothing has been destroyed or altered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence is being stored in a secure evidence room at the F.B.I.’s Minneapolis field office, according to the memo. The document also stated that “CBP has preserved all relevant body-worn camera footage from the incident and will do so for 75 years,” referring to Customs and Border Protection, which includes U.S. Border Patrol, one of the two main homeland security agencies involved in the immigration crackdown, alongside ICE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos on social media that were verified by The New York Times contradict D.H.S.’s account of Mr. Pretti’s killing. The department said the episode began after a man “approached US Border Patrol officers with a 9 mm semi-automatic handgun” and they tried to disarm him. Footage shows Mr. Pretti was holding a phone, not a gun, before agents pulled him to the ground and shot him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamed Aleaziz contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/body-cam-video-alex-pretti-minneapolis-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:55:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A History of the Department of Homeland Security, the Agency Overseeing ICE</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26minneapolis-ice-timeline/26minneapolis-ice-timeline-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President George W. Bush signing the legislation that officially created the Homeland Security Department in 2002.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/dhs-ice-trump-timeline.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:06:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Orders ICE Chief to Appear in Court Over Potential Contempt</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg/27minneapolis-ice-contempt-qlbg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
ICE’s acting director, Todd Lyons, was ordered to personally explain the agency’s actions to a federal judge.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/ice-director-minnesota-contempt.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:10:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>She’s the Face of Trump’s Aviation Safety Board, and She’s a Democrat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg/27DC-HOMENDY-cmjg-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Jennifer Homendy, the chairwoman of the National Transportation Safety Board, reconvening a hearing in July on the midair collision above Washington.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/jennifer-homendy-trump-transportation-safety-board.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:35:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Florida State Senator Ileana Garcia Warns Immigration Will Cost G.O.P. the Midterms</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ileana-garcia-trump-immigration-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/us/00nat-miami-senator/00nat-miami-senator-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Florida State Sen. Ileana Garcia sees herself as a truth-teller within her party. The killing of Alex Pretti by Border Patrol agents in Minneapolis, she said, was “abhorrent.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ileana-garcia-trump-immigration-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:03:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Population Growth Slows Sharply as Immigration Numbers Plunge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-census-fjcl/27nat-census-fjcl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Population growth in Florida slowed markedly last year, according to new census estimates.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/census-2025-estimates-population-immigration.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:35:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Andrea Lucas, EEOC Chair, Recasts Workplace Discrimination in Trump’s Image</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp/00biz-eeoc-01-vwzp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Andrea Lucas, the chair of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, said she was determined to undo the consequences of an “aggressive focus by D.E.I. activists.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eocc-dei-employment-discrimination.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:49:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Yale Offers Free Tuition to Families With Incomes Under $200,000</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-yale-qljh/27nat-yale-qljh-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Yale University campus in New Haven, Conn.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/yale-free-tuition.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:38:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mark Carney Rejects Suggestions That He Walked Back His Davos Speech to Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz/27trump-news-carney-bessent-wpkz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada dismissed Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent’s suggestion that he had retracted his assertion that President Trump had created an irrevocable “rupture” to the world order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian leader spoke to reporters in Ottawa on Tuesday, the day after Mr. Bessent said on Fox News that he was in the Oval Office while Mr. Carney “was very aggressively walking back some of the unfortunate remarks” he had made at the World Economic Forum in Davos during a telephone call with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that speech, Mr. Carney, though he did not specifically name Mr. Trump was clear in his intent, calling on the world’s middle powers to stop accommodating the United States just “to go along to get along,” and to instead band together to counter its political and economic power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked on Tuesday if he had rescinded any of his remarks while speaking with Mr. Trump, Mr. Carney said “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To be absolutely clear, and I said this to the president, I meant what I said in Davos,” Mr. Carney told reporters, referring to the Swiss ski resort town where the gathering of billionaires, investors, executives and politicians was held last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “It was clear. It was a broader set of issues, and Canada was the first country to understand the change in U.S. trade policy that he initiated, and we’re responding to that.” Mr. Carney added that during their conversation on Monday, the president had “understood’’ Canada’s position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week Mr. Carney warned other middle powers that they faced potential danger if they do not stand up for their own interests and push back against Mr. Trump’s aggressive economic moves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His remarks received an unusual standing ovation and were widely praised around the world and stood in stark contrast to Mr. Trump’s long and rambling address at Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the aftermath of Mr. Carney’s speech, Mr. Trump revoked his invitation to Canada for membership on his Gaza “Board of Peace,” though Mr. Carney had not fully committed to the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney arrived in Switzerland after striking a trade deal with China that will allow a small number of Chinese electric vehicles to enter Canada at a low tariff rate. During the Biden administration, Canada joined the United States and imposed a 100 percent tariff on Chinese E.V.s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, Mr. Trump seemed to bless Mr. Carney’s agreement with China, saying, “That’s OK, that’s what he should be doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But later, on social media, he threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canadian exports “If Canada makes a deal with China.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney has repeatedly said that Canada has no plan to seek a broader free trade deal with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I explained to him our arrangement with China,” Mr. Carney said of his conversation with Mr. Trump on Tuesday. “I explained to him what we’re doing: 12 new deals on four continents in six months — he was impressed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday Canada and India released a joint statement about expanding trade in Canadian oil and natural gas. Mr. Carney is scheduled to travel to India next month to meet Prime Minister Narendra Modi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday Mr. Carney suggested that Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threat was a negotiating tactic ahead of a review of the free trade agreement between Canada, the United States and Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president is a strong negotiator and I think some of these comments and positioning should be viewed in the broader context of that,” Mr. Carney said at a news conference.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/carney-trump-davos-speech-canada-us.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:54:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Washington D.C. Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton Announces Retirement</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27trump-news-norton-vphw/27trump-news-norton-vphw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Delegate Eleanor Holmes Norton announced her retirement.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/eleanor-holmes-norton-retirement-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:00:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>On Immigration, the G.O.P. Finds Itself in a Shocking Place: On Defense</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq/pol-campaign-immig-hjcq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Protesters rallying outside the Minneapolis office of Senator Amy Klobuchar, a Minnesota Democrat, demanding she vote against funding for Immigration and Customs Enforcement.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/minnesota-politics-immigration-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:29:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>One Person Is Wounded in Shooting Involving U.S. Border Patrol in Arizona</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2024/03/11/multimedia/27xp-border/11budget-border-btpv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A person shot was in critical condition, medical officials and aid groups said. The area where the shooting occurred has been the focus of border enforcement for decades.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/border-shooting-arizona.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:30:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>TikTok Blames Technical Problems After Users Claimed It Blocked ICE Posts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf/27minneapolis-ice-tiktok1-pkbf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
TikTok’s U.S. entity said in a statement on Monday that a power outage at an American data center had impeded users from uploading new videos.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/tiktok-ice-minneapolis-technical-problems.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:28:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Senator Warnock Says ‘Soul of Our Nation Is at Stake’ During Visit to Minneapolis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf/27minneapolis-ice-warnock-visit-topart-bpkf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Senator Raphael Warnock, Democrat of Georgia, on Tuesday at the site where federal agents shot and killed Alex Pretti in Minneapolis on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/senator-warnock-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:00:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Texas Moves to Curtail H-1B Visas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf/27nat-texas-visas-wmtf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gov. Greg Abbott has sought to expand on policies coming out of the Trump administration.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/texas-immigrants-h1b-visas.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:47:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Judge Temporarily Blocks Deportation of 5-Year-Old Detained by ICE in Minnesota</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-liam1/27minneapolis-ice-Liam-jvht-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A protester holding an artwork of Liam Conejo Ramos in Portland, Maine, last week.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/ice-liam-ramos-minneapolis-deportation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:55:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Democrats Push to Impeach DHS Secretary Kristi Noem After Minneapolis Shooting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl/27minneapolis-ice-noem-dems-topart-kfpl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
From left, Representatives Pete Aguilar, Democrat of California and the Democratic Caucus chair; Hakeem Jeffries, Democrat of New York and the minority leader; and Katherine Clark, Democrat of Massachusetts and the minority whip, at a news conference in Washington this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/kristi-noem-dhs-impeach-minneapolis.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:55:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>