<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 08:54:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What’s It Like to Climb a Skyscraper?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23xp-climbing-top/23xp-climbing-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Goodwin’s left shoulder felt like it was on fire and his right hand was covered in blisters by the time he finished climbing one side of Toronto’s CN Tower in 1986. Back then, it was the tallest structure in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was terrified,” he said, recalling the day he reached the base of the tower’s observation deck, 1,100 feet above a crowd of onlookers and with no rope, harness or other safety equipment. “Every move had to be perfect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Alex Honnold, a rock climber who was the subject of the Oscar-winning documentary “Free Solo,” will attempt to get everything right when he climbs Taipei 101, a 1,667-foot-tall skyscraper in Taiwan, without a rope. With Netflix livestreaming the climb, this niche pursuit has never received such global publicity before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaling skyscrapers is not like rock climbing or going up smaller buildings. Those in the club of just a dozen or so known skyscraper climbers worldwide say it has unique and intense physical and mental demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a largely underground sport because it is usually illegal. Alain Robert, a Frenchman who has scaled some 200 buildings since the 1990s, mostly with his bare hands, said that he has been arrested more than 170 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like you’re literally in a movie,” Mr. Robert said, with “cops that are trying to catch the bad guy climbing the building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious risks make it rare for someone to obtain permission to climb a tall building like Mr. Honnold did. “I’ve never been willing to get arrested,” the 40-year-old said in a recent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the serene natural landscape surrounding climbers on routes like El Capitan in Yosemite National Park, which Mr. Honnold scaled in 2017, skyscraper climbers must overcome urban noise, crowds and, occasionally, police officers determined to arrest them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like King Kong in the city,” said Titouan Leduc, 24, a French climber who scaled Warsaw’s Varso Tower, the tallest skyscraper in the European Union, last year. He was briefly arrested after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who have climbed skyscrapers say their bodies face different demands compared with rock climbing. According to Mr. Goodwin, 70, it mainly comes down to repetitiveness versus variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a rock face, each move presents a new puzzle: climbers’ hands search for different holds — crimps, jugs, slopers — and they constantly adapt their bodies. But along the side of a building, climbers repeat the same few movements hundreds of times to pass over dozens of stories of windows, steel bars and concrete gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can do a pull-up and think it’s not all too bad, but try doing 20, 50, 100,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Doing the same kind of move over and over and over — it can really tax your muscles and fingers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over decades, Mr. Robert, 63, developed his own system for rating buildings based on how difficult they are to climb. A building’s grips mattered more than its height, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave the Brooklyn Bridge a difficulty rating of two out of 10 after climbing it in 1994. He gave the same rating to the Eiffel Tower, which he scaled with his bare hands in 1996. “It’s really like a ladder,” he said of the Paris landmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also the last person to climb Taipei 101, in 2004, then the tallest building in the world. He completed the climb just days after having surgery on his left elbow, in heavy rain and with a top rope, which he said the authorities had required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Robert gave Taipei 101 a rating of six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the small gaps on the surface of the Sydney Opera House, which he climbed in 1997 and rated as a seven, allowed him to hold on only with his fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, Mr. Robert scaled what he said was one of the most difficult buildings he had ever climbed, rating it a nine: the Sears Tower, now called the Willis Tower, in Chicago. He gave the Burj Khalifa in the United Arab Emirates, the world’s tallest building, the same grade after climbing it in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult building he ever encountered? A relatively humble 44-story office building west of Paris in 1998. He said the only way up the Framatome, now called the Tour Areva, is by jamming one’s fingers into a vertical groove between glass panels. Halfway through that climb, he said, the crack unexpectedly became so narrow that his fingers could barely fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like your entire life is hanging at the tip of your finger,” he said. He rated that difficulty a 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some climbers said they were concerned that Mr. Honnold’s climb, carried live on Netflix, would encourage reckless, untrained attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My message to kids: Don’t do it,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Unless you’re a world-class climber like Alex Honnold and Alain Robert, unless you have that ability, it’s a suicide mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For others, the danger keeps them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only way I felt alive was when I was risking my life,” Mr. Robert said, adding that he might try climbing another building in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:03:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.K.’s Starmer Calls Trump’s Claims About NATO Soldiers in Afghanistan ‘Appalling’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-soldiers-afghanistan-trump-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23trump-news-nato-afghanistan-zbmk/23trump-news-nato-afghanistan-zbmk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
British soldiers in Helmand Province, Afghanistan, in 2007. Britain lost 457 soldiers during two decades of fighting in Afghanistan.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-soldiers-afghanistan-trump-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:10:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Push to Take Greenland Holds Promise and Peril for Putin</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-putin-russia-us-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-russia-assess-wmlj/23int-russia-assess-wmlj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia in Anchorage, in August.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-putin-russia-us-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:57:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Court Dismisses Bid to Prevent Auction of Nelson Mandela Memorabilia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/africa/nelson-mandela-memorabilia-auction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-safrica-mandela-czmg/23int-safrica-mandela-czmg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Shirts that had belonged to Nelson Mandela at an auction in New York City in 2021. Guernsey’s in New York scheduled a separate online auction in 2024 that received widespread criticism in South Africa.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/africa/nelson-mandela-memorabilia-auction.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:35:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Turnabout on Greenland Shows the Limits of His Coercive Powers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/trumps-greenland-power.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23dc-assess-top-kpqc/23dc-assess-top-kpqc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Donald J. Trump on Air Force One en route to Washington on Thursday night.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/trumps-greenland-power.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:08:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under Pressure from Trump, Venezuela Agrees to Accept More U.S. Deportation Flights</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A deportation flight from the United States arriving at Simón Bolívar International Airport in Venezuela on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:26:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark Visits Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/denmark-greenland-prime-minister-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25int-greeland-pm-wbqc/25int-greeland-pm-wbqc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark, in the tan coat; the mayor of Nuuk, Greenland, Avaaraq Olsenand; and Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen of Greenland set off on a highly choreographed walk through the city on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/denmark-greenland-prime-minister-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:53:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Joint Chiefs Chairman Issues Rare Invitation to Foreign Military Heads</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/military-western-hemisphere-leaders.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23dc-military-vqpf/23dc-military-vqpf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gen. Dan Caine, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, is convening a rare meeting next month of dozens of military chiefs from across the Western Hemisphere, another sign of the region’s rising prominence in the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top military leaders from 34 countries, including nations such as Denmark, Britain and France that have territories in the area, have been invited to the gathering in Washington on Feb. 11. It is expected to focus, in part, on enhancing regional coordination in fighting drug trafficking and transnational criminal organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the U.S. commando raid this month that seized President Nicolás Maduro of Venezuela, and this week’s contentious debate between President Trump and European allies over the future of Greenland, the unusual gathering casts a spotlight on the potential military implications of the administration’s “Donroe Doctrine” and a new security strategy that prioritizes the Western Hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Participating defense leaders will explore the importance of strong partnerships, continued cooperation, and united efforts to counter criminal and terrorist organizations, as well as external actors undermining regional security and stability,” General Caine’s office said in statement on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While General Caine and top aides have sought to cast the meeting in terms of enhancing security cooperation among regional partners, it comes at a fraught time for Washington’s relations with its immediate neighbors as well as allies in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada delivered a stark speech in Davos, Switzerland, on Tuesday, describing the end of the era underpinned by U.S. hegemony. He called the current phase “a rupture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is intensifying pressure on Mexico to allow American military forces or C.I.A. officers to conduct joint operations to dismantle fentanyl labs inside the country, according to U.S. officials. The push comes as Mr. Trump presses the Mexican government to grant the United States a larger role in the battle against drug cartels that produce fentanyl and smuggle it into the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week saw the on-again, off-again fight over Greenland escalate and then cool off. Mr. Trump has said the United States needs Greenland for national security. After previously threatening to seize the island by force, he signaled this week that he was open to compromise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussions to resolve the future of Greenland have focused on proposals to increase NATO’s presence in the Arctic, give America a sovereign claim to pockets of Greenland’s territory and block potentially hostile adversaries from mining the island’s minerals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military leaders have sought to insulate themselves from these diplomatic and political tensions, trying to keep military channels open even as world leaders hurl invectives at one another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior American commanders overseeing operations in Europe, Africa and the Pacific routinely meet with their military counterparts in gatherings overseas. But aside from smaller meetings in different parts of Latin America, the Pentagon has never before convened a group of military brass this large from the Western Hemisphere, U.S. officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the meeting next month, General Caine is expected to press for further coordination on countering drugs and transnational criminal groups in the region, Western officials said. The meeting was set for next week but was postponed because of the snowstorm forecast for Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mission has already run into stumbling blocks. Britain, for instance, in September cut off sharing any intelligence related to the United States attacking what it says are boats carrying drugs in the Caribbean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Isacson, a regional security specialist at the Washington Office on Latin America, said in an email that “the Trump administration expects the militaries of the region to respond to U.S. priorities far more than at any other time since the Cold War ended.” He said that list started with fighting drugs and organized crime and included avoiding association with China, Iran, perhaps Russia and other powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Isacson said “there may be explicit or implicit threats to militaries that don’t honor those priorities, with a nod to what’s happening in Venezuela.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Caine, a former F-16 fighter pilot and Pentagon liaison to the C.I.A., has limited experience in Latin America. But his foreign policy adviser, Laura F. Dogu, is a former U.S. ambassador to Honduras and Nicaragua, and was recently given an additional assignment as envoy to Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Caine will be joined at the conference by Gen. Gregory M. Guillot, the head of Northern Command, which oversees homeland defense and Greenland; and Lt. Gen. Evan L. Pettus, the acting head of Southern Command, which oversees Latin America. Mr. Trump’s nominee to take over Southern Command, Gen. Francis L. Donovan, is awaiting Senate confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late November, General Caine visited Trinidad and Tobago, a tiny nation in the Caribbean just off the coast of Venezuela, where he met with Prime Minister Kamla Persad-Bissessar. In a statement at the time, General Caine’s office said the visit was focused on “strengthening regional stability, and regional unity on the vital importance of countering illicit trafficking and transnational criminal organizations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days after General Caine left the country, U.S. Marines activated a state-of-the-art mobile long-range sensor known as G/ATOR, or Ground/Air Task-Oriented Radar, as part of the Pentagon’s steady buildup of forces in the Caribbean over the past several months. Trinidad’s government has also agreed to allow the U.S. military to use its airports.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/military-western-hemisphere-leaders.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:03:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia Jails U.S. Navy Veteran for Five Years</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/russia-jails-american-sailor-chuck-zimmerman.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-russia-jailedAmerican-qjvb/23int-russia-jailedAmerican-qjvb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An American adventurer who set sail from North Carolina to New Zealand about 18 months ago has ended up imprisoned in Russia, sentenced to five years after being convicted of “arms smuggling” because of a rifle, a pistol and ammunition that he kept aboard his sailboat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles Wayne Zimmerman had headed toward Russia in hopes of meeting a young woman he had encountered on Instagram who went by the handle Evil Elya, having complimented her on her looks and twice sent her flowers, according to a sentencing document posted on Friday by the Central District Court in the Black Sea resort town of Sochi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zimmerman, 58, appears to be the latest American who the Russian authorities have grabbed in pursuit of what is called “hostage diplomacy,” meting out harsh sentences to U.S. citizens in order to trade them for Russians held abroad or other diplomatic gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the U.S. State Department confirmed Mr. Zimmerman’s incarceration and said it was providing “consular assistance” for him, without further details. No U.S. diplomat has visited Mr. Zimmerman, who goes by Chuck, since he was first detained last June, his younger sister, Robin Stultz, said in brief remarks via email on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Stultz, a bank manager in Virginia, had earlier issued a statement, saying, “This is an obvious set up to get another American they can trade.” How Mr. Zimmerman came to be in Russia remains somewhat murky, as the version of events presented by his family and that in the court documents differ. Ms. Stultz maintains that the Russian Navy forced her brother to sail to Sochi after intercepting his sailboat almost immediately after he entered the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Witkoff, the presidential envoy who has been negotiating with the Kremlin on a peace deal in the Ukraine war, was believed to have raised the issue of Mr. Zimmerman and other incarcerated Americans during his repeated visits to Moscow, according to Kieran Ramsey, the chief investigative officer of Global Reach, an organization in Washington that helps families seeking the release of Americans imprisoned abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Witkoff, who was most recently in Moscow on Thursday, could not immediately be reached for comment. At least 10 Americans are jailed in Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Mr. Zimmerman was arrested in Sochi in June 2025, the case came to light only after a Russian appeals court issued a statement on Monday confirming that it had upheld the five-year sentence announced in October. The statement included a video of Mr. Zimmerman sitting on his sailboat, along with glimpses of a rifle and ammunition boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One witness, who had participated in the inspection of the sailboat, said that she had spotted a rusty pistol on a table, and Mr. Zimmerman then volunteered that he had another weapon, digging out the rifle, court documents said. He kept it onboard for protection, according to his sister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Of course he had a firearm on board,” Ms. Stultz said in her statement. “You can’t just call 911 if something goes wrong out at sea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In appealing the sentence, Dmitry Starkov, Mr. Zimmerman’s lawyer, said that Mr. Zimmerman had been unaware that having the weapon was illegal under Russian law. He argued that a five-year sentence was excessively harsh, according to documents from the appeals court. Reached by telephone, Mr. Starkov declined to comment further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zimmerman, a U.S. Navy veteran and a master electrician, had used his life savings to buy the 35-foot sailboat to fulfill his dream of sailing around the world, according to a website his family made to help seek his return. The father of two daughters, he had lived most of his life in Salem, Va., but had arranged to work in New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Stultz said that she had been in touch with her brother by text message almost daily before his detention. “He’s my rock,” she said. Before Russia, he had stopped in Portugal, Spain, Sicily, Greece and Turkey, court documents said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His family said that they were not aware of plans to visit Russia, nor of any contact with a woman there. But Mr. Zimmerman had obtained a Russian visa, court documents indicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian Navy intercepted the sailboat in international waters on June 17, and then escorted it on a 22-hour trip to Sochi, according to the family website. Russian court documents do not mention any interception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The woman on Instagram told the court that she did not know Mr. Zimmerman. She had written him only once — back in 2022 to thank him for the first batch of flowers — and then blocked him when he persisted, according to court documents. She worked for the Russian tax service, the documents said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The woman, whose full name was redacted, lived in Kazan, deep in the interior of Russia and about 1,200 miles northeast of Sochi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zimmerman is being held in a Russian penal colony in the Krasnodar region. The seven months he has already spent imprisoned in Russia will count toward his sentence, court documents said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alina Lobzina contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/russia-jails-american-sailor-chuck-zimmerman.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:07:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prosecutors in Spain End Investigation Into Julio Iglesias</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/julio-iglesias-abuse-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/obituaries/23spain-Iglesias/23spain-Iglesias-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors in Madrid said on Friday that they had ended an investigation into the singer Julio Iglesias, saying that Spanish officials had no legal authority to examine claims that he had sexually abused two former employees in the Caribbean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision came nearly three weeks after the two women filed a complaint with a Spanish court accusing Mr. Iglesias, 82, of abusing one of them in the Dominican Republic and the other in the Bahamas. Mr. Iglesias denied the accusations in a social media post on Jan. 16, describing them as “absolutely false.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prosecutors closed the case because they had no jurisdiction to proceed, given that “all of the allegedly criminal acts would have occurred outside Spanish territory, specifically in the Dominican Republic and the Bahamas,” they said in a written decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They added that the accusers “neither reside in Spain nor maintain their center of life, interests, or activity in this country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Iglesias made his name singing love ballads, and he has sold hundreds of millions of records over his six-decade career. He is the father of the singer Enrique Iglesias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early January, two Spanish-language news outlets published a three-year joint investigation into Mr. Iglesias, highlighting broader allegations from 15 people who accused the singer of sexual assault and harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Iglesias and his representatives did not respond to requests for comment about the broader claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his social media post, Mr. Iglesias denied “having abused, coerced, or been disrespectful to any woman,” but he did not specifically address the journalists’ findings.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/julio-iglesias-abuse-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:17:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Many Bases Does America Have in Greenland Now?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-greenland-military-bases.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23greenland-military-01-gcjt/23greenland-military-01-gcjt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decades ago, the United States had a big footprint in Greenland: thousands of troops, more than a dozen bases, strategic bombers, weather stations and a cavernous facility under the ice. Today, there is just one active base, a remote missile defense station. Some of the old ones have been turned into commercial airstrips. Others have faded into rusty ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has said the United States needs Greenland for national security. After previously threatening to seize the island by force, he signaled this week that he’s open to compromise. One proposal under discussion would allow the United States to own pockets of land in Greenland for military bases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland, which is an overseas territory of Denmark, and Denmark have bristled at giving up any of their sovereignty, and it’s not clear that such a plan could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Americans have the Pituffik Space Base (pronounced Bee-doo-FEEK) in northwestern Greenland. Its 150 personnel run missile defense and space surveillance. Its location at the top of the globe, not far from the North Pole, allows its radar to detect missiles in their earliest moments of flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is quite literally the outermost eye of American defense,” said Peter Ernstved Rasmussen, a Danish defense analyst. “Pituffik is where the U.S. can detect a launch, calculate the trajectory and activate its missile defense systems. It’s irreplaceable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot. During World War II, the Germans invaded Denmark and set up clandestine weather stations on Greenland’s east coast. Around the same time, the United States military built its own weather stations on the west coast to help forecast conditions for battles in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, the United States was building airstrips in places like Narsarsuaq, Ikateq and Kangerlussuaq, all in the southern half of the island. These runways served as a steppingstone for long-range bombers flying between the United States and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the war, many bases closed down. Some, like the Sondrestrom Air Base in Kangerlussuaq, remained under American control until 1992. During the Cold War, the United States set up a string of early warning radar stations across the island that could detect missiles flying over the North Pole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, some of the old American airstrips, like the one in Kangerlussuaq, have been upgraded into small commercial airports and are used by Air Greenland, the national airline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other bases, like in Narsarsuaq and Ikateq, lie in shambles. Most of the Cold War radar stations have been dismantled but one still stands on a hilltop in Kangerlussuaq. Locals call it “Mickey Mouse.” Its two big circular dishes, which haven’t been turned on in decades, resemble a pair of giant ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the old American bases are in such disrepair that they would be almost impossible to restore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most likely place to expand would be around the active Pituffik base, said Troy J. Bouffard, the director of the Center for Arctic Security and Resilience at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. The site is relatively undefended, so one possibility would be to install short- to medium-range air defense weapons near the base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Otherwise, Pituffik gets destroyed easily,” he said. “And then we’re blind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another likely place for expansion might be the Kangerlussuaq airport, a Danish military official said. It was big in World War II and situated in a protected spot with reasonably good weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has spoken about placing antimissile interceptors on Greenland as part of a so-called Golden Dome missile defense shield, but where they could go is not clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American officials have indicated they are worried that their access to Greenland could be curbed if the island broke off from Denmark and went independent. If that ever happened, Greenlanders say it is most likely decades away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 1951 Danish-American defense pact, the United States already has sweeping access to build new bases and station more troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration wants a new arrangement, and one proposal is modeled on the “sovereign base area” agreement in Cyprus, where Britain’s military bases are British territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has also repeatedly said that Russia and China threaten Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But China is too far away to mount a major incursion, said Mikkel Runge Olesen, a researcher at the Danish Institute for International Studies in Copenhagen. And Russia’s navy is inferior to NATO’s sea capacity, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A Russian surface fleet making its way to Greenland?” he said. “They’d be massacred.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bouffard said that even if there’s no significant military threat to Greenland right now, the world is changing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Pituffik was never really a top-tier target before,” he said, adding, “It’s going to increase in importance — big time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that as global warming melts the ice in the Arctic Circle, there will be a lot more competition for resources and shipping lanes that become more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bouffard said that, contrary to what Mr. Trump claims, there is no immediate threat from Russia or China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, he added, “There will be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maya Tekeli contributed reporting from Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-greenland-military-bases.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:39:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canadian Ex-Snowboarder Accused of Running Drug Ring Is Arrested</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/obituaries/23canada-wedding-arrest/23canada-wedding-arrest-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former Olympic snowboarder from Canada accused of murder and running an international drug-trafficking ring has been arrested, the F.B.I. announced on Friday, ending a long search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan Wedding, 44, who has been charged with smuggling cocaine into the United States, was arrested on Thursday in Mexico, the F.B.I.’s director, Kash Patel, said in a social media post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. has said that Mr. Wedding ran a major drug trafficking organization and collaborated with the Sinaloa Cartel in Mexico, where the authorities said he had been hiding. Mr. Wedding had been on the F.B.I.’s list of its 10 most wanted fugitives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was first indicted in October 2024 on cocaine trafficking charges. He was later charged with murder, including the killing of Jonathan Acebedo-Garcia, a Canadian who had been expected to testify against Mr. Wedding. The authorities said Mr. Wedding hired a hit man to kill Mr. Acebedo-Garcia in 2025 in Medellin, Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wedding’s arrest comes two weeks before the Winter Olympics begin in Italy. He competed in the 2002 Salt Lake City Games, finishing 24th in parallel giant slalom snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a developing story. It will be updated.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:11:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Says U.S. ‘Armada’ Is Heading to Iran, Raising Pressure on Regime</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said late Thursday that a large naval force was heading to Iran, continuing his threats of U.S. military action against the government nearly a month after protests erupted across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re watching Iran,” Mr. Trump told reporters aboard Air Force One as he returned to the United States from the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. “We have a big flotilla going in that direction, and we’ll see what happens,” he added, describing the force as an “armada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had appeared to back away from threats to strike Iran, saying he had received assurances that detained protesters there would not be executed. Leaders across the Middle East had also warned Mr. Trump that a military confrontation could destabilize the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Pentagon ordered the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln and three Tomahawk-missile-firing destroyers in the South China Sea to head to the Middle East, according to two U.S. officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Air Force in the past week also sent a dozen F-15E fighters to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to the officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maj. Gen. Ali Abdollahi Aliabadi, a commander in Iran’s Khatam-al Anbiya Central Headquarters, said on Thursday that any attack on the country would “turn all U.S. interests, bases and centers of influence” into targets, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government said this week that it had quelled antigovernment protests, which erupted last month. Iran’s state television has said that more than 3,100 people were killed during the demonstrations, but human rights groups monitoring the unrest say the toll is significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human Rights Activists in Iran, a group based in Washington, said on Thursday that over 5,000 people had been killed so far, the majority of them protesters, while the Iran Human Rights group based in Norway put the figure at more than 3,400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump said that his threats of intervention had stopped more than 830 executions, mostly of young men, though Iran’s prosecutor general, Mohammad Movahedi, denied that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This claim is completely false; neither does such a number exist, nor has the judiciary made such a decision,” Mr. Movahedi said on Friday, according to the judiciary’s Mizan News Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Iranian officials previously said that rioters would be considered “enemies of God,” a charge that could carry the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether any executions had taken place. The Iranian government has instituted a severe digital and communications blackout, limiting the flow of information out of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say that the U.S. military deployment in the region was meant to ramp up pressure on the Iranian government and prepare defenses in the event of retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The increased buildup, particularly the aircraft carrier, provides an expanded set of offensive options,” said Dana Stroul, research director at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy and a former U.S. deputy assistant secretary of defense for the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demonstrations began in response to the collapsing Iranian currency and an economy that have pushed many Iranians into hardship. Iran’s economy has been under sustained pressure for years, largely as a result of Western sanctions linked to its nuclear ambitions, as well as corruption and mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the protests spread across the country, they were seen as a direct challenge to Iran’s clerical rulers, who have held power for nearly half a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities responded with a deadly crackdown, with witness reports of security forces shooting demonstrators at close range. Officials branded demonstrators “rioters” and “terrorists,” saying they were backed by foreign powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the demonstrations gained momentum, Mr. Trump said on Jan. 2 that the United States was “locked and loaded” to protect Iranian protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. officials said Mr. Trump was exploring diplomacy with Iran, even as he weighed military options, including strikes. He then declared that all talks were off and urged protesters to seize government institutions, though he later said that Iran had responded to his demands by halting the killing and execution of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump told the reporters on Air Force One that he had warned the Iranian government, “If you hang those people, you are going to be hit harder than you’ve ever been hit,” adding that the assault would make previous attacks on Iran’s nuclear program “look like peanuts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ali Vaez, an Iran specialist at the International Crisis Group, which focuses on conflict prevention, said the U.S. military threat was credible, given its strikes on Iran last June. “What is unclear is what the end goal is,” he said, adding that Mr. Trump’s initial promise to rescue protesters appeared to have given way to seeking retribution against the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiana Hayeri, Eric Schmitt and Leily Nikounazar contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:25:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Peru’s President May Be Ousted Over Secret Meetings With Chinese Businessmen</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/peru-president-chinese-businessmen-meetings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-peru-scandal-kjqc/23int-peru-scandal-kjqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secret recordings of Peruvian presidents are nothing new. Nor are corruption accusations leading to impeachments. Over the past decade, Peru has had seven presidents, none of whom has managed to hang on for longer than three years. One resigned within a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country’s current president, José Jerí, 39, who presided over the impeachment of his predecessor and who was then installed in her place last October, could join that list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a leaked video released this month, CCTV footage from Dec. 26 shows Mr. Jerí being dropped off by a car belonging to the president’s office and then attempting to cover his face with the hood of his sweatshirt as he entered Xin Yan Restaurant, which is owned by Yang Zhihua, a Chinese businessman who has come under government scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another video leaked a week later shows Mr. Jerí in one of the numerous corner stores that Mr. Yang owns in the capital, Lima. He can be seen shouting into his phone in front of Mr. Yang. Local media had reported that Mr. Yang’s store had been ordered shut down for violating a municipal ordinance. Three days later, the ordinance was struck down by a federal regulatory body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Peruvian law, Mr. Jerí, who has acknowledged the authenticity of the videos, is legally required to log all his official activities and did not disclose his visits to the restaurant and the store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under withering questioning from federal lawmakers this week, Mr. Jerí has been defiant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he had known Mr. Yang, who he calls “Johnny,” before he became president. As for the visits, he enjoys Chinese food and happened to pass the store and thought to buy some candy and paintings. (But, he added, “Johnny wouldn’t let me pay because he was being kind to me.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the shouting? It was a call from his press secretary about an unrelated matter that had upset him. He refused to share his phone’s call history with lawmakers and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These are normal actions that people, regardless of their position, carry out, but they have been distorted for purposes that the investigations will surely reveal,” he said in Congress on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí’s defense has been met with deep skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 20 lawmakers have signed onto motions that, if passed, would result in Mr. Jerí’s impeachment, a number that kept rising on Thursday. Of the 130 members of the lower house, 66 must vote for impeachment for a president to be removed. And on Tuesday, Peru’s prosecutors’ office said it had opened a graft investigation into his meetings with Mr. Yang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yang has more than a dozen companies in Peru, including a construction firm that has won several contracts from the police, a hydroelectric company that was granted a state concession to build a dam, and a ceramics factory that, according to a national trade association, was built without proper permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times obtained a confidential report on Thursday about Chinese companies accused of corruption in Peru that was drafted by a congressional committee last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it, Mr. Yang was identified as a junior partner in a more than $50 million highway project led by a local subsidiary of China Railway Engineering Corporation that became the subject of an arbitration dispute. The report accuses Mr. Yang’s construction company of conspiring to defraud the Peruvian state by using the economic leverage of large, Chinese state-owned companies to secure contracts for projects that were later abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí’s office did not respond to a request for an interview and Mr. Yang could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willax, a conservative cable channel, broadcast a third video of Mr. Jerí with Mr. Yang. It appears to have been recorded by a person wearing a hidden camera, and offers a glimpse of a separate moment at Mr. Yang’s store during Mr. Jerí’s visit there on Jan. 6. It shows members of Mr. Jerí’s team collecting bags of goods from people who appear to be the store’s employees. Someone off-camera says, “This is for the comandante.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru’s Congress is currently on summer break, complicating efforts to summon an extraordinary plenary session to impeach Mr. Jerí, though lawmakers from across the political spectrum have expressed support for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru already has presidential elections scheduled for April. Part of Mr. Jerí’s defense has been to accuse his political opponents of releasing the videos to “alter the electoral process.” Before the scandal broke, Mr. Jerí enjoyed a relatively high approval rating of 51 percent in the latest polling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Peruvians have responded to the mushrooming scandal with jadedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our politicians are all corrupt and they sell themselves to the highest bidder,” said Jacinta Martínez, 45, a landscaper in Lima. “Today it’s the Chinese who are buying them, tomorrow it will be Peruvians or Venezuelans or Americans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru’s relationship with China has grown increasingly close. More than a decade has passed since China became Peru’s biggest trading partner, and in 2024, Chinese companies completed construction of an enormous port north of Lima — part of Beijing’s Belt and Road initiative. China is the main buyer of Peru’s largest export, copper. Chinese companies are heavily involved in Peruvian infrastructure and telecommunications, and Peruvians can visit China visa-free as tourists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has sought to counter Chinese influence in Peru, in large part through forging a closer military partnership. Mr. Jerí has tried to thread the needle by welcoming both Chinese and American investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Jerí’s brief time in office, President Trump notified Congress that he intended to make Peru a “Major Non-NATO Ally,” a designation that Colombia, Brazil and Argentina also share, and the State Department said Peru had asked to purchase $1.5 billion worth of U.S. equipment and services to support construction of a new naval base near Lima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, the U.S. Senate approved Mr. Trump’s nomination of Bernie Navarro, a self-described America First champion who has vowed to “root out” growing Chinese influence, as the new ambassador to Peru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of Mr. Jerí’s political allies have said that they believe the geopolitical jockeying between the United States and China precipitated the scandal embroiling the president. In an interview with a Peruvian newspaper this week, Prime Minister Ernesto Alvarez said the videos may have been leaked to the media to damage Mr. Jerí for seeking stronger ties with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It could be China because they’re very upset about the” naval base,” he said, “and because we’ve stated transparently that Peru should be an ally of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese and American embassies in Lima did not respond to requests for comment, nor did Mr. Navarro, the incoming U.S. ambassador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, Cuarto Poder, the same outlet that published the video of Mr. Jerí in Mr. Yang’s shop, reported that another Chinese businessman, Ji Wu Xiaodong, who is under investigation for his role in a criminal organization involved in illegal logging, had visited the presidential palace three times since Mr. Jerí took office. Mr. Ji Wu had been ordered held under house arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí told lawmakers that Mr. Ji Wu was a friend of Mr. Yang’s and said he did not know Mr. Ji Wu well and that he barely spoke Spanish. Mr. Ji Wu is accredited by Peru’s foreign ministry as an official Chinese-Spanish translator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Peru’s energy regulator, Osinergmin, Mr. Yang’s hydroelectric company, Hidroeléctrica America, has made no progress on building the $24.4 million, 20 megawatt dam as of the end of last year. It is due for completion in March. The company could lose a $244,000 deposit it if does not fulfill the contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his testimony before lawmakers this week, Mr. Jerí mentioned two additional, unregistered meetings with Mr. Yang — two more December meals at Mr. Yang’s Xin Yan Restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos of those meetings have yet to emerge, but on a late night TV show on Wednesday, Beto Ortiz, a journalist for Willax claimed that he knew of 19 more videos of Mr. Jerí meeting with Mr. Yang, and teased details from the ones he’d seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For his part Mr. Jerí said he is eager to have any videos of him made public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hopefully they’ll start airing them,” Mr. Jerí said at a news conference on Thursday afternoon, “so we can verify and get many more clues about who’s behind them and what the links are between them.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/peru-president-chinese-businessmen-meetings.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:33:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukrainian, Russian and U.S. Officials to Meet in Abu Dhabi for Peace Talks</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/ukraine-russia-war-us-peace-talks-abu-dhabi.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-ukraine-ljqv/23int-ukraine-ljqv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian, Russian and American negotiators were expected to hold meetings on Friday in the United Arab Emirates, the latest in a flurry of recent diplomatic efforts to end the war in Ukraine as the fourth anniversary since Russia’s full-scale invasion approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian state news agency Tass reported that a “working group on security issues” was meeting in Abu Dhabi, the capital of the United Arab Emirates, on Friday, confirming an earlier statement by President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine. Russia’s delegation was to be led by Igor Kostyukov, the head of Russia’s military intelligence, Tass reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not immediately clear when the meetings would start nor how they would play out. Ukrainian and Russian negotiators have rarely met directly in past rounds of talks, instead relying on the United States as a mediator. Steve Witkoff, President Trump’s special envoy, and Jared Kushner, Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, were also expected to be in Abu Dhabi, but it was not clear if they would be directly involved in the trilateral talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the table is a revised 20-point peace plan drawn up by Ukraine and the United States, covering a range of issues such as potential territorial arrangements and security guarantees that Kyiv wants to prevent future Russian aggression, as well as plans to rebuild the war-ravaged nation. But the Ukrainian and Russian authorities are still at odds over territory, with Russia demanding a big chunk in an eastern region known as the Donbas, and on security guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Witkoff said on Thursday that the meetings in Abu Dhabi would be working groups handling specific components of the peace plan, including what he called “military-to-military” aspects and “prosperity,” or postwar economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think we’ve got it down to one issue, and we have discussed iterations of that issue, and that means it’s solvable,” he said at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, without elaborating. “So if both sides want to solve this, we’re going to get it solved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked later by a reporter at Davos about Mr. Witkoff’s comment, Mr. Zelensky said that Russia’s demand to control all of the Donetsk region in eastern Ukraine, even areas now held by the Ukrainian Army, remained unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Witkoff and Mr. Kushner are expected in Abu Dhabi after meeting late on Thursday with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. Tass said that they would be there for a meeting with Russian officials on economic issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yuri Ushakov, the foreign policy adviser to Mr. Putin, told reporters after the four-hour meeting with Mr. Putin that it had been “useful in all aspects, both for us and the United States,” according to Tass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ushakov said that Russia was interested in solving the war “through political and diplomatic means” but that until then it would continue to push on the battlefield “where the Russian Armed Forces hold the strategic initiative,” Tass reported. Ukrainian officials have characterized the fighting as at a near stalemate, with Mr. Zelensky saying on Thursday that both armies were exhausted after four years of war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks on Friday also come after a meeting in Davos between Mr. Zelensky and Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky had said this week that he would attend the gathering in Switzerland only if “real results for Ukraine” were on the table, fueling expectations of a possible breakthrough in the peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky and Mr. Trump said after meeting that their talks had been “good,” and Mr. Zelensky said that they had reached an agreement on U.S. security guarantees for Ukraine after the war. But the leaders offered no details on what these guarantees would entail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I believe they’re at a point now where they can come together and get a deal done,” Mr. Trump said in Davos on Wednesday, referring to the two sides in the Russia-Ukraine peace talks. “And if they don’t, they’re stupid. I don’t want to insult anyone, but you got to get this deal done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew E. Kramer contributed reporting from Kyiv, Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/ukraine-russia-war-us-peace-talks-abu-dhabi.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:42:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Final Indignities Inflicted on Iran’s Protest Victims</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/world/00int-iran-cemetery1/00int-iran-cemetery1-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The families rooted frantically through the piles of corpses, so crammed together that the living had to take care not to step on the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wailing and cursing, they searched the body bags for the number assigned to their loved one for burial — a surreal veneer of bureaucracy imposed onto a chaotic nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the breaking point only came when weary-looking cemetery workers arrived in refrigerated trucks to dump still more corpses on the ground. The body bags landed with sickening thuds in front of onlookers who had come to bury their children, siblings, fathers, mothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That moment — it broke people. People couldn’t just watch them throwing the bodies out like that,” said Kiarash, a witness who described the scene this month at Behesht-e Zahra, the largest cemetery in Tehran. “There was a mother lying on her child’s body, begging for help so they wouldn’t throw him somewhere,” Kiarash added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enraged, the crowds began pushing their way into the hallway of the mortuary, cursing Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei — a criminal offense in the country — as security forces looked on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mothers were crying, shouting,” Kiarash said. “And all the people were shouting things like, ‘Death to Khamenei.’” As Kiarash reached for his phone to film them, he said, security forces quickly stopped him. Others, however, did manage to surreptitiously film and share the protests that day, in videos that have been verified by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash, who, like others interviewed, asked to be identified only by his first name to protect his relatives, gave The New York Times rare, detailed testimony of his experiences during a visit to his family in Iran, which coincided with the anti-government protests that roiled the country for weeks. A violent crackdown unleashed by the government has stifled those demonstrations for now, residents say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The staggering toll of this suppression has only begun to emerge — obscured by a government shutdown of the internet and telephone lines for more than a week. Though some communications are slowly being restored, reliable testimony and evidence is emerging piecemeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human rights groups say they have gathered so many individual testimonies of people who witnessed large numbers of bodies collecting at morgues and cemeteries across the country that they expect the death toll to rise far beyond the current estimates of up to 4,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, like Kiarash, three rights groups interviewed by The Times recounted shocking treatment of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mahmood Amiry-Moghaddam, director of Iran Human Rights, an advocacy group based in Oslo, said that his team had also received witness accounts of bodies being piled on top of one another in Tehran and in the coastal city of Rasht. The group documented testimonies from people who said that they had been forced to search through trucks loaded with bodies to find their loved ones in Tehran and in the northeastern city of Mashhad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mashhad’s poorest neighborhoods, some families recounted being asked to pay impossible sums, sometimes as high as $6,000, to retrieve the bodies of protesters, according to testimonies gathered by the Center for Human Rights in Iran, an organization based in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people cannot pick up their loved ones’ bodies because they can’t pay that kind of money,” said Hadi Ghaemi, the head of the center. “So the bodies are just being dumped and buried in mass graves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of imposing a “bullet price” on the families of dead dissidents dates to the Islamic Republic’s brutal crackdown on its opponents in the 1980s, when the authorities required a fee to return the bodies of those it executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the evidence that rights groups are now piecing together comes from travelers smuggling out information when they leave Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor told The Times that he spirited out videos and testimony from medics in the central city of Isfahan. They shared information about a heavy death toll from that city alone from Jan. 8-10, at the height of the government’s crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now everyone knows someone who was killed,” said the doctor, Mohammed. “The silence imposed on people is not normal — it’s a silence that carries the dust of death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that he had seen hundreds of bodies during his visit to Behesht-e Zara, on the afternoon of Jan. 10, when he had joined his brother to bury a family friend. The friend, a 41-year-old mother of two, had been shot in the neck at a protest the night before, Kiarash said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mourners at the cemetery started at a reception area, where they received a number that matched the tag on their loved one’s body, Kiarash recounted. Then they made their way toward the mortuary, where cemetery workers perform the Muslim rites of washing the corpses and covering them in a simple white shroud before returning them to their loved ones for burial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the families waited outside the mortuary, they noticed that piles of bodies had been stacked in warehouses nearby, Kiarash said. The sight prompted a frenzy as people broke past the security forces to see if their loved ones were among the piles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was rows upon rows” of bodies, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian, an Iranian in exile abroad, said that his family had undergone a similar experience to Kiarash’s at the same cemetery. Dian’s father was shot dead at a protest, his family told him, and they buried him at Behesht-e Zahra a day after Kiarash was there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian’s family also described scenes of corpses stacked on top of one another and of cemetery workers insulting the families of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What unnerved Kiarash most, he said, was watching cemetery workers carelessly handling tiny body bags — for children, he guessed, no more than 10 or 12 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Throwing bodies on top of each other, throwing the children in small bags — they’d get crushed beneath them,” he said. “Every time I say this, my heart breaks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young conscripts overseeing the crowd looked as stunned as the people they were meant to be controlling, Kiarash added: “Some of them were crying.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behesht-e Zahra holds a powerful resonance for Iranians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, the founder of the Islamic Republic established after the 1979 revolution, is entombed there. It is also the final resting place of thousands of soldiers who lost their lives in the Iran-Iraq war during the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the authorities bulldozed over a plot there holding many political prisoners, who were executed by the thousands during the ’80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many rights groups estimate that the toll from Iran’s latest unrest could pass 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage from Jan. 10, taken at a forensics laboratory a short distance away from Behesht-e Zahra, has also emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The videos show sobbing crowds searching through bodies piled on the floor as 40-foot-long refrigerator trucks, similar to those Kiarash described, arrive to unload still more dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final indignity is the burial itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arina Moradi, who works for the Norway-based rights group Hengaw, said that the authorities in Tehran had forced her family to pay money to retrieve the body of her cousin, Siavash Shirzad, 38. But they denied Mr. Shirzad’s family the right to bury him in his birth city, Bukan, in western Iran, where his family lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family was forced to bury him in a remote ancestral village instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They paid the money, then they had to agree they would not allow any demonstrations or anything, that they would bury him in silence,” Ms. Moradi said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tightly restricting burial rites, Mr. Ghaemi said, is a lesson that the Islamic Republic learned from the 1979 revolution. Then, funerals for protesters and the customary Shiite Muslim memorial services conducted 40 days after a person’s death became critical to maintaining the momentum of demonstrations that ultimately overthrew the shah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason authorities are so sensitive about where bodies get buried is that they become symbols to the people they live among — and the potential for gatherings at the cemetery that could ignite larger protest,” Mr. Ghaemi said. “They basically deny people the right to mourn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Behesht-e Zahra, Dian said that security guards had accompanied his family to their burial plot to monitor them. In a video shared by the family, the mourners simply chanted, “Honorable one! Honorable one!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that security guards had rushed his family friends through their final goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One officer was standing over us: ‘You have 30 minutes to do whatever you need,’” Kiarash recalled. The friend was lowered into the grave; the dirt poured over her body was quickly watered to tamp down the dust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash says that the silence imposed by the government’s crackdown cannot last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The word hatred is not strong enough to signify what people are feeling,” he said. “It’s over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanam Mahoozi, Monika Cvorak and Artemis Moshtaghian contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:13:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Europe Learned From the Greenland Crisis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/sovereignty-european-union-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-europe-sovereignty-assess-01-jbpg/24int-europe-sovereignty-assess-01-jbpg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if the Europeans needed another wake-up call about the contempt in which President Trump holds them, his mocking antipathy at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, was a good reminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Davos presented another lesson to Europe. Standing together on the principle of territorial integrity and sovereignty, while warning of severe economic countermeasures, the Europeans achieved an apparent retreat from Mr. Trump over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sovereignty and the inviolability of borders are fundamental tenets of the European project, built out of the ruins of World War II, when the aggressive imperialism of big powers led to millions of deaths. The lesson was clear: Defending borders collectively is the only way small states are protected from the predations of larger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Europe finds itself again confronted by big powers with expansionist goals. Russia continues its effort to conquer Ukraine, whose sovereignty it had recognized in numerous treaties. And the United States has been demanding that Denmark, an E.U. and NATO ally, hand over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But preserving territorial integrity and sovereignty is the red line, expressed both in the European Union, a collective of 27 nations, and in NATO, a military alliance of 32 nations. It can seem quixotic in the current world to be defending international law, the U.N. Charter and the Helsinki Accords, which all insist on the inviolability of borders, but in a sense, that is Europe’s fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That borders can be challenged by force, and the threat of force threatens the core tenets of European security and aspirations since the end of World War II,” said Ian Lesser, the head of the Brussels office of the German Marshall Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The war in Ukraine brought it to the fore,” he continued, “but the idea that the United States, the principal guarantor of European security, should be challenging the concept of sovereignty and territorial integrity is a serious concern.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Leonard, the director of the European Council on Foreign Relations, argued that the continent has been rediscovering the importance of sovereignty in the face of challenges from the “great powers” of China, Russia and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most of European history since World War II has been about taming sovereignty and pooling it” in multilateral institutions, he said. But the new world is “fundamentally changing the nature of the E.U.,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans realize that they cannot defend the old, rules-based order on a global level, “but they can be sure it survives in Europe,” he said. “Thus the importance of Ukraine and Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Leonard said he hoped that “Europeans will take the lesson of the last few days, that when they stand up for sovereignty and territorial integrity and these rules they can defend them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada won praise for a speech in Davos in which he said that the old international order was dead. “Middle powers” like Canada and Europe, he said, must form new alliances as the great powers abandon postwar international norms and treaties and rely instead on “economic integration as weapons, tariffs as leverage, financial infrastructure as coercion, supply chains as vulnerabilities to be exploited.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a rupture in the old order, Mr. Carney said: “When the rules no longer protect you, you must protect yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has been absorbing that lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans have resisted Mr. Trump’s demands that Ukraine hand over to Russia territory that Moscow has not conquered. And the Europeans have insisted that even if a peace deal left Russian troops occupying 20 percent of Ukraine, the occupation would never be recognized as permanent, not even in Crimea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Europeans have come up with more money and military aid for Ukraine than the United States, and they have largely picked up the slack after Mr. Trump cut off funding for Ukraine. They recently agreed to another 90 billion euros ($106 billion) in economic and military aid to Kyiv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it has been the Europeans who have expressed solidarity with Denmark and Greenland against Mr. Trump’s demands to annex the island on the same principle of territorial integrity, and who seem to have caused him to back down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Emmanuel Macron of France spoke for many Europeans at Davos when he said, “Europe has very strong tools now, and we have to use them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Bart De Wever of Belgium was harsher. “So many red lines are being crossed,” he said at the forum. “Being a happy vassal in one thing, being a miserable slave is something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Trump presidency has taught Europe that its initial policy of flattering Mr. Trump has been a failure, and that standing up for core principles is vital, said a senior European official, speaking anonymously given the sensitivity of the U.S.-European relationship. In essence, he agreed, Europe has learned that a little flattery is fine, so long as you have a gun in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the case with Denmark and Greenland. For many weeks, European leaders and officials hoped that Mr. Trump would back down over his intention to take Greenland “the easy way” or “the hard way.” Instead he threatened even more punitive tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the European Union scheduled an emergency summit meeting for right after Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of Mr. Trump’s threats, the Europeans suspended a pending U.S.-E.U. trade agreement on tariffs that had been criticized as too weak. Instead, they prepared a retaliation of €93 billion ($109 billion) in countertariffs on American goods — the gun in the pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of those countertariffs upset the markets, said Mr. Leonard of the European Council on Foreign Relations. The effect appeared to have an impact on Mr. Trump and his aides, he said, by showing “that the Europeans were serious and through the markets they pushed Trump to pull back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, in discussion with Mark Rutte, the NATO secretary general, then appeared to back down, saying there was an unspecified framework for “a deal” on Greenland and removing his own threatened tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president declared victory, but the real winner in this case were the Europeans, both the European Union and NATO, grasping on to this core principle of no border changes without the consent of the countries involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the E.U. summit meeting early Friday morning, Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, the bloc’s executive arm, said the latest tariff threats offered a tactical lesson for dealing with the United States. “Firmness, outreach, preparedness and unity” had been effective, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So going forward we should maintain this very approach.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smaller European nations, like the Baltic and Nordic states, are deeply worried about the great powers’ attack on sovereignty, said Jana Puglierin, head of the German office of the European Council on Foreign Relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the end of their business model,” she said. “It’s the very foundation of the European Union and the postwar order, where one country gets one vote, no matter how small.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia, China and the United States are trying to change the entire international order, she said, and Europe is in the middle. All of those countries “are trying to split us,” she said, “because it is easier to deal with us when we are divided.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental question is whether the European Union and NATO can still function in this new, more rapacious world, she said. These institutions “are based on the invulnerability of sovereignty and the principle of consensus, and the challenge now is to the very existence of the organizations that have brought peace and prosperity to Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/sovereignty-european-union-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 23:49:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Unlikely Source of Crypto Innovation: Afghanistan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/crypto-innovation-afghanistan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/00int-afghan-crypto-01-promo/00int-afghan-crypto-01-kvbh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a bustling money changer in northwestern Syria, a 46-year-old farmer gripped a plastic card like a lifeline. She had never heard of cryptocurrency, but the card held $500 of it to help restart her farm after nearly 14 years of civil war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teller confirmed the total and cashed out the account, the farmer, Hala Mahmoud Almahmoud, smiled with relief and paused to give thanks. Where had such technology come from, she asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer surprised her: Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain-based cash transfers are not the kind of innovation that many people would expect from a country better known for its repressive Taliban leadership, which views the internet with suspicion. But in a nation that has largely turned its back on the world, an Afghan start-up is building tools that it hopes will transform how humanitarian aid is delivered in countries shattered by conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve lived through these challenges ourselves, so we know how to develop an approach that works,” said Zakia Hussaini, 26, a programmer at the start-up, HesabPay, which designed the technology driving Ms. Almahmoud’s card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early proponent of the platform was the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees. The agency uses it to support more than 86,000 families in Afghanistan in one of the biggest public blockchain aid initiatives in the world. Mercy Corps, which donated the funds to Ms. Almahmoud, worked with HesabPay to expand its reach to include Syria, and programs for Sudan and Haiti are in development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Syria, getting money from abroad can be complicated. Cash is scarce, international banks steer clear of the country and remittance firms like Western Union can charge as much as 10 percent in transfer fees. HesabPay allows organizations like Mercy Corps to sidestep those roadblocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanzar Kakar, the Afghan American entrepreneur behind HesabPay, used to run Afghanistan’s leading payroll processor. But the U.S. withdrawal from Afghanistan in 2021 and the Taliban’s return set off a financial collapse. Sanctions put a halt to international transfers, and the central bank unraveled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address the country’s increasing financial insecurity, Mr. Kakar turned to blockchain. He built HesabPay, named after the local word for “account,” as a phone-based app that enabled instant transfers from one digital wallet to another, bypassing banks and the Taliban government. The Afghan government has since granted his business a license to operate officially as a financial institution, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the platform has more than 650,000 wallets in Afghanistan, of which about 50,000 are in regular use, moving approximately $60 million a month in stablecoins backed by the afghani, Afghanistan’s currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since February 2025, the U.N. has used HesabPay to deliver nearly $25 million via 80,000 digital wallets to vulnerable Afghans returning home, said Carmen Hett, the corporate treasurer of the U.N. refugee agency. “This helps reduce transaction fees, waiting periods and enhance traceability, real-time monitoring and accountability of transactions,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not surprising that organizations like Mercy Corps and the United Nations are turning to blockchain-based money transfers to deliver aid, said Ric Shreves, an expert in decentralized finance solutions and the president of the Decentralized Cooperation Foundation. For such organizations, he said, “it’s almost all upsides, compared to the way aid has traditionally been delivered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are still risks, he said, especially when the payment systems are based on local-currency stablecoins, as they are in Afghanistan. (In Syria, the cryptocurrency in HesabPay wallets is backed by the U.S. dollar, a more stable option.) Just as wallets can be shut down for interacting with sanctioned individuals, they can also theoretically be shut down by a country’s central bank for political reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When we provide people with a nonphysical means of doing transactions, that also means there’s a possibility that those transactions could be blocked through technological means,” Mr. Shreves said. Digital currencies are demonstrably safer than cash, he added, but they still cannot be stashed under a mattress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, aid groups have increasingly turned to cash as a fast and dignified form of assistance. But cash has a flaw: It is hard to track. Donors want proof that their money reaches the right hands. Since President Trump slashed U.S. foreign assistance early last year, groups like Mercy Corps have come under even more pressure to demonstrate their impact and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is where blockchain comes in, creating a digital trail that records exactly how much was sent, to whom, and where it was spent. That mix of speed and accountability could be “a way to win back trust from those who have come to doubt the usefulness of aid,” said Scott Onder, Mercy Corps’s chief investment officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HesabPay comes with additional safeguards, like a real-time dashboard that tracks wallet activity and cross-checks it against international compliance databases. The company says the system is designed to detect illicit activity like terrorist financing, money laundering and online scams, and to raise an alert the moment suspicious transactions appear. For aid donors, it offers a level of oversight rarely possible in fragile states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a recent online demonstration, Nigel Pont, the company’s senior adviser for humanitarian affairs, clicked on a purple dot representing a HesabPay agent in Afghanistan. Dozens of pale blue beneficiary wallets fanned out, showing recent transfers. Another click revealed where the money went next. Then one wallet pulsed red with a potential scam alert — an awkward moment in a live demo, but exactly the kind of risk the system is built to expose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“From an aid donor perspective, that’s immensely valuable,” said Mr. Pont, who previously served as chief strategy officer at Mercy Corps. “A system that can automatically flag a fraud risk means you can check it out immediately instead of waiting six months for a report that somebody stole 20 grand.” No system is entirely corruption-proof, he conceded, but then again, a bag of cash is not, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abdul Halim Hasan, 22, who was waiting in the same line as Ms. Almahmoud for his turn at the money changer in Syria, said he imagined that one day he could use HesabPay as a regular bank account, receiving funds, making payments and saving money safely. But for the moment, it was enough that his HesabPay card allowed him to gain access to money he needed to restart his life after war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I certainly want to see this method spread in Syria,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leen Rihawi contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/crypto-innovation-afghanistan.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:01:08 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>