<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:40:11 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Winter Storm Pummels Toronto With Near-Record Snowfall</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/americas/toronto-snow-winter-storm.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25winter-storm-toronto-lghq/25winter-storm-toronto-lghq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toronto was on its way Sunday to having its snowiest day on record. For a city used to harsh winters, that’s saying a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 10 p.m., Toronto Pearson International Airport had received about 18 inches (46 centimeters) of snow on Sunday, the airport said. Snow was still falling. The most snow Toronto has received in a single day was the 19 inches that fell on Dec. 11, 1944, the Toronto Star newspaper reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperatures at the airport dipped to as low as 9 degrees Fahrenheit (minus 13 Celsius) in Toronto, and with gusts reaching nearly 30 miles per hour, the wind chill reached as low as minus 9 Fahrenheit (minus 23 Celsius), according to the Canadian government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday evening, the city had declared a “major snowstorm condition.” Mayor Olivia Chow said on social media that the peak of the heavy snowfall would end around 11 p.m., and that the city had over 600 snowplows on its roads and sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The airport said that around 65 percent of all departures and arrivals had been canceled from Saturday evening through Sunday. It was unclear how many were canceled because of bad weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All Toronto Public Library branches were closed on Sunday, as were some restaurants across the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of Toronto schools will be closed on Monday. The Toronto District School Board said that classes and after school programs would be canceled. The Toronto Catholic District School Board said high school exams scheduled for Monday would be rescheduled.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/americas/toronto-snow-winter-storm.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:46:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Winter Storm Disrupts Air Travel Plans for Thousands on Monday</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/storm-flight-cancellations-delays.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26winter-storm-air-traffic-vclq/26winter-storm-air-traffic-vclq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Air travel was slowly beginning to recover on Monday, though thousands of flights across dozens of airports remained canceled and delayed after a winter storm brought heavy snow and ice to much of the Eastern United States over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 4,000 departing and arriving flights to the United States were canceled and over 2,000 were delayed as of 10 a.m., according to FlightAware, a flight tracking site. More disruptions were expected later and most major airlines were offering travel waivers and rebooking options for customers affected by the storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the storm began wreaking havoc on Friday, airlines may be able to bounce back quickly. Because they had days to prepare, many airlines canceled flights and moved planes and workers to be ready to restart normal operations. The end of January is among the slowest periods for air travel of the year, meaning carriers have more resources and flexibility to respond to storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transportation secretary, Sean Duffy, said on Monday that he hoped flights would return to normal by midweek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re looking at Wednesday as our hope to get back to a normal schedule,” he said in an interview on CNBC. He added: “The snow is subsiding in the northeast, so now it’s dig-out day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the recovery could be bumpy. Sunday was the worst day for flight cancellations since the early days of the pandemic in March 2020, according to Mr. Duffy. And lingering ice and frigid temperatures could slow flights in the days ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, airports in Atlanta, Dallas and Charlotte, N.C., saw the largest number of cancellations for departing flights, but the disruption followed the weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boston Logan International Airport was reporting the highest number of cancellations on Monday, with about 300, or 60 percent of its scheduled departures, according to FlightAware. Nearly half the departures out of Kennedy Airport, La Guardia Airport, and Newark Liberty International Airport had been canceled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flights were expected to gradually restart on Monday at Washington’s Reagan National Airport after airlines canceled all trips the day before, the airport said on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American Airlines, the world’s largest carrier, was the most affected airline over the weekend and on Monday. The airline has a big hub at the Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport, one of the busiest airports in the world. Fort Worth was among the first major cities hit by the storm on Friday. American had canceled about 3,000 flights from Friday through Sunday, according to FlightAware. It had canceled more than 650 on Monday, more than any other carrier.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/business/storm-flight-cancellations-delays.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:42:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi’s Purge of the Chinese Military</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/china-xi-military-purge-israel-hostage-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-theworld-china-general-01-qmwf-promo/27int-theworld-china-general-01-qmwf-promo-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese politics is often a black box. Foreign leaders struggle to gauge what Beijing is thinking, be it about A.I. or Taiwan. So when it emerged this weekend that President Xi Jinping had pushed out the most senior general in the Chinese military command structure, it caught many by surprise. Today, my colleague Chris Buckley in Taipei writes about the fallout from Xi’s military purge — and how it might affect potential plans for a Taiwan invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Chris Buckley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of generals have been toppled in President Xi Jinping’s unrelenting campaign against perceived corruption and disloyalty over the past three years. But this weekend’s downfall of Gen. Zhang Youxia, who had been the Chinese president’s chief deputy in the military, was of a different order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xi’s decision to oust Zhang and another top general means the Central Military Commission, the small committee that commands China’s armed forces, has only two members left: Xi himself and the officer he has used to oversee the purges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This move “represents the total annihilation of the high command,” said Christopher K. Johnson, a former C.I.A. analyst who follows Chinese elite politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 75, Zhang was old enough that Xi could have ushered him into retirement. Instead, Xi made him a public pariah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s defense ministry announced that he was under investigation for unspecified breaches of laws and political discipline. An editorial in the military’s official newspaper, the People’s Liberation Army Daily on Sunday hinted that Zhang was being accused of corruption, and, perhaps more important, of disloyalty to Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What prompted Xi to finally turn against Zhang is now a topic of fevered speculation in Beijing and beyond. Some believe Xi may have come to see him as too powerful, after the general’s own rivals were toppled in previous purges. Others believe Xi concluded that systemic corruption was so deep that he needed drastic surgery to clear the way for a new generation of commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still other allegations are more serious: The Wall Street Journal reported on Sunday, citing anonymous sources, that Zhang had been accused of leaking nuclear secrets to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does seem clear is that Zhang’s purge — the most dramatic in a wave of military purges that has unfolded since 2023 — has raised questions about China’s strategy toward Taiwan, at a time when China’s military has been severely diminished by Xi’s anti-corruption campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigations and disappearances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Xi became China’s leader in 2012, he moved quickly to shake up the military, which was rife with corruption and organizationally stuck in the past. Zhang was one of the commanders Xi picked to help lead this overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after a decade in charge, Xi seemed to conclude that some of his own handpicked protégés had been infected by the military’s corruption, and a new cycle of investigations and purges began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, waves of top commanders and officers in the Chinese military, and executives for arms manufacturers, have been removed from office and placed under investigation — or, in some cases, have disappeared from view without explanation. Investigations have taken down admirals, regional military commanders and members of the Central Military Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigations’ toll on the military was visible at a meeting last year of the Communist Party’s Central Committee, a council of top officials. Of the 44 uniformed officers appointed to the committee in 2022, 29 — roughly two-thirds — had been purged or were missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang had long seemed to be spared scrutiny. Xi kept him in office past retirement age, and made him his top vice chairman of the Central Military Commission — Xi’s eyes and ears in running the People’s Liberation Army’s forces day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lack of operational experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang being pushed out is especially significant because he was a celebrated war veteran, in a nation where few active commanders have experienced real combat. Zhang fought in China’s last war, a border conflict with Vietnam that began in 1979 and lasted years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xi seems to have calculated that in the longer term, his shake-up will make the military less corrupt, more loyal and more effective in pursuing his goals. But the disruptions caused by the purges could leave Xi less confident that his commanders are ready for combat, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no one right now at the highest level who has operational experience or who is in charge of training and exercises,” said Shanshan Mei, a political scientist who studies China’s armed forces. “This is going to cut very deep.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s also not clear that the changes will lead to more restraint. Another former U.S. government official shared his worries about the potential consequences of purging one of the people who could speak candidly to Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang “could assess U.S. and Taiwan military capabilities objectively and explain to Xi Jinping what the military risks and costs of an operation to take Taiwan would be,” Drew Thompson, a former Pentagon official, wrote on Substack. “I worry about the consequences of someone other than Zhang Youxia providing Xi Jinping with military advice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read Chris’s full story here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggling to contain the fallout from his administration’s deadly actions in Minneapolis, President Trump sent a new official to oversee the immigration enforcement operation there and backed off his attacks on Minnesota’s governor, Tim Walz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following a phone call between the governor and the president, Walz’s office said the governor got Trump to agree to talk to federal officials about ensuring an independent investigation into the killings this month of Alex Pretti and Renee Good. Trump also agreed to look into reducing the number of federal agents in Minnesota, the governor’s office said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Guttenfelder, a New York Times photographer based in Minneapolis, was at the scene after Pretti’s killing on Saturday. Watch the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said yesterday that it had recovered the remains of Master Sgt. Ran Gvili, an Israeli police officer whose body was the last one held in Gaza. The retrieval closes a painful chapter for Israelis and also paves the way for the next phase of the cease-fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel announced that it would reopen the border between the Gaza Strip and Egypt within days. The move would allow Palestinians who fled the enclave during the two-year war to return home for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials in the Middle East are increasingly worried that the U.S. will strike Iran in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. faced dangerous cold after a heavy snowstorm that disrupted travel and killed at least 21 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large ferry sank in the southern Philippines, killing at least 18 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gunmen in Mexico opened fire on a crowded football field, killing 11 people. The shooting occurred in an area fought over by drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The E.U. will investigate Elon Musk’s X social media platform over A.I.-generated sexualized images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gold reached a record high as investors sought shelter from geopolitical uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Who is the most important person at each Premier League club? Our reporters share their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Madison Keys, the defending Australian Open champion, lost to a fellow American, Jessica Pegula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycling: Two kangaroos caused a major crash at the Tour Down Under race in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the early years of the war in Ukraine, fighting slowed in the winter. Snow and mud made it more difficult for armored vehicles to get around. Now, as drone attacks dominate, the pace of fighting is intense year round, and the winter has unexpected effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trees are bare, their leaves no longer providing camouflage. Footprints in the snow are easy to spot from above. Lower temperatures make thermal cameras on drones more effective. So tactics have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— An influencer set herself a goal of collecting 1,000 rejections for auditions and job applications, recording each “no” in a notebook. Now, rejection spreadsheets are popping up across social media. No rejection is too big or too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is better known for its repressive Taliban government than for tech innovation. But a crypto start-up there is building online payment tools that could transform humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An app, HesabPay, allows instant transfers between digital wallets, bypassing banks and the Taliban. The U.N. has used it to deliver nearly $25 million to vulnerable Afghans returning home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is proving useful in other countries shattered by conflict. People in Syria are now receiving aid money in cryptocurrency through the app, and programs for Sudan and Haiti are in development. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch: In the new season of “Bridgerton,” a fan favorite will step into the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise: Forget about muscle mass as you age; focus on strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repair: These are the essential tools to have in your home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bacon-and-egg pie is a rustic specialty from New Zealand, here zipped up with a mixture of sriracha and cream. It’s close in feeling to steak-and-kidney pie, that sturdy pub staple, and makes for terrific picnic fare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: Scale your recipes up or down with this helpful new tool and tips from New York Times Cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these islands?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bahamas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aitutaki, Cook Islands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lakshadweep, India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Maldives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Buckley was our guest writer today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/china-xi-military-purge-israel-hostage-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 15:42:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NATO Chief Says Europe Is ‘Dreaming’ if It Thinks It Can Defend Itself Without U.S.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/nato-chief-europe-greenland-trump-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-greenland-nato-1-wzft/26int-greenland-nato-1-wzft-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Rutte, the secretary general of NATO, warned Europe on Monday that it could not defend itself without the United States in remarks aimed to address the growing worries that the United States and Europe are pulling apart over President Trump’s ambitions for Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If anyone thinks here again that the European Union, or Europe as a whole, can defend itself without the U.S., keep on dreaming,” Mr. Rutte told members of the European Parliament in Brussels. “You can’t. We can’t. We need each other.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte’s remarks followed days of anxiety that crested last week after President Trump said in a speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, that he would not seize Greenland, an autonomous Danish territory, backing off earlier threats. Mr. Trump used the same speech to belittle Europe, essentially saying that it wouldn’t exist without America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had also threatened to impose additional tariffs on European countries that resisted his bid to control Greenland, but he backed away from those as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte, a former Dutch prime minister, has cultivated a chummy relationship with Mr. Trump, and that has raised some eyebrows in Europe. On Monday, he backed up the American president’s strategic vision for the Arctic and a stronger defense of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also defended himself for helping ease Mr. Trump away from his escalating threats and for trying to lead the American president toward a compromise over the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s and Greenland’s leaders have bristled at the notion that Mr. Trump and Mr. Rutte might be negotiating Greenland’s future behind their backs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Of course, I have no mandate to negotiate on behalf of Denmark, so I didn’t, and I will not,” he said. “That’s up to Denmark to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several members of the European Parliament pressed Mr. Rutte for more information on what exactly he had discussed with Mr. Trump last week and what it might mean for Denmark and Greenland, both of which have strongly rejected the idea of an American takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte wasn’t very specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He didn’t elaborate on the framework of a deal with NATO over Greenland’s future that Mr. Trump said last week he had reached. That announcement brought immense relief after months of repeated threats, though many across Europe are worried that Mr. Trump could change his mind again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte said that there were “two work streams going forward” that involved Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One was talks between NATO allies over a broader Arctic defense plan that would involve Greenland, a gigantic island that lies mostly in the Arctic Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other was a process involving representatives from the United States, Denmark and Greenland that started earlier this month in Washington and is continuing, Mr. Rutte said. Danish officials said that they held a meeting on Thursday in Washington about Greenland, but they declined to share any details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several Western officials have said that one possible compromise that NATO was discussing was that the United States would gain sovereign status for American bases in Greenland. The United States has kept military forces on the island since World War II, when Nazi Germany seized Denmark and the Danish ambassador to Washington struck an agreement with the United States to defend Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Rutte’s discussions with Mr. Trump last week, Danish leaders quickly made clear that any compromise on Greenland’s sovereignty remained “a red line.” Mr. Rutte, who was invited to attend a meeting of the Parliament’s security and defense committee, didn’t comment on the base-sovereignty idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several members of the European Parliament asked sharp questions on Monday, including Villy Sovndal, a Danish representative, who said, “We’re not going to give any square meter to any country because of threats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout his remarks, Mr. Rutte praised Mr. Trump, joking that he knew that might irritate his audience. Mr. Trump’s bombastic speech last week in Davos deeply rattled Europe, especially his assertion, which struck many nations as insulting, that “without us, right now, you’d all be speaking German and a little Japanese, perhaps.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte’s remarks were more diplomatic. But he did emphasize that, more than 70 years after World War II, Europe was still dependent on American military might. He said that Europe would have to spend far more on defense than it was already spending to field its own formidable nuclear arsenal.“Forget that you can ever get there with 5 percent,” he said, referring to the 5 percent of gross domestic product that NATO members have pledged to spend on defense annually by 2035. “It will be 10 percent. You have to build up your own nuclear capability that cost billions and billions of euros.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if Europe really did try to go it alone, he added, “Hey, good luck.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also repeated Mr. Trump’s insistence that China and Russia were becoming a threat to Arctic security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is doing a lot of good stuff, I believe — I know, I’m irritating a lot of you again,” Mr. Rutte said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte said that when it came to Arctic defense, “I think he’s right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maya Tekeli contributed reporting from Nuuk, Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/nato-chief-europe-greenland-trump-us.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:30:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese Panda Fans Bid Farewell to Furry Ambassadors</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/japan-pandas-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-pandas-japan-1-qbtm/26int-pandas-japan-1-qbtm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky lottery winners got one minute to bid goodbye to Xiao Xiao and Lei Lei, twin pandas set to leave Japan on Tuesday amid mounting tensions with China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting in to the Ueno Zoo in Tokyo for a last look at the beloved Chinese diplomats was not easy, but visitors came in droves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since December, when the pandas’ imminent departure was announced, about 4,800 people per day — nearly 200,000 in total — have flocked to the zoo. To score a slot, they filled out online applications, braved crowds and long lines, and most recently competed in a lottery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xiao Xiao and Lei Lei were born at the Ueno Zoo in 2021, and remained on loan there as part of China’s longstanding global panda diplomacy program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though their departure had been planned previously, negotiations over potential replacements stalled after comments in November by Japan’s prime minister, Sanae Takaichi, that Tokyo could intervene militarily if China were to attack Taiwan. China regards the self-governing democracy as part of its territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi’s comments prompted Beijing to urge Chinese tourists to avoid Japan, and to restrict Japanese seafood imports and increase military patrols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are signs that Japan may remain panda free for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, China’s Foreign Ministry reiterated the government’s warnings against travel to Japan, and several major Chinese airlines extended cancellation policies announced in the wake of the spat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panda diplomacy has a long history in China, dating back more than 1,300 years. Historical records show that the Empress Wu Zetian of the Tang Dynasty sent a pair of pandas in cages gilded with red flowers to the Emperor Tenmu in Japan around 660 A.D. The bears were accompanied by animal trainers and imperial guards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Centuries later, in 1972, pandas, an endangered species, again played a role after China and Japan normalized ties following a 35-year rupture. China announced that it would give two bears to Japan to mark the establishment of diplomatic relations between the nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the arrival of those two bears, Kang Kang and Lan Lan, furry, bamboo-chewing ambassadors have gained legions of fans in Japan and drawn millions of visitors to Japanese zoos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The departure of Xiao Xiao and Lei Lei on Tuesday will mark the first time that Japan has been without pandas in more than half a century, though there is hope for those devastated by the looming absence. Pauses in panda diplomacy have happened before. In 2024, Washington welcomed two pandas to the National Zoo after nearly a year without one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts have suggested that the departure of Xiao Xiao and Lei Lei now is intended to bypass policymakers and send Japan’s citizens a pointed message. What effect that might have is unpredictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nancy Snow, a former professor of public diplomacy at Kyoto University, wrote in Nikkei Asia on Monday that “the panda decision, far from softening attitudes, may reinforce perceptions of China as transactional and punitive.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/japan-pandas-china.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 12:59:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canadian Beluga Whales Could Find New Homes in United States</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/canada/canada-marineland-beluga-whales.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/world/26int-canada-whales/26int-canada-whales-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After threatening to euthanize about 30 beluga whales, Marineland, a shuttered Canadian aquatic park, is now likely to send the animals to marine facilities in the United States, the Canadian government said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland, once a bustling tourist destination in Niagara Falls, Ontario, is headed toward bankruptcy and last year asked the federal government for financial help and approval to export the animals to a theme park in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joanne Thompson, Canada’s fisheries minister, turned down the request, largely because the animals would continue living in captivity, prompting Marineland to threaten to put down the whales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the whales would likely still be in captivity in the United States, Ms. Thompson said she had reconsidered her opposition and had conditionally approved Marineland’s new application to send the animals across the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My focus throughout has been the best interest of the whales and that is what has guided this decision,” Ms. Thompson said in a statement on Monday. She said she was awaiting more information from Marineland before granting final permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minister’s office did not respond to questions regarding where the animals are likely to be sent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We extend our gratitude to the minister and the Canadian government for prioritizing the lives of these remarkable marine mammals,” a representative for Marineland said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland is also planning on sending its remaining four dolphins to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camille Labchuk, executive director of Animal Justice, a Canadian animal rights nonprofit, said in a statement that the “the minister had little choice” but to approve the whale’s export, given the park’s threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, she said: “It is also essential to ensure the whales will not be bred in the US. These animals must be the last generation to suffer in captivity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada adopted legal restrictions in 2019 barring the breeding of captive whales and dolphins for entertainment purposes. The options for whales bred in captivity are limited, since they lack skills like hunting and social interaction, which animals in the wild possess in order to survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland, which has been closed to the public since 2024 following years of dwindling ticket sales, has been accused of animal abuse, charges that it has denied. The park is in the process of selling off its rides and is weighing offers to purchase its land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1961 by a Slovenian immigrant, the park grew over the years into a popular destination that covered 1,000 acres and included an amusement park, dining and other animal enclosures, including one for bears.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/canada/canada-marineland-beluga-whales.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:29:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Briefed on Intelligence Saying Iran’s Government Is Weaker</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-reports-iran-government.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-iran01-photo-bcgw/26dc-iran01-photo-bcgw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has received multiple U.S. intelligence reports indicating that the Iranian government’s position is weakening, according to several people familiar with the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports signal that the Iranian government’s hold on power is at its weakest point since the shah was overthrown in the 1979 revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests that erupted late last year, according to the reports, shook elements of the Iranian government, especially as they reached into areas of the country that officials thought were strongholds of support for Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, Iran’s supreme leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the protests have died down, the government remains in a difficult position. Intelligence reports have repeatedly highlighted that in addition to the protests, Iran’s economy is historically weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic hardship ignited sporadic protests in late December. As the demonstrations spread in January, the Iranian government found it had few options to ease the financial difficulties families were feeling. Officials resorted to a heavy handed crackdown that further alienated wide swaths of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military has been building up its forces in the region, but it is not clear what steps the Trump administration may be considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is consistently briefed on intelligence matters around the world,” Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said in a statement. “It would be a dereliction of duty as commander in chief if he were not regularly briefed on these matters. With respect to Iran, President Trump continues to closely monitor the situation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump warned that he could strike Iran as the government’s bloody crackdown on the protests expanded. Still, his advisers have been divided on the benefits of strikes, particularly if they were simply symbolic strikes against elements of the government involved in the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump then seemed to back down on any sort of immediate strike in support of the protests after the Iranian government called off a planned execution of a protester. Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel had also asked Mr. Trump to postpone an attack on Iran, according to a senior U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a broader campaign may have more appeal to some of Mr. Trump’s most hawkish aides and allies who see an opportunity to force out the country’s leadership. And Mr. Trump continues to hold out the threat of force, describing his buildup of naval forces in the region as an “armada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has also mused aloud about Iran’s nuclear program, delivering warnings and reminding the Iranian government of the strikes he ordered last year against its most heavily fortified research sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina, said that he had spoken with Mr. Trump in recent days about Iran and that he expected the president to fulfill his promise to help Iranians who had been protesting their government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The goal is to end the regime,” Mr. Graham said in a brief interview. “They may stop killing them today, but if they’re in charge next month, they’ll kill them then.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Monday, the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln, accompanied by three warships equipped with Tomahawk missiles, entered the U.S. Central Command’s area of responsibility in the western Indian Ocean, said a U.S. official who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss those details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the White House were to order a strike on Iran, the carrier could, in theory, take action within a day or two, military officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has already sent a dozen additional F-15E attack planes to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to U.S. officials. And the Pentagon has dispatched more Patriot and THAAD air defenses to the region to help protect American troops there from any retaliatory strikes by Iranian short- and medium-range missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-range bombers based in the United States that could strike targets in Iran remain on a higher-than-usual alert status. The Pentagon heightened the alert status two weeks ago, when Mr. Trump requested options to respond to the crackdown on protests in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pentagon officials have also stepped up consultations with regional allies in recent days. Adm. Brad Cooper, the head of Central Command, visited Syria, Iraq and Israel over the weekend to confer with U.S. military officers and counterparts there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point of Admiral Cooper’s trip was to visit American troops and detention sites in northeast Syria, a senior U.S. military official said. The U.S. military began transferring Islamic State prisoners to Iraq from northeastern Syria last week amid growing concern that thousands of former fighters and their family members could escape from detention as the Syrian government takes control of much of the area from Kurdish-led forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But U.S. officials have also delivered a message to Iraqi officials: In the event of rising tension with Iran, should Shiite militias in Iraq fire on U.S. bases or troops, the United States would retaliate against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American officials have also been consulting with regional partners on Iran. In addition to conversations with Israeli officials and meetings in Baghdad, Trump administration officials have held talks with Saudi and Qatari officials, according to a U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-reports-iran-government.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:44:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Record Debt in the World’s Richest Nations Threatens Global Growth</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Record-high debt in the United States, Britain, France, Italy and Japan risks slowing growth and destabilizing the global economy.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:01:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>All-Night Concerts Bring Fleeting Normalcy in a War-Ravaged Nation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performer stood in front of an audience of 800, right before dawn on a recent Sunday. It was the tail end of his eight-hour extravaganza featuring pop, hip-hop and Burmese folk music. He was upbeat, relishing his recent return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Regardless of any difficulties you face, one day, summer will come,” U Than Zaw Htwe, 30, told his audience, many of whom were sitting cross-legged on a silver tarp in an open field on the outskirts of Yangon, Myanmar’s biggest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life in Myanmar was upended five years ago, when the military seized power in a coup. Now the junta is trying to project a veneer of legitimacy and normalcy, even as it is fighting a grinding civil war with pro-democracy rebels and other groups. It has held elections, which have been widely derided as a sham. It has organized a massive hot-air balloon festival. And it has allowed some traditional music artists to return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Than Zaw Htwe is one of them, leading a new 70-member troupe that was founded in October. He performs zat pwe (pronounced zat-PWAY), or “story show,” an opera-like art form that dates back to the 1800s. Today, it is a kaleidoscope of Burmese pop, synchronized dance, slapstick comedy and the retelling of legends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His shows — which go from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. — are booked out until April. Known by his stage name San Yay Moe, his videos have flooded Burmese TikTok accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are feeling mentally suffocated,” he said in an interview. “They need happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another performer had a similar message for his audience at one of his recent shows. “Live in the present,” said U Chit Myo Htike, perhaps the most prominent zat pwe performer and whose stage name is Phoe Chit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many urbanites in the country are doing just that. In Yangon, nightclubs are heaving. Domestic tourism is booming in parts of the country where there is no fighting. Night bazaars are now held regularly. Many of these events are sanctioned by the junta, which controls the nation’s cities but not its hinterlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INDIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CHINA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MYANMAR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naypyidaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LAOS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yangon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THAILAND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andaman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 MILES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent Sunday, I stood in line with hundreds of peopleto watch a performance. It was the last night of a three-day run in Hmawbi township, on Yangon’s outskirts. The tickets ranged from 30,000 kyats to 60,000 kyats, or about $14 to $28, which is relatively pricey, given that the average monthly wage is about $75. (I shelled out roughly $10 more for a chair.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With temperatures dipping in to the low 60s Fahrenheit, many in the audience settled in with blankets and beanies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For three days a week, this is their happy hour,” U Aung Kyaw Tun, the founder of the San Yay Moe troupe, said in English. He said he once experimented with shorter shows that ended at midnight, but the audience was not satisfied and clamored to stay until the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear that San Yay Moe was the biggest draw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU!” a woman behind me screamed in English toward the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love you too!” San Yay Moe responded, also in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with tradition, audience members showed their appreciation by heading to the stage and pinning cash on the performers’ outfits. At one point, San Yay Moe had so much money pinned on his sleeves that the bills looked like feathers on wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around midnight, I went backstage, where wages were being distributed. Mr. Aung Kyaw Tun said he made about 100 million kyats, or $25,000, for the three nights. San Yay Moe gets to take home the money that is given to him by fans, this time roughly 70 million kyats, or $17,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 1.30 a.m., it was time for San Yan Moe to perform a medley of songs. He strode out in a purple suit with a strip of silver sequins running down his trousers and top. A group of backup dancers gyrated behind him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was one of his hypersonic costume changes. Off came his purple top and on came a white vest. The audience waved their hands in the air. Near the stage, a group of men moshed around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 3.30 a.m., the show moved into an adaptation of the Ramayana, the Hindu epic. By this time, I was fading; but not San Yay Moe, who was in character, writhing onstage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, I returned to Yangon to see Phoe Chit perform. His show felt almost like a spiritual experience. The audience knew the words to all his songs, and took out handkerchiefs and cellphones to wave along to the music. One was a ballad titled “To A Friend,” in which the singer urges a jilted friend to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, Phoe Chit moved to a play in multiple acts that touched on filial themes and had a climax in which the lead character was forced to marry his brother’s pregnant girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Phoe Chit, 43, was among a list of celebrities who received distinguished artist awards from Senior Gen. Min Aung Hlaing, the military commander who led the coup in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, Phoe Chit was detained for a brief period on suspicion that he was helping fund armed resistance to the junta, according to some reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phoe Chit declined to comment but said that his troupe started performing last February after a hiatus of six years because he got the approval from the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the night bazaars and the San Yay Moe show, many used the phrase “political situation” to refer to what their country was going through. I asked people whether they were happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want a new normal,” said Shoon Lae Po, 25, who runs a currency exchange service and was strolling around at a night bazaar, which sold snacks like “husband and wife” pastries, and offered “ceramic astrology,” palm-reading and Burmese pythons for stroking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her partner, Thiri Zaw Zaw, 23, chimed in. “It’s been five years, we cannot stay like this,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Yangon, two residents told me that they had stopped going to the movies and traveling after the coup. They wept as they spoke of their guilt, thinking about friends who had gone into the jungles and taken up arms against the junta. But one of them said that she was planning a holiday trip for the sake of her mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thazin Oo, 26, a student, said people turned up to the shows to “relieve their stress” and because “there’s nothing to entertain us at the moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are not happy anymore,” she said. But when I asked what stress she felt, her friend chimed: “Just say work stress!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, the sun was rising. A comedian intoned into the microphone: “Go home please, we want to sleep!” The audience chuckled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was past 6 a.m. A white strobe light turned on. It was the cue to leave. San Yay Moe walked around taking selfies. Others packed up their blankets and baskets and filed out of the field. Outside, trucks with workers huddled in their beds streamed past, ready to start a new day.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:01:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Seeks Trade With China Without Triggering Trump’s Fury</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain will leave on Tuesday for a high-stakes visit to China, seeking new trade and investment from the world’s second-largest economy as relations between the United States and its Western allies grow increasingly volatile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer took office 18 months ago with a promise to improve relations with China, and British officials hope that his three-day, finance-focused mission to Beijing and Shanghai will result in deals that can spur Britain’s lagging economy — and his Labour Party’s dismal standing — into recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Starmer, the first British prime minister to visit China since 2018, will have to navigate an increasingly fraught space between two global superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His trip comes just days after President Trump threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canada if the country’s prime minister, Mark Carney, made a trade deal with China. There is no indication that Canada and China are discussing a broad economic agreement, but Mr. Carney agreed to lower tariffs on some Chinese electric vehicles on a visit this month with Xi Jinping, China’s top leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Governor Carney thinks he is going to make Canada a ‘Drop Off Port’ for China to send goods and products into the United States, he is sorely mistaken,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media, calling Mr. Carney ”governor” in a reference to his repeated threats to annex Canada and make it the 51st U.S. state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China’s leadership, Mr. Starmer’s visit gives Beijing an opportunity to court another staunch U.S. ally alienated by the Trump administration. Chancellor Rachel Reeves, Britain’s most senior finance official, and Peter Kyle, the country’s trade secretary, are accompanying Mr. Starmer on his trip, along with several of the country’s top financial services CEOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Theresa May, the last British prime minister to visit China, went there in 2018, she vowed to cement what her predecessors had dubbed a “golden era” of Chinese-British relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Starmer, however, meeting with Mr. Xi is risky. The political consensus in much of Britain has turned decidedly against China, with growing concerns over national security and human rights, and deep anger about the dumping of cheap Chinese products on global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer suffered blowback when prosecutors dropped a case last September against two British nationals accused of spying for China, and when his government last week approved a controversial Chinese mega-embassy in central London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics, including the Trump administration, say the embassy will allow China to conduct widespread spying. Mr. Starmer’s visit was partly contingent on British approval of the embassy, according to Chinese analysts and Chinese state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those tensions between economic and national security interests are at the heart of Mr. Starmer’s trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We labor under these misapprehensions that we’re going to be able to get a lot of money quick, that it’s going to enable the government to tell a good news story about the economy, which they desperately need,” said Luke de Pulford, the executive director of the Inter-Parliamentary Alliance on China, an international group of lawmakers that pushes for a more critical view of the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can understand the political imperatives,” he said, “but the longer-term resilience, health, national security of the U.K. is at stake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer is not the only leader who has taken the risk of triggering Mr. Trump’s ire by trekking to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;António Costa, the president of the European Council, and Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, met with Mr. Xi in July at the Great Hall of the People. President Emmanuel Macron of France was welcomed in China last month with a red carpet and an honor guard. Chancellor Friedrich Merz of Germany is expected to go in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Mr. Trump has lashed out directly only at Mr. Carney, who warned in a recent speech of a “rupture” in the world order because of the superpower competition between the United States and China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we’re reminded that we live in an era of great-power rivalry,” Mr. Carney said in Davos, Switzerland last week. He added: “The middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Starmer is looking to hedge against an increasingly mercurial Washington, Beijing will be more than willing to oblige — but on its terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think China is trying to drive a wedge between the United States and its allies,” said Kerry Brown, a professor of Chinese studies at King’s College London. “Mr. Trump is managing that very nicely on his own and needs no help from Beijing. But China is an opportunist, and if there are some favorable winds coming its way because of how everyone else is feeling about America now, then they will take these.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China will likely expect Britain to welcome more Chinese investment and exports, Mr. Brown said. It will also want to depoliticize a bilateral relationship that has been dominated for years by security and human rights issues and by the status of Hong Kong, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One area of friction is the fate of Jimmy Lai, the former Hong Kong media tycoon who was convicted in December of national security crimes, and who has become a symbol of the erosion of freedoms in the former British colony. Mr. Lai, a British citizen, is expected to be sentenced in the coming weeks and faces up to life in prison. Mr. Starmer has called for Mr. Lai’s release. Beijing has dismissed such calls as “blatant interference” in its internal affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yvette Cooper, Britain’s foreign secretary, is not joining Mr. Starmer on his trip to China, suggesting that political issues are taking a back seat to the desire for economic investments. One British official, speaking on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy, said such issues would be raised but would not be a focus of the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opening Britain’s market to Chinese firms and depoliticizing its relationship with China would signal growing cracks in the U.S.-led alliance that had previously worked to restrain China but that has been shaken by Mr. Trump’s threats to seize Greenland and by his vows to punish those who oppose the move. (The president has since backed off both threats, but worries remain.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, China has been casting itself as a stable and reliable power. Beijing argues that the United States is trying to return the world to the “law of the jungle” in which big powers bully weaker ones simply because they can — although China has few reservations about exerting its own leverage over smaller nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts in China, noting that Mr. Starmer has made economic growth a top priority, say that British companies want greater access to the Chinese market and that British consumers need affordable Chinese technologies like electric vehicles, solar panels and wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This visit signifies a restart of China-U.K. relations under a new situation,” said Wu Xinbo, the dean at the Institute of International Studies at Fudan University in Shanghai. “Both sides hope, through this visit, to confirm the positioning and development path” so that bilateral relations can “reach a new high point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berry Wang contributed reporting from Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:01:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gunmen Kill 11 After Soccer Match in Mexico</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/americas/mexico-shooting-salamanca-cartels.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-mexico-shooting-zmgk/26int-mexico-shooting-zmgk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gunmen opened fire on a crowded soccer field in Mexico on Sunday, killing 11 and injuring 12, in an attack that appeared to highlight the persistent violence from the nation’s cartels despite the government’s efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gunfire hit people who were socializing after a soccer match, according to local officials, capping a particularly violent period in Salamanca, a city of 275,000 in the central state of Guanajuato.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another incident left five people dead in Salamanca on Saturday, and a week earlier, authorities disarmed an explosive device at a state-owned oil facility there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are going through a dark moment, a serious breakdown of our social fabric,” Cesar Prieto, Salamanca’s mayor, said in a video address on Sunday night. “Sadly, criminal groups are trying to subdue the government, something they will never achieve.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guanajuato had Mexico’s highest number of murders last year, with 2,035 intentional homicides. That violence has been largely driven by a turf war between a local cartel and the Jalisco New Generation Cartel, Mexico’s most powerful criminal group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salamanca, in particular, lies near a border that separates territory controlled by each group, and is also home to an important oil refinery. Both cartels want to control Salamanca to aid their drug-trafficking and fuel-theft businesses. Local officials said they were investigating Sunday’s shooting, including whether either cartel was involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mass shooting is an especially unwelcome development for the Mexican government, which has been carrying out an aggressive campaign against drug cartels in an effort to show the White House that it is serious about stopping the flow of drugs to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has been threatening land strikes against the cartels in Mexico for months, saying the groups run the country. President Claudia Sheinbaum of Mexico has said repeatedly that a unilateral strike would be a violation of Mexican sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, more specific threats from Mr. Trump, as well as the U.S. capture of President Nicolás Maduro of Venezuela, have heightened fears among Mexican officials that Mexico could be in the crosshairs next. The Trump administration has also been pushing Mexican officials to allow U.S. forces in Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Mexico has been eager to hit the cartels harder, hoping it can stave off any U.S. action. In recent days, Mexico announced the capture of several highly sought-after criminals, including a former Canadian Olympic snowboarder who had become a prolific cocaine trafficker. Mexico also transferred 37 accused criminals to the United States last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s efforts have helped lower the number of homicides by more than 20 percent in Mexico compared with a year prior. It has focused much of its firepower on the Sinaloa cartel, a notorious criminal organization based in the nation’s west, and has succeeded in significantly weakening the group. But security experts have said that, at the same time, the Jalisco cartel has strengthened its grip on other parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That includes Guanajuato. Homicides in the state dropped over the second half of last year, but the fighting between the Jalisco cartel and the Santa Rosa de Lima cartel, a local group, has meant the killing has continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The soccer field where the shooting occurred on Sunday is a popular gathering point in the community, with matches drawing large crowds each weekend, said Orlando Arredondo Gallardo, a Salamanca government spokesman. “There are children, there are food stands,” he said. “Everyone attends, especially on Sundays, which is when it’s more family-oriented.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 12 people injured in the shooting included a woman and a child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Shortell, Emiliano Rodríguez Mega and Miguel García Lemus contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/americas/mexico-shooting-salamanca-cartels.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 09:12:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Taliban Say They’re Ready to Release U.S. Prisoners. But Which Ones?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/taliban-afghanistan-prisoners.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-afghanistan-prisoners-01-zbth/26int-afghanistan-prisoners-01-zbth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, U.S. and Afghan officials have secretly negotiated the release of U.S. detainees — a priority for President Trump and a nonnegotiable prerequisite for any further diplomatic engagement with the Taliban.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet even as at least five U.S. prisoners have been freed from Afghanistan over the past year, talks have stalled over the fate of remaining detainees, according to three people involved in the negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While several U.S. prisoners remain in custody, Afghan officials say the release of the last Afghan inmate at Guantánamo Bay rests with the United States and should be part of any further deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guantánamo inmate’s case and the whereabouts of a U.S. citizen in Afghan custody remain a central flashpoint between the Trump administration, which accuses Afghanistan of hostage diplomacy, and a Taliban government that denies those accusations while it seeks recognition from the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want these two American detainees to be released, and, at the same time, the fate of our detainee who is in Guantánamo should be made clear,” Zabiullah Mujahid, the Taliban spokesman, said in an interview with The Times in the southern Afghan city of Kandahar — the first time Afghan officials are making their demand public. “Our prisoner should be released.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Afghan detainee, Muhammad Rahim, is accused of acting as a courier and interpreter for Osama Bin Laden within Al Qaeda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the Taliban have decided to comment publicly on a potential prisoner swap is unclear. But it signals an impasse in negotiations with the Trump administration, which has publicly demanded the release of at least three Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban say they have only two — identified by U.S. officials as Dennis Walter Coyle, an academic held since last January, and Polynesis Jackson, a former U.S. Army soldier whose reasons for being in the country remain murky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghan officials say they do not know the whereabouts of a third U.S. citizen, Mahmood Habibi, who the F.B.I. says was arrested in Afghanistan in 2022 shortly after the C.I.A. killed Ayman al-Zawahri, Al Qaeda’s leader, in Kabul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan’s foreign minister, Amir Khan Muttaqi, said no American prisoner was being held for bargaining purposes. “We support finding a solution to this issue as soon as possible,” Mr. Muttaqi said in a subsequent interview with The Times in Kabul. “We never arrest someone to make deals with their country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Muttaqi added, “We want progress in all areas with the United States,” including the reopening of the U.S. embassy in Kabul and strengthened security cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States does not formally recognize the Taliban as Afghanistan’s legitimate authority, but U.S. envoys have traveled several times to Afghanistan over the past year to secure the release of American detainees. At least four have already been freed under the second Trump administration, according to the White House — none of them as part of prisoner swaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A participant in the negotiations, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss ongoing release efforts, said the Trump administration would not consider any further public engagement until all remaining U.S. citizens were freed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Department declined to discuss the case of Mr. Rahim, but the administration’s position was unequivocal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We know the Taliban abducted and detained Mahmood Habibi over three years ago,” a State Department spokesperson said. “The Taliban should immediately release Dennis Coyle, Mahmood Habibi and all Americans detained in Afghanistan and end its practice of hostage diplomacy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The previous administration had offered Mr. Rahim in a prisoner swap that included Mr. Habibi, but the Taliban rejected that offer, American officials say. Instead, the Taliban government freed Ryan Corbett and William Wallace McKenty last January in exchange for Khan Mohammed, a convicted drug dealer who was released from a U.S. federal prison. The Taliban later freed three other Americans — George Glezmann and Faye Hall in March; and Amir Amiry in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior U.S. official added that Mr. Rahim would not be part of any future deal despite the Taliban government’s demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Habibi’s brother, Ahmad, said officials from the Trump administration had promised him that there would be no deal for Mr. Rahim, the Guantánamo prisoner, until Mr. Habibi was returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have proof the Taliban’s G.D.I. arrested him, so they are only prolonging things by refusing to admit it,” Mr. Habibi said about the General Directorate of Intelligence, Afghanistan’s intelligence agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Afghan intelligence services didn’t respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Afghan official with direct knowledge of the negotiations said that the Taliban had released U.S. detainees last year, and the United States had lifted bounties on senior Afghan officials, as part of a framework meant to settle the prisoners’ issue. But recent developments, including the deadly attack on two National Guard troops that U.S. officials say was committed by a 29-year-old Afghan man near the White House in November, had brought the negotiations to a stalemate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Afghan official, speaking on condition of anonymity to comment on the negotiations, said the Taliban would be willing to discuss Mr. Habibi’s fate only after other U.S. detainees and Mr. Rahim had been released. Mr. Habibi was never part of the initial framework agreed upon last year, the official added, but Mr. Rahim was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Department lists Mr. Coyle, who is from Colorado, as a wrongful detainee, and his family has taken a more visible role in advocating for his release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The circumstances surrounding the detention of Mr. Jackson, like Mr. Habibi’s, are more opaque.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, President Trump said in a television interview about Mr. Coyle’s detention by the Taliban, “I’m not happy about them holding anybody, especially if he’s not guilty of anything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rahim, the Afghan prisoner, has been held in Guantánamo since 2008 and is the last Afghan citizen there. The United States says Mr. Rahim, now 60, had advanced knowledge of Al Qaeda attacks. He was subjected to “extensive use of the C.I.A’s enhanced-interrogation techniques,” including sleep deprivation that once lasted nearly six days, according to the Senate Committee’s Report on the C.I.A.’s Use of Torture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rahim’s family says he did not do anything wrong and has asked the Taliban administration to secure his release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has never been charged with crimes while held in Guantánamo Bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safiullah Padshah and Yaqoob Akbary contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/taliban-afghanistan-prisoners.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:41:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Reports of Progress, Kremlin Says Ukraine Talks Will Continue</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/russia-ukraine-war-peace-talks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-russia-ukraine-htbq/26int-russia-ukraine-htbq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talks among Russian, Ukrainian and American officials to end the war in Ukraine are set to resume next week, the Kremlin spokesman said on Monday, after a round of negotiations that President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine described as constructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two days of talks, the first face-to-face negotiations by Ukraine and Russia since June, wrapped up on Saturday in Abu Dhabi, capital of the United Arab Emirates. Mr. Zelensky said on social media on Saturday that more meetings would be held “provided there is readiness to move forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Dmitri S. Peskov, the Kremlin spokesman, told reporters in Moscow that further talks were scheduled for next week, though he did not specify a date. A U.S. official, speaking on the condition of anonymity to describe diplomatic strategy, said the talks were set for Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Ukrainian and Russian officials left the rare direct talks in Abu Dhabi in a somewhat optimistic mood, according to official Ukrainian statements and Russian state media reports. After months of negotiations, Ukraine and the United States have come to an agreement on much of a 20-point peace plan, but it remains unclear if Russia will ultimately agree to any proposal to end the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Mr. Zelensky said the delegations had discussed an American role in postwar security guarantees for Ukraine and that negotiations on the issue would continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, he said that Ukraine and Russia both should be willing to compromise. But Mr. Peskov, in his remarks Monday, gave little indication that the Kremlin was ready to back down on its full aims in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major sticking point is control of territory in eastern Ukraine. On that question, Mr. Peskov insisted that Moscow would accept nothing less than terms that Russia says were reached by President Trump and President Vladimir V. Putin this past summer in Alaska. Russia says the American president agreed to a deal in which Ukraine would surrender parts of the Donbas region that Russian forces have been unable to capture through four years of war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Witkoff, an American envoy who participated in the Abu Dhabi talks, said before those meetings that just one major issue was left to be resolved. Mr. Zelensky said the issue was territory. “It’s all about the eastern part of our country,” he said last week in Davos, Switzerland, where he was attending the World Economic Forum. “It’s all about the land.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its daily brief on the war in Ukraine, the Institute for the Study of War said the Kremlin may be using the new trilateral talks simply to stall for time, as Moscow has done repeatedly through years of on-again-off-again negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The institute, a policy organization based in Washington, noted that Russia hoped to avoid the additional sanctions that Mr. Trump had threatened if the Kremlin refused to negotiate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peace process has taken on a greater urgency for Ukraine: Moscow has intensified a bombing campaign against civilian infrastructure in Kyiv and other cities, leaving hundreds of thousands without power or heating during a brutal Ukrainian winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Sunday evening, more than 1,300 apartment buildings in Kyiv had no power or heat, according to Vitali Klitschko, the city’s mayor.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/russia-ukraine-war-peace-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:25:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As U.S. Warships Get Closer, Iran and Allies Ramp Up Retaliation Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/us-warships-gulf-waters-iran-retaliation-threats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-iran-retaliation-vjpl/26int-iran-retaliation-vjpl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As U.S. warplanes and aircraft carriers approach the Persian Gulf, Tehran and its regional allies are warning they will respond aggressively to a potential strike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fiery rhetoric has been a standard part of Iran and its allies’ messaging to Washington. The last time those words were tested — when U.S. warplanes joined Israel in a 12-day war against Iran last June — the result was a relatively minimal retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recent surge in threats follows President Trump’s announcement last Thursday that he was sending a large naval force, which he called an “armada,” into the Persian Gulf. “We’ll see what happens,” he told reporters as he returned from the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials in the Middle East are increasingly worried the United States will strike Iran in the coming days, an attack that could trigger a cycle of retaliation against U.S. bases across the region by Iran and its proxy groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Monday, the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln, accompanied by three warships equipped with Tomahawk missiles, entered the Central Command’s area of responsibility in the western Indian Ocean, said a U.S. official who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss those details. If the White House were to order attacks on Iran, the carrier could, in theory, take military action within a day or two. The United States has already sent a dozen F-15E attack planes to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to U.S. officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly warned he could strike Iran since a wave of demonstrations erupted in late December and then swelled to nationwide protests. In early January, he said the United States was “locked and loaded” if “innocent protesters” were killed. Days later, he encouraged protesters to keep demonstrating, saying “help is on its way.” Soon after that, Iranian security forces unleashed a brutal crackdown that rights groups say has killed thousands of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was no U.S. military action after the killings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iranian officials have now intensified their frequent warnings against an attack, with several officials now releasing statements daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, both Iran’s foreign and defense ministries , vowed retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our response will be more decisive and more painful than before if we become the target of a U.S.–Zionist attack,” Reza Talaei-Nik, the defense ministry spokesman said, in reference to the June war that Israel launched against Iran, and which was briefly joined by U.S. warplanes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours later, the commander of Iran’s navy said the country’s armed forces are “fully prepared to safeguard the nation’s sovereignty,” according to the semiofficial news agency ISNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A massive billboard was unfurled in a central square of Tehran on Sunday, depicting a bloodied aircraft carrier in the shape and colors of the American flag. It showed a blue flight deck, studded with fighter jets exploding into white stars, and water streaming behind in streaks of red and white. A slogan written in both Persian and English read: “If you sow the wind, you will reap the whirlwind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s regional dominance has starkly diminished over the last two years,. Israel has attacked and weakened the Lebanese force Hezbollah, long seen as Tehran’s most potent regional ally, and the Palestinian militant group Hamas, in the wake of the Oct. 7 attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The perceived threat posed by Iran’s regional alliance, which also includes militias in Iraq and the Houthi forces in Yemen, was further undermined by those forces’ apparent reluctance to retaliate during the June war, which battered Iran’s nuclear and military sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump warned earlier in January that if Iran executed protesters, he would act, and has since argued that those threats of intervention stopped more than 830 executions — a claim that Iran’s prosecutor general denied as “completely false.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear whether Iran has executed any protesters, in part because information has been hard to verify amid a widespread digital and communications blackout across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Mr. Trump appeared to back away from a strike, after receiving a string of urgent warnings from several Middle East leaders that it could spark a regional conflagration. Iranian officials had told their counterparts in the Gulf and Iraq that their countries would not be spared in retaliatory attacks against U.S. military sites they host, according to regional officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since the movement of U.S. warships and fighter jets, Iran’s proxies have begun to openly threaten to join their patron for any retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Lebanon, Naim Qassim, the leader of Hezbollah, broadcast a televised speech to hundreds of supporters at a gathering in the southern suburb of Beirut, where the group holds sway. Many of them waved posters of the Iranian flag or Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, a top religious leader to Shiite Muslims across the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When Trump threatens Imam Khamenei, he is threatening tens of millions who follow this leader,” Mr. Qassim told the crowd. “It is our duty to confront this threat with all necessary measures and preparedness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kataib Hezbollah, the most powerful Iran-backed Shiite militia in neighboring Iraq, urged its fighters to prepare for a potential war in a statement on Sunday, and said that if the conflict escalated, its clerical leaders could decide to declare “martyrdom operations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A war against Iran, the group said, “will not be easy. You will taste every form of deadly suffering, nothing of you will remain in our region, and we will strike terror in your hearts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In meetings in Baghdad in recent days, Joe Kent, the director of the U.S. National Counterterrorism Center, warned Iraqis that if Iranian-backed militias in Iraq were to strike U.S. troops, the United States would retaliate against those Shiite militias, according to Iraqi and American officials. U.S. forces maintain a large presence in Erbil, in Iraq’s semiautonomous Kurdistan region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, the United Arab Emirates’ foreign ministry released a statement reiterating its “commitment to not allowing its airspace, territory, or waters to be used in any hostile military actions against Iran, and to not providing any logistical support in this regard.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Donegan, a retired vice admiral and former top Navy commander in the Middle East, said that the outcome of any attack on Iran’s government is unpredictable, which is why Mr. Trump’s likely aim, he said, would be to improve his position in future negotiations rather than an outright military victory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Despite past attacks against their missile systems and command-and-control, they still have a lot of missiles and drones that can strike U.S. bases in the region. So an element of this U.S. posture will be reinforced defense,” he said. “I see this current posture of forces as a maximum pressure move with a ‘deal’ being the desired outcome.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vivian Nereim, Julian Barnes, , Aaron Boxerman, Sanam Mahoozi, and Dayana Iwaza contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/us-warships-gulf-waters-iran-retaliation-threats.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 11:50:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Remains of Last Captive in Gaza Are Retrieved, Closing a Chapter for Israel</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/gaza-hostage-returned-israel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-israel-ran-gvili-new1-hvqg/26int-israel-ran-gvili-new1-hvqg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel recovered the remains of its last captive from the Gaza Strip on Monday, scouring a cemetery to unearth the body of a 24-year-old police officer and help a traumatized nation turn the page on one of the most agonizing chapters in its history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said it had found and brought back the body of Master Sgt. Ran Gvili, a member of an elite police counterterrorism unit who, recuperating from a fractured shoulder, had rushed into battle as Hamas led a surprise assault on Oct. 7, 2023, setting off the two-year war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing the recovery of Israel’s fallen paves the way for the next phase of President Trump’s peace plan for Gaza. The plan calls for Israel to reopen the Rafah border crossing between Gaza and Egypt, allowing Palestinians who fled the enclave to return home for the first time. But Israel had refused to reopen the border until Sergeant Gvili’s body was returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Monday, hours before saying it had recovered Sergeant Gvili’s remains, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu’s office said that Israel would open the crossing after finishing the search. After the announcement that Sergeant Gvili’s body had indeed been retrieved, a spokesman for the Israeli military unit responsible for overseeing passage in and out of Gaza, Shimi Zuaretz, said that Rafah would reopen in the “next days.” The Israeli government would have to sign off on the exact timing, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Gvili was shot while defending one of southern Israel’s border communities, Kibbutz Alumim. He was then seized and taken to Gaza by militants from Palestinian Islamic Jihad, an armed extremist group that joined in the attack, according to the Israeli authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Gvili was among about 250 people that Palestinian militants abducted on Oct. 7, most of them civilians, during an attack that left about 1,200 people dead in Israel and unleashed a war that killed some 70,000 Palestinians. Many of the hostages were released during two brief cease-fires, but dozens perished in captivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israel Defense Forces said it identified his remains using dental records, after finding his body in a cemetery in central Gaza, in a search that began Sunday morning. Israeli news reports said more than 200 other graves were examined before Sergeant Gvili’s was found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chief of staff of the Israel Defense Forces, Lt. Gen. Eyal Zamir, posted a video in which he spoke by phone with Sergeant Gvili’s parents. After they described their relief and thanked him and the entire army, he said, “We have completed the mission of bringing everyone back, and we upheld a very meaningful I.D.F. value — leaving no one behind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing about the war had been more tormenting to Israelis than the drawn-out captivity of those, alive and dead, who remained in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It fueled a powerful antiwar movement aimed at bringing the hostages home, galvanized mass protests in the heart of Tel Aviv and inspired angry slogans on banners, billboards and car bumpers across Israel. Hostages’ families blamed Mr. Netanyahu for prolonging the war and endangering their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fate of the hostages also turned President Trump into an Israeli national hero when his administration orchestrated a cease-fire that secured the release of the 20 living hostages in exchange for nearly 2,000 Palestinian prisoners and detainees — including 250 who had been serving life sentences for deadly attacks on Israelis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cease-fire, which took effect Oct. 10, also called for Hamas to turn over the bodies of 28 captives in Gaza to Israel within 72 hours. It took three and a half months for Israel to recover the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas said it needed time and heavy equipment to retrieve some of the bodies, saying they were under rubble after two years of bombardment. Each of the bodies returned to Israel was exchanged for the bodies of 15 deceased Gazans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel accused Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad of intentionally dragging their feet over returning the remains. Analysts said Hamas may have been trying to stave off the second phase of the cease-fire, particularly its call for the group to put down its weapons, which Hamas has long regarded as essential to its identity and grip on power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas rebuffed Israel’s accusations, saying that, in Sergeant Gvili’s case, the location of his remains had been unknown and bad weather had hampered the search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a small stampede to claim credit for the recovery of his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is an extraordinary achievement for the State of Israel,” Mr. Netanyahu, who is up for re-election this year, told reporters in the Knesset. “We promised — I promised — to bring everyone back, and we have brought everyone back, every last one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump made this possible,” Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, wrote on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Congratulations to my great team of Champions,” Mr. Trump wrote on his social-media site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Hamas took credit, in its own way, saying in a statement that it had “exerted significant efforts in the search” for Sergeant Gvili’s remains, and had provided “information as it became available, which contributed to the recovery of the body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans for carrying out the second phase of the peace plan are still taking shape. It calls for Hamas to hand over governing of the enclave to a technocratic committee of Palestinians and international experts, supported by an international stabilization force deployed in Gaza and overseen by a “Board of Peace” led by Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Jared Kushner, the president’s son-in-law, sketched out an ambitious, almost fantastical new vision for Gaza, now in ruins, with soaring skyscrapers along the beach, industrial areas and new cities built from scratch. Land is already being cleared for construction to begin in parts of southern Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Netanyahu cautioned on Monday that rebuilding would have to wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are on the threshold of the next phase,” he said. “The next phase is the disarmament of Hamas and the demilitarization of the Gaza Strip — it is not reconstruction. We have an interest in advancing this phase and not delaying it, and that is what we will do. The sooner we disarm Hamas and demilitarize the Gaza Strip, the sooner we will complete the objectives of the war.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Netanyahu brought Sergeant Gvili’s family to accompany him on his visit to the United States last month for meetings with Mr. Trump and administration officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Time doesn’t heal my broken heart — it only reduces the chance of bringing Ran home,” Talik Gvili, Sergeant Gvili’s mother, said at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all Israelis had seemed to take to heart the recovery of the bodies of their compatriots. Which may help explain why Israel’s police commissioner, Danny Levy, posted a video on Monday of his emotional phone call with Sergeant Gvili’s father, Itzik Gvili.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just want to tell you that he was found intact, with his uniform and everything on him,” Commissioner Levy told the bereaved man. “You are receiving your son as he was when he went out — even with a tear in his pants. I don’t know if that is any comfort, but it was important to me to tell you these details, that you should know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaron Boxerman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/gaza-hostage-returned-israel.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:00:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Xi’s China, Even the Mightiest General Can Fall</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/china-xi-zhang-youxia-military.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-china-general-khjv/26int-china-general-khjv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Gen. Zhang Youxia met with U.S. officials in Beijing in 2024, he exuded the confidence of a man who was seen as the most trusted deputy in the military of China’s top leader, Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang did not appear worried that he had to look over his shoulder to make sure he was pleasing the leader, said Jake Sullivan, who was the U.S. national security adviser attending the meeting, which lasted at least an hour. “He spoke in an unvarnished way that was typical of a military guy, but also reflective of someone who didn’t feel like he had to be cautious.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That image of General Zhang’s invulnerability, and closeness to Mr. Xi, shattered over the weekend, when China’s defense ministry announced that he was under investigation for unspecified breaches of laws and political discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang’s downfall is of a different magnitude from the dozens of other generals who have been toppled in Mr. Xi’s unrelenting campaign against perceived corruption and disloyalty over the past three years. His fate has astonished even longtime experts who thought that they had taken full measure of Mr. Xi, China’s most powerful and imperious leader in generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s fair to say this is a seismic event,” Mr. Sullivan said. For Mr. Xi to “take out somebody who he had such a long history with is striking and raises a lot of questions,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 75, General Zhang was old enough that Mr. Xi could in theory have ushered him into retirement. Instead, Mr. Xi made a public pariah of him. An editorial about General Zhang in the Liberation Army Daily on Sunday hinted that he was being accused of corruption, and, perhaps more important, of disloyalty to Mr. Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang and another commander who fell with him, Gen. Liu Zhenli, had “trampled on” the authority of the military chairman — that is, Mr. Xi — and had “severely undermined the party’s absolute leadership over the military,” the editorial said. Their actions had “rendered massive damage” on the military’s political soundness and combat readiness, it said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It reads more to suggest that they really were challenging Xi Jinping, that it was really a personal betrayal,” said Shanshan Mei, a political scientist at RAND, a research organization, who studies China’s military. “Corruption is mentioned, but to me this gist of what they are accused of is very political, betraying Xi.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What prompted Mr. Xi to finally turn against General Zhang is now a topic of fevered speculation in Beijing and beyond. Some experts believe that Mr. Xi may have come to see General Zhang as too powerful after the general’s own rivals were toppled in previous purges. Others believe Mr. Xi concluded that systemic corruption was so deep that he needed drastic surgery to clear the way for a new generation of commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other allegations have emerged. The Wall Street Journal reported on Sunday, citing anonymous sources, that General Zhang has been accused of leaking nuclear secrets to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timing of the investigation has drawn attention to General Zhang’s recent high-level engagements. Mr. Sullivan said their discussions of nuclear issues in 2024 — in the presence of about 20 other Chinese military officers — were strictly general. He said that he brought up nuclear weapons in the context of China’s overall military buildup, but said that General Zhang said nothing sensitive or even substantive on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That was not one of the main topics of the discussion,” Mr. Sullivan said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Xi and General Zhang are both “princelings,” the sons of revolutionaries who served under Mao Zedong. General Zhang’s father was a general who served alongside Mr. Xi’s father, Xi Zhongxun, in northwest China. There is no evidence that General Zhang and Mr. Xi were close as children, but their shared background might have helped to cement their bond at some point, said Joseph Torigian, the author of a biography of the older Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang was a celebrated war veteran in a nation where few active commanders have endured real combat. Mr. Xi kept him in office past retirement, and made him his top vice chairman of the Central Military Commission — Mr. Xi’s eyes and ears in running the People’s Liberation Army’s forces day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if formal charges are leveled against General Zhang, he may face a secret trial in the military justice system. If so, he is almost certain to be convicted and imprisoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang’s downfall “will ultimately have a big effect on the power elite in Beijing because it removes one of their safety boundaries,” said Deng Yuwen, a former editor of a Chinese Communist Party newspaper in Beijing who now lives in the United States. “Even Zhang Youxia’s personal relationship with Xi Jinping was no guarantee of his safety, so nobody can feel safe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Zhang joined the army in late 1968 and later distinguished himself as a frontline officer during China’s grinding, yearslong border war with Vietnam from 1979. Accounts from troops described him as an audacious and wily unit leader who urged soldiers to use more artillery during a series of battles for Longshan, a disputed area on the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We must first grab him by his throat so that he can’t escape, advance or move, and then we strike,” General Zhang told a junior officer, Li Zhongping, according to a Chinese oral history of the war published in 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Xi became China’s leader in 2012, he quickly moved to shake up the military, which was rife with corruption and organizationally stuck in the past, ill equipped to deal with the country’s expanding naval, air and nuclear weapons ambitions. General Zhang was one of the commanders tapped by Mr. Xi to help lead his overhaul of the People’s Liberation Army, or P.L.A., culminating in a major reorganization from 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Zhang was a key enabler of Xi’s military reform agenda prior to late-2015 — before Xi became powerful enough to impose himself on the P.L.A.,” said James Char, an assistant professor at Nanyang Technological University in Singapore who studies the Chinese military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, General Zhang, who was then the head of a military region in northeast China, joined a delegation of senior Chinese military officers who visited the United States. Drew Thompson, then a Pentagon official helping to organize the visit, said the general was strikingly confident and inquisitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other Chinese officers “stood up faster and straighter when he entered a room,” Mr. Thompson in a post on Substack on Monday. He added: “He wasn’t afraid to talk to foreigners, unlike some other senior officers who were often afraid or unable to engage.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that year, he was promoted to head the Chinese military’s armaments department, an office that bought weapons, a post he held until 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The department had the makings of “a petri dish of corruption for all the obvious reasons: Developing and procuring expensive weapons systems makes it a nice place to collect bribes and kickbacks,” said Daniel Mattingly, a professor at Yale University who is studying Chinese military politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other senior officers who worked in the department were later felled in anti-corruption investigations. Yet General Zhang had long seemed to be spared scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the purge of General Zhang could raise questions about China’s strategy toward Taiwan and the risks of war. Mr. Thompson, the former Pentagon official, saw the general as someone who “had seen combat and been humbled by it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think he could assess U.S. and Taiwan military capabilities objectively and explain to Xi Jinping what the military risks and costs of an operation to take Taiwan would be,” Mr. Thompson wrote of General Zhang. “I worry about the consequences of someone other than Zhang Youxia providing Xi Jinping with military advice.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/asia/china-xi-zhang-youxia-military.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:52:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Venezuela, Freeing the Economy, but Nothing Else</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/americas/venezuela-economy-rodriguez.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25int-venezula-economy-lqcf/25int-venezula-economy-lqcf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s new leader wants citizens to be hopeful, but not too hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three weeks after U.S. forces whisked President Nicolás Maduro away from Caracas, the capital, his vice president and replacement, Delcy Rodríguez, is rapidly liberalizing the economy without ceding any political control in an autocratic nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With President Trump’s blessing, Ms. Rodríguez has moved to redirect Venezuela’s oil exports from China to the much more lucrative market in the United States. Earlier this month she funneled the first tranche from these oil sales, $300 million, to Venezuela’s banking system, halting the collapse of the national currency and putting hyperinflation fears to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is rapidly rewriting laws to bring in foreign investment and boost wages, leading many economists to forecast double-digit economic growth in Venezuela this year. She is promising economic transparency and accountability, an implicit recognition of years of looting of state funds by the government that she has served for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The expectation of an economic bonanza has triggered a rally on Caracas’s small stock exchange and led to a surge in real estate prices. The prices of Venezuela’s bonds, long in default, are rising on hopes Ms. Rodríguez will restructure the country’s debt. As the Trump administration hints it might roll back more U.S. sanctions on Venezuela, foreign investors are lining up scouting missions in Caracas, hoping to snap up the cheap real estate, mines and factories devalued by years of crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are expecting that 2026 will be a better year,” Ms. Rodríguez, 53, told Venezuela’s governors and mayors in a televised address last week. “We know that it will be this way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sense of economic euphoria is spreading in the shadow of a deeply repressive state, which Ms. Rodríguez has so far shown little sign of dismantling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heavily armed security agents have been stopping drivers and checking their phones on Caracas’s roads. Several checkpoints manned by military counterintelligence officers have sprung up near Ms. Rodríguez’s residence in her densely populated upmarket neighborhood in eastern Caracas, checking locals and passers-by alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez’s government has released some political prisoners, more than 200 according to rights groups, but hundreds remain behind bars. And some new prisoners have already taken the released detainees’ places, a process that the opposition calls Venezuela’s “revolving door” of repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former political prisoner, an American named James Luckey-Lange, said in an interview that as prison authorities were preparing to release him and a group of other detainees this month, they were simultaneously processing a group of new arrivals, including a 17-year-old. Practically all of them, including Mr. Luckey-Lange, had been accused of crimes related to terrorism, charges that rights groups say are nearly always fabricated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the economic front, Venezuelan financial regulators have been constantly calling the owners of Venezuela’s publicly traded companies, asking them to justify the surge in their stock prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular procedure took on a threatening undertone in a country where dozens have been detained for allegedly celebrating Mr. Maduro’s downfall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several businessmen contacted by the regulators recounted the ensuing absurd discussions, in which they tried to explain to the officials why their stock is surging, without mentioning the downfall of an autocrat largely responsible for one of the deepest economic collapses in modern history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Maduro’s fall has so far brought no noticeable change to Venezuela’s severely restricted freedom of expression. At least two prominent Venezuelan journalists have been castigated or threatened by officials for mentioning taboo topics in their programs since the U.S. attack on Caracas on Jan. 3, according to the people involved, who spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The taboos have including mentioning the name of the exiled opposition leader María Corina Machado, who has been lobbying lawmakers in Washington to force new elections in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere of fear that has gripped government opponents in Venezuela for years has now even spread to an unlikely new group: officials and businessmen who owe their positions and fortunes to personal ties with the Maduro family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since taking office, Ms. Rodríguez has demoted or fired several Maduro loyalists and overhauled the second tier of the country’s military command, even as she continued to publicly assert that she is a mere caretaker working for the president’s return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most prominent dismissal thus far targeted Alex Saab, a powerful Colombian businessman sanctioned by the United States for laundering money for Mr. Maduro. Ms. Rodríguez worked with the U.S. military this month to force a tanker carrying oil belonging to Mr. Saab to return to Venezuela, and in the past week she removed the businessman from his government posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez’s supporters in the government said the interim leader is trying to thread a needle. She is trying to increase her popularity by working to create a sense of hope and optimism in the country after 13 years of Mr. Maduro’s rule. But this optimism cannot spill into open celebrations, according to people who know her, who spoke on condition of anonymity to be able to discuss sensitive matters. The fear, they said, is that open celebrations could provoke a violent counterreaction from paramilitaries loyal to the ousted president, who have been pining for revenge after the humiliation inflicted on them by the U.S. forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez’s critics say the lack of any meaningful political concessions since Mr. Maduro’s downfall is a feature of her governing model, not a temporary glitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez, they say, may be trying to recreate the path of economic development followed by China, which in the 1980s opened up to foreign investment and market forces, without sacrificing the ruling party’s monopoly on power. Some commentators have already taken to calling her Delcyping, a reference to Deng Xiaoping, the architect of China’s market liberalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This outcome may be difficult to replicate. Some government insiders say Venezuela remains a more open society today than China was at the time, and the expected economic boom is likely to lead many Venezuelans to demand greater say in how any new oil wealth is spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And unlike China, Ms. Rodríguez’s government depends for its survival today on an outside power, the United States, which may have other ideas about how the country should be governed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A combination of economic liberalization and outside pressure could also lead Venezuela to replicate the path of another superpower, the Soviet Union. In the late 1980s, a more open economy exposed the shortcomings of its political system, emboldened its citizens and brought down one-party rule.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/americas/venezuela-economy-rodriguez.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:22:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel Says It Will Reopen Gaza-Egypt Border, a Palestinian Lifeline, in Days</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/israel-gaza-egypt-rafah-crossing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26gaza-rafah-lbhq/26gaza-rafah-lbhq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel has said that it will reopen the border between the Gaza Strip and Egypt within days for travelers on foot, a move that would allow Palestinians who fled the enclave during the two-year war to return home for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aid officials said they hoped that the reopening of the border crossing would also allow them to evacuate those in Gaza who need medical care abroad — thought to number more than 18,000 people, according to the World Health Organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a social media post early Monday morning, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu’s office said that the border crossing, near the city of Rafah, would reopen after the completion of a search in Gaza for the remains of the last captive yet to be returned to Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on Monday, the Israeli military announced that it had at last found the remains of the captive — Master Sgt. Ran Gvili, a police officer shot during the Hamas-led attack on Oct. 7, 2023 — after months of searches in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel agreed to allow the Rafah crossing to reopen as part of the cease-fire deal struck in October. But Israeli leaders demanded that Hamas first returned the remains of all deceased Israelis and foreign nationals in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, with Mr. Gvili’s body back in Israel, that mission was complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel’s decision to reopen the border — where both Israel and Egypt are expected to impose tight scrutiny over who crosses — advances the fragile cease-fire with Hamas. Yet the next steps for implementing President Trump’s plan for Gaza, which include disarming Hamas and deploying an international force there, are mired in uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 100,000 Palestinians have left Gaza since the beginning of the war, according to Palestinian officials. Now, many of them must decide whether to return to the enclave, most of which lies in ruins after two years of Israeli bombardment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Displaced Palestinians in Egypt Await Reopening of Gaza Border&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli government is still refusing to let foreign journalists into Gaza. It argued in a Supreme Court hearing Monday morning that to do so would put Israeli soldiers at risk even though the cease-fire is more than three months old and Israel has allowed international aid workers to enter the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For foreign journalists, Gaza has been off-limits since the start of the war in 2023, except for a small number of reporters invited on carefully controlled, abbreviated visits escorted by Israeli soldiers. A longstanding petition by foreign journalists seeking to report from inside the territory was considered by the Israeli Supreme Court on Monday after numerous delays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In oral arguments, Justice Ruth Ronnen suggested that the Rafah crossing’s reopening could allow foreign journalists to enter Gaza through Egypt. But a lawyer for the Foreign Press Association, Gilead Sher, argued that the group’s 400 members, who include employees of The New York Times, should be able to enter from Israel, where they are based.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We see international aid entering daily to the Strip, we see international aid workers and U.N. workers, and Israelis entering,” along with officials of the World Bank, Mr. Sher said, according to a pool report. “But foreign journalists are prohibited.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A government lawyer, Yonatan Nadav, said that letting journalists into Gaza posed risks to Israeli soldiers, but he agreed to describe those risks only in a closed court session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lawyer for the Union of Journalists in Israel, Amir Basha, also spoke in favor of letting foreign journalists into Gaza, arguing that they represented a vital and missing source of independent information, alongside the Israeli military and Palestinian reporters in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No one is arguing with the aid workers’ value,” he said. “But journalists should not be last, they should be first among equals. Because of the information that journalists offer to the public, it cannot be that the Israeli public’s right to know is last in line.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court did not say when it would issue a ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rafah crossing lies near what was once the southern city of Rafah, which was largely razed by Israeli forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first nine months of the war, tens of thousands of Palestinians were able to flee to Egypt through the crossing. Some were sponsored by international aid groups who coordinated their exit with Israel and Egypt. Many others paid exorbitant bribes to intermediaries connected with the Egyptian government to secure exit papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May 2024, that tenuous escape was cut off as Israeli forces swept along the Gaza side of the border and seized the crossing. Israel and Egypt could not agree on conditions for reopening the border, which has mostly been closed ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closure cut off a key route for severely ill and wounded Gazans seeking medical treatment outside the enclave’s battered health system. Some Palestinians, such as cancer patients needing chemotherapy, died without access to proper treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential for renewed conflict in Gaza is still very much present. Hamas has entrenched its control over half of the enclave, the Israeli military controls the other half, and most people are still huddled in crowded tent camps or in the rubble of half-destroyed homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kamel Ayyad, 53, fled for Egypt in November 2023 with his wife and three daughters. While he said that he hoped to return to Gaza, he noted that most of his friends and acquaintances say that going back now is too risky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Gaza’s still experiencing a cold war, or an unofficial war — it’s not stable,” said Mr. Ayyad, an official with St. Porphyrius, a Greek Orthodox church in Gaza. “No one wants to gamble with the lives of their family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is far from clear how long Gazans will be able to stay in Egypt, which has made clear that their presence ought to be temporary. “We’re between a rock and a hard place,” Mr. Ayyad said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/israel-gaza-egypt-rafah-crossing.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 13:19:17 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>