<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 21:58:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What We Know About the Deadly High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high-speed train ran off its track and crashed into another high-speed train late Sunday in southern Spain, killing at least 21 people and injuring dozens of others, according to the local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accident is the deadliest train accident in Spainsince 2013, when 80 people died after a train veered off a curved section of track in the country’s northwest. The country has the second-longest high-speed rail network in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision on Sunday occurred at 7:45 p.m. in Adamuz, in the southern province of Córdoba. The train that derailed first was a privately-operated one that was traveling to Madrid from Málaga, on the country’s southern coast. The rear cars of that train fell into the opposite track, where it collided with an incoming train operated by Spain’s national rail company, which was bound for the southern city of Huelva, west of Seville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo, the operator of the first train, said that around 300 passengers were on board at the time of the crash. Renfe, the operator of the second train, has not said how many passengers it was carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spain’s state-owned rail infrastructure agency said in a statement that rail traffic between Madrid and several major cities in southern Andalucía — including Córdoba, Seville, Málaga and Huelva — will be suspended on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency response crews continued to search through the wreckage of the crash early Monday, with officials warning that the death toll may rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 2013 disaster, the derailment on Sunday happened on a straight portion of the track. An independent commission has been launched to investigate what caused it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, told reporters that the first train to derail was only a few years old and that the section of the track where the accident occurred had been recently renovated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accident is extremely strange,” he said. “It happened on a straightaway. All the experts we have consulted are extremely baffled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “If there had not been an oncoming train, we would not be talking about casualties of any type.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez of Spain expressed sympathy for the victims’ families on social media, saying that “the entire country stands with them in this extremely difficult moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tonight is a night of deep pain for our country,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Andalucía government has set up a medical post at the crash site for victims, while the Córdoba city government has issued an urgent appeal for doctors to help treat the injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paco Carmona, the director of Córdoba’s fire brigade, told public television that emergency crews were prioritizing assistance for victims still trapped in the two carriages most severely damaged in the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:54:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Prince Harry’s Case Against Daily Mail Publisher</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prince Harry’s latest legal case in Britain is set to begin on Monday in London’s High Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prince and several other high-profile figures are accusing Associated Newspapers, the publisher of The Daily Mail, of unlawful information gathering, including phone hacking, and of intruding into their private lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial is set to last for more than two months, and Harry is scheduled to testify on Thursday. The other claimants include Elton John and his husband, David Furnish, the actresses Liz Hurley and Sadie Frost, a former British government minister, and a racial justice campaigner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry and the other claimants accuse the company of carrying out or commissioning unlawful activities to reveal private information about their lives for articles published from 1997 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written arguments presented at a preliminary hearing in May said there had been “clear, systematic and sustained use of unlawful information gathering by private investigators” hired by Associated Newspapers, with “payments spanning decades” and involvement by newspaper executives and numerous journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators are accused of hacking and tapping phones, placing listening devices in cars and “blagging” — a way of tricking people into handing over information — to obtain phone numbers, personal records and bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newspaper group, which owns The Daily Mail, The Mail on Sunday and several other titles that are not implicated in the case, has denied all the accusations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a preliminary hearing on Thursday, four days before the trial was to start, a lawyer for Associated Newspapers, Anthony White, said he would argue that some of the claimants’ witnesses “are not telling the truth” and that he would raise questions about their credibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated Newspapers said in a statement that its journalists had not commissioned or obtained information derived from illegal activity and called the accusations “preposterous and without foundation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It added, “The stories concerned, many of which were published 20 or more years ago, and not subject to any complaint at the time, were the product of responsible journalism based on legitimate sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a schedule jointly drawn up by both legal teams, the trial will run for more than two months and end on March 26. The judge hearing the case, Matthew Nicklin, is expected to consider the evidence and arguments before giving a ruling at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case will begin with lawyers for the claimants and Associated Newspapers giving an outline of their case. Prince Harry is expected to give evidence in person at the High Court on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elton John, the other claimants and witnesses, including Ms. Frost’s former husband, the actor Jude Law, are also set to be questioned by lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators accused of wrongdoing will appear at the trial, as will the former editor of The Daily Mail, Paul Dacre, and several past and present Associated Newspapers executives and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case is one of several pursued by Harry since 2020, when he and his wife, Meghan Markle, stepped down from their royal roles and left Britain, later making their home in Montecito, Calif.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have centered on accusations of press intrusion, which Harry said was a key reason behind their decision to move. In an interview with Oprah Winfrey in 2021, Harry said that he feared “history repeating itself,” referring to the death of his mother, Princess Diana, in a car crash while she was being chased by paparazzi in Paris in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said there was an “invisible contract” between Britain’s royal family and the country’s tabloids, adding, “There is a level of control by fear that has existed for generations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owners of The Daily Mirror, another tabloid, settled a claim over phone hacking in February 2024. During that case, Harry became the first senior royal to testify in court since 1891.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2025, Rupert Murdoch’s News Group Newspapers agreed to pay a “substantial” amount of damages to Harry to settle a long-running lawsuit relating to articles in The Sun and the long-closed News of the World. News Group apologized for “serious intrusion” into Harry’s personal life between 1996 and 2011 and admitted for the first time to unlawful activities by private investigators working for The Sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry lost an unrelated legal battle last May over his publicly funded security in Britain, which was downgraded after his decision to step back from royal duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But late last year, the government body responsible for royal security decisions began a review of his protection arrangements, according to two people familiar with the situation who were not given permission to speak publicly. The review appears to offer a glimmer of good news for the prince, who has spoken of his desire to visit Britain with his family if his automatic right to security is reinstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael D. Shear contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 08:04:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Links His Push for Greenland to Not Winning Nobel Peace Prize</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is now claiming that one reason he is pushing to acquire Greenland is that he didn’t win the Nobel Peace Prize, according to a text message he sent to Norway’s prime minister over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonas Gahr Store, Norway’s leader, received the text message on Sunday, an official in the prime minister’s office said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Considering your Country decided not to give me the Nobel Peace Prize for having stopped 8 Wars PLUS, I no longer feel an obligation to think purely of Peace, although it will always be predominant, but can now think about what is good and proper for the United States of America,” Mr. Trump wrote in the message, which was first published by PBS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also questioned Denmark’s claim to Greenland, saying, “There are no written documents,” and adding, “The World is not secure unless we have Complete and Total Control of Greenland. Thank you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions over Greenland have sharply escalated in the last week, and the message injected a new level of uncertainty into Mr. Trump’s thinking and his campaign to gain control of the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland has been part of the Danish Kingdom for more than 300 years, and world leaders have condemned Mr. Trump’s insistence that the United States take over the territory, a giant icebound island in the Arctic region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to copies of the messages provided by the Norwegian prime minister’s office, Mr. Trump’s message was a response to one that Mr. Store sent Mr. Trump on Sunday. It was co-signed by the president of Finland, Alexander Stubb, a leader with whom Mr. Trump is close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European leaders asked to speak to Mr. Trump about Greenland and his threat of using tariffs to pressure Denmark into selling it, which Denmark has refused to do. They asked for a phone call and struck a collaborative tone, writing, “We believe we all should work to take this down and de-escalate — so much is happening around us where we need to stand together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump’s response, Mr. Store said in a statement, “As regards the Nobel Peace Prize, I have on several occasions clearly explained to Trump what is well known, namely that it is an independent Nobel Committee, and not the Norwegian government, that awards the prize,” Mr. Store said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly challenged Denmark’s claims to Greenland, but in decades-old agreements that the United States has signed with Denmark, the United States has recognized Denmark’s close connection to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2004 amendment to an older defense pact between Denmark and the United States, which grants the United States broad military access, explicitly recognizes Greenland as “an equal part of the Kingdom of Denmark.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in 1916, Denmark sold what are now the U.S. Virgin Islands to the United States for $25 million in gold. In the treaty for that deal, a clause reads, “The United States of America will not object to the Danish Government extending their political and economic interests to the whole of Greenland.”In the past year, as Mr. Trump has repeatedly vowed to “get” Greenland, Denmark has repeatedly rebuffed him. Denmark’s position is that it does not have the authority to sell the self-governing territory and that Greenland’s 57,000 inhabitants will decide their own fate. Polls and interviews show that an overwhelming majority of Greenlanders strongly oppose joining the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Greenlanders staged the biggest protest of recent months. Hundreds marched through the snowy streets of Nuuk, the capital, chanting, “No means no,” “Greenland is already great” and “Yankee, go home!”In the past few days, Denmark and other European countries have sent more military forces to the island. Small groups of Danish soldiers dressed in green camouflage and dark woolen hats have been walking through downtown Nuuk. Beyond the harbor, a 200-foot-long Danish warship capable of breaking through ice has been patrolling the shoreline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A much-anticipated three-way meeting last week of the United States, Denmark and Greenland, hosted by Vice President JD Vance in Washington, did not produce any breakthroughs and seemed to instead create misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first time Greenland had been included in a such high-level discussions, and the Danish and Greenlandic officials left saying that a working group had been formed to explore possibilities for a solution. But the Trump administration said afterwards that the two sides would begin “technical talks on the acquisition of Greenland,” a statement that raised even more concern in Greenland, in Denmark and across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Kingsley, Jeanna Smialek and Steven Erlanger contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:06:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When President Trump said he planned to establish and lead a “Board of Peace” to oversee the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas in Gaza, many did not know what to make of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, letters went out asking countries to join the newly minted body, among them historically close U.S. allies like Canada, France, Britain, and Saudi Arabia. But Russia and Belarus, hardly allies, were also on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a perusal of the body’s charter — which governments received alongside their invitations — suggested that Mr. Trump hopes the Board of Peace could get involved in all kinds of global conflicts, not just the one in the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics reacted furiously, saying the Trump administration appeared to be setting up the board as a potential American-dominated rival to the United Nations, which Mr. Trump has long accused of liberal bias and waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chairman, Mr. Trump would have considerable influence over the Board of Peace. With countries being asked to pay more than $1 billion for permanent membership, its budget could be substantial, though it is unclear how much control Mr. Trump would have over how the money is spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presence of Turkey and Qatar on one of the board’s subcommittees also prompted an immediate outcry from Israel, which has been at odds with the Turkish government, particularly over the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we know so far about the Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the board appeared to be part of Mr. Trump’s vision for postwar Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His plan called the board a “new international transitional body” that would help supervise the rebuilding of the Palestinian enclave. The board’s members would include world leaders, with Mr. Trump sitting at the head of the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council later formally backed the board in a U.S.-drafted resolution in November, giving it the force of international legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution gave the board a mandate to work with governments to recruit international peacekeepers for Gaza. It was to carry out Mr. Trump’s plan in Gaza until the internationally recognized Palestinian Authority conducted reforms, the resolution said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the United States circulated the board’s charter on Friday, it became clear that Mr. Trump envisions a much bigger role for the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed charter said the Board of Peace would “secure enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict,” not just Gaza, according to a copy shared with The New York Times. It also called for “a more nimble and effective international peace-building body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of invitees includes Britain, Jordan, Russia and more. But so far, only a handful — like the pro-Trump Argentine president, Javier Milei, and Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary — have said they will join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite overseeing Gaza, neither the Board of Peace nor a Gaza Executive Board underneath it have any Palestinian members as yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board is, however, to oversee the work of a group of Palestinian technocrats charged with administering public services in Gaza. Analysts say they will face a formidable challenge, given that Gaza is still split in two between areas under Israeli and Hamas control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some countries appear skeptical. To acquire a permanent seat on the Board of Peace, each would have to pay more than a billion dollars in cash within the first year to fund the body’s operations. (States can join for three years for free.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The charter would invest considerable personal power in Mr. Trump as chairman. It says that he will name members of a second “Executive Board” to carry out the board’s decisions, and that Mr. Trump would wield considerable veto power over its actions. He would also be able to name his own successor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump would also be permitted to enact “resolutions or other directives” to carry out the board’s mission, and to “create, modify or dissolve subsidiary entities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France does not currently intend to join, as the board’s charter raises serious questions about respecting the role of the United Nations, said a senior French official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to comply with government protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how many countries will pay the fee to become permanent members, as opposed to accepting the optional three-year term for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not exactly clear how much oversight the Board of Peace will exert over Gaza and for how long. But two subcommittees reporting to Mr. Trump’s board have already been set up to carry out his Gaza peace plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the White House named a “Gaza Executive Board” that includes Jared Kushner, the president’s son-in-law, and Steve Witkoff, Mr. Trump’s envoy. The group also has Qatari and Egyptian officials, as well as an Israeli businessman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a rare public break with Mr. Trump, Israel criticized the makeup of the committee, particularly the presence of Qatar and Turkey. Both countries helped mediate between Israel and Hamas to secure the Gaza cease-fire, but Israeli officials have accused them of being too close to Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ségolène Le Stradic contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:20:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Like an Earthquake’: How 40 People Died in a Spanish Train Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salvador Jiménez was on a high-speed train to Madrid on Sunday evening, speeding through the arid countryside of southern Spain, when the carriage shook so violently that he thought it had hit an animal on the tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lights went out. A voice on the public-address system made a plea for medical assistance. Soon the passengers were breaking windows with emergency hammers to escape, Mr. Jiménez, 37, said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision turned out to be with another train, killing at least 40 people in the deadliest railway crash in Spain since 2013. Two cars at the back of Mr. Jiménez’s Madrid-bound train derailed near Adamuz, a town in southern Spain, where they crossed onto the track of an oncoming southbound train, according to a preliminary report by official investigators. Seconds later, at around 7:45 p.m., the southbound train slammed into the carriages, and two cars careened down a 12-foot embankment, the preliminary report said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was like an earthquake,” said Mr. Jiménez, a broadcast journalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crash left Spaniards in grief and shock, shaking a country that has come to depend, and take great pride in, its sprawling and efficient national rail system, the largest high-speed system in Europe and second largest in the world, behind China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Spanish society is asking what happened, how it happened, and how this tragedy could have occurred,” Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez said at a media briefing near the crash site on Monday. He said officials would strive to answer the questions about what happened on tracks, switches and junctions that were renovated only in May and with a new train that had been inspected as recently as Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither the privately owned northbound train carrying around 300 passengers or the southbound one operated by Spain’s state-owned rail operator was speeding, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accident is extremely strange,” Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, told reporters, saying it took place on a straight stretch of track. He warned that the death toll was “not final” and that “all the experts we have consulted are extremely baffled” about what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial questions have centered on whether the crash was caused by the condition of the track. Mr. Puente said on Spanish radio that investigators are assessing whether a break in a section of track at the site of the derailment was “the cause or the consequences” of the derailment. But he warned that this was only speculation for now, and urged patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Íñaki Barrón, president of the Railway Accident Investigation Commission, said in an interview with RTVE that the crash did not seem a result of human error or a problem with signals, and that the cause could lie in “the interaction between the track and the vehicle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of the crash was so severe that bodies were found hundreds of yards from the crash location, according to a broadcast interview with Juanma Moreno, the president of the regional government of Andalucía, the province where the crash occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Some of the dead are difficult to recognize,” Mr. Moreno said, adding that DNA analysis was being used to identify victims. “The impact was very strong, very strong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency workers were still working desperately on Monday evening to reach bodies believed to be under overturned carriages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of the crash startled people within earshot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrés Pastor Valverde, 53, a metalworker who lives nearby, was watching his son’s soccer game when he heard the crash, followed by a stream of sirens and alarms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mayor of Adamuz, Rafael Ángel Moreno, was one of the first people on the scene, rushing to the train station with a police officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A terrible scene,” he said in an interview, his voice quavering. “People were trying to get out of the train, there were many injured.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gonzalo Sánchez Aguilar, 46, happened to be driving near the crash site and went to help. He loaded injured survivors into his car to rush them to a hospital, he said in an interview. “I saw a lot of dead bodies,” he said. “Really bad injuries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train to Madrid,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operated by Iryo,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;derailed at&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7:45 p.m. Sunday,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with its tail end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;impeding the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;other track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo train,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;headed northeast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train to Huelva,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operated by Renfe,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;was going at around&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;130 m.p.h. when it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;collided with the end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of the derailed Iryo train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPAIN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madrid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Site of crash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huelva&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the collision,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Renfe train ended&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;up about 2,000 feet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;away. Its front two cars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fell down a 12-foot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;embankment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renfe train,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;headed southwest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train to Madrid,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operated by Iryo,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;derailed at 7:45 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday, with its tail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;end impeding the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;other track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;N&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo train,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;headed northeast&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The train to Huelva,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;operated by Renfe,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;was going at around&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;130 m.p.h. when it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;collided with the end&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of the derailed Iryo train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SPAIN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madrid&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Site of crash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huelva&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renfe train,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;headed southwest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the collision,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Renfe train ended&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;up about 2,000 feet&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;away. Its front two cars&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fell down a 12-foot&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;embankment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: Guardia Civil; Spanish transportation ministry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samuel Granados, Raj Saha and Ashley Wu/The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scale of the disaster shocked veteran doctors who found themselves treating the victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francisco Alamillos, 63, a surgeon, was reading in bed on Sunday evening when he received a message from Reina Sofía Hospital in the nearby city of Córdoba, where he works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“100 injured people,” the message read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Alamillos and his wife, also a surgeon, sped to the hospital, where the entrance was jammed with doctors coming to help, and the wards were filling up with survivors injured with pelvic fractures, lower-limb fractures, and facial injuries. “I had never seen so many injured patients at the same time,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scenes shook a population that makes regular use of its national rail network. In a country of nearly 50 million, more than 40 million passengers traveled on Spain’s high-speed rail carriers in 2024, a 77 percent increase from 2019, according to an annual report from the country’s National Commission of Markets and Competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once operated primarily by the Spanish national provider Renfe, Spain’s high-speed lines have been increasingly opened to private train service providers in recent years as part of a liberalization process prompted by European Union regulations. Beginning in 2021, providers like the French company Ouigo and Italy’s Iryo — which operated one of the trains involved in the crash — began offering passenger services on Spanish rail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spanish Union of Railway Drivers said it had sent a letter in August asking the state-owned rail operator and Spain’s railway safety agency to look into possible flaws on lines across Spain, including at the site where the trains crashed. The union emphasized on Monday that it did not know the cause of the tragedy, but asserted that railway infrastructure had deteriorated because of increased traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The union did not say whether it had received a response to the letter. The rail operator and the rail safety agency did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The identities of the victims emerged steadily throughout Monday. María Clauss and Óscar Toro, a married couple, were killed in the train derailment, according to an announcement by a union of journalists they belonged to. The Spanish National Police confirmed an officer was among the dead. On Facebook, members of the Zamorano Álvarez family said they were mourning the loss of four relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others were still waiting on Monday evening for news about loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Córdoba, Manuel de la Torre was hoping for news of his 79-year-old aunt, one of five family members who were in the first car of the southbound train. His relatives, including three of his aunt’s grandchildren, were returning from seeing a musical. Some suffered broken bones, he said, but he has yet to hear about his aunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are just waiting, not knowing whether it’s good or bad,” Mr. de la Torre said. “But after a whole day now, you don’t expect happy news.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amelia Nierenberg, Christine Negroni, Roser Toll Pifarré, Yan Zhuang, Jin Yu Young and Max Kim contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:50:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death Toll Rises in Guatemalan Gang Riots</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-guatemala-promo/19int-guatemala-01-hbcv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deadly gang violence over the weekend in Guatemala has raised concerns about the stability of the country and President Bernardo Arévalo’s ability to deliver on his promise to root out corruption and organized crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He declared a state of emergency on Sunday to crack down on gangs after inmates took dozens of guards hostage at three prisons across the country and several officers were killed in episodes connected to the violence. The government said the riots and reprisal killings had been a coordinated response by leaders of criminal organizations after the authorities took away their prison privileges, including restaurant meals and air conditioning demanded by one crime boss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day after Mr. Arévalo announced that the state of emergency would last for 30 days and empower the national police and military to act against gangs, the police death toll had risen to nine. The new powers allowed the authorities to set up checkpoints and claim broader authority to make arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he had announced the state of emergency because the violence had been “aimed at terrorizing the population.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday, the police had regained control of the prisons, and the guards had been freed, Mr. Arévalo said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts said that the unrest came at a critical time for Guatemala, a Central America country of 18 million people where gangs exert influence even on politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the major decisions facing Mr. Arévalo this year is choosing a new attorney general. He said on Sunday that the violence came just as the country was trying to free itself of corruption. He called those behind the violence “criminal political mafias that resist and seek to instill terror because they know that this year Guatemala will recover its justice system.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some inmates with access to cellphones and the internet have called for the removal of Mr. Arévalo from power. In response to questions about threats against the president, Henry Saenz, Guatemala’s minister of defense, said on the radio on Monday that “the army supports the president” and that Mr. Arévalo would serve out his term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s extremely worrying,” Ana María Méndez Dardón, the Central America director at the Washington Office on Latin America, a rights group, said of the state of affairs in Guatemala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a warning that this year being so decisive for Guatemala and especially for the justice of Guatemala,” she continued, “that these parallel groups of power are seeking to break the constitutional order, to destabilize and generate this chaos to harm President Bernardo Arévalo in order to be able to continue perpetuating the impunity to which they have been accustomed to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Arévalo, an anticorruption crusader and a moderate, was elected in 2023 in a surprise victory that left the country’s conservative establishment reeling, particularly the attorney general’s office, which has been a primary force in blocking his agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, 20 inmates accused of being gang members escaped from a maximum-security prison outside the capital, Guatemala City. The inmates were described by officials as high-ranking operatives of the Barrio 18 gang, which has long been linked to organized crime and violence around Central America and which the Trump administration designated as a foreign terrorist organization in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A political crisis ensued, and Mr. Arévalo replaced several senior officials, called for an overhaul of the country’s prison system — where gangs are believed to operate unchecked amid rampant bribery and corruption — and said the country would have help from the U.S. authorities, including the F.B.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over the weekend, the tension between the Guatemalan authorities and the gangs reached a breaking point. Officials said they would not negotiate with inmates over the privileges they were demanding. Riots broke out in the prisons, and the authorities raided them to reestablish control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, police officers on patrol in the Guatemala City area were slain in what Marco Antonio Villeda, Guatemala’s interior minister, called retaliatory killings by gangs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also said at a news conference on Sunday that Aldo Dupie Ochoa, known as “El Lobo” (The Wolf), a leader of the Barrio 18 gang, had been the main instigator of the riots at one prison. He said Mr. Ochoa was demanding a transfer to another prison and benefits like special food delivery and a king bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funeral services for eight officers were held on Monday. A ninth and 10th police officer died as a result of the prison operations, the Guatemalan national police said on Monday. Six other officers were hospitalized with gunshot wounds, said Edwin Monroy, a police spokesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as of midday Monday, he said that 10 members of the Barrio 18 gang had been arrested in connection with the attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some civil rights are suspended during a state of emergency, Mr. Arévalo said that it would not affect citizens. The measure calls for deploying all active police officers — approximately 45,000 — and members of the army to make patrols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, in Guatemala City, there were few vehicles or pedestrians. A large number of security personnel were on the streets, stopping and checking vehicles. Public and private schools were closed, but officials said they would resume classes on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:47:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Trump Uses the Oval Office to Flex Power on the World Stage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-oval-office-world-leaders.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-foreign-leaders-promo/trump-foreign-leaders-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first year of his second term, President Trump used the Oval Office in a way his predecessors haven’t, as a veritable reality show with a revolving cast of world leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 40 international leaders made the trek to Washington to meet with the American president last year, many with the cameras rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were ambushes, threats, obsequious displays and the realignment of longstanding American foreign policy. Where previous presidents would have briefly posed for a photo before getting down to business behind closed doors, Mr. Trump relished the spectacle of the lengthy exchanges in front of the press in an Oval Office he has redecorated in gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dressing down President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine in February, Mr. Trump, a former star of “The Apprentice” and professional wrestling productions, notably said: “This is going to be great television.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was more serious than just a show: The fate of wars, prisoners, human rights and crippling economic sanctions all hung in the balance with every exchange. To appease Mr. Trump, world leaders often came bearing gifts, the more flattering, the better — an invitation from the king, a new Air Force One or even a Nobel Prize medal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a candidate who campaigned on an “America First” agenda, Mr. Trump’s second term has thus far been defined as much by a focus on international affairs as domestic matters. He brought the world to him and, with the rare exception, on his terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In doing so, it was as much a display of power to those at home as it was to those abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump displays a lot of the characteristics of a populist leader that really revels in the politics of spectacle,” said Lisel Hintz, professor at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies. “He’s a deal maker, but he’s also a TV producer. TV is so ingrained in how he thinks about the world, how he thinks about politics, and how he thinks about power.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a look at some of the key ways in which Mr. Trump conducted diplomacy from the Oval Office in his first year back in office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take long for Mr. Trump to shake up longstanding American foreign policy stances, welcoming in strongmen rulers of countries that previous administrations had at times kept at arm’s length.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He partnered with President Nayib Bukele of El Salvador, deporting hundreds of Venezuelan migrants to a notorious Salvadoran prison, including a wrongful deportation that neither president claimed the power to fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He welcomed President Recep Tayyip Erdogan of Turkey, even joking that the Turkish leader had manipulated the vote in his country. “He knows about rigged elections, better than anybody,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His open embrace of Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman of Saudi Arabia was perhaps the most striking scene. Former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. had once pledged to make Saudi Arabia a “pariah” after the killing of the dissident and journalist Jamal Khashoggi in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump acted as a defender of the crown prince during a visit to the Oval Office, his first to the country since Mr. Khashoggi’s murder. When a reporter asked about the killing of Mr. Khashoggi, Mr. Trump quickly cut her off. “He’s done a phenomenal job, and you don’t have to embarrass our guest by asking a question like that,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That evening, Mr. Trump held a black-tie dinner for the crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the White House, Mr. Trump hosted 45 meetings with 46 foreign leaders during the first year of his second term, including five visits from Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, four visits from the secretary general of NATO, Mark Rutte, and four visits from Mr. Zelensky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is the most transparent president in history, and he leads all foreign policy from the top,” said Anna Kelly, a White House spokeswoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like few presidents before him, Mr. Trump showed a willingness to upend America’s stance on major conflicts, sometimes leaving friends and foes scrambling to try to figure out his next move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump used his meetings with Mr. Netanyahu — with whom he has had an on-again, off-again relationship — to try to shake up the dynamic between Israel and the Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During one such visit, Mr. Trump said the United States would take over Gaza and turn it into the “Riviera of the Middle East,” prompting a widespread outcry. During another, he announced a deal resulting in the release of Israeli hostages from Gaza, after he demanded Mr. Netanyahu apologize to the Qataris for a deadly missile strike on Doha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no shake-up of international relations was more dramatic than the broadside attack Mr. Trump and Vice President JD Vance leveled against Mr. Zelensky, accusing him of being insufficiently grateful of American support for his country against the Russian invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spectacle underscored how little longstanding alliances mean to Mr. Trump and just how much he has oscillated in his approach to the Russian invasion, swinging between support for Ukraine and sympathy for President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. But ultimately, his tactics appear to have done little to bring the two sides closer to peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It did have the effect of sending the Ukrainians scrambling to see how can we get back in the good graces of the United States,” said Matthew Kroenig, vice president and senior director of the Atlantic Council’s Scowcroft Center for Strategy and Security. “Trump writes about this in ‘The Art of the Deal’ decades ago. This is the way you negotiate. You throw the other side off balance and get them kind of crawling back to the table.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky was not alone in feeling ambushed after taking a seat in the Oval Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In May, Mr. Trump rebuked President Cyril Ramaphosa of South Africa, lecturing him with false claims about a genocide against white Afrikaner farmers. He even played what he said was video evidence of their persecution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Turn the lights down and just put this on,” he told his aides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ramaphosa was forced to scramble to defend his country and joked that he must not have brought a lavish enough present, citing a plane the Qatari government had recently gifted Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am sorry I don’t have a plane to give you,” Mr. Ramaphosa said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I wish you did,” Mr. Trump replied. “I’d take it. If your country offered the U.S. Air Force a plane, I would take it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting had been expected to be tense given Mr. Trump had suspended aid to the country, but it proved notable for how he was able to push his political agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His administration had recently slashed refugee admissions for everyone — except Afrikaners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other world leaders took note of the televised disasters for Mr. Zelensky and Mr. Ramaphosa. They would come bearing gifts and praise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gifts have been varied, ranging from a multi-million-dollar plane to more personal appeals. Chancellor Friedrich Merz of Germany presented the president with a framed copy of Mr. Trump’s German-born grandfather’s birth certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Netanyahu gave Mr. Trump with a gold-plated pager, the same kind Israel rigged with explosives, killing Hezbollah operatives and others in Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just last week, María Corina Machado, Venezuela’s opposition leader and last year’s Nobel Peace Prize winner, presented her prize to Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of gifts, flattery and praise have been a popular tactic too. Mr. Rutte, as he seeks to keep Mr. Trump engaged on the side of Ukraine, has heaped such volumes of praise that he has been mocked by commentators as over-the-top. Mr. Rutte once referred to Mr. Trump as “daddy,” prompting the White House to highlight the remark with a music video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the meetings, and their accompanying flattery and gifts, have produced results, such as a trade deal or lowering of tariffs. Other times, the win for international leaders is simply avoiding the wrath of the country with the world’s most powerful military and economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president has demonstrated a strong penchant for personal diplomacy, including putting it on full display in the Oval Office in front of the press, creating an arena with all the volatility and suspense of a reality TV show,” said Michael Froman, president of the Council on Foreign Relations. “On one hand, this allows for a degree of spontaneity at the highest levels; on the other, it runs the risk of circumventing a rigorous policy process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in his second term, Mr. Trump shrank the National Security Council, underscoring his belief in his ability to conduct policy on a leader-to-leader basis. He has moved rapidly to build national security and foreign policy teams who share his skepticism of foreign interventions, and who will not oppose him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he returned to the Oval Office, Mr. Zelensky adopted a more deferential tone in his interactions with Mr. Trump. The leader of Ukraine presented Mr. Trump with a golf club that had belonged to a service member who lost his leg during the war with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Golf, Mr. Zelensky knew, is a favorite pastime of Mr. Trump’s.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-oval-office-world-leaders.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With Threats to Greenland, Trump Sets America on the Road to Conquest</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-america-conquest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-assess-top2-gzfb/20dc-assess-top2-gzfb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems safe to assume that when Harry Truman forged NATO at the dawn of the Cold War, he never imagined that over the course of nearly eight decades the only country that would wage economic war and threaten actual war against the allies for the purpose of territorial conquest would be the United States itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet that is the reality of this upside-down, might-makes-right world of President Trump’s creation as he slaps tariffs on America’s treaty partners and holds out the possibility of using military force to strong-arm Denmark and its European friends into giving up Greenland, a territory whose citizens do not want to become part of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never in the past century has America gone forth to seize other countries’ land and subjugate its citizens against their will. Since the days of World War I, America was the country that resisted conquest, standing up to Hitler’s Germany, Tojo’s Japan, Stalin’s Soviet Union, Kim Il-sung’s North Korea and Saddam Hussein’s Iraq when they seized foreign terrain. Now Mr. Trump aspires to put America into the category of conquerors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coercing a loyal ally into giving up territory over its adamant objections would have been seen not long ago as preposterous, even mad — indeed, one of Mr. Trump’s own cabinet secretaries in his first term privately considered it delusional when he raised it back then. But it is a measure of how much Mr. Trump has changed the definition of normal that his appetite for seizing land that does not belong to him is debated as a serious proposition rather than dismissed out of hand as a brazen violation of U.S. treaty obligations and international law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that the United States has always respected the sovereignty of other nations. There have been plenty of times in its history when America has toppled governments or temporarily occupied countries it considered hostile. But never has it done so against a longtime ally that posed no threat. And not since the Spanish-American War of 1898 has it kept territory that it captured through force of arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States in the 20th century “took the lead in de-legitmating colonial rule and ending the age of empire,” said Charles Kupchan, a professor of international affairs at Georgetown and former Europe adviser to President Barack Obama. “Those days may be coming to an end. If the United States were to use economic and military coercion to take control of Greenland, it would be an unabashed act of imperial aggression against a democratic ally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s advisers dispute that analysis. “We don’t go in there trying to conquer anybody and trying to take over anybody’s country,” said Gov. Jeff Landry of Louisiana, recently named by Mr. Trump as his special envoy to “make Greenland a part of the U.S.,” in the governor’s words. Speaking on Fox News on Friday, he added: “We say: ‘Listen. We represent liberty. We represented economic strength. We represent protection.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the president himself is sending a different message, one of pressure, not persuasion. “We are going to do something on Greenland whether they like it or not,” he told reporters this month. “One way or the other, we’re going to have Greenland,” he said aboard Air Force One last week. Over the weekend, he vowed to punish European countries that have stood by Denmark against his territorial demands by increasing taxes on their imported goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has rebuffed efforts at diplomacy. When Norway’s prime minister asked to talk about the dispute on Sunday, the president refused, sending a text making clear that he had no interest in a conversation “considering your Country decided not to give me the Nobel Peace Prize for having stopped 8 Wars PLUS.” (The prize is awarded by an independent committee, not Norway’s government, and Mr. Trump’s claim to have ended eight wars is exaggerated.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s stated rationale is that the United States needs Greenland for security reasons. His logic is that Russia or China could take it over, so therefore the United States should take it over. But neither Russia nor China has shown any inclination lately to seize Greenland for itself. The only country threatening Greenland at the moment is Mr. Trump’s America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If security were really the issue, the United States already has troops in Greenland and, under a 1951 agreement, could send more forces and reopen bases there tomorrow if it wanted to. In his five years in the White House, Mr. Trump has never seen the threat to Greenland being so urgent that he chose to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, Mr. Trump’s interest seems less about security than about grandiosity. “I said, ‘Why don’t we have that?’” he explained in a 2021 interview for the book “The Divider” about his first term. “You take a look at a map. I’m a real estate developer, I look at a corner, I say, ‘I’ve got to get that store for the building that I’m building,’ etc. It’s not that different. I love maps. And I always said: ‘Look at the size of this. It’s massive. That should be part of the United States.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with The New York Times this month, he framed it in terms of personal desire. Asked why ownership was important instead of just fortifying Greenland, he said, “Because that’s what I feel is psychologically needed for success.” Asked if he meant psychologically important for himself or psychologically important for the country, he said, “Psychologically important for me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump got turned onto taking Greenland by the billionaire businessman Ronald S. Lauder, a friend since school, whose interest has raised questions about who might profit from such a move. During his first term, Mr. Trump instructed his national security adviser, John R. Bolton, to come up with a plan to buy it. Mr. Bolton thought an outright purchase was not viable, but saw value in enhancing security ties and assigned a team to figure out how to satisfy the president’s desire short of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was not enough for Mr. Trump. For months, he demanded action. He suggested taking federal money from Puerto Rico, a U.S. territory he disdained since being criticized for his response to a 2017 hurricane there, and using it to buy Greenland. At one point, according to an administration official, Mr. Trump suggested they just trade Puerto Rico for Greenland because “Puerto Rico was dirty and the people were poor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort to buy Greenland in his first term blew up when The Wall Street Journal reported it in 2019, prompting the Danes to reject it out of hand. But few understood then just how deep Mr. Trump’s fixation was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland never came up during the 2024 campaign, but on Dec. 22 of that year, just weeks after winning his old office back, Mr. Trump posted an online message calling acquisition of Greenland “an absolute necessity.” And unlike in his first term, this time he pointedly left military force on the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danish leaders responded by making clear that Greenland was not for sale, but otherwise sought to not provoke Mr. Trump and asked European allies not to get involved in hopes that the president would move on. By midyear, it seemed as if he had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, once again just before Christmas, Mr. Trump revived the issue. By the president’s account, Mr. Landry called him at Mar-a-Lago and pitched himself as special envoy on Greenland. This time, the Danes have concluded that a low profile will not work and have enlisted European allies to speak out and even send forces to Greenland for military exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, America is viewed as the rapacious aggressor likeliest to seize NATO territory, not Russia. During the singing of the national anthem before an NBA game in London on Sunday, a spectator shouted, “Leave Greenland alone!” generating applause. Protesters took to the streets in Denmark and Greenland over the weekend, chanting, “Yankee, go home!” The Russians, for their part, cheered the discord, chortling about the “collapse of the transatlantic union,” as Kirill Dmitriev, the Kremlin negotiator, put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland is not the only example of Mr. Trump trying to take what belongs to other countries. Since sending Delta Force commandos into Venezuela to capture President Nicolás Maduro on federal drug charges, Mr. Trump has asserted that he now “runs” the country and is taking its oil. While he is not talking about absorbing Venezuela into the United States, he has threatened to make Canada the “51st state” and threatened to seize the Panama Canal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s disregard for the territorial integrity of other nations stands in contrast to his own speech to the United Nations in 2017 when he used the words “sovereign” or “sovereignty” 21 times. “We must reject threats to sovereignty, from the Ukraine to the South China Sea,” he said then, calling for “respect for law” and “respect for borders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now he seems intent on returning to an age of Manifest Destiny, when the United States built an empire in the 19th century by pushing across the continent, violently forcing Native Americans off their land and waging war against Mexico to procure much of the west. Such imperialism largely ended by the turn of the century after America seized the Philippines, Puerto Rico and Guam from Spain. After years of bloody resistance, the United States eventually granted the Philippines independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it emerged as a global power in the 20th century, the United States positioned itself as a defender of other countries against foreign aggression. It came to the aid of Europe against Germany twice, refused for decades to accept Soviet annexation of the Baltic States, freed much of the Pacific from Imperial Japan, stopped the takeover of South Korea by the North, expelled Iraqi invaders from Kuwait and, more recently, armed Ukraine to fight off Vladimir V. Putin’s Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States helped create the United Nations to protect the sovereignty of independent countries. “All members shall refrain in their international relations from the threat or use of force against the territorial integrity or political independence of any state, or in any other manner inconsistent with the purposes of the United Nations,” says Article 2 of the U.N. Charter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, who by contrast has agreed to recognize Russia’s illegal annexation of Ukrainian territory as part of a possible peace deal, has articulated no legal doctrine allowing him to do with Greenland what Mr. Putin is trying to do with Ukraine. Instead, he has argued that he can do anything he wants, declaring that the only limits on his global power are “my own morality” and “my own mind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stephen Miller, his deputy chief of staff, has dismissed international treaties as “international niceties” and demanded to know “by what right does Denmark assert control over Greenland?” Mr. Trump adopted that line of argument in his text to Norway’s prime minister, stating, “There are no written documents,” although Greenland has been part of Denmark longer than the United States has been a nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Republicans have pushed back, while trying to blame the people around the president. “The fact that a small handful of ‘advisors’ are actively pushing for coercive action to seize territory of an ally is beyond stupid,” Senator Thom Tillis, a North Carolina Republican who helped lead a congressional delegation to Denmark, wrote on social media over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is not the first American president to eye Greenland. Truman himself agreed that it could be an important addition to the country and in 1946 made a secret offer to Denmark to buy it for $100 million in gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Denmark declined to sell, Truman did not punish it. Nor did he threaten to invade. He took no for an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-america-conquest.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:17:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘No Going Back’: Trump Doubles Down on Greenland Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-macron-rutte.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-trump-greenland-europe-gwmf/20int-trump-greenland-europe-gwmf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump ratcheted up his feud with European leaders on Tuesday, firing off a series of mocking social media posts that reinforced his designs on Greenland, as he risked damaging the longstanding trans-Atlantic diplomatic alignment beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day before he was scheduled to join allies at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Trump insisted that the United States must have Greenland, the semiautonomous Danish territory, repeating a persistent demand that has shaken the foundations of the NATO alliance. “There can be no going back,” he wrote in one of a series of posts on his Truth Social platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another post, he shared messages from President Emmanuel Macron of France, who said, “I do not understand what you are doing on Greenland.” A senior French official confirmed that the messages were authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions over Greenland threatened to dominate the meeting in Davos. Speaking there later Tuesday morning, Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, suggested that the European Union would take steps to bolster its security in light of the crisis and would be looking at “how to strengthen our security partnerships with partners such as the U.K., Canada, Norway, Iceland and others.” She did not offer details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. von der Leyen also argued that Europe needed to change to adapt to a more hostile era, saying, “Nostalgia will not bring back the old order.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with Mr. Trump’s threats, including a warning that he will impose new tariffs on nations that oppose his territorial demands, European leaders have scrambled to formulate a response and were expected to gather in Brussels this week to come up with a way to answer Mr. Trump’s provocations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron, who was scheduled to speak at Davos on Tuesday afternoon, appeared to be trying to appeal to Mr. Trump in person, inviting him to dinner in Paris on Thursday, according to the messages Mr. Trump shared online. Mr. Macron offered to set up a meeting there of leaders of the Group of 7 countries — with additional invitations to the Russians, Ukrainians, Danes and Syrians. It was not immediately known whether Mr. Trump responded to Mr. Macron’s messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also shared a message from Mark Rutte, NATO’s secretary general, in which Mr. Rutte said he was “committed to finding a way forward on Greenland.” An official at the North Atlantic Treaty Organization said the exchange was authentic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said that he had spoken with Mr. Rutte and reiterated his claims that American control of Greenland was essential for the security of the United States and of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are the only POWER that can ensure PEACE throughout the World,” Mr. Trump wrote as he insisted on American military might. “And it is done, quite simply, through STRENGTH!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also lashed out at British plans to relinquish control of one of the Chagos Islands, in the Indian Ocean, calling it an “act of GREAT STUPIDITY” and saying it was “another in a very long line of National Security reasons why Greenland has to be acquired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The messages from Mr. Trump follow weeks of renewed tensions over Greenland. He recently threatened to impose steep tariffs on European allies and linked his push for Greenland to not winning the Nobel Peace Prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland, a majority Indigenous territory, has said that it is not for sale. Its leader said last week that Greenlanders would rather stay part of the Danish kingdom, its former colonizer, than join the Americans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Denmark announced that it would be increasing its military presence in and around Greenland, as NATO allies in Europe — including France, Germany and Scandinavian countries — deployed personnel to Greenland in a gesture of solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark, which has said it has a “fundamental disagreement” with the United States over Greenland and has insisted it will not sell or surrender the territory, sent a small contingent of about 100 Danish soldiers to western Greenland on Monday, along with the Danish army chief, Peter Boysen, the country’s state broadcaster said. Analysts said Denmark’s military moves were part of an effort to show Mr. Trump that the country was taking seriously his concerns about Arctic security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump has not stopped. In another post early Tuesday, he shared a computer-generated image of himself planting a flag on Greenland. The image features a wooden placard that reads: “GREENLAND, US TERRITORY, EST. 2026.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ségolène Le Stradic and Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-macron-rutte.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:09:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>If You Were Inspired by the Northern Lights, You’re Not Alone</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/northern-lights-aurora-inspiration-history.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-aurora-church/20xp-aurora-church-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northern lights dazzled overnight during one of the largest solar radiation storms in decades, streaking the skies of North America and Northern Europe with bursts of red, green and orange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were inspired, you’re not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aurora borealis has intrigued humans for millenniums. Scholars have identified portrayals in prehistoric cave paintings, in the Bible and other ancient historical texts, and in a number of myths and legends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Inuit believed that the lights were torches ignited by the spirits of the dead to guide new spirits to a higher realm, wrote Harald Falck-Ytter in “Aurora: The Northern Lights in Mythology, History, and Science” (1999).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some cultures, including an Indigenous Siberian tribe, viewed the phenomenon as a sign of imminent childbirth. In ancient China, a written record from 2,600 B.C. said that an emperor’s mother had become pregnant after seeing “a big lightening circulating around” a star in the northern sky, “with the light shining all over the field.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northern lights also captivated the ancient Greeks and Romans. The Greek philosopher and biographer Plutarch described “a flaming cloud that did not rest in one place but moved along with intricate and regular movements.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first century A.D., the Roman philosopher Seneca marveled at the variation in the aurora’s colors: “Some are a very intense red; some have a weak, pale flame; some have a bright light; some pulsate; some are a uniform yellow with no discharges or rays emerging.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aurora borealis got its scientific name from Galileo in the early 17th century, at a time when Renaissance scholars were studying the phenomenon intensely. He named it after Aurora, the Roman goddess of dawn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The astronomer Edmond Halley, the namesake for Halley’s comet, linked the northern lights to the Earth’s magnetic field, setting off research into the science behind them. He expected to die without seeing them but finally got a chance in 1716, at the age of 59.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other scientists would later confirm Halley’s hypothesis. The northern lights happen when charged particles from the sun, carried by the solar wind, collide with gases in Earth’s upper atmosphere, guided toward the planet’s poles by its magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lights have inspired plenty of artists, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Aurora Borealis,” an 1865 painting by the American landscape painter Frederic Edwin Church, shows a ship trapped in Arctic ice under turquoise and red streaks in the night sky. He based the painting not on direct observation but on sketches and descriptions from Isaac Hayes, a polar explorer who had seen the northern lights during an 1861 voyage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same year the painting was made, the northern lights inspired Herman Melville to write the poem “Aurora Borealis.” It commemorated the end of the American Civil War, during which the northern lights reached as far south as Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poem’s irregular cadence echoes the glimmering lights it describes: the “Retreatings and advancings,” the “Transitions and enhancings” and the “million blades that glowed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, the northern lights have animated songs by the rock bands Death Cab for Cutie and Renaissance, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lyrics of the 1976 song “Aurora Borealis,” by the country singer known as C.W. McCall, are particularly evocative. It tells a story of stargazing in Colorado, glimpsing the Milky Way over Wyoming and seeing the northern lights from Montana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’re like flames from some prehistoric campfire, leaping and dancing in the sky and changing colors,” he sings. “It’s like the equinox, the changing of the seasons: summer to fall, young to old, then to now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Norway, the northern lights were celebrated in a modern architectural marvel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Northern Lights Cathedral, completed in 2013, features a winding titanium facade and sloping concrete walls designed to mimic the coiling shapes of an aurora. Its spire stretches 154 feet into the sky.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/northern-lights-aurora-inspiration-history.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:36:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A.I., Big Tech and Trump Shine Most Brightly at the Davos Spectacle</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/davos-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21biz-davos-mood-01-tkfh/21biz-davos-mood-01-tkfh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours before the official start of the World Economic Forum on Monday evening, a line of more than four dozen people snaked onto the sidewalk in front of the AI House, a nonprofit convened in the name of providing a “multi-stakeholder platform for visionary dialogue and collaboration on key questions shaping the next frontier.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of doors down, an even longer line of attendees jostled for space inside a forum on artificial intelligence and cybersecurity hosted by Axios, the American news operation. People took selfies while swapping tips on how to score invites to the glitziest parties thrown by global technology companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just down the block, a rented storefront outfitted as the gathering place for the Alliance for Global Good-Gender Equity and Equality sat mostly empty. The initiative was launched by the Indian government two years ago to bolster women’s health and education. Here at Davos, its place was mostly unnoticed. People passed by hurriedly, en route to neon-tinted cocktails served up by a cryptocurrency firm or a pulsating lounge experience paid for by an A.I. company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a small stretch of a promenade, the main street threading the village of Davos in the Swiss Alps, was a visual distillation of what has come of the World Economic Forum, a conference long touted as the central gathering place of the global elite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high-minded panel discussions about climate change, caring for refugees and the future of health care were there to be heard in lesser venues. But the action was dominated by technology giants and their euphoria over the lucrative potential of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m a very bullish character,” said Daniel Newman, chief executive of the Futurum Group, a consultancy based in Austin, Texas, that advises major tech companies on new ventures. “This is an exponential time, and the world is changing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later that night, Mr. Newman would join with two partner organizations to host what was billed as an “A.I. and Exploration Salon,” where a crowd of entrepreneurs drawn from Silicon Valley to France hoisted margaritas and danced to house music. Then came a performance from a “mentalist” who gathered random numbers from the crowd and somehow multiplied and subtracted them to yield the digits representing the day’s date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Newman took the stage, he used that trick to advertise the transformative potential of A.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Great technology can feel like magic,” he said. “This is the fastest technological gigacycle in history.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this, the 56th Davos event, conversation featured complaints about the traffic crawling through the narrow streets, a perennial lament as visiting heads of state commandeer seemingly every Land Rover between here and Uzbekistan. But this year the traffic has been worsened by the fact that the forum has attracted the largest crowd in its history, some 3,000 people from 130 countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anticipation was intently focused on the looming arrival of President Trump, who was expected on Wednesday. Security had already been tightened, and the sidewalks were as crowded as midtown Manhattan during rush hour. Davos, always a logistical torment, was certain to become more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional wisdom had it that Mr. Trump was entering hostile territory: a conference devoted to multilateral cooperation held in Europe, just as he advances threats to seize Greenland from Denmark, a fellow member of the North Atlantic alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was clearly some truth to that expectation. As Christine Lagarde, president of the European Central Bank, entered the Congress Center on Tuesday morning, I asked her whether she anticipated that Europe would stay firm in opposing Mr. Trump’s threatened incursion, including the use of punitive tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes,” she said. “I’m a central banker, not a policymaker, but I certainly hope so.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, the European Commission president Ursula von der Leyen used a keynote address to urge the Trump administration not to proceed with tariffs in pursuit of its claims on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our response will be unflinching, united and proportional,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a modest gathering held in a repurposed storefront a 15-minute walk from the center of the action on Monday evening, a group of European diplomats and activists held a conversation billed “Trans-Atlantic relations in the era of Trump. Can we keep the E.U.-U.S. bond?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the participants described an imperative to oppose Mr. Trump on Greenland. They described the confrontation as a historical test of the continent’s true principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is about guarding, holding on to human values,” said Sandrine Dixson-Declève, the global ambassador for the Club of Rome, a think tank focused on sustainability and economic inequality. She described the current moment as feeling much like the 1930s, which culminated in the Holocaust. “I have my grandfather’s voice in my head,” she said. “‘Do not forget history.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A member of Poland’s parliament, Aleksandra Uznańska-Wiśniewska, accused the White House of trying to impose an unjust peace on Ukraine, with money outweighing any concern for human rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The vision of Trump is to end the conflict as soon as possible, to reestablish business as usual with Russia,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But these sorts of conversations were tucked away. The dominant spectacle was the largest storefronts on the promenade decked out as headquarters and hospitality centers for some of the world’s largest consulting companies and technology brands: Meta, Salesforce, Tata. Qatar and the United Arab Emirates occupied massive retail spaces, advertising their openness for business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prime spot on the promenade, an old church near the conference center, had been reconfigured into USA House, a venue sponsored by McKinsey and Microsoft, among others, that was billed as spotlighting “enduring themes associated with American leadership, including innovation, opportunity, collaboration and democratic values.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draped in red, white and blue banners adorned with bald eagles, USA House sat across the street from Palantir, an American data analytics company that Mr. Trump has relied on to increase surveillance for Homeland Security and the Pentagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a media briefing on Tuesday, the U.S. Treasury secretary Scott Bessent said that he planned to meet with non-American chief executives to urge them to remain calm in the face of tensions surrounding Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Take a deep breath and let this play out,” Mr. Bessent said. “Do not listen to the media hysteria.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crowds thronging the USA House contributed to the sense that Davos has been refashioned, or perhaps just reinforced. Though critics have long accused the World Economic Forum of serving up a performance of earnest inquiry and compassion while really conducting a business conference, this year the pretenses are mostly gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karen Harris, managing director of the Macro Trends Group at Bain &amp; Company, has been attending the forum since 2018. As she surveyed the offerings this year, she detected a shift away from the traditional conceit that members of nongovernmental organizations are supposed to gather in Davos to advise world leaders on how to elevate humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That doesn’t feel like the agenda anymore,” she said “Certainly the agenda and who’s heroicized feels different.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As she spoke, word was circulating that Mr. Trump planned to convene chief executives for a large meeting on Wednesday, a source of intrigue and scheduling anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those engaged in artificial intelligence expressed certainty that he would be greeted not as a rogue threat to the global order but as a provider of enormous opportunities to make money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most of these C.E.O.s are focused on nurturing values for their shareholders,” said Mr. Newman, the Futurum Group chief executive. “They have grown bullish that he’ll move policy, cut through the red tape.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tech executives he works with once talked about diversity, equity and inclusion along with climate sustainability. Not anymore. They have adopted the guise of the American president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Part of being a great C.E.O. is being a chameleon,” Mr. Newman explained. “Trump is the most influential voice in the world right now. These C.E.O.s are pleased to be in an environment that’s largely right for business.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordyn Holman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/business/davos-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 09:52:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel Seizes U.N. Agency’s Jerusalem Headquarters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/israel-unrwa-jerusalem.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-gaza-unrwa-photo-pvcg/20int-gaza-unrwa-photo-pvcg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flanked by bulldozers, Israeli officials seized the Jerusalem headquarters of the United Nations agency for Palestinian refugees on Tuesday and oversaw the demolition of some of the structures in its compound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move further escalates Israel’s crackdown on the United Nations Relief and Works Agency, generally known by its acronym UNRWA. The organization had long been one of the leading aid agencies in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip, but over the last two years the Israeli government, which has long been at odds with the agency, has passed sweeping legislation criminalizing its operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement defending the decision to seize the compound, Oren Marmorstein, a spokesman for Israel’s foreign ministry, said UNRWA “has long ceased to be a humanitarian aid organization, serving instead as a greenhouse for terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philippe Lazzarini, the head of UNRWA, called the Israeli move “a new level of open &amp; deliberate defiance of international law” in a post on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UNRWA was founded in 1949 to serve Palestinians who were displaced in the wars surrounding Israel’s establishment and their descendants. The Knesset, Israel’s parliament, passed laws that banned the agency and severely curbed its activity in the occupied West Bank and Gaza. It stripped UNRWA of its diplomatic immunity and barred its facilities from receiving electricity and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli officials have also accused UNRWA’s Gaza branch of being compromised, saying that Palestinian militant groups had managed to substantially infiltrate the organization. After the Hamas-led attack on southern Israel on Oct. 7, 2023, which ignited the devastating war in Gaza, Israeli officials named 19 UNRWA employees who they say participated in the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An internal U.N. inquiry found that at least nine employees may have participated in the Oct. 7 attack, and the agency fired them. The organization employs about 13,000 people in the Gaza Strip, and UNRWA’s leaders say Israel has never provided evidence to back up its claim that there had been widespread infiltration by Hamas or other groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most recent legislation, passed in late December, also allowed the Israeli government to seize UNRWA’s properties, including the agency’s headquarters. At its largest, hundreds of aid workers and other people employed by UNRWA worked at the Jerusalem compound, according to Jonathan Fowler, a spokesman for the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UNRWA’s international staff began leaving Israel about a year ago when the legislation first went into effect. The compound has largely been vacant since then, although Israeli officials entered it in December and put up an Israeli flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under an international convention that Israel has ratified, U.N. facilities are supposed to be “inviolable,” similar to the status of a foreign embassy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It remains a United Nations compound, no matter what they say,” Mr. Fowler said. “Even if in December, they ripped down the U.N. flag and put up the Israeli flag.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Marmorstein, the Israeli spokesman, disputed that the seizure was illegal. The compound “does not enjoy any immunity,” he said in a statement, arguing that it was “carried out in accordance with both Israeli and international law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the ban, UNRWA has continued some activities in parts of East Jerusalem, which Israel occupied in the 1967 Mideast war and later annexed, Mr. Fowler said. The agency operates at least two clinics, one of which has already received a cease-and-desist order from the Israeli government, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/israel-unrwa-jerusalem.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:54:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Few Dozen European Troops in Greenland Triggered Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/europe-troops-greenland-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20trump-news-greenland-troops-pfzw/20trump-news-greenland-troops-pfzw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European nations sent a small group of military personnel to Greenland last week to show solidarity with the island, an autonomous territory of Denmark, and to demonstrate a willingness to increase security in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In total, France, Germany, Norway, Sweden, the Netherlands, Finland and Britain dispatched a few dozen people. Denmark also increased its own military presence in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That move landed badly in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Denmark, Norway, Sweden, France, Germany, The United Kingdom, the Netherlands, and Finland have journeyed to Greenland, for purposes unknown,” President Trump posted on Truth Social on Saturday, before announcing 10 percent tariffs on those nations, kicking in next month and increasing to 25 percent in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many European leaders have since rushed to explain that they did not intend to defy the United States by sending troops, and that they were simply demonstrating their ability to police the Arctic. Britain has said that it sent one officer, and in only an “observational capacity.” German troops have already gone home, local media reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark has taken a different tack: It very publicly sent more troops this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danish military posted images of its forces arriving in Greenland on Monday to take part in a NATO training exercise called Operation Arctic Endurance, led by Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nation, which has said it has a “fundamental disagreement” with the United States over Greenland and has insisted it will not sell or surrender the territory, sent a contingent of about 100 soldiers to western Greenland on Monday, along with its army chief, Peter Boysen, according to the country’s public broadcaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercise was continuing to “develop,” the Danish military said Tuesday in a news release, following what it described as “initial planning visits” last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the added Danish soldiers appeared to be from a battalion that specializes in defensive measures like building fortifications and obstacles, according to the Danish broadcaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s armed forces also said on Tuesday that its military could for the first time “operate across all of Greenland, including high-alpine terrain,” which is among the world’s harshest environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lynsey Chutel contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/europe-troops-greenland-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:42:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Skies Clear, and a New Outpost Springs Up at the Bottom of the World</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/climate/antarctica-camping-thwaites-glacier.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20cli-av-touchdown-01-tkzh/20cli-av-touchdown-01-tkzh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a series of weather delays threatened to derail their mission, scientists on Monday managed at last to set up camp on Antarctica’s remote and fast-melting Thwaites Glacier. For the next few weeks, they will be attempting a difficult but vital operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They aim to bore half a mile through the ice and place instruments in the warming ocean waters below, giving the world a rare, close-up look at how this gargantuan glacier is being corroded by the sea. Researchers fear that Thwaites’s thinning could someday trigger its total collapse, which would raise sea levels around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The break in the weather couldn’t have come soon enough. After crossing the southern seas and reaching Thwaites early this month, the researchers were unable to travel the last 19 miles to their planned research site because helicopters from their ship, the icebreaker Araon, couldn’t land on the cloud-swathed ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the scientists and their roughly 17 tons of gear have been flown safely onto the glacier, they have no time to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their drilling equipment will take a week to set up. Blizzards could slow their work. Whether or not their scientific goals are achieved, the team’s 10 members need to be off the glacier by Feb. 7, when the Araon must begin its return journey to New Zealand. The ship is scheduled to embark another Antarctic voyage shortly after this one wraps up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re very lucky to be here; we also work very hard to be here,” said Scott Polfrey, a mechanical engineer at the British Antarctic Survey and member of the drilling team. “It’s important for everybody here that we do things safely and we come home with hopefully some hard-hitting scientific results that speak about our planet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked, during a break from moving gear at the camp, whether he had any first-night rituals while working on glaciers, Peter Davis, an oceanographer on the team, said: “Probably collapse, because everyone is just always knackered, absolutely knackered, after the first day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big haul started late on Sunday afternoon, when the clouds parted and the Araon’s two helicopters flew a dozen loads of cargo onto the glacier. The helicopters ferried more freight and people on Monday, and by 4 p.m., the scientists and engineers were putting up tents, unpacking supplies and shoveling snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, as Chang W. Lee, my photographer colleague, and I were being flown onto Thwaites, the team’s camp first appeared as specks on the colossal white plateau, insignificant next to the enormous crevasses that furrowed its snowy surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The camp sits on a flat, 650-foot-long strip of ice, with boundaries that the team marked with flags and willow branches stuck into the hard, icy snow. Its wider end, roughly 160 feet across, is where the drill will be set up. Its narrower end is where 10 single-occupancy sleeping tents have been pitched in a neat row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team will eat in a mess tent that has an air fryer, a bread machine and an assortment of low-effort meals, including freeze-dried chicken fajita bowls and quick-cooking Korean beef and radish soup. Two toilet tents are as simple as it gets: a lidded seat propped up over a deep hole in the snow. Power for their drilling and camp equipment comes from several generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One important task on Monday was piling snow around the edges of the tents so they didn’t blow away. Another was digging a big hole for burying the team’s coolers of frozen meat and vegetables. “Obviously we’re in the world’s best freezer,” said Taff Raymond, one of the team’s two safety guides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At around 6:15 p.m., the air at the camp was 24.8 degrees Fahrenheit, or minus-4 degrees Celsius. The snow dampened all sound. Skuas patrolled the area, the seabirds alighting on the wooden crates and steel chests that had so rudely invaded their domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientists’ camp sits in a modest depression in Thwaites’s surface, giving the landscape more shape and variety than it seemed to have from the sky. To the north, the sun caught the jagged crests of what looked like distant mountains. In fact, they were the tops of the gigantic, fast-deteriorating icebergs that are all that’s left of Thwaites’s western tongue. The glacier had engulfed us in all dimensions; we were mere specks on the giant’s back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it’s what’s happening thousands of feet below, not at the icy surface, that made the team want to drill at this spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warm ocean currents are constantly flowing into the waters under Thwaites and melting the glacier’s undersides. Large plumes of fresh water are also escaping from gaps between the glacier and the bedrock, where underground heat and friction are melting the ice at its base. All these waters mix and muddle under Thwaites, affecting where and how quickly the glacier thins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such complexities help explain why scientists have at times observed Antarctic ice melting at two or three times the rates predicted by mathematical models, said Ji Sung Na, a senior researcher at the Korea Polar Research Institute who is part of the drilling team. Only by collecting sustained measurements in the water under the ice can scientists improve their models and better project future melting, Dr. Na said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several members of the drilling team bored a hole through Thwaites’s eastern ice shelf for a similar purpose in 2020. An expedition two years later to drill in another area was foiled by sea ice, which blocked the Araon from sailing close enough to Thwaites for the scientists to travel to their planned research site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Davis, the oceanographer, last camped on the glacier in 2020. “We thought that was going to be the most complex terrain we’d ever work on,” he said. “Little did we know.” He was referring to the fractured and fast-moving ice beneath this year’s campsite, which has already caused a scare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drilling team’s safety guides, Mr. Raymond and Jinsuk Kim, slept on the glacier Sunday night, before their colleagues were flown in. They were standing at the camp’s wider end, they said, when they heard a terrible loud crunching noise beneath their feet. The ice below the surface was breaking apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guides tightened the camp’s boundaries, probably not for the last time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My goal is finishing as fast as we can,” Mr. Kim said, of the drilling operation. “We need to leave as fast as we can.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/climate/antarctica-camping-thwaites-glacier.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:45:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump, Venezuela and Oil</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/venezuela-oil-trump-greenland-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-theworld-venezuela-oil-promo/21int-theworld-venezuela-oil-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One early sign that things might not go so smoothly for the U.S. in its quest for Venezuelan oil was how American energy companies responded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a meeting between oil executives and President Trump this month at the White House, Darren Woods, head of Exxon Mobil, called Venezuela “uninvestable.” Another oil magnate and Trump ally, Harold Hamm, was more diplomatic, but not exactly enthusiastic. Venezuela has “its challenges,” Hamm said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has made it clear that he wants to move fast. At that meeting, which he called less than a week after U.S. troops captured the Venezuelan president, Nicolás Maduro, Trump told oil executives to “rapidly rebuild” the South American country’s oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, exclusive reporting by my colleague Anatoly Kurmanaev found that the U.S. has already begun selling 50 million barrels of the Venezuelan oil that had previously been trapped by a partial U.S. blockade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are good reasons for the U.S. administration to prioritize speed, Anatoly told me. The Venezuelan economy was days from collapsing. Oil storage was near capacity. The currency was in free fall. Officials had to get that trapped oil out and dollars in as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was a race against time,” Anatoly said. “Trump has no interest in a collapsed Venezuela right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the longer term, Trump has bigger ambitions. He wants what he calls “energy dominance” — enough weight in the global oil market to curb the power of OPEC countries and gain leverage over China. Venezuela is part of that plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the weeks since the invasion, these longer-term ambitions to gain effective control of Venezuela’s oil industry have “run headlong into reality,” my colleague Anton Troianovski wrote last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s grand plans might take years to come to fruition — if they come to fruition at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slow and expensive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem for Trump is that the U.S. doesn’t have a national oil company. Exxon, Chevron and the like are private corporations that will start projects only when they see a good business opportunity. When they look at Venezuela, they don’t like what they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case for investing in Venezuelan oil isn’t straightforward. The country has a lot of oil, but gaining access to it and turning it into a profitable business would take a lot of time and upfront investment, as my colleague Peter Coy writes. That’s the kind of thing that U.S. oil companies, which have recently sought to economize on investments and cut risk, don’t like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low oil prices mean the incentive to invest is limited. “Many analysts believe that a vast oversupply of oil is already sloshing around global markets,” Anton wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem: The U.S. may have removed Maduro, and achieved seeming compliance from his successor, for now, but it’s far from clear that it has achieved long-term political stability in Venezuela. A history of political turmoil, which led to the assets of U.S. oil companies being nationalized in the first place, is part of why executives view the country as “uninvestable” today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as some of my colleagues have been reporting, there are signs that cracks have already begun appearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Zero oil’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the discontent many Venezuelans feel toward their government, oil has been an integral part of the country’s opposition to the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For the last three decades, they have been fed an ideology of ‘Chavismo,’ with its goal of harnessing oil wealth to transform the country, empower the poor and stand up to the United States and its imperial ambitions,” writes my colleague Maria Abi-Habib.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so some Venezuelans find it hard to swallow their new status as a country willing to cooperate — and share oil wealth — with the Americans who just invaded them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At this point, we should have cut off the oil, we shouldn’t have sold any oil to the United States. Zero oil, zero oil!” one Venezuelan told Maria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear how long the new government will manage to stave off these forces in order to continue cooperation with the United States. Even if it does, other ingredients for instability abound: The country remains filled with paramilitary groups, Colombian guerrillas and gangs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not the kind of environment that looks tempting to an oil executive watching from Texas. But Trump is also willing to strong-arm them into submission. “I’ll probably be inclined to keep Exxon out,” the president told reporters after the White House meeting. “I didn’t like their response.” Exxon’s stock slipped in the aftermath, though it has since recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump is scheduled to speak at the World Economic Forum today, one day after leaders denounced his threats to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada gave a searing speech about a “rupture” in the world order. President Emmanuel Macron of France said Europe had little regard for “bullies,” after Trump threatened 200 percent tariffs on French wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of comments and social media posts ahead of his arrival, Trump mocked European leaders as being weak. His standoff with Europe rattled markets. Greenland’s prime minister would not rule out the possibility of a U.S. attack, even though he said it was “not likely.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russian strikes left thousands of apartment buildings in Kyiv without heat in subfreezing temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators in Spain zeroed in on a problem with the track that may have caused the train crash that killed at least 41 people. Here’s how the collision unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bombing in a Chinese restaurant in Kabul killed at least seven people, with the Islamic State claiming responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel seized the headquarters of the U.N. agency for Palestinian refugees in Jerusalem and demolished some of its buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump accused Britain of “an act of great stupidity” for agreeing to hand over control of the Chagos Islands to Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain approved construction of a Chinese mega-embassy in London despite spying fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia passed tighter gun control laws after a mass shooting at a Hanukkah celebration in Sydney killed over a dozen people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guatemala’s president declared a state of emergency to crack down on gangs after uprisings in three prisons killed 10 police officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubans in Florida, who had long benefited from legal privileges unavailable to other U.S. immigrants, are being deported in record numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Naomi Osaka entered her first Australian Open match in style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Evaluating each Premier League team’s plans for the January transfer window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— U.S. Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, in response to questions about European efforts to block Trump from seizing Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “The Kholops” opened in St. Petersburg in 2024, Russians raced to see the play about 19th century nobles, which is not-so-subtly scathing about Russian life under President Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest plot twist: Authorities have not shut it down. Officials seemed to recognize that closing “The Kholops” (the title means “The Serfs”) would create a scandal. Many critics and theatergoers have also theorized that the play has avoided intense scrutiny because most of its judgments arrive indirectly. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Milan-Cortina Olympics are less than three weeks away, but the venue for ice hockey, one of the Winter Games’ premier events, is still a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 1,000 workers are scheduled for round-the-clock shifts until the arena in Milan is completed. The opening ceremony is on Feb. 6, and the head of Milan’s Olympic committee said he was confident that “the arena will be done by Feb. 5.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The late-stage work has raised anxiety because the National Hockey League has warned that its players, scheduled to participate in the Olympics for the first time in a dozen years, will pull out if the ice is not safe or ready. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: “Eating Ashes,” by Brenda Navarro, is a tale of migration, loss and memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Care: Here are seven things women should know about heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wear: Should you cuff your pants? Our fashion critic has thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess: Do you know these book titles inspired by Shakespeare?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Red, a common dish served in Ghana, is a popular stew of beans and peppers. It often starts with soaking and slowly cooking the legumes until tender. This recipe uses canned beans and yields a spice-forward, piquant sauce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is this rock formation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stewart Island, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kapiti Island, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kangaroo Island, Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasmania, Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/venezuela-oil-trump-greenland-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:14:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hidden In a Stream, New Clues About Cause of Spain Rail Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/spain-missing-part-undercarriage-key-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-spain-undercarriage-02-bhmq-promo/20int-spain-undercarriage-02-bhmq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the nearly two days since a high-speed train crash in southern Spain, investigators have focused on whether a fault in the track could be to blame for the derailment of a northbound train that swerved into the path of an oncoming southbound train, resulting in a devastating collision that killed at least 42 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on Tuesday, the emergence of a previously unreported train undercarriage — half submerged in a stream flowing through a steep-sided gully 900 feet from the railway — gave experts a potential new clue about what caused the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hulking piece of debris, seen by a photographer for The New York Times on Tuesday afternoon, was not marked or cordoned off by government investigators and had not previously been disclosed by officials. When shown images and maps locating the undercarriage on Tuesday, police officers assisting the investigation in Adamuz, a town in southern Spain near the city of Córdoba, first said they had been looking for it, and later said they knew about it, but could not comment on an ongoing investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADIF, a state-owned authority that manages much of Spain’s rail infrastructure, said on Tuesday evening that the part had been located by investigators, but did not respond to a question about when it was found. The Times was not able to confirm which train it came from, whether it landed there on Sunday, or how it got there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts on Tuesday said the discovery of the undercarriage, if it indeed belonged to one of the two trains involved in the crash, could provide a critical clue to what went wrong, and whether parts of the train itself contributed to the disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is going to be real important if this turns out to be the root cause of the accident,” said David B. Clarke, an associate professor and railroad expert at the Center for Transportation Research in Knoxville, Tenn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One person briefed on the government investigation, who spoke on condition of anonymity because the person was not authorized to speak publicly about the case, said the photograph of the undercarriage appeared to show a set of wheels that could shed light on the cause of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distance that the undercarriage appeared to have traveled from the tracks also could be an important piece of information, according to Andrew Maloney, a transportation attorney in New York who has specialized in civil lawsuits related to transportation accidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The location of where parts are found can be critically important in reconstructing the accident sequence,” Mr. Maloney said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a part is found far from the crash site, “it could mean that it was the cause of the derailment,” Mr. Maloney said. “If it’s found with the rest of the wreckage or close by, it may mean it became detached after the derailment and collision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Italian state-controlled railway group ‍Ferrovie dello Stato, which is the majority owner of Iryo, which operated the derailed train, declined to comment about whether the undercarriage belonged to their train. Iryo did not return a request for comment. Renfe, the state-owned company that operated the second train, said questions about the undercarriage should be addressed to the investigators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new finding came as Spanish authorities struggled to identify the dead and used heavy machines to look for more bodies. On Tuesday evening, data provided by Spain’s Interior Ministry showed that 25 bodies still had not been identified. The Spanish police said they had received missing-person reports for 40 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crash, Spain’s worst railway disaster since 2013, has deeply disturbed a country that depends on, and takes great pride in, its high-speed rail system, the largest in Europe and the second largest in the world, behind only China’s. Late Tuesday, a regional train in Gelida, Spain, derailed in Gelida, Barcelona, injuring around 15 people, according to Martí Anglada, a regional official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier Tuesday, many Spanish news reports focused on a different photograph, released by the Spanish police, of investigators examining a particular stretch of track near the disaster site. The Commission for the Investigation of Railway Accidents had said that it was examining the general condition of the track as a possible cause of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, said in a radio interview on Tuesday that there had been “an initial break” in the track, but he added that “no technician is yet able to say whether it is a cause or a consequence” of the derailment. “If the rail broke first, we would need to find out why a solid steel rail broke,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authorities said the crash would shut down service on the line between Madrid, Spain’s capital, and the southern city of Córdoba for weeks, raising concerns for the economy of a key area in southern Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a line that connects and brings us a lot of economic and tourist flow. First of all, it’s going to be a long stretch until the track can be repaired. Secondly, there’s a feeling of insecurity that can spread,” said José María Bellido, the mayor of Córdoba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the day, harrowing new details emerged from survivors of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passengers on the northbound train recounted cars vibrating strangely, carriages lurching, suitcases tumbling and glasses sliding off tables onto the floor during the initial derailment. About 20 seconds later, around 7:45 p.m., the southbound train, operated by the national rail provider, Renfe, barreled into the derailed carriages. Its first two cars fell down a 12-foot embankment, a preliminary report said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northbound train, which had about 300 people aboard, continued for hundreds of yards before coming to a stop. Surviving passengers described wandering in the dark and cold through a scene strewn with corpses, as local residents rushed to help.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/spain-missing-part-undercarriage-key-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:47:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia Passes Tighter Gun Control Laws, Weeks After Bondi Massacre</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/gun-control-buyback.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-oz-gunlaws-mqfk/20int-oz-gunlaws-mqfk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia on Tuesday passed new laws that implement a national gun buyback, limit imports of firearms and tighten background checks, swiftly adopting tougher gun control measures after a mass shooting at a Hanukkah celebration last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves echoed Australia’s legislative response to a massacre decades ago, which made the country a model for gun control in the eyes of many. But critics said the new legislation, and another bill promising to crack down on hate speech, had been rushed and received limited scrutiny. Some have said that the push for new gun laws belied a failure by the government to address antisemitism in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guns used in the attack on Dec. 14, in which two men killed 15 people and wounded dozens of others at Bondi Beach in Sydney, were bought legally. The authorities have characterized the shooting as a terrorist attack motivated by antisemitic ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now more than four million firearms in Australia, a record, according to the authorities. Details of the gun buyback have yet to be finalized, but it is expected to be the largest since the one conducted after the 1996 mass shooting in Port Arthur, Tasmania, where a gunman killed 35 people. That buyback was announced 12 days after the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the new laws, background checks for people applying for firearm licenses can now include an assessment by national intelligence agencies, and in some cases, the authorities will check to see whether the applicant is an Australian citizen. Only citizens will be allowed to import guns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The terrorists had hate in their hearts, but they also had high-powered rifles in their hands,” Prime Minister Anthony Albanese told Parliament before the vote on Tuesday. “We’re taking action on both — tackling antisemitism, tackling hate, and getting dangerous guns off our streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite some opposition to the bill, it passed easily in a special session of Parliament in Canberra, the capital. Lawmakers were recalled two weeks early from a summer break by Mr. Albanese, whose popularity has slumped since the Bondi attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on Tuesday, Parliament passed the bill targeting hate speech, which critics say could have damaging repercussions for freedom of expression. It allows the government to designate organizations as hate groups if they promote violence, and it gives the authorities more leeway to deny entry visas to people with extremist views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mehreen Faruqi, the deputy leader of the Greens party, called the bill “appalling,” saying it was not a “responsible response” to racism and extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This bill will have a chilling and draconian effect on political debate, on protest, on civil rights and on people speaking up against human rights abuses perpetrated by Israel or any other nation-state,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some parts of the bill, which would have made it an offense to incite hate or spread ideas of “racial superiority” over another person or group, were dropped this week after politicians, legal experts and others said they would impede freedom of speech.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/gun-control-buyback.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:09:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Are the Chagos Islands and the Diego Garcia Base?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/chagos-islands-diego-garcia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-chagos-explainer-photo-lpzf/20int-chagos-explainer-photo-lpzf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump on Tuesday cited Britain’s decision to relinquish control over the Chagos Islands to Mauritius as one reason the United States should acquire Greenland, a semiautonomous island controlled by Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Shockingly, our ‘brilliant’ NATO Ally, the United Kingdom, is currently planning to give away the Island of Diego Garcia, the site of a vital U.S. Military Base, to Mauritius, and to do so FOR NO REASON WHATSOEVER,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media. He added that decision was an “act of GREAT STUPIDITY.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the colonial era, Britain had controlled the Chagos, a necklace of strategic islands in the Indian Ocean. In the 1960s, Britain began expelling the inhabitants of the more than 55 islands in the remote archipelago as part of a plan to build a strategically important air base with the United States on Diego Garcia, the largest of the islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mauritius, an island nation in East Africa, has claimed sovereignty over the islands since gaining independence from Britain in 1968.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, the government of Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain, under growing legal and diplomatic pressure, agreed to hand over the Chagos Islands, which are about halfway between Africa and Indonesia, to Mauritius. The decision followed years of negotiations and a ruling by the International Court of Justice, the highest court in the United Nations, that Britain had acted unlawfully by detaching the archipelago from Mauritius’s control in 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last May, the governments of Britain and Mauritius signed an agreement outlining the deal. (To go into effect, it will have to be ratified by both countries.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the terms of the agreement — one that members of the Trump administration at first celebrated — the United States and Britain would continue to operate the military base on Diego Garcia for an initial period of 99 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The base, used to serve U.S. Navy ships and refuel long-range bombers, is vital because the Indian Ocean is viewed as an arena for great-power rivalry. A base in the ocean, the United States reasoned, would help keep the Soviet Union and China at bay at the pinnacle of the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, Diego Garcia’s location makes it a valuable listening post for surveillance and intelligence gathering. It is also home to about 4,000 U.S. and British military and civilian contract personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal negotiations between Britain and Mauritius over the Chagos began in 2022, when the government in London was run by the Conservatives. The talks gained momentum when African countries began pressing Britain to hand over sovereignty. The islands, some said, were Britain’s “last colony in Africa.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States, eager to secure long-term access to the base on Diego Garcia, had privately encouraged the British government to resolve the dispute over the islands. And at the time of the deal, Secretary of State Marco Rubio praised the agreement and said that Mr. Trump had “expressed his support for this monumental achievement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s comments on Tuesday reflected a stark U-turn from that position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was another example of the president citing seemingly unrelated foreign actions as an apparent pretext for his wish to take control of Greenland. Over the weekend, Mr. Trump told Norway’s prime minister in a text message that since being denied the Nobel Peace Prize — which is administered by the Norwegian Nobel Committee, an independent entity — he no longer felt obliged to “think purely of Peace” in his bid to control Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/chagos-islands-diego-garcia.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:40:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Approves Contentious Chinese Mega-Embassy in London</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British government on Tuesday approved construction of a Chinese mega-embassy in the heart of London, rejecting the objections of critics who said the new building will make it easier for China to conduct spying operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval of the embassy, which comes after years of debate and delays, means China can move closer toward construction on a 5.5-acre site near the Tower of London. If it goes ahead, the new embassy will be China’s largest in Europe, although the plans are subject to numerous conditions and could yet be appealed in court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site was the home of Britain’s Royal Mint for more than 150 years. It was purchased by Beijing in 2018, when Boris Johnson was prime minister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opponents of the new embassy have warned that the location is close to the City of London, the capital’s financial district, and next to fiber-optic cables that transport vast amounts of sensitive data. They argue that Chinese officials could use the cables to spy on companies, on dissidents living in exile or on ordinary Britons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A joint letter released on Tuesday by Ken McCallum, the director of MI5, the country’s domestic security service, and Anne Keast-Butler, the director of GCHQ, its intelligence and cybersecurity agency, said it that “as with any foreign embassy on U.K. soil, it is not realistic to expect to be able wholly to eliminate each and every potential risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they said that work by the intelligence agencies and the government to create a “package of national security mitigations for the site” had been “expert, professional and proportionate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also noted that the new site would replace seven different Chinese diplomatic locations currently in use in London. “This consolidation should bring clear security advantages,” they wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision angered China hawks, dissidents, local residents and some of Mr. Starmer’s own Labour Party lawmakers, all of whom campaigned for more than a year to stop its construction. Sarah Champion, a Labour lawmaker who has publicly opposed the embassy, wrote on social media that the decision was “deeply disappointing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval was formally announced by Steve Reed, the country’s housing minister. In a statement, he said that “all material considerations were taken into account when making this decision. The decision is now final unless it is successfully challenged in court.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A legal fight appears likely, since opposition to the embassy has been building for several years. Protesters have declared their anger at the prospect, including by carrying signs and banners that read “CCP is Watching You. Stop the Mega Embassy!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approval of the project was initially denied in 2022 by the borough council of Tower Hamlets, where the site is located. China later resubmitted the project for approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement could be a diplomatic boost for the prime minister’s efforts to improve relations with China ahead of his first trip to the country while in office, which is expected to take place in the coming weeks. Mr. Starmer has said he wants to increase investment opportunities with China after years of icy relations between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also comes at a time when Britain, along with other European nations, is under extraordinary pressure from President Trump to submit to his desire to acquire Greenland, putting the trans-Atlantic alliance under strain.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 10:31:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Church Leaders Say Over 160 Were Kidnapped in Nigeria, but Officials Deny It</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/nigeria-christian-church-kidnapping.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/newsgraphics/images/icons/defaultPromoCrop.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Church leaders in northern Nigeria said at least 163 members of evangelical congregations were kidnapped after gunmen burst into Sunday morning services in Kaduna State, but government and security officials are disputing the claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to two leaders of Christian groups in the region, bandits arrived by motorcycle and stormed 9 a.m. services at three churches in the community of Kurmin Wali, kidnapping scores of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of the groups sent representatives to Kurmin Wali to investigate after hearing about kidnappings on Sunday, but the representatives were turned away by a convoy of military and local government vehicles blocking the road, according to the Rev. John Joseph Hayab, the vice chairman of the Christian Association of Northern Nigeria, and Reuben Buhari, a spokesman for Christian Solidarity Worldwide Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Buhari said that his group later spoke by phone to church members who described bandits rounding up congregants and forcing them into the bush. He said that the gunmen later released older women and young children and that another 11 people escaped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on Monday, local and security officials emerged from a meeting at Kaduna State government offices and told reporters that they had investigated the kidnapping claims and found them to be false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The officials dismissed the reports of kidnappings as fear-mongering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nigeria has been plagued by a security crisis in recent years that often plays out in rural areas where people live hand-to-mouth. Security has become a highly politicized issue in certain parts of the country amid growing disputes over whether Christians are being attacked for their faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nigerians of all faiths have suffered, and there is no clear evidence that Christians are attacked more frequently than Muslims, the other main religious group in the country. On Christmas Day, the U.S. launched missile strikes on northwestern Nigeria to fight what President Trump has called a “Christian genocide” led by Islamist terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dauda Madaki, the chairman of the regional government in the area, said that he had sent police and other security forces to Kurmin Wali but that they had found “no evidence of the attack.” He said two village officials from Kurmin Wali had also disputed the incident. Those officials could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alhaji Muhammad Rabiu, the police commissioner in Kaduna State, also denied the kidnapping and challenged anyone to list the names of the kidnapped victims and other particulars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of Christian Solidarity Worldwide Nigeria, one of the groups that raised the alarm about the recent kidnappings, showed The New York Times a preliminary list of names that they said they would release to the public after they had finalized it and alerted family members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kurmin Wali has been a hot spot for attacks in recent months, according to Christian Solidarity Worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than two weeks ago, the group said, 21 residents of the village were abducted and freed in exchange for a ransom totaling about $5,000. Many nearby residents have abandoned their homes for safer areas because of a flurry of kidnappings in recent years, the group said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nigeria’s military stepped up security in some parts of the country after militants stormed St. Mary’s Catholic School in Papiri, in the northwest, in November. Twelve staff members and 253 children were abducted, although some were released. Schools in some parts of Nigeria that had been shut for weeks afterward reopened this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rev. Yunusa Sabo Nmadu, a leader of Christian Solidarity Worldwide Nigeria, applauded the recent military buildup in some parts of northern Nigeria but said more must be done to stop kidnappers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With each abduction, locals become increasingly impoverished and sink deeper into debt as they continue to pay ransoms,” he said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/nigeria-christian-church-kidnapping.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:48:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Islamic State Claims Deadly Attack on Chinese Restaurant in Afghanistan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/isis-kabul-bomb-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-afghanistan-isis-ztfw/20int-afghanistan-isis-ztfw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bombing claimed by the Islamic State wing in Afghanistan killed at least seven people and wounded more than a dozen in a Chinese restaurant in Kabul on Monday, officials said, in a sign of the group’s persistent threat despite the Afghan government’s claim to have vanquished it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blast ripped through a noodle restaurant on a busy street of central Kabul filled with shops selling flowers, antiquities and rugs on Monday afternoon. A single attacker detonated his explosive vest 30 minutes after entering the restaurant, according to a statement released by the Islamic State through its media wing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Afghan Interior Ministry, Abdul Mateen Qani, told The New York Times that seven people had been killed, including a Chinese citizen. He also said that the assault had been carried out by a single attacker from the Islamic State Khorasan Province, or ISIS-K, the group’s Afghanistan affiliate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike most Western countries, China has maintained sustained diplomatic ties with the Taliban administration in Afghanistan. In 2023, China became the first country to appoint an ambassador in Afghanistan since the Taliban took power in 2021, and has signed mining contracts to tap into vast Afghan oil and mineral reserves. China has also vowed to include Afghanistan in the Belt and Road Initiative, its trillion-dollar global infrastructure project. Its foreign minister, Wang Yi, even visited Kabul last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But China has grown increasingly wary about potential insecurity in Afghanistan, even though the government has control of large swaths of the country and has tried to woo foreign investors back. China now advises its citizens against traveling to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ISIS-K said it has targeted Chinese citizens in retaliation for Beijing’s oppression of Uyghurs, a Muslim ethnic minority in China, and has criticized the Afghan government’s dealings with Beijing. In 2022, its militants injured at least five Chinese citizens in an attack on a hotel popular with Chinese visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ISIS-K sees the Taliban-China relationship as one of the biggest betrayals of a jihadist group,” Iftikhar Firdous, the executive director of the research platform Khorasan Diary, said about the partnerships made by the Taliban since the group took over Afghanistan in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Firdous, said the attacks pointed to “a growing anti-Chinese jihadist nexus in the region, of which ISIS-K is the primary benefactor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has urged the Taliban government to engage in “more visible and verifiable actions to dismantle and eliminate all terrorist organizations based in Afghanistan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“China strongly condemns and firmly opposes all forms of terrorism and supports Afghanistan and regional countries in jointly combating all forms of terrorist violence,” Guo Jiakun, a spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, said at a news briefing on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces heavily guarded the area around the Chinese noodle restaurant on Tuesday, as residents were still cleaning broken glass littering the street. Businesses had reopened, with employees in flower shops making bouquets and blood stains still visible on the windows of nearby boutiques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency, an Italian nonprofit medical group operating in Kabul, said it had received 20 people at its surgical center on Monday, including seven who were dead on arrival. A child was among the dead, Emergency’s country director, Dejan Panic, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Stevenson contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/isis-kabul-bomb-china.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 12:15:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Four Shark Attacks in 48 Hours, Australia Shuts Dozens of Beaches</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/australia-sydney-shark-attacks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-oz-sharks-zkvb/20int-oz-sharks-zkvb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of beaches in eastern Australia were closed on Tuesday, after four shark attacks in a span of 48 hours, a spree that the head of a lifeguard group described as unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, a surfer was knocked off his board by a shark near Point Plomer Beach, about 200 miles north of Sydney. He was briefly hospitalized with minor injuries, local news media reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That episode followed a spate of attacks off the coastline of Sydney, Australia’s largest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, a 27-year-old surfer’s leg was bitten by a shark in waters off Manly Beach. Fellow beachgoers administered first aid before the surfer was taken to the hospital with what the police described as “life-changing injuries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same day, and just a few miles away, an 11-year-old boy escaped injury after a shark bit his surfboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth episode occurred on Sunday afternoon, when a shark bit the legs of a boy who was swimming with friends in Sydney’s east. The authorities have said that the boy, who is believed to be 12 or 13 years old, was “fighting for his life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a dozen beaches in northern Sydney, including Manly and Palm Beach, will be closed on Tuesday and Wednesday, the local authorities said. Further north, near Point Plomer Beach, the authorities have closed several beaches for 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Pearce, the chief executive of the volunteer lifeguard organization Surf Life Saving New South Wales, called the number of attacks “unprecedented” and urged people to avoid swimming at northern Sydney beaches for the next 48 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists say the attacks in Sydney were most likely the work of bull sharks — a species that is considered among the most dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weather conditions in the past week have been conducive to an increased shark presence off Sydney’s shores, Leonardo Guida, a shark scientist with the Australian Marine Conservation Society said. Ocean temperatures have been warmer-than-average and runoff from heavy rainfall has brought prey into the ocean water for sharks to feast on, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other sharks, bull sharks have the ability to swim in fresh and salt water, allowing them to hunt in a range of marine environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shark attacks are rare in Australia but this week’s episodes come after a deadly attack in Sydney’s northern beaches in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Many are still grieving the loss of Mercury Psillakis and we are all shocked this can have happened again so soon on our beaches,” Sue Heins, the mayor of the Northern Beaches Council, said in a statement Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia has done more than perhaps any other country to try to mitigate shark attacks. It is one of the a few countries to use shark nets, a contentious form of beach protection, as well as noninvasive measures such as drone monitoring and smart drumlines — floating traps with hooks that snare sharks and alert officials so they can be released.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/australia-sydney-shark-attacks.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 22:12:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Has France’s President Finally Lost His Personal Touch With Trump?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/trump-macron-relationship-texts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-france-assess01-photo-qblw/20int-france-assess01-photo-qblw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When President Trump threatened President Emmanuel Macron of France on Monday with tariffs and dismissed him as irrelevant, it was the latest flare-up in a topsy-turvy relationship that has blown hot and cold for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since first taking power within months of each other in 2017, the two have had frequent disagreements — exacerbated, from Mr. Trump’s side, by insults, threats and public derision. Generally, Mr. Macron managed to temper those arguments, and Mr. Trump’s most impulsive moves, through moments of friendship and expressions of admiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Mr. Trump’s threats to impose new tariffs on Champagne and other French exports have raised questions about whether that approach has finally run out of road. As Mr. Trump threatens to invade Greenland, the territory of a NATO ally, it is unclear whether Mr. Macron’s tactic of charming him will continue to defuse their biggest disagreements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have to stop with the charm,” Philippe Aghion, a French economist who was awarded the Nobel Prize last year, told the French television station BFM from Davos, Switzerland, on Tuesday. “The president of the republic put too much belief in charm, thinking it would work. No. That doesn’t pay off.” He called on European leaders to “do whatever it takes” to oppose Trump’s bid to acquire Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper, Mr. Macron and Mr. Trump always seemed destined to clash, given their opposing views on trade, immigration and climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet they continued to communicate. They share at least two common traits: Both really like to talk, and both have built foreign policies underpinned by direct, personal relationships with other leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Trump’s first presidential visit to Paris in 2017, the two leaders held hands, kissed cheeks and lavished praise on one another. A year later, when Mr. Macron made a state visit to the White House, Mr. Trump gingerly brushed his shoulder and announced, “I like him a lot.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next year, however, he took Mr. Macron to task for his criticism of Mr. Trump’s leadership of NATO, calling it “very insulting” and “very, very nasty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron held his ground. “My statement created some reactions,” he said. “I do stand by it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, Mr. Macron’s strategy in dealing with Mr. Trump’s emotional outbursts and fickle positions has been to remain friendly but firm, while pushing for stronger European independence and defending Europe’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Trump’s second, more tumultuous term began, Mr. Macron has doubled down on that strategy, even as Mr. Trump has increased his threats and personal derision, interlaced with the odd expression of affection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last June, when Mr. Macron said Mr. Trump had left a G7 summit early to work on an Iran-Israel cease-fire, the American president lashed out on social media, saying, “Whether purposely or not, Emmanuel always gets it wrong.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Macron was working in July on a campaign to recognize Palestinian statehood at a United Nations summit, and to bring other countries onboard, Mr. Trump told reporters in Washington that “what he says doesn’t matter.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s a good guy, I like him, but that statement doesn’t carry weight,” Mr. Trump said of Mr. Macron.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, French diplomats have said that the two men speak on the phone regularly, as often as every other day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their familiarity was on display in September, when Mr. Macron was in New York for the United Nations summit. One night, leaving the session, he and his team got caught in a motorcade. After Mr. Macron couldn’t convince a police officer to let him through, he pulled out his phone and called Mr. Trump. The president answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Guess what?” Mr. Macron told him, chuckling. “I am waiting the street because everything is frozen for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Mr. Trump confirmed — perhaps unwittingly — the two men’s constant, if conflicted, relationship by posting private text exchanges with Mr. Macron on Truth Social. The French president used them to celebrate their alignment on Syria and Iran, but he also wrote: “I don’t understand what you are doing in Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he invited Mr. Trump to Paris, for a meal and a meeting with other European leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us have a dinner together in Paris together on Thursday before you go back,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Castelain contributed reporting from Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/trump-macron-relationship-texts.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:20:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Chinese Island Where Dreams of Real Estate Glory Never Die</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/china-ocean-flower-island-real-estate.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/20int-china-fantasy-island-83602-cover/20int-china-fantasy-island-83602-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by Dubai and bloated by the outsize ambitions of a disgraced Chinese property developer, Ocean Flower Island, a cluster of man-made islets in the South China Sea, flopped as a business. But it still dazzles as a breathtaking fiesta of fantasy and folly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hugely expensive, partially completed project — a gigantic shopping mall without shops, a theme park without visitors, dozens of abandoned high-rise housing blocks and artificial beaches too dangerous to swim — helps explain why China’s yearslong real estate crisis never really seems to end. There is so much money and so much hope entangled in the wreckage that it is too big to clear away quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This place is a dead zone,” said Zhou Qingbin, a visitor from the nearby coastal city of Danzhou. The municipal government of Danzhou now controls much of Ocean Flower Island and is struggling to figure out what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was built by Evergrande, a Chinese real estate developer that collapsed under more than $300 billion of debt in 2021. Evergrande’s implosion and the troubles of other big property developers have shattered confidence in real estate, once an important driver of China’s economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New home sales have dropped to their lowest level in more than 15 years, according to figures released by the statistics bureau in Beijing on Monday. The sector has become such a headache that the Chinese authorities recently began censoring pessimistic online posts about the property market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, the Danzhou government seems to be pressing on with Evergrande’s original concept. It was intended as a Chinese version of Dubai’s Palm Island Jumeirah — only bigger. Evergrande sank around $12 billion, most of it borrowed, into what was supposed to be China’s biggest built-from-scratch entertainment, conference and shopping destination, with the islets forming the petals of a flower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That investment, though huge, fell short of the $23 billion the company said it needed to build apartments to house up to 200,000 people. That has left Ocean Flower Island in limbo. Before its collapse, Evergrande said it had completed 60,000 apartments and handed them over to buyers. Other buildings, however, never rose beyond their concrete foundations, which, flooded by rainwater, have become fishing holes. Thirty-nine high-rise apartment blocks that were nearly finished but never sold are marooned on a wasteland of rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole project was the brainchild of Xu Jiayin, Evergrande’s founder and former chairman, who was once China’s richest man and is now in jail. A gushing account by Evergrande said Mr. Xu came up with the idea for Ocean Flower Island during a 2011 vacation in Singapore. Sequestered in his room, the company said, he sketched out designs for an artificial archipelago in the shape of a bougainvillea and “meticulously oversaw every detail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he did not appear to have nailed down how the project would make enough money to build the fake islands and pay back a growing pile of debt to Chinese and foreign lenders. Evergrande also needed to persuade officials in China’s southern province of Hainan to sign off on a venture that violated environmental protection and other laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang Qi, the former mayor and Communist Party chief of Danzhou, who approved Ocean Flower Island, was convicted of corruption in 2020 and sentenced to life in prison. Other local officials have also been convicted on various corruption charges, including the former governor and party secretary of Hainan, Luo Baoming, who was jailed for 15 years in December for taking around $16 million in bribes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From its inception, Ocean Flower Island was driven by the same idea that drove much of China’s frenzy of construction during a decades-long economic boom: Build it and they will come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a country with 1.4 billion people and expectations of ever-rising incomes, this was for years a safe bet, until it wasn’t. In 2021, Beijing, worried by out-of-control lending, issued a directive restricting access to loans by property developers. Credit from banks, the biggest of which are controlled by the state, dried up. Evergrande seized up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danzhou government is trying to keep the project alive. It pitches Ocean Flower Island to Chinese vacationers and would-be home-buyers as a “unique lifestyle concept.” There are no reliable estimates of the current population, beyond the thousands of people who initially purchased properties — a fraction of early projections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Palm Island in Dubai, where the grand villas were snapped up by celebrities, soccer stars and foreign officials looking for a sunny sanctuary, Ocean Flower Island drew mostly retirees from northern China looking for a warm place to winter. The main street in the residential area is lined with restaurants offering northern specialties like steamed buns and hot pot, as well as geriatric health care services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang Qun, 70, a retiree from the province of Heilongjiang, said that when he bought his apartment five years ago there were crowds of people at the Evergrande office clamoring to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the office is littered with old brochures and property contracts and is staffed with government-supervised clerks responsible for sorting out paperwork for properties purchased years ago. If Mr. Zhang sold his apartment now, he would lose half his investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other traces of Evergrande are vending machines stocked with dusty bottles of “Evergrande Spring” mineral water. Mr. Xu, Evergrande’s former chairman, vanished from public view in 2021. A report last March by the Supreme People’s Procuratorate said that he had been prosecuted for crimes including financial fraud and disorderly financial management. It did not say whether he had been convicted or where he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A lot of people lost money because of Evergrande, and are angry,” said Li Yanbo, a real estate agent on Ocean Flower Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who bought apartments early made big profits, at least on paper, as the price per square yard more than tripled between 2015 and a 2021 peak. Those who arrived late lost their shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Evergrande, Mr. Li added, was not all bad: “Some people think they were cheated, but there are others who would never have had a chance to get an apartment if not for Evergrande.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Property prices on Ocean Flower Island, he added, have stabilized somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every city in China has unfinished tower blocks left stranded by Evergrande’s demise. But probably nowhere has Mr. Xu’s hubris left such a high concentration of excess as in Ocean Flower Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help accommodate what was supposed to be a flood of tourists, Evergrande built The Castle, a hotel with 5,100 rooms. Its two outdoor swimming pools have been drained of water, and the hotel has stayed afloat by catering to budget travelers on peak-season package tours. For much of the year, it is largely empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of wind whistles through the broken windows of luxury coastal villas fit for Russian oligarchs. Some have been taken over by laborers who sleep on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shopping streets featuring Italian, German, Chinese and other styles of architectures look like deserted movie sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plaza flanked by eight fake churches, including a red brick structure resembling a cathedral, is meant as an Instagram-able setting for wedding photos. The churches are now used as the backdrop for a sound and light show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ocean Flower Island still has believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wang Xian, a retired banker from the northern province of Hebei, acknowledged that Evergrande’s founder “went too far and thought he could do anything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with around 300 million Chinese people retiring over the next decade, he noted, many will want to find a sunny and safe place to live. “If just 1 percent come here,” he said, “this place will be a big success.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Li You contributed research from Shanghai.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/china-ocean-flower-island-real-estate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:09:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Shifts Away From Kurdish-Led Forces in Fight Against ISIS</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/syria-isis-camp-al-hol-kurds.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-syria-isis-photo-zkpb/20int-syria-isis-photo-zkpb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. special envoy to Syria said on Tuesday that Washington no longer needed to rely on Kurdish-led forces as its primary partner to fight the Islamic State terrorist group in Syria because the government was ready to take over security duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments by the envoy, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., appeared to be a significant shift in U.S. policy toward the Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F. — Washington’s primary ally in Syria over the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today, the situation has fundamentally changed,” Mr. Barrack said in a post on X. He went on, “The original purpose of the SDF as the primary anti-ISIS force on the ground has largely expired, as Damascus is now both willing and positioned to take over security responsibilities, including control of ISIS detention facilities and camps.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. suffered a series of stunning setbacks over the past two weeks in battles with government forces over control of northeastern Syria. Severely weakened after the loss of territory and strategic assets such as oil fields and dams, it agreed on Sunday to merge its forces into the Syria military and to relinquish territory and infrastructure it had governed for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Barrack has been leading American efforts to calm days of violence in northeastern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement on Sunday was intended to end weeks of deadly clashes between the two sides. It would have had the S.D.F. merge into the national military and hand over control of security infrastructure, including prisons holding Islamic State detainees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But clashes and violence in recent days have made the agreement look increasingly tenuous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reham Mourshed and Raja Abdulrahim contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/syria-isis-camp-al-hol-kurds.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:11:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fresh Russian Strikes Cut Heat to Thousands in Ukraine’s Freezing Capital</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/ukraine-russia-kyiv-heat-cold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-ukraine-heat-02-gkqc/20int-ukraine-heat-02-gkqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russian strikes left thousands of apartment buildings in Ukraine’s capital without heat in subfreezing temperatures on Tuesday, the latest assault in a campaign that the Ukrainian authorities say is aimed at breaking the country’s morale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine said that Russia had fired “a significant number” of ballistic and cruise missiles, along with over 300 attack drones, across the country overnight. The emergency services were engaged in a number of regions, he said in a statement, adding that “the most difficult situation for now is in Kyiv,” the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 5,600 high-rise buildings there were without heat on Tuesday, according to the city’s mayor, Vitali Klitschko. He noted that most of those buildings had only just had their heat restored after the last large-scale attack on Kyiv’s infrastructure on Jan. 8, and he said that one side of the city was without water on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With temperatures at around 6 degrees Fahrenheit, or minus 14 Celsius, the authorities found themselves again scrambling to restore services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kyiv, home to about three million people, has been among the Ukrainian cities hardest hit by Russia’s repeated attacks on energy infrastructure. Ukrainian officials say the strikes weaponize winter — aiming to freeze the country into submission to force it to accept concessions in peace talks brokered by the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation has significantly deteriorated in recent weeks, as Russia has intensified the attacks. Many people in the capital have electricity for just a few hours a day. Backup batteries have run low. Without water or heat in the Parliament building, lawmakers were ordered to work remotely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities recently moved to close schools until February amid the crisis. They also have deployed mobile kitchens to provide hot meals and set up tents around the capital where residents can get warm and charge their devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration’s efforts to broker an end to the war in Ukraine have in recent days seemingly taken a back seat to another crisis: Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As European leaders rushed to respond to President Trump’s rapidly escalating campaign to acquire Greenland, Ukrainian officials urged allies to maintain support and for the world not to look away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky on Tuesday appealed for more air defenses from partners and said “it is important that the world does not remain silent” about the overnight Russian strikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ukraine’s foreign minister, Andriy Sybiha, said that the “barbaric strike this morning is a wake-up call to world leaders gathering in Davos: support for the Ukrainian people is urgent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There will be no peace in Europe without a lasting peace for Ukraine,” he wrote on X. “We need urgent additional energy assistance, air defense and interceptors, as well as sanctions pressure on Moscow.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/ukraine-russia-kyiv-heat-cold.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:01:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Venezuelan Political Prisoner Finally Comes Home</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/venezuela-prisoner-release.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/world/00Int-Venezuela-Prisoner-promo/00Int-Venezuela-Prisoner-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year behind bars as a political prisoner under the Maduro regime in Venezuela, one of the first things that Ángel Godoy did was apologize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freed last Wednesday, Mr. Godoy, a political activist and columnist, returned to his home in Los Teques, 40 minutes outside the capital, Caracas, where his son showed him a photo of his high school graduation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m sorry I wasn’t there,” Mr. Godoy whispered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now you are,” his son, Miguelangel Godoy Briceño, replied. “And I need you to help me study for university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy, 52, walked along the walls of his apartment and touched the family photos to confirm that this was home. In the living room, there was a poster of his face that his wife had used as a backdrop for every video she recorded about her husband’s detention on Jan. 8, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He took a marker and wrote across it in big letters: RELEASED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy and his family had been waiting for this moment for 371 days, but their hopes grew earlier this month after President Nicolás Maduro was seized by U.S. forces in Caracas and the Venezuelan government announced that it would start freeing “an important number” of political prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy is one of the lucky ones. To date, only 143 of Venezuela’s estimated nearly 900 political prisoners have been released, according to a leading human rights group, Foro Penal. And much of the Maduro government’s machinery of repression remains largely intact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was that very apparatus that snatched Mr. Godoy as he was getting home a year ago and accused him of terrorism, and incitement of armed actions and hatred. He has denied the charges, which are commonly brought against political prisoners in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy said masked men had jumped out of an unmarked van with tinted windows and took him away. Although the men weren’t wearing official insignia, Mr. Godoy shouted to his neighbors that it was the country’s intelligence agency, which has been accused of numerous human rights violations, and asked them to tell his wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next 25 days, his family members did not hear from him. They did not see him for 96 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy was held at several prisons, including El Helicoide, the infamous sprawling building in Caracas that was built as the world’s first drive-through shopping mall but instead became a torture center, human rights groups say. He called his judicial process and his over-the-phone arraignment “shameful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s behind bars,” his wife, Adriana Briceño, said. “But so are we as a family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in prison, Mr. Godoy and his wife of 19 years kept their hope alive through their love for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Ms. Briceño used candy to send messages, writing words of encouragement or notes about domestic news inside the wrappers. Mr. Godoy wrote back on tiny folded scraps of paper, smuggled out in the dirty laundry his wife collected on visiting days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love you more than life itself,” he wrote in one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy kept all of the candy wrappers. But when he was transferred to another prison, everything stayed in his old cell. To his wife’s surprise, the guards gave all of those mementos to her when she retrieved his belongings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day Mr. Godoy was freed, his wife was given the news just as she entered the prison for a visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Godoy heard his name called for release, “all hell broke loose,” he said. Fellow prisoners hugged him. “I said, ‘My God,’ he recalled. “I couldn’t believe it. Everyone was shouting: ‘Freedom, freedom, freedom!’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside, Mr. Godoy saw a country marked by the U.S. strikes. Riding home with his wife and brother-in-law, he told them about his time behind bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us not repeat this darkness,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy’s neighbors greeted him with embraces and tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside Mr. Godoy’s apartment were reminders of an interrupted life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dining room table remained set with Christmas decorations. In the freezer was a traditional Christmas corn tamale that his wife had set aside for him — just in case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the objects had come from the prison, among them a craggy teddy bear made by other prisoners using scraps of fabric from a mattress in Mr. Godoy’s cell, a wedding anniversary gift for his wife. There was also a cloth ball covered in messages for his son. To get the ball out of prison through his wife, Mr. Godoy negotiated with the warden and allowed a thorough inspection of every word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one corner of the family’s apartment sat a worn plastic table. Mr. Godoy used the table in his cell, and his family recovered it after his transfer to another prison. On its surface he had written a verse from the Bible: “Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though Mr. Godoy is free, the Venezuelan authorities maintain control over him. He is prohibited from leaving the country and must appear in court every 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that first afternoon out of prison, Mr. Godoy sat down at the very table his wife had kept decorated. And he ate the very foods she had saved for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was indeed home.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/venezuela-prisoner-release.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Syria’s Government, Kurdish Deal Is a Big Win on Shaky Ground</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/syria-fighting-kurdish-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20syria-assess-01-gjwp/20syria-assess-01-gjwp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria won nearly every concession he had pushed for in the deal that he struck on Sunday with the Kurdish-led militia that had controlled much of the country’s northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only a day later, the fragility of the deal was exposed as violence erupted in the northeast, posing a major test for Mr. al-Sharaa as his government tries to secure control over the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chaos highlighted the pitfalls of Mr. al-Sharaa’s attempt to bring all Syrian territory under his government's control after nearly 14 years of civil war that left the country deeply fractured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past year, Mr. al-Sharaa had been caught in protracted discussions with Kurdish leaders over the terms for joining his new government. The Kurds had significant bargaining chips, including the longtime backing of the United States and control of the country’s gas and oil fields. And many Syrians saw the talks as a harbinger of much larger questions about inclusion of minorities in government and the sharing of political power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How willing would Mr. al-Sharaa be to decentralize power in his government? And how long would he be willing to engage in negotiations with groups demanding some autonomy before moving those decisions to the battlefield?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, this month, Mr. al-Sharaa’s patience seemed to have run out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After months of stalled negotiations with the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., the government made a military push into Kurdish-held territory last week. Within days, those forces had reached the outskirts of Raqqa — the largest city administered by the Kurdish authorities — after the Kurds suffered a series of battlefield defeats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday, the leader of the S.D.F., Mazloum Abdi, agreed to a cease-fire deal with Mr. al-Sharaa that looked like a surrender, analysts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. lost nearly all of the concessions the Syrian government had offered during previous rounds of negotiations. After previously winning its major sticking point — joining the Syrian military in its own distinct battalions — it now appears that its members will join as individuals. The S.D.F. also lost control over Syria’s gas and oil fields, its main leverage in negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, Syrian leaders marginalized Kurdish citizens, curbing their rights and stripping many of their citizenship. The Kurds aligned with the United States, with both fighting Islamic State in the northeast. Even after the Islamic State was defeated in Syria, Kurdish leaders believed the Americans would continue to support them as Mr. al-Sharaa’s government took power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they were dealt a brutal blow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, the U.S. special envoy to Syria, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., announced that the United States had effectively traded the S.D.F. as a counterterrorism partner for Mr. al-Sharaa’s government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The original purpose of the SDF as the primary anti-ISIS force on the ground has largely expired, as Damascus is now both willing and positioned to take over security responsibilities,” Mr. Barrack said in a post on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kurdish leaders have loudly criticized Mr. al-Sharaa’s government for concentrating power in the hands of a small group of loyalists from his former rebel days and for not being inclusive enough of minorities in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, Kurdish leaders accused government forces of violating the cease-fire and reiterated calls for Mr. al-Sharaa to decentralize his authority in what appeared to be a last-ditch effort to claw back some of the concessions they had previously won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, Islamic State fighters escaped from prisons and family members from a camp guarded by Kurdish forces as they withdrew from their posts, and Syrian and Kurdish officials said that talks about carrying out their deal were breaking down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement itself sent a stark message to other Syrian minorities, including the Druse militias that currently control the southern province of Sweida and the Alawites on the coast. Calls have come from within both groups for greater autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a significant territorial, military and political win” for Mr. al-Sharaa, said Dareen Khalifa, a senior adviser at the International Crisis Group. “The political message now is that it’s only a matter of time for everyone else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa has pledged that his government will protect the rights of all minorities — something that the United States and others in the international community have said they will monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an overture to Syrian Kurds on Friday, he issued a decree recognizing Kurdish as a national language alongside Arabic, and adopting Nowruz, the Persian New Year, widely celebrated by Kurds, as an official holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looming over the deal was the United States, a longtime ally of the S.D.F. and partner in its fight to oust the Islamic State from northeastern Syria since 2015. Over the past year, the tensions between the government and the S.D.F. had put the United States in a difficult position as it tried to balance between its two Syrian partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the United States has maintained its support for Kurdish forces since the Assad dictatorship collapsed in late 2024, the Trump administration has also embraced Mr. al-Sharaa. In November, President Trump hosted the Syrian leader, who was formerly designated a terrorist by the United States for his former ties to Al Qaeda at the White House. He waived punishing sanctions on Syria that had devastated its economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. appeared to have been banking on its American allies as a bulwark against exactly the kind of military push that the Syrian government made last week, a major miscalculation and not the first time Washington failed to come to the force’s aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While American officials intervened to broker the cease-fire deal, the Kurds got neither the military support they had hoped for nor even an international outcry over the government’s military attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Kurds have equated the U.S. response with the total abandonment of their longtime ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States “left the Kurds, their allies, between the fists of ISIS and Al Qaeda,” said Siyamend Ali, a spokesman for the S.D.F., referring to Mr. al-Sharaa’s previous affiliation with Al Qaeda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. approach to the clashes between the S.D.F. and the government also created divisions in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Syrian government made its lightning advance into Kurdish territory, Senator Lindsey Graham of South Carolina, a Trump ally, threatened to call for sanctions to be reinstated on Mr. al-Sharaa’s government. He repeated the threat on Monday as Kurdish forces claimed that armed groups affiliated with the government had attacked prisons it controlled in the northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Syrian government forces continue to advance in the north toward Raqqa, I will push for reimposing Caesar Act sanctions on steroids,” he wrote in a post on X, referring to punitive sanctions that Congress repealed last month. He added, “If you want a conflict with the U.S. Senate and to do permanent damage to the U.S.-Syria relationship — keep going.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a threat that Mr. al-Sharaa, who has bet that reviving the country’s economy will shore up support for his government, cannot ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s seizure of the oil and gas fields previously under S.D.F. control is another major win that could offer the government an economic lifeline — and another card to play to further shore up support with the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the clashes that erupted as government forces sought to take control over security infrastructure in the northeast — as agreed upon in Sunday’s deal — highlighted the fragility of the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. al-Sharaa met with the leader of the S.D.F. in Damascus on Monday, the S.D.F. claimed that their discussions with the government about putting the new deal in place had broken down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The situation has now deteriorated to an alarming degree,” Adulkarim Omar, a representative of the S.D.F.’s political arm, said in a statement on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F.’s near-total capitulation also stoked fears that more hard-line elements within the Kurdish forces might splinter and become spoilers to peace in the northeast. Others also worried that the way in which the Syrian government might try to govern the region could unleash a new host of problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. al-Sharaa has rejected his Islamist roots, many Syrians remain to be convinced that he will share power with his former opponents and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For much of the past year, the government’s model for exerting control has been to install trusted allies from its rebel coalition in cities across the country. But that approach has largely backfired, leading to poor governance, according to Lara Nelson, policy director at ETANA Syria, a Syrian research group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The question now is around the implementation of governance,” Ms. Nelson said. “It has to be governed by the local people who have those organic links to their areas; otherwise it will be unsustainable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hwaida Saad and Raja Abdulrahim contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/syria-fighting-kurdish-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:53:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Heckles Europe Before Heading to Davos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/davos-trump-europe.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-mocking-europe-01-lczq/20int-mocking-europe-01-lczq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump and his entourage will be in Europe this week. And they are showing their contempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, already hobnobbing with elites at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, had a sharp retort when reporters asked him about European leaders’ efforts to block Mr. Trump from seizing Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I imagine they will form the dreaded European working group,” Mr. Bessent said, calling it their “most forceful weapon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no secret that the president and his aides view Europe as a weak, ineffectual collection of nations dominated by liberal leaders and tangled in bureaucracy. His administration’s official national security strategy, released last month, said Europe had lost its “civilizational self-confidence” amid a “failed focus on regulatory suffocation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But rarely has the mocking been so overt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on Tuesday morning, as Europe’s leaders continued to wring their hands over the president’s latest threats to Greenland, Mr. Trump posted an apparently A.I.-generated meme that showed him hoisting an American flag while standing on the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Greenland. U.S. Territory. Est. 2026,” the meme read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had not even arrived in Switzerland yet. But as he prepared to speak there on Wednesday, he continued to heap dismissive scorn on the leaders he was about to greet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reporters told Mr. Trump that President Emmanuel Macron of France was not going to join the American-led “Board of Peace” overseeing Gaza, Mr. Trump waved aside Mr. Macron’s opinions as irrelevant, saying he would be “out of office in a few months.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ll put a 200 percent tariff on his wines and Champagnes, and he’ll join, but he doesn’t have to join,” the president said, flexing the power of the American market and underscoring France’s vulnerability to his whims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also posted flattering messages from Mr. Macron and Mark Rutte, the Secretary General of NATO, on Truth Social — showing just how much European leaders are heaping praise on Mr. Trump in what appears to be an attempt to keep him engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will use my media engagements in Davos to highlight your work,” Mr. Rutte wrote in the message that Mr. Trump shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us try to build great things,” Mr. Macron said, though he also noted: “I do not understand what you are doing on Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also targeted Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain, giving him his signature all-caps treatment as he complained that the United Kingdom had decided to give up sovereignty of Diego Garcia and the other Chagos Islands, while retaining control of a U.K.- and U.S.-operated military base there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, the United Kingdom relinquished control of the islands, a remote archipelago it had held since the colonial era, to Mauritius. At the time, Secretary of State Marco Rubio praised the deal, which came after years of negotiations, and after a court found that Britain had acted unlawfully by detaching the archipelago from Mauritius in 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our ‘brilliant’ NATO Ally, the United Kingdom, is currently planning to give away the Island of Diego Garcia,” the president wrote on his social media site, accusing Britain of doing so “FOR NO REASON WHATSOEVER.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added that international powers “only recognize STRENGTH” and that giving away the island was an “act of GREAT STUPIDITY.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s heckling has troubled European leaders, many of whom are hoping to communicate with him on the sidelines of the Davos meetings. Leaders from across the 27-nation European Union will also gather in Brussels on Thursday evening to discuss how to respond to his latest threats on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the United States looks like a more and more volatile ally — and a hugely unpredictable one — European leaders are saying the continent must move away from its tight ties to America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Union’s executive arm, said during a speech at Davos on Tuesday morning that the old way of doing things was over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nostalgia will not bring back the old order,” she said, arguing against “playing for time — and hoping for things to revert soon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added, “If this change is permanent, then Europe must change permanently too.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But so far, Europe has mainly been trying to accommodate Mr. Trump and keep him at the table — worried that he’ll pull back needed American support from NATO or Ukraine — even as he mocks them as weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gavin Newsom, the Democratic governor of California, called global leaders “pathetic” on Tuesday for failing to stand up to Mr. Trump, saying that Europeans needed to have a “backbone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I should have brought a bunch of kneepads for all the world leaders,” he told reporters in Davos. “I mean, handing out crowns — I mean, this is pathetic — the Nobel Prizes that are being given away. It’s just pathetic.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/davos-trump-europe.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:32:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Spain Mourns Train Crash Victims, Investigators Focus on Track</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-train-crash-track-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-spain-train-bhqm/20int-spain-train-bhqm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spanish authorities were struggling on Tuesday to identify those killed in a collision between two high-speed trains that left at least 41 people dead on Sunday, as investigators focused on whether a problem with the track may have caused it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crash, Spain’s worst railway disaster since 2013, has prompted days of national mourning and a rare call for political unity. But it has also shaken a country that depends on, and takes great pride in, its high-speed rail system, the largest in Europe and the second largest in the world, behind only China’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a day after the crash in Adamuz, a town in southern Spain near the city of Córdoba, 23 autopsies had been completed, but only five bodies had been definitively identified with fingerprint matches, according to data coordinated by Spain’s Interior Ministry. The Spanish police said they had received missing-person reports for 40 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crash occurred when a privately operated train bound for Madrid partly derailed and two of its cars fell onto the opposite track, where they were struck by an incoming train. Many Spanish news reports on Tuesday focused on a photograph, released by the Guardia Civil, of investigators examining a particular stretch of track near the disaster site. The Commission for the Investigation of Railway Accidents has said that it is examining the general condition of the track as a possible cause of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, said in a radio interview on Tuesday that there had been “an initial break” in the track, but he added that “no technician is yet able to say whether it is a cause or a consequence” of the derailment. “If the rail broke first, we would need to find out why a solid steel rail broke,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, more vivid details of the crash from surviving passengers began to emerge in the Spanish press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passengers on the Madrid-bound train recounted cars vibrating strangely, carriages lurching, suitcases tumbling and glasses sliding off tables onto the floor during the initial derailment. About 20 seconds later, around 7:45 p.m., the other train, operated by the national rail provider, Renfe, barreled into the derailed carriages. Its first two cars fell down a 12-foot embankment, a preliminary report said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Madrid-bound train, which had about 300 people aboard, continued for hundreds of meters before coming to a stop. Surviving passengers described wandering in the dark and cold through a scene strewn with corpses, as local residents rushed to help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two trains collided on Sunday in southern Spain, killing at least 40 people. Here is what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I used my quad back and forward to transport the injured,” said one resident, Gonzalo Sánchez, referring to the off-road vehicle he drove through the steep, slippery terrain. “It was the best way I could help.” He spent hours bringing rescue workers to the trains and passengers away from the wreck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One survivor, a 6-year-old girl, wandered through the dark as her parents, her brother and her cousin lay dead among the wreckage of the southbound Renfe train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mayor of Adamuz, Rafael Ángel Moreno, who was one of the first people on the scene, spoke with emotion about an “overwhelming solidarity” in his town of about 4,100 people. Despite Spain’s cantankerous political landscape, that unity seemed to extend across the country on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez, of the governing Socialist Party, made a joint appearance in Adamuz with Juanma Moreno, the president of the regional government of Andalucía, from the conservative Popular Party. “Every tragedy demands two things: unity in grief, unity in response,” Mr. Sánchez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader of the hard-right wing Vox party, Santiago Abascal, has blamed the Sánchez government for the accident, writing on social media, “Nothing works under corruption and deceit.” But the leader of the Popular Party, Alberto Núñez Feijóo, also appeared in Adamuz, recalling that he was the president of the Galicia region when a train crash there killed 80 people in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have shown that when Spain faces a major problem, it unites,” Mr. Feijóo said, adding, “We have a great country.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-train-crash-track-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 06:57:41 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>