<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:43:21 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What We Know About the Deadly High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high-speed train ran off its track and crashed into another high-speed train late Sunday in southern Spain, killing at least 21 people and injuring dozens of others, according to the local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accident is the deadliest train accident in Spainsince 2013, when 80 people died after a train veered off a curved section of track in the country’s northwest. The country has the second-longest high-speed rail network in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision on Sunday occurred at 7:45 p.m. in Adamuz, in the southern province of Córdoba. The train that derailed first was a privately-operated one that was traveling to Madrid from Málaga, on the country’s southern coast. The rear cars of that train fell into the opposite track, where it collided with an incoming train operated by Spain’s national rail company, which was bound for the southern city of Huelva, west of Seville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo, the operator of the first train, said that around 300 passengers were on board at the time of the crash. Renfe, the operator of the second train, has not said how many passengers it was carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spain’s state-owned rail infrastructure agency said in a statement that rail traffic between Madrid and several major cities in southern Andalucía — including Córdoba, Seville, Málaga and Huelva — will be suspended on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency response crews continued to search through the wreckage of the crash early Monday, with officials warning that the death toll may rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 2013 disaster, the derailment on Sunday happened on a straight portion of the track. An independent commission has been launched to investigate what caused it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, told reporters that the first train to derail was only a few years old and that the section of the track where the accident occurred had been recently renovated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accident is extremely strange,” he said. “It happened on a straightaway. All the experts we have consulted are extremely baffled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “If there had not been an oncoming train, we would not be talking about casualties of any type.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez of Spain expressed sympathy for the victims’ families on social media, saying that “the entire country stands with them in this extremely difficult moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tonight is a night of deep pain for our country,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Andalucía government has set up a medical post at the crash site for victims, while the Córdoba city government has issued an urgent appeal for doctors to help treat the injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paco Carmona, the director of Córdoba’s fire brigade, told public television that emergency crews were prioritizing assistance for victims still trapped in the two carriages most severely damaged in the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:54:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sanae Takaichi, Japan’s Prime Minister, Calls for Snap Election</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sanae Takaichi, the prime minister of Japan, called early elections just three months into her tenure.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:57:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How 40 People Died In a Train Crash in Andalucia, Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Emergency officials at the scene of the crash on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:50:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taxing the Ultrarich</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/taxing-billionaires-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-theworld-billionaires-promo/20int-theworld-billionaires-promo-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of billionaires has exploded, yet they often pay taxes at rates well below average.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/taxing-billionaires-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 20:25:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Death Toll Rises in Guatemalan Gang Riots</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-guatemala-promo/19int-guatemala-01-hbcv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A ceremony to honor eight police officers who died in attacks by gang members the day before, on Monday in Guatemala City.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 20:35:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Trump Flexes Power in White House Meetings With Zelensky and Others</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-oval-office-world-leaders.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-foreign-leaders-promo/trump-foreign-leaders-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With cameras rolling, President Trump met with more than 40 international leaders in his first year back in office.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-oval-office-world-leaders.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>With Threats to Greenland, Trump Sets America on the Road to Conquest</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-america-conquest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-assess-top2-gzfb/20dc-assess-top2-gzfb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump has declared that the only limits on his global power are “my own morality” and “my own mind.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-greenland-america-conquest.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:03:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fresh Russian Strikes Cut Heat to Thousands in Ukraine’s Freezing Capital</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/ukraine-russia-kyiv-heat-cold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-ukraine-heat-02-gkqc/20int-ukraine-heat-02-gkqc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
More than 5,600 high-rise buildings in Kyiv, the Ukrainian capital, were left without heat after the latest attacks from Russia, officials said Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/ukraine-russia-kyiv-heat-cold.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:12:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Doubles Down on Greenland Threats in Flurry of Truth Social Posts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-macron-rutte.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-trump-greenland-europe-gwmf/20int-trump-greenland-europe-gwmf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump returning to the White House early on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-macron-rutte.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:09:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Northern Lights Have Inspired Humans for Thousands of Years</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/northern-lights-aurora-inspiration-history.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-aurora-church/20xp-aurora-church-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
“Aurora Borealis,” an 1865 painting by the American landscape painter Frederic Edwin Church.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/northern-lights-aurora-inspiration-history.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:24:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Spain Mourns Train Crash Victims, Investigators Focus on Track</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-train-crash-track-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20spain-train-01-wjzb/20spain-train-01-wjzb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
More than a day after a crash on Sunday in Adamuz, a town in southern Spain, 23 autopsies had been completed, but only five bodies had been definitively identified by fingerprint.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-train-crash-track-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:04:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Approves Contentious Chinese Mega-Embassy in London</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Royal Mint Court, the site of the proposed new Chinese Embassy in London.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:04:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Church Leaders Say Over 160 Were Kidnapped in Nigeria, but Officials Deny It</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/nigeria-christian-church-kidnapping.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;Christian groups said gunmen abducted congregants during Sunday services at three churches, but security and government officials dismissed the reports as fear-mongering.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/africa/nigeria-christian-church-kidnapping.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:48:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia Passes Tighter Gun Control Laws, Weeks After Bondi Massacre</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/gun-control-buyback.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-oz-gunlaws-mqfk/20int-oz-gunlaws-mqfk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia on Tuesday passed new laws that implement a national gun buyback, limit imports of firearms and tighten background checks, swiftly adopting tougher gun control measures after a mass shooting at a Hanukkah celebration last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moves echoed Australia’s legislative response to a massacre decades ago, which made the country a model for gun control in the eyes of many. But critics said the new legislation, and another bill promising to crack down on hate speech, had been rushed and received limited scrutiny. Some have said that the push for new gun laws belied a failure by the government to address antisemitism in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guns used in the attack on Dec. 14, in which two men killed 15 people and wounded dozens of others at Bondi Beach in Sydney, were bought legally. The authorities have characterized the shooting as a terrorist attack motivated by antisemitic ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now more than four million firearms in Australia, a record, according to the authorities. Details of the gun buyback have yet to be finalized, but it is expected to be the largest since the one conducted after the 1996 mass shooting in Port Arthur, Tasmania, where a gunman killed 35 people. That buyback was announced 12 days after the shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the new laws, background checks for people applying for firearm licenses can now include an assessment by national intelligence agencies, and in some cases, the authorities will check to see whether the applicant is an Australian citizen. Only citizens will be allowed to import guns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The terrorists had hate in their hearts, but they also had high-powered rifles in their hands,” Prime Minister Anthony Albanese told Parliament before the vote on Tuesday. “We’re taking action on both — tackling antisemitism, tackling hate, and getting dangerous guns off our streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite some opposition to the bill, it passed easily in a special session of Parliament in Canberra, the capital. Lawmakers were recalled two weeks early from a summer break by Mr. Albanese, whose popularity has slumped since the Bondi attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later on Tuesday, Parliament passed the bill targeting hate speech, which critics say could have damaging repercussions for freedom of expression. It allows the government to designate organizations as hate groups if they promote violence, and it gives the authorities more leeway to deny entry visas to people with extremist views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Mehreen Faruqi, the deputy leader of the Greens party, called the bill “appalling,” saying it was not a “responsible response” to racism and extremism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This bill will have a chilling and draconian effect on political debate, on protest, on civil rights and on people speaking up against human rights abuses perpetrated by Israel or any other nation-state,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some parts of the bill, which would have made it an offense to incite hate or spread ideas of “racial superiority” over another person or group, were dropped this week after politicians, legal experts and others said they would impede freedom of speech.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/gun-control-buyback.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:51:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Syria’s Government, Kurdish Deal Is a Big Win</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/for-syrias-government-kurdish-deal-is-a-big-win.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20syria-assess-01-gjwp/20syria-assess-01-gjwp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria could not have struck a better deal than the one he just made with the Kurdish-led militia that had controlled much of the country’s northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the past year, Mr. al-Sharaa had been caught in protracted discussions with Kurdish leaders over the terms for joining his new government. The Kurds had significant bargaining chips, including the longtime backing of the United States and control of the country’s gas and oil fields. And many Syrians saw the talks as a harbinger of much larger questions about inclusivity of minorities in government and the sharing of political power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How willing would Mr. al-Sharaa be to decentralize power in his new government? And how long would he be willing to engage in negotiations with groups demanding some autonomy before moving those decisions to the battlefield?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, earlier this month, Mr. al-Sharaa’s patience seemed to have run out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After months of stalled negotiations with the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., the government made a military push into Kurdish-held territory last week. Within days, those forces had reached the outskirts of Raqqa — the largest city administered by the Kurdish authorities — after the Kurds had suffered a series of battlefield defeats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday, the leader of the S.D.F., Mazloum Abdi, agreed to a deal with Mr. al-Sharaa that looked like a surrender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. lost nearly all of the concessions the Syrian government had offered during previous rounds of negotiations. After previously winning its major sticking point — joining the Syrian military in its own distinct battalions — it now appears that its members will join as individuals. The S.D.F. also lost control over Syria’s gas and oil fields, its main leverage in negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a brutal blow to Kurdish leaders, who have loudly criticized Mr. al-Shara’s government for concentrating power in the hands of a small group of loyalists from his former rebel days and for not being inclusive enough of minorities in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day after signing the deal, Kurdish leaders accused government forces of violating the cease-fire and reiterated calls for Mr. al-Sharaa to decentralize his authority in what appeared to be a last-ditch effort to claw back some of the concessions they had previously won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement itself sent a stark message to other Syrian minorities, including the Druse militias that currently control southern province of Sweida and the Alawites on the coast. Calls have come from within both groups for greater autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a significant territorial, military and political win” for Mr. al-Sharaa, said Dareen Khalifa, a senior adviser at the International Crisis Group. “The political message now is that it’s only a matter of time for everyone else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa has pledged that his government will protect the rights of all minorities — something that the United States and others in the international community have said they will be monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an overture to Syrian Kurds on Friday, he issued a decree recognizing Kurdish as a national language alongside Arabic, and adopted Nowruz, the Persian New Year, widely celebrated by Kurds, as an official holiday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looming over the deal was the United States, a longtime ally of the S.D.F. and partner in its fight to oust the Islamic State from northeastern Syria since 2015. Over the past year, the tensions between the government and the S.D.F. had put the U.S. in a difficult position as it tried to balance between its two Syrian partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the U.S. has maintained its support for Kurdish forces since the Assad dictatorship collapsed in late 2024, the Trump administration has also embraced Mr. al-Sharaa. In November, President Trump hosted the Syrian leader, who was formerly designated a terrorist by the U.S. for his former ties to Al Qaeda at the White House. He waived punishing sanctions on Syria that had devastated its economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. appeared to have been banking on its American allies as a bulwark against exactly the kind of military push that the Syrian government made last week, a major miscalculation and not the first time Washington had failed to come to the force’s aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While American officials intervened to broker the cease-fire deal, the Kurds got neither the military support they had hoped for nor even an international outcry over the government’s military attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Kurds even equated the U.S. response with the total abandonment of their longtime ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States “left the Kurds, their allies, between the fists of ISIS and Al Qaeda,” said Siyamend Ali, a spokesman for the S.D.F., referring to Mr. al-Sharaa’s previous affiliation with Al Qaeda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. approach to the clashes between the S.D.F. and the government also sparked divisions in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Syrian government made its lightning advance into Kurdish territory, Senator Lindsey Graham of South Carolina, a Trump ally, threatened to call for sanctions to be reinstated on Mr. al-Sharaa’s government. He repeated the threat on Monday as Kurdish forces claimed that armed groups affiliated with the government had attacked prisons it controlled in the northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Syrian government forces continue to advance in the north toward Raqqa, I will push for reimposing Caesar Act sanctions on steroids,” he wrote in a post on X, referring to punitive sanctions that Congress repealed earlier this month. “If you want a conflict with the U.S. Senate and to do permanent damage to the U.S.-Syria relationship keep going.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a threat that Mr. al-Sharaa, who has bet that reviving the country’s economy will shore up support for his government, cannot ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s seizure of the oil and gas fields previously under S.D.F. control is another major win that could offer the government an economic lifeline — and another card to play to further shore up support with the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the clashes that erupted as government forces sought to take control over security infrastructure in the northeast — as agreed upon in Sunday’s deal — highlighted the fragility of Sunday’s agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After President al-Sharaa met with the leader of the S.D.F. in Damascus on Monday, the S.D.F. claimed that their discussions with the government about implementing the new deal had broken down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The situation has now deteriorated to an alarming degree,” Adulkarim Omar, a representative of the S.D.F.’s political arm, said in a statement on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F.’s near total capitulation also stoked fears that more hard-line elements within the Kurdish forces might splinter and become spoilers to peace in the northeast. Others also worried that the way in which the Syrian government may try to govern the region could unleash a new host of problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. al-Sharaa has rejected his Islamist roots, many Syrians remain to be convinced that he will share power with his former opponents and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For much of the past year, the government’s model for exerting control has been to install trusted allies from its rebel coalition in cities across the country. But that approach has largely backfired, leading to poor governance, according to Lara Nelson, policy director at ETANA Syria, a Syrian research group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The question now is around the implementation of governance,” Ms. Nelson said. “It has to be governed by the local people who have those organic links to their areas, otherwise it will be unsustainable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hwaida Saad and Raja Abdulrahim contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/for-syrias-government-kurdish-deal-is-a-big-win.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 04:30:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When President Trump said he planned to establish and lead a “Board of Peace” to oversee the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas in Gaza, many did not know what to make of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, letters went out asking countries to join the newly minted body, among them historically close U.S. allies like Canada, France, Britain, and Saudi Arabia. But Russia and Belarus, hardly allies, were also on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a perusal of the body’s charter — which governments received alongside their invitations — suggested that Mr. Trump hopes the Board of Peace could get involved in all kinds of global conflicts, not just the one in the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics reacted furiously, saying the Trump administration appeared to be setting up the board as a potential American-dominated rival to the United Nations, which Mr. Trump has long accused of liberal bias and waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chairman, Mr. Trump would have considerable influence over the Board of Peace. With countries being asked to pay more than $1 billion for permanent membership, its budget could be substantial, though it is unclear how much control Mr. Trump would have over how the money is spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presence of Turkey and Qatar on one of the board’s subcommittees also prompted an immediate outcry from Israel, which has been at odds with the Turkish government, particularly over the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we know so far about the Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the board appeared to be part of Mr. Trump’s vision for postwar Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His plan called the board a “new international transitional body” that would help supervise the rebuilding of the Palestinian enclave. The board’s members would include world leaders, with Mr. Trump sitting at the head of the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council later formally backed the board in a U.S.-drafted resolution in November, giving it the force of international legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution gave the board a mandate to work with governments to recruit international peacekeepers for Gaza. It was to carry out Mr. Trump’s plan in Gaza until the internationally recognized Palestinian Authority conducted reforms, the resolution said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the United States circulated the board’s charter on Friday, it became clear that Mr. Trump envisions a much bigger role for the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed charter said the Board of Peace would “secure enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict,” not just Gaza, according to a copy shared with The New York Times. It also called for “a more nimble and effective international peace-building body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of invitees includes Britain, Jordan, Russia and more. But so far, only a handful — like the pro-Trump Argentine president, Javier Milei, and Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary — have said they will join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite overseeing Gaza, neither the Board of Peace nor a Gaza Executive Board underneath it have any Palestinian members as yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board is, however, to oversee the work of a group of Palestinian technocrats charged with administering public services in Gaza. Analysts say they will face a formidable challenge, given that Gaza is still split in two between areas under Israeli and Hamas control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some countries appear skeptical. To acquire a permanent seat on the Board of Peace, each would have to pay more than a billion dollars in cash within the first year to fund the body’s operations. (States can join for three years for free.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The charter would invest considerable personal power in Mr. Trump as chairman. It says that he will name members of a second “Executive Board” to carry out the board’s decisions, and that Mr. Trump would wield considerable veto power over its actions. He would also be able to name his own successor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump would also be permitted to enact “resolutions or other directives” to carry out the board’s mission, and to “create, modify or dissolve subsidiary entities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France does not currently intend to join, as the board’s charter raises serious questions about respecting the role of the United Nations, said a senior French official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to comply with government protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how many countries will pay the fee to become permanent members, as opposed to accepting the optional three-year term for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not exactly clear how much oversight the Board of Peace will exert over Gaza and for how long. But two subcommittees reporting to Mr. Trump’s board have already been set up to carry out his Gaza peace plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the White House named a “Gaza Executive Board” that includes Jared Kushner, the president’s son-in-law, and Steve Witkoff, Mr. Trump’s envoy. The group also has Qatari and Egyptian officials, as well as an Israeli businessman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a rare public break with Mr. Trump, Israel criticized the makeup of the committee, particularly the presence of Qatar and Turkey. Both countries helped mediate between Israel and Hamas to secure the Gaza cease-fire, but Israeli officials have accused them of being too close to Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ségolène Le Stradic contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:20:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At the Center of Trump’s Vision for Rebuilding Ukraine: BlackRock</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In mid-December, as negotiations to end Russia’s war in Ukraine gathered pace, a group of Ukrainian officials sat in a conference room in New York for a meeting with senior executives at BlackRock, the world’s largest asset manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had come to discuss a crucial element of a peace plan drafted by Kyiv and Washington: Ukraine’s postwar recovery. BlackRock had been enlisted to help build a strategy for what President Volodymyr Zelensky has called an $800 billion “prosperity plan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting, held at BlackRock’s headquarters, kick-started work on identifying funding sources and investment priorities, according to three officials familiar with the conversation, who requested anonymity to discuss a closed-door meeting. More details are expected to be unveiled this week at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in Kyiv and other European capitals, BlackRock’s role has generated more questions than answers, as the Trump administration steers plans for rebuilding Ukraine toward American business interests. Seven European and Ukrainian officials, who asked for anonymity to discuss sensitive talks, voiced doubts about BlackRock’s ability to attract the enormous investments envisioned. Some indicated that the firm’s involvement could turn away potential investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the officials noted that BlackRock had already tried, and failed, in the war’s early years to raise billions to rebuild Ukraine. Confidential slide presentations viewed by The New York Times indicate that BlackRock had trouble attracting investors at that time. A slide from April 2023 projected that the firm would help mobilize $50 billion to $80 billion. A year later, another slide slashed the target to $15 billion to $30 billion. The project was shelved in mid-2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock struggled in part because of concerns in Europe that money from its governments could end up in a privately run American fund, according to the European and Ukrainian officials. Europe is expected to fund the vast majority of Ukraine’s recovery. With BlackRock now back at the table, the European worries are likely to resurface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, the firm has played a pro bono, advisory role in the new talks. It is unclear whether that mandate will expand as negotiations progress, or if peace is reached. A BlackRock spokesman declined to comment for this article. The White House and the Ukrainian economy ministry did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The involvement in the talks of a private firm whose main business is to maximize financial returns has reinforced concerns that the Trump administration views Ukraine’s reconstruction as a profit-making opportunity for the U.S. government and American companies, rather than as primarily a humanitarian or security matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, President Trump pushed for a deal granting the United States a stake in Ukraine’s mineral wealth. In peace talks with Kyiv, the president’s main negotiators have been real estate developers: his billionaire friend Steve Witkoff, and Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, Jared Kushner. BlackRock’s chief, Larry Fink, has sat next to Mr. Kushner in talks with Ukrainian leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current draft peace plan lays out an array of U.S. investment opportunities and calls for a free-trade agreement. “There’s a lot of wealth to be had,” Mr. Trump said about Ukraine’s future during negotiations with Mr. Zelensky last month in Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian officials have likened their country’s recovery blueprint to the Marshall Plan, the U.S.-funded project to rebuild Europe after World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That effort, which cost about $150 billion in today’s money, would be dwarfed by the $800 billion “prosperity plan” described by Mr. Zelensky. The enormous sum has led some Ukrainian economists and business figures to view the U.S. proposal with deep skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington might try to tap some of the roughly $250 billion in Russian assets frozen in Europe — an idea that was included in a draft Russian-U.S. peace plan. But two of the European officials said there would be fierce opposition to handing control of the assets to a U.S.-led recovery fund. There are also fears among European officials that BlackRock’s involvement signals that the Trump administration intends to sideline Europe in postwar planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Marshall Plan was led by the U.S. government. The possibility that Ukraine’s recovery could be shaped by BlackRock, a private firm, has raised concerns about transparency and potential conflicts of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock’s involvement in Ukraine dates to the fall of 2022, when Kyiv began to imagine a postwar future after pushing Russian troops from large areas of territory. That September, Andrew Forrest, an Australian mining magnate, introduced Mr. Zelensky to BlackRock’s chief executive, Mr. Fink. They discussed how the firm could advise Kyiv on setting up a reconstruction fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weeks later, the two sides signed a memorandum of understanding formalizing the collaboration. Under the agreement, which was seen by The Times, BlackRock’s consulting arm would help design the fund’s structure and governance, and pitch it to potential investors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fund’s central idea was to draw money from governments and financial institutions, and leverage it to attract several times as much in private lending capital, said Oleksandr Gryban, a former deputy economy minister for Ukraine who worked on the fund. Public money would serve as seed capital, absorbing the first losses and acting as a de-risking mechanism to entice private investors wary of putting money into Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slide presentations from 2023 and 2024 show that BlackRock aimed to raise money from European development banks, including KfW of Germany and Proparco of France. None of the documents indicate that BlackRock planned to invest its own money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as the firm approached European countries, it encountered strong reluctance, according to European and Ukrainian officials. The Europeans cautioned that BlackRock lacked experience in Ukraine. Although the slide presentations did not name a fund manager, the officials said they had expected BlackRock to take that role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When BlackRock halted its search for investors last year, European officials stepped in. They started their own reconstruction fund for Ukraine, with a more modest target of raising 1 billion euros, about $1.15 billion, this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Six months later, however, BlackRock was back in the picture. On Dec. 10, Mr. Fink sat with American negotiators as they joined an online meeting with Mr. Zelensky and senior Ukrainian officials. “This was the first meeting of the group that will work on a document regarding the reconstruction and economic recovery of Ukraine,” Mr. Zelensky said afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock’s role, he later explained, will be to “organize the implementation of the strategic recovery plan.” He said the plan envisioned multiple funds covering different areas like reconstruction, economic development and human capital. Ukrainian officials say governments and financial institutions would fund needed but noncommercial sectors, such as education, while private investors would focus on commercial activities that could offer higher returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach echoes BlackRock’s original proposals. The firm’s slide presentations outlined several sector-specific funds to finance projects using a mix of public and private money. Energy, infrastructure, agriculture, manufacturing and information technology were listed as priority sectors. A slide from April 2024 identified nine potential investment projects, including the development of wind farms and lithium deposits, totaling $1.1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear whether BlackRock or the Trump administration has approached U.S. investors about participating in the recovery plan. But Mr. Zelensky suggested last month that the plan would favor American business interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BlackRock itself could stand to profit from the recovery as the owner of Global Infrastructure Partners, one of the world’s largest financiers of projects to build airports, bridges and tunnels. Last year, Global Infrastructure Partners stepped in to assist the Trump administration by purchasing two ports in Panama from a Hong Kong company that had become the focus of tensions between Panama and Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Zelensky presented the U.S.-Ukraine draft peace plan to reporters last month, he said that a “Ukraine Development Fund” — the same name used in BlackRock’s original fund project — would be established “to invest in high-growth sectors, including technology, data centers and artificial intelligence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are sectors that the White House has prioritized more broadly for investment, pushing for deals that have financially benefited members of the Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of a recovery plan tilted toward high-growth sectors has drawn criticism. Meaghan Mobbs, who runs a charity in Ukraine and is the daughter of Keith Kellogg, Mr. Trump’s former envoy to Ukraine, wrote on social media that BlackRock’s involvement risked prioritizing “profitable sectors over public needs” and weakening oversight of recovery funds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oleksii Sobolev, Ukraine’s economy minister, said this month that some $500 billion would need to come from public sources, in the form of grants and low-interest loans from public banks. But several Ukrainian business figures and officials expressed doubt that governments and financial institutions could raise such a sum, which exceeds in value all the military, financial and humanitarian aid that Ukraine has received since the war began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has left many Ukrainian business figures to see Kyiv’s talk of an $800 billion recovery plan mostly as political messaging calibrated for a business-first Trump administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We need to say it to please Trump,” said Sergey Fursa, deputy director of the Kyiv-based investment firm Dragon Capital. “But right now, we simply don’t see where that kind of money would come from. This is wishful thinking.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:49:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Clashes Erupt Around Syrian Prisons Holding Islamic State Fighters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/syria-prisons-isis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19syria-prisons-01-zpqj/19syria-prisons-01-zpqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clashes erupted on Monday around two prisons in northeastern Syria holding members of the terrorist group Islamic State, a day after a Kurdish-led militia agreed to hand over control over the prisons to the Syrian government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That agreement between the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., and the central government ended weeks of deadly clashes between the two sides. The S.D.F. agreed to merge into the national military and hand over control of security infrastructure — including prisons housing about 8,000 Islamic State detainees — to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the clashes around two of those prisons underscored the fragility of that deal. Within hours, both the government and the S.D.F. accused each other of trying to derail the agreement. The government accused the S.D.F. of releasing Islamic State detainees from al-Shaddadi prison in Hasakah Province and of exploiting the security threat posed by those detainees for political gains, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement was a significant victory for the government and a stunning setback for the S.D.F., which lost control over territory, oil resources and other strategic assets just in the past few days. The S.D.F. emerged with few cards to play in future negotiations over any power its leaders and its forces may retain as part of the new government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The violence also revived fears around whether the new government would be able to maintain the same level of security the S.D.F. had in an area that once served as the heartland of the Islamic State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Monday evening, Syrian officials said they had taken control of al-Shaddadi prison and were combing the area in an effort to rearrest an unspecified number of prisoners they said had been released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F., in turn, accused armed groups “affiliated” with those in power in Damascus, the capital, of attacking the prison early Monday morning, without identifying the attackers more specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.D.F. officials also accused armed groups of attacking another prison, al-Aqtan, in Raqqa, which is the largest city administered by Kurdish authorities and which once served as the capital of the Islamic State’s self-proclaimed caliphate. At least nine S.D.F. fighters were killed in the clashes, the S.D.F said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clashes made it clear that the cease-fire reached on Sunday had not yet quelled the tensions between Kurdish forces and Syria’s central government over who controls the country’s northeastern region. The Islamic State seized much of that region in 2014 and ruled it for years before the S.D.F., with U.S. backing, reclaimed the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government institutions in the northeastern province, a semiautonomous region long administered by the Kurds, will also come under the central government’s authority as will Syria’s gas and oil fields in the area, nearly all of which have been under Kurdish control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement was widely viewed as little more than a surrender by the S.D.F., which for months has been in stalled negotiations with the government over the terms of their integration into the new Syrian state that assumed control after the ouster of the dictator Bashar al-Assad in late 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after a lightning advance by the Syrian military into Kurdish-held territory this month, the S.D.F. forces were put on the back foot and ultimately agreed to the cease-fire deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the deal, the central government was to assume security responsibility over prisons holding more than 8,000 Islamic State members captured during the civil war, including al-Shaddadi and al-Aqtan prisons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central government is also to take over the sprawling Al Hol detention camp, which houses tens of thousands of family members of Islamic State fighters, many of them foreigners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the clashes around the prisons broke out, the S.D.F. accused the U.S.-led coalition, which maintains a few troops on the ground, of ignoring calls for help. A senior U.S. military official denied the S.D.F. claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second U.S. official, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters, said Monday they are working to de-escalate the tense situation. The official also said a number of prisoners had been recaptured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Islamic State seized territory in northeastern Syria in 2014 and ruled there and neighboring Iraq for years, brutally enforcing its strict interpretation of Islamic law. As the S.D.F. battled to reclaim that land with U.S. support, they detained thousands of ISIS fighters and tens of thousands of their relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the years since the Islamic State was routed in 2017, the land that was retaken in northeastern Syria has remained under S.D.F. control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. al-Assad’s ouster, the S.D.F. entered negotiations to integrate into the new national military. The deal on Sunday was the second it had struck with the government in less than a year. Whether it holds up is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, the Syrian government sought to position itself as the best ally to international partners in dealing with the threat from ISIS detainees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Interior Ministry accused the S.D.F. of a “serious security violation threatening Syrian, regional, and international security,” in a statement on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Restoring legitimate state institutions and enforcing the rule of law are the only permanent guarantees of security and stability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Schmitt contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/syria-prisons-isis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 19:25:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Is Pushing the U.S.-Europe Alliance Onto a Precipice</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-nato-alliance.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-europe-alliance01-photo-jbtp/19int-europe-alliance01-photo-jbtp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens to an 80-year-old diplomatic alliance when its leading power threatens a military invasion of one member, wages economic war on the others and vows to cultivate political and cultural resistance to their governments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the alliance doomed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question is being asked in capitals across Europe as leaders rush to respond to President Trump’s rapidly escalating campaign to acquire Greenland over the objections of the people who live there. At issue most urgently is whether resisting Mr. Trump’s territorial ambitions risks damaging Europe’s relationship with the United States beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders — like President Emmanuel Macron of France and Lars Klingbeil, Germany’s finance minister — appear willing to take that risk, urging Europe’s nations to consider deploying an economic “bazooka” in response to Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders from across Europe are expected to gather in Brussels this week to present a united response to Mr. Trump’s provocations. Veteran observers of European politics said the alliance between Europe and the United States that formed in the aftermath of World War II had already been fundamentally altered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no longer an alliance designed primarily to advance the interests of like-minded democracies, they said. Instead, it is a relationship on Mr. Trump’s terms alone — one in which he wields the leverage that comes from American power to force Europeans to cater to his whims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To use what is essentially economic warfare with allies is unprecedented in this way,” said Ian Lesser, who leads the Brussels office of the German Marshall Fund, a research group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There appears to be a consensus in much of Europe that it needs to build new economic and military capacities to make it less dependent on the United States. But that will take years, if not decades. In the meantime, Europe’s businesses and financial markets will still be intertwined with the buying power of consumers in the United States, and Ukraine will still need American weapons to defend itself against Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, months of diplomatic effort to negotiate a cease-fire in the Ukraine war have only underscored that NATO, which was formed to defend Europe, is unable to fend off Russian aggression without security guarantees by the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”It would be foolish at a time of war in Europe to jettison all of the sort of strategic and operational benefits that come with the alliance,” Mr. Lesser said. “But if the United States is no longer a reliable partner in that alliance, then Europe needs to do something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That effort is already underway, slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same day that Mr. Trump announced his latest tariff threat on social media, Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, and António Costa, the president of the European Council, were in Paraguay to sign a major trade deal with a bloc of Latin American countries, one that was 25 years in the making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has so far been happy to welcome European money to purchase American-made arms for Ukraine and other countries in Eastern Europe. And he relishes surprising his so-called allies, as he demonstrated on Saturday when he announced tariffs on a group of European nations, including Britain, unless Greenland is sold to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That raises the stakes for the decisions that Europe is grappling with in the days ahead. It must choose how aggressively to confront Mr. Trump without knowing what the always-unpredictable president will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Is he serious? What does Europe do now? How does the U.S. respond?” Mr. Lesser said. “There will be those who say, ‘OK, how do we get through this? Is it possible to simply to engage in a kind of negotiation or investment or whatever it may be, that will defer anything radical?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has already made it clear that he views America’s European allies with disdain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his annual National Security Strategy, released last month, officials from Mr. Trump’s administration questioned whether some European countries would remain “reliable allies” in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document conceded that Europe was “strategically and culturally vital” to the United States. But it said the continent faced the “stark prospect of civilizational erasure” unless the United States helped like-minded “patriotic European parties” — a phrase that was widely understood to mean the far right — to win power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Europeans on the receiving end of those assertions, the president’s threats about acquiring Greenland “the easy way” or “the hard way” have further eroded the trust that was central to their alliance with the United States for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Going back to the level of trust that we saw beforehand would require, I think, generational change,” said Rosa Balfour, the director of Carnegie Europe, a political think tank. “The attack on Europe is not just coming from an individual, you know — it’s been turned into an ideology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the latest Greenland threats, more voices have begun urging assertive action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement over the weekend, Mr. Macron vowed that “no intimidation or threat will influence us — neither in Ukraine, nor in Greenland, nor anywhere else in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He called Mr. Trump’s tariff threats “unacceptable” and vowed: “Europeans will respond in a united and coordinated manner should they be confirmed. We will ensure that European sovereignty is upheld.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others, like Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain, have argued for a diplomatic solution and cautioned against grandstanding. “That’s an understandable instinct, but it’s not effective,” the prime minister told reporters on Monday morning. “It never has been. It may make politicians feel good, but it does nothing for working people whose jobs, livelihoods and security rely on the relationships that we build across the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ms. Balfour said that more leaders were beginning to realize that capitulating to Mr. Trump’s demands was not always in Europe’s interests. In fact, it often leads Mr. Trump to demand more concessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If true, that could have implications for the alliance with the United States and whether it survives in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reality, I think, is sinking into the mind-sets of those people who have been advocating caution, dialogue and ‘Let’s listen to what Trump has to say,’” Ms. Balfour said. “You can feel that kind of change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting from Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-nato-alliance.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:18:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Links His Push for Greenland to Not Winning Nobel Peace Prize</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is now claiming that one reason he is pushing to acquire Greenland is that he didn’t win the Nobel Peace Prize, according to a text message he sent to Norway’s prime minister over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonas Gahr Store, Norway’s leader, received the text message on Sunday, an official in the prime minister’s office said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Considering your Country decided not to give me the Nobel Peace Prize for having stopped 8 Wars PLUS, I no longer feel an obligation to think purely of Peace, although it will always be predominant, but can now think about what is good and proper for the United States of America,” Mr. Trump wrote in the message, which was first published by PBS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also questioned Denmark’s claim to Greenland, saying, “There are no written documents,” and adding, “The World is not secure unless we have Complete and Total Control of Greenland. Thank you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions over Greenland have sharply escalated in the last week, and the message injected a new level of uncertainty into Mr. Trump’s thinking and his campaign to gain control of the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland has been part of the Danish Kingdom for more than 300 years, and world leaders have condemned Mr. Trump’s insistence that the United States take over the territory, a giant icebound island in the Arctic region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to copies of the messages provided by the Norwegian prime minister’s office, Mr. Trump’s message was a response to one that Mr. Store sent Mr. Trump on Sunday. It was co-signed by the president of Finland, Alexander Stubb, a leader with whom Mr. Trump is close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European leaders asked to speak to Mr. Trump about Greenland and his threat of using tariffs to pressure Denmark into selling it, which Denmark has refused to do. They asked for a phone call and struck a collaborative tone, writing, “We believe we all should work to take this down and de-escalate — so much is happening around us where we need to stand together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump’s response, Mr. Store said in a statement, “As regards the Nobel Peace Prize, I have on several occasions clearly explained to Trump what is well known, namely that it is an independent Nobel Committee, and not the Norwegian government, that awards the prize,” Mr. Store said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly challenged Denmark’s claims to Greenland, but in decades-old agreements that the United States has signed with Denmark, the United States has recognized Denmark’s close connection to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2004 amendment to an older defense pact between Denmark and the United States, which grants the United States broad military access, explicitly recognizes Greenland as “an equal part of the Kingdom of Denmark.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in 1916, Denmark sold what are now the U.S. Virgin Islands to the United States for $25 million in gold. In the treaty for that deal, a clause reads, “The United States of America will not object to the Danish Government extending their political and economic interests to the whole of Greenland.”In the past year, as Mr. Trump has repeatedly vowed to “get” Greenland, Denmark has repeatedly rebuffed him. Denmark’s position is that it does not have the authority to sell the self-governing territory and that Greenland’s 57,000 inhabitants will decide their own fate. Polls and interviews show that an overwhelming majority of Greenlanders strongly oppose joining the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Greenlanders staged the biggest protest of recent months. Hundreds marched through the snowy streets of Nuuk, the capital, chanting, “No means no,” “Greenland is already great” and “Yankee, go home!”In the past few days, Denmark and other European countries have sent more military forces to the island. Small groups of Danish soldiers dressed in green camouflage and dark woolen hats have been walking through downtown Nuuk. Beyond the harbor, a 200-foot-long Danish warship capable of breaking through ice has been patrolling the shoreline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A much-anticipated three-way meeting last week of the United States, Denmark and Greenland, hosted by Vice President JD Vance in Washington, did not produce any breakthroughs and seemed to instead create misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first time Greenland had been included in a such high-level discussions, and the Danish and Greenlandic officials left saying that a working group had been formed to explore possibilities for a solution. But the Trump administration said afterwards that the two sides would begin “technical talks on the acquisition of Greenland,” a statement that raised even more concern in Greenland, in Denmark and across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Kingsley, Jeanna Smialek and Steven Erlanger contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:06:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Updates: At Least 39 Are Dead in High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-promo-9amest/18spain-crash-eyewitness-pgtq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Crews were working to retrieve bodies after two high-speed trains derailed in southern Spain. The regional authorities said 41 people were hospitalized, with a dozen of them in intensive care.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:09:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Four Shark Attacks in 48 Hours, Australia Shuts Dozens of Beaches</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/australia-sydney-shark-attacks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-oz-sharks-zkvb/20int-oz-sharks-zkvb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of beaches in eastern Australia were closed on Tuesday, after four shark attacks in a span of 48 hours, a spree that the head of a lifeguard group described as unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, a surfer was knocked off his board by a shark near Point Plomer Beach, about 200 miles north of Sydney. He was briefly hospitalized with minor injuries, local news media reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That episode followed a spate of attacks off the coastline of Sydney, Australia’s largest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, a 27-year-old surfer’s leg was bitten by a shark in waters off Manly Beach. Fellow beachgoers administered first aid before the surfer was taken to the hospital with what the police described as “life-changing injuries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same day, and just a few miles away, an 11-year-old boy escaped injury after a shark bit his surfboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fourth episode occurred on Sunday afternoon, when a shark bit the legs of a boy who was swimming with friends in Sydney’s east. The authorities have said that the boy, who is believed to be 12 or 13 years old, was “fighting for his life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a dozen beaches in northern Sydney, including Manly and Palm Beach, will be closed on Tuesday and Wednesday, the local authorities said. Further north, near Point Plomer Beach, the authorities have closed several beaches for 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Pearce, the chief executive of the volunteer lifeguard organization Surf Life Saving New South Wales, called the number of attacks “unprecedented” and urged people to avoid swimming at northern Sydney beaches for the next 48 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists say the attacks in Sydney were most likely the work of bull sharks — a species that is considered among the most dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weather conditions in the past week have been conducive to an increased shark presence off Sydney’s shores, Leonardo Guida, a shark scientist with the Australian Marine Conservation Society said. Ocean temperatures have been warmer-than-average and runoff from heavy rainfall has brought prey into the ocean water for sharks to feast on, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike other sharks, bull sharks have the ability to swim in fresh and salt water, allowing them to hunt in a range of marine environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shark attacks are rare in Australia but this week’s episodes come after a deadly attack in Sydney’s northern beaches in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Many are still grieving the loss of Mercury Psillakis and we are all shocked this can have happened again so soon on our beaches,” Sue Heins, the mayor of the Northern Beaches Council, said in a statement Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia has done more than perhaps any other country to try to mitigate shark attacks. It is one of the a few countries to use shark nets, a contentious form of beach protection, as well as noninvasive measures such as drone monitoring and smart drumlines — floating traps with hooks that snare sharks and alert officials so they can be released.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/australia/australia-sydney-shark-attacks.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 22:12:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Islamic State Claims Deadly Attack on Chinese Restaurant in Afghanistan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/isis-kabul-bomb-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-afghanistan-isis-ztfw/20int-afghanistan-isis-ztfw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bombing claimed by the Islamic State wing in Afghanistan killed at least seven people and wounded more than a dozen in a Chinese restaurant in Kabul on Monday, officials said, in a sign of the group’s persistent threat despite the Afghan government’s claim to have vanquished it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blast ripped through a noodle restaurant on a busy street of central Kabul filled with shops selling flowers, antiquities and rugs on Monday afternoon. A single attacker detonated his explosive vest 30 minutes after entering the restaurant, according to a statement released by the Islamic State through its media wing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Afghan Interior Ministry, Abdul Mateen Qani, told The New York Times that seven people had been killed, including a Chinese citizen. He also said that the assault had been carried out by a single attacker from the Islamic State Khorasan Province, or ISIS-K, the group’s Afghanistan affiliate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike most Western countries, China has maintained sustained diplomatic ties with the Taliban administration in Afghanistan. In 2023, China became the first country to appoint an ambassador in Afghanistan since the Taliban took power in 2021, and has signed mining contracts to tap into vast Afghan oil and mineral reserves. China has also vowed to include Afghanistan in the Belt and Road Initiative, its trillion-dollar global infrastructure project. Its foreign minister, Wang Yi, even visited Kabul last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But China has grown increasingly wary about potential insecurity in Afghanistan, even though the government has control of large swaths of the country and has tried to woo foreign investors back. China now advises its citizens against traveling to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ISIS-K said it has targeted Chinese citizens in retaliation for Beijing’s oppression of Uyghurs, a Muslim ethnic minority in China, and has criticized the Afghan government’s dealings with Beijing. In 2022, its militants injured at least five Chinese citizens in an attack on a hotel popular with Chinese visitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“ISIS-K sees the Taliban-China relationship as one of the biggest betrayals of a jihadist group,” Iftikhar Firdous, the executive director of the research platform Khorasan Diary, said about the partnerships made by the Taliban since the group took over Afghanistan in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Firdous, said the attacks pointed to “a growing anti-Chinese jihadist nexus in the region, of which ISIS-K is the primary benefactor.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has urged the Taliban government to engage in “more visible and verifiable actions to dismantle and eliminate all terrorist organizations based in Afghanistan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“China strongly condemns and firmly opposes all forms of terrorism and supports Afghanistan and regional countries in jointly combating all forms of terrorist violence,” Guo Jiakun, a spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, said at a news briefing on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces heavily guarded the area around the Chinese noodle restaurant on Tuesday, as residents were still cleaning broken glass littering the street. Businesses had reopened, with employees in flower shops making bouquets and blood stains still visible on the windows of nearby boutiques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency, an Italian nonprofit medical group operating in Kabul, said it had received 20 people at its surgical center on Monday, including seven who were dead on arrival. A child was among the dead, Emergency’s country director, Dejan Panic, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexandra Stevenson contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/isis-kabul-bomb-china.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:49:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Venezuelan Political Prisoner Finally Comes Home</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/venezuela-prisoner-release.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/world/00Int-Venezuela-Prisoner-promo/00Int-Venezuela-Prisoner-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year behind bars as a political prisoner under the Maduro regime in Venezuela, one of the first things that Ángel Godoy did was apologize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freed last Wednesday, Mr. Godoy, a political activist and columnist, returned to his home in Los Teques, 40 minutes outside the capital, Caracas, where his son showed him a photo of his high school graduation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m sorry I wasn’t there,” Mr. Godoy whispered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now you are,” his son, Miguelangel Godoy Briceño, replied. “And I need you to help me study for university.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy, 52, walked along the walls of his apartment and touched the family photos to confirm that this was home. In the living room, there was a poster of his face that his wife had used as a backdrop for every video she recorded about her husband’s detention on Jan. 8, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He took a marker and wrote across it in big letters: RELEASED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy and his family had been waiting for this moment for 371 days, but their hopes grew earlier this month after President Nicolás Maduro was seized by U.S. forces in Caracas and the Venezuelan government announced that it would start freeing “an important number” of political prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy is one of the lucky ones. To date, only 143 of Venezuela’s estimated nearly 900 political prisoners have been released, according to a leading human rights group, Foro Penal. And much of the Maduro government’s machinery of repression remains largely intact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was that very apparatus that snatched Mr. Godoy as he was getting home a year ago and accused him of terrorism, and incitement of armed actions and hatred. He has denied the charges, which are commonly brought against political prisoners in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy said masked men had jumped out of an unmarked van with tinted windows and took him away. Although the men weren’t wearing official insignia, Mr. Godoy shouted to his neighbors that it was the country’s intelligence agency, which has been accused of numerous human rights violations, and asked them to tell his wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next 25 days, his family members did not hear from him. They did not see him for 96 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy was held at several prisons, including El Helicoide, the infamous sprawling building in Caracas that was built as the world’s first drive-through shopping mall but instead became a torture center, human rights groups say. He called his judicial process and his over-the-phone arraignment “shameful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s behind bars,” his wife, Adriana Briceño, said. “But so are we as a family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in prison, Mr. Godoy and his wife of 19 years kept their hope alive through their love for each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Ms. Briceño used candy to send messages, writing words of encouragement or notes about domestic news inside the wrappers. Mr. Godoy wrote back on tiny folded scraps of paper, smuggled out in the dirty laundry his wife collected on visiting days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love you more than life itself,” he wrote in one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy kept all of the candy wrappers. But when he was transferred to another prison, everything stayed in his old cell. To his wife’s surprise, the guards gave all of those mementos to her when she retrieved his belongings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day Mr. Godoy was freed, his wife was given the news just as she entered the prison for a visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mr. Godoy heard his name called for release, “all hell broke loose,” he said. Fellow prisoners hugged him. “I said, ‘My God,’ he recalled. “I couldn’t believe it. Everyone was shouting: ‘Freedom, freedom, freedom!’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside, Mr. Godoy saw a country marked by the U.S. strikes. Riding home with his wife and brother-in-law, he told them about his time behind bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us not repeat this darkness,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Godoy’s neighbors greeted him with embraces and tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside Mr. Godoy’s apartment were reminders of an interrupted life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dining room table remained set with Christmas decorations. In the freezer was a traditional Christmas corn tamale that his wife had set aside for him — just in case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the objects had come from the prison, among them a craggy teddy bear made by other prisoners using scraps of fabric from a mattress in Mr. Godoy’s cell, a wedding anniversary gift for his wife. There was also a cloth ball covered in messages for his son. To get the ball out of prison through his wife, Mr. Godoy negotiated with the warden and allowed a thorough inspection of every word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one corner of the family’s apartment sat a worn plastic table. Mr. Godoy used the table in his cell, and his family recovered it after his transfer to another prison. On its surface he had written a verse from the Bible: “Even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though Mr. Godoy is free, the Venezuelan authorities maintain control over him. He is prohibited from leaving the country and must appear in court every 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that first afternoon out of prison, Mr. Godoy sat down at the very table his wife had kept decorated. And he ate the very foods she had saved for him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was indeed home.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/venezuela-prisoner-release.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 01:02:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Chinese Island Where Dreams of Real Estate Glory Never Die</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/china-ocean-flower-island-real-estate.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/20int-china-fantasy-island-83602-cover/20int-china-fantasy-island-83602-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by Dubai and bloated by the outsize ambitions of a disgraced Chinese property developer, Ocean Flower Island, a cluster of man-made islets in the South China Sea, flopped as a business. But it still dazzles as a breathtaking fiesta of fantasy and folly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hugely expensive, partially completed project — a gigantic shopping mall without shops, a theme park without visitors, dozens of abandoned high-rise housing blocks and artificial beaches too dangerous to swim — helps explain why China’s yearslong real estate crisis never really seems to end. There is so much money and so much hope entangled in the wreckage that it is too big to clear away quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This place is a dead zone,” said Zhou Qingbin, a visitor from the nearby coastal city of Danzhou. The municipal government of Danzhou now controls much of Ocean Flower Island and is struggling to figure out what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was built by Evergrande, a Chinese real estate developer that collapsed under more than $300 billion of debt in 2021. Evergrande’s implosion and the troubles of other big property developers have shattered confidence in real estate, once an important driver of China’s economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New home sales have dropped to their lowest level in more than 15 years, according to figures released by the statistics bureau in Beijing on Monday. The sector has become such a headache that the Chinese authorities recently began censoring pessimistic online posts about the property market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, the Danzhou government seems to be pressing on with Evergrande’s original concept. It was intended as a Chinese version of Dubai’s Palm Island Jumeirah — only bigger. Evergrande sank around $12 billion, most of it borrowed, into what was supposed to be China’s biggest built-from-scratch entertainment, conference and shopping destination, with the islets forming the petals of a flower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That investment, though huge, fell short of the $23 billion the company said it needed to build apartments to house up to 200,000 people. That has left Ocean Flower Island in limbo. Before its collapse, Evergrande said it had completed 60,000 apartments and handed them over to buyers. Other buildings, however, never rose beyond their concrete foundations, which, flooded by rainwater, have become fishing holes. Thirty-nine high-rise apartment blocks that were nearly finished but never sold are marooned on a wasteland of rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole project was the brainchild of Xu Jiayin, Evergrande’s founder and former chairman, who was once China’s richest man and is now in jail. A gushing account by Evergrande said Mr. Xu came up with the idea for Ocean Flower Island during a 2011 vacation in Singapore. Sequestered in his room, the company said, he sketched out designs for an artificial archipelago in the shape of a bougainvillea and “meticulously oversaw every detail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he did not appear to have nailed down how the project would make enough money to build the fake islands and pay back a growing pile of debt to Chinese and foreign lenders. Evergrande also needed to persuade officials in China’s southern province of Hainan to sign off on a venture that violated environmental protection and other laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang Qi, the former mayor and Communist Party chief of Danzhou, who approved Ocean Flower Island, was convicted of corruption in 2020 and sentenced to life in prison. Other local officials have also been convicted on various corruption charges, including the former governor and party secretary of Hainan, Luo Baoming, who was jailed for 15 years in December for taking around $16 million in bribes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From its inception, Ocean Flower Island was driven by the same idea that drove much of China’s frenzy of construction during a decades-long economic boom: Build it and they will come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a country with 1.4 billion people and expectations of ever-rising incomes, this was for years a safe bet, until it wasn’t. In 2021, Beijing, worried by out-of-control lending, issued a directive restricting access to loans by property developers. Credit from banks, the biggest of which are controlled by the state, dried up. Evergrande seized up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danzhou government is trying to keep the project alive. It pitches Ocean Flower Island to Chinese vacationers and would-be home-buyers as a “unique lifestyle concept.” There are no reliable estimates of the current population, beyond the thousands of people who initially purchased properties — a fraction of early projections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Palm Island in Dubai, where the grand villas were snapped up by celebrities, soccer stars and foreign officials looking for a sunny sanctuary, Ocean Flower Island drew mostly retirees from northern China looking for a warm place to winter. The main street in the residential area is lined with restaurants offering northern specialties like steamed buns and hot pot, as well as geriatric health care services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang Qun, 70, a retiree from the province of Heilongjiang, said that when he bought his apartment five years ago there were crowds of people at the Evergrande office clamoring to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the office is littered with old brochures and property contracts and is staffed with government-supervised clerks responsible for sorting out paperwork for properties purchased years ago. If Mr. Zhang sold his apartment now, he would lose half his investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other traces of Evergrande are vending machines stocked with dusty bottles of “Evergrande Spring” mineral water. Mr. Xu, Evergrande’s former chairman, vanished from public view in 2021. A report last March by the Supreme People’s Procuratorate said that he had been prosecuted for crimes including financial fraud and disorderly financial management. It did not say whether he had been convicted or where he was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A lot of people lost money because of Evergrande, and are angry,” said Li Yanbo, a real estate agent on Ocean Flower Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who bought apartments early made big profits, at least on paper, as the price per square yard more than tripled between 2015 and a 2021 peak. Those who arrived late lost their shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Evergrande, Mr. Li added, was not all bad: “Some people think they were cheated, but there are others who would never have had a chance to get an apartment if not for Evergrande.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Property prices on Ocean Flower Island, he added, have stabilized somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every city in China has unfinished tower blocks left stranded by Evergrande’s demise. But probably nowhere has Mr. Xu’s hubris left such a high concentration of excess as in Ocean Flower Island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help accommodate what was supposed to be a flood of tourists, Evergrande built The Castle, a hotel with 5,100 rooms. Its two outdoor swimming pools have been drained of water, and the hotel has stayed afloat by catering to budget travelers on peak-season package tours. For much of the year, it is largely empty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of wind whistles through the broken windows of luxury coastal villas fit for Russian oligarchs. Some have been taken over by laborers who sleep on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shopping streets featuring Italian, German, Chinese and other styles of architectures look like deserted movie sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plaza flanked by eight fake churches, including a red brick structure resembling a cathedral, is meant as an Instagram-able setting for wedding photos. The churches are now used as the backdrop for a sound and light show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ocean Flower Island still has believers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wang Xian, a retired banker from the northern province of Hebei, acknowledged that Evergrande’s founder “went too far and thought he could do anything.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with around 300 million Chinese people retiring over the next decade, he noted, many will want to find a sunny and safe place to live. “If just 1 percent come here,” he said, “this place will be a big success.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Li You contributed research from Shanghai.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/china-ocean-flower-island-real-estate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 00:09:42 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>