<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 06:59:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Trump Returns to a Familiar Role: Sowing Trade Chaos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/trump-trade-chaos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22dc-trade-thcf/22dc-trade-thcf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump on Wednesday gave a menacing speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, before backtracking on a brewing trade war with Europe.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/trump-trade-chaos.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 10:26:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A 67,800-Year-Old Handprint May Be the World’s Oldest Rock Art</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/indonesia-handprint-rock-art-research.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;“It was hiding in plain sight all this time,” one researcher said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/indonesia-handprint-rock-art-research.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 07:22:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Davos, Talk of Climate Change Retreats to the Sidelines</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/climate/davos-climate-change-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22cli-newsletter-Davos-qjbh/22cli-newsletter-Davos-qjbh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
At the Davos forum in recent years, the focus on climate change and stopping biodiversity loss has taken a back seat to issues like cryptocurrency, artificial intelligence and geopolitics.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/climate/davos-climate-change-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 11:22:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Britain’s Bases in Cyprus Could Be a Blueprint for Trump’s Greenland Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/greenland-trump-bases-cyprus.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22xp-greenland-cyprus1-bvth/22xp-greenland-cyprus1-bvth-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump said on Wednesday that he had reached a framework for a deal on the future of Greenland with Mark Rutte, left, the NATO secretary general.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/greenland-trump-bases-cyprus.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:41:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Barron Trump Called U.K. Police After Witnessing Woman ‘Getting Beat Up’ on Video Call</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/barron-trump-london-call-woman-assault.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-UK-BARRON-TRUMP-ckwz/22int-UK-BARRON-TRUMP-ckwz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Barron Trump at President Trump’s inaugural parade in Washington, D.C., in January last year, days after his phone call to the London police.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/barron-trump-london-call-woman-assault.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:32:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Emboldened Trump’s Whipsaw Approach to the World</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-foreign-policy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-davos-trump-wrapup01-photo-jmqh/22int-davos-trump-wrapup01-photo-jmqh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump at a reception with business leaders at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-foreign-policy.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 14:30:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Davos Stops Pretending</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/davos-trump-greenland-ukraine.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-theworld-davos-trump-promo/23int-theworld-davos-trump-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davos has long been a weather vane for the world, a perch from which to observe the rise of China, the disruptive power of A.I. and now, the breakdown of the postwar order. I spoke to my colleague Peter Goodman, our in-house Davos expert, about what this annual gathering of the powerful can tell us about the strange moment we’re in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter, you’ve come here, what, 12 times? And you’ve written a book: “Davos Man: How the Billionaires Devoured the World.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tell us about Davos Man — shorthand for the hundreds of business and tech magnates and political leaders who flock to the event every year — and how he’s adapting to the Trump era. (And yes, it’s still mostly men.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Davos men used to tell us that they were gathered here on the mountaintop, not just to do deals and make themselves richer, but to make the world better. They would have us believe that if we just deregulate more and cut more taxes and give them greater largess to do what they do, they will take care of climate change and gender inequality and social injustice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was always a completely absurd proposition, this idea that the ultimate beneficiaries of the status quo would be the ones to fix it. And now that pretense is more or less gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take me back to the origins of this meeting in Davos. How did it start?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it goes back to 1971, which was actually another year of trans-Atlantic tension. Nixon left the gold standard. The dollar fell. The U.S. imposed tariffs on European imports. And the Europeans were totally blindsided. This German economist, Klaus Schwab, convenes this gathering of politicians and academics and business people in Davos. It gradually grows into this giant business conference that’s also an exercise in virtue signaling. The Davos motto is: “Committed to improving the state of the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Has Davos changed since you first started coming?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The change is dramatic. Some of it is physical, and some of it is ethos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s like a Las Vegas Strip element to how things have developed. These pop-up storefronts for the world’s biggest multinationals have totally taken over the village. When I first came here, there was a chocolate truffle place and a toy store where I bought a present for my kids. Now it’s all been taken up by giant tech companies, consultancies and crypto companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people paying the bills here like to boast: “Oh, I was in Davos for four days. I never left my hotel suite because everyone else had to come to me to court me for investments.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the change in ethos?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems pretty clear that Larry Fink of BlackRock, who took over from Klaus Schwab, is leaning into making this purely a business conference. “Committed to improving the state of the world” has mostly disappeared from view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the former buzzwords — social justice, sustainability — have gone. They’ve sanitized virtually every part of it to make the Trump administration feel welcome. It was a big score that they got Trump to attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Trump’s first administration, people described Trump and Davos as opposing forces. That seems to have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time Trump was here, in 2018, the conventional narrative was, it’s a clash of worlds, the globalists who want to make everything better rubbing up against the guy who’s like a wrecking ball pointed at the liberal democratic order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t really true even then, right? The C.E.O.s who pay the bills here were mostly delighted with this guy, who represented tax cuts and deregulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s a similar dynamic now. I mean, these C.E.O.s work for shareholders. They’re publicly traded companies. And by the way, they’re looking quarter to quarter. So if you ask them, what’s the long-term damage from the erosion of central bank independence? They’ll give you an answer that all things being equal, they’d prefer that the Fed’s independence be sacred, and that rule of law prevail. But all things are never equal, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that Trump is at war with anything he considers woke. Larry Fink used to write annual shareholder letters about corporate responsibility and how climate change would be solved by the capital markets. Now there’s no talk of sustainability whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the old virtue signaling is gone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right, to the extent that’s there’s virtue signaling, it’s signaling to Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More from Davos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Trump’s ultimatum on Greenland, negotiators are considering plans to create sovereign U.S. bases and ban resource extraction by Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark is pushing back hard on any concessions on its sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration laid out a highly speculative vision for the future of Gaza at a gathering to inaugurate its “Board of Peace.” (Watch the video.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friedrich Merz, the chancellor of Germany, urged Europe to strengthen its militaries to survive in an international order whose “very foundations have been shaken.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine criticized European countries for what he described as their geopolitical weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Instead of becoming a truly global power, Europe remains a beautiful but fragmented kaleidoscope of small and middle powers,” Zelensky said in a speech. “Instead of taking the lead in defending freedom worldwide, especially when America’s focus shifts elsewhere, Europe looks lost, trying to convince the U.S. president to change. But he will not change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zelensky’s speech came after he held private talks with Trump in Davos. The leaders tersely described their talks as “good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before, Gov. Gavin Newsom of California called world leaders “pathetic” for “rolling over” to Trump. (Watch the video.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk’s Grok chatbot generated millions of sexualized images of women, according to a Times analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours after Japan restarted a reactor at a large nuclear complex, a technical malfunction forced it back offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. immigration agents detained a 5-year-old boy in Minneapolis, incensing residents who feel they are under siege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Filipino journalist was convicted on charges of financing terrorism and sentenced to up to 18 years in prison. Rights groups called it an attack on press freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rifaat al-Assad, the brother and uncle of Syrian tyrants who was known as “the butcher of Hama,” died in Dubai this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Check out our Champion’s League projections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skiing: How Lindsey Vonn’s new titanium knee brought her back to the Olympics at 41.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest gossip: Here is everything you need to know about the Beckham family feud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— They are nature’s super feather, one of six types on a bird’s body. Tiny, hairlike filoplumes detect pressure, touch and vibration, and translate them into neuronal signals. They provide birds with detailed information as they fly, telling them to adjust their feathers to stay warm, or to release heat. They may also detect the movement of parasites, prompting the birds to preen or emit oil in that area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tânia Maria de Medeiros Filha is causing a major cinematic stir in Brazil and abroad. At 79, she has become a breakout star as the hostess of a safe house in “The Secret Agent,” which earned four Oscar nominations yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite only appearing onscreen for 11 minutes in the film, Tânia Maria has amassed a cult following and drawn praise from international film critics. “I think it’s because of my simplicity,” she told our reporter in an interview, chalking up the frenzy to her authenticity in a role not far from her real-life persona. Read more about her newfound celebrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on the Oscars: “Sinners” scored a record 16 nominations, followed by “One Battle After Another,” which earned 13. Catch up on all the nominations here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world of travel can be full of surprises — disrupted unexpectedly by weather and by politics — but our travel reporters are doing their best to look ahead at what trends we can expect to take off this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some predictions: A rise in “microvacations,” or one- to three-day trips, often to far-flung destinations, for travelers short on time. And at wellness destinations, a growing focus on the healing effects of sound, such as “vibroacoustic” spa treatments that use specialized beds and headphones so that guests not only hear but physically feel therapeutic tracks. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask: Should you keep hitting snooze on your alarm? We’ve got some answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen: Our music critic honors the classics of pop gibberish songs with this playlist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organize: Is your medicine cabinet a mess? Here are tips on what to toss and what to keep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: “The Typewriter and the Guillotine” recounts Janet Flanner’s career in Paris as The New Yorker magazine’s first foreign correspondent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Turkish yogurt cake is similar to a lemon-scented cheesecake, but it’s lighter and has a fresher, tangier flavor. It’s good both warm and cold, either on its own or topped with berries. Make sure to use a thick, strained yogurt, or the texture won’t be as creamy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these canals?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Petersburg, Russia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suzhou, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico City, Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tigre, Argentina&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. Have a great weekend! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/davos-trump-greenland-ukraine.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:20:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Kennedy Plan to Test a Vaccine in West African Babies Is Blocked</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/health/hepatitis-b-vaccine-africa-study.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/xx-bissau-vaccine-01-pfcz/xx-bissau-vaccine-01-pfcz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The West African nation of Guinea-Bissau has suspended a controversial U.S.-funded study of the hepatitis B vaccine in infants there after an outcry from public health researchers over the ethics of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention approved a $1.6 million grant for the study last month, days after the health secretary, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., lifted the agency’s longstanding recommendation to give the vaccine to all infants at birth. Although the World Health Organization also recommends giving the shot at birth, Mr. Kennedy said more research was needed about the effects of a birth dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, which was to be carried out by Danish researchers, swiftly became the subject of furor in the public health world, with researchers in Africa and the United States saying that it violated key tenets of ethical science. A Trump administration health official said the study had been paused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International agreements on medical research in humans require researchers to offer the globally accepted standard of care (in this case, vaccination at birth) to any participant in a clinical trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this study, half of the 14,000 infants studied were not going to be given the vaccine until they were six weeks old. Researchers were not going to screen pregnant women for hepatitis B — a basic step that would protect the babies of infected women, who could be vaccinated at birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Hilliard, a spokeswoman for the Department of Health and Human Services, which oversees the C.D.C., said the goal of the research had been to answer questions about the effects of the hepatitis B vaccine. The study design was “based on the highest scientific and ethical standards,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One in five people in Guinea-Bissau lives with hepatitis B, a virus that can cause severe liver damage and cancer, and each year thousands of infants there are exposed to the virus at birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country currently vaccinates infants against hepatitis B at six weeks of age, as part of routine immunization. The government plans to introduce birth-dose vaccination, which is more expensive, in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, the Danish researchers intended to take advantage of the fact that Guinea-Bissau, one of the world’s least developed countries, is not yet able to follow the global standard. They planned to vaccinate some children at birth, and assess them over time compared with children who got the six-week dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This takes us back to bad research practices with the argument being that the standard of care is not available in that particular environment,” said Dr. Boghuma Titanji, an infectious diseases physician at Emory University. “Researchers are exploiting a scarcity situation to basically ram through this unethical study.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birth-dose vaccination for hepatitis B prevents mother-to-child transmission of the virus. Infants infected at birth have a significantly higher risk of developing chronic liver disease as adults, and many die in their 30s or 40s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Quinhin Nantote, Guinea-Bissau’s minister of public health, said the study had not received proper ethical approval, and his office has suspended it. He said the government would consider if and how the study could proceed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has not been sufficient review to take a final decision on this study,” he said. “We don’t have the necessary input from the ethical committee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The guiding principle of my work is ‘go there.’ I want to hear directly from the people who are affected by disease, or lack of access to a new drug. I’ve been writing about global health for 30 years and have reported from more than 80 countries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many public health leaders say the study poses a question that has already been overwhelmingly answered by science: The birth dose of the vaccine prevents suffering and premature death. Given this evidence, this study, in its goal and its design, is problematic, said Dr. Jeanne Marrazzo, chief executive officer of the Infectious Diseases Society of America and the former top vaccine official for the National Institutes of Health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Essentially, you’re saying that lives of people in those settings don’t deserve the best interventions that we have available in countries with a different standard of care,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other vaccine experts have raised different concerns with the study, which has additional private funding. It is designed to look for effects from the hepatitis B vaccine that include changes in neurological development and atopic dermatitis, a skin condition, but not at whether African children whose vaccines were delayed were more likely to carry hepatitis B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study grant was awarded to a team from the University of Southern Denmark whose work has been widely criticized by other researchers. Mr. Kennedy cited their work when he decided to cut off vaccine aid for the developing world, although the team has found a mix of benefits and harms that they attribute to vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Christine Stabell Benn, the principal investigator on the Danish team, said the study had been approved by the relevant authorities in Guinea-Bissau and had met her university’s requirements for research ethics oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, an official with the Guinea-Bissau National Health Research Ethics Committee, who did not want to be named, citing the lack of authority to give interviews, told The New York Times that the study had been reviewed and approved in the fourth quarter of 2025, before the coup and change in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Commodore Nanote, the health minister, told reporters in a press briefing on Thursday that he was not certain whether the ethics committee had in fact reviewed the study. “We have no evidence of any meeting they held, we don’t even have minutes of a negotiated approval,” he said. “We believe that they did not hold a meeting, did not gather and did not address the issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guinea-Bissau consistently ranks among the 10 least-developed nations in the world, with a minimal health system — the country does not have a single oncologist or M.R.I. machine, for example. A military coup in November has further weakened fragile state institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gavi, the international organization that helps low-income countries purchase vaccines, began to assist countries in introducing birth-dose hepatitis B vaccination last year. (Mr. Kennedy ended U.S. funding to Gavi, significantly constraining its finances. Congress has proposed restoring funding in the spending bill now under consideration.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birth-dose vaccines are more expensive because they can be harder to deliver (roughly half of women in the country give birth at home), and refrigeration and other infrastructure has to be set up in labor wards to preserve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason that children in Guinea-Bissau are not getting the birth dose presently is not because there is uncertainty about the vaccine. It’s because they’re unable to implement their policy for resource-related reasons,” said Dr. Keymanthri Moodley, an emeritus professor of bioethics at Stellenbosch University in South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said the study was reminiscent of controversy in the 1990s about a C.D.C.-funded clinical trial in East and Southern Africa that tested a drug that blocked pregnant women with H.I.V. from transmitting the virus to their babies. Women in one part of the trial received a placebo — and as a result, many babies were infected with the then-fatal illness. The researchers defended the trial by saying that since the drug was not available in the countries where they tested the intervention, no one was worse off than they would have been without the research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that controversy, changes were made to the Declaration of Helsinki, an international agreement that sets out the terms of ethical medical research, to require that research participants in the control group receive the “best proven” intervention. In the case of the Guinea-Bissau trial, that would be the birth-dose vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health officials in Guinea-Bissau expressed frustration with the study as an example of foreign-funded research that is not well communicated to the population who will be studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a huge lack of information regarding this health testing, or any health experiments,” Cadija Mané, a former senior official in the Health Ministry, said. “There needs to be a better flow of information.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ricci Shryock contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/health/hepatitis-b-vaccine-africa-study.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 13:59:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mark Carney Says Firmly That ‘Canada Doesn’t Live Because of the United States’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/canada/carney-trump-canada-speech.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22canada-carney-bzlg/22canada-carney-bzlg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Mark Carney became Canada’s prime minister last year, he was known mostly as a technocratic central banker who had gone on to success in the world of global finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Mr. Carney returned this week from the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, he was suddenly a global political star. The normally reserved audience at the annual gathering of billionaires, investors, chief executives and politicians rose in an exceptional standing ovation at the end of Mr. Carney’s rousing, 30-minute speech on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney was praised for his candid assessment of what he called an irrevocable “rupture” to the global order caused by President Trump, and for urging other middle powers to join Canada in charting a distinct path away from the world’s superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in sharp contrast to other world leaders who flatter Mr. Trump or keep their heads down for fear of provoking him, Mr. Carney speaks bluntly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, less than a day after returning from Davos, Mr. Carney set out Canada’s direction in a speech in Quebec City, saying that his country “must be a beacon — an example to a world at sea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In a time of rising walls and thickening borders, we demonstrate how a country can be both open and secure, welcoming and strong, principled and powerful,” he said, speaking where his cabinet was meeting, in a fortress built by the British more than 200 years ago to fend off American invaders. “There are literally billions of people who aspire to what we have built. A pluralistic society that works. A public square that’s loud, diverse and free. An economy that delivers broadly shared prosperity. A democracy that chooses to protect the most vulnerable against the powerful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He continued: “Canada can’t solve all the world’s problems. But we can show that another way is possible. That the arc of history isn’t destined to be warped towards authoritarianism and exclusion. It can still bend towards progress and justice."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney’s speech on Thursday, like the one in Davos on Tuesday, did not mention Mr. Trump by name. But the reference was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speech dealt largely with domestic issues, including a recent rekindling of support for separatism in Quebec, and appeared to be an effort to both reassure and energize Canadians who have been left angered, exhausted and fearful by Mr. Trump’s year in office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we’re reminded that we live in an era of great power rivalry,” Mr. Carney said on Tuesday in Switzerland. “That the rules-based order is fading. That the strong can do what they can, and the weak must suffer what they must.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney said that for their survival, nations should no longer “go along to get along” with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Carney and Mr. Trump have a generally cordial relationship, the two speeches underscored the Canadian leader’s plan to further distance his country from Mr. Trump’s version of the United States, the largest market for Canada’s export-dependent economy and a nation with which it shares the world’s longest land border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Canada is in a free trade agreement with the United States and Mexico, Mr. Trump has imposed a variety of tariffs that threaten key Canadian industries including autos, steel and aluminum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how Mr. Trump’s desire to take over Greenland, another neighbor of Canada’s, is resolved, the issue has stirred concern and anger among Canadians about his threats to make Canada the 51st state. Shortly before Mr. Carney spoke in Davos, Mr. Trump posted on social media an A.I. photograph that included a United States flag superimposed over a map of Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a rambling speech in Davos on Wednesday, Mr. Trump struck back at Mr. Carney’s words from the day before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Canada gets a lot of freebies from us. By the way, they should be grateful also, but they’re not,” Mr. Trump said. “I watched your prime minister yesterday. He wasn’t so grateful — they should be grateful to us, Canada. Canada lives because of the United States. Remember that, Mark, the next time you make your statements.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two men did not meet in Davos. On Thursday, Mr. Carney returned rhetorical fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Canada and the United States have built a remarkable partnership in the economy, in security and in rich cultural exchange,” Mr. Carney said. “But Canada doesn’t live because of the United States. Canada thrives because we are Canadian.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/canada/carney-trump-canada-speech.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nazis, Soviets and Trump: America’s Fixation With Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/greenland-trump-cold-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22dc-greenland-coldwar-01-zbgk/22dc-greenland-coldwar-01-zbgk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last Nazis on Greenland were captured in October 1944, when American soldiers raided a hidden German weather station on the island’s desolate west coast and took dozens of prisoners. Within a year, Germany would be defeated and World War II would be over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But 80 years of both tension and cooperation between Denmark and the United States over Greenland was just beginning — culminating in President Trump’s current obsession with acquiring the Arctic island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the story begins with World War II, it was shaped by the Cold War that followed, in which the United States transformed barren Greenland into a major military asset, populating it with air bases, towering radar sites and even a never-completed underground bunker complex meant to house nuclear missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was all possible under an agreement with Denmark that granted the United States nearly unlimited military freedom on the island, one that remains in force today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We did it before, we can do it again,” said Daniel Fried, a former senior State Department official who worked on Soviet issues in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether Mr. Trump understands this history has been a mystery as European leaders try to convince him to drop his insistence on owning the island. Mr. Trump said on Wednesday that a “framework” for a deal had been reached, but the details remained murky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an era before military air power, before Mr. Trump was even born, American military planners gave Greenland little thought. But when Germany invaded and occupied Denmark in 1940, they realized that the island, then a Danish colony sparsely populated by mainly Inuit people, was vulnerable to Nazi control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With airfields perilously close to America’s east coast, important mineral reserves and an ideal location to track weather that shaped battle conditions in Europe, Greenland’s defense was considered essential to the United States. It was an idea that would persist for decades before fading briefly after the Cold War and returning with a vengeance in the Trump era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s king had welcomed the American force and approved a written agreement granting the broad military latitude on the island, as long as a threat existed, without giving up any Danish sovereignty. With Germany vanquished and the war over, however, his country was ready to bid the Americans farewell. “Danish public opinion was expecting a return to full control of Greenland,” explained a study of the matter by the Danish Institute of Public Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington had other ideas. The advent of long-range bombers had created a new sense of vulnerability just as the Soviet Union was emerging as a new threat to the United States. Greenland happened to lie along the most direct flight path to the Eastern United States from Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Greenland’s 800,000 square miles make it the world’s largest island and stationary aircraft carrier,” Time magazine wrote in January 1947. It “would be invaluable, in either conventional or push-button war, as an advance radar outpost,” and a forward position for future rocket-launching sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Americans had no intention of leaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bad news was delivered in December 1946 by the U.S. secretary of state, James F. Byrnes. During a meeting at the Waldorf Astoria hotel in New York, Mr. Byrnes explained to his Danish counterpart, Gustav Rasmussen, that Greenland had become “vital to the defense of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the American military’s presence could be extended, Mr. Byrnes said, he had a better idea: Denmark should simply sell Greenland to America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea “seemed to come as a shock” to Mr. Rasmussen, who accurately predicted that his government would reject the idea, according to another State Department memo. But unlike the current blowup, the matter was handled “quietly” by both sides, noted Heather Conley, a nonresident senior fellow at the American Enterprise Institute who specializes in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Truman administration did not push, partly for fear that Moscow would claim that the United States had stolen land from a European ally. As the Soviet threat grew more vivid in Europe, Denmark became more willing to let American troops stay in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1951, the United States and Denmark reached an agreement “uniting their efforts for collective defense” under the auspices of the newly formed North Atlantic Treaty Organization. While stressing Denmark’s continued sovereignty over the island, the agreement granted the United States broad freedom to “construct, install, maintain and operate facilities and equipment” and to “station and house personnel,” along with other rights related to military activity. That included deepening harbors and even maintaining postal facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement did not include an expiration date, and Denmark has never asserted one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the agreement’s few limitations was to delineate specific “defense areas” within which the United States could operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the deal in hand, and freshly alarmed by a Soviet-backed communist offensive in Korea, the U.S. military quickly went to work. In a secret crash project, military engineers working around the clock in 24-hour Arctic daylight built a major air base at Thule in northwest Greenland. Manned by thousands of American personnel, the base’s 10,000-foot runway would serve as a launching point for strategic bombers and spy planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a dozen military bases and radar and weather monitoring stations eventually opened across the island. A 1,240-foot tower was erected at Thule for long wave transmissions to eastern Canada. In 1959, the United States started Project Ice Worm, another secret endeavor that envisioned a giant complex of bunkers, dozens of feet underground, meant to house nuclear missiles that could survive a Soviet first strike. (The project was deemed unfeasible and abandoned after several years.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as missile technology improved, the United States established more systems meant to provide early warning for a Soviet attack. While they were considered invaluable, the systems were far from foolproof: In October 1960, one U.S. radar system detected a massive Soviet missile launch with near certainty. It turned out that the system had spotted the moon rising over Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark raised few objections, satisfied that its sovereignty over Greenland remained protected. To underscore the point, a Danish flag flew alongside the American one at Thule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangement was tested in January 1968, when a U.S. B-52 bomber carrying four hydrogen bombs crashed while trying to make an emergency landing at Thule. The bomber had been part of an “airborne alert” program run by the U.S. Strategic Air Command, which kept several nuclear-armed bombers airborne 24 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bombs were incinerated on impact in conventional explosions, but left radioactive traces even after an arduous cleanup. Some Danish politicians expressed outrage that the United States had brought nuclear weapons to the island, although American officials insisted that such weapons were implicitly covered by the 1951 agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the peak of the United States’ military presence in Greenland during the Cold War, some 10,000 U.S. personnel were stationed on the island. But after the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991, the cost of a large footprint on an Arctic island made little sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most U.S. installations on Greenland were closed over the next decade, with U.S. activity consolidating at Thule, whose name was changed in 2023 to Pituffik in an acknowledgment of a former Inuit settlement there. It is now a U.S. Space Force base, staffed by about 150 people who manage early warning radar and satellite communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump argues that Greenland is once again vital to American security, and many national security experts agree. They point to growing Arctic competition with Russia and China over natural resources and shipping lanes as melting ice reshapes the region. Mr. Trump also says that Greenland is crucial to the ambitious “Golden Dome” missile defense system he hopes to build in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump has never made clear why he must control Greenland to serve these needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Conley of the American Enterprise Institute said that a solution, if there were one, might mirror the events of the early Cold War. Having been denied ownership of the island, Mr. Trump appears to be considering an enhanced U.S. military presence on Greenland that is part of a new NATO mission to defend the island. “That’s the right approach,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Fried agreed, but said he wished the process could have played out quietly, the way it did nearly a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump could have achieved this without all the drama,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/greenland-trump-cold-war.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:12:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>No Beer for You: How British Pubs Fought a Tax Increase</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-pubs-rates-u-turn.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-uk-pubs-02-promo/23int-uk-pubs-02-gvlt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With its wooden beams, thatched roof and open log fire, the 17th-century Old Thatch pub offers a warm welcome to customers in southern England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But one influential group of Britons can expect a frosty reception: lawmakers from the governing Labour Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Old Thatch is one of more than 1,400 pubs and restaurants to have banned all Labour legislators in a protest over a planned increase in a property tax, which landlords say will cost them thousands of pounds a year. Announced just before Christmas, when many Britons gather in pubs to celebrate the holiday, the pub ban gained widespread attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it appears to have worked. The government is expected to announce concessions within days, the latest in a series of policy flip-flops that critics have seized on as evidence of Prime Minister Keir Starmer’s weakness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have them on the run,” said Andy Lennox, landlord of the pub in Wimborne near Bournemouth, where the rebellion began. He wants to see the detail of the policy reversal before calling off the ban: “If you don’t have the stick, you don’t get the carrot.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few parts of British life generate as much affection as pubs, and angering landlords has produced an especially swift backlash from a hospitality sector already buffeted by Brexit, the Covid-19 pandemic, inflation and higher energy prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trigger for the landlords’ protest was a change in business rates — an annual tax on commercial property — that was announced in November alongside the budget. The government is also ending some temporary concessions granted to pubs and restaurants during the pandemic that have been winding down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to UKHospitality, a trade body representing the sector, pubs on average can expect business rates to increase 15 percent this year — equivalent to an extra £1,400, or about $1,880 per pub, even after transitional help. In the 2027 to 2028 financial year, average rates will be £4,500 more than today and £7,000 higher the following year, the organization said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Kennell, an associate professor at Surrey University who studies the hospitality industry, said that Brexit had made it harder for pubs to recruit freely from continental Europe, and the sector was then hit hard by lockdowns during the pandemic. Pubs are also particularly exposed to increases in the minimum wage and rises in payroll tax — two other policies that Labour has introduced in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The government wants to talk about big-ticket investments, where a minister can go and put a hard hat on and stand in front of a factory,” said Dr. Kennell. In contrast, he said, pubs and restaurants are often overlooked, despite their central role in Britain’s social fabric and as employers. “If you look at Italy, France, Spain, hospitality careers are seen as being prestigious,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the government announced its plans in 2025, the Treasury said that, thanks to its interventions, “the sector’s total bill will only increase by 4 percent next year.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week the chancellor of the Exchequer, Rachel Reeves, promised more help for “our pubs and the hospitality sector.” Speaking in Davos earlier this week, she added, “The situation the pubs face is different from other parts of the hospitality sector, but we will be setting out the detail in the next few days.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over a beer at the Old Thatch, Mr. Lennox said that the protest would most likely continue if the concessions promised by Mr. Starmer applied just to pubs but not to restaurants — as Ms. Reeves hinted she was considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lennox, who runs a total of eight pubs and restaurants, wants the government to cut VAT, a sales tax, from the standard rate of 20 percent to 13 percent for hospitality businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He described how the campaign began after James Fowler, a friend who runs a nearby restaurant called The Larder House, put a sign in his window banning Labour lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some critics question the practicality of the ban. There are 404 Labour members of Parliament, and very few landlords will recognize more than a handful. Others have spoken out against the idea of excluding an entire group of people from places they may want to go with families or friends, or where they would interact with people in the community whom they are meant to represent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a video filmed outside the Larder House, Tom Hayes, the member of Parliament representing the local area of Bournemouth East, made an impassioned argument against the exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s the Christmas season, it’s meant to be the joyful season. But The Larder House and other businesses with a ‘No Labour MPs’ sticker in the window, they are undermining the inclusive culture that business owners locally have helped to nourish,” he said. “My job has just got a million times harder because I can’t go and bang the drum for business with the chancellor if I can’t speak with business leaders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Hayes did not respond to requests for comment. Months before the ban, he had praised Mr. Fowler and several other hospitality business owners during a parliamentary debate on supporting the hospitality sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As entrepreneurs, they are investing time, money and personal risk to create jobs and community hubs,” Mr. Hayes said. “They shoulder costs and were often overlooked in policy discussions over the past 14 years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the Old Thatch, there was support for the ban from customers. “Yes, hit them where it hurts — they can’t have a pint,” said Karen Rawlings, 61, who runs a nearby pet care business. “It’s a shame they have to go that far as they are turning away business away, but if it makes a point, fair play.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In London, the issue is so sensitive at the Pineapple pub, which Mr. Starmer frequented before he became prime minister, that staff declined to discuss it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the nearby Bull &amp; Gate, Frances Marfleet, 35, who works in health care, said that pubs play an important role in communities. “It’s a big part of our culture in this country,” she said. “If the pub around the corner from your house, that has provided you with joy every weekend for 20 years, suddenly closes, that is really impactful — negatively — on your life, that’s sad.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-pubs-rates-u-turn.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 20:01:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Son-in-Law of Venezuelan Opposition Candidate Freed</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/edmundo-gonzalez-rafael-tudares-detention.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-venezuela-release02-photo-jhpf/22int-venezuela-release02-photo-jhpf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edmundo González, the man widely considered the legitimate winner of Venezuela’s tainted 2024 presidential election, said Thursday that his son-in-law Rafael Tudares had been released after more than a year in Venezuelan detention — one of several recent high-profile releases amid continuing repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González’s daughter confirmed he was free. “After 380 days of an unjust arbitrary detention and having endured, for more than a year, an inhuman situation of enforced disappearance, my husband Rafael Tudares Bracho has returned home,” Mariana González de Tudares wrote on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González, 76, said that the move ended “a year marked by uncertainty, silence, and anguish” for his family but that it underscored the necessity of Venezuela’s freeing all remaining political prisoners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Rafael’s release does not erase what happened,” he said in a video posted to social media. “On the contrary, it reinforces a demand that remains fully in force.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Tudares was detained last year while walking his children to school, Mr. González said, when hooded men dressed in black seized him and drove him away. His disappearance was part of a government crackdown after the 2024 election that led Mr. González, a retired diplomat, to flee into exile in Spain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s interim government, led by Delcy Rodríguez, has begun freeing a limited number of detainees since U.S. forces captured President Nicolás Maduro this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of almost 900 political prisoners in Venezuela, 151 have been let go, according to a leading human rights group, Foro Penal, with many of those freed still facing charges, travel bans and regular enforced court appearances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. González said last month that her husband had been sentenced to 30 years in prison after a single closed-door hearing the month before on conspiracy charges. The accusations of conspiracy included another person that Mr. Tudares’s family said he had never met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities, she said, denied the family and lawyers access to the case file, classified the proceedings as confidential and barred him from choosing his own lawyer. Mr. Tudares’s legal case, his family said, was a violation of due process and international human rights standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. González said at the time that Mr. Tudares was being held at Rodeo One, a high-security prison where former detainees have reported abuse, and that she had not been able to visit or communicate with him. A coalition of opposition groups said he had been “subjected to prolonged isolation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A United Nations report said Mr. Tudares was held incommunicado for more than eight months, with his family given no official information about his whereabouts. While the authorities accused him of crimes including forgery, conspiracy, terrorism, money laundering and criminal association, the report said the actual basis for the charges appeared to be his relationship to Mr. González and his role as a legal representative for his father-in-law in a property matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Tudares’s release came days after Ms. González said she had been the target of three separate extortion attempts that indicated her husband’s freedom depended on forcing her father to abandon his political cause. The government did not respond immediately to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts said Mr. Tudares’s release could be linked to pressure from Washington. It came a day after the U.S. representative to the Organization of American States called for the liberation of all political prisoners in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Slowly but surely the government is being forced to release even high-profile political prisoners,” said Geoff Ramsey, who studies Colombia and Venezuela at the Atlantic Council, a Washington research institute. “As much as Delcy Rodríguez claims she’s in the driver’s seat, she’s having to make an increasing number of concessions to Washington.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, he added, repression continues and, amid Venezuela’s rapprochement with the Trump administration, whether there will be an opening of political freedom remains an open question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump, said in an interview on Fox News this month that it was “going to be a while before they can have elections,” adding, “but ultimately they’ll have elections.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phil Gunson, an analyst based in Caracas with the International Crisis Group, a research organization, said the government had been holding Mr. Tudares hostage to try to force his father-in-law to abandon his claim to the presidency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But it may also reflect the fact that — for now at least — there seems little prospect that Washington will insist the Rodriguez government honor the true result of the 2024 presidential election,” Mr. Gunson said. “More plausible is a fresh election at some indeterminate future date. In that regard, perhaps Edmundo González represents less of a threat to Chavismo.” Chavismo refers to the socialist-influenced political movement that has led the country for more than two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/edmundo-gonzalez-rafael-tudares-detention.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 09:00:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky Laces Into Europe, Saying It Must Step Up or Be Left Behind</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/davos-zelensky.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-davos-zelensky-photo-ftmc/22int-davos-zelensky-photo-ftmc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine used a blunt speech before the world’s political and business elites on Thursday to take aim at European countries, denouncing their inability to stop Russia’s aggression and their timid response to President Trump’s threat to seize Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky’s speech, delivered at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, was among his most scathing critiques of Europe. It was unexpected, given that the continent has become Ukraine’s most reliable ally as the Trump administration has stepped back from supporting Kyiv’s war effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The address amounted to a call to action for a continent that Mr. Zelensky portrayed as unprepared for a world growing more dangerous by the day. He warned that Europe must unite and step up or risk being left behind in an increasingly competitive global order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ukraine has a direct interest in Europe’s long-term strength, as Kyiv seeks to tie its own future to the continent’s by pursuing membership in the European Union. Mr. Zelensky has argued that Europe’s fate is also tied to Ukraine’s, with a revanchist Russia on its doorstep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Instead of becoming a truly global power, Europe remains a beautiful but fragmented kaleidoscope of small and middle powers,” Mr. Zelensky said on Thursday afternoon. “Instead of taking the lead in defending freedom worldwide, especially when America’s focus shifts elsewhere, Europe looks lost, trying to convince the U.S. president to change. But he will not change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had been unclear just a couple of days ago whether Mr. Zelensky would even appear in Davos. He said earlier in the week that he would attend only if “real results for Ukraine” were on the table, fueling expectations that a deal on a postwar recovery plan or security guarantees might be reached. No such agreement materialized on Thursday. Mr. Zelensky met with Mr. Trump, and both leaders described their talks as “good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky’s trip to Davos came as he has to deal with a host of issues at home, starting with Russia’s slow but steady advance on the battlefield and a sustained campaign of strikes on the energy infrastructure that has plunged most of the country into darkness amid the cold of winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the Ukrainian leader has rarely missed an occasion to meet with his American counterpart to press his case. On Thursday, Mr. Zelensky said that he and Mr. Trump had reached an agreement on U.S. security guarantees for Ukraine after the war. He offered no details on what these guarantees would entail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, he had said that U.S. security guarantees were “essentially ready.” But European officials in Kyiv said at the time that the nature of these guarantees remained unclear. Mr. Trump did not comment on the issue on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With peace in Ukraine seemingly no closer at hand, Mr. Zelensky turned to imploring Europe to do more to fill the vacuum left by Mr. Trump in sustaining the post-World War II global order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His remarks risked straining Ukraine’s alliance with a continent that has remained a steadfast source of financial, humanitarian and military support throughout the war, especially after the United States under Mr. Trump disengaged from Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky’s speech offered an unfiltered list of what he saw as Europe’s failures to assert geopolitical strength compared with the United States, which he said had acted forcefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He noted that while there were “different opinions” about the U.S. military operation in Venezuela to capture its leader, Nicolás Maduro, “the fact remains: Maduro is on trial in New York.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sorry, but Putin is not on trial,” he added, referring to President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky also contrasted U.S. actions against oil tankers linked to Venezuela and Russia with Europe’s limited enforcement against Russia’s so‑called shadow fleet of tankers that ferry oil under false flags to help Moscow evade sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as Mr. Zelensky spoke, however, President Emmanuel Macron of France announced that the French Navy had intercepted an oil tanker in the Mediterranean Sea that traveled from Russia. The vessel, Mr. Macron said, was “subject to international sanctions and suspected of flying a false flag.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky perhaps hit a raw nerve in exposing Europe’s reliance on U.S. support. He made clear that the continent needed to prepare for a future in which America could no longer be counted on to come to its allies’ defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today, Europe relies only on the belief that if danger comes, NATO will act,” he said, referring to the Western military alliance, whose power comes largely from the United States’ military. “But no one has really seen the alliance in action. If Putin decides to take Lithuania or strike Poland, who will respond? Who will respond?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right now, NATO exists thanks to the belief that the United States will act, that it will not stand aside and will help. But what if it doesn’t?” Mr. Zelensky continued. “Believe me, this question is everywhere, in the minds of every European leader.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those were striking remarks coming from a leader who has long pressed for Ukraine’s integration into NATO, viewing membership in the military alliance as the country’s strongest security guarantee against future Russian aggression. The Trump administration has said it opposes admitting Ukraine to NATO after the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky called on Europe to step up as it vows to deploy troops to Ukraine after any peace deal with Russia. In private, some Ukrainian officials have dismissed Europe’s pledges, saying such forces would not deter Russia and lack experience fighting a modern war increasingly shaped by new technologies such as drones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky’s administration has long said that Ukraine’s best hope for protecting itself from Russia in the long term is to maintain the strength of its own military, which is the most powerful in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ukrainian leader arrived in Davos shortly after Mr. Trump’s threat to annex Greenland by force had threatened to plunge the Western alliance into disarray. Greenland, a Danish territory, is itself part of NATO, making the threat tantamount to one NATO member attacking another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, ultimately, walked back his threats in Davos, saying that an understanding had been reached with NATO to avoid a confrontation. Still, Mr. Zelensky criticized Europe’s response, which included sending a small contingent of troops to Greenland as a show of solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If you send 30 or 40 soldiers to Greenland — what is that for?” he said. “What message does it send? What’s the message to Putin? To China?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky said Ukraine needed Europe’s power “to protect our own independence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directly addressing European leaders, he added, “You need Ukraine’s independence, too — because tomorrow, you may have to defend your way of life. And when Ukraine is with you, no one will wipe their feet on you.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/davos-zelensky.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:22:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Denmark Bristles at Idea of Giving Up Any Sovereignty in Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump-us-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-greenland-denmark01-photo-hmbp/22int-greenland-denmark01-photo-hmbp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danish officials pushed back on Thursday against any talk of compromising on the sovereignty of Greenland amid confusion over what kind of deal NATO leaders may have struck with President Trump over the future of the Arctic island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can negotiate on everything political; security, investments, economy. But we cannot negotiate on our sovereignty,” Mette Frederiksen, Denmark’s prime minister, said in a statement on Thursday about Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland has been part of the Danish kingdom for more than 300 years, and “only Denmark and Greenland themselves can make decisions on issues concerning Denmark and Greenland,” Ms. Frederiksen said.It is not clear whether Denmark’s position could scuttle any possible agreement over Greenland that Mr. Trump said he had reached with Mark Rutte, NATO’s secretary general, on Wednesday evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had been insisting that the United States take over the island, despite resistance from Denmark and Greenland. He did not reveal the details of a possible breakthrough though he called it “the ultimate long term deal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior Danish official, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy, said: “There have been no direct discussions between Denmark and the U.S. about the possibility of granting the U.S. sovereign parcels of land.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several Western officials said one possible compromise floated by NATO officials was that the United States could obtain sovereignty over land for its military bases in Greenland. Right now, it has one, a remote missile defense station with around 150 personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen said that she has been speaking with Mr. Rutte “on an ongoing basis.” But it’s not clear how much Denmark has been actually involved in the discussions with Mr. Trump. She seemed to be trying to protect Denmark and Greenland from being excluded and emphasized that Mr. Rutte “does not have a mandate to negotiate on behalf of Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nor does he have a mandate to negotiate on behalf of Denmark,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials in Greenland’s semiautonomous government seemed upset as well about what was unfolding and their lack of participation in the decision making.“I don’t know what there is in the agreement or the deal about my country, that over some discussions I didn’t attend,” Jens-Frederik Nielsen, the island’s prime minister, said on Thursday. “I don’t know what’s concrete in it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already under an American-Danish defense pact, the United States enjoys sweeping military access to Greenland. A potential new arrangement could upgrade American control over its bases on the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Ms. Frederiksen bristled at any suggestion of changing the sovereign status of any territory on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our red lines are the same as they have been all along,” she said in a televised interview. “We will of course not cede sovereignty. And Greenland’s future must be defined by Greenland, and Greenland is part of Denmark.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troels Lund Poulsen, Denmark’s defense minister, indicated that the Greenland crisis might have eased but that it wasn’t over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There will certainly be more difficult conversations with the Americans,” he said in a post on social media. “But following Wednesday’s meeting between NATO Secretary General Mark Rutte and Donald Trump, we are in a clearly better place today than we were yesterday.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “Rutte cannot of course negotiate an agreement on behalf of Denmark or Greenland, but my impression is that Rutte has worked loyally for the unity of NATO.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is very positive that NATO will now do more to strengthen security in and around the Arctic,” he said. “I am very happy about that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenlanders haven’t been happy at all. They have resented Mr. Trump’s acquisitive approach to their homeland since he first floated the idea of buying the island, the world’s largest, from Denmark during his first term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday night, in his speech to the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Trump mistakenly referred to Greenland as Iceland and kept describing it as “a piece of ice” and once even called it a “big, beautiful piece of ice.”It is true that most of Greenland is covered by a thick ice sheet. But Greenlanders find it offensive that Mr. Trump rarely mentions the 57,000 people living on the island, who are mostly Indigenous. On Wednesday night, Aaja Chemnitz, one of the two Greenlandic members of the Danish Parliament and a major political figure in Greenland, said it was wrong that Mr. Trump was negotiating with NATO about Greenland without Greenland at the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we are witnessing these days in statements from Trump is completely absurd,” she said in a post that appeared on Facebook. “NATO has absolutely no mandate to negotiate anything whatsoever without us in Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nothing about us, without us,” she said. “There is total confusion being created.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonas Gahr Støre, the prime minister of Norway, warned in an interview published Thursday that the situation is “by no means over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just a few days ago, Mr. Trump had sent him a text message saying he wanted to take control of Greenland because he hadn’t won a Nobel Peace Prize, which an independent panel administers in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“With Trump, things can come and go,” Mr. Store said in another interview, broadcast live with the Norwegian broadcaster, NRK. “So we must keep a close watch.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview at Davos with a Norwegian financial paper, DN, Mr Støre said that Mr. Trump hadn’t abandoned his interest in Greenland and that maybe it was the stock market slide earlier this week that had motivated him to change course. After Mr. Trump had threatened to use tariffs to pressure European countries to hand over Greenland, markets fell around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Important parts of American business have sent signals that this is not good for them,” Mr. Store said. “He reads the market, and I think that is part of the reason we saw a change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henrik Pryser Libell contributed reporting from Oslo.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump-us-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 12:33:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Lays Out a Glittering Plan for Gaza, Including Skyscrapers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/middleeast/us-gaza-peace-trump-kushner-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-gaza-tvmw/22int-gaza-tvmw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration laid out an ambitious and highly speculative vision for the future of the Gaza Strip at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Thursday, as Washington tries to advance the thorny cease-fire between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation by Jared Kushner, President Trump’s son-in-law, featured slides that depicted gleaming skyscrapers rising on Gaza’s coast and the construction of entirely new cities. The plan would require investment of at least $25 billion in the devastated Palestinian enclave, according to the proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaza would be rebuilt in phases, he said, starting with the south. The southern city of Rafah — which Israel largely razed during its war against Hamas — would be rebuilt in two to three years, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We said, ‘Let’s plan for catastrophic success,’” Mr. Kushner said in Davos, adding that there was no “Plan B.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, however, those sweeping ideas exist mostly on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas has not agreed to lay down its arms and disband its battalions of fighters. The United States has struggled to convince countries to contribute soldiers to a proposed peacekeeping force for Gaza. And it is far from clear who would provide the billions that the Trump administration’s lofty plans would require.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kushner outlined the proposal during a gathering in a Davos conference room to formally inaugurate Mr. Trump’s “Board of Peace,” which the president said last year would help oversee both the Israel-Hamas truce and the reconstruction of Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the ceremony, Ali Shaath, the head of a Palestinian committee of technocrats that the board would oversee, said that the Rafah border crossing with Egypt is scheduled to reopen next week. But Israel has not confirmed that. Israeli authorities have vowed to keep the border closed until Hamas returns the body of Ran Gvili, the last Israeli captive whose remains are still in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Trump administration circulated a proposed charter for the Board of Peace that would expand its mandate to other conflicts. That has provoked fierce controversy, with critics now calling the board an attempt to set up a Trump-dominated alternative to the United Nations. Since then, some allies of the United States — including France, Britain, Norway and Sweden — have said they would not join it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel said this week that Israel would join the board, although the country has expressed reservations about the makeup of one of the board’s key committees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the world leaders who officially joined the board at the Davos gathering on Thursday were right-wing populists like President Javier Milei of Argentina and Viktor Orban, the Hungarian prime minister. Close Arab allies of the United States like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Qatar also sent representatives to sign on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the signing ceremony, Mr. Trump seemed to concede that disarming Hamas still posed a major obstacle to his plans for Gaza. He did not say how, exactly, he would pressure the militants to lay down their arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were born with rifles in their hands,” Mr. Trump said. “But they have to give up their weapons, and if they don’t do that, it’s going to be the end of them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas has agreed to hand over day-to-day governance of Gaza to the committee led by Mr. Shaath, a group of independent Palestinian technocrats backed by the United States. But it has not agreed to hand over control of the enclave’s security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say the committee’s success will partly depend on whether Israel eases the restrictions it has imposed on Gaza. In recent months, Israel has kept the Rafah border crossing all but closed, even though it had agreed to open it as part of the truce agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Kushner said the United States would host a Gaza investment conference for the private sector in Washington in a few weeks. He conceded that moving money into the Palestinian enclave could be “a little risky” but said it would also provide “amazing investment opportunities.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/middleeast/us-gaza-peace-trump-kushner-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 17:13:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Rift With Europe Is Clear. Europe Must Decide What to Do About It.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/trump-rift-europe.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-europe-assess01-photo-gqmv/22int-europe-assess01-photo-gqmv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depth of the rift between President Trump and Europe was on full display on Wednesday as Mr. Trump delivered remarks in Davos, Switzerland, airing his disdain for Europe’s immigration policies, its regulations and its strident unwillingness to give him Greenland, which he insists America must own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Europe has been looking to find a diplomatic answer to de-escalate the crisis. Hope for such an off ramp came late Wednesday, when Mr. Trump posted on Truth Social to announce that he and Mark Rutte, the NATO secretary general, were working on a deal that could resolve the dispute over Greenland, an autonomous territory of Denmark. He suggested that tariffs he had previously threatened to impose on European nations starting Feb. 1 would no longer kick in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But neither he nor NATO provided any details of what such that framework might look like, and there is no guarantee that such a deal will be finished. A member of the Danish parliament from Greenland called the deal into question in a social media post, saying it had created “total confusion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dust had not yet settled Wednesday night. But one thing was clear. Mr. Trump’s comments throughout the day underscored just how little the United States and Europe — long the closest of allies — now have in common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While we may no longer be literally staring down the barrel of a gun on the trans-Atlantic relationship, we are still in a very rocky place,” said Jacob Funk Kirkegaard, a senior fellow at Bruegel, a research institute in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are fundamentally at odds, in a way that can only reflect the very different values between most governments in Europe and the Trump administration,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European leaders, many of them shocked by Mr. Trump’s threats to take over the sovereign territory of an E.U. member and NATO ally, must still come together on what they might or should do if Mr. Trump changes his position again — and about the trans-Atlantic relationship more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday evening, leaders from across the 27-nation European Union will gather in Brussels to discuss the perilous state of Europe’s relationship with the United States. They may discuss the contours of the plan Mr. Trump alluded to in his social media post. They will debate how they should approach this new and more hostile era, especially when Russia is still waging war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had announced over the weekend that he intended to apply levies of 10 percent on several European nations that have recently sent troops to Greenland as part of a NATO exercise. Although he has suspended those tariffs, it is unclear if that will last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mere possibility set off a panicked flurry. European ambassadors met for an emergency gathering on Sunday to discuss the development, and many European leaders called Mr. Trump directly. Thursday’s summit was called in response to the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion is likely to touch on the state of play after the gathering in Davos, including Mr. Rutte’s discussion with Mr. Trump. Leaders will also vet what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the tariff issue is resolved, and even if the Greenland matter is resolved, Mr. Trump’s aggressive push for the island — and his language about Europe in recent days and weeks — have exposed a serious rupture forming between the partners that is far from healed. Europe is grappling with a changed reality, after decades in which it relied on a stable relationship with the United States for both trade and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The shift in the international order is not only seismic — but it is permanent,” Ursula von der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on Wednesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior European official, speaking anonymously to discuss sensitive diplomatic matters, appealed for a bit of calm, noting that Mr. Trump recently threatened to sanction any country that did business with Iran, but has not done so until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson, he suggested, was to keep Europe’s powder dry, not to overreact and escalate needlessly with a key ally, and push for diplomacy. To that end, he said the bloc should be ready to retaliate — to have leverage — but should not react unnecessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union already has a 93 billion euro, or $107 billion, list of U.S. goods prepared that it is poised to hit with retaliatory tariffs after Feb. 6. The list was finalized last year in response to Mr. Trump’s earlier trade war, and it will snap into place automatically unless E.U. officials take proactive moves to suspend it — making it a natural first step, should retaliation prove necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also had his usual harsh words for NATO during his speech on Wednesday, asserting that NATO allies would not come to the aid of the United States if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the only time Article V of the NATO treaty, the commitment to collective defense, was ever invoked was to aid the United States after it was attacked on Sept. 11, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NATO troops fought alongside American soldiers in Afghanistan for a decade, and Denmark itself had more soldiers die per capita in Afghanistan than America did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, at Davos, Mr. Rutte, the NATO secretary general, praised Mr. Trump for pushing member states to spend more on their own defense, which has strengthened the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked if he could imagine NATO without the United States, he said simply, “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States “is by far the most powerful nation on earth, and the president of the United States is the leader of the free world,” he said, adding, “And you cannot envision NATO without the leader of the free world being an integral part of that organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte also touched on the most pressing security issue for Europeans, which is Russian aggression against Ukraine — right on the E.U.’s borders — and not an icy island in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The risk here is that we focus, of course, on Greenland, because we have to make sure that issue gets solved in an amicable way,” Mr. Rutte said on a panel in Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ukraine should be our No. 1 priority, and then we can discuss all the issues, including Greenland,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koba Ryckewaert contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/trump-rift-europe.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:44:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipino Journalist Gets Prison in Case Seen as Attack on Free Press</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/philippines-cumpio-journalist-prison.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-philippines-journalist-wzgv/22int-philippines-journalist-wzgv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Philippine court on Thursday convicted a journalist on charges of financing terrorism and sentenced her to more than a decade in prison, in a ruling that rights and press groups said was a blatant attack on press freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Regional Trial Court in Tacloban City gave the journalist, Frenchie Mae Cumpio, and her former roommate Marielle Dumaquil a jail sentence of 12 to 18 years, the maximum allowed. But the women, who have been in prison since they were arrested in 2020, were acquitted of charges of possessing firearms and explosives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before her arrest, Ms. Cumpio, who turns 27 this month, worked as a radio reporter and wrote articles for Eastern Vista, an online publication focused on the Eastern Visayas region of the Philippines. The authorities said her coverage of the community and local politics was biased in favor of communist insurgents, who have long had a presence in the region. She was convicted of being a conduit for funds for the rebels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To many, Ms. Cumpio’s case was a glaring example of “red-tagging,” a practice by some Filipino authorities of linking their critics to the communist insurgency. She was arrested when Rodrigo Duterte was in power, a president who repeatedly attacked his critics in the media and moved to silence them. His successor and the current president of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., had vowed to support a free press in the Philippines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This absurd verdict shows that the various pledges made by President Ferdinand Marcos Jr. to uphold press freedom are nothing but empty talk,” said Beh Li Yih, the Asia-Pacific director of the Committee to Protect Journalists. “Although the journalist was cleared on the charge of illegal possession of firearms, the ruling underscores the lengths that Philippine authorities are willing to go to silence critical reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Philippines must free Frenchie Mae Cumpio without conditions and stop criminalizing journalists,” she continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporters Without Borders, an organization that advocates press freedom, said it had carried out its own investigation into the allegations against the women and concluded that it was a fabricated case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are appalled by this verdict,” said Aleksandra Bielakowska, the advocacy manager for the group. She added that the conviction was a “devastating failure on the part of the Philippine justice system and the authorities’ blatant disregard for press freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the government’s National Task Force to End Local Communist Armed Conflict said the ruling was “a clear affirmation” that the justice system worked because the court threw out the weapons possession charge against Ms. Cumpio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This alone demolishes the false narrative that the courts are mere rubber stamps for the state or instruments of political persecution,” Joel Sy Egco, the spokesman, said in a statement. “It shows judicial independence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Cumpio and Ms. Dumaquil are expected to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/philippines-cumpio-journalist-prison.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:37:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Trump’s Ultimatum, Greenland Talks Include Sovereign U.S. Bases, No Drilling for Russia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-deal-framework.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-greenland-framework-mlkb/22int-greenland-framework-mlkb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negotiations to resolve the future of Greenland have focused in recent days on proposals to increase NATO’s presence in the Arctic, give America a sovereign claim to pockets of Greenland’s territory and block potentially hostile adversaries from mining the island’s minerals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those elements, described by eight senior Western security and diplomatic officials, offer the fullest picture yet of the contours of a potential Greenland compromise that President Trump announced on Wednesday without details. His move appeared to at least temporarily defuse an American-made trans-Atlantic crisis over the Danish territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critically, the proposals under discussion would stop short of Mr. Trump’s goal of transferring ownership of all of Greenland to the United States from Denmark, according to the officials, all of whom spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy. The officials cautioned that many details have yet to be finalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if these discussions will ultimately yield agreement over the territory. Denmark, which publicly opposes ceding ownership of any Greenlandic land, may not agree to the plans on the table. Still, the officials said they were hopeful that they could simultaneously address Mr. Trump’s stated concerns about securing the Arctic against possible threats from Russia and China, while holding to Europe’s “red line” that Greenland was not for sale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, the proposals would:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a significant new NATO mission in the Arctic. Multiple officials have dubbed this mission “Arctic Sentry,” in a nod to similarly named NATO missions in the Baltic Sea and Eastern Europe that are meant to counter an increasingly aggressive Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update a pact signed between Denmark and the United States in 1951. The pact gives the U.S. military wide access to Greenland, an autonomous Danish territory, for operations including the construction and operation of military bases. American officials have said they are concerned that this access could be curbed or ended if Greenland were to obtain independence. NATO officials have discussed expanding the 1951 pact with a new agreement that would effectively create pockets of American soil in the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an agreement would likely be modeled on a “sovereign base area” agreement in Cyprus, where Britain’s military bases are regarded as British territory. That would give the United States greater control over the land than it currently exerts over U.S. embassy sites. Mr. Trump and other officials have said that territory in Greenland could prove important for his plans to build a so-called Golden Dome missile defense system for the United States, which could include components stationed in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restrict non-NATO member countries, particularly Russia and China, from obtaining rights to mine the rare-earth minerals that lie deep under Greenland’s ice sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those plans have been under discussion inside NATO over the last year, as a direct response to Mr. Trump’s stated ambitions. Since returning to the White House in 2025, Mr. Trump has described publicly, with increasing intensity, his desire to own Greenland. Denmark, with equal intensity, has insisted it would not sell, with Danish leaders saying that the island’s fate is up to Denmark, not NATO. Greenland’s prime minister, Jens-Frederik Nielsen, said on Thursday he was not in favor of giving the United States sovereignty over military bases there. “We are ready to discuss a lot of things,” Mr. Nielsen said, adding, “Sovereignty is a red line.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of giving the U.S. a sovereign claim to its bases in Greenland, similar to Britain’s bases in Cyprus, was raised among NATO and Western military officials on Wednesday, according to two officials, one of whom was present in those discussions. Asked for comment, Gen. Alexus G. Grynkewich, the top NATO commander in Europe, said in a brief conversation with The New York Times on Thursday that the idea was discussed as a matter for political leaders to resolve rather than the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you should know. The Times makes a careful decision any time it uses an anonymous source. The information the source supplies must be newsworthy and give readers genuine insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark did not respond to a request for comment. But in a public statement on Thursday, posted on social media, she appeared to accept some of the details under discussion while rejecting others, including the idea of transferring ownership of any part of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can negotiate on everything political; security, investments, economy. But we cannot negotiate on our sovereignty,” the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump gave almost no details of the agreement on Wednesday evening, in brief interviews with reporters in Davos that followed it, or in his public statements on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked about the proposed agreement, Adm. Giuseppe Cavo Dragone, the Italian chairman of the NATO Military Committee, said at a press briefing on Thursday that officials were “at the very early stage” of creating a framework for securing the Arctic and Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Grynkewich said, “We’ve done no planning yet” for the joint Arctic operations. He added, “We have not received political guidance to move out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a spreading sense of relief on Thursday among European leaders that the escalating crisis over Greenland had been defused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a speech in Davos, Switzerland, on Wednesday, Mr. Trump ruled out using military force to take the island but raised the specter of imposing economic pain on allies if he didn’t get what he wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, that evening, he abruptly announced he had reached a deal with Mr. Rutte, and he called off the tariffs he had planned to impose on imports from Denmark and many of the European countries that had risen to its defense over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some European leaders on Thursday welcomed Mr. Trump’s announcement and expressed optimism that it would eventually result in a victory for Arctic security and NATO unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will protect Denmark, Greenland, the north, from the threat posed by Russia,” Friedrich Merz, the chancellor of Germany, said in a speech at Davos on Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will uphold the principles on which the trans-Atlantic partnership is founded, namely sovereignty and territory,” Mr. Merz said. “We support talks between Denmark, Greenland, the United States on the basis of these principles.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting from Brussels, and Amelia Nierenberg from London.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-deal-framework.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 16:32:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>