<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:56:49 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Gabriel Barkay, 81, Dies; His Discoveries Revised Biblical History</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16Barkay--01-vwgz/16Barkay--01-vwgz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Barkay, a leading figure in biblical archaeology whose many discoveries in and around Jerusalem, including a pair of silver amulets from the seventh century B.C. that contained a priestly inscription, changed how historians understood early Jewish life, died on Sunday in Jerusalem. He was 81.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His daughter, Naama Barkay, said his death, in a care facility, was from complications of an autoimmune disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay, whose name was sometimes written Barkai, spent more than 50 years leading some of the most important digs into the ancient history of central Israel, a record that earned him a reputation as the “dean” of biblical archaeologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zachi Dvira, an archaeologist and former student of his, wrote in a biographical essay for Dr. Barkay’s 80th birthday that he “believes that archaeology serves as a vital link between the past and the present, and he embodies this principle through his actions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was especially interested in how the region’s earliest residents treated the dead. During the late 1970s, he examined a network of burial caves carved into the hills southwest of Jerusalem, where he found a pair of amulets containing scrolls from the mid-600s B.C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took years to figure out how to unravel the scrolls without ruining their script, but when they were finally opened and the Paleo-Hebrew text was translated, in 1986, Dr. Barkay found that they contained a priestly benediction from the Old Testament book of Numbers. It was the oldest instance of writing from the Bible — and evidence, he argued, that the writing of the Old Testament began several centuries earlier than many historians had thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to the history of Jerusalem itself, Dr. Barkay considered himself a “maximalist” in the debate over the ancient city’s size and importance. He used the placement of burial sites, which had to be set a specific distance outside the city walls, to show that it was much larger than the so-called minimalists had argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was very much a public-facing archaeologist, offering his expert opinion in TV series like “The Naked Archaeologist” and documentaries like “The Real Da Vinci Code.” He gave frequent public lectures and offered training for tour guides around the Old City of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also something of an activist: In 2000, after the Israeli government refused to stop a Muslim organization, the Waqf, from digging out space for a subterranean mosque on the holy site in Jerusalem known to Jews as the Temple Mount, he and several other archaeologists formed the Committee for the Prevention of the Destruction of Antiquities on the Temple Mount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not oppose the mosque, they said, but rather the lack of archaeologists’ involvement in a project involving the removal of thousands of tons of earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2005, he and others founded the Temple Mount Sifting Project, a crowdsourced program to examine the estimated 400 truckloads of dirt taken from the site. Since then, volunteers have identified about a half-million artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was sometimes criticized as a tool of right-wing Israeli governments eager to establish historical claim to the Temple Mount, which is a holy site for Jews, Muslims and Christians but is primarily controlled by the Waqf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Dr. Barkay insisted that his interest was purely intellectual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sneezing in Jerusalem is an intensive political activity,” he told The Times of Israel in 2019. “You could turn your head to the right, or the left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Breslauer was born in Budapest on June 20, 1944, soon after Nazi Germany occupied the city. He and his mother, Rosa (Legaty) Breslauer, were forced into the newly created ghetto and barely escaped a death march to Vienna, saved only by the liberation of Budapest by Soviet troops in January 1945.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I owe my life to the Russian army, to nobody else than Joseph Stalin,” he said in a 2023 interview. “Many others owe him their death; I owe him my life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Eliezer Breslauer, had already been sent to a camp in Ukraine, though he survived and later rejoined the family. Mr. Breslauer later worked for the Jewish Agency, which facilitated emigration to Israel. Gabriel and his parents emigrated themselves in 1950, settling in Jerusalem, and they changed their surname to Barkay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a child, he was taken with the empty, arid stretches of land outside the city that, he knew, bore the imprint of millenniums of human habitation. By 10, he was conducting his own digs, and a few years later, he joined the Israel Exploration Society, an amateur archaeological club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He received his bachelor’s degree in archaeology and geography from Hebrew University in 1967 and his doctorate in archaeology from Tel Aviv University in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By then, he was already a veteran archaeologist, with a series of digs in Israel, Egypt and Iran to his name. He was a popular lecturer as well, first at Tel Aviv University and later at Bar-Ilan University and Jerusalem University College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay’s first marriage ended in divorce. Along with his daughter, from his first marriage, he is survived by a son from that marriage, Elad; his partner, Esther Yerushalem; and six grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay insisted that archaeology was not just about the past, but was also a tool for examining the way history reaches up into the present through the materials people left behind. And he remained in thrall with Jerusalem, one of the oldest continuously inhabited cities in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is my 56th year in Jerusalem,” he said in a 2006 lecture at Bar-Ilan. “I know the city. But every day, I discover there is more and more to be known about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Berman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:09:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How a Play Skewering Modern Russia Evaded a Crackdown to Become a Hit</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/theater/russia-theater-kholops.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;Everyone expected “The Kholops,” a drama exploring oppression, to be shut down soon after it opened in St. Petersburg. Instead, it is two years into a sold-out run.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/theater/russia-theater-kholops.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:00:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Wall Street Turned Its Back on Climate Change</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/climate/how-wall-street-turned-its-back-on-climate-change.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17cli-wallstreet-01-fqhl/17cli-wallstreet-01-fqhl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Climate activists protest BlackRock in New York City in 2023.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/climate/how-wall-street-turned-its-back-on-climate-change.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 04:14:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mr. Carney Goes to Beijing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/canada/carney-china-trade-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17canadaletter-CX-mfgv/17canadaletter-CX-mfgv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Mark Carney with Xi Jinping, China’s top leader.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/canada/carney-china-trade-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:00:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prize Fight</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/briefing/prize-fight.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;In the run-up to the Oscar nominations, a chat with a reporter who has followed every twist and turn of the race.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/briefing/prize-fight.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:23:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria’s President Affirms Kurds’ Rights, in Overture to the Minority</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-rights-decree-clashes.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-Syria-Kurds-bwhq/16int-Syria-Kurds-bwhq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria issued a decree on Friday affirming the rights of Kurdish Syrians, according to state media, in what was widely considered an overture to the minority group after days of deadly clashes between government and Kurdish forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presidential decree recognized Kurdish as a national language, alongside Arabic, and adopted Nowruz, the Persian new year that is widely celebrated by Kurds, as an official holiday in Syria. Mr. al-Sharaa also called for the government to grant Syrian citizenship to Kurdish residents who were stripped of it after a 1962 census designed to curb Kurdish political influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement on Friday came after days of intense fighting between Mr. al-Sharaa’s government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., that many feared could escalate into a broader conflict between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Beware of believing the narrative that we want harm to our Kurdish people,” Mr. al-Sharaa said in a video announcing the decree posted on the Syrian Arab News Agency, the state media outlet. “Your well-being is our well-being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, Mr. al-Sharaa’s government and the S.D.F. have been engaged in negotiations to integrate the group into the new national military. But progress on those talks has stalled in recent months, and last week, tensions between the two sides erupted into clashes in the northern city of Aleppo. At least 24 civilians were killed in five days of fighting while thousands were forced to flee their neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was some of the most intense fighting since the end of the civil war in December 2024, when Mr. al-Sharaa’s coalition of rebel groups ousted the dictatorship of Bashar al-Assad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening, the prospect of another major clash hung over northern Syria after government troops amassed outside areas in eastern Aleppo held by S.D.F. fighters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the time Mr. al-Sharaa announced the decree affirming Kurdish Syrians’ rights, the national military said it had begun striking those S.D.F. positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, the leader of the S.D.F., Mazloum Abdi, said in a post on X that his forces would withdraw from the contested area and redeploy to regions east of the Euphrates River. It remained unclear whether doing so would head off further clashes with the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fighting over the past week has underscored the challenge Mr. al-Sharaa faces as he vows to unite a country that is deeply fractured after nearly 14 years of civil war. Since his largely Sunni Muslim government came to power, two regions of Syria home to mostly minority groups — the Kurdish-controlled northeast and the Druse in the southern province of Sweida — have refused to submit to the central government’s authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders of both are wary of Mr. al-Sharaa, the former commander of a rebel group once allied to Al Qaeda, and his Islamist-led government. Some also doubt the government’s ability to protect minority rights after bouts of sectarian-driven violence over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurds, who make up about a tenth of Syria’s population, were denied many basic rights, including identity papers and business licenses, under more than five decades of the Assad family’s rule in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decree Mr. al-Sharaa signed on Friday “breaks decisively” with decades of “Arab nationalist exclusion that denied Kurds” in Syria, according to Ibrahim al-Assil, a senior research fellow at the Middle East Initiative at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, many remained skeptical of the announcement and the motivations behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“⁠Mistrust runs deep, and many Kurds are cautiously welcoming this while remaining skeptical,” Mr. al-Assil said. “Ultimately, the decree will be judged by behavior, not words.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reham Mourshed contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-rights-decree-clashes.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:54:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>$2 Rental Batteries Are Helping to Power South Africa</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/batteries-south-africa-electricity.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-safrica-solar-batteries-promo/17int-safrica-solar-batteries-1-jkwp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost as soon as Anselmo Munghabe plopped the 23-pound battery onto a table in his tin shack barbershop, people began to flock in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He plugged two power strips into the battery. Soon it sprouted a bouquet of cellphones and wires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers had arrived not to cut their hair, but to charge their phones, paying Mr. Munghabe 5 rand (about 30 cents) for each plug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Munghabe’s community north of Johannesburg has been without electricity since last April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although nine in 10 South Africans are connected to the national electricity grid, power cuts in the country are frequent. Poor, dense urban areas like Mr. Munghabe’s are hit particularly hard because the grid is overloaded, causing transformers to break and leaving residents in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These batteries allow business owners like Mr. Munghabe to keep their operations open, and provide them with an extra source of income by charging neighbors to use the batteries. They have become a fixture in Tembisa, a sprawling township where residents occupy a mix of tin shacks and concrete homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The batteries are part of a business venture launched last year by the oil company, BP. The program, known as BPowerd, offers daily rental batteries, ranging from 300 to 1,000 watts and able to power lights, televisions, laptops and some appliances for several hours before they must be returned and recharged for the next day’s use. Customers like Mr. Munghabe pick up the batteries from a nearby gas station equipped with solar panels to charge the batteries. It comes as BP focuses its business squarely on oil and gas, abandoning previous efforts to diversify to renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BOtswana&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretoria&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOUTH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFRICA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;400 MILES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tembisa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOUTH AFRICA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 miles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents use the batteries to operate makeshift music studios, convenience stores, taverns and church services. One woman relies on a battery to run her nebulizer. A grandmother said she uses them to power her television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program is part of a growing effort to bring energy solutions to the more than half a billion Africans who don’t have access to electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 200 million people in sub-Saharan Africa live in households that rely on some form of solar power, according to the global association for the off-grid solar energy industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BP program, which plans to expand to Nigeria, is similar to one launched about a decade ago by another company, MOPO, which has about 125,000 batteries in circulation in seven African nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MOPO sets up its battery-charging stations at modest structures in communities, allowing it to reach rural areas that may not have gas stations or other major infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daily rental solar batteries have another limitation. The power they offer is limited, meaning they may not work for many large appliances and electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blackout in Mr. Munghabe’s section of Tembisa forced him to close his barbershop for a month because he did not have power to operate his hair clippers. Then a customer told him about the rentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He rents one for 40 rand ($2.35) per day; a smaller 300-watt battery goes for half the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tembisa, residents lug the batteries — by hand, by wheelbarrow, sometimes by trash can — each day between the gas station hubs and their homes or businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Munghabe, 37, said his daily battery rental rate was covered, and then some, by the money he makes allowing people to charge their phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts in renewable energy say this system could play a critical role on the continent as demand for electricity grows. Renting a small battery is far cheaper than buying solar panels and batteries outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think this is a game changer,” said Ifeoma Malo, the founder of Clean Technology Hub, a Nigeria-based firm that does research and incubation for green technologies. “This is creating inclusiveness in access.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/batteries-south-africa-electricity.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 03:04:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Refuge for Afghan Music Is at Risk of Falling Silent</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/09/multimedia/00int-afghan-music-promo/00int-afghan-music-1-cwth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pakistani city of Peshawar once offered refuge to generations of Afghans, including musicians who preserved their country’s rich tradition of songs and ballads beyond the Taliban’s reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the rhythms that resonate in wedding halls, concert stages and apartment blocks are falling silent, as the Pakistani government pursues a wave of expulsions that has already forced out a million Afghans since last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The musicians are part of a community of Afghan artists that has flourished over decades, and that also includes carpet weavers and dancers. Pakistan provided a haven for millions of Afghans fleeing war and political instability, first from Soviet invaders in the 1980s and later from the Taliban, who first seized power in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban have banned music, persecuted artists and burned or smashed instruments, both in the 1990s and since reclaiming power in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, the Pakistani authorities have publicly accused the Taliban government of supporting insurgents targeting Pakistan, and in retaliation have declared millions of Afghans illegal — including those who fled after the Taliban takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning, the celebratory notes of an Afghan wedding song wafted through Muhammad Hassan Zamri’s music shop after he pushed a worn cassette into a tape deck. A longtime Afghan client ran his fingers through his white beard and sighed, leaving his green tea untouched as he bathed in nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I cannot bring them to Afghanistan because the Taliban will torch them,” Mr. Zamri said about his 2,000 cassette tapes, half of which bowed the crumbling wooden shelves of his shop. Mr. Zamri, who is 52 and fled Afghanistan in the 1980s, said he had already hidden the other half of his collection — a private archive of recordings dating back to the 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not know what might happen to them if he were sent back to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exiled Afghan artists have also kept Afghan music alive in other neighboring countries, in Europe and in the United States. But nowhere have musicians flourished across as many generations as in Pakistan, and in Peshawar in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wave of emigration, in the 1980s, brought artists like Qamar Gula, one of Afghanistan’s most famous female singers. Exiled Afghan musicians, mostly from the Pashto community, also recorded songs of resistance against the 1979 Soviet invasion on cassette tapes that were smuggled back across the border to bolster the mujahedeen fighting the Red Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Afghanistan plunged into civil war in the 1990s, more artists arrived in Pakistan, performing to the rhythm of tabla drums and rubab, an instrument like a lute. Among them was Homayoun Sakhi, a rubab master who fled to Peshawar as a teenager and later performed in concert halls across the United States, Europe and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Pakistani artists and fellow Afghan musicians have accommodated the newcomers. Tiny apartments became makeshift talent agencies visited by Pakistanis seeking to hire Afghan bands for weddings. Recording studios provided professional equipment to cultural icons like Sadiq Fitrat Nashenas, a star from a golden era for Afghan music before the Soviets came.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the early 2000s, Peshawar was home to more than 500 Afghan musicians, according to local news reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Peshawar has contributed to making many Afghan musicians superstars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hayat Roghani, the founder of Mafkoora, a cultural center in Peshawar where Afghan artists perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Taliban takeover, in 2021, pushed a new generation of Afghan artists to Peshawar. Now, their songs are promoted on TikTok and YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baryali Wali, a Pashto singer, hid his instruments in Kabul, Afghanistan’s capital, and fled across the border a month after the Taliban seized power in 2021. He has not been back since and missed his daughter’s wedding last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wali said he feared that the collective soul of Afghan music would vanish if artists were expelled to Afghanistan. “There are Afghan musicians in exile across the world, but it’s important to have a group component like we have here,” he said in a recording studio in Peshawar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expulsions and forced returns have increased in Peshawar and its surrounding province in recent weeks, according to data collected by the International Organization for Migration. “We’re all keeping our heads low now,” Mr. Wali said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent evening at Mafkoora, the cultural center, the singer Saidullah Wafa performed a tune of longing. “This is my beloved country, this is my life, this is my Afghanistan,” he sang to the notes of two acolytes playing the drums and rubab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band played one last song — a jab at the Taliban — before packing up their instruments. “With the Taliban over there or the police here, we feel the same fear,” Mr. Wafa said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one of the musicians, Ikram Shinwari, tried to flee Afghanistan in 2021 with his harmonium, the Taliban ordered him to destroy it with his own hands, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahmad Sarmast, the exiled founder of the Afghanistan National Institute of Music, said that since reclaiming power, the Taliban had gradually imposed repressive cultural policies similar to those of their first era of rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now Afghanistan might be the only silent nation in the world,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wasim Sajjad and Zia ur-Rehman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:06:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Can Cuba Survive Without Venezuela’s Oil?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/americas/cuba-venezuela-oil-power-blackouts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-cuba-oil-02-tpch/17int-cuba-oil-02-tpch-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A Cuban-flagged oil tanker anchored near the Matanzas terminal this month in Cuba.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/americas/cuba-venezuela-oil-power-blackouts.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 04:54:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Spain’s ‘Little Caracas,’ Venezuelan Exiles Are Still Waiting</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/spain-little-caracas-venezuela-exiles-maduro-gonzalez.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-spain-venezuelans-01-hctp-promo/17int-spain-venezuelans-01-hctp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the deposed Venezuelan autocrat Nicolás Maduro lingers in a Brooklyn prison, the mild-mannered former ambassador who overwhelmingly beat him in the country’s 2024 presidential election is struggling to steer his homeland’s future from a modest apartment in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a simple headquarters kept spotless by his wife and sparsely decorated with a Virgin Mary statuette, the politician, Edmundo González, 76, is addressed as “presidente” as he works on prisoner releases, speaks with dignitaries and drafts a platform for what seems likely to be a long shadow government, according to fellow exiles who have met with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González, who went into exile after Mr. Maduro and his oppressive military apparatus refused to accept defeat, is perhaps the leading figure of Spain’s Venezuelan diaspora. With roughly 700,000 members, it is the largest Venezuelan community outside the Americas, wielding outsize influence and standing to gain big from Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to a president-elect and a first lady in waiting, it includes a dashing opposition leader; a former mayor of Caracas; and myriad politicians, generals and mysterious businessmen — some enriched with oil, others corruption — who have bought up so much of Madrid’s exclusive Salamanca neighborhood that some parts have become known as Little Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Madrid is the center where the leaders with the highest political responsibilities are based,” said Ismael García, a prominent member of the Venezuelan opposition who works with Mr. González in Spain. It is where, he said, “the most important issues are discussed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overarching issue for Spain’s Venezuelan exiles is the whiplash induced by the United States’ removal of Mr. Maduro, only to stick with his deputy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many in the Madrid diaspora — especially conservatives who took up the Trumpian “Make Venezuela Great Again” motto — had campaigned for American military intervention. They fantasized about a swift return home to see their families, run for office or replenish their fortunes in vast petroleum fields. They celebrated the Jan. 3 abduction of Mr. Maduro by American special forces and expected it to prompt the installation of Mr. González or María Corina Machado, the opposition leader and Nobel Peace Prize winner who propped up his candidacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But despite Mr. González’s staking his claim to the presidency and saying in a video that Mr. Maduro’s removal was “not enough,” the president-elect remains in Madrid. President Trump has, some exiles complain, pulled the rug out from under the long-suffering opposition by sticking with Mr. Maduro’s hard-line vice president, Delcy Rodríguez, as the regime figure better positioned to deliver the oil and change that Mr. Trump has demanded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Their champagne might grow stale,” said Boris Izaguirre, a Venezuelan writer and showman who hosted Miss Venezuela competitions and who has become one of Spain’s leading television personalities. He spoke in the tearoom of the Wellington Hotel, which he called the “town hall” of the diaspora’s power players who he said had dollar signs in their eyes when they talked of returning “to help Venezuela.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think these are happy days for them,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Izaguirre then left for a dinner, where, he said later, some of the city’s leading right-wing Venezuelans debated the need to adapt to the new, less ideologically pure, reality in which Mr. Maduro’s allies remained in charge despite his capture. It reminded Mr. Izaguirre of a quote attributed to a saint by Truman Capote: “More tears are shed over answered prayers than unanswered ones.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An analysis, passed around the diaspora’s group chats, argued that there needed to be a gradual transition in the regime, which still had control of the military and intelligence services, before Ms. Machado or Mr. González could safely return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carlos Tablante, a Venezuelan former minister now based in Madrid, said it was unrealistic for the exiled opposition to rush back to a country still run by officials who could fling them in jail. “It’s more useful to have an elected president in Madrid than in prison in Caracas,” said Mr. Tablante, who last saw Mr. González in a New Year’s Eve video phone greeting from across town. Still, others worry about losing momentum and that Mr. González and his ilk may be forced to become permanent Madrid residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela and Spain have long and tight ties. Many Spaniards fled to Venezuela during the dictatorship of Francisco Franco. When Hugo Chávez took power in Caracas, establishing a socialist-influenced ruling model, nationalizing major industries and pushing out Spanish oil and banking interests, many wealthy Venezuelans began seeking sanctuary in Spain. That exodus only increased under Mr. Maduro, who succeeded Mr. Chávez in 2013, and included Chávez associates looking to park their cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Venezuela became an ideological dividing line in Spain’s domestic politics, with Spanish conservatives aligning with exiles to try to paint their left-leaning prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, as Maduro-lite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Venezuelans around Madrid found the comparison far-fetched, especially because Mr. Sánchez, who has tried to position himself as a bridge between Mr. González and Ms. Rodríguez, has provided sanctuary to many of the exiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, Mr. González was especially concerned that a rising anti-migrant sentiment among his allies in Spanish conservative parties could hurt the country’s large Venezuelan diaspora, according to Mr. Tablante, the former minister, who has met with the president-elect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. González declined to speak to The New York Times. He has been told by Ms. Machado to lie low, exiles say, as she desperately seeks to get on the good side of Mr. Trump — including by giving him her Nobel Peace Prize on Thursday at a meeting at the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these strange weeks, Madrid has become a mix of “parties and fear,” said Johanna von Müller-Klingspor, a restaurateur who is active in Madrid society and a foundation supporting Venezuelan exiles. Her Salamanca neighborhood restaurant is, she said, “the embassy” where the well-heeled and politically powerful exiles — including, she said, Mr. González — come to eat tequeños, fried dough stuffed with cheese, under taxidermic ibex heads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. von Müller-Klingspor, 50, said she has admired Ms. Machado since they got to know each other in her 20s in Caracas. But she said that a transition to democracy needed to take place before Ms. Machado or Mr. González could take their rightful place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madrid is not short on options for potential Venezuelan leaders. Its handsome Salamanca streets are also home to Leopoldo López, the wealthy and Harvard-trained pro-democracy activist who led opposition protests to Mr. Maduro in 2014. Mr. López suffered years of imprisonment and house arrest and fled to Spain in 2020. Mr. López’s father, another prominent exile, has become a member of the European Parliament with Spain’s conservative People’s Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Madrid’s Venezuelan diaspora extends well beyond the leading political and business figures. In the busy Maravillas Market, lined with Venezuelan food stalls, Alessandro Di Stasio, a Venezuelan investigative journalist, said he had welcomed the news of Mr. Maduro’s removal, but remained careful about what he published under his name. “I will return when democracy is guaranteed,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these exiled voices, said María Costanza Cipriani, whose imprisoned husband was Ms. Machado’s lawyer, helped call for a Venezuela that would eventually respect the 2024 election results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They are the voice of Venezuela outside Venezuela,” she said. “They amplify our voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/spain-little-caracas-venezuela-exiles-maduro-gonzalez.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:01:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uganda Opposition Leader Bobi Wine Is ‘Restricted’ to His Home, the Police Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-museveni.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-uganda-politics-lvmc/17int-uganda-politics-lvmc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main opposition leader in Uganda was “restricted” to his home, the Ugandan police said on Saturday morning, before an expected announcement by the country’s electoral commission that President Yoweri Museveni had won re-election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposition leader, Bobi Wine, who challenged Mr. Museveni in the election, is at his home near the capital, Kampala, the police spokesman Rusoke Kituuma said at a news conference on Saturday. He added: “His home is restricted because we don’t want it to be used as a springboard for inciting violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late on Friday, Mr. Wine’s party, the National Unity Platform, said on social media that he had been abducted and that Ugandan security forces had landed a helicopter on the grounds of his mansion outside the capital, Kampala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, the party’s secretary general, David Lewis, said in a telephone interview that he could not confirm the accuracy of that social media post, which was on X. By midmorning, the post appeared to have been deleted. Mr. Wine would communicate for himself, Mr. Lewis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither the party’s statements nor the precise location of Mr. Wine could be independently verified. Since Tuesday, Ugandan authorities have cut access to the internet nationwide, severely limiting communication in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet blackout was a measure to stop the spread of misinformation that could potentially be weaponized, the government said. The effect has been to dramatically reduce the information flow available to most Ugandans and to block their ability to communicate by email, social media and WhatsApp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Museveni, 81, has ruled Uganda for four decades since he fought his way to power at the head of a rebellion in 1986. An election win would give him five more years in office. Partial results from the vote, which was on Thursday, were announced by the electoral commission, whose leaders were appointed by the president. They showed him far ahead of Mr. Wine or any of the other presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan authorities have deployed a heavy police and military presence to the streets of Kampala in recent days in an effort to forestall protests. Analysts have said it is part of a strategy to minimize the need for what could be a more heavy-handed response should violence begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet blackout has also made it more difficult for opposition supporters to organize in the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview at his home on Monday, Mr. Wine, who became famous as a pop star before entering politics, hinted that he thought he might lose the election, saying that he feared rigging and warning that in the event of defeat he would call for protests. He also predicted that the internet would be cut and that he would be placed under house arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am hounded everywhere by the police and the military,” Mr. Wine said. “I don’t know where I’m going to be. I don’t know where my fellow leaders are going to be, but we know that the people of Uganda will be there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wine also challenged the ruling National Resistance Movement party in 2021. The ruling party was rattled but ultimately easily prevailed. Dozens of people were killed during the 2021 campaign, and Mr. Wine was detained and beaten several times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, few people gave Mr. Wine, 43, a realistic chance of victory. His campaign, though energetic, has been weakened by defections and a lack of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling party has also been able to deploy significant institutional advantages, given the dominance it has established during decades in power. Mr. Museveni’s central argument to voters is that the country has made huge gains in terms of stability and economic growth under his leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given his age, however, many Ugandans are focused on who might succeed him as president. Mr. Museveni’s son, Gen. Muhoozi Kainerugaba, who heads the country’s armed forces, is viewed as the most likely successor.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-museveni.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 06:28:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s Supreme Leader, Unbending Over Time</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/iran-ayatollah-khamenei.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/00int-iran-khamenei-01-tvqj/00int-iran-khamenei-01-tvqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 12-day war with Israel and the United States last June, Iran’s supreme leader reportedly retreated to a bunker beneath his sprawling compound in central Tehran, avoiding public appearances and all electronic communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That bunker mentality resonates with many Iran analysts as a metaphor for the 37-year rule of Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, 86, over the Islamic Republic. He has created a static, authoritarian system resistant to change. The twin pillars of that system remain his ideological fixations — the refusal of any political or social changes that might dilute the power of the regime, and implacable enmity toward the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He is an obstructionist; I do not see him late in life compromising on ideology and his legacy,” said Sanam Vakil, the director of the Middle East and North Africa Program at Chatham House, an international affairs think tank in London. “Whatever it takes to stay in power down to the last Iranian, he’s very keen to keep this system intact, and sees it as an existential and ideological struggle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than 25 years, each new round of nationwide protests, which in recent times have erupted with increasing frequency, has been met with ever more brutal repression. Thousands of protesters have been shot dead on the streets or imprisoned and at times executed. The latest killings, along with the anticipated start of hanging protesters after summary trials, prompted President Trump to threaten American military intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the protests and hence the bloodshed have slowed in recent days, the U.S. threat created a dilemma for Ayatollah Khamenei and his enforcers, analysts said. Escalating repression might prompt an American attack, but allowing the protests to grow could present a real challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In either case, the situation is likely to widen the yawning gulf between the government and the Iranian people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few expected Ayatollah Khamenei to show restraint for long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He sees compromise as an avenue to further weakening and unraveling of the Islamic Republic,” Ms. Vakil said. “Of course, the irony is that his inability to compromise is also leading to the weakening and unraveling of the Islamic Republic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Khamenei’s default argument has long been that Iran’s problems, and certainly any instability, are caused by enemies at home, or especially abroad, intent on destroying the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The enemy’s plots must be recognized,” he said in public remarks during the first week of the current unrest. “The enemy does not rest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among other issues, he described the volatile swings in the foreign exchange rate that helped prompt the demonstrations as “the work of the enemy.” Sometimes he says the enemy is “world arrogance,” a favored pseudonym for the United States, or Israel, which he has called “a cancerous tumor that must be removed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Khamenei’s predecessor, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, remains the symbol of the 1979 revolution that overthrew the shah and ushered in the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He established the regime’s abiding intolerance, fomenting terror against any challengers, first with mass executions of officials from the shah’s reign and then by turning on his leftist allies. Ayatollah Khomeini described protests against his rule as a war on God, condemning opponents as “wild animals” who deserved to be shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ayatollah Khomeini died in 1989, Mr. Khamenei, a protégé who had been president of Iran since 1981, emerged as the consensus candidate for supreme leader. He had been jailed six times under the shah and had lost the use of his right arm after a failed assassination attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a mid-ranking cleric, Mr. Khamenei lacked the exalted religious credentials required for his new role. So the clergy quickly anointed him an ayatollah, and in 1994 elevated him to the status of marja, or a source of emulation for all Muslims. He also carries the title Vali Faqih, meaning the most senior guardian of the Shiite Muslim faith. He has not left the country in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Khamenei was conscious of his lower religious status. “I am an individual with many faults and shortcomings,” he said at the beginning of his rule. “I am truly a minor seminarian. However, a responsibility has been placed on my shoulders, and I will use all my capabilities and all my faith in the Almighty in order to be able to bear this heavy responsibility.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He set about concentrating sweeping power in his own hands, giving him the last word in all matters of state in order to safeguard the revolution and the vision of Ayatollah Khomeini.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Khamenei controls the judiciary and appoints the head of state television, as well as the men on the Guardian Council that vets election candidates. He names the ministers running key national security departments including interior, defense, intelligence and foreign affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has fostered Iran’s nuclear program while denying that Tehran is pursuing weapons, and built the system of regional allies that crumbled over the past two years with the collapse of the regime of Bashar al-Assad in Syria and the decimation of Hezbollah in Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Khamenei alone appoints the commanders of the Revolutionary Guards Corps and the Basij, the powerful armed forces established as a kind of separate militia to preserve the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has also expanded those forces while creating a rotating inner circle of men whose backgrounds mirrored his own — lesser clerics and military commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the system is opaque and difficult to analyze, his apparatchiks have remained deeply loyal. They have not broken publicly with him despite the government’s many economic and military failures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That solidarity means repeated unrest has failed to produce any substantial cracks in the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Significant nationwide protests erupted in 1999 over the shuttering of a reformist newspaper; in 2009 over presidential elections widely believed to be rigged; in the late 2010s over rising prices of basic goods including fuel; and in 2022 over the death of a woman killed in custody after being accused of not wearing a proper hijab to cover her hair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each flare-up amplified calls for change and even for the downfall of Ayatollah Khamenei. The last bout, titled, “Women, Life, Freedom,” also led to more women challenging the often draconian enforcement of the mandatory hijab law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The violence against demonstrators also escalated each time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests have weakened the regime, but not fatally, and it remains unable to address the social and economic issues that form the root of the public’s dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern Iranian society has evolved to be more urban and connected to the outside world, with more educated women, analysts noted. But Ayatollah Khamenei has not changed with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sweeping economic sanctions that sharply limited sales of Iran’s oil have severely contracted government spending, while rampant inflation has left the public poorer and more hostile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly 20 percent of the electorate of 61 million people remain hard-core supporters of the regime, analysts said. But they estimate that most Iranians view the supreme leader as a corrupt, murderous dictator whose animosity toward the West has left the country bankrupt and isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington has long criticized Iran’s human rights record and portrayed the regime as a menace to its people, to the region and the wider world. Ayatollah Khamenei has always responded to the accusations by saying they are rooted in hostility over Tehran’s rejecting the hegemony of what he calls “the Great Satan.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through it all, he has grown increasingly paranoid about enemies both real and imagined, analysts said, and remains deeply suspicious of the threats presented by internal dissent, reform and foreign influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American and Israeli attacks on Iran last June killed dozens of elite military commanders and top scientists, while also weakening the country’s nuclear facilities. Iran’s retaliatory strikes on Israel killed 32 people and injured hundreds while causing relatively minor structural damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Khamenei portrays the outcome as a victory, not least because the regime endured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It has been proven that the Iranian nation, by relying on its own capabilities and under the shadow of faith and righteous action, can stand firm against corrupt and oppressive arrogant powers and convey the call to Islamic values more loudly than ever before,” he said in a speech in December right before the latest demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitty Bennett contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/iran-ayatollah-khamenei.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:02:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World Leaders Consider Joining Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World leaders on Saturday were weighing whether to join President Trump’s “Board of Peace,” as the Trump administration tries to move ahead with its ambitious postwar vision for the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least four countries — Argentina, Canada, Egypt and Turkey — said they had received invitations to participate. The board, made up of world leaders and chaired by Mr. Trump, is supposed to carry out his peace plan for Israel and Hamas, among other responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a post on Truth Social this week, Mr. Trump called the body “the Greatest and Most Prestigious Board ever assembled at any time, any place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But much about its mandate and vision remain unclear, and critics have wondered if Mr. Trump hopes to create a kind of American-dominated alternative to the United Nations Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada was formally asked on Friday to join the Board of Peace, a senior Canadian official said Saturday. Speaking anonymously in accordance with protocol, the official said Mr. Carney planned to accept the invitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Javier Milei of Argentina wrote on social media that he had accepted Mr. Trump’s invitation. Egypt and Turkey, which helped mediate between Israel and Hamas during the Gaza war, also said they had been asked to join, although neither immediately said whether they would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Badr Abdelatty, Egypt’s foreign minister, said at a news conference on Saturday that his country was weighing the matter. And Burhanettin Duran, a Turkish government spokesman, said on social media that Mr. Trump had sent a letter to Mr. Erdogan on Friday inviting him to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump’s peace plan — now enshrined in a U.N. Security Council resolution — the Board of Peace is supposed to help carry out the next steps in the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board’s full membership has not been announced. Instead, over the last week, U.S. officials have focused on announcing a series of committees that will have a key role but that will work beneath the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the White House named two executive committees that are to be staffed largely by Mr. Trump’s close aides, businessmen, and Middle Eastern officials. One of the committees is specifically focused on overseeing Gaza. It includes Tony Blair, the former British prime minister, and Yakir Gabay, an Israeli businessman — but no Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the United States announced a third committee composed of Palestinian technocrats to oversee public services in Gaza. They will face the difficult task of rebuilding a functioning administration in the enclave, which was devastated by Israel’s two-year military campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Trump administration is eager to show that its postwar plans are moving forward, analysts say there has been little tangible progress on many of the toughest roadblocks, more than three months after the truce between Israel and Hamas went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel continues to bomb Gaza on a near-daily basis, at times killing civilians, saying it is responding to cease-fire violations. Hamas has yet to return the body of the final Israeli captive in Gaza. The two sides seem little closer to agreeing on the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matina Stevis-Gridneff contributed reporting from Doha, Qatar and Rawan Sheikh Ahmad from Haifa, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:36:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Inside the Doctors Without Borders Clinics That Israel Is Closing in Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/gaza-doctors-without-borders-c.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/11/multimedia/11int-israel-msf-01-zpth/11int-israel-msf-01-zpth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aseel Hamada sat waiting for a physical therapy appointment at a medical clinic in Gaza City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She’d lost her right leg from above the knee and suffered wounds to her arm and face on Sept. 9, when the apartment she was preparing to evacuate along with her family was hit by tank fire. She is still waiting to undergo plastic surgery on her facial wounds, which she concealed behind a surgical mask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the clinic, run by Doctors Without Borders, may be forced to shut down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If M.S.F. stops working, people will lose their lives,” Ms. Hamada, 24, said quietly, using the acronym for Médecins Sans Frontières, the group’s French name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are no alternatives,” she added. “M.S.F. is everywhere in Gaza because the need simply is everywhere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli government has given Doctors Without Borders until the end of February to pull out of the Gaza Strip, and has already cut off its ability to bring in supplies. Under new regulations, Israel demands that international aid groups provide lists of Palestinians on their Gaza payrolls, a measure it says is intended to ensure that militants do not infiltrate the groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel has produced evidence that one M.S.F. worker killed in an airstrike in 2024 was a member of Palestinian Islamic Jihad and involved in rocket production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctors Without Borders says it vets all new hires but was unaware of the worker’s P.I.J. activity and would never knowingly hire a militant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It noted that at least 15 of its workers were killed in the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctors Without Borders is among a few dozen groups that refused to comply with the new policy. It said that doing so would violate European privacy laws and rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new Israeli policy also gives officials the right to bar aid groups for certain categories of political speech. Israeli officials said that the group’s frequent denunciations of the Gaza war as “genocidal” and accusations that Israel was committing war crimes amounted to prohibited efforts to “delegitimize” the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In publicly seeking to explain their decision to bar Doctors Without Borders, Israeli officials have also asserted that the group was exaggerating its importance in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But visits to several M.S.F. clinics and hospitals showed its vital role in the territory’s medical system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Busy treatment wards and clinics, overworked nurses and physicians, and waiting rooms crowded with grateful patients all put a human face on the organization’s statistics. Collectively, they make clear that shutting down its operations in Gaza would be a devastating blow to an already ravaged health care system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a fragile cease-fire, most Gazans are still living in tents or damaged buildings. Getting enough food or clean drinking water can be a daily struggle. Israel rejects accusations that it has starved Palestinians in Gaza and says it allows the flow of international aid, fuel and other supplies to hospitals. It has blamed the United Nations for failing to distribute supplies that are already in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aid groups have said the restrictions imposed by the Israeli military have often made delivering food within Gaza difficult, and see the new Israeli policy as another measure preventing Palestinians from receiving more than the bare minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Israeli lawmakers banned the United Nations agency for Palestinian refugees — long the biggest aid provider in Gaza — as part of a yearslong clash with the organization. Only about half of Gaza’s hospitals are running, according to the U.N., and more than 18,500 patients need urgent medical evacuation abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a ward run by Doctors Without Borders at Nasser Hospital in Khan Younis, the largest functioning hospital, Abdullah al-Belbeisy, 20, was being treated for severe burns on his hands and face. A cooking-gas tank had exploded when neighbors in the next tent were lighting a wood fire — a common accident among displaced families forced to live in makeshift conditions. About 15 patients waited to receive wound care or physical therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a clean, healthy place,” Mr. al-Belbeisy, said “Without M.S.F., many of us wouldn’t survive. ”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amal Abu Warda, 63, sat with her right hand heavily bandaged, her fingers swollen and stiff. She had been hit by shrapnel in September and had undergone 10 procedures at the group’s facilities, including a skin graft. After 12 physical therapy sessions, she said that she was starting to gain control over her fingers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near the ward’s entrance, Mohammed Baraka, 26, worked through leg exercises, after previous operations that left metal plates in his leg. He comes every other day — sometimes making the six-kilometer trip on crutches, he said — “so I don’t lose my ability to walk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cease-fire hasn’t diminished the need for surgery. One orthopedic surgeon, Dr. Mohammed Di’bis, 29, said doctors were performing roughly 20 operations a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Di’bis, whose government salary from the Ministry of Health is supplemented by Doctors Without Borders, said any interruption in the group’s work would be “deeply unjust.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Without M.S.F., we’d lose essential medications, dressing materials and even medical devices,” he said. “In many cases, M.S.F. has been the only organization supplying the hospital here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maryam Z. Deloffre, an expert on humanitarian aid at George Washington University, said international law requires all warring parties to facilitate the flow of humanitarian aid to civilians without imposing arbitrary restrictions, though repressive states frequently set barriers that leave relief organizations having to make compromises to do their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Humanitarian workers are frequently confronting these kinds of moral dilemmas,” she said. If aid groups agree to comply with such restrictions, they can be seen as complicit but would still be helping people. If they refuse to comply and withdraw, then they’re standing on principle but failing to help those in need, she explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we need to consider here is, what company does Israel want to keep?” she added. “It tends to be authoritarian, belligerent states who do this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several nonprofits are complying with the new Israeli restrictions. They include more ideologically conservative groups, and others that are less outspoken than Doctors Without Borders. Among them is World Central Kitchen, a relief organization founded by the celebrity chef José Andrés that has taken a leading role in the Gaza aid effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roberta Alves, a spokeswoman for World Central Kitchen, confirmed that it had registered under the new rules but declined to comment further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others following the new rules include Samaritan’s Purse, an evangelical group; Catholic Relief Services; and the International Medical Corps, which ran field hospitals in Gaza throughout the war. Samaritan’s Purse declined to comment, and the other two groups did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Doctors Without Borders clinic in Gaza City, Wafaa Zomlot, 39, a physical therapist, was puzzled by Israel’s demands for Palestinian workers’ names.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nothing about us is hidden,” she added, adding that staff have long undergone security checks for permission to travel. “The Israeli authorities already know everyone in Gaza.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With just weeks until the deadline to shut down, workers and patients were filled with despair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hunter McGovern, a project coordinator at the clinic, which specializes in wound care for traumatic injuries, recalled what happened when military action in September forced the clinic to shut down temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was heartbreaking,” he said. “Around 270 to 280 patients a day depended on our services. If you do not change the bandages on some of these horrific wounds, people risk serious infections and even death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the clinic reopened over a week later, said Luay Harb, 41, a nursing supervisor, patients immediately returned. “That tells us something important,” he said. “The service we provide is essential.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Deir al-Balah, at one of the group’s field hospitals inside a tent, Islam Abu Jabal, 33, brought her 2-year-old daughter, Elaf, who was burned when a pot of water boiling over a wood fire slipped and spilled on her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Abu Jabal said she had tried other clinics but kept coming back to this one. “Here, I feel safe,” she said. “My daughter feels safe. The doctors treated her with kindness and patience. They didn’t just dress her wounds, they cared for her.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearby, Ahmed Shaldan, 22, sat in a wheelchair awaiting his fifth physical therapy session for a leg injury from a missile strike&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Told that Doctors Without Borders would be forced out, he said he was stunned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This care is not extra, it’s essential,” Mr. Shaldan said. He looked down at his leg. “If I want to walk again, I need this place.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/gaza-doctors-without-borders-c.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:16:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Is the Russian Military Adapting Effectively to the Drone Age?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/russia-debate-drones-battle-tactics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/17/multimedia/00int-Russia-Military-kcqp/00int-Russia-Military-kcqp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent combat video from Ukraine features what military analysts call a Russian “Frankenstein tank,” surrounded by a protective shell of roughly welded metal plates. The tank survives two dozen drone strikes before a last one ignites it and forces the crew to evacuate amid a hail of shellfire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video captures a profound shift in modern warfare, with relatively cheap drones neutralizing much more expensive weapons, not to mention troops. It was released in late October by DeepState, a Ukrainian organization that monitors battlefield developments, and its location in southeastern Ukraine was verified by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skirmishes like the one involving the Frankenstein tank, highlighting the power of drones, have prompted a roiling debate among senior Russian military officers, military bloggers and other analysts about how the war is being waged. The discussion comes as Russia finds itself locked in a war of attrition in Ukraine, and touches on a broad array of military issues including equipment, training and, most of all, tactics. Many are asking whether Russia has adapted effectively to the way drones have transformed the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a century, Russia relied on a steamroller of troops, tanks and artillery to smash through enemy lines. In this war, because of drones, Russia has resorted out of necessity to using small teams of three to five troops to try to take territory. But that tactic has not allowed the military to take very much land. It is barely inching forward, amid heavy losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What’s going on in the Russian-Ukrainian war is very new to all military experts, who are trying to adapt,” said Aleksandr Golts, a veteran Russian military analyst now with the Swedish Institute of International Affairs. “There is a lot of innovation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument over how the war is being waged is playing out in military journals and online forums, often couched in careful language or historical examples to avoid running afoul of Russian laws barring criticism of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military analysts, much like combat bloggers, are given certain leeway if they avoid attacking the premise of the conflict. They “cannot blame the Kremlin directly” for any problems, Mr. Golts said, so they blame “military science.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some propose ideas outside of the box. For example, two well-regarded military thinkers, Gen. Yury Baluyevsky, a former chief of the general staff, and Ruslan Pukhov, a prominent analyst, recently wrote an obituary of the tank in the journal Russia in Global Affairs. Now that drones dominate combat, they questioned the value of “a vulnerable vehicle with limited weapon abilities, approaching the cost of a fighter aircraft.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia started the war with around 10,000 tanks, Mr. Golts said, but that has dropped to somewhere over 3,000. It can produce only about 200 per year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Criticism directly from soldiers has also resulted in equipment changes to render those on the front less vulnerable, experts said. More than 190 weapon systems have been modernized, according to newspapers published by the Defense Ministry. For example, troops driving transport trucks used to be easy targets because the cabs were not armor-plated, but they are now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Russian analysts find it safer to use historical analogies, noted Krisztian Jojart, an expert on the Russian military at the Swedish Defense University. He cited a recent article attributing the poor performance of Soviet forces after the 1979 invasion of Afghanistan to a lack of training specific to the battlefield. Military readers, he said, would understand the subtext in the current war — soldiers not being trained for the conditions in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a decade ago, Russia began developing smaller, well-trained tactical groups of 600 to 800 men that could act as rapid-reaction forces, but the high-intensity warfare of the 2022 invasion of Ukraine decimated them. That prompted the military to revert to larger forces. Then came the drones, and the smaller groups of three to five men to try to neutralize them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Massing forces near the front line has become a death trap. A roughly 20-mile-wide stretch between the opposing armies has become what military analysts call a “transparent battlefield,” where drones can detect, track and attack virtually anything that moves, crippling attempts to maneuver the combined forces needed for a large-scale offensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most significant recent change in Russian tactics has been deploying small detachments of two to five soldiers on motorcycles or in all-terrain vehicles, trying to penetrate deep behind enemy lines to kill drone operators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The current tactics are a road to nowhere,” Mr. Golts said. “So you can break through Ukrainian defenses — then what?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A team of five men on motorbikes cannot seize territory. When Russia tries to assemble a large strike force to follow them, Ukraine rushes in reinforcements and the cycle repeats, experts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian military wants to figure out an effective counter for the drones in order to resume massing large enough concentrations of troops and armaments to take and hold more territory, Mr. Golts and others said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian military specialists writing about the war have surmised that the way the forces are organized cannot keep pace with the way the war is being fought, said Dara Massicot, an expert on the Russian military at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace in Washington. But it is not clear what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some experts question how much the Russian defense establishment really wants to change, with short-term combat fixes considered more likely than a thorough overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A study published in August by the Center for Naval Analyses, a national security research organization in Arlington, Va., concluded that Russia had not carried out any fundamental shift in military doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russian military thinkers often subscribe to a “technology will solve the problem” attitude, the study said. In other words, they expect that some technology will eventually neutralize drones so that the military can again dominate the battlefield by maneuvering large forces. “There is little thinking about alternative operational concepts,” the study said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia established a specialized unit to deal with drones in 2024, but in November, under a special order from President Vladimir V. Putin, it expanded its efforts by establishing a separate branch of the military called the Unmanned Systems Force. Drones on both sides now execute myriad battlefield tasks, including reconnaissance, radio-electronic warfare and attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drones have become the primary weapon against soldiers and equipment, with 70 percent of Russia’s combat deaths attributed to them as of early 2025, according to Russian statistics cited in a policy journal, Russia in Global Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training is another issue that has come up. Many of the first civilians mobilized in 2022 were given the chance to fire off a few rounds before being thrust onto the battlefield. Now, at least, many are taught how to distinguish the sound of different types of drones, experts said. But discipline and professionalism are sorely lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from drone attacks, Russian forces struggle to execute complicated joint maneuvers of different types of forces because soldiers lack the training needed to understand their orders, said Jack Watling, a senior research fellow in land warfare at the Royal United Services Institute, a think tank in London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new soldier in the West typically gets about 20 weeks of training, he said, while a new Russian soldier gets about three weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Absent training, some soldiers and military bloggers have assembled lengthy “survival guides” to advise troops on everything from clothing and weapons to confronting a drone attack. (One technique is to run in a zigzag toward the sun in hopes of blinding a drone’s optical system.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the front line remains stalled, military experts believe that the Russian military will be forced to recalibrate its overall tactics and training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanks might resume a central role once anti-drone tactics are refined, said Dmitri Kuznets, a military analyst for Meduza, an independent news site published outside Russia. But, he said, “the time when Russia constructed an armored fist at the front has passed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Milana Mazaeva and Aric Toler contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/russia-debate-drones-battle-tactics.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 01:00:16 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>