<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 08:24:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Maduro’s Enforcer Faces an Uneasy Transition, and a Bounty on His Head</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-diosdado-cabello-maduro.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/00int-diosdado-cabello-02-qpgj/00int-diosdado-cabello-02-qpgj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a television studio, Venezuela’s feared interior minister would brandish a plastic club and call out the names of government critics — who knew what that usually meant. They could expect government agents to show up and take them away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly what happened last year to Juan Pablo Guanipa, a prominent opposition politician, after the interior minister, Diosdado Cabello, ripped into him on his weekly show. Mr. Guanipa was arrested, charged with terrorism and treason and sent to prison, where he remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a decade, Mr. Cabello’s show, “Con el Mazo Dando” (With the Club Striking) is one way, experts say, he has overseen Venezuela’s machinery of repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the United States raided Venezuela this month and seized its president, Nicolás Maduro, the Trump administration called it a law enforcement operation, pointing to a new indictment accusing Mr. Maduro of narco-terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another name prominently featured in the indictment? Mr. Cabello. And like Mr. Maduro, the U.S. government has placed a bounty for his capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Mr. Cabello remains firmly in power, part of interim leader Delcy Rodríguez’s core circle, seen by her side in televised events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with Ms. Rodríguez needing to placate Mr. Trump, one of her biggest challenges could be Mr. Cabello, arguably the second most powerful figure in her government whose fate is now intertwined with the fate of the political movement that has ruled Venezuela for more than two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through allies he controls security services, pro-government militias known as colectivos that are deployed to stamp out dissent and has deep ties to Venezuela’s military. In late 2024, he helped install a cousin to run the country’s secret police, known as the SEBIN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello and the forces under him are some of the most fervently anti-imperialist members of a movement whose roots are anchored in resisting foreign intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While publicly supporting Ms. Rodríguez, he has also continued condemning the U.S. raid, calling it in one speech a “barbaric, treacherous attack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello, in a recent broadcast alongside police commandos, said the country had remained calm following the U.S. attack because of the state’s monopoly on weapons. “We are guarantors of the country’s tranquillity,” he said, a comment that some experts said suggested the strong hand Mr. Cabello wields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a very revealing speech about the role he wants to play, and it’s also a threat about what could happen if people go after him,” said Verónica Zubillaga a Venezuelan sociologist at the University of Illinois Chicago who studies violence in Venezuela. “It’s a warning to be careful, because he can set off waves of extreme violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello is widely seen as representing the most opaque and hard-line wing of Chavismo, the political movement founded by Mr. Maduro’s predecessor and mentor, Hugo Chávez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former Venezuelan government official, who spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal, said Mr. Cabello was something of a mystery, even within the upper echelons of his government, with no personal ties except with a small number of military officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few Venezuelan officials have more to lose from any weakening of the government’s grip on power: the United States has indicted him for drug trafficking, accused him of running a transnational criminal network and offered a $25 million payment for information leading to his detention. The United Nations and human rights groups have cited him in some of Venezuela’s gravest abuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s just as bad a guy as Maduro, if not more,” said Risa Grais-Targow, the Latin America director for Eurasia Group, a political risk consultancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Venezuelan government did not respond to a request for comment about Mr. Cabello.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, Ms. Rodríguez and Mr. Cabello have represented competing strains within Chavismo — she the outward-facing technocrat focused on sanctions relief, he the uncompromising militant. Today they have a shared stake in Chavismo’s survival: she needs him to maintain control of the country and he needs her to safeguard his position in a U.S.-friendly government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello, 62, was born in the eastern state of Monagas and, as a teenager, joined an extreme left-wing student group that foreshadowed Chavismo. He later trained as a military officer, graduating in 1987 from the Venezuelan Military Academy and then earning two degrees in engineering. He met Mr. Chávez at the military academy, where they played together on the baseball team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He and Mr. Chávez were part of a group of military officers who mounted a failed coup against a democratically elected government in 1992. In the ensuing years Mr. Cabello was a top ally to Mr. Chávez as he built his political movement, helping organize grass-roots organizations and consolidating different factions to create a disciplined political machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Chávez’s presidency, he became a fixture of power, serving separately as governor, head of the National Assembly, cabinet minister and vice president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zair Mundaray, a former Venezuelan prosecutor who spent 17 years in the Attorney General’s Office and investigated Mr. Cabello, said corruption followed him through every post he held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You could make an encyclopedia of all the crimes Diosdado Cabello has committed,” said Mr. Mundaray, who went into exile in 2017. “If there’s something to steal, he steals it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chavismo, a blend of populism, nationalism and state control of key industries, like oil, was founded by Mr. Chávez, who was elected president in 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fueled by a prolonged oil boom in the 2000s, the government expanded social programs and reduced poverty, but a drop in oil prices set off an extraordinary economic collapse, a mass exodus and popular discontent. The government’s response was to crush dissent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello has long controlled the system that has sustained the government: arresting, torturing, and disappearing political opponents while hollowing out democratic institutions. Multiple former intelligence agents, detainees, and senior Venezuelan officials told U.N. investigators in a report that Mr. Cabello gave direct orders to the SEBIN intelligence service, including whom to arrest, release, and torture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello opposed the July 2024 elections, according to analysts, which Mr. Maduro agreed to hold in exchange for partial sanctions relief from the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But though tallies collected by the opposition and verified by international observers showed that Mr. Maduro had lost decisively, he declared himself the winner. He would use Mr. Diosdado to help legitimize his authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month after the election Mr. Maduro appointed Mr. Cabello as interior minister — a move widely interpreted as a rebuke to Ms. Rodríguez and her brother Jorge, the president of the National Assembly, who experts said had supported the election, and an acknowledgment that the Maduro government would rely on brute force to maintain power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello soon announced the implementation of “Operation Knock Knock,” the deployment of security forces to raid homes and arrest government opponents. In all, the government said it arrested more than 2,000 people for protesting election results, a policing campaign widely denounced by human rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his new post, Mr. Cabello consolidated authority over the intelligence services, the national police, the national guard and the armed civilian groups known as colectivos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Cabello has toned down some of his rhetoric attacking the United States since Mr. Maduro’s capture, experts say he has long opposed any form of liberalization or opening up internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think of him as being from the old school of dictatorship,” said David Smilde, a sociologist who studies violence in Venezuela at Tulane University and lived in the country part-time until last year. “You see your government as like a sweater. If you pull a thread, it all starts coming apart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antonio Marval, a lawyer appointed as a Supreme Court justice several years ago by Venezuela’s legislature, which at the time was controlled by the opposition, recalled how his appointment quickly put him in Mr. Cabello’s cross hairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 17, 2017, Mr. Cabello warned on his show that the new justices named by the legislature, which included Mr. Marval, would be targeted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We all know that when a threat is made publicly on Con el Mazo Dando, with the national reach that its host had — and still has — it is accompanied by real actions,” Mr. Marval said. “The message was clear: to silence us, to break us, and to instill fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He fled Venezuela shortly afterward, escaping by boat to Curaçao.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some critics, Mr. Cabello embodies the ugliest characteristics of Venezuela’s Chavista revolution: a system built not on popular consent, but on fear, violence and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the U.S. wanted to make another point or wanted to do something very decisive,’’ Ms. Grais-Targow said, “I think he would be the most obvious target.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;——————————-&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-diosdado-cabello-maduro.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:04:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How a Screwdriver Salesman Helped Fuel U.S. Airstrikes in Nigeria</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/africa/nigeria-christmas-bombing-republicans.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/02/multimedia/00int-nigeria-screwdriver-1-vkfp/00int-nigeria-screwdriver-1-vkfp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Emeka Umeagbalasi, 56, at his home in Onitsha, Nigeria, last month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/africa/nigeria-christmas-bombing-republicans.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 20:01:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World Leaders Consider Joining Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World leaders on Saturday were weighing whether to join President Trump’s “Board of Peace,” as the Trump administration tries to move ahead with its ambitious postwar vision for the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least four countries — Argentina, Canada, Egypt and Turkey — said they had received invitations to participate. The board, made up of world leaders and chaired by Mr. Trump, is supposed to carry out his peace plan for Israel and Hamas, among other responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a post on Truth Social this week, Mr. Trump called the body “the Greatest and Most Prestigious Board ever assembled at any time, any place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But much about its mandate and vision remain unclear, and critics have wondered if Mr. Trump hopes to create a kind of American-dominated alternative to the United Nations Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada was formally asked on Friday to join the Board of Peace, a senior Canadian official said Saturday. Speaking anonymously in accordance with protocol, the official said Mr. Carney planned to accept the invitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Javier Milei of Argentina wrote on social media that he had accepted Mr. Trump’s invitation. Egypt and Turkey, which helped mediate between Israel and Hamas during the Gaza war, also said they had been asked to join, although neither immediately said whether they would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Badr Abdelatty, Egypt’s foreign minister, said at a news conference on Saturday that his country was weighing the matter. And Burhanettin Duran, a Turkish government spokesman, said on social media that Mr. Trump had sent a letter to Mr. Erdogan on Friday inviting him to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump’s peace plan — now enshrined in a U.N. Security Council resolution — the Board of Peace is supposed to help carry out the next steps in the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board’s full membership has not been announced. Instead, over the last week, U.S. officials have focused on announcing a series of committees that will have a key role but that will work beneath the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the White House named two executive committees that are to be staffed largely by Mr. Trump’s close aides, businessmen, and Middle Eastern officials. One of the committees is specifically focused on overseeing Gaza. It includes Tony Blair, the former British prime minister, and Yakir Gabay, an Israeli businessman — but no Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the United States announced a third committee composed of Palestinian technocrats to oversee public services in Gaza. They will face the difficult task of rebuilding a functioning administration in the enclave, which was devastated by Israel’s two-year military campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Trump administration is eager to show that its postwar plans are moving forward, analysts say there has been little tangible progress on many of the toughest roadblocks, more than three months after the truce between Israel and Hamas went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel continues to bomb Gaza on a near-daily basis, at times killing civilians, saying it is responding to cease-fire violations. Hamas has yet to return the body of the final Israeli captive in Gaza. The two sides seem little closer to agreeing on the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matina Stevis-Gridneff contributed reporting from Doha, Qatar and Rawan Sheikh Ahmad from Haifa, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 11:20:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Advances on Kurdish-Held Areas as Washington Urges Restraint</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/syrian-kurds-raqqa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-syria-raqqa-ktcm/17int-syria-raqqa-ktcm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Syrian government troops advanced into Kurdish-held territory in the north on Saturday, seizing key towns and sparking fresh clashes that threatened to unravel a once-promising political agreement meant to reunify a fractured nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The escalation follows intense fighting earlier this month between the government and the Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., a Kurdish-led militia that is backed by the United States, and it raises the prospect of a government push toward Raqqa, the largest city administered by Kurdish authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raqqa became globally emblematic of the Syrian conflict after the Islamic State seized it in 2014, and declared it the capital of its self-proclaimed caliphate. The city was devastated during the U.S.-backed campaign to defeat the jihadist group and has since remained under S.D.F. control, with a small American military presence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the fall of the dictator Bashar al-Assad in December 2024, Kurdish-led forces have been hesitant to submit to the new government’s authority. For nearly a year, the two sides have engaged in negotiations over the integration of Kurdish military and civilian institutions into the new Syrian state, but those talks have stalled in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renewed fighting has sharpened concerns in Washington about the prospect of a broader confrontation between Kurdish-led forces and Damascus, which could destabilize U.S.-led efforts to prevent a resurgence of the Islamic State and endanger American troops still stationed in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military advance on Saturday came hours after Kurdish fighters withdrew from several positions east of the major city of Aleppo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. announced the withdrawal after President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria issued a decree on Friday affirming the rights of Kurdish Syrians. The announcement was widely seen as an attempt to ease tensions after government forces struck S.D.F. positions in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation quickly deteriorated on Saturday as each side accused the other of violating the terms of the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adm. Brad Cooper, the head of U.S. military forces in the Middle East, urged Syrian government forces, in a statement on Saturday, to “cease any offensive actions” in areas near Aleppo. The U.S. special envoy to Syria, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., also met in northern Iraq on Saturday with Mazloum Abdi, the S.D.F.’s commander, and Masoud Barzani, the veteran Iraqi Kurdish leader, as Washington worked to avoid a broader confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exchanges of fire have been reported in several of towns and villages as government forces said they were advancing through oil-rich areas toward the strategic town of Tabqa, a move that would place government troops roughly 30 miles from Raqqa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renewed clashes capped weeks of violence that have amounted to some of the most intense fighting since the end of the civil war in December 2024, when Mr. al-Sharaa’s coalition of rebel groups ousted the Assad regime.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/syrian-kurds-raqqa.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 22:53:23 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Yankee, Go Home’: Greenlanders Protest Trump’s Takeover Plans</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/greenland-denmark-protest-trump-takeover.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-greenland-protests-promo/17int-greenland-protests-mtzv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time since President Trump renewed his campaign to take over Greenland, people across the Arctic island braved the freezing temperatures and took to the icy streets on Saturday in coordinated protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators waved Greenlandic flags, as some people openly cried in the rain, at a protest in Nuuk, the capital, when Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen suddenly appeared. The crowd roared as he climbed onto a snowbank to raise a flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We said it last year, and we will keep saying it: We are not for sale,” said Isak Berthelsen, a 43-year-old electrician from Nuuk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating the message, he added, did not feel exhausting. “It’s energizing,” he said. “It shows that we are strong enough to say no, and that we have our own voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nielsen led several hundred Greenlanders as they marched through the capital’s center, a rare sight in a city of fewer than 20,000 residents. Some carried hand-painted signs reading “No means no,” “Greenland Is Already Great” and “Yankee, go home!” Others displayed harsher — and cruder — slogans aimed at the U.S. administration. Demonstrations were also held in Aasiaat, Qaqortoq and Ilulissat, with rallies taking place in Copenhagen and other Danish cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many protesters said on Saturday that they had reached a breaking point after Mr. Trump repeatedly suggested that the United States would take Greenland, a semiautonomous part of Denmark, “one way or the other,” and that it would happen “whether they like it or not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a lot of unrest inside people right now,” said Kristian Johansen, 67, a retired carpenter who lives in Nuuk and helped organize the demonstration. “Every new statement makes it worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign ministers from Denmark and Greenland had traveled to Washington days earlier to defuse the situation in a meeting with Vice President JD Vance and Secretary of State Marco Rubio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the White House said the talks would move into a phase focused on the “technicalities of acquiring Greenland.” Danish and Greenlandic officials rejected that characterization, saying they had agreed to continue discussions aimed at addressing American security concerns without a takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on Saturday, Mr. Trump announced that he would impose new tariffs on Denmark — and several other NATO countries that have expressed solidarity with it — unless they relent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crowd in Nuuk included teachers, children, fishermen and retirees, many wrapped in Greenlandic flags, joining the protest in hopes of conveying their anger, frustration and fear to Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know how else you talk to someone who doesn’t understand anything at all,” said Angu Kristensen, 63.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polls and interviews conducted over recent weeks have shown that Greenlanders overwhelmingly oppose becoming part of the United States. Instead, most say they prefer to remain a self-governing territory within the Kingdom of Denmark, where they enjoy a high standard of living and broad autonomy over domestic affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we have to choose between the United States and Denmark here and now, we choose Denmark,” Mr. Nielsen said on Tuesday in a joint news conference with Denmark’s prime minister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protesters from across Denmark packed Copenhagen’s City Hall Square before marching to the U.S. Embassy on Saturday, with some carrying signs of solidarity with Greenland, like “This Land Is Their Land.” Others directed their messages at the Trump administration, including “Make America Smart Again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanne Dueholm, 61, had come into the city from her horse farm in Lejre with her husband and daughter, sporting hats that said, “Make America Go Away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When Trump began making threats, I thought: He is just like Putin — he needs another country, so he takes it,” she said, adding, “but you can’t have that mind-set in a democratic world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, NATO allies in Europe, including France, Germany and several Scandinavian countries, deployed personnel to Greenland as part of Danish-led exercises, in a gesture of solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It shows that we have support from Europe and NATO, and that we are not standing alone,” said Anso Lauritzen, 49, an organizer of the protest in Ilulissat. At the same time, she added, many Greenlanders remain uneasy about militarization. “Most people here don’t want the military in Greenland,” she said. “But right now, it feels better than nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is not the first American leader to be drawn to Greenland’s strategic location and vast natural resources. The United States explored acquiring the island in 1867 and again in 1946. But Denmark has long resisted relinquishing control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greenland’s long history with Denmark, “we have many wounds and a lot of pain between us,” said Maria Meier Brun, a social worker whose father was Greenlandic and who joined the protests in Copenhagen. But, she said, there was also a sense of unity between the two peoples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not American, and we will never be American,” she said. “Some time ago, we wanted to be partners. But right now, I don’t really want to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nuuk, demonstrators gathered near a darkened U.S. consulate, sealed off by police barricades, playing traditional drums and chanting, “Kalaallit Nunaat,” the name for the island in Greenlandic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president has nothing to do here,” said Parnuna Olsen, 25, a high school student in Nuuk. Others shouted in agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he were to come to Greenland, she said, he would not be welcomed, adding that her response would not be polite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa Abend contributed reporting from Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/greenland-denmark-protest-trump-takeover.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 13:34:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why London’s Chimney Sweeps Are Enjoying a Resurgence</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/london-chimney-sweeps-energy-prices.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/30/multimedia/00int-uk-sweep-01-bvjh/00int-uk-sweep-01-bvjh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against a gray London skyline, a spiky round brush protruded from the chimney of a large family house as Josh Firkins got to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brush would have been familiar, Mr. Firkins said, to his great-great-great-grandfather Charles, who began working as a chimney sweep in the mid-19th century. Other aspects of the job would have seemed outlandish to him, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A digital camera revealed the chimney’s interior. An industrial vacuum cleaner removed soot and other debris dislodged by the brush. Earlier, a drone buzzed above the house, scanning the state of the rooftop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chimney sweeps were once an essential part of British life, when households relied on coal and wood-burning fires to heat their homes. They have played an outsize role in the cultural imagination, whether because of Dick Van Dyke’s portrayal of Bert in “Mary Poppins” or — less cheerfully — the children sent up flues in the 18th and 19th centuries, some getting stuck or suffocating in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mass adoption of central heating in the second half of the 20th century, and the introduction of clean air regulations, meant open fires fell out of fashion and the industry shrank. But some firms survived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, many sweeps, including those in the Firkins family business, say the trade has been experiencing an improbable resurgence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the National Association of Chimney Sweeps, demand has been bolstered by high energy prices, the popularity of wood-burning stoves and an international climate that has prompted warnings that electricity supplies could be vulnerable to attack by hostile states like Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are thinking, ‘Let’s have a backup, let’s have a fire, let’s have a stove in case the electricity goes off,’” said Martin Glynn, the president of the chimney sweeps association, whose membership has risen to about 750 today, from about 590 in 2021. “If you have the ability to burn logs or smokeless fuel, you can keep cooking and have some heating. There is a big increase in demand and people are reopening their fireplaces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent day, he said, three people had booked training courses. The association’s membership now includes 40 female sweeps. “It’s alive and kicking,” he said of the group, adding: “We don’t send little boys up chimneys any more, instead it’s CCTV and smoke testing equipment. It’s almost like being a chimney technician.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A revival of open fires and stoves in homes, even on a small scale, does not come without costs. Scientists and campaigners warn that both produce a fine particulate matter, PM2.5, a harmful pollutant that is associated with respiratory problems, heart disease and even dementia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, England banned the sale of almost all traditional coal for domestic use. But even urban areas like London allow the burning of officially authorized smokeless fuels, which produce very little visible smoke, but do generate soot, although much less than coal does. To limit air pollution, the British government recommends that chimneys be professionally swept once a year, and that households choose the cleanest available fuels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chimney sweeps have been in business in Britain since at least 1519, the date of the first recorded payment to one, according to a history of the trade, “British Chimney Sweeps” by Benita Cullingford. Records are sparse because sweeps had no guild to keep documents, unlike in some other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 18th and 19th centuries, “climbing boys,” often orphans, were enlisted to clamber up narrow chimneys. This dangerous, sometimes deadly activity was outlawed by an act of Parliament in 1875, not long after the death of George Brewster, 11, who got stuck in a chimney in Fulbourn, near Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Census records show that Charles Firkins, Mr. Firkins’s ancestor, was sweeping chimneys in 1860. By 1864, his three brothers had joined him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family had its share of drama, including one altercation, recorded in the local press, in which Charles punched a rival who mocked the way he advertised his services with the cry, “Sweep, sweep.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Firkins, 37, has heard of builders recovering the remains of children in chimneys. More common is the discovery of hidden items. Mr. Firkins uncovered a stash of love letters written by men to a male doctor dating from an era before homosexuality was legalized. Mr. Firkins’s father once recovered a revolver, which was turned in to the police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a century and a half after the family business began, chimney sweeping remains profitable for H Firkins &amp; Sons. In the winter months, Mr. Firkins said, “we’ll probably take 70 to 80 calls a day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People enjoy sitting in front of a fire,” he said. “You can shut the curtains, light a fire and it doesn’t really matter what’s going on outside. People have a glass of wine, the fire’s alight, they read a book. I guess they switch off.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He believes the rising cost of living is driving the surge in business. Although fires are less efficient than gas or electric systems, they can help ration the use of central heating, while those with access to free or cheap wood can save cash in areas where burning logs is permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our busiest times are when there is a recession or when energy prices are high,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the house in north London, where Mr. Firkins was recently working, Michael Netter, 41, an expert in building conservation and sustainability, watched as his fireplaces were checked during a renovation before he and his family move in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Netter, who has lived in London for 14 years, was raised in Toledo, Ohio, in a house with an open fireplace. Still, it was unusual to have his chimney swept by a family firm dating back to 1860. “We certainly wouldn’t have that in the Midwest,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain, the profession seems safe for another generation, judging from the enthusiasm of Tom Joslin, 19, who joined Mr. Firkins as an apprentice 14 months ago, after leaving college and trying catering and bar work. His youthful appearance causes clients to jokingly ask if he will be climbing into the chimney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are one or two downsides, Mr. Joslin said, including dealing with creatures that lurk in chimneys — large spiders, birds that get stuck and the occasional angry hornet. But those are only minor inconveniences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I absolutely love it,” he said. “It’s the best job I think I could ever get.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/london-chimney-sweeps-energy-prices.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 20:01:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Dark History of France’s Embassy in Iraq Goes on Trial in Paris</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/jewish-family-iraq-embassy-.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/world/18int-baghdad-embassy-top/18int-baghdad-embassy-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 60 years ago, the French government rented a stately mansion in Baghdad from a Jewish Iraqi family and set up its embassy there. France still uses the building as its embassy, but it has not paid rent to the family in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the family is suing France for $22 million, arguing that the country profited from an Iraqi government campaign of antisemitism. The family says France unilaterally abandoned its contract with it, benefiting from a much cheaper deal offered by the Iraqi government, which expropriated the house under a law that dispossessed Jewish owners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ezra and Khedouri Lawee — brothers who built the home starting in 1935 on the banks of the Tigris River — believed France, a powerful tenant, would honor its commitments to the family when it occupied the house in 1965, despite any potential threats from the Iraqi authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To save the house, my father leased it to the French,” said Mayer Lawee, 86, the son of Ezra Lawee and one of the last surviving family members who lived in the house. “My father was upset. It’s his home. He built it from scratch and it was taken away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a hearing set for Monday in Paris, the family’s lawyers plan to put French principles on trial, presenting the case through the lens of the country’s avowed commitments to righting its past wrongs. The French government, however, views the matter narrowly, and has argued for dismissal, saying that any culpability lies with Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case, involving an unusual blend of contractual and human rights claims, also highlights the plight of about 130,000 Iraqi Jews who from 1941 to 1951 fled or were forced from Iraq, where their ancestors had lived since the biblical “Babylonian Captivity” 2,600 years earlier. The Lawees were among 900,000 Jews who fled or were expelled from Arab and Muslim countries after the founding of Israel in 1948&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family’s lawyers contend the case is analogous to claims made by the descendants of Holocaust victims, who are entitled to restitution from the French government for property stolen during the Nazi era. “The French state’s decision to submit to the antisemitic regulations of a foreign state is unconstitutional, illegal and violates international conventions,” Jean-Pierre Mignard and Imrane Ghermi, lawyers for the family, argued in a complaint filed in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France counters that the damages claimed by the family “are directly caused by decisions adopted by the Iraqi authorities.” But in disavowing all responsibility, President Emmanuel Macron’s government finds itself in the awkward position of relying on discriminatory Iraqi laws in its defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lawee brothers designed the large house with classic columns, curved porticos and expansive rooms, each with his wife and children taking a side, and everyone gathering on the roof or in the garden, Mayer Lawee recalled. But in the late 1940s, amid mounting animosity against Jews over the establishment of Israel, he said, Iraq’s king urged the family to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the family soon settled in Canada, where the brothers built similar homes on neighboring Montreal lots with features deliberately reminiscent of their Baghdad mansion. Still, two relatives remained in the Iraqi house for a decade, then entrusted it to a caretaker until the family’s agent made a deal with France in 1964.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The precise terms of that agreement, just what happened afterward and which laws apply are in dispute. But it is clear that for six turbulent decades, through the rise and fall of Saddam Hussein and two U.S.-led invasions, France has continued using the house as its official outpost in Baghdad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 1969, when Iraq claimed ownership of the mansion, France has paid rent to the Iraqi government. The family contends that France at first also kept paying it according to the original deal, but stopped in 1974, and ignored its inquiries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France has argued that Iraqi laws depriving Jews of property, beginning in the 1950s, justified French compliance with the Iraqi authorities. It has also demanded more proof of the family’s claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Younger members of the family grew up with elders speaking Arabic and waxing nostalgic about homes that they would never see again, that subsequent generations could never know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I consider myself Iraqi, and then a Canadian, which is funny since I’ve never been to Iraq,” said Philip Khazzam, 66, a grandson of Ezra Lawee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Baghdad house loomed large in family lore, and as his elders aged, Mr. Khazzam grew more interested in what happened. The more he dug, he said, the more he became convinced that France had acted unjustly by profiting from Iraq’s discrimination with no objection or explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve only seen pictures of our house. But still, it lives in me every day,” Mr. Khazzam said. “Which is why it matters to me — all the decades later and halfway around the world — much more than an ordinary building ever could. It still is a part of our family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron has portrayed France as a leader in restitution efforts as debates about restoring property unjustly acquired through war, totalitarianism or colonialism have swept Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, though, the French have been slow to return looted goods, drawing sharp criticism and recently prompting legal changes to speed the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lawees hope that shifting sentiment and laws will influence the court to take an expansive view of their claim, framing it in this wider context. Still, experts in cultural property law said the family does not have a traditional restitution claim, like Nazi-era looting cases. France tightly circumscribes what qualifies for restitution. The family’s claim, based on one country’s submission to another’s discriminatory policies, seems to fall squarely outside that category, they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evelien Campfens, an art and cultural heritage law lecturer at the University of Amsterdam, said that French restitution measures technically would not apply to the Lawee home because it is outside France. But because the property has an intangible value and precious memories for the family, she said, it may be possible for their lawyers to draw an analogy to the looted property in traditional restitution cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effort may be more politically powerful than legally sound, according to Anne-Sophie Nardon, a French cultural property lawyer. “I think the goal is to first make the case public and force the government to speak and enter into negotiations,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But failed talks are what led to court. French officials in 2021 responded to the family’s inquiries after attempts over decades yielded no responses. The family hoped France would exert influence in Iraq to help it reclaim the home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, France suggested the family try to re-establish Iraqi citizenship to potentially regain ownership rights, rather than attempt an untested diplomatic process. The family says no Iraqi lawyer would handle its case, and in 2024, it took its claim to a French administrative court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, Mr. Khazzam wrote to Mr. Macron, urging France to resolve the matter in mediation. “France does not want to occupy stolen property,” he said. “This is for the dictators and thieves who run failing states.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron has not answered. His office did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French president has been outspoken about France’s role in the Holocaust and has pledged to vigilantly fight antisemitism. “In the face of hatred, the republic will always have the last word,” he said in September, responding to a rise in attacks against Jews. “The nation will always be mobilized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet in resisting the Lawees’ call for accountability, the government risks calling that commitment into question, and damaging its reputation, said Ms. Campfens of the University of Amsterdam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a moral claim,” she said, “and it is embarrassing for the French government.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/jewish-family-iraq-embassy-.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 23:03:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>