<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 18:48:46 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Iran’s Protests Have Been Completely Squashed, Government Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/iran-protests-crushed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-iran-protests-mgjv/21int-iran-protests-mgjv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A photograph taken during a tour for international news media shows a tax office that was burned during protests, on Wednesday in Tehran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/iran-protests-crushed.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 01:42:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Moves on Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/trumps-greenland-davos-isis-syria.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-theworld-trump-greenland-promo/22int-theworld-trump-greenland-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fate of Greenland has loomed large this week at the World Economic Forum in Davos. Long before Trump arrived, it was all anyone wanted to talk about. While waiting in line for the many security checks. In the corridors of the sprawling conference center. At the bar after hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ladies’ room, I stumbled across a group of French diplomats touching up their makeup while listing ways Europeans could retaliate. A session titled “Can Europe Defend Itself?” was wildly oversubscribed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day started with a lot of anticipation for Trump’s speech to the forum, during which he addressed the topic of Greenland, ruling out the use of force, but, seemingly, threatening economic warfare. It ended with Trump calling off those threats, saying on social media that he had reached a framework agreement with Mark Rutte, the secretary general of NATO, “with respect to Greenland and, in fact, the entire Arctic Region.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement followed a NATO meeting on Wednesday where top military officers discussed a compromise in which Denmark would give the United States sovereignty over small pockets of the island where the United States could build military bases, according to three senior officials familiar with the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, there are still many questions — and many objections to any sort of deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaja Chemnitz, one of the two Greenlandic members of the Danish parliament and a major political figure in Greenland, rejected Trump’s negotiations with NATO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What we are witnessing these days in statements from Trump is completely absurd. NATO has absolutely no mandate to negotiate anything whatsoever without us in Greenland,” she said in a post on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speech in Davos&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the day, Trump had taken the main stage at the World Economic Forum, in an auditorium packed with hundreds of elected and business leaders, who patiently listened to him boast about turning the U.S. into the “hottest country” in the world. (Our fact check of the speech is here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then he pivoted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Would you like me to say a few words about Greenland?” Trump asked. There were a few scattered chuckles. But they quickly turned into an anxious silence, punctuated by audible gasps, as the president lashed out at NATO allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He ruled out the use of force, which came as a surprise to some: “I don’t have to use force. I don’t want to use force. I won’t use force.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he did seem to threaten economic and security consequences for Europe if the United States wasn’t allowed to purchase the island — only to reverse course hours later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A potential deal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we know about a potential deal is very limited. Officials speaking to my colleagues on condition of anonymity compared the idea of giving the U.S. sovereignty over small parts of Greenland to Britain’s military bases in Cyprus, which are regarded as British territory. (The officials said they did not know if that idea had inspired the framework announced by Trump.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a day of whiplash, and the status of negotiations is still uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a degree of relief among some European leaders when Trump ruled out an invasion to claim the island, and some Greenlanders and Danes expressed hope at the prospect of a potential solution. Lars Lokke Rasmussen, Denmark’s foreign minister, told a Danish television channel that the day ended better than it began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This morning we had a president who would not rule out taking Greenland by force. Now he says he will not take Greenland by force,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland — or Iceland, as Trump called it a couple of times — Europe and NATO were not the only targets of Trump in his speech. Here’s a look at everything (and everyone) Trump targeted at Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada received a standing ovation when he declared that the world order had undergone “a rupture.” Carney’s view is widely shared here. And that feeling looks certain to remain, whatever happens next with Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional reporting by Jim Tankersley, Zolan Kanno-Youngs and Lara Jakes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depth of the rift between Trump and Europe has been on full display. This evening, E.U. leaders will gather in Brussels to try and figure out what comes next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, leaders have gathered in Davos to discuss a shared economic and political future. Yesterday, Trump transformed the forum into the setting of a dramatic rupture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. announced yesterday that it had moved 150 Islamic State fighters from a detention facility in northeastern Syria to Iraq and that it might eventually move up to 7,000 more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transfer followed concerns that thousands of former ISIS fighters and their family members could escape from detention as the Syrian government and Kurdish-led forces vie for control of the area. The 150 fighters were taken to an unspecified “secure location in Iraq,” the U.S. Central Command said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurdish-led militia known as the Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., agreed on Sunday to hand over control of the prisons to the Syrian government. The transition has been rocky. In recent days, detainees escaped from at least one prison amid skirmishes. Chaos appeared to break out after S.D.F. forces abruptly withdrew from the Al Hol detention camp, which houses tens of thousands of family members of ISIS fighters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. was the U.S.’s closest ally in Syria for more than a decade. That alliance is now disintegrating as the U.S. throws its weight behind the new Syrian government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli forces killed at least 11 people in Gaza, including three Palestinian journalists who the Israeli military said were flying a drone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Japan restarted a reactor at a large nuclear complex, nearly 15 years after the Fukushima meltdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prince Harry became emotional as he testified in London’s High Court about what he called intrusive news coverage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taiwan’s $40 billion military spending plan was blocked by opposition legislators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our photographer found a wrecked train undercarriage that could identify the cause of a train crash in Spain that killed at least 42 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Parliament voted to delay a major trade deal with four South American countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Han Duck-soo, the former prime minister of South Korea, was sentenced to 23 years for collaborating with the imposition of martial law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government said that it had successfully suppressed anti-government protests after a deadly crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olympics: A ski jumping scandal is rocking Norway, weeks before the start of the Winter Games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Emma Raducanu talked about what went wrong in her second-round loss at the Australian Open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— When Veronika, a 13-year-old cow in Austria, has an itch, she scratches it by expertly wielding a stick. Researchers say it’s the first scientifically documented case of tool use by cattle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ocean Flower Island real estate project in Hainan Province, China, was supposed to rival Palm Island Jumeirah in Dubai. Instead, it’s a $12 billion “dead zone,” as one visitor put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The artificial island has a gigantic shopping mall without shops, a theme park without visitors, high-rise housing blocks without residents and beaches too dangerous for swimming. My colleagues paid a visit to the project, a symbol of China’s never-ending real estate crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the cheese that drew Canadian customers across the U.S. border to Willey’s Store in Greensboro, Vermont. Alongside Americans, they shopped for Withersbrook Blue, a recent winner at the World Cheese Awards, and creamy Harbison, which has woodsy notes derived from its spruce-bark wrapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But recently, Trump’s threats and tariffs have driven many Canadians away. Willey’s Store sales declined by 33 percent last year, and the entire town is struggling. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Train: If lifting weights intimidates you, get strong with a medicine ball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: In the novel “Tangerinn,” an Italian Moroccan woman examines her family’s legacy of immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch: Here are seven under-the-radar movies streaming right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Switzerland, rosti (pronounced roosh-ti) is considered a national dish, and it’s most popular in the country’s German-speaking regions. Traditionally, rosti is made from grated potatoes and fried in a skillet. Our dressed-up version is served with smoked salmon, sour cream and a poached egg. It’s perfect for a weekend breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these buildings?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Istanbul, Turkey&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marrakesh, Morocco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeddah, Saudi Arabia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/trumps-greenland-davos-isis-syria.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 20:31:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ Would Have Global Scope but One Man in Charge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-board-peace-united-nations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-board-peace-mkft/21dc-board-peace-mkft-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the proposed charter of the “Board of Peace” that the United States sent to national capitals in recent weeks, one man has the power to veto decisions, approve the agenda, invite members, dissolve the board entirely and designate his own successor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His name is spelled out in Article 3.2: “Donald J. Trump shall serve as inaugural chairman.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Trump, then peace,” Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary, one of President Trump’s closest allies in Europe, wrote on Facebook on Sunday after Mr. Trump invited him to join the board. “We have, of course, accepted this honorable invitation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Israel, Belarus, Pakistan and several more countries also said they were joining, ahead of a signing ceremony planned for Thursday in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But many officials and experts in international affairs were stunned by the breadth of the initiative, the latest example of Mr. Trump taking apart the American-built, post-World War II international system and building a new one, with himself at the center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a direct assault on the United Nations,” said Marc Weller, a Cambridge international law professor who specializes in peace negotiations and has worked closely with the global body. “This initiative is likely to be seen as a takeover of the world order by one individual in his own image.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.N. Security Council itself endorsed the creation of a Board of Peace in November in a resolution welcoming the U.S.-brokered peace plan to end Israel’s war in Gaza. According to that resolution, the board is to function as a “transitional administration” through 2027 to oversee the redevelopment of Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in unveiling the Board of Peace in the last week, the Trump administration has cast Gaza as only a part of what the new institution would do. While its powers are not defined, its mission would overlap with the United Nations’ aim of maintaining international peace and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump has proven himself a pretty capable and aggressive leader,” said Fred Fleitz, the chief of staff of the National Security Council for part of Mr. Trump’s first term. “This is taking advantage of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed charter, seen by The New York Times, says the board would seek to “secure enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steve Witkoff, Mr. Trump’s peace envoy, who was named as a member of the group’s “executive board,” told CNBC that more than 20 countries had already agreed to join and that the Board of Peace would be “a great group of leaders coming together” in “sharing opinion to achieve peace.” He listed Russia, Ukraine, Iran, Sudan and Syria as among the places in need of “bridging relationships.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I wish the United Nations could do more,” Mr. Trump said Tuesday. “I wish we didn’t need a Board of Peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked whether he wanted the board to replace the United Nations, Mr. Trump said that it “might.” He added: “I believe you got to let the U.N. continue because the potential is so great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Nations itself has sought to play down any tensions. A spokesman, Farhan Haq, told reporters that the U.N. “has coexisted alongside any number of organizations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Trump administration’s ambiguous messaging about the Board of Peace has added to the head-spinning nature of an extraordinary January in American foreign policy. The U.S. attack on Venezuela, the threats of strikes on Iran and Mr. Trump’s demands to take over Greenland have all sent the message that the United States is seeking to exert its global power in a newly unilateral way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace, with its sprawling mission and with Mr. Trump as its long-term chairman, appeared to be an attempt at building an institution to codify the American dominance that the president envisions. Norway, Sweden and France have already said they do not intend to join. The French foreign minister, Jean-Noël Barrot, said his country would say “no to creating an organization as it has been presented, which would replace the United Nations,” according to The Associated Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The bond of trust has been broken” between the United States and its allies, said R. Nicholas Burns, a former U.S. ambassador to NATO, China and elsewhere. “The overreach by the administration on Greenland and the miscalculation they have made has really brought about a different European view and Canadian view.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, Mr. Trump withdrew from 66 international organizations that his administration deemed “wasteful, ineffective, and harmful.” He has suggested that he sees his board filling some of that vacuum — offering the world a more assertive brand of American engagement, personified by Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Board of Peace “will be established as a new international organization,” Mr. Trump wrote in his letter to Mr. Orban, which the Hungarian prime minister posted online. The organization’s charter says in its opening line that “durable peace” requires “the courage to depart from approaches and institutions that have too often failed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Fleitz, who is now at the America First Policy Institute, a conservative think tank close to the administration, said the decision to include Russia and China among the invited members reflected the intended “broad-based” nature of the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They want to reduce the possibility that various countries will try to sabotage it,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia and China have veto power on the U.N. Security Council, so they would be likely to look askance at any weakening of the body. But both have also tried to curry favor with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China has said it was invited but not whether it would accept. President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia also stopped short of accepting the invitation, saying his foreign ministry needed to analyze the matter. But in an example of how countries can try to use Mr. Trump’s ambitions to advance their own interests, Mr. Putin added that Russia was prepared to contribute $1 billion to the board — as long as the money comes out of the Russian assets that were frozen in the West after Mr. Putin invaded Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The draft charter for the board stipulates the $1 billion fee for countries that seek to stay on for longer than a three-year term. A U.S. official said on Tuesday that the board “will implement the highest financial controls and oversight mechanisms” for the cash it collects, and that “funds will sit only in approved accounts at reputable banks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. official confirmed that Mr. Trump could play a central role in the board even after leaving the presidency. Mr. Trump can hold the chairmanship “until he resigns it,” the official said. “A future U.S. president, however, may choose to appoint or designate the United States’ representative to the board.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Weller, the peace negotiations specialist, argued that the expected $1 billion contributions could further sap funding from the U.N., whose agencies were told by the United States in December that they needed to “adapt, shrink or die.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he said that the central personal role envisioned for Mr. Trump was unlike any other agreement he had seen in his experience in international affairs. It was, he said, unlikely to represent a sustainable pathway to world peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Peace in the world requires a broad, international consensus,” Mr. Weller said. “That can hardly be created through a new institution that is entirely dependent on the will of one man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isabel Kershner, Aaron Boxerman, Michael Crowley and Zolan Kanno-Youngs contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-board-peace-united-nations.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:48:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Witkoff and Kushner Will Meet With Putin for Ukraine Talks</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/putin-meeting-witkoff-kushner-moscow-us-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22trump-news-russia-qbmz/22trump-news-russia-qbmz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Steve Witkoff, President Trump’s special envoy, and Jared Kushner, Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, at Davos on Wednesday. They are expected to meet on Thursday with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/putin-meeting-witkoff-kushner-moscow-us-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:51:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Newsom Blames Trump for Cancellation of His Davos Appearance</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/newsom-trump-davos-usa-house.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22xp-newsom-davos-vbjz/22xp-newsom-davos-vbjz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gov. Gavin Newsom of California at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/newsom-trump-davos-usa-house.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 01:03:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin Says Russia Could Donate to ‘Board of Peace’ if U.S. Unfroze Assets</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/putin-board-of-peace-frozen-assets.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22trump-news-russian-assets-vthb/22trump-news-russian-assets-vthb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia at the Kremlin on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/putin-board-of-peace-frozen-assets.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:33:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Returns to a Familiar Role: Sowing Trade Chaos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/trump-trade-chaos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22dc-trade-thcf/22dc-trade-thcf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump on Wednesday gave a menacing speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, before backtracking on a brewing trade war with Europe.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/trump-trade-chaos.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 06:22:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A 67,800-Year-Old Handprint May Be the World’s Oldest Rock Art</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/indonesia-handprint-rock-art-research.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;“It was hiding in plain sight all this time,” one researcher said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/indonesia-handprint-rock-art-research.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 07:22:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Three Dead After Shooting in Rural Australian Town</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/australia/australia-lake-cargelligo-shooting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22oz-shooting-vzwh/22oz-shooting-vzwh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The Australian and Aboriginal flags at half-staff for the victims of the Bondi Beach shooting in Sydney on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/australia/australia-lake-cargelligo-shooting.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:29:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela’s Edmundo González Said His Son-in-Law Was Freed From Detention</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/edmundo-gonzalez-rafael-tudares-detention.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-venezuela-release02-photo-jhpf/22int-venezuela-release02-photo-jhpf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mariana González de Tudares, right, daughter of the former Venezuelan presidential candidate Edmundo González, waiting this month outside a detention center in Caracas, Venezuela.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/edmundo-gonzalez-rafael-tudares-detention.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 09:00:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky Laces Into Europe, Saying It Must Step Up or Be Left Behind</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/davos-zelensky.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-davos-zelensky-photo-ftmc/22int-davos-zelensky-photo-ftmc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine delivered a blunt speech in Davos, Switzerland, on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/davos-zelensky.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 09:21:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Denmark Bristles at Idea of Giving Up Any Sovereignty in Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump-us-reaction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-greenland-denmark01-photo-hmbp/22int-greenland-denmark01-photo-hmbp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark, in Copenhagen on Tuesday, released a statement saying, “Only Denmark and Greenland themselves can make decisions on issues concerning Denmark and Greenland.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump-us-reaction.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:48:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Lays Out a Glittering Plan for Gaza, Including Skyscrapers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/middleeast/us-gaza-peace-trump-kushner-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-gaza-tvmw/22int-gaza-tvmw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump with other world leaders at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/middleeast/us-gaza-peace-trump-kushner-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 09:12:24 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Rift With Europe Is Clear. Europe Must Decide What to Do About It.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/trump-rift-europe.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-europe-assess01-photo-gqmv/22int-europe-assess01-photo-gqmv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depth of the rift between President Trump and Europe was on full display on Wednesday as Mr. Trump delivered remarks in Davos, Switzerland, airing his disdain for Europe’s immigration policies, its regulations and its strident unwillingness to give him Greenland, which he insists America must own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Europe has been looking to find a diplomatic answer to de-escalate the crisis. Hope for such an off ramp came late Wednesday, when Mr. Trump posted on Truth Social to announce that he and Mark Rutte, the NATO secretary general, were working on a deal that could resolve the dispute over Greenland, an autonomous territory of Denmark. He suggested that tariffs he had previously threatened to impose on European nations starting Feb. 1 would no longer kick in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But neither he nor NATO provided any details of what such that framework might look like, and there is no guarantee that such a deal will be finished. A member of the Danish parliament from Greenland called the deal into question in a social media post, saying it had created “total confusion.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dust had not yet settled Wednesday night. But one thing was clear. Mr. Trump’s comments throughout the day underscored just how little the United States and Europe — long the closest of allies — now have in common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While we may no longer be literally staring down the barrel of a gun on the trans-Atlantic relationship, we are still in a very rocky place,” said Jacob Funk Kirkegaard, a senior fellow at Bruegel, a research institute in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are fundamentally at odds, in a way that can only reflect the very different values between most governments in Europe and the Trump administration,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European leaders, many of them shocked by Mr. Trump’s threats to take over the sovereign territory of an E.U. member and NATO ally, must still come together on what they might or should do if Mr. Trump changes his position again — and about the trans-Atlantic relationship more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday evening, leaders from across the 27-nation European Union will gather in Brussels to discuss the perilous state of Europe’s relationship with the United States. They may discuss the contours of the plan Mr. Trump alluded to in his social media post. They will debate how they should approach this new and more hostile era, especially when Russia is still waging war in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had announced over the weekend that he intended to apply levies of 10 percent on several European nations that have recently sent troops to Greenland as part of a NATO exercise. Although he has suspended those tariffs, it is unclear if that will last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mere possibility set off a panicked flurry. European ambassadors met for an emergency gathering on Sunday to discuss the development, and many European leaders called Mr. Trump directly. Thursday’s summit was called in response to the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion is likely to touch on the state of play after the gathering in Davos, including Mr. Rutte’s discussion with Mr. Trump. Leaders will also vet what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the tariff issue is resolved, and even if the Greenland matter is resolved, Mr. Trump’s aggressive push for the island — and his language about Europe in recent days and weeks — have exposed a serious rupture forming between the partners that is far from healed. Europe is grappling with a changed reality, after decades in which it relied on a stable relationship with the United States for both trade and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The shift in the international order is not only seismic — but it is permanent,” Ursula von der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on Wednesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior European official, speaking anonymously to discuss sensitive diplomatic matters, appealed for a bit of calm, noting that Mr. Trump recently threatened to sanction any country that did business with Iran, but has not done so until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lesson, he suggested, was to keep Europe’s powder dry, not to overreact and escalate needlessly with a key ally, and push for diplomacy. To that end, he said the bloc should be ready to retaliate — to have leverage — but should not react unnecessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union already has a 93 billion euro, or $107 billion, list of U.S. goods prepared that it is poised to hit with retaliatory tariffs after Feb. 6. The list was finalized last year in response to Mr. Trump’s earlier trade war, and it will snap into place automatically unless E.U. officials take proactive moves to suspend it — making it a natural first step, should retaliation prove necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also had his usual harsh words for NATO during his speech on Wednesday, asserting that NATO allies would not come to the aid of the United States if attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the only time Article V of the NATO treaty, the commitment to collective defense, was ever invoked was to aid the United States after it was attacked on Sept. 11, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NATO troops fought alongside American soldiers in Afghanistan for a decade, and Denmark itself had more soldiers die per capita in Afghanistan than America did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, at Davos, Mr. Rutte, the NATO secretary general, praised Mr. Trump for pushing member states to spend more on their own defense, which has strengthened the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked if he could imagine NATO without the United States, he said simply, “No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States “is by far the most powerful nation on earth, and the president of the United States is the leader of the free world,” he said, adding, “And you cannot envision NATO without the leader of the free world being an integral part of that organization.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte also touched on the most pressing security issue for Europeans, which is Russian aggression against Ukraine — right on the E.U.’s borders — and not an icy island in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The risk here is that we focus, of course, on Greenland, because we have to make sure that issue gets solved in an amicable way,” Mr. Rutte said on a panel in Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ukraine should be our No. 1 priority, and then we can discuss all the issues, including Greenland,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Koba Ryckewaert contributed to this report.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/trump-rift-europe.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 06:43:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipino Journalist Gets Prison in Case Seen as Attack on Free Press</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/philippines-cumpio-journalist-prison.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-philippines-journalist-wzgv/22int-philippines-journalist-wzgv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Philippine court on Thursday convicted a journalist on charges of financing terrorism and sentenced her to more than a decade in prison, in a ruling that rights and press groups said was a blatant attack on press freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Regional Trial Court in Tacloban City gave the journalist, Frenchie Mae Cumpio, and her former roommate Marielle Dumaquil a jail sentence of 12 to 18 years, the maximum allowed. But the women, who have been in prison since they were arrested in 2020, were acquitted of charges of possessing firearms and explosives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before her arrest, Ms. Cumpio, who turns 27 this month, worked as a radio reporter and wrote articles for Eastern Vista, an online publication focused on the Eastern Visayas region of the Philippines. The authorities said her coverage of the community and local politics was biased in favor of communist insurgents, who have long had a presence in the region. She was convicted of being a conduit for funds for the rebels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To many, Ms. Cumpio’s case was a glaring example of “red-tagging,” a practice by some Filipino authorities of linking their critics to the communist insurgency. She was arrested when Rodrigo Duterte was in power, a president who repeatedly attacked his critics in the media and moved to silence them. His successor and the current president of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., had vowed to support a free press in the Philippines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This absurd verdict shows that the various pledges made by President Ferdinand Marcos Jr. to uphold press freedom are nothing but empty talk,” said Beh Li Yih, the Asia-Pacific director of the Committee to Protect Journalists. “Although the journalist was cleared on the charge of illegal possession of firearms, the ruling underscores the lengths that Philippine authorities are willing to go to silence critical reporting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Philippines must free Frenchie Mae Cumpio without conditions and stop criminalizing journalists,” she continued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporters Without Borders, an organization that advocates press freedom, said it had carried out its own investigation into the allegations against the women and concluded that it was a fabricated case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are appalled by this verdict,” said Aleksandra Bielakowska, the advocacy manager for the group. She added that the conviction was a “devastating failure on the part of the Philippine justice system and the authorities’ blatant disregard for press freedom.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the government’s National Task Force to End Local Communist Armed Conflict said the ruling was “a clear affirmation” that the justice system worked because the court threw out the weapons possession charge against Ms. Cumpio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This alone demolishes the false narrative that the courts are mere rubber stamps for the state or instruments of political persecution,” Joel Sy Egco, the spokesman, said in a statement. “It shows judicial independence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Cumpio and Ms. Dumaquil are expected to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/asia/philippines-cumpio-journalist-prison.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 05:26:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil’s Newest Film Icon Is Not Your Typical Star</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/tania-maria-brazil-the-secret-agent.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-brazil-film01-photo-qjwc/22int-brazil-film01-photo-qjwc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even shielded by dark sunglasses, Tânia Maria de Medeiros Filha can’t step outside these days without fans fawning over her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wherever I go, people recognize me,” the 79-year-old actress said. “It’s marvelous,” she added. “But it hasn’t gone to my head.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, Ms. Madeiros doesn’t have a decades-long career as a leading lady of Brazilian cinema. In fact, she has just a few credits to her name, some of them as an extra. Before setting foot on a film set for the very first time a few years ago, she spent her days weaving rugs in her sleepy hometown in Brazil’s northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Tânia Maria, as she is commonly known, is causing a major cinematic stir at home and abroad with a show-stealing performance in Brazil’s latest buzzy film, “The Secret Agent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a modest but captivating 11 minutes onscreen, Tânia Maria has drawn praise from international film critics, grabbed newspaper headlines and amassed more than 100,000 followers on social media in just months. And the movie that has catapulted her to fame overnight is now widely expected to earn an Oscar nomination on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tânia Maria, for one, chalks up the frenzy to her authenticity in a role not far from her real-life persona. “I think it’s because of my simplicity,” she said in an interview this month, in between takes for her next film. “I am that person. I am Mrs. Sebastiana.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Secret Agent,” a slow-burning political thriller set in the late 1970s, tells the tale of a former professor, played by a melancholic Wagner Moura, who finds himself on the run from Brazil’s brutal military dictatorship. When he seeks refuge in a safe house in the city of Recife, he is welcomed by his hostess: Mrs. Sebastiana, played by Tânia Maria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clad in floral dresses and puffing on a cigarette, Tânia Maria portrays the housemother to a group of political refugees defying the regime. With authority and charisma, she plays matchmaker among her guests and plots their escapes from the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film’s international success, a year after “I’m Still Here” earned Brazil’s first-ever Oscar for best international feature film, has spurred a fresh wave of excitement in Latin America’s largest nation. It also is shining a spotlight on the culture, folklore and dialects of the northeast, where the movie is set, inspiring pride and appreciation in the rich heritage of a region long overlooked in much of Brazilian cinema.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tânia Maria, in her role as the straight-talking grandmother aiding strangers in trouble, embodies a familiar and beloved part of Brazil’s cultural identity, said Aline Diniz, a film commentator and television presenter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve all met a Tânia Maria in our lives here,” Ms. Diniz said. “She is old-school Brazil at its core. She just feels like a hug.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tânia Maria got her start in cinema by chance, when Kleber Mendonça Filho, the director of the “Secret Agent” and one of Brazil’s most renowned filmmakers, came to her hometown to shoot another movie in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She noticed the commotion in town and wandered over to the set, where she learned the film crew was looking for local talent and paying the equivalent of $10 per day. “And that was that,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tânia Maria quickly won over Mr. Mendonça Filho.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She was supposed to be an extra in the film,” he said in an interview. “But she caught my attention so much that I suggested giving her a line.” Tânia Maria’s single line in that production, “Bacurau,” quickly drew widespread attention on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when Mr. Mendonça Filho started writing “The Secret Agent,” he says he couldn’t help but think of Tânia Maria as he conceived of her character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s someone who is very charismatic,” he said. “Direct, tough and, at the same time, good-humored,” he added. “She reminds me of all the older ladies I’ve ever known.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite having no formal acting training, Tânia Maria is a natural on set, according to Mr. Mendonça Filho. “This is someone who nails it every single time,” he said. “She is a grand actress.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her acting chops have not gone unnoticed. In a pre-Oscar roundup last month, Variety highlighted her performance in a glowing review. And, in an annual list of memorable film appearances, The New York Times cheekily listed Tânia Maria’s few minutes onscreen as the “best cigarette acting” of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actress said she is working on kicking that habit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Before, I used to smoke three packs a day,” she told Brazil’s biggest newsmagazine program this month. “If you want to hire Tânia Maria now, it’s without the cigarettes. I can put a cigarette in my hand, but I won’t smoke it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attention garnered by the film, and by Tânia Maria herself, have set off hopes that Brazil could win Hollywood’s most prestigious prize for a second year in a row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a Sunday evening this month, film lovers trickled into a Rio de Janeiro movie theater for a watch party to see whether “The Secret Agent” would win an award at the Golden Globes, after racking up accolades at film festivals across Europe, the United States and Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some were also there to win their own prize: being crowned the best Tânia Maria impersonator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The half-dozen contestants were mostly clad in florals and oversized glasses. All puffed theatrically on make-believe cigarettes, as they snapped photos in front of a life-size cardboard poster for “The Secret Agent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m here representing our new icon,” said Marta Torres, 44, as she held up a massive cigarette made of construction paper. She was especially moved by Tânia Maria’s performance, she added, because she herself is from Brazil’s northeast. “I feel so represented,” she said. “There is something so Brazilian in her, and in the film.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Francisca Oliveira, 80, the actress she was imitating served as an inspiration. “She’s brilliant,’’ she said. “She has so much presence, she’s just so authentic and real.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just before the contest kicked off inside one of the auditoriums, Tânia Maria appeared on a towering screen. “Just stopping by to wish you all the best,” she said in a video to her fans, as they cheered and filmed her message on their phones. “Have a blast!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each contestant then strutted across a small stage, delivering a favorite line from Mrs. Sebastiana, the character Tânia Maria plays. The winner was announced: a 9-year-old boy in floral print and dark glasses eerily similar to those worn by the actress in the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He couldn’t eat all day, he was so excited,” his mother, Carolina Machado, 48, said. “He loves her.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the contest, the lights dimmed and the Golden Globes ceremony began. About an hour in, as the show cut to a commercial break, the smiling face of Tânia Maria, beamed from the screen again, toasting with the frosty beer being advertised. More thunderous applause followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “The Secret Agent” was announced as the winner in two categories — best film in a foreign language and best actor in a motion picture drama — the room erupted in cheers that could have rivaled any World Cup final. Some jumped out of their seats, embracing each other and wiping away tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Tânia Maria, the frenzy around “The Secret Agent” has marked the high point of her short career as an actress. But she certainly doesn’t plan to retire anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m not old, you know?” she said. “I’m just getting started.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/americas/tania-maria-brazil-the-secret-agent.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 06:48:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Trump’s Ultimatum, Greenland Talks Include Sovereign U.S. Bases, No Drilling for Russia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-deal-framework.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-greenland-framework-mlkb/22int-greenland-framework-mlkb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Negotiations to resolve the future of Greenland have focused in recent days on proposals to increase NATO’s presence in the Arctic, give America a sovereign claim to pockets of Greenland’s territory and block potentially hostile adversaries from mining the island’s minerals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those elements, described by eight senior Western security and diplomatic officials, offer the fullest picture yet of the contours of a potential Greenland compromise that President Trump announced on Wednesday without details. His move appeared to at least temporarily defuse an American-made trans-Atlantic crisis over the Danish territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critically, the proposals under discussion would stop short of Mr. Trump’s goal of transferring ownership of all of Greenland to the United States from Denmark, according to the officials, all of whom spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy. The officials cautioned that many details have yet to be finalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear if these discussions will ultimately yield agreement over the territory. Denmark, which publicly opposes ceding ownership of any Greenlandic land, may not agree to the plans on the table. Still, the officials said they were hopeful that they could simultaneously address Mr. Trump’s stated concerns about securing the Arctic against possible threats from Russia and China, while holding to Europe’s “red line” that Greenland was not for sale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, the proposals would:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a significant new NATO mission in the Arctic. Multiple officials have dubbed this mission “Arctic Sentry,” in a nod to similarly named NATO missions in the Baltic Sea and Eastern Europe that are meant to counter an increasingly aggressive Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update a pact signed between Denmark and the United States in 1951. The pact gives the U.S. military wide access to Greenland, an autonomous Danish territory, for operations including the construction and operation of military bases. American officials have said they are concerned that this access could be curbed or ended if Greenland were to obtain independence. NATO officials have discussed expanding the 1951 pact with a new agreement that would effectively create pockets of American soil in the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an agreement would likely be modeled on a “sovereign base area” agreement in Cyprus, where Britain’s military bases are regarded as British territory. That would give the United States greater control over the land than it currently exerts over U.S. embassy sites. Mr. Trump and other officials have said that territory in Greenland could prove important for his plans to build a so-called Golden Dome missile defense system for the United States, which could include components stationed in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restrict non-NATO member countries, particularly Russia and China, from obtaining rights to mine the rare-earth minerals that lie deep under Greenland’s ice sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of those plans have been under discussion inside NATO over the last year, as a direct response to Mr. Trump’s stated ambitions. Since returning to the White House in 2025, Mr. Trump has described publicly, with increasing intensity, his desire to own Greenland. Denmark, with equal intensity, has insisted it would not sell, with Danish leaders saying that the island’s fate is up to Denmark, not NATO. Greenland’s prime minister, Jens-Frederik Nielsen, said on Thursday he was not in favor of giving the United States sovereignty over military bases there. “We are ready to discuss a lot of things,” Mr. Nielsen said, adding, “Sovereignty is a red line.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of giving the U.S. a sovereign claim to its bases in Greenland, similar to Britain’s bases in Cyprus, was raised among NATO and Western military officials on Wednesday, according to two officials, one of whom was present in those discussions. Asked for comment, Gen. Alexus G. Grynkewich, the top NATO commander in Europe, said in a brief conversation with The New York Times on Thursday that the idea was discussed as a matter for political leaders to resolve rather than the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you should know. The Times makes a careful decision any time it uses an anonymous source. The information the source supplies must be newsworthy and give readers genuine insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark did not respond to a request for comment. But in a public statement on Thursday, posted on social media, she appeared to accept some of the details under discussion while rejecting others, including the idea of transferring ownership of any part of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can negotiate on everything political; security, investments, economy. But we cannot negotiate on our sovereignty,” the statement said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump gave almost no details of the agreement on Wednesday evening, in brief interviews with reporters in Davos that followed it, or in his public statements on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked about the proposed agreement, Adm. Giuseppe Cavo Dragone, the Italian chairman of the NATO Military Committee, said at a press briefing on Thursday that officials were “at the very early stage” of creating a framework for securing the Arctic and Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General Grynkewich said, “We’ve done no planning yet” for the joint Arctic operations. He added, “We have not received political guidance to move out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a spreading sense of relief on Thursday among European leaders that the escalating crisis over Greenland had been defused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a speech in Davos, Switzerland, on Wednesday, Mr. Trump ruled out using military force to take the island but raised the specter of imposing economic pain on allies if he didn’t get what he wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, that evening, he abruptly announced he had reached a deal with Mr. Rutte, and he called off the tariffs he had planned to impose on imports from Denmark and many of the European countries that had risen to its defense over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some European leaders on Thursday welcomed Mr. Trump’s announcement and expressed optimism that it would eventually result in a victory for Arctic security and NATO unity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will protect Denmark, Greenland, the north, from the threat posed by Russia,” Friedrich Merz, the chancellor of Germany, said in a speech at Davos on Thursday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will uphold the principles on which the trans-Atlantic partnership is founded, namely sovereignty and territory,” Mr. Merz said. “We support talks between Denmark, Greenland, the United States on the basis of these principles.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting from Brussels, and Amelia Nierenberg from London.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/world/europe/trump-greenland-deal-framework.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 08:43:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>