<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 04:39:20 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Maduro’s Enforcer Faces an Uneasy Transition, and a Bounty on His Head</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-diosdado-cabello-maduro.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/00int-diosdado-cabello-02-qpgj/00int-diosdado-cabello-02-qpgj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a television studio, Venezuela’s feared interior minister would brandish a plastic club and call out the names of government critics — who knew what that usually meant. They could expect government agents to show up and take them away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s exactly what happened last year to Juan Pablo Guanipa, a prominent opposition politician, after the interior minister, Diosdado Cabello, ripped into him on his weekly show. Mr. Guanipa was arrested, charged with terrorism and treason and sent to prison, where he remains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over a decade, Mr. Cabello’s show, “Con el Mazo Dando” (With the Club Striking) is one way, experts say, he has overseen Venezuela’s machinery of repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the United States raided Venezuela this month and seized its president, Nicolás Maduro, the Trump administration called it a law enforcement operation, pointing to a new indictment accusing Mr. Maduro of narco-terrorism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another name prominently featured in the indictment? Mr. Cabello. And like Mr. Maduro, the U.S. government has placed a bounty for his capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Mr. Cabello remains firmly in power, part of interim leader Delcy Rodríguez’s core circle, seen by her side in televised events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But with Ms. Rodríguez needing to placate Mr. Trump, one of her biggest challenges could be Mr. Cabello, arguably the second most powerful figure in her government whose fate is now intertwined with the fate of the political movement that has ruled Venezuela for more than two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through allies he controls security services, pro-government militias known as colectivos that are deployed to stamp out dissent and has deep ties to Venezuela’s military. In late 2024, he helped install a cousin to run the country’s secret police, known as the SEBIN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello and the forces under him are some of the most fervently anti-imperialist members of a movement whose roots are anchored in resisting foreign intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While publicly supporting Ms. Rodríguez, he has also continued condemning the U.S. raid, calling it in one speech a “barbaric, treacherous attack.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello, in a recent broadcast alongside police commandos, said the country had remained calm following the U.S. attack because of the state’s monopoly on weapons. “We are guarantors of the country’s tranquillity,” he said, a comment that some experts said suggested the strong hand Mr. Cabello wields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a very revealing speech about the role he wants to play, and it’s also a threat about what could happen if people go after him,” said Verónica Zubillaga a Venezuelan sociologist at the University of Illinois Chicago who studies violence in Venezuela. “It’s a warning to be careful, because he can set off waves of extreme violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello is widely seen as representing the most opaque and hard-line wing of Chavismo, the political movement founded by Mr. Maduro’s predecessor and mentor, Hugo Chávez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former Venezuelan government official, who spoke on condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal, said Mr. Cabello was something of a mystery, even within the upper echelons of his government, with no personal ties except with a small number of military officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few Venezuelan officials have more to lose from any weakening of the government’s grip on power: the United States has indicted him for drug trafficking, accused him of running a transnational criminal network and offered a $25 million payment for information leading to his detention. The United Nations and human rights groups have cited him in some of Venezuela’s gravest abuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s just as bad a guy as Maduro, if not more,” said Risa Grais-Targow, the Latin America director for Eurasia Group, a political risk consultancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Venezuelan government did not respond to a request for comment about Mr. Cabello.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, Ms. Rodríguez and Mr. Cabello have represented competing strains within Chavismo — she the outward-facing technocrat focused on sanctions relief, he the uncompromising militant. Today they have a shared stake in Chavismo’s survival: she needs him to maintain control of the country and he needs her to safeguard his position in a U.S.-friendly government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello, 62, was born in the eastern state of Monagas and, as a teenager, joined an extreme left-wing student group that foreshadowed Chavismo. He later trained as a military officer, graduating in 1987 from the Venezuelan Military Academy and then earning two degrees in engineering. He met Mr. Chávez at the military academy, where they played together on the baseball team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He and Mr. Chávez were part of a group of military officers who mounted a failed coup against a democratically elected government in 1992. In the ensuing years Mr. Cabello was a top ally to Mr. Chávez as he built his political movement, helping organize grass-roots organizations and consolidating different factions to create a disciplined political machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Chávez’s presidency, he became a fixture of power, serving separately as governor, head of the National Assembly, cabinet minister and vice president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zair Mundaray, a former Venezuelan prosecutor who spent 17 years in the Attorney General’s Office and investigated Mr. Cabello, said corruption followed him through every post he held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You could make an encyclopedia of all the crimes Diosdado Cabello has committed,” said Mr. Mundaray, who went into exile in 2017. “If there’s something to steal, he steals it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chavismo, a blend of populism, nationalism and state control of key industries, like oil, was founded by Mr. Chávez, who was elected president in 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fueled by a prolonged oil boom in the 2000s, the government expanded social programs and reduced poverty, but a drop in oil prices set off an extraordinary economic collapse, a mass exodus and popular discontent. The government’s response was to crush dissent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello has long controlled the system that has sustained the government: arresting, torturing, and disappearing political opponents while hollowing out democratic institutions. Multiple former intelligence agents, detainees, and senior Venezuelan officials told U.N. investigators in a report that Mr. Cabello gave direct orders to the SEBIN intelligence service, including whom to arrest, release, and torture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello opposed the July 2024 elections, according to analysts, which Mr. Maduro agreed to hold in exchange for partial sanctions relief from the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But though tallies collected by the opposition and verified by international observers showed that Mr. Maduro had lost decisively, he declared himself the winner. He would use Mr. Diosdado to help legitimize his authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A month after the election Mr. Maduro appointed Mr. Cabello as interior minister — a move widely interpreted as a rebuke to Ms. Rodríguez and her brother Jorge, the president of the National Assembly, who experts said had supported the election, and an acknowledgment that the Maduro government would rely on brute force to maintain power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Cabello soon announced the implementation of “Operation Knock Knock,” the deployment of security forces to raid homes and arrest government opponents. In all, the government said it arrested more than 2,000 people for protesting election results, a policing campaign widely denounced by human rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his new post, Mr. Cabello consolidated authority over the intelligence services, the national police, the national guard and the armed civilian groups known as colectivos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Cabello has toned down some of his rhetoric attacking the United States since Mr. Maduro’s capture, experts say he has long opposed any form of liberalization or opening up internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think of him as being from the old school of dictatorship,” said David Smilde, a sociologist who studies violence in Venezuela at Tulane University and lived in the country part-time until last year. “You see your government as like a sweater. If you pull a thread, it all starts coming apart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antonio Marval, a lawyer appointed as a Supreme Court justice several years ago by Venezuela’s legislature, which at the time was controlled by the opposition, recalled how his appointment quickly put him in Mr. Cabello’s cross hairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On July 17, 2017, Mr. Cabello warned on his show that the new justices named by the legislature, which included Mr. Marval, would be targeted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We all know that when a threat is made publicly on Con el Mazo Dando, with the national reach that its host had — and still has — it is accompanied by real actions,” Mr. Marval said. “The message was clear: to silence us, to break us, and to instill fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He fled Venezuela shortly afterward, escaping by boat to Curaçao.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some critics, Mr. Cabello embodies the ugliest characteristics of Venezuela’s Chavista revolution: a system built not on popular consent, but on fear, violence and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the U.S. wanted to make another point or wanted to do something very decisive,’’ Ms. Grais-Targow said, “I think he would be the most obvious target.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;——————————-&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-diosdado-cabello-maduro.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 19:04:54 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gabriel Barkay, 81, Dies; His Discoveries Revised Biblical History</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16Barkay--01-vwgz/16Barkay--01-vwgz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Barkay, a leading figure in biblical archaeology whose many discoveries in and around Jerusalem, including a pair of silver amulets from the seventh century B.C. that contained a priestly inscription, changed how historians understood early Jewish life, died on Sunday in Jerusalem. He was 81.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His daughter, Naama Barkay, said his death, in a care facility, was from complications of an autoimmune disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay, whose name was sometimes written Barkai, spent more than 50 years leading some of the most important digs into the ancient history of central Israel, a record that earned him a reputation as the “dean” of biblical archaeologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zachi Dvira, an archaeologist and former student of his, wrote in a biographical essay for Dr. Barkay’s 80th birthday that he “believes that archaeology serves as a vital link between the past and the present, and he embodies this principle through his actions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was especially interested in how the region’s earliest residents treated the dead. During the late 1970s, he examined a network of burial caves carved into the hills southwest of Jerusalem, where he found a pair of amulets containing scrolls from the mid-600s B.C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took years to figure out how to unravel the scrolls without ruining their script, but when they were finally opened and the Paleo-Hebrew text was translated, in 1986, Dr. Barkay found that they contained a priestly benediction from the Old Testament book of Numbers. It was the oldest instance of writing from the Bible — and evidence, he argued, that the writing of the Old Testament began several centuries earlier than many historians had thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to the history of Jerusalem itself, Dr. Barkay considered himself a “maximalist” in the debate over the ancient city’s size and importance. He used the placement of burial sites, which had to be set a specific distance outside the city walls, to show that it was much larger than the so-called minimalists had argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was very much a public-facing archaeologist, offering his expert opinion in TV series like “The Naked Archaeologist” and documentaries like “The Real Da Vinci Code.” He gave frequent public lectures and offered training for tour guides around the Old City of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also something of an activist: In 2000, after the Israeli government refused to stop a Muslim organization, the Waqf, from digging out space for a subterranean mosque on the holy site in Jerusalem known to Jews as the Temple Mount, he and several other archaeologists formed the Committee for the Prevention of the Destruction of Antiquities on the Temple Mount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not oppose the mosque, they said, but rather the lack of archaeologists’ involvement in a project involving the removal of thousands of tons of earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2005, he and others founded the Temple Mount Sifting Project, a crowdsourced program to examine the estimated 400 truckloads of dirt taken from the site. Since then, volunteers have identified about a half-million artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was sometimes criticized as a tool of right-wing Israeli governments eager to establish historical claim to the Temple Mount, which is a holy site for Jews, Muslims and Christians but is primarily controlled by the Waqf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Dr. Barkay insisted that his interest was purely intellectual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sneezing in Jerusalem is an intensive political activity,” he told The Times of Israel in 2019. “You could turn your head to the right, or the left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Breslauer was born in Budapest on June 20, 1944, soon after Nazi Germany occupied the city. He and his mother, Rosa (Legaty) Breslauer, were forced into the newly created ghetto and barely escaped a death march to Vienna, saved only by the liberation of Budapest by Soviet troops in January 1945.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I owe my life to the Russian army, to nobody else than Joseph Stalin,” he said in a 2023 interview. “Many others owe him their death; I owe him my life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Eliezer Breslauer, had already been sent to a camp in Ukraine, though he survived and later rejoined the family. Mr. Breslauer later worked for the Jewish Agency, which facilitated emigration to Israel. Gabriel and his parents emigrated themselves in 1950, settling in Jerusalem, and they changed their surname to Barkay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a child, he was taken with the empty, arid stretches of land outside the city that, he knew, bore the imprint of millenniums of human habitation. By 10, he was conducting his own digs, and a few years later, he joined the Israel Exploration Society, an amateur archaeological club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He received his bachelor’s degree in archaeology and geography from Hebrew University in 1967 and his doctorate in archaeology from Tel Aviv University in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By then, he was already a veteran archaeologist, with a series of digs in Israel, Egypt and Iran to his name. He was a popular lecturer as well, first at Tel Aviv University and later at Bar-Ilan University and Jerusalem University College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay’s first marriage ended in divorce. Along with his daughter, from his first marriage, he is survived by a son from that marriage, Elad; his partner, Esther Yerushalem; and six grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay insisted that archaeology was not just about the past, but was also a tool for examining the way history reaches up into the present through the materials people left behind. And he remained in thrall with Jerusalem, one of the oldest continuously inhabited cities in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is my 56th year in Jerusalem,” he said in a 2006 lecture at Bar-Ilan. “I know the city. But every day, I discover there is more and more to be known about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Berman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:09:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Refuge for Afghan Music Is at Risk of Falling Silent</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/09/multimedia/00int-afghan-music-promo/00int-afghan-music-1-cwth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pakistani city of Peshawar once offered refuge to generations of Afghans, including musicians who preserved their country’s rich tradition of songs and ballads beyond the Taliban’s reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the rhythms that resonate in wedding halls, concert stages and apartment blocks are falling silent, as the Pakistani government pursues a wave of expulsions that has already forced out a million Afghans since last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The musicians are part of a community of Afghan artists that has flourished over decades, and that also includes carpet weavers and dancers. Pakistan provided a haven for millions of Afghans fleeing war and political instability, first from Soviet invaders in the 1980s and later from the Taliban, who first seized power in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban have banned music, persecuted artists and burned or smashed instruments, both in the 1990s and since reclaiming power in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, the Pakistani authorities have publicly accused the Taliban government of supporting insurgents targeting Pakistan, and in retaliation have declared millions of Afghans illegal — including those who fled after the Taliban takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning, the celebratory notes of an Afghan wedding song wafted through Muhammad Hassan Zamri’s music shop after he pushed a worn cassette into a tape deck. A longtime Afghan client ran his fingers through his white beard and sighed, leaving his green tea untouched as he bathed in nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I cannot bring them to Afghanistan because the Taliban will torch them,” Mr. Zamri said about his 2,000 cassette tapes, half of which bowed the crumbling wooden shelves of his shop. Mr. Zamri, who is 52 and fled Afghanistan in the 1980s, said he had already hidden the other half of his collection — a private archive of recordings dating back to the 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not know what might happen to them if he were sent back to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exiled Afghan artists have also kept Afghan music alive in other neighboring countries, in Europe and in the United States. But nowhere have musicians flourished across as many generations as in Pakistan, and in Peshawar in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wave of emigration, in the 1980s, brought artists like Qamar Gula, one of Afghanistan’s most famous female singers. Exiled Afghan musicians, mostly from the Pashto community, also recorded songs of resistance against the 1979 Soviet invasion on cassette tapes that were smuggled back across the border to bolster the mujahedeen fighting the Red Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Afghanistan plunged into civil war in the 1990s, more artists arrived in Pakistan, performing to the rhythm of tabla drums and rubab, an instrument like a lute. Among them was Homayoun Sakhi, a rubab master who fled to Peshawar as a teenager and later performed in concert halls across the United States, Europe and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Pakistani artists and fellow Afghan musicians have accommodated the newcomers. Tiny apartments became makeshift talent agencies visited by Pakistanis seeking to hire Afghan bands for weddings. Recording studios provided professional equipment to cultural icons like Sadiq Fitrat Nashenas, a star from a golden era for Afghan music before the Soviets came.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the early 2000s, Peshawar was home to more than 500 Afghan musicians, according to local news reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Peshawar has contributed to making many Afghan musicians superstars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hayat Roghani, the founder of Mafkoora, a cultural center in Peshawar where Afghan artists perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Taliban takeover, in 2021, pushed a new generation of Afghan artists to Peshawar. Now, their songs are promoted on TikTok and YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baryali Wali, a Pashto singer, hid his instruments in Kabul, Afghanistan’s capital, and fled across the border a month after the Taliban seized power in 2021. He has not been back since and missed his daughter’s wedding last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wali said he feared that the collective soul of Afghan music would vanish if artists were expelled to Afghanistan. “There are Afghan musicians in exile across the world, but it’s important to have a group component like we have here,” he said in a recording studio in Peshawar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expulsions and forced returns have increased in Peshawar and its surrounding province in recent weeks, according to data collected by the International Organization for Migration. “We’re all keeping our heads low now,” Mr. Wali said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent evening at Mafkoora, the cultural center, the singer Saidullah Wafa performed a tune of longing. “This is my beloved country, this is my life, this is my Afghanistan,” he sang to the notes of two acolytes playing the drums and rubab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band played one last song — a jab at the Taliban — before packing up their instruments. “With the Taliban over there or the police here, we feel the same fear,” Mr. Wafa said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one of the musicians, Ikram Shinwari, tried to flee Afghanistan in 2021 with his harmonium, the Taliban ordered him to destroy it with his own hands, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahmad Sarmast, the exiled founder of the Afghanistan National Institute of Music, said that since reclaiming power, the Taliban had gradually imposed repressive cultural policies similar to those of their first era of rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now Afghanistan might be the only silent nation in the world,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wasim Sajjad and Zia ur-Rehman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:06:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Can Cuba Survive Without Venezuela’s Oil?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/americas/cuba-venezuela-oil-power-blackouts.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-cuba-oil-02-tpch/17int-cuba-oil-02-tpch-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuba needs 100,000 barrels of oil a day to keep the lights on, experts say, and to keep its buses, trains and factories running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But because of President Trump, it is not getting nearly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Trump administration exerting control over Venezuela’s oil industry, Cuba is receiving only a trickle of the oil it needs — a shortage experts warn is increasingly likely to trigger a humanitarian crisis unlike any the country has ever experienced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From diesel to operate buses to gasoline for cars to jet fuel to power airplanes, oil is in short supply in Cuba. A nation already enduring prolonged blackouts could come to a grinding halt as reserves run out, the country plunges into darkness and its economy craters, according to energy experts and economists who follow Cuba closely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A government-run television and radio broadcaster in central Cuba announced Tuesday that it had been off the air for several days because it had run out of diesel to power its station. Without power many people also do not have running water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 20 years ago, Venezuela’s president at the time, Hugo Chávez, struck a deal with his ideological ally, Fidel Castro, to provide oil and help keep Cuba afloat, though the amount has declined sharply over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lacking cash or lines of credit, Cuba compensated Venezuela by sending doctors, nurses and other professionals. Cubans were also a key part of President Nicolás Maduro’s security detail, and 32 of them died in the United States’ attack to capture him in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But following the U.S. raid, President Trump declared that oil shipments to Cuba would stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“THERE WILL BE NO MORE OIL OR MONEY GOING TO CUBA — ZERO!” Mr. Trump wrote on Truth Social.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan to cripple — and ultimately topple — Cuba’s government is widely seen as a dream of Secretary of State Marco Rubio, the son of Cuban immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its peak, Venezuela sent its ally some 100,000 barrels a day. More recently, that number had dropped to about 35,000 barrels a day, experts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Cuba loses that, the impact is basically going to be catastrophic,” said Jorge R. Piñon, a former oil executive who is now a researcher for the energy institute at the University of Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The chain of events is that the Cuban economy literally collapses, there is no food in the markets, the trains are not moving, the buses are not moving,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico had been sending about 22,000 barrels a day, but that figure dropped to about 7,000 toward the end of 2025, Mr. Piñon said. One shipment from Mexico of about 85,000 barrels arrived this month.Other countries, like Russia, that have at times supplied oil to Cuba, have not come to their rescue, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cuban government has sharply criticized the United States for blocking the Venezuelan oil shipments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuba's foreign minister, Bruno Rodríguez, said Cuba had the right to import oil without interference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Law and justice are on Cuba’s side,” he said on X. “The US is behaving like a criminal and uncontrolled hegemon that threatens peace and security not only of Cuba and this hemisphere but of the entire world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubans are already feeling the abrupt loss of Venezuelan oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To avoid long queues at gas stations, the Cuban government is making people use an app to sign up for a spot in line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carlos Manuel Vargas, 78, a retired teacher who now works as a security guard, said his turn comes up about every two months. But since Mr. Maduro’s ouster on Jan. 3, Mr. Vargas said his place in line had not budged: He has been No. 10,231 for nearly two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vargas’s spouse has cancer, and he needs gas to go to the hospital, so he said his only other option is buying gasoline at the much more expensive dollar-based gas stations, where lines are shorter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If I have to sell my cellphone or my TV, I will,” Mr. Vargas said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuba experienced outages even when Venezuelan oil was flowing, at least two dozen widespread, long-duration blackouts — known as W.L.D.s — in the past two years, said Juan A.B. Belt, an economist who studies the oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The blackouts are amazing,” he said. “These are wide-area and long-duration events. They had so many — some lasting several days and quite a few covering the entire country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond blackouts, the lack of fuel has also upended the water supply because water pumps require electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sustained oil shortage that triggers multiple hardships will almost certainly stir discontent in the country of nine million people and place new pressure on a government that has struggled to address the country’s longstanding economic challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has responded harshly to popular unrest in the past. During the last wave of huge street demonstrations, in 2021, which was motivated by human rights abuses and pandemic-related economic problems, the government detained more than 1,400 people, according to human rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Miguel Díaz-Canel has acknowledged the crisis and responded by railing against the U.S. government and a decades-long trade embargo that limits its ability to do business internationally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The very dark object of imperialist desire is Venezuelan oil,” he said in a recent speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Díaz-Canel, a former minister of higher education, party leader and vice president, became president in 2018. He took over from Raúl Castro, the brother of Fidel Castro, a socialist icon who died in 2016. He is the first person outside the Castro family to lead Cuba since its 1959 revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in 1960, Mr. Díaz-Canel is not as respected as many older party leaders and is widely believed to hold little sway over his own nation’s affairs. Raúl Castro, 94, still has considerable power over government as well as the powerful military, which manages the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Díaz-Canel’s tenure in office “almost exactly overlaps with utter economic, logistical, health, migratory, social and political catastrophe,” said Ted Henken, a Cuba scholar at Baruch College in New York. “Cubans associate him with the crisis of the last five years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real power in Cuba rests with GAESA, Cuba’s military-controlled conglomerate, and with the state security agency — not with the president, Mr. Henken said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closest parallel to what Cuba is now facing took place 35 years ago when the Soviet Union collapsed, which also meant the end of oil shipments and tumbled Cuba into a major economic crisis known as the “special period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That crisis eased after Cuba discovered oil fields of its own, opened the country to tourism and eventually began receiving oil from Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the tourism industry, hit by sanctions by the Trump administration, has never recovered from pandemic shutdowns, and domestic oil production amounts to only about 40 percent of Cuba’s oil needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of tourists visiting Cuba has declined 68 percent compared with 2019, said Emilio Morales, an economist who owns a consulting company that specializes in Cuba. Cuba invested heavily in tourism, but wound up with white elephant hotels that sit largely empty, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts note that the Communist government survived the grim days after the Soviet Union’s dissolution, and it would be premature to predict its collapse now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the Trump administration’s desire to weaken Cuba’s government, the United States, for now, will not pressure Mexico to reduce or cut off shipments to Cuba to avoid worsening conditions there, according to an administration official who was not authorized to speak publicly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration does not believe the Cuban government has much oil in storage, the official said, and is concerned that the government will use whatever oil it does have on hand to keep its intelligence and security apparatus going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Department recently announced it was sending $3 million in humanitarian aid through the Catholic Church to areas in Cuba affected in the fall by Hurricane Melissa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked whether the Trump administration was risking setting off a humanitarian crisis by cutting off Venezuelan oil shipments, Jeremy P. Lewin, an acting under secretary of state, said that those shipments never benefited Cuban people — an argument belied by those experiencing blackouts in Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump urged the Cuban government to “make a deal” or suffer the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t play games with this president,” Mr. Lewin said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carlos Fernández de Cossio, Cuba’s deputy foreign minister, said the United States was making “apocalyptic threats” while Cubans were in the street honoring the 32 intelligence and military officers who died in the U.S. attack against Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are clear miscalculations,” he wrote on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the two nations’ governments engage in a war of words, Cubans are left in increasingly dire straits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s been ages since I got my turn to buy gas,” a user of the queuing app, Maritza Fernández, posted last week on it. “How long do I have to wait?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David C. Adams contributed reporting from Florida, Hannah Berkeley Cohen from Curaçao, and James Wagner from Mexico City.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/americas/cuba-venezuela-oil-power-blackouts.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 04:54:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Uganda Opposition Leader Bobi Wine Is ‘Restricted’ to His Home, the Police Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-museveni.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-uganda-politics-lvmc/17int-uganda-politics-lvmc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main opposition leader in Uganda was “restricted” to his home, the Ugandan police said on Saturday morning, before an expected announcement by the country’s electoral commission that President Yoweri Museveni had won re-election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposition leader, Bobi Wine, who challenged Mr. Museveni in the election, is at his home near the capital, Kampala, the police spokesman Rusoke Kituuma said at a news conference on Saturday. He added: “His home is restricted because we don’t want it to be used as a springboard for inciting violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late on Friday, Mr. Wine’s party, the National Unity Platform, said on social media that he had been abducted and that Ugandan security forces had landed a helicopter on the grounds of his mansion outside the capital, Kampala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, the party’s secretary general, David Lewis, said in a telephone interview that he could not confirm the accuracy of that social media post, which was on X. By midmorning, the post appeared to have been deleted. Mr. Wine would communicate for himself, Mr. Lewis said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither the party’s statements nor the precise location of Mr. Wine could be independently verified. Since Tuesday, Ugandan authorities have cut access to the internet nationwide, severely limiting communication in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet blackout was a measure to stop the spread of misinformation that could potentially be weaponized, the government said. The effect has been to dramatically reduce the information flow available to most Ugandans and to block their ability to communicate by email, social media and WhatsApp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Museveni, 81, has ruled Uganda for four decades since he fought his way to power at the head of a rebellion in 1986. An election win would give him five more years in office. Partial results from the vote, which was on Thursday, were announced by the electoral commission, whose leaders were appointed by the president. They showed him far ahead of Mr. Wine or any of the other presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan authorities have deployed a heavy police and military presence to the streets of Kampala in recent days in an effort to forestall protests. Analysts have said it is part of a strategy to minimize the need for what could be a more heavy-handed response should violence begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet blackout has also made it more difficult for opposition supporters to organize in the capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview at his home on Monday, Mr. Wine, who became famous as a pop star before entering politics, hinted that he thought he might lose the election, saying that he feared rigging and warning that in the event of defeat he would call for protests. He also predicted that the internet would be cut and that he would be placed under house arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am hounded everywhere by the police and the military,” Mr. Wine said. “I don’t know where I’m going to be. I don’t know where my fellow leaders are going to be, but we know that the people of Uganda will be there.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wine also challenged the ruling National Resistance Movement party in 2021. The ruling party was rattled but ultimately easily prevailed. Dozens of people were killed during the 2021 campaign, and Mr. Wine was detained and beaten several times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, few people gave Mr. Wine, 43, a realistic chance of victory. His campaign, though energetic, has been weakened by defections and a lack of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling party has also been able to deploy significant institutional advantages, given the dominance it has established during decades in power. Mr. Museveni’s central argument to voters is that the country has made huge gains in terms of stability and economic growth under his leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given his age, however, many Ugandans are focused on who might succeed him as president. Mr. Museveni’s son, Gen. Muhoozi Kainerugaba, who heads the country’s armed forces, is viewed as the most likely successor.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-museveni.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 06:28:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>World Leaders Consider Joining Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz/17int-israel-gaza-pqmz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World leaders on Saturday were weighing whether to join President Trump’s “Board of Peace,” as the Trump administration tries to move ahead with its ambitious postwar vision for the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least four countries — Argentina, Canada, Egypt and Turkey — said they had received invitations to participate. The board, made up of world leaders and chaired by Mr. Trump, is supposed to carry out his peace plan for Israel and Hamas, among other responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a post on Truth Social this week, Mr. Trump called the body “the Greatest and Most Prestigious Board ever assembled at any time, any place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But much about its mandate and vision remain unclear, and critics have wondered if Mr. Trump hopes to create a kind of American-dominated alternative to the United Nations Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada was formally asked on Friday to join the Board of Peace, a senior Canadian official said Saturday. Speaking anonymously in accordance with protocol, the official said Mr. Carney planned to accept the invitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Javier Milei of Argentina wrote on social media that he had accepted Mr. Trump’s invitation. Egypt and Turkey, which helped mediate between Israel and Hamas during the Gaza war, also said they had been asked to join, although neither immediately said whether they would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Badr Abdelatty, Egypt’s foreign minister, said at a news conference on Saturday that his country was weighing the matter. And Burhanettin Duran, a Turkish government spokesman, said on social media that Mr. Trump had sent a letter to Mr. Erdogan on Friday inviting him to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Mr. Trump’s peace plan — now enshrined in a U.N. Security Council resolution — the Board of Peace is supposed to help carry out the next steps in the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board’s full membership has not been announced. Instead, over the last week, U.S. officials have focused on announcing a series of committees that will have a key role but that will work beneath the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the White House named two executive committees that are to be staffed largely by Mr. Trump’s close aides, businessmen, and Middle Eastern officials. One of the committees is specifically focused on overseeing Gaza. It includes Tony Blair, the former British prime minister, and Yakir Gabay, an Israeli businessman — but no Palestinians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the United States announced a third committee composed of Palestinian technocrats to oversee public services in Gaza. They will face the difficult task of rebuilding a functioning administration in the enclave, which was devastated by Israel’s two-year military campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Trump administration is eager to show that its postwar plans are moving forward, analysts say there has been little tangible progress on many of the toughest roadblocks, more than three months after the truce between Israel and Hamas went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel continues to bomb Gaza on a near-daily basis, at times killing civilians, saying it is responding to cease-fire violations. Hamas has yet to return the body of the final Israeli captive in Gaza. The two sides seem little closer to agreeing on the way forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matina Stevis-Gridneff contributed reporting from Doha, Qatar and Rawan Sheikh Ahmad from Haifa, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/middleeast/trump-gaza-israel-board-peace.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 11:20:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Advances on Kurdish-Held Areas as Washington Urges Restraint</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/syrian-kurds-raqqa.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-syria-raqqa-ktcm/17int-syria-raqqa-ktcm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Syrian government troops advanced into Kurdish-held territory in the north on Saturday, seizing key towns and sparking fresh clashes that threatened to unravel a once-promising political agreement meant to reunify a fractured nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The escalation follows intense fighting earlier this month between the government and the Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., a Kurdish-led militia that is backed by the United States, and it raises the prospect of a government push toward Raqqa, the largest city administered by Kurdish authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raqqa became globally emblematic of the Syrian conflict after the Islamic State seized it in 2014, and declared it the capital of its self-proclaimed caliphate. The city was devastated during the U.S.-backed campaign to defeat the jihadist group and has since remained under S.D.F. control, with a small American military presence in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the fall of the dictator Bashar al-Assad last year, Kurdish-led forces have been hesitant to submit to the new government’s authority. For nearly a year, the two sides have engaged in negotiations over the integration of Kurdish military and civilian institutions into the new Syrian state, but those talks have stalled in recent months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renewed fighting has sharpened concerns in Washington about the prospect of a broader confrontation between Kurdish-led forces and Damascus, which could destabilize U.S.-led efforts to prevent a resurgence of the Islamic State and endanger American troops still stationed in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military advance on Saturday came hours after Kurdish fighters withdrew from several positions east of the major city of Aleppo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. announced the withdrawal after President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria issued a decree on Friday affirming the rights of Kurdish Syrians. The announcement was widely seen as an attempt to ease tensions after government forces struck S.D.F. positions in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation quickly deteriorated on Saturday as each side accused the other of violating the terms of the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adm. Brad Cooper, the head of U.S. military forces in the Middle East, urged Syrian government forces, in a statement on Saturday, to “cease any offensive actions” in areas near Aleppo. The U.S. special envoy to Syria, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., also met in northern Iraq on Saturday with Mazloum Abdi, the S.D.F.’s commander, and Masoud Barzani, the veteran Iraqi Kurdish leader, as Washington worked to avoid a broader confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exchanges of fire have been reported in several of towns and villages as government forces said they were advancing through oil-rich areas toward the strategic town of Tabqa, a move that would place government troops roughly 30 miles from Raqqa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The renewed clashes capped weeks of violence that have amounted to some of the most intense fighting since the end of the civil war in December 2024, when Mr. al-Sharaa’s coalition of rebel groups ousted the Assad regime.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/syrian-kurds-raqqa.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:18:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Yankee, Go Home’: Greenlanders Protest Trump’s Takeover Plans</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/greenland-denmark-protest-trump-takeover.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-greenland-protests-promo/17int-greenland-protests-mtzv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time since President Trump renewed his campaign to take over Greenland, people across the Arctic island braved the freezing temperatures and took to the icy streets on Saturday in coordinated protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrators waved Greenlandic flags, as some people openly cried in the rain, at a protest in Nuuk, the capital, when Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen suddenly appeared. The crowd roared as he climbed onto a snowbank to raise a flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We said it last year, and we will keep saying it: We are not for sale,” said Isak Berthelsen, a 43-year-old electrician from Nuuk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repeating the message, he added, did not feel exhausting. “It’s energizing,” he said. “It shows that we are strong enough to say no, and that we have our own voice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Nielsen led several hundred Greenlanders as they marched through the capital’s center, a rare sight in a city of fewer than 20,000 residents. Some carried hand-painted signs reading “No means no,” “Greenland Is Already Great” and “Yankee, go home!” Others displayed harsher — and cruder — slogans aimed at the U.S. administration. Demonstrations were also held in Aasiaat, Qaqortoq and Ilulissat, with rallies taking place in Copenhagen and other Danish cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many protesters said on Saturday that they had reached a breaking point after Mr. Trump repeatedly suggested that the United States would take Greenland, a semiautonomous part of Denmark, “one way or the other,” and that it would happen “whether they like it or not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a lot of unrest inside people right now,” said Kristian Johansen, 67, a retired carpenter who lives in Nuuk and helped organize the demonstration. “Every new statement makes it worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foreign ministers from Denmark and Greenland had traveled to Washington days earlier to defuse the situation in a meeting with Vice President JD Vance and Secretary of State Marco Rubio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the meeting, the White House said the talks would move into a phase focused on the “technicalities of acquiring Greenland.” Danish and Greenlandic officials rejected that characterization, saying they had agreed to continue discussions aimed at addressing American security concerns without a takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then on Saturday, Mr. Trump announced that he would impose new tariffs on Denmark — and several other NATO countries that have expressed solidarity with it — unless they relent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crowd in Nuuk included teachers, children, fishermen and retirees, many wrapped in Greenlandic flags, joining the protest in hopes of conveying their anger, frustration and fear to Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know how else you talk to someone who doesn’t understand anything at all,” said Angu Kristensen, 63.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polls and interviews conducted over recent weeks have shown that Greenlanders overwhelmingly oppose becoming part of the United States. Instead, most say they prefer to remain a self-governing territory within the Kingdom of Denmark, where they enjoy a high standard of living and broad autonomy over domestic affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we have to choose between the United States and Denmark here and now, we choose Denmark,” Mr. Nielsen said on Tuesday in a joint news conference with Denmark’s prime minister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protesters from across Denmark packed Copenhagen’s City Hall Square before marching to the U.S. Embassy on Saturday, with some carrying signs of solidarity with Greenland, like “This Land Is Their Land.” Others directed their messages at the Trump administration, including “Make America Smart Again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanne Dueholm, 61, had come into the city from her horse farm in Lejre with her husband and daughter, sporting hats that said, “Make America Go Away.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When Trump began making threats, I thought: He is just like Putin — he needs another country, so he takes it,” she said, adding, “but you can’t have that mind-set in a democratic world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, NATO allies in Europe, including France, Germany and several Scandinavian countries, deployed personnel to Greenland as part of Danish-led exercises, in a gesture of solidarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It shows that we have support from Europe and NATO, and that we are not standing alone,” said Anso Lauritzen, 49, an organizer of the protest in Ilulissat. At the same time, she added, many Greenlanders remain uneasy about militarization. “Most people here don’t want the military in Greenland,” she said. “But right now, it feels better than nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is not the first American leader to be drawn to Greenland’s strategic location and vast natural resources. The United States explored acquiring the island in 1867 and again in 1946. But Denmark has long resisted relinquishing control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greenland’s long history with Denmark, “we have many wounds and a lot of pain between us,” said Maria Meier Brun, a social worker whose father was Greenlandic and who joined the protests in Copenhagen. But, she said, there was also a sense of unity between the two peoples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are not American, and we will never be American,” she said. “Some time ago, we wanted to be partners. But right now, I don’t really want to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nuuk, demonstrators gathered near a darkened U.S. consulate, sealed off by police barricades, playing traditional drums and chanting, “Kalaallit Nunaat,” the name for the island in Greenlandic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The president has nothing to do here,” said Parnuna Olsen, 25, a high school student in Nuuk. Others shouted in agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If he were to come to Greenland, she said, he would not be welcomed, adding that her response would not be polite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa Abend contributed reporting from Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/europe/greenland-denmark-protest-trump-takeover.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 13:34:21 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>