<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:12:17 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Death Toll Rises in Guatemalan Gang Riots</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-guatemala-promo/19int-guatemala-01-hbcv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deadly gang violence over the weekend in Guatemala has raised concerns about the stability of the country and President Bernardo Arévalo’s ability to deliver on his promise to root out corruption and organized crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He declared a state of emergency on Sunday to crack down on gangs after inmates took dozens of guards hostage at three prisons across the country and several officers were killed in episodes connected to the violence. The government said the riots and reprisal killings had been a coordinated response by leaders of criminal organizations after the authorities took away their prison privileges, including restaurant meals and air conditioning demanded by one crime boss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day after Mr. Arévalo announced that the state of emergency would last for 30 days and empower the national police and military to act against gangs, the police death toll had risen to nine. The new powers allowed the authorities to set up checkpoints and claim broader authority to make arrests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he had announced the state of emergency because the violence had been “aimed at terrorizing the population.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Sunday, the police had regained control of the prisons, and the guards had been freed, Mr. Arévalo said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts said that the unrest came at a critical time for Guatemala, a Central America country of 18 million people where gangs exert influence even on politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the major decisions facing Mr. Arévalo this year is choosing a new attorney general. He said on Sunday that the violence came just as the country was trying to free itself of corruption. He called those behind the violence “criminal political mafias that resist and seek to instill terror because they know that this year Guatemala will recover its justice system.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some inmates with access to cellphones and the internet have called for the removal of Mr. Arévalo from power. In response to questions about threats against the president, Henry Saenz, Guatemala’s minister of defense, said on the radio on Monday that “the army supports the president” and that Mr. Arévalo would serve out his term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s extremely worrying,” Ana María Méndez Dardón, the Central America director at the Washington Office on Latin America, a rights group, said of the state of affairs in Guatemala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a warning that this year being so decisive for Guatemala and especially for the justice of Guatemala,” she continued, “that these parallel groups of power are seeking to break the constitutional order, to destabilize and generate this chaos to harm President Bernardo Arévalo in order to be able to continue perpetuating the impunity to which they have been accustomed to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Arévalo, an anticorruption crusader and a moderate, was elected in 2023 in a surprise victory that left the country’s conservative establishment reeling, particularly the attorney general’s office, which has been a primary force in blocking his agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, 20 inmates accused of being gang members escaped from a maximum-security prison outside the capital, Guatemala City. The inmates were described by officials as high-ranking operatives of the Barrio 18 gang, which has long been linked to organized crime and violence around Central America and which the Trump administration designated as a foreign terrorist organization in September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A political crisis ensued, and Mr. Arévalo replaced several senior officials, called for an overhaul of the country’s prison system — where gangs are believed to operate unchecked amid rampant bribery and corruption — and said the country would have help from the U.S. authorities, including the F.B.I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over the weekend, the tension between the Guatemalan authorities and the gangs reached a breaking point. Officials said they would not negotiate with inmates over the privileges they were demanding. Riots broke out in the prisons, and the authorities raided them to reestablish control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, police officers on patrol in the Guatemala City area were slain in what Marco Antonio Villeda, Guatemala’s interior minister, called retaliatory killings by gangs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also said at a news conference on Sunday that Aldo Dupie Ochoa, known as “El Lobo” (The Wolf), a leader of the Barrio 18 gang, had been the main instigator of the riots at one prison. He said Mr. Ochoa was demanding a transfer to another prison and benefits like special food delivery and a king bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funeral services for eight officers were held on Monday. A ninth and 10th police officer died as a result of the prison operations, the Guatemalan national police said on Monday. Six other officers were hospitalized with gunshot wounds, said Edwin Monroy, a police spokesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as of midday Monday, he said that 10 members of the Barrio 18 gang had been arrested in connection with the attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some civil rights are suspended during a state of emergency, Mr. Arévalo said that it would not affect citizens. The measure calls for deploying all active police officers — approximately 45,000 — and members of the army to make patrols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday, in Guatemala City, there were few vehicles or pedestrians. A large number of security personnel were on the streets, stopping and checking vehicles. Public and private schools were closed, but officials said they would resume classes on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/death-toll-rises-in-guatemalan-gang-riots.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:32:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Approves Contentious Chinese Mega-Embassy in London</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/multimedia/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh/13int-uk-china-embassyHFO-jlqh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British government on Tuesday approved construction of a Chinese mega-embassy in the heart of London, rejecting the objections of critics who said the new building will make it easier for China to conduct spying operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval of the embassy, which comes after years of debate and delays, means China can move closer toward construction on a 5.5-acre site near the Tower of London. If it goes ahead, the new embassy will be China’s largest in Europe, although the plans are subject to numerous conditions and could yet be appealed in court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site was the home of Britain’s Royal Mint for more than 150 years. It was purchased by Beijing in 2018, when Boris Johnson was prime minister.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opponents of the new embassy have warned that the location is close to the City of London, the capital’s financial district, and next to fiber-optic cables that transport vast amounts of sensitive data. They argue that Chinese officials could use the cables to spy on companies, on dissidents living in exile or on ordinary Britons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A joint letter released on Tuesday by Ken McCallum, the director of MI5, the country’s domestic security service, and Anne Keast-Butler, the director of GCHQ, its intelligence and cybersecurity agency, said it that “as with any foreign embassy on U.K. soil, it is not realistic to expect to be able wholly to eliminate each and every potential risk.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they said that work by the intelligence agencies and the government to create a “package of national security mitigations for the site” had been “expert, professional and proportionate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also noted that the new site would replace seven different Chinese diplomatic locations currently in use in London. “This consolidation should bring clear security advantages,” they wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision angered China hawks, dissidents, local residents and some of Mr. Starmer’s own Labour Party lawmakers, all of whom campaigned for more than a year to stop its construction. Sarah Champion, a Labour lawmaker who has publicly opposed the embassy, wrote on social media that the decision was “deeply disappointing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approval was formally announced by Steve Reed, the country’s housing minister. In a statement, he said that “all material considerations were taken into account when making this decision. The decision is now final unless it is successfully challenged in court.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A legal fight appears likely, since opposition to the embassy has been building for several years. Protesters have declared their anger at the prospect, including by carrying signs and banners that read “CCP is Watching You. Stop the Mega Embassy!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approval of the project was initially denied in 2022 by the borough council of Tower Hamlets, where the site is located. China later resubmitted the project for approval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement could be a diplomatic boost for the prime minister’s efforts to improve relations with China ahead of his first trip to the country while in office, which is expected to take place in the coming weeks. Mr. Starmer has said he wants to increase investment opportunities with China after years of icy relations between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also comes at a time when Britain, along with other European nations, is under extraordinary pressure from President Trump to submit to his desire to acquire Greenland, putting the trans-Atlantic alliance under strain.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/chinese-embassy-london-starmer.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 18:10:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel Seizes U.N. Agency’s Jerusalem Headquarters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/israel-unrwa-jerusalem.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-gaza-unrwa-photo-pvcg/20int-gaza-unrwa-photo-pvcg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flanked by bulldozers, Israeli officials seized the Jerusalem headquarters of the United Nations agency for Palestinian refugees on Tuesday and oversaw the demolition of some of the structures in its compound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move further escalates Israel’s crackdown on the United Nations Relief and Works Agency, generally known by its acronym UNRWA. The organization had long been one of the leading aid agencies in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip, but over the last two years the Israeli government, which has long been at odds with the agency, has passed sweeping legislation criminalizing its operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement defending the decision to seize the compound, Oren Marmorstein, a spokesman for Israel’s foreign ministry, said UNRWA “has long ceased to be a humanitarian aid organization, serving instead as a greenhouse for terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philippe Lazzarini, the head of UNRWA, called the Israeli move “a new level of open &amp; deliberate defiance of international law” in a post on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UNRWA was founded in 1949 to serve Palestinians who were displaced in the wars surrounding Israel’s establishment and their descendants. The Knesset, Israel’s parliament, passed laws that banned the agency and severely curbed its activity in the occupied West Bank and Gaza. It stripped UNRWA of its diplomatic immunity and barred its facilities from receiving electricity and water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli officials have also accused UNRWA’s Gaza branch of being compromised, saying that Palestinian militant groups had managed to substantially infiltrate the organization. After the Hamas-led attack on southern Israel on Oct. 7, 2023, which ignited the devastating war in Gaza, Israeli officials named 19 UNRWA employees who they say participated in the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An internal U.N. inquiry found that at least nine employees may have participated in the Oct. 7 attack, and the agency fired them. The organization employs about 13,000 people in the Gaza Strip, and UNRWA’s leaders say Israel has never provided evidence to back up its claim that there had been widespread infiltration by Hamas or other groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most recent legislation, passed in late December, also allowed the Israeli government to seize UNRWA’s properties, including the agency’s headquarters. At its largest, hundreds of aid workers and other people employed by UNRWA worked at the Jerusalem compound, according to Jonathan Fowler, a spokesman for the agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UNRWA’s international staff began leaving Israel about a year ago when the legislation first went into effect. The compound has largely been vacant since then, although Israeli officials entered it in December and put up an Israeli flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under an international convention that Israel has ratified, U.N. facilities are supposed to be “inviolable,” similar to the status of a foreign embassy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It remains a United Nations compound, no matter what they say,” Mr. Fowler said. “Even if in December, they ripped down the U.N. flag and put up the Israeli flag.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Marmorstein, the Israeli spokesman, disputed that the seizure was illegal. The compound “does not enjoy any immunity,” he said in a statement, arguing that it was “carried out in accordance with both Israeli and international law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the ban, UNRWA has continued some activities in parts of East Jerusalem, which Israel occupied in the 1967 Mideast war and later annexed, Mr. Fowler said. The agency operates at least two clinics, one of which has already received a cease-and-desist order from the Israeli government, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/israel-unrwa-jerusalem.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:38:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump, Venezuela and Oil</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/venezuela-oil-trump-greenland-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-theworld-venezuela-oil-promo/21int-theworld-venezuela-oil-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One early sign that things might not go so smoothly for the U.S. in its quest for Venezuelan oil was how American energy companies responded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a meeting between oil executives and President Trump this month at the White House, Darren Woods, head of Exxon Mobil, called Venezuela “uninvestable.” Another oil magnate and Trump ally, Harold Hamm, was more diplomatic, but not exactly enthusiastic. Venezuela has “its challenges,” Hamm said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has made it clear that he wants to move fast. At that meeting, which he called less than a week after U.S. troops captured the Venezuelan president, Nicolás Maduro, Trump told oil executives to “rapidly rebuild” the South American country’s oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, exclusive reporting by my colleague Anatoly Kurmanaev found that the U.S. has already begun selling 50 million barrels of the Venezuelan oil that had previously been trapped by a partial U.S. blockade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are good reasons for the U.S. administration to prioritize speed, Anatoly told me. The Venezuelan economy was days from collapsing. Oil storage was near capacity. The currency was in free fall. Officials had to get that trapped oil out and dollars in as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was a race against time,” Anatoly said. “Trump has no interest in a collapsed Venezuela right now.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the longer term, Trump has bigger ambitions. He wants what he calls “energy dominance” — enough weight in the global oil market to curb the power of OPEC countries and gain leverage over China. Venezuela is part of that plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the weeks since the invasion, these longer-term ambitions to gain effective control of Venezuela’s oil industry have “run headlong into reality,” my colleague Anton Troianovski wrote last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump’s grand plans might take years to come to fruition — if they come to fruition at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slow and expensive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem for Trump is that the U.S. doesn’t have a national oil company. Exxon, Chevron and the like are private corporations that will start projects only when they see a good business opportunity. When they look at Venezuela, they don’t like what they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case for investing in Venezuelan oil isn’t straightforward. The country has a lot of oil, but gaining access to it and turning it into a profitable business would take a lot of time and upfront investment, as my colleague Peter Coy writes. That’s the kind of thing that U.S. oil companies, which have recently sought to economize on investments and cut risk, don’t like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low oil prices mean the incentive to invest is limited. “Many analysts believe that a vast oversupply of oil is already sloshing around global markets,” Anton wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem: The U.S. may have removed Maduro, and achieved seeming compliance from his successor, for now, but it’s far from clear that it has achieved long-term political stability in Venezuela. A history of political turmoil, which led to the assets of U.S. oil companies being nationalized in the first place, is part of why executives view the country as “uninvestable” today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as some of my colleagues have been reporting, there are signs that cracks have already begun appearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Zero oil’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all the discontent many Venezuelans feel toward their government, oil has been an integral part of the country’s opposition to the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For the last three decades, they have been fed an ideology of ‘Chavismo,’ with its goal of harnessing oil wealth to transform the country, empower the poor and stand up to the United States and its imperial ambitions,” writes my colleague Maria Abi-Habib.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so some Venezuelans find it hard to swallow their new status as a country willing to cooperate — and share oil wealth — with the Americans who just invaded them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At this point, we should have cut off the oil, we shouldn’t have sold any oil to the United States. Zero oil, zero oil!” one Venezuelan told Maria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear how long the new government will manage to stave off these forces in order to continue cooperation with the United States. Even if it does, other ingredients for instability abound: The country remains filled with paramilitary groups, Colombian guerrillas and gangs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not the kind of environment that looks tempting to an oil executive watching from Texas. But Trump is also willing to strong-arm them into submission. “I’ll probably be inclined to keep Exxon out,” the president told reporters after the White House meeting. “I didn’t like their response.” Exxon’s stock slipped in the aftermath, though it has since recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump is scheduled to speak at the World Economic Forum today, one day after leaders denounced his threats to take over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada gave a searing speech about a “rupture” in the world order. President Emmanuel Macron of France said Europe had little regard for “bullies,” after Trump threatened 200 percent tariffs on French wine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of comments and social media posts ahead of his arrival, Trump mocked European leaders as being weak. His standoff with Europe rattled markets. Greenland’s prime minister would not rule out the possibility of a U.S. attack, even though he said it was “not likely.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russian strikes left thousands of apartment buildings in Kyiv without heat in subfreezing temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators in Spain zeroed in on a problem with the track that may have caused the train crash that killed at least 41 people. Here’s how the collision unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bombing in a Chinese restaurant in Kabul killed at least seven people, with the Islamic State claiming responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel seized the headquarters of the U.N. agency for Palestinian refugees in Jerusalem and demolished some of its buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump accused Britain of “an act of great stupidity” for agreeing to hand over control of the Chagos Islands to Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain approved construction of a Chinese mega-embassy in London despite spying fears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australia passed tighter gun control laws after a mass shooting at a Hanukkah celebration in Sydney killed over a dozen people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guatemala’s president declared a state of emergency to crack down on gangs after uprisings in three prisons killed 10 police officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cubans in Florida, who had long benefited from legal privileges unavailable to other U.S. immigrants, are being deported in record numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Naomi Osaka entered her first Australian Open match in style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Evaluating each Premier League team’s plans for the January transfer window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— U.S. Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, in response to questions about European efforts to block Trump from seizing Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When “The Kholops” opened in St. Petersburg in 2024, Russians raced to see the play about 19th century nobles, which is not-so-subtly scathing about Russian life under President Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest plot twist: Authorities have not shut it down. Officials seemed to recognize that closing “The Kholops” (the title means “The Serfs”) would create a scandal. Many critics and theatergoers have also theorized that the play has avoided intense scrutiny because most of its judgments arrive indirectly. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Milan-Cortina Olympics are less than three weeks away, but the venue for ice hockey, one of the Winter Games’ premier events, is still a construction site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 1,000 workers are scheduled for round-the-clock shifts until the arena in Milan is completed. The opening ceremony is on Feb. 6, and the head of Milan’s Olympic committee said he was confident that “the arena will be done by Feb. 5.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The late-stage work has raised anxiety because the National Hockey League has warned that its players, scheduled to participate in the Olympics for the first time in a dozen years, will pull out if the ice is not safe or ready. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: “Eating Ashes,” by Brenda Navarro, is a tale of migration, loss and memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Care: Here are seven things women should know about heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wear: Should you cuff your pants? Our fashion critic has thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess: Do you know these book titles inspired by Shakespeare?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Red, a common dish served in Ghana, is a popular stew of beans and peppers. It often starts with soaking and slowly cooking the legumes until tender. This recipe uses canned beans and yields a spice-forward, piquant sauce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is this rock formation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stewart Island, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kapiti Island, New Zealand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kangaroo Island, Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tasmania, Australia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/venezuela-oil-trump-greenland-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 20:37:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographer Discovers Train Part That Could Hold Key to Spain Train Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-missing-part-undercarriage-key-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-spain-undercarriage-02-bhmq-promo/20int-spain-undercarriage-02-bhmq-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The undercarriage of a train found near the crash site near Adamuz, Spain on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/spain-missing-part-undercarriage-key-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 23:42:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Escalates Tensions With European Allies With Greenland and Gaza Efforts</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-europe-tensions-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20dc-prexy-top-vhtl/20dc-prexy-top-vhtl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Asked how far he was willing to go to acquire Greenland, President Trump told reporters, “You’ll find out.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/us/politics/trump-europe-tensions-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 17:43:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Carney Speech on U.S. ‘Rupture’ and Canada’s Survival Draws Standing Ovation at Davos</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/canada/carney-speech-davos-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20img-carney-davos-ztlf/20img-carney-davos-ztlf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney got a standing ovation in Davos for starkly describing the end of Pax Americana. He is looking for new allies to help his country survive it.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/canada/carney-speech-davos-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:32:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Another Train Crash in Spain Kills 1 and Hurts 37, Officials Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/train-crash-catalonia-spain.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20xp-spain-ftmk/20xp-spain-ftmk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A train crash in the Catalonia area of Spain killed one person and injured 37 more on Tuesday night, according to regional authorities, days after Spain’s worst railway disaster since 2013. Train service on the regional rail system has been suspended until Wednesday morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the injured, five were in serious condition, according to the Catalonian Emergency Medical Services. In all, 17 people were taken to local hospitals, regional authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the Spanish newspaper El País, the person who was killed was an employee of the train company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crash happened when a retaining wall fell onto the tracks of the Rodalies Catalunya R4 line in Gelida, a town outside Barcelona. One person had to be rescued from the train, according to the Catalonian Fire Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All service on the train line has been suspended because of damage to infrastructure from a storm in the area, according to the Adif train authority. The region has had five consecutive days of rain, according to the Catalonian Meteorological Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Central Airport and Public Transport Area, which is responsible for investigating railway accidents, is on the scene, according to the Catalonian Police. Over 70 firefighters were responding, according to the Fire Department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catalonia is a coastal, autonomous region in northeastern Spain that includes Barcelona and is bordered by France to the north. In 2017, the region tried to secede from Spain, setting off days of protests and escalating longstanding friction with the country’s central government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the train and the collapsed wall have been stabilized and the train has been emptied, firefighters said. A support center has been opened for the relatives of those who were on the train, the local government said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The acting president of Catalonia, Albert Dalmau Miranda, sent his condolences, on social media, to the man who was killed. In a separate incident, he said, another man died Tuesday morning after being swept away by floodwaters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We send all our warmth, support and companionship to those affected in these very difficult times,” Mr. Miranda wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday evening, a high-speed collision between two trains in southern Spain killed at least 41 people and injured dozens more. As of Monday evening, at least 12 of the 41 people hospitalized remained in intensive care, the authorities said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cause of that crash remains under investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/europe/train-crash-catalonia-spain.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 19:14:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pressured by Trump, Mexico Sends 37 Accused Criminals to U.S.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/mexico-cartels-suspects-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/01/22/multimedia/20int-mexico-trump-1/20int-mexico-trump-1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico sent 37 people accused of being criminal operatives to the United States on Tuesday, the latest apparent bid to alleviate pressure from President Trump to do more to combat the powerful groups smuggling drugs across the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first such transfer this year, when Mr. Trump’s threats of military action against Mexico have grown more direct, but the third since he took office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexican authorities have now sent nearly 100 people accused of being key criminals to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transfers are part of a larger effort by Mexican authorities to appease Mr. Trump as he threatens unilateral strikes inside Mexican territory — an act that Mexico’s President Claudia Sheinbaum has said would be a violation of her nation’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amid those threats, Ms. Sheinbaum has launched an aggressive campaign against cartels, strengthened policing at the border, bent to Mr. Trump’s economic demands and sent dozens of accused criminals north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts in Mexico have raised questions about the legal grounds and political gambit of the transfers, as they have been completed outside the normal extradition process. Omar García Harfuch, Mexico’s security chief, said Tuesday that the transfers were legal and that, in agreement with the U.S. Justice Department, the death penalty would not be pursued. (Capital punishment is prohibited in Mexico.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These individuals posed a real threat to the country’s security,” he posted online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Harfuch added that the detainees were sent to various U.S. cities on Mexican military planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year, Mr. Trump has threatened military measures and tariffs to try to force Mexican officials to take more action against cartels and illegal immigration. In the aftermath of the U.S. strike in Venezuela, Mr. Trump’s threats have grown sterner. He said in a Fox News interview on Jan. 8 that the United States would “start now hitting land, with regard to the cartels” in Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those comments greatly concerned Mexicans officials, who had believed that the two countries’ deep economic ties and improved security cooperation would shield Mexico from unilateral action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, The New York Times reported that the United States was intensifying pressure on Mexico to allow U.S. military forces to conduct joint operations to dismantle fentanyl labs inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheinbaum and Mr. Trump spoke briefly on Jan. 12. Even though she said that she again rejected Mr. Trump’s offer of U.S. troops in Mexico, she said they agreed to talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But late last week, despite a phone call between Secretary of State Marco Rubio and his Mexican counterpart and a joint statement about upcoming security meetings, the State Department said in a social media post that “the United States made clear that incremental progress in facing border security challenges is unacceptable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Ms. Sheinbaum defended her country’s efforts, sharing data that she said underscored her administration’s progress in fighting drug trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added that the United States needed to better tackle the drug trade within its own borders, as well as the flow of guns into Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Trump’s comments about land strikes in Mexico, Mexican officials have wanted to show results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They announced arrests of people they accused of being part of criminal groups that the Trump administration has designated as foreign terrorist organizations. They touted raids of drug labs and drug seizures, including what they said was $20 million worth of fentanyl smuggled into Mexico City’s airport as cosmetics from Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Mexican officials said they arrested, with help from the F.B.I., a fugitive named Alejandro Rosales Castillo, who had been on the U.S. agency’s Top Ten Most Wanted list since 2017 for murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all, Mexican authorities have handed over 92 “high-impact criminals,” in Mr. Harfuch’s words, since Mr. Trump took office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unclear whether the accused criminals had been convicted of offenses in Mexico or were being held awaiting trial. Mexican officials linked many to cartels, saying they had trafficked drugs and laundered money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the detainees transferred to the United States, according to the Mexican government: Daniel Alfredo Blanco Joo, accused by Mexican authorities of being a logistics operator linked to the Sinaloa Cartel who helped smuggle drugs into the United States; José Luis Sánchez Valencia, whom Mexican officials said was part of the powerful Jalisco New Generation Cartel and related to its leader; and Ricardo González Sauceda, who is accused of being a regional leader of the Cártel del Noreste and was sanctioned by the U.S. in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s an offering,” said Carlos Pérez Ricart, an expert on organized crime and professor at the Center for Research and Teaching in Economics in Mexico City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest handover, he said, is “far from a magic solution” to stave off Mr. Trump’s pressure. “But at least the Mexican government is buying itself some time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pérez Ricart said that the legal and political debate surrounding the transfers have subsided since the first one last year, in part, because of Mr. Trump’s military action in Venezuela has made his threats more real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Nicas contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/mexico-cartels-suspects-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 17:50:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Heads to Davos Amid Deep Worries About U.S.-European Alliance</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-trump-davos-hwzf/21dc-trump-davos-hwzf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is known for disrupting global summits, lashing out at allies and hanging the possibility of tariffs over trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, America’s international alliances have largely weathered his threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Mr. Trump descends on a gathering of the world’s wealthiest and most powerful leaders in the Swiss Alps on Wednesday, he will encounter a group of longtime diplomatic partners now reassessing their relationships with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s pugilistic demands to acquire Greenland have bewildered many of the European leaders attending the World Economic Forum in Davos, raising questions about the strength of the trans-Atlantic alliance and turning the elitist gathering into an all-hands effort to de-escalate tensions with an emboldened American president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked Tuesday how far he was willing to go to acquire Greenland, Mr. Trump told reporters at the White House, “You’ll find out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His vague threats of territorial expansion, as well as warnings of new tariffs against European leaders who do not heed his demands, have brought Mr. Trump’s relationship with his counterparts there to a new low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday before his trip to Davos, Mr. Trump mocked European leaders on social media and shared private missives from leaders including President Emmanuel Macron of France, who wrote, “I do not understand what you are doing on Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fraught dynamics reflect the latest twist in the Trump administration’s bumpy relationship with Europe. Mark Rutte, NATO’s secretary general, has sought to build a rapport with Mr. Trump. But the administration’s national security strategy released last month warned that Europe faces “civilizational erasure” and said the United States should help Europe “correct its current trajectory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s fair to say that Davos, like so many other international institutions or forums, is another piece of the system that Trump is going to fundamentally transform,” said Michael Froman, a Davos attendee and the president of the Council on Foreign Relations, a U.S. think tank. He said all topics at the annual World Economic Forum had effectively taken a back seat “to discuss whether this is the beginning of the end of the Western alliance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders acknowledged a new reality in which they could not rely on the United States. Mr. Macron warned that “imperial ambitions are resurfacing” and that the U.S. had openly aimed to “weaken and subordinate Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron said he would respond by pushing for “more sovereignty and more autonomy for the Europeans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada described the current moment as a “breaking of the world order, the end of a pleasant fiction and the beginning of a brutal reality where the geopolitics of the great powers is not subject to any constraint.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders at the summit were contemplating retaliatory tariffs against the United States. But Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, who arrived at Davos before Mr. Trump, warned such a move would be “unwise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the summit’s attention will be focused on Mr. Trump’s planned delivery Wednesday of a speech the White House has described as a “special address” to the forum, though a delay in his departure because of an electrical problem on Air Force One threatened to push back the timing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, who is leading the largest ever U.S. delegation to Davos, with multiple cabinet secretaries, was also expected to hold meetings with foreign leaders and attend a reception with chief executives in finance and cryptocurrency on Wednesday evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump is scheduled to make an announcement on his “board of peace,” a group he has said will help rebuild Gaza. Mr. Trump has invited President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, whom European leaders have sought to isolate over his invasion of Ukraine, to join the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear which other leaders will attend that announcement. Mr. Macron, who was invited, does not plan to join the board. Asked on Monday about the refusal, Mr. Trump threatened to impose a 200 percent tariff on French wine, one of the country’s best-known exports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other global dynamics are expected to play out at the forum. The administration’s criminal investigation of Jerome H. Powell, the Federal Reserve chair, has rattled many of the banking chiefs flocking to Davos. And his standoff with European leaders over Greenland led to a drop in the value of U.S. stocks, the dollar and government bonds on Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While international issues will most likely dominate Mr. Trump’s time in Davos, his aides have said he will use the summit to address concerns about affordability in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is planning to dedicate at least some of his remarks on Wednesday to detailing how his administration will make housing more affordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even some of Mr. Trump’s advisers have privately worried about the optics of attending a summit for wealthy bankers and chief executives when some critics in his base have accused him of focusing too much on foreign policy and not on the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the White House on Tuesday, Mr. Trump promoted his economic policies, dismissing polling showing many Americans are frustrated over his handling of the economy. Mr. Trump blamed his advisers, suggesting they were not doing enough to promote his administration’s successes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Maybe I have bad public relations people,” Mr. Trump said. “But we’re not getting it across.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 20:00:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Was Macron Wearing Sunglasses in Davos?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/macron-sunglasses-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21xp-macron-kmzp/21xp-macron-kmzp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French are known for their style. So when President Emmanuel Macron addressed the World Economic Forum on Tuesday, it was striking to see him wearing sunglasses indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A medical issue, however, and not the dictates of fashion, prompted Mr. Macron to take the stage in Davos, Switzerland, in a pair of blue-tinted aviator-style glasses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron did not acknowledge his unconventional choice of spectacles during his 18-minute speech. The sunglasses made their first appearance last Thursday, when he sported an inflamed right eye during a New Year’s speech to France’s armed forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Please pardon the unsightly appearance of my eye,” he told the troops, after removing the glasses for the speech, adding that the condition was “completely harmless.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;French news reports have indicated that Mr. Macron has been suffering from broken blood vessels in his eye. The condition is known medically as a subconjunctival hemorrhage, which can be caused by trauma, coughing, sneezing, high blood pressure or medications like blood thinners, according to the American Academy of Ophthalmology. The condition typically goes away without treatment within two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders have used their speeches in Davos to challenge President Trump’s increasingly bellicose posture to traditional allies of the United States. On Tuesday, Mr. Macron warned of a “shift toward a world without rules,” referring to the growing disregard for international law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules of etiquette, which forbid wearing sunglasses indoors, could be overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media, Mr. Macron’s sunglasses were seen as a political statement, projecting a tough image in the face of Mr. Trump’s threats to impose tariffs on French wine and champagne and to annex Greenland. He has previously used his clothing to send a message, donning a turtleneck in the winter of 2022 as Europe contended with an energy crisis in the wake of Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people likened the bespectacled Mr. Macron to the naval aviator played by Tom Cruise in “Top Gun.” Others recalled former President Joe Biden’s penchant for aviators, though Mr. Biden was not known to wear his sunglasses while addressing world leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/macron-sunglasses-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:48:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Greenland Tensions Rattle Global Markets</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/greenland-stocks-bonds-dollar-gold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21Biz-Global-Markets-01-pjqm/21Biz-Global-Markets-01-pjqm-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Stocks in Japan and throughout Asia edged lower on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/greenland-stocks-bonds-dollar-gold.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:31:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rising Global Temperatures May Affect Choices for Winter Olympic Venues</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/climate/winter-olympics-climate-change.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21CLI-winter-olymics-climate-01-hlmw/21CLI-winter-olymics-climate-01-hlmw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gus Schumacher, a member of the U.S. cross-country skiing team, left, competing in Planica, Slovenia, in March 2023.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/climate/winter-olympics-climate-change.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:00:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan’s $40 Billion Military Spending Plan Stalled by Political Impasse</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/taiwan-trump-military-gridlock-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/10/multimedia/00int-taiwan-politics-qvcp/00int-taiwan-politics-qvcp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A political quagmire in Taiwan has stalled plans by its President Lai Ching-te to sharply increase military spending, even as President Donald Trump has pressed the island to pay more for its own defense against China’s campaign to bring the island under its control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opposition lawmakers who dominate the legislature have blocked Mr. Lai’s ambitious proposal to spend $40 billion across eight years on military equipment from moving forward without concessions from Mr. Lai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Taiwan, the impasse has implications beyond just a domestic political fight. It could raise questions about Taiwan’s ability to strengthen its defenses at a time when Mr. Trump is urging America’s allies and partners to shoulder more of the burden for their own security. Mr. Lai has pledged to lift military and security outlays to more than 3 percent of Taiwan’s economy this year to mollify the United States, the island’s chief security backer against Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Lai’s plan is caught in a tangle of budgetary and legal disputes between his party and the opposition parties. Both sides have used hardball tactics and accused each other of acting unlawfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking with longstanding practice, Mr. Lai’s premier refused to sign off on a law passed by the opposition-controlled legislature that would shift some tax revenues from the central government to local administrations. Opposition lawmakers, in turn, denounced the premier’s move to stymie the revenue law as unconstitutional. They have also called Mr. Lai a dictator and moved to impeach him, an effort that is largely symbolic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have never experienced such a massive crisis of constitutional rule of law as we have right now,” Weng Hsiao-ling, a lawmaker from the Nationalist Party, the main opposition party, said in an interview. “Executive power is not operating according to the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of Mr. Lai’s Democratic Progressive Party, for their part, say that the opposition is trying to paralyze his administration. They accuse some opposition politicians of taking their cues from Beijing and of endangering Taiwan’s security by holding up defense spending. They are frustrated that the opposition has twice rejected Mr. Lai’s nominations to Taiwan’s constitutional court, effectively sidelining the body that could help defuse such disputes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Su Chiao-hui, a lawmaker from the Democratic Progressive Party, said that the opposition’s blocking of nominees damaged Taiwan’s ability to resolve conflicts. “They changed the rules, and the referee is gone,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The friction reflects growing divisions in Taiwan over whether to hold tight to its relationship with the United States or try rapprochement with Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lai’s party says that Taiwan is its own country, and stronger defense and deeper ties with the United States are the way to protect Taiwan against China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nationalist Party, however, favors expanded ties with Beijing. Some of its leaders, including its chairwoman, Cheng Li-wun, have suggested that Mr. Lai’s strategy will escalate tensions with China. They have said that they generally support military spending to protect Taiwan, but have emphasized their skepticism about Mr. Lai’s plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s an increasingly clear partisan divide of perception in Taiwan in terms of views of the U.S., views of China,” said Wei-ting Yen, a political scientist at Academia Sinica, a Taiwanese research academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions between the two sides grew last year after Mr. Lai’s party backed a recall campaign to oust dozens of Nationalist Party legislators, which ultimately failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nationalist lawmakers are not in a “terribly good mood to make further compromises with Lai,” said Alexander C. Huang, an international security expert who was formerly that party’s director of international affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opposition lawmakers have blocked deliberations on Mr. Lai’s military spending plan, as well as the annual budget, demanding, among other things, that Mr. Lai first appear before the legislature for questioning. The opposition has also pointed to what it says are unacceptably long delays in deliveries of U.S. weapons, including F-16 fighter jets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve paid up, but the weapons are nowhere to be seen,” Fu Kun-chi, a Nationalist Party leader, said last month. “We support national defense, but don’t support being fleeced in arms purchases.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compromise may still be possible. The Nationalists have pushed for more public disclosure of details; the government has said that revealing some details would compromise security, but gave lawmakers a private briefing this week and released more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. representative in Taipei, Raymond Greene, has backed Mr. Lai’s military spending proposals and urged the parties to work together, while the State Department pledged to work with industry to deliver equipment more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some officials from Taiwan’s governing party hope that lawmakers from a smaller opposition party, the Taiwan People’s Party, will break with the Nationalists, giving Mr. Lai the votes to pass his plans. He appears buoyed after Taiwan and Washington signed a framework agreement to reduce Mr. Trump’s tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington may increase pressure on the opposition, aware that a public breach with the United States would be politically fraught for any party in Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The opposition Nationalists naturally hope to keep a balance between China and the U.S.,” said Su Tzu-chiao, a political scientist at Soochow University in Taipei, “but they cannot directly oppose the U.S.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/taiwan-trump-military-gridlock-china.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:41:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Man Gets Life in Prison for Killing Shinzo Abe, Former Leader of Japan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/japan-shinzo-abe-killer-verdict.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-japan-abe-pbhv/21int-japan-abe-pbhv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man was sentenced to life in prison on Wednesday for assassinating Shinzo Abe, Japan’s longest-serving prime minister, bringing an end to a case that shocked the nation and provoked debate about political violence and broader societal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetsuya Yamagami, 45, was found guilty of killing Mr. Abe by a district court in the western city of Nara. He admitted in October to shooting Mr. Abe with a homemade gun at an election rally in Nara in 2022, but his lawyers had sought a shorter sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case of Mr. Yamagami, who was unemployed and had briefly served in Japan’s military, known as the Self-Defense Forces, divided Japanese society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people expressed sympathy for him because of his difficult childhood; his family faced economic hardships, and his father and brother both died by suicide. Others said he should receive a harsh penalty for killing Mr. Abe, a towering figure in Japanese politics who stepped down in 2020. Mr. Abe, 67, was stumping for a junior politician near a train station in Nara when he was shot in the neck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the trial, which lasted about two months, Mr. Yamagami said he shot Mr. Abe because he perceived him as supporting the powerful Unification Church, a South Korea-based group with substantial operations in Japan. Mr. Yamagami said the church had bankrupted his family by forcing his mother, a member, to turn over her life savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I felt that striking back at the Unification Church — or, rather, dealing them a significant hit — was the very meaning of my life,” he said during the trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial drew intense interest in Japan, where political violence and shootings are rare. The last time such a high-profile assassination occurred was in 1936, when two former prime ministers were killed during a coup by the Imperial Japanese Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nara, nearly 700 people lined up outside the courthouse on Wednesday, hoping to be among the 33 members of the public allowed inside the courtroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiuko Notoya contributed reporting from Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/japan-shinzo-abe-killer-verdict.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 02:51:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean Ex-Premier Gets 23 Years in Prison for Role in Martial Law</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/south-korea-prime-minister-martial-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-skorea-han-hpcm/21int-skorea-han-hpcm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Han Duck-soo, South Korea’s former prime minister, arriving at Seoul Central District Court on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/south-korea-prime-minister-martial-law.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 00:51:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French Doctor Listened to Women’s Pain, Then Transformed How It Was Treated</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/france-doctor-house-of-women.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/10/multimedia/00int-france-doctor-profile-01-kftp/00int-france-doctor-profile-01-kftp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Dr. Ghada Hatem-Gantzer on the patio of the House of Women medical center that she built in Saint-Denis, France.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/france-doctor-house-of-women.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:02:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Latin America, Loathing of Maduro Smothers Outcry Over U.S. Raid</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/latin-america-venezuela-us-raid-maduro-polls.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/00int-latam-response01a-photo-kgqm/00int-latam-response01a-photo-kgqm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Argentina, dormant high school group chats roared to life with news of Nicolás Maduro’s capture. Colombians debated exit plans if they were next on Washington’s list, Ecuadorean schoolteachers paused lessons to discuss the U.S. raid, and a Peruvian beauty queen even weighed in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet this regional frenzy did not translate into a significant wave of organized protests across a continent that has long harbored resentment over the United States’ Cold War-era meddling in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some Latin Americans denounced what they decried as American imperialism in Venezuela, a more supportive response to President Trump’s action prevailed, with several polls showing that a majority of Latin Americans endorsed the intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am happy because I saw the fall of a dictator and I am happy because my Venezuelan friends are happy,” said Carlos Segura, 36, a professor in Buenos Aires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventy-four percent of Peruvians, sixty-three percent of Chileans, a majority of Colombians, Brazilians, Argentines, and even Panamanians, whose country was itself invaded by the United States to remove an authoritarian leader nearly three decades ago, approved of the capture, according to several polls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mexico, the response was more evenly split, reflecting a significant leftist base and widespread opposition to Mr. Trump’s policies. The country’s leftist leader, Claudia Sheinbaum, issued a carefully worded rejection of the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, disagreements among regional leaders over the U.S. removal of Mr. Maduro were tempered by a desire to avoid direct friction with Mr. Trump. And at the ground level, divisions among Latin Americans were softened by the left’s struggle to mobilize against the capture of a reviled authoritarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever unhappiness exists toward Mr. Trump and his desire to project dominance over Latin America, a shift toward pragmatism is eclipsing old ideological loyalties, at least for now, experts said. That could certainly change if Mr. Trump follows through on threats to launch land strikes, perhaps in Mexico or in South America, targeting what he says are drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the case of Venezuela, many Latin Americans opposed Mr. Maduro’s rule and felt the impact of its fallout — including millions of Venezuelans who migrated throughout the region fleeing poverty and repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“International law, imperialism, this is the discourse of the elite,” said Marta Lagos, the founder of Latinobarómetro, an annual public opinion survey across Latin America. Popular support for the U.S. intervention, “has nothing to do with ideology,” she said. “They choose whatever is possible to fix things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of Venezuela’s political future is in flux, with the interim government run by those who ruled alongside Mr. Maduro, and their repressive behavior has continued targeting people engaged in public displays of celebration over the U.S. intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But outside the country, a resounding wave of euphoria rang out, louder than the traditional “Yankees go home” cries, as many Latin Americans joined the Venezuelan diaspora in welcoming Mr. Maduro’s toppling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was the only way Venezuelans could get rid of this guy,” said Lorena Plaza, 37, a schoolteacher in Quito, Ecuador. “Maybe it wasn’t the right way, but there really wasn’t another way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Argentina, where the Venezuelan crisis has been a fixture of domestic political friction for more than a decade as a cautionary lesson of socialist misrule, car horns erupted at dawn on Jan. 3 after news of Mr. Maduro’s capture spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An A.I. generated song by a Venezuelan living in Argentina that mocks how China and Russia failed to defend their Venezuelan ally — “where are the communists?” — became a major sensation, gathering more than 11 million views on TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Panamanians and Venezuelans celebrating from now on every Jan. 3,” read a post from El Gallinazo, a popular Panamanian Instagram account that featured a video of two men dancing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some regional reactions to Mr. Maduro’s extraction still fell along familiar left-right divides. Many supporters of Brazil’s president, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, a leftist, and Mexico’s Ms. Sheinbaum, opposed the U.S. attack. In Chile, President Gabriel Boric — who has tried to stake out a new brand of leftist politics by distancing himself from the region’s socialist dictatorships — nonetheless issued a sharply worded condemnation of the American action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Mr. Roman said, “you don’t really see the left rallying behind this as a major crying call.” Mr. Maduro’s rule proved so plainly calamitous, he added “it’s not an easy topic for the left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 3, while celebrations erupted in the heart of Buenos Aires, Argentina’s capital, leftist parties called for a protest outside the city’s U.S. Embassy — but the demonstration ended up being relatively modest in size. A survey by the polling firm Altica showed that 31 percent of Argentines opposed the U.S. intervention, while 61 percent supported it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentiment was largely different in Europe, where a majority of Spaniards, Germans and Britons condemned the attack, according to recent polls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the U.S. invasion of Iraq in 2003, Argentina, a Gallup International survey found, registered the highest level of opposition of any country surveyed — 83 percent — with many Latin American nations also strongly criticizing the military action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Iraq was much closer in time to the Cold War, as well as a faraway geographical conflict, experts noted, while Venezuela was an immediate, nearby, destabilizing threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Maduro turned out to be the neighbor who is noisy and disruptive, so when the police came to pick him up they were like: ‘finally,’” said Patricio Navia, a Chilean political scientist at New York University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Levitsky, a political scientist at Harvard University, noted that three decades have passed since the Cold War helped contribute to U.S. meddling in Central America and a support for brutal dictatorships that entrenched anti-American sentiments across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has been a pretty big generational change,” he said. “Many Latin Americans don’t remember that period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Latin Americans now are worried about more pressing and urgent concerns, experts said, including crime waves fueled in large part by the power and spread of drug trafficking groups that have plagued countries like Ecuador or Costa Rica, nations that had been considered relatively safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Latin Americans are willing to embrace virtually any solution to end the violence, regardless of the methods employed. That “by all means necessary” logic can take the form of endorsing the illiberal methods of El Salvador’s president, Nayib Bukele, who has suspended key civil liberties while cracking down on crime — but also of condoning outside intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Latin Americans don’t like a U.S. invasion,” Mr. Navia said, “but they dislike economic crises and humanitarian crises even more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela has been in crisis since 2014, when oil prices plunged, with food and medicine becoming scarcer and more expensive and the Maduro government becoming increasingly repressive, propelling one of the largest migration crises in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the eight million Venezuelans who fled the country in recent years, nearly seven million migrated to Latin American countries, most to Colombia and Perú, according to the Migration Policy institute, a research center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some nations, the influx has stretched budgets and angered locals who view the newcomers as competition for jobs and other services. And even though people who have committed crimes are a tiny fraction of the many Venezuelans who have fled, the infiltration of criminal gangs among the migrants have brought new crimes and fears among local populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Colombians saw in Mr. Maduro’s government an ally of armed Colombian rebel groups that have long terrorized their country. One of the largest has established a deep footprint along the border between Colombia and Venezuela, fomenting violence and displacing many Colombians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any action that could potentially weaken these groups is often welcomed by many Colombians — even if it means the United States raiding a sovereign country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are willing to look at El Salvador,” Ms. Lagos said. “People are willing to pay a price.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Daniel Politi and Lucía Cholakian Herrera from Buenos Aires, Argentina, Simon Romero and Annie Correal from Bogotá, Colombia, James Wagner from Mexico City, Mitra Taj from Lima, Peru, and José María León Cabrera from Quito, Ecuador.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/latin-america-venezuela-us-raid-maduro-polls.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:06:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Maduro’s Last Dance, a New Rhythm Goes Viral in Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/maduro-venezuela-dancing-tiktok.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/world/00int-venezuela-viralsong-top/00int-venezuela-viralsong-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peering from under a cap emblazoned with Venezuela’s flag, Miguel Alejandro Herrera smiled at the camera, and then started swaying his hips to a catchy Latin rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Where is China? Where is Russia? Why didn’t they act? What’s the excuse?” Mr. Herrera lip-synced in Spanish, bouncing his shoulders to the beat. “Maduro is in a federal prison, and now I ask myself: Where are the communists who were going to help him?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, which he said he made with artificial intelligence, is a celebration of Nicolás Maduro’s ouster as Venezuela’s leader and a jab at some of his closest alliances, said Mr. Herrera, a music producer and social media commentator known online as Kilómetro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was posted on Jan. 8, the video has drawn more than 11 million views on TikTok and 5 million on Instagram. And it has racked up thousands of comments, most of them cheering Mr. Herrera and Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I knew the theme was going to catch on,” Mr. Herrera, 28, said in an interview from Argentina, where he has been living in exile since 2024. “But I didn’t know it was going to be this big.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera’s song plays on a trope familiar to most Venezuelans: the jingles long deployed by Mr. Maduro and his political movement. In the lead-up to his capture, Mr. Maduro had taken to breaking into musical routines, including dancing to techno beats remixed with the slogan “No War, Yes Peace.” (His dancing may have ultimately contributed to his downfall.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, and the enormous response it has set off, stand in sharp contrast with the narrative offered by Venezuela’s government, which has leaned on the state-controlled broadcaster to show what appear to be large crowds of protesters, insisting that Venezuelans are overwhelmingly upset about Mr. Maduro’s ouster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few in Venezuela have dared to disagree, as a new wave of repression has taken hold. Since the U.S. operation that led to Mr. Maduro’s capture, Venezuelan security forces have boarded buses, searched phones and questioned people, seeking evidence of support for his removal. Fearing reprisal, many Venezuelans are sidestepping the subject at workplaces, coffee shops and other public settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet online, at home and abroad, Mr. Herrera’s catchy tune appears to be resonating. “I say what people inside Venezuela cannot say,” Mr. Herrera said. “Many people write to me saying they have the song saved for when they can play it loud on the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His video plays on the familiar use of sentimental, upbeat or triumphant melodies by Chavismo, the socialist-inspired movement first embodied by Hugo Chávez and, later, by his successor, Mr. Maduro. Those tunes were once so catchy, Mr. Herrera said, that they would even move Venezuelans who opposed Mr. Maduro. “Now that has changed,” he said. “Now, the opposition’s music is better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Mr. Herrera sought to create a summer hit, not unlike the ones that typically hit airwaves around this time of year in the Southern Hemisphere. “The rhythm is, like, tropical,” he added. “It’s perfect for listening in the car, for going to the beach, for celebrating.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera’s post has also set off a wave of memes, including an A.I.-generated video of President Trump spinning the tune on a D.J. turntable as Mr. Maduro, in a prison cell and clad in an orange jumpsuit, swings his hips to the rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of Mr. Herrera’s video has been fueled in part by Venezuela’s vast and vocal diaspora. Fleeing repression and economic woes, about eight million people have left the country since 2015, many settling in Spain, the United States or countries in South America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera began making videos ahead of the presidential election in 2024. Many of them explained electoral rules, urged Venezuelans to register to vote and supported the candidate challenging Mr. Maduro. Mr. Herrera eventually amassed several million followers, and his posts garnered hundreds of thousands of views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Mr. Maduro claimed victory despite evidence that the opposition had won by a large margin, Mr. Herrera decided to leave Venezuela. “We packed our bags that night,” Mr. Herrera said. “I left for my safety.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many Venezuelans abroad, Mr. Herrera isn’t quite ready to go back yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with Mr. Maduro out of the picture, Venezuela is still being run by his inner circle of loyalists. The United States has endorsed the nation’s interim leader, Delcy Rodríguez, warning that more strikes could come if she failed to follow America’s interests when it came to oil, but making almost no mention of human rights or democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one post, Mr. Herrera depicts Ms. Rodríguez as a string puppet manipulated by Mr. Trump. Mr. Herrera said he believed that, with the United States exerting so much control, Venezuela was on course for substantive change. “The United States is there, and she has to do what Trump wants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Mr. Herrera said he would keep making videos. “It’s a fight for the freedom of my country,” he said. “More than a job, it’s a hope of returning to a free country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria Ramírez contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/maduro-venezuela-dancing-tiktok.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:04:51 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>