<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 01:16:06 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What to Know About Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ for Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When President Trump said he planned to establish and lead a “Board of Peace” to oversee the cease-fire between Israel and Hamas in Gaza, many did not know what to make of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, letters went out asking countries to join the newly minted body, among them historically close U.S. allies like Canada, France, Britain, and Saudi Arabia. But Russia and Belarus, hardly allies, were also on the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a perusal of the body’s charter — which governments received alongside their invitations — suggested that Mr. Trump hopes the Board of Peace could get involved in all kinds of global conflicts, not just the one in the Gaza Strip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics reacted furiously, saying the Trump administration appeared to be setting up the board as a potential American-dominated rival to the United Nations, which Mr. Trump has long accused of liberal bias and waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As chairman, Mr. Trump would have considerable influence over the Board of Peace. With countries being asked to pay more than $1 billion for permanent membership, its budget could be substantial, though it is unclear how much control Mr. Trump would have over how the money is spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presence of Turkey and Qatar on one of the board’s subcommittees also prompted an immediate outcry from Israel, which has been at odds with the Turkish government, particularly over the war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what we know so far about the Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the board appeared to be part of Mr. Trump’s vision for postwar Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His plan called the board a “new international transitional body” that would help supervise the rebuilding of the Palestinian enclave. The board’s members would include world leaders, with Mr. Trump sitting at the head of the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Nations Security Council later formally backed the board in a U.S.-drafted resolution in November, giving it the force of international legitimacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution gave the board a mandate to work with governments to recruit international peacekeepers for Gaza. It was to carry out Mr. Trump’s plan in Gaza until the internationally recognized Palestinian Authority conducted reforms, the resolution said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after the United States circulated the board’s charter on Friday, it became clear that Mr. Trump envisions a much bigger role for the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed charter said the Board of Peace would “secure enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict,” not just Gaza, according to a copy shared with The New York Times. It also called for “a more nimble and effective international peace-building body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The list of invitees includes Britain, Jordan, Russia and more. But so far, only a handful — like the pro-Trump Argentine president, Javier Milei, and Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary — have said they will join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite overseeing Gaza, neither the Board of Peace nor a Gaza Executive Board underneath it have any Palestinian members as yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board is, however, to oversee the work of a group of Palestinian technocrats charged with administering public services in Gaza. Analysts say they will face a formidable challenge, given that Gaza is still split in two between areas under Israeli and Hamas control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some countries appear skeptical. To acquire a permanent seat on the Board of Peace, each would have to pay more than a billion dollars in cash within the first year to fund the body’s operations. (States can join for three years for free.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The charter would invest considerable personal power in Mr. Trump as chairman. It says that he will name members of a second “Executive Board” to carry out the board’s decisions, and that Mr. Trump would wield considerable veto power over its actions. He would also be able to name his own successor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump would also be permitted to enact “resolutions or other directives” to carry out the board’s mission, and to “create, modify or dissolve subsidiary entities.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France does not currently intend to join, as the board’s charter raises serious questions about respecting the role of the United Nations, said a senior French official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to comply with government protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how many countries will pay the fee to become permanent members, as opposed to accepting the optional three-year term for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not exactly clear how much oversight the Board of Peace will exert over Gaza and for how long. But two subcommittees reporting to Mr. Trump’s board have already been set up to carry out his Gaza peace plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the White House named a “Gaza Executive Board” that includes Jared Kushner, the president’s son-in-law, and Steve Witkoff, Mr. Trump’s envoy. The group also has Qatari and Egyptian officials, as well as an Israeli businessman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a rare public break with Mr. Trump, Israel criticized the makeup of the committee, particularly the presence of Qatar and Turkey. Both countries helped mediate between Israel and Hamas to secure the Gaza cease-fire, but Israeli officials have accused them of being too close to Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ségolène Le Stradic contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:48:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Was Macron Wearing Sunglasses in Davos?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/macron-sunglasses-davos.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21xp-macron-kmzp/21xp-macron-kmzp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French are known for their style. So when President Emmanuel Macron addressed the World Economic Forum on Tuesday, it was striking to see him wearing sunglasses indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A medical issue, however, and not the dictates of fashion, prompted Mr. Macron to take the stage in Davos, Switzerland, in a pair of blue-tinted aviator-style glasses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron did not acknowledge his unconventional choice of spectacles during his 18-minute speech. The sunglasses made their first appearance last Thursday, when he sported an inflamed right eye during a New Year’s speech to France’s armed forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Please pardon the unsightly appearance of my eye,” he told the troops, after removing the glasses for the speech, adding that the condition was “completely harmless.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;French news reports have indicated that Mr. Macron has been suffering from broken blood vessels in his eye. The condition is known medically as a subconjunctival hemorrhage, which can be caused by trauma, coughing, sneezing, high blood pressure or medications like blood thinners, according to the American Academy of Ophthalmology. The condition typically goes away without treatment within two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders have used their speeches in Davos to challenge President Trump’s increasingly bellicose posture to traditional allies of the United States. On Tuesday, Mr. Macron warned of a “shift toward a world without rules,” referring to the growing disregard for international law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules of etiquette, which forbid wearing sunglasses indoors, could be overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media, Mr. Macron’s sunglasses were seen as a political statement, projecting a tough image in the face of Mr. Trump’s threats to impose tariffs on French wine and champagne and to annex Greenland. He has previously used his clothing to send a message, donning a turtleneck in the winter of 2022 as Europe contended with an energy crisis in the wake of Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people likened the bespectacled Mr. Macron to the naval aviator played by Tom Cruise in “Top Gun.” Others recalled former President Joe Biden’s penchant for aviators, though Mr. Biden was not known to wear his sunglasses while addressing world leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Macron’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/macron-sunglasses-davos.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:36:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Stocks Rebound After Trump Backs Off European Tariffs</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/greenland-stocks-bonds-dollar-gold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21Biz-Global-Markets-02-pjqm/21Biz-Global-Markets-02-pjqm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump takes questions from reporters during a news conference in the James S. Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on Tuesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/business/greenland-stocks-bonds-dollar-gold.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:04:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rising Global Temperatures May Affect Choices for Winter Olympic Venues</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/climate/winter-olympics-climate-change.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21CLI-winter-olymics-climate-01-hlmw/21CLI-winter-olymics-climate-01-hlmw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gus Schumacher, a member of the U.S. cross-country skiing team, left, competing in Planica, Slovenia, in March 2023.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/climate/winter-olympics-climate-change.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 03:00:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The New Wild Card on Travelers’ Itineraries: Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/uncertainty-is-the-only-certainty.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/travel/21Uncertainty-illo/21Uncertainty-illo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Politics, military action and climate change have increased risk for destinations that once seemed like sure bets, forcing travelers to change how they plan.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/travel/uncertainty-is-the-only-certainty.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:43:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Did the U.S. Ever Own Greenland? Fact-Checking Trump’s Davos Speech.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/fact-check-trump-davos-speech.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-factcheck-mczq/21dc-factcheck-mczq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump speaking at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/fact-check-trump-davos-speech.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:14:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s Protests Have Been Completely Squashed, Government Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/iran-protests-crushed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-iran-protests-mgjv/21int-iran-protests-mgjv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A photograph taken during a tour for international news media shows a tax office that was burned during protests, on Wednesday in Tehran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/iran-protests-crushed.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:16:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Moves on Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/trumps-greenland-davos-isis-syria.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-theworld-trump-greenland-promo/22int-theworld-trump-greenland-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After assailing Europe in a long speech at Davos, the president said he had won an agreement on the future of the Arctic territory.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/trumps-greenland-davos-isis-syria.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:16:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Talk of Greenland ‘Deal’ Framework Draws Mixed Reactions</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/trump-greenland-deal-news.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-greenland-reax01-photo-cqpb/21int-greenland-reax01-photo-cqpb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
People walking past a large mural in Nuuk, Greenland, on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/trump-greenland-deal-news.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:23:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Davos, a Clash Between Trump’s World and the Old World</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/davos-trump-speech-greenland-deal.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-davos-scene01-photo-bqgm/21int-davos-scene01-photo-bqgm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Audience members listening to President Trump’s address at Davos on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/davos-trump-speech-greenland-deal.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:29:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’ Would Have Global Scope but One Man in Charge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-board-peace-united-nations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21dc-board-peace-mkft/21dc-board-peace-mkft-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Israel, Saudi Arabia and other nations have said they would join President Trump’s proposed “Board of Peace,” but France, Norway and Sweden have said no.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/us/politics/trump-board-peace-united-nations.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:24:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Rifaat al-Assad, Paramilitary Leader and ‘Butcher of Hama,’ Dies at 88</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/rifaat-al-assad-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21assad-hvmj/21assad-hvmj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Rifaat Assad in his office in Marbella, Spain, in 2005. For more than 50 years, many of them spent in cosseted exile, he was an integral part of the family that ruled Syria with an iron fist.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/rifaat-al-assad-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:28:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Pressured by Trump, Mexico Sends 37 Accused Criminals to U.S.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/mexico-cartels-suspects-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/01/22/multimedia/20int-mexico-trump-1/20int-mexico-trump-1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico sent 37 people accused of being criminal operatives to the United States on Tuesday, the latest apparent bid to alleviate pressure from President Trump to do more to combat the powerful groups smuggling drugs across the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first such transfer this year, when Mr. Trump’s threats of military action against Mexico have grown more direct, but the third since he took office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexican authorities have now sent nearly 100 people accused of being key criminals to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transfers are part of a larger effort by Mexican authorities to appease Mr. Trump as he threatens unilateral strikes inside Mexican territory — an act that Mexico’s President Claudia Sheinbaum has said would be a violation of her nation’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amid those threats, Ms. Sheinbaum has launched an aggressive campaign against cartels, strengthened policing at the border, bent to Mr. Trump’s economic demands and sent dozens of accused criminals north.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts in Mexico have raised questions about the legal grounds and political gambit of the transfers, as they have been completed outside the normal extradition process. Omar García Harfuch, Mexico’s security chief, said Tuesday that the transfers were legal and that, in agreement with the U.S. Justice Department, the death penalty would not be pursued. (Capital punishment is prohibited in Mexico.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These individuals posed a real threat to the country’s security,” he posted online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Harfuch added that the detainees were sent to various U.S. cities on Mexican military planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not immediately respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a year, Mr. Trump has threatened military measures and tariffs to try to force Mexican officials to take more action against cartels and illegal immigration. In the aftermath of the U.S. strike in Venezuela, Mr. Trump’s threats have grown sterner. He said in a Fox News interview on Jan. 8 that the United States would “start now hitting land, with regard to the cartels” in Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those comments greatly concerned Mexicans officials, who had believed that the two countries’ deep economic ties and improved security cooperation would shield Mexico from unilateral action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, The New York Times reported that the United States was intensifying pressure on Mexico to allow U.S. military forces to conduct joint operations to dismantle fentanyl labs inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Sheinbaum and Mr. Trump spoke briefly on Jan. 12. Even though she said that she again rejected Mr. Trump’s offer of U.S. troops in Mexico, she said they agreed to talk more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But late last week, despite a phone call between Secretary of State Marco Rubio and his Mexican counterpart and a joint statement about upcoming security meetings, the State Department said in a social media post that “the United States made clear that incremental progress in facing border security challenges is unacceptable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, Ms. Sheinbaum defended her country’s efforts, sharing data that she said underscored her administration’s progress in fighting drug trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added that the United States needed to better tackle the drug trade within its own borders, as well as the flow of guns into Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. Trump’s comments about land strikes in Mexico, Mexican officials have wanted to show results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They announced arrests of people they accused of being part of criminal groups that the Trump administration has designated as foreign terrorist organizations. They touted raids of drug labs and drug seizures, including what they said was $20 million worth of fentanyl smuggled into Mexico City’s airport as cosmetics from Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Mexican officials said they arrested, with help from the F.B.I., a fugitive named Alejandro Rosales Castillo, who had been on the U.S. agency’s Top Ten Most Wanted list since 2017 for murder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all, Mexican authorities have handed over 92 “high-impact criminals,” in Mr. Harfuch’s words, since Mr. Trump took office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unclear whether the accused criminals had been convicted of offenses in Mexico or were being held awaiting trial. Mexican officials linked many to cartels, saying they had trafficked drugs and laundered money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the detainees transferred to the United States, according to the Mexican government: Daniel Alfredo Blanco Joo, accused by Mexican authorities of being a logistics operator linked to the Sinaloa Cartel who helped smuggle drugs into the United States; José Luis Sánchez Valencia, whom Mexican officials said was part of the powerful Jalisco New Generation Cartel and related to its leader; and Ricardo González Sauceda, who is accused of being a regional leader of the Cártel del Noreste and was sanctioned by the U.S. in May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s an offering,” said Carlos Pérez Ricart, an expert on organized crime and professor at the Center for Research and Teaching in Economics in Mexico City.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest handover, he said, is “far from a magic solution” to stave off Mr. Trump’s pressure. “But at least the Mexican government is buying itself some time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pérez Ricart said that the legal and political debate surrounding the transfers have subsided since the first one last year, in part, because of Mr. Trump’s military action in Venezuela has made his threats more real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Nicas contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/americas/mexico-cartels-suspects-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:37:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prince Harry Gives Emotional Testimony About Effects of News Coverage</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/prince-harry-emotional-court-daily-mail.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-uk-harry-pktw/21int-uk-harry-pktw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prince Harry became visibly emotional on Wednesday as he testified in London’s High Court about the effects of what he called intrusive news coverage on his life and that of his wife, Meghan Markle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry was giving evidence in his case against Associated Newspapers, the publisher of the British tabloids The Daily Mail and The Mail on Sunday. He and six other high-profile figures, including Elton John, have accused the company of phone hacking, obtaining personal records through deception and other forms of unlawful information gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated Newspapers has denied all the accusations, saying its articles about Harry were the result of legitimate journalistic work and the prince’s “leaky” social circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry said in court that his yearslong legal battle with the company had been a “horrible experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They continue coming after me; they have made my wife’s life an absolute misery,” he said, his voice cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The articles at the center of the case, published between 2001 and 2013, reported intimate details of Harry’s romantic relationships, his social activities and his feelings about his mother’s death. He said reading them had been a “recurring traumatic experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He accused the news media of “commercializing” his life since his childhood and “delving into every single aspect of my private life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry is the first well-known figure in the case to give evidence in the trial, which is scheduled to last more than two months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a written witness statement filed with the court, Harry said that the death of his mother, Princess Diana, while being chased by paparazzi in 1997 meant he had always had an “uneasy relationship” with the press, but that he was “conditioned to accept” constant coverage because of his role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said that the royal family had a policy of “never complain, never explain” over inaccurate and invasive articles which he became “increasingly troubled by” after his relationship with Ms. Markle began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry accused Associated Newspapers journalists, and private investigators acting on their behalf, of hacking his voice mail messages, tapping landline phone calls, “blagging” records — getting them through deception — and obtaining phone bills and private flight information. “Whenever I got on a plane, or in a car, I always expected I was being followed,” he said. “I was under 24-hour surveillance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue for the High Court to decide is whether — on the “balance of probabilities” — the specific articles in question were the product of unlawful information gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In written arguments presented to the court, lawyers representing Associated Newspapers said that the social circles around Harry and the other claimants “were ‘leaky’” and that their friends and associates “did regularly provide information to the press.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company’s lawyer Anthony White repeatedly asked Harry on Wednesday if it was possible that his associates had communicated with journalists at parties and other social occasions. Mr. White said the newspapers had obtained information from legitimate sources and reporting practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry denied that his friends were the source of the articles and accused journalists of “making up quotes to create a narrative and disguise the true source of information.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He challenged the basis of Mr. White’s questions during a series of tense exchanges and was gently reprimanded by Judge Matthew Nicklin for “arguing the case” rather than answering questions in his role as a witness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You tend to argue back to the barrister about what he is putting to you,” Judge Nicklin said. “Your role is simply to answer the questions as best as you can.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judge said the evidence that Harry contested would be examined at a later stage of the trial, during questioning of witnesses including the journalists who wrote the articles and private investigators who worked for Associated Newspapers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry’s claim relates to 14 articles published in The Daily Mail and The Mail on Sunday, which he argues were the product of unlawful information gathering. One, published in July 2006 under the headline “LET HER REST IN PEACE,” contained details of what the prince said were “confidential discussions” with his brother, Prince William, about the publication of a photograph of their dying mother in the Italian media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another article, published earlier that year, revealed details about Harry’s relationship with his girlfriend then, Chelsy Davy, and her feelings about his joining the British Army. The prince argued that those details, including that he had called Ms. Davy “from a shop when choosing a costume outfit” could have come only from phone tapping. In his written statement, Harry said the article put “massive strain” on their relationship and created “paranoia and distrust.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case is one of several legal battles that Harry has pursued since 2020, when he and his wife stepped down from their royal roles and left Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owners of The Daily Mirror, another tabloid, settled a claim over phone hacking in February 2024. Last January Rupert Murdoch’s News Group Newspapers agreed to pay “substantial” damages to Harry and admitted for the first time to unlawful activities by private investigators working for The Sun.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/prince-harry-emotional-court-daily-mail.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:44:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada Flexes on Global Stage With an Eye to Its Own Survival</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/canada/carney-speech-davos-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20img-carney-davos-ztlf/20img-carney-davos-ztlf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada delivered a stark speech in Davos, Switzerland, on Tuesday, prompting global political and corporate leaders in the audience to rise from their seats for a rare standing ovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He described the end of the era underpinned by United States hegemony, calling the current phase “a rupture.” He never mentioned President Trump by name, but his reference was clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speech came as President Trump doubled down on his threats to take Greenland away from Denmark, saying he would slap fresh tariffs on European powers as punishment for their support of Greenland’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global leaders have been scrambling to find a unified response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we’re reminded that we live in an era of great-power rivalry,” Mr. Carney said. “That the rules-based order is fading. That the strong can do what they can, and the weak must suffer what they must.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And he warned, “The middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He would know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump started his second presidential term making claims on Canada as the 51st state and threatening Canada’s previous leader, Justin Trudeau, whom Mr. Trump publicly derided, with unilaterally scrapping agreements that have governed the relationship between the neighboring countries for over a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has imposed tariffs on Canada, which is one of America’s two top trading partners along with Mexico, that are crippling some of Canada’s key economic sectors, such as autos, steel, aluminum and lumber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s allies, particularly Steve Bannon, have talked about the benefits of the United States’ annexing Canada to access its vast Arctic and natural resources, including critical minerals and rare earths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Canadian leader warned that middle powers need to stand together or they’ll find themselves “on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney chastised other leaders too, many of whom would have been following his speech in Davos, for not standing up for their interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a strong tendency for countries to go along to get along,” he said. “To accommodate. To avoid trouble. To hope that compliance will buy safety. It won’t.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney made clear he is choosing a different path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He wrote his own speech, according to a government official, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss the inner workings of his team, which is a departure since speeches of this magnitude are usually prepared by high-level staff members with the leader’s input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney, a former investment executive who has served as the governor of Canada and England’s central banks, has attended the global gathering about 30 times, according to his office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney spoke not long after Mr. Trump had posted an altered image on social media that featured a map of American flags superimposed over both Canada and the United States, as well as Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It highlighted the Canadian prime minister’s motives for flexing his rhetorical muscle on the Davos stage: Canada’s economic and, perhaps literal, survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada’s integration with the United States runs deep across its economy, defense and culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The position of the country in the ongoing Greenland crisis is a little distinct to that of the European powers finding themselves in Mr. Trump's cross hairs, even if they are all NATO allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked how far he was willing to go to acquire Greenland, Mr. Trump said, on Tuesday before departing the United States for Davos: “You’ll find out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney has repeatedly said Canada stands squarely behind Greenland and Denmark, but unlike European powers, did not send troops to participate in the most recent military exercise. President Trump is threatening those nations with fresh tariffs, but not Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, President Emmanuel Macron of France echoed Mr. Carney, saying that “we do prefer respect to bullies. And we do prefer rule of law to brutality.” He denounced Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threats as an unacceptable “endless accumulation of new tariffs” used as “leverage against territorial sovereignty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada exports some 75 percent of its goods and services to the United States; its second largest partner, China, gets less than 5 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two countries share the world’s longest land border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American troops exercise and cooperate with Canadians daily, including in the Arctic, and the two militaries work closely together at every level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two nations have a joint command for North American air defense. This week aircraft from both countries are at an American air base in Greenland as part of a regular training exercise that the joint air command said had been approved by Denmark. This is a situation that would rapidly grow very difficult for Canada should the United States choose to militarily involve itself in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney had been trying to strike an agreement with Mr. Trump over trade, and the two men appear to enjoy a friendly rapport. Even so, talks are frozen (the two were scheduled to be in Davos on Wednesday but had no meeting set).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A regular review of a free-trade agreement between the Canada, the United States and Mexico, known as the U.S.M.C.A., is due this year and its fate is very much up in the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has said the United States does not need anything that Canada exports, even as, for example, the majority of the oil the United States imports comes from Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, at a moment when the United States is led by a capricious, unpredictable and at times menacing president, Canada is trying to break its longtime dependence on America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney’s speech came at the end of a week on the road with official visits to China and Qatar. Mr. Carney struck a deal with China to allow a small number of electric vehicles into Canada at a reduced tariff, breaking with U.S. policy that it has followed since the Biden administration, in exchange for China lowering some tariffs on Canadian agricultural goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More important, perhaps, China and Canada declared themselves to be in a “strategic partnership” that signals a new era of cooperation with America’s rival for superpower dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tally of his international travel since first becoming prime minister last March highlights Mr. Carney’s relentless hustle. He has spent nearly 60 days traveling internationally, trying to secure new trade deals. By comparison, Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain and Mr. Macron have each spent about 40 days on international travel during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pace and intensity of Mr. Carney’s global outreach, together with his promise to help Canada survive this epochal shift in American power, has created great expectations among Canadians who elected him last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even senior advisers, speaking anonymously to talk freely about the risks of this strategy, say there is a chance of under delivering, and acknowledge that no one partner or deal can quickly supplant the overwhelming role the United States plays in Canada’s economy and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At home, the opposition Conservative Party has accused him of focusing too much on overseas travel that doesn’t immediately yield results and neglecting domestic issues such as the cost of living and housing. Mr. Carney is one seat short of a parliamentary majority, a deficit that could hinder his ability to govern, even as he wins accolades for his overseas performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There are a lot of voters who wanted to see this from Mark Carney, and expected it from him,” said Ginny Roth, a former conservative adviser and partner at Crestview Strategy, a Canadian public affairs firm. “But there’s also a huge percentage of the electorate, up to 40 percent, that lives in a different world, that doesn’t have the luxury to worry about what Mark Carney said at Davos.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/canada/carney-speech-davos-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 07:49:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Man Gets Life in Prison for Killing Shinzo Abe, Former Leader of Japan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/japan-shinzo-abe-killer-verdict.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-japan-abe-pbhv/21int-japan-abe-pbhv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man was sentenced to life in prison on Wednesday for assassinating Shinzo Abe, Japan’s longest-serving prime minister, bringing an end to a case that shocked the nation and provoked debate about political violence and broader societal issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tetsuya Yamagami, 45, was found guilty of killing Mr. Abe by a district court in the western city of Nara. He admitted in October to shooting Mr. Abe with a homemade gun at an election rally in Nara in 2022, but his lawyers had sought a shorter sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case of Mr. Yamagami, who was unemployed and had briefly served in Japan’s military, known as the Self-Defense Forces, divided Japanese society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people expressed sympathy for him because of his difficult childhood; his family faced economic hardships, and his father and brother both died by suicide. Others said he should receive a harsh penalty for killing Mr. Abe, a towering figure in Japanese politics who stepped down in 2020. Mr. Abe, 67, was stumping for a junior politician near a train station in Nara when he was shot in the neck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the trial, which lasted about two months, Mr. Yamagami said he shot Mr. Abe because he perceived him as supporting the powerful Unification Church, a South Korea-based group with substantial operations in Japan. Mr. Yamagami said the church had bankrupted his family by forcing his mother, a member, to turn over her life savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I felt that striking back at the Unification Church — or, rather, dealing them a significant hit — was the very meaning of my life,” he said during the trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial drew intense interest in Japan, where political violence and shootings are rare. The last time such a high-profile assassination occurred was in 1936, when two former prime ministers were killed during a coup by the Imperial Japanese Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nara, nearly 700 people lined up outside the courthouse on Wednesday, hoping to be among the 33 members of the public allowed inside the courtroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiuko Notoya contributed reporting from Tokyo.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/20/world/asia/japan-shinzo-abe-killer-verdict.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:22:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Starts Moving ISIS Detainees From Syria to Iraq</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/isis-syria-prisons-iraq.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-iraq-syria-photo-jmlv/21int-iraq-syria-photo-jmlv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military began transferring Islamic State prisoners from northeastern Syria to Iraq on Wednesday, amid growing concern that thousands of former fighters and their family members could escape from detention as the Syrian government and Kurdish-led forces vie for control of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Central Command, which oversees U.S. military operations in the Middle East, said in a statement that American forces had already transported 150 fighters for the Islamic State, also known as ISIS, from a detention facility in northeastern Syria to an unspecified “secure location in Iraq.” The military said as many as 7,000 detainees could ultimately be moved from Syrian custody to Iraqi-run facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are closely coordinating with regional partners, including the Iraqi government, and we sincerely appreciate their role in ensuring the enduring defeat of ISIS,” said Adm. Brad Cooper, the head of U.S. military forces in the Middle East. “Facilitating the orderly and secure transfer of ISIS detainees is critical to preventing a breakout that would pose a direct threat to the United States and regional security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transfer effort reflected growing concern about the security of detention sites in northeastern Syria, which for years have been guarded by the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F. The group has come under assault over the past week during a lightning offensive by Syrian government troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But over the past two days, fresh bouts of violence have erupted around prisons holding Islamic State detainees as Kurdish forces withdrew and Syrian government forces moved in. As many as 200 detainees escaped from one of those prisons, al-Shaddadi, according to a U.S. military official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. The turmoil stoked fears among U.S. and regional officials of a wider prison break in northeastern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a fragile cease-fire, the S.D.F. has agreed to relinquish control of prisons and other critical infrastructure as part of a long-awaited deal to integrate Kurdish-held regions into the Syrian state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Washington’s public support for Syria’s new president, Ahmed al-Sharaa, the move appeared to underscore lingering doubts in Washington over the government’s ability to ensure security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the transfers were being carried out urgently, over days rather than weeks, amid concerns about whether Syrian government forces could safely manage the detainees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, the S.D.F. was Washington’s chief ally in Syria, backed by U.S. air power, funding and intelligence as the Kurdish-led militia steered the ground fight against the Islamic State. But on Tuesday, the U.S. special envoy to Syria, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., indicated that Washington no longer needed the group in that role, marking a major shift in American policy.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/isis-syria-prisons-iraq.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:11:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israeli Strikes in Gaza Kill 11, Including Three Journalists</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/israel-gaza-strikes-journalists.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22int-gaza-journalists-photo-fmcv/22int-gaza-journalists-photo-fmcv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli forces killed at least 11 people in the Gaza Strip on Wednesday, Gaza health officials said, including three Palestinian journalists who the Israeli military said were flying a drone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Journalists Syndicate, a labor union, said the three men were documenting the “suffering of civilians in displacement camps.” The Israeli military said they were operating a drone that was “affiliated with Hamas” and that its forces believed it posed a threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said the details of the incident were under examination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three journalists were identified as Abdel Raouf Shaath, Mohammad Salah Qishta and Anas Ghneim by the journalists’ union. One of those journalists, Mr. Shaath, had been a regular freelancer for the French newswire Agence France-Presse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Egyptian Relief Committee, a state-backed group providing aid in the Gaza Strip, said in a statement that Mr. Qishta had been documenting the organization’s relief efforts. The journalists’ union said they had been driving a car in the central town of Al-Zahra when the three journalists were targeted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Egyptian Commitee began housing residents in a shelter there as part of a plan to support displaced people in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gazan airspace is under the complete control of the Israeli military, which closely tracks even commercial drones that lift off in the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesday’s killings were the latest in what has been an extremely deadly conflict for Palestinian journalists in Gaza. Israel has barred foreign journalists throughout the war and continues to do so three months into its cease-fire with Hamas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of early January, the Committee to Project Journalists reported that Israeli forces had killed at least 206 journalists and media workers in Gaza since the start of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International law says journalists, like all civilians during war, cannot be considered military targets if they are conducting independent reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At times during the conflict, the Israeli military has deliberately attacked and killed Palestinian reporters it accused of belonging to Hamas’s armed wing, the al-Qassam Brigades. Several were employees of Al Jazeera, the Qatari-owned broadcaster, which called the allegations baseless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called an Israeli strike that killed five journalists at a Gaza hospital a “tragic mishap.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ameera Harouda contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/israel-gaza-strikes-journalists.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:39:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Maduro’s Last Dance, a New Rhythm Goes Viral in Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/maduro-venezuela-dancing-tiktok.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/world/00int-venezuela-viralsong-top/00int-venezuela-viralsong-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peering from under a cap emblazoned with Venezuela’s flag, Miguel Alejandro Herrera smiled at the camera, and then started swaying his hips to a catchy Latin rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Where is China? Where is Russia? Why didn’t they act? What’s the excuse?” Mr. Herrera lip-synced in Spanish, bouncing his shoulders to the beat. “Maduro is in a federal prison, and now I ask myself: Where are the communists who were going to help him?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, which he said he made with artificial intelligence, is a celebration of Nicolás Maduro’s ouster as Venezuela’s leader and a jab at some of his closest alliances, said Mr. Herrera, a music producer and social media commentator known online as Kilómetro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was posted on Jan. 8, the video has drawn more than 11 million views on TikTok and 5 million on Instagram. And it has racked up thousands of comments, most of them cheering Mr. Herrera and Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I knew the theme was going to catch on,” Mr. Herrera, 28, said in an interview from Argentina, where he has been living in exile since 2024. “But I didn’t know it was going to be this big.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera’s song plays on a trope familiar to most Venezuelans: the jingles long deployed by Mr. Maduro and his political movement. In the lead-up to his capture, Mr. Maduro had taken to breaking into musical routines, including dancing to techno beats remixed with the slogan “No War, Yes Peace.” (His dancing may have ultimately contributed to his downfall.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video, and the enormous response it has set off, stand in sharp contrast with the narrative offered by Venezuela’s government, which has leaned on the state-controlled broadcaster to show what appear to be large crowds of protesters, insisting that Venezuelans are overwhelmingly upset about Mr. Maduro’s ouster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few in Venezuela have dared to disagree, as a new wave of repression has taken hold. Since the U.S. operation that led to Mr. Maduro’s capture, Venezuelan security forces have boarded buses, searched phones and questioned people, seeking evidence of support for his removal. Fearing reprisal, many Venezuelans are sidestepping the subject at workplaces, coffee shops and other public settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet online, at home and abroad, Mr. Herrera’s catchy tune appears to be resonating. “I say what people inside Venezuela cannot say,” Mr. Herrera said. “Many people write to me saying they have the song saved for when they can play it loud on the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His video plays on the familiar use of sentimental, upbeat or triumphant melodies by Chavismo, the socialist-inspired movement first embodied by Hugo Chávez and, later, by his successor, Mr. Maduro. Those tunes were once so catchy, Mr. Herrera said, that they would even move Venezuelans who opposed Mr. Maduro. “Now that has changed,” he said. “Now, the opposition’s music is better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Mr. Herrera sought to create a summer hit, not unlike the ones that typically hit airwaves around this time of year in the Southern Hemisphere. “The rhythm is, like, tropical,” he added. “It’s perfect for listening in the car, for going to the beach, for celebrating.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera’s post has also set off a wave of memes, including an A.I.-generated video of President Trump spinning the tune on a D.J. turntable as Mr. Maduro, in a prison cell and clad in an orange jumpsuit, swings his hips to the rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of Mr. Herrera’s video has been fueled in part by Venezuela’s vast and vocal diaspora. Fleeing repression and economic woes, about eight million people have left the country since 2015, many settling in Spain, the United States or countries in South America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Herrera began making videos ahead of the presidential election in 2024. Many of them explained electoral rules, urged Venezuelans to register to vote and supported the candidate challenging Mr. Maduro. Mr. Herrera eventually amassed several million followers, and his posts garnered hundreds of thousands of views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when Mr. Maduro claimed victory despite evidence that the opposition had won by a large margin, Mr. Herrera decided to leave Venezuela. “We packed our bags that night,” Mr. Herrera said. “I left for my safety.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many Venezuelans abroad, Mr. Herrera isn’t quite ready to go back yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with Mr. Maduro out of the picture, Venezuela is still being run by his inner circle of loyalists. The United States has endorsed the nation’s interim leader, Delcy Rodríguez, warning that more strikes could come if she failed to follow America’s interests when it came to oil, but making almost no mention of human rights or democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one post, Mr. Herrera depicts Ms. Rodríguez as a string puppet manipulated by Mr. Trump. Mr. Herrera said he believed that, with the United States exerting so much control, Venezuela was on course for substantive change. “The United States is there, and she has to do what Trump wants.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, Mr. Herrera said he would keep making videos. “It’s a fight for the freedom of my country,” he said. “More than a job, it’s a hope of returning to a free country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria Ramírez contributed research.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/maduro-venezuela-dancing-tiktok.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 05:57:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>She Listened to Women’s Pain. Then She Transformed How It Was Treated.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/france-doctor-house-of-women.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/10/multimedia/00int-france-doctor-profile-01-kftp/00int-france-doctor-profile-01-kftp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a veteran doctor treating pregnant women in the suburbs of Paris, Ghada Hatem-Gantzer realized that most of her patients needed more than she could offer them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hatem-Gantzer, an obstetrician gynecologist, often oversaw care for women who had suffered sexual abuse, self-harm or alcoholism. She would urge them to see a psychologist, seek legal advice and file a police complaint. If the patient seemed tense, she might also recommend a physiotherapist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer found, was that all these services were dispersed across an archipelago of state institutions, instead of being centralized in one building. As a result, the women struggled to find the help they needed, meaning that their complex traumas often went unaddressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was so complicated,” Dr. Hatem-Gantzer, 66, said in a recent interview. “Whereas if I tell you, ‘Well, next door is the therapist, the cop is there, then you can go to the support group, you can go to yoga on Mondays and do theater on Tuesdays’ — now that’s something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hatem-Gantzer built that “something else” almost 10 years ago in St.-Denis, one of Paris’s poorest suburbs, on a patch of muddy ground next to a hospital where she led the maternity ward. Here, she established a one-stop shop, known as House of Women, where female victims of violence have access to a wide range of social, legal and medical assistance, all in the same building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a labor of love that almost failed. Sponsors were hard to convince. Even after she had secured the land, it took years to start building. At one point, she almost gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, almost a decade after it opened, her project has become the template for how hospitals across France treat female victims of violence. About 30,000 women have been treated in its halls since 2016. Thirty similar centers have opened in France and neighboring Belgium, and four others will be inaugurated in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototype invented by Dr. Hatem-Gantzer is such a success that two recent French prime ministers have each separately said that all of France’s 100 or so regional authorities need one. A movie about the creation of the first facility in St.-Denis will be released in March.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer set off an “earthquake” and established herself as a “role model” for the rest of the medical profession, said Anne Ferrer-Villeneuve, a hospital director who was inspired by Dr. Hatem-Gantzer to set up a similar facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hatem-Gantzer created “a real response to a need that we saw, but whose scale we had not appreciated,” said Dr. Ferrer, the director of the University Hospital of Montpellier, a major medical center in southern France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hatem-Gantzer was born in 1959 in Beirut, Lebanon, to a father who was a telecommunications engineer and a homemaker mother. She was 15 when the Lebanese civil war erupted. As fighting raged in the streets outside, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer recalled, she sheltered on her building’s staircase, seeking refuge in books by Jean-Paul Sartre, Albert Camus, Simone de Beauvoir — “anything I could get my hands on,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she finished high school, she left for Paris, where she studied medicine and quickly fell in love with obstetrics, a job she found “both exciting and terrifying.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She went on to work at various maternity wards in Paris, helping hundreds of women give birth — including, as I recently found out, my own mother. Though most of her patients came from well-to-do backgrounds, she realized that many of them had suffered from domestic violence, prompting her to wonder if she could do more for her patients than offer them only medical treatment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her frustration at the limitations of her profession swelled in 2011 after she was appointed as head of the maternity ward in the largest hospital in St.-Denis, a hardscrabble area home to many immigrants. Her patients often lived in poverty, suffered from domestic abuse or were victims of female genital mutilation. Many, having recently arrived in France, barely spoke its language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was an explosive cocktail,” Dr. Hatem-Gantzer said. “To the fact of being a woman was added all the difficulties of St.-Denis that came with poverty and migration.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving in to family pressure, one patient had left a stable job in her home country to live in a small, unsanitary apartment in Paris with an alcoholic husband who beat her. Another patient, about 15 when Dr. Hatem-Gantzer met her, had fled her home in West Africa after suffering genital mutilation and forced marriage. Migrating through northern Africa toward France, she was raped several times and robbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listening to these women, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer said, was “a source of anger.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2012, she started thinking of ways to offer them better care, and the idea of a single facility dedicated to treating violence started taking shape. The director of the hospital said Dr. Hatem-Gantzer could build the center on a vacant parking lot near the hospital — but only if she found the money herself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it became obvious that she wouldn’t receive significant public funds, she started seeking private ones. Eventually, she convinced three donors, including the Kering Foundation, a philanthropic group run by the owners of Gucci. But it wasn’t enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In the United States, you can come in and say, ‘I have a project, I’m raising funds,’ and people will say, ‘OK, I’ll bet on it, we’ll see how it goes.’ In France, it’s not like that at all,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2015, still short of funds, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer thought she had reached the end of the road. She called her three sponsors and said she would return the money. “They told me, ‘Don’t even dream about it,’” she said. With their help, she found other private sponsors, and the project was back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like, you have to cross the Atlantic, and when you’re in the middle, you don’t ask yourself whether you want to continue or not. At one point, I just had to keep rowing,” Dr. Hatem-Gantzer said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house finally opened in July 2016, some 20 rooms spread across two floors. Designed by a friend of Dr. Hatem-Gantzer, it has a small garden and bright multicolored walls, with windows letting the light in from all sides. At its heart is a small patio with colorful furniture — a nod to the architecture of homes in the Middle East. It’s Dr. Hatem-Gantzer’s favorite spot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The facility offers each patient a personalized treatment, with access to psychologists, psychiatrists, social workers, legal counsels and planned parenthood representatives, as well as general practitioners and gynecologists. It also organizes abortions and repairs genital cutting. A police officer is stationed inside one day a week, so women can file complaints on site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year after its opening, the #MeToo movement erupted in the United States, and it later trickled through French institutions, giving greater momentum to projects like House of Women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The world changed. When I talked about this in 2013, people didn’t understand what I was talking about,” Dr. Hatem-Gantzer said. But MeToo was “like a kind of explosion, everywhere,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually, other hospitals and institutions began to follow suit, first in Brussels, in 2017, and then in Bordeaux, France, in 2019. That interest accelerated in 2021, when Dr. Hatem-Gantzer was given 10 million euros — about $11 million — by two private foundations to expand the project across France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also expanded the original house in St.-Denis, where patients can now practice gardening and yoga, learn French, attend jewelry and photography workshops, and join trips to museums and theaters. Some of their art pieces hang on the house’s walls, in between pictures of feminist icons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a French class last month, one of the patients burst into tears after her teachers and classmates surprised her with a birthday cake. “You have given me all the love I never had,” she told them before blowing out her candles. It was the first time, she told the gathering, that someone had ever thought of celebrating her birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hatem-Gantzer is no longer involved in day-to-day operations at the house. Most of her time is now devoted to awareness programs in schools and companies, and fund-raising, though she still performs operations to repair genital mutilation and offers advice to the center’s leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s a night light, a compass,” said Marianne Sonda, a manager at the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her next major project is a new center for patients aged 3 to 25 suffering from sexual violence, which will soon open in Paris amid a reported increase in sexual assaults against children in schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite her success, Dr. Hatem-Gantzer considers her job far from over. Speaking at a lecture to raise awareness about sexual violence in universities last month, she couldn’t help but notice the absence of men in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s my greatest despair,” she said, “and I think my career will end without this figure really improving every time we speak about sexual violence.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/europe/france-doctor-house-of-women.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:12:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan’s $40 Billion Military Spending Plan Stalled by Political Impasse</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/taiwan-trump-military-gridlock-china.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/10/multimedia/00int-taiwan-politics-qvcp/00int-taiwan-politics-qvcp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A political quagmire in Taiwan has stalled plans by its President Lai Ching-te to sharply increase military spending, even as President Donald Trump has pressed the island to pay more for its own defense against China’s campaign to bring the island under its control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opposition lawmakers who dominate the legislature have blocked Mr. Lai’s ambitious proposal to spend $40 billion across eight years on military equipment from moving forward without concessions from Mr. Lai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Taiwan, the impasse has implications beyond just a domestic political fight. It could raise questions about Taiwan’s ability to strengthen its defenses at a time when Mr. Trump is urging America’s allies and partners to shoulder more of the burden for their own security. Mr. Lai has pledged to lift military and security outlays to more than 3 percent of Taiwan’s economy this year to mollify the United States, the island’s chief security backer against Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Lai’s plan is caught in a tangle of budgetary and legal disputes between his party and the opposition parties. Both sides have used hardball tactics and accused each other of acting unlawfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking with longstanding practice, Mr. Lai’s premier refused to sign off on a law passed by the opposition-controlled legislature that would shift some tax revenues from the central government to local administrations. Opposition lawmakers, in turn, denounced the premier’s move to stymie the revenue law as unconstitutional. They have also called Mr. Lai a dictator and moved to impeach him, an effort that is largely symbolic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We have never experienced such a massive crisis of constitutional rule of law as we have right now,” Weng Hsiao-ling, a lawmaker from the Nationalist Party, the main opposition party, said in an interview. “Executive power is not operating according to the law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Members of Mr. Lai’s Democratic Progressive Party, for their part, say that the opposition is trying to paralyze his administration. They accuse some opposition politicians of taking their cues from Beijing and of endangering Taiwan’s security by holding up defense spending. They are frustrated that the opposition has twice rejected Mr. Lai’s nominations to Taiwan’s constitutional court, effectively sidelining the body that could help defuse such disputes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Su Chiao-hui, a lawmaker from the Democratic Progressive Party, said that the opposition’s blocking of nominees damaged Taiwan’s ability to resolve conflicts. “They changed the rules, and the referee is gone,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The friction reflects growing divisions in Taiwan over whether to hold tight to its relationship with the United States or try rapprochement with Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lai’s party says that Taiwan is its own country, and stronger defense and deeper ties with the United States are the way to protect Taiwan against China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nationalist Party, however, favors expanded ties with Beijing. Some of its leaders, including its chairwoman, Cheng Li-wun, have suggested that Mr. Lai’s strategy will escalate tensions with China. They have said that they generally support military spending to protect Taiwan, but have emphasized their skepticism about Mr. Lai’s plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s an increasingly clear partisan divide of perception in Taiwan in terms of views of the U.S., views of China,” said Wei-ting Yen, a political scientist at Academia Sinica, a Taiwanese research academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions between the two sides grew last year after Mr. Lai’s party backed a recall campaign to oust dozens of Nationalist Party legislators, which ultimately failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nationalist lawmakers are not in a “terribly good mood to make further compromises with Lai,” said Alexander C. Huang, an international security expert who was formerly that party’s director of international affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opposition lawmakers have blocked deliberations on Mr. Lai’s military spending plan, as well as the annual budget, demanding, among other things, that Mr. Lai first appear before the legislature for questioning. The opposition has also pointed to what it says are unacceptably long delays in deliveries of U.S. weapons, including F-16 fighter jets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve paid up, but the weapons are nowhere to be seen,” Fu Kun-chi, a Nationalist Party leader, said last month. “We support national defense, but don’t support being fleeced in arms purchases.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compromise may still be possible. The Nationalists have pushed for more public disclosure of details; the government has said that revealing some details would compromise security, but gave lawmakers a private briefing this week and released more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. representative in Taipei, Raymond Greene, has backed Mr. Lai’s military spending proposals and urged the parties to work together, while the State Department pledged to work with industry to deliver equipment more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some officials from Taiwan’s governing party hope that lawmakers from a smaller opposition party, the Taiwan People’s Party, will break with the Nationalists, giving Mr. Lai the votes to pass his plans. He appears buoyed after Taiwan and Washington signed a framework agreement to reduce Mr. Trump’s tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington may increase pressure on the opposition, aware that a public breach with the United States would be politically fraught for any party in Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The opposition Nationalists naturally hope to keep a balance between China and the U.S.,” said Su Tzu-chiao, a political scientist at Soochow University in Taipei, “but they cannot directly oppose the U.S.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/asia/taiwan-trump-military-gridlock-china.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 08:03:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.S. Pivot in Syria Leaves an Old Ally in the Lurch</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/us-pivot-in-syria-leaves-an-old-ally-in-the-lurch.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/multimedia/21int-Syria-Kurds-01-bpgv/21int-Syria-Kurds-01-bpgv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than a decade, they were the United States’ closest allies in Syria, fighting against the Islamic State, guarding American bases and running internment camps and prisons that held tens of thousands of jihadists and their relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That alliance is now disintegrating. The United States has turned away from its longtime allies, the Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., and thrown its support behind the new government of President Ahmed al-Sharaa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without U.S. backing, the S.D.F., a Kurdish-led force, has wobbled and beaten a retreat as the government moves troops into northeastern Syria to seize control, ending a standoff that has endured since President al-Sharaa took power in December 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collapse of the S.D.F. marks a turning point in Syria’s political transition after the fall of former President Bashar al-Assad and now paves the way for the government to take over the strategic region, its oil fields and rich agricultural lands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pivot by Washington is a huge win for Mr. al-Sharaa, who has struggled to pull the country back together, as well as for Turkey, which vehemently opposed American support for the S.D.F. and backed Mr. al-Sharaa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the S.D.F. and its supporters, including U.S. officials who worked closely with the group, it feels like a betrayal of those who fought loyally alongside the United States and lost many thousands of combatants in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bleakness of the S.D.F. position was laid out by Ilham Ahmed, a senior leader of the Kurdish-led civilian administration in northeastern Syria, when she appealed at a news conference last week for the United States to stop playing both sides and to take a clear position to stop an offensive against its positions by Syrian government forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If there is no reaction it is easy to presume they gave a green light,” she said of the American position on the government offensive. “They should take a clear stance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ahmed also appealed for wider international support to enforce a cease-fire and support the political demands of the Kurdish administration. But she said that Arab states supported the al-Sharaa government and that reactions from European countries had been weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The entire world owes these troops who fought against ISIS,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. was born following the terrifying rise of the Islamic State, which took over a swath of territory straddling the Syria-Iraq border in 2013 and built a so-called caliphate on a harsh interpretation of Islamic law and sheer brutality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeking a way to fight the group without putting American troops on the front lines, the United States partnered with a Kurdish militia. It air dropped weapons to help break the siege of the Kurdish town of Kobani in 2014, and the partnership expanded from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the U.S., it made sense. The fighters were well trained, not Islamist, and eager to work with American troops. In time, with U.S. financial and military support, they grew, added Arab fighters and rebranded themselves as the Syrian Democratic Forces (although there was very little about them that was actually democratic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With logistical and air support from the United States and others, the S.D.F. destroyed the ISIS caliphate, pushing the group from its last patch of territory in Syria in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It continued to work with the United States to prevent the resurgence of ISIS and provide security across northeastern Syria with a force of tens of thousands of men and women under arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That alliance angered Turkey, who saw the group as no more than an extension of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party, a Kurdish militant group that has fought a bloody, 30-year insurgency against the Turkish state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also angered Syrian rebel groups and activists for imposing Kurdish rule over Arab-majority areas and doing its own deals with the Assad regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rebel offensive that toppled the Assad regime in December 2024, changed the paradigm for the Kurds. The United States established close ties with Mr. al-Sharaa and sought to bring the two groups to work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. ambassador to Turkey and envoy for Syria, Thomas J. Barrack Jr., led the negotiations and secured an agreement between Mr. al-Sharaa and the Kurdish leader of the S.D.F., Mazloum Abdi, in March last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those negotiations stalled and missed the deadline for S.D.F. to integrate its armed units and administration into the Damascus government by the end of 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa complained that the Kurdish side kept augmenting its demands while making no move to withdraw from Arab-majority areas. The Kurdish leaders said they were holding out for security guarantees for their people in light of sectarian killings elsewhere in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end Mr. al-Sharaa lost patience and moved to seize control of two Kurdish-held neighborhoods in the city of Aleppo. From there Syrian forces moved rapidly, securing two large provincial capitals of Raqqa and Deir al-Zour in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newaf Xelil, an analyst at the Berlin-based Kurdish Center for Studies, said the swift advance of Mr. al-Sharaa’s forces in recent weeks had been enabled by the full embrace of his government by Turkey, Saudi Arabia and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has baffled many in the S.D.F., he said, who still distrust Mr. al-Sharaa and many of his fighters for their past links to Islamic militancy and jihadism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa was sent to Syria from Iraq more than a decade ago by the leader of the Islamic State, where he founded a Qaeda-affiliated rebel group. He later broke with Al Qaeda but has never fully renounced the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurds, given their more secular outlook, could help dilute the Islamist character of Syria’s new government, Mr. Xelil said, a goal many thought that the United States shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We thought that they wanted Syria to become a normal government with an army not made up of jihadists,” he said, adding that it could have helped Syria reconcile with Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fighting in recent days could complicate the merger of S.D.F. fighters into the new security forces, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He criticized Mr. Barrack, the U.S. envoy, for his full-throated support for Damascus. Mr. Barrack wrote on social media on Tuesday that the S.D.F.’s role had “expired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurds had hugely miscalculated, Asli Aydintasbas, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution in Washington, wrote in a WhatsApp message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“While the U.S. has never promised a Catholic marriage to the S.D.F., there was a sense that the relationship would continue and seamlessly merge into a more decentralized Syrian structure. All of that planning is now meaningless.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump showed his ambivalence to the Kurdish position in comments to the media on Tuesday, while he commended Mr. al-Sharaa’s efforts to control the situation and secure prisons where thousands of ISIS members are detained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He is working very hard, the president of Syria,” Mr. Trump said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I spoke with him yesterday because we were talking about the prisons, and what was going on. We have some of the worst terrorists in the world in those prisons, and he is watching it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the U.S. Central Command announced Wednesday that it had transported 150 ISIS fighters detained in the city of Hasakah to a facility in Iraq, to prevent a breakout, a sign of growing security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said the U.S. was also working to protect the Kurds. “I like the Kurds,” he said. “But just so you understand, the Kurds were paid tremendous amounts of money, given oil and other things, so they were doing it for themselves more than they were doing this for us. But we got along with the Kurds and we are trying to protect the Kurds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hussam Hammoud contributed reporting from Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/middleeast/us-pivot-in-syria-leaves-an-old-ally-in-the-lurch.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 09:35:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Latin America, Loathing of Maduro Smothers Outcry Over U.S. Raid</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/latin-america-venezuela-us-raid-maduro-polls.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/00int-latam-response01a-photo-kgqm/00int-latam-response01a-photo-kgqm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Argentina, dormant high school group chats roared to life with news of Nicolás Maduro’s capture. Colombians debated exit plans if they were next on Washington’s list, Ecuadorean schoolteachers paused lessons to discuss the U.S. raid, and a Peruvian beauty queen even weighed in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet this regional frenzy did not translate into a significant wave of organized protests across a continent that has long harbored resentment over the United States’ Cold War-era meddling in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some Latin Americans denounced what they decried as American imperialism in Venezuela, a more supportive response to President Trump’s action prevailed, with several polls showing that a majority of Latin Americans endorsed the intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am happy because I saw the fall of a dictator and I am happy because my Venezuelan friends are happy,” said Carlos Segura, 36, a professor in Buenos Aires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seventy-four percent of Peruvians, sixty-three percent of Chileans, a majority of Colombians, Brazilians, Argentines, and even Panamanians, whose country was itself invaded by the United States to remove an authoritarian leader nearly three decades ago, approved of the capture, according to several polls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mexico, the response was more evenly split, reflecting a significant leftist base and widespread opposition to Mr. Trump’s policies. The country’s leftist leader, Claudia Sheinbaum, issued a carefully worded rejection of the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, disagreements among regional leaders over the U.S. removal of Mr. Maduro were tempered by a desire to avoid direct friction with Mr. Trump. And at the ground level, divisions among Latin Americans were softened by the left’s struggle to mobilize against the capture of a reviled authoritarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever unhappiness exists toward Mr. Trump and his desire to project dominance over Latin America, a shift toward pragmatism is eclipsing old ideological loyalties, at least for now, experts said. That could certainly change if Mr. Trump follows through on threats to launch land strikes, perhaps in Mexico or in South America, targeting what he says are drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the case of Venezuela, many Latin Americans opposed Mr. Maduro’s rule and felt the impact of its fallout — including millions of Venezuelans who migrated throughout the region fleeing poverty and repression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“International law, imperialism, this is the discourse of the elite,” said Marta Lagos, the founder of Latinobarómetro, an annual public opinion survey across Latin America. Popular support for the U.S. intervention, “has nothing to do with ideology,” she said. “They choose whatever is possible to fix things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of Venezuela’s political future is in flux, with the interim government run by those who ruled alongside Mr. Maduro, and their repressive behavior has continued targeting people engaged in public displays of celebration over the U.S. intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But outside the country, a resounding wave of euphoria rang out, louder than the traditional “Yankees go home” cries, as many Latin Americans joined the Venezuelan diaspora in welcoming Mr. Maduro’s toppling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was the only way Venezuelans could get rid of this guy,” said Lorena Plaza, 37, a schoolteacher in Quito, Ecuador. “Maybe it wasn’t the right way, but there really wasn’t another way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Argentina, where the Venezuelan crisis has been a fixture of domestic political friction for more than a decade as a cautionary lesson of socialist misrule, car horns erupted at dawn on Jan. 3 after news of Mr. Maduro’s capture spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An A.I. generated song by a Venezuelan living in Argentina that mocks how China and Russia failed to defend their Venezuelan ally — “where are the communists?” — became a major sensation, gathering more than 11 million views on TikTok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Panamanians and Venezuelans celebrating from now on every Jan. 3,” read a post from El Gallinazo, a popular Panamanian Instagram account that featured a video of two men dancing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some regional reactions to Mr. Maduro’s extraction still fell along familiar left-right divides. Many supporters of Brazil’s president, Luiz Inácio Lula da Silva, a leftist, and Mexico’s Ms. Sheinbaum, opposed the U.S. attack. In Chile, President Gabriel Boric — who has tried to stake out a new brand of leftist politics by distancing himself from the region’s socialist dictatorships — nonetheless issued a sharply worded condemnation of the American action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Mr. Roman said, “you don’t really see the left rallying behind this as a major crying call.” Mr. Maduro’s rule proved so plainly calamitous, he added “it’s not an easy topic for the left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 3, while celebrations erupted in the heart of Buenos Aires, Argentina’s capital, leftist parties called for a protest outside the city’s U.S. Embassy — but the demonstration ended up being relatively modest in size. A survey by the polling firm Altica showed that 31 percent of Argentines opposed the U.S. intervention, while 61 percent supported it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentiment was largely different in Europe, where a majority of Spaniards, Germans and Britons condemned the attack, according to recent polls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the U.S. invasion of Iraq in 2003, Argentina, a Gallup International survey found, registered the highest level of opposition of any country surveyed — 83 percent — with many Latin American nations also strongly criticizing the military action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Iraq was much closer in time to the Cold War, as well as a faraway geographical conflict, experts noted, while Venezuela was an immediate, nearby, destabilizing threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Maduro turned out to be the neighbor who is noisy and disruptive, so when the police came to pick him up they were like: ‘finally,’” said Patricio Navia, a Chilean political scientist at New York University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Steven Levitsky, a political scientist at Harvard University, noted that three decades have passed since the Cold War helped contribute to U.S. meddling in Central America and a support for brutal dictatorships that entrenched anti-American sentiments across the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has been a pretty big generational change,” he said. “Many Latin Americans don’t remember that period.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Latin Americans now are worried about more pressing and urgent concerns, experts said, including crime waves fueled in large part by the power and spread of drug trafficking groups that have plagued countries like Ecuador or Costa Rica, nations that had been considered relatively safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Latin Americans are willing to embrace virtually any solution to end the violence, regardless of the methods employed. That “by all means necessary” logic can take the form of endorsing the illiberal methods of El Salvador’s president, Nayib Bukele, who has suspended key civil liberties while cracking down on crime — but also of condoning outside intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Latin Americans don’t like a U.S. invasion,” Mr. Navia said, “but they dislike economic crises and humanitarian crises even more.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela has been in crisis since 2014, when oil prices plunged, with food and medicine becoming scarcer and more expensive and the Maduro government becoming increasingly repressive, propelling one of the largest migration crises in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the eight million Venezuelans who fled the country in recent years, nearly seven million migrated to Latin American countries, most to Colombia and Perú, according to the Migration Policy institute, a research center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some nations, the influx has stretched budgets and angered locals who view the newcomers as competition for jobs and other services. And even though people who have committed crimes are a tiny fraction of the many Venezuelans who have fled, the infiltration of criminal gangs among the migrants have brought new crimes and fears among local populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Colombians saw in Mr. Maduro’s government an ally of armed Colombian rebel groups that have long terrorized their country. One of the largest has established a deep footprint along the border between Colombia and Venezuela, fomenting violence and displacing many Colombians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any action that could potentially weaken these groups is often welcomed by many Colombians — even if it means the United States raiding a sovereign country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are willing to look at El Salvador,” Ms. Lagos said. “People are willing to pay a price.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Daniel Politi and Lucía Cholakian Herrera from Buenos Aires, Argentina, Simon Romero and Annie Correal from Bogotá, Colombia, James Wagner from Mexico City, Mitra Taj from Lima, Peru, and José María León Cabrera from Quito, Ecuador.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/21/world/americas/latin-america-venezuela-us-raid-maduro-polls.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:13:16 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>