<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 08:46:01 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Nobel Committee Takes Heat at Home as Machado Courts Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/machado-trump-meeting-nobel-peace-prize.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/world/15int-machado-nobel/15int-machado-nobel-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has made it unmistakable how he feels about last year’s Nobel Peace Prize going to a Venezuelan opposition leader, María Corina Machado, and not him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I single-handedly ENDED 8 WARS, and Norway, a NATO Member, foolishly chose not to give me the Noble Peace Prize,” he said on social media last week. Beyond misspelling the award’s name, he also attributed the decision to the entire country of Norway rather than the five-member committee that makes its choices independently of the government in Oslo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Ms. Machado is expected to meet in Washington with Mr. Trump, with whom she has repeatedly sought to curry favor by proposing to share the award with him. She has cheered the U.S. military’s capture of Venezuela’s president, Nicolás Maduro, and remained mum about a bombing campaign against boats Mr. Trump says are smuggling drugs. The American strikes have killed more than 100 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thorny situation is being greeted with scorn across the Atlantic Ocean in Norway, where the prize is regarded not just as prestigious and freighted with symbolism but also the country’s prime soft-power tool. The Nobel Institute, which awards it, has been in serious damage-control mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Friday, after Ms. Machado floated the idea of sharing the prize with Mr. Trump in a Fox News interview, the institute offered a reminder about what the rules governing the award allow, saying that the facts were “clear and well established.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Once a Nobel Prize is announced, it cannot be revoked, shared or transferred to others,” the institute wrote. “The decision is final and stands for all time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before Ms. Machado arrived in Washington, Kristian Harpviken, the director of the institute, who is also the secretary of the committee that chooses award recipients, said he would not be drawn further into the deepening controversy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The prize is awarded on the basis of the laureate’s contributions by the time that the committee’s decision is taken,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That explanation has been insufficient for many Norwegians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A Nobel committee can never guard against peace prize laureates committing acts that run counter to the intention of the prize,’’ Lena Lindgren, a columnist for the Norwegian weekly Morgenbladet, said in an interview. “But what is new now is that the prize is being used in a political game, a warlike game.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear what Ms. Machado hopes to gain out of her meeting with Mr. Trump. After ousting Mr. Maduro, he declined to install her in power, saying “she’s a very nice woman, but she doesn’t have the respect” needed to lead the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Independently verified vote counts in Venezuela’s 2024 presidential election showed that Ms. Machado’s party had beaten Mr. Maduro by a wide margin. The Venezuelan authorities nonetheless declared Mr. Maduro the victor, and his government embarked on a harsh repression campaign against critics of the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is far from the first time the Nobel committee has been criticized for its choice, or been accused of abetting violent leaders or governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Global outrage followed the choice of President Barack Obama, who at the time was presiding over military engagements on several continents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And less than a year after receiving the award, Abiy Ahmed, the president of Ethiopia, embarked on a scorched-earth campaign in his country’s Tigray region that left hundreds of thousands dead, wounded and starving. Henry Kissinger and Lê Đức Thọ were awarded the prize before a cease-fire to end the Vietnam War broke down, with Mr. Kissinger ultimately trying to return the prize amid a wave of protests. His North Vietnamese counterpart rejected it outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes the dispute swirling around Ms. Machado unusual, according to Asle Sveen, a former researcher at the Nobel Institute, is Norwegians’ particularly dim view of Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Machado “has dedicated her Peace Prize to a highly controversial president, to put it mildly,” he said. “It is nearly universally accepted in Norway that Donald Trump attacks liberal democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Norwegian tabloid, Nettavisen, conducted a poll before the announcement of the award that found three-quarters of respondents were against it being bestowed on Mr. Trump, even if he were instrumental in orchestrating a peace agreement in Ukraine or Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Nobel Committee has compromised the prize” by not foreseeing how Ms. Machado and Mr. Trump would use it to justify military intervention in Venezuela, Ms. Lindgren said. “Norway has been politically embarrassed and has failed to manage the symbolic capital.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the 2024 election in Venezuela, Ms. Machado went into hiding for more than a year. In December, she secretly left Venezuela to receive her award in Norway. She missed the award ceremony but appeared in Oslo to greet supporters. Her escape was orchestrated by a company run by U.S. veterans with special operations and intelligence training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spokesmen for Ms. Machado did not respond to requests for comment for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American lawmakers, including Marco Rubio, who was then a Republican senator from Florida and is now Mr. Trump’s secretary of state, had written a letter to the Nobel Committee in 2024 advocating that they award Ms. Machado the peace prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They noted her “peaceful resistance to tyrants” and her “unwavering moral compass,” and said that her efforts showed the “urgent need for international solidarity in the face of aggressive and expansive authoritarianism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is little doubt that Ms. Machado has long risked her safety to challenge an authoritarian government that jails opponents, tortures critics and censors the press. But she has also embraced Mr. Trump’s military buildup in the Caribbean, repeated debunked claims that Mr. Maduro manipulated U.S. elections and parroted the Trump administration’s claim that Mr. Maduro simultaneously led two drug organizations, despite scant evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her assertions fueled accusations that she was amplifying misinformation in what, until now, seemed a failed attempt to gain the American president’s support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, not all Norwegians agree that the award to Ms. Machado was a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If turned out that she supported the U.S. boat strikes, that would not be the best reflection on a laureate, said Marianne Dahl, research director at the Peace Research Institute Oslo. But Ms. Machado was awarded for her pro-democracy work in 2024, Ms. Dahl said. She drew similarities between Ms. Machado and past winners who led popular movements in Nazi Germany, apartheid South Africa and Soviet republics, as well as during the so-called Arab Spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is easy to sit in comfortable Norway and criticize her for talking sweet to Trump,” Ms. Dahl said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, she noted, is exactly what many European and even Norwegian leaders have done. “And they don’t have a repressive regime pursuing them, as Machado has had,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/machado-trump-meeting-nobel-peace-prize.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:21:34 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel and Arab Nations Ask Trump to Refrain From Attacking Iran</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-iran-israel-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-iran-bhlj/15dc-iran-bhlj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel has asked President Trump to postpone any plans for an American military attack on Iran, a senior U.S. official said on Thursday, even as the Iranian government continues to grapple with nationwide protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Netanyahu spoke to Mr. Trump on Wednesday, the same day the American president said he had received information from “very important sources on the other side” that Iran had stopped killing protesters and was not going forward with executions. That appeared to signal that Mr. Trump was backing away from a potential U.S. attack on Iran, which he has been weighing for days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Mr. Trump sent a similar ambiguous signal last June even after he had largely made up his mind to order an attack on Iran. And a senior U.S. official said late Wednesday that Mr. Trump had not set aside the military options his commanders had presented in recent days, and whether he ordered an attack depends on what Iranian security agencies do next in regard to the mass protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Oman and Egypt, all partners of Washington, have also been asking the Trump administration not to attack Iran, said an official from a Gulf Arab nation. Senior officials from those countries have been calling U.S. officials with that message over the last two days, the official said. They have told the Americans that a U.S. attack could lead to a wider regional conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, those Arab nations have been telling Iranian officials not to attack countries in the region if the United States decides to strike Iran, the official said. The four nations have been coordinating their messaging to both Washington and Tehran, the official said. Two diplomats in the region also said several Arab nations have pressed the Trump administration not to attack Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We believe in dialogue and we believe in solving any disagreements at the negotiating table,” Adel al-Jubeir, the foreign minister of Saudi Arabia, said at a minerals forum in Riyadh, the kingdom’s capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House declined to comment. The Israeli prime minister’s office did not have immediate comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran ordered its air space closed to commercial flights late Wednesday, but has reopened it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. officials have been preparing for Iran to retaliate against an attack by striking American military assets in the region, mainly a U.S. air base in Qatar or troops stationed in Iraq and Syria. But Israel could also be a target for Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran fired many ballistic missiles at Israel during a 12-day war between the two nations in June that the United States also took part in by striking three Iranian nuclear sites. Some of the Iranian missiles got past Israeli air defenses and killed civilians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To retaliate against the U.S. strikes in June, Iran fired ballistic missiles at Al Udeid Air Base in Qatar, the largest American military base in the Middle East. About 10,000 troops are stationed there. The Iranian barrage caused no deaths or injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Pentagon had begun moving some troops from the base as Mr. Trump weighed options for a U.S. strike on Iran. A Pentagon official said on Thursday that the Defense Department has lowered the alert level at the air base and that troops have been returning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government has cut off internet service across the country, and it has been difficult to get information about the events unfolding there. Security forces have killed hundreds or thousands of protesters to try to end the broad anti-government demonstrations that have been taking place across Iran since late December, according to Iranian officials and human rights groups outside the country. Two Iranian officials told The New York Times on Monday that at least 3,000 people had been killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has said since Jan. 2 that he could order an attack on Iran if the government harms protesters, even though he has denounced people who demonstrate against his policies in the United States. On Tuesday, he wrote on social media that Iranian protesters should take over government institutions, and that “HELP IS ON ITS WAY.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s judiciary said on Thursday that it had not issued a death sentence for Erfan Soltani, a protester whose execution had been widely reported as imminent and drawn international attention. The comments were reported by Iran’s state broadcaster, and were published on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is good news,” Mr. Trump said on Thursday on social media, citing an unspecified Fox News report that said an unnamed Iranian protester and others would not be sentenced to death. “Hopefully, it will continue!” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Eric Schmitt from Washington, Aaron Boxerman from Jerusalem, Vivian Nereim from Riyadh and Abdi Latif Dahir from Beirut.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/us/politics/trump-iran-israel-us.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:27:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Milan Court Closes Fraud Case Against Italian Influencer Chiara Ferragni</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/chiara-ferragni-pandoro-cake-italy-influencer.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15xp-ferragni-vgqw/15xp-ferragni-vgqw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A court in Milan closed a fraud case on Wednesday against Chiara Ferragni, Italy’s most famous influencer, that involved accusations of charity fraud and had prompted an exodus of sponsors and followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ferragni, 38, had built a formidable empire online sharing the intricacies of her life. Then, she was accused of misleading consumers in 2022 with the sale of a pink-boxed Christmas cake, or pandoro, and the brewing scandal brought her unwanted attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors had initially accused her of aggravated fraud and asked for a prison sentence of 20 months. But the charge was downgraded to fraud by the judge, who then dismissed it because a victim had not filed a formal complaint, as required in Italy to uphold a fraud case. Victims had previously withdrawn a complaint under the terms of a settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A nightmare I have experienced for two years is over,” Ms. Ferragni told reporters outside the courtroom in Milan on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said in a social media post to her 28 million followers on Instagram on Thursday that the judge determined “that there were not even the basic grounds for a criminal trial to exist.” One of her defense lawyers, Marcello Bana, said in an interview that he hoped Milan prosecutors would not appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A prosecutor on the case, Eugenio Fusco, confirmed that Ms. Ferragni had been cleared of the charges, adding that prosecutors had not determined whether they would appeal. The judge had 90 days after his decision to file his verdict, after which prosecutors could decide whether to appeal, Mr. Fusco said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, Ms. Ferragni was accused of misleading consumers by endorsing a cake, produced by the Balocco bakery conglomerate, that was priced at about $10, about two and a half times more than that of a normal Balocco pandoro. In promotional messaging, Ms. Ferragni implied to her followers that sales from the cakes would go toward buying equipment for cancer treatment at a children’s hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But an Italian journalist, Selvaggia Lucarelli, questioned how much of the proceeds were going to Ms. Ferragni and how much would be going to the hospital. Balocco, she reported, had already made a donation to the hospital, and Ms. Ferragni’s partnership with the bakery conglomerate was a commercial venture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revelation, which came to be known as “Pandoro Gate,” eventually led to a media frenzy around Ms. Ferragni, who had until then been widely known as part of a first generation of social media influencers promoting brands around their fashion choices and lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2023, the Italian Competition Authority, which regulates commercial practices, fined Ms. Ferragni roughly 1.1 million euros (about $1.3 million) and Balocco 420,000 euros (about $487,000) over what it called misleading advertising. Companies affiliated with Ms. Ferragni, the authority said, had made more than 1 million euros in licensing fees, without paying anything to the children’s hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ferragni apologized to her followers in an unusually unglamorous video, shared to Instagram in 2023, saying that she had made “a communication error” and would donate 1 million euros to the hospital. “I realize that I could have been more vigilant,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the accusations embroiled Ms. Ferragni in more scandal. Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni criticized her in a speech, suggesting that Ms. Ferragni was not a good role model. Sponsors, among them Coca-Cola, dropped their partnerships with her, and hundreds of thousands of people on Instagram unfollowed her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case against Ms. Ferragni led to tighter regulations for influencers in Italy. In November, the nation’s regulatory agency for communication industries announced new rules requiring that influencers with more than 500,000 followers on a single platform — or those who average more than 1 million viewers a month across platforms — register as a “relevant influencer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Italian consumer rights group brought a class-action suit against Ms. Ferragni in 2023, accusing her of misleading consumers. Shortly after, prosecutors in Milan said that they would investigate her. Ms. Ferragni, they said, had misled consumers previously, including on a collaboration with a sweets company in which she implied that sales from Easter eggs would go toward a charity group, they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Ferragni had since settled the class action suit, agreeing to pay 150 euros, or about $174, to each buyer of the limited edition pandoro cakes and to make a donation to a foundation for female victims of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aimee Ortiz contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/chiara-ferragni-pandoro-cake-italy-influencer.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:48:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Healthy Brain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/brain-health-challenge-trump-iran.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-theworld-well-challenge-promo/16int-theworld-well-challenge-gif-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, we kicked off 2026 by featuring the 5-Day Brain Health Challenge: a set of activities from our colleagues on the Well desk designed to be good for your brain, and to tee up healthy habits for the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that self-care advice can sometimes sound a little off-key. There’s a lot happening. President Trump attacked Venezuela. Iran might be next. … Eat more berries?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe the crazier the world feels, the more important it becomes to look after yourself. As my colleague Dana Smith, who designed the challenge, put it: “Regardless of what’s going on in the world, when you or your family has a health crisis, everything stops.” So, in some ways, there is nothing more important. Today I talk to Dana about how to keep your brain healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dana, you do a Well challenge at the start of every year. What made you focus on brain health this year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to focus on brain health because it’s a topic that touches all of us, and it’s one that can feel pretty scary and out of our control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people I know, myself included, have someone in their family who’s experienced dementia or a stroke. And there are a lot of headlines that are very doom and gloom: A million people will develop dementia every year, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that doesn’t tell the whole story. I think what is less known is that there are actually things you can do to maintain your brain health. And while the number of people with dementia is rising because we have a large aging population, the rates of dementia are actually declining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is due to lifestyle?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s almost entirely due to that. Our genes haven’t changed, our brains haven’t really changed, but our lifestyles have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The No. 1 thing is fewer people smoke, and that has had a really dramatic effect on people’s physical health and brain health. The other main contributor is better heart health. Your heart health and your brain health are closely linked. And so more people controlling their blood pressure, especially, has also made a big difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what we really wanted to get across with the Well challenge: There are clear, actionable steps that people can take to benefit their brain health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about those steps. In some ways your recommendations are very familiar, right? Eat well, sleep well, exercise. Why remind people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing we try to do at Well is explain the science behind this type of lifestyle advice. It’s easy to kind of roll your eyes and say, “Yeah, yeah, I know.” So we want people to understand why these things help your brain stay healthy for longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason exercise is so good for your brain, for example, is that there are these amazing molecules called exerkines that your muscles and other organs release. Some of them go up to your brain where they actually help to heal damaged neurons and create new connections between neurons. They can even protect your brain from shrinking with age. I mean, these are incredibly cool mechanisms that underpin this simple advice of “get some exercise.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Feeling inspired to get moving? Read this story on the best sports for longevity, and watch the video below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical health to me is quite intuitive. Like if I exercise and I eat well, I can feel it and maybe even see it in my body. What does a healthy brain look and feel like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the clearest example of this is sleep. If you get a good night’s rest, you feel great the next day. If you have a poor night’s sleep, you feel terrible. You feel sluggish, you’re irritable, you can’t perform at your best. That, to me, really encapsulates a good brain day versus a bad brain day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that people also kind of intuitively can feel a bad brain day versus a good one. And I think what usually contributes to a good one are those small self-care steps, like going outside for a walk, that often are also the ones that benefit our physical health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is maintaining brain health any different from just maintaining overall health?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A healthy body includes a healthy brain. I really think that they’re one and the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump appears to be backing away from a potential U.S. attack on Iran, which he had been weighing for days. On Wednesday, the president spoke to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel, who asked him to postpone any plans for an American military attack on Iran, according to a U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Oman and Egypt have also asked the Trump administration to stand down, warning that U.S. military action could lead to a wider regional conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel’s caution about a U.S. attack on Iran is well justified, experts said. The risks of blowback against Israel — including a new war — are too great. And the chances are remote that anything short of a major offensive could topple Iran’s clerical rulers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran appeared yesterday to backpedal on previous threats to execute protesters, even as the government continues a brutal crackdown after weeks of demonstrations. Here’s what Iranian officials are saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People in Greenland are fearful of what might come next after a meeting with the Trump administration ended in an impasse. Several NATO countries announced plans to send troops to Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four astronauts returned home to Earth after a medical evacuation from the International Space Station. Watch them splash down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump threatened to invoke the Insurrection Act, which authorizes the president to use the military inside the U.S., to quell protests in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;María Corina Machado, the Nobel laureate and Venezuelan opposition leader, met with Trump after offering to share her prize with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uganda held a presidential election, with Yoweri Museveni, 81, widely expected to extend his rule of nearly four decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social networks in Australia removed or deleted nearly five million accounts belonging to teenagers, one month after a ban went into effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least two people were killed when a crane collapsed on an expressway in Thailand — the second fatal episode involving cranes this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvard, once the world’s most productive research university, has dropped to No. 3 as Chinese universities climb the rankings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social media platform X said it would block Grok, the A.I. chatbot created by Elon Musk, from generating sexualized and naked images of real people in some locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Morocco faces Senegal on Sunday in the Africa Cup of Nations final.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: The Australian Open begins this weekend. Here’s what to watch for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Do you remember sitting in front of the television, devouring music video after music video on MTV? This website recreates that experience. With channels arranged by era or genre, it can take you back to the days of hair metal and heartland rock, or grunge and goth, or ’90s hip-hop and R&amp;B. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After nearly two weeks of delay, my colleague Chang W. Lee, a New York Times photographer, was finally able to launch his drone to capture images of Antarctica from the air. “I’ve been waiting for this moment for a long time,” he said. Take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chang and Raymond Zhong, a climate reporter, are traveling with a scientific expedition to study Antarctica’s fastest melting glacier. You can follow their progress here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new video game by a Chinese developer taps into fears felt by many: scams and human trafficking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one part of the game, called “Blood Money: Lethal Eden,” a woman you met online drugs you and takes you to an office where a boss promises your freedom — but only if you can scam enough money out of unsuspecting victims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People around the world have been kidnapped and forced to work in scam compounds in Southeast Asia. Scenes in the game look a lot like the images of real scam compounds, including an abandoned one that New York Times journalists recently visited in Myanmar. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L’affogato al caffè, a dessert of gelato drowned in espresso, is a delectable Italian treat. The ice cream can be fior di latte, chocolate or whatever you like. The magic of affogato is that you get two pleasures in one: a spoonable dessert sauced with coffee, and a cream-blushed drink to chase it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is this city?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shenyang, China&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sapporo, Japan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innsbruck, Austria&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yakutsk, Russia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love a good hustler movie.I’d been hearing all this breathless praise for “Marty Supreme,” a new movie directed by Josh Safdie about a table tennis-playing, serial-hustler-gambler-rambler in 1950s America, played by Timothée Chalamet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consensus in podcast interviews and countless articles seemed to be: Chalamet is totally amazing. The table tennis scenes are insane. This movie is going to blow you away. It will win every award on the planet, guaranteed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally watched “Marty Supreme” last Saturday, a day before the Golden Globes. Chalamet was amazing. The table tennis was insane. But the movie didn’t blow me away, despite the incredible hype — an example of successful hustling! (Our critic liked it more than I did, calling it electrifying.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine described “Marty Supreme” as a B-minus compared with “Uncut Gems,” a 2019 movie by Safdie and his brother, Benny. It is, well, a gem of a movie. The first time I watched it I had to stop because it was so stressful. (My muscles ached from all the clenching.) The second time I loved it so much that I watched it a third time. It may be the most exhilarating movie I’ve ever seen. Check it out: That’s my recommendation this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you need to lower your pulse afterward, listen to “Spinning Away,” a Brian Eno collab with John Cale. Dreamy and soothing. Definitely not suitable for the soundtrack of a Safdie movie!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a great weekend! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/brain-health-challenge-trump-iran.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 20:31:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Inside the Fight to Keep Iran Online</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/iran-online-starlink.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/00biz-iran-internet-starlink-hgjm/00biz-iran-internet-starlink-hgjm-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s communications blackout last week seemed complete. Internet and cellular networks had been shut down by the authorities. Online banking, shopping and text messaging services stopped working. Information about the growing protests was scarce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet a ragtag network of activists, developers and engineers pierced Iran’s digital barricades. Using thousands of Starlink satellite internet systems that they had quietly smuggled into the country, they got online and spread images of troops firing into the streets and families searching for bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their actions, described by digital rights researchers and others, forced Iran’s government to respond. The authorities deployed military-grade electronic weaponry designed to disrupt the GPS signals that Starlink equipment needs to function, a step that activists and civil society groups said was rarely taken outside battlefields like those in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cracks exposed in Iran’s internet shutdown were no accident. Since 2022, activists and civil society groups have worked on sneaking Starlink terminals into the country, aided by a U.S. government sanctions exemption for Starlink and American companies to offer communication tools in Iran. About 50,000 of the terminals are now in Iran, according to digital activists, in defiance of an Iranian law passed last year that bans the systems, and rules prohibiting unlicensed services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You need to plan to have that infrastructure in place,” said Fereidoon Bashar, the executive director of ASL19, a digital rights group focused on Iran. “This is because of years of planning and work among different groups.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hidden networks of Starlinks — and the Iranian government’s aggressive response against them — shows how national digital blackouts are becoming harder for authorities to enforce. Governments have long used internet disruptions to suppress dissent in countries like India, Myanmar and Uganda. But the spread of tools like satellite internet have complicated the shutdowns and created a cat-and-mouse hunt against new technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starlink, provided by Elon Musk’s rocket company, SpaceX, beams an internet connection from satellites to terminals on Earth, bypassing any land-based censorship infrastructure. That has helped the service play an outsize role in Iran’s protests, helping demonstrators organize and communicate with the outside world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starlink is still available only to a sliver of the Iranian population, and information about the protests, which have left an estimated 3,000 dead, remains limited. For most people, the internet continues to be heavily restricted, even as some domestic services have reopened. Video game services have removed chat options, while e-commerce platforms have blocked messaging features, researchers said, an effort to keep the economy going while limiting communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the most severe internet shutdown that we have experienced,” said Ahmad Ahmadian, an exiled activist who was also involved in smuggling the satellite internet systems into Iran. “Starlink is a lifeline.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reliance on Starlink underscores Mr. Musk’s geopolitical influence. This week, the world’s richest man said all Starlink services in Iran would be free of charge. President Trump has also emphasized the importance of satellite internet technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SpaceX spokesman could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most internet shutdowns worldwide, governments order local internet service providers to turn off access. Other techniques that filter internet data allow authorities to more narrowly target what connections are cut. In 2024, 296 internet shutdowns took place in 54 countries, the most on record, according to the rights group Access Now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran has long been a practitioner of internet blackouts, with its online censorship system considered one of the most sophisticated in the world outside China. The government has built a state-run internet, the National Information Network, which is essentially walled off from the rest of the world. The authorities tightly control access to global internet content, while providing smooth connections for approved domestic services like banking, shopping, transportation and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the need arises, Iran’s government has surgically cut off the internet in some areas, while still giving access to essential online services, internet monitors said. Its system is not perfect, and many Iranians have used virtual private networks, known as VPNs, and other tools to use Instagram and other global services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on Jan. 8, as mass protests swelled, Iranian officials turned off the internet altogether, sending the country of 90 million people into a digital blackout. VPNs stopped working. Iran’s internet traffic dropped 99 percent, according to Netblocks, a monitoring group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government “panicked,” said Amir Rashidi, a cybersecurity expert with Miaan, a digital rights group focused on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activists who had prepared for a communications blockade swung into action. After the authorities shut down the internet during violent protests in 2022, activists and civil society groups hatched plans to smuggle in Starlinks from neighboring countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Department coordinated with SpaceX on the sanctions exemption for digital communication tools in Iran. It also provided support to civil society groups about how to hide the systems from government detection, according to a Biden administration official involved in the plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Activating Starlink,” Mr. Musk posted online that year about Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ahmadian, now executive director of the rights group Holistic Resilience in Los Angeles, said he had helped others get some of the first Starlink terminals across the border. “We turned it on, and it just worked like a charm,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraged by the success, Mr. Ahmadian said, he helped build a smuggling network. Clustering on Telegram channels and other online platforms, merchants sold Starlink units and coordinated delivery routes through the United Arab Emirates, Iraqi Kurdistan, Armenia and Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the latest protests, it cost $700 to $800 to smuggle a Starlink terminal into Iran, Mr. Ahmadian said. A black market emerged for people seeking access to Instagram, YouTube and other restricted platforms, mainly among more wealthy Iranians, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roughly 50,000 Starlink terminals now in Iran are hidden on rooftops and discreet locations. Developers have built tools so a Starlink connection can be shared, turning a single terminal into a gateway for others farther away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government was aware of Starlink’s growing presence but did not do much to curtail the use until recently, said Doug Madory, an internet infrastructure expert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest electronic jamming efforts against Starlink worked in certain areas, but the terminals are too numerous and dispersed to block completely, researchers said. An Israeli intelligence official said Iran’s government appeared to focus on blocking Starlink terminals in neighborhoods close to the largest universities, to force students offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities have flown drones to find the Starlink units, activists said. They also tried to invoke fear by broadcasting the confiscation of the satellite terminals and warning that possession of a Starlink is a crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation in Iran with satellite internet systems “is a litmus test for electronic warfare in the civilian environment,” said Thomas Withington, a military communications expert at the Royal United Services Institute. “Access to satellite communications used to be for the military. That paradigm is changing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several activists said Starlink had been vital, but they were concerned that Mr. Musk might one day change his mind and turn off the service. In authoritarian countries where Mr. Musk has business interests, like China, he has said the service is unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/technology/iran-online-starlink.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:08:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Nobel Medal Has Been Sold Before for Millions of Dollars</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/nobel-peace-prize-sold-auctions.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-nobel-worth-01-tbvj/15int-nobel-worth-01-tbvj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, the Russian journalist Dmitry Muratov auctioned his Nobel Peace Prize for a record-breaking $103.5 million to raise money for Ukrainian child refugees. In 2014, James Watson sold his for over $4 million, having been awarded the medal decades earlier for codiscovering the structure of DNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nobel Prize has become the focus of an ethical debate about who gets to claim it after María Corina Machado, Venezuela’s opposition leader, offered to share hers with President Trump despite the Nobel Committee’s stipulation that the prize cannot be revoked, shared or transferred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can, however, be sold for millions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the 1980s, the Nobel medal has been made with 18-karat recycled gold, according to the Nobel Committee. And, in a few auctions across the prize’s history, it has fetched a wide range of prices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francis Crick, who was awarded the prize with Mr. Watson, received over $2 million for his medal. The Nobel Peace Prize awarded in 1936 to Carlos Saavedra Lamas, a former foreign minister of Argentina, sold for $1.1 million in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not all attempts to sell the medal have brought staggering returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1994 medal awarded to John Nash for his work in game theory sold for under $1 million in 2019. The 1982 prize awarded to the physicist Kenneth Wilson failed to reach a minimum bid of $450,000 in 2016. And William Faulkner’s failed to sell in 2013, after bidding stalled at $425,000, short of the minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has openly coveted the prize, and Ms. Machado dedicated it to him when she received it in October.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Ms. Machado said she had “presented the president of the United States the medal of the Nobel Peace Prize,” describing a moment during a private lunch earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was not immediately clear if she had given Mr. Trump the actual prize and if he had accepted it.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/nobel-peace-prize-sold-auctions.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 15:17:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela’s Interim Leader Balances Maduro’s Script With Trump’s Demands</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-rodriguez-maduro-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-venezuela-speech-Delcy-jqpb/15int-venezuela-speech-Delcy-jqpb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During her first State of the Union address on Thursday, Delcy Rodríguez, Venezuela’s interim leader, walked a political tight rope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez echoed the fiery, anti-imperialist rhetoric used by her predecessors in the speech, which she said she had co-written with Nicolás Maduro just hours before he was captured by U.S. commandos, and she launched a verbal offensive against the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, she also seemed to follow President Trump’s agenda by saying she was opening Venezuela’s oil fields, a specific demand of the U.S. government, and releasing political prisoners, which Mr. Trump has called “a very important and smart gesture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Let us not be afraid of diplomacy,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has threatened Ms. Rodríguez with consequences “worse than Maduro” if she does not comply with U.S. interests. Mr. Maduro now sits in a Brooklyn prison awaiting trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, she requested attendants to honor “all the heroes and heroines who died in combat” against the United States, which she called “the invading aggressor,” and said that the capture of Mr. Maduro and his wife, Cilia Flores, had crossed a line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They attacked, assaulted, killed, invaded and kidnapped President Maduro and the first lady,” she said. “There is a stain on relations between the United States and Venezuela.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking before the National Assembly in the capital, Caracas, for about 40 minutes, Ms. Rodríguez tried to send a message of stability to a nation uncertain of its future — although some of her claims seem to be disputed by the reality on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela, she said, was already on a path of economic recovery before the recent U.S. incursion, driven primarily by the oil sector. She added that the country had achieved zero fuel imports last year, a first in over a decade, as oil production reached 1.168 million barrels per day in December, according to a slide she presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a recent survey by Gallup showed that three in five Venezuelans struggled at times to afford food last year, among the highest rate in the region. About 90 percent of Venezuelans live in poverty, according to independent watchdogs. And recent reports indicate a sharp decline in oil production because of infrastructure decay and the effects of a U.S. naval blockade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During her speech, Ms. Rodríguez, who was until Mr. Maduro’s capture the country’s minister of petroleum while serving as his vice president, called on legislators to approve a bill that would allow opening oil fields “where there is no infrastructure” and “investment has never been made.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move seemed designed to meet specific U.S. demands, potentially giving American oil companies access to untapped oil reserves. But the proposal might signal a departure from previous policies carried out by Mr. Maduro’s predecessor, Hugo Chávez, who prioritized state-led nationalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In the face of aggression and a ferocious threat, we are forging an energy partnership defined by decency, dignity and independence,” Ms. Rodríguez said on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump dined with Venezuela’s opposition leader and the newest Nobel laureate, María Corina Machado, the White House press secretary, Karoline Leavitt, praised the interim government in Venezuela led by Ms. Rodríguez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They have been extremely cooperative, and they have, thus far, met all of the demands and requests of the United States and of the president,” Ms. Leavitt told reporters. “And I think you have all seen that play out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez, she added, had also confirmed that the Venezuelan authorities would be freeing political prisoners, highlighting the recent release of five U.S. citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her speech, Ms. Rodríguez addressed the releases — which some human rights groups estimate to be about 84 so far — although she accused political prisoners of being “foreign mercenaries who came to kill us” and of committing criminal acts “of hatred, violence and intolerance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, she added, the releases were approved “because President Maduro believed that we should move forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Ms. Machado said she had presented Mr. Trump with “the medal of the Nobel Peace Prize,” and Mr. Trump confirmed it. The act was seen as part of her efforts to cozy up to Mr. Trump. The Norwegian Nobel Institute previously said in a statement that the prize cannot be revoked, shared or transferred to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, Ms. Machado has accused Ms. Rodríguez of being part of the Maduro administration’s repressive machinery and of acting as Venezuela’s main point of contact with Russia, China and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Venezuela has the right to relations with China, with Russia, with Cuba, with Iran, with all the peoples of the world,” Ms. Rodríguez responded during her televised speech, “and with the United States, as well.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She then appeared to send a message to Ms. Machado.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If one day, as acting president, I have to go to Washington, I will do so with my head held high, walking, not on my knees,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/venezuela-rodriguez-maduro-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 16:13:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Many Fiery Remarks, Little Clarity on What’s Next at Security Council Meeting on Iran</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/iran-protests-security-council.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-Iran-unsc-cgtq/15int-Iran-unsc-cgtq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a week of threatening to strike Iran in retaliation for the government killing protesters, the United States brought its case against the country to the United Nations Security Council on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the United States offered little clarity on what action, if any, it intended to take against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mike Waltz, the U.S. ambassador to the U.N., told the council that President Trump “stands by the brave people of Iran. Period,” adding that the level of violence and repression that Iran has unleashed against its own citizens had repercussions for international peace and stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is a man of action, not endless talk like we see at the United Nations,” Mr. Waltz said. “He has made it clear all options are on the table to stop the slaughter and no one should know that better than the leadership of the Iranian regime.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nationwide uprising has erupted across Iran since late December. Initially fueled by a tanking economy and currency, the unrest has grown to demanding an end to nearly five decades of Islamic theocracy. After initial economic gestures to contain the unrest, Iran’s leaders cracked down violently, shutting down the internet and firing, at times seemingly indiscriminately, on unarmed protesters. An Iranian health ministry official said more than 3,000 people have been killed, including more than 100 security forces. Rights groups like the Norway-based Iran Human Rights said that more than 3,400 had been killed and thousands of others injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has swayed from saying early this month that the United States was “locked and loaded and ready to go,” and this week calling on Iranian protesters to seize government institutions because help was on the way, to announcing diplomatic negotiations were back on the table, then off, and finally suggesting Iran had heeded to his call to stop killing and executing protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia and China, permanent members of the Security Council and allies of Iran, condemned the United States, saying it was war mongering and meddling in the internal affairs of a sovereign nation. China said U.S. military intervention would plunge the region into an abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia’s ambassador to the U.N., Vasily Nebenzya, said Mr. Trump’s rhetoric on Iran in recent days was “reckless” and amounted to “nothing but incitements to violently overthrow” the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s deputy ambassador to the U.N., Gholamhossein Darzi, delivered a long and fiery speech, striking a more confrontational tone than Iran’s foreign minister, Abbas Araghchi, has in recent days. Mr. Araghchi has indicated a willingness to defuse tensions with Washington by returning to negotiations over Tehran’s nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Darzi, however, attacked both the United Nations and the United States, labeled protesters in Iran as terrorists, and denied Iran had killed any of them, blaming the United States and Israel for the bloodshed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any act of aggression — direct or indirect — will be met with a decisive, proportionate and lawful response,” Mr. Darzi said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As he railed, some U.N. officials and diplomats present in the chamber appeared stunned. He also denounced the two well-known opposition activists the United States had invited to address the council, Masih Alinejad and Ahmad Batebi, as being on “Mossad’s payroll,” repeating common tropes used by the government to discredit its critics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In October, a federal judged sentenced two men who had been hired by Iran in a plot to assassinate Ms. Alinejad in New York, where she lives. In her remarks to the council, she read the names of some of the victims who have been killed in the recent protests. “The list of names goes on and on,” Ms. Alinejad said. “They knew they would face guns and bullets, but they wanted justice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Batebi recounted that when he was a university student in Iran in 1999 he was arrested for participating in protests and sentenced to death. He had drawn the authorities’ ire after a photo of him holding up the bloody shirt of a fellow student landed on the cover of the Economist magazine. He was jailed for eight years, two of which were in solitary confinement, and repeatedly tortured, including in mock executions. He escaped and came to the United States in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Batebi told the council that his body remained covered with scars from his time in prison, when interrogators cut him and poured salt over his wounds. “I can show you my body if you don’t believe me right now,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turning toward Mr. Darzi, the Iranian representative, he said: “I’m here in front of you — you tried to kill me but you couldn’t. You cannot kill all the people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Darzi appeared to smirk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Don’t laugh, sir, don’t laugh at me,” Mr. Batebi said, “because a day will come when you have to go to court and answer to all the things you did.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/iran-protests-security-council.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 17:54:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Citing Secret Plot, U.K. Conservative Party Fires a Senior Lawmaker</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/uk-robert-jenrick-fired-badenoch-conservatives-reform.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-uk-conservatives-01-jvlg/15int-uk-conservatives-01-jvlg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior lawmaker for Britain’s Conservative Party was accused on Thursday of “plotting” to defect to a rival party and was ousted, highlighting the fierce competition that is underway for the future of the country’s political right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kemi Badenoch, the leader of the Conservatives, said on social media that she had fired Robert Jenrick, one of the party’s leading lawmakers, after being “presented with clear, irrefutable evidence” that he wanted to leave in a way that would cause maximum damage to his longtime party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Badenoch did not name the party, but Mr. Jenrick, who has hard-right views, had been rumored to be considering defecting to Reform U.K., the right-wing populist party led by Nigel Farage. Mr. Jenrick did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her surprise move came after a string of Conservative politicians across the country joined Reform, which has surged in popularity since the last general election and has led the polls for almost a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jenrick’s dismissal followed an announcement on Monday that Nadhim Zahawi, a former Conservative minister who once served as chancellor, had joined Reform, citing the need for “a glorious revolution.” On Wednesday, Reform officials announced that 14 local Conservative council members had switched to the party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defections are a boost for Mr. Farage, whose anti-immigrant views and Trump-like populism have transformed Reform from a fringe party into a political powerhouse on the right. Public surveys show Mr. Farage and his party with strong support across some parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has largely come at the expense of the Conservatives, who dominated British politics for decades. The party of Margaret Thatcher and Boris Johnson now consistently trails behind Reform in the polls, although in recent weeks it has regained a little ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reform’s popularity has also altered the political debate for Prime Minister Keir Starmer and his struggling Labour Party. Mr. Starmer and his allies have increasingly taken aim at Mr. Farage and Reform as they try to claw back the support that helped them win the general election in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The British public are tired of political psychodrama and so am I,” Ms. Badenoch said. “They saw too much of it in the last government, they’re seeing too much of it in THIS government. I will not repeat those mistakes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked at a news conference on Thursday after the dismissal whether Mr. Jenrick was about to be unveiled as a new member of Reform, Mr. Farage said: “Is he one of many that I’ve talked to about what the future might look like? Absolutely. Have I signed a deal with him? No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Farage added that Reform would “welcome” further defections from people who shared the party’s beliefs and said he would call Mr. Jenrick to “see what he wants to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jenrick became one of Britain’s youngest-ever government ministers in 2019 and later served as minister for immigration for 11 months. He was appointed as a Conservative centrist and a loyalist to Prime Minister Rishi Sunak and was seen as a moderating force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he later had a political transformation. After the Conservatives lost power in July 2024, he became increasingly vocal on social media and garnered a large following on X, sharing videos in which he challenged fare dodgers on the London Underground and took up divisive positions on migration and security.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/uk-robert-jenrick-fired-badenoch-conservatives-reform.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:15:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After an Inconclusive Meeting, Greenlanders Ask: Now What?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/trump-greenland-denmark-meeting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-greenland-gplh/15int-greenland-gplh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s what Greenlanders are asking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big meeting in Washington over Greenland’s future happened on Wednesday. It was historic because Greenland was included for the first time at such high levels. Its foreign minister sat down with Vice President JD Vance and Secretary of State Marco Rubio to talk about the gigantic icebound island that has been part of Denmark for more than 300 years but that President Trump insists the United States should take over, possibly with military force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hope was to work out a compromise, find some path forward. But the conclusion from Denmark’s foreign minister, who was also there, was that a “fundamental disagreement” remained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Honestly, I feel flat. And I’m disappointed,” said Paalo Kuitse, a mechanic in the southern town of Qaqortoq. “What we are missing are answers about what will happen next.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m afraid the next step from the U.S. will be harsh,” he said, adding, “The U.S. has the biggest military machine in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danish political establishment, even opposition parties, has tried to put the best face on the meeting. Some politicians even called it “diplomacy at its best.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It would have been completely naive to believe that the threat of taking over Greenland would go away,” said Rasmus Jarlov, a conservative lawmaker. But, he said, at least the officials didn’t start arguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland’s 57,000 people have been watching all this unfold in disbelief. For generations, they have mostly been left alone to survive in one of the coldest, most barren and remote places on the planet. They have built a blended lifestyle, adhering to traditions like hunting seals and whales while also enjoying a high Scandinavian standard of living. Polls and interviews indicate that most don’t want to ditch their free education and free health care for an American system of vast inequality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many took great pride in seeing their foreign minister, Vivian Motzfeldt, standing in Washington on Wednesday and speaking Greenlandic to a bank of reporters, saying it was important for her to communicate to her people back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a cafe in Nuuk broadcast the news live, people started clapping when she spoke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel relieved when you hear it, but you never really know what will happen,” said Agnetha Mikka Petersen, who was watching the broadcast with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said she had a dream that American ships and planes bombed Nuuk’s airport. “I’m afraid of what could happen to Greenland — and what could happen to Denmark,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Greenlanders say what people all over the world say about Mr. Trump: that he’s highly unpredictable. On Wednesday, the president seemed to strike a more measured tone. When asked by a reporter if he would use force to acquire Greenland, a threat he has repeatedly made, he said: “You’re saying that. I didn’t say it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He emphasized — again — that Greenland was crucial for the United States’ security and that Denmark can’t defend it in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s not a thing that Denmark can do about it if Russia or China wants to occupy Greenland, but there’s everything we can do,” he said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he added: “I have a very good relationship with Denmark, and we’ll see how it all works out. I think something will work out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump consistently glides past the fact that because Greenland is part of Denmark, and Denmark part of NATO, the United States would in any case be obliged to defend Greenland if Russia or China attacked, something analysts say is remote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foreign policy scholars tried to find some positive embers. The meeting might not have broken the impasse, said Penny Naas, senior vice president at the German Marshall Fund of the United States, a policy organization focused on trans-Atlantic cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But it also didn’t result in the worse-case scenario,” she said. “It bought time for each side to explore the issue further and to see where there might be potential compromises that don’t violate anyone’s red lines.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s foreign minister, Lars Lokke Rasmussen, came out of the meeting looking deflated and said that a “working group” would convene in the coming weeks. Marisol Maddox, a senior fellow at the Institute of Arctic Studies at Dartmouth University, called that “a positive, concrete step.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One possible compromise, she said, would be to “tweak” the existing America-Danish defense agreements that already give the United States sweeping military access to Greenland and “develop something the Trump administration could own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Greenlanders aren’t so hopeful about all this working out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We need economic security and lower costs of living. Those are the things we have to deal with together — instead of being spectators,” said Jens Peter Lange, a dental technician in Illulissat, a town in western Greenland, who also works as a commercial fishermen to make ends meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He dismissed the working group as “just a talking club for civil servants” that would rack up high bills flying between capitals and buying duty-free goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they can’t give me a tool to sell my fish at a better price,” he said, “then it’s not for me.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/europe/trump-greenland-denmark-meeting.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 14:16:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuba Receives Remains of 32 Citizens Killed in U.S. Strikes in Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/cuba-remains-venezuela-strikes-maduro.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-cuba-mpwk/15int-cuba-mpwk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuban national television broadcast live on Thursday morning the return of the remains of 32 of its citizens, who were killed in the U.S. strikes on Venezuela during the operation in the early morning of Jan. 3 to capture the ousted Venezuelan president, Nicolás Maduro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remains arrived in boxes, smaller than caskets, draped in the Cuban flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, Cuba has sent thousands of its citizens to Venezuela, which, in turn, provided Cuba with oil. Many of the Cubans sent to Venezuela are teachers and doctors, but they also include intelligence agents and security guards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times reported in December that, in the face of increasing U.S. military pressure, Mr. Maduro had expanded the role of Cuban bodyguards in his personal security detail and placed more Cuban counterintelligence agents in Venezuela’s military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remains were received at Havana’s international airport by Cuban President Miguel Díaz-Canel and the country’s Minister of the Interior, Maj. Gen. Lázaro Alberto Álvarez Casas, among other high-ranking officials in the Cuban Communist Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The enemy speaks euphorically of high-precision operations, of elite troops, of supremacy. We, on the other hand, speak of faces, of families who lost their father, their son, their husband, their brother,” said Mr. Álvarez, speaking at the airport. “People do not become great because of their material wealth, but because of their ability to keep the memory of their heroes alive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ousting of Mr. Maduro was a significant blow to Cuba, which relied heavily on Venezuelan oil to keep its economy afloat. Venezuelan oil shipments to Cuba have essentially ceased. Experts have described Cuba’s economy as being in “free fall” since the U.S. government cut off the supply of Venezuelan oil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, President Trump said in a social media post that “no more oil or money” would be going to Cuba from Venezuela, and that the United States military would be involved in enforcing a separation between the two countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Venezuela doesn’t need protection anymore from the thugs and extortionists who held them hostage for so many years,” Mr. Trump wrote. “Venezuela now has the United States of America, the most powerful military in the World (by far!), to protect them, and protect them we will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loss of Venezuelan oil would be “catastrophic” for Cuba, according to Jorge Piñon, a former oil executive in Mexico and an expert on the energy industry at the University of Texas at Austin, who said that Venezuela had been supplying roughly a third of Cuba’s daily fuel needs.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/americas/cuba-remains-venezuela-strikes-maduro.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:57:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel Watches Iran Protests Closely, but Is Wary of Intervening</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/israel-iran-protests-netanyahu.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/14/multimedia/14int-israel-iran-01-whjk/14int-israel-iran-01-whjk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No country is watching the protests in Iran with greater interest than Israel, which sees the Islamic Republic as a mortal enemy and an existential threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran has been the obsession of Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel, who has portrayed the government in Tehran and its supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, as a global menace on the order of Nazi Germany. The two countries fought a 12-day war last June in which Israel, briefly joined by the United States, bombed Iranian military and nuclear sites while Iran bombarded Israel with ballistic missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israelis would cheer if the Iranian regime were to fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet former officials and analysts say that the Israeli leadership is unlikely to do much to try to precipitate a regime change, seeing the Iranian government as far from the brink of collapse and the current protests as insufficient to push it to that point. Israel is unlikely to attack Iran unless it is invited into a U.S.-led operation, or unless Iran attacks Israel first, they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And its caution about a U.S. attack on Iran is well justified, experts said. The risks of blowback against Israel — including a new war — are too great. And the chances that anything short of a major offensive could topple Iran’s authoritarian clerical rulers are too remote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how Israel views the protests and its own options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli analysts predict that the current wave of demonstrations in Iran will be short-lived. The protesters lack leadership and the means to defend themselves, they said, pointing to reports this week that Iranian security forces had killed thousands of demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If there were millions of people on the street, it would be very difficult to stop them. You cannot kill everyone,” said Sima Shine, a veteran former Iran expert at Israel’s Mossad spy agency. “But we don’t see millions. We see thousands. And this regime knows how to handle that. Their first tool is to kill people, and to make sure that everybody knows that they’re killing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli analysts say the protests are being suppressed in part by the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps and its volunteer militia, the Basij.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are highly motivated to defend the existing power structure because their fates are tied to that of the government, which has brutalized the Iranian people for years, said Zohar Palti, formerly the head of the Mossad’s intelligence directorate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the regime changes, they’re dead,” he added. “That’s the reason they’re killing people in the streets.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A successful uprising would require a well-organized opposition capable of keeping pressure on Iran even in the face of sustained, violent repression, said Eyal Hulata, who was Israel’s national security adviser from 2021 to 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is something that is lacking in Iran, and this is the main reason why everyone is a bit skeptical that this might actually succeed,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using tools like social media to amplify opposition voices or cyberattacks to sabotage the government — the kinds of things that can be done from afar, apart from military action — is not enough to threaten the Islamic Republic, experts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I haven’t seen that cyber knows how to collapse countries,” Mr. Palti said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with Iran cutting off the internet and stifling independent reporting on the protests, it has been difficult even for Israel — whose intelligence service has repeatedly embarrassed the Iranians with its ability to operate in their country — to obtain an accurate picture of the situation on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which underscores the difficulties of toppling a government from afar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Israel cannot change the regime in Iran,” Mr. Hulata said. “Israel can provide assistance to opposition groups, maybe exert a little bit of influence,” he added. “But this in itself is not sufficient.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What could make a difference in Iran, several experts said, is a much bigger military action hampering the government’s ability to crack down on the protests. That could entail targeting Revolutionary Guard forces, the Basij, or Iran’s command-and-control systems. That is no small challenge in such a vast country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli leaders would also welcome an attack on Iran’s ballistic missiles and missile factories, which they and other countries in the region see as threats and which Iran considers a vital deterrent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But such a strike would not be for Israel to mount, analysts said. It would be up to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, for Israel, the likely gains from any intervention in Iran are far outweighed by the risks of intervening, experts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most of the options are bad for Israel,” said Danny Citrinowicz, a former Iran expert for Israeli military intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Israel, the biggest risk is that its actions give credence to the Iranian government’s assertion that foreign provocateurs are behind these protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel is “doing the utmost to be seen as looking at events from the outside,” Mr. Citrinowicz said, lest Iran use evidence of any overt Israeli actions to justify the use of force against protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an obscure Israeli government minister told a radio interviewer that the country had operatives in Iran “right now,” Mr. Netanyahu ordered officials to stop giving interviews on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also the risk of blowback directly against Israel at a time when it already has troops in Gaza, the Israeli-occupied West Bank, Syria and Lebanon, and is still replenishing its stocks of defensive munitions after two years of fending off attacks from multiple countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any Israeli intervention detected by Iran could increase the likelihood of a serious miscalculation by Tehran, experts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Iran believes Israel is building up to an attack, it could mount a pre-emptive strike against Israel. Israel’s air force could be expected to respond with force, given how poorly Iran’s air defenses performed in the June war. But experts say it would make little sense to put Israeli citizens at risk if such an intervention has little chance of toppling the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israeli national-security experts spoke with great respect for U.S. military capabilities to threaten the Iranian government. But they also said that a limited American action, like a symbolic strike on a few targets, could be counterproductive, especially if the United States were to follow up by agreeing to new talks with Iran on its nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Shine said that would amount to a betrayal of the Iranian protesters, whom Mr. Trump has repeatedly encouraged, unless the United States imposed preconditions that aided the protesters, like restoring internet service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Ms. Shine said, negotiations would raise the possibility that Iran could reach an agreement with the United States that lifts economic sanctions on Tehran but — like the Obama administration’s nuclear deal with Iran, which Mr. Netanyahu adamantly opposed — doesn’t restrict its ballistic-missile arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was always for an agreement,” Ms. Shine said. “But this regime is so bad, and what they’re doing now is so bad that you ask yourself if it’s not time to do everything you can to see that it collapses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reza Pahlavi, the exiled son of the last shah of Iran, has put himself forward as a future leader of Iran. Mr. Netanyahu welcomed him to Israel in 2023, and some ministers in his government have promoted Mr. Pahlavi online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some demonstrators in Iran appear to be rallying around him, judging from videos that show crowds raising the flag flown by his father’s monarchy and chanting, “Long live the shah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Israeli national security experts were skeptical of Mr. Pahlavi’s ability to rally significant Iranian support, saying he lacked experience, charisma and a meaningful base inside the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Citrinowicz, the former Israeli military analyst, said it was a mistake for Mr. Pahlavi to meet with Mr. Netanyahu and for Israeli officials to continue to amplify him because it associates the idea of regime change with Israel. That risks alienating some potential demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also little chance of Mr. Pahlavi returning to Iran, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most Iranians,” he said, “don’t want to replace one dictator with another.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/israel-iran-protests-netanyahu.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:24:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘We Came Here to Vote’: Ugandans Go to Polls Despite Major Delays</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/africa/uganda-election-museveni.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-uganda-elections-1-pjhg/15int-uganda-elections-1-pjhg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ugandans headed to the polls on Thursday for an election in which President Yoweri Museveni, 81, is expected to extend his rule of nearly four decades in the east African nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vote is taking place against the backdrop of an internet blackout imposed by the authorities. Technical problems with the biometric voting machines introduced in recent weeks in a bid to prevent voting fraud have caused widespread disruptions at polling places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By midmorning, few people had cast their ballots, with lines forming at polling stations in the capital, Kampala, and elsewhere. “I am ready to wait,” said Ssenyondwa Martha, who said she had arrived at her polling station in Kampala around sunrise. “We came here to vote.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electoral commission announced on Thursday that the country’s more than 50,000 polling stations would revert to paper verification for voter identities for the rest of the day, according to the spokesman, Julius Mucunguzi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven candidates are contesting the election, but Mr. Museveni’s main challenger is Bobi Wine, the former pop star whose real name is Robert Kyagulanyi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing on the support of Uganda’s young voters, Mr. Wine’s campaign rattled the ruling National Resistance Movement during the last election in 2021. In an interview on Monday, Mr. Wine acknowledged that recent defections had weakened his campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We code-named this a ‘protest vote,’” he said. “If the vote is rigged, we shall call for protests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to journalists after voting near his home in rural western Uganda on Thursday, Mr. Museveni accused the opposition of fraudulently obtaining millions of extra votes during the previous election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any opposition candidate in Uganda must contend with the overwhelming financial and political advantages of a ruling party that is deeply embedded in the state machinery. The entire electoral commission is selected by the president, who has been in power for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one example of the ruling party’s dominance, Kampala has for weeks been plastered with posters promoting Mr. Museveni and his party’s candidates for Parliament. The posters, in the party’s color yellow, dwarf the number of posters from Mr. Wine’s National Unity Platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an apparent bid to forestall any opposition demonstrations, the authorities cut the internet nationwide on Tuesday, justifying the decision on the grounds that it would stop the weaponization of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan government has been accused of weakening civil society groups over the years, with the country’s bureau for nongovernmental organizations closing several such groups in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Center for Constitutional Governance said on Tuesday that it had received a letter from the government accusing it of engaging “in activities which are prejudicial to the security and laws of Uganda,” and that it was being forced to close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Uganda Law Society condemned the decision. “This action, taken just days before the general election, is not coincidental,” the society said, calling it an effort to silence civil society and an “attack the public’s right to accountability.” The Center for Constitutional Governance monitors the health of the country’s democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United Nations human rights agency said Wednesday that the internet blackout and suspension of civil society groups were “deeply worrying,” with Amnesty International calling for the immediate lifting of the internet restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Museveni has campaigned on the slogan “Protecting the Gains” made since he fought his way to power as the head of a rebellion in 1986. He said at his final campaign on Tuesday that the economy had grown 17-fold during his tenure and now exports products such as milk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Making sure that all Ugandans benefit from the country’s economic gains was a priority for his next term, he said. “Love Uganda. Why? Because you need it for your own good,” Mr. Museveni told journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Uganda’s economy lags behind its eastern neighbor Kenya, the country is a diplomatic powerhouse in the region and the largest contributor to a peacekeeping force in Somalia. Ugandan troops are also stationed in the Democratic Republic of Congo and in South Sudan, where they support the president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ugandan government, like many others in Africa, has been at pains to manage its relationship with the Trump administration. The State Department said on Wednesday that it would suspend the processing of immigrant visas for people from 75 countries, including Uganda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Election results are expected to be announced over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/africa/uganda-election-museveni.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 11:20:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Squished Between Chairs’ on a Train: How Some Passengers Survived a Crane Collapse</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/asia/thailand-train-crane-survivors.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15int-thailand-train-01-ljwf-promo/15int-thailand-train-01-ljwf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The little boy was excited to be taking off on a trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had been on a train all Wednesday morning, heading east from the Bangkok suburbs. He had been looking at the scenery through the window and laid his head on the tray table to nap. Then there was a loud boom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saitee Katpia, his grandmother, was sitting next to him at a window seat. She said that she lost consciousness briefly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she came to, she said that it felt like the train car was being crushed. Her head was bleeding. The boy, 6, was on the floor and squeezed in by a chair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He kept saying ‘my leg hurts, my leg hurts,’” Ms. Saitee said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, she mustered the strength to pull him out and guided him out the train car, which had derailed and had a split carved into it. On her way to safety, she heard a man cry out for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I could not help him,” she said from a hospital bed on Thursday, with at least 10 stitches on her face. “He was a big guy and — me, myself — I had blood dripping on my face.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A crane had fallen on the passenger train in northeastern Nakhon Ratchasima Province on Wednesday. At least 32 people were killed and dozens of others were injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 24 hours later on Thursday, another crane collapsed, this time on an expressway in Samut Sakhon Province on the southwestern outskirts of Bangkok, killing at least two people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The episodes have raised urgent questions about construction safety in Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both sites had the same contractor, a firm called Italian-Thai Development. It had already come under scrutiny after the collapse of a building in Bangkok last year that resulted in more than 90 deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The firm said that it would take “full responsibility” for the train accident on Wednesday and “provide full compensation and medical care” to the families of the victims and the injured. It also said it would support the local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its representatives were not reachable on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of the tragedy on Wednesday, Prime Minister Anutin Charnvirakul called for a law to permanently blacklist companies with repeated fatal accidents from bidding on any government projects. One of his deputies, Phipat Ratchakitprakarn, said the government was moving to halt all aboveground construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special Express Train No. 21, a three-car train, was carrying about 200 people between Bangkok and the eastern city of Ubon Ratchathani on Wednesday. On parts of the route, an elevated high-speed railway is being constructed, with funding from Beijing. China envisions the line connecting it with Southeast Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Thai authorities said that construction operations should not have been running while the passenger train was passing through the area. They said the crane fell on two cars, causing the train to derail and catch fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all of the victims have been identified yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surachart Uintarakari said that his sister and brother-in-law, who were sitting next to each other, were among them. Rescuers found a necklace that their children identified as belonging to their mother, but DNA testing is yet to be completed, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The bodies are totally burned,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little after 9 a.m. Wednesday, the train was about halfway through its voyage, passing by Thanon Kot Village.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There, Penporn Pumjantuek was working at her family’s food stall — whipping up an order of Thai basil stir fry served with steamed rice and a fried egg — when she heard a loud crash and metal screeching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the stall, she saw a mangled passenger train car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Penporn said she helped about 20 passengers come out through a split in the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A resident, Somjai Duangchang, reached another car that had derailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I broke the glass. The first thing I saw was dead passengers,” Mr. Somjai said. “Chairs squeezed the passengers and people were stuck, squished between chairs.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he pushed chairs to free a woman and her baby, eventually helping about a handful of people out of the car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in a few minutes, a fire erupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I saw some people were still alive but we couldn’t help them,” Ms. Penporn said, adding that they were stuck under pieces of metal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Saitee, the grandmother, initially thought the train had crashed. It was only when she squeezed out of the car and was outside did she realize that a crane had fallen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her grandson, she said, suffered shattered bones in his legs and was being treated at a hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suchatvee Suwansawat, a former president of the Council of Engineers Thailand, said that the machinery that had collapsed was a launching crane that is used to position girders. He thought the cause was human error, while also questioning the quality of the crane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadly accidents on Wednesday and Thursday were among thousands across Thailand that have killed hundreds of people. The country ranks 13th globally in occupational fatalities, recording 5.3 fatalities per 100,000 workers, according to the International Labor Organization, citing the most recently reported data from 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no independent central body, like the National Transportation Safety Board in the United States, to investigate accidents transparently. So once an accident moves out of the news cycle, the government and the construction companies rarely make any of these findings public. Researchers have found that companies often pay “grease money” to inspectors to overlook safety violations or to fast-track permits without proper engineering audits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surachet Pravinvongvuth, an opposition politician in Parliament, has been an outspoken proponent of Thailand’s need for workplace safety reform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There must be due process to pin a charge on those big construction companies, but it won’t be easy,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Surachart, who is waiting for DNA testing results for the victims, questioned whether contractors adhered to any safety standards.He added of contractors, “Accidents happen repeatedly but they keep getting hired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sui-Lee Wee and Kittiphum Sringammuang contributed reporting from Bangkok.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/asia/thailand-train-crane-survivors.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 09:30:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Says It Will Not Execute Protester Amid International Outcry</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/iran-protests-erfan-soltani-execution.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15Iran-protests-01-lckz/15Iran-protests-01-lckz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s judiciary said on Thursday that it had not issued a death sentence for Erfan Soltani, a protester whose execution had been widely reported as imminent and drawn intense international attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comments were reported by Iran’s state broadcaster, and were published on social media. President Trump said on Wednesday that he had been told the execution of protesters would not go ahead, and that the killing in Iran had stopped, without offering further details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is good news,” Mr. Trump said on Thursday on social media, citing an unspecified Fox News report that said an unnamed Iranian protester and others would not be sentenced to death. “Hopefully, it will continue!” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran and the region remain on edge, however, after Mr. Trump said in recent days that he would intervene to protect protesters. On Thursday, Iranian state media reported that the airspace over the country had reopened hours after it was restricted for most flights, a move that had fueled fears of a potential U.S.-Iran military confrontation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protester, Mr. Soltani, 26, was sentenced to death just days after he was arrested in early January, his family and human rights groups had said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Islamic Republic of Iran Broadcasting, or IRIB, said on social media that the judiciary had said that Mr. Soltani faced “charges of assembly and collusion against national security and propaganda against the system.” It added that the death penalty does not exist in Iranian law for those offenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the charges are confirmed by the prosecutor’s office and a legal verdict is issued by a competent court, the punishment provided for by law will be imprisonment,” the state broadcaster’s post said. Mr. Soltani was being held at the Central Prison of Karaj, west of the capital Tehran, it added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday night, Iran’s foreign minister, Abbas Araghchi, denied that Iran intended to execute protesters, calling the claim part of a misinformation campaign by outside elements designed to provoke Mr. Trump into taking action against his country. In an interview on Fox News, Mr. Araghchi added that he had not heard of plans to hang demonstrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than two weeks, the Iranian authorities have mounted a sweeping crackdown on protests, deploying a range of heavy-handed tactics in an effort to suppress some of the largest demonstrations the country’s clerical authoritarian rulers have faced since taking power nearly half a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unrest erupted in late December, when merchants and shopkeepers in Tehran’s markets and bazaars protested in response to the sharp collapse of the Iranian rial, soaring inflation and worsening economic conditions. Iran’s economy has been battered by crippling American and European sanctions and a 12-day war with Israel last year, as well as years of graft and mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests quickly spread nationwide as demonstrators voiced broader discontent with the government. The authorities imposed an internet blackout, restricting the flow of information and making it difficult to track where protests have been occurring in recent days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has urged protesters to continue demonstrating, and has been exploring how to respond, including possible military strikes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s chief justice, Gholam-Hossein Mohseni-Ejei, said on Thursday that the prosecution of “rioters” — a term officials have used to refer to the protesters — would be carried out swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Those elements who were connected to foreign intelligence services and their handlers, and who provided direction to rioters and terrorists either on the ground or from outside, are among the top priorities for prosecution and punishment,” Mr. Mohseni-Ejei was quoted by the state broadcaster as saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, the U.S. military began evacuating an unspecified number of nonessential personnel from Al Udeid Air Base in Qatar because of the rising tensions, according to two American military officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters. Iran fired missiles at the base in June, after the United States attacked its nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiana Hayeri, Sanam Mahoozi and Leily Nikounazar contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/15/world/middleeast/iran-protests-erfan-soltani-execution.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 12:22:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ex-South Korean Leader Gets Prison Term in First Ruling Over Martial Law</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/asia/skorea-yoon-prison-martial-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-skorea-yoon-lbvj/16int-skorea-yoon-lbvj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Korea’s impeached and ousted former president, Yoon Suk Yeol, was sentenced to ​five years in prison on Friday on charges of fabricating an official document in an attempt to justify his short-lived imposition of martial law in late 2024 and illegally using his bodyguards to ​prevent his arrest on insurrection charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentence on Friday from a three-judge panel at the Seoul Central District Court was the first in ​eight separate court trials stemming from his ill-fated martial law declaration. The ruling on the most consequential charge — insurrection — is scheduled to be delivered by a different panel of judges on Feb. 19. Prosecutors ​in that case have sought the death penalty for Mr. Yoon​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their ruling on Friday, the judges convicted Mr. Yoon of obstructing justice when he ordered his presidential secret service agents to block law enforcement officials from serving a court-issued warrant to detain him on insurrection charges last January. The officials eventually detained him ​several days later on their second attempt to serve the warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He turned ​his Presidential Security Service​, trained to be loyal to the country, into a de facto private army for his personal safety and interests,” presiding judge Baek Dae-hyun said in the ruling on Friday, which was nationally televised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon was also convicted of abusing his power when he failed to invite some of his cabinet members to a cabinet meeting on the night of Dec. 3, 2024, denying them their right to review his plan for martial law before​ he declared it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Dissident’s Next Act: Kwon Pyong recounted for the first time the series of gambles that got him out of China by jet ski, and almost a year later, out of South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standoff With Doctors: Doctors at medical facilities across South Korea walked off the job in a one-day strike on June 18, expanding a months-old protest against the government’s health care policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Impeachment Threat: President Yoon Suk Yeol has been accused of intervening in an inquiry into the accidental death of a South Korean marine during a peacetime search and rescue operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliament Election: South Koreans delivered a stinging defeat to Yoon and his party, giving the opposition one of its biggest electoral victories in recent decades and pushing Yoon to the verge of being a lame duck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon’s original martial law decree was not endorsed with signatures from his cabinet members. On Friday, he was convicted of fabricating a document to make it look as if ​his martial law plan had been reviewed and endorsed by cabinet members. He was also found guilty of ordering the removal of data from government-issued secure phones of his collaborators in martial law, ​such as military generals, in order to obstruct investigators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M​r. Yoon’s acts amounted to an abuse of his presidential power and a “grave crime,” Judge Baek said​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M​r. Yoon, who appeared at the courtroom on Friday, exited after the ruling without comment. He and his lawyers have a week to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Mr. Yoon was unpopular throughout his two and a half years in office​. He governed a deeply polarized country, constantly clashing with the majority opposition over ​his policies and scandals involving his wife. The tensions culminated when he declared martial law on Dec. 3, 2024. He banned all political activities and sent troops to take over the opposition-controlled National Assembly, which he called a “monster” and “den of criminals” that he said “paralyzed” his administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his martial law decree lasted only six hours. The legislature voted it down while citizens held back troops to prevent them from raiding its main voting hall. ​When the Assembly impeached him, suspending him from office, Mr. Yoon holed up in his hillside presidential residence in central Seoul​, vowing to “fight to the end​.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​He repeatedly ignored summons from investigators to face questioning for insurrection charges.​ When they sought to detain him last January, he refused to surrender. His ​bodyguards built barricades of buses and formed human chains to repel investigators and police officers, raising fears of a clash.​ Mr. Yoon insisted that the officials had no right to detain him because he said his call for martial law had been legal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when the investigators visited the compound again several days later in overwhelming numbers could they​ serve the warrant and detain ​him. Mr. Yoon was the first sitting president of South Korea to be arrested in a criminal investigation. He was later formally removed from office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon’s martial law, although short-lived, threatened decades of hard-won democracy in South Korea and exposed deep fractures in its politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, South Korea elected a new president, Lee Jae Myung, one of the political leaders whom prosecutors said Mr. Yoon had planned to arrest under his martial law. Small groups of die-hard supporters of the ousted leader still hold rallies in Seoul, calling his impeachment invalid and chanting, in English, “Yoon again!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his jail cell and through his lawyers, Mr. Yoon continues to argue that he declared martial law to “wake” citizens up to the danger posed by “anti-state forces” among the political left. He has called special prosecutors who indicted him “a pack of wolves” controlled by “dark forces.” His old People Power Party remains mired in internal fighting between those who call for disowning him and those who remain sympathetic toward him. The party planned to change its name to make a fresh start.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/asia/skorea-yoon-prison-martial-law.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 22:47:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada Breaks With U.S. to Slash Tariffs on Some Chinese Electric Vehicles</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/canada/canada-slash-tariffs-chinese-evs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-china-canada-tgfz/16int-china-canada-tgfz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada will lower tariffs on some Chinese electric vehicles and China will do the same for Canadian canola products, a major shift in policy that was announced on Friday during a landmark state visit by Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney announced that Canada will allow up to 49,000 Chinese electric vehicles into the Canadian market under a preferential tariff rate of 6.1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, at the behest of the Biden administration, Canada imposed a 100 percent tariff on Chinese electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the new tariff changes are modest, they signal an important break with the United States as Canada seeks to urgently diversify its trading partners and reduce its reliance on the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Donald J. Trump has imposed on tariffs on some key Canadian exports like lumber, steel and autos. He has also threatened Canadian sovereignty, a shift Mr. Carney has described as a “rupture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney also announced on Friday that China would make a “considerable investment into Canada’s auto-sector” within the next three years as part of the agreement to lower tariffs on electric vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exchange, Mr. Carney said that China will lower tariffs on Canadian canola seed to a combined rate of approximately 15 percent, down from about 85 percent, offering fast relief to a major Canadian agricultural sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement came just after Mr. Carney met with President Xi Jinping of China in Beijing Friday, during a three-day state visit that both leaders hailed as a significant reboot in their nations’ previously frosty relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Xi and I are announcing that Canada and China are forging a new strategic partnership,” Mr. Carney said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/canada/canada-slash-tariffs-chinese-evs.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:36:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Tale of Two Meetings: Trump Chooses Oil Over Democracy</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/americas/venezuela-trump-machado-rodriguez.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-venezuela-analysis-whgv/16int-venezuela-analysis-whgv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One has U.S. sanctions imposed on her for undermining democracy. The other just won the Nobel Peace Prize. Both want to lead Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump made clear this week which one he preferred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delcy Rodríguez — the sanctioned vice president of the ousted autocrat Nicolás Maduro — is “a terrific person” with whom “we’re getting along very well,” Mr. Trump said Wednesday after what he described as a “great conversation” with Ms. Rodríguez, whom he has backed as Venezuela’s interim president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day later, he had lunch with María Corina Machado — leader of the Venezuelan opposition — and took the medal she was awarded for the Nobel Peace Prize, which he had repeatedly said he deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During their meeting, the White House press secretary, Karoline Leavitt, told reporters that “based on realities on the ground,” Mr. Trump believed Ms. Machado lacked the respect and support to be Venezuela’s leader. That echoed his previous comments, despite signs of Ms. Machado’s broad approval in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for Ms. Rodríguez? She has “been extremely cooperative” and agreed to share Venezuela’s oil with the United States, Ms. Leavitt said, so “the president likes what he’s seeing and will expect that cooperation to continue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s now-clear endorsement of a Maduro loyalist over a crusader for democracy supports the notion that his goal in Venezuela appears to be first about creating a stable, allied source of oil — and then maybe, if and when the time comes, a democratic transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He is also committed to hopefully seeing elections in Venezuela one day,” Ms. Leavitt said Thursday. “But I don’t have an updated timetable for you today.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Machado said the time was now. “I told him we’re ready to move forward quickly and effectively toward a transition to democracy,” she said on Thursday in a 1,000-word news release about her visit to Washington. She added that she had told Mr. Trump about human-rights abuses committed under Mr. Maduro and Ms. Rodríguez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s 48-word social media post about the meeting thanked Ms. Machado for giving him “her Nobel Peace Prize for the work I have done.” He added it was “such a wonderful gesture of mutual respect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The Nobel Institute again shared a public reminder on Thursday that the 7-ounce gold medal “can change owners, but the title of a Nobel Peace Prize laureate cannot.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Machado later told Fox News that she had given Mr. Trump the medal on behalf of the Venezuelan people “because he deserves it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the same time, in Venezuela, Ms. Rodríguez was delivering her first State of the Union address — and skewering the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a stain on our relations,” she told the National Assembly. “They crossed the red line.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We know they are a lethal nuclear power,” she added. “We’ve seen their record over the history of humanity, and we’re not afraid to confront them diplomatically.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also appeared to be referring to Ms. Machado when she made a swipe at opposition figures “who competed to see who could grovel the most,” while saying that if she had to go to Washington, “I will do so standing tall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language fit with years of attacks against the United States by Mr. Maduro and his government. Watching only Venezuelan state television in recent days could make one think that Ms. Rodríguez was bent on confronting Mr. Trump. But in the background, there have been clear signs of cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez’s government has been opening up Venezuela’s oil to U.S. interests, released more than 80 political prisoners and began exploring the reopening of its embassy in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They have thus far met all of the demands,” Ms. Leavitt said Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, hundreds of political dissidents remain imprisoned, and Venezuelans report increased repression in the country, including armed men at checkpoints who search residents’ phones for signs of opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Mr. Maduro’s capture, some White House officials, as well as a C.I.A. analysis, argued that Ms. Machado and her allies would struggle to consolidate control of Venezuela if installed as its leaders. Ms. Rodríguez, they argued, represented the most stable near-term option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Secretary of State Marco Rubio described a threefold plan for Venezuela. “Step one is the stabilization of the country,” he said. “We don’t want it descending into chaos.” The next steps involved securing Venezuela’s oil, followed by amnesty for the opposition. “Some of this will overlap,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly discussed Venezuela’s oil — and has hardly ever mentioned a democratic transition. On Wednesday, in a post about his call with Ms. Rodríguez, he said they had discussed “Oil, Minerals, Trade and, of course, National Security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will rebuild it in a very profitable way,” he told The New York Times last week, after saying that he envisioned the United States controlling Venezuela for “much longer” than a year. “And we’re going to be taking oil.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked about elections, he repeatedly deflected. “I love democracy,” he said at one point. “I’m a big fan.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/americas/venezuela-trump-machado-rodriguez.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:02:31 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>