<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 02:53:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Kennedy Plan to Test a Vaccine in West African Babies Is Blocked</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/health/hepatitis-b-vaccine-africa-study.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/xx-bissau-vaccine-01-pfcz/xx-bissau-vaccine-01-pfcz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The West African nation of Guinea-Bissau has suspended a controversial U.S.-funded study of the hepatitis B vaccine in infants there after an outcry from public health researchers over the ethics of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention approved a $1.6 million grant for the study last month, days after the health secretary, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., lifted the agency’s longstanding recommendation to give the vaccine to all infants at birth. Although the World Health Organization also recommends giving the shot at birth, Mr. Kennedy said more research was needed about the effects of a birth dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, which was to be carried out by Danish researchers, swiftly became the subject of furor in the public health world, with researchers in Africa and the United States saying that it violated key tenets of ethical science. A Trump administration health official said the study had been paused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International agreements on medical research in humans require researchers to offer the globally accepted standard of care (in this case, vaccination at birth) to any participant in a clinical trial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this study, half of the 14,000 infants studied were not going to be given the vaccine until they were six weeks old. Researchers were not going to screen pregnant women for hepatitis B — a basic step that would protect the babies of infected women, who could be vaccinated at birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Hilliard, a spokeswoman for the Department of Health and Human Services, which oversees the C.D.C., said the goal of the research had been to answer questions about the effects of the hepatitis B vaccine. The study design was “based on the highest scientific and ethical standards,” she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One in five people in Guinea-Bissau lives with hepatitis B, a virus that can cause severe liver damage and cancer, and each year thousands of infants there are exposed to the virus at birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country currently vaccinates infants against hepatitis B at six weeks of age, as part of routine immunization. The government plans to introduce birth-dose vaccination, which is more expensive, in 2028.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, the Danish researchers intended to take advantage of the fact that Guinea-Bissau, one of the world’s least developed countries, is not yet able to follow the global standard. They planned to vaccinate some children at birth, and assess them over time compared with children who got the six-week dose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This takes us back to bad research practices with the argument being that the standard of care is not available in that particular environment,” said Dr. Boghuma Titanji, an infectious diseases physician at Emory University. “Researchers are exploiting a scarcity situation to basically ram through this unethical study.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birth-dose vaccination for hepatitis B prevents mother-to-child transmission of the virus. Infants infected at birth have a significantly higher risk of developing chronic liver disease as adults, and many die in their 30s or 40s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Quinhin Nantote, Guinea-Bissau’s minister of public health, said the study had not received proper ethical approval, and his office has suspended it. He said the government would consider if and how the study could proceed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There has not been sufficient review to take a final decision on this study,” he said. “We don’t have the necessary input from the ethical committee.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The guiding principle of my work is ‘go there.’ I want to hear directly from the people who are affected by disease, or lack of access to a new drug. I’ve been writing about global health for 30 years and have reported from more than 80 countries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many public health leaders say the study poses a question that has already been overwhelmingly answered by science: The birth dose of the vaccine prevents suffering and premature death. Given this evidence, this study, in its goal and its design, is problematic, said Dr. Jeanne Marrazzo, chief executive officer of the Infectious Diseases Society of America and the former top vaccine official for the National Institutes of Health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Essentially, you’re saying that lives of people in those settings don’t deserve the best interventions that we have available in countries with a different standard of care,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other vaccine experts have raised different concerns with the study, which has additional private funding. It is designed to look for effects from the hepatitis B vaccine that include changes in neurological development and atopic dermatitis, a skin condition, but not at whether African children whose vaccines were delayed were more likely to carry hepatitis B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study grant was awarded to a team from the University of Southern Denmark whose work has been widely criticized by other researchers. Mr. Kennedy cited their work when he decided to cut off vaccine aid for the developing world, although the team has found a mix of benefits and harms that they attribute to vaccines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Christine Stabell Benn, the principal investigator on the Danish team, said the study had been approved by the relevant authorities in Guinea-Bissau and had met her university’s requirements for research ethics oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, an official with the Guinea-Bissau National Health Research Ethics Committee, who did not want to be named, citing the lack of authority to give interviews, told The New York Times that the study had been reviewed and approved in the fourth quarter of 2025, before the coup and change in government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Commodore Nanote, the health minister, told reporters in a press briefing on Thursday that he was not certain whether the ethics committee had in fact reviewed the study. “We have no evidence of any meeting they held, we don’t even have minutes of a negotiated approval,” he said. “We believe that they did not hold a meeting, did not gather and did not address the issue.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guinea-Bissau consistently ranks among the 10 least-developed nations in the world, with a minimal health system — the country does not have a single oncologist or M.R.I. machine, for example. A military coup in November has further weakened fragile state institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gavi, the international organization that helps low-income countries purchase vaccines, began to assist countries in introducing birth-dose hepatitis B vaccination last year. (Mr. Kennedy ended U.S. funding to Gavi, significantly constraining its finances. Congress has proposed restoring funding in the spending bill now under consideration.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Birth-dose vaccines are more expensive because they can be harder to deliver (roughly half of women in the country give birth at home), and refrigeration and other infrastructure has to be set up in labor wards to preserve them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason that children in Guinea-Bissau are not getting the birth dose presently is not because there is uncertainty about the vaccine. It’s because they’re unable to implement their policy for resource-related reasons,” said Dr. Keymanthri Moodley, an emeritus professor of bioethics at Stellenbosch University in South Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said the study was reminiscent of controversy in the 1990s about a C.D.C.-funded clinical trial in East and Southern Africa that tested a drug that blocked pregnant women with H.I.V. from transmitting the virus to their babies. Women in one part of the trial received a placebo — and as a result, many babies were infected with the then-fatal illness. The researchers defended the trial by saying that since the drug was not available in the countries where they tested the intervention, no one was worse off than they would have been without the research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that controversy, changes were made to the Declaration of Helsinki, an international agreement that sets out the terms of ethical medical research, to require that research participants in the control group receive the “best proven” intervention. In the case of the Guinea-Bissau trial, that would be the birth-dose vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health officials in Guinea-Bissau expressed frustration with the study as an example of foreign-funded research that is not well communicated to the population who will be studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a huge lack of information regarding this health testing, or any health experiments,” Cadija Mané, a former senior official in the Health Ministry, said. “There needs to be a better flow of information.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ricci Shryock contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/health/hepatitis-b-vaccine-africa-study.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:50:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nazis, Soviets and Trump: America’s Fixation With Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/greenland-trump-cold-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/22dc-greenland-coldwar-01-zbgk/22dc-greenland-coldwar-01-zbgk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last Nazis on Greenland were captured in October 1944, when American soldiers raided a hidden German weather station on the island’s desolate west coast and took dozens of prisoners. Within a year, Germany would be defeated and World War II would be over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But 80 years of both tension and cooperation between Denmark and the United States over Greenland was just beginning — culminating in President Trump’s current obsession with acquiring the Arctic island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the story begins with World War II, it was shaped by the Cold War that followed, in which the United States transformed barren Greenland into a major military asset, populating it with air bases, towering radar sites and even a never-completed underground bunker complex meant to house nuclear missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was all possible under an agreement with Denmark that granted the United States nearly unlimited military freedom on the island, one that remains in force today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We did it before, we can do it again,” said Daniel Fried, a former senior State Department official who worked on Soviet issues in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether Mr. Trump understands this history has been a mystery as European leaders try to convince him to drop his insistence on owning the island. Mr. Trump said on Wednesday that a “framework” for a deal had been reached, but the details remained murky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an era before military air power, before Mr. Trump was even born, American military planners gave Greenland little thought. But when Germany invaded and occupied Denmark in 1940, they realized that the island, then a Danish colony sparsely populated by mainly Inuit people, was vulnerable to Nazi control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With airfields perilously close to America’s east coast, important mineral reserves and an ideal location to track weather that shaped battle conditions in Europe, Greenland’s defense was considered essential to the United States. It was an idea that would persist for decades before fading briefly after the Cold War and returning with a vengeance in the Trump era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s king had welcomed the American force and approved a written agreement granting the broad military latitude on the island, as long as a threat existed, without giving up any Danish sovereignty. With Germany vanquished and the war over, however, his country was ready to bid the Americans farewell. “Danish public opinion was expecting a return to full control of Greenland,” explained a study of the matter by the Danish Institute of Public Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington had other ideas. The advent of long-range bombers had created a new sense of vulnerability just as the Soviet Union was emerging as a new threat to the United States. Greenland happened to lie along the most direct flight path to the Eastern United States from Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Greenland’s 800,000 square miles make it the world’s largest island and stationary aircraft carrier,” Time magazine wrote in January 1947. It “would be invaluable, in either conventional or push-button war, as an advance radar outpost,” and a forward position for future rocket-launching sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Americans had no intention of leaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bad news was delivered in December 1946 by the U.S. secretary of state, James F. Byrnes. During a meeting at the Waldorf Astoria hotel in New York, Mr. Byrnes explained to his Danish counterpart, Gustav Rasmussen, that Greenland had become “vital to the defense of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the American military’s presence could be extended, Mr. Byrnes said, he had a better idea: Denmark should simply sell Greenland to America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea “seemed to come as a shock” to Mr. Rasmussen, who accurately predicted that his government would reject the idea, according to another State Department memo. But unlike the current blowup, the matter was handled “quietly” by both sides, noted Heather Conley, a nonresident senior fellow at the American Enterprise Institute who specializes in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Truman administration did not push, partly for fear that Moscow would claim that the United States had stolen land from a European ally. As the Soviet threat grew more vivid in Europe, Denmark became more willing to let American troops stay in Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1951, the United States and Denmark reached an agreement “uniting their efforts for collective defense” under the auspices of the newly formed North Atlantic Treaty Organization. While stressing Denmark’s continued sovereignty over the island, the agreement granted the United States broad freedom to “construct, install, maintain and operate facilities and equipment” and to “station and house personnel,” along with other rights related to military activity. That included deepening harbors and even maintaining postal facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement did not include an expiration date, and Denmark has never asserted one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the agreement’s few limitations was to delineate specific “defense areas” within which the United States could operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the deal in hand, and freshly alarmed by a Soviet-backed communist offensive in Korea, the U.S. military quickly went to work. In a secret crash project, military engineers working around the clock in 24-hour Arctic daylight built a major air base at Thule in northwest Greenland. Manned by thousands of American personnel, the base’s 10,000-foot runway would serve as a launching point for strategic bombers and spy planes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than a dozen military bases and radar and weather monitoring stations eventually opened across the island. A 1,240-foot tower was erected at Thule for long wave transmissions to eastern Canada. In 1959, the United States started Project Ice Worm, another secret endeavor that envisioned a giant complex of bunkers, dozens of feet underground, meant to house nuclear missiles that could survive a Soviet first strike. (The project was deemed unfeasible and abandoned after several years.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as missile technology improved, the United States established more systems meant to provide early warning for a Soviet attack. While they were considered invaluable, the systems were far from foolproof: In October 1960, one U.S. radar system detected a massive Soviet missile launch with near certainty. It turned out that the system had spotted the moon rising over Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark raised few objections, satisfied that its sovereignty over Greenland remained protected. To underscore the point, a Danish flag flew alongside the American one at Thule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arrangement was tested in January 1968, when a U.S. B-52 bomber carrying four hydrogen bombs crashed while trying to make an emergency landing at Thule. The bomber had been part of an “airborne alert” program run by the U.S. Strategic Air Command, which kept several nuclear-armed bombers airborne 24 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bombs were incinerated on impact in conventional explosions, but left radioactive traces even after an arduous cleanup. Some Danish politicians expressed outrage that the United States had brought nuclear weapons to the island, although American officials insisted that such weapons were implicitly covered by the 1951 agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the peak of the United States’ military presence in Greenland during the Cold War, some 10,000 U.S. personnel were stationed on the island. But after the Soviet Union collapsed in 1991, the cost of a large footprint on an Arctic island made little sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most U.S. installations on Greenland were closed over the next decade, with U.S. activity consolidating at Thule, whose name was changed in 2023 to Pituffik in an acknowledgment of a former Inuit settlement there. It is now a U.S. Space Force base, staffed by about 150 people who manage early warning radar and satellite communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump argues that Greenland is once again vital to American security, and many national security experts agree. They point to growing Arctic competition with Russia and China over natural resources and shipping lanes as melting ice reshapes the region. Mr. Trump also says that Greenland is crucial to the ambitious “Golden Dome” missile defense system he hopes to build in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump has never made clear why he must control Greenland to serve these needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Conley of the American Enterprise Institute said that a solution, if there were one, might mirror the events of the early Cold War. Having been denied ownership of the island, Mr. Trump appears to be considering an enhanced U.S. military presence on Greenland that is part of a new NATO mission to defend the island. “That’s the right approach,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Fried agreed, but said he wished the process could have played out quietly, the way it did nearly a century ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Trump could have achieved this without all the drama,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/22/us/politics/greenland-trump-cold-war.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 06:54:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What’s It Like to Climb a Skyscraper?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23xp-climbing-top/23xp-climbing-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Goodwin’s left shoulder felt like it was on fire and his right hand was covered in blisters by the time he finished climbing one side of Toronto’s CN Tower in 1986. Back then, it was the tallest structure in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was terrified,” he said, recalling the day he reached the base of the tower’s observation deck, 1,100 feet above a crowd of onlookers and with no rope, harness or other safety equipment. “Every move had to be perfect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Alex Honnold, a rock climber who was the subject of the Oscar-winning documentary “Free Solo,” will attempt to get everything right when he climbs Taipei 101, a 1,667-foot-tall skyscraper in Taiwan, without a rope. With Netflix livestreaming the climb, this niche pursuit has never received such global publicity before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaling skyscrapers is not like rock climbing or going up smaller buildings. Those in the club of just a dozen or so known skyscraper climbers worldwide say it has unique and intense physical and mental demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a largely underground sport because it is usually illegal. Alain Robert, a Frenchman who has scaled some 200 buildings since the 1990s, mostly with his bare hands, said that he has been arrested more than 170 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like you’re literally in a movie,” Mr. Robert said, with “cops that are trying to catch the bad guy climbing the building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious risks make it rare for someone to obtain permission to climb a tall building like Mr. Honnold did. “I’ve never been willing to get arrested,” the 40-year-old said in a recent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the serene natural landscape surrounding climbers on routes like El Capitan in Yosemite National Park, which Mr. Honnold scaled in 2017, skyscraper climbers must overcome urban noise, crowds and, occasionally, police officers determined to arrest them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like King Kong in the city,” said Titouan Leduc, 24, a French climber who scaled Warsaw’s Varso Tower, the tallest skyscraper in the European Union, last year. He was briefly arrested after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who have climbed skyscrapers say their bodies face different demands compared with rock climbing. According to Mr. Goodwin, 70, it mainly comes down to repetitiveness versus variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a rock face, each move presents a new puzzle: climbers’ hands search for different holds — crimps, jugs, slopers — and they constantly adapt their bodies. But along the side of a building, climbers repeat the same few movements hundreds of times to pass over dozens of stories of windows, steel bars and concrete gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can do a pull-up and think it’s not all too bad, but try doing 20, 50, 100,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Doing the same kind of move over and over and over — it can really tax your muscles and fingers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over decades, Mr. Robert, 63, developed his own system for rating buildings based on how difficult they are to climb. A building’s grips mattered more than its height, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave the Brooklyn Bridge a difficulty rating of two out of 10 after climbing it in 1994. He gave the same rating to the Eiffel Tower, which he scaled with his bare hands in 1996. “It’s really like a ladder,” he said of the Paris landmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also the last person to climb Taipei 101, in 2004, then the tallest building in the world. He completed the climb just days after having surgery on his left elbow, in heavy rain and with a top rope, which he said the authorities had required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Robert gave Taipei 101 a rating of six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the small gaps on the surface of the Sydney Opera House, which he climbed in 1997 and rated as a seven, allowed him to hold on only with his fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, Mr. Robert scaled what he said was one of the most difficult buildings he had ever climbed, rating it a nine: the Sears Tower, now called the Willis Tower, in Chicago. He gave the Burj Khalifa in the United Arab Emirates, the world’s tallest building, the same grade after climbing it in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult building he ever encountered? A relatively humble 44-story office building west of Paris in 1998. He said the only way up the Framatome, now called the Tour Areva, is by jamming one’s fingers into a vertical groove between glass panels. Halfway through that climb, he said, the crack unexpectedly became so narrow that his fingers could barely fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like your entire life is hanging at the tip of your finger,” he said. He rated that difficulty a 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some climbers said they were concerned that Mr. Honnold’s climb, carried live on Netflix, would encourage reckless, untrained attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My message to kids: Don’t do it,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Unless you’re a world-class climber like Alex Honnold and Alain Robert, unless you have that ability, it’s a suicide mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For others, the danger keeps them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only way I felt alive was when I was risking my life,” Mr. Robert said, adding that he might try climbing another building in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:03:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>U.K.’s Starmer Calls Trump’s Claims About NATO Soldiers in Afghanistan ‘Appalling’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-soldiers-afghanistan-trump-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23trump-news-nato-afghanistan-zbmk/23trump-news-nato-afghanistan-zbmk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
British soldiers in Helmand Province, Afghanistan, in 2007. Britain lost 457 soldiers during two decades of fighting in Afghanistan.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/uk-soldiers-afghanistan-trump-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:10:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>For Greenland Tourism, Trump’s Interest Creates Uncertainty</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/travel/greenland-tourism-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23Greenland-tourism-06-thbf/23Greenland-tourism-06-thbf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Tourism in Greenland, a semiautonomous territory of the Kingdom of Denmark, has been rising steadily for years. Now some in the tourism industry are worried that recent geopolitical attention will have a negative impact.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/travel/greenland-tourism-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 07:53:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Push to Take Greenland Holds Promise and Peril for Putin</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-putin-russia-us-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-russia-assess-wmlj/23int-russia-assess-wmlj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia in Anchorage, in August.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-putin-russia-us-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:57:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Court Dismisses Bid to Prevent Auction of Nelson Mandela Memorabilia</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/africa/nelson-mandela-memorabilia-auction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-safrica-mandela-czmg/23int-safrica-mandela-czmg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Shirts that had belonged to Nelson Mandela at an auction in New York City in 2021. Guernsey’s in New York scheduled a separate online auction in 2024 that received widespread criticism in South Africa.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/africa/nelson-mandela-memorabilia-auction.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:35:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Turnabout on Greenland Shows the Limits of His Coercive Powers</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/trumps-greenland-power.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23dc-assess-top-kpqc/23dc-assess-top-kpqc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Donald J. Trump on Air Force One en route to Washington on Thursday night.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/trumps-greenland-power.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 13:08:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under Pressure from Trump, Venezuela Agrees to Accept More U.S. Deportation Flights</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A deportation flight from the United States arriving at Simón Bolívar International Airport in Venezuela on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:26:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark Visits Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/denmark-greenland-prime-minister-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25int-greeland-pm-wbqc/25int-greeland-pm-wbqc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark, in the tan coat; the mayor of Nuuk, Greenland, Avaaraq Olsenand; and Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen of Greenland set off on a highly choreographed walk through the city on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/denmark-greenland-prime-minister-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:53:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Joint Chiefs Chairman Issues Rare Invitation to Foreign Military Heads</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/military-western-hemisphere-leaders.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23dc-military-vqpf/23dc-military-vqpf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gen. Dan Caine’s meeting comes at a fraught time for Washington’s relations with its immediate neighbors as well as allies in Europe.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/us/politics/military-western-hemisphere-leaders.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:03:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia Jails U.S. Navy Veteran for Five Years</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/russia-jails-american-sailor-chuck-zimmerman.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-russia-jailedAmerican-qjvb/23int-russia-jailedAmerican-qjvb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Steve Witkoff, the presidential envoy who has been negotiating with the Kremlin on a peace deal in the Ukraine war, was believed to have raised the issue of incarcerated Americans during his repeated visits to Moscow.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/russia-jails-american-sailor-chuck-zimmerman.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 14:07:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Prosecutors in Spain End Investigation Into Julio Iglesias</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/julio-iglesias-abuse-investigation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/obituaries/23spain-Iglesias/23spain-Iglesias-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prosecutors in Madrid said on Friday that they had ended an investigation into the singer Julio Iglesias, saying that Spanish officials had no legal authority to examine claims that he had sexually abused two former employees in the Caribbean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision came nearly three weeks after the two women filed a complaint with a Spanish court accusing Mr. Iglesias, 82, of abusing one of them in the Dominican Republic and the other in the Bahamas. Mr. Iglesias denied the accusations in a social media post on Jan. 16, describing them as “absolutely false.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prosecutors closed the case because they had no jurisdiction to proceed, given that “all of the allegedly criminal acts would have occurred outside Spanish territory, specifically in the Dominican Republic and the Bahamas,” they said in a written decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They added that the accusers “neither reside in Spain nor maintain their center of life, interests, or activity in this country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Iglesias made his name singing love ballads, and he has sold hundreds of millions of records over his six-decade career. He is the father of the singer Enrique Iglesias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early January, two Spanish-language news outlets published a three-year joint investigation into Mr. Iglesias, highlighting broader allegations from 15 people who accused the singer of sexual assault and harassment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Iglesias and his representatives did not respond to requests for comment about the broader claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his social media post, Mr. Iglesias denied “having abused, coerced, or been disrespectful to any woman,” but he did not specifically address the journalists’ findings.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/julio-iglesias-abuse-investigation.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:17:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Friends, Romans, Celebrities Pay Last Respects to Valentino</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/valentino-funeral.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-italy-valentino-01-mvcf/23int-italy-valentino-01-mvcf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were celebrities from overseas, like Anne Hathaway and Liz Hurley. There were colleagues in couture, like Donatella Versace and Tom Ford. And there were journalists, like Anna Wintour and Suzy Menkes, who had chronicled their world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elite of fashion and entertainment assembled in Rome on Friday to pay their last respects to the designer Valentino Garavani, who died on Monday at 93 and whose six-decade career concocted some of the most memorable clothes of the 20th century. They were joined by crowds of Romans — both well-heeled and sneakered — who gathered to mourn a man whose life story, since his arrival in Rome in 1959, had become entwined with that of his adopted city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hundreds gathered in and outside the cavernous brick walls of the Basilica of Saint Mary of the Angels and Martyrs, one of Rome’s most storied churches, which Michelangelo fashioned out of a ruined Roman bath complex in the 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most were dressed in black, punctuated here and there by an interloper in red, the color that became a trademark of the Valentino fashion empire. Some who could not attend the funeral sent large wreaths, like the actress Sophia Loren, whose offering bore the message: “Always in my heart.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a fitting setting for a solemn funeral that repeatedly touched on the theme of beauty, the driving force of a career in which Mr. Garavani designed dresses for celebrities including Jacqueline Kennedy, Elizabeth Taylor and Julia Roberts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of the funeral, the Rev. Pietro Guerini described Mr. Garavani — who was known to many simply by his first name — as a “seeker of beauty, creator of beauty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want to thank Maestro Valentino for the treasure of beauty he has given to individuals and to humanity as a whole,” Father Guerini said. “We thank him for the many gifts of beauty he has created, bringing happiness in this way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, the windows of the flagship Maison Valentino store in downtown Rome were obscured by black panels decorated with one of Mr. Garavani’s most famous comments: “I love beauty. It’s not my fault.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funeral ended with a few brief words by Mr. Garavani’s two closest allies — Giancarlo Giammetti, his lifelong business partner, and Bruce Hoeksema, his companion since 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Giammetti said he had learned to appreciate beauty through his relationship with Mr. Garavani. “Through him I understood what it meant,” Mr. Giammetti said. “It was a beauty,” he added, “that followed us throughout our lives, that accompanied us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choking with emotion, Mr. Hoeksema said: “I don’t say goodbye today, I say thank you. For choosing me, for walking with me, and for leaving me changed forever.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the funeral, the mayor of Rome, Roberto Gualtieri, grieved a man whose work became synonymous with the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Valentino embodied the beauty of Rome, he knew how to project the lights and colors of our city’s heritage onto the world stage,” Mr. Gualtieri said, pledging that the city would honor the designer, “as he deserves to be remembered, because he is a symbol of beauty and of our city.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing this week in Il Messaggero, Rome’s local newspaper, Mario Ajello — a veteran chronicler of all things Roman — recalled that Mr. Garavani once said “I don’t work in Rome, I am Rome.” It was a testament, Mr. Ajello wrote, to the designer’s spiritual and artistic connection to the city — he was “a Roman prince who cared about Rome’s global image and did so much to promote it,” staging shows and celebrations in the city’s iconic locations. His clothes, like the city, captured an “eternal formality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlighting Mr. Garavani’s popularity, some 10,000 people patiently queued in line at a wake held Wednesday and Thursday in a wing of the palazzo that houses the Maison Valentino headquarters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wake drew both the few who could afford to wear Mr. Garavani’s creations — some of which cost tens of thousands of dollars — and the many who could only aspire to buy one. Gabriella Camicia, 85, came to pay homage to a designer whose rise to fame coincided with her youth and the glamorous world of Rome in the 1960s. “For us, it was unthinkable that we could afford such clothes, but even dreams can give a boost to life,” Ms. Camicia said. “Just seeing them gave us so much joy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Garavani’s coffin moved along the nave of the basilica, the mourners burst into loud applause. Then the coffin was taken for burial in Rome’s Prima Porta cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was a leader of an era of fashion and that’s what makes him so exceptional, and why there are so many people who have crossed continents to come today,” said Ms. Menkes, who spent a quarter century writing about fashion for The International Herald Tribune.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It wasn’t just about him making clothes, he also built relationships with his clients,” Ms. Menkes added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They loved the clothes, they loved him, and he loved them. I really can’t think of another designer who could take over if we think of it like that,” she said. “The era is over.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/valentino-funeral.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 08:40:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam’s Leader Consolidates Power, Pledging ‘New Era of Prosperity’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/vietnam-lam-power-congress.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-vietnam-leader-01-fckz/23int-vietnam-leader-01-fckz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vietnam’s Communist Party bolstered the power of the country’s top leader, To Lam, on Friday, making him both party chief and president at its party congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Vietnam’s political process to formally announce the move has not yet taken place, the twice-a-decade congress ended two days ahead of schedule with a new list of Politburo members that indicates Mr. Lam’s dual role has been approved — evidence of what officials described as his forcefulness and consolidation of support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We pledge to stand united,” Mr. Lam said in one of his final speeches on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Comrades,” he added, “the road ahead still holds many major tasks, requiring high determination, strict discipline and unceasing effort.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The supercharged elevation of Mr. Lam, 68, a former minister of public security whose mild-mannered mien obscures his track record of embracing risk and reform, upsets Vietnam’s traditional sharing of authority among four leaders. Barring a sudden reversal, it moves Vietnam closer to the strongman model of China, which Hanoi has long avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also highlights the country’s growing sense of economic urgency and a willingness to bet big on change in a moment of global uncertainty. Mr. Lam’s agenda — laid out in resolutions and speeches that followed his rise to party secretary in 2024 — focuses on unleashing the private sector, digitizing government and getting bureaucracy out of the way of business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His “streamlining of revolution,” as state media sometimes calls it, is widely seen as a framework for the most significant economic reforms since Vietnam’s first liberalization wave near the end of the Cold War in the late 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, and now, the country worried about falling behind. Vietnam used to fear poverty and isolation. Now it sees itself as playing catch up to Asian success stories like South Korea. For years, it has been experiencing war-delayed, breakneck industrialization, claiming an economic growth rate of 8 percent in 2025 that Mr. Lam has promised to drive to double digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few countries remain as optimistic or as eager as Vietnam to squeeze upward mobility from globalization — while U.S.-China trade dynamics allow for it, and while Vietnam’s population of 102 million still has a bumper crop of young workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even party members who worry that Mr. Lam may be amassing too much power for himself and his acolytes in the country’s state security apparatus or large state-favored conglomerates said they concluded that a very strong leader represented Vietnam’s best chance to reach its goal of becoming a rich, developed country by 2045.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lam has pledged to make the most of that opportunity. In his main congress speech, at a convention center in Hanoi flush with communist symbols, where the scent of red and yellow flowers greeted delegates, he focused on “breakthroughs and action.” He called on the government to “choose correctly, deploy quickly, do thoroughly, measure by results.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Unlock and liberate productive forces and all resources,” he said. “Establish a new growth model; synchronously implement digital transformation, green transformation and energy transition; improve human resource quality; attract and utilize talents; develop new productive forces.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His dual role makes him the top official overseeing these goals at home and the head of state representing Vietnam overseas. His predecessor, Nguyen Phu Trong, briefly held both roles as did Mr. Lam, temporarily, after Mr. Trong’s death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, however, the Politburo named alongside Mr. Lam includes several members viewed as his strong allies. Among the “four pillars” that have now become three, there will be a new prime minister, Le Minh Hung. At 55, he is the youngest member of the Politburo, and he has a background in finance. Tran Thanh Man, 63, who became chair of the National Assembly when Mr. Lam was promoted two years ago, will stay in his position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several other Politburo leaders either worked for Mr. Lam at the ministry of public security or have ties to him through his home province of Hung Yen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The key point is that To Lam is now given a strong mandate to accelerate his reforms across multiple areas, from governance to economic policies,” said Nguyen Khac Giang, a visiting fellow at the ISEAS-Yusof Ishak Institute in Singapore. “We’re going to see a Vietnam which is more developmental than ideological in the next five years.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, he added, great power comes with a heavy burden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“More power can help him carry out the reforms faster,” Mr. Giang said, “but can lead to greater risks of making wrong choices.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country faces many challenges. State-supported firms significantly drag down the economy’s productivity, according to economists. Pollution is worsening. Housing costs are rising in cities while luxury developments on the outskirts are ghost towns, leading to fears of a property bust. Banking, environmental protection and airport immigration lines still feel years behind for a country that wants to be seen as a peer to Asia’s developed economies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside pressures add even more complex dilemmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese investment in factories has surged, a boon for short-term growth that also threatens Vietnam’s domestic industrial base at a time when Hanoi is seeking to move up the value chain of manufacturing. Competition for factory workers is becoming more intense, as Vietnam’s work force becomes older and more middle-class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the United States has been more standoffish than Hanoi had hoped after signing a comprehensive strategic partnership in 2023. Mr. Lam had pushed for the upgrade in relations, according U.S. officials. More recently, he has expressed disappointment in what has become a mixed bag of American foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defense Secretary Pete Hegseth recently visited Hanoi to reaffirm security ties, but the Trump administration’s tariffs have stung. They have slowed growth in many industries (furniture, for one) while the lack of a finalized trade deal has paused some foreign investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lam has been frank about many of these issues. He receives praise, especially from young, Western-educated Vietnamese, for being the first party leader to talk in public about the problems Vietnam needs to solve at home and with partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if things go wrong, how will he respond?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts and many citizens continue to wonder if the tactics Mr. Lam used to get to the top, which included his execution of an anti-corruption drive that ended up purging many of his rivals, would return with a vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lam spent nearly his entire career in state security. Along with his economic reforms, he has further empowered the police, expanding their reach into business and surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alexander Vuving, a professor at the Asia-Pacific Center for Security Studies in Honolulu, said the greatest risk for Vietnam’s top leader was, behind the scenes, a “lack of consensus and lack of legitimacy, which may cause him to embrace more authoritarianism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of the congress showed no signs of visible discord. The meeting featured higher levels of security control than in the past, with extra efforts made to keep the media from delegates. In the convention hall entrance, officials could simply be glimpsed gathering in small groups near an exhibit promoting the party’s accomplishments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Black-and-white photos of a country still struggling just a generation ago led to color spreads of gleaming infrastructure and bar charts, tall with economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also quotes in bold from Mr. Lam on what he promised to deliver: “renewal and development,” along with “a new era of prosperity.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/vietnam-lam-power-congress.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 05:16:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Many Bases Does America Have in Greenland Now?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-greenland-military-bases.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23greenland-military-01-gcjt/23greenland-military-01-gcjt-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decades ago, the United States had a big footprint in Greenland: thousands of troops, more than a dozen bases, strategic bombers, weather stations and a cavernous facility under the ice. Today, there is just one active base, a remote missile defense station. Some of the old ones have been turned into commercial airstrips. Others have faded into rusty ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has said the United States needs Greenland for national security. After previously threatening to seize the island by force, he signaled this week that he’s open to compromise. One proposal under discussion would allow the United States to own pockets of land in Greenland for military bases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland, which is an overseas territory of Denmark, and Denmark have bristled at giving up any of their sovereignty, and it’s not clear that such a plan could work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Americans have the Pituffik Space Base (pronounced Bee-doo-FEEK) in northwestern Greenland. Its 150 personnel run missile defense and space surveillance. Its location at the top of the globe, not far from the North Pole, allows its radar to detect missiles in their earliest moments of flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is quite literally the outermost eye of American defense,” said Peter Ernstved Rasmussen, a Danish defense analyst. “Pituffik is where the U.S. can detect a launch, calculate the trajectory and activate its missile defense systems. It’s irreplaceable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot. During World War II, the Germans invaded Denmark and set up clandestine weather stations on Greenland’s east coast. Around the same time, the United States military built its own weather stations on the west coast to help forecast conditions for battles in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, the United States was building airstrips in places like Narsarsuaq, Ikateq and Kangerlussuaq, all in the southern half of the island. These runways served as a steppingstone for long-range bombers flying between the United States and Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the war, many bases closed down. Some, like the Sondrestrom Air Base in Kangerlussuaq, remained under American control until 1992. During the Cold War, the United States set up a string of early warning radar stations across the island that could detect missiles flying over the North Pole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, some of the old American airstrips, like the one in Kangerlussuaq, have been upgraded into small commercial airports and are used by Air Greenland, the national airline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other bases, like in Narsarsuaq and Ikateq, lie in shambles. Most of the Cold War radar stations have been dismantled but one still stands on a hilltop in Kangerlussuaq. Locals call it “Mickey Mouse.” Its two big circular dishes, which haven’t been turned on in decades, resemble a pair of giant ears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the old American bases are in such disrepair that they would be almost impossible to restore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most likely place to expand would be around the active Pituffik base, said Troy J. Bouffard, the director of the Center for Arctic Security and Resilience at the University of Alaska Fairbanks. The site is relatively undefended, so one possibility would be to install short- to medium-range air defense weapons near the base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Otherwise, Pituffik gets destroyed easily,” he said. “And then we’re blind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another likely place for expansion might be the Kangerlussuaq airport, a Danish military official said. It was big in World War II and situated in a protected spot with reasonably good weather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has spoken about placing antimissile interceptors on Greenland as part of a so-called Golden Dome missile defense shield, but where they could go is not clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American officials have indicated they are worried that their access to Greenland could be curbed if the island broke off from Denmark and went independent. If that ever happened, Greenlanders say it is most likely decades away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under a 1951 Danish-American defense pact, the United States already has sweeping access to build new bases and station more troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration wants a new arrangement, and one proposal is modeled on the “sovereign base area” agreement in Cyprus, where Britain’s military bases are British territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has also repeatedly said that Russia and China threaten Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But China is too far away to mount a major incursion, said Mikkel Runge Olesen, a researcher at the Danish Institute for International Studies in Copenhagen. And Russia’s navy is inferior to NATO’s sea capacity, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A Russian surface fleet making its way to Greenland?” he said. “They’d be massacred.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bouffard said that even if there’s no significant military threat to Greenland right now, the world is changing fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Pituffik was never really a top-tier target before,” he said, adding, “It’s going to increase in importance — big time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts say that as global warming melts the ice in the Arctic Circle, there will be a lot more competition for resources and shipping lanes that become more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Bouffard said that, contrary to what Mr. Trump claims, there is no immediate threat from Russia or China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, he added, “There will be.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maya Tekeli contributed reporting from Copenhagen.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/trump-greenland-military-bases.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 12:39:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canadian Ex-Snowboarder Accused of Running Drug Ring Is Arrested</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/obituaries/23canada-wedding-arrest/23canada-wedding-arrest-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former Olympic snowboarder from Canada accused of murder and running an international drug-trafficking ring has been arrested, the F.B.I. announced on Friday, ending a long search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan Wedding, 44, who has been charged with smuggling cocaine into the United States, was arrested on Thursday in Mexico, the F.B.I.’s director, Kash Patel, said in a social media post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. has said that Mr. Wedding ran a major drug trafficking organization and collaborated with the Sinaloa Cartel in Mexico, where the authorities said he had been hiding. Mr. Wedding had been on the F.B.I.’s list of its 10 most wanted fugitives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was first indicted in October 2024 on cocaine trafficking charges. He was later charged with murder, including the killing of Jonathan Acebedo-Garcia, a Canadian who had been expected to testify against Mr. Wedding. The authorities said Mr. Wedding hired a hit man to kill Mr. Acebedo-Garcia in 2025 in Medellin, Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wedding’s arrest comes two weeks before the Winter Olympics begin in Italy. He competed in the 2002 Salt Lake City Games, finishing 24th in parallel giant slalom snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a developing story. It will be updated.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:11:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Says U.S. ‘Armada’ Is Heading to Iran, Raising Pressure on Regime</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said late Thursday that a large naval force was heading to Iran, continuing his threats of U.S. military action against the government nearly a month after protests erupted across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re watching Iran,” Mr. Trump told reporters aboard Air Force One as he returned to the United States from the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. “We have a big flotilla going in that direction, and we’ll see what happens,” he added, describing the force as an “armada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had appeared to back away from threats to strike Iran, saying he had received assurances that detained protesters there would not be executed. Leaders across the Middle East had also warned Mr. Trump that a military confrontation could destabilize the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Pentagon ordered the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln and three Tomahawk-missile-firing destroyers in the South China Sea to head to the Middle East, according to two U.S. officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Air Force in the past week also sent a dozen F-15E fighters to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to the officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maj. Gen. Ali Abdollahi Aliabadi, a commander in Iran’s Khatam-al Anbiya Central Headquarters, said on Thursday that any attack on the country would “turn all U.S. interests, bases and centers of influence” into targets, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government said this week that it had quelled antigovernment protests, which erupted last month. Iran’s state television has said that more than 3,100 people were killed during the demonstrations, but human rights groups monitoring the unrest say the toll is significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human Rights Activists in Iran, a group based in Washington, said on Thursday that over 5,000 people had been killed so far, the majority of them protesters, while the Iran Human Rights group based in Norway put the figure at more than 3,400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump said that his threats of intervention had stopped more than 830 executions, mostly of young men, though Iran’s prosecutor general, Mohammad Movahedi, denied that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This claim is completely false; neither does such a number exist, nor has the judiciary made such a decision,” Mr. Movahedi said on Friday, according to the judiciary’s Mizan News Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Iranian officials previously said that rioters would be considered “enemies of God,” a charge that could carry the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether any executions had taken place. The Iranian government has instituted a severe digital and communications blackout, limiting the flow of information out of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say that the U.S. military deployment in the region was meant to ramp up pressure on the Iranian government and prepare defenses in the event of retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The increased buildup, particularly the aircraft carrier, provides an expanded set of offensive options,” said Dana Stroul, research director at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy and a former U.S. deputy assistant secretary of defense for the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demonstrations began in response to the collapsing Iranian currency and an economy that have pushed many Iranians into hardship. Iran’s economy has been under sustained pressure for years, largely as a result of Western sanctions linked to its nuclear ambitions, as well as corruption and mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the protests spread across the country, they were seen as a direct challenge to Iran’s clerical rulers, who have held power for nearly half a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities responded with a deadly crackdown, with witness reports of security forces shooting demonstrators at close range. Officials branded demonstrators “rioters” and “terrorists,” saying they were backed by foreign powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the demonstrations gained momentum, Mr. Trump said on Jan. 2 that the United States was “locked and loaded” to protect Iranian protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. officials said Mr. Trump was exploring diplomacy with Iran, even as he weighed military options, including strikes. He then declared that all talks were off and urged protesters to seize government institutions, though he later said that Iran had responded to his demands by halting the killing and execution of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump told the reporters on Air Force One that he had warned the Iranian government, “If you hang those people, you are going to be hit harder than you’ve ever been hit,” adding that the assault would make previous attacks on Iran’s nuclear program “look like peanuts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ali Vaez, an Iran specialist at the International Crisis Group, which focuses on conflict prevention, said the U.S. military threat was credible, given its strikes on Iran last June. “What is unclear is what the end goal is,” he said, adding that Mr. Trump’s initial promise to rescue protesters appeared to have given way to seeking retribution against the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiana Hayeri, Eric Schmitt and Leily Nikounazar contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:25:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Peru’s President May Be Ousted Over Secret Meetings With Chinese Businessmen</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/peru-president-chinese-businessmen-meetings.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-peru-scandal-kjqc/23int-peru-scandal-kjqc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secret recordings of Peruvian presidents are nothing new. Nor are corruption accusations leading to impeachments. Over the past decade, Peru has had seven presidents, none of whom has managed to hang on for longer than three years. One resigned within a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country’s current president, José Jerí, 39, who presided over the impeachment of his predecessor and who was then installed in her place last October, could join that list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a leaked video released this month, CCTV footage from Dec. 26 shows Mr. Jerí being dropped off by a car belonging to the president’s office and then attempting to cover his face with the hood of his sweatshirt as he entered Xin Yan Restaurant, which is owned by Yang Zhihua, a Chinese businessman who has come under government scrutiny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another video leaked a week later shows Mr. Jerí in one of the numerous corner stores that Mr. Yang owns in the capital, Lima. He can be seen shouting into his phone in front of Mr. Yang. Local media had reported that Mr. Yang’s store had been ordered shut down for violating a municipal ordinance. Three days later, the ordinance was struck down by a federal regulatory body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Peruvian law, Mr. Jerí, who has acknowledged the authenticity of the videos, is legally required to log all his official activities and did not disclose his visits to the restaurant and the store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under withering questioning from federal lawmakers this week, Mr. Jerí has been defiant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he had known Mr. Yang, who he calls “Johnny,” before he became president. As for the visits, he enjoys Chinese food and happened to pass the store and thought to buy some candy and paintings. (But, he added, “Johnny wouldn’t let me pay because he was being kind to me.”)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the shouting? It was a call from his press secretary about an unrelated matter that had upset him. He refused to share his phone’s call history with lawmakers and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These are normal actions that people, regardless of their position, carry out, but they have been distorted for purposes that the investigations will surely reveal,” he said in Congress on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí’s defense has been met with deep skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 20 lawmakers have signed onto motions that, if passed, would result in Mr. Jerí’s impeachment, a number that kept rising on Thursday. Of the 130 members of the lower house, 66 must vote for impeachment for a president to be removed. And on Tuesday, Peru’s prosecutors’ office said it had opened a graft investigation into his meetings with Mr. Yang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yang has more than a dozen companies in Peru, including a construction firm that has won several contracts from the police, a hydroelectric company that was granted a state concession to build a dam, and a ceramics factory that, according to a national trade association, was built without proper permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times obtained a confidential report on Thursday about Chinese companies accused of corruption in Peru that was drafted by a congressional committee last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it, Mr. Yang was identified as a junior partner in a more than $50 million highway project led by a local subsidiary of China Railway Engineering Corporation that became the subject of an arbitration dispute. The report accuses Mr. Yang’s construction company of conspiring to defraud the Peruvian state by using the economic leverage of large, Chinese state-owned companies to secure contracts for projects that were later abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí’s office did not respond to a request for an interview and Mr. Yang could not be reached for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willax, a conservative cable channel, broadcast a third video of Mr. Jerí with Mr. Yang. It appears to have been recorded by a person wearing a hidden camera, and offers a glimpse of a separate moment at Mr. Yang’s store during Mr. Jerí’s visit there on Jan. 6. It shows members of Mr. Jerí’s team collecting bags of goods from people who appear to be the store’s employees. Someone off-camera says, “This is for the comandante.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru’s Congress is currently on summer break, complicating efforts to summon an extraordinary plenary session to impeach Mr. Jerí, though lawmakers from across the political spectrum have expressed support for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru already has presidential elections scheduled for April. Part of Mr. Jerí’s defense has been to accuse his political opponents of releasing the videos to “alter the electoral process.” Before the scandal broke, Mr. Jerí enjoyed a relatively high approval rating of 51 percent in the latest polling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Peruvians have responded to the mushrooming scandal with jadedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our politicians are all corrupt and they sell themselves to the highest bidder,” said Jacinta Martínez, 45, a landscaper in Lima. “Today it’s the Chinese who are buying them, tomorrow it will be Peruvians or Venezuelans or Americans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peru’s relationship with China has grown increasingly close. More than a decade has passed since China became Peru’s biggest trading partner, and in 2024, Chinese companies completed construction of an enormous port north of Lima — part of Beijing’s Belt and Road initiative. China is the main buyer of Peru’s largest export, copper. Chinese companies are heavily involved in Peruvian infrastructure and telecommunications, and Peruvians can visit China visa-free as tourists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has sought to counter Chinese influence in Peru, in large part through forging a closer military partnership. Mr. Jerí has tried to thread the needle by welcoming both Chinese and American investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During Mr. Jerí’s brief time in office, President Trump notified Congress that he intended to make Peru a “Major Non-NATO Ally,” a designation that Colombia, Brazil and Argentina also share, and the State Department said Peru had asked to purchase $1.5 billion worth of U.S. equipment and services to support construction of a new naval base near Lima.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December, the U.S. Senate approved Mr. Trump’s nomination of Bernie Navarro, a self-described America First champion who has vowed to “root out” growing Chinese influence, as the new ambassador to Peru.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of Mr. Jerí’s political allies have said that they believe the geopolitical jockeying between the United States and China precipitated the scandal embroiling the president. In an interview with a Peruvian newspaper this week, Prime Minister Ernesto Alvarez said the videos may have been leaked to the media to damage Mr. Jerí for seeking stronger ties with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It could be China because they’re very upset about the” naval base,” he said, “and because we’ve stated transparently that Peru should be an ally of the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chinese and American embassies in Lima did not respond to requests for comment, nor did Mr. Navarro, the incoming U.S. ambassador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, Cuarto Poder, the same outlet that published the video of Mr. Jerí in Mr. Yang’s shop, reported that another Chinese businessman, Ji Wu Xiaodong, who is under investigation for his role in a criminal organization involved in illegal logging, had visited the presidential palace three times since Mr. Jerí took office. Mr. Ji Wu had been ordered held under house arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jerí told lawmakers that Mr. Ji Wu was a friend of Mr. Yang’s and said he did not know Mr. Ji Wu well and that he barely spoke Spanish. Mr. Ji Wu is accredited by Peru’s foreign ministry as an official Chinese-Spanish translator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Peru’s energy regulator, Osinergmin, Mr. Yang’s hydroelectric company, Hidroeléctrica America, has made no progress on building the $24.4 million, 20 megawatt dam as of the end of last year. It is due for completion in March. The company could lose a $244,000 deposit it if does not fulfill the contract.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his testimony before lawmakers this week, Mr. Jerí mentioned two additional, unregistered meetings with Mr. Yang — two more December meals at Mr. Yang’s Xin Yan Restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Videos of those meetings have yet to emerge, but on a late night TV show on Wednesday, Beto Ortiz, a journalist for Willax claimed that he knew of 19 more videos of Mr. Jerí meeting with Mr. Yang, and teased details from the ones he’d seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For his part Mr. Jerí said he is eager to have any videos of him made public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hopefully they’ll start airing them,” Mr. Jerí said at a news conference on Thursday afternoon, “so we can verify and get many more clues about who’s behind them and what the links are between them.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/peru-president-chinese-businessmen-meetings.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 10:33:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukrainian, Russian and U.S. Officials to Meet in Abu Dhabi for Peace Talks</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/ukraine-russia-war-us-peace-talks-abu-dhabi.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-ukraine-ljqv/23int-ukraine-ljqv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ukrainian, Russian and American negotiators were expected to hold meetings on Friday in the United Arab Emirates, the latest in a flurry of recent diplomatic efforts to end the war in Ukraine as the fourth anniversary since Russia’s full-scale invasion approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russian state news agency Tass reported that a “working group on security issues” was meeting in Abu Dhabi, the capital of the United Arab Emirates, on Friday, confirming an earlier statement by President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine. Russia’s delegation was to be led by Igor Kostyukov, the head of Russia’s military intelligence, Tass reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not immediately clear when the meetings would start nor how they would play out. Ukrainian and Russian negotiators have rarely met directly in past rounds of talks, instead relying on the United States as a mediator. Steve Witkoff, President Trump’s special envoy, and Jared Kushner, Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, were also expected to be in Abu Dhabi, but it was not clear if they would be directly involved in the trilateral talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the table is a revised 20-point peace plan drawn up by Ukraine and the United States, covering a range of issues such as potential territorial arrangements and security guarantees that Kyiv wants to prevent future Russian aggression, as well as plans to rebuild the war-ravaged nation. But the Ukrainian and Russian authorities are still at odds over territory, with Russia demanding a big chunk in an eastern region known as the Donbas, and on security guarantees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Witkoff said on Thursday that the meetings in Abu Dhabi would be working groups handling specific components of the peace plan, including what he called “military-to-military” aspects and “prosperity,” or postwar economic recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think we’ve got it down to one issue, and we have discussed iterations of that issue, and that means it’s solvable,” he said at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, without elaborating. “So if both sides want to solve this, we’re going to get it solved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked later by a reporter at Davos about Mr. Witkoff’s comment, Mr. Zelensky said that Russia’s demand to control all of the Donetsk region in eastern Ukraine, even areas now held by the Ukrainian Army, remained unresolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Witkoff and Mr. Kushner are expected in Abu Dhabi after meeting late on Thursday with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia. Tass said that they would be there for a meeting with Russian officials on economic issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yuri Ushakov, the foreign policy adviser to Mr. Putin, told reporters after the four-hour meeting with Mr. Putin that it had been “useful in all aspects, both for us and the United States,” according to Tass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ushakov said that Russia was interested in solving the war “through political and diplomatic means” but that until then it would continue to push on the battlefield “where the Russian Armed Forces hold the strategic initiative,” Tass reported. Ukrainian officials have characterized the fighting as at a near stalemate, with Mr. Zelensky saying on Thursday that both armies were exhausted after four years of war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks on Friday also come after a meeting in Davos between Mr. Zelensky and Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky had said this week that he would attend the gathering in Switzerland only if “real results for Ukraine” were on the table, fueling expectations of a possible breakthrough in the peace talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky and Mr. Trump said after meeting that their talks had been “good,” and Mr. Zelensky said that they had reached an agreement on U.S. security guarantees for Ukraine after the war. But the leaders offered no details on what these guarantees would entail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I believe they’re at a point now where they can come together and get a deal done,” Mr. Trump said in Davos on Wednesday, referring to the two sides in the Russia-Ukraine peace talks. “And if they don’t, they’re stupid. I don’t want to insult anyone, but you got to get this deal done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andrew E. Kramer contributed reporting from Kyiv, Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/europe/ukraine-russia-war-us-peace-talks-abu-dhabi.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 09:42:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Final Indignities Inflicted on Iran’s Protest Victims</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/world/00int-iran-cemetery1/00int-iran-cemetery1-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The families rooted frantically through the piles of corpses, so crammed together that the living had to take care not to step on the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wailing and cursing, they searched the body bags for the number assigned to their loved one for burial — a surreal veneer of bureaucracy imposed onto a chaotic nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the breaking point only came when weary-looking cemetery workers arrived in refrigerated trucks to dump still more corpses on the ground. The body bags landed with sickening thuds in front of onlookers who had come to bury their children, siblings, fathers, mothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That moment — it broke people. People couldn’t just watch them throwing the bodies out like that,” said Kiarash, a witness who described the scene this month at Behesht-e Zahra, the largest cemetery in Tehran. “There was a mother lying on her child’s body, begging for help so they wouldn’t throw him somewhere,” Kiarash added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enraged, the crowds began pushing their way into the hallway of the mortuary, cursing Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei — a criminal offense in the country — as security forces looked on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mothers were crying, shouting,” Kiarash said. “And all the people were shouting things like, ‘Death to Khamenei.’” As Kiarash reached for his phone to film them, he said, security forces quickly stopped him. Others, however, did manage to surreptitiously film and share the protests that day, in videos that have been verified by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash, who, like others interviewed, asked to be identified only by his first name to protect his relatives, gave The New York Times rare, detailed testimony of his experiences during a visit to his family in Iran, which coincided with the anti-government protests that roiled the country for weeks. A violent crackdown unleashed by the government has stifled those demonstrations for now, residents say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The staggering toll of this suppression has only begun to emerge — obscured by a government shutdown of the internet and telephone lines for more than a week. Though some communications are slowly being restored, reliable testimony and evidence is emerging piecemeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human rights groups say they have gathered so many individual testimonies of people who witnessed large numbers of bodies collecting at morgues and cemeteries across the country that they expect the death toll to rise far beyond the current estimates of up to 4,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, like Kiarash, three rights groups interviewed by The Times recounted shocking treatment of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mahmood Amiry-Moghaddam, director of Iran Human Rights, an advocacy group based in Oslo, said that his team had also received witness accounts of bodies being piled on top of one another in Tehran and in the coastal city of Rasht. The group documented testimonies from people who said that they had been forced to search through trucks loaded with bodies to find their loved ones in Tehran and in the northeastern city of Mashhad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mashhad’s poorest neighborhoods, some families recounted being asked to pay impossible sums, sometimes as high as $6,000, to retrieve the bodies of protesters, according to testimonies gathered by the Center for Human Rights in Iran, an organization based in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people cannot pick up their loved ones’ bodies because they can’t pay that kind of money,” said Hadi Ghaemi, the head of the center. “So the bodies are just being dumped and buried in mass graves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of imposing a “bullet price” on the families of dead dissidents dates to the Islamic Republic’s brutal crackdown on its opponents in the 1980s, when the authorities required a fee to return the bodies of those it executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the evidence that rights groups are now piecing together comes from travelers smuggling out information when they leave Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor told The Times that he spirited out videos and testimony from medics in the central city of Isfahan. They shared information about a heavy death toll from that city alone from Jan. 8-10, at the height of the government’s crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now everyone knows someone who was killed,” said the doctor, Mohammed. “The silence imposed on people is not normal — it’s a silence that carries the dust of death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that he had seen hundreds of bodies during his visit to Behesht-e Zara, on the afternoon of Jan. 10, when he had joined his brother to bury a family friend. The friend, a 41-year-old mother of two, had been shot in the neck at a protest the night before, Kiarash said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mourners at the cemetery started at a reception area, where they received a number that matched the tag on their loved one’s body, Kiarash recounted. Then they made their way toward the mortuary, where cemetery workers perform the Muslim rites of washing the corpses and covering them in a simple white shroud before returning them to their loved ones for burial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the families waited outside the mortuary, they noticed that piles of bodies had been stacked in warehouses nearby, Kiarash said. The sight prompted a frenzy as people broke past the security forces to see if their loved ones were among the piles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was rows upon rows” of bodies, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian, an Iranian in exile abroad, said that his family had undergone a similar experience to Kiarash’s at the same cemetery. Dian’s father was shot dead at a protest, his family told him, and they buried him at Behesht-e Zahra a day after Kiarash was there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian’s family also described scenes of corpses stacked on top of one another and of cemetery workers insulting the families of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What unnerved Kiarash most, he said, was watching cemetery workers carelessly handling tiny body bags — for children, he guessed, no more than 10 or 12 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Throwing bodies on top of each other, throwing the children in small bags — they’d get crushed beneath them,” he said. “Every time I say this, my heart breaks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young conscripts overseeing the crowd looked as stunned as the people they were meant to be controlling, Kiarash added: “Some of them were crying.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behesht-e Zahra holds a powerful resonance for Iranians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, the founder of the Islamic Republic established after the 1979 revolution, is entombed there. It is also the final resting place of thousands of soldiers who lost their lives in the Iran-Iraq war during the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the authorities bulldozed over a plot there holding many political prisoners, who were executed by the thousands during the ’80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many rights groups estimate that the toll from Iran’s latest unrest could pass 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage from Jan. 10, taken at a forensics laboratory a short distance away from Behesht-e Zahra, has also emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The videos show sobbing crowds searching through bodies piled on the floor as 40-foot-long refrigerator trucks, similar to those Kiarash described, arrive to unload still more dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final indignity is the burial itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arina Moradi, who works for the Norway-based rights group Hengaw, said that the authorities in Tehran had forced her family to pay money to retrieve the body of her cousin, Siavash Shirzad, 38. But they denied Mr. Shirzad’s family the right to bury him in his birth city, Bukan, in western Iran, where his family lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family was forced to bury him in a remote ancestral village instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They paid the money, then they had to agree they would not allow any demonstrations or anything, that they would bury him in silence,” Ms. Moradi said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tightly restricting burial rites, Mr. Ghaemi said, is a lesson that the Islamic Republic learned from the 1979 revolution. Then, funerals for protesters and the customary Shiite Muslim memorial services conducted 40 days after a person’s death became critical to maintaining the momentum of demonstrations that ultimately overthrew the shah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason authorities are so sensitive about where bodies get buried is that they become symbols to the people they live among — and the potential for gatherings at the cemetery that could ignite larger protest,” Mr. Ghaemi said. “They basically deny people the right to mourn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Behesht-e Zahra, Dian said that security guards had accompanied his family to their burial plot to monitor them. In a video shared by the family, the mourners simply chanted, “Honorable one! Honorable one!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that security guards had rushed his family friends through their final goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One officer was standing over us: ‘You have 30 minutes to do whatever you need,’” Kiarash recalled. The friend was lowered into the grave; the dirt poured over her body was quickly watered to tamp down the dust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash says that the silence imposed by the government’s crackdown cannot last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The word hatred is not strong enough to signify what people are feeling,” he said. “It’s over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanam Mahoozi, Monika Cvorak and Artemis Moshtaghian contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:13:09 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>