<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:34:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What’s It Like to Climb a Skyscraper?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23xp-climbing-top/23xp-climbing-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Goodwin’s left shoulder felt like it was on fire and his right hand was covered in blisters by the time he finished climbing one side of Toronto’s CN Tower in 1986. Back then, it was the tallest structure in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was terrified,” he said, recalling the day he reached the base of the tower’s observation deck, 1,100 feet above a crowd of onlookers and with no rope, harness or other safety equipment. “Every move had to be perfect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Alex Honnold, a rock climber who was the subject of the Oscar-winning documentary “Free Solo,” will attempt to get everything right when he climbs Taipei 101, a 1,667-foot-tall skyscraper in Taiwan, without a rope. With Netflix livestreaming the climb, this niche pursuit has never received such global publicity before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaling skyscrapers is not like rock climbing or going up smaller buildings. Those in the club of just a dozen or so known skyscraper climbers worldwide say it has unique and intense physical and mental demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a largely underground sport because it is usually illegal. Alain Robert, a Frenchman who has scaled some 200 buildings since the 1990s, mostly with his bare hands, said that he has been arrested more than 170 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like you’re literally in a movie,” Mr. Robert said, with “cops that are trying to catch the bad guy climbing the building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious risks make it rare for someone to obtain permission to climb a tall building like Mr. Honnold did. “I’ve never been willing to get arrested,” the 40-year-old said in a recent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the serene natural landscape surrounding climbers on routes like El Capitan in Yosemite National Park, which Mr. Honnold scaled in 2017, skyscraper climbers must overcome urban noise, crowds and, occasionally, police officers determined to arrest them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like King Kong in the city,” said Titouan Leduc, 24, a French climber who scaled Warsaw’s Varso Tower, the tallest skyscraper in the European Union, last year. He was briefly arrested after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who have climbed skyscrapers say their bodies face different demands compared with rock climbing. According to Mr. Goodwin, 70, it mainly comes down to repetitiveness versus variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a rock face, each move presents a new puzzle: climbers’ hands search for different holds — crimps, jugs, slopers — and they constantly adapt their bodies. But along the side of a building, climbers repeat the same few movements hundreds of times to pass over dozens of stories of windows, steel bars and concrete gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can do a pull-up and think it’s not all too bad, but try doing 20, 50, 100,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Doing the same kind of move over and over and over — it can really tax your muscles and fingers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over decades, Mr. Robert, 63, developed his own system for rating buildings based on how difficult they are to climb. A building’s grips mattered more than its height, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave the Brooklyn Bridge a difficulty rating of two out of 10 after climbing it in 1994. He gave the same rating to the Eiffel Tower, which he scaled with his bare hands in 1996. “It’s really like a ladder,” he said of the Paris landmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also the last person to climb Taipei 101, in 2004, then the tallest building in the world. He completed the climb just days after having surgery on his left elbow, in heavy rain and with a top rope, which he said the authorities had required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Robert gave Taipei 101 a rating of six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the small gaps on the surface of the Sydney Opera House, which he climbed in 1997 and rated as a seven, allowed him to hold on only with his fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, Mr. Robert scaled what he said was one of the most difficult buildings he had ever climbed, rating it a nine: the Sears Tower, now called the Willis Tower, in Chicago. He gave the Burj Khalifa in the United Arab Emirates, the world’s tallest building, the same grade after climbing it in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult building he ever encountered? A relatively humble 44-story office building west of Paris in 1998. He said the only way up the Framatome, now called the Tour Areva, is by jamming one’s fingers into a vertical groove between glass panels. Halfway through that climb, he said, the crack unexpectedly became so narrow that his fingers could barely fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like your entire life is hanging at the tip of your finger,” he said. He rated that difficulty a 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some climbers said they were concerned that Mr. Honnold’s climb, carried live on Netflix, would encourage reckless, untrained attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My message to kids: Don’t do it,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Unless you’re a world-class climber like Alex Honnold and Alain Robert, unless you have that ability, it’s a suicide mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For others, the danger keeps them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only way I felt alive was when I was risking my life,” Mr. Robert said, adding that he might try climbing another building in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:03:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Under Pressure from Trump, Venezuela Agrees to Accept More U.S. Deportation Flights</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql/23int-venezuela-deportations-tpql-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A deportation flight from the United States arriving at Simón Bolívar International Airport in Venezuela on Thursday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/americas/venezuela-trump-ice-deportation-flights.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 15:26:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Australian Boy, 12, Dies After Shark Attack Near Sydney</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/australia/australia-shark-attack-boy-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24xp-shark-blwf/24xp-shark-blwf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A closed beach at Vaucluse near Sydney on Monday. Nico Antic was attacked on Sunday afternoon by what the authorities believed to have been a bull shark.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/australia/australia-shark-attack-boy-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 00:00:39 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Despite Trump’s Words, China and Russia Are Not Threatening Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/trump-china-russia-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23dc-greenland-security-01-kmjq/23dc-greenland-security-01-kmjq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump has repeatedly cited security as his rationale for wanting to acquire Greenland.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/politics/trump-china-russia-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 04:19:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How a Photographer Stumbled Upon a Key Picture of the Spain Train Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/insider/how-a-photographer-stumbled-upon-a-key-picture-of-the-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24Insider-Spain-train-crash-vwjc/24Insider-Spain-train-crash-vwjc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The undercarriage of a train found near the crash site in Adamuz, Spain.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/insider/how-a-photographer-stumbled-upon-a-key-picture-of-the-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 01:02:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Mark Carney Takes On Donald Trump and Emerges as a Global Political Star</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/canada/carney-trump-us-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24canadaletter-carney-lghc/24canadaletter-carney-lghc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Mark Carney received a standing ovation for his speech at the World Economic Forum.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/canada/carney-trump-us-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 02:00:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cold Comfort</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/briefing/cold-comfort.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;How can the perpetually shivering warm up to winter?&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/briefing/cold-comfort.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 02:37:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canadian Ex-Snowboarder Accused of Running Drug Ring Is Arrested</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/obituaries/23canada-wedding-arrest/23canada-wedding-arrest-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former Olympic snowboarder from Canada accused of murder and running an international drug-trafficking ring has been arrested, the F.B.I. announced on Friday, ending a long search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ryan Wedding, 44, who has been charged with smuggling cocaine into the United States, was arrested on Thursday in Mexico, the F.B.I.’s director, Kash Patel, said in a social media post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F.B.I. has said that Mr. Wedding ran a major drug trafficking organization and collaborated with the Sinaloa Cartel in Mexico, where the authorities said he had been hiding. Mr. Wedding had been on the F.B.I.’s list of its 10 most wanted fugitives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was first indicted in October 2024 on cocaine trafficking charges. He was later charged with murder, including the killing of Jonathan Acebedo-Garcia, a Canadian who had been expected to testify against Mr. Wedding. The authorities said Mr. Wedding hired a hit man to kill Mr. Acebedo-Garcia in 2025 in Medellin, Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wedding’s arrest comes two weeks before the Winter Olympics begin in Italy. He competed in the 2002 Salt Lake City Games, finishing 24th in parallel giant slalom snowboarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a developing story. It will be updated.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/canada/ryan-wedding-arrest.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:11:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Says U.S. ‘Armada’ Is Heading to Iran, Raising Pressure on Regime</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb/23int-iran-trump-01-tpzb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump said late Thursday that a large naval force was heading to Iran, continuing his threats of U.S. military action against the government nearly a month after protests erupted across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re watching Iran,” Mr. Trump told reporters aboard Air Force One as he returned to the United States from the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland. “We have a big flotilla going in that direction, and we’ll see what happens,” he added, describing the force as an “armada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had appeared to back away from threats to strike Iran, saying he had received assurances that detained protesters there would not be executed. Leaders across the Middle East had also warned Mr. Trump that a military confrontation could destabilize the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Pentagon ordered the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln and three Tomahawk-missile-firing destroyers in the South China Sea to head to the Middle East, according to two U.S. officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Air Force in the past week also sent a dozen F-15E fighters to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to the officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maj. Gen. Ali Abdollahi Aliabadi, a commander in Iran’s Khatam-al Anbiya Central Headquarters, said on Thursday that any attack on the country would “turn all U.S. interests, bases and centers of influence” into targets, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government said this week that it had quelled antigovernment protests, which erupted last month. Iran’s state television has said that more than 3,100 people were killed during the demonstrations, but human rights groups monitoring the unrest say the toll is significantly higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human Rights Activists in Iran, a group based in Washington, said on Thursday that over 5,000 people had been killed so far, the majority of them protesters, while the Iran Human Rights group based in Norway put the figure at more than 3,400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump said that his threats of intervention had stopped more than 830 executions, mostly of young men, though Iran’s prosecutor general, Mohammad Movahedi, denied that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This claim is completely false; neither does such a number exist, nor has the judiciary made such a decision,” Mr. Movahedi said on Friday, according to the judiciary’s Mizan News Agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Iranian officials previously said that rioters would be considered “enemies of God,” a charge that could carry the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether any executions had taken place. The Iranian government has instituted a severe digital and communications blackout, limiting the flow of information out of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say that the U.S. military deployment in the region was meant to ramp up pressure on the Iranian government and prepare defenses in the event of retaliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The increased buildup, particularly the aircraft carrier, provides an expanded set of offensive options,” said Dana Stroul, research director at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy and a former U.S. deputy assistant secretary of defense for the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The demonstrations began in response to the collapsing Iranian currency and an economy that have pushed many Iranians into hardship. Iran’s economy has been under sustained pressure for years, largely as a result of Western sanctions linked to its nuclear ambitions, as well as corruption and mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the protests spread across the country, they were seen as a direct challenge to Iran’s clerical rulers, who have held power for nearly half a century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities responded with a deadly crackdown, with witness reports of security forces shooting demonstrators at close range. Officials branded demonstrators “rioters” and “terrorists,” saying they were backed by foreign powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the demonstrations gained momentum, Mr. Trump said on Jan. 2 that the United States was “locked and loaded” to protect Iranian protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. officials said Mr. Trump was exploring diplomacy with Iran, even as he weighed military options, including strikes. He then declared that all talks were off and urged protesters to seize government institutions, though he later said that Iran had responded to his demands by halting the killing and execution of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump told the reporters on Air Force One that he had warned the Iranian government, “If you hang those people, you are going to be hit harder than you’ve ever been hit,” adding that the assault would make previous attacks on Iran’s nuclear program “look like peanuts.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ali Vaez, an Iran specialist at the International Crisis Group, which focuses on conflict prevention, said the U.S. military threat was credible, given its strikes on Iran last June. “What is unclear is what the end goal is,” he said, adding that Mr. Trump’s initial promise to rescue protesters appeared to have given way to seeking retribution against the regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiana Hayeri, Eric Schmitt and Leily Nikounazar contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/trump-armada-iran-naval-force.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 17:25:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Final Indignities Inflicted on Iran’s Protest Victims</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/21/world/00int-iran-cemetery1/00int-iran-cemetery1-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The families rooted frantically through the piles of corpses, so crammed together that the living had to take care not to step on the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wailing and cursing, they searched the body bags for the number assigned to their loved one for burial — a surreal veneer of bureaucracy imposed onto a chaotic nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the breaking point only came when weary-looking cemetery workers arrived in refrigerated trucks to dump still more corpses on the ground. The body bags landed with sickening thuds in front of onlookers who had come to bury their children, siblings, fathers, mothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That moment — it broke people. People couldn’t just watch them throwing the bodies out like that,” said Kiarash, a witness who described the scene this month at Behesht-e Zahra, the largest cemetery in Tehran. “There was a mother lying on her child’s body, begging for help so they wouldn’t throw him somewhere,” Kiarash added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enraged, the crowds began pushing their way into the hallway of the mortuary, cursing Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei — a criminal offense in the country — as security forces looked on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mothers were crying, shouting,” Kiarash said. “And all the people were shouting things like, ‘Death to Khamenei.’” As Kiarash reached for his phone to film them, he said, security forces quickly stopped him. Others, however, did manage to surreptitiously film and share the protests that day, in videos that have been verified by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash, who, like others interviewed, asked to be identified only by his first name to protect his relatives, gave The New York Times rare, detailed testimony of his experiences during a visit to his family in Iran, which coincided with the anti-government protests that roiled the country for weeks. A violent crackdown unleashed by the government has stifled those demonstrations for now, residents say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The staggering toll of this suppression has only begun to emerge — obscured by a government shutdown of the internet and telephone lines for more than a week. Though some communications are slowly being restored, reliable testimony and evidence is emerging piecemeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human rights groups say they have gathered so many individual testimonies of people who witnessed large numbers of bodies collecting at morgues and cemeteries across the country that they expect the death toll to rise far beyond the current estimates of up to 4,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, like Kiarash, three rights groups interviewed by The Times recounted shocking treatment of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mahmood Amiry-Moghaddam, director of Iran Human Rights, an advocacy group based in Oslo, said that his team had also received witness accounts of bodies being piled on top of one another in Tehran and in the coastal city of Rasht. The group documented testimonies from people who said that they had been forced to search through trucks loaded with bodies to find their loved ones in Tehran and in the northeastern city of Mashhad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mashhad’s poorest neighborhoods, some families recounted being asked to pay impossible sums, sometimes as high as $6,000, to retrieve the bodies of protesters, according to testimonies gathered by the Center for Human Rights in Iran, an organization based in New York.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“These people cannot pick up their loved ones’ bodies because they can’t pay that kind of money,” said Hadi Ghaemi, the head of the center. “So the bodies are just being dumped and buried in mass graves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of imposing a “bullet price” on the families of dead dissidents dates to the Islamic Republic’s brutal crackdown on its opponents in the 1980s, when the authorities required a fee to return the bodies of those it executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the evidence that rights groups are now piecing together comes from travelers smuggling out information when they leave Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor told The Times that he spirited out videos and testimony from medics in the central city of Isfahan. They shared information about a heavy death toll from that city alone from Jan. 8-10, at the height of the government’s crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now everyone knows someone who was killed,” said the doctor, Mohammed. “The silence imposed on people is not normal — it’s a silence that carries the dust of death.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that he had seen hundreds of bodies during his visit to Behesht-e Zara, on the afternoon of Jan. 10, when he had joined his brother to bury a family friend. The friend, a 41-year-old mother of two, had been shot in the neck at a protest the night before, Kiarash said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mourners at the cemetery started at a reception area, where they received a number that matched the tag on their loved one’s body, Kiarash recounted. Then they made their way toward the mortuary, where cemetery workers perform the Muslim rites of washing the corpses and covering them in a simple white shroud before returning them to their loved ones for burial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the families waited outside the mortuary, they noticed that piles of bodies had been stacked in warehouses nearby, Kiarash said. The sight prompted a frenzy as people broke past the security forces to see if their loved ones were among the piles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It was rows upon rows” of bodies, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian, an Iranian in exile abroad, said that his family had undergone a similar experience to Kiarash’s at the same cemetery. Dian’s father was shot dead at a protest, his family told him, and they buried him at Behesht-e Zahra a day after Kiarash was there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dian’s family also described scenes of corpses stacked on top of one another and of cemetery workers insulting the families of the dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What unnerved Kiarash most, he said, was watching cemetery workers carelessly handling tiny body bags — for children, he guessed, no more than 10 or 12 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Throwing bodies on top of each other, throwing the children in small bags — they’d get crushed beneath them,” he said. “Every time I say this, my heart breaks.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young conscripts overseeing the crowd looked as stunned as the people they were meant to be controlling, Kiarash added: “Some of them were crying.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behesht-e Zahra holds a powerful resonance for Iranians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, the founder of the Islamic Republic established after the 1979 revolution, is entombed there. It is also the final resting place of thousands of soldiers who lost their lives in the Iran-Iraq war during the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, the authorities bulldozed over a plot there holding many political prisoners, who were executed by the thousands during the ’80s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many rights groups estimate that the toll from Iran’s latest unrest could pass 10,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage from Jan. 10, taken at a forensics laboratory a short distance away from Behesht-e Zahra, has also emerged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The videos show sobbing crowds searching through bodies piled on the floor as 40-foot-long refrigerator trucks, similar to those Kiarash described, arrive to unload still more dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final indignity is the burial itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arina Moradi, who works for the Norway-based rights group Hengaw, said that the authorities in Tehran had forced her family to pay money to retrieve the body of her cousin, Siavash Shirzad, 38. But they denied Mr. Shirzad’s family the right to bury him in his birth city, Bukan, in western Iran, where his family lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family was forced to bury him in a remote ancestral village instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They paid the money, then they had to agree they would not allow any demonstrations or anything, that they would bury him in silence,” Ms. Moradi said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tightly restricting burial rites, Mr. Ghaemi said, is a lesson that the Islamic Republic learned from the 1979 revolution. Then, funerals for protesters and the customary Shiite Muslim memorial services conducted 40 days after a person’s death became critical to maintaining the momentum of demonstrations that ultimately overthrew the shah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The reason authorities are so sensitive about where bodies get buried is that they become symbols to the people they live among — and the potential for gatherings at the cemetery that could ignite larger protest,” Mr. Ghaemi said. “They basically deny people the right to mourn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Behesht-e Zahra, Dian said that security guards had accompanied his family to their burial plot to monitor them. In a video shared by the family, the mourners simply chanted, “Honorable one! Honorable one!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash said that security guards had rushed his family friends through their final goodbyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One officer was standing over us: ‘You have 30 minutes to do whatever you need,’” Kiarash recalled. The friend was lowered into the grave; the dirt poured over her body was quickly watered to tamp down the dust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kiarash says that the silence imposed by the government’s crackdown cannot last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The word hatred is not strong enough to signify what people are feeling,” he said. “It’s over.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanam Mahoozi, Monika Cvorak and Artemis Moshtaghian contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/middleeast/iran-protests-victims-bodies.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 16:13:09 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>An Unlikely Source of Crypto Innovation: Afghanistan</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/crypto-innovation-afghanistan.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/00int-afghan-crypto-01-promo/00int-afghan-crypto-01-kvbh-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a bustling money changer in northwestern Syria, a 46-year-old farmer gripped a plastic card like a lifeline. She had never heard of cryptocurrency, but the card held $500 of it to help restart her farm after nearly 14 years of civil war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a teller confirmed the total and cashed out the account, the farmer, Hala Mahmoud Almahmoud, smiled with relief and paused to give thanks. Where had such technology come from, she asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer surprised her: Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain-based cash transfers are not the kind of innovation that many people would expect from a country better known for its repressive Taliban leadership, which views the internet with suspicion. But in a nation that has largely turned its back on the world, an Afghan start-up is building tools that it hopes will transform how humanitarian aid is delivered in countries shattered by conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve lived through these challenges ourselves, so we know how to develop an approach that works,” said Zakia Hussaini, 26, a programmer at the start-up, HesabPay, which designed the technology driving Ms. Almahmoud’s card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early proponent of the platform was the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees. The agency uses it to support more than 86,000 families in Afghanistan in one of the biggest public blockchain aid initiatives in the world. Mercy Corps, which donated the funds to Ms. Almahmoud, worked with HesabPay to expand its reach to include Syria, and programs for Sudan and Haiti are in development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Syria, getting money from abroad can be complicated. Cash is scarce, international banks steer clear of the country and remittance firms like Western Union can charge as much as 10 percent in transfer fees. HesabPay allows organizations like Mercy Corps to sidestep those roadblocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanzar Kakar, the Afghan American entrepreneur behind HesabPay, used to run Afghanistan’s leading payroll processor. But the U.S. withdrawal from Afghanistan in 2021 and the Taliban’s return set off a financial collapse. Sanctions put a halt to international transfers, and the central bank unraveled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address the country’s increasing financial insecurity, Mr. Kakar turned to blockchain. He built HesabPay, named after the local word for “account,” as a phone-based app that enabled instant transfers from one digital wallet to another, bypassing banks and the Taliban government. The Afghan government has since granted his business a license to operate officially as a financial institution, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the platform has more than 650,000 wallets in Afghanistan, of which about 50,000 are in regular use, moving approximately $60 million a month in stablecoins backed by the afghani, Afghanistan’s currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since February 2025, the U.N. has used HesabPay to deliver nearly $25 million via 80,000 digital wallets to vulnerable Afghans returning home, said Carmen Hett, the corporate treasurer of the U.N. refugee agency. “This helps reduce transaction fees, waiting periods and enhance traceability, real-time monitoring and accountability of transactions,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not surprising that organizations like Mercy Corps and the United Nations are turning to blockchain-based money transfers to deliver aid, said Ric Shreves, an expert in decentralized finance solutions and the president of the Decentralized Cooperation Foundation. For such organizations, he said, “it’s almost all upsides, compared to the way aid has traditionally been delivered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are still risks, he said, especially when the payment systems are based on local-currency stablecoins, as they are in Afghanistan. (In Syria, the cryptocurrency in HesabPay wallets is backed by the U.S. dollar, a more stable option.) Just as wallets can be shut down for interacting with sanctioned individuals, they can also theoretically be shut down by a country’s central bank for political reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When we provide people with a nonphysical means of doing transactions, that also means there’s a possibility that those transactions could be blocked through technological means,” Mr. Shreves said. Digital currencies are demonstrably safer than cash, he added, but they still cannot be stashed under a mattress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, aid groups have increasingly turned to cash as a fast and dignified form of assistance. But cash has a flaw: It is hard to track. Donors want proof that their money reaches the right hands. Since President Trump slashed U.S. foreign assistance early last year, groups like Mercy Corps have come under even more pressure to demonstrate their impact and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is where blockchain comes in, creating a digital trail that records exactly how much was sent, to whom, and where it was spent. That mix of speed and accountability could be “a way to win back trust from those who have come to doubt the usefulness of aid,” said Scott Onder, Mercy Corps’s chief investment officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HesabPay comes with additional safeguards, like a real-time dashboard that tracks wallet activity and cross-checks it against international compliance databases. The company says the system is designed to detect illicit activity like terrorist financing, money laundering and online scams, and to raise an alert the moment suspicious transactions appear. For aid donors, it offers a level of oversight rarely possible in fragile states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a recent online demonstration, Nigel Pont, the company’s senior adviser for humanitarian affairs, clicked on a purple dot representing a HesabPay agent in Afghanistan. Dozens of pale blue beneficiary wallets fanned out, showing recent transfers. Another click revealed where the money went next. Then one wallet pulsed red with a potential scam alert — an awkward moment in a live demo, but exactly the kind of risk the system is built to expose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“From an aid donor perspective, that’s immensely valuable,” said Mr. Pont, who previously served as chief strategy officer at Mercy Corps. “A system that can automatically flag a fraud risk means you can check it out immediately instead of waiting six months for a report that somebody stole 20 grand.” No system is entirely corruption-proof, he conceded, but then again, a bag of cash is not, either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abdul Halim Hasan, 22, who was waiting in the same line as Ms. Almahmoud for his turn at the money changer in Syria, said he imagined that one day he could use HesabPay as a regular bank account, receiving funds, making payments and saving money safely. But for the moment, it was enough that his HesabPay card allowed him to gain access to money he needed to restart his life after war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I certainly want to see this method spread in Syria,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leen Rihawi contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/crypto-innovation-afghanistan.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 20:01:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi’s Purge of China’s Military Brings Its Top General Down</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/china-top-general-xi-military-purge.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-china-military-mvfl/24int-china-military-mvfl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gen. Zhang Youxia, a vice chairman of China’s Central Military Commission, has been accused of “violations of discipline and the law,” the Ministry of National Defense said on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/asia/china-top-general-xi-military-purge.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 05:07:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What Europe Learned From the Greenland Crisis</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/sovereignty-european-union-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-europe-sovereignty-assess-01-jbpg/24int-europe-sovereignty-assess-01-jbpg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if the Europeans needed another wake-up call about the contempt in which President Trump holds them, his mocking antipathy at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, was a good reminder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Davos presented another lesson to Europe. Standing together on the principle of territorial integrity and sovereignty, while warning of severe economic countermeasures, the Europeans achieved an apparent retreat from Mr. Trump over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sovereignty and the inviolability of borders are fundamental tenets of the European project, built out of the ruins of World War II, when the aggressive imperialism of big powers led to millions of deaths. The lesson was clear: Defending borders collectively is the only way small states are protected from the predations of larger ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Europe finds itself again confronted by big powers with expansionist goals. Russia continues its effort to conquer Ukraine, whose sovereignty it had recognized in numerous treaties. And the United States has been demanding that Denmark, an E.U. and NATO ally, hand over Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But preserving territorial integrity and sovereignty is the red line, expressed both in the European Union, a collective of 27 nations, and in NATO, a military alliance of 32 nations. It can seem quixotic in the current world to be defending international law, the U.N. Charter and the Helsinki Accords, which all insist on the inviolability of borders, but in a sense, that is Europe’s fate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That borders can be challenged by force, and the threat of force threatens the core tenets of European security and aspirations since the end of World War II,” said Ian Lesser, the head of the Brussels office of the German Marshall Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The war in Ukraine brought it to the fore,” he continued, “but the idea that the United States, the principal guarantor of European security, should be challenging the concept of sovereignty and territorial integrity is a serious concern.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Leonard, the director of the European Council on Foreign Relations, argued that the continent has been rediscovering the importance of sovereignty in the face of challenges from the “great powers” of China, Russia and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most of European history since World War II has been about taming sovereignty and pooling it” in multilateral institutions, he said. But the new world is “fundamentally changing the nature of the E.U.,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans realize that they cannot defend the old, rules-based order on a global level, “but they can be sure it survives in Europe,” he said. “Thus the importance of Ukraine and Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Leonard said he hoped that “Europeans will take the lesson of the last few days, that when they stand up for sovereignty and territorial integrity and these rules they can defend them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mark Carney of Canada won praise for a speech in Davos in which he said that the old international order was dead. “Middle powers” like Canada and Europe, he said, must form new alliances as the great powers abandon postwar international norms and treaties and rely instead on “economic integration as weapons, tariffs as leverage, financial infrastructure as coercion, supply chains as vulnerabilities to be exploited.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a rupture in the old order, Mr. Carney said: “When the rules no longer protect you, you must protect yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has been absorbing that lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans have resisted Mr. Trump’s demands that Ukraine hand over to Russia territory that Moscow has not conquered. And the Europeans have insisted that even if a peace deal left Russian troops occupying 20 percent of Ukraine, the occupation would never be recognized as permanent, not even in Crimea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Europeans have come up with more money and military aid for Ukraine than the United States, and they have largely picked up the slack after Mr. Trump cut off funding for Ukraine. They recently agreed to another 90 billion euros ($106 billion) in economic and military aid to Kyiv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it has been the Europeans who have expressed solidarity with Denmark and Greenland against Mr. Trump’s demands to annex the island on the same principle of territorial integrity, and who seem to have caused him to back down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Emmanuel Macron of France spoke for many Europeans at Davos when he said, “Europe has very strong tools now, and we have to use them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Bart De Wever of Belgium was harsher. “So many red lines are being crossed,” he said at the forum. “Being a happy vassal in one thing, being a miserable slave is something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Trump presidency has taught Europe that its initial policy of flattering Mr. Trump has been a failure, and that standing up for core principles is vital, said a senior European official, speaking anonymously given the sensitivity of the U.S.-European relationship. In essence, he agreed, Europe has learned that a little flattery is fine, so long as you have a gun in your pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the case with Denmark and Greenland. For many weeks, European leaders and officials hoped that Mr. Trump would back down over his intention to take Greenland “the easy way” or “the hard way.” Instead he threatened even more punitive tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the European Union scheduled an emergency summit meeting for right after Davos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of Mr. Trump’s threats, the Europeans suspended a pending U.S.-E.U. trade agreement on tariffs that had been criticized as too weak. Instead, they prepared a retaliation of €93 billion ($109 billion) in countertariffs on American goods — the gun in the pocket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of those countertariffs upset the markets, said Mr. Leonard of the European Council on Foreign Relations. The effect appeared to have an impact on Mr. Trump and his aides, he said, by showing “that the Europeans were serious and through the markets they pushed Trump to pull back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, in discussion with Mark Rutte, the NATO secretary general, then appeared to back down, saying there was an unspecified framework for “a deal” on Greenland and removing his own threatened tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The president declared victory, but the real winner in this case were the Europeans, both the European Union and NATO, grasping on to this core principle of no border changes without the consent of the countries involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the E.U. summit meeting early Friday morning, Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, the bloc’s executive arm, said the latest tariff threats offered a tactical lesson for dealing with the United States. “Firmness, outreach, preparedness and unity” had been effective, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So going forward we should maintain this very approach.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smaller European nations, like the Baltic and Nordic states, are deeply worried about the great powers’ attack on sovereignty, said Jana Puglierin, head of the German office of the European Council on Foreign Relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is the end of their business model,” she said. “It’s the very foundation of the European Union and the postwar order, where one country gets one vote, no matter how small.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia, China and the United States are trying to change the entire international order, she said, and Europe is in the middle. All of those countries “are trying to split us,” she said, “because it is easier to deal with us when we are divided.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental question is whether the European Union and NATO can still function in this new, more rapacious world, she said. These institutions “are based on the invulnerability of sovereignty and the principle of consensus, and the challenge now is to the very existence of the organizations that have brought peace and prosperity to Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/sovereignty-european-union-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 23:49:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How a Water Balloon Fight in Venezuela Ended in Charges of Treason</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/americas/venezuela-arrests-repression.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-venezuela-repression-blwp/24int-venezuela-repression-blwp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The boys were there for a water balloon fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an annual tradition to start Carnival celebrations in Barcelona, a working-class coastal city in Venezuela’s east. But only two days after the capture of the nation’s president, Nicolás Maduro, all of their shouting and laughing was not sitting well with the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local police officers and National Guard soldiers arrived in force and, according to two of the boys and the relatives of four others, fired shots. The boys and young men — aged 13 to 25 — scattered, but the police arrested 25 of them. Two days later, state prosecutors filed charges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their crime? Treason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“‘I’m going to screw you all over,’” one of the boys, 17, recalled a police officer telling him after his arrest, using an expletive. “‘You all support Donald Trump.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reporter and photographer from The New York Times this past week visited the neighborhood where most of the detainees live and interviewed two of the boys and seven of their family members. Many of them, as well as other Venezuelans across the country, spoke on the condition of anonymity out of fear of reprisal from the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those interviews revealed that, under the Venezuelan interim government backed by the Trump administration, citizen surveillance and repression are alive and well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has praised Venezuela’s interim leadership as highly cooperative, particularly in opening up U.S. access to the country’s oil. Those leaders, who are the same people who helped direct the authoritarian Maduro regime, have also drawn positive headlines for their release of nearly 150 political prisoners, or about a sixth of the nation’s estimated total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But at the same time, they have quietly added to those ranks, detaining and jailing people suspected of opposing the government, as part of a nationwide campaign to stamp out dissent since the United States captured Mr. Maduro three weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces have set up checkpoints on highways, searched citizens’ cellphones, extorted people whose phones contained criticism of the government and arrested dozens of others suspected of celebrating Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can be detained simply for traveling the streets. Not in the sense that they put you in prison, but that they stop you and demand your phone,” said Andrés Azpúrua, an internet-freedom activist in Venezuela who tracks government repression. “This has been happening for a long time. But not at these scales.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that many Venezuelans, while maybe more hopeful since Mr. Maduro’s capture, remain terrified of saying so out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We know what’s going on, but no one can express an opinion,” said a 49-year-old driver, who lives in the same state as the detained boys. “We want to shout, to celebrate, but we can’t. I want to, but I don’t know where.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the interview, the man frequently spoke in a whisper, worried his neighbor might overhear and report him to the police. He added that he leaves his phone behind every time he goes out, fearful the police will search it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Venezuelan government did not respond to a request for comment. Diosdado Cabello, the nation’s powerful interior minister who runs much of the state’s intelligence and security forces, acknowledged last week that some officers had extorted citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have told the police officers that for anyone who wants to be a policeman, extortion has no place here,” he said, according to a post from his political party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuelans’ anxiety is driven by years of harsh, systematic repression by the Maduro government. A complex mix of security forces — from military soldiers and police officers, to intelligence agents and masked, armed militias — spied on, threatened, extorted and arrested people perceived to be a potential threat to the regime. Targets included opposition politicians, activists, academics, journalists and even regular people who had simply criticized the government in private conversations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past two weeks, Venezuelan authorities have slowly been releasing about a sixth of the nation’s nearly 900 political prisoners, according to human-rights groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House has taken credit. Mr. Trump has also consistently praised Venezuela’s interim leader, Delcy Rodríguez, who was Mr. Maduro’s vice president, while undercutting her rival, María Corina Machado, the exiled opposition leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She’s doing a very good job. We have a very good relationship,” Mr. Trump said of Ms. Rodríguez this past week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, Ms. Rodríguez has been overseeing a crackdown at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day Mr. Maduro was captured, Ms. Rodríguez announced a state of emergency in Venezuela that, in effect, gave the government the authority to detain anyone suspected of supporting the U.S. attack. She claimed Mr. Maduro had signed the measure — supposedly as he rushed for safety after the attacks began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, Venezuelan authorities have arrested at least 31 people and accused them of supporting the U.S. attack, according to an analysis of local news reports. Several were detained for videos they posted on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most striking case was the arrest of the 25 boys and young men in Barcelona, a midsize city about five hours east of Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the recent visit by The Times journalists, the city was on edge. Armed officers at four checkpoints interrogated and sometimes searched passers-by. At sundown in the dense neighborhood where the detainees lived, about a dozen police officers on motorcycles patrolled the streets. The police presence had increased since Mr. Maduro’s capture, according to residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble for the neighborhood youth began on Jan. 5. Boys and young men filled water balloons at the bank of the Neverí River and then, according to videos, chased one another around a vacant lot, tossing the balloons and laughing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the authorities showed up, the young people thought the arrests would be only temporary to teach them a lesson about causing commotion in the street. But when the police began mentioning Mr. Trump and Mr. Maduro, and then transferred the group to a larger jail, it became clear the situation was more serious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We all started crying and asking why, saying that they weren’t criminals, that they were just children playing for Carnival,” said the mother of two detainees, describing the scene of distressed parents outside the jailhouse. “Because the country was in trouble,” the police told her, she added. “And if we knew how the country was, why did we let our children be in the street?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifteen minors in the group were arraigned on several charges including “treason to the homeland,” according to a court document viewed by The Times. Families of the 10 detainees over 18 said they had also been charged with treason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Families began distributing videos about the teenagers on social media, denouncing their detention. The videos gained traction in the local community, and a week after they were jailed, the authorities released the 15 minors under the condition that they remain in Venezuela and return to court once a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the 10 adult detainees remain imprisoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I haven’t eaten for days,” said Scarlett Ruiz, 24, the sister of one detainee who is 19 and had been preparing to enter college this year. She said the family has been taking him meals and attending court hearings for the past two weeks, watching his condition deteriorate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My brother isn’t sleeping. He has bags under his eyes,” Ms. Ruiz said. “They tell them things like, ‘You’re not going to get out of here.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;María Reyes said she worried about her 21-year-old son in detention because he regularly suffered from epileptic seizures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Karen García, the mother of an 18-year-old detainee, said she had not seen her son since Jan. 5. She is confused how her family got wrapped up in the situation. “We’re not political people at all, nor are we interested in giving opinions on that,” she said. “The only thing we want is freedom for our boys.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/americas/venezuela-arrests-repression.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 01:01:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran’s Ayatollah and His Guards Falter After Storm of War and Protests</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/middleeast/iran-protests-ayatollah-revolutionary-guards.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-iran-irgc01a-photo-gkhw/24int-iran-irgc01a-photo-gkhw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weeks after Israeli warplanes pounded Iran’s capital last June, the country’s top generals stood in their socks at the entrance of a mosque in northern Tehran, mourning the men who had been killed in the strikes — leaders who they would now replace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strikes had caused the greatest single blow to Iran’s military in decades, wiping out the top leadership of the Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps, the feared praetorian guard to the country’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the question was how would this new generation of leaders, catapulted to the top, would guide the country through a singularly challenging period, including growing economic stress, the prospect of new international sanctions and regular threats of yet more military strikes from President Trump and Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer came in recent weeks when those new leaders responded to nationwide protests with breathtaking brutality, opening fire on unarmed protesters and massacring thousands of people. At least one Iranian human rights group based in the United States said it had confirmed 5,002 deaths, including 207 members of the security forces, during the protests from Dec. 28 to mid-January. In their first official toll on Wednesday, the Iranian authorities said that 3,117 people had died.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface, the bloody crackdown affirmed the unity of Iran’s ruling system — centered on the ayatollah and the Revolutionary Guards, estimated to number about 150,000 — and its willingness to take ruthless action to ensure its survival. But Iran experts said the bloody response was also a sign of the system’s growing weakness, exposing the limits of Ayatollah Khamenei’s 37-year rule as he wrestles with surging domestic unrest and intense foreign pressure at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, Mr. Trump said that an American “armada” was heading toward Iran, but that he hoped he would not have to use it. He again warned the Iranian government against killing protesters or restarting its nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That combination of factors put the ruling system under immense strain, said Afshon Ostovar, an Iran expert at the Naval Postgraduate School in California and the author of “Vanguard of the Imam,” a history of the Revolutionary Guards. “Right off the bat, they saw the protests as an existential threat,” he said. “They turned to live fire really quickly because their weakness was acute, and they knew it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ayatollah’s legitimacy under open challenge, the Revolutionary Guards are emerging as the core of the system. “You have this aging theocrat whose days are numbered,” Mr. Ostovar said. “And you have security forces that are taking an increasingly aggressive response to any threat to the regime.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upheaval has renewed comparisons between the Islamic Republic and the Soviet Union in the 1980s, before it collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran has seldom faced a greater array of challenges. Its network of regional proxies, including Hezbollah and Hamas, is in tatters. Its contentious nuclear program, estimated to cost tens of billions of dollars, failed to bring deterrence. Supplies of water and electricity are running low. Edicts forcing Iranian women to wear head scarves, a symbolic totem of the ayatollah’s conservative rule, are being openly flouted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The regime is ideologically bankrupt, economically at a dead end, and unable to rescue itself,” said Ali Vaez, the Iran project director for the International Crisis Group, a research body. “But it still has the will, and a fearsome capacity for repression.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ayatollah, who promised to strengthen the Islamic Republic after he came to power in 1989, has led the country into this predicament, critics say. His intransigence, rooted in resistance to the United States and Israel, but also in opposition to change at home, was once a pillar of his iron rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that approach is seen by some as a mark of vulnerability, even by some of his own supporters, and analysts say his authority is at its lowest in decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The American and Israeli airstrikes in June initially provoked a nationalist surge inside Iran, as people across the political spectrum united against foreign aggression. “All these stupid attacks by the Zionists have brought Iranians together,” Abdulkarim Alizadeh, a retired commander with the Revolutionary Guards, said last summer as he left the mosque in northern Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s enemies had “miscalculated” if they hoped the attacks would provoke a popular uprising, Kamal Kharazi, a senior adviser to the supreme leader, told The New York Times in July. “On the contrary,” he said, “the war led to national unity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are prepared for all scenarios,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But defiance soon gave way to economic reality as the United Nations imposed new sanctions on Iran, causing the national currency to collapse. Protests on Dec. 28 in Tehran’s the main bazaars — whose merchants played a central role in the 1979 revolution — quickly spread across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, the balance of power in Iran has been quietly shifting from Ayatollah Khamenei, 86, to the Revolutionary Guards. They are not only a security behemoth. They control a media empire, large parts of the economy, oil exports, seaports, an intelligence agency and an air force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They have everything that it takes to assume power,” Mr. Vaez said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One scenario is that a figure favored by the Revolutionary Guards would seize power after the death of Ayatollah Khamenei, transforming Iran from a theocracy to a military-dominated country like Pakistan or Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another scenario is that a faction of the Revolutionary Guards, fearful of American-backed regime change, could move against him first. “While a military coup was unthinkable a few years ago,” Mr. Ostovar said, “it’s becoming increasingly likely now because of all the pressures building on the regime.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The picture is further complicated by the generational divide inside the Revolutionary Guards, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the older generation came of age during the war with Iraq in the 1980s, a time of deprivation and hardship, younger officers rose through the ranks at a time of Iranian expansion, as its influence spread through Syria, Iraq, Lebanon and Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dismayed by the loss of that foreign network over the past few years, as well as by the severe damage to Iran’s nuclear program caused by the 12-day war in June, a more aggressive and assertive faction has emerged among younger members of the Revolutionary Guards, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while an older group of Revolutionary Guards has gotten rich — with children in elite private schools, homes in foreign countries and luxury cars — the younger generation has yet to taste much of that wealth, and wants to protect what it sees as its rightful reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They know that if the regime goes, they will lose their meal ticket — and be first in line for retribution,” Mr. Ostovar said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where Iran goes from here is hard to know, but its future path has drawn comparisons with countries like North Korea, Turkey, Egypt and Russia. Still, predictions are fraught: In recent weeks, the internet has been restricted and a curtain of fear has fallen over the country, making information especially scarce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s government has survived at least four earlier waves of protest, many of which also stirred speculation of regime change, while the ayatollah has defied rumors that he was dying of cancer or was in poor health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But most analysts agree that, this time, the pressure on Ayatollah Khamenei and the Revolutionary Guards is likely to only increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not a sustainable situation where you wait for an elderly leader to die to put things back in order,” said Mr. Vaez, drawing comparisons with the last years of Mao Zedong in China, or Leonid I. Brezhnev in the Soviet Union. In Iran, “the problem is the country doesn’t have the time to wait him out.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/middleeast/iran-protests-ayatollah-revolutionary-guards.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 01:00:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine Expects Answers From Russia as Peace Talks Continue, Zelensky Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/ukraine-us-russia-peace-talks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-ukraine-talks-lmgj/24int-ukraine-talks-lmgj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rare three-way talks among Russian, Ukrainian and American officials entered their second day on Saturday in the United Arab Emirates, as President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine said that he expected “at least some answers” from Russia on the current draft of a plan to end the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peace plan originated last fall as a proposal negotiated between the Trump administration and Russia, but it has since been revised several times, with input from Ukraine, the United States, European nations and other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky argued in recent days that it was time for Russia to provide answers on the peace plan as it now stands, even as Moscow has shown little appetite to stop its attacks on Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peace plan’s 20 points cover security, postwar reconstruction, exchanges of prisoners and other matters tied to the conflict, which started nearly four years ago with Russia’s full-scale invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking late Friday after the first day of talks, Mr. Zelensky said in a video address to Ukrainians that he was regularly in touch with the country’s negotiators in Abu Dhabi, the capital of the United Arab Emirates, and that they “should already have at least some answers” on Moscow’s position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Zelensky said it was “still too early to draw conclusions” on whether Russia would negotiate in good faith. The talks are expected to wrap up on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is necessary that not only Ukraine has the desire to end this war and achieve full security, but that a similar desire somehow emerges in Russia as well,” Mr. Zelensky said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite some progress in recent months of peace negotiations, Ukraine and Russia are still at odds over key sticking points tied to security and territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Ukraine fleshed out proposals for postwar security guarantees with both the United States and Europe, with some European countries vowing that they would commit troops to dissuade Russia from invading again. But Moscow has rejected any deployment of troops from NATO member states on Ukrainian territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Ukrainian authorities have refused Russia’s request to control all of the Donetsk region, a former industrial and coal-mining powerhouse in eastern Ukraine that the war has left mostly in ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Ukrainian negotiators have discussed what Steve Witkoff, the Trump administration’s envoy for peace talks, has called various “iterations” of compromises. Suggestions have included putting neutral forces as peacekeepers in part of the Donetsk region or forming a demilitarized zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Russia has rejected any settlement on territory that departs from what Russian officials have characterized as an agreement reached between President Trump and President Vladimir V. Putin at a summit in Alaska last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After those talks, neither leader publicly laid out a detailed plan for dividing Ukrainian territory, although Mr. Trump told European leaders at the time that he supported a plan to end the war by ceding unconquered territory to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Mr. Zelensky said the talks in the United Arab Emirates would focus on control of territory in eastern Ukraine. Any compromise for Ukraine would be bitter after more than a decade of bloodshed defending the region, beginning with a first Russian military incursion in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky told reporters at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Thursday that “we are at the moment, if all the sides will work a lot, we will end this war.” But he also suggested that Russia might “play games” that would derail talks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/ukraine-us-russia-peace-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 03:29:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How a Year of Trump Changed Britain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/trump-uk-changes.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-uk-trump-01-mfcp/24int-uk-trump-01-mfcp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain has learned, after a roller coaster year that ended in a tense confrontation over Greenland, that it cannot change President Trump. The more tantalizing question is whether Mr. Trump has changed Britain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer’s charm offensive toward the president did not spare Britain a fusillade of new tariff threats and stinging social media posts over the British government’s opposition to Mr. Trump’s designs on Greenland. Mr. Starmer might argue that Mr. Trump’s subsequent climb-down validated his emollient approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Mr. Trump also turned against a deal made by Mr. Starmer, which he had previously endorsed, to relinquish a chain of strategically sensitive islands in the Indian Ocean to Mauritius. He disparaged it as an “act of GREAT STUPIDITY,” handing Mr. Starmer’s opponents a cudgel with which to beat him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, the leader of the opposition Conservative Party, Kemi Badenoch, parroted Mr. Trump’s criticism. “This is surrendering British territory, with a strategic military base on it, for no reason whatsoever,” she said to Sky News, referring to the air base on an island in the chain, Diego Garcia, which is jointly operated by Britain and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never mind that Britain began negotiating the return of the chain, the Chagos Islands, under a government led by Ms. Badenoch’s Conservatives. Or that Mr. Trump’s pique appeared to be caused less by the loss of the islands than by Mr. Starmer’s refusal to go along with an American takeover of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a telling example of how Mr. Trump has commandeered the political debate in Britain, often shifting it in his direction. On topics as diverse as immigration, climate change, geopolitics and social justice, Mr. Trump has moved Britain’s “Overton window,” the term used to refer to the range of ideas that are considered acceptable to mainstream society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no doubt that Trump has shifted the center of gravity in British politics,” said Tim Bale, a professor of politics at Queen Mary University of London. “Politicians on the right — and not just those who belong to the populist, radical right but to a supposedly mainstream party like the Conservatives — are prepared to propose policies and use language that hitherto would have been seen as beyond the pale.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just as importantly, like Trump, they’ve gotten away with it,” he added, “and, as a result, are tempted to go further and further — all of which has led to both a coarsening and a polarization of debate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Mr. Starmer, a center-left politician known for his tempered style, has strayed into the divisive rhetoric of Mr. Trump. Last year, speaking about immigration, he warned that Britain risked becoming an “island of strangers” if it did not regain control of its borders. (Mr. Starmer later expressed regret for those words, which drew invidious comparisons to an infamous speech about immigration by a Conservative Party lawmaker, Enoch Powell, in 1968.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under pressure from a right-wing anti-immigration party, Reform U.K., which is in turn partly inspired by Mr. Trump, the Labour government has adopted strikingly tougher policies toward asylum seekers. Mr. Starmer has posted photographs and footage on social media of young men being rounded up, fingerprinted and interviewed by the authorities, and the government has boasted about the removal of almost 50,000 people since it came to power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s influence is felt in a backlash against diversity, equity and inclusion policies. Blue Labour, an activist group that promotes culturally conservative values within the Labour Party, has called on the government to legislate against such policies in hiring, in part to fend off the threat from Reform. The Guardian newspaper reported in October that many British companies were changing their policies in response to attacks on “woke” policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, too, there is Mr. Trump’s insurgency against the establishment, which has its echoes in Britain. This month, a former senior adviser to Mr. Starmer, Paul Ovenden, roiled political waters with a column in The Times of London, in which he condemned unelected civil servants who, he claimed, waste their time on “political folderol” rather than on issues that ordinary citizens care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The supremacy of the Stakeholder State,” Mr. Ovenden called it, in words that bear more than a passing resemblance to the “deep state” vilified by allies of Mr. Trump, like Stephen K. Bannon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the changes in British policies, like the cuts to foreign aid, are driven by fiscal constraints. Others, like the pressure to water down climate change targets, are prompted by fears that they could hamper long-term economic growth. Yet they dovetail with Mr. Trump’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain has continued to embrace renewable energy even as Mr. Trump has ridiculed the wind turbines that dot the North Sea. “One thing I’ve noticed,” Mr. Trump said in Davos, Switzerland, this past week, “is that the more windmills a country has, the more money that country loses and the worse that country is doing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s influence is not limited to Britain. Timothy Garton Ash, an author and historian at Oxford University, argued that the president had had a bigger effect on Germany and Poland. Germany has embarked on a landmark rearmament program to compensate for Mr. Trump’s disengagement from Europe. In Poland, the right-wing populist Law and Justice Party benefited from Mr. Trump’s endorsement in last year’s presidential elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Where you can see his influence in Britain is on the right-wing conversation,” Mr. Garton Ash said. “It has blurred the boundaries between liberal conservatives and the anti-liberal right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Starmer fended off Ms. Badenoch’s attacks on the Chagos Islands deal, one could see the risks in Mr. Trump’s influence. The prime minister told Parliament, in an uncharacteristic break with Mr. Trump, that the president’s criticism was not about the islands but was a calculated effort to put pressure on Britain to acquiesce in his attempted conquest of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By jumping on Mr. Trump’s remarks, Mr. Starmer said, Ms. Badenoch was “undermining our position, Britain’s position, on Greenland.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer’s steely tone suggested that there were limits to his solicitous treatment of Mr. Trump. He said he would not be cowed, either by the president’s reversal on the Chagos deal or by threats of additional tariffs. Mr. Trump dropped the tariff threat after negotiating the outlines of a deal on Greenland with NATO. But on Friday, the Conservatives forced the government to delay a debate in Parliament on legislation enshrining the Chagos deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diplomats have credited Mr. Starmer’s softly-softly approach to the president with reducing the damage of tariffs — the Trump administration signed a first-in-the-world trade deal with Britain — and with keeping Mr. Trump more engaged in the war in Ukraine than he might otherwise have been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, said Peter Westmacott, a former British ambassador to Washington, “It did not moderate Trump’s demands for Greenland, while his ill-informed outburst on Diego Garcia was plain nasty. So Starmer has had to call him out publicly on important issues of principle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most vivid example of this came on Friday when Mr. Starmer rebuked Mr. Trump for saying that European troops had “stayed a little off the front lines” during the Afghanistan war. Mr. Starmer said his remarks were “insulting and frankly appalling” to Britain, which lost 457 soldiers in two decades of fighting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The challenge,” Mr. Westmacott said, “is to do that without provoking even worse reactions from the notoriously thin-skinned president.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/trump-uk-changes.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 01:01:52 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>