<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:07:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Live Updates: Trains Collide After Derailment in Spain, Killing at Least 21</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-spain-derail-kjhc/18int-spain-derail-kjhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A high-speed train smashed into another train after derailing in the southern province of Córdoba, officials said. The cause of the accident was not immediately clear.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:24:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Guatemala Declares State of Emergency to Address Gang Violence</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/guatemala-emergency-drug-cartels.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19xp-guatemala-jfpl/19xp-guatemala-jfpl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Guatemalan riot police officers guard the entrance to the men’s Preventive Detention Center in Guatemala City on Sunday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/guatemala-emergency-drug-cartels.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:56:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What We Know About the Deadly High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high-speed train ran off its track and crashed into another high-speed train late Sunday in southern Spain, killing at least 21 people and injuring dozens of others, according to the local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accident is the deadliest train accident in Spainsince 2013, when 80 people died after a train veered off a curved section of track in the country’s northwest. The country has the second-longest high-speed rail network in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision on Sunday occurred at 7:45 p.m. in Adamuz, in the southern province of Córdoba. The train that derailed first was a privately-operated one that was traveling to Madrid from Málaga, on the country’s southern coast. The rear cars of that train fell into the opposite track, where it collided with an incoming train operated by Spain’s national rail company, which was bound for the southern city of Huelva, west of Seville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo, the operator of the first train, said that around 300 passengers were on board at the time of the crash. Renfe, the operator of the second train, has not said how many passengers it was carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spain’s state-owned rail infrastructure agency said in a statement that rail traffic between Madrid and several major cities in southern Andalucía — including Córdoba, Seville, Málaga and Huelva — will be suspended on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency response crews continued to search through the wreckage of the crash early Monday, with officials warning that the death toll may rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 2013 disaster, the derailment on Sunday happened on a straight portion of the track. An independent commission has been launched to investigate what caused it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, told reporters that the first train to derail was only a few years old and that the section of the track where the accident occurred had been recently renovated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accident is extremely strange,” he said. “It happened on a straightaway. All the experts we have consulted are extremely baffled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “If there had not been an oncoming train, we would not be talking about casualties of any type.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez of Spain expressed sympathy for the victims’ families on social media, saying that “the entire country stands with them in this extremely difficult moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tonight is a night of deep pain for our country,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Andalucía government has set up a medical post at the crash site for victims, while the Córdoba city government has issued an urgent appeal for doctors to help treat the injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paco Carmona, the director of Córdoba’s fire brigade, told public television that emergency crews were prioritizing assistance for victims still trapped in the two carriages most severely damaged in the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:03:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Davos Convenes, Deference to Trump Has Replaced Everything</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/davos-president-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19Biz-Davos-preview-01-hvwf/19Biz-Davos-preview-01-hvwf-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Attendees at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, last year.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/davos-president-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:28:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain Closes High-Speed Rail Network in South After Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-high-speed-rail-closed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-rail-network-ghbv/18spain-crash-rail-network-ghbv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Passengers at a train station in Madrid on Sunday, after the train derailment in southern Spain.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-high-speed-rail-closed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:56:27 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Human Rights Lawyer Philippe Sands Fears a New Age of Impunity</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/magazine/genocide-trial-human-right-international-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/01/magazine/01mag-sands-HP-square/01mag-sands-HP-square-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philippe Sands, one of the world’s pre-eminent human rights attorneys, grew up in the shadow of bleak times. He worries that history is taking an unfortunate detour.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/magazine/genocide-trial-human-right-international-law.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:52:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Has an Offramp on Greenland. He Doesn’t Seem to Want It.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-greenland-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19dc-assess-01-qvgt/19dc-assess-01-qvgt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
For President Trump, the sheer size of Greenland’s territory holds part of the appeal; it is about three times the size of Texas, and bigger than Alaska.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-greenland-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:03:57 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Survivors of Deadly Train Crash in Spain Describe Hellish Scenes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-train-crash-survivors.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-spain-crash-eyewitness-photo-hbpq/19int-spain-crash-eyewitness-photo-hbpq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Members of the Spanish Civil Guard, along with other emergency personnel, working next to one of the trains involved in the accident in Adamuz on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-train-crash-survivors.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:46:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The crash occurred on a new stretch of high-speed rail track, officials say.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/the-crash-occurred-on-a-new-stretch-of-high-speed-rail-track-officials-say</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-network-glmp/18spain-crash-network-glmp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A train operated by Iryo, a private company, that partially derailed and was hit by another train on Monday near Adamuz, in southern Spain.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/the-crash-occurred-on-a-new-stretch-of-high-speed-rail-track-officials-say</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:37:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A labor union raised concerns last year about Spain’s railway lines.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/a-labor-union-raised-concerns-last-year-about-spains-railway-lines</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-union-letter-tzlq/18spain-crash-union-letter-tzlq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Members of the Spanish Civil Guard, along with other emergency personnel, work next to one of the trains involved in the accident, in Cordoba, Spain, on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/a-labor-union-raised-concerns-last-year-about-spains-railway-lines</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:12:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How 40 People Died In a Train Crash in Andalucia, Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw/18spain-crash-scene-mqvw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Emergency officials at the scene of the crash on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-crash-scene-40-train-track.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:35:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Taxing the Ultrarich</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/taxing-billionaires-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/multimedia/20int-theworld-billionaires-promo/20int-theworld-billionaires-promo-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of billionaires has exploded, yet they often pay taxes at rates well below average.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/taxing-billionaires-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:28:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Prince Harry’s Case Against Daily Mail Publisher</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prince Harry’s latest legal case in Britain is set to begin on Monday in London’s High Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prince and several other high-profile figures are accusing Associated Newspapers, the publisher of The Daily Mail, of unlawful information gathering, including phone hacking, and of intruding into their private lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial is set to last for more than two months, and Harry is scheduled to testify on Thursday. The other claimants include Elton John and his husband, David Furnish, the actresses Liz Hurley and Sadie Frost, a former British government minister, and a racial justice campaigner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry and the other claimants accuse the company of carrying out or commissioning unlawful activities to reveal private information about their lives for articles published from 1997 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written arguments presented at a preliminary hearing in May said there had been “clear, systematic and sustained use of unlawful information gathering by private investigators” hired by Associated Newspapers, with “payments spanning decades” and involvement by newspaper executives and numerous journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators are accused of hacking and tapping phones, placing listening devices in cars and “blagging” — a way of tricking people into handing over information — to obtain phone numbers, personal records and bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newspaper group, which owns The Daily Mail, The Mail on Sunday and several other titles that are not implicated in the case, has denied all the accusations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a preliminary hearing on Thursday, four days before the trial was to start, a lawyer for Associated Newspapers, Anthony White, said he would argue that some of the claimants’ witnesses “are not telling the truth” and that he would raise questions about their credibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated Newspapers said in a statement that its journalists had not commissioned or obtained information derived from illegal activity and called the accusations “preposterous and without foundation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It added, “The stories concerned, many of which were published 20 or more years ago, and not subject to any complaint at the time, were the product of responsible journalism based on legitimate sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a schedule jointly drawn up by both legal teams, the trial will run for more than two months and end on March 26. The judge hearing the case, Matthew Nicklin, is expected to consider the evidence and arguments before giving a ruling at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case will begin with lawyers for the claimants and Associated Newspapers giving an outline of their case. Prince Harry is expected to give evidence in person at the High Court on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elton John, the other claimants and witnesses, including Ms. Frost’s former husband, the actor Jude Law, are also set to be questioned by lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators accused of wrongdoing will appear at the trial, as will the former editor of The Daily Mail, Paul Dacre, and several past and present Associated Newspapers executives and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case is one of several pursued by Harry since 2020, when he and his wife, Meghan Markle, stepped down from their royal roles and left Britain, later making their home in Montecito, Calif.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have centered on accusations of press intrusion, which Harry said was a key reason behind their decision to move. In an interview with Oprah Winfrey in 2021, Harry said that he feared “history repeating itself,” referring to the death of his mother, Princess Diana, in a car crash while she was being chased by paparazzi in Paris in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said there was an “invisible contract” between Britain’s royal family and the country’s tabloids, adding, “There is a level of control by fear that has existed for generations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owners of The Daily Mirror, another tabloid, settled a claim over phone hacking in February 2024. During that case, Harry became the first senior royal to testify in court since 1891.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2025, Rupert Murdoch’s News Group Newspapers agreed to pay a “substantial” amount of damages to Harry to settle a long-running lawsuit relating to articles in The Sun and the long-closed News of the World. News Group apologized for “serious intrusion” into Harry’s personal life between 1996 and 2011 and admitted for the first time to unlawful activities by private investigators working for The Sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry lost an unrelated legal battle last May over his publicly funded security in Britain, which was downgraded after his decision to step back from royal duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But late last year, the government body responsible for royal security decisions began a review of his protection arrangements, according to two people familiar with the situation who were not given permission to speak publicly. The review appears to offer a glimmer of good news for the prince, who has spoken of his desire to visit Britain with his family if his automatic right to security is reinstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael D. Shear contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 08:07:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>French Prime Minister Sébastien Lecornu Says He Will Pass Budget Without a Vote</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/france-budget-no-confidence-vote.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-france-budget01-photo-jpcw/19int-france-budget01-photo-jpcw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Sébastien Lecornu in the National Assembly in Paris on Wednesday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/france-budget-no-confidence-vote.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:26:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sanae Takaichi, Japan’s Prime Minister, Calls for Snap Election</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sanae Takaichi, the prime minister of Japan, called early elections just three months into her tenure.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:57:02 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza’s Board of Peace: What to Know</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp/19int-gaza-board-explain-photo-zhkp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Gaza City in December.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:02:28 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Hezbollah’s Ties to Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/hezbollah-venezuela-ties.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2020/04/24/world/19int-venezuela-hezbollah/19int-venezuela-hezbollah-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Hezbollah fighters at the Lebanon-Syria border in 2017.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/hezbollah-venezuela-ties.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:27:25 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At the Center of Trump’s Vision for Rebuilding Ukraine: BlackRock</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mezhova, in eastern Ukraine, in December. Ukrainian officials have likened their country’s recovery blueprint to the Marshall Plan, the U.S.-funded project to rebuild Europe after World War II.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:49:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Clashes Erupt Around Syrian Prisons Holding Islamic State Fighters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/syria-prisons-isis.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19syria-prisons-01-zpqj/19syria-prisons-01-zpqj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clashes erupted on Monday around two prisons in northeastern Syria holding members of the terrorist group Islamic State, a day after a Kurdish-led militia agreed to hand over control over the prisons to the Syrian government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That agreement between the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., and the central government ended weeks of deadly clashes between the two sides. The S.D.F. agreed to merge into the national military and hand over control of security infrastructure — including prisons housing about 8,000 Islamic State detainees — to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the clashes around two of those prisons underscored the fragility of that deal. Within hours, both the government and the S.D.F. accused each other of trying to derail the agreement. The government accused the S.D.F. of releasing Islamic State detainees from al-Shaddadi prison in Hasakah Province and of exploiting the security threat posed by those detainees for political gains, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement was a significant victory for the government and a stunning setback for the S.D.F., which lost control over territory, oil resources and other strategic assets just in the past few days. The S.D.F. emerged with few cards to play in future negotiations over any power its leaders and its forces may retain as part of the new government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The violence also revived fears around whether the new government would be able to maintain the same level of security the S.D.F. had in an area that once served as the heartland of the Islamic State.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Monday evening, Syrian officials said they had taken control of al-Shaddadi prison and were combing the area in an effort to rearrest an unspecified number of prisoners they said had been released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F., in turn, accused armed groups “affiliated” with those in power in Damascus, the capital, of attacking the prison early Monday morning, without identifying the attackers more specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S.D.F. officials also accused armed groups of attacking another prison, al-Aqtan, in Raqqa, which is the largest city administered by Kurdish authorities and which once served as the capital of the Islamic State’s self-proclaimed caliphate. At least nine S.D.F. fighters were killed in the clashes, the S.D.F said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clashes made it clear that the cease-fire reached on Sunday had not yet quelled the tensions between Kurdish forces and Syria’s central government over who controls the country’s northeastern region. The Islamic State seized much of that region in 2014 and ruled it for years before the S.D.F., with U.S. backing, reclaimed the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government institutions in the northeastern province, a semiautonomous region long administered by the Kurds, will also come under the central government’s authority as will Syria’s gas and oil fields in the area, nearly all of which have been under Kurdish control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The agreement was widely viewed as little more than a surrender by the S.D.F., which for months has been in stalled negotiations with the government over the terms of their integration into the new Syrian state that assumed control after the ouster of the dictator Bashar al-Assad in late 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after a lightning advance by the Syrian military into Kurdish-held territory this month, the S.D.F. forces were put on the back foot and ultimately agreed to the cease-fire deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the deal, the central government was to assume security responsibility over prisons holding more than 8,000 Islamic State members captured during the civil war, including al-Shaddadi and al-Aqtan prisons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central government is also to take over the sprawling Al Hol detention camp, which houses tens of thousands of family members of Islamic State fighters, many of them foreigners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the clashes around the prisons broke out, the S.D.F. accused the U.S.-led coalition, which maintains a few troops on the ground, of ignoring calls for help. A senior U.S. military official denied the S.D.F. claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second U.S. official, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss operational matters, said Monday they are working to de-escalate the tense situation. The official also said a number of prisoners had been recaptured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Islamic State seized territory in northeastern Syria in 2014 and ruled there and neighboring Iraq for years, brutally enforcing its strict interpretation of Islamic law. As the S.D.F. battled to reclaim that land with U.S. support, they detained thousands of ISIS fighters and tens of thousands of their relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the years since the Islamic State was routed in 2017, the land that was retaken in northeastern Syria has remained under S.D.F. control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. al-Assad’s ouster, the S.D.F. entered negotiations to integrate into the new national military. The deal on Sunday was the second it had struck with the government in less than a year. Whether it holds up is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday evening, the Syrian government sought to position itself as the best ally to international partners in dealing with the threat from ISIS detainees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Interior Ministry accused the S.D.F. of a “serious security violation threatening Syrian, regional, and international security,” in a statement on X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Restoring legitimate state institutions and enforcing the rule of law are the only permanent guarantees of security and stability.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Schmitt contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/middleeast/syria-prisons-isis.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:04:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Splits Emerge Among Venezuelans as Revolutionary Dream Fades</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/venezuela-chavismo-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-venezuela-chavista-vfgw/19int-venezuela-chavista-vfgw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For nearly three decades, Venezuelans have been fed an ideology of “Chavismo,” with its goal of harnessing oil wealth to transform the country, empower the poor and stand up to the United States and its imperial ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet on Thursday, the director of the C.I.A. was in Caracas to meet with Venezuela’s interim president to discuss greater bilateral collaboration, as Washington starts to take its cut of the country’s vast oil wealth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the United States invaded to snatch President Nicolás Maduro this month, Venezuelans have been struggling to come to terms with their government’s new alliance with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Maduro awaits trial in the United States, his inner circle continues to run Venezuela. It is made up of self-described Chavistas, but their ideological credentials are now being questioned by die-hard believers who remain loyal to former President Hugo Chávez’s approach of blending socialism, nationalism, state control of key industries and anti-imperialism (read: anti-Americanism).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At this point, we should have cut off the oil, we shouldn’t have sold any oil to the United States. Zero oil, zero oil!” said one 63-year-old Venezuelan, Beatriz, who asked that only her first name be used as the government cracks down on dissent. “It’s the only way President Nicolás Maduro — the legitimate president of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela — will return to our country.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days after Mr. Maduro was seized, Beatriz took to the streets to chant anti-American slogans. The crowd of hundreds around her in downtown Caracas chanted in unison, demanding that President Trump return their former leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Devuélvenos a Nico!” they cried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the combative, anti-American crowds that first came out after Mr. Maduro’s capture appear to have been tamed in the past week. The government’s new message: Get on board, we are doing business with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Venezuela’s interim president, Delcy Rodríguez, gave her first State of the Union address last week, she maintained a delicate balance between anti-American rhetoric and the new reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They attacked, assaulted, killed, invaded and kidnapped President Maduro and the first lady,” Ms. Rodríguez said Thursday. “There is a stain on relations between the United States and Venezuela.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She then whipsawed, urging legislators to approve a bill to open oil fields to new investments. “Let us not be afraid of diplomacy,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez is now offering a newer groupthink to replace the anti-Americanism her government once stoked: “Dudar es traicionar,” or “Doubt is treason.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The slogan appeared last year as the specter of U.S. invasion neared. Now it is printed on hats and jackets handed out by the government and angrily whispered among Venezuelans when anyone registers outrage about the government’s alliance with Washington — the enemy they had once been told was preventing Venezuela from achieving prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Maduro has long blamed the United States for the economic collapse that ripped through the country beginning in 2013, leading to children dying from hunger and hospitals running out of basic supplies, Washington’s sanctions on Venezuela’s economy did not begin until 2017 during the first Trump administration. Before then, sanctions had largely targeted Venezuelan officials and barred Washington from selling arms to the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, economic mismanagement, corruption and a fall in the price of oil — which had buttressed Mr. Chávez’s socialism — led to internal discontent by the time Mr. Maduro took power in 2013, leading to the migration of nearly eight million Venezuelans. Many who fled were the most economically vulnerable citizens, the very working-class Venezuelans Mr. Chávez had vowed to empower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Venezuelans tightened their belts, Mr. Maduro’s government became a virtual kleptocracy, analysts said. The president made sure to buy the loyalty of the armed forces. Venezuela now has some 2,000 admirals and generals with all the perks and high pay that entails (the United States has several hundred to service a much larger population).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cracks of Chavismo were already starting to form when Maduro took power, but now how do those hard-core Chavistas jibe with the events of the past few weeks?” asked Alejandro Velasco, an associate professor of history at New York University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Under Chávez the goal was not power for power’s sake, it was to deploy national resources to empower those who had been left behind,” Mr. Velasco said. “But with Maduro — who no longer had access to the wealth when oil prices collapsed — the goal became power for power itself."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said that while Mr. Chávez had started to co-opt state institutions to remake them in his image, he had allowed free and fair elections during his tenure. Mr. Maduro was accused of rigging them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some Chavistas want officials to be held accountable for how easily the United States was able to invade Venezuela’s airspace this month. While ordinary citizens went hungry, the government continued to buy weapons, boasting late last year that Venezuela was well protected against foreign invasion. Yet it took only about two hours to capture Mr. Maduro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But many Chavistas are painfully aware that their country’s arsenal can be used against them. Fighting a superpower is one thing, squashing internal unrest another. Venezuelans have seen their armed forces do it repeatedly for over a decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Ms. Rodríguez’s government continues to work with Washington, some Chavistas suspect her allies may have been in cahoots with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A betrayal! Whoever did it will pay for it before God and before our people,” one protester, Victor, said at another anti-American rally in Caracas this month. He, too, asked that his last name be withheld for fear of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But forefront on his mind, as for many other Venezuelans, was the fate of the oil wealth that has long held the promise of feeding and clothing their families, and lifting their economic fortunes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a vassal state is not an option for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The United States wants to seize the wealth we have here,” Victor said. “But we are a people who truly fight for their homeland. And we do not want to be slaves.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camille Rodríguez Montilla contributed reporting from Caracas, Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/venezuela-chavismo-us.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:23:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Slow Emergency Response Blamed in Deadly Fire That Tore Through Pakistani Mall</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/pakistan-karachi-fire-mall.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-pakistan-fire-01-mghv/19int-pakistan-fire-01-mghv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fire tore through a crowded mall in Karachi this past weekend, leaving at least 23 people dead and dozens missing on Monday in the latest tragedy that urban planners and shopkeepers have blamed on chronic mismanagement in Pakistan’s largest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road outside the mall was crowded on Monday with hundreds of residents who gathered around the blackened shell of a once-thriving market. Shopkeepers stood in silence, staring at ruined livelihoods, while families pressed against police cordons, dialing unanswered phones. Nearby, other market stalls were closed in mourning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire, which burned for nearly 24 hours, began spreading around 10 p.m. on Saturday on the lower floors of Gul Plaza, one of the busiest wholesale marketplaces in downtown Karachi. It housed about 1,200 shops selling luggage, crockery, decorative items, plastic goods, toys, garments and household supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haji Sabir, a shopkeeper who said he had narrowly escaped, said the area had been bustling: “It was wedding season. The market was crowded.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rescue officials said the flames first broke out from the lower-level shops and climbed inside the building, casting an orange glow over the surrounding narrow streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time firefighters brought the blaze under control at around 10 p.m. on Sunday night, Gul Plaza had been almost completely destroyed, leaving a burned and empty shell behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 23 people were confirmed dead, according to the state-run emergency services. Dozens more were feared to be trapped in stairwells, shops and under collapsed floors. Rescue workers said the exact toll might take days to establish, as several parts of the structure remained unstable and inaccessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials initially suspected an electrical short circuit, but said the cause had yet to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday morning, fire engines kept spraying water on the burning building from one side, while demolition workers pulled down badly damaged parts from the other. Rescue teams trudged through dark corridors looking for any sign of survivors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the building, melted electrical wires hung from the ceilings. Rolling iron shutters on storefronts were still tightly closed, some twisted out of shape. Cellphones belonging to missing merchants rang under the ash and broken concrete, but no one answered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside, grief hardened into anger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If the fire engines had arrived on time, with proper ladders, this could have been contained,” said Mujtaba Ali, whose relative was among those believed to be trapped inside. “They were calling us from inside, saying the stairways were locked. What chance did they have?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merchants said that some people escaped from the ground floor, but when the fire reached the upper levels, it was too late. Firefighters’ ladders could reach no higher than the fifth floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inferno brought back painful memories in a city long plagued by deadly fires. In 2012, more than 260 workers died in a garment factory after being trapped behind barred windows. In 2023, a fire at a shopping mall killed 10 people and injured 22 others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every time, officials promise change. Every time, the city quietly returns to business as usual,” said Zahid Farooq, joint director of the Urban Resource Center, a Karachi-based nonprofit organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is a culture of legalizing illegal practices,” he said. “Buildings made for 500 shops are packed with more than 1,200 shops. When buildings are overcrowded, and exits are blocked, tragedy becomes unavoidable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Karachi, Pakistan’s economic hub of more than 20 million people, fire safety laws exist mostly on paper, experts say. Building inspections are rare and punishments for violations are weak. Builders add extra floors without permission. Stairwells are locked to stop theft. Electrical wiring is poorly repaired and heavily overloaded. In crowded markets, illegal extensions clog the narrow streets so much that even small fire engines can hardly pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the weekend rescue operation, fire engines were delayed by roadside encroachments, including those unauthorized expansions, according to officials and rescue personnel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On social media, a short audio clip spread quickly, showing a man crying, “We’re trapped from all sides. Fire is everywhere. Please forgive me if I did something wrong.” The recording ends abruptly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Murad Ali Shah, the chief minister for Sindh Province, whose capital is Karachi, ordered an inquiry into the blaze. He directed the authorities to carry out immediate fire safety audits of commercial buildings across the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the human toll, the economic losses are expected to be severe. The Karachi Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the city’s leading mercantile body, said more than 1,000 small and medium shops had been destroyed, wiping out years of savings and cutting off the only source of income for hundreds of families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the crowd outside Gul Plaza was Sharif Khan, 42, who had opened a crockery shop just a year earlier, using a bank loan of about $7,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I put everything I had into that shop,” Mr. Khan said, his eyes fixed on the blackened ruins. “The goods are gone, the shop is gone, but the debt remains. I have no hope that the government will help us.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/pakistan-karachi-fire-mall.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:08:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Is Pushing the U.S.-Europe Alliance Onto a Precipice</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-nato-alliance.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-europe-alliance01-photo-jbtp/19int-europe-alliance01-photo-jbtp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens to an 80-year-old diplomatic alliance when its leading power threatens a military invasion of one member, wages economic war on the others and vows to cultivate political and cultural resistance to their governments?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the alliance doomed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question is being asked in capitals across Europe as leaders rush to respond to President Trump’s rapidly escalating campaign to acquire Greenland over the objections of the people who live there. At issue most urgently is whether resisting Mr. Trump’s territorial ambitions risks damaging Europe’s relationship with the United States beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some leaders — like President Emmanuel Macron of France and Lars Klingbeil, Germany’s finance minister — appear willing to take that risk, urging Europe’s nations to consider deploying an economic “bazooka” in response to Mr. Trump’s latest tariff threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders from across Europe are expected to gather in Brussels this week to present a united response to Mr. Trump’s provocations. Veteran observers of European politics said the alliance between Europe and the United States that formed in the aftermath of World War II had already been fundamentally altered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is no longer an alliance designed primarily to advance the interests of like-minded democracies, they said. Instead, it is a relationship on Mr. Trump’s terms alone — one in which he wields the leverage that comes from American power to force Europeans to cater to his whims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“To use what is essentially economic warfare with allies is unprecedented in this way,” said Ian Lesser, who leads the Brussels office of the German Marshall Fund, a research group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There appears to be a consensus in much of Europe that it needs to build new economic and military capacities to make it less dependent on the United States. But that will take years, if not decades. In the meantime, Europe’s businesses and financial markets will still be intertwined with the buying power of consumers in the United States, and Ukraine will still need American weapons to defend itself against Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, months of diplomatic effort to negotiate a cease-fire in the Ukraine war have only underscored that NATO, which was formed to defend Europe, is unable to fend off Russian aggression without security guarantees by the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”It would be foolish at a time of war in Europe to jettison all of the sort of strategic and operational benefits that come with the alliance,” Mr. Lesser said. “But if the United States is no longer a reliable partner in that alliance, then Europe needs to do something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That effort is already underway, slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same day that Mr. Trump announced his latest tariff threat on social media, Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, and António Costa, the president of the European Council, were in Paraguay to sign a major trade deal with a bloc of Latin American countries, one that was 25 years in the making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has so far been happy to welcome European money to purchase American-made arms for Ukraine and other countries in Eastern Europe. And he relishes surprising his so-called allies, as he demonstrated on Saturday when he announced tariffs on a group of European nations, including Britain, unless Greenland is sold to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That raises the stakes for the decisions that Europe is grappling with in the days ahead. It must choose how aggressively to confront Mr. Trump without knowing what the always-unpredictable president will do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Is he serious? What does Europe do now? How does the U.S. respond?” Mr. Lesser said. “There will be those who say, ‘OK, how do we get through this? Is it possible to simply to engage in a kind of negotiation or investment or whatever it may be, that will defer anything radical?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has already made it clear that he views America’s European allies with disdain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his annual National Security Strategy, released last month, officials from Mr. Trump’s administration questioned whether some European countries would remain “reliable allies” in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document conceded that Europe was “strategically and culturally vital” to the United States. But it said the continent faced the “stark prospect of civilizational erasure” unless the United States helped like-minded “patriotic European parties” — a phrase that was widely understood to mean the far right — to win power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Europeans on the receiving end of those assertions, the president’s threats about acquiring Greenland “the easy way” or “the hard way” have further eroded the trust that was central to their alliance with the United States for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Going back to the level of trust that we saw beforehand would require, I think, generational change,” said Rosa Balfour, the director of Carnegie Europe, a political think tank. “The attack on Europe is not just coming from an individual, you know — it’s been turned into an ideology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the latest Greenland threats, more voices have begun urging assertive action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a statement over the weekend, Mr. Macron vowed that “no intimidation or threat will influence us — neither in Ukraine, nor in Greenland, nor anywhere else in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He called Mr. Trump’s tariff threats “unacceptable” and vowed: “Europeans will respond in a united and coordinated manner should they be confirmed. We will ensure that European sovereignty is upheld.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Others, like Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain, have argued for a diplomatic solution and cautioned against grandstanding. “That’s an understandable instinct, but it’s not effective,” the prime minister told reporters on Monday morning. “It never has been. It may make politicians feel good, but it does nothing for working people whose jobs, livelihoods and security rely on the relationships that we build across the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Ms. Balfour said that more leaders were beginning to realize that capitulating to Mr. Trump’s demands was not always in Europe’s interests. In fact, it often leads Mr. Trump to demand more concessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If true, that could have implications for the alliance with the United States and whether it survives in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Reality, I think, is sinking into the mind-sets of those people who have been advocating caution, dialogue and ‘Let’s listen to what Trump has to say,’” Ms. Balfour said. “You can feel that kind of change.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeanna Smialek contributed reporting from Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-greenland-europe-nato-alliance.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:18:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Links His Push for Greenland to Not Winning Nobel Peace Prize</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump is now claiming that one reason he is pushing to acquire Greenland is that he didn’t win the Nobel Peace Prize, according to a text message he sent to Norway’s prime minister over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonas Gahr Store, Norway’s leader, received the text message on Sunday, an official in the prime minister’s office said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Considering your Country decided not to give me the Nobel Peace Prize for having stopped 8 Wars PLUS, I no longer feel an obligation to think purely of Peace, although it will always be predominant, but can now think about what is good and proper for the United States of America,” Mr. Trump wrote in the message, which was first published by PBS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump also questioned Denmark’s claim to Greenland, saying, “There are no written documents,” and adding, “The World is not secure unless we have Complete and Total Control of Greenland. Thank you!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tensions over Greenland have sharply escalated in the last week, and the message injected a new level of uncertainty into Mr. Trump’s thinking and his campaign to gain control of the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland has been part of the Danish Kingdom for more than 300 years, and world leaders have condemned Mr. Trump’s insistence that the United States take over the territory, a giant icebound island in the Arctic region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to copies of the messages provided by the Norwegian prime minister’s office, Mr. Trump’s message was a response to one that Mr. Store sent Mr. Trump on Sunday. It was co-signed by the president of Finland, Alexander Stubb, a leader with whom Mr. Trump is close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European leaders asked to speak to Mr. Trump about Greenland and his threat of using tariffs to pressure Denmark into selling it, which Denmark has refused to do. They asked for a phone call and struck a collaborative tone, writing, “We believe we all should work to take this down and de-escalate — so much is happening around us where we need to stand together.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Trump’s response, Mr. Store said in a statement, “As regards the Nobel Peace Prize, I have on several occasions clearly explained to Trump what is well known, namely that it is an independent Nobel Committee, and not the Norwegian government, that awards the prize,” Mr. Store said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has repeatedly challenged Denmark’s claims to Greenland, but in decades-old agreements that the United States has signed with Denmark, the United States has recognized Denmark’s close connection to the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 2004 amendment to an older defense pact between Denmark and the United States, which grants the United States broad military access, explicitly recognizes Greenland as “an equal part of the Kingdom of Denmark.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in 1916, Denmark sold what are now the U.S. Virgin Islands to the United States for $25 million in gold. In the treaty for that deal, a clause reads, “The United States of America will not object to the Danish Government extending their political and economic interests to the whole of Greenland.”In the past year, as Mr. Trump has repeatedly vowed to “get” Greenland, Denmark has repeatedly rebuffed him. Denmark’s position is that it does not have the authority to sell the self-governing territory and that Greenland’s 57,000 inhabitants will decide their own fate. Polls and interviews show that an overwhelming majority of Greenlanders strongly oppose joining the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Greenlanders staged the biggest protest of recent months. Hundreds marched through the snowy streets of Nuuk, the capital, chanting, “No means no,” “Greenland is already great” and “Yankee, go home!”In the past few days, Denmark and other European countries have sent more military forces to the island. Small groups of Danish soldiers dressed in green camouflage and dark woolen hats have been walking through downtown Nuuk. Beyond the harbor, a 200-foot-long Danish warship capable of breaking through ice has been patrolling the shoreline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A much-anticipated three-way meeting last week of the United States, Denmark and Greenland, hosted by Vice President JD Vance in Washington, did not produce any breakthroughs and seemed to instead create misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the first time Greenland had been included in a such high-level discussions, and the Danish and Greenlandic officials left saying that a working group had been formed to explore possibilities for a solution. But the Trump administration said afterwards that the two sides would begin “technical talks on the acquisition of Greenland,” a statement that raised even more concern in Greenland, in Denmark and across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Kingsley, Jeanna Smialek and Steven Erlanger contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:14:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Updates: At Least 39 Are Dead in High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-promo-9amest/18spain-crash-eyewitness-pgtq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Crews were working to retrieve bodies after two high-speed trains derailed in southern Spain. The regional authorities said 41 people were hospitalized, with a dozen of them in intensive care.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:11:36 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>