<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:15:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>At Davos, Global Leaders Gather to Ponder the Future of a Messy World</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-world-economic-forum-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19sp-davos-lede-inyt-03-gphj/19sp-davos-lede-inyt-03-gphj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Tens of thousands of Iranians have taken to the streets during the latest uprising, including an anti-government protest in Tehran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-world-economic-forum-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 19:20:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Ultimatum to Europe</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/greenland-europe-tariffs-kyiv.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-theworld-greenland-denmark-promo-wtjz/19int-theworld-greenland-denmark-promo-wtjz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump threatened heavy tariffs on countries standing between him and Greenland. E.U. leaders are scrambling for a response.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/greenland-europe-tariffs-kyiv.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:39:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Updates: Trains Collide After Derailment in Spain, Killing at Least 21</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-spain-derail-kjhc/18int-spain-derail-kjhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A high-speed train smashed into another train after derailing in the southern province of Córdoba, officials said. The cause of the accident was not immediately clear.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:01:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate Crash Weighs on China’s Economic Growth</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/china-gdp-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19Biz-China-GDP-01-jmft/19Biz-China-GDP-01-jmft-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
China is still grappling with a property market crash that began four years ago, after many years of overbuilding.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/china-gdp-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 18:47:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Are New Zealanders Moving to Australia? More Money, Better Vibes.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/new-zealand-australia-moving-relocation.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/27/multimedia/0xp-nzexodus-pcjm/0xp-nzexodus-pcjm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Travelers at Wellington International Airport, in New Zealand last month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/new-zealand-australia-moving-relocation.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:01:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>As Davos Convenes, Deference to Trump Has Replaced Everything</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/davos-president-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19Biz-Davos-preview-01-hvwf/19Biz-Davos-preview-01-hvwf-mediumSquareAt3X-v3.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Attendees at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, last year.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/davos-president-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:01:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain Closes High-Speed Rail Network in South After Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-high-speed-rail-closed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-rail-network-ghbv/18spain-crash-rail-network-ghbv-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Passengers at a train station in Madrid on Sunday, after the train derailment in southern Spain.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-high-speed-rail-closed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:32:17 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>I.M.F. Raises Forecast for Global Growth as Tariff Drag Fades</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/imf-world-economic-outlook-2026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19dc-globalecon-wvqp/19dc-globalecon-wvqp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
An exhibit at a conference held by Nvidia, which makes chips that power artificial intelligence. Surging investment in technology is poised this year to offset the headwinds of rising protectionism.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/business/imf-world-economic-outlook-2026.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:30:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>No Country Has Ever Been Held Responsible for Genocide. Can This Lawyer Change That?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/magazine/genocide-trial-human-right-international-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/01/magazine/01mag-sands-HP-square/01mag-sands-HP-square-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philippe Sands, one of the world’s pre-eminent human rights attorneys, is arguing the case against Myanmar at The Hague.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/magazine/genocide-trial-human-right-international-law.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:00:51 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Has an Offramp on Greenland. He Doesn’t Seem to Want It.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-greenland-nato.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19dc-assess-01-qvgt/19dc-assess-01-qvgt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
For President Trump, the sheer size of Greenland’s territory holds part of the appeal; it is about three times the size of Texas, and bigger than Alaska.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/trump-greenland-nato.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:02:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Survivors of Deadly Train Crash in Spain Describe Hellish Scenes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-train-crash-survivors.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-eyewitness-pgtq/18spain-crash-eyewitness-pgtq-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Members of the Spanish Civil Guard, along with other emergency personnel, work next to one of the trains involved in the accident near Adamuz, Spain, on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/spain-train-crash-survivors.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:48:40 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Starmer Pushes Back Against Greenland Tariff Threat as ‘Completely Wrong’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/starmer-uk-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18trump-news-greenland-lbjm/18trump-news-greenland-lbjm-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain speaking to the news media at Downing Street in London on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/us/politics/starmer-uk-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:21:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>European Union Officials Lean Toward Negotiating, Not Retaliating, Over Trump Tariff Threat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/european-union-respond-trump-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-tariffs-retaliate-fzkp/18int-tariffs-retaliate-fzkp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with the threat of punishing tariffs by President Trump if he does not get his way over acquiring Greenland, European Union leaders began to coalesce around a negotiation strategy on Sunday, without ruling out retaliatory taxes of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump on Saturday had demanded a deal to buy Greenland, saying on social media that otherwise he would slap tariffs on a group of European nations, starting with 10 percent in February, then ramping up to 25 percent in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, ambassadors from across the 27-nation bloc met in Brussels to take stock of the situation. While those were just preliminary talks, they made a few things clear. Officials would rather negotiate than retaliate, for one. But they are also committed to protecting Greenland, an autonomous territory of Denmark, from being bought or taken over if that is not what its people want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration showed no signs of backing down. In an interview on NBC’s “Meet the Press,” Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said that European leaders would eventually understand that American control of Greenland would be “best for Greenland, best for Europe and best for the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The European leaders will come around,” Mr. Bessent said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Washington continues to escalate its efforts, European officials could also consider hitting back, two diplomats familiar with the discussions said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials are entertaining the possibility of allowing a list of retaliatory tariffs worth 93 billion euros, or $107 billion — drawn up during last year’s trade war — to take effect in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some members of the European Parliament and Emmanuel Macron, the French president, have suggested that the European Union should activate an even more drastic tool: A never-used weapon intended to combat economic coercion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That option — officially called the “anti-coercion instrument,” and unofficially referred to as Europe’s trade “bazooka” — could be used to slap restrictions on big American technology companies or other service providers that conduct large amounts of business on the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be a first resort, the diplomats said, because it would risk escalating the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the European Union’s options are likely to be up for discussion later this week, when leaders gather in Brussels. António Costa, the president of the European Council, which gives the European Union political direction, announced on Sunday that he had “decided to convene an extraordinary meeting” of European leaders in the coming days. An E.U. official added that the meeting might be in person, and that it could take place on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a session would allow prime ministers and presidents from across the bloc to discuss how they might respond to Mr. Trump. It would also come just as, or before, many European policymakers head to Davos, Switzerland, for the annual World Economic Forum. Mr. Trump is also planning to attend, creating a chance for conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many European leaders are still hoping they might be able to talk things out, discussions have essentially been futile so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has been hesitant to retaliate against the United States, in part because it relies on America for military technologies and support for NATO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Brando Benifei, a member of the European Parliament and the chair of its delegation for U.S. relations, said that calculus may be shifting, in part because popular opinion in Europe has turned more critical of the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A lot of people are saying that we are clearly over a red line,” he said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain spoke to Mr. Trump on Sunday and told him that “applying tariffs on allies for pursuing the collective security of NATO allies is wrong,” a Downing Street spokesman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy’s prime minister, Giorgia Meloni, told reporters on Sunday that she had also spoken to Mr. Trump and called the proposed tariffs a “mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Rutte, the secretary-general of NATO, said on social media that he, too, had spoken with Mr. Trump about Greenland, but provided few details, saying only that “we will continue working on this” and that he looked forward to seeing Mr. Trump at Davos this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not immediately comment on the spate of calls, which come a day after Mr. Trump’s announcement of new tariffs was met with unified outrage by U.S. allies. Several of those allies, including Britain, France and Germany, released a forceful joint statement with Denmark on Sunday that decried the tariff threats, saying that they “undermine transatlantic relations and risk a dangerous downward spiral.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The co-signers of the statement, all NATO countries, said they would continue to stand in solidarity with Greenland and vowed to remain “united and coordinated in our response.” The statement was later endorsed by several other European countries, including Iceland, Latvia and Lithuania.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/european-union-respond-trump-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:16:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Guatemala Declares State of Emergency to Address Gang Violence</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/guatemala-emergency-drug-cartels.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19xp-guatemala-jfpl/19xp-guatemala-jfpl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Guatemalan riot police officers guard the entrance to the men’s Preventive Detention Center in Guatemala City on Sunday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/guatemala-emergency-drug-cartels.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:56:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Can Vietnam’s Communist Party Supercharge Its Economy With Private Enterprise?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/vietnam-communist-party-congress-economy.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-vietnam-explainer-1-ktlw/19int-vietnam-explainer-1-ktlw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Communist Party of Vietnam on Monday opened its most consequential party congress in decades, as the nation — an emerging middle power and one of Asia’s most dynamic countries — is facing its best and last chance to “get rich before getting old.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 40 years of reform and an extraordinary rise out of poverty, Vietnam is under mounting pressure to pursue bolder reforms to catch up with regional neighbors like South Korea and Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vietnam, a country of 102 million people, has a shrinking window in which the working-age population will still be large enough to drive rapid growth before society ages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, shifting geopolitics offer a mix of pressure and opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both China and the United States see Vietnam as strategically important. It has a long coastline along the contested sea routes of the South China Sea, as well as a rapidly growing manufacturing base that draws on Chinese supply chains and ships more of its exports to the United States than anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Washington and Beijing, along with Moscow and much of Europe, are all pushing Vietnam to lean their way while trying to gauge where the country is heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weeklong party congress in Hanoi ends Jan. 25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, Vietnam’s one-party state has been governed by the top four members of the Communist Party’s Politburo — the so-called “Four Pillars” — the general secretary, the president, the prime minister and the chair of the National Assembly. The arrangement was designed to keep power from being concentrated in a single leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the party is now rushing to reach ambitious targets set by the last congress: raising per capita gross domestic product by about 70 percent to $8,500 by 2030 and building enough of an industrial economy to become a high-income developed country by 2045.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is very important for the party to deliver on these goals,” said Nguyen Hong Hai, political scientist at VinUniversity in Hanoi. “The Communist Party’s legitimacy will be reinforced by its performance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an era of uncertainty fueled by the United States and China, the party chief, To Lam, is likely to amass more power by also taking on the role of president. Cuba and China have similar structures with single leaders who head up the party and the state. According to several officials and diplomats, who declined to be named as they discussed party nominations, Mr. Lam, 68, is the only nominee for both posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current president, Luong Cuong, 68, a military general, is expected to retire. If Mr. Lam’s dual role is approved, it would signal that the military, a powerful faction since the war, has been at least somewhat sidelined — as Mr. Lam consolidates power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until recently, Mr. Lam was mostly known as an enforcer. A former head of public security, he rose to become Vietnam’s top leader in 2024 after the death of his predecessor, Nguyen Phu Trong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, Mr. Lam’s party leadership has delivered a whirlwind of change, starting with a huge administrative overhaul that consolidated provinces and put tens of thousands of officials out of work. A lover of soccer, jazz and classical music, he has also promoted a building spree for stadiums and opera houses, along with new roads, train lines and airports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes, he has sought to elevate loyalists, strengthen ties to large quasi-state-run companies, and win over both the party establishment and prominent figures from southern Vietnam whom his predecessor treated as pariahs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among his methods: He has brought large entourages on trips overseas while speaking frequently about an “era of national rise” for Vietnam, with the private sector playing a bigger role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Lam is seen as a potential transitional figure who could create more amenable conditions for a broader range of private enterprise. But critics stress that the party still prioritizes central control. Despite their low productivity, state-owned and state-favored companies still enjoy special treatment. New laws give greater power to authorities to find and crack down on “anti-state” commentary, with some worrying that could include accurate, unflattering information about the economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The congress will draw together 1,586 delegates, representing the 5.6 million people who are registered party members. Most delegates are appointed by the party. Their job this week will entail discussing Communist Party promotions after shuttling from upscale Marriott and Lotte hotels to a convention center in Hanoi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There, they will name around 200 officials to the Central Committee. That group picks the 17 to 19 members of the Politburo, the party’s most powerful body, from which the committee chooses the general secretary and other “pillars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intraparty jockeying for power has been going on for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaks and internal discussion of the most significant choices suggest that the congress will produce a mix of continuity and a sharper tilt toward rapid economic reform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh, 67, a police general and former intelligence officer, is expected to retire and be replaced by Le Minh Hung, 55, the youngest member of the Politburo. He has a background in finance and is a former governor of the State Bank of Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last of the four “pillars,” Tran Thanh Man, 63, is expected to stay in his post as the chair of the National Assembly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of those expecting promotion at the provincial and ministry levels have ties to Mr. Lam’s home province of Hung Yen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The party plans to draw up a new model for economic growth, to rely less on low-skilled labor, and more on science and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Vietnam is still facing very major challenges, including the risk of falling further behind economically, failing to adapt quickly enough to climate change and environmental degradation,” according to a party report set to be presented at the congress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That report said Vietnam would seek strategic projects with other countries because “with some important partners, trust remains low, uneven and not truly sustainable.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That appeared to be a reference to the United States. A trade deal with Washington still hasn’t been finalized. Despite the strain of tariffs, Vietnam’s economic growth topped 8 percent last year, in large part because Chinese factories have moved into Vietnam at a rapid pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country’s main challenge lies with implementing policies that build more openness, efficiency and competition, analysts say. Internally, an oligarchy of state-favored firms with low productivity represent one danger. U.S. trade tensions and a surge of Chinese factories — heavily subsidized by Beijing — also threaten to keep Vietnam from its goal of developing a strong domestic industrial economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent congresses, policy adjustments had often been incremental. This year, many Vietnamese are hoping for more decisive moves as the forces of stability and urgency compete.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/vietnam-communist-party-congress-economy.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:01:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Prince Harry’s Case Against Daily Mail Publisher</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb/19int-uk-harry-explainer-ghjb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prince Harry’s latest legal case in Britain is set to begin on Monday in London’s High Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prince and several other high-profile figures are accusing Associated Newspapers, the publisher of The Daily Mail, of unlawful information gathering, including phone hacking, and of intruding into their private lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial is set to last for more than two months, and Harry is scheduled to testify on Thursday. The other claimants include Elton John and his husband, David Furnish, the actresses Liz Hurley and Sadie Frost, a former British government minister, and a racial justice campaigner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s what to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry and the other claimants accuse the company of carrying out or commissioning unlawful activities to reveal private information about their lives for articles published from 1997 to 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Written arguments presented at a preliminary hearing in May said there had been “clear, systematic and sustained use of unlawful information gathering by private investigators” hired by Associated Newspapers, with “payments spanning decades” and involvement by newspaper executives and numerous journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators are accused of hacking and tapping phones, placing listening devices in cars and “blagging” — a way of tricking people into handing over information — to obtain phone numbers, personal records and bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The newspaper group, which owns The Daily Mail, The Mail on Sunday and several other titles that are not implicated in the case, has denied all the accusations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a preliminary hearing on Thursday, four days before the trial was to start, a lawyer for Associated Newspapers, Anthony White, said he would argue that some of the claimants’ witnesses “are not telling the truth” and that he would raise questions about their credibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Associated Newspapers said in a statement that its journalists had not commissioned or obtained information derived from illegal activity and called the accusations “preposterous and without foundation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It added, “The stories concerned, many of which were published 20 or more years ago, and not subject to any complaint at the time, were the product of responsible journalism based on legitimate sources.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a schedule jointly drawn up by both legal teams, the trial will run for more than two months and end on March 26. The judge hearing the case, Matthew Nicklin, is expected to consider the evidence and arguments before giving a ruling at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case will begin with lawyers for the claimants and Associated Newspapers giving an outline of their case. Prince Harry is expected to give evidence in person at the High Court on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elton John, the other claimants and witnesses, including Ms. Frost’s former husband, the actor Jude Law, are also set to be questioned by lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The private investigators accused of wrongdoing will appear at the trial, as will the former editor of The Daily Mail, Paul Dacre, and several past and present Associated Newspapers executives and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case is one of several pursued by Harry since 2020, when he and his wife, Meghan Markle, stepped down from their royal roles and left Britain, later making their home in Montecito, Calif.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many have centered on accusations of press intrusion, which Harry said was a key reason behind their decision to move. In an interview with Oprah Winfrey in 2021, Harry said that he feared “history repeating itself,” referring to the death of his mother, Princess Diana, in a car crash while she was being chased by paparazzi in Paris in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said there was an “invisible contract” between Britain’s royal family and the country’s tabloids, adding, “There is a level of control by fear that has existed for generations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The owners of The Daily Mirror, another tabloid, settled a claim over phone hacking in February 2024. During that case, Harry became the first senior royal to testify in court since 1891.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 2025, Rupert Murdoch’s News Group Newspapers agreed to pay a “substantial” amount of damages to Harry to settle a long-running lawsuit relating to articles in The Sun and the long-closed News of the World. News Group apologized for “serious intrusion” into Harry’s personal life between 1996 and 2011 and admitted for the first time to unlawful activities by private investigators working for The Sun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harry lost an unrelated legal battle last May over his publicly funded security in Britain, which was downgraded after his decision to step back from royal duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But late last year, the government body responsible for royal security decisions began a review of his protection arrangements, according to two people familiar with the situation who were not given permission to speak publicly. The review appears to offer a glimmer of good news for the prince, who has spoken of his desire to visit Britain with his family if his automatic right to security is reinstated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael D. Shear contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/prince-harry-trial-daily-mail-associated-newspapers-uk.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 20:01:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sanae Takaichi, Japan’s Prime Minister, Calls for Snap Election</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh/19int-japan-election-01-jmzh-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Sanae Takaichi, the prime minister of Japan, called early elections just three months into her tenure.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/asia/japan-takaichi-early-election.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 03:10:31 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What to Know About Hezbollah’s Ties to Venezuela</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/hezbollah-venezuela-ties.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2020/04/24/world/19int-venezuela-hezbollah/19int-venezuela-hezbollah-mediumSquareAt3X-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Hezbollah fighters at the Lebanon-Syria border in 2017.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/hezbollah-venezuela-ties.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:00:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>What We Know About the Deadly High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq/18spain-crash-WWK-gkcq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A high-speed train ran off its track and crashed into another high-speed train late Sunday in southern Spain, killing at least 21 people and injuring dozens of others, according to the local authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accident is the deadliest train accident in Spainsince 2013, when 80 people died after a train veered off a curved section of track in the country’s northwest. The country has the second-longest high-speed rail network in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The collision on Sunday occurred at 7:45 p.m. in Adamuz, in the southern province of Córdoba. The train that derailed first was a privately-operated one that was traveling to Madrid from Málaga, on the country’s southern coast. The rear cars of that train fell into the opposite track, where it collided with an incoming train operated by Spain’s national rail company, which was bound for the southern city of Huelva, west of Seville.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iryo, the operator of the first train, said that around 300 passengers were on board at the time of the crash. Renfe, the operator of the second train, has not said how many passengers it was carrying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spain’s state-owned rail infrastructure agency said in a statement that rail traffic between Madrid and several major cities in southern Andalucía — including Córdoba, Seville, Málaga and Huelva — will be suspended on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency response crews continued to search through the wreckage of the crash early Monday, with officials warning that the death toll may rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the 2013 disaster, the derailment on Sunday happened on a straight portion of the track. An independent commission has been launched to investigate what caused it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Óscar Puente, Spain’s transport minister, told reporters that the first train to derail was only a few years old and that the section of the track where the accident occurred had been recently renovated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accident is extremely strange,” he said. “It happened on a straightaway. All the experts we have consulted are extremely baffled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He added: “If there had not been an oncoming train, we would not be talking about casualties of any type.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez of Spain expressed sympathy for the victims’ families on social media, saying that “the entire country stands with them in this extremely difficult moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Tonight is a night of deep pain for our country,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Andalucía government has set up a medical post at the crash site for victims, while the Córdoba city government has issued an urgent appeal for doctors to help treat the injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paco Carmona, the director of Córdoba’s fire brigade, told public television that emergency crews were prioritizing assistance for victims still trapped in the two carriages most severely damaged in the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/what-we-know-spain-train-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 22:42:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Links His Push for Greenland to Not Winning Nobel Peace Prize</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf/19trump-norway-sub-vwjf-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
President Trump and Prime Minister Jonas Gahr Store of Norway during a meeting last year.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/trump-norway-greenland-nobel.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:29:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At the Center of Trump’s Vision for Rebuilding Ukraine: BlackRock</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc/19int-ukraine-blackrock-vtpc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Mezhova, in eastern Ukraine, in December. Ukrainian officials have likened their country’s recovery blueprint to the Marshall Plan, the U.S.-funded project to rebuild Europe after World War II.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/ukraine-reconstruction-blackrock.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:02:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Splits Emerge Among Venezuelans as Revolutionary Dream Fades</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/venezuela-chavismo-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-venezuela-chavista-vfgw/19int-venezuela-chavista-vfgw-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Demonstrators demanding the release of President Nicolás Maduro in Caracas, Venezuela, on Friday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/americas/venezuela-chavismo-us.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 05:47:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Updates: At Least 39 Are Dead in High-Speed Train Crash in Spain</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/18/multimedia/18spain-crash-promo-9amest/18spain-crash-eyewitness-pgtq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Rescuers were working to retrieve bodies from the wreckage after two trains derailed in southern Spain. The cause of the train crash, the deadliest in Spain since 2013, was still being determined.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/live/2026/01/18/world/spain-high-speed-train-derailment</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:10:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria, in Ruins</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/syria-aleppo-damascus-damage-reconstruction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/07/XX-Syria-Destruction-Visual-60268-cover/XX-Syria-Destruction-Visual-60268-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Syria, the destruction from 13 years of war has become part of the landscape. There is barely a town or city undamaged, or a community untouched, in the sprawling country of 23 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main cities like Damascus, the capital, entire neighborhoods and suburbs were pulverized as the dictator Bashar al-Assad and Russia and Iran, his allies, sought to crush an armed rebellion that emerged from the 2011 Arab Spring uprising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fighting and repression forced more than half of the population to flee their homes. They left behind ghost towns, whole sections of cities where block after block remains shrouded in darkness and uninhabitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rebels eventually toppled the regime in December 2024. Focused on consolidating power, the new government of President Ahmed al-Sharaa has barely begun the task of clearing and rebuilding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over three million Syrians have already returned since Mr. al-Assad fled and took refuge in Russia. Many are living in the ruins, or in a tent beside them. Some have patched up an apartment perched halfway up the empty skeleton of a residential block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ancient city of Aleppo and its surrounding province experienced some of the most extensive damage through the years of war — and has been the site of recent clashes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front line ran through the fabled old city, renowned for its courtyard houses and covered souk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They were fighting over it,” said Razan Abdulwahab, an architect coordinating projects in the area for the U.N.-Habitat, the United Nations urban development program. “It is a big disaster.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixty percent of the old city was destroyed, including many buildings registered as antiquities, she said. Even as work is underway to restore parts of the souk, the old city remains a horrifying landscape of dust and rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I cannot forget that day, looking at all the damage,” said Abdul Qadir, a trader who returned in 2017 to find his business and home near the old city destroyed. “Why? For what?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Syrians are struggling to survive. A third of all housing in the country is damaged or destroyed. Unemployment is high, and 90 percent of Syrians are living in poverty, according to the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.N.-Habitat survey found that 31 percent of housing stock needs to be rebuilt or restored, leaving the country shy 1.9 million homes for roughly 10 million people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strain is visible. In the southwestern city of Dara’a, a cradle of the Syrian uprising in 2011, neighborhoods that supported the rebellion lie decimated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some places, the rubble is so deep that people cannot find where their houses once stood, said Muhammad Kheir Bajbuj, 50. Sometimes, they cannot even find the street.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only two houses are occupied on his street, his own and that of a cousin, who returned with her family after a charity helped repair her roof. “Very few people came back because most of us have no money,” Mr. Bajbuj said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the main cities, villages and towns are littered with land mines and unexploded bombs. The explosives are killing and maiming those who return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One afternoon last summer in Deir al-Zour, in eastern Syria, a woman and her teenage son set off an explosion as they were scavenging in a trash dump. The mother was killed and the boy was badly injured in the face and eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deir al-Zour has been described as the most heavily damaged city in Syria by U.N.-Habitat. Traffic weaves past craters and around mounds of rubble. Children play in the ruins beneath great slabs of concrete hanging perilously from buildings. Dust clogs the air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like much of eastern Syria, Deir al-Zour suffered the additional trial of being subjugated by the Islamic State, or ISIS. Its roads and bridges are broken. Its churches and mosques are reduced to rubble. Schools and hospitals are few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task to rebuild is immense. Housing alone will cost $80 billion, U.N.-Habitat estimates. The World Bank has put Syria’s reconstruction costs at an estimated $216 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is still no talk of putting together a comprehensive economic reconstruction plan,” the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace reported recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Trump administration and many other Western donors cutting international assistance budgets, Syria’s government is seeking money from the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That bears its own risks, experts warned. If not handled fairly, private-sector-led reconstruction can lead to renewed cronyism and social inequality that could create more instability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we really want stability, reconstruction support has to be provided,” said Hiroshi Takabayashi, the head of the country program in Syria for U.N.-Habitat. Syria was a cornerstone for stability for much of the Middle East, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If we fail here,” he said, “this whole world order may not be sustained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After so much loss and destruction, Syrians do not ask for much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Who will give me compensation? Who will pay us back for the people we lost, the money we lost?” said Kadri Musalli, a storekeeper in Deir al-Zour, who said his brother bled out on the street under shellfire during the fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can climb back up and achieve civilized growth,” he said, “but it will be very, very slow.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/19/world/europe/syria-aleppo-damascus-damage-reconstruction.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 01:04:27 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>