<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 10:59:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What’s It Like to Climb a Skyscraper?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/23/multimedia/23xp-climbing-top/23xp-climbing-top-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Goodwin’s left shoulder felt like it was on fire and his right hand was covered in blisters by the time he finished climbing one side of Toronto’s CN Tower in 1986. Back then, it was the tallest structure in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I was terrified,” he said, recalling the day he reached the base of the tower’s observation deck, 1,100 feet above a crowd of onlookers and with no rope, harness or other safety equipment. “Every move had to be perfect.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Alex Honnold, a rock climber who was the subject of the Oscar-winning documentary “Free Solo,” will attempt to get everything right when he climbs Taipei 101, a 1,667-foot-tall skyscraper in Taiwan, without a rope. With Netflix livestreaming the climb, this niche pursuit has never received such global publicity before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaling skyscrapers is not like rock climbing or going up smaller buildings. Those in the club of just a dozen or so known skyscraper climbers worldwide say it has unique and intense physical and mental demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also a largely underground sport because it is usually illegal. Alain Robert, a Frenchman who has scaled some 200 buildings since the 1990s, mostly with his bare hands, said that he has been arrested more than 170 times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like you’re literally in a movie,” Mr. Robert said, with “cops that are trying to catch the bad guy climbing the building.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious risks make it rare for someone to obtain permission to climb a tall building like Mr. Honnold did. “I’ve never been willing to get arrested,” the 40-year-old said in a recent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the serene natural landscape surrounding climbers on routes like El Capitan in Yosemite National Park, which Mr. Honnold scaled in 2017, skyscraper climbers must overcome urban noise, crowds and, occasionally, police officers determined to arrest them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You feel like King Kong in the city,” said Titouan Leduc, 24, a French climber who scaled Warsaw’s Varso Tower, the tallest skyscraper in the European Union, last year. He was briefly arrested after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who have climbed skyscrapers say their bodies face different demands compared with rock climbing. According to Mr. Goodwin, 70, it mainly comes down to repetitiveness versus variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a rock face, each move presents a new puzzle: climbers’ hands search for different holds — crimps, jugs, slopers — and they constantly adapt their bodies. But along the side of a building, climbers repeat the same few movements hundreds of times to pass over dozens of stories of windows, steel bars and concrete gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can do a pull-up and think it’s not all too bad, but try doing 20, 50, 100,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Doing the same kind of move over and over and over — it can really tax your muscles and fingers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over decades, Mr. Robert, 63, developed his own system for rating buildings based on how difficult they are to climb. A building’s grips mattered more than its height, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He gave the Brooklyn Bridge a difficulty rating of two out of 10 after climbing it in 1994. He gave the same rating to the Eiffel Tower, which he scaled with his bare hands in 1996. “It’s really like a ladder,” he said of the Paris landmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also the last person to climb Taipei 101, in 2004, then the tallest building in the world. He completed the climb just days after having surgery on his left elbow, in heavy rain and with a top rope, which he said the authorities had required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Robert gave Taipei 101 a rating of six.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the small gaps on the surface of the Sydney Opera House, which he climbed in 1997 and rated as a seven, allowed him to hold on only with his fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1999, Mr. Robert scaled what he said was one of the most difficult buildings he had ever climbed, rating it a nine: the Sears Tower, now called the Willis Tower, in Chicago. He gave the Burj Khalifa in the United Arab Emirates, the world’s tallest building, the same grade after climbing it in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most difficult building he ever encountered? A relatively humble 44-story office building west of Paris in 1998. He said the only way up the Framatome, now called the Tour Areva, is by jamming one’s fingers into a vertical groove between glass panels. Halfway through that climb, he said, the crack unexpectedly became so narrow that his fingers could barely fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like your entire life is hanging at the tip of your finger,” he said. He rated that difficulty a 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some climbers said they were concerned that Mr. Honnold’s climb, carried live on Netflix, would encourage reckless, untrained attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My message to kids: Don’t do it,” Mr. Goodwin said. “Unless you’re a world-class climber like Alex Honnold and Alain Robert, unless you have that ability, it’s a suicide mission.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For others, the danger keeps them going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only way I felt alive was when I was risking my life,” Mr. Robert said, adding that he might try climbing another building in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/23/world/asia/climbing-buildings-skyscrapers-alex-honnold.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 20:28:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>William H. Foege, Key Figure in the Eradication of Smallpox, Dies at 89</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/william-h-foege-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2022/09/01/obituaries/00Foege1/00Foege1-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William H. Foege, who developed the vaccination strategy that helped wipe out smallpox in the 1970s, one of the world’s greatest public health triumphs, and who led the United States’ early response to the AIDS epidemic as director of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, died on Saturday night at his home in Atlanta. He was 89.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Mark Rosenberg, a friend and colleague, said the cause was congestive heart failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among public health professionals, Dr. Foege was almost without peer — the grand old man of public health, a field that many feel is under siege by the Trump administration. His successors at the C.D.C., the nation’s primary public health agency, often sought his counsel. In 2012, President Barack Obama awarded him the Presidential Medal of Freedom, the nation’s highest honor given to a civilian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As director of the C.D.C. under two presidents — Jimmy Carter, a Democrat, and Ronald Reagan, a Republican — Dr. Foege put forth an expansive vision for the agency. He had it focus on leading killers beyond infectious disease, including auto injuries and gun violence, the latter bringing the C.D.C. into conflict with the National Rifle Association and Republicans on Capitol Hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving the agency in 1983, he created programs that sharply increased childhood vaccinations on a global scale. Dr. Thomas R. Frieden, a former New York City health commissioner who later ran the C.D.C. under Mr. Obama, invoked a baseball superlative when preparing Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg for a meeting with Dr. Foege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I said, ‘Basically, he’s the Babe Ruth of public health,’” Dr. Frieden recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tall as an N.B.A. forward (he was 6-foot-7) and graced with a patient manner as the son of an Iowa minister, Dr. Foege was serving as a Lutheran Church missionary doctor in Africa when, in 1966, the World Health Organization launched an international program to eradicate smallpox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The W.H.O. program in West and Central Africa was initially administered by the C.D.C., and it was recruiting as many doctors as it could find to help set up an eradication project in eastern Nigeria. Dr. Foege, who at 29 had earned a master’s degree in public health only the year before, was invited to join.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with his wife and a young son, Dr. Foege (pronounced FAY-gee, with a hard “g”) moved to Enugu, the region’s capital. They lived in a four-room mud-walled hut with “no electricity, no running water, no indoor bathroom,” Dr. Foege recalled in an interview in 2023. The nearest telephone was 90 miles away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There, working as a consultant with Dr. Donald A. Henderson, the W.H.O. smallpox program leader, and Dr. J. Donald Millar, director of the C.D.C. eradication project in West Africa, Dr. Foege trained and deployed teams of specialists determined to vaccinate as many people as possible. At the time, West Africa was considered the most intractable smallpox region in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highly contagious, often disfiguring and deadly, smallpox had killed as many as 500 million people throughout history. An infected person would be covered with sores of oozing pus and blood that smelled like decomposing flesh. Dr. Foege said he could smell smallpox the minute he entered a room. It was “the scent of death,” he said in a recent podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conventional modern approach to controlling the disease was vaccination of everybody in an infected region. It was effective as long as there was an adequate supply of vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 1966, Dr. Foege was summoned to control a smallpox outbreak 90 miles east of Enugu. But unable to acquire enough vaccine to inoculate everyone in the area, he proposed a more efficient, surgical approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His team identified those infected in the villages, isolated them, and vaccinated everyone who had been in contact with them. They then vaccinated everyone who had been in contact with that second group. As a next step, they vaccinated people who had gathered in primary public places, like markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In effect, Dr. Foege and his team built a ring of containment around the initial outbreak, halting the spread of the disease. He said the strategy — now known as “ring vaccination” — was based on principles he learned when he spent summers fighting wildfires in the American West as a younger man. Fire crews worked to extinguish the heart of the fire while trying to prevent its spread by building fire lines, perimeters cleared of vegetation, often down to bare soil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It wasn’t a new strategy,” Dr. Foege said in an interview for this obituary in 2020. “What was important was that we got rid of the first strategy, which was mass vaccination. We showed that you could forget about mass vaccination and go right to the second part.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When civil war broke out in Nigeria, pitting secessionists in the east against the federal government in Lagos, Dr. Foege’s family was evacuated. But Dr. Foege, having rejoined the C.D.C., stayed behind in the eastern region to lead the effort to stamp out smallpox there. It was dangerous work: He was constantly encountering roadblocks, often maintained by armed teenage rebels, who, he later wrote, “mixed guns, alcohol and bravado.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When officials in Lagos cut off vaccine supplies to the east, threatening the success of his program, Dr. Foege was defiant, and undeterred. He and one of his C.D.C. team members hopped in his white Dodge pickup truck and drove 350 miles, across a bridge over the Niger River and into the capital city to raid a government warehouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While his C.D.C. colleague distracted a security guard, Dr. Foege loaded up the truck with stolen vaccine, cold packs, jet injector parts and other supplies. He drove back, terrified of being caught — only to run into a wall of trucks and bulldozers blocking the bridge at the river’s western edge, cutting off his passage back to safety. He fast-talked his way through in a meeting with the rebel leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I explained that we had just stolen vaccine from the federal government, and he was happy about that,” Dr. Foege recalled in an interview with The New York Times in 2023. “He cleared a path for us, and when we got across the bridge, we could breathe a sigh of relief.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the summer of 1967, smallpox had been eradicated in eastern Nigeria, and Dr. Foege reported the results at a C.D.C. meeting in Ghana. Dr. Millar and his C.D.C. specialists in Africa soon embraced the containment approach as the primary tactic for eradicating smallpox in West and Central Africa, a goal that was achieved in the spring of 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Foege, as a C.D.C. consultant, was next dispatched, in 1973, to help design and lead smallpox eradication projects in India, one of the last countries where the disease still had a hold. He had served as a Peace Corps volunteer in India in the early 1960s and was familiar with the country. Again, his family, which had grown by two more sons, accompanied him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge in India was consistent with what he had learned in Africa. Working with the Indian national and state authorities, he shuttled between planning meetings and the field as a senior leader in an eradication program that grew to enlist tens of thousands of investigators and technicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of villages where the disease was present, along with the number of new smallpox infections, began to fall in 1974, when political interference almost derailed the project. The minister of health in the northeast state of Bihar had become alarmed at what he viewed as a slow pace in controlling infections and vowed to replace the surveillance-containment program with mass vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing so would have wasted months of logistics preparation, training and early successes in reducing infections. “Did he have any idea that he was threatening to put the entire India program, indeed the entire global program, in jeopardy?” Dr. Foege wrote in “House on Fire: The Fight to Eradicate Smallpox (2011), one of several books he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a meeting with the minister to decide the issue in May 1974, a young Indian doctor, a field technician for the project, stood up and described himself as just a poor village man. In the event of a fire, he said, no one in his village poured water on houses that weren’t burning. Instead, as in the surveillance-containment strategy, they poured water only on the burning house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A chill went up my spine,” Dr. Foege wrote. “This man condensed all the work, discussions, discoveries and massive human effort of the previous seven months into a few words and the indelible image of a fire.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bihar minister backed off. A year later, the last case of smallpox in India was eradicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s last known smallpox case was that of a cook in Somalia in 1978, Dr. Foege said. Two years later, the W.H.O. formally declared that smallpox was the first infectious disease to be altogether eliminated. Dr. Foege, Dr. Henderson and Dr. Millar are widely credited with being the principal architects of that eradication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the three, Dr. Foege was the last survivor. Dr. Millar died in 2015, Dr. Henderson in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Foege was appointed to direct the C.D.C. in 1977, during the Carter administration. Four years later, the C.D.C. published the first reports of a “rare cancer” in homosexual men — the first hint of the coming AIDS epidemic. Dr. Foege, grappling with budget cuts and an indifferent Reagan White House, “borrowed money and borrowed people” from other programs, he said, to build a task force of epidemiologists to investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next two years, until he left the C.D.C., Dr. Foege navigated the political currents in Washington around a highly charged epidemic, as scientists raced to identify the virus causing the so-called “gay cancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He privately pushed his higher-ups at the Department of Health and Human Services to ask Congress for more funding. When they refused, he told lawmakers that the C.D.C. had what it needed. When Democrats in Congress wanted him to provide the names of men infected, Dr. Foege refused, saying patients deserved their privacy. He stepped down in 1983, he said in an interview, partly out of frustration with the Reagan White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After leaving government, Dr. Foege focused on strengthening global health programs for children. In 1984, a working group composed of members of the W.H.O., UNICEF, the World Bank, the United Nations Development Program and the Rockefeller Foundation recruited him to lead what was christened the Task Force for Child Survival, based in Atlanta, its mission to increase global immunization of children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the task force started, roughly 15 percent of the world’s children had received at least one vaccine. By 1990, the rate had increased to 80 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Foege often said that all public health is global health, by which he meant that infectious disease knows no borders. He spoke frequently of the moral obligation to be a “good ancestor,” said Dr. Rosenberg, who worked with Dr. Foege at the C.D.C. and is president emeritus of the task force, since renamed the Task Force for Global Health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He thought that public health has a basic responsibility to take care of not just the people right next to us, but everybody,” Dr. Rosenberg added, “and he expanded that concept of everybody in the world to everybody who’s going to be born in the future. That was a tremendous leap, a visionary statement.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1986, Mr. Carter and his wife, the former first lady Rosalynn Carter, named Dr. Foege executive director of the Carter Center, a nongovernmental organization in Atlanta focused on global conflict and health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bill Foege was a pre-eminent public health practitioner who dedicated his life to what he called science in the service of humanity,” Mr. Carter said in a statement for this obituary, issued before his own death in December 2024. “He saved the lives of millions of people around the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;William Herbert Foege was born on March 12, 1936, in Decorah, Iowa. He was the eldest of two boys and the third eldest of six children raised in a series of parsonages by his parents, the Rev. William A. and Anne Erika Foege.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He received a B.A. in biology from Pacific Lutheran University, in Parkland, Wash., in 1957, and a medical degree from the University of Washington in 1961. He spent a short time with the Peace Corps in India and received a master’s degree in public health from Harvard University in 1965.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1997, Dr. Foege joined the Rollins School of Public Health at Emory University in Atlanta as a professor of international health. Two years later, as Bill and Melinda Gates were preparing to launch their world health foundation, Mr. Gates recruited Dr. Foege to develop programs to fight disease. As a senior fellow with the foundation for 10 years, he influenced its decision to invest $750 million to start a public-private global child-vaccination project called Gavi, the Vaccine Alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Foege was described by friends and colleagues as someone who was comfortable with taking risks in pursuit of a goal, a trait that perhaps helped explain one of the few missteps of his career: his defense of the failed blood-testing technology promoted by Theranos, the Silicon Valley start-up founded by Elizabeth Holmes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, two years after he joined the company’s board and as the effectiveness of the Theranos technology was coming under intense scrutiny, Dr. Foege published an opinion article on the political news site The Hill. “In my opinion, the very foundation of Theranos’ inventions — and its hundreds of patents — is credible,” he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 2018, six months before Theranos collapsed, the Securities and Exchange Commission charged Ms. Holmes with fraud for misleading investors about the capabilities of the technology and overstating the company’s revenues. In 2022, she was found guilty on four of 11 counts of fraud and sentenced to a little more than 11 years in prison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Foege’s honors included the 1996 Calderone Prize, the most prestigious public health award; and the 2005 Public Welfare Medal, the National Academy of Science’s highest award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Survivors include his wife, Paula (Ristad) Foege; two sons, Robert and Michael; three sisters, Mildred Toepel, Annette Stixrud and Carolyn Hellberg; four grandchildren; and two great-grandchildren. His eldest son, David, died in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his later years, Dr. Foege became a prominent critic of both the first and second Trump administrations’ actions regarding public health. In 2020, when the Covid-19 pandemic was sweeping the world, he criticized the White House for initially downplaying the threat and making inaccurate public statements about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve broken every rule that we’ve learned on disease control,” he said in the interview for this obituary that year. “The first and most important rule is to know the truth. You have to set up a surveillance system to know the truth, otherwise you’re responding blindly. The truth changes every day in the White House.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was furious with the current health secretary, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., who has taken steps to dismantle many of the programs that Dr. Foege helped build, and whose views on vaccination he regarded as dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kennedy’s words can be as lethal as the smallpox virus,” he wrote in an opinion piece for the health and science website STAT in August, after Mr. Kennedy had promoted cod liver oil as a treatment for measles and called vaccination a personal choice. In an email message at the time, he wrote, “I had no idea I would be this angry at the age of 89.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a single accomplishment for which Dr. Foege will be remembered, it is the eradication of smallpox, which killed 300 million people in the 20th century alone. Among the books on his living room coffee table was one published in 2009 and titled “Scientists Greater Than Einstein: The Biggest Lifesavers of the Twentieth Century.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book tells the stories of 10 scientists who were not famous, but whose work had an outsize impact on humanity. The cover drawing is a silhouette of those featured inside. There are no names, but Dr. Foege’s presence is obvious. He stands a head taller than the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/us/william-h-foege-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 17:21:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Japan’s Leader Won’t Enter the Male-Dominated Sumo Ring</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/asia/japan-takaichi-sumo-gender.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/25int-japan-gender-01-cwbl/25int-japan-gender-01-cwbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the New Year Grand Sumo Tournament in Tokyo reached its adrenaline-pumping conclusion on Sunday, thousands of spectators cheered as star athletes were feted inside Japan’s most prestigious wrestling ring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But someone was missing: Japan’s prime minister, who typically hands out a giant gilded trophy at the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanae Takaichi, the first woman to serve as prime minister in Japan’s history, skipped the ceremony, yielding to a longstanding ban on women inside the sumo ring, known as the dohyo. She dispatched the Japanese education minister, a man, to read a certificate on her behalf; officials said she wanted to respect sumo’s “traditional culture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision was in keeping with the cautious approach to gender issues taken by Ms. Takaichi, a hard-line conservative who is seeking to expand her power in a snap election next month. Since breaking the glass ceiling in October, she has rarely spoken about the historical significance of her election, choosing instead to define feminism on her own terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than denounce sexism in Japanese society, Ms. Takaichi has leaned into public discussions about her clothing and appearance. She has emphasized traditional values, balancing her career with caring for her ailing husband. And she has sought to project an image as a warm, determined leader who loves to “work and work and work and work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Ms. Takaichi’s election has helped normalize the image of powerful women in Japan’s patriarchal society, her critics say that she should do more to promote gender equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She is sending the message that a woman is not an ornament — that women can be outspoken and driven,” said Kumiko Nemoto, a sociology professor at Senshu University in Tokyo. “Yet her vision of feminism has done little, so far, to advance the cause of gender equality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the campaign, Ms. Takaichi promised to bring “Nordic levels” of gender equality, which are typically closer to 50 percent, to her cabinet. But only two of the 18 members she appointed were women. That came plainly into view during a visit to Japan this month by Giorgia Meloni, Italy’s prime minister. Ms. Takaichi invited Ms. Meloni, the only other female leader among the Group of 7 nations, to pose for photographs with the women in her cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other conservative women in politics, including Ms. Meloni and Margaret Thatcher, the former British prime minister, Ms. Takaichi has embraced policies that critics say have eroded women’s rights. She opposes changing a longstanding law that requires married couples to share a surname, and she has backed efforts to preserve the male lineage of Japan’s imperial family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her supporters say that she embraces a different type of feminism, one that focuses on concerns about women’s safety and health. She has endorsed, for example, an effort to build more bathrooms for women in Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Waka Ikeda, a commentator and researcher, wrote this month in The Japan Times newspaper that Ms. Takaichi was pushing a version of conservative feminism that was rooted in the idea of working within existing structures, rather than “revolutionary transformation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This isn’t anti-feminist,” she wrote. “It’s a different feminist tradition, one that resonates with Japan’s silent majority.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi hinted at her vision when she invited two dozen women serving as ambassadors to Japan to her office this month. She told the ambassadors that she had aspired to be Japan’s prime minister — not its “first female prime minister.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I go about my daily work without giving much thought to it,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She warned about the “glass cliff,” a phenomenon in which women are appointed to steer organizations through crisis, only to be set up for failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It leads to the prejudice that women are not suited to being leaders,” she said. “Let’s work hard together and produce results in order to eradicate such words.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi has at times been the subject of sexist tropes. When President Trump visited Tokyo shortly after her election, commentators dissected her body language, saying she appeared too friendly when she locked arms with Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her sartorial choices — she favors blue suits and black handbags — have also been a frequent topic of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lawmaker in Parliament recently criticized her clothes, saying that she should wear “Japan’s finest fabrics and those crafted by its top artisans.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi responded with a lengthy meditation on social media about the stress she felt choosing clothes for high-profile events like the Group of 20 summit in South Africa. She wrote that she was heeding the lawmaker’s advice and had spent several hours selecting “clothes that don’t look cheap” and that “won’t get me looked down upon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grand Sumo tournament, which took place over 15 days this month, was seen as a test of how substantially Ms. Takaichi might seek to change Japan’s cultural norms. She skipped another sumo event in November.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minoru Kihara, the chief cabinet secretary, said earlier this week that the government, in deciding how to deal with the sumo awards ceremony, was considering the “prime minister’s intention that she would like to value the traditional culture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japan Sumo Association said in a statement that it was “committed to the success of the traditional culture of Grand Sumo.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sumo aficionados expressed disappointment that Ms. Takaichi did not present the trophy as many of her male predecessors had. Over the years, several female officials in Japan have lobbied the association for permission to enter the ring. The group has rejected their requests; it came under fire at one point for forcing a female mayor to speak from a podium outside the ring instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi “is the last person who wants to change women’s rights or promote feminism,” said Shizuka Wada, an author who has been critical of sumo culture. “This tradition will never change so long as she is prime minister.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women have long been banned from professional sumo rings in Japan. In the Shinto faith, one of the country’s main religions, they are considered impure because of menstruation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomoko Nakagawa, a former mayor of the city of Takarazuka, said Ms. Takaichi had a chance to help advance women’s rights. As mayor in 2018, Ms. Nakagawa was rejected by the sumo association when she tried to make a speech inside a training stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Women are treated as unclean even in the modern era,” she said. “Will she allow such a tradition to last in the future? I expect the prime minister to raise some questions at some point.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/asia/japan-takaichi-sumo-gender.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:57:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine Expects Answers From Russia as Peace Talks Continue, Zelensky Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/ukraine-us-russia-peace-talks.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-ukraine-talks-lmgj/24int-ukraine-talks-lmgj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rare three-way talks among Russian, Ukrainian and American officials entered their second day on Saturday in the United Arab Emirates, as President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine said that he expected “at least some answers” from Russia on the current draft of a plan to end the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peace plan originated last fall as a proposal negotiated between the Trump administration and Russia, but it has since been revised several times, with input from Ukraine, the United States, European nations and other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky argued in recent days that it was time for Russia to provide answers on the peace plan as it now stands, even as Moscow has shown little appetite to stop its attacks on Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peace plan’s 20 points cover security, postwar reconstruction, exchanges of prisoners and other matters tied to the conflict, which started nearly four years ago with Russia’s full-scale invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking late Friday after the first day of talks, Mr. Zelensky said in a video address to Ukrainians that he was regularly in touch with the country’s negotiators in Abu Dhabi, the capital of the United Arab Emirates, and that they “should already have at least some answers” on Moscow’s position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Zelensky said it was “still too early to draw conclusions” on whether Russia would negotiate in good faith. The talks are expected to wrap up on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is necessary that not only Ukraine has the desire to end this war and achieve full security, but that a similar desire somehow emerges in Russia as well,” Mr. Zelensky said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite some progress in recent months of peace negotiations, Ukraine and Russia are still at odds over key sticking points tied to security and territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Ukraine fleshed out proposals for postwar security guarantees with both the United States and Europe, with some European countries vowing that they would commit troops to dissuade Russia from invading again. But Moscow has rejected any deployment of troops from NATO member states on Ukrainian territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Ukrainian authorities have refused Russia’s request to control all of the Donetsk region, a former industrial and coal-mining powerhouse in eastern Ukraine that the war has left mostly in ruins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. and Ukrainian negotiators have discussed what Steve Witkoff, the Trump administration’s envoy for peace talks, has called various “iterations” of compromises. Suggestions have included putting neutral forces as peacekeepers in part of the Donetsk region or forming a demilitarized zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Russia has rejected any settlement on territory that departs from what Russian officials have characterized as an agreement reached between President Trump and President Vladimir V. Putin at a summit in Alaska last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After those talks, neither leader publicly laid out a detailed plan for dividing Ukrainian territory, although Mr. Trump told European leaders at the time that he supported a plan to end the war by ceding unconquered territory to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Mr. Zelensky said the talks in the United Arab Emirates would focus on control of territory in eastern Ukraine. Any compromise for Ukraine would be bitter after more than a decade of bloodshed defending the region, beginning with a first Russian military incursion in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Zelensky told reporters at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, on Thursday that “we are at the moment, if all the sides will work a lot, we will end this war.” But he also suggested that Russia might “play games” that would derail talks.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/europe/ukraine-us-russia-peace-talks.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 13:18:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria Announces Cease-Fire Extension, Hours After Truce With Kurds Expired</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/middleeast/syria-kurdish-militia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-syria-kurds-hbqf/24int-syria-kurds-hbqf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Syria’s defense ministry said on Saturday that it would extend a cease-fire across all military operations for 15 days, hours after a weeklong truce with a Kurdish-led militia in the country’s northeast expired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ministry said in a statement on social media that the extension was in support of an operation led by the United States to transfer detainees from the Islamic State group held in Syria to Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Syrian government troops have in recent weeks taken control of large areas of territory held by Kurds in eastern and northern Syria, including strategic assets like oil fields and dams, after intense clashes with the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the Syrian armed forces took over parts of the northeast, the United States began relocating detainees from the Islamic State, also known as ISIS, amid concerns that thousands of former fighters and their relatives could break out of detention in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The defense ministry’s statement on Saturday made no explicit reference to the government’s conflict with the S.D.F., though the group said in a subsequent post on social media that an agreement had been reached through international mediation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Syrian government and the Kurds agreed last Sunday to an immediate cease-fire that called for the full integration of Kurdish troops into the national army, a longstanding demand of the Syrian government, as well as the handing over of administrative control of much of the northeast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Syrian state news agency SANA reported on Tuesday that the government had given the S.D.F. four days to submit a detailed plan for the integration of Hasakah Province, which was the only province left under the militia’s authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unclear whether a plan had been submitted, and a spokesman for the group did not immediately respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts widely saw the truce deal as a capitulation, because the S.D.F. lost almost all of the concessions the Syrian government had offered in earlier negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SANA cited an unnamed government source on Saturday night as saying that the cease-fire had ended, and that it was weighing its next steps. And Syria’s foreign ministry had dismissed reports circulating on social media that the deadline would be extended, SANA said, citing a ministry official, Mohammad Taha al-Ahmad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All options remain on the table, alongside calm and dialogue, to enforce the law, preserve Syria’s unity and safeguard the rights of the Syrian people,” Mr. al-Ahmad said, according to SANA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F. had accused the government on social media of deploying troops in breach of the cease-fire, saying it was an effort to “undermine de-escalation and steer the situation toward war instead of political solutions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s recent advances have strengthened President Ahmed al-Sharaa’s grip on Syria, more than a year after his rebel forces overthrew the dictatorship of Bashar al-Assad, whose family had ruled the country for decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa has sought to bring Syria’s diverse ethnic and religious communities under centralized rule with himself at the helm in the capital, Damascus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has also pledged that all of Syria’s minority communities will be protected under his government and, this month, signed a decree affirming Kurdish rights, including calls to restore Syrian citizenship to Kurds stripped of it after a 1962 census.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The S.D.F., which has long positioned itself as the defender of Syrian Kurds and administered a de facto state in northeastern Syria, has posed the most formidable challenge to Mr. al-Sharaa’s effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurdish-led militia has resisted full integration into the government’s army, seeking autonomy over its territories and security in northeastern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet those Kurdish forces have also long been key partners of the United States, assisting in the fight against the Islamic State guarding American bases and managing detention camps and prisons that housed thousands of jihadists and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partnership appeared to come undone this week, after the U.S. special envoy to Syria, Thomas J. Barrack, said that Washington no longer viewed Kurdish-led forces as its main partner in the fight against the Islamic State. Mr. Barrack said he believed that the Syrian government was now ready to take on those responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That apparent policy shift reflected Washington’s increasing confidence in Mr. al-Sharaa, who maintains a close relationship with President Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the Kurdish militia fighters, “There’s a profound sense of abandonment and fear, layered with exhaustion,” said Nanar Hawach, a senior Syria analyst at the International Crisis Group, which focuses on conflict prevention. “For them, individual integration into the Syrian army isn’t a bureaucratic detail. It is the end of the project they have fought for.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cease-fire remained fragile and, this week, fighting broke out around two prisons in northeast Syria that housed ISIS members, highlighting the vulnerability of the agreement and raising fears that some may escape during the handover process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, U.S. Central Command, which is responsible for American military operations in the Middle East, said that U.S. forces had already relocated 150 Islamic State fighters from a detention center in northeastern Syria to an undisclosed “secure location” in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military added that as many as 7,000 ISIS detainees currently held in Syria could eventually be transferred to facilities managed by Iraqi authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the cease-fire, the S.D.F. agreed to transfer control of the northern province of Raqqa and the eastern province of Deir al-Zour to the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the cease-fire was extended, the United Nations warned of a looming humanitarian crisis in some Kurdish-held cities in Syria, citing disruptions to electricity and water amid bitter winter conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farhan Haq, the deputy spokesman for the U.N. secretary general, said on Friday that all roads into Kobani, a Kurdish stronghold in northern Syria, were closed, and that disruptions to electricity, water and internet were limiting access to basic services. Food and essential supplies are at risk of shortages, he said, and while health facilities remain open, medicine remains limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.N. was working with its partners and local authorities to conduct additional assessments and secure access, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, even as Mr. al-Sharaa makes territorial gains, he faces a crucial test, Mr. Hawach said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Al-Sharaa has an opportunity here,” he said. “If he can now demonstrate that integration means genuine inclusion, it would be the strongest signal yet that Syria’s new order is different from what came before.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reham Mourshed, Hussam Hammoud and Muhammad Haj Kadour contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/middleeast/syria-kurdish-militia.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:52:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens Canada With Tariffs as Post-Davos Fallout Continues</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/canada/trump-canada-tariffs.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/multimedia/24int-canada-trump-tkcv/24int-canada-trump-tkcv-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump on Saturday threatened Canada with steep tariffs if it “makes a deal with China” and insulted Prime Minister Mark Carney, his latest swing at the country since Mr. Carney pushed back against his policies in a highly publicized speech in Davos, Switzerland, this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Canada makes a deal with China, it will immediately be hit with a 100% Tariff against all Canadian goods and products coming into the U.S.A.,” Mr. Trump said in a post on Truth Social. He referred to Mr. Carney as “Governor Carney,” a reference to Mr. Trump’s repeated insistence that Canada should become the 51st U.S. state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no indication that Canada and China are in discussions about a broad trade agreement. Mr. Trump may have been reacting to Mr. Carney’s state visit to China last week, during which he agreed to lower tariffs on some Chinese electric vehicles in exchange for China doing the same for some Canadian agricultural products. The closely watched visit was billed as a crucial reset in the two countries’ relationship, but the trade agreement itself was modest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada gave Jamieson Greer, the U.S. Trade Representative, a detailed preview of the agreement with China before it was signed, a senior Canadian official said, speaking on condition of anonymity to divulge details about communication between the two administrations. Mr. Trump appeared to praise Mr. Carney after the deal was announced. (“Good for him,” he said.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But he soured on the prime minister after Mr. Carney’s Davos speech, in which Mr. Carney declared that the U.S.-led world order had been ruptured and called on “middle powers” like Canada to band together to survive a new and perilous era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without mentioning Mr. Trump or the United States by name, Mr. Carney pointedly called out the use of tariffs as coercion. “More recently, great powers have begun using economic integration as weapons, tariffs as leverage, financial infrastructure as coercion, supply chains as vulnerabilities to be exploited,” Mr. Carney said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speech did not go down well with Mr. Trump, who responded in his own address the next day at Davos, saying that Canada “lives because of the United States.” Mr. Trump also rescinded an invitation to Mr. Carney to join his “Board of Peace.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Carney’s office did not immediately respond to a request for comment about Mr. Trump’s post on Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Trump routinely fails to make good on his tariff threats, calling Mr. Carney “governor” could be a bad sign for the two countries’ relationship. After returning to the White House last year, Mr. Trump routinely applied the title to Mr. Carney’s predecessor, Justin Trudeau, as part of his rhetoric about the United States annexing Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our economics reporters — based in New York, London, Brussels, Berlin, Hong Kong and Seoul — are digging into every aspect of the tariffs causing global turmoil. They are joined by dozens of reporters writing about the effects on everyday people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between Mr. Trump and Mr. Carney had been much more respectful, at least until the Davos gathering. The leaders met several times last year, twice in the White House, and Mr. Trump expressed admiration for Mr. Carney’s electoral victory last spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, their warm words have not materialized into an improved trade relationship. Though the United States has a three-way trade agreement with Canada and Mexico, the Trump administration has imposed tariffs on certain exports from both countries, which in Canada’s case have hurt its steel, aluminum, automobile and lumber industries. A review of the three-way trade deal is due this year, and its renewal is far from certain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has maintained that the United States does not need anything from Canada, even as it gets most of its imported oil from its northern neighbor and their economies continue to be closely integrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest flashpoint bodes ill for Canada’s efforts to stabilize its relationship with the Trump administration, just as Mr. Carney looks for new allies and trading partners to lessen his country’s overwhelming dependence on the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though Mr. Carney is a former governor of the central banks of both Canada and Britain, he is new to elected office, and he has staked his leadership of Canada on a strategy of diversifying from the United States and streamlining trade within Canada itself. He has also committed billions to making Canada less dependent on the United States for its defense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his Davos speech, Mr. Carney indicated that he had given up hopes of a return to the way things had been before Mr. Trump’s second term. “The old order is not coming back. We should not mourn it,” he said. “Nostalgia is not a strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/24/world/canada/trump-canada-tariffs.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 17:26:47 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Podcaster Poking at France’s Biggest Secrets</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/europe/philippe-collin-france-podcast-history-world-war-ii.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2025/12/31/multimedia/00int-france-podcast-01-wbkq/00int-france-podcast-01-wbkq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past fall, the French podcaster Philippe Collin traveled with his millions of listeners to an enormous, almost 900-year-old castle in southwestern Germany, where members of the Nazi-backed French collaborationist government retreated after the D-Day landings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the sound of laughter and clinking champagne glasses, Mr. Collin’s listeners heard how the French collaborators celebrated Christmas in the castle’s grand mirrored gallery during the last year of World War II and planned their return to Paris on the backs of German tanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a part of French history that is little known, decidedly inglorious and — to many in France — best forgotten. Yet by making podcasts about it, as part of a broader series about France’s checkered World War II history, Mr. Collin has become among the most popular podcasters in France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His podcast, “Facing History,” has proved an unlikely but smashing success, passing 40 million downloads. Among historians and politicians, it has spurred reappraisals of key historical figures. And, amid fears of an expansion of Russia’s war farther into Europe and the growing popularity of the French far right, Mr. Collin hopes it will burrow into the minds of his listeners and inspire them to defend the soul of the French Republic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am trying to reactivate the memory of the resistance,” Mr. Collin explained over coffee recently, referring to the French underground movements that resisted the Nazis during the German occupation of much of France in 1940-45.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Collin, 50, has spent his career as a producer and host of France’s most popular radio station, France Inter, where he built a reputation as an innovator and someone keen to try new things. Over the years, he has hosted shows as varied as the afternoon daily talk show and a weekly program on American culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more than four years, his focus has been historical podcast series, many at least partly dedicated to France’s delicate, complicated experience of World War II, as both a victim of Nazi Germany and a collaborator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each series of “Facing History” lasts eight to 10 hours and is packed with archival radio clips, snatches of letters and memoirs read by actors, and interviews with as many as 12 historians. Despite — or perhaps because of — their uncomfortable subjects and rigorous treatment, the shows have proved popular. The series on the German castle has been downloaded more than two million times. Mr. Collin’s 2024 novel, “The Barman of the Ritz,” was so popular, its cover went back onto Paris subway walls in January to announce the paperback version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast has given him material for three spinoff books, three television documentaries and a nine-hour play about Léon Blum, France’s first Jewish prime minister, who was sent to the Buchenwald concentration camp. Two more plays based on the series are in the works, and historians credit Mr. Collin with finding new information for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Rousso, a celebrated French historian of World War II, said that even he learned things while listening to Mr. Collin’s podcasts. “For me, he is an historian,” said Mr. Rousso, who has appeared on three of the podcasts. “He has the ability to create a historical narrative that is uniquely his own.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all historians agree. Mr. Collin caused an uproar among experts on France’s war in Algeria after the podcast downplayed reports that Jean-Marie Le Pen, a far-right leader, tortured Algerians during the conflict. After the podcast, a confession by Mr. Le Pen, published posthumously, acknowledged the reports were true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Collin “dabbles in everything, and like all people who dabble in everything, he very often doesn’t really know what he’s talking about,” said Fabrice Riceputi, a historian who was motivated by the podcast to write a book documenting Mr. Le Pen’s torture of Algerians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The French passion for its national history can explain some of the series’ success. But Mr. Collin thinks the country’s current mood has made it particularly receptive to these stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The podcast began less than a year before Russia’s invasion of Ukraine, and fears of a larger war, engulfing France, have since grown. At the same time, France’s far-right party has surged. Polls show that one of its leaders would win the next presidential election in 2027, which would create the first far-right government in France since the collaborationist Vichy regime in World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People have a sense the Republic is threatened again and are looking for tools to combat that,” Mr. Collin said. Adding to that sense of social anxiety, he said, are the deaths of the last remaining heroes from the war — “the guardians of the memory of the resistance,” as he calls them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are in the process of breaking away from that past,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By his own admission, Mr. Collin is “obsessed” with that past. He was trained as a historian, doing his master’s degree on the purge of suspected collaborators near the end of World War II. He would have continued had his parents had the money to keep funding his studies, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Born in 1975, he grew up in the tiny village of Le Fret in Brittany, the eldest of two sons of a mother who was a child care assistant and a father who worked in the navy. Like many in France, the family was haunted by the history of the war. Both of his grandfathers had been captured soldiers. Meals with the extended family were peppered with their stories, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, there was the discovery of a terrible family secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His favorite great-uncle, Marcel Grob, whom he visited every summer in the Alsace region, had fought with the Waffen S.S. — the fanatical Nazi unit known for civilian massacres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When he learned the truth, Mr. Collin cut his great-uncle off. He didn’t attend Mr. Grob’s funeral, he said, because he thought to himself, “I’m not going to the funeral of a Nazi.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, he received Mr. Grob’s military service record and realized he had made a painful mistake. Mr. Grob, then just 17, had been a forced conscript. Through research, Mr. Collin learned that the families of conscripts who evaded their orders were sent to German labor camps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All of a sudden, I said to myself, ‘What would you have done in his place?’” Mr. Collin said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, he published a graphic novel, “The Journey of Marcel Grob,” as a form of apology. He spent eight years writing “Barman of the Ritz,” about a Jewish bartender during the war who served Nazis at night and found fake papers for Jewish employees by day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Collin has two stepsons with his partner, Sonia Devillers, another well-known radio journalist at France Inter. He said one of them recently asked him if he thought about the war every single day. “I said yes,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his podcasts are often about much more. With his team of 10, he has examined Napoleon, the writer Molière and Louis XV’s official mistress, Jeanne de Barry. His latest series is about the Statue of Liberty, a gift to the United States from the French public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His podcast on the life of Alfred Dreyfus, a Jewish Army captain wrongly convicted of treason in the late 19th century, helped inspire a French lawmaker to sponsor a law that gave Mr. Dreyfus a posthumous promotion. “I listened to the entirety of Philippe Collin’s podcast,” the lawmaker, Charles Sitzenstuhl, said in an email. “It made a deep impression on me and helped me in my work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there were a drum beat to the series, it would be what Mr. Collin calls the “values of the French Republic.” By that, he means liberty, equality and fraternity — the country’s motto, born during the French Revolution in 1789 — as well as the societal systems that ensure the promise is kept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He worries those values are being attacked and sees France’s current divisions as an echo of those of the 1930s, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today, we are facing a form of radicalization and polarization within society, and we can clearly see the seeds of a civil war — an ideological civil war — being replanted,” he said. “We are losing our way, much like the United States, for that matter. People in the United States can no longer speak to each other.” There, he said, “the ‘other’ is no longer a human being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He hopes his podcast offers listeners a kind of antidote. But, he said, he remains humble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We aren’t in politics,” he said. “We are just a podcast.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Castelain contributed reporting from Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/europe/philippe-collin-france-podcast-history-world-war-ii.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:21:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Woman Who Stands Between Donald Trump and Greenland</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/europe/mette-frederiksen-denmark-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/22/multimedia/00int-denmark-leader-pfbm/00int-denmark-leader-pfbm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mette Frederiksen has never tolerated bullies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When she was in high school, Ms. Frederiksen, Denmark’s prime minister, stood up to a pack of skinheads for teasing immigrant kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn’t go so well. She got socked in the face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this week, she ducked a punch, a big one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After escalating threats from President Trump about seizing Greenland, Denmark’s gigantic overseas territory, Mr. Trump seems finally to have backed down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a speech to the world’s financial elite in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Trump said he would not use force to take Greenland. Later he said he and NATO leaders had worked out “the framework of a future deal” that would make everyone happy. That remains to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there were other factors to Mr. Trump’s reversal, like rising congressional opposition and falling stock markets, but there’s no doubt that Ms. Frederiksen’s carefully crafted defense helped block Mr. Trump from getting something he really wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months, Ms. Frederiksen has played a nervous game of brinkmanship with Mr. Trump, and it looks like she has won — for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As negotiations continue, Ms. Frederiksen remains locked in an unwanted struggle, trying to calibrate how to make clear to the mercurial Mr. Trump that the answer to his demand that the United States have Greenland is a hard no, without antagonizing him into threatening to snatch it away again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already, she has signaled her resistance to one of the compromises that Mr. Trump appeared to be considering — the establishment of American sovereignty over military bases on Greenland. Sovereignty, she insists, remains a “red line.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent time with Ms. Frederiksen this fall, in Greenland, where she agreed to a rare sit-down interview in an old house overlooking the sea. We asked her if she felt Mr. Trump was acting like a bully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He is able to speak in a very clear way,” she replied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So am I.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That quiet resolve, rather than flattery, has set her apart from other European leaders when it comes to handling Mr. Trump. It has made her extraordinarily popular at home. Opinion polls in Denmark show her party surging. Elections are later this year and the polls suggest she’s primed to win a third term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her rising support reflects just how much Greenland means for her country, let alone for Mr. Trump and Greenlanders themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Trump, the island represents the extreme of his imperial ambitions: seizing an enormous land from a NATO ally in what would be the biggest territorial acquisition in American history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the 57,000 Greenlanders, a mostly Inuit population with long and complicated ties to Denmark, their future is at stake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for Ms. Frederiksen, who swept into office in 2019 as the youngest prime minister in Danish history, the dispute is undeniably existential, threatening her country’s very identity, composition and stature on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week’s fast-moving developments demonstrated her tactical skills. After Mr. Trump, declared that since he didn’t win the Nobel Peace Prize he was giving up on peace and would push ahead on Greenland, she rolled up her sleeves, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She imported troops from her own coalition of the willing — including Britain, Germany, France and Iceland — to Greenland. She rallied Europe to speak out in Denmark’s defense. She resisted Mr. Trump’s threats of tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until that moment, many Danes had resigned themselves that there was little their country could do if indeed Mr. Trump moved on the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen’s risky strategy to call in foreign military and law enforcement personnel, albeit a tiny contingent of a few dozen and ostensibly part of an Arctic training exercise, was a signal that any military action that Mr. Trump took “would be very nasty and ugly,” said Bent Winther, a Danish political commentator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her point was that, “if you’re going to take Greenland by force, you’d have to put British and French and German officers in handcuffs,” Mr. Winther said. “I think that was part of the game.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen’s sparring with Mr. Trump has come to define her leadership. It started from her very first weeks in office in 2019, when she arrived at the age of 41 as the head of the center-left Social Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That summer, during his first term, Mr. Trump suggested that the United States buy Greenland, which has been part of Denmark for more than 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen dismissed it as “absurd,” which provoked Mr. Trump to cancel a trip to Copenhagen and call her remarks “nasty.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does she regret saying that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a closed chapter,” she said in the interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump reopened that chapter again, on Jan. 7, 2025, even before his inauguration, when he said for the first time that he wouldn’t rule out using military force to get Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That same day, the president’s eldest son, Donald Trump Jr., made a lightning quick visit to Nuuk, Greenland’s capital, in the depths of winter, ostensibly for business. His appearance drew a band of pro-Trump social media influencers dressed in bulky snowsuits and American flags who passed out $100 bills, which turned off many Greenlanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next week, Ms. Frederiksen held a heated phone call with Mr. Trump. According to European officials who were briefed afterward, Mr. Trump berated her for 45 minutes. She did not want to talk about that one either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A phone call between two colleagues has to be a phone call between two colleagues,” she told us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Winther, who co-wrote a biography about her — “Mette F” — in 2019, traces her cool self-assuredness and penchant for underdog causes to her childhood home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her father, Flemming Frederiksen, was a typographer, union leader and active member of the Social Democrats. He worked in a newspaper production room as the paper was transitioning into the automated era and stood up for workers about to be rendered obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When people ask me: ‘When did you get interested in politics?’ I don’t know what to say,” Ms. Frederiksen said during our interview. “I cannot remember not being interested in politics.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was shy, she said, but also strident. After recounting the run-in with the skinhead in high school, she said, “I don’t know if it tells something about my character, maybe it tells us more about his.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first political party she joined was the youth wing of the African National Congress. She rapidly rose through the ranks of the youth wing of the Social Democrats, winning a seat in 2001 to Denmark’s parliament. Mr. Winter said she arrived with “extraordinary confidence, you know, the confidence you can only feel when you are very young.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was 24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, she had a different look — casual clothes, spiky hair. She quickly gained a reputation for being a strong public speaker and unafraid of taking on party elders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her tenure has been marked by crisis. During the Covid pandemic her government abruptly ordered a cull of millions of minks (raised for fur), fearful they could spread the virus. It was a controversial decision and resulted in several high-level resignations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She survived the fallout and ultimately was credited with guiding Denmark through those years with relatively low infections while keeping public services as open as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Vladimir V. Putin ordered the invasion of Ukraine, she called for Europe to act. She was among the first on the continent to commit F-16 fighter jets to the Ukrainian military and boosted weapons production for Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her country, like some others, has been the victim of unsolved drone incursions widely believed to have been instigated by Russia, perhaps as payback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On immigration, she has put in place some of Europe’s harshest asylum rules — including utilizing camps abroad and family separations. The moves have been criticized by human rights groups but have sharply reduced arrivals and shored her up politically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we spoke with her in September, she was visiting Greenland to apologize for Danish doctors forcing contraception on Greenlandic women and girls, part of a long abusive colonial legacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most Danish political analysts give her high marks for how she has handled Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s difficult for me to really find any major errors,” said Ulrik Pram Gad, a respected academic on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gad said that as Mr. Trump began to get aggressive about Greenland, Ms. Frederiksen did a good job of coordinating with Greenlandic officials and rallying European capitals, such as London and Paris, “trying to get our message out of other people’s mouths.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason? Denmark needs Greenland. With it, Denmark is the world’s 12th largest sovereign state. It sits on the Arctic Council, the leading international forum for Arctic affairs. It keeps its special (though now troubled) relationship to the United States, which has been protecting Greenland since World War II and maintains a military base at the northern end of the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When they don’t have Greenland anymore, they will lose 98 percent of their area,” said Pele Broberg, the leader of a Greenlandic political party that has been critical of Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So it’s very simple,” Mr. Broberg said. “They’re important as long as they own us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen, for her part, has supported Greenland’s autonomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The future of Greenland belongs to the Greenlandic people,” she said. “It’s more two countries now working together than an old colony, with all what is included in that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the 50-minute interview, Ms. Frederiksen was more comfortable talking foreign affairs than about her own life. She is on her second marriage, with a Danish cinematographer, Bo Tengberg, and together they are raising five children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside politics, she finds respite in spending time at the family summer house, cooking and preserving food, and staying fit through spinning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said one of her most important guiding principles was keeping Europe’s alliance with America strong — or at least intact. As recently as 2024, she said that she wouldn’t allow “a single piece of paper” to slip between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past week, she has said that she still believes in a close relationship with the United States, citing “a common interest in ensuring our security.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Some Europeans have loved the U.S. because of dollars and ‘Dallas’ and so on. That’s not how I am,” she told us. “I really believe that everything would have gone wrong for Europe if it wasn’t for D-Day and for the big role of the U.S. in ending the Second World War.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You saved us,” she said. “And by the way, you have done that again and again.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So my starting point is that I will do whatever I can to keep us together in this world, and therefore I’m not starting a conflict,” she said. “I’m trying to solve a conflict.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/europe/mette-frederiksen-denmark-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 00:57:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Venezuela, Families Search for Relatives Who Are Detained and Missing</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/americas/in-venezuela-families-search-for-relatives-who-are-detained-and-missing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/24/25int-venezuela-disappeared-new-54446-cover/25int-venezuela-disappeared-new-54446-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After taking a 10-hour bus ride across Venezuela in a quest to find her missing husband, Carolina Carrizo fashioned a makeshift bed out of discarded sofa cushions to sleep outside Zona 7, a detention center in Caracas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, she said, about 30 uniformed police officers looking for weapons forced their way inside her home in western Venezuela and took her husband, Omar Torres, 53, a political activist. The authorities never acknowledged the arrest, she said, and she has not heard from him since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has slept outside Zona 7 since arriving in Caracas two weeks ago. She is not even sure that he is there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the Trump administration’s capture of Venezuela’s president, Nicolás Maduro, its interim government has drawn international headlines for releasing dozens of political prisoners who rights groups say were wrongfully detained. The trickle of releases has shone a renewed spotlight on a related phenomenon in Venezuela: people who were arrested, largely for political reasons, and then disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump’s words of praise for what he says is the accommodating attitude of the interim leader, Delcy Rodríguez, has made families in Venezuela hopeful that the newfound cooperation between the two countries could bring freedom for dozens of people who were taken without a trace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re all here, outside the prisons, because of Trump, because of what he did,” Ms. Carrizo said. “Now I just want my husband back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For two weeks, other mothers, wives and girlfriends from across Venezuela have slept on the street outside Zona 7, where their tents sit next to dozens of police officers wielding riot shields. The police claim the jail is empty, but the families say that they have heard screams coming from inside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I feel that Trump is the one who is going to get them out,” said Betsy Orellana, who said her son, Rodolfo José Rodríguez Orellana, a former police officer, is serving a 24-year sentence for participating in a plot to overthrow the government. He has been missing since August, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The locations of at least 66 prisoners are unknown in Venezuela, according to Foro Penal, a leading rights group, which tracks politically motivated detentions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of those, about 30 of them, like Ms. Orellana’s son, were arrested during an attempted invasion of Venezuela in 2020 known as Operation Gideon. The effort to topple Mr. Maduro, hatched by an American former Green Beret, failed spectacularly: Eight would-be rebels were killed and the rest are still in prison, and have not been heard from since being transferred in August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Venezuelan government did not respond to requests for comment for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forced disappearances is a decades-old practice that became a notorious tool used by Latin American dictatorships against critics — from foreigners to students and political activists. The practice is categorized as a violation of international law and a crime against humanity because the authorities are obligated to acknowledge when a person is in police custody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Venezuela, some people have been missing for over a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Venezuelan law, detainees are supposed to be brought before a court within 48 hours, a provision that human rights activists say is often ignored. But in the cases of the disappeared, the families do not even know where they are being held.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Venezuelan government unleashed a harsh crackdown, called “Operation Knock-Knock,” to stamp out dissent after a July 2024 presidential election that Mr. Maduro claimed to have won despite vote tallies showing he lost decisively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 800 people considered political prisoners are still detained after 154 were released in recent days, according to Foro Penal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even in a countries where human rights are frequently violated, the disappearance of inmates is considered particularly serious because the detainees are outside the protection of the law, human rights experts said. It is difficult for families to hire defense lawyers for a case that officially does not exist, making the defendant particularly vulnerable, experts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International, in a report last year, said Venezuela saw a significant increase in forced disappearances after the 2024 elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People would disappear for hours, days, weeks or months, the organization said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clara del Campo, the South America campaigner for Amnesty International, said families “literally” knock on prison doors asking for their loved ones, but the guards claim no one by that name is in custody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It speaks to the ingenuity of repressive governments whereby they find new ways of applying cruelty and punishing those that they consider real or perceived dissidents,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “desaparecido” became common in the 1970s in Argentina, when a military dictatorship abducted as many as 30,000 people, tortured them and, in hundreds of cases, threw them from airplanes into the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, the term was largely considered synonymous with “missing and most likely dead.” In more recent years, the practice became commonplace in countries like Nicaragua, where missing people are believed to be alive but imprisoned, with no records to document it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Nicaragua, several dozen people who were detained and missing were recently released, but nine remain unaccounted for, according to a prisoner monitoring group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Caracas, Venezuela’s capital, Victor Borges, 39, a political activist, has been missing since Nov. 25, relatives said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is as if the earth swallowed him,” said his former partner, Yesley Bello, 26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witnesses told Ms. Bello that vehicles bearing the insignia of Venezuela’s Bolivarian National Police arrived at Mr. Borges’s workplace, an elite private school, where he cared for animals at the school’s petting zoo, and took him away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His family can rattle off the names of government agencies, prisons, hospitals, police stations and morgues where they have gone to ask about him. Each time, the family said, they were told the same thing: No one by that name was there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Bello has begun to consider the possibility that he may never return to her or his five children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I will tell them about the great father they had,” she said, her eyes filling with tears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martina Rapido, a researcher with Human Rights Watch, said that forced disappearance is “always a strategy to break not only the person who is detained, but also their families, sometimes in retaliation for political opposition.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rapido said the disappearances generally fit one of two patterns. They are often short-term detentions that last a few days. But others involve high-profile activists who are held incommunicado for an extended period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marilis Rodríguez, 58, traveled 200 miles to Caracas recently from the city of Acarigua searching of her son, Carlos José Rodríguez Rodríguez. She said the police took Mr. Rodríguez, 29, from his home on Sept. 23, 2025, after accusing him of illegally selling dollars on the black market, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My son was taken from his house for an investigation,” Ms. Rodríguez said. “They were going to question him about something, and it’s going to be four months since we last heard from him.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said her son, a vendor of imported goods, was not politically active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She said she was told at one prison in Caracas that he had been released, only to be told a day later that it was not true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rodríguez’s first child, a boy, was born after he was taken, so they have yet to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The family said it had tried to find him in at least five prisons in Caracas and also asked about him at every police station in Acarigua.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve turned the town of Acarigua upside down,” said Adriana Graterol, a cousin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leomaris Prado traveled eight hours by bus from Guárico State to El Helicoide, a prison with a reputation as a center for torture in Caracas, looking for her father. Leonardo Prado, a mechanic, has been missing since Dec. 28, when she said he was stopped at a checkpoint and taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her father was not politically active, Ms. Prado said, but had recently gotten into a dispute with noisy neighbors who happened to be police officers, and his family now wonders whether that triggered his detention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m here because I want proof that my father is alive,” Ms. Prado said. “I want them to tell me where he is. I want them to tell me why they took him. I want them to show me the evidence.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/americas/in-venezuela-families-search-for-relatives-who-are-detained-and-missing.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:02:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran Crushed a Citizen Uprising With Lethal Force</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/middleeast/iran-how-crackdown-was-done.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/1-ILAM_2x3-still/1-ILAM_2x3-still-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tehran, the capital of Iran, security forces opened fire at protesters from the roof of a police station. In Karaj, they fired live rounds into a march, shooting one person in the head. In Isfahan, young men barricaded themselves in an alley as gunfire and explosions rang out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scattered protests had percolated since late December, starting with a strike in Tehran’s bazaar and fueled by a plunging economy. But by early January, Iranians had revolted en masse, and the security forces began to crack down with deadly force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not just the protests unnerving the regime. President Trump encouraged the demonstrators and threatened military intervention. In many places, riots flared in parallel with peaceful protests; government buildings, commercial properties, mosques and police stations were set on fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Jan. 9, Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, ordered the Supreme National Security Council, the body tasked with safeguarding the country, to crush the protests by any means necessary, according to two Iranian officials briefed on the ayatollah’s directive. Security forces were deployed with orders to shoot to kill and to show no mercy, the officials said. The death toll surged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Iran shutting down the internet and disrupting phone service, some Iranians managed to evade restrictions to share witness accounts and hundreds of videos, many of which The New York Times was able to collect and authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times has verified videos of security forces opening fire on protesters in at least 19 different cities and in at least six different neighborhoods in Tehran in early January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TURKMENISTAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caspian Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mashhad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times verified footage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of security forces firing on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;demonstrators at these&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isfahan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiraz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KUWAIT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAUDI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARABIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gulf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TURKMENISTAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caspian Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mashhad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times verified footage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of security forces firing on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;demonstrators at these locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isfahan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiraz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KUWAIT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAUDI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARABIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gulf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: Verified footage; Institute for the Study of War and American Enterprise Institute’s Critical Threats Project (all protests)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These videos show the breadth and ferocity of the regime’s crackdown. So do the testimonies of doctors and a nurse working in hospitals in Iran, and photographs shared by a witness and authenticated by The Times of hundreds of victims brought to a Tehran morgue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times also interviewed two dozen Iranians in Tehran, Isfahan, Shiraz, Rasht and Ahvaz who had attended protests, as well as relatives of people killed. Protesters, residents and medical staff interviewed for this article all asked that their names or full names not be published for fear of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Monday, Jan. 12, the protests had largely been crushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As more information emerges from Iran, the death toll has hit at least 5,200 people, including 56 children, according to the Washington-based Human Rights Activists News Agency. Iran Human Rights, a Norway-based group that also monitors the situation in Iran, has confirmed at least 3,400 killed. Both organizations say that the numbers could prove two or three times larger as verification continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s National Security Council said in a statement that 3,117 people had been killed, among them 427 of its security forces. Officials, including Mr. Khamenei, have blamed terrorist cells tied to Israel and the United States for the uprising and killings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not merely a violent protest crackdown. It is a state-orchestrated massacre,” said Raha Bahreini, a lawyer and an Iran researcher at Amnesty International.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 8, Nasim Pouraghayee, 45, a mother of two, and her husband, Ali, marched with large crowds in the Sadeghiyeh neighborhood in Tehran. She called her mother to say the atmosphere was boisterous and the turnout huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abruptly, things turned deadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her husband was walking behind her, hands wrapped around her shoulders to protect her, according to a cousin of Ms. Pouraghayee’s who, in an interview, recounted the events of the night as described by Ali. A bullet hit Ms. Pouraghayee in the neck; she fell to the ground and began vomiting blood, the cousin said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nasim, Nasim, Nasim,” her husband screamed, holding her face. But she was unresponsive. “Help, help,” he pleaded to other protesters fleeing the chaos, but nobody came forward. He felt his wife’s body getting cold as he picked her up, the cousin said, and walked for an hour and a half to reach their car. When they reached the hospital, she was pronounced dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video verified by The Times captured the sound of live fire being directed at protesters in Sadeghiyeh. The protesters turn, flee and scream as gunshots are heard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 40 verified videos show gunmen and security forces cracking down on demonstrations. Across the footage, they are seen riding in pairs on motorbikes and using a variety of weapons, including firearms, batons and tear gas. In a video filmed in Haft Howz Square in Tehran, men and women flee amid the sound of gunfire. Some protesters clearly have leg wounds, and leave trails of blood along a sidewalk as they limp away, a video verified by The Times showed. On the street, some can also be seen carrying people unable to walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mohammad, 40, a shop owner, said he and his younger brother were among the demonstrators in Tehran Pars, a middle-class neighborhood in eastern Tehran, on Friday, Jan. 9, when they heard the rat-tat-tat of gunfire. “I saw two young men who were running away collapse; they were shot from the back,” Mohammad said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces fired on protesters from the rooftop of a police station in Tehran Pars for more than six minutes, one video shows. The video shows the muzzle blasts of several rifles and picks up the sound of hundreds of gunshots and what appears to be automatic fire. A group of protesters run away along an adjacent street. Minutes later, a person is dragged inside the courtyard of the police station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another video filmed farther along the same street — and in the direction the security forces were firing — shows protesters sheltering from incoming gunfire. “Put your phone down, they’ll shoot your hand off,” one person says. “There’s a sniper among them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of bullets striking nearby can be heard amid chants of “Death to Khamenei.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video that The Times confirmed was filmed at the nearby Tehran Pars Hospital showed several body bags lined up on the ground outside an emergency room entrance as people could be heard wailing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A husband and wife had a violent encounter with members of the Basij militia, a plainclothes security force, on motorcycles in Karim Khan in central Tehran. The wife, 50, who is a designer, said in an interview that the men shot indiscriminately into the air and at people, and screamed, “Get back inside.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The husband was shot in his lower back with a pellet bullet. The wife said a member of the Basij found her hiding behind an electric pole, stood near her and pointed a gun to her forehead, several millimeters away from her eye. He threatened to kill her, but had run out bullets, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A series of videos verified by The Times from Jan. 8 in Fardis, a suburb of Karaj, showed hundreds of people marching, then fleeing when a tear-gas canister is fired in their direction. Gunshots ring out. Another video, filmed near a police station in Fardis, shows a protester who appears to have been shot in the head. More than two dozen gunshots are heard as screaming protesters take cover. In the last video, the lifeless bodies of seven people sprawl on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mashhad, a conservative city in the northeast, huge crowds gathered on Jan. 8 chanting slogans against the government, a video verified by The Times showed. Later that night, a group of protesters were walking down a road about a mile away from where the crowds had been when security forces on motorcycles rode up to them. Some of the officers dismounted and beat demonstrators with batons, while others fanned out, pointing firearms down the street as gunshots rang out nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another video filmed at a protest in Mashhad and verified by The Times, a person is seen lying on the ground as others run to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Look, they shot a girl,” the person recording the video said. “They are using weapons of war.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the country, hospitals swamped by thousands of injured protesters were unprepared for the scale of the gunshot wounds they were seeing, according to interviews and text messages with eight doctors and one nurse in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun violence is rare in Iran, and private citizens are not allowed to own weapons. The doctors and the nurse sharing their experiences in Tehran, Mashhad, Isfahan and Zanjan described scenes of chaos: medical staff frantically trying to save lives, white uniforms drenched in blood. They said patients lay on benches and chairs, and even on bare floors, in the overcrowded emergency rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said hospitals were short of blood and searching for trauma and vascular surgeons. The internet shutdown prevented medical staff from checking patients’ names and medical history, they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nurse at Nikan Hospital in Tehran said in an interview that the hospital resembled a war zone. A doctor at Shohada Tajrish Hospital in north Tehran, a sprawling government medical facility, said that, on average, medical staff saw about 70 protesters with gunshot wounds per hour on the two days of peak violence, Jan. 9 and 10. Many patients were dead on arrival or shortly afterward, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an audio message shared with The Times, a physician in Mashhad called the situation at his hospital “terrifying.” In addition to a staggering number of injured protesters, he said, security forces showed up demanding access to patients to arrest them. He said a team of physicians had set up an ad hoc triage unit at a villa outside of the city, where they treated patients too afraid to go to hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An anesthesiologist at a hospital in the Sattar Khan neighborhood of Tehran said in a text message shared with The Times that in just one night, his hospital had seen 300 injured protesters. A text message from a doctor at a university hospital in Zanjan shared with The Times said most victims were shot in the upper torso, head and neck, and that the hospital had recorded about 200 killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times received photos and videos from inside hospitals that are too gruesome to show. Other very graphic images were posted online by an account with a record of publishing images later found to be authentic. They showed bloody, lifeless bodies inside hospitals said to be in Tehran. Some victims appeared to have been shot in the head. The Times was unable to independently authenticate the images from inside hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farabi Eye Hospital in Tehran, a national hub for ophthalmology, registered about 500 cases of eye injury from pellet bullets on Jan. 8 and several hundred eye injuries with live bullets on the following two nights, a surgeon said in a text message. He was in the operating room for three nights straight and said he wished for death when he had to empty both eye sockets of a 13-year-old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor in Isfahan said in a text message that they had seen “young people whose brains were smashed with live bullets, and a mom who was shot in the neck, her two small children were crying in the car, a child whose bladder, hip and rectum was crushed with a bullet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I witnessed will forever haunt me,” the doctor added. “I feel guilty that I’m alive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos, videos and text conversations shared with The Times by Dr. Kayvan Mirhadi, an Iranian American doctor in Rochester, N.Y., who has been in regular contact with medical teams and hospitals in Iran, showed dozens of apparent gunshot and pellet wounds to the torso, limbs, head and eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They are essentially executing people on the streets,” Dr. Mirhadi said. “Starting Thursday, the reports of injuries I was receiving changed significantly. It went from brute force, fractures and tear gas to skull fractures and gunshot wounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some images shared by Dr. Mirhadi were sent by people asking how to treat their own wounds or those of relatives. One person asked about a bullet wound in his brother’s leg. Another sent a photo of an eye, with blood pouring out of a gash just above it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times sent a representative sample of 17 images to experts from the Independent Forensic Expert Group coordinated by the International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims, who determined that the injuries appeared to be caused by buckshot or birdshot fired at close range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HRANA, the rights agency in Washington, documented a significant number of injuries from pellet gunfire during recent protests, including shots into the eyeball. It said 7,402 people had serious injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video obtained by the London-based Persian-language news channel Iran International and verified by The Times shows bodies in the courtyard of Alghadir Hospital, less than a mile from where protesters were fired upon and injured in Haft Howz Square. Some of the bodies are covered and tied in plastic bags; others are wrapped in blankets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A woman crouches over the body of a man wrapped in a blanket whose eyes remain closed. She weeps and speaks to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bodies shrouded in black plastic bags covered every space and surface. Stacked in refrigerators. Placed on the floor inside. Scattered, row after row, on the ground in the parking lot and courtyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran’s main morgue, Kahrizak Forensic Center, was overflowing in the immediate aftermath of the killing spree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of bodies overwhelmed the capacity of the morgue, a government official admitted on state television, blaming the killings on terrorist cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the handling and processing of bodies was also disorderly, according to videos and a person who visited the morgue. Families searching for loved ones were taken to a hall where a television screen flashed the faces of the dead, each with a number assigned to it. There were several photos of some victims because the severity of their injuries required multiple angles to identify them, according to the visitor to the morgue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes families would ask the morgue staff to pause, rewind and zoom in, the visitor said. Others would immediately recognize a loved one and collapse. People screamed, wailed and hit their faces and bodies in shock and grief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple images and videos verified by The Times showed hundreds of bodies laid out at the Kahrizak morgue within days of the protests erupting on Jan. 8. Outside the center, men unzipped black body bags as they searched for missing relatives. Others tearfully embraced as they discovered bodies. Inside a large hall where dozens more were laid out, women wailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One 16-minute video filmed outside the center showed close to 300 victims laid out on sidewalks and asphalt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a line. A line of people, so they can pick up their deceased,” the person filming said. “The young people. Their apple of their eyes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staff in white lab coats unzipped body bags and examined victims’ wounds. One staff member identified a wound at the back of one victim’s head, blood trailing from it, and jotted details in a notebook. Another documented apparent bullet wounds on the torso of a bloodied victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the camera moved through the crowd, people could be seen going from body to body searching for a loved one. Men embraced tearfully over the dead body of someone they identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one heartbreaking video, a father sobbed as he searched inside the center for his son, Sepehr Shokri, 19, a boxer. “Sepehr, my son, where are you?” he cried. “Damn Khamenei, this is his crime. Sepehr, Baba, where are you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times obtained photographs of over 300 bodies brought to Kahrizak. The photographs showed the faces of the dead, the top of their black body bags unzipped, with white identity cards on their chests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens were marked as “unknown man,” “unknown woman,” “unknown child.” Over 190 were marked only by numbers. The Times identified 29 legible names, among them Mohammad Erfan Faraji, 18, who an Iranian rights organization reported was shot during protests in Shahr Rey, a suburb of Tehran about 10 miles from the morgue where his body was photographed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times could not make a conclusive assessment of injuries based on the images. But a majority of the bodies showed severe head trauma, large gashes and collapsed eye sockets. Some were severely disfigured. Several still had tubes in their mouths and EKG pads on their chests, indicating the bodies had been transported from a hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nizam Peerwani, a forensic adviser for Physicians for Human Rights who analyzed the images for The Times, said the evidence suggested multiple victims had been “brutally bludgeoned or beaten up at the scene or in detention.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one woman recognized her husband on the screen and dropped to the floor, another woman approached her, said the person who was at the morgue. She told her, “Get up, get up my dear, you have work to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across Iran, funerals are taking place. Parents are burying children. Children are burying parents. Siblings, friends, neighbors, colleagues, classmates and teammates are attending burial processions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the faces and stories of the victims surface, recounted by relatives or friends and posted on social media, so does the story of the uprising. The protesters killed represent a broad swath of Iran, ethnically, economically and socially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many were very young. Teenagers and people in their early twenties took to the streets with dreams of a better life, of a prosperous future and of freedom, their families say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 21-year-old basketball star who played for a national team; a 17-year-old Kurdish soccer player with a national youth club; a 15-year-old swimming champion; a 19-year-old college student majoring in Italian; a 26-year-old English teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The death on Jan. 8 of Sina Ashkbousi, 17, was described by his aunt in an audio message posted on the Instagram page of lawyers in Iran who represent human rights cases. “Sina was killed with a direct bullet in his heart in Tehran Pars,” she said. “He was very smart, a dreamer. He was after freedom and was very kind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funerals have turned into protests, with thousands of attendees holding pictures of victims and chanting “Death to Khamenei,” videos verified by The Times show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage showed huge crowds at a funeral for three people killed in Malekshahi, a rural area in the province of Ilam, on Jan. 4. A week later, videos circulating on social media appeared to show huge crowds not far away, in Abdanan, another city in Ilam, for the funeral of Alireza Saidi, 16, who was said to have been killed in Tehran during protests that week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At these funerals and that of Ahmad Khosravani, the basketball star, the crowd departed from the traditional mourning rituals of crying and reciting the Quran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead they clapped, cheered and chanted in unison, saying, “This fallen flower is a gift to the nation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;___________MethodologyDespite a communications blackout, Iranians managed to use virtual private networks, or VPNs, and forbidden Starlink satellite internet systems to share witness accounts and videos, many of which The New York Times was able to collect and authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some videos were shared directly with Times journalists. Others with Iranian human rights groups, BBC Persian and the Iranian blog Vahid Online, all of whom circulated the videos on Telegram, X and Instagram.The Times collected over 300 videos and independently verified over 160 of them by matching details seen in the videos — like business names, street fronts, signs and trees — with archival images, satellite imagery and Google Street View. Iranian reporters with The Times watched and listened to the videos for accents or other details indicating their authenticity. Sometimes we referred to verification carried out by GeoConfirmed, a research collective that specializes in geolocating where videos are filmed.The Times independently confirmed all the videos reported on for this story. Two weeks on from the worst of the violence, footage is still emerging. Confirming the date those videos were filmed is not always possible. But by checking that the videos are new and not posted during previous crackdowns in Iran, and by mapping out when and where protests and crackdowns happened in January, we corroborated the date they were most likely taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Haley Willis. Videos produced by Jon Hazell. Additional video production by Natalie Reneau, Jeffrey Bernier and Josh Holder. Map by Samuel Granados.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/middleeast/iran-how-crackdown-was-done.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 01:34:48 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>