<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 10:04:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Ex-South Korean Leader Gets Prison Term in First Ruling Over Martial Law</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/asia/south-korea-yoon-prison-martial-law.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-skorea-yoon-lbvj/16int-skorea-yoon-lbvj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Korea’s impeached and ousted former president, Yoon Suk Yeol, was sentenced to ​five years in prison on Friday for fabricating an official document used to briefly impose martial law in 2024 as well as illegally using his bodyguards to ​prevent his arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sentence on Friday from a three-judge panel at the Seoul Central District Court was the first in ​eight separate court trials stemming from his ill-fated martial law declaration. The ruling on the most consequential charge — insurrection — is scheduled to be delivered by a different panel of judges on Feb. 19. Prosecutors ​in that case have sought the death penalty for Mr. Yoon​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In their ruling on Friday, the judges convicted Mr. Yoon of obstructing justice when he ordered his presidential secret service agents to block law enforcement officials from serving a court-issued warrant to detain him on insurrection charges last January. The officials eventually detained him ​several days later on their second attempt to serve the warrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He turned ​his Presidential Security Service​, trained to be loyal to the country, into a de facto private army for his personal safety and interests,” the presiding judge, Baek Dae-hyun, said in the ruling on Friday, which was nationally televised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon was also convicted of abusing his power when he failed to invite some of his cabinet members to a cabinet meeting on the night of Dec. 3, 2024, denying them their right to review his plan for martial law before​ he declared it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Dissident’s Next Act: Kwon Pyong recounted for the first time the series of gambles that got him out of China by jet ski, and almost a year later, out of South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standoff With Doctors: Doctors at medical facilities across South Korea walked off the job in a one-day strike on June 18, expanding a months-old protest against the government’s health care policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Impeachment Threat: President Yoon Suk Yeol has been accused of intervening in an inquiry into the accidental death of a South Korean marine during a peacetime search and rescue operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliament Election: South Koreans delivered a stinging defeat to Yoon and his party, giving the opposition one of its biggest electoral victories in recent decades and pushing Yoon to the verge of being a lame duck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon’s original martial law decree was not endorsed with signatures from his cabinet members. On Friday, he was convicted of fabricating a document to make it look as if ​his martial law plan had been reviewed and endorsed by cabinet members. He was also found guilty of ordering the removal of data from government-issued secure phones of his collaborators in martial law, ​such as military generals, in order to obstruct investigators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M​r. Yoon’s acts amounted to an abuse of his presidential power and a “grave crime,” Judge Baek said​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M​r. Yoon, who appeared at the courtroom on Friday, exited after the ruling without comment. He and his lawyers have a week to appeal the ruling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Mr. Yoon was unpopular throughout his two and a half years in office​. He governed a deeply polarized country, constantly clashing with the majority opposition over ​his policies and scandals involving his wife. The tensions culminated when he declared martial law on Dec. 3, 2024. He banned all political activities and sent troops to take over the opposition-controlled National Assembly, which he called a “monster” and “den of criminals” that he said “paralyzed” his administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his martial law decree lasted only six hours. The legislature voted it down while citizens held back troops to prevent them from raiding its main voting hall. ​When the Assembly impeached him, suspending him from office, Mr. Yoon holed up in his hillside presidential residence in central Seoul​, vowing to “fight to the end​.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​He repeatedly ignored summons from investigators to face questioning for insurrection charges.​ When they sought to detain him last January, he refused to surrender. His ​bodyguards built barricades of buses and formed human chains to repel investigators and police officers, raising fears of a clash.​ Mr. Yoon insisted that the officials had no right to detain him because he said his call for martial law had been legal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when the investigators visited the compound again several days later in overwhelming numbers could they​ serve the warrant and detain ​him. Mr. Yoon was the first sitting president of South Korea to be arrested in a criminal investigation. He was later formally removed from office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon’s martial law, although short-lived, threatened decades of hard-won democracy in South Korea and exposed deep fractures in its politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, South Korea elected a new president, Lee Jae Myung, one of the political leaders whom prosecutors said Mr. Yoon had planned to arrest under his martial law. Small groups of die-hard supporters of the ousted leader still hold rallies in Seoul, calling his impeachment invalid and chanting, in English, “Yoon again!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his jail cell and through his lawyers, Mr. Yoon continues to argue that he declared martial law to “wake” citizens up to the danger posed by “anti-state forces” among the political left. He has called special prosecutors who indicted him “a pack of wolves” controlled by “dark forces.” His old People Power Party remains mired in internal fighting between those who call for disowning him and those who remain sympathetic toward him. The party planned to change its name to make a fresh start.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/asia/south-korea-yoon-prison-martial-law.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 11:35:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>C.I.A. Director Meets With Venezuela’s Interim President in Caracas</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/cia-director-ratcliffe-venezuela.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/multimedia/15dc-intel-pflc/15dc-intel-pflc-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The C.I.A. director, John Ratcliffe, met with Delcy Rodríguez, the interim president of Venezuela, in Caracas on Thursday, reinforcing the Trump administration’s message that it sees the interim government as the best path to stability in the country in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ratcliffe is the most senior American official, and first cabinet member, to visit Venezuela since the U.S. military seized President Nicolás Maduro in a raid in the capital nearly two weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting came a day after President Trump spoke to Ms. Rodríguez on the phone and on the same day he met with María Corina Machado, the leader of Venezuela’s opposition and a Nobel laureate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high-profile visit by Mr. Ratcliffe, and the message of cooperation, could be seen as something of a snub to the opposition, whose supporters have been frustrated that the Trump administration has not tried to put Ms. Machado’s ally Edmundo González into power since Mr. Maduro was seized. Mr. González won the 2024 election, international election experts say, after Ms. Machado was barred from running, but Mr. Maduro refused to give up power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A U.S. official said that Mr. Ratcliffe met with Ms. Rodríguez at Mr. Trump’s direction “to deliver the message that the United States looks forward to an improved working relationship.” The official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity to describe the sensitive meeting, added that the two discussed intelligence cooperation, economic stability and the need to ensure that the country was no longer a “safe haven for America’s adversaries, especially narco-traffickers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Trump administration officials, Mr. Ratcliffe’s visit is meant to be an endorsement of the kind of stability that Ms. Rodríguez offers and a sign of trust-building and collaboration between the two governments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As early as last summer, senior U.S. officials were discussing how to maintain stability in Venezuela. At the time, the Trump administration was beginning to put together a counterdrug campaign that would involve attacking boats at sea that it said were smuggling drugs and that would eventually lead to Mr. Maduro’s capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As officials planned the campaign of boat strikes, removing Mr. Maduro, either through negotiations or by force, was the president’s goal, officials said. But there was intense talk about how to prevent chaos from spreading around the country after Mr. Maduro was forced out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senior officials raised the prospect that breaking up the Venezuelan government after removing Mr. Maduro — even to make way for an opposition leader — would be akin to the mistakes the United States made in Iraq when it dismantled the Iraqi army and created an insurgency, officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amid the discussions last summer, the C.I.A. delivered an early assessment that Ms. Rodríguez, then Venezuela’s vice president, was a pragmatic politician, rather than an ideologue, who would be willing to negotiate and potentially even work with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One intelligence report circulated to senior policymakers mentioned that she wore a $15,000 dress to her inauguration, prompting an official to quip that “she is a socialist but the most capitalistic one I’ve seen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Rodríguez had been involved in negotiations with Richard Grenell, Mr. Trump’s special envoy, as well as other officials, as the administration looked for a deal to get Mr. Maduro to voluntarily give up power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No agreement was reached, but people briefed on the discussions said that Ms. Rodríguez proved herself pragmatic, someone who was looking for potential points of agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C.I.A. analysts assessed that having Ms. Rodríguez continue as interim leader was the best way to prevent Venezuela from “descending into some chaotic situation,” a senior official said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lessons learned from Iraq hung heavily over the debates at the top ranks of the Trump administration. Administration officials said that the Bush administration’s decision to push out the entire Iraqi government and dismantle the army ushered in a long era of instability and insurgency that cost Iraqi and American lives and mired the United States in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump and key members of his administration have been critics of the U.S. war in Iraq. But their criticism has focused less on the goal of removing the dictator Saddam Hussein from power and more on the decision to keep troops in the country to provide security for elections and install a democratic government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the operation to remove Mr. Maduro, Mr. Trump has said little about restoring democracy in Venezuela, spending more energy on discussing expanding the role of U.S. companies in the country’s oil industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secretary of State Marco Rubio has also said he wants to see a “transition to democracy” in Venezuela, noting that he worked on the issue for years as a senator. He has long praised Ms. Machado but has noted that the reality is that the opposition is not present in Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The senior official predicted that when Venezuela held elections, Ms. Machado would have a chance to run. But in the short term, the official said, Ms. Rodríguez is seen as someone who can keep control of the security forces, maintain infrastructure and “cooperate and coordinate with the U.S. government.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/cia-director-ratcliffe-venezuela.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:20:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bobi Wine, Ugandan Opposition Leader, Was Abducted, His Party Says</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-abduction.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-uganda-wine-1-jmwb/17int-uganda-wine-1-jmwb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Supporters of the opposition leader Bobi Wine in Kampala, Uganda, on Monday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/africa/uganda-bobi-wine-abduction.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:39:18 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Has Machado’s Nobel Prize, but Neither Got What They Really Wanted</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-machado-nobel-prize.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16dc-trump-nobel-bzch/16dc-trump-nobel-bzch-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since President Trump first took office in 2017, he has been obsessed with the Nobel Peace Prize, and has made no effort to hide his deep sense of injustice that President Barack Obama won it in 2009 for, in the eyes of the Nobel committee, his “extraordinary efforts to strengthen international diplomacy and cooperation between peoples.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has a different view, which he offered in an interview with The New York Times last week: Mr. Obama “was there for a few weeks, and he got it. He didn’t even know why he got it.” Mr. Trump then recited the now-familiar list of “eight wars” he claims to have stopped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this culminated on Thursday afternoon in a bizarre scene in a White House that has had its share of jaw-dropping events. The president took possession of the 2025 Nobel Peace Prize, which its true recipient, María Corina Machado, had turned over, framed in gold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a window into the president’s psyche, including his deep need for affirmation of his role as a “peacemaker,” even after a year of ordering military strikes on several continents. It was also revealing of Ms. Machado’s political calculations. Her party overwhelmingly won the 2024 presidential election in Venezuela but has been barred by Mr. Trump from any role in governing the nation after the capture of Nicolás Maduro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said he was “honored” to finally receive the prize, and he grinned broadly as he posed with Ms. Machado in the Oval Office, holding the oversized frame. Shortly after, Ms. Machado left. The medal stayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Maria presented me with her Nobel Peace Prize for the work I have done,” Mr. Trump later effused on social media. “Such a wonderful gesture of mutual respect. Thank you Maria!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, it was a pretty hollow event for both of them. Mr. Trump can hang the medal on the wall, but to the rest of the world — and in the records of the Nobel committee — he cannot legitimately call himself a Nobel laureate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was made clear a few hours later by Kristian Berg Harpviken, the director of the Norwegian Nobel Institute, who archly noted that “receiving the symbols of the Peace Prize does not make anyone a Peace Prize laureate.” This has been tried before, he noted, including once in 1943 when Knut Hamsun, who won the Nobel literature prize in 1920, sent it to the Nazi propaganda minister, Joseph Goebbels. (Mr. Hamsun, who often espoused admiration for Hitler, mailed the medallion to Goebbels. But it was lost after Goebbels committed suicide in 1945.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gifting plan also did not seem to work for Ms. Machado, at least immediately. As she and Mr. Trump were meeting, the C.I.A. director, John Ratcliffe, was in Caracas meeting with Delcy Rodríguez, the interim president of Venezuela. She had been Mr. Maduro’s vice president, and was part of the forces that barred Ms. Machado from running in the election — one of many steps the Maduro government took to fix the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, Mr. Trump has chosen to operate Venezuela through the very people Ms. Machado fought. The prize — the one Mr. Trump claimed as his own — was essentially given to mark the bravery of those who stood up to the forces Mr. Trump has now embraced, betting that Ms. Rodríguez will do his bidding and grant U.S. companies access to the world’s largest oil reserve. And Mr. Trump believes the old regime — not Ms. Machado — is most likely to enable the United States to run Venezuela’s affairs by remote control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, in short, realpolitik in its rawest form, something Henry A. Kissinger would have admired. If that means embracing the political power structure set up by Hugo Chávez and Mr. Maduro — and rejected by a strong majority of Venezuelans — that is the price that Mr. Trump appears willing to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seemed like Ms. Machado had been cornered into making her gift. At first, she had “dedicated” the Nobel to Mr. Trump. But in an interview last week, Sean Hannity, the Fox News commentator and one of Mr. Trump’s supporters and informal advisers, asked the opposition leader, “Did you at any point offer to give him the Nobel Peace Prize?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Machado said that “it hasn’t happened yet, but I certainly would love to be able to personally tell him” that he, and the Venezuelan people, shared in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That changed, and now Ms. Machado appears to be playing the long game. She is betting that sooner or later, the survivors of the Maduro regime will be ousted, and so giving Mr. Trump what he wants — that golden Nobel medallion — is a worthwhile investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have no doubt that President Trump, his administration and the people of the United States support democracy, justice, freedom and the mandate of the people of Venezuela,” she said on Friday in a speech to the Heritage Foundation, ticking off four values that Mr. Trump has spoken about very little as he has described his plans to bring American enterprises, especially oil companies, back to the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She insisted that “once the regime is out and the transition is accomplished, the United States will not only be a safer nation, but one that will have more prosperity and strength in our hemisphere.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bigger mystery is how Mr. Trump regards the handover of the prize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He clearly was interested in possessing it, perhaps because possession, as he has said of Greenland, is “psychologically important.” Of course, he already has one Nobel Peace Prize medallion just steps from the Oval Office: the 1906 award given to Theodore Roosevelt, which is kept in the Roosevelt Room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roosevelt won the prize for bringing an end to the Russo-Japanese War, and even some of Mr. Trump’s critics have said that, if Mr. Trump could do the same for the war between Russia and Ukraine, he would be the natural candidate for the next award. But that has been frustratingly elusive, as Mr. Trump himself often admits, even while ticking off other conflicts — India vs. Pakistan, Thailand vs. Cambodia, Israel vs. Hamas and Egypt vs. Ethiopia, among others — that he claims credit for ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said on Friday that Mr. Trump intended to keep the prize, but noted that “its final home in the White House is still yet to be decided.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she suggested that the issue was not over for Mr. Trump, that the wrong he believes was committed against him by the Nobel committee has not been resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It does not solve the problem,” she said, “and he’s still worthy of actually being the recipient of the reward.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/us/politics/trump-machado-nobel-prize.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 14:58:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Gabriel Barkay, 81, Dies; His Discoveries Revised Biblical History</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16Barkay--01-vwgz/16Barkay--01-vwgz-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Barkay, a leading figure in biblical archaeology whose many discoveries in and around Jerusalem, including a pair of silver amulets from the seventh century B.C. that contained a priestly inscription, changed how historians understood early Jewish life, died on Sunday in Jerusalem. He was 81.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His daughter, Naama Barkay, said his death, in a care facility, was from complications of an autoimmune disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay, whose name was sometimes written Barkai, spent more than 50 years leading some of the most important digs into the ancient history of central Israel, a record that earned him a reputation as the “dean” of biblical archaeologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zachi Dvira, an archaeologist and former student of his, wrote in a biographical essay for Dr. Barkay’s 80th birthday that he “believes that archaeology serves as a vital link between the past and the present, and he embodies this principle through his actions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was especially interested in how the region’s earliest residents treated the dead. During the late 1970s, he examined a network of burial caves carved into the hills southwest of Jerusalem, where he found a pair of amulets containing scrolls from the mid-600s B.C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took years to figure out how to unravel the scrolls without ruining their script, but when they were finally opened and the Paleo-Hebrew text was translated, in 1986, Dr. Barkay found that they contained a priestly benediction from the Old Testament book of Numbers. It was the oldest instance of writing from the Bible — and evidence, he argued, that the writing of the Old Testament began several centuries earlier than many historians had thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came to the history of Jerusalem itself, Dr. Barkay considered himself a “maximalist” in the debate over the ancient city’s size and importance. He used the placement of burial sites, which had to be set a specific distance outside the city walls, to show that it was much larger than the so-called minimalists had argued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay was very much a public-facing archaeologist, offering his expert opinion in TV series like “The Naked Archaeologist” and documentaries like “The Real Da Vinci Code.” He gave frequent public lectures and offered training for tour guides around the Old City of Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was also something of an activist: In 2000, after the Israeli government refused to stop a Muslim organization, the Waqf, from digging out space for a subterranean mosque on the holy site in Jerusalem known to Jews as the Temple Mount, he and several other archaeologists formed the Committee for the Prevention of the Destruction of Antiquities on the Temple Mount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How The Times decides who gets an obituary. There is no formula, scoring system or checklist in determining the news value of a life. We investigate, research and ask around before settling on our subjects. If you know of someone who might be a candidate for a Times obituary, please suggest it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did not oppose the mosque, they said, but rather the lack of archaeologists’ involvement in a project involving the removal of thousands of tons of earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2005, he and others founded the Temple Mount Sifting Project, a crowdsourced program to examine the estimated 400 truckloads of dirt taken from the site. Since then, volunteers have identified about a half-million artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was sometimes criticized as a tool of right-wing Israeli governments eager to establish historical claim to the Temple Mount, which is a holy site for Jews, Muslims and Christians but is primarily controlled by the Waqf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Dr. Barkay insisted that his interest was purely intellectual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sneezing in Jerusalem is an intensive political activity,” he told The Times of Israel in 2019. “You could turn your head to the right, or the left.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel Breslauer was born in Budapest on June 20, 1944, soon after Nazi Germany occupied the city. He and his mother, Rosa (Legaty) Breslauer, were forced into the newly created ghetto and barely escaped a death march to Vienna, saved only by the liberation of Budapest by Soviet troops in January 1945.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I owe my life to the Russian army, to nobody else than Joseph Stalin,” he said in a 2023 interview. “Many others owe him their death; I owe him my life.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His father, Eliezer Breslauer, had already been sent to a camp in Ukraine, though he survived and later rejoined the family. Mr. Breslauer later worked for the Jewish Agency, which facilitated emigration to Israel. Gabriel and his parents emigrated themselves in 1950, settling in Jerusalem, and they changed their surname to Barkay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a child, he was taken with the empty, arid stretches of land outside the city that, he knew, bore the imprint of millenniums of human habitation. By 10, he was conducting his own digs, and a few years later, he joined the Israel Exploration Society, an amateur archaeological club.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He received his bachelor’s degree in archaeology and geography from Hebrew University in 1967 and his doctorate in archaeology from Tel Aviv University in 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By then, he was already a veteran archaeologist, with a series of digs in Israel, Egypt and Iran to his name. He was a popular lecturer as well, first at Tel Aviv University and later at Bar-Ilan University and Jerusalem University College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay’s first marriage ended in divorce. Along with his daughter, from his first marriage, he is survived by a son from that marriage, Elad; his partner, Esther Yerushalem; and six grandchildren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Barkay insisted that archaeology was not just about the past, but was also a tool for examining the way history reaches up into the present through the materials people left behind. And he remained in thrall with Jerusalem, one of the oldest continuously inhabited cities in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is my 56th year in Jerusalem,” he said in a 2006 lecture at Bar-Ilan. “I know the city. But every day, I discover there is more and more to be known about it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Berman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/gabriel-barkay-dead.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:46:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Thousands Evicted From the 19th-Century ‘Venice of Nigeria’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/africa/nigeria-makoko-fishing-village-destroyed.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-nigeria-makoko-promo/16int-nigeria-makoko-promo-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents of a 19th-century fishing community nicknamed the “Venice of Nigeria” have been left homeless after a government eviction that sent excavators to carry out demolitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders in the community of Makoko in Nigeria and two other nearby settlements in Lagos Lagoon say at least 10,000 people have lost their homes during a demolition process that began in late December and was ongoing Friday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Makoko community leaders and humanitarian groups said at least four people had died during the demolitions. Among them were two infants and a 70-year-old woman who they said suffered respiratory issues after tear gas was fired to scatter families trying to protect their homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokesman for the Lagos State government declined to comment on the reports of deaths and pointed to several news stories citing the government’s position that the demolition was necessary for safety — to move residents away from a nearby power line that could someday fall — and for urban planning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;State officials and private entities have engaged in numerous efforts in recent years to clear areas in the name of development in Lagos, a sprawling megacity of about 20 million people. Residents say that informal communities in the city are sometimes given little or no warning before being ordered to evacuate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Families settled in the 1800s in Makoko; they live in small shacks on stilts in the lagoon, where they make a living catching and smoking fish that supplies many markets in the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largely impoverished area, which residents access by canoe, is on full display for commuters traveling across a busy bridge. Last year, state government officials told Makoko residents that homes could not exist within 30 meters of the power line, which stretches across the lagoon. Later, officials extended the distance to 100 meters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents met with government officials and agreed to comply. Makoko leaders planted a Nigerian flag in the water at what they said was the 100-meter mark. But as amphibious excavators began work, the machines ripped down homes well past the flag, they said. Nonprofit groups working with residents used aerial photos to estimate that the excavators had torn down homes as far as 500 meters from the power line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning in Makoko, loud crunching noises from a yellow excavator echoed off the water as homes and fishing shacks were reduced to piles of splintered boards, plastic bowls, crab shells and clothing. Some panicked residents preemptively began destroying their own homes, collecting planks and sheets of tin in narrow wooden canoes, hoping to rebuild elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isaac Atamado, 15, was threading his canoe through the inky water to get to a pile of broken planks. “This was my house,” he said, looking at what was left of the two-story shack on the lagoon, where he said 12 members of his family had lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He ran when he saw the excavator heading for his home Tuesday, and was left barefoot, with only the shirt and pants he was wearing after it was demolished. He has been sleeping on the wet, dirty floor of his narrow canoe with his brother. He said he was unsure where his family will live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francis Samson Vituwa, a Makoko community leader, said thousands of residents were in similar situations. Mr. Vituwa can trace his roots to his grandfather who settled in Makoko. “It’s a good life here,” he said. Living in Makoko has allowed him to support his wife and send his five children to school, he said. “There’s no good coming from this.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several residents staged protests this week at the State House of Assembly in Lagos, where officials pledged on two separate days to pause the demolitions, said Megan Chapman, co-director of Justice &amp; Empowerment Initiatives, one of the community groups supporting residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But excavators have kept at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is still a community to save,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ismail Auwal contributed reporting from Kano, Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/africa/nigeria-makoko-fishing-village-destroyed.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:49:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syria’s President Affirms Kurds’ Rights, in Overture to the Minority</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-rights-decree-clashes.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-Syria-Kurds-bwhq/16int-Syria-Kurds-bwhq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria issued a decree on Friday affirming the rights of Kurdish Syrians, according to state media, in what was widely considered an overture to the minority group after days of deadly clashes between government and Kurdish forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presidential decree recognized Kurdish as a national language, alongside Arabic, and adopted Nowruz, the Persian new year that is widely celebrated by Kurds, as an official holiday in Syria. Mr. al-Sharaa also called for the government to grant Syrian citizenship to Kurdish residents who were stripped of it after a 1962 census designed to curb Kurdish political influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The announcement on Friday came after days of intense fighting between Mr. al-Sharaa’s government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., that many feared could escalate into a broader conflict between the two sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Beware of believing the narrative that we want harm to our Kurdish people,” Mr. al-Sharaa said in a video announcing the decree posted on the Syrian Arab News Agency, the state media outlet. “Your well-being is our well-being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, Mr. al-Sharaa’s government and the S.D.F. have been engaged in negotiations to integrate the group into the new national military. But progress on those talks has stalled in recent months, and last week, tensions between the two sides erupted into clashes in the northern city of Aleppo. At least 24 civilians were killed in five days of fighting while thousands were forced to flee their neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was some of the most intense fighting since the end of the civil war in December 2024, when Mr. al-Sharaa’s coalition of rebel groups ousted the dictatorship of Bashar al-Assad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday evening, the prospect of another major clash hung over northern Syria after government troops amassed outside areas in eastern Aleppo held by S.D.F. fighters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the time Mr. al-Sharaa announced the decree affirming Kurdish Syrians’ rights, the national military said it had begun striking those S.D.F. positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after, the leader of the S.D.F., Mazloum Abdi, said in a post on X that his forces would withdraw from the contested area and redeploy to regions east of the Euphrates River. It remained unclear whether doing so would head off further clashes with the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fighting over the past week has underscored the challenge Mr. al-Sharaa faces as he vows to unite a country that is deeply fractured after nearly 14 years of civil war. Since his largely Sunni Muslim government came to power, two regions of Syria home to mostly minority groups — the Kurdish-controlled northeast and the Druse in the southern province of Sweida — have refused to submit to the central government’s authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders of both are wary of Mr. al-Sharaa, the former commander of a rebel group once allied to Al Qaeda, and his Islamist-led government. Some also doubt the government’s ability to protect minority rights after bouts of sectarian-driven violence over the past year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kurds, who make up about a tenth of Syria’s population, were denied many basic rights, including identity papers and business licenses, under more than five decades of the Assad family’s rule in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decree Mr. al-Sharaa signed on Friday “breaks decisively” with decades of “Arab nationalist exclusion that denied Kurds” in Syria, according to Ibrahim al-Assil, a senior research fellow at the Middle East Initiative at Harvard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, many remained skeptical of the announcement and the motivations behind it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“⁠Mistrust runs deep, and many Kurds are cautiously welcoming this while remaining skeptical,” Mr. al-Assil said. “Ultimately, the decree will be judged by behavior, not words.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reham Mourshed contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-rights-decree-clashes.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 00:06:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Protests Quelled Since Deadly Crackdown, Residents Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/iran-protests-deadly-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-iran-protests-lbpq/16int-iran-protests-lbpq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heavy police presence and deadly crackdowns on protesters appeared to have largely suppressed demonstrations in many cities and towns across Iran, according to several witnesses and a human rights group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks, Iran has been convulsed by protests sparked by a collapsing economy and a currency in free fall, with the demonstrations snowballing into a broader antigovernment movement. The authorities have sought to quell the protests with brutal force and have plunged the country into a communications blackout that has made it difficult to know what’s happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four residents reached by The New York Times in the capital, Tehran, said that the streets had mostly been quiet of protests this week as the severity of the crackdown and the high number of casualties became clear. Security forces were deployed in large numbers to nearly every neighborhood, said the residents, who lived in different parts of the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four spoke on the condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal. They said that it felt as if the capital was under martial law, with the typically bustling and traffic-clogged streets largely empty. Shops and restaurants in some areas were closed after 6 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is massive disappointment and disillusionment,” said another resident, who worked in central Tehran and also spoke on the condition of anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been no large-scale protests documented in Iran since Sunday, according to Arina Moradi and Mina Khani, members of the Norway-based Hengaw Organization for Human Rights, which has been monitoring the demonstrations since they began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Moradi said in an interview that a heavy military and security presence remained across many cities and towns, with thousands of people having been detained. She said numerous universities had closed following protests last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Israeli defense assessment found that the scale of protests had noticeably declined since Sunday, following the Iranian forces’ escalating use of live ammunition and the internet blackout, according to two Israeli officials who spoke to the Times on the condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the numbers continued to drop, they said, several Israeli intelligence officials monitoring Iran had concluded that the current wave of protests had effectively been subdued by the regime. The two officials noted, however, that the Israeli assessment had been complicated by the disruption of internet and telephone services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions across Iran and the region have been high after Mr. Trump recently declared he was prepared to intervene to protect protesters, including potential military strikes against the country, U.S. officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel and several Arab nations have urged President Trump not to strike Iran, a senior U.S. official said. Many Gulf States worry that an attack could destabilize the region and jeopardize their reputations as safe hubs for business and tourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin said on Friday that President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia offered to mediate so as to ensure regional stability after speaking with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and President Masoud Pezeshkian of Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The situation in the region is extremely tense,” a Kremlin spokesman, Dmitri S. Peskov, told reporters on Friday, adding that Mr. Putin was trying to facilitate a de-escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Iranian authorities have stepped back from threats to execute protesters, following international condemnation and the looming possibility of U.S. military action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But regional analysts note that Tehran is drawing a line between ordinary demonstrators and those it labels “rioters” or “terrorists” purportedly backed by foreign powers. Experts say this careful framing is intended to intimidate the population and discourage further protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has been instilling fear into protesters by sending text messages warning families not to let their children go out into the streets. Other messages have urged people to report suspicious activities or encouraged them to attend pro-government rallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a screenshot shared by a resident with The New York Times, a text message asserting to be from the intelligence branch of Iran’s powerful Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps said it had received more than 400,000 calls to a hotline for reporting “terrorist networks,” and that they had been “identified and dismantled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s violent crackdown has had an especially chilling effect on the protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witnesses said security forces had fired on unarmed demonstrators at close range. More than 2,600 people have been killed since protests began, according to the Washington-based Human Rights Activists News Agency. The Norway-based Iran Human Rights group said that more than 3,400 people had been killed and thousands of others injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Mr. Trump said the United States was “locked and loaded” to protect Iranian protesters, whom he later urged to take over government institutions, saying U.S. support was imminent. Since then, Mr. Trump has announced that diplomatic talks with Iran were on, then off, and most recently said Iran had responded to his demands by halting the killing and execution of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said on Thursday that President Trump and his team were “closely monitoring the situation” and that “all options remain on the table.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ronen Bergman and Paul Sonne contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/iran-protests-deadly-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:25:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>$2 Rental Batteries Are Helping to Power South Africa</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/batteries-south-africa-electricity.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17int-safrica-solar-batteries-promo/17int-safrica-solar-batteries-1-jkwp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost as soon as Anselmo Munghabe plopped the 23-pound battery onto a table in his tin shack barbershop, people began to flock in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He plugged two power strips into the battery. Soon it sprouted a bouquet of cellphones and wires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customers had arrived not to cut their hair, but to charge their phones, paying Mr. Munghabe 5 rand (about 30 cents) for each plug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Munghabe’s community north of Johannesburg has been without electricity since last April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although nine in 10 South Africans are connected to the national electricity grid, power cuts in the country are frequent. Poor, dense urban areas like Mr. Munghabe’s are hit particularly hard because the grid is overloaded, causing transformers to break and leaving residents in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These batteries allow business owners like Mr. Munghabe to keep their operations open, and provide them with an extra source of income by charging neighbors to use the batteries. They have become a fixture in Tembisa, a sprawling township where residents occupy a mix of tin shacks and concrete homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The batteries are part of a business venture launched last year by the oil company, BP. The program, known as BPowerd, offers daily rental batteries, ranging from 300 to 1,000 watts and able to power lights, televisions, laptops and some appliances for several hours before they must be returned and recharged for the next day’s use. Customers like Mr. Munghabe pick up the batteries from a nearby gas station equipped with solar panels to charge the batteries. It comes as BP focuses its business squarely on oil and gas, abandoning previous efforts to diversify to renewables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BOtswana&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretoria&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOUTH&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFRICA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;400 MILES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tembisa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johannesburg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SOUTH AFRICA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10 miles&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residents use the batteries to operate makeshift music studios, convenience stores, taverns and church services. One woman relies on a battery to run her nebulizer. A grandmother said she uses them to power her television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program is part of a growing effort to bring energy solutions to the more than half a billion Africans who don’t have access to electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 200 million people in sub-Saharan Africa live in households that rely on some form of solar power, according to the global association for the off-grid solar energy industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BP program, which plans to expand to Nigeria, is similar to one launched about a decade ago by another company, MOPO, which has about 125,000 batteries in circulation in seven African nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MOPO sets up its battery-charging stations at modest structures in communities, allowing it to reach rural areas that may not have gas stations or other major infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daily rental solar batteries have another limitation. The power they offer is limited, meaning they may not work for many large appliances and electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blackout in Mr. Munghabe’s section of Tembisa forced him to close his barbershop for a month because he did not have power to operate his hair clippers. Then a customer told him about the rentals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He rents one for 40 rand ($2.35) per day; a smaller 300-watt battery goes for half the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tembisa, residents lug the batteries — by hand, by wheelbarrow, sometimes by trash can — each day between the gas station hubs and their homes or businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Munghabe, 37, said his daily battery rental rate was covered, and then some, by the money he makes allowing people to charge their phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Experts in renewable energy say this system could play a critical role on the continent as demand for electricity grows. Renting a small battery is far cheaper than buying solar panels and batteries outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think this is a game changer,” said Ifeoma Malo, the founder of Clean Technology Hub, a Nigeria-based firm that does research and incubation for green technologies. “This is creating inclusiveness in access.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/africa/batteries-south-africa-electricity.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 20:01:15 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A Refuge for Afghan Music Is at Risk of Falling Silent</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/09/multimedia/00int-afghan-music-promo/00int-afghan-music-1-cwth-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pakistani city of Peshawar once offered refuge to generations of Afghans, including musicians who preserved their country’s rich tradition of songs and ballads beyond the Taliban’s reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the rhythms that resonate in wedding halls, concert stages and apartment blocks are falling silent, as the Pakistani government pursues a wave of expulsions that has already forced out a million Afghans since last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The musicians are part of a community of Afghan artists that has flourished over decades, and that also includes carpet weavers and dancers. Pakistan provided a haven for millions of Afghans fleeing war and political instability, first from Soviet invaders in the 1980s and later from the Taliban, who first seized power in the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban have banned music, persecuted artists and burned or smashed instruments, both in the 1990s and since reclaiming power in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, the Pakistani authorities have publicly accused the Taliban government of supporting insurgents targeting Pakistan, and in retaliation have declared millions of Afghans illegal — including those who fled after the Taliban takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent morning, the celebratory notes of an Afghan wedding song wafted through Muhammad Hassan Zamri’s music shop after he pushed a worn cassette into a tape deck. A longtime Afghan client ran his fingers through his white beard and sighed, leaving his green tea untouched as he bathed in nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I cannot bring them to Afghanistan because the Taliban will torch them,” Mr. Zamri said about his 2,000 cassette tapes, half of which bowed the crumbling wooden shelves of his shop. Mr. Zamri, who is 52 and fled Afghanistan in the 1980s, said he had already hidden the other half of his collection — a private archive of recordings dating back to the 1950s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not know what might happen to them if he were sent back to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exiled Afghan artists have also kept Afghan music alive in other neighboring countries, in Europe and in the United States. But nowhere have musicians flourished across as many generations as in Pakistan, and in Peshawar in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first wave of emigration, in the 1980s, brought artists like Qamar Gula, one of Afghanistan’s most famous female singers. Exiled Afghan musicians, mostly from the Pashto community, also recorded songs of resistance against the 1979 Soviet invasion on cassette tapes that were smuggled back across the border to bolster the mujahedeen fighting the Red Army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Afghanistan plunged into civil war in the 1990s, more artists arrived in Pakistan, performing to the rhythm of tabla drums and rubab, an instrument like a lute. Among them was Homayoun Sakhi, a rubab master who fled to Peshawar as a teenager and later performed in concert halls across the United States, Europe and Asia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Pakistani artists and fellow Afghan musicians have accommodated the newcomers. Tiny apartments became makeshift talent agencies visited by Pakistanis seeking to hire Afghan bands for weddings. Recording studios provided professional equipment to cultural icons like Sadiq Fitrat Nashenas, a star from a golden era for Afghan music before the Soviets came.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the early 2000s, Peshawar was home to more than 500 Afghan musicians, according to local news reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Peshawar has contributed to making many Afghan musicians superstars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hayat Roghani, the founder of Mafkoora, a cultural center in Peshawar where Afghan artists perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second Taliban takeover, in 2021, pushed a new generation of Afghan artists to Peshawar. Now, their songs are promoted on TikTok and YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Baryali Wali, a Pashto singer, hid his instruments in Kabul, Afghanistan’s capital, and fled across the border a month after the Taliban seized power in 2021. He has not been back since and missed his daughter’s wedding last summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Wali said he feared that the collective soul of Afghan music would vanish if artists were expelled to Afghanistan. “There are Afghan musicians in exile across the world, but it’s important to have a group component like we have here,” he said in a recording studio in Peshawar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expulsions and forced returns have increased in Peshawar and its surrounding province in recent weeks, according to data collected by the International Organization for Migration. “We’re all keeping our heads low now,” Mr. Wali said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent evening at Mafkoora, the cultural center, the singer Saidullah Wafa performed a tune of longing. “This is my beloved country, this is my life, this is my Afghanistan,” he sang to the notes of two acolytes playing the drums and rubab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The band played one last song — a jab at the Taliban — before packing up their instruments. “With the Taliban over there or the police here, we feel the same fear,” Mr. Wafa said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one of the musicians, Ikram Shinwari, tried to flee Afghanistan in 2021 with his harmonium, the Taliban ordered him to destroy it with his own hands, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahmad Sarmast, the exiled founder of the Afghanistan National Institute of Music, said that since reclaiming power, the Taliban had gradually imposed repressive cultural policies similar to those of their first era of rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now Afghanistan might be the only silent nation in the world,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wasim Sajjad and Zia ur-Rehman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/world/asia/afghan-music-taliban-pakistan-deportations.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 20:01:12 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>