<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 00:46:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Doomsday Clock Ticks Closer Than Ever to Apocalypse</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/doomsday-clock-2026.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28xp-doomsday-gwtb/28xp-doomsday-gwtb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Doomsday Clock, a metaphorical timepiece meant to depict how close humanity is to destruction, ticked closer than ever to midnight on Tuesday: 85 seconds to the stroke of doom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the grimmest outlook yet on Earth’s future from the clock’s creators, a nonprofit organization and publication called the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists that has set the clock each year since 1947.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions between nuclear powers, failures in climate action, disruptive technologies like artificial intelligence and the rise of autocracy are among the reasons that the Bulletin’s experts in global security, climate and nuclear science cited for advancing it four seconds from last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 27, 2026, the Doomsday Clock was set at 85 seconds to midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Catastrophic risks are on the rise, cooperation is on the decline, and we are running out of time,” said Alexandra Bell, president and chief executive of the Bulletin. “Change is both necessary and possible, but the global community must demand swift action from their leaders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antinuclear activists were paying attention to the Doomsday Clock — especially those working with survivors of the atomic bombings in Japan at the end of World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is a warning that we need to take urgent action to avoid global catastrophe,” Hideo Asano, coordinator of the Japan Campaign to Abolish Nuclear Weapons in Tokyo, said in an interview. “We should know that the risk of nuclear war is the highest since the end of the Cold War.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nuclear arms race between the United States and the Soviet Union was the primary concern when the clock was invented. At the time, the people involved with the Bulletin included Albert Einstein and some of the scientists who made the first nuclear weapons, such as J. Robert Oppenheimer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clock was first set at seven minutes to midnight, and has fluctuated throughout its nearly 80-year history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics have dismissed the clock as a stunt based on subjective assessments. Others have said that its repeated warnings of total annihilation could be dismissed by the public — the public policy equivalent of the boy who cried wolf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Cold War’s tensions rose, the clock’s hand moved forward. Intermittently, it was wound back — including when the two nuclear-armed superpowers showed signs of cooperation in the 1960s and when they signed a major arms-control treaty in 1991, a few months before the Soviet Union collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That year the clock showed the greatest distance to midnight, 17 minutes. It has ticked steadily closer since, aside from a brief reversal in 2010. More nuclear tests happened, including in Pakistan and North Korea. Countries failed to live up to their climate pledges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some events from 2025 that the scientists said had informed this year’s Doomsday Clock setting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russia-Ukraine war entered its fourth year, characterized by Russian tests of nuclear-capable weapons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conflict between India and Pakistan flared, highlighting the risks of all-out war between the two nuclear-armed countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States and Israel launched attacks on Iranian nuclear sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;North Korea kept building its nuclear arsenal, tested missiles designed to carry nuclear warheads and tightened relations with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China increased its stockpile of nuclear warheads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last major nuclear arms control agreement between the United States and Russia moved closer to expiry in February this year, which would end 60 years of nuclear constraints between the two powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States announced plans for a new missile defense system based on space-based interceptors, called the “Golden Dome,” raising the possibility of conflict in space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global average temperature was the third warmest on record.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate change drove deadly weather events, including a flood in the Democratic Republic of Congo that killed dozens of people and extreme heat that killed tens of thousands in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration dismantled climate and pollution regulations and abandoned efforts to tackle global warming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration stripped back the United States’ public health infrastructure, reducing its ability to respond to pandemics and other biological threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists warned that the laboratory synthesis of cells they call “mirror life” could cause a devastating pandemic, crop failures and the collapse of ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence grew more sophisticated, raising concerns that it could be used to create new weapons and exacerbate disinformation campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bulletin also cited the rise of “nationalistic autocracy” in countries around the world. It said that the leaders of the United States, Russia and China varied in their autocratic leanings but all favored competition over cooperation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The rise of autocracies is not in itself an existential threat, but an us-versus-them, zero-sum approach increases the risk of global catastrophe,” the group said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Asano, the antinuclear activist, echoed the sentiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are also concerned by the fact that nationalism and unilateralism are growing,” he said, arguing that countries were underestimating the importance of universal values and mutual benefit. “We believe that unilateralism is not the solution to the existential global risks.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/doomsday-clock-2026.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 02:57:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Life on an Antarctic Glacier: Tea, Cheese and Lots of Shoveling</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/climate/antarctica-thwaites-glacier-drilling.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28cli-av-camplife-01-gphf/28cli-av-camplife-01-gphf-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, a week after scientists from Britain and South Korea pitched tents on Antarctica’s remote Thwaites Glacier, they were pretty much ready to start drilling into the half-mile-deep ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The multiday drilling operation would be the culmination of the eight-week voyage of the icebreaker Araon. If successful, it would allow the researchers to lower instruments through the glacier into the ocean below, providing never-before-seen data on how the water is melting the ice from the bottom up, adding to global sea-level rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But fierce winds, like those that had been whipping for days around the researchers’ campsite, could cause their drill equipment to freeze up or become buried in snowdrifts. They would also make it difficult for the scientists to stay outside while boring the hole and installing instruments beneath the ice, in a process they expected to take more than 60 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calmer conditions were forecast for Wednesday, which was when the scientists hoped to get to work. They were fine with having to wait an extra day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’ve come this far,” said Peter Davis, an oceanographer at the British Antarctic Survey. “It would be annoying if we failed at the last hurdle, just for the sake of a day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, the team’s 10 members were largely in good spirits, satisfied that their hard work had brought them to the cusp of completing their mission, against very long odds. After a week on the glacier, their clothing was grimier, the men’s facial hair bushier. Some people’s faces were lightly bronzed by snow tans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone had been shoveling a lot of snow, both to clear it from their tents and equipment, and to gather a supply of water for starting the drilling, which will use hot water to melt a hole deeper and deeper into the ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a break from shoveling, Seunghwan Oh, an engineer and, at 23, the team’s youngest member, described his feelings about the experience perhaps a little too candidly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Save me from this hell,” he said with an uneasy laugh, one that suggested he wasn’t entirely joking. “Please, take me to the Araon.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such an extreme working environment, it helps to stick to a routine, said Won Sang Lee, the expedition’s chief scientist. The team works from 8 a.m. to 6 p.m., with breaks for lunch and tea. Dinner is at 6 or 7 p.m. in the mess tent, followed by a discussion of the next day’s plans before team members crawl into their sleeping tents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that has allowed camping on Thwaites to feel more like normal life is fast satellite internet, via Starlink, which the team hadn’t used before in Antarctica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides helping the scientists stay connected with loved ones, good internet access has made it easier to communicate with the crew and other researchers back on the Araon, which has been traveling to different areas in the waters around Thwaites. One of the team’s safety guides, Taff Raymond, has been sharing videos and weather data every morning from camp to help the helicopter pilots assess whether it’s safe to fly over it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before leaving the ship last week to camp on the glacier, Keith Makinson, an oceanographer and drilling engineer, said he worried that fast internet would make everyone antisocial, preferring to spend their down time sitting and scrolling rather than talking to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That concern hadn’t been fully borne out, Dr. Makinson said Tuesday, though he acknowledged, “There are moments of silence that are not eating, when everyone’s catching up on news from home,” he said. “Not for too long.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a midday tea break, the scientists and engineers gathered in the unheated mess tent for a bit of chatting and a bit of scrolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Raymond had baked a fresh loaf in the bread machine, and the tent smelled wonderful. The team members cut up the bread and ate it with strawberry jam and slices of “Tasty cheese,” a kind of aged Cheddar from New Zealand and Australia. Mr. Raymond made a pot of black tea with snow that had been melted and boiled on a portable gas stove. Power for the bread machine and other electrical devices comes from gasoline-fueled generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Davis, the oceanographer, asked if I wanted a cup. I declined, saying I couldn’t possibly dip into the team’s stash when they still had so much work to do on the glacier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s fine, we’re nearly finished,” Dr. Davis said, a moment before he realized the boldness of his statement and deflated it by adding, “He says confidently.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One way or another, we are,” Dr. Makinson said, and he was right. The Araon has to begin its return journey to New Zealand on Feb. 7 or thereabouts, whether the drilling has succeeded by then or not.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/climate/antarctica-thwaites-glacier-drilling.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 08:03:50 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Threatens Iran With ‘Massive Armada’ and Presses a Set of Demands</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-iran-armada.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28DC-PREXY-hmkc/28DC-PREXY-hmkc-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The USS Abraham Lincoln in 2024. The aircraft carrier group is currently stationed in striking distance of targets in Iran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/us/politics/trump-iran-armada.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:44:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canada’s New Reality</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/canada-tariffs-trump-iran-threats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/29/multimedia/29int-theworld-canada-promo/29int-theworld-canada-promo-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A truck stop on a trade route in Alberta.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/canada-tariffs-trump-iran-threats.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 12:48:42 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hillary Clinton and Tucker Carlson Speak at Saudi Business Forum</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/hillary-clinton-tucker-carlson-riyadh.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-saudi-clinton-1-bmkp/28int-saudi-clinton-1-bmkp-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Hillary Clinton at the Democratic National Convention in Chicago in 2024. She called the changes in Saudi Arabia “exhilarating to see.”
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/hillary-clinton-tucker-carlson-riyadh.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:53:37 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Plane Carrying Colombian Politicians Crashes in Area Contested by Rebels</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/americas/colombian-plane-politicians-missing.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/world/28int-colombia-plane/28int-colombia-plane-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A commercial plane carrying 15 people, including two politicians, crashed in a restive region along Colombia’s border with Venezuela on Wednesday, according to SATENA, the airline operating the flight. There were no survivors, an official said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane, a Beechcraft 1900 turboprop, was traveling between the cities of Cúcuta and Ocaña. Ocaña is in the Catatumbo region, a mountainous zone where the Colombian government has been ratcheting up a conflict with the country’s most powerful armed group, the National Liberation Army, or the ELN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An airline statement said the aircraft last made contact with air-traffic control at 11:54 a.m. local time, approximately 11 minutes before its scheduled landing in Ocaña. William Villamizar, the governor of the department of Norte de Santander, where the plane crashed, told a local news channel that no one survived the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane was carrying 13 passengers and two crew members. The list of passengers released by SATENA included two local politicians, Diógenes Quintero and Carlos Salcedo, who were running for congressional office in upcoming national elections. Mr. Quintero’s campaign team also posted news of his death on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SATENA, Colombia’s state-owned airline, is generally considered safe, and the last crash that resulted in fatalities was more than 35 years ago. Many of the airline’s pilots are former member of the military. Its fleet of propeller planes connects remote regions of Colombia to urban centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simón Posada contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/americas/colombian-plane-politicians-missing.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:39:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Why the Cold War Pact Known as NORAD Is Making Headlines</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/canada/norad-us-canada-security-agreement.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28xp-norad-01-bzqg/28xp-norad-01-bzqg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, the United States is not scrapping NORAD, but the government still wants Canada to buy American jets for the common defense of both countries, the State Department said on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product of a Cold War-era agreement between the United States and Canada, the North American Aerospace Defense Command, or NORAD, usually makes headlines when children across North America follow its Santa tracker on Christmas, but President Trump’s administration recently put it on the map for a different reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump talked up the need for a stronger Arctic defense as part of a recent push to acquire Greenland, NORAD’s capability to protect airspace came into the administration’s focus this week — at the same time as tariff tensions resurfaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because the U.S. ambassador to Canada dropped what seemed like a bombshell: There could be a change to the U.S.-Canada pact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In comments to the Canadian public broadcaster CBC News, published on Monday, U.S. Ambassador Pete Hoekstra said that if Canada did not purchase American-made F-35 fighter jets, made by Lockheed Martin, “NORAD would have to be altered” and that the United States may have to fly into Canadian airspace to fill defense gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The statement stirred fears about what it could mean for the decades-long pact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Hoekstra was talking about logistical hurdles and equipment, not the agreement itself, the State Department clarified in a statement to The New York Times on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ambassador Hoekstra’s comments were taken out of context to create headlines rather than to objectively portray his comments about the role that NORAD and the F-35 play in protecting the North America,” a State Department spokesperson said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, for many people who have checked the NORAD Santa Claus tracker, or who have heard about NORAD jets intercepting and shooting down small balloons, the increased attention will raise some basic questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The North American Aerospace Defense Command is a defense organization operated jointly by the United States and Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people recognize it for tracing Santa’s fantastical global journey, as it has done for more than six decades. But the organization’s deeper work hums in the background of everyday life, as it tracks air and maritime threats that might be coming toward North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NORAD functions as both a warning system and an aerospace shield, acting as the frontline of defense for both Canada and the United States, said Andrea Charron, a professor at the University of Manitoba in Winnipeg who is also the director of the Center for Defense and Security Studies there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The fact that NORAD exists is a deterrent to adversaries,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NORAD’s stated purpose is to “prevent air attacks against North America, safeguard the sovereign airspaces of the United States and Canada by responding to unknown, unwanted and unauthorized air activity approaching and operating within these airspaces, and provide aerospace and maritime warning for North America.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got a confidential news tip? The New York Times would like to hear from readers who want to share messages and materials with our journalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Cold War creation, NORAD was established in 1958 when the prospect of Soviet missiles and bombers crossing the Arctic was considered the gravest threat to North America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NORAD is also responsible for surveying the skies during major events, such as the Super Bowl and the World Cup, and it establishes no-fly zones, for example, wherever the U.S. president travels within North America, Professor Charron said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NORAD is led by a commander — currently Gen. Gregory M. Guillot of the U.S. Air Force — who reports to both the U.S. president and the Canadian prime minister. The leaders of both countries have the authority to issue an order to NORAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deputy commander is Lt. Gen. Iain Huddleston, a senior Royal Canadian Air Force officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Hoekstra’s comments spurred headlines and raised concerns, it was not immediately clear what he meant by “altered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The State Department clarified on Wednesday that Mr. Hoekstra was not referring to a change to the pact that governs NORAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His comments, the State Department said, referred to the modernization of NORAD, of which the F-35 jets were a “key planned part.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Canada decided to significantly reduce its investment in the F-35, that would create a significant gap in the defense structure of North America,” the State Department said. “Filling that gap is not news, it is common sense.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NORAD is crucial to the defense of both the United States and Canada; as such, the lofty goal of modernizing its capabilities is of key interest to both countries. In 2022, Canada announced it would spend nearly 5 billion Canadian dollars over the following six years upgrading its defense systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada began a review of its fighter jet deal with the United States after Mr. Trump imposed tariffs on Canadian imports last year. The review will assess whether the new fleet remains compatible with Canada’s military needs and the protection of its sovereignty “in light of evolving geopolitics,” according to Canada’s defense department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F-35 jet is a “flying supercomputer,” said Tom Karako, the director of the missile defense project at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington, and even more key, it offers interoperability and interchangeability among allies that use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s the fact that U.S. and Canadian F-35s and U.S. and NATO F-35s operating together are going to do so far more smoothly and seamlessly than trying to connect with some other aircraft,” Mr. Karako said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professor Charron said NORAD “works beautifully because it is binational and therefore needs the agreement of both before changes are made.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”NORAD is so part and parcel of how we defend Canada and the United States,” she said. “I really couldn’t imagine what we would do without it.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/canada/norad-us-canada-security-agreement.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 14:08:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Veteran Indian Politician Among 5 Killed in Plane Crash</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/india-plane-crash.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28INDIA-CRASH-vhml/28INDIA-CRASH-vhml-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ajit Pawar, a veteran Indian politician and the deputy chief minister of Maharashtra, one of India’s most powerful states, died in a plane crash on Wednesday, along with the four other people on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bombardier Learjet 45 crashed as it was preparing to land in the city of Baramati, Mr. Pawar’s political constituency, where he was to campaign for upcoming local elections. Photos of the accident site shared on social media showed thick smoke rising from the wreckage of the burned aircraft and debris strewed across an open field near the city’s airport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pawar’s personal security officer, an attendant and two crew members were also killed in the crash, according to a statement by India’s Ministry of Civil Aviation. Officials said they would open an investigation into the cause of the crash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plane was operated by a Delhi-based aviation charter company, officials said. It had aborted one landing and had received clearance to make a second when the accident happened, they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pawar, 66, was a member of an influential political family who forged alliances to navigate his way to the top of Maharashtra’s hardscrabble politics. He had been in his role for a little over a year as part of the state’s governing coalition, which is led by the Bharatiya Janata Party, the Hindu nationalist political party of Prime Minister Narendra Modi. Mr. Pawar was one of two deputy chief ministers in an unusual power-sharing agreement meant to retain stability within the coalition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pawar had been traveling from Mumbai, the state capital, to address public meetings as part of a campaign for upcoming local elections, according to local media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A career politician, he had served as deputy chief minister six times under different governments, with his latest term beginning in 2024. He held significant portfolios within the state cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a condolence message posted on social media, Mr. Modi called him a “leader of the people” who was “widely respected as a hardworking personality at the forefront of serving the people of Maharashtra.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is a very difficult day for Maharashtra today. For me, personally, I have lost a strong friend,” Devendra Fadnavis, the chief minister of Maharashtra, said as he declared a public holiday in the state and three days of mourning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The entire country is mourning this loss,” he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eknath Shinde, the other deputy in the state, called Mr. Pawar a team player and an “articulate, committed and hardworking leader.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2023, Mr. Pawar broke away from his uncle, Sharad Pawar, a three-time chief minister of Maharashtra who had co-founded the Nationalist Congress Party, a fixture of state politics. Mr. Pawar then joined an alliance led by the B.J.P. that formed Maharashtra’s government after winning the 2024 state election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The split weakened the elder Mr. Pawar’s hold on the state — whose capital Mumbai is India’s financial and entertainment behemoth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pawar is survived by his wife, the politician Sunetra Pawar, and two sons, Jay and Parth Pawar.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/india-plane-crash.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:52:13 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Missing in Kabul: The U.S. Citizen Witnesses Say Was Held by the Taliban</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/us-citizen-missing-afghanistan-taliban.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-afghanistan-detainee-gfhc/28int-afghanistan-detainee-gfhc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a summer morning in 2022, Afghan men blindfolded a U.S.-Afghan citizen on a street of Kabul, the country’s capital, and drove him away in his own S.U.V. to an unknown location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The men said they were from the Taliban’s intelligence services, according to three witnesses whose statements were obtained by The New York Times. The officers stormed the apartment that the U.S.-Afghan citizen, Mahmood Shah Habibi, had just left. They seized his laptop, some books and paperwork, and departed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the last time Mr. Habibi was seen in public. His arrest and unknown whereabouts remain at the center of tensions between the Trump administration, which has made the release of U.S. citizens held abroad a priority, and a Taliban government seeking to forge diplomatic and economic ties with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghan officials deny holding Mr. Habibi, or even knowing where he is. They have not responded to questions from the Times about his arrest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the details of his detention — recollected in the witness statements shared with the U.S. State Department, the National Security Council and the Afghan authorities — support the claim made by American officials that the Taliban arrested him, at least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least five cars carrying Afghan intelligence officers blocked the street leading to the apartment building where Mr. Habibi lived, and which he had just left, according to the statements. The men stopped Mr. Habibi as he was about to drive to his office and later searched the apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Habibi disappeared about a week after the C.I.A. — in a 2022 strike in Kabul — killed Ayman al-Zawahri, Al Qaeda’s leader and a key plotter of the Sept. 11, 2001, terrorist attacks on the United States. Whether he is alive or not remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Habibi worked as a contractor for Asia Consultancy Group, a Kabul-based telecommunications company, according to the F.B.I. He and his driver were detained with 29 other employees of the firm, all of whom, except one, have since been freed. .U.S. officials would not discuss whether Mr. Habibi had a role in the strike, nor on the nature of his or his colleagues’ work. But his father, Ahmadullah, and brother, Ahmad, have denied that he was involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The Taliban saying they never heard of my brother is contradicted by witness statements, technical data and other information that shows without a doubt that they both arrested him and held him with 30 other colleagues at G.D.I. headquarters,” said Ahmad Habibi, referring to the initials for Afghanistan’s intelligence agency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban spokesman, Zabiullah Mujahid, said in a text message on Wednesday, “The Islamic Emirate doesn’t have Mahmood Shah Habibi,” using the Taliban’s formal name for the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with the Times this month, Mr. Mujahid said that Afghanistan was ready to release two U.S. prisoners — identified by U.S. officials as Dennis Walter Coyle, a U.S. citizen from Colorado held since last January, and Polynesis Jackson, a former U.S. Army soldier whose reasons for being in the country remain murky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In exchange, Mr. Mujahid said the Taliban wanted the release of the last Afghan held at Guantánamo Bay, Muhammad Rahim, who is accused by the C.I.A. of having been a courier and translator to Osama Bin Laden within Al Qaeda. Mr. Rahim, 60, has never been charged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discussing Mr. Habibi’s fate or whereabouts is off the table as long as Mr. Rahim is not freed, said an Afghan official with direct knowledge of the negotiations who insisted on anonymity to discuss ongoing release efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a direct witness of the arrest, the Taliban blindfolded Mr. Habibi in the back of his own white S.U.V. before driving him away. “I asked one of the guys who they were, and he said they are G.D.I. Mujahideen,” one witness said in a statement, referring to the term for fighters used by the Taliban.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another group of intelligence officers from G.D.I. later stormed Mr. Habibi’s apartment, took Mr. Habibi’s laptop, some books and paperwork, according to the witnesses’ statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the men who stormed the apartment and introduced himself as the G.D.I. unit’s leader told an eyewitness that Mr. Habibi was a U.S. spy and that G.D.I. had been tracking him for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blindfolded, Mr. Habibi and a co-worker were driven to a facility where they were interrogated about the C.I.A. strike on Mr. al-Zawahri, according to the co-worker’s statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least five U.S. prisoners have been freed from Afghanistan over the past year, but negotiations for the release of remaining detainees have stalled in recent months. The Trump administration says Mr. Rahim’s release is off the table and has accused the Taliban of hostage diplomacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amir Khan Muttaqi, the Afghan foreign minister, denied the accusations in an interview with The Times. He instead called on the Trump administration to reopen the U.S. Embassy in Kabul and develop trade with Afghanistan — including through the country’s vast reserves of copper, aluminum and rare earth minerals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A participant in the negotiations, who spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss release efforts, said the Trump administration would not consider any further public engagement with the Taliban until all remaining U.S. citizens, including Mr. Habibi, are freed.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/us-citizen-missing-afghanistan-taliban.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 02:58:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iraq’s Nominee for Prime Minister Rejects Trump Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/trump-iraq-prime-minister-al-maliki.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28-int-iraq-trump-fptg/28-int-iraq-trump-fptg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nominee to be Iraq’s next prime minister, Nuri Kamal al-Maliki, vowed to continue pursuing the position on Wednesday, and dismissed a threat made by President Trump to withdraw U.S. support for the country if his nomination went ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We categorically reject this blatant American interference in Iraq’s internal affairs and consider it a violation of its sovereignty,” Mr. al-Maliki wrote in a post on social media, saying that Mr. Trump’s comments contravened Iraq’s democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Iraq’s elections in November, the country’s most powerful Shiite political bloc won a majority of votes, and nominated Mr. al-Maliki, a former prime minister, to lead the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s ultimatum, issued Tuesday, was the latest push by his administration to pressure Iraq into reducing the influence of its larger and more powerful neighbor, Iran, amid Washington’s escalating confrontation with Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iraq’s current caretaker government has so far been silent on Mr. Trump’s comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Maliki’s relations with Washington weren’t always this bad. In fact, he was first elected prime minister in 2006 with U.S. backing. But over the course of two four-year terms, he became increasingly seen as aligned with Iran, the regional Shiite power, and was accused of fueling sectarianism with policies that favored Iraq’s Shiite majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics accuse Mr. al-Maliki of enacting sectarian policies that fueled the rise of the Sunni militant group, Islamic State. In 2014, the group seized nearly a third of Iraq, sparking a yearslong U.S.-led international military campaign to defeat the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, Mr. Trump wrote on social media that Mr. al-Maliki’s last term in office, which ended in 2014, plunged the country into “poverty and total chaos.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If elected, the United States of America will no longer help Iraq and, if we are not there to help, Iraq has ZERO chance of Success, Prosperity, or Freedom,” Mr. Trump added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former prime minister has remained a powerful player in Iraqi politics and sought a third term in Iraq’s November elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is not surprising that the Trump administration would oppose a third term for Maliki,” said Victoria J. Taylor, who led Iraq policy at the State Department during the Biden administration, and is currently at the Atlantic Council, a think tank. “It is more surprising that the United States did not try to thwart his nomination earlier in the government formation process.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several smaller parties within Iraq’s majority bloc, the Coordination Framework, have thrown their support behind Mr. al-Maliki and also rejected Mr. Trump’s statement as a violation of sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bloc is set to meet on Wednesday to decide whether it will carry on with Mr. al-Maliki’s nomination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his statement, Mr. al-Maliki said he would “continue to work until we reach the end, in a manner that achieves the higher interests of the Iraqi people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Schmitt contributed reporting&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/trump-iraq-prime-minister-al-maliki.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 14:40:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Landslide Leaves Town in Sicily Perched on a Cliff’s Edge</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/sicily-town-landslide.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-italy-cliff-town-1-fqpb/28int-italy-cliff-town-1-fqpb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of a town in Sicily teetered on a cliff’s edge on Wednesday, days after a landslide cut a wide chasm that destroyed buildings and threatened to swallow more, including structures in the historic city center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The landslide in the town of Niscemi happened on Sunday, triggered in part by intense rain from Cyclone Harry, one of the most damaging storms in the Mediterranean in decades. On Wednesday, rain continued to fall and the hillside was still crumbling, heightening the danger to buildings and infrastructure near the edge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 1,500 people had been evacuated from neighborhoods along the chasm, which stretched for about 2.5 miles. Houses and apartment buildings were perched precariously at the edge, and aerial footage showed underground pipes and cables dangling from exposed foundations. A silver-gray sedan was partly suspended over the abyss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are in a movie, in a horror film, it’s still all up in the air,” said Stefania Di Giovanni, who lives a kilometer from the edge. She said she did not know when she would be able to return to the restaurant she owns in Niscemi’s historic center.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Niscemi is one of the towns hit worst by Cyclone Harry, which brought heavy rain and flooding to Sicily and Italy’s southern coast. Italy’s prime minister, Giorgia Meloni, who visited Niscemi on Wednesday, called the situation there “particularly complex” and said she was “determined to provide immediate responses.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her government has declared a national emergency across Sicily, Sardinia and Calabria, all areas affected by the cyclone, and has set aside 100 million euros, about $120 million, for the disaster response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fabio Ciciliano, the head of Italy’s National Civil Protection Service, said the crumbling hillside in Niscemi was preventing emergency workers from approaching the scene. He said it was hard to calculate the extent of the damage or say when, if ever, people could return to their imperiled homes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“At the moment, it’s very hard to imagine the future” of the town and the surrounding area, he said by telephone after surveying the area in a helicopter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The only thing we can do now is wait,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parts of Niscemi’s historic center and nearby businesses are at risk, the authorities have said. Frida Rooftop Bar on the old town square has a view of the seaside town of Gela and the ocean beyond, its draw since it opened in 2020, but it is now on the fault line, said Gaetano Parisi, whose family owns the establishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We built this dream five years ago, but at the moment, we don’t know if this dream will continue to exist,” Mr. Parisi said by telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luigi Virone, a doctor at the local hospital who grew up in Niscemi, owns one of the town’s oldest houses. Built in 1693, it is now a pub, in a terraced part of the historic center with Baroque-era homes, which many fear will not survive the disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Virone said he tried to visit the area on Sunday, just after the landslide, and found a stricken neighborhood as people were forced to evacuate. “Disbelieving and lost faces, eyes welling with tears, frightened children carrying precious items,” he wrote in a message. “Others didn’t even have time to grab clothes to wear the next day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he felt “helpless, frustrated, and small compared to the force of nature.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyclone Harry was unprecedented, at least in human memory, said Giulio Betti, a climatologist and meteorologist with the National Research Council, citing the intensity of the storm, which swept through an extended area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Niscemi, a town of about 25,000 built on a sloping plateau, has a centuries-old history of landslides and may have to reconsider how it builds, said Giuseppe Collura, a geologist with the Sicily Italian Society of Environmental Geology. The same area struck by the landslide was hit by one in 1997 that affected several buildings, requiring that they be demolished, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There was a high probability that these events would, in short, be repeated over time in these areas,” Mr. Collura said. Niscemi was struck by a landslide earlier this month, the Italian authorities said; Mr. Collura said the one that followed on Sunday was “a second step,” part of the same geological development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Rev. Giuseppe Cafà, a priest in Niscemi, said the week had felt apocalyptic, with many residents wondering how they will rebuild or plan a life. Some fear being isolated for weeks or months as the state repairs the roads. With some schools closed because of damage, many parents wonder where their children will finish the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though most of Niscemi is not directly threatened by the disaster, the imperiled historic center, the town’s oldest neighborhood, is its heart, Father Cafà said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s as if we were losing our roots,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/sicily-town-landslide.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:06:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Melania Trump Documentary Pulled From South African Theaters</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/melania-trump-documentary-south-africa-cancel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-safrica-melania-1-zgjp/28int-safrica-melania-1-zgjp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Melania,” the new documentary about the first lady, scheduled to open worldwide on Friday, has been pulled from theaters in South Africa after the film’s local distributor said on Wednesday that it would no longer release it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Based on recent developments, we’ve taken the decision to not go ahead with a theatrical release in territory,” said Thobashan Govindarajulu, the head of sales and marketing for the distributor, Filmfinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Govindarajulu declined to say what recent developments had led to the decision, but said that the company was not pressured or asked to pull the film. “That was our decision,” he said. The decision was first reported by the South African outlet News24.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The promotion of the film about Melania Trump has been as polarizing as her husband, President Trump, who has touted the movie as a “must watch.” But theaters have reported thin advanced ticket sales, despite Amazon investing $40 million for the rights to the film and spending tens of millions more on marketing, which industry analysts saw as a big risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film, which follows Ms. Trump in the weeks before her husband’s second inauguration, has also drawn criticism because of its director, Brett Ratner. The documentary is Mr. Ratner’s first Hollywood film since he was accused of sexual misconduct in 2017, during the height of the #MeToo movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to pull the film in South Africa comes at a time of deep hostility between the South African government and Mr. Trump. The president has been extremely critical of South Africa since the start of his second term, spreading false allegations that the country’s white minority is facing a genocide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many South Africans have grown angry with what they see as Mr. Trump’s promotion of misinformation about their country, and with the punishing tariffs he has introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is unclear whether icy relations between South Africa and the United States, low ticket sales, or something else led to the decision by Filmfinity to cancel the film’s release. But the choice came abruptly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Sardi, the chief executive of Ster-Kinekor, one of South Africa’s major movie theater chains, shared a message from Filmfinity this week indicating that “Melania” had complied with all local regulations and would be released. In an interview on Wednesday, Mr. Sardi said he did not know why the distributor had pulled the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Our basic position would be we’re not in the business of censorship,” he said. “I expect the decision would have been a commercial one balanced with a whole lot of current issues.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spokeswoman for South Africa’s content regulator, the Film and Publications Board, said on Wednesday that the board was not aware that the film had been pulled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zimasa Matiwane contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/melania-trump-documentary-south-africa-cancel.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 10:32:05 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Naval Drills With Iran, South Africa Faces New U.S. Scrutiny</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/south-africa-iran-navy-drills-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-safrica-iran-1-tjkw/28int-safrica-iran-1-tjkw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naval exercises held off the coast of South Africa have led to a new round of hostility between the country and the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercises, held this month, were led by China and joined by members of the BRICS group of emerging economies, including South Africa, Russia and the United Arab Emirates. Two of the group’s original members, Brazil and India, did not participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the weeklong exercises approached on Jan. 9, President Cyril Ramaphosa of South Africa ordered his defense officials to ensure that Iran, which was scheduled to participate, was downgraded to observer status, according to his office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Tehran participated in the drills anyway, including in live-fire exercises that took place at the height of the mass demonstrations in Iran this month, during which thousands of protesters were killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what allies of Mr. Ramaphosa had thought was an attempt to avoid agitating President Trump has become another setback in his country’s strained relationship with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the exercises, the U.S. Embassy in Pretoria strongly rebuked the South African government, accusing it of “choosing to stand with a regime that brutally represses its people and engages in terrorism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The South African government has said that China organized the drills and handled the invitations, and that South Africa simply hosted them in its waters. The Chinese government did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That explanation has done little to quell the uproar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drills were the second time in six months Mr. Ramaphosa appeared to be blindsided on Iran by his own military. Last August, the South African military’s top general visited Tehran, where he spoke glowingly of the relationship between the two countries. Mr. Ramaphosa did not know about or approve the visit, according to his office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a middle power and Africa’s largest economy, South Africa has long struggled to balance its relationship with various international partners. South African officials view the country’s BRICS membership as a crucial step to fulfilling its geopolitical ambitions of greater economic independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, the BRICS bloc has more bluntly positioned itself as a bulwark against U.S. hegemony. The naval drills were not an official BRICS exercise, but they ended up showcasing divisions in the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government released a statement this month downplaying its absence, saying that the exercises were “entirely a South African initiative in which some BRICS members took part.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brazil, which has tried to position itself as a leading voice on diplomacy in the global south, sent a naval officer to observe. The Brazilian Navy said in a statement that it did not participate because it could not deploy ships to the region in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military drills are about much more than improving the technical capabilities of a country’s armed forces, said Priyal Singh, a senior researcher at the Institute for Security Studies, a think tank in South Africa. “A joint naval exercise is all about the optics as well,” Mr. Singh said. “It’s about sending a geopolitical message.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The South African government has vowed to investigate Iran’s participation and the fact that a presidential order was seemingly ignored. That process is off to a rocky start. Nearly two weeks after the defense minister said the inquiry would take place, it has yet to begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Mr. Ramaphosa’s political opponents have accused him of weak leadership and called on him to swiftly discipline the officials who allowed Iran to participate, he is also facing scrutiny from within his own party. Those critics accuse him of letting America’s unpredictable, strongman president influence his foreign policy decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some South Africans have grown tired of Mr. Trump’s repeated attacks on their country, including his false claims that Afrikaners are facing a genocide. Some rank-and-file members of Mr. Ramaphosa’s party, the African National Congress, have asked why leaders continue to engage with Washington, said Lindiwe Zulu, a member of the party’s national executive committee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We feel you are kowtowing toward this man,” some members have said, according to Ms. Zulu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She added that many were dismayed by what they saw as Mr. Trump’s edicts “about who we must keep relations with, how we must conduct our international relations, how we conduct even our internal relations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vincent Magwenya, a spokesman for Mr. Ramaphosa, said the South African leader had sought to cancel Iran’s participation in the naval drills to protect his country’s “own national interest.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That does not translate to us selling our sovereignty,” he said, but was rather a matter of “care and pragmatism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consequences South Africa may face from the United States, its second largest trading partner, are unclear. A bill to renew a preferential trade program for dozens of African nations was recently passed by the House and awaits action in the Senate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some South Africans fear that the Trump administration might exclude their country from the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hari Kumar contributed reporting from New Delhi, and Ana Ionova from Rio de Janeiro.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/south-africa-iran-navy-drills-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:02:16 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Putin to Host Syrian Leader With Russian Military Bases on the Agenda</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/russia-putin-syria-al-sharaa-meeting.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-russia-syria-01-hckq/28int-russia-syria-01-hckq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia was set to welcome President Ahmed al-Sharaa of Syria in Moscow on Wednesday as the two leaders work to establish a new relationship between their countries more than a year after the fall of the Russian-backed Syrian dictator Bashar al-Assad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trip is Mr. al-Sharaa’s second to Russia since he seized power in Syria in late 2024, sweeping across the country into Damascus, the capital, and forcing Mr. al-Assad to flee into a gilded exile in Russia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. al-Sharaa, a onetime Qaeda fighter turned rebel commander and statesman, has taken a pragmatic approach to Moscow, despite spending years on the battlefield under Russian airstrikes. He has said that Syria is not in a position to be antagonizing world powers, and he has asked Russia to aid Syria in its reconstruction. At the same time, he has said that Mr. al-Assad must be brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin spokesman Dmitri S. Peskov told reporters on Wednesday that Mr. Putin would welcome Mr. al-Sharaa for negotiations, noting that relations between Moscow and Damascus had been developing since the fall of the previous Syrian government. Mr. Peskov declined to comment on whether the extradition of Mr. al-Assad back to Syria would be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage posted online showed Mr. al-Sharaa descending the steps of his airplane on Wednesday in Moscow in the snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At stake for the Kremlin is the fate of Russia’s military footprint in Syria, which has included the Hmeimim Air Base and a naval base at Tartus, on the Mediterranean, as well as the air base at Qamishli, in northeastern Syria’s Kurdish region, near the Turkish border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, reports surfaced that Russia was removing its forces from Qamishli. The Syrian government under Mr. al-Sharaa is establishing control over the Kurdish region from the Syrian Democratic Forces, a group of predominantly Kurdish fighters that the United States backed to wage war against the Islamic State but that Washington has since largely abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has said that Mr. al-Sharaa’s government can now handle the threat posed by any resurgence of the Islamic State.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/russia-putin-syria-al-sharaa-meeting.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 07:02:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Russian Strike Kills Five, Train Sheds Burned Cars and Carries On</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/ukraine-train-attack.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-ukraine-train-pzfw/28int-ukraine-train-pzfw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the luckiest smoke break of Oleksandr Pysmenny’s life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, as the train he was riding on traveled through the Kharkiv region of eastern Ukraine, Mr. Pysmenny, 27, got out of the bed in his compartment and went to a corridor for a cigarette. He then heard the sound of a diving Russian drone, followed by an explosion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It had hit his carriage. The doors back to it were blocked. He climbed outside, ran around the burning car and climbed back in to try to help his friends. He picked up the bloodied wife of one of his friends and carried her away from the train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A Russian drone can kill you faster than smoking,” Mr. Pysmenny’s wife, Maria Shtern, 25, wrote on social media. She was not on the train that was attacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ukrainian Railways train, which was carrying more than 200 passengers, was attacked by three drones. Five people were killed in the strike, the latest in Russia’s monthslong campaign against the Ukrainian rail infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the attack, the burning carriages were disconnected and the remaining 10 cars continued the journey. The train, with 147 passengers still on board, arrived at the next station after a five-hour delay. There, passengers were provided with food by World Central Kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the three drones, one struck a carriage with 18 people on board, and the other two landed nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Russia must be held accountable for what it does,” President Volodymyr Zelensky said in his evening address to the Ukrainian people. “And this means responsibility not only for strikes against our people, against our lives, but for the very ability to carry out such strikes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trains have been a critical part of Ukraine’s logistics during the war. They are used to evacuate civilians from frontline areas. With the country’s airports closed, they connect Ukrainians to Europe. They also deliver goods as Russian strikes close maritime routes in the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, Russia has intensified its attacks on Ukraine’s rail infrastructure. In December, a strike hit a key junction station in Fastiv, in the Kyiv region, that connects the capital with western Ukraine and Europe. Train stations in Sumy, Kharkiv and Kherson have also been hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the attack on the train on Tuesday, Ms. Shtern said that Mr. Pysmenny, a police officer who also does tasks on the front line, had helped get his colleagues out of the burning train. They were in stable condition in a hospital, she added. Mr. Pysmenny did not feel well after the strike and went to a hospital for a checkup, though he was not injured in the attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was so lucky,” Ms. Shtern said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Pysmenny recalled carrying his friend’s wife away from the train. “I saw my friend’s wife walking toward me; she was covered in blood,” he said. As they hid under trees, they heard another drone flying over their heads.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/ukraine-train-attack.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:10:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>In Nigeria, a Catholic Bishop Navigates a Nation of Extremes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/nigeria-catholic-bishop-muslims-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-nigeria-bishop-new-mhpg/28int-nigeria-bishop-new-mhpg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after Christmas, Bishop Matthew Hassan Kukah rushed to a special children’s Mass early in the morning, unaware that his diocese of Sokoto in northwest Nigeria had been struck by missiles during the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He glanced at his phone after the Mass ended and found a text from a friend at the Vatican. It said, the Americans have bombed Sokoto. His heart raced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city of Sokoto is in a region that has been overwhelmingly Muslim since the 19th century, when it was a Muslim caliphate. The bishop was aware that President Trump had been loudly blaming Muslims for what the president called a “Christian genocide” in Nigeria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishop Kukah feared that his small Roman Catholic flock in this Muslim region was ground zero for a U.S. war on Islam. He worried that all his work building bridges between the faiths had gone to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When you say Sokoto has been bombed in an environment that is already so hysterically charged, it means you have declared war against the Muslims,” he said, sitting at the breakfast table in his quiet compound in Sokoto. “This is their headquarters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several hours later it became clear that missiles had struck miles outside the city of Sokoto, aimed at Islamist extremists in their hide-outs. Bishop Kukah was relieved. The targets were the criminals causing the real problems in Nigeria, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said in a social media post that the missiles were aimed at “ISIS Terrorist Scum in Northwest Nigeria, who have been targeting and viciously killing, primarily, innocent Christians.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For months the bishop has been trying to tone down the fiery talk from Washington and certain quarters of Nigeria of what they called a Christian genocide in the country. Rather, he and many other Nigerians say, it is a complicated cycle of violence in a nation of some 240 million people that is evenly split between Muslims and Christians, and is victimizing both communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishop Kukah said that some priests and parishioners in his diocese had been kidnapped. One of his young seminarians was murdered, he said, after defending his faith to his Muslim captors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He said he was losing a battle for permission to build a chapel on the campus of a local university named for a celebrated Muslim leader. And he has tried and failed to help parishioners who are civil servants get promotions after being passed over, he said, because of their Christian faith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All are clear signs, he said, of Christian persecution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This has been my life,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the bishop points out that the targets of violence in Nigeria are not just Christians. Many Muslims have also been victims of horrific acts, he said. A lack of general security, not just religion, is to blame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His message was amplified in October when he stood in a Catholic university hall in Rome and told an audience of church leaders and religious freedom activists from across the world that Nigeria’s worsening security crisis was caused by a complex mix of terrorism, religious persecution and criminal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Today, the floods of blood in Nigeria have no boundaries. This is why the debate over what is happening to us has become so confusing within and outside Nigeria,” the bishop told the audience. “Although we cannot find the right words, the simple truth is that Nigerians are dying for a living.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His remarks drew immediate blowback from some Nigerians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thompson Udenwa, a Nigerian civil rights activist, questioned the bishop’s “sudden change of tone” about the persecution of Christians. Raphael Oluwaseun Fagbohun, the presiding bishop of the Old Catholic Apostolic Church in Nigeria, which is independent of the Roman Catholic Church, demanded a public apology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bishop Kukah has not only betrayed the Christian faith but also the trust of the nation,” Bishop Fagbohun said in a New Year’s message to his flock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The criticism was frustrating for Bishop Kukah, who has spent his entire career preaching nuance in a society of extremes. He has written or contributed to more than a half-dozen books. He has held fellowships at Harvard and Oxford, and delivered dozens of addresses at university convocations. He has mediated a violent conflict between militants and oil executives in the Niger Delta and served as a United Nations appointee to usher in peaceful elections. All of it has been dedicated to exploring the gray areas of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Ahmed Bola Tinubu, Western diplomats, scholars and others refer to him as “the conscience of a nation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had knocked on the metal gate of his modest, tree-filled compound in Sokoto one morning earlier this month, and he welcomed me to his breakfast table as he wrapped up a call with a retired diocesan cook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You are 81 now, I know, but I see your voice is sounding very, very strong — well done,” the bishop told the man, and promised to send a cash gift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishop Kukah, a soft-spoken 73-year-old with a gaptoothed smile and a penchant for self-deprecating tales, said he first got the urge to join the seminary as a little boy, when a priest drove a pickup truck through his tiny village in Kaduna State. He and his friends clung to the truck, hopped in the back and stayed there until the priest made them get out. In his boyish mind, priesthood came with a pickup truck. He decided then and there he would become a priest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He became a seminarian at age 24 and, after earning a reputation as a moderate voice, has been tapped by the Vatican through the years to serve in roles tied to peacemaking, human rights and interfaith dialogue. His position and his curiosity have taken him across the globe — just last month he visited Egypt and explored the Library of Alexandria. He is a furious consumer of news, academic papers and literature of all kinds, including The New Yorker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ten thousand words!” he said about articles in the publication. “The arrogance! It’s like reading a short book!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2012, he founded the Kukah Center, a policy research organization housed in a small office complex in the capital, Abuja, that focuses on interfaith dialogue and good governance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishop Kukah said he spent recent weeks trying to elaborate on — but not back down from — his remarks in Rome. He issued an official statement from the Kukah Center and sat for radio interviews, explaining that the government’s inability to enforce security was at the root of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are signs that some Nigerians are receptive to the bishop’s message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a crowded book talk in Abuja earlier this month where Bishop Kukah was introducing the author, an audience member stood and praised the bishop for his nuanced views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The room erupted in applause.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/africa/nigeria-catholic-bishop-muslims-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 01:00:43 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘The Man’ of Her Household: The Rise and Fall of a First Lady</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/korea-first-lady-kim-keon-hee-jail.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/00int-skorea-firstlady-07-gkqb/00int-skorea-firstlady-07-gkqb-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the first days of her husband’s presidency, Kim Keon Hee was unlike other South Korean first ladies, who stayed in their husbands’ shadows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her high profile — and her comments like she was “the man” of her household — rattled the country’s patriarchal society. A prominent dog lover, she accomplished what animal rights groups had tried but could not for decades: make South Korea ban dog meat for food. At the same time, she was prone to scandals and was accused of overstepping her role, leading to many misogynistic attacks against her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Ms. Kim, 53, who tried to style herself after Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, is the country’s first former first lady to be imprisoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, a three-judge panel in Seoul found her guilty of accepting a $43,000 necklace, plus a Chanel handbag, from the Unification Church, which prosecutors said sought government favors in return. Ms. Kim was sentenced to 20 months in prison, in the first ruling for the three criminal trials she is facing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The accused wrongfully used her status as a profit-making tool,” said the presiding judge, Woo In-sung. “She failed to reject the expensive luxury goods but instead used them to decorate herself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her downfall came alongside that of her husband, former President Yoon Suk Yeol, after he attempted to declare martial law in late 2024. He was driven, special prosecutors have said, in part by his desperate attempt to shield her, as well as himself, from criminal investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“She played a leading role from the moment Yoon Suk Yeol entered politics and went on to form a ‘political partnership’ with him,” Oh Jeong-hee, a special prosecutor, said after the trial began in September. “She held no official position, but enjoyed a status rivaling the president’s.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After his martial law collapsed, Mr. Yoon was expelled from office and arrested on insurrection charges. Ms. Kim is not accused of being involved in Mr. Yoon’s decree. But she was arrested last August and has been indicted on criminal charges, including accepting expensive gifts — such as luxury handbags and diamond necklaces — from people who special prosecutors said secured government jobs and other favors with her help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon called his marriage to Ms. Kim in 2012 his “happiest memory.” He was a prosecutor at the time and Ms. Kim, his junior by 12 years, was an art exhibition organizer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He acknowledged her role in shaping his political career. During his presidential campaign, Mr. Yoon said he woke up at five or six one morning to find her lying on the bed and answering text messages on Mr. Yoon’s smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Dissident’s Next Act: Kwon Pyong recounted for the first time the series of gambles that got him out of China by jet ski, and almost a year later, out of South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standoff With Doctors: Doctors at medical facilities across South Korea walked off the job in a one-day strike on June 18, expanding a months-old protest against the government’s health care policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Impeachment Threat: President Yoon Suk Yeol has been accused of intervening in an inquiry into the accidental death of a South Korean marine during a peacetime search and rescue operation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parliament Election: South Koreans delivered a stinging defeat to Yoon and his party, giving the opposition one of its biggest electoral victories in recent decades and pushing Yoon to the verge of being a lame duck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I said ‘Are you crazy? What are you doing up this late?’” he recalled during a news conference in late 2024. “She said she was replying to our supporters, thanking them and promising them to do a good job.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In South Korea’s cutthroat politics, Ms. Kim became a favorite target of Mr. Yoon’s enemies. On social media, critics claimed she had changed her appearance with plastic surgery and interviewed men who claimed they met her when they said she worked as a hostess in a Seoul nightclub. She denied that and other lurid rumors about her past, including shamanism. Songs went viral that belittled her as a woman who used sex as a tool for climbing the social ladder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women’s rights groups bristled at such attacks as channeling the country’s misogynistic culture. But Ms. Kim also angered them by sympathizing with a politician convicted of sexual violence against his secretary. Her corruption scandals made her even harder to defend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For Yoon’s detractors, it was not enough to criticize him for his martial law and other mishandling of state affairs,” said Park Jia, vice chairwoman at the Seoul Women’s Association. “They wanted to humiliate him by digging up his wife’s past,” she said, and depict him as “a man who cannot even control his wife.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the election campaign, Ms. Kim apologized for inflating her résumé — two universities in Seoul later retracted her degrees citing plagiarism — and promised a humble wife’s role if Mr. Yoon was elected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she also seemed to set the tone for what was to come. In comments to a reporter that were secretly recorded, she said that if she “took power,” officials would go after journalists who had been digging up dirt on her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before long, presidential aides handpicked by her often ran the show in Mr. Yoon’s office, and bypassed more senior secretaries, according to Kim Dae-nam, a former Yoon aide, whose secretly recorded telephone conversations with reporters were leaked in 2024. Mr. Yoon’s office called Mr. Kim’s claims baseless, but reports about Ms. Kim’s influence piled up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her public actions, critics saw a sense of entitlement. When she attended a government event with her pet dog, Ms. Kim handed its leash over to Mr. Yoon’s chief of presidential staff, according to Youn Kun Young, a lawmaker who disclosed the episode in a parliamentary hearing. When Ms. Kim once visited Gyeongbok Palace in central Seoul, she sat on the royal throne, according to witnesses who testified in Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kim seldom spoke in public. But she curated her public image by releasing a flood of handout photos of her accompanying Mr. Yoon on trips abroad, visiting military barracks, meeting poor children and cuddling pet dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That image began crumbling when spy cam footage of Ms. Kim accepting a $2,200 Dior pouch from a visitor months after Mr. Yoon’s inauguration was made public in late 2023. More scandals involving her unfolded, but Mr. Yoon called them “fake news” spread by his enemies to “demonize” his wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many critics began likening Ms. Kim to a “sorceress” manipulating the “blind” man they said Mr. Yoon was. Even the country’s conservative news media, which had supported Mr. Yoon, became exasperated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is only one person — President Yoon Suk Yeol — who can clarify that Kim Keon Hee is not the president of South Korea,” Kim Sun Duk, an editorial writer at Dong-A Ilbo, a major conservative newspaper, wrote in October 2024. “We all know that he cannot. Therein lies the tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By late 2024, most South Koreans supported the opposition’s demand for a special prosecutor to investigate allegations against Ms. Kim, according to surveys. Mr. Yoon had repeatedly opposed such bills, even as his approval ratings nose-dived below 20 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they throw stones, I will take them and press on,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Yoon and Han Dong-hoon — the leader of the People Power Party, to which Mr. Yoon also belonged — became sworn enemies over their differences over Ms. Kim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Drag Han Dong-hoon to me so I can shoot him dead,” Mr. Yoon said when he discussed martial law with military generals over heavy drinking in October 2024, according to one of the officers there, Lt. Gen. Kwak Jong-geun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But investigators said that Ms. Kim appeared unaware of Mr. Yoon’s martial law plans. She visited a plastic surgeon the evening that Mr. Yoon declared martial law. After it failed, Ms. Kim screamed at Mr. Yoon for “ruining everything,” according to prosecutors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, a court sentenced Mr. Yoon to five years in prison in a case related to his martial law decree. A ruling in his insurrection case, in which prosecutors have sought the death sentence, is expected next month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ms. Kim first appeared for questioning by investigators in August, she called herself “a nobody.” But the list of gifts they said she accepted in return for favors included a gold turtle figurine, a luxury clutch bag, a $27,700 wristwatch, a $97,000 painting and another $43,000 diamond necklace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She faced two others charges, including stock manipulation, in the trial that concluded Wednesday but was cleared of both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Kim’s lawyers vowed to protect her from “exaggerations and political framing” by prosecutors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she wondered whether she would ever live with Mr. Yoon again, said her lawyer, Yoo Jeong-hwa. Mr. Yoon also told a court last month that he did not expect to return home anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My wife is under arrest. What am I going to do even if I go home?” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/asia/korea-first-lady-kim-keon-hee-jail.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:23:06 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>A City Where Every Step Outside Risks Death by Drone</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/kherson-ukraine-drones-russia.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/28/multimedia/28int-ukraine-kherson-dispatch-bwvg-promo/28int-ukraine-kherson-dispatch-bwvg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was pickup time at the day care. As other children and parents milled about, Tanya Leshchenko sat on a bench in a hallway and bundled her 5-year-old daughter into a purple winter coat. But before stepping outside, one more task remained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Leshchenko checked an online chat group for warnings of incoming attack drones. The group posts crowdsourced alerts in the city of Kherson, in southern Ukraine, where the daily risk of death from flying robots offers a vision of an eerie, postapocalyptic future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One warning last fall simply said, “I hear a drone!” — an ominous buzzing that has become a grim, intermittent soundtrack in the city. On the day when Ms. Leshchenko, 36, was picking up her daughter, however, the sky was calm. They walked out and headed toward the bus stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You cannot outrun a drone,” Ms. Leshchenko said, before adding: “It’s scary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Kherson, a city of broad tree-lined boulevards and stately czarist-era mansions, residents fear the open sky. The entire city lies within range of cheap Russian quadcopter drones, which Moscow’s forces launch from territory they occupy just across the Dnipro River.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 200 civilians have been killed and 2,000 wounded in drone strikes over the past year, the authorities say. Ukrainians call the attacks a “human safari.” Russian drone operators drop grenades on people working in their gardens or ambling down sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kherson, whose population has fallen to about 65,000 after three-quarters of residents fled, has become the site of the most intensive use of drones in war crimes anywhere in the world, rights groups say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is moving below ground. Hospitals, a maternity ward, government offices, a theater and dozens of other institutions have been relocated to underground sites. Basement activity rooms have replaced outdoor playgrounds. All schools are online only.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The city is experimenting with myriad drone defenses, though none are wholly effective. The military has built a wall of jamming antennas along a riverbank. Dozens of miles of nets intended to catch drones before they reach an object and explode have been strung over thoroughfares. On sidewalks, 250 concrete escape chambers have been set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Municipal workers carry hand-held drone detectors as they labor outside repairing bomb damage or mending drone nets. The devices work by intercepting feeds from drones’ cameras, showing what the Russian drone operator sees when zeroing in on a target. Seeing yourself or your car on the detector’s screen is terrible news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It happened once to Yaroslav Shanko, the city’s military-civilian administrator, a position akin to mayor. How did he respond? “You need to reach maximum speed and maneuver” to get out of the drone’s view, Mr. Shanko said. Screeching around corners and plowing down alleys at more than 80 miles per hour, Mr. Shanko’s driver escaped the drone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rights groups say that other war-torn or crime-afflicted cities around the world are likely to look like Kherson in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small quadcopter drones, some adapted from hobbyist models, have democratized precision-guided munitions that previously cost tens or hundreds of thousands of dollars. They have been used to target civilians in the Sudanese civil war and in Mexican gang conflicts, said Belkis Wille, an associate director at Human Rights Watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Kherson is the clearest example of a campaign to target civilians with quadcopter drones, but this is really just the start of what we fear will become a reality for civilians in conflict areas” across the globe, Ms. Wille said. “The cost of targeting civilians has come way down.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kherson has never caught a break through four years of war. Russian forces occupied the city for nine months at the start of the full-scale invasion, before retreating. An 18th-century Russian aristocrat and lover of Catherine the Great, Prince Grigory Potemkin, is considered the founder of the modern city and was buried in a local church. When they retreated, Russian soldiers took his bones with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Ukrainian troops liberated Kherson in November 2022, Russian forces took to firing artillery into the city from across the river. Once small drones evolved into effective weapons the following year, a new scourge began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drone injuries are now so common, said Oleh Pinchuk, a surgeon, that, “We forgot about car accidents here.” Sometimes, the wounded watch wide-eyed in a hospital bed, several days into their recovery, when Russian forces post video online from the camera of the drone that attacked them. They see themselves on the screen, getting bigger and bigger as the drone draws nearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once drones close in, they are all but impossible to evade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mykola Hyadamaka, 67, a retired driver, recalled hearing a drone chasing his car. He raced home and tried to dash in his front door but fumbled with the gate to his yard. He was hit by shrapnel from a grenade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is no escape,” he said in an interview in his hospital bed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serhiy Schevchenko, 36, a plumber, was chased by a drone around a tree before it blew up nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There was nowhere to hide,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volodymyr Oleinichuk, 52, a parking lot attendant, dived under a shed after hearing a drone. It circled overhead, waiting for him to crawl out, he said. When he did not, it dropped a grenade near the foundation, spraying shrapnel under the shed and wounding him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A particularly frightening aspect of drone attacks, Mr. Oleinichuk noted, is the sense of intelligence driving the machine as a pilot searches and maneuvers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is somebody behind it, controlling it,” Mr. Oleinichuk said. “I heard how he was looking for me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With schools closed, underground activity areas are among the few places for children to socialize. They offer dance, art and other classes, and screen movies. A dance class at one center was called “United by Love.” Organizers put sandboxes in the subterranean play areas on the theory that children needed a substitute for touching soil in playgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outside, danger lurks. When drones come, “You need to hide in a shelter, or just anywhere where you cannot see the sky,” said Daria, an 11-year-old who over the summer hid under trees in a park when a drone flew over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although so many have fled Kherson, Ms. Leshchenko, the woman who picked up her daughter, Alyona, at day care recently, said that she did not plan to leave. Her family has nowhere to go, she added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once she got to the bus stop, a concrete shelter would provide protection. She would check the online chat group again. Then she would walk home quickly, holding Alyona’s hand.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/europe/kherson-ukraine-drones-russia.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 06:55:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Killed Thousands of Protesters. Here Are Five of Their Stories.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/iran-protester-deaths.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/world/00int-iran-deaths07/00int-iran-deaths07-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One was a 23-year-old budding fashion designer, another a prospective engineering student bound for Tehran. There was also a mother, father and son who had once considered emigrating as a family in hopes of a better life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All were killed in the protests that convulsed Iran for weeks starting in late December, according to their families and human rights groups. The demonstrations began over economic malaise but swelled into a nationwide antigovernment movement that posed the most serious threat to the regime in years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government violently quelled the protests and authorities imposed a stringent internet and communication blackout that has made it difficult to know the magnitude of the crackdown and the death toll. Rights groups say thousands have been killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times has been able to piece together some of the stories of those who have been killed in recent weeks, through interviews with their family members outside the country and reports by human rights groups. Not all of the details could be independently verified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of those family members had recently left Iran, while others said they had managed to receive international phone calls from relatives in Iran this month, during a brief respite from the blackout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The families said that their loved ones were motivated to join the protests by a desire for change in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government did not respond to a request for comment regarding any of the cases detailed in this story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran says the protests began as legitimate demonstrations by people expressing their economic grievances, but quickly escalated into riots organized by foreign infiltrators. The Iranian authorities have accused the United States and Israel of being behind the violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protesters’ families, however, offer sharply different accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He went out for freedom,” Ensieh Raoufi said of her cousin, Sorena Golgoon, 18, who she said was killed in early January while protesting in his hometown, the coastal city of Tonekabon. Ms. Raoufi said she spoke to both of Mr. Golgoon’s parents after his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hengaw Organization for Human Rights, which is based in Norway and monitored the unrest in Iran, reported that Mr. Golgoon had been killed during the protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group said in a statement on social media that Mr. Golgoon was “killed by direct fire from Iranian government forces” and that his family was “under intense pressure from government authorities to falsely claim that he was killed by protesters.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a phone interview, Ms. Raoufi, who lives in France, described her cousin as a kind and generous person. Weeks before his death, she said, he had given his jacket to a homeless person amid a winter chill. Ms. Raoufi said that Mr. Golgoon’s dream of working for an international car manufacturer led him to pursue studies in mechanical engineering in the capital, Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loss had left the family in profound sorrow, Ms. Raoufi said. “Their grief is endless.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robina Aminian, a 23-year-old fashion student, had just finished a college exam in early January when she decided to join the protests in Tehran, according to her aunt, Hali Nouri, who lives in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Nouri said that she was told by her sister, Ameneh Nouri, who identified Ms. Aminian’s body, that Ms. Aminian was shot in the head. Iran Human Rights, a Norway-based advocacy organization, published a report on Ms. Aminian’s death, saying that a shooting occurred on the night of Jan. 8 after she left the Shariati Technical and Vocational College for Girls, where she was a student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The youngest in her family, Ms. Aminian was an avid guitarist and had a creative and kind spirit, Ms. Nouri said. She was also known for weaving traditional Iranian elements into her designs. “She knew what she wanted in life,” Ms. Nouri said. “She wanted to be free, to live unrestrained.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Nouri said her sister and six other relatives told her that the authorities in Marivan, a city in western Iran, had disrupted Ms. Aminian’s memorial service. She said that it was canceled after security officers, stationed outside the home of a family member, prevented some relatives from paying their respects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Marivan governor’s office did not respond to a request for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mahmood Amiry-Moghaddam, the director of Iran Human Rights, said the group has documented several cases in Iran’s recent protests, including Ms. Aminian’s, in which the authorities imposed tight security measures on funerals to prevent such gatherings from turning into anti-government protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iranian authorities have put the official death toll at 3,117, a figure that rights groups say vastly underestimates the toll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Human Rights Activists in Iran, a Washington-based organization, more than 6,200 people were killed, most of them protesters. Iran Human Rights, based in Norway, estimated the toll at more than 3,400.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one case, several members of one family were killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zahra Bani-Amerian, her husband, Bijan Mostafavi, and their son, Danial Mostafavi, were shot in their car by government forces during protests in Karaj, west of Tehran, earlier this month, according to a report by Hengaw, the rights group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two relatives of the family who spoke to The Times said the family was shot in the city. They said that another son, Davoud Mostafavi, 27, was injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relatives were Michael Askari, who lives in Turkey and said he is Ms. Bani-Amerian’s cousin, and Abbas, who left Iran earlier this month. Abbas requested that only his first name be used and did not want to publicize his relationship to the deceased for fear of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Askari said that Ms. Bani-Amerian had sent him a text message just days before her death, saying that the government was killing people “one by one.” In a screenshot of the message shared with The Times, Ms. Bani-Amerian said that she felt other countries were failing to help Iranians amid the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Bani-Amerian, 48, was a retired employee of Iran’s Social Security Organization, and was curious, humorous and loved singing, Mr. Askari said. Her husband, Mr. Mostafavi, 56, had for years been a beloved teacher in Sonqor in western Iran, according to the two relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their son, Danial, 19, was cheerful and loved video games. At one point, the family considered leaving Iran for Turkey, but Mr. Mostafavi hesitated, saying emigrating and starting over at his age wasn’t easy, Mr. Askari added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abbas said that, before leaving Iran earlier this month, he had been involved in arrangements for the family’s funeral in Sonqor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authorities imposed restrictions on the service, he said, and compelled them to bury their loved ones before sunrise. The Hengaw rights group said in a statement that the family was buried under tight security measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Askari said that he was determined to find ways to preserve the memory of the family. “I will not let them be forgotten in silence,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/28/world/middleeast/iran-protester-deaths.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 02:10:37 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>