<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:48:21 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How Greenland Is Reacting to Trump’s ThreatsHow Greenland Is Reacting to Trump’s Threats</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/video/world/europe/100000010642168/how-greenland-is-reacting-to-trumps-threats.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/13/arts/RV_Thumbnail-1/RV_Thumbnail-1--facebookJumbo.jpg?video-overlay" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Our reporter Jeffrey Gettleman is on the ground in Greenland, seeing how people have reacted to Trump’s desire to take it over. He and our senior writer Katrin Bennhold discuss what Greenland means to the United States, Denmark and Greenlanders.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/video/world/europe/100000010642168/how-greenland-is-reacting-to-trumps-threats.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 09:09:03 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran Protests Quelled Since Deadly Crackdown, Residents Say</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/iran-protests-deadly-crackdown.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/16/multimedia/16int-iran-protests-lbpq/16int-iran-protests-lbpq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heavy police presence and deadly crackdowns on protesters appeared to have largely suppressed demonstrations in many cities and towns across Iran, according to several witnesses and a human rights group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For weeks, Iran has been convulsed by protests sparked by a collapsing economy and a currency in free fall, with the demonstrations snowballing into a broader antigovernment movement. The authorities have sought to quell the protests with brutal force and have plunged the country into a communications blackout that has made it difficult to know what’s happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four residents reached by The New York Times in the capital, Tehran, said that the streets had mostly been quiet of protests this week as the severity of the crackdown and the high number of casualties became clear. Security forces were deployed in large numbers to nearly every neighborhood, said the residents, who lived in different parts of the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All four spoke on the condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal. They said that it felt as if the capital was under martial law, with the typically bustling and traffic-clogged streets largely empty. Shops and restaurants in some areas were closed after 6 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is massive disappointment and disillusionment,” said another resident, who worked in central Tehran and also spoke on the condition of anonymity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been no large-scale protests documented in Iran since Sunday, according to Arina Moradi and Mina Khani, members of the Norway-based Hengaw Organization for Human Rights, which has been monitoring the demonstrations since they began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Moradi said in an interview that a heavy military and security presence remained across many cities and towns, with thousands of people having been detained. She said numerous universities had closed following protests last month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Israeli defense assessment found that the scale of protests had noticeably declined since Sunday, following the Iranian forces’ escalating use of live ammunition and the internet blackout, according to two Israeli officials who spoke to the Times on the condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the numbers continued to drop, they said, several Israeli intelligence officials monitoring Iran had concluded that the current wave of protests had effectively been subdued by the regime. The two officials noted, however, that the Israeli assessment had been complicated by the disruption of internet and telephone services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensions across Iran and the region have been high after Mr. Trump recently declared he was prepared to intervene to protect protesters, including potential military strikes against the country, U.S. officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel and several Arab nations have urged President Trump not to strike Iran, a senior U.S. official said. Many Gulf States worry that an attack could destabilize the region and jeopardize their reputations as safe hubs for business and tourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kremlin said on Friday that President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia offered to mediate so as to ensure regional stability after speaking with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and President Masoud Pezeshkian of Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The situation in the region is extremely tense,” a Kremlin spokesman, Dmitri S. Peskov, told reporters on Friday, adding that Mr. Putin was trying to facilitate a de-escalation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, the Iranian authorities have stepped back from threats to execute protesters, following international condemnation and the looming possibility of U.S. military action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But regional analysts note that Tehran is drawing a line between ordinary demonstrators and those it labels “rioters” or “terrorists” purportedly backed by foreign powers. Experts say this careful framing is intended to intimidate the population and discourage further protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has been instilling fear into protesters by sending text messages warning families not to let their children go out into the streets. Other messages have urged people to report suspicious activities or encouraged them to attend pro-government rallies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a screenshot shared by a resident with The New York Times, a text message asserting to be from the intelligence branch of Iran’s powerful Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps said it had received more than 400,000 calls to a hotline for reporting “terrorist networks,” and that they had been “identified and dismantled.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government’s violent crackdown has had an especially chilling effect on the protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witnesses said security forces had fired on unarmed demonstrators at close range. More than 2,600 people have been killed since protests began, according to the Washington-based Human Rights Activists News Agency. The Norway-based Iran Human Rights group said that more than 3,400 people had been killed and thousands of others injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Mr. Trump said the United States was “locked and loaded” to protect Iranian protesters, whom he later urged to take over government institutions, saying U.S. support was imminent. Since then, Mr. Trump has announced that diplomatic talks with Iran were on, then off, and most recently said Iran had responded to his demands by halting the killing and execution of protesters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said on Thursday that President Trump and his team were “closely monitoring the situation” and that “all options remain on the table.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ronen Bergman and Paul Sonne contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/16/world/middleeast/iran-protests-deadly-crackdown.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:39:36 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Wall Street Turned Its Back on Climate Change</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/climate/how-wall-street-turned-its-back-on-climate-change.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/17/multimedia/17cli-wallstreet-01-fqhl/17cli-wallstreet-01-fqhl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Climate activists protest BlackRock in New York City in 2023.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/17/climate/how-wall-street-turned-its-back-on-climate-change.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:16:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Avalanches Across Austrian Alps Kill 8 Skiers in One Day</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/austria-alps-avalanches.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18xp-avalanches01-photo-mhpt/18xp-avalanches01-photo-mhpt-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A photo provided by the mountain rescue service in the Pongau region of Austria shows rescuers searching for avalanche victims on Saturday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/austria-alps-avalanches.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:00:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Can Davos Help Protect the Planet?</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-conference-sustainability.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19sp-Davos-QandA-inyt-01-tvql/19sp-Davos-QandA-inyt-01-tvql-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The town of Davos, Switzerland, site of the World Economic Forum’s annual meeting. Over the years, the event’s organizers have been working to reduce the environmental impact of the meeting.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-conference-sustainability.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:00:32 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>At Davos, Global Leaders Gather to Ponder the Future of a Messy World</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-world-economic-forum-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19sp-davos-lede-inyt-03-gphj/19sp-davos-lede-inyt-03-gphj-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Tens of thousands of Iranians have taken to the streets during the latest uprising, including an anti-government protest in Tehran.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/business/davos-world-economic-forum-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 01:00:44 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump’s Ultimatum to Europe</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/greenland-europe-tariffs-kyiv.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/19/multimedia/19int-theworld-greenland-denmark-promo-wtjz/19int-theworld-greenland-denmark-promo-wtjz-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump threatened heavy tariffs on countries standing between him and Greenland. E.U. leaders are scrambling for a response.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/greenland-europe-tariffs-kyiv.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:37:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>High-Speed Train Crash in Spain Leaves at Least 10 Dead</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/spain-high-speed-train-derailment.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-spain-derail-fkbl/18int-spain-derail-fkbl-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Emergency workers at the scene of the wreckage after two trains derailed in Adamuz, Spain, on Sunday.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/spain-high-speed-train-derailment.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:16:58 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>European Union Officials Lean Toward Negotiating, Not Retaliating, Over Trump Tariff Threat</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/european-union-respond-trump-greenland.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-tariffs-retaliate-fzkp/18int-tariffs-retaliate-fzkp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with the threat of punishing tariffs by President Trump if he does not get his way over acquiring Greenland, European Union leaders began to coalesce around a negotiation strategy on Sunday, without ruling out retaliatory taxes of their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump on Saturday had demanded a deal to buy Greenland, saying on social media that otherwise he would slap tariffs on a group of European nations, starting with 10 percent in February, then ramping up to 25 percent in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, ambassadors from across the 27-nation bloc met in Brussels to take stock of the situation. While those were just preliminary talks, they made a few things clear. Officials would rather negotiate than retaliate, for one. But they are also committed to protecting Greenland, an autonomous territory of Denmark, from being bought or taken over if that is not what its people want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration showed no signs of backing down. In an interview on NBC’s “Meet the Press,” Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent said that European leaders would eventually understand that American control of Greenland would be “best for Greenland, best for Europe and best for the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The European leaders will come around,” Mr. Bessent said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Washington continues to escalate its efforts, European officials could also consider hitting back, two diplomats familiar with the discussions said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials are entertaining the possibility of allowing a list of retaliatory tariffs worth 93 billion euros, or $107 billion — drawn up during last year’s trade war — to take effect in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And some members of the European Parliament and Emmanuel Macron, the French president, have suggested that the European Union should activate an even more drastic tool: A never-used weapon intended to combat economic coercion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That option — officially called the “anti-coercion instrument,” and unofficially referred to as Europe’s trade “bazooka” — could be used to slap restrictions on big American technology companies or other service providers that conduct large amounts of business on the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be a first resort, the diplomats said, because it would risk escalating the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the European Union’s options are likely to be up for discussion later this week, when leaders gather in Brussels. António Costa, the president of the European Council, which gives the European Union political direction, announced on Sunday that he had “decided to convene an extraordinary meeting” of European leaders in the coming days. An E.U. official added that the meeting might be in person, and that it could take place on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such a session would allow prime ministers and presidents from across the bloc to discuss how they might respond to Mr. Trump. It would also come just as, or before, many European policymakers head to Davos, Switzerland, for the annual World Economic Forum. Mr. Trump is also planning to attend, creating a chance for conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many European leaders are still hoping they might be able to talk things out, discussions have essentially been futile so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has been hesitant to retaliate against the United States, in part because it relies on America for military technologies and support for NATO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Brando Benifei, a member of the European Parliament and the chair of its delegation for U.S. relations, said that calculus may be shifting, in part because popular opinion in Europe has turned more critical of the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A lot of people are saying that we are clearly over a red line,” he said in an interview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain spoke to Mr. Trump on Sunday and told him that “applying tariffs on allies for pursuing the collective security of NATO allies is wrong,” a Downing Street spokesman said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy’s prime minister, Giorgia Meloni, told reporters on Sunday that she had also spoken to Mr. Trump and called the proposed tariffs a “mistake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Rutte, the secretary-general of NATO, said on social media that he, too, had spoken with Mr. Trump about Greenland, but provided few details, saying only that “we will continue working on this” and that he looked forward to seeing Mr. Trump at Davos this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The White House did not immediately comment on the spate of calls, which come a day after Mr. Trump’s announcement of new tariffs was met with unified outrage by U.S. allies. Several of those allies, including Britain, France and Germany, released a forceful joint statement with Denmark on Sunday that decried the tariff threats, saying that they “undermine transatlantic relations and risk a dangerous downward spiral.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The co-signers of the statement, all NATO countries, said they would continue to stand in solidarity with Greenland and vowed to remain “united and coordinated in our response.” The statement was later endorsed by several other European countries, including Iceland, Latvia and Lithuania.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/european-union-respond-trump-greenland.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 14:56:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Here’s What to Know About the Protests in Iran</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/article/iran-protests-inflation-currency.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/03/multimedia/03int-iran-demonstrations-fmct/03int-iran-demonstrations-fmct-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A deadly crackdown by Iran’s government appeared to have largely suppressed protests that began in late December over economic woes but broadened into a mass movement challenging the country’s authoritarian clerical rulers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A communication blackout and a flow of disinformation have made it hard to independently assess what is going on inside Iran. But on Sunday, state media reported plans for a limited, gradual return of internet services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests on the streets of Tehran, the capital, have been largely stamped out in recent days, according to several witnesses and a human rights group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of people have been killed, including security forces, according to a senior Iranian health ministry official, as the demonstrations were brutally repressed by Iranian authorities. Eyewitnesses and human rights groups say government forces fired on protesters in cities across the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has repeatedly threatened to intervene militarily in Iran to stop the killing of protesters, and on Saturday said the country needed “new leadership.” But he has also expressed willingness to negotiate with the Iranian government, and there is little clarity on what the United States might do next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, Iran’s supreme leader, alleged that the United States had “launched” the protests “to serve their own objectives.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But the Iranian nation defeated them,” Mr. Khamenei told supporters in Tehran, according to Iranian state media. He called Mr. Trump a “criminal” because of “the casualties, the damage and the false accusations against the people of Iran.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s economy has been under sustained pressure for years, largely as a result of U.S. and European sanctions tied to its nuclear ambitions. A 12-day war with Israel this past June, which the United States joined to bomb Iranian nuclear facilities, further drained the country’s financial resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the currency plunged against the U.S. dollar in late December, amid persistently high inflation, merchants and university students staged days of protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the rallies grew, the protests became a broader criticism of the rule of Iran’s theocratic government. Across social media and television, protesters were seen chanting slogans including “Death to the dictator” and “Iranians, raise your voice, shout out for your rights.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonstrations spread to dozens of cities across Iran, according to tracking by the U.S.-based Institute for the Study of War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government initially signaled a willingness to listen to protesters and announced plans to provide most citizens with a monthly payment equivalent to about $7. But Iranian officials then hardened their stance, an echo of previous rounds of unrest when the authorities used mass arrests and violence to suppress demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Iranian government has accused some protesters of attacking government property, mosques and other buildings. Fars, a news agency affiliated with Iran’s Revolutionary Guards Corps, has attributed some of the unrest to armed agitators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: As of Jan. 8. Shows protests since Dec. 29. Source: Institute for the Study of War and AEI's Critical Threats Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Samuel Granados/The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting information about the protests and ensuing crackdown is difficult because of the near-total shutdown of the internet and cellphone calls. In recent days, however, there have been periods when some Iranians appear to have been able to make calls abroad or briefly get on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, several state affiliated news outlets said the government would begin gradually reconnecting communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fars news agency, affiliated with Iran’s Revolutionary Guards, said text messages were working again. It said the government would soon begin allowing the use of Iran’s “domestic internet” — the websites and social media platforms the state has effectively walled off from the global internet. In a “final stage,” it said, access to the broader internet would eventually be reopened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s state agency, IRNA, has also said that residents will again be able to use Google search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human rights groups have struggled to reach their contacts inside Iran and follow the methodology they normally use to verify information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these continuing difficulties, human rights groups say they have counted thousands dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than 3,000 protesters and 166 security forces have been killed since the protests began, according to the U.S.-based Human Rights Activists News Agency. The group is still working to verify more than 4,000 other reported deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran Human Rights, a group based in Norway, said more than 3,400 people had been killed and thousands more injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Witnesses have described seeing security forces firing on unarmed demonstrators at close range and snipers firing into crowds from rooftops in downtown Tehran. Videos uploaded by opposition activists on social media have shown families huddled over bloodied corpses in unzipped body bags, while footage on Iranian state television has shown body bags in a morgue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brutal crackdown appears to have had a chilling effect on the demonstrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been no large-scale protests documented in Iran since Sunday, according to the Norway-based Hengaw Organization for Human Rights, which has been monitoring the demonstrations. A heavy military and security presence remains across many cities and towns, and thousands of people have been detained, according to the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump said on Wednesday that he had been told that planned executions of protesters would not go ahead and that the killing in Iran had stopped, without offering further details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But analysts say the Iranian government is increasingly trying to draw a distinction between ordinary protesters and those whom it calls rioters and terrorists, backed by foreign powers. That nuance of messaging, the analysts said, was intended to put pressure on citizens and dissuade them from protesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s chief justice, Gholam-Hossein Mohseni-Ejei, said on Thursday that the prosecution of “rioters” would be carried out swiftly, according to the state broadcaster, while Iran’s attorney general, Mohammad Movahedi Azad, said last week that rioters would be considered an “enemy of God,” a charge that could carry the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We do not seek to lead the country toward war,” Mr. Khamenei, the supreme leader, said on Saturday. “But we will not let domestic criminals go unpunished.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts say the unrest shows that many Iranians consider the Islamic Republic to be more interested in self-preservation than in improving their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ali Vaez, Iran project director for the International Crisis Group, a research institution, said the Iranian government was “only buying time until the next round of confrontation between the state and society.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s government is weakened on the international stage and dealing with the fear of another round of U.S. or Israeli military strikes. Threats from Mr. Trump have been especially resonant after the capture of Venezuela’s president, Nicolás Maduro, early this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has said the United States is “locked and loaded and ready to go” if the Iranian government used lethal force against demonstrators, but he has yet to follow through on that threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on Saturday, he told Politico that “it’s time to look for new leadership in Iran” — a statement that will surely sound ominous after the capture of Mr. Maduro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic and Republican lawmakers have expressed wariness about American interference in Iran, which would most likely lead to a forceful reaction from Iranian authorities, possibly by targeting U.S. and Israeli military bases. Israel and Arab nations have asked Mr. Trump to postpone any plans for an American attack on Iran, amid fears it could lead to a wider regional conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has also left the door open to diplomacy with Iran, but it is unclear what ground any negotiations would cover. Talks on Iran’s nuclear program have stalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said on Thursday that Mr. Trump and his team were “closely monitoring the situation” and that “all options remain on the table.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aurelien Breeden and Sanjana Varghese contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/article/iran-protests-inflation-currency.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 05:43:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>The Biggest Challenge in Venezuela? Forget the Oil, It’s Stocking the Fridge.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/venezuela-economy-food-prices.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-venezuela-economy-jvhk/18int-venezuela-economy-jvhk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nair Granado rushed to buy groceries as soon as she got her $60 paycheck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She knew it wouldn’t be enough to fill the pantry in her home on the eastern fringes of Caracas, Venezuela’s capital. Still, she worried that, before long, her earnings would not be enough to cover even the basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Prices are rising every day,” said Ms. Granado, 33, a lab receptionist living in a sprawling working-class neighborhood with her two children. “It’s completely out of control.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After more than a decade in crisis, Venezuela is no stranger to food shortages, high prices and economic pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the U.S. military raid that removed Venezuela’s leader, Nicolás Maduro, has plunged the South American nation into a chaotic new chapter of political and economic uncertainty, setting off a new wave of inflation and currency woes pushing basic grocery items out of the reach of many Venezuelans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Granado, on a recent weekday, could still afford to buy flour and half a carton of eggs. But she did not even dream of buying meat — at more than $9 per pound, the price had nearly doubled in only a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You really have to find ways to be frugal, to make your salary stretch,” Ms. Granado said. “It’s getting harder to buy things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic turmoil is now threatening to deepen a yearslong humanitarian crisis in Venezuela, where more than 70 percent of people already live in poverty, according to a survey by a group of leading universities in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new affordability crisis is hitting Venezuelans especially hard because many have already been living on the edge of hunger for years, said Phil Gunson, a senior analyst with the International Crisis Group, a research organization, who has lived in Venezuela for over two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They’ve sold everything they could, they’ve tightened their belts until there are no more holes left,” Mr. Gunson said. “So there’s nothing left to fall back on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the core of the sharp rise in food costs is Venezuela’s dependence on the U.S. dollar, widely used in everyday transactions because it is typically less volatile than the country’s own currency, the bolívar. When Venezuela’s economy, once Latin America’s richest, spiraled deeper into crisis in 2019, driven by government mismanagement and exacerbated by U.S. sanctions, many people began to save, spend and charge in U.S. dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, even though the country’s economy is not formally “dollarized,” Venezuelans today rely on U.S. dollars for their daily spending. Vendors often buy from suppliers in dollars, so they peg prices to the currency. And they typically charge higher prices if buyers want to pay in Venezuelan bolívars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New U.S. sanctions over the past year have also forced Venezuela to sell less oil on the global market, which has reduced the volume of dollars circulating in its economy and made the currency more valuable. Now, anxiety about Venezuela’s economic future has sent the value of the dollar soaring, effectively doubling local prices of staples like meat, cheese and milk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Central Bank of Venezuela sets an official exchange rate, but most people rely on an unofficial rate called the “parallel dollar,” which reflects what dollars actually sell for on the street. This past week, the unofficial value of the dollar peaked at twice the official rate. It has since stabilized, but remains well above the official rate — and grocery store prices have not fallen in step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the incomes of Venezuelans, who are mostly paid in bolívars, “have gone up in smoke” as the value of the bolívar has dropped, said José Guerra, an economist and professor at the Central University of Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So we have a case of an economy that is experiencing extremely high inflation and, at the same time, may be entering an economic recession,” he added, estimating inflation could reach 2,000 percent this year. (The Venezuelan government does not publish official economic statistics and has persecuted economists tracking inflation.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venezuela’s minimum monthly wage, eroded by a decade of inflation and not adjusted in years, is now equivalent to roughly 50 cents. The government has tried to plug the gap, in part, by paying public-sector workers bonuses, though these have also diminished in value as the currency continues to wither.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are signs the United States is already brokering deals for the sale of Venezuelan oil, which could help stave off an economic disaster in the country and inject critical dollars into its economy. But, in the short term, this potential economic lifeline is a long way from helping ordinary Venezuelans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A survey by Gallup showed that last year, three in five Venezuelans struggled at times to afford food, among the highest rates in Latin America and the Caribbean. Even among the wealthiest 20 percent of Venezuela’s population, more than half said they were finding it difficult to pay for groceries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, soup kitchens and other community projects that once fed those in need have also been forced to close, as Mr. Maduro targeted nongovernmental groups with restrictive new rules. The government does deliver basic food baskets to the poor, but this welfare program is plagued by frequent and lengthy delays that can leave families without provisions for months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Venezuela’s interim government is focused on its new client-like relationship with the Trump administration, many Venezuelans are simply trying to figure out ways to stretch their dwindling purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johana Paredes, 30, said she was used to rationing the month’s groceries for her family of four. But the new sharp increase in food prices has made it difficult to buy even essential items that were, until recently, within reach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This past week, we couldn’t do any grocery shopping,” Ms. Paredes said, showing the scant supplies in her tin-roofed home in Los Teques, an hour outside Caracas. “That’s why there aren’t even potatoes,” she added. “Before, we were rich and we didn’t even know it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Caracas, shoppers toured the stalls of the city’s most iconic municipal market hunting for a bargain, as vendors shouted prices in dollars and inflated them in bolívars. Leaning on the counter of the butcher shop where he works, Jesús Balza, 50, said customers were buying less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are only spending on necessities,” he said. “Whoever used to buy a kilo of cheese is now buying half.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was on full display in Valencia, a city in central Venezuela, as shoppers walked out of supermarkets with half-empty bags. Marilsa Mendoza spent her budget of 13,000 bolívars, the equivalent of $35, on only a few necessities: flour, rice, pasta, oil and butter. Until a few weeks ago, she was able to buy far more for the same amount. “Everything is terrible, more or less double the price,” said Ms. Mendoza, 52, a hot dog vendor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has outlined grand plans to revive Venezuela’s oil industry, vowing to strike a series of deals that would bring American investment into the sector. The main engine of the economy has decayed after years of mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while there are early signs that these plans may be taking shape, it is not yet clear whether this financial lifeline will ultimately materialize and fix Venezuela’s broken economy over the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Venezuelans long ago lost faith in their government’s ability to improve their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will whatever oil deals are in the works “actually benefit Venezuela,” asked Mr. Gunson, the analyst. “Only time will tell,” he added. “Right now, all we have is Trump saying that he’s taking the oil and he’s going to sell it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As leaders in Caracas and Washington wrestle over Venezuela’s future, Ms. Paredes said she was holding out hope that real transformation would soon begin to reach people like her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We try to stay positive, believing that things will really change,” she said. “Because honestly, we don’t see any improvement. Everything just keeps getting worse.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Tibisay Romero, María Victoria Fermín, Maria Ramírez and Patricia Sulbarán.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/venezuela-economy-food-prices.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 04:19:48 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>After Trump Reignites a Trade War Over Greenland, Europe Weighs Going All-Out</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/greenland-us-trade-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-europe-tariffs-assess-01-gblw/18int-europe-tariffs-assess-01-gblw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a single post on Saturday night, President Trump upended months of progress on trade negotiations with an ultimatum that puts Europe on a crash course with the United States — long its closest ally and suddenly one of its biggest threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Truth Social post, Mr. Trump demanded a deal to buy Greenland, saying that otherwise he would slap tariffs on a group of European nations, first 10 percent in February, then 25 percent in June.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It appeared to leave little room for Europe to maneuver or negotiate in a harsh and combative era of geopolitics. It also left Europe with few options to counter Mr. Trump without repercussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European leaders are loath to accept the forced takeover of an autonomous territory that is controlled by Denmark, a member of both NATO and the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials and outside analysts increasingly argue that Europe will need to respond to Mr. Trump with force, most likely by hitting back on trade. But doing so could come at a heavy cost both to the bloc’s economy and to its security, since Europe remains heavily reliant on the United States for support through NATO and in Russia’s war with Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We either fight a trade war, or we’re in a real war,” said Jacob Funk Kirkegaard, a senior fellow at Bruegel, a research institute in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europeans have spent more than a year insisting that Greenland is not for sale and have constantly repeated that the fate of the massive northern island must be decided by its people and by Denmark. Last week, a group of European nations sent personnel to Greenland for military exercises — a show of solidarity that may have triggered Mr. Trump, since the same nations are the ones to be slapped with tariffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercises were intended to reinforce Europe’s commitment to policing the Arctic. Mr. Trump has insisted that the United States needs to own Greenland to improve security in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that sense, the exercises were part of an ongoing effort to placate Mr. Trump. For weeks, officials across Europe had dismissed Mr. Trump’s threats to take Greenland, even by military force, as unlikely. Many saw them more as negotiating tactics and hoped that they could satisfy the American president with a willingness to beef up defense and spending on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Trump’s fixation on owning the island and his escalating rhetoric is crushing European hopes that appeasement and dialogue will work. Facing the reality that a negotiated compromise is less and less likely, Europeans are now racing to figure out how to respond to Mr. Trump’s pressure campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within hours of the post, members of the European Parliament announced that they will freeze the ratification of the trade deal that Mr. Trump and Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, struck last summer. And members of European Parliament are openly calling for trade retaliation. Ambassadors from across the 27-nation bloc will gather in Brussels for an emergency meeting at 5 p.m. on Sunday, diplomats said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitting back is complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has a trade weapon specifically created to defend against political coercion quickly and forcefully, and as Mr. Trump’s threats sank in, policymakers argued that this is the time to wield it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool — officially called the “anti-coercion instrument,” unofficially called Europe’s trade “bazooka” — could be used to slap limitations on big American technology companies or other service providers that do large amounts of business on the continent. But using it would sharply ratchet up trans-Atlantic tensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Europe has spent the past year avoiding such escalation, and for a reason. The continent remains deeply reliant on the United States for NATO protection and for support against Russia in the war on Ukraine, so a full-on trade war could have consequences on other fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The question is — how far do you want to go?” said Penny Naas, an expert on European public policy at the German Marshall Fund think tank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;European leaders are still hoping that they might be able to talk things out. Ms. von der Leyen struck an accommodating tone in a social media post on Saturday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Dialogue remains essential, and we are committed to building on the process begun already last week between the Kingdom of Denmark and the U.S.,” she wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But she also warned that tariffs would “risk a dangerous downward spiral.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, talks have been all but futile. Foreign policy officials from Denmark and Greenland met with Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Vice President JD Vance in Washington last week. Afterward, the Danes and Greenlanders acknowledged that the two sides remained at an impasse, but expressed hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two sides, they noted, had agreed to set up a high-level working group to work through their issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That optimism was quickly snuffed out when the White House said that the group was meant to work on America’s “acquisition” of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is just all brute force,” Ms. Naas said. “The president really wants Greenland, and he’s not backing off of it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenland shows little sign of wanting to be acquired, by money or by military force. Greenlanders have at times chafed at Danish power, but polls and interviews indicate that most don’t want to give up their free education and universal health care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Mr. Trump takes on a more aggressive posture, European leaders are growing blunter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Macron, the president of France, wrote on social media on Saturday night that “no intimidation nor threat will influence us.” Ulf Kristersson, the prime minister of Sweden, wrote that “we will not let ourselves be blackmailed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Keir Starmer, the prime minister of Britain — which, like Norway, is not in the European Union, but was listed among the countries that will be slapped with tariffs — called Mr. Trump’s tariff move “completely wrong.” Mr. Starmer has carefully cultivated a positive relationship with the White House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We will of course be pursuing this directly with the U.S. administration,” he said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/greenland-us-trade-war.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 13:02:35 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>$1 Billion in Cash Buys a Permanent Seat on Trump’s ‘Board of Peace’</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-israel-board-kzcl/18int-israel-board-kzcl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump’s “Board of Peace” is billing itself as a new international peacekeeping body — and permanent membership won’t come cheap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump is inviting countries to join beyond a three-year term, if they’re willing to cough up more than a billion dollars in cash within the board’s first year, according to a draft of the board’s charter reviewed by The New York Times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while the board was conceived as part of Mr. Trump’s plan to oversee Gaza, there is no mention of Gaza in the charter. That omission added to speculation that the group may have a broader mandate to cover other conflicts and could even be aimed at creating a U.S.-dominated alternative to the United Nations Security Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Security Council resolution adopted in November 2025 endorsed Mr. Trump’s plan for ending the Israel-Hamas war in Gaza and welcomed the establishment of the board as a transitional administration that would set the framework and coordinate funding for Gaza’s redevelopment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The enclave was devastated during the two years of war. About 80 percent of the buildings in Gaza have been damaged or destroyed, according to the United Nations. Many of the roughly 2 million residents are still living in tents among millions of tons of rubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board’s charter was sent out with invitations to potential members over the weekend. A copy reviewed by The Times was verified by an official on the condition of anonymity because of the delicate diplomacy. News of the $1 billion buy-in was previously reported by Bloomberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, the White House announced the board’s members would include Secretary of State Marco Rubio, Jared Kushner, Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, and Ajay Banga, the head of the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several countries said they had received invitations to join, including Argentina, Canada, Egypt and Turkey. King Abdullah II of Jordan has also been invited, the Jordanian Foreign Ministry announced on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump, who is to chair the board, said in a post on Truth Social last week that it will be “the Greatest and Most Prestigious Board ever assembled at any time, any place,” though much about it remained unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The charter appears to outline a much more ambitious role for the board than the one described in Mr. Trump’s plan for Gaza, published in October 2025, as well as the subsequent Security Council resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board’s mission, according to the charter, is to seek “to promote stability, restore dependable and lawful governance, and secure enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict” and “to undertake peace-building functions in accordance with international law.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The preamble emphasizes the need for what it calls “a more nimble and effective international peace-building body” and laments that “too many approaches to peace-building foster perpetual dependency and institutionalize crisis rather than leading people beyond it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the charter, the board is expected to meet for voting at least annually, and expenses are to be funded through voluntary contributions from member states or other sources. The charter does not elaborate on the peacekeeping efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the “Board of Peace,” the White House on Friday also outlined a “Gaza Executive Board” that would help liaise with a committee of Palestinian technocrats appointed to administer daily life in Gaza. The Gaza executive board includes Ali al-Thawadi, a senior Qatari official, and Hakan Fidan, the Turkish foreign minister, among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The composition of the executive board prompted the office of Israel’s prime minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, to issue a rare public protest against the Trump administration, saying it “was not coordinated with Israel and runs contrary to its policy.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While an Israeli businessman is on the executive board, Israeli government officials have not been named to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miri Regev, an Israeli minister from Mr. Netanyahu’s conservative Likud party, told Israel’s public broadcaster, Kan, on Saturday that Israel objected to participation of Qatar and Turkey, adding, “Prime Minister Netanyahu will do everything to change that decision.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relations between Israel and Turkey have oscillated over the decades, but since the war in Gaza, set off by Hamas’s attack against Israel in October 2023, they have deteriorated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Recep Tayyip Erdogan of Turkey has downgraded ties with Israel, repeatedly compared Mr. Netanyahu to Adolf Hitler and praised Hamas, while hosting its officials. Israeli officials are anxious about the prospect of Turkey gaining influence over Gaza’s future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Israel struck Qatar in September 2025 in a failed attempt to kill Hamas leaders meeting there, Mr. Netanyahu defended the action and lashed out against the country for giving what he called “safe haven” to the militant group, even as Qatar was trying to negotiate a cease-fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qatari officials have said they hosted Hamas officials at the request of the U.S. government to facilitate channels of communication. Mr. Netanyahu has in the past relied on Qatar to send millions of dollars a month to Gaza, a policy that was intended to keep the peace but that also helped prop up Hamas’s rule over the territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel’s priority is seeing Gaza demilitarized. Hamas so far has not agreed to lay down its arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabby Sobelman contributed reporting from Rehovot, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/trump-board-of-peace-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 05:37:01 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Come Help Us’: Wildfires Grip Parts of Chile, Killing at Least 16</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/chile-wildfires.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-chile-fires-fqvk/18int-chile-fires-fqvk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least 16 people have died as ferocious wildfires gripped Southern Chile, burning homes and thousands of hectares of land, the authorities said Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blazes destroyed entire neighborhoods in the southern region of Biobío, according to local authorities, forcing the evacuation of thousands of people to temporary shelters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage captured expansive flames lashing at buildings, with dense smoke obscuring the horizon under a heavy orange haze. Collapsed buildings and carbonized cars lined the scorched streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I am devastated,” said Rodrigo Vera, the mayor of Penco, a city of about 50,000 people, 250 miles South of Santiago, as he described a scene of desperation on Chilean radio on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Vera said that some firefighters were trapped in the fire, and that he had seen others crying on the floor of the command post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 20,000 people had to leave their homes, Mr. Vera said, and emergency crews evacuated patients from a hospital that came under threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mayor issued an appeal to the national government. “I beg you please from the deepest part of my heart: Come help us,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early hours of Sunday, Chile’s president, Gabriel Boric, declared a “state of catastrophe” for the regions of Ñuble and Biobío. That allowed the government to deploy the army to these areas, where the fires had already affected over 24,000 hectares of land, about 60,000 acres, according to the forestry commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile’s public security minister, Luis Cordero, put the death toll at 16 on Sunday. “There are people who are yet to be located, many of whom may be in shelters,” he said. “The information will be updated progressively as family members report back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile’s national forestry commission said that there are 24 fires actively being fought nationwide, with the majority in the southern forests. The latest surge of fires has been exacerbated by a heat wave in southern Chile, where temperatures were expected to reach 100 degrees Fahrenheit (38 Celsius) today, and winds of up to 55 miles per hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile battles wildfires every summer, with most of the fires concentrated over the hottest months, January and February. Last summer, there were 3,018 fires in the country, and this year there have already been 2,825, with the hottest period of the year only beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this summer season, the government announced in November a budget of about $180 million to fight the fires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, the deadliest wildfires in Chile’s history ravaged the country’s central coastline, killing 135 people and destroying or damaging 8,188 homes. On that occasion, high winds and prolonged drought contributed to the fires sweeping through the hills and causing widespread devastation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wildfires have also gripped the Argentine Patagonia in recent weeks, engulfing nearly 30,000 hectares since mid-December, according to Greenpeace. Though they did not claim any lives, the fires burned through native forests, destroying homes across multiple communities and killing wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucía Cholakian Herrera contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/americas/chile-wildfires.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:09:59 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Syrian Government and Kurdish-led Force Agree to Unite After Clashes</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-ceasefire.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-syria-explainer-hkmp/18int-syria-explainer-hkmp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Syrian government and a Kurdish-led militia agreed on Sunday to an immediate cease-fire, after weeks of on-and-off clashes, and to a full integration of the militia into the national military forces, according to state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not the first time that the government and the Kurdish-led Syrian Democratic Forces, or S.D.F., have reached such a deal. But the 14-point agreement came after two days of significant territorial advances by government forces into areas long held by the S.D.F., which left the force in a significantly weaker negotiating position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the deal, the S.D.F. agreed to hand over the northern province of Raqqa and the eastern province of Deir al Zour. That will leave only one province, northeastern Hasakah, in S.D.F. hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government institutions in a largely autonomous northeastern region dominated by Kurds will also come under the central government’s authority, according to the agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government will also take control of all the country’s gas and oil fields, nearly all of which have been under S.D.F. control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Muhammad Haj Kadour contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/middleeast/syria-kurds-ceasefire.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 12:14:55 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Bleak Times in Copenhagen: Danes Feel Betrayed and Bewildered by Trump</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/18/multimedia/18int-denmark-mood-02-ptvk-copy/18int-denmark-mood-02-ptvk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henrik Bager, a Danish soldier who served with Americans in Iraq and Afghanistan, said President Trump’s vow to get Greenland from Denmark and his insults about Denmark’s military were “a punch to the gut.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rasmus Jarlov, a voluble center-right member of the Danish Parliament and the chairman of its Defense Committee, said that “we know full well that the Americans can destroy us,” but should Mr. Trump, who has not ruled out military force, attack a fellow NATO ally, “of course we will fight back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next breath, Mr. Jarlov said it was “absolutely so weird to be uttering something like that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Casper O. Jensen, a Danish pollster who has lived in the United States and calls it “close to his heart,” sounded like a jilted lover. “I thought we had a really good thing going on,” he said. “Apparently not.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are bleak times in Copenhagen, where Danes say they feel betrayed, bewildered and frightened by Mr. Trump’s threats to take over Greenland, the semiautonomous Danish territory and a source of national identity and pride. Greenland, 50 times the size of Denmark, has long made the tiny Nordic nation more of a player on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We’re not small when you add Greenland,” said David Trads, a political commentator and the author of three books on the United States, including his most recent, “America Turns the Clock Back.” “It makes us more important.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump’s view is that the United States needs to take over Greenland because Russia and China pose a security threat in the Arctic, and because the island is essential for the “Golden Dome” missile shield he wants to build to protect the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark, NATO allies and most security experts say Mr. Trump already has all the access to Greenland that he needs given existing treaties and the willingness of Denmark, long one of the most pro-American countries in Europe, to do anything — short of giving up Greenland — that the president wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past week in Copenhagen, where wall-to-wall television coverage of the crisis seemed to match the mood of the dark Scandinavian winter, Danes pored over every utterance from Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Saturday, thousands of Danes had packed Copenhagen’s City Hall Square before marching to the U.S. Embassy in protest, while hundreds demonstrated in Nuuk, Greenland’s capital. Hours later, Mr. Trump said he was putting new tariffs on Denmark and other European nations until they come to the negotiating table to sell him Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Danes have been particularly stunned by Mr. Trump’s taunts that Denmark relies on “two dog sleds” to defend the Arctic island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s like fifth graders bullying the small guy in the corner,” said Company Sgt. Maj. Bager, the Danish soldier who served in Iraq and Afghanistan. Danes in his unit died during his 2009 deployment to Helmand Province in Afghanistan, he said, and the rhetoric from the White House hurts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“First time you get disappointed, then you get angry, and then you start feeling sad, you know?” he said. “I can’t remember when we haven’t been with you. You asked us to go. We went.” You asked us “to send airplanes, we sent airplanes.” Denmark, he said, “never said no.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam Price, the creator of “Borgen,” a Danish TV political drama that became an international hit, set its fourth and final season in Greenland. In episodes that aired in 2022 in the United States, a geopolitical struggle unfolds between the United States, China and Russia after large reserves of oil are discovered on the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Price likes to take real events and push them beyond what has actually happened. But in an interview this past week, he said that had he pitched a story line to Netflix that an American president was vowing to get Greenland from Denmark “one way or another” — the exact words of Mr. Trump — “I would have been laughed out of the pitching room.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They would have said, ‘It’s too much, it is too crazy,’” Mr. Price said in his Copenhagen office, where a large photograph of sled dogs and icebergs in Greenland covers one wall. “I mean, you wouldn’t have an American president that would actually threaten a NATO ally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many Danes believe Mr. Trump wants to own Greenland because, as he put it to The New York Times in an interview this month, “that’s what I feel is psychologically needed for success.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaja Chemnitz, one of two members of Parliament who represent Greenland, said in an interview that “maybe you should take it up with his therapist if it’s a question of making sure that he feels better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Chemnitz, who said Greenlanders were having trouble sleeping for fear of an American invasion, was host last week to a bipartisan congressional delegation led by Senator Chris Coons, Democrat of Delaware, to Denmark. In her view, Mr. Trump is more interested in the minerals and oil in Greenland than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sentiment was echoed by Oliver Haagensen, 21, a medical student at Aarhus University, who was skating the other day at an outdoor rink in Copenhagen’s Christianshavn neighborhood. Like everyone else, he was keeping up with the news on Mr. Trump. “He knows that Russia and China want the minerals and oil, and he wants to get there first,” Mr. Haagensen said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was some short-lived relief in Copenhagen after a meeting on Wednesday in Washington, where Denmark’s foreign minister, Lars Lokke Rasmussen, emerged from talks with Vice President JD Vance and Secretary of State Marco Rubio. Mr. Rasmussen said that although a “fundamental disagreement” remained with Mr. Trump and that the American president “has this wish of conquering Greenland,” there would be a “working group” group to continue talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on Thursday, Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, told reporters that the Danes and Greenlanders had agreed “to continue to have technical talks on the acquisition of Greenland,” which Denmark and Greenland said was not the case at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trads, the political commentator, had been skeptical that the meeting would produce anything. On Wednesday over coffee near the Danish Parliament, he said that the only thing that Denmark had on its side against Mr. Trump was time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Danish government hopes that Mr. Trump’s party will lose the midterm elections, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If that doesn’t happen, then we’re just waiting for the three years to pass,” Mr. Trads said. “It’s a long time, but we don’t have anything else. So that’s the whole tactic, just to make sure it goes on and on and on, and somehow he is preoccupied with something else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark colonized Greenland in 1721, and over the centuries, Greenlanders often felt mistreated by the Danes, particularly by a past policy of forcing contraception on young women and girls. In recent decades, the island has moved to home rule. Denmark, which still sends the island of 56,000 people large economic subsidies, now supports its gradual path to independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been tensions along that road, but Mr. Trump has had the effect, Danes said, of pushing the former colonizer and the colonized closer together. “If we have to choose between the United States and Denmark here and now, we choose Denmark,” Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen of Greenland said last week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is extraordinary about Mr. Trump’s involvement, said Martin Breum, an Arctic expert and TV journalist and the author of “Cold Rush: The Astonishing True Story of the New Quest for the Polar North,” are the president’s repeated falsehoods about Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There is extreme consternation that your president appears completely immune to data, facts, arguments and common knowledge,” Mr. Breum said. “He continues to state what is obviously, factually wrong. This seems unbelievable to many people in this country. We cannot understand what is happening. We wonder what is next.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carsten Jensen, a prominent Danish novelist and the author of “We, The Drowned,” a work of historical fiction about a century of Danish seafaring, said he knew what was next if Europe did not stand together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m 100 percent convinced that Greenland will become American within a short time,” he said gloomily in an interview. “One day, there will be a lot of American military presence in the airport of Nuuk, and that’s it.” NATO will protest, he said, but he predicted it would not end the alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“European nations won’t break up NATO because of Greenland,” he said. “It’s too insignificant.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a less dark note, Anne Bech, 60, a schoolteacher who was volunteering last Wednesday at Copenhagen’s central library for a session of the Danish tradition of morgensang — communal morning singing — said the theme of songs for the day, about caring for others, had been selected long before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But today it’s even more important,” she said as retirees, students and people on their way to work filed in and picked up songbooks. “We’re very anxious about your president.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next half-hour, a chorus of voices, accompanied by a piano and flute, filled the library’s top floor. The lyrics at the end of Song No. 150 seemed fitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there’s winter darkness at my door&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m empty and sad like never before&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show me a way, just a tiny path&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;out of the darkness I’m caught in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa Abend contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/18/world/europe/denmark-greenland-trump.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 10:24:32 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>