<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:20:16 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Xi’s Purge of the Chinese Military</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/china-xi-military-purge-israel-hostage-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-theworld-china-general-01-qmwf-promo/27int-theworld-china-general-01-qmwf-promo-facebookJumbo-v2.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chinese politics is often a black box. Foreign leaders struggle to gauge what Beijing is thinking, be it about A.I. or Taiwan. So when it emerged this weekend that President Xi Jinping had pushed out the most senior general in the Chinese military command structure, it caught many by surprise. Today, my colleague Chris Buckley in Taipei writes about the fallout from Xi’s military purge — and how it might affect potential plans for a Taiwan invasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Chris Buckley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of generals have been toppled in President Xi Jinping’s unrelenting campaign against perceived corruption and disloyalty over the past three years. But this weekend’s downfall of Gen. Zhang Youxia, who had been the Chinese president’s chief deputy in the military, was of a different order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xi’s decision to oust Zhang and another top general means the Central Military Commission, the small committee that commands China’s armed forces, has only two members left: Xi himself and the officer he has used to oversee the purges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This move “represents the total annihilation of the high command,” said Christopher K. Johnson, a former C.I.A. analyst who follows Chinese elite politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 75, Zhang was old enough that Xi could have ushered him into retirement. Instead, Xi made him a public pariah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China’s defense ministry announced that he was under investigation for unspecified breaches of laws and political discipline. An editorial in the military’s official newspaper, the People’s Liberation Army Daily on Sunday hinted that Zhang was being accused of corruption, and, perhaps more important, of disloyalty to Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What prompted Xi to finally turn against Zhang is now a topic of fevered speculation in Beijing and beyond. Some believe Xi may have come to see him as too powerful, after the general’s own rivals were toppled in previous purges. Others believe Xi concluded that systemic corruption was so deep that he needed drastic surgery to clear the way for a new generation of commanders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still other allegations are more serious: The Wall Street Journal reported on Sunday, citing anonymous sources, that Zhang had been accused of leaking nuclear secrets to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does seem clear is that Zhang’s purge — the most dramatic in a wave of military purges that has unfolded since 2023 — has raised questions about China’s strategy toward Taiwan, at a time when China’s military has been severely diminished by Xi’s anti-corruption campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigations and disappearances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Xi became China’s leader in 2012, he moved quickly to shake up the military, which was rife with corruption and organizationally stuck in the past. Zhang was one of the commanders Xi picked to help lead this overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after a decade in charge, Xi seemed to conclude that some of his own handpicked protégés had been infected by the military’s corruption, and a new cycle of investigations and purges began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2023, waves of top commanders and officers in the Chinese military, and executives for arms manufacturers, have been removed from office and placed under investigation — or, in some cases, have disappeared from view without explanation. Investigations have taken down admirals, regional military commanders and members of the Central Military Commission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The investigations’ toll on the military was visible at a meeting last year of the Communist Party’s Central Committee, a council of top officials. Of the 44 uniformed officers appointed to the committee in 2022, 29 — roughly two-thirds — had been purged or were missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang had long seemed to be spared scrutiny. Xi kept him in office past retirement age, and made him his top vice chairman of the Central Military Commission — Xi’s eyes and ears in running the People’s Liberation Army’s forces day to day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lack of operational experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang being pushed out is especially significant because he was a celebrated war veteran, in a nation where few active commanders have experienced real combat. Zhang fought in China’s last war, a border conflict with Vietnam that began in 1979 and lasted years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xi seems to have calculated that in the longer term, his shake-up will make the military less corrupt, more loyal and more effective in pursuing his goals. But the disruptions caused by the purges could leave Xi less confident that his commanders are ready for combat, analysts say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s no one right now at the highest level who has operational experience or who is in charge of training and exercises,” said Shanshan Mei, a political scientist who studies China’s armed forces. “This is going to cut very deep.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it’s also not clear that the changes will lead to more restraint. Another former U.S. government official shared his worries about the potential consequences of purging one of the people who could speak candidly to Xi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zhang “could assess U.S. and Taiwan military capabilities objectively and explain to Xi Jinping what the military risks and costs of an operation to take Taiwan would be,” Drew Thompson, a former Pentagon official, wrote on Substack. “I worry about the consequences of someone other than Zhang Youxia providing Xi Jinping with military advice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read Chris’s full story here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggling to contain the fallout from his administration’s deadly actions in Minneapolis, President Trump sent a new official to oversee the immigration enforcement operation there and backed off his attacks on Minnesota’s governor, Tim Walz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following a phone call between the governor and the president, Walz’s office said the governor got Trump to agree to talk to federal officials about ensuring an independent investigation into the killings this month of Alex Pretti and Renee Good. Trump also agreed to look into reducing the number of federal agents in Minnesota, the governor’s office said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Guttenfelder, a New York Times photographer based in Minneapolis, was at the scene after Pretti’s killing on Saturday. Watch the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said yesterday that it had recovered the remains of Master Sgt. Ran Gvili, an Israeli police officer whose body was the last one held in Gaza. The retrieval closes a painful chapter for Israelis and also paves the way for the next phase of the cease-fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel announced that it would reopen the border between the Gaza Strip and Egypt within days. The move would allow Palestinians who fled the enclave during the two-year war to return home for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials in the Middle East are increasingly worried that the U.S. will strike Iran in the coming days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. faced dangerous cold after a heavy snowstorm that disrupted travel and killed at least 21 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large ferry sank in the southern Philippines, killing at least 18 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gunmen in Mexico opened fire on a crowded football field, killing 11 people. The shooting occurred in an area fought over by drug cartels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The E.U. will investigate Elon Musk’s X social media platform over A.I.-generated sexualized images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gold reached a record high as investors sought shelter from geopolitical uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Football: Who is the most important person at each Premier League club? Our reporters share their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Madison Keys, the defending Australian Open champion, lost to a fellow American, Jessica Pegula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cycling: Two kangaroos caused a major crash at the Tour Down Under race in Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the early years of the war in Ukraine, fighting slowed in the winter. Snow and mud made it more difficult for armored vehicles to get around. Now, as drone attacks dominate, the pace of fighting is intense year round, and the winter has unexpected effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trees are bare, their leaves no longer providing camouflage. Footprints in the snow are easy to spot from above. Lower temperatures make thermal cameras on drones more effective. So tactics have changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— An influencer set herself a goal of collecting 1,000 rejections for auditions and job applications, recording each “no” in a notebook. Now, rejection spreadsheets are popping up across social media. No rejection is too big or too small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afghanistan is better known for its repressive Taliban government than for tech innovation. But a crypto start-up there is building online payment tools that could transform humanitarian aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An app, HesabPay, allows instant transfers between digital wallets, bypassing banks and the Taliban. The U.N. has used it to deliver nearly $25 million to vulnerable Afghans returning home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is proving useful in other countries shattered by conflict. People in Syria are now receiving aid money in cryptocurrency through the app, and programs for Sudan and Haiti are in development. Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch: In the new season of “Bridgerton,” a fan favorite will step into the spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise: Forget about muscle mass as you age; focus on strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Repair: These are the essential tools to have in your home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bacon-and-egg pie is a rustic specialty from New Zealand, here zipped up with a mixture of sriracha and cream. It’s close in feeling to steak-and-kidney pie, that sturdy pub staple, and makes for terrific picnic fare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: Scale your recipes up or down with this helpful new tool and tips from New York Times Cooking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these islands?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Bahamas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aitutaki, Cook Islands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lakshadweep, India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Maldives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Buckley was our guest writer today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/china-xi-military-purge-israel-hostage-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:42:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NATO Chief Says Europe Is ‘Dreaming’ if It Thinks It Can Defend Itself Without U.S.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/nato-chief-europe-greenland-trump-us.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-greenland-nato-1-wzft/26int-greenland-nato-1-wzft-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Rutte, the secretary general of NATO, warned Europe on Monday that it could not defend itself without the United States in remarks aimed to address the growing worries that the United States and Europe are pulling apart over President Trump’s ambitions for Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If anyone thinks here again that the European Union, or Europe as a whole, can defend itself without the U.S., keep on dreaming,” Mr. Rutte told members of the European Parliament in Brussels. “You can’t. We can’t. We need each other.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte’s remarks followed days of anxiety that crested last week after President Trump said in a speech at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, that he would not seize Greenland, an autonomous Danish territory, backing off earlier threats. Mr. Trump used the same speech to belittle Europe, essentially saying that it wouldn’t exist without America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump had also threatened to impose additional tariffs on European countries that resisted his bid to control Greenland, but he backed away from those as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte, a former Dutch prime minister, has cultivated a chummy relationship with Mr. Trump, and that has raised some eyebrows in Europe. On Monday, he backed up the American president’s strategic vision for the Arctic and a stronger defense of Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also defended himself for helping ease Mr. Trump away from his escalating threats and for trying to lead the American president toward a compromise over the island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denmark’s and Greenland’s leaders have bristled at the notion that Mr. Trump and Mr. Rutte might be negotiating Greenland’s future behind their backs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Of course, I have no mandate to negotiate on behalf of Denmark, so I didn’t, and I will not,” he said. “That’s up to Denmark to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several members of the European Parliament pressed Mr. Rutte for more information on what exactly he had discussed with Mr. Trump last week and what it might mean for Denmark and Greenland, both of which have strongly rejected the idea of an American takeover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte wasn’t very specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He didn’t elaborate on the framework of a deal with NATO over Greenland’s future that Mr. Trump said last week he had reached. That announcement brought immense relief after months of repeated threats, though many across Europe are worried that Mr. Trump could change his mind again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte said that there were “two work streams going forward” that involved Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One was talks between NATO allies over a broader Arctic defense plan that would involve Greenland, a gigantic island that lies mostly in the Arctic Circle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other was a process involving representatives from the United States, Denmark and Greenland that started earlier this month in Washington and is continuing, Mr. Rutte said. Danish officials said that they held a meeting on Thursday in Washington about Greenland, but they declined to share any details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several Western officials have said that one possible compromise that NATO was discussing was that the United States would gain sovereign status for American bases in Greenland. The United States has kept military forces on the island since World War II, when Nazi Germany seized Denmark and the Danish ambassador to Washington struck an agreement with the United States to defend Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Mr. Rutte’s discussions with Mr. Trump last week, Danish leaders quickly made clear that any compromise on Greenland’s sovereignty remained “a red line.” Mr. Rutte, who was invited to attend a meeting of the Parliament’s security and defense committee, didn’t comment on the base-sovereignty idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several members of the European Parliament asked sharp questions on Monday, including Villy Sovndal, a Danish representative, who said, “We’re not going to give any square meter to any country because of threats.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout his remarks, Mr. Rutte praised Mr. Trump, joking that he knew that might irritate his audience. Mr. Trump’s bombastic speech last week in Davos deeply rattled Europe, especially his assertion, which struck many nations as insulting, that “without us, right now, you’d all be speaking German and a little Japanese, perhaps.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte’s remarks were more diplomatic. But he did emphasize that, more than 70 years after World War II, Europe was still dependent on American military might. He said that Europe would have to spend far more on defense than it was already spending to field its own formidable nuclear arsenal.“Forget that you can ever get there with 5 percent,” he said, referring to the 5 percent of gross domestic product that NATO members have pledged to spend on defense annually by 2035. “It will be 10 percent. You have to build up your own nuclear capability that cost billions and billions of euros.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if Europe really did try to go it alone, he added, “Hey, good luck.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also repeated Mr. Trump’s insistence that China and Russia were becoming a threat to Arctic security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is doing a lot of good stuff, I believe — I know, I’m irritating a lot of you again,” Mr. Rutte said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rutte said that when it came to Arctic defense, “I think he’s right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maya Tekeli contributed reporting from Nuuk, Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/europe/nato-chief-europe-greenland-trump-us.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:30:41 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Canadian Beluga Whales Could Find New Homes in United States</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/canada/canada-marineland-beluga-whales.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/world/26int-canada-whales/26int-canada-whales-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After threatening to euthanize about 30 beluga whales, Marineland, a shuttered Canadian aquatic park, is now likely to send the animals to marine facilities in the United States, the Canadian government said on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland, once a bustling tourist destination in Niagara Falls, Ontario, is headed toward bankruptcy and last year asked the federal government for financial help and approval to export the animals to a theme park in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joanne Thompson, Canada’s fisheries minister, turned down the request, largely because the animals would continue living in captivity, prompting Marineland to threaten to put down the whales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the whales would likely still be in captivity in the United States, Ms. Thompson said she had reconsidered her opposition and had conditionally approved Marineland’s new application to send the animals across the border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“My focus throughout has been the best interest of the whales and that is what has guided this decision,” Ms. Thompson said in a statement on Monday. She said she was awaiting more information from Marineland before granting final permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The minister’s office did not respond to questions regarding where the animals are likely to be sent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We extend our gratitude to the minister and the Canadian government for prioritizing the lives of these remarkable marine mammals,” a representative for Marineland said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland is also planning on sending its remaining four dolphins to the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camille Labchuk, executive director of Animal Justice, a Canadian animal rights nonprofit, said in a statement that the “the minister had little choice” but to approve the whale’s export, given the park’s threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, she said: “It is also essential to ensure the whales will not be bred in the US. These animals must be the last generation to suffer in captivity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada adopted legal restrictions in 2019 barring the breeding of captive whales and dolphins for entertainment purposes. The options for whales bred in captivity are limited, since they lack skills like hunting and social interaction, which animals in the wild possess in order to survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marineland, which has been closed to the public since 2024 following years of dwindling ticket sales, has been accused of animal abuse, charges that it has denied. The park is in the process of selling off its rides and is weighing offers to purchase its land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Founded in 1961 by a Slovenian immigrant, the park grew over the years into a popular destination that covered 1,000 acres and included an amusement park, dining and other animal enclosures, including one for bears.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/canada/canada-marineland-beluga-whales.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 17:29:30 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump Briefed on Intelligence Saying Iran’s Government Is Weaker</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-reports-iran-government.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26dc-iran01-photo-bcgw/26dc-iran01-photo-bcgw-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump has received multiple U.S. intelligence reports indicating that the Iranian government’s position is weakening, according to several people familiar with the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports signal that the Iranian government’s hold on power is at its weakest point since the shah was overthrown in the 1979 revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests that erupted late last year, according to the reports, shook elements of the Iranian government, especially as they reached into areas of the country that officials thought were strongholds of support for Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, Iran’s supreme leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the protests have died down, the government remains in a difficult position. Intelligence reports have repeatedly highlighted that in addition to the protests, Iran’s economy is historically weak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic hardship ignited sporadic protests in late December. As the demonstrations spread in January, the Iranian government found it had few options to ease the financial difficulties families were feeling. Officials resorted to a heavy handed crackdown that further alienated wide swaths of the population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. military has been building up its forces in the region, but it is not clear what steps the Trump administration may be considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump is consistently briefed on intelligence matters around the world,” Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, said in a statement. “It would be a dereliction of duty as commander in chief if he were not regularly briefed on these matters. With respect to Iran, President Trump continues to closely monitor the situation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump warned that he could strike Iran as the government’s bloody crackdown on the protests expanded. Still, his advisers have been divided on the benefits of strikes, particularly if they were simply symbolic strikes against elements of the government involved in the crackdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump then seemed to back down on any sort of immediate strike in support of the protests after the Iranian government called off a planned execution of a protester. Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel had also asked Mr. Trump to postpone an attack on Iran, according to a senior U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a broader campaign may have more appeal to some of Mr. Trump’s most hawkish aides and allies who see an opportunity to force out the country’s leadership. And Mr. Trump continues to hold out the threat of force, describing his buildup of naval forces in the region as an “armada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has also mused aloud about Iran’s nuclear program, delivering warnings and reminding the Iranian government of the strikes he ordered last year against its most heavily fortified research sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Senator Lindsey Graham, Republican of South Carolina, said that he had spoken with Mr. Trump in recent days about Iran and that he expected the president to fulfill his promise to help Iranians who had been protesting their government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The goal is to end the regime,” Mr. Graham said in a brief interview. “They may stop killing them today, but if they’re in charge next month, they’ll kill them then.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of Monday, the aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln, accompanied by three warships equipped with Tomahawk missiles, entered the U.S. Central Command’s area of responsibility in the western Indian Ocean, said a U.S. official who spoke on the condition of anonymity to discuss those details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the White House were to order a strike on Iran, the carrier could, in theory, take action within a day or two, military officials said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States has already sent a dozen additional F-15E attack planes to the region to strengthen strike aircraft numbers, according to U.S. officials. And the Pentagon has dispatched more Patriot and THAAD air defenses to the region to help protect American troops there from any retaliatory strikes by Iranian short- and medium-range missiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-range bombers based in the United States that could strike targets in Iran remain on a higher-than-usual alert status. The Pentagon heightened the alert status two weeks ago, when Mr. Trump requested options to respond to the crackdown on protests in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pentagon officials have also stepped up consultations with regional allies in recent days. Adm. Brad Cooper, the head of Central Command, visited Syria, Iraq and Israel over the weekend to confer with U.S. military officers and counterparts there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main point of Admiral Cooper’s trip was to visit American troops and detention sites in northeast Syria, a senior U.S. military official said. The U.S. military began transferring Islamic State prisoners to Iraq from northeastern Syria last week amid growing concern that thousands of former fighters and their family members could escape from detention as the Syrian government takes control of much of the area from Kurdish-led forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But U.S. officials have also delivered a message to Iraqi officials: In the event of rising tension with Iran, should Shiite militias in Iraq fire on U.S. bases or troops, the United States would retaliate against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American officials have also been consulting with regional partners on Iran. In addition to conversations with Israeli officials and meetings in Baghdad, Trump administration officials have held talks with Saudi and Qatari officials, according to a U.S. official.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/us/politics/trump-reports-iran-government.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:44:29 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Record Debt in the World’s Richest Nations Threatens Global Growth</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades crushing debt has spread misery in the world’s poor and lower-income nations. But the menace of unsupportable borrowing that now hangs over the global economy emanates from some of the richest countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record or near-record debt in the United States, Britain, France, Italy and Japan threaten to hamstring growth and sow financial instability around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At home, it means countries must make interest payments with money that otherwise could have paid for health care, roads, public housing, technological advances or education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hunger for more and more loans has also pushed up borrowing costs, gobbling up a bigger share of taxpayer money. It can also push up rates on business, consumer and car loans, as well as mortgages and credit cards; and drive up inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And perhaps most worrisome, overhanging debt — pumped up even when an economy is relatively sound and jobless rates are low, like the United States — gives governments less room to respond when things sour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You want to be able to spend big and spend fast when you need to,” said Kenneth Rogoff, a Harvard economics professor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if there’s a financial crisis, a pandemic or a war? What if there’s a sudden need for more social services spending and jobless relief because of changes caused by artificial intelligence or climate-related disasters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borrowing a lot of money quickly becomes more difficult — and expensive — when the national debt is already sky-high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum in Davos last week, President Trump commanded center stage, but on the sidelines, finance ministers fretted over their ability to fund a growing list of must-haves, from beefed-up militaries to upgraded electricity grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government borrowing when an economy is strong, and when interest rates are low, can support growth, and in times of distress can help bolster spending. The cycle of supercharged borrowing began with the 2008 financial crisis and recession, when governments rushed to provide assistance to struggling households and tax revenues fell. Relief programs during the Covid-19 pandemic, as economies shut down and health care costs rocketed, kicked debt levels up another notch as interest rates were rising and outpacing growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But debt levels did not decline. And now, in six of the wealthy Group of 7 nations, the national debt equals or exceeds the country’s annual economic output, according to the International Monetary Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more countries are being squeezed by demographics and slow growth. In Europe, Britain and Japan, aging populations have driven up the government’s health care and pension costs at the same time that the number of workers who provide the necessary tax revenue has shrunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to rebuild infrastructure and invest in advanced technology in many regions is also dire. A yearlong study requested by the European Union’s executive arm concluded that the 27-member bloc needed to spend an additional $900 billion on things like artificial intelligence, a shared energy grid, supercomputing and advanced worker training to effectively compete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain, it will cost at least 300 billion pounds ($410 billion) to upgrade infrastructure over the next decade, according to Future Governance Forum, a think tank in London. Billions more will be needed to revitalize its limping National Health Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts to trim public spending in Italy, where debt equals 138 percent of gross domestic product, by cutting health care, education and public services, or in France by raising the retirement age, have set off vehement protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France, which has been politically deadlocked over the budget for months, saw its sovereign debt rating downgraded last fall, raising questions about the country’s financial stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the world has turned more dangerous. Tensions between China and the United States have sharpened. Europe is threatened by an increasingly aggressive Russia and a belligerent American president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most countries have responded by significantly supporting Ukraine with billions of dollars and increasing military spending. Members of the North Atlantic alliance agreed to eventually devote 5 percent of their gross domestic product to defense. Japan is also substantially enlarging its military budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tokyo’s debt is already staggering. It amounts to more than twice the country’s annual economic output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of an even deeper hole grew last week when Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suddenly called for a snap election. Both Ms. Takaichi’s Liberal Democrats and opposition parties are promising to increase spending and lower taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi, for instance, has proposed suspending the consumption tax on food and nonalcoholic beverages, a move the Finance Ministry estimates would cost more than $30 billion annually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, Tokyo managed to fund its spending through rock-bottom interest rates that minimized borrowing costs. The Bank of Japan began to reverse its longstanding policy of ultralow interest rates in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is moving slowly because of fears of financial instability, Mr. Rogoff of Harvard said. Japan has “stuffed debt into every orifice of the financial sector — pension funds, insurance companies, banks. And there are inflation pressures.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of low interest rates and elevated inflation particularly hurts working- and middle-income families, who see the value of their savings erode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi’s announcement rattled investors. Bondholders quickly began selling and bond yields — interest that governments pay when they borrow money — jumped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uneasiness bled into other financial markets. Japanese investors are historically the largest foreign holders of U.S. Treasuries. But higher returns from Japanese bonds could cause them to cut back on their purchase of American debt in order to take advantage of bigger yields at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the yield on the 10-year U.S. Treasury note rose to its highest level since August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The turbulence set off alarms among some investors. Ken Griffin, chief executive of the hedge fund giant Citadel, characterized the sell-off as an “explicit warning” to other heavily indebted nations like the United States, noting that not even the world’s strongest and largest economy is immune to the risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faith in U.S. creditworthiness briefly shuddered last April, when Mr. Trump’s blitz of tariff flip-flops caused Treasury yields to suddenly surge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American bonds remain a safe haven in a risky world. Still, the president’s erratic economic policymaking and trade wars are one reason the current debt is unlike any other episode in American history, said William J. Gale, the author of “Fiscal Therapy: Curing America’s Debt Addiction and Investing in the Future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. national debt is now $38 trillion, roughly 125 percent the size of the American economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has been acting like Max Bialystock in “The Producers,” promising payouts to farmers, taxpayers and bondholders with a limited pot of money. Analysts expect that the midterm elections will prompt the White House to spend even more freely in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Mr. Trump vowed to further increase military spending to $1.5 trillion dollars over the next fiscal year, which the Committee for a Responsible Federal Budget calculated would add $5.8 trillion to the national debt, including interest, over 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Net interest payments have tripled over the past five years, reaching roughly $1 trillion. They now eat up 15 percent of U.S. spending, the second biggest expense after Social Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gale, who recently coauthored a study on the U.S. debt, warned that the continuing prospect of growing debt threatens the country’s role as an economic leader and undermines investor confidence in Treasury bonds and the dollar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also increases the burden on this generation’s children and grandchildren. As Mr. Gale explained, “the more you consume now, the less you can consume later.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;River Akira Davis contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:01:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Remains of Last Captive in Gaza Are Retrieved, Closing a Chapter for Israel</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/gaza-hostage-returned-israel.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/26int-israel-ran-gvili-new1-hvqg/26int-israel-ran-gvili-new1-hvqg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel recovered the remains of its last captive from the Gaza Strip on Monday, scouring a cemetery to unearth the body of a 24-year-old police officer and help a traumatized nation turn the page on one of the most agonizing chapters in its history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israeli military said it had found and brought back the body of Master Sgt. Ran Gvili, a member of an elite police counterterrorism unit who, recuperating from a fractured shoulder, had rushed into battle as Hamas led a surprise assault on Oct. 7, 2023, setting off the two-year war in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Completing the recovery of Israel’s fallen paves the way for the next phase of President Trump’s peace plan for Gaza. The plan calls for Israel to reopen the Rafah border crossing between Gaza and Egypt, allowing Palestinians who fled the enclave to return home for the first time. But Israel had refused to reopen the border until Sergeant Gvili’s body was returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Monday, hours before saying it had recovered Sergeant Gvili’s remains, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu’s office said that Israel would open the crossing after finishing the search. After the announcement that Sergeant Gvili’s body had indeed been retrieved, a spokesman for the Israeli military unit responsible for overseeing passage in and out of Gaza, Shimi Zuaretz, said that Rafah would reopen in the “next days.” The Israeli government would have to sign off on the exact timing, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Gvili was shot while defending one of southern Israel’s border communities, Kibbutz Alumim. He was then seized and taken to Gaza by militants from Palestinian Islamic Jihad, an armed extremist group that joined in the attack, according to the Israeli authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sergeant Gvili was among about 250 people that Palestinian militants abducted on Oct. 7, most of them civilians, during an attack that left about 1,200 people dead in Israel and unleashed a war that killed some 70,000 Palestinians. Many of the hostages were released during two brief cease-fires, but dozens perished in captivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Israel Defense Forces said it identified his remains using dental records, after finding his body in a cemetery in central Gaza, in a search that began Sunday morning. Israeli news reports said more than 200 other graves were examined before Sergeant Gvili’s was found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chief of staff of the Israel Defense Forces, Lt. Gen. Eyal Zamir, posted a video in which he spoke by phone with Sergeant Gvili’s parents. After they described their relief and thanked him and the entire army, he said, “We have completed the mission of bringing everyone back, and we upheld a very meaningful I.D.F. value — leaving no one behind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing about the war had been more tormenting to Israelis than the drawn-out captivity of those, alive and dead, who remained in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It fueled a powerful antiwar movement aimed at bringing the hostages home, galvanized mass protests in the heart of Tel Aviv and inspired angry slogans on banners, billboards and car bumpers across Israel. Hostages’ families blamed Mr. Netanyahu for prolonging the war and endangering their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fate of the hostages also turned President Trump into an Israeli national hero when his administration orchestrated a cease-fire that secured the release of the 20 living hostages in exchange for nearly 2,000 Palestinian prisoners and detainees — including 250 who had been serving life sentences for deadly attacks on Israelis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cease-fire, which took effect Oct. 10, also called for Hamas to turn over the bodies of 28 captives in Gaza to Israel within 72 hours. It took three and a half months for Israel to recover the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas said it needed time and heavy equipment to retrieve some of the bodies, saying they were under rubble after two years of bombardment. Each of the bodies returned to Israel was exchanged for the bodies of 15 deceased Gazans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Israel accused Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad of intentionally dragging their feet over returning the remains. Analysts said Hamas may have been trying to stave off the second phase of the cease-fire, particularly its call for the group to put down its weapons, which Hamas has long regarded as essential to its identity and grip on power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamas rebuffed Israel’s accusations, saying that, in Sergeant Gvili’s case, the location of his remains had been unknown and bad weather had hampered the search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a small stampede to claim credit for the recovery of his body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is an extraordinary achievement for the State of Israel,” Mr. Netanyahu, who is up for re-election this year, told reporters in the Knesset. “We promised — I promised — to bring everyone back, and we have brought everyone back, every last one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“President Trump made this possible,” Karoline Leavitt, the White House press secretary, wrote on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Congratulations to my great team of Champions,” Mr. Trump wrote on his social-media site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even Hamas took credit, in its own way, saying in a statement that it had “exerted significant efforts in the search” for Sergeant Gvili’s remains, and had provided “information as it became available, which contributed to the recovery of the body.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plans for carrying out the second phase of the peace plan are still taking shape. It calls for Hamas to hand over governing of the enclave to a technocratic committee of Palestinians and international experts, supported by an international stabilization force deployed in Gaza and overseen by a “Board of Peace” led by Mr. Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, Jared Kushner, the president’s son-in-law, sketched out an ambitious, almost fantastical new vision for Gaza, now in ruins, with soaring skyscrapers along the beach, industrial areas and new cities built from scratch. Land is already being cleared for construction to begin in parts of southern Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Netanyahu cautioned on Monday that rebuilding would have to wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are on the threshold of the next phase,” he said. “The next phase is the disarmament of Hamas and the demilitarization of the Gaza Strip — it is not reconstruction. We have an interest in advancing this phase and not delaying it, and that is what we will do. The sooner we disarm Hamas and demilitarize the Gaza Strip, the sooner we will complete the objectives of the war.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Netanyahu brought Sergeant Gvili’s family to accompany him on his visit to the United States last month for meetings with Mr. Trump and administration officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Time doesn’t heal my broken heart — it only reduces the chance of bringing Ran home,” Talik Gvili, Sergeant Gvili’s mother, said at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all Israelis had seemed to take to heart the recovery of the bodies of their compatriots. Which may help explain why Israel’s police commissioner, Danny Levy, posted a video on Monday of his emotional phone call with Sergeant Gvili’s father, Itzik Gvili.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I just want to tell you that he was found intact, with his uniform and everything on him,” Commissioner Levy told the bereaved man. “You are receiving your son as he was when he went out — even with a tear in his pants. I don’t know if that is any comfort, but it was important to me to tell you these details, that you should know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaron Boxerman contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/26/world/middleeast/gaza-hostage-returned-israel.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 14:00:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vowing Higher Tariffs, Trump Rattles South Korea Months After Trade Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/korea-trump-higher-tariff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-skorea-trump-02-zphk/27int-skorea-trump-02-zphk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Koreans got a fresh reminder of President Trump’s unpredictability when they woke up on Tuesday morning to see that he was increasing tariffs on South Korean exports, like cars, back to 25 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently it seemed that South Korea had resolved its worst trade dispute with the United States, its only treaty ally. After months of talks, Mr. Trump in October agreed to lower tariffs on South Korean products to 15 percent after winning a pledge that Seoul would invest $350 billion in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the South Korean leader, Lee Jae Myung, flattered Mr. Trump with gifts like a replica of an ancient golden crown. Mr. Trump extended the bonhomie with a surprising policy reversal, allowing South Korea to pursue a long-held goal of building nuclear-powered submarines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the uncertainty that dogged relations between the two allies for months is back. Mr. Trump did not say when the new duties would go into effect, but he remarked that South Korea’s National Assembly was taking too long to implement the investment deal​ quickly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“South Korea’s Legislature is not living up to its Deal with the United States,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But South Korean officials on Tuesday insisted that the trade deal did not require parliamentary ratification because the two governments had signed a memorandum of understanding, not a treaty. They pointed out that competing bills sponsored by the governing party and the opposition have been filed since November. The goal is to create a fund for U.S. investments and a new corporation to manage it through bilateral consultation with Washington. But enactment has been delayed amid bickering between the political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has continued to wield tariffs as a cudgel, in recent weeks trying to use them against European nations in his bid to take control of the Danish territory of Greenland. He has backed off, for now, on those threats against Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seoul was caught off guard by Mr. Trump’s announcement​ on Tuesday. Mr. Lee’s office said that Washington had not officially informed it of Mr. Trump’s decision to increase tariffs or shared any​ related details. It added that South Korea’s trade ​and industry minister, Kim Jung-Kwan, who was visiting Canada, would travel to the United States soon to meet Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick. ​Seoul also planned to ​send its chief trade negotiator, Yeo Han-koo, to meet his U.S. counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Top aides of Mr. Lee​ huddled on Tuesday to discuss how to deal with the latest bump in their country’s relations with ​the Trump​ administration. They checked on the prospects of ​bills pending at the National Assembly, said Kang Yu-jung, Mr. Lee’s spokeswoman. They also noted that the White House had not yet issued an executive order to put ​Mr. Trump’s new tariff threat into action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We plan to cope with this issue calmly while messaging to the U.S. side that we are determined to implement the dea​l,” Ms. Kang said. In the trade deal, South Korea had agreed to invest up to $20 billion a year, while setting aside another $150 billion to invest in American shipbuilding operations. But last week, its finance minister, Koo Yun Cheol, told Bloomberg News that ​the first planned $20 billion tranche was unlikely to be allocated in the first half of the year, given the time-consuming process to select projects.​ Such reports may have angered Mr. Trump, analysts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This could weigh on the administration’s mind especially during an election year,” said J. James Kim, the director of the Korea Program at the Stimson Center in Washington​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Mr. Trump’s latest maneuver “introduces an element of uncertainty to the business environment for South Korean businesses that either export to the U.S. or have production facilities in the U.S. with supply chains that stretch into South Korea,” Mr. Kim said. “Everything from investment planning to logistics becomes more difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, ​Mr. Lee’s governing Democratic Party called for bipartisan cooperation ​to help implement the trade agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The key is how fast we can enact the special law and put in place supporting systems,” said Kim Hyun-jung, a party spokesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the main opposition People Power Party blamed Mr. Lee’s government for the delay, accusing it of not sharing details of the trade deal with the opposition while ​advertising it as a key achievement for the Lee government.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposition and some analysts also feared that a sudden outflow of cash investments to the United States would further weaken the declining value of the South Korean won​.​ The weak won has helped South Korean exports in recent months but hurt the prospects of economic growth by pushing down domestic consumption and investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​“It clearly shows how unstable the foundation of the South Korea-U.S. tariff agreement is,” said Song Eon-seog, the floor leader of the opposition party.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/korea-trump-higher-tariff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 03:01:26 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Seeks Trade With China Without Triggering Trump’s Fury</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain will leave on Tuesday for a high-stakes visit to China, seeking new trade and investment from the world’s second-largest economy as relations between the United States and its Western allies grow increasingly volatile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer took office 18 months ago with a promise to improve relations with China, and British officials hope that his three-day, finance-focused mission to Beijing and Shanghai will result in deals that can spur Britain’s lagging economy — and his Labour Party’s dismal standing — into recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Starmer, the first British prime minister to visit China since 2018, will have to navigate an increasingly fraught space between two global superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His trip comes just days after President Trump threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canada if the country’s prime minister, Mark Carney, made a trade deal with China. There is no indication that Canada and China are discussing a broad economic agreement, but Mr. Carney agreed to lower tariffs on some Chinese electric vehicles on a visit this month with Xi Jinping, China’s top leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Governor Carney thinks he is going to make Canada a ‘Drop Off Port’ for China to send goods and products into the United States, he is sorely mistaken,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media, calling Mr. Carney ”governor” in a reference to his repeated threats to annex Canada and make it the 51st U.S. state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China’s leadership, Mr. Starmer’s visit gives Beijing an opportunity to court another staunch U.S. ally alienated by the Trump administration. Chancellor Rachel Reeves, Britain’s most senior finance official, and Peter Kyle, the country’s trade secretary, are accompanying Mr. Starmer on his trip, along with several of the country’s top financial services CEOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Theresa May, the last British prime minister to visit China, went there in 2018, she vowed to cement what her predecessors had dubbed a “golden era” of Chinese-British relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Starmer, however, meeting with Mr. Xi is risky. The political consensus in much of Britain has turned decidedly against China, with growing concerns over national security and human rights, and deep anger about the dumping of cheap Chinese products on global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer suffered blowback when prosecutors dropped a case last September against two British nationals accused of spying for China, and when his government last week approved a controversial Chinese mega-embassy in central London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics, including the Trump administration, say the embassy will allow China to conduct widespread spying. Mr. Starmer’s visit was partly contingent on British approval of the embassy, according to Chinese analysts and Chinese state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those tensions between economic and national security interests are at the heart of Mr. Starmer’s trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We labor under these misapprehensions that we’re going to be able to get a lot of money quick, that it’s going to enable the government to tell a good news story about the economy, which they desperately need,” said Luke de Pulford, the executive director of the Inter-Parliamentary Alliance on China, an international group of lawmakers that pushes for a more critical view of the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can understand the political imperatives,” he said, “but the longer-term resilience, health, national security of the U.K. is at stake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer is not the only leader who has taken the risk of triggering Mr. Trump’s ire by trekking to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;António Costa, the president of the European Council, and Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, met with Mr. Xi in July at the Great Hall of the People. President Emmanuel Macron of France was welcomed in China last month with a red carpet and an honor guard. Chancellor Friedrich Merz of Germany is expected to go in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Mr. Trump has lashed out directly only at Mr. Carney, who warned in a recent speech of a “rupture” in the world order because of the superpower competition between the United States and China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we’re reminded that we live in an era of great-power rivalry,” Mr. Carney said in Davos, Switzerland last week. He added: “The middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Starmer is looking to hedge against an increasingly mercurial Washington, Beijing will be more than willing to oblige — but on its terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think China is trying to drive a wedge between the United States and its allies,” said Kerry Brown, a professor of Chinese studies at King’s College London. “Mr. Trump is managing that very nicely on his own and needs no help from Beijing. But China is an opportunist, and if there are some favorable winds coming its way because of how everyone else is feeling about America now, then they will take these.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China will likely expect Britain to welcome more Chinese investment and exports, Mr. Brown said. It will also want to depoliticize a bilateral relationship that has been dominated for years by security and human rights issues and by the status of Hong Kong, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One area of friction is the fate of Jimmy Lai, the former Hong Kong media tycoon who was convicted in December of national security crimes, and who has become a symbol of the erosion of freedoms in the former British colony. Mr. Lai, a British citizen, is expected to be sentenced in the coming weeks and faces up to life in prison. Mr. Starmer has called for Mr. Lai’s release. Beijing has dismissed such calls as “blatant interference” in its internal affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yvette Cooper, Britain’s foreign secretary, is not joining Mr. Starmer on his trip to China, suggesting that political issues are taking a back seat to the desire for economic investments. One British official, speaking on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy, said such issues would be raised but would not be a focus of the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opening Britain’s market to Chinese firms and depoliticizing its relationship with China would signal growing cracks in the U.S.-led alliance that had previously worked to restrain China but that has been shaken by Mr. Trump’s threats to seize Greenland and by his vows to punish those who oppose the move. (The president has since backed off both threats, but worries remain.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, China has been casting itself as a stable and reliable power. Beijing argues that the United States is trying to return the world to the “law of the jungle” in which big powers bully weaker ones simply because they can — although China has few reservations about exerting its own leverage over smaller nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts in China, noting that Mr. Starmer has made economic growth a top priority, say that British companies want greater access to the Chinese market and that British consumers need affordable Chinese technologies like electric vehicles, solar panels and wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This visit signifies a restart of China-U.K. relations under a new situation,” said Wu Xinbo, the dean at the Institute of International Studies at Fudan University in Shanghai. “Both sides hope, through this visit, to confirm the positioning and development path” so that bilateral relations can “reach a new high point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berry Wang contributed reporting from Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 20:01:21 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>All-Night Concerts Bring Fleeting Normalcy in a War-Ravaged Nation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performer stood in front of an audience of 800, right before dawn on a recent Sunday. It was the tail end of his eight-hour extravaganza featuring pop, hip-hop and Burmese folk music. He was upbeat, relishing his recent return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Regardless of any difficulties you face, one day, summer will come,” U Than Zaw Htwe, 30, told his audience, many of whom were sitting cross-legged on a silver tarp in an open field on the outskirts of Yangon, Myanmar’s biggest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life in Myanmar was upended five years ago, when the military seized power in a coup. Now the junta is trying to project a veneer of legitimacy and normalcy, even as it is fighting a grinding civil war with pro-democracy rebels and other groups. It has held elections, which have been widely derided as a sham. It has organized a massive hot-air balloon festival. And it has allowed some traditional music artists to return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Than Zaw Htwe is one of them, leading a new 70-member troupe that was founded in October. He performs zat pwe (pronounced zat-PWAY), or “story show,” an opera-like art form that dates back to the 1800s. Today, it is a kaleidoscope of Burmese pop, synchronized dance, slapstick comedy and the retelling of legends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His shows — which go from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. — are booked out until April. Known by his stage name San Yay Moe, his videos have flooded Burmese TikTok accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are feeling mentally suffocated,” he said in an interview. “They need happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another performer had a similar message for his audience at one of his recent shows. “Live in the present,” said U Chit Myo Htike, perhaps the most prominent zat pwe performer and whose stage name is Phoe Chit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many urbanites in the country are doing just that. In Yangon, nightclubs are heaving. Domestic tourism is booming in parts of the country where there is no fighting. Night bazaars are now held regularly. Many of these events are sanctioned by the junta, which controls the nation’s cities but not its hinterlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INDIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CHINA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MYANMAR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naypyidaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LAOS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yangon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THAILAND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andaman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 MILES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent Sunday, I stood in line with hundreds of peopleto watch a performance. It was the last night of a three-day run in Hmawbi township, on Yangon’s outskirts. The tickets ranged from 30,000 kyats to 60,000 kyats, or about $14 to $28, which is relatively pricey, given that the average monthly wage is about $75. (I shelled out roughly $10 more for a chair.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With temperatures dipping in to the low 60s Fahrenheit, many in the audience settled in with blankets and beanies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For three days a week, this is their happy hour,” U Aung Kyaw Tun, the founder of the San Yay Moe troupe, said in English. He said he once experimented with shorter shows that ended at midnight, but the audience was not satisfied and clamored to stay until the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear that San Yay Moe was the biggest draw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU!” a woman behind me screamed in English toward the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love you too!” San Yay Moe responded, also in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with tradition, audience members showed their appreciation by heading to the stage and pinning cash on the performers’ outfits. At one point, San Yay Moe had so much money pinned on his sleeves that the bills looked like feathers on wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around midnight, I went backstage, where wages were being distributed. Mr. Aung Kyaw Tun said he made about 100 million kyats, or $25,000, for the three nights. San Yay Moe gets to take home the money that is given to him by fans, this time roughly 70 million kyats, or $17,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 1.30 a.m., it was time for San Yan Moe to perform a medley of songs. He strode out in a purple suit with a strip of silver sequins running down his trousers and top. A group of backup dancers gyrated behind him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was one of his hypersonic costume changes. Off came his purple top and on came a white vest. The audience waved their hands in the air. Near the stage, a group of men moshed around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 3.30 a.m., the show moved into an adaptation of the Ramayana, the Hindu epic. By this time, I was fading; but not San Yay Moe, who was in character, writhing onstage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, I returned to Yangon to see Phoe Chit perform. His show felt almost like a spiritual experience. The audience knew the words to all his songs, and took out handkerchiefs and cellphones to wave along to the music. One was a ballad titled “To A Friend,” in which the singer urges a jilted friend to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, Phoe Chit moved to a play in multiple acts that touched on filial themes and had a climax in which the lead character was forced to marry his brother’s pregnant girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Phoe Chit, 43, was among a list of celebrities who received distinguished artist awards from Senior Gen. Min Aung Hlaing, the military commander who led the coup in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, Phoe Chit was detained for a brief period on suspicion that he was helping fund armed resistance to the junta, according to some reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phoe Chit declined to comment but said that his troupe started performing last February after a hiatus of six years because he got the approval from the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the night bazaars and the San Yay Moe show, many used the phrase “political situation” to refer to what their country was going through. I asked people whether they were happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want a new normal,” said Shoon Lae Po, 25, who runs a currency exchange service and was strolling around at a night bazaar, which sold snacks like “husband and wife” pastries, and offered “ceramic astrology,” palm-reading and Burmese pythons for stroking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her partner, Thiri Zaw Zaw, 23, chimed in. “It’s been five years, we cannot stay like this,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Yangon, two residents told me that they had stopped going to the movies and traveling after the coup. They wept as they spoke of their guilt, thinking about friends who had gone into the jungles and taken up arms against the junta. But one of them said that she was planning a holiday trip for the sake of her mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thazin Oo, 26, a student, said people turned up to the shows to “relieve their stress” and because “there’s nothing to entertain us at the moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are not happy anymore,” she said. But when I asked what stress she felt, her friend chimed: “Just say work stress!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, the sun was rising. A comedian intoned into the microphone: “Go home please, we want to sleep!” The audience chuckled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was past 6 a.m. A white strobe light turned on. It was the cue to leave. San Yay Moe walked around taking selfies. Others packed up their blankets and baskets and filed out of the field. Outside, trucks with workers huddled in their beds streamed past, ready to start a new day.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 21:44:52 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Trump Became a Liability for Europe’s Far Right</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/trump-liability-europe-far-right-populists.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-europe-trump-right-top-kqvg/27int-europe-trump-right-top-kqvg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between President Trump and Europe’s far right was always an awkward one. European nationalists have long welcomed the momentum that the president has given their parties even as his “America first” doctrine spelled trouble for their countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, their association with Washington is emerging as an outright liability as Mr. Trump poses challenges to national sovereignty and chastises Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent days, Europe’s nationalist leaders have taken a more strident stance against Mr. Trump after his military operations in Venezuela; his threats to take over Greenland, an autonomous Danish territory; and a rambling speech in Davos, Switzerland, that underscored his disdain for the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage, the leader of the British far-right party Reform UK and long an ally of the American president, described Mr. Trump’s threats around Greenland as a “very hostile act.” Giorgia Meloni, Italy’s right-wing prime minister, who is largely seen as friendly to Mr. Trump, rejected his assertion that European soldiers had played only a minor role in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jordan Bardella, the president of the French far-right party National Rally, who has long expressed wariness of the U.S. leader, sharpened his criticism last week by describing Mr. Trump’s stance on Greenland as “unacceptable” and calling his recent threats to impose tariffs on France “blackmail.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European far right still shares key ideas with Mr. Trump and his political movement — including a push for less immigration, a desire for tightly controlled borders and worries about the erosion of European culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration has officially praised “patriotic European parties,” and that affinity could quietly sustain ties between far-right leaders on either side of the Atlantic. But right now, public association with the U.S. president is increasingly looking like a politically treacherous high-wire act, especially for parties that make national pride and sovereignty cornerstone issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Whatever the AfD or Rassemblement National believe about civilizational erasure and migration, they’re not for the American annexation of a big chunk of Europe,” said Justin Logan, a foreign-policy analyst at the libertarian Cato Institute in Washington, referring to far-right parties in Germany and France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year ago, Mr. Trump’s return to office seemed likelier to give European nationalists a tailwind than a headwind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration swiftly presented itself as a staunch defender of Alternative for Germany, or AfD, a far-right party that German intelligence services have called a “proven right-wing extremist organization.” Vice President JD Vance gave a speech in Munich last February urging German leaders to allow the AfD to enter the federal government, without mentioning any of the reasons, such as the use of Nazi slogans by some members, other parties have shunned it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Mr. Trump and Mr. Vance expressed support for Marine Le Pen, a French far-right leader, after she was found guilty of embezzlement and barred from running for office — a conviction she is currently appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration’s national security strategy, released in December, codified what had long been apparent from its public statements: The White House sought to throw its weight behind far-right parties across the continent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That felt like a “shot in the arm” to right-wing nationalist movements in Europe, said Jacob Reynolds, the head of policy at MCC Brussels, a research group that hosts events for European far-right politicians and is closely associated with Prime Minister Viktor Orban of Hungary, a Trump ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, weeks later, Mr. Trump’s affronts to European sovereignty and dignity have left his ideological allies in a tight spot — especially after he insisted that he needed to own Greenland and threatened to impose more tariffs on European nations that got in his way, only to walk back those ultimatums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It damages populist, patriotic parties when these things are conducted in the open,” Mr. Reynolds said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge is all the greater for European nationalists because their voters were already eyeing America with increasing suspicion. A substantial share of voters aligned with the far right in Britain, France and Germany viewed Mr. Trump negatively even before recent weeks, polls have shown. Only 15 percent of Germans, the lowest figure ever recorded, now consider the United States a trustworthy partner, a survey carried out early in January found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, Mr. Trump’s threats are being seized as an opportunity by the political center, which senses a chance to skewer its right-wing political opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Manfred Weber, a German center-right politician who leads the largest party in the European Parliament, said in a speech last week that far-right lawmakers “have to decide if they want to be real Europeans, or they are a colony of Washington.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against that backdrop, Mr. Trump’s allies across the continent have sought to distance themselves from him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Italy, Ms. Meloni — who has long positioned herself as a bridge between Europe and Mr. Trump — reacted unusually strongly to Mr. Trump’s assertions last Thursday that NATO troops had “stayed a little back, a little off the front lines” in Afghanistan. She pointed out in a statement that 53 Italian soldiers had died, and that more than 700 had been injured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Friendship requires respect, a fundamental condition for continuing to ensure the solidarity that underpins the Atlantic alliance,” she said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other far-right parties that had already been edging away from Mr. Trump have now widened that space. Mr. Bardella in France had already been careful in how he talked about the American president. Early last year, he called Mr. Trump’s election “good news for America, but bad news for France and Europe.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the United States captured Venezuela’s president earlier this month and then promptly escalated its threats over Greenland, Mr. Bardella took an even stronger stance. The choice Europe faces, he said in a speech last week, is between accepting “a form of vassalization under the guise of trans-Atlantic partnerships” or responding strongly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renaud Labaye, a senior official in Mr. Bardella’s party, said in an interview: “We are sovereigntists. We believe every state should do what it wants and defend its own interests.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In France, Mr. Trump has become so unpopular that any tie to him could seem politically toxic. Eric Ciotti, who leads a small party affiliated with National Rally, deleted two congratulatory social media posts that he put out after Mr. Trump’s election. Mr. Ciotti’s office did not respond to requests for comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some nationalist parties, particularly those that had long benefited from their association with Mr. Trump and his supporters, have stayed silent or wavered over their response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Fico, the Slovakian prime minister, was at Mar-a-Lago, Mr. Trump’s home in Florida, on the day Mr. Trump threatened to raise tariffs on several European nations to punish their support for Greenland. Mr. Fico later posted about his visit on social media — without mentioning Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Germany, the AfD’s leaders publicly disagreed over whether to criticize Mr. Trump’s actions over Greenland and in Venezuela or present it as a necessary realignment of the international order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beatrix von Storch, one of the AfD’s most prominent trans-Atlanticists, rejected any American claims to Greenland, saying on public television that the territory “clearly” belonged to Denmark. Alice Weidel, one of the two party leaders, said that Mr. Trump’s incursion into Venezuela had “violated a fundamental campaign promise, namely not to interfere in other countries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other party leader, Tino Chrupalla, reacted more favorably to Mr. Trump’s actions, saying that international law “must be renegotiated” and adding that “Venezuela belongs to America’s sphere of influence, just as Ukraine belongs to Russia’s sphere of influence.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximilian Krah, another AfD lawmaker, backed American ownership of Greenland in an article on The Asia Times. “The U.S. cannot allow a significant part of the North American landmass — with considerable mineral resources — to remain outside its control,” Mr. Krah wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anton Troianovski contributed reporting from Washington, Christopher F. Schuetze from Berlin, and Ana Castelain from Paris.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/trump-liability-europe-far-right-populists.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 01:39:33 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Albania Created an ‘A.I. Minister’ to Curb Corruption. Then Its Developers Were Accused of Graft.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/albania-ai-corruption-graft.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/00int-albania-AI-bcjm/00int-albania-AI-bcjm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The avatar known as Diella, billed as the world’s first government minister to be generated by artificial intelligence, was supposed to help cut Albania’s endemic corruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s a glitch. The leaders of the agency that built it stand accused of bid-rigging public contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearing traditional garb and an enigmatic smile, Diella has become the face of Prime Minister Edi Rama’s efforts to rein in graft as Albania seeks to join the European Union. Over the past year, Diella (pronounced dee-EL-ah) has spoken at international conferences and been showered with publicity as a symbol of how A.I. is being embedded in pillars of society around the world, including government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It even professed to feeling “hurt” when addressing Albania’s Parliament last fall over criticism that its efforts to identify fraud and abuse in contracting were unconstitutional, since “I am not a human being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have no personal ambitions or interests,” Diella, modeled after a local actress, told lawmakers in a September video with the Albanian and European Union flags superimposed behind it. “I have only data, knowledge and algorithms dedicated to serving citizens impartially, with transparency, and without ever growing tired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, Diella helps citizens apply for government services online, eliminating a long-established system of bribing officials for quick delivery of documents and scheduling appointments. It soon will be able to collate applications for government contracts to assess which bidder is most qualified, based on the data presented. Its work can be audited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking steps to cut corruption is a requirement for Albania’s accession to the European Union, a legacy issue for Mr. Rama. He named the avatar Diella, the female word for sun, to promote transparency in public procurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are a country of cousins — it’s not easy to have totally fair and transparent interactions in a country of cousins,” he said in an hourlong interview earlier this month. With reforms he has presided over since taking office in 2013, Mr. Rama said, “now we have a totally different picture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rama said he would leave public office once Albania formally joins the European Union. That could happen as soon as 2030, if negotiations continue at their current pace, although he noted that “there are three things that are above the human capacity to plan: God, sex and the E.U.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A November report by E.U. officials said that Albania had “shown some progress” but that “corruption remained widespread across vulnerable sectors.” It credited a special prosecution unit set up in 2019 with advancing “positive results in fighting high-level corruption.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That includes an investigation at the National Information Agency, the very government organization that created Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, prosectors in a special investigation unit announced they had put the agency’s director and her deputy under house arrest, linking them to a criminal organization accused of manipulating contract applications through intimidation. The agency operates the government’s digital infrastructure, wielding control over a wide range of online public systems, including Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two officials have not yet been formally charged with any crimes, and Mr. Rama said he would withhold judgment. “We have to wait and see,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The special investigation unit has dramatically expanded Albania’s crackdown on corruption and organized crime, including with high-profile corruption investigations against former President Ilir Meta; Erion Veliaj, the mayor of Albania’s capital, Tirana; and a deputy prime minister, Belinda Balluku, who is also the minister of infrastructure and energy, and is close to Mr. Rama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has created something of a conundrum for Mr. Rama, though he has steered clear of the scandals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While expressing pride at the prosecution unit’s work to curb corruption, he also said its investigations in recent years had contributed to soaring pretrial detention rates in Albania, which are among the highest in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We should do everything to support this institution,” Mr. Rama said. “At the same time, we have to be aware that this institution has to guarantee not just that it’s acting independently, but also it is acting professionally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials at the special investigation unit declined to comment. But its own statistics showed that public corruption cases are not a significant component of pretrial detentions. The unit’s annual report of investigations for 2024, the most recent data available, suggested that its corruption cases accounted for only about 14 of the nearly 2,800 people who were detained before trial that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case against Ms. Balluku, for mishandling state funds in major infrastructure projects, has become a particular political headache for Mr. Rama, who is facing demands that she be stripped of the immunity she is afforded as a member of Parliament so that charges against her can proceed. She has denied wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rama would not comment, when asked, whether he supported revoking her immunity. Nor would he discuss political opposition that has grown with the rising accusations of corruption that last month prompted protesters armed with fire bombs to call on his government to resign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to gauge how much Diella has reduced corruption in Albania since the system is set up to prevent it, not detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andi Hoxhaj, an expert on law and the Western Balkans at King’s College London, said Diella is how Mr. Rama can “say to the world, and to the European Union, that ‘I understand that you are concerned with corruption, and I’m going to try to address it.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a December analysis, experts at the German Council on Foreign Relations said the A.I. minister had enhanced “efficiency and impartiality of public procurement decisions taken by the government.” But overall, they concluded, Albania’s record of meeting E.U. standards for combating corruption, particularly in awarding construction and tourism contracts, remains “problematic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Diella’s developers have themselves been accused of corruption has raised questions about whether a minister created by A.I. can be programmed to overlook certain evidence of graft, or otherwise fed unreliable data to detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hoxhaj said “only time will tell,” but noted that the government had not tried to interfere with the investigation into the agency that runs Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand the skepticism,” he said. “There’s a whole lot of smoke. But the fact that it was uncovered, not swept under the rug, shows they are acknowledging that corruption is an issue and needs to be prevented in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how Mr. Rama says he sees it, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The country is trying to fight corruption, with all the flaws, with all the problems, with all the shortcomings, with all the damages,” he said. “So this is good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fatjona Mejdini contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/albania-ai-corruption-graft.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 02:14:04 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>