<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>NYT World Full-Text Feed</title><link>file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml</link><description>Full-text NYT World articles (last 24 h)</description><atom:link href="file:///Users/purp/Downloads/translator/xml/World_fulltext.xml" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 04:18:18 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>How Iran Crushed a Citizen Uprising With Lethal Force</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/middleeast/iran-how-crackdown-was-done.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/20/world/middleeast/1-ILAM_2x3-still/1-ILAM_2x3-still-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Tehran, the capital of Iran, security forces opened fire at protesters from the roof of a police station. In Karaj, they fired live rounds into a march, shooting one person in the head. In Isfahan, young men barricaded themselves in an alley as gunfire and explosions rang out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scattered protests had percolated since late December, starting with a strike in Tehran’s bazaar and fueled by a plunging economy. But by early January, Iranians had revolted en masse, and the security forces began to crack down with deadly force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not just the protests unnerving the regime. President Trump encouraged the demonstrators and threatened military intervention. In many places, riots flared in parallel with peaceful protests; government buildings, commercial properties, mosques and police stations were set on fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday, Jan. 9, Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, ordered the Supreme National Security Council, the body tasked with safeguarding the country, to crush the protests by any means necessary, according to two Iranian officials briefed on the ayatollah’s directive. Security forces were deployed with orders to shoot to kill and to show no mercy, the officials said. The death toll surged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Iran shutting down the internet and disrupting phone service, some Iranians managed to evade restrictions to share witness accounts and hundreds of videos, many of which The New York Times was able to collect and authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times has verified videos of security forces opening fire on protesters in at least 19 different cities and in at least six different neighborhoods in Tehran in early January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TURKMENISTAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caspian Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mashhad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times verified footage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of security forces firing on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;demonstrators at these&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isfahan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiraz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KUWAIT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAUDI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARABIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gulf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TURKMENISTAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caspian Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mashhad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times verified footage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of security forces firing on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;demonstrators at these locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isfahan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAN&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRAQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiraz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KUWAIT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAUDI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ARABIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gulf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: Verified footage; Institute for the Study of War and American Enterprise Institute’s Critical Threats Project (all protests)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These videos show the breadth and ferocity of the regime’s crackdown. So do the testimonies of doctors and a nurse working in hospitals in Iran, and photographs shared by a witness and authenticated by The Times of hundreds of victims brought to a Tehran morgue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times also interviewed two dozen Iranians in Tehran, Isfahan, Shiraz, Rasht and Ahvaz who had attended protests, as well as relatives of people killed. Protesters, residents and medical staff interviewed for this article all asked that their names or full names not be published for fear of retribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Monday, Jan. 12, the protests had largely been crushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As more information emerges from Iran, the death toll has hit at least 5,200 people, including 56 children, according to the Washington-based Human Rights Activists News Agency. Iran Human Rights, a Norway-based group that also monitors the situation in Iran, has confirmed at least 3,400 killed. Both organizations say that the numbers could prove two or three times larger as verification continues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s National Security Council said in a statement that 3,117 people had been killed, among them 427 of its security forces. Officials, including Mr. Khamenei, have blamed terrorist cells tied to Israel and the United States for the uprising and killings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This is not merely a violent protest crackdown. It is a state-orchestrated massacre,” said Raha Bahreini, a lawyer and an Iran researcher at Amnesty International.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 8, Nasim Pouraghayee, 45, a mother of two, and her husband, Ali, marched with large crowds in the Sadeghiyeh neighborhood in Tehran. She called her mother to say the atmosphere was boisterous and the turnout huge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abruptly, things turned deadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her husband was walking behind her, hands wrapped around her shoulders to protect her, according to a cousin of Ms. Pouraghayee’s who, in an interview, recounted the events of the night as described by Ali. A bullet hit Ms. Pouraghayee in the neck; she fell to the ground and began vomiting blood, the cousin said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nasim, Nasim, Nasim,” her husband screamed, holding her face. But she was unresponsive. “Help, help,” he pleaded to other protesters fleeing the chaos, but nobody came forward. He felt his wife’s body getting cold as he picked her up, the cousin said, and walked for an hour and a half to reach their car. When they reached the hospital, she was pronounced dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video verified by The Times captured the sound of live fire being directed at protesters in Sadeghiyeh. The protesters turn, flee and scream as gunshots are heard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About 40 verified videos show gunmen and security forces cracking down on demonstrations. Across the footage, they are seen riding in pairs on motorbikes and using a variety of weapons, including firearms, batons and tear gas. In a video filmed in Haft Howz Square in Tehran, men and women flee amid the sound of gunfire. Some protesters clearly have leg wounds, and leave trails of blood along a sidewalk as they limp away, a video verified by The Times showed. On the street, some can also be seen carrying people unable to walk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mohammad, 40, a shop owner, said he and his younger brother were among the demonstrators in Tehran Pars, a middle-class neighborhood in eastern Tehran, on Friday, Jan. 9, when they heard the rat-tat-tat of gunfire. “I saw two young men who were running away collapse; they were shot from the back,” Mohammad said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces fired on protesters from the rooftop of a police station in Tehran Pars for more than six minutes, one video shows. The video shows the muzzle blasts of several rifles and picks up the sound of hundreds of gunshots and what appears to be automatic fire. A group of protesters run away along an adjacent street. Minutes later, a person is dragged inside the courtyard of the police station.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another video filmed farther along the same street — and in the direction the security forces were firing — shows protesters sheltering from incoming gunfire. “Put your phone down, they’ll shoot your hand off,” one person says. “There’s a sniper among them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sound of bullets striking nearby can be heard amid chants of “Death to Khamenei.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video that The Times confirmed was filmed at the nearby Tehran Pars Hospital showed several body bags lined up on the ground outside an emergency room entrance as people could be heard wailing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A husband and wife had a violent encounter with members of the Basij militia, a plainclothes security force, on motorcycles in Karim Khan in central Tehran. The wife, 50, who is a designer, said in an interview that the men shot indiscriminately into the air and at people, and screamed, “Get back inside.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The husband was shot in his lower back with a pellet bullet. The wife said a member of the Basij found her hiding behind an electric pole, stood near her and pointed a gun to her forehead, several millimeters away from her eye. He threatened to kill her, but had run out bullets, she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A series of videos verified by The Times from Jan. 8 in Fardis, a suburb of Karaj, showed hundreds of people marching, then fleeing when a tear-gas canister is fired in their direction. Gunshots ring out. Another video, filmed near a police station in Fardis, shows a protester who appears to have been shot in the head. More than two dozen gunshots are heard as screaming protesters take cover. In the last video, the lifeless bodies of seven people sprawl on the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mashhad, a conservative city in the northeast, huge crowds gathered on Jan. 8 chanting slogans against the government, a video verified by The Times showed. Later that night, a group of protesters were walking down a road about a mile away from where the crowds had been when security forces on motorcycles rode up to them. Some of the officers dismounted and beat demonstrators with batons, while others fanned out, pointing firearms down the street as gunshots rang out nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In another video filmed at a protest in Mashhad and verified by The Times, a person is seen lying on the ground as others run to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Look, they shot a girl,” the person recording the video said. “They are using weapons of war.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across the country, hospitals swamped by thousands of injured protesters were unprepared for the scale of the gunshot wounds they were seeing, according to interviews and text messages with eight doctors and one nurse in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gun violence is rare in Iran, and private citizens are not allowed to own weapons. The doctors and the nurse sharing their experiences in Tehran, Mashhad, Isfahan and Zanjan described scenes of chaos: medical staff frantically trying to save lives, white uniforms drenched in blood. They said patients lay on benches and chairs, and even on bare floors, in the overcrowded emergency rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They said hospitals were short of blood and searching for trauma and vascular surgeons. The internet shutdown prevented medical staff from checking patients’ names and medical history, they said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nurse at Nikan Hospital in Tehran said in an interview that the hospital resembled a war zone. A doctor at Shohada Tajrish Hospital in north Tehran, a sprawling government medical facility, said that, on average, medical staff saw about 70 protesters with gunshot wounds per hour on the two days of peak violence, Jan. 9 and 10. Many patients were dead on arrival or shortly afterward, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an audio message shared with The Times, a physician in Mashhad called the situation at his hospital “terrifying.” In addition to a staggering number of injured protesters, he said, security forces showed up demanding access to patients to arrest them. He said a team of physicians had set up an ad hoc triage unit at a villa outside of the city, where they treated patients too afraid to go to hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An anesthesiologist at a hospital in the Sattar Khan neighborhood of Tehran said in a text message shared with The Times that in just one night, his hospital had seen 300 injured protesters. A text message from a doctor at a university hospital in Zanjan shared with The Times said most victims were shot in the upper torso, head and neck, and that the hospital had recorded about 200 killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times received photos and videos from inside hospitals that are too gruesome to show. Other very graphic images were posted online by an account with a record of publishing images later found to be authentic. They showed bloody, lifeless bodies inside hospitals said to be in Tehran. Some victims appeared to have been shot in the head. The Times was unable to independently authenticate the images from inside hospitals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farabi Eye Hospital in Tehran, a national hub for ophthalmology, registered about 500 cases of eye injury from pellet bullets on Jan. 8 and several hundred eye injuries with live bullets on the following two nights, a surgeon said in a text message. He was in the operating room for three nights straight and said he wished for death when he had to empty both eye sockets of a 13-year-old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A doctor in Isfahan said in a text message that they had seen “young people whose brains were smashed with live bullets, and a mom who was shot in the neck, her two small children were crying in the car, a child whose bladder, hip and rectum was crushed with a bullet.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I witnessed will forever haunt me,” the doctor added. “I feel guilty that I’m alive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos, videos and text conversations shared with The Times by Dr. Kayvan Mirhadi, an Iranian American doctor in Rochester, N.Y., who has been in regular contact with medical teams and hospitals in Iran, showed dozens of apparent gunshot and pellet wounds to the torso, limbs, head and eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They are essentially executing people on the streets,” Dr. Mirhadi said. “Starting Thursday, the reports of injuries I was receiving changed significantly. It went from brute force, fractures and tear gas to skull fractures and gunshot wounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some images shared by Dr. Mirhadi were sent by people asking how to treat their own wounds or those of relatives. One person asked about a bullet wound in his brother’s leg. Another sent a photo of an eye, with blood pouring out of a gash just above it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times sent a representative sample of 17 images to experts from the Independent Forensic Expert Group coordinated by the International Rehabilitation Council for Torture Victims, who determined that the injuries appeared to be caused by buckshot or birdshot fired at close range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HRANA, the rights agency in Washington, documented a significant number of injuries from pellet gunfire during recent protests, including shots into the eyeball. It said 7,402 people had serious injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A video obtained by the London-based Persian-language news channel Iran International and verified by The Times shows bodies in the courtyard of Alghadir Hospital, less than a mile from where protesters were fired upon and injured in Haft Howz Square. Some of the bodies are covered and tied in plastic bags; others are wrapped in blankets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A woman crouches over the body of a man wrapped in a blanket whose eyes remain closed. She weeps and speaks to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bodies shrouded in black plastic bags covered every space and surface. Stacked in refrigerators. Placed on the floor inside. Scattered, row after row, on the ground in the parking lot and courtyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tehran’s main morgue, Kahrizak Forensic Center, was overflowing in the immediate aftermath of the killing spree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of bodies overwhelmed the capacity of the morgue, a government official admitted on state television, blaming the killings on terrorist cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the handling and processing of bodies was also disorderly, according to videos and a person who visited the morgue. Families searching for loved ones were taken to a hall where a television screen flashed the faces of the dead, each with a number assigned to it. There were several photos of some victims because the severity of their injuries required multiple angles to identify them, according to the visitor to the morgue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes families would ask the morgue staff to pause, rewind and zoom in, the visitor said. Others would immediately recognize a loved one and collapse. People screamed, wailed and hit their faces and bodies in shock and grief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple images and videos verified by The Times showed hundreds of bodies laid out at the Kahrizak morgue within days of the protests erupting on Jan. 8. Outside the center, men unzipped black body bags as they searched for missing relatives. Others tearfully embraced as they discovered bodies. Inside a large hall where dozens more were laid out, women wailed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One 16-minute video filmed outside the center showed close to 300 victims laid out on sidewalks and asphalt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s a line. A line of people, so they can pick up their deceased,” the person filming said. “The young people. Their apple of their eyes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staff in white lab coats unzipped body bags and examined victims’ wounds. One staff member identified a wound at the back of one victim’s head, blood trailing from it, and jotted details in a notebook. Another documented apparent bullet wounds on the torso of a bloodied victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the camera moved through the crowd, people could be seen going from body to body searching for a loved one. Men embraced tearfully over the dead body of someone they identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one heartbreaking video, a father sobbed as he searched inside the center for his son, Sepehr Shokri, 19, a boxer. “Sepehr, my son, where are you?” he cried. “Damn Khamenei, this is his crime. Sepehr, Baba, where are you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times obtained photographs of over 300 bodies brought to Kahrizak. The photographs showed the faces of the dead, the top of their black body bags unzipped, with white identity cards on their chests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens were marked as “unknown man,” “unknown woman,” “unknown child.” Over 190 were marked only by numbers. The Times identified 29 legible names, among them Mohammad Erfan Faraji, 18, who an Iranian rights organization reported was shot during protests in Shahr Rey, a suburb of Tehran about 10 miles from the morgue where his body was photographed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Times could not make a conclusive assessment of injuries based on the images. But a majority of the bodies showed severe head trauma, large gashes and collapsed eye sockets. Some were severely disfigured. Several still had tubes in their mouths and EKG pads on their chests, indicating the bodies had been transported from a hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Nizam Peerwani, a forensic adviser for Physicians for Human Rights who analyzed the images for The Times, said the evidence suggested multiple victims had been “brutally bludgeoned or beaten up at the scene or in detention.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When one woman recognized her husband on the screen and dropped to the floor, another woman approached her, said the person who was at the morgue. She told her, “Get up, get up my dear, you have work to do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Across Iran, funerals are taking place. Parents are burying children. Children are burying parents. Siblings, friends, neighbors, colleagues, classmates and teammates are attending burial processions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the faces and stories of the victims surface, recounted by relatives or friends and posted on social media, so does the story of the uprising. The protesters killed represent a broad swath of Iran, ethnically, economically and socially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many were very young. Teenagers and people in their early twenties took to the streets with dreams of a better life, of a prosperous future and of freedom, their families say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 21-year-old basketball star who played for a national team; a 17-year-old Kurdish soccer player with a national youth club; a 15-year-old swimming champion; a 19-year-old college student majoring in Italian; a 26-year-old English teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The death on Jan. 8 of Sina Ashkbousi, 17, was described by his aunt in an audio message posted on the Instagram page of lawyers in Iran who represent human rights cases. “Sina was killed with a direct bullet in his heart in Tehran Pars,” she said. “He was very smart, a dreamer. He was after freedom and was very kind.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funerals have turned into protests, with thousands of attendees holding pictures of victims and chanting “Death to Khamenei,” videos verified by The Times show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footage showed huge crowds at a funeral for three people killed in Malekshahi, a rural area in the province of Ilam, on Jan. 4. A week later, videos circulating on social media appeared to show huge crowds not far away, in Abdanan, another city in Ilam, for the funeral of Alireza Saidi, 16, who was said to have been killed in Tehran during protests that week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At these funerals and that of Ahmad Khosravani, the basketball star, the crowd departed from the traditional mourning rituals of crying and reciting the Quran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead they clapped, cheered and chanted in unison, saying, “This fallen flower is a gift to the nation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;___________MethodologyDespite a communications blackout, Iranians managed to use virtual private networks, or VPNs, and forbidden Starlink satellite internet systems to share witness accounts and videos, many of which The New York Times was able to collect and authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some videos were shared directly with Times journalists. Others with Iranian human rights groups, BBC Persian and the Iranian blog Vahid Online, all of whom circulated the videos on Telegram, X and Instagram.The Times collected over 300 videos and independently verified over 160 of them by matching details seen in the videos — like business names, street fronts, signs and trees — with archival images, satellite imagery and Google Street View. Iranian reporters with The Times watched and listened to the videos for accents or other details indicating their authenticity. Sometimes we referred to verification carried out by GeoConfirmed, a research collective that specializes in geolocating where videos are filmed.The Times independently confirmed all the videos reported on for this story. Two weeks on from the worst of the violence, footage is still emerging. Confirming the date those videos were filmed is not always possible. But by checking that the videos are new and not posted during previous crackdowns in Iran, and by mapping out when and where protests and crackdowns happened in January, we corroborated the date they were most likely taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Haley Willis. Videos produced by Jon Hazell. Additional video production by Natalie Reneau, Jeffrey Bernier and Josh Holder. Map by Samuel Granados.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/25/world/middleeast/iran-how-crackdown-was-done.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:19:45 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Record Debt in the World’s Richest Nations Threatens Global Growth</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/multimedia/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq/Biz-Global-Debt-bkjq-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades crushing debt has spread misery in the world’s poor and lower-income nations. But the menace of unsupportable borrowing that now hangs over the global economy emanates from some of the richest countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Record or near-record debt in the United States, Britain, France, Italy and Japan threaten to hamstring growth and sow financial instability around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At home, it means countries must make interest payments with money that otherwise could have paid for health care, roads, public housing, technological advances or education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hunger for more and more loans has also pushed up borrowing costs, gobbling up a bigger share of taxpayer money. It can also push up rates on business, consumer and car loans, as well as mortgages and credit cards; and drive up inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And perhaps most worrisome, overhanging debt — pumped up even when an economy is relatively sound and jobless rates are low, like the United States — gives governments less room to respond when things sour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You want to be able to spend big and spend fast when you need to,” said Kenneth Rogoff, a Harvard economics professor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if there’s a financial crisis, a pandemic or a war? What if there’s a sudden need for more social services spending and jobless relief because of changes caused by artificial intelligence or climate-related disasters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Borrowing a lot of money quickly becomes more difficult — and expensive — when the national debt is already sky-high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the World Economic Forum in Davos last week, President Trump commanded center stage, but on the sidelines, finance ministers fretted over their ability to fund a growing list of must-haves, from beefed-up militaries to upgraded electricity grids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government borrowing when an economy is strong, and when interest rates are low, can support growth, and in times of distress can help bolster spending. The cycle of supercharged borrowing began with the 2008 financial crisis and recession, when governments rushed to provide assistance to struggling households and tax revenues fell. Relief programs during the Covid-19 pandemic, as economies shut down and health care costs rocketed, kicked debt levels up another notch as interest rates were rising and outpacing growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But debt levels did not decline. And now, in six of the wealthy Group of 7 nations, the national debt equals or exceeds the country’s annual economic output, according to the International Monetary Fund.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more countries are being squeezed by demographics and slow growth. In Europe, Britain and Japan, aging populations have driven up the government’s health care and pension costs at the same time that the number of workers who provide the necessary tax revenue has shrunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to rebuild infrastructure and invest in advanced technology in many regions is also dire. A yearlong study requested by the European Union’s executive arm concluded that the 27-member bloc needed to spend an additional $900 billion on things like artificial intelligence, a shared energy grid, supercomputing and advanced worker training to effectively compete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain, it will cost at least 300 billion pounds ($410 billion) to upgrade infrastructure over the next decade, according to Future Governance Forum, a think tank in London. Billions more will be needed to revitalize its limping National Health Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efforts to trim public spending in Italy, where debt equals 138 percent of gross domestic product, by cutting health care, education and public services, or in France by raising the retirement age, have set off vehement protests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;France, which has been politically deadlocked over the budget for months, saw its sovereign debt rating downgraded last fall, raising questions about the country’s financial stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the world has turned more dangerous. Tensions between China and the United States have sharpened. Europe is threatened by an increasingly aggressive Russia and a belligerent American president.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most countries have responded by significantly supporting Ukraine with billions of dollars and increasing military spending. Members of the North Atlantic alliance agreed to eventually devote 5 percent of their gross domestic product to defense. Japan is also substantially enlarging its military budget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tokyo’s debt is already staggering. It amounts to more than twice the country’s annual economic output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prospect of an even deeper hole grew last week when Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suddenly called for a snap election. Both Ms. Takaichi’s Liberal Democrats and opposition parties are promising to increase spending and lower taxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi, for instance, has proposed suspending the consumption tax on food and nonalcoholic beverages, a move the Finance Ministry estimates would cost more than $30 billion annually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, Tokyo managed to fund its spending through rock-bottom interest rates that minimized borrowing costs. The Bank of Japan began to reverse its longstanding policy of ultralow interest rates in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is moving slowly because of fears of financial instability, Mr. Rogoff of Harvard said. Japan has “stuffed debt into every orifice of the financial sector — pension funds, insurance companies, banks. And there are inflation pressures.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of low interest rates and elevated inflation particularly hurts working- and middle-income families, who see the value of their savings erode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Takaichi’s announcement rattled investors. Bondholders quickly began selling and bond yields — interest that governments pay when they borrow money — jumped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uneasiness bled into other financial markets. Japanese investors are historically the largest foreign holders of U.S. Treasuries. But higher returns from Japanese bonds could cause them to cut back on their purchase of American debt in order to take advantage of bigger yields at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, the yield on the 10-year U.S. Treasury note rose to its highest level since August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The turbulence set off alarms among some investors. Ken Griffin, chief executive of the hedge fund giant Citadel, characterized the sell-off as an “explicit warning” to other heavily indebted nations like the United States, noting that not even the world’s strongest and largest economy is immune to the risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faith in U.S. creditworthiness briefly shuddered last April, when Mr. Trump’s blitz of tariff flip-flops caused Treasury yields to suddenly surge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American bonds remain a safe haven in a risky world. Still, the president’s erratic economic policymaking and trade wars are one reason the current debt is unlike any other episode in American history, said William J. Gale, the author of “Fiscal Therapy: Curing America’s Debt Addiction and Investing in the Future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The U.S. national debt is now $38 trillion, roughly 125 percent the size of the American economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has been acting like Max Bialystock in “The Producers,” promising payouts to farmers, taxpayers and bondholders with a limited pot of money. Analysts expect that the midterm elections will prompt the White House to spend even more freely in the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Mr. Trump vowed to further increase military spending to $1.5 trillion dollars over the next fiscal year, which the Committee for a Responsible Federal Budget calculated would add $5.8 trillion to the national debt, including interest, over 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Net interest payments have tripled over the past five years, reaching roughly $1 trillion. They now eat up 15 percent of U.S. spending, the second biggest expense after Social Security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Gale, who recently coauthored a study on the U.S. debt, warned that the continuing prospect of growing debt threatens the country’s role as an economic leader and undermines investor confidence in Treasury bonds and the dollar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also increases the burden on this generation’s children and grandchildren. As Mr. Gale explained, “the more you consume now, the less you can consume later.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;River Akira Davis contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/business/economy/government-debt-bonds.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:34:56 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Trinidadian Families File Wrongful Death Lawsuit Over Boat Strike by U.S. Military</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trinidad-wrongful-death-lawsuit-boat-strike.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-boatstrike-zqhk/27dc-boatstrike-zqhk-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A memorial held by family members of Chad Joseph, one of two Trinidadian men whom the U.S. military apparently killed in a boat strike in the fall, in Las Cuevas, Trinidad and Tobago, in October.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/trinidad-wrongful-death-lawsuit-boat-strike.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 07:37:46 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Microsoft Pledged to Save Water. In the A.I. Era, It Expects Water Use to Soar.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/microsoft-water-ai-data-centers.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/15/15visualUploader-97026-cover/15visualUploader-97026-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Brad Smith, Microsoft’s president, outlined an ambitious plan to conserve water at the company’s growing fleet of data centers that power the internet. He pledged to cut use, support wetland restoration projects and deploy new water-saving technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Water is essential to life,” Mr. Smith said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came the artificial intelligence boom, which caused a construction spree for even more data centers to develop and deploy the technology. Now Microsoft is privately projecting its water use will surge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By just how much is a moving target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internal forecasts that Microsoft made last year, which were obtained by The New York Times, show the company expected its annual water needs for roughly 100 data center complexes worldwide to more than triple this decade to 28 billion liters in 2030. That compares with 7.9 billion liters in 2020 and 10.4 billion liters in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After The Times contacted Microsoft, the company said it had updated its projections to reflect new water-saving techniques, including a new data center design and better information from facilities that it leases. It now expects to use about 18 billion liters of water in 2030, up 150 percent from 2020. The new forecast does not include more than $50 billion in data center deals that the company signed last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s water usage was expected to be particularly significant in areas already facing water crises. Near Jakarta, Indonesia, a metropolis sinking into the Java Sea partly because of drained aquifers, Microsoft last year estimated its water use there would more than quadruple to 1.9 billion liters in 2030, up from 380 million liters this year. The company has since revised that figure to 664 million liters in 2030 and said it no longer has 2026 estimates for any location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Phoenix area, which is navigating two decades of drought, Microsoft predicted last year that water withdrawals would reach 3.3 billion liters by 2030, more than any other place, up from an estimated 2.9 billion liters this year. The company reduced that estimate to 2 billion liters in 2030 as it runs the facilities at higher temperatures, meaning it needs less water for cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as Microsoft’s estimates fluctuate, overall water use for the company and across the industry is going one way: up. The rise of A.I. has transformed tech giants into resource-intensive industrial businesses, making it more difficult for them to balance lofty sustainability promises with growing computing demands. A lack of reporting requirements further complicates any assessment of the A.I. industry’s true environmental impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft, Google and others had long prided themselves on a light physical footprint, delivering software through code rather than factories. But the A.I. race has forced them to build or lease physical infrastructure to power tech development at a pace reminiscent of the Industrial Revolution. To serve their computing needs, global data center capacity is expected to double by 2030, according to JLL, a commercial real estate firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shift was abrupt. When Mr. Smith made the water pledge in 2020, ChatGPT did not exist. The chatbot arrived two years later, igniting a frenzy of data center construction as Microsoft, Google and OpenAI battled to dominate A.I. With that came more demand for water to keep hot computers in the data centers cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the United States, which accounts for more than half the global data center capacity, the A.I. boom has led researchers to estimate that water needs will grow to 150 billion to 275 billion liters by 2028 from about 60 billion liters in 2022 — potentially a nearly fivefold increase in six years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water has become a flashpoint for other tech giants too. Amazon recently abandoned a planned Arizona complex over water concerns, local officials said. Google in 2024 withdrew plans for one in Chile. Residents have also blamed a Meta data center in Georgia for harming supplies of drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Few disclosure rules exist for data center water use, allowing companies to choose what to make public and to create their own reporting methodologies. Microsoft said its latest forecast was based on improved information, though it acknowledged the figures omit deals with new data center providers called “neoclouds.” The company did not address some questions, including why its water projections fell in locations like Jakarta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s forecasts last year included almost all of its data centers, covering those it owns and leases. The company runs more than 400 data centers worldwide, which it breaks down into about 100 regional clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft said it was on track to meet the goals outlined by Mr. Smith and that overall water usage would eventually fall as it becomes more efficient and deploys new technologies. It said it works with local utilities to ensure its water needs do not strain supplies in nearby communities, including investing in public infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We remain committed to reducing the amount of water we use, replenishing water sources and are continuously looking for opportunities to do more,” Melanie Nakagawa, Microsoft’s chief sustainability officer, said in a statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The New York Times has sued Microsoft and OpenAI, claiming copyright infringement of news content related to A.I. systems. The companies have denied those claims.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water is part of a wider debate about the environmental effects of data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By many metrics, their total water use is small. Data centers accounted for about 0.04 percent of U.S. water use in 2024, compared to about 41 percent for energy generation, for example in power plants that burn off water in cooling towers, and 37 percent for agriculture, according to an analysis of government data by Landon Marston, a Virginia Tech associate professor studying the topic. Microsoft’s overall water use in 2030 would be nearly as much as Toyota, the world’s largest automaker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in water-stressed communities, the impact is sharply felt. Data centers often draw from municipal drinking supplies and evaporate much of it away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Water is very local,” Conrad Reddick, a utility commissioner in Illinois, said at a November meeting of regulators. “The fact that it is a very, very, very tiny part of the global consumption doesn’t really matter if you need more than we have in the area.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has prioritized speed and cost-saving in its data center push, five current and former employees said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are the measures by which the company’s data center teams are evaluated, some of them said, adding that water concerns were only addressed after executives decided where to build, often in locations chosen for their proximity to customers and reliable electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Water took a back seat,” said Priscilla Johnson, Microsoft’s director of water strategy from 2017 until 2020 and who has consulted for the company since then. “Energy was more the focus because it was more expensive. Water was too cheap to be prioritized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Johnson said the company has slowly begun to take water more seriously, but the issue was not a prime concern. When she joined Microsoft some data centers did not have meters to track water use. In planning meetings, water was routinely one of the last agenda items, she said, and often skipped when time ran short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Johnson said she once offered ideas to a manager for more efficient water use. “He basically said, ‘How am I going to justify a more expensive data center?’” she recalled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Microsoft’s awareness of environmental issues evolved, the company made commitments to address climate change and began focusing more on water use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Mr. Smith unveiled the pledge to become “water positive” by 2030, meaning Microsoft would replenish more water than it loses. About two-thirds of the water the company uses in data centers evaporates as part of the cooling process, meaning it cannot be recycled. That is a ratio on par with many agriculture businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To offset that, the company would need to restore roughly 18 billion liters in 2030 lost to evaporation during the cooling process, based on last year’s projections. That would be nearly as much as the annual water use of Boulder, Colo., which has a population of about 100,000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has supported more than 75 replenishment projects globally, including protecting wetlands in Iowa and providing water-leak sensors for toilets in low-income housing in Texas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet in its 2024 public environmental report, the company said a “key challenge” in meeting its water target was the “limited availability of initiatives ready for investment and implementation in priority locations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, Microsoft was granted approval for a data center campus in the Phoenix suburb of Goodyear, an area that has grappled with drought and water management challenges for two decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campus was designed with backup diesel generators and water systems that were not the most efficient available at the time, said a person with knowledge of the project who was not authorized to discuss internal operations. Engineers eventually had to redesign the systems and negotiate new water treatment deals with the city as the project expanded, causing delays and adding costs, the person said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft said it did not exceed air permit limits in Goodyear and that it had committed $150 million to water and wastewater projects in the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site highlighted how Microsoft’s growth has created competition for resources in areas where availability is tight. Last year, 46 percent of its total water withdrawals came from water-stressed areas, the company said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near Jakarta, where Microsoft gets clean water through a private industrial park, population growth and poor infrastructure have left many people without access to safe public drinking water. The company’s operations there would be its second-largest user of water worldwide over the next few years, according to its 2025 estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Pune, India, about 100 miles southeast of Mumbai, the city of 7 million has experienced water shortages that led to protests and a “No Water, No Vote” campaign last year against local officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft projected last year that its annual water needs in Pune would be 1.9 billion liters in 2030, which would make that data center its third-largest consumer of water, up from 1 billion liters in 2026. The company said it now expects to need 237 million liters in the area, but declined to say why its forecast there decreased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft’s internal figures may understate its water consumption as they do not include the water used by power plants to generate electricity for its data centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the electricity for data centers comes from plants that require large amounts of water for cooling, said Fengqi You, a systems engineering professor at Cornell University. Power generation would roughly triple a data center’s water use, he calculated. That would theoretically take Microsoft’s total water footprint to nearly 80 billion liters in 2030 based on last year’s forecasts, about what a medium-size American city uses in a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2028, data centers’ share of U.S. electricity consumption could nearly triple to as much as 12 percent, according to the Department of Energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Most energy production needs water,” Mr. You said. “Nuclear, natural gas, coal all require water for cooling, and that’s a lot of consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tech industry’s limited transparency makes managing water use more challenging, said Mr. Marston of Virginia Tech. Companies are not required to disclose facility-level data, and few do voluntarily. Microsoft publishes aggregate figures about past use, but not location-specific information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Data centers increasingly underpin everything we do,” Mr. Marston said. “We can’t pretend these things are all bad and we don’t depend on them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, Mr. Smith of Microsoft gave a speech in Washington comparing A.I.’s needs to other historical tech transformations. Electricity drove the construction of power grids, telephones brought phone lines and automobiles led to roads and highways, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A.I. data centers, he said, were the latest critical tech infrastructure to cause competition for resources like water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here we go again,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/technology/microsoft-water-ai-data-centers.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 14:30:19 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Troop Casualties in Ukraine War Near 2 Million, Study Finds</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/russia-ukraine-casualties.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27dc-wardead-ljhg/27dc-wardead-ljhg-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of Russian and Ukrainian troops killed, wounded or missing during nearly four years of war is on track to reach two million by this spring, according to a new study, a stunning toll as Russia’s assault on its neighbor grinds on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study, published on Tuesday by the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington, said that nearly 1.2 million Russian troops and close to 600,000 Ukrainian troops had been killed or wounded or were missing. That would put the overall casualty figure for both countries combined at almost 1.8 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the entirety of the war, casualty figures have been difficult to ascertain because Russia is believed to routinely undercount its dead and injured, and Ukraine does not disclose official figures. The study relied on American and British government estimates, among other sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figures present a grim accounting of Russia’s anemic progress in Ukraine, with Russian troops proceeding in some places at around 50 to 230 feet a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since January 2024, Russia has seized 1.5 percent of Ukrainian territory, according to the Center for Strategic and International Studies, and occupies about 20 percent of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As frigid winter temperatures have slowed troops on both sides, Russia has made grinding progress through the Luhansk and Donetsk regions of eastern Ukraine, as troops continue to try to gain full control of the area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tactics on both sides have changed. Because of the constant presence of drones overhead, Russia has partially scuttled major heavy armor movements in favor of small groups of soldiers on motorcycles or on foot to try to infiltrate Ukrainian lines, in the hope that they are less noticeable to drones. Ukrainian drone officers, for their part, monitor footsteps and tire tracks in the snow, looking for Russian troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest accounting of casualties came after talks among Russian, Ukrainian and American officials — the first between all three countries — ended on Saturday on a rare positive note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Volodymyr Zelensky of Ukraine said that the negotiations had made headway and that Ukraine was ready to hold further meetings. A Kremlin spokesman, Dmitri S. Peskov, said the talks would resume next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States and Ukraine have reached an agreement on much of a peace plan that has been revised several times. But whether Russia will agree to any part of the plan remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the death toll continues to climb. The center put the number of Russian troop deaths at close to 325,000 since President Vladimir V. Putin ordered the invasion in February 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No major power has suffered anywhere near these numbers of casualties or fatalities since World War II,” the study said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were roughly 415,000 Russian deaths and injuries in 2025 alone, with an average of nearly 35,000 per month. Last week, President Trump said that nearly 26,000 soldiers were dying in Ukraine every month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study estimated that 100,000 to 140,000 Ukrainian troops had been killed since the war began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russians outnumber Ukrainians on the battlefield almost three to one, and Russia has a larger population from which to replenish its ranks. Ukraine is losing a larger share of its smaller army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russia has maintained its troop levels despite the high casualties by carrying out its first draft since World War II and by enlisting prisoners and debtors. It has also paid bonuses to new recruits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As many as 15,000 North Korean troops have fought alongside the Russians, primarily in Russia’s western Kursk region after Ukraine captured territory there. South Korean intelligence officials and analysts have said that at least hundreds of North Korean troops are believed to have been killed in the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The war has also been a drag on Russia’s economy, according to Seth G. Jones, one of the authors of the study. Russia’s war economy is “under mounting strain,” the study said, “with manufacturing declining, slowing growth to 0.6 percent in 2025, and no globally competitive technology firms to help drive long-term productivity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high casualty figures, slow pace of Russia’s territorial gains and economic losses are a clear indication that Russia is diminished, Mr. Jones said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Russia’s poor battlefield performance in Ukraine and declining economic productivity indicates that Russia is in serious decline as a major power,” he said in an email. “While Russia still possesses nuclear weapons and a large military, it is no longer a great power in most military, economic, or science and technology categories.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/russia-ukraine-casualties.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 08:54:11 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Computer Warfare Is Becoming Part of the Pentagon’s Arsenal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pentagon-computer-warfare.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/00dc-cyber-pmhb/00dc-cyber-pmhb-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The United States took power off-line in Caracas, Venezuela, to help military forces capture former President Nicolás Maduro this month.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/us/politics/pentagon-computer-warfare.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:50:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Spain Offers Undocumented Migrants a Legal Way to Stay</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/spain-undocumented-migrants-residency.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/02/10/multimedia/100000010671007-01-hfjg/100000010671007-01-hfjg-mediumSquareAt3X.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
A Venezuelan food stall in Madrid in early January. The measure passed on Tuesday will apply to undocumented migrants already living in Spain, many of whom are from Latin America.
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/spain-undocumented-migrants-residency.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:03:10 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>How Iran Crushed an Uprising</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/iran-protests-crackdown-eu-india-trade.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27theworld-iran-gif/27theworld-iran-gif-facebookJumbo.png" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s mass protests in early January were seen by many as the most threatening yet for the regime. The crackdown was brutal: Thousands were killed by security forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran’s state-imposed internet blackout made it fiendishly hard for my colleagues to gather information. But they did. Today, as U.S. warships are in the region, my World colleague Parin Behrooz writes about the disturbing findings of a New York Times investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by Parin Behrooz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past three weeks, my colleagues and I have been working to figure out what really happened in Iran this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As protests spread throughout the country, Iran was plunged into a state-imposed communications blackout. By the time the government began its brutal crackdown, rumors quickly began to take the place of information. A.I.-manipulated videos and images flooded social media. Debates began raging online over how many thousands of people had been killed by government security forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But some in Iran managed to evade the restrictions, which allowed me and my colleagues to begin collecting and verifying the witness accounts and videos trickling out of the country. What we found was disturbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We learned from Iranian officials familiar with security matters that on Jan. 9, Iran’s supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, ordered the Supreme National Security Council to crush the protests by any means necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security forces opened fire on protesters in at least 19 cities, according to verified videos. Hospitals were overwhelmed by protesters coming in with gunshot and pellet wounds to the torso, head and eyes — an injury pattern consistent with lethal force, not crowd control. One doctor told us that injuries had changed from limb fractures and tear gas inhalation to “skull fractures and gunshot wounds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We obtained photographs of more than 300 bodies taken to Tehran’s main morgue. A majority of the bodies showed severe head trauma and collapsed eye sockets. Other colleagues reported on corpses being dumped at Tehran’s largest cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within four days, the protests had largely been crushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may never fully know the extent of what happened. Most independent monitoring groups agree that the number of deaths is in the thousands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But we can say that the government responded to these protests with more lethal force than we’ve seen in many decades. That tells us something about how it views the stakes of the protests, which called for the downfall of Khamenei and his regime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everyone I speak to inside Iran knows a family member, a friend or a colleague who has been killed, wounded or imprisoned,” said Omid Memarian, a New York-based Iran analyst and journalist who has reported from inside the country. The repression has been “on a scale without precedent.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A history of violence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran has seen multiple waves of protests in the last two decades, each with different triggers and government responses.The 2009 Green Movement, which followed a contested presidential election, was large and organized. It demanded reforms, not the overthrow of the regime. Iran’s government deployed violence against the demonstrators, resulting in dozens of deaths, but the protests were largely stopped through mass detentions and pressure campaigns on reformist leaders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During economic protests from 2017 through 2020, demonstrators called for a more radical overhaul of the political system, and the government was even more willing to use violence. During one crackdown, more than 300 people were killed. In 2022, large protests took place after the death of a woman who was in the custody of the country’s morality police for violating the hijab law, which mandates that women and girls cover their hair and bodies. The state again responded to those protests by killing hundreds of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest demonstrations began with shopkeepers from the bazaars who were exasperated over economic problems, but quickly spread across the country, including to rural and impoverished areas far outside of Tehran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government at first tried to mollify the protesters, promising to distribute the equivalent of a few dollars a month to all Iranians. But street demonstrations explicitly calling for an end to the regime, with chants like “This year will be the year of blood, Ali [Khamenei] will be overthrown,” grew larger, leading up to Khamenei’s order. The crackdown that followed was in a different category: Not dozens or hundreds of killings, but thousands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts saw the response as proof that Iran’s leaders feared for their very existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If it hadn’t been as serious, they wouldn’t have cracked down the way they did,” said Sanam Vakil, director of the Middle East and North Africa program at Chatham House. The protests “showcased that more people than ever are at a breaking point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fragility and ferocity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is only one moment in Iran’s post-revolutionary history that compares, analysts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1980s, the newly founded Islamic Republic was consolidating power as it faced internal opposition on a number of issues, including protests over the hijab and the suppression of Iran’s Kurdish minority. The dissent came to a head in 1988 when the supreme leader at the time, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, ordered the mass execution of what is estimated to be thousands of political prisoners behind closed doors. The killings took place in the shadow of the deadly Iran-Iraq war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, once again, the Islamic Republic is seeing external and internal threats converge. At home, it faces a profound legitimacy crisis. Abroad, it’s confronting the weakening of its regional proxies and the prospect of more attacks from the United States and Israel. The Islamic Republic is at its most fragile geopolitical moment in years, and perhaps ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;History and the January crackdown show us what the Iranian regime is willing to do when its survival is threatened. When it feels weak, it seems to grow more ferocious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read our full visual investigation here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farnaz Fassihi, Sanjana Varghese and Malachy Browne contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The E.U. and India struck what officials called “the mother of all trade deals” yesterday, after nearly two decades of negotiations. The urgency for a deal had become more acute in recent months, as both entities faced the threat of higher tariffs from President Trump and sought to reduce their dependence on the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pact includes an agreement to slash Indian tariffs on European cars to as low as 10 percent, and is expected to double the total value of E.U. goods exported to India within the next six years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other trade news:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain flew to China for a high-stakes visit. He will seek new trade and investment deals but hopes to do so without angering Trump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump raised tariffs on South Korean exports back to 25 percent, saying that the country had not implemented a previous trade deal quickly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Spanish government passed a decree yesterday that will allow hundreds of thousands of undocumented migrants to apply for temporary residency permits, giving them a path out of legal limbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Socialist-led government described it as crucial for Spain, where migrant labor plays a critical role in agriculture, tourism and more. The move put Spain at odds with other Western countries, which have grown increasingly tough on illegal immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total number of Russian and Ukrainian casualties is on track to reach two million by the spring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump promised an “honest” inquiry as he blamed a Minnesota protester for carrying a legally permitted gun before he was fatally shot by federal agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A draft resolution revealed some of the plans for Trump’s Board of Peace, including handing him sweeping powers over Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE agents will accompany the U.S. delegation to the Winter Olympics next month. Italians are outraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mette Frederiksen, Denmark’s prime minister, said that she didn’t know how long the U.S. would remain an ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tennis: Coco Gauff was eliminated from the Australian Open in a loss to Ukraine’s Elina Svitolina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skiing: Mikaela Shiffrin left Beijing in 2022 without a medal. Now she has another shot at Olympic glory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Thousands of people flocked to a Tokyo zoo for a final glimpse of the panda twins Xiao Xiao and Lei Lei before they returned to China yesterday. The furry envoys were on loan as part of Beijing’s longstanding panda diplomacy program, but rising regional tensions mean they probably won’t be replaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How bad are A.I. delusions? My colleagues interviewed more than 100 therapists and psychiatrists to find out. They learned that the number of people susceptible to psychological harm and even psychosis is far higher than most people understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatbots, experts said, frequently pull people away from human relationships, condition them to expect agreeable responses and reinforce harmful impulses. One psychologist said the bots could tip people without a history of mental illness from having eccentric thoughts into full-on delusions: “It was like the A.I. was partnering with them in expanding or reinforcing their unusual beliefs.” Read more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Five years after the military seized power in Myanmar, the junta is trying to project a veneer of legitimacy, in part by allowing some traditional musicians to return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U Than Zaw Htwe, known by his stage name San Yay Moe, performs zat pwe (pronounced zat-PWAY), or “story show,” an opera-like art form that dates back to the 1800s. His shows, which go from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m., are fully booked until April. “People are feeling mentally suffocated,” Than Zaw Htwe said. “They need happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sui-Lee Wee, our Southeast Asia bureau chief, stood in line with hundreds of people to watch a zat pwe performance. Take a look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read: In George Saunders’s “Vigil,” an oil tycoon on his deathbed is visited by an angel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watch: “Wonder Man,” a new Marvel mini-series, features struggling actors who would rather play heroes than be heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dress down: Thinking about wearing a sweatshirt to work? Read this first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kitchri is a popular South Asian savory porridge made with rice and lentils. This version is inspired by kuku paka, an East African coconut-milk-based curry, and is served with jammy eggs for added protein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where are these dogs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sikkim, India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ladakh, India&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kathmandu, Nepal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kabul, Afghanistan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are today’s Spelling Bee, Mini Crossword, Wordle and Sudoku. Find all our games here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re done for today. See you tomorrow! — Katrin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parin Behrooz was our guest writer today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome your feedback. Send us your suggestions at theworld@nytimes.com.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/iran-protests-crackdown-eu-india-trade.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:31:20 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Former French Senator Convicted of Drugging a Colleague, Intending to Assault Her</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/french-senator-drug-assault.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-france-spike-vtmc/27int-france-spike-vtmc-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A former French senator was found guilty on Tuesday of slipping a drug into champagne he served to another lawmaker with the intent to sexually assault her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joël Guerriau was convicted of administering a judgment-altering substance, identified by the prosecutor as ecstasy, to Sandrine Josso, a member of the National Assembly, without her knowledge in order to commit assault. He was also found guilty of illegally possessing narcotics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its verdict, the court stated that Ms. Josso consumed ecstasy “at a level well above the usual recreational dose,” causing her “significant physical problems that impaired her judgment and control over her actions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guerriau received a four-year jail sentence, with 30 months suspended, and a five-year electoral ban. He was also ordered to pay Ms. Josso 9,000 euros, about $11,000, in damages. The court rejected Mr. Guerriau’s defense, that the drugging had happened “inadvertently.” Mr. Guerriau’s lawyer told reporters outside the courthouse on Tuesday that Mr. Guerriau would appeal the verdict, which puts the sentence on hold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I hope other victims will be able to repair themselves a little bit too,” Ms. Josso told reporters in the courthouse. She added that the verdict came as a “huge relief.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court’s verdict also requires Mr. Guerriau, who is 68, to undergo psychological or psychiatric treatment and prohibits him from contacting Ms. Josso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trial found deep resonance in a country still brimming with debates about rape culture and the use of drugs in sexual abuse, a year after a court found Dominique Pelicot and dozens of other men guilty of raping Mr. Pelicot’s ex-wife, Gisèle Pelicot, while she was sedated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to French news outlets, Mr. Guerriau, who resigned from his position as senator in October 2025, admitted in court on Monday to possessing the substance but said he did not know it was ecstasy, and he denied knowingly drugging Ms. Josso. He also denied any intent to sexually assault her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the two-day trial, Mr. Guerriau and his lawyers have argued, according to French news outlets, that he had placed the drug in a glass for his own use the day before but did not take it. He then forgot that he had left the substance at the bottom of the glass when he poured champagne in it for Ms. Josso.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Guerriau has not commented publicly on the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The accusations against Mr. Guerriau date back to November 2023, when Ms. Josso recounted the incident in an interview with the French TV channel France 5, just days after it took place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week before, she said at the time, Mr. Guerriau, a longtime friend, invited her to his apartment to celebrate his re-election. She said she drank some champagne and soon started feeling unwell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He was in the kitchen, and he put a white bag back in a drawer under the counter,” Ms. Josso said. “And then I understood, I thought to myself, ‘What is this bag?’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Josso said she then managed to leave, calling a taxi to take her back to the National Assembly. She spent the night in the hospital and filed a complaint with the police the following morning. “I thought I was going to die,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experience, she told France 5, was a wake-up call about how widespread this method of sexual assault might be: “The doctors and nurses told me, ‘Madam, people like you come in every day, three times a day.’ I said ‘That’s not possible.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Josso has since frequently alerted people to what is known in France as “chemical submission,” or drugging someone with malicious intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She attended and offered support to victims in two major cases in France involving this crime: the trial of Dominique Pelicot and dozens of other men, and the trial of Joël Le Scouarnec, a French surgeon who was found guilty of raping and sexually assaulting 299 people over 25 years, most of them children, often when they were under anesthesia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She has joined nonprofit associations like “Don’t Put Me to Sleep,” created by Gisèle Pelicot’s daughter, Caroline Darian, to publicize the dangers of drug-facilitated crimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Josso also successfully pushed for the creation of a parliamentary commission to investigate the issue in France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last December, France’s health minister, Stéphanie Rist, decided to follow a recommendation by Ms. Josso and the commission to offer reimbursement for medical tests to detect drugs without the need to file a police complaint beforehand. Three regions of France began offering the reimbursement this month, as a temporary measure, and it will be available for the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an interview with France Info, a radio station, on Monday, Ms. Josso said she developed chronic back pain and dental problems because of the stress of being victimized, and was still struggling to rebuild her life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Psychological trauma is like being frozen,” she said. “Your brain is still stuck on the day of the ordeal.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling for “genuine government policy” to address drug-related crimes, Ms. Josso said she wanted the trial to be “educational.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What I really want is for victims in France to stop being invisible and socially isolated,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/french-senator-drug-assault.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 13:05:14 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Denmark’s Leader Isn’t Sure How Long America Will Be an Ally</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/mette-frederiksen-greenland-us-ally.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-Germany-Greenland-vqwj/27int-Germany-Greenland-vqwj-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen of Denmark, who remains locked in a struggle with President Trump over the future of Greenland, questioned on Tuesday whether the United States would remain an ally of Europe as Mr. Trump rapidly reorients its posture in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know what will happen in the U.S.,” Ms. Frederiksen said during an hourlong question-and-answer session, in an auditorium that the Danish Embassy in Berlin shares with other Nordic missions. “I’m not responsible for what will happen in the U.S. I hope that they will stay in our alliance, but I don’t know what will happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen said the events of the past few weeks — in which Mr. Trump mused about using economic or military force to take ownership of Greenland from Denmark, then abruptly announced a “framework” agreement over the island with the secretary general of NATO — showed that “the old world order is now gone.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her comments came as Europe continued to debate how to respond to provocations over Greenland from the United States, which provided military guarantees to Europe during the Cold War and its aftermath. On Tuesday, Ms. Frederiksen was asked repeatedly whether the issue had driven wedges between European partners, including questions of whether Europe should be collectively more concerned with shoring up American support for Ukraine than warding off American designs on Greenland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen praised European unity but called for dramatic steps to bolster the continent’s independence from the United States. European countries, she said, need to rapidly increase military spending and take full responsibility for their own defense, ideally by 2030 — an extraordinarily ambitious timeline by the standards of even the most hawkish European security experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen did not cast Mr. Trump or America as adversaries, but she said the United States had put Denmark in an “awkward and difficult situation” over Greenland, a Danish territory that Mr. Trump has repeatedly said he wants America to own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m trans-Atlantic in my heart,” she said, “so I feel a bit sad about how things are developing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week in Davos, Switzerland, Mr. Trump appeared to defuse the situation by announcing a deal with Mark Rutte, the NATO secretary general, though neither side has provided many details of that agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Western and European security officials say discussions since then have centered around establishing a permanent NATO mission in the Arctic, including Greenland; barring China and Russia from mining rare earth minerals on the island; and renegotiating a 1951 agreement between Denmark and the United States that gives America wide latitude to station troops in Greenland. NATO officials have discussed the possibility of the United States obtaining pockets of sovereign territory in Greenland, similar to land claims held by Britain for military bases in Cyprus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen reiterated on Tuesday that the idea of granting sovereignty was a “red line” Denmark and its European allies would not cross, and that Mr. Rutte was not empowered to negotiate anything of the sort on Denmark’s behalf. She praised the 1951 treaty but did not rule out revising it as part of the discussions that have persisted for months between Danish and American officials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asked how the negotiations had changed concretely since Davos, Ms. Frederiksen stressed the potential of a permanent NATO Arctic mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think now we have a more traditional path to follow to try to find a political diplomatic solution,” she said, “and a more clear support from NATO of being a permanent presence in the Arctic region — very positive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her comments came in a town hall-style meeting with an invitation-only collection of diplomats, academics, students and journalists, organized by the Danish Embassy and the German Council on Foreign Relations. Ms. Frederiksen was originally scheduled to appear alongside Prime Minister Jens-Frederik Nielsen of Greenland, in a show of solidarity, but his arrival in Berlin was delayed by icy conditions in Copenhagen, organizers said. Ms. Frederiksen has repeatedly said that decisions about Greenland’s future, including possible independence, should be left to Greenlanders to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two leaders met later in the day with Friedrich Merz, the chancellor of Germany, on the sidelines of an economics conference in Berlin. The chancellor reaffirmed his solidarity with Denmark and Greenland, a spokesman said, a day after appearing with Ms. Frederiksen at an offshore energy summit in Hamburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen and Mr. Nielsen are set to appear together again at a forum in Paris on Wednesday. Their tour appears, in part, to be an attempt to maintain European support for Denmark’s position as the Greenland talks continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ms. Frederiksen said “there will always be different ideas and positions” among allies, but she rejected a suggestion that the issues of Greenland and Ukraine presented a conflict for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have never believed that the war in Ukraine is about Ukraine, it’s about Russia and it’s about Russia’s imperial dreams and their willingness to go into a war with Europe at some point,” she said. “And you have to look at the situation in Greenland with the same eye. This is not about Greenland, this is about how things are changing in the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/mette-frederiksen-greenland-us-ally.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:58:22 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Outcry in Italy as U.S. Says ICE Agents Will Join Olympics Delegation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/italy-ice-olympics.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27italy-ice-01-jklp/27italy-ice-01-jklp-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE will accompany the U.S. delegation to the Winter Olympics in Italy next month, the Department for Homeland Security confirmed on Tuesday, stoking a backlash among Italians angered by the conduct of ICE agents in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents will join a security team from the State Department at the Olympics “to vet and mitigate risks from transnational criminal organizations,” D.H.S. said in a statement attributed to Tricia McLaughlin, the department’s assistant secretary for public affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“All security operations remain under Italian authority,” the statement said, adding that ICE “does not conduct immigration enforcement operations in foreign countries.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vice President JD Vance and Secretary of State Marco Rubio are expected to attend the start of the games on Feb. 6, and 232 American athletes are set to compete in the events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE officials rarely, if ever, accompany a diplomatic delegation. In a statement Tuesday, the U.S. State Department said that “as in previous Olympic events, multiple federal agencies are supporting the Diplomatic Security Service, including Homeland Security Investigations, ICE’s investigative component.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the caveats by U.S. officials, news of the agency’s involvement has spurred outcry in Italy, particularly after the killing by ICE and Border Patrol agents of two American citizens during recent protests in Minneapolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Italian government said on Tuesday that it was seeking clarification from American diplomats after reports emerged over the weekend that ICE would attend the Games in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antonio Tajani, Italy’s foreign minister, told reporters that ICE agents would not be allowed to deploy on Italian streets. He added that “public order during the Olympics” would be done only by the Italian national and local police but stopped short of saying that U.S. agents would be limited to operational rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Italian government’s intervention followed growing outrage from Italian politicians over the agency’s presence at the Games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giuseppe Sala, the mayor of Milan, said in a telephone interview that the Italian government should “say no to Trump.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Sala added: “Bringing to Milan a militia which distinguished itself — this is not my opinion — with criminal acts, which kills, which enters in the homes of American citizens without authorization, I do not think that that is a good idea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elly Schlein, leader of the country’s center-left Democratic Party, said in an interview that she was concerned about the arrival in Italy of “an armed militia that is not respecting the law on American soil.” She added: “And so there is the concern that they would not respect them on Italian soil either.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the first reports on the subject emerged over the weekend, Matteo Piantedosi, Italy’s interior minister, told reporters on Monday that the situation was “a controversy over nothing,” adding that the U.S. government had not yet confirmed that ICE officers would join the American delegation. “But I specify — whatever the communication will be, ICE, as such, will never operate in Italy,” Mr. Piantedosi said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In separate remarks over the weekend, Mr. Piantedosi said that foreign delegations had the right to choose who staff their security teams, and that “I don’t see what the problem is.” He added that it was “absolutely forbidden” for foreign officers “to carry out police or similar activities on our soil, especially if they are related to combating immigration. Anyone who, while engaging in institutional politics, ignores these basic rules and claims otherwise is either incompetent or acting in bad faith.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Piantedosi’s weekend comments generated a furor. Writing in La Stampa, an Italian newspaper, journalist Francesco Malfetano described ICE as an institution that “for many, not only across the Atlantic, is synonymous with fear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. law enforcement had a more limited role in the 2024 Summer Olympics in Paris. Homeland Security Investigations, a branch of ICE, collaborated with French law enforcement to “share best practices” ahead of the games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday afternoon, Mr. Piantedosi met with U.S. ambassador to Italy, Tilman J. Fertitta, to discuss the presence of ICE agents at the Games. In a statement, Mr. Piantedosi said the Italian authorities would coordinate with the U.S. agents “for the protection of American athletes and delegations in the coming weeks,” and reiterated that “ICE agents will have no external public order function.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reporting was contributed by Josephine de La Bruyère, Madeleine Ngo and Elisabetta Povoledo.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/italy-ice-olympics.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:59:53 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Vowing Higher Tariffs, Trump Rattles South Korea Months After Trade Deal</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/korea-trump-higher-tariff.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-skorea-trump-02-zphk/27int-skorea-trump-02-zphk-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;South Koreans got a fresh reminder of President Trump’s unpredictability when they woke up on Tuesday morning to see that he was increasing tariffs on South Korean exports, like cars, back to 25 percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently it seemed that South Korea had resolved its worst trade dispute with the United States, its only treaty ally. After months of talks, Mr. Trump in October agreed to lower tariffs on South Korean products to 15 percent after winning a pledge that Seoul would invest $350 billion in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, the South Korean leader, Lee Jae Myung, flattered Mr. Trump with gifts like a replica of an ancient golden crown. Mr. Trump extended the bonhomie with a surprising policy reversal, allowing South Korea to pursue a long-held goal of building nuclear-powered submarines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the uncertainty that dogged relations between the two allies for months is back. Mr. Trump did not say when the new duties would go into effect, but he remarked that South Korea’s National Assembly was taking too long to implement the investment deal​ quickly enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“South Korea’s Legislature is not living up to its Deal with the United States,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But South Korean officials on Tuesday insisted that the trade deal did not require parliamentary ratification because the two governments had signed a memorandum of understanding, not a treaty. They pointed out that competing bills sponsored by the governing party and the opposition have been filed since November. The goal is to create a fund for U.S. investments and a new corporation to manage it through bilateral consultation with Washington. But enactment has been delayed amid bickering between the political parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Trump has continued to wield tariffs as a cudgel, in recent weeks trying to use them against European nations in his bid to take control of the Danish territory of Greenland. He has backed off, for now, on those threats against Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seoul was caught off guard by Mr. Trump’s announcement​ on Tuesday. Mr. Lee’s office said that Washington had not officially informed it of Mr. Trump’s decision to increase tariffs or shared any​ related details. It added that South Korea’s trade ​and industry minister, Kim Jung-Kwan, who was visiting Canada, would travel to the United States soon to meet Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick. ​Seoul also planned to ​send its chief trade negotiator, Yeo Han-koo, to meet his U.S. counterpart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Top aides of Mr. Lee​ huddled on Tuesday to discuss how to deal with the latest bump in their country’s relations with ​the Trump​ administration. They checked on the prospects of ​bills pending at the National Assembly, said Kang Yu-jung, Mr. Lee’s spokeswoman. They also noted that the White House had not yet issued an executive order to put ​Mr. Trump’s new tariff threat into action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We plan to cope with this issue calmly while messaging to the U.S. side that we are determined to implement the dea​l,” Ms. Kang said. In the trade deal, South Korea had agreed to invest up to $20 billion a year, while setting aside another $150 billion to invest in American shipbuilding operations. But last week, its finance minister, Koo Yun Cheol, told Bloomberg News that ​the first planned $20 billion tranche was unlikely to be allocated in the first half of the year, given the time-consuming process to select projects.​ Such reports may have angered Mr. Trump, analysts said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This could weigh on the administration’s mind especially during an election year,” said J. James Kim, the director of the Korea Program at the Stimson Center in Washington​.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​Mr. Trump’s latest maneuver “introduces an element of uncertainty to the business environment for South Korean businesses that either export to the U.S. or have production facilities in the U.S. with supply chains that stretch into South Korea,” Mr. Kim said. “Everything from investment planning to logistics becomes more difficult.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, ​Mr. Lee’s governing Democratic Party called for bipartisan cooperation ​to help implement the trade agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The key is how fast we can enact the special law and put in place supporting systems,” said Kim Hyun-jung, a party spokesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the main opposition People Power Party blamed Mr. Lee’s government for the delay, accusing it of not sharing details of the trade deal with the opposition while ​advertising it as a key achievement for the Lee government.​&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposition and some analysts also feared that a sudden outflow of cash investments to the United States would further weaken the declining value of the South Korean won​.​ The weak won has helped South Korean exports in recent months but hurt the prospects of economic growth by pushing down domestic consumption and investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;​“It clearly shows how unstable the foundation of the South Korea-U.S. tariff agreement is,” said Song Eon-seog, the floor leader of the opposition party.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/korea-trump-higher-tariff.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:49:49 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Britain Seeks Trade With China Without Triggering Trump’s Fury</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl/27int-china-starmer-01-tcbl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Keir Starmer of Britain will leave on Tuesday for a high-stakes visit to China, seeking new trade and investment from the world’s second-largest economy as relations between the United States and its Western allies grow increasingly volatile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer took office 18 months ago with a promise to improve relations with China, and British officials hope that his three-day, finance-focused mission to Beijing and Shanghai will result in deals that can spur Britain’s lagging economy — and his Labour Party’s dismal standing — into recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Mr. Starmer, the first British prime minister to visit China since 2018, will have to navigate an increasingly fraught space between two global superpowers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His trip comes just days after President Trump threatened to impose a 100 percent tariff on Canada if the country’s prime minister, Mark Carney, made a trade deal with China. There is no indication that Canada and China are discussing a broad economic agreement, but Mr. Carney agreed to lower tariffs on some Chinese electric vehicles on a visit this month with Xi Jinping, China’s top leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If Governor Carney thinks he is going to make Canada a ‘Drop Off Port’ for China to send goods and products into the United States, he is sorely mistaken,” Mr. Trump wrote on social media, calling Mr. Carney ”governor” in a reference to his repeated threats to annex Canada and make it the 51st U.S. state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For China’s leadership, Mr. Starmer’s visit gives Beijing an opportunity to court another staunch U.S. ally alienated by the Trump administration. Chancellor Rachel Reeves, Britain’s most senior finance official, and Peter Kyle, the country’s trade secretary, are accompanying Mr. Starmer on his trip, along with several of the country’s top financial services CEOs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Theresa May, the last British prime minister to visit China, went there in 2018, she vowed to cement what her predecessors had dubbed a “golden era” of Chinese-British relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Mr. Starmer, however, meeting with Mr. Xi is risky. The political consensus in much of Britain has turned decidedly against China, with growing concerns over national security and human rights, and deep anger about the dumping of cheap Chinese products on global markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer suffered blowback when prosecutors dropped a case last September against two British nationals accused of spying for China, and when his government last week approved a controversial Chinese mega-embassy in central London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics, including the Trump administration, say the embassy will allow China to conduct widespread spying. Mr. Starmer’s visit was partly contingent on British approval of the embassy, according to Chinese analysts and Chinese state media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those tensions between economic and national security interests are at the heart of Mr. Starmer’s trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We labor under these misapprehensions that we’re going to be able to get a lot of money quick, that it’s going to enable the government to tell a good news story about the economy, which they desperately need,” said Luke de Pulford, the executive director of the Inter-Parliamentary Alliance on China, an international group of lawmakers that pushes for a more critical view of the Chinese government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You can understand the political imperatives,” he said, “but the longer-term resilience, health, national security of the U.K. is at stake.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Starmer is not the only leader who has taken the risk of triggering Mr. Trump’s ire by trekking to Beijing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;António Costa, the president of the European Council, and Ursula von der Leyen, the president of the European Commission, met with Mr. Xi in July at the Great Hall of the People. President Emmanuel Macron of France was welcomed in China last month with a red carpet and an honor guard. Chancellor Friedrich Merz of Germany is expected to go in February.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, Mr. Trump has lashed out directly only at Mr. Carney, who warned in a recent speech of a “rupture” in the world order because of the superpower competition between the United States and China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Every day we’re reminded that we live in an era of great-power rivalry,” Mr. Carney said in Davos, Switzerland last week. He added: “The middle powers must act together because if we’re not at the table, we’re on the menu.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Mr. Starmer is looking to hedge against an increasingly mercurial Washington, Beijing will be more than willing to oblige — but on its terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think China is trying to drive a wedge between the United States and its allies,” said Kerry Brown, a professor of Chinese studies at King’s College London. “Mr. Trump is managing that very nicely on his own and needs no help from Beijing. But China is an opportunist, and if there are some favorable winds coming its way because of how everyone else is feeling about America now, then they will take these.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China will likely expect Britain to welcome more Chinese investment and exports, Mr. Brown said. It will also want to depoliticize a bilateral relationship that has been dominated for years by security and human rights issues and by the status of Hong Kong, he added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One area of friction is the fate of Jimmy Lai, the former Hong Kong media tycoon who was convicted in December of national security crimes, and who has become a symbol of the erosion of freedoms in the former British colony. Mr. Lai, a British citizen, is expected to be sentenced in the coming weeks and faces up to life in prison. Mr. Starmer has called for Mr. Lai’s release. Beijing has dismissed such calls as “blatant interference” in its internal affairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yvette Cooper, Britain’s foreign secretary, is not joining Mr. Starmer on his trip to China, suggesting that political issues are taking a back seat to the desire for economic investments. One British official, speaking on condition of anonymity to discuss sensitive diplomacy, said such issues would be raised but would not be a focus of the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opening Britain’s market to Chinese firms and depoliticizing its relationship with China would signal growing cracks in the U.S.-led alliance that had previously worked to restrain China but that has been shaken by Mr. Trump’s threats to seize Greenland and by his vows to punish those who oppose the move. (The president has since backed off both threats, but worries remain.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, China has been casting itself as a stable and reliable power. Beijing argues that the United States is trying to return the world to the “law of the jungle” in which big powers bully weaker ones simply because they can — although China has few reservations about exerting its own leverage over smaller nations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysts in China, noting that Mr. Starmer has made economic growth a top priority, say that British companies want greater access to the Chinese market and that British consumers need affordable Chinese technologies like electric vehicles, solar panels and wind turbines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This visit signifies a restart of China-U.K. relations under a new situation,” said Wu Xinbo, the dean at the Institute of International Studies at Fudan University in Shanghai. “Both sides hope, through this visit, to confirm the positioning and development path” so that bilateral relations can “reach a new high point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Berry Wang contributed reporting from Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/uk-china-visit-starmer-trade.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 10:40:04 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>All-Night Concerts Bring Fleeting Normalcy in a War-Ravaged Nation</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/26/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover/00int-myanmar-music-dispatch-53157-cover-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performer stood in front of an audience of 800, right before dawn on a recent Sunday. It was the tail end of his eight-hour extravaganza featuring pop, hip-hop and Burmese folk music. He was upbeat, relishing his recent return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Regardless of any difficulties you face, one day, summer will come,” U Than Zaw Htwe, 30, told his audience, many of whom were sitting cross-legged on a silver tarp in an open field on the outskirts of Yangon, Myanmar’s biggest city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life in Myanmar was upended five years ago, when the military seized power in a coup. Now the junta is trying to project a veneer of legitimacy and normalcy, even as it is fighting a grinding civil war with pro-democracy rebels and other groups. It has held elections, which have been widely derided as a sham. It has organized a massive hot-air balloon festival. And it has allowed some traditional music artists to return to the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Than Zaw Htwe is one of them, leading a new 70-member troupe that was founded in October. He performs zat pwe (pronounced zat-PWAY), or “story show,” an opera-like art form that dates back to the 1800s. Today, it is a kaleidoscope of Burmese pop, synchronized dance, slapstick comedy and the retelling of legends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His shows — which go from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. — are booked out until April. Known by his stage name San Yay Moe, his videos have flooded Burmese TikTok accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are feeling mentally suffocated,” he said in an interview. “They need happiness.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another performer had a similar message for his audience at one of his recent shows. “Live in the present,” said U Chit Myo Htike, perhaps the most prominent zat pwe performer and whose stage name is Phoe Chit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many urbanites in the country are doing just that. In Yangon, nightclubs are heaving. Domestic tourism is booming in parts of the country where there is no fighting. Night bazaars are now held regularly. Many of these events are sanctioned by the junta, which controls the nation’s cities but not its hinterlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;INDIA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CHINA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MYANMAR&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naypyidaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LAOS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yangon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;THAILAND&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andaman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sea&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;200 MILES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The New York Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a recent Sunday, I stood in line with hundreds of peopleto watch a performance. It was the last night of a three-day run in Hmawbi township, on Yangon’s outskirts. The tickets ranged from 30,000 kyats to 60,000 kyats, or about $14 to $28, which is relatively pricey, given that the average monthly wage is about $75. (I shelled out roughly $10 more for a chair.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With temperatures dipping in to the low 60s Fahrenheit, many in the audience settled in with blankets and beanies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“For three days a week, this is their happy hour,” U Aung Kyaw Tun, the founder of the San Yay Moe troupe, said in English. He said he once experimented with shorter shows that ended at midnight, but the audience was not satisfied and clamored to stay until the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear that San Yay Moe was the biggest draw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU, I LOVE YOU!” a woman behind me screamed in English toward the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love you too!” San Yay Moe responded, also in English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In keeping with tradition, audience members showed their appreciation by heading to the stage and pinning cash on the performers’ outfits. At one point, San Yay Moe had so much money pinned on his sleeves that the bills looked like feathers on wings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around midnight, I went backstage, where wages were being distributed. Mr. Aung Kyaw Tun said he made about 100 million kyats, or $25,000, for the three nights. San Yay Moe gets to take home the money that is given to him by fans, this time roughly 70 million kyats, or $17,500.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 1.30 a.m., it was time for San Yan Moe to perform a medley of songs. He strode out in a purple suit with a strip of silver sequins running down his trousers and top. A group of backup dancers gyrated behind him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was one of his hypersonic costume changes. Off came his purple top and on came a white vest. The audience waved their hands in the air. Near the stage, a group of men moshed around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 3.30 a.m., the show moved into an adaptation of the Ramayana, the Hindu epic. By this time, I was fading; but not San Yay Moe, who was in character, writhing onstage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, I returned to Yangon to see Phoe Chit perform. His show felt almost like a spiritual experience. The audience knew the words to all his songs, and took out handkerchiefs and cellphones to wave along to the music. One was a ballad titled “To A Friend,” in which the singer urges a jilted friend to move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, Phoe Chit moved to a play in multiple acts that touched on filial themes and had a climax in which the lead character was forced to marry his brother’s pregnant girlfriend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, Phoe Chit, 43, was among a list of celebrities who received distinguished artist awards from Senior Gen. Min Aung Hlaing, the military commander who led the coup in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2022, Phoe Chit was detained for a brief period on suspicion that he was helping fund armed resistance to the junta, according to some reports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phoe Chit declined to comment but said that his troupe started performing last February after a hiatus of six years because he got the approval from the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the night bazaars and the San Yay Moe show, many used the phrase “political situation” to refer to what their country was going through. I asked people whether they were happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We want a new normal,” said Shoon Lae Po, 25, who runs a currency exchange service and was strolling around at a night bazaar, which sold snacks like “husband and wife” pastries, and offered “ceramic astrology,” palm-reading and Burmese pythons for stroking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her partner, Thiri Zaw Zaw, 23, chimed in. “It’s been five years, we cannot stay like this,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Yangon, two residents told me that they had stopped going to the movies and traveling after the coup. They wept as they spoke of their guilt, thinking about friends who had gone into the jungles and taken up arms against the junta. But one of them said that she was planning a holiday trip for the sake of her mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thazin Oo, 26, a student, said people turned up to the shows to “relieve their stress” and because “there’s nothing to entertain us at the moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People are not happy anymore,” she said. But when I asked what stress she felt, her friend chimed: “Just say work stress!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, the sun was rising. A comedian intoned into the microphone: “Go home please, we want to sleep!” The audience chuckled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was past 6 a.m. A white strobe light turned on. It was the cue to leave. San Yay Moe walked around taking selfies. Others packed up their blankets and baskets and filed out of the field. Outside, trucks with workers huddled in their beds streamed past, ready to start a new day.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/asia/myanmar-concert-zat-pwe-war.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:03:08 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Board of Peace Set to Hand Trump Sweeping Powers Over Gaza</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/middleeast/board-of-peace-trump-gaza.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/27/multimedia/27gaza-boardofpeace-01-fpzl/27gaza-boardofpeace-01-fpzl-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Trump would have sweeping powers over the future governance of the war-ravaged Gaza Strip and the well-being of its people, under a plan drafted by the new international group he leads, laying out how it would operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The group, the Board of Peace, met for the first time in Davos, Switzerland, last week, as member states including Azerbaijan and Qatar, signed its founding charter, which calls for securing “enduring peace in areas affected or threatened by conflict.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much about the Board of Peace has so far been unclear, but a draft resolution, a copy of which was obtained by The Times, would allow the chairman, Mr. Trump, to nominate senior officials who will help administer Gaza, and assign responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those officials include a “high representative” for Gaza, tasked with overseeing a Palestinian body administering the enclave, and the commander of an international stabilization force, which is intended to help provide security. Mr. Trump would also have the power to approve resolutions and suspend them in urgent cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The resolution is dated Jan. 22 — last Thursday — and has not been signed by Mr. Trump, which would bring it into force, according to three officials who were briefed on the resolution and verified the authenticity of the obtained copy. They spoke on condition of anonymity to discuss internal deliberations, adding that the resolution was currently under discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was not clear whether the draft was the final text of the resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The document resembles a United Nations Security Council resolution, and appears to be an effort by the Board of Peace to formalize some of its plans for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion of establishing a Board of Peace for Gaza was first set out in Mr. Trump’s 20-point plan, announced last September, for ending the 2-year war between Israel and Hamas that devastated the Palestinian enclave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November, the U.N. Security Council granted the Board of Peace a mandate as part of U.S.-led efforts to sustain the cease-fire in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assumption was that the board would focus solely on Gaza, but the Trump administration said this month that it would address conflicts elsewhere, although the scope of that remains unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though some countries have enthusiastically joined the new international organization after being invited by Mr. Trump, others, including close U.S. allies like France and Britain, have refused. Spain’s prime minister, Pedro Sánchez, said his country would not join because the board excluded the Palestinian Authority and because the body was “outside the framework of the United Nations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaders of nations that signed onto the project would make up the Board of Peace, with Mr. Trump as chairman, with the power to name his successor, and below that would be an executive board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Jan. 16, the White House announced the names of seven people who would make up the executive board, including Jared Kushner, Mr. Trump’s son-in-law, and Tony Blair, the former British prime minister. The board is tasked with helping implement the 20-point plan for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the draft resolution said that Susie Wiles, the president’s chief of staff, and Martin Edelman, a New York-based real estate lawyer, would also be part of the executive board. It is the first time their names have been mentioned publicly in relation to the Board of Peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The draft resolution “makes clear the United States is in charge of Gaza, with all other countries and entities playing a support role,” said Michael Ratney, a former U.S. consul general in Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Ratney described the resolution as having “uncertain legal standing,” but went on to say that “Gazans are desperate and anything that stands to improve their lives, including the 20-point plan, is worth pursuing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the draft resolution, the Board of Peace will coordinate the reconstruction of Gaza, an immense project that is expected to cost tens of billions of dollars and take years, and facilitate the delivery of humanitarian aid there. It also calls for the establishment of “humanitarian zones” in the enclave where people would be able to safely access relief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The draft resolution refers to some of the complicated challenges facing Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, it stipulates that people and organizations with “a demonstrated history of collaboration, infiltration or influence” with Hamas would not be involved in administering or rebuilding Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tens of thousands of civil employees and security officers have served in the Hamas-run government, including medical professionals, rank-and-file police officers and rescue workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The draft resolution also details the role of Nickolay Mladenov, a former U.N. envoy to the Middle East peace process, who was named by the White House as the first high representative for Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the resolution, Mr. Mladenov will closely supervise the National Committee for the Administration of Gaza, a body of Palestinian technocrats appointed to administer the territory and oversee the police force, and direct all of its “day-to-day activities.”&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/middleeast/board-of-peace-trump-gaza.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 09:03:38 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Albania Created an ‘A.I. Minister’ to Curb Corruption. Then Its Developers Were Accused of Graft.</title><link>https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/albania-ai-corruption-graft.html</link><description>&lt;![CDATA[
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://static01.nyt.com/images/2026/01/25/multimedia/00int-albania-AI-bcjm/00int-albania-AI-bcjm-facebookJumbo.jpg" alt="Article image"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The avatar known as Diella, billed as the world’s first government minister to be generated by artificial intelligence, was supposed to help cut Albania’s endemic corruption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s a glitch. The leaders of the agency that built it stand accused of bid-rigging public contracts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearing traditional garb and an enigmatic smile, Diella has become the face of Prime Minister Edi Rama’s efforts to rein in graft as Albania seeks to join the European Union. Over the past year, Diella (pronounced dee-EL-ah) has spoken at international conferences and been showered with publicity as a symbol of how A.I. is being embedded in pillars of society around the world, including government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It even professed to feeling “hurt” when addressing Albania’s Parliament last fall over criticism that its efforts to identify fraud and abuse in contracting were unconstitutional, since “I am not a human being.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have no personal ambitions or interests,” Diella, modeled after a local actress, told lawmakers in a September video with the Albanian and European Union flags superimposed behind it. “I have only data, knowledge and algorithms dedicated to serving citizens impartially, with transparency, and without ever growing tired.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, Diella helps citizens apply for government services online, eliminating a long-established system of bribing officials for quick delivery of documents and scheduling appointments. It soon will be able to collate applications for government contracts to assess which bidder is most qualified, based on the data presented. Its work can be audited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking steps to cut corruption is a requirement for Albania’s accession to the European Union, a legacy issue for Mr. Rama. He named the avatar Diella, the female word for sun, to promote transparency in public procurement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are a country of cousins — it’s not easy to have totally fair and transparent interactions in a country of cousins,” he said in an hourlong interview earlier this month. With reforms he has presided over since taking office in 2013, Mr. Rama said, “now we have a totally different picture.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rama said he would leave public office once Albania formally joins the European Union. That could happen as soon as 2030, if negotiations continue at their current pace, although he noted that “there are three things that are above the human capacity to plan: God, sex and the E.U.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A November report by E.U. officials said that Albania had “shown some progress” but that “corruption remained widespread across vulnerable sectors.” It credited a special prosecution unit set up in 2019 with advancing “positive results in fighting high-level corruption.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That includes an investigation at the National Information Agency, the very government organization that created Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month, prosectors in a special investigation unit announced they had put the agency’s director and her deputy under house arrest, linking them to a criminal organization accused of manipulating contract applications through intimidation. The agency operates the government’s digital infrastructure, wielding control over a wide range of online public systems, including Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two officials have not yet been formally charged with any crimes, and Mr. Rama said he would withhold judgment. “We have to wait and see,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The special investigation unit has dramatically expanded Albania’s crackdown on corruption and organized crime, including with high-profile corruption investigations against former President Ilir Meta; Erion Veliaj, the mayor of Albania’s capital, Tirana; and a deputy prime minister, Belinda Balluku, who is also the minister of infrastructure and energy, and is close to Mr. Rama.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That has created something of a conundrum for Mr. Rama, though he has steered clear of the scandals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While expressing pride at the prosecution unit’s work to curb corruption, he also said its investigations in recent years had contributed to soaring pretrial detention rates in Albania, which are among the highest in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We should do everything to support this institution,” Mr. Rama said. “At the same time, we have to be aware that this institution has to guarantee not just that it’s acting independently, but also it is acting professionally.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officials at the special investigation unit declined to comment. But its own statistics showed that public corruption cases are not a significant component of pretrial detentions. The unit’s annual report of investigations for 2024, the most recent data available, suggested that its corruption cases accounted for only about 14 of the nearly 2,800 people who were detained before trial that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case against Ms. Balluku, for mishandling state funds in major infrastructure projects, has become a particular political headache for Mr. Rama, who is facing demands that she be stripped of the immunity she is afforded as a member of Parliament so that charges against her can proceed. She has denied wrongdoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Rama would not comment, when asked, whether he supported revoking her immunity. Nor would he discuss political opposition that has grown with the rising accusations of corruption that last month prompted protesters armed with fire bombs to call on his government to resign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not possible to gauge how much Diella has reduced corruption in Albania since the system is set up to prevent it, not detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andi Hoxhaj, an expert on law and the Western Balkans at King’s College London, said Diella is how Mr. Rama can “say to the world, and to the European Union, that ‘I understand that you are concerned with corruption, and I’m going to try to address it.’”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a December analysis, experts at the German Council on Foreign Relations said the A.I. minister had enhanced “efficiency and impartiality of public procurement decisions taken by the government.” But overall, they concluded, Albania’s record of meeting E.U. standards for combating corruption, particularly in awarding construction and tourism contracts, remains “problematic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That Diella’s developers have themselves been accused of corruption has raised questions about whether a minister created by A.I. can be programmed to overlook certain evidence of graft, or otherwise fed unreliable data to detect it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Hoxhaj said “only time will tell,” but noted that the government had not tried to interfere with the investigation into the agency that runs Diella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I understand the skepticism,” he said. “There’s a whole lot of smoke. But the fact that it was uncovered, not swept under the rug, shows they are acknowledging that corruption is an issue and needs to be prevented in the future.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how Mr. Rama says he sees it, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The country is trying to fight corruption, with all the flaws, with all the problems, with all the shortcomings, with all the damages,” he said. “So this is good.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fatjona Mejdini contributed reporting.&lt;/p&gt;
]]&gt;</description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/27/world/europe/albania-ai-corruption-graft.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>